<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The cuckovv. Richardus Niccols, in Artibus Bac. Oxon</title>
            <author>Niccols, Richard, 1584-1616.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-07">2003-07 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08182</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18517</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113202</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848439</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848439</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13532</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A08182)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13532)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 723:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The cuckovv. Richardus Niccols, in Artibus Bac. Oxon</title>
                  <author>Niccols, Richard, 1584-1616.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 51, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by F[elix] K[ingston] and are to be sold by W. C[otton],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Printer's and bookseller's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cuckoos --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13532:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13532:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CVCKOW.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>At, etiam cubat cuculus: surge amator, i domum.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>RICHARDVS NICCOLS, in Artibus Bac. Oxon. <hi>Aulae Mag.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by <hi>F. K.</hi> and are to be sold by <hi>W. C.</hi> 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13532:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13532:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVL GOOD FRIEND, MASTER THOMAS WROTH an affecter and fauourer of <hi>the Muses.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Cuckowes poem let me thus excuse</l>
               <l>To you (deare friend, the Patron of my verse)</l>
               <l>Though some blind night-born <hi>Momus</hi> it abuse,</l>
               <l>As but a iest vnworthy to reherse:</l>
               <l>Yet who such iests, as this shall idly blame,</l>
               <l>Shall for their meede merit a Cuckowes name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I speake not this; but that in future time,</l>
               <l>When as my wit with riper fruit shall grow,</l>
               <l>My <hi>Muse</hi> may speake to thee in sweeter ryme,</l>
               <l>And for thy worth some grauer poem show:</l>
               <l>Meane time accept of what I heere do bring,</l>
               <l>Though Cuckow-like my <hi>Muse</hi> doth harshly sing.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours at commaund, R. NICCOLLS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13532:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Know that the nature of our Cuckow is a thing so well knowne, that I neede not despaire of any mans knowledge herein; and there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ore for me (especially in these parts where it is so well knowne) to present only a Cuckow, were to bring an Owle to <hi>Athens,</hi> a bird better knowne there then a Cuckow. Wherefore (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ing the literall exposition to him, that is better skild in the nature of a Cuckow, then my selfe, I remit the cause of my affect in this subiect, to thy deeper consideration. To the prodigall want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wits of our age, that are either too curious to contemne al, or too free to affect all, let them know, that I neither despaire at the furious frownes of the one, neither relie vpon the fawning fancie of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: only I submit my selfe to the censure of him, that is more then a meere reader, to whom I do impart part of my poore poeticall skill, vpon which I haue bestowed some idle houres; idle I call them, not in disgrace of so famous a skill: but to giue the world notice, that I make it not the chiefe part of my profession: but rather place it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst those things of accomplement required in a scholar, or gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman; which if (gentle Reader) thou shalt gently accept, my new borne <hi>Muse,</hi> that now sings harsh and hoarse in the shape of a Cuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kow, may by thy incouragement hereafter sing to thee in a more pleasing note. And so wishing, that her obscuritie and vnac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with thee, bee not the barre of her good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment in thy conceit, as being but a stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: yet as friend, I bid thee <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13532:3"/>
            <head>THE CVCKOW.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen <hi>Perseus</hi> bride, that starre of heauen had fled</l>
               <l>The Dragons paw by helpe of <hi>Gorgons</hi> head,</l>
               <l>And on the sea-gods golden-edged brim</l>
               <l>Her gold-out-glistring lockes began to trim:</l>
               <l>Then did the lustie Ram with horned crest</l>
               <l>Rouse vp <hi>Europas</hi> grim-curl'd-headed beast,</l>
               <l>Who loudly bellowing did chase away</l>
               <l>The tedious night, and call'd backe cheerefull day.</l>
               <l>For then <hi>Hyperions</hi> son, the daies bright king</l>
               <l>In pompe did court the Ladie of the spring;</l>
               <l>And she againe in all her rich aray</l>
               <l>Did wanton with him in lasciuious play,</l>
               <l>Vntill her wombe with loues sweet fruit did grow,</l>
               <l>The sweetest fruit, that wombe did euer show:</l>
               <l>For it brought forth the worlds admired birth,</l>
               <l>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Flora,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fairest child on earth;</l>
               <l>Who in short time did grow so great in fame</l>
               <l>For needle worke, that neuer any dame,</l>
               <l>Although her cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ing were exceeding rare</l>
               <l>With faire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Floraes</hi> skill might make compare:</l>
               <l>To show the which, the world she set on wing</l>
               <l>Of sweet delight, to welcome in the spring:</l>
               <l>The mountaine tops she clad in coate of greene,</l>
               <l>And spotted them with gold as they had been</l>
               <l>Starrie <hi>Olympi;</hi> and the vales below</l>
               <l>She deckt with daintier worke, then art can show;</l>
               <l>Vpon the ground mantled in verdent hew,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:13532:4"/>Out of her fruitfull lap each day she threw,</l>
               <l>The choicest flowers, that any curious eye</l>
               <l>In natures garden euer did espie:</l>
               <l>The loftie trees, whose leauie lockes did shake</l>
               <l>And with the wind did daliance seeme to make,</l>
               <l>Shee with sweet breathing blossomes did adorne,</l>
               <l>That seem'd to laugh the winter past to scorne,</l>
               <l>Who when mild <hi>Zephirus</hi> did gently blow</l>
               <l>Delightfull odors round about did throw;</l>
               <l>While ioyous birds beneath the leauie shade,</l>
               <l>With pleasant singing sweet respondence made</l>
               <l>vnto the murmuring streames, that seem'd to play</l>
               <l>With siluer shels, that in their bosom lay:</l>
               <l>Thus with delight did <hi>Flora</hi> decke each thing</l>
               <l>To welcome in her mother ioyfull spring,</l>
               <l>Who had not long triumph'd in this our clime</l>
               <l>Before the tidings of her ioyous prime</l>
               <l>Were spread abroad, which, when those birds that shrunke</l>
               <l>Into the wooden walles of hollow trunck,</l>
               <l>For truth did heare, abroad they boldly came</l>
               <l>To welcome Lady <hi>Ver,</hi> that louely dame;</l>
               <l>Mong'st whom two chiefe there were, <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow hight;</l>
               <l>In whom god <hi>Vulcans</hi> loue tooke most delight,</l>
               <l>The other that sweet singer <hi>Philomel,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or <hi>Casta</hi> hight, whom <hi>Phoebe</hi> loued well:</l>
               <l>These two were chiefe, that in contention stood</l>
               <l>Amongst the pleasant singers of the wood</l>
               <l>To be chiefe carroler and lead the ring,</l>
               <l>Of all the rest to welcome in the spring.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow was a bird hatcht in that houre,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Mars</hi> did sport in <hi>Cythereas</hi> bowre,</l>
               <l>Whereby the note, which his hoarse voice doth beare</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:13532:4"/>Is harsh and fatall to the wedded eare:</l>
               <l>But little <hi>Philomela</hi> farre more blest</l>
               <l>Was foster'd in faire <hi>Phoebes</hi> owne deare brest,</l>
               <l>Whom she no more the Nightingale did name;</l>
               <l>But to consort her nature to the same</l>
               <l>Shee call'd her <hi>Casta,</hi> word of much import,</l>
               <l>And made her chiefe of birds in their consort.</l>
               <l>Betwixt <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow and this little bird</l>
               <l>Th'approach of spring a great contention stird,</l>
               <l>Who should be deem'd the chiefe of birds to bring</l>
               <l>The happie tidings of th'approaching spring:</l>
               <l>For <hi>Philomel</hi> once in a pearlie morne,</l>
               <l>When heauen with sun-bright lookes did earth adorne</l>
               <l>Hearing each bird record her curious lay,</l>
               <l>Vnto the wood with speed did take her way,</l>
               <l>Where shee did presse into the thickest throng</l>
               <l>And did so sweetly in delicious song</l>
               <l>Chaunt out aloude her welcome to the spring,</l>
               <l>That all the birds did cease to heare her sing:</l>
               <l>But as she sate admir'd of euery one,</l>
               <l>Redoubling quauers in diuision,</l>
               <l>And sweetly warbling out that chaste set song,</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Phoebe</hi> taught to her when shee was young,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow came, and from his greedie throate</l>
               <l>breathing out ditties of an vnchast note,</l>
               <l>As wroth that other birds should seeke to make</l>
               <l>Her mistres of the quier, thus boldly spake:</l>
               <l>Thou wretch (said he) what high aspiring spirit</l>
               <l>Doth harbor in thy brest? what is thy merit</l>
               <l>That thou should'st be chiefe carroler to sing</l>
               <l>Amongst vs all to welcome in the spring?</l>
               <l>Is not my dame the goddesse of delight,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:13532:5"/>And Queene of Loue, whose altars are bedight</l>
               <l>With broad blowne blossomes of the blooming spring,</l>
               <l>Of budding youth: then cease and let mee sing;</l>
               <l>For I of birds am chiefest in her sight</l>
               <l>And in my ditties she takes most delight:</l>
               <l>Then cease thou fondling cease, and let me sing</l>
               <l>A pleasing welcome to the wanton spring.</l>
               <l>This said, he chaunted out his wonted lay,</l>
               <l>Which did in woods all wedded birds affray:</l>
               <l>But little <hi>Casta</hi> nought at all dismaide,</l>
               <l>Being safely shrowded in the leauie shade</l>
               <l>Return'd this short replie: (Cuckow) (quoth shee)</l>
               <l>What thou hast said, I graunt; yet now heare me.</l>
               <l>Where daintie dames are dight to wanton sin</l>
               <l>Loosely araid youths wandring eyes to win,</l>
               <l>Whom slick-hair'd slipper-lossels do dispoile</l>
               <l>Of beauties, bud with loues sweete seeming toile,</l>
               <l>While smock sworne boyes stand by and keepe account,</l>
               <l>How oft aloft they lustily do mount;</l>
               <l>There with good right may thy harsh sounding throate</l>
               <l>Without controll record thy bastard note.</l>
               <l>But in all woods, where my faire virgin dame</l>
               <l>With her chaste Nymphes did keepe laborious game</l>
               <l>To slacke the strength of loues bow-bending string,</l>
               <l>Thou must not speake thy welcome to the spring:</l>
               <l>For <hi>Phoebes</hi> selfe with all her Nymphes consent</l>
               <l>Did make me cheefe of birds, for that intent.</l>
               <l>This said, <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow perfect in the sleight</l>
               <l>Of cunning guile, and knowing loues delight</l>
               <l>Had thrill'd their hearts, that in faire <hi>Phoebes</hi> groue</l>
               <l>Once rang'd at will in scorne of Ladie loue,</l>
               <l>Made this replie: (quoth he) seeing thou dost vaunt</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:13532:5"/>Of <hi>Phoebe</hi> and her Nymphes, thereby to daunt</l>
               <l>My courage in this claime, I do agree,</l>
               <l>That they decide the cause 'twixt thee and mee;</l>
               <l>And if they iudge thy note the sweeter sound,</l>
               <l>Cheefe singer of the quier, thou shalt be crown'd:</l>
               <l>But if to them my song more pleasing be,</l>
               <l>To make me che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>fe in woods, thou shalt agree.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Casta</hi> being swift to giue such counsell eare</l>
               <l>Supposing <hi>Phoebes</hi> Nymphes, such loue did beare</l>
               <l>To chaster thoughts, that they would all detest</l>
               <l>The vnchaste dittie of <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckowes brest,</l>
               <l>Was well contented that it should be so</l>
               <l>And with <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow for this cause did go,</l>
               <l>Vnto the bower of blisse, for so it hight,</l>
               <l>Where then those Nymphes to be did most deligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>It is a place, that thoughts cannot deuise</l>
               <l>A plot more like vnto a Paradise;</l>
               <l>Shall I compare it to <hi>Cytheron</hi> greene,</l>
               <l>On which the warre-god did compresse loues queene,</l>
               <l>Or to <hi>Adonis</hi> garden farre renown'd,</l>
               <l>In which eternall spring is euer found?</l>
               <l>O farre more pleasant is this pleasant place,</l>
               <l>Then all the blisfull bowers beneath heauens face!</l>
               <l>It seated is farre in a pleasa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t wood,</l>
               <l>Where many a loftie Iouiall tree hath stood,</l>
               <l>Not much vnlike, that wood by thornie groue</l>
               <l>Full of the tree erected vnto <hi>Ioue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which seated is vpon the Northern Strand,</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Saxon Segberts</hi> sacred tower doth stand,</l>
               <l>By which the Prince of <hi>Albions</hi> watrie deepes</l>
               <l>From the French Ocean with swift currant sweepes,</l>
               <l>Wafting each yeare by his Labrynthian strand,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:13532:6"/>More then a thousand keele from forren land,</l>
               <l>Who oft, when <hi>Boreas</hi> at their safetie raues,</l>
               <l>And with proud blasts doth cuffe the siluer waues,</l>
               <l>Do nimblie fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ch <hi>Lauolto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> vp and downe</l>
               <l>Vpon the waues in scorn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Boreas</hi> frowne:</l>
               <l>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>uch a famous w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>od, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s that, is this,</l>
               <l>In wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ch doth stand th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>sant bower of blisse:</l>
               <l>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>to the which, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> as <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow came</l>
               <l>Knowing each w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> led throughout the same,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Philomel</hi> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ady way,</l>
               <l>Which to the bow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>r of blisse dir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ctly lay;</l>
               <l>Where in the way they both amazed stood</l>
               <l>To see the pleasance of tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wood,</l>
               <l>There many blissefull bowers they did behold;</l>
               <l>Whose dwelle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s nei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>her vext with heate nor cold</l>
               <l>Did there enioy all things, that might delight</l>
               <l>The cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ie of any liuing wight:</l>
               <l>For pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ntie th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e to lauish in her gift</l>
               <l>Furnisht each place in scorne of niggard thrift;</l>
               <l>There many Nymphes of more then heauenly hew</l>
               <l>Had their abode; although alas but few</l>
               <l>Amongst them all did come of heauenly kind,</l>
               <l>So hard it is to gaine the gifts of mind:</l>
               <l>Yet stately portance, vnto them was giuen</l>
               <l>And in proportion like the stares of heauen</l>
               <l>They bare thems<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lues: yet want both will and power</l>
               <l>From loues assault to shield faire beauties bower</l>
               <l>And more to beautifie the goodly frames,</l>
               <l>Which God and nature gaue these goodly dames,</l>
               <l>Gentrie th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ir cradles at their birth did rock</l>
               <l>And drew their linage from an auncient stock:</l>
               <l>But what alas a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ailes the vading flower</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:13532:6"/>Of beauties bud in those, that haue no power</l>
               <l>To guid the least part of the weaker sence</l>
               <l>And learne the lesson of pure continence?</l>
               <l>Or what is birth to those, that so they winne</l>
               <l>The seeming sweetnes of alluring sinne?</l>
               <l>Bastard their birth and all their stock deprau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>To gaine the thing, which appetite doth craue:</l>
               <l>Beautie in such, though much, is but disgrace,</l>
               <l>And high borne birth, though kingly, yet but base.</l>
               <l>For faire is foule, where vertue is vnknowne,</l>
               <l>And birth is base, where gifts of grace are none.</l>
               <l>From hence <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow with faire <hi>Philomel,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Acquainted with each passage very well)</l>
               <l>Forward proceeded in this pleasant wood</l>
               <l>Vntill they came vnto that place, where stood</l>
               <l>The bower of blisse it selfe, so fairely deckt,</l>
               <l>That neuer eye beheld so faire aspect:</l>
               <l>In th'ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>er portch sate many a slick-hear'd Squier</l>
               <l>Of pleasing semblance, full of loose desire,</l>
               <l>Of feature fit to feast a Ladies e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e;</l>
               <l>But manlie exercise vnfit to trie:</l>
               <l>Their cunning did consist in sleights of loue,</l>
               <l>With which from loy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ltie they oft did moue</l>
               <l>Ladies fraile hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s: for vnto many a one</l>
               <l>They vow'd them<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>elues; though faithful vnto none,</l>
               <l>Vnto the secrets of the vnc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>aste she<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t</l>
               <l>They sworne were, an oath for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ch vnmeet:</l>
               <l>For which their seruice ofte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>imes they fed</l>
               <l>On ransackt swee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nes of the nup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>iall bed:</l>
               <l>But let not such disco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rse d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>file my pen</l>
               <l>With argument<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ch reprochfull men;</l>
               <l>Let it suffice that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>o bring</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:13532:7"/>
                  <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow heere to welcome in our spring.</l>
               <l>Mong'st these, there was a squier of greatest place</l>
               <l>And cheefest held in that great Ladies grace,</l>
               <l>Which dwelt in this same bower: for many a night</l>
               <l>With her he stole a snatch of loues delight:</l>
               <l>For he was lustie, young, fit for her tooth,</l>
               <l>And her great wealth did well content his youth.</l>
               <l>Yet he was false, disloyall to his dame;</l>
               <l>For in his common talke deuoid of shame</l>
               <l>He of his Ladies fauour was too francke,</l>
               <l>For which I con that louer little thanke;</l>
               <l>He was the vsher to this daintie dame</l>
               <l>And <hi>Vanitie</hi> men gaue him vnto name,</l>
               <l>To whom <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow often louting low</l>
               <l>By his obsequious signes his mind did show</l>
               <l>And chaunted out to <hi>Philomels</hi> disgrace</l>
               <l>His vnchaste note, well knowne in that same place:</l>
               <l>For this same Squier full well I wot did know</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckowes note and vnto him did go,</l>
               <l>Where seeing little <hi>Casta</hi> by him stand,</l>
               <l>Cause of their comming friendly did demaund:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow proud of such an intertaine</l>
               <l>Did tell the iarre begun betwixt them twaine,</l>
               <l>Who should be cheefe of all the birds to sing</l>
               <l>As herbenger to welcome in the spring,</l>
               <l>And now to end the same, they both were come</l>
               <l>Agreed to stand vnto the wood-Nymphes doome;</l>
               <l>Wherefore they crau'd accesse vnto his dame,</l>
               <l>That with her Nymphes she might decide the same:</l>
               <l>This gentle Squier soone graunted their requests</l>
               <l>And kindlie did conduckt his new come guests</l>
               <l>Into an in ward court, where they should stay,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:13532:7"/>Till to his dame their message he did say;</l>
               <l>Where, while they staid, with great delight they spent</l>
               <l>The time in viewing this faire continent,</l>
               <l>This bower of blisse, this paradise of pleasure,</l>
               <l>Where lauish plentie did exceed all measure;</l>
               <l>The inner portch seem'd entrance to intice,</l>
               <l>It fashion'd was with such quaint rare deuice,</l>
               <l>The top with cannopie of greene was spred</l>
               <l>Thicken'd with leaues of th'Iuies wanton hed,</l>
               <l>About the which the <hi>Eglentine</hi> did twine</l>
               <l>His prickling armes the branches to combine,</l>
               <l>Bearing sweete flowers of more then fragrant odour,</l>
               <l>Which stellified the roofe with painted colour;</l>
               <l>On either side the vine did broad dilate</l>
               <l>His swollen veines with wreathings intricate,</l>
               <l>Whose bunches to the ground did seeme t'incline,</l>
               <l>As freely offring of their luscious wine:</l>
               <l>Through this same portch went many a worthy wight</l>
               <l>Vnto the bower of blisse, both day and night,</l>
               <l>Who at their entrance fresh and flush as May</l>
               <l>Did beare themselues adorn'd in rich aray:</l>
               <l>But few return'd without the common curse</l>
               <l>Of strange disease of emptinesse in purse,</l>
               <l>Who wanting golden shewers for <hi>Danaes</hi> lap,</l>
               <l>As discontented with their sad mishap</l>
               <l>Walkt to and fro, forlorne in deepe disdaine</l>
               <l>With willow braunch, for prise of all their paine.</l>
               <l>From this same portch, a walke directly lay,</l>
               <l>Which to the bower it selfe did leade the way</l>
               <l>With fruit-trees thicke beset on either side,</l>
               <l>Whose goodly fruit themselues did seeme to hide</l>
               <l>Beneath the leaues, as lurking from the eies</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:13532:8"/>Of strangers greedie view, fearing surprise,</l>
               <l>Whose arched bowes and leauie twigs together</l>
               <l>With true loue knots intangled each in other,</l>
               <l>Seem'd painted walles, on which when <hi>Zephire</hi> blew</l>
               <l>They spread themselues, disclosing vnto view</l>
               <l>The blossomes, buds, the birds and painted flies,</l>
               <l>That in their leaues lay hid from strangers eies;</l>
               <l>This walke of people neuer emptie was:</l>
               <l>For to the bower of blisse one could not passe;</l>
               <l>But that the way did swarme with ietting iacks,</l>
               <l>Who bare vpon their french diseased backes,</l>
               <l>Whole manners, castles, townes and Lordships sold</l>
               <l>Cut out in clippings and in shreds of gold:</l>
               <l>Their chambring fortitude they did descrie</l>
               <l>By their soft maiden voice and flickering eie,</l>
               <l>Their womans manhood by their cloaths perfum'd,</l>
               <l>Coy lookes, curl'd lockes, and thin beards halfe consum'd,</l>
               <l>Whose nice, effeminate and base behauiour</l>
               <l>Was counted comely, neate and cleanly gesture;</l>
               <l>This pleasant walke, when gentle <hi>Philomel</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And Cuckow her proud foe had viewed well</l>
               <l>Passing forth, one loe there they did behold</l>
               <l>High lifted vp with loftie roofe of gold</l>
               <l>The bower of blisse, in which there did abide</l>
               <l>The Ladies selfe, that should their cause decide,</l>
               <l>On which the heauens still in a stedfast state</l>
               <l>Look't alway blithe, diuerting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>roward fate,</l>
               <l>Not suffering y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ie frost, or s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rching sunne</l>
               <l>To vex th'in habitants, that there did wonne:</l>
               <l>For there eternall spring doth euer dwell,</l>
               <l>Nay they of other season ought can tell,</l>
               <l>They labour not with hands of industrie</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:13532:8"/>To furrow vp the earthes fertilitie,</l>
               <l>Bubbles of sweate decline not from their brow,</l>
               <l>Ne stooping labour makes their backes to bow:</l>
               <l>Yet plentie of all fruits vpon their ground,</l>
               <l>Seedlesse and artlesse euery where is found:</l>
               <l>Vnto this bower <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow and his mate</l>
               <l>Approaching nigh, loe standing at the gate,</l>
               <l>Which framed was of purest Iuorie</l>
               <l>All painted ore with many a historie,</l>
               <l>So sweetly wrought, that arte in them did seeme</l>
               <l>To mocke at nature as of no esteeme,</l>
               <l>Eftsoones they heard a pleasing harmonie</l>
               <l>Of musikes most melodious minstralsie,</l>
               <l>Where sweet voic'd birds, soft winds and waters fall,</l>
               <l>With voice and Violl made agreement all,</l>
               <l>The birds vnto the voice did sweetly sing,</l>
               <l>The voice did speake vnto the Viols string,</l>
               <l>That to the wind did sound now high now low,</l>
               <l>The wind to waters fall did gently blow;</l>
               <l>Thus birds, voice, Violl, winds and waters all</l>
               <l>Did sing, did speake, did sound, did blow, did fall:</l>
               <l>As thus <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow and his opposite,</l>
               <l>The Nightingale stood harkening with delight</l>
               <l>Vnto this musike, loe that Squire came</l>
               <l>Hight <hi>Vanitie</hi> with answere from his dame,</l>
               <l>That'gainst the morne themselues they should prepare,</l>
               <l>Their cause in ample manner to declare;</l>
               <l>For with her Nymphes in iudgement she would sit,</l>
               <l>And which of them, they should esteeme most fit,</l>
               <l>She would denounce for cheefe in woods to sing,</l>
               <l>As herbinger vnto the ioyfull spring:</l>
               <l>This newes did glad them both; for both did feed</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:13532:9"/>Themselues with hope: although but one could speed</l>
               <l>And both prepar'd each other to excell</l>
               <l>In the next morne, to beare away the bell:</l>
               <l>The little <hi>Philomel</hi> with curious care,</l>
               <l>Sitting alone her ditties did prepare,</l>
               <l>And many tunes, whose harmonie did passe</l>
               <l>All musike else that ere inuented was;</l>
               <l>One while the meane part shee did sweetly warble,</l>
               <l>The tennor now, the Base and then the trebble:</l>
               <l>Then all at once with many parts in one,</l>
               <l>Diuiding sweetly in diuision;</l>
               <l>Now some sweete straine to mind she doth restore,</l>
               <l>Which all the winter shee had conn'd before,</l>
               <l>And with such cunning deskants thereupon,</l>
               <l>That curious art nere doctrin'd any one</l>
               <l>With Lute, with Violl, or with voice in quier,</l>
               <l>That to her matchlesse musike might aspire:</l>
               <l>Meane time <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow, knowing that his voice</l>
               <l>Had no varietie, no change, no choice:</l>
               <l>But through the wesand pipe of his harsh throate</l>
               <l>Cri'd only Cuckow, that prodigious note,</l>
               <l>That want with wits supplie he did amend,</l>
               <l>And made that Squier, <hi>Vanitie</hi> his friend,</l>
               <l>Who did so worke for him, as it befell,</l>
               <l>That iudgement went against poore <hi>Philomel.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The time came on, and th'Opall coloured morne,</l>
               <l>Bright-cheek<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Aurora</hi> leaning all sorlorne</l>
               <l>Old <hi>Tytho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in his bed, did vp arise</l>
               <l>Opening the gates of the orientall skies,</l>
               <l>Through which the daies bright king came dauncing out</l>
               <l>With glorious golden lockes bespread about</l>
               <l>His s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>oulders broad; from whence such luster came,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:13532:9"/>That all the world did seeme a golden flame:</l>
               <l>For then <hi>Auroraes</hi> trumpe, the peasants clocke,</l>
               <l>Daies herbinger, the bloody crested cocke</l>
               <l>With flaggie wings had beate black night away,</l>
               <l>And sung sweet tidings of approaching day,</l>
               <l>At which both birds vp starting from their rest</l>
               <l>Quaintly to plead their cause, themselues addrest,</l>
               <l>Which with her Nymphes, that day in solemne state</l>
               <l>The Ladie of this bower should debate,</l>
               <l>Which flying fame vpon her wings did beare,</l>
               <l>Making it vulgar newes in euery eare,</l>
               <l>And with her siluer trumpe did Echo out</l>
               <l>Report thereof, in all the woods about;</l>
               <l>Which once being blowen abroad, all the whole quier</l>
               <l>Of singers in the wood with great desire,</l>
               <l>(To know in this same strife, who should preuaile</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow, or the little <hi>Nightingale</hi>)</l>
               <l>Came flocking through the aire, and as they flew,</l>
               <l>Their diuers warbling notes about they threw;</l>
               <l>There came the Larke, who still as she did flie</l>
               <l>With outstretcht' wings aspir'd the cloud brow'd skie,</l>
               <l>There Progne came who did present for food</l>
               <l>In tragicke feast, her owne deare <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>tis</hi> blood</l>
               <l>To bloodie <hi>Tereus,</hi> in auengment fell</l>
               <l>Of sister deare <hi>Pandions Philomel,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who now transform'd vnto the sent-strong Swallow,</l>
               <l>Shaftlike did flie through the ayres concaue hollow;</l>
               <l>With these there came the Thrush, that loues the grape,</l>
               <l>The speckled Spinck, that liues by gummie sappe,</l>
               <l>The Redbrest sweet, that loues the lookes of men,</l>
               <l>The lustfull Sparrow and the little Wren,</l>
               <l>The chattering Pie, the quick conceited Stare,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:13532:10"/>The golden Finch and Linnot singing rare</l>
               <l>With many more, whose notes the aire did fill</l>
               <l>With true consort, sweet worke of natures skill,</l>
               <l>Who to the bower of blisse did take their way,</l>
               <l>To h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>are the iarre decided, that same day,</l>
               <l>Which the approach of spring did late excite</l>
               <l>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>wixt <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow and his opposite:</l>
               <l>The place, in which this matter should be tride</l>
               <l>Was in a greene pailde round on euery side,</l>
               <l>In which was pight a stately cannopi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>;</l>
               <l>For that great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and her companie,</l>
               <l>Many a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Nymph of great estate,</l>
               <l>That should that day <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckowes cause debate;</l>
               <l>Who being pearch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> aloft in open sight</l>
               <l>Vpon a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> braunch, had well ydight</l>
               <l>And deckt his plumes to make a pleasant show,</l>
               <l>When he should pleade his cause against his foe,</l>
               <l>Who on the other side her selfe did place,</l>
               <l>In hope <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow foulely to disgrace,</l>
               <l>Not doubting but those Nymphes for <hi>Phoebes</hi> sake</l>
               <l>In this so iusta cause, her part would take:</l>
               <l>The time being come, loe like as when <hi>Ioues</hi> bride,</l>
               <l>Heauens Iuory fingered queene in pompe doth ride</l>
               <l>To heauens high court, aboue the Planets seauen,</l>
               <l>To sit in counsell with the gods of heauen:</l>
               <l>Euen so forth comes that faire renowmed dame,</l>
               <l>Chiefest of all the bower of blisse, that came</l>
               <l>To iudge the controuersie that befell,</l>
               <l>Betwixt <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow and faire <hi>Philomel,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shee was a Ladi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> gaudie in attire</l>
               <l>And to content th'affect of her desire,</l>
               <l>Th'earthes golden bowels often wounded were</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:13532:10"/>And th'Indian slaue with steele did often teare</l>
               <l>The hard rockes rubie ribs in hope to find</l>
               <l>Treasure to pleasure her disdainfull mind:</l>
               <l>Proudly she pas'd it with a princely gate,</l>
               <l>As earth had been too meane for her estate,</l>
               <l>Looking to heauen with her disdain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ull eies;</l>
               <l>For humble obiect she did still dispise:</l>
               <l>Yet was her birth but meane, and her esteeme</l>
               <l>Respectiuely compa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>'d, but base did seeme,</l>
               <l>Loosely she was aray'd in wanton weed</l>
               <l>Which wander<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s eies did with inticement feed,</l>
               <l>For she was clad in robe of tissue thinne,</l>
               <l>Through which so brim appear'd her snowie skin,</l>
               <l>That it did seeme to those, that did it see,</l>
               <l>No whit obscur'd, but farre more white to bee;</l>
               <l>Her Iuorie brests did euer open lie</l>
               <l>To readie spoile of gazers greedie eie,</l>
               <l>And both her lillie paps were bare to winne</l>
               <l>Her louers melting heart to wanton sinne;</l>
               <l>Her name the which was <hi>Meehafasto</hi> hight</l>
               <l>Her double nature did expresse aright:</l>
               <l>With her there hither came a goodly crew</l>
               <l>Of louely Nymphes of seeming Angels hue,</l>
               <l>Featur'd each where in bodies li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eament,</l>
               <l>As if they late had left the firmament,</l>
               <l>Or as if heauens diuine triplicitie,</l>
               <l>Out of some fift vnknowne simplicitie,</l>
               <l>For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> complexions hue had fram'd some mixture,</l>
               <l>Passing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> homely gift of common nature:</l>
               <l>But pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ie 'twas, such angell-seeming creatures</l>
               <l>With vlcerous minds deform'd such heauenly features:</l>
               <l>For they were wanton, full of loose desire</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:13532:11"/>And in their heart did nourish lustfull fire,</l>
               <l>With glauncing lookes, like summers euening lights</l>
               <l>They could allure the rash beholders sights,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Heliotropon</hi>-like with sun-like skill</l>
               <l>Could cause soft hearts to turne vnto their will,</l>
               <l>When they list speake, their words like to a lake</l>
               <l>Breaking through rocks of rubie, seem'd to make</l>
               <l>Celestiall musike with their pleasing sound,</l>
               <l>Amongst the siluer pearles, that stood around,</l>
               <l>With which they <hi>Syren</hi>-like could often moue</l>
               <l>Modest <hi>Hypolitus</hi> to wanton loue,</l>
               <l>They all acoutered were in sundrie fashion,</l>
               <l>Seeming t'haue been all of a seuerall nation,</l>
               <l>Some in the antique Roman Lords attire</l>
               <l>Did shape themselues, as seeming to aspire</l>
               <l>Some captaines place, or as if they had been</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Symiramis,</hi> that manlike monster queene,</l>
               <l>In Persian loose aray, some did delight,</l>
               <l>Or rather disaray, so loosely dight,</l>
               <l>In the french doublet some againe did i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t</l>
               <l>wanting but slops to make a man compleat,</l>
               <l>Some on their heads did beare the fatall signe,</l>
               <l>Which of fooles future fortune did diuine,</l>
               <l>Others againe Morisko caps did weare</l>
               <l>Maid-marrian-like with brooches in each eare</l>
               <l>And Indian-like did paint inch thicke in view;</l>
               <l>Though natures red and white were Angels hew.</l>
               <l>Thus with their fashions strange varietie,</l>
               <l>They did bewray their minds inormitie:</l>
               <l>For things externall sought with strong affect,</l>
               <l>Internall thoughts both good and bad detect,</l>
               <l>Which, when the little <hi>Casta</hi> did behold</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:13532:11"/>Poore bird her fearefull heart did wax stone cold:</l>
               <l>But now too late shee did repent, that shee</l>
               <l>Had made them iudges of her cause to bee:</l>
               <l>For thither now, they were alreadie come</l>
               <l>According to their minds to giue their doome,</l>
               <l>Where heapes of people thronging in the way</l>
               <l>Did earlie waite for them by breake of day</l>
               <l>To know, what bird should beare away the bell</l>
               <l>The bastard Cuckow or faire <hi>Philomel:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The iudges being set, vp straight did stand,</l>
               <l>The crier of the court who did command</l>
               <l>High, with shrill voice and great authoritie</l>
               <l>A generall silence through the companie;</l>
               <l>Which done forth stept the little <hi>Casta</hi> hight,</l>
               <l>Who being pearcht aloft in open sight</l>
               <l>After obeysance to those damsels made,</l>
               <l>That were as iudges set, thus boldly said:</l>
               <l>(Fairest of faire) who from the ioyous prime</l>
               <l>Of your great birth, vntill this very time,</l>
               <l>Haue trained been in this celestiall place,</l>
               <l>This bower of blisse in vertue and in grace,</l>
               <l>For vertues sake vouchsafe with silent pause</l>
               <l>To heare poore <hi>Philomela</hi> plead her cause.</l>
               <l>What once I haue been, now I need not tell,</l>
               <l>Nor what I am, I know, yee know it well:</l>
               <l>Yee know, that once, when in great Athens towne</l>
               <l>My Sire, good king <hi>Pandion</hi> wore the crowne,</l>
               <l>A Ladie then I was, as now yee bee</l>
               <l>And daughter to a king, till wo is mee,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Thracian</hi> king, whose lust-burnt thoughts did flame</l>
               <l>And burne in foule desire, did worke my shame:</l>
               <l>In <hi>Thracian</hi> woods (O euer be forgot</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:13532:12"/>The place in which mine honor he did blot)</l>
               <l>In <hi>Thracian</hi> woods (I say) the tyrant fell</l>
               <l>Vnto his will did force poore <hi>Philomel,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And lest his wicked acte I should des<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rie</l>
               <l>The cruell edged steele he did applie</l>
               <l>Vnto my tongue, and with most bitter smart</l>
               <l>Did rob me of the Echo of my heart:</l>
               <l>All this and more then this, yee all do know</l>
               <l>So common is poore <hi>Philomelaes</hi> woe.</l>
               <l>Yee know likewise how in auengement fell</l>
               <l>My furious sister, <hi>Progne</hi> did compell</l>
               <l>The lustfull <hi>Tereus</hi> in a fatall feast</l>
               <l>To swallow downe into his lust-burnt brest</l>
               <l>His owne deare sonne, his <hi>Itis,</hi> that sweet youth,</l>
               <l>Whose death breeds in my heart eternall ruth:</l>
               <l>For which when as the tyrant did decree</l>
               <l>With wrathfull sword to wreake reuenge on me</l>
               <l>Heauen pittie tooke and gaue to me this shape,</l>
               <l>By which his fell intent I did escape,</l>
               <l>And as an exile from all mens abode</l>
               <l>I since haue liued in the desert wood,</l>
               <l>Where sitting once on humble thorne alone</l>
               <l>And in my wofull di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ties making mone</l>
               <l>For my old Sire, <hi>Pandion,</hi> that good King,</l>
               <l>Whose timelesse death my sad mischance did bring;</l>
               <l>Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, That great Huntresse of renowmed fame,</l>
               <l>The Ladie <hi>Phoebe</hi> following the game,</l>
               <l>In the wild wood hath silent stood in pittie</l>
               <l>To heare the sad tunes of my dolefull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>And being mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>'d with deepe remorse of mind</l>
               <l>That fates had been so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and vnk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d</l>
               <l>'Gainst me poore wretch, she did vou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hsafe to show</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:13532:12"/>Compassion towards me in my bitter woe.</l>
               <l>While in these woods and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> she did vse,</l>
               <l>Mong'st all the quier for chiefe, she <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> me c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>use</l>
               <l>To be her bird, and while shee was my dame</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Philomel,</hi> but <hi>Casta</hi> was my name,</l>
               <l>And, for I was the daughter of a King,</l>
               <l>Shee made me cheefe of all the quier to sing,</l>
               <l>And in her woods ordained me the shade</l>
               <l>To shroude my selfe from <hi>Tereus</hi> bloodie blade:</l>
               <l>But loe alas, what time hath brought to passe,</l>
               <l>Loe heere a tyrant, worse then <hi>Ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> was,</l>
               <l>Loe heere <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow my sterne enemie</l>
               <l>Claiming my right with proud authoritie,</l>
               <l>Who this same blissefull place as death did shun,</l>
               <l>When as my dame in these same woods did wonne.</l>
               <l>(O) how it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> me, that a bird so base</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pandions</hi> princely daughter should disgrace,</l>
               <l>Who by condition of his qualitie</l>
               <l>Vnto the world discries his basta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>die:</l>
               <l>Is't not inough, that once I being a dame</l>
               <l>Y borne o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> auncient Kings of worthie fame,</l>
               <l>Now liue a bird loathing mans companie</l>
               <l>In desert woods for loue to chastitie,</l>
               <l>And in the echoing mountaines loudly sing</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phoebes</hi> chaste song, when as the lustie spring</l>
               <l>Stirres vp young bloods, that with my chaster layes</l>
               <l>I may recall them from their wanton waies?</l>
               <l>But must a bird the basest of the crue</l>
               <l>In all the woodstand vp to wrest my due</l>
               <l>Vnto his lot, which <hi>Phoebe</hi> did ordaine</l>
               <l>Should vnto me for euermore remaine?</l>
               <l>Nor is it yet enough alas, that I</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:13532:13"/>From stately palaces of kings do flie,</l>
               <l>Still dreading <hi>Tereus</hi> lothsome luxurie</l>
               <l>To liue in woods farre from all companie?</l>
               <l>But must another <hi>Tereus</hi> seeke t'expell</l>
               <l>From woods likewise the forlorne <hi>Philo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>el?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Alas if so, where shall I hide my head,</l>
               <l>Where shall I shun th'ineuitable dread</l>
               <l>Of bloodie <hi>Tereus</hi> hot lust-sparkling face,</l>
               <l>If nor in woods, nor house I shall haue place?</l>
               <l>To you therefore (faire Nymphes) to your iust doome</l>
               <l>That as the vmpiers of my cause are come</l>
               <l>I do appeale, not doubting but the loue</l>
               <l>You beare to <hi>Phoebes</hi> name your hearts will moue</l>
               <l>In this so iust a cause to pittie mee,</l>
               <l>That was as deare to her as deare might bee;</l>
               <l>Which if yee do, your fame shall neuer die</l>
               <l>And <hi>Castas</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>elfe shall sing your praise on hie.</l>
               <l>This said, shee breathed from her brest so cleare</l>
               <l>The sweetest layes, that eare did euer heare,</l>
               <l>To which all other birds about the place</l>
               <l>Did tune their diuers notes to do her grace,</l>
               <l>As in approuance of her worth to sing</l>
               <l>As chiefe in woods to welcome in the spring,</l>
               <l>Which did so daunt <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckowes daring pride,</l>
               <l>That of the thought his shamefull head to hide:</l>
               <l>But knowing well that he had friends in place</l>
               <l>That of those partiall Nymphes had got him grace,</l>
               <l>Feare set aside, and his obeysance made,</l>
               <l>Vnto those Nymphes these words he boldly said:</l>
               <l>(Yee glorious ofspring of great honors bed,</l>
               <l>Vertues fair<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> impes, mirrors of womanhed,</l>
               <l>Bright Angel-like sweet Nymphes, whose beauties blaze</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:13532:13"/>Adornes the world like <hi>Tytans</hi> golded rayes)</l>
               <l>Vouchsafe with gentle patience for a space</l>
               <l>Your gratious silence, while I pleade my case.</l>
               <l>The iarre begun b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>twixt my foe and me,</l>
               <l>The subiect of my purps'd speech should be;</l>
               <l>But fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>st both words and wit, I must applie</l>
               <l>To make an answere to mine enemie.</l>
               <l>Though of my birth no boaster I will be</l>
               <l>Seeing in this cause it nought auaileth me;</l>
               <l>Yet, that I may, that scandalisme refute,</l>
               <l>Which my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e foe doth vnto me impute,</l>
               <l>Know that <hi>Ioues</hi> bird, the Eagle prince of ayre</l>
               <l>Did foster me being young with tender care,</l>
               <l>In whose proud neasty built, in <hi>Iouiall</hi> tree</l>
               <l>My dame by secret stelth conueied me.</l>
               <l>In that same clime, where <hi>AEstas</hi> sits in pride</l>
               <l>Beneath the tropick of hot sommers guide,</l>
               <l>The crabbed <hi>Cancer,</hi> where in earthes coole cels,</l>
               <l>The hot sun painted people euer dwels,</l>
               <l>Not far from whence great <hi>Nilus</hi> euermore</l>
               <l>With fruitfull waues doth wash th'Egyptian shore,</l>
               <l>There was I bred, and there my fame first grew,</l>
               <l>Which thence long since about the wide world flew.</l>
               <l>For South from thence the land of <hi>Cyprus</hi> lies,</l>
               <l>Whereas the people vse to sacrifice</l>
               <l>To lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>es faire Queene, of whom I wonne great grace,</l>
               <l>When she was wroth with people o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> that place:</l>
               <l>For once being sore offended with them all</l>
               <l>And musing with he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>selfe, what plague should fall</l>
               <l>Vpon their heads, she chaunc'd to cast he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> eie</l>
               <l>Vpon an home, which she did soone applie</l>
               <l>Vnto their browes, whereby they straight forsooke</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:13532:14"/>Their former shape, and Oxe-like was their looke:</l>
               <l>But they blind buzzards could not see the same,</l>
               <l>Whereby the lesser was their griefe and shame,</l>
               <l>Till ore their goodly heads, I wau'd my wing</l>
               <l>And cuckow in their eares aloud did sing;</l>
               <l>Which when they heard, like raging Buls they bore</l>
               <l>Their lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>tie heads, and with loud bellowing rore</l>
               <l>Did show their iealous thoughts: for which men say</l>
               <l>They called are <hi>Cerastes</hi> to this day:</l>
               <l>And for this fact of mine the <hi>Cyprian</hi> dame,</l>
               <l>The Queene of loue did giue to me for name</l>
               <l>The song, which I did sing and did decree,</l>
               <l>That I thence forth her only bird should be;</l>
               <l>She bore me to that garden of great fame,</l>
               <l>Which yet of her <hi>Adonis</hi> beares the name,</l>
               <l>Where she her selfe did teach me how to sing,</l>
               <l>Her sweet delights vnto the youthfull spring;</l>
               <l>And did appoint, that the yeares youthly prime</l>
               <l>Should be the season of my singing time:</l>
               <l>For well she knew, that season did belong</l>
               <l>Vnto the nature of my pleasant song;</l>
               <l>As for my foe, although her layes be sweet:</l>
               <l>Yet be they sad patheticall vnmeet</l>
               <l>To be recorded, when the lustie spring</l>
               <l>Tidings of pleasure to the world doth bring,</l>
               <l>More fit with little Redbrest on a thorne</l>
               <l>To beare a part, and helpe her for to mourne</l>
               <l>For losse of sommer, when cold winters breath</l>
               <l>To all our pleasures threatens hatefull death:</l>
               <l>Then (gentle dames, great Ladies of delight)</l>
               <l>Who in this bower of blisse both day and night</l>
               <l>haue your abode, where winter neuer lowres</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:13532:14"/>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> on your heads powres downe his stormie shewers;</l>
               <l>Let it be seene that ye haue need of none</l>
               <l>The sommer past in winter to bemone:</l>
               <l>So s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>all <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow sing your lasting praise</l>
               <l>Before loues Queene in his delightfull laies.</l>
               <l>This said, he chaunted out his Cuckows song,</l>
               <l>Which laughter bred among'st the thickest throng,</l>
               <l>Nor any prettie bird about the place</l>
               <l>Would in their song vouchsafe to do him grace.</l>
               <l>But see the chaunce the Nymphes being in a pause</l>
               <l>And in consult how to decide this cause,</l>
               <l>And each one being husht with greedie eare</l>
               <l>To heare that sentence, which they least did feare,</l>
               <l>Of all the Nymphes vp stood the chiefest dame</l>
               <l>And thus this vniust sentence did proclaime:</l>
               <l>(O all yee singers of the woods sweet quier)</l>
               <l>Heare now the doome, which ye did long desire,</l>
               <l>And (ye) twixt whom the iarre begun but late,</l>
               <l>As yet hangs in suspence without debate,</l>
               <l>Know that each others cause doth now abide</l>
               <l>In equall ballance, which we thus decide.</l>
               <l>Seeing to the nature of each others song,</l>
               <l>Two parts of all the yeare seeme to belong,</l>
               <l>That part in equall doome we will ordaine,</l>
               <l>Which is most meet for either of you twaine;</l>
               <l>First touching <hi>Philomel,</hi> seeing that her dittie</l>
               <l>Is alwaies passionate and mouing pittie,</l>
               <l>Seeing with her, when she sings in wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ull wise</l>
               <l>The echoing mountaines seeme to sympathize,</l>
               <l>And rockes do weepe, and trees do seeme to grone,</l>
               <l>When in lamenting layes she list to mone</l>
               <l>In that sad time, when <hi>Boreas</hi> winged scouts</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:13532:15"/>Locks vp the fruitfull <hi>Terras</hi> water spouts,</l>
               <l>And with congealing puffes do crystalize</l>
               <l>The cloud-like waues of <hi>Neptunes</hi> liquid skies;</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Philomel</hi> in her pathetike straine</l>
               <l>For sommers losse in leauelesse woods complaine,</l>
               <l>Lest, when her dolefull ditties she doth sing</l>
               <l>She do disturbe the pleasance of our spring:</l>
               <l>But for <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow seeing he neuer sings,</l>
               <l>But when sweet <hi>Zephirus</hi> on gentle wings,</l>
               <l>Breathing good morrowes to the faire <hi>Aurora,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Begins each day to kisse his wanton <hi>Flora;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>We thinke it meete, that he be chiefe to sing,</l>
               <l>Where ere he meets the Ladie of the spring.</l>
               <l>And seeing, when earth hath lost her flowring May</l>
               <l>He cannot sing for greefe of her decay,</l>
               <l>Here let him stay, where he may euer sing</l>
               <l>Seeing heere with vs we haue eternall spring.</l>
               <l>This is our doome and thus we do debate</l>
               <l>The cause betwixt <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow and his mate.</l>
               <l>Thus hauing said, she ceast, and thereupon</l>
               <l>Such murmur, as we heare in woods, that grone,</l>
               <l>When winds rouz'd vp through hollow grounds do break,</l>
               <l>Such noise was heard 'mong'st those, that heard her speake;</l>
               <l>And all the quier of birds about the place</l>
               <l>Did droope and hang the head, for such disgrace</l>
               <l>To wronged <hi>Philomel,</hi> and for her sake,</l>
               <l>A mournefull melodie did seeme to make:</l>
               <l>But what alas auailes their discontent,</l>
               <l>Those partiall iudges rose, and with them went</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow singing his triumphant song,</l>
               <l>While <hi>Philomel</hi> bewailes her helpelesle wrong,</l>
               <l>Who being vniustly robbed of her right</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:13532:15"/>And from the bower of blisse exiled quite,</l>
               <l>Calling to mind, how that she once had been</l>
               <l>The happie daughter of a King and Queene,</l>
               <l>And since that she in shape of bird did liue,</l>
               <l>What honor <hi>Phoebes</hi> selfe to her did giue,</l>
               <l>Now from all future hope being quite cast downe,</l>
               <l>Orecome with griefe, she fell in suddaine swoune,</l>
               <l>And groueling in the dust on her sad brest,</l>
               <l>With deadly sorrowe being sore opprest,</l>
               <l>Poore bird she hung the wing and gasp'd for breath</l>
               <l>Seeming to yeeld vnto the panges of death;</l>
               <l>To whom her sister <hi>Progne</hi> standing by</l>
               <l>With speed to her recouery did flie,</l>
               <l>And houering ouer her, made pitious plaint</l>
               <l>For to reuiue her, that began to faint,</l>
               <l>Dead was her heart, to see her sister lie</l>
               <l>In such a traunce and often wish'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to die,</l>
               <l>Shee strock't her temples with her pretie beake</l>
               <l>And raysing vp her limbes, that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>re so weake,</l>
               <l>With gentle touch did feele each tender part,</l>
               <l>And stroue to strengthen her now dying heart:</l>
               <l>Vnto her aide the gentle Redbrest came,</l>
               <l>The Wren, and fruitfull Titmouse, that sterne dame,</l>
               <l>Who did applie their helpe at need so well,</l>
               <l>That now the slitting life of <hi>Philomel</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Halfe conquer'd with cold death, did make retreate</l>
               <l>Vnto the heart, the house of natiue heate;</l>
               <l>Which, when her sister <hi>Progne</hi> did espie</l>
               <l>These words of comfort, shee did soone applie;</l>
               <l>(Ay me) quoth she, (deare sister) thou that art</l>
               <l>Now made the image of vnpatient smart,</l>
               <l>Why dost thou not in these sad passions show</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:13532:16"/>Thy wonted patience in afflicting woe,</l>
               <l>And to our counsell lend thy listening eare,</l>
               <l>The which may teach thee patiently to beare</l>
               <l>This rufull sorrow, which doth stop thy breath</l>
               <l>And seekes to hasten thy vntimely death;</l>
               <l>Speake (o deare sister) speake, and tell vs why</l>
               <l>Thy soule with griefe opprest should seeke to die.</l>
               <l>She hauing said, the wofull <hi>Philomel,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whose sad soule all this while in traunce did dwell,</l>
               <l>Did lift vp th'heauie windowes of her eies</l>
               <l>And spake these rufull words in wofull wise.</l>
               <l>Tempestuous chaunce her vtmost spite hath spent,</l>
               <l>And at me wretch her vtmost dart hath sent,</l>
               <l>Nor any plague is left, that she can tell,</l>
               <l>With which t'oppresse the fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lorne <hi>Philomel.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For since the time, that I, as well you know</l>
               <l>Was, (woe alas that now I am not so)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pandions</hi> daughter in my virgins state,</l>
               <l>I haue endur'd sterne fortunes vtmost hate;</l>
               <l>Can I forget my <hi>Thracian</hi> slauerie</l>
               <l>Beneath false <hi>Tereus</hi> lustfull villanie,</l>
               <l>Or cease to thinke vpon my virgins rape,</l>
               <l>With losse of tongue and Ladies louely shape?</l>
               <l>Yea can I liue and leaue to haue in mind</l>
               <l>Fortunes last wrong, not least, but most vnkind,</l>
               <l>Those Nymphes late doome, I meane, by whose decree</l>
               <l>A forlorne outcast I shall euer bee?</l>
               <l>For from <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckowes song my shame doth spring</l>
               <l>And where alas, will not <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow sing?</l>
               <l>Sith then, to me poore wretch by cru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ll fate</l>
               <l>Naught else is left of former princely state?</l>
               <l>But shame and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>oe, why do I longer feed</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:13532:16"/>On loathed light, which wo afresh will breed?</l>
               <l>This said, she suncke againe in deadly swound:</l>
               <l>But <hi>Progne</hi> quickly rais'd her vp from ground,</l>
               <l>Thrice did she sincke as dead, and thrice againe</l>
               <l>Did <hi>Progne</hi> raise her vp with busie paine;</l>
               <l>At last, when life her setled place did take</l>
               <l>To comfort her, the little Wren thus spake:</l>
               <l>Now certes madame <hi>Philomel,</hi> quoth shee,</l>
               <l>You haue great cause of plaint we all do see,</l>
               <l>The which I weene would pierce the stoutest heart</l>
               <l>And launch the boldest brest with bleeding smart;</l>
               <l>Yet comfort to you take, and do not you</l>
               <l>Let passions rage rob reason of her due;</l>
               <l>Thinke with your selfe, as now too true it is,</l>
               <l>That in this pleasant place, this bower of blisse,</l>
               <l>Since that <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow findeth entertaine,</l>
               <l>For vs no certaine safetie doth remaine:</l>
               <l>For well we see the Nymphes of this same place</l>
               <l>Haue giuen ouer that same wonted chase</l>
               <l>Of harmefull beasts, which <hi>Phoebe</hi> did delite</l>
               <l>Following strange game with greedie appetite,</l>
               <l>Yea 'tis reported many <hi>Satyrs</hi> rude</l>
               <l>Into their company themselues intrude,</l>
               <l>By whose inticement you they did forsake</l>
               <l>In their false doome <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckowes part to take:</l>
               <l>Then do not greeue at this their vniust doome,</l>
               <l>Ne thinke your selfe disgrac'd as ouercome</l>
               <l>Before such dames; for grace it seemes to me</l>
               <l>To be disgrac'd of those, that gracelesse be:</l>
               <l>But swage your griefe in this so ruefull case,</l>
               <l>And go with vs vnto our dwelling place,</l>
               <l>Where though alone in desert place it be;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:13532:17"/>Yet there from feare of foes you shall be free:</l>
               <l>For as dame Titmouse and Redbrest can tell</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow seldome sings, where we do dwell,</l>
               <l>True, (neighbour Wren) the Redbrest did replie,</l>
               <l>We liue in safetie, though in penurie;</l>
               <l>And if dame <hi>Philomel</hi> with vs will go,</l>
               <l>Such kindnesse as poore Robbins bower can show</l>
               <l>She shall command, and though in that same wood,</l>
               <l>None of the courtly birds haue their abode;</l>
               <l>Yet there do many gentle singers dwell,</l>
               <l>That will be louing vnto <hi>Philomel.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yea; quoth the Titmouse, neither shall she there</l>
               <l>Of proud <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckowes thieatnings stand in feare.</l>
               <l>For all birds there his bastard note abhors</l>
               <l>And euermore do make him deadly wars,</l>
               <l>Twice sixe stout sonnes, at this same very houre</l>
               <l>I haue now liuing in my little bower,</l>
               <l>All which shall serue the wronged <hi>Philomel</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Against <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow, if with vs she dwell:</l>
               <l>Thus did these birds with gentle speech assay</l>
               <l>Sad <hi>Philomelaes</hi> greefe to driue away;</l>
               <l>But long it was, ere sorrow would depart,</l>
               <l>It was so deepely setled in her heart:</l>
               <l>Yet at the length the Swallow, <hi>Progne</hi> hight</l>
               <l>Did so perswade her, that she tooke her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>light</l>
               <l>With little Titmouse, Robbin and the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>en</l>
               <l>To desert woods farre from th'abodes of men:</l>
               <l>But <hi>Prognes</hi> selfe returned backe againe</l>
               <l>To <hi>Trinobant,</hi> where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> still <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>emaine:</l>
               <l>Thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ower o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>as <hi>Philomel</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Exil'd for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> woods to dwell</l>
               <l>While there <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> Cuckow as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bird did sing</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:13532:17"/>To tell the pleasures of the youthfull spring:</l>
               <l>The mansion house, in which poore <hi>Philomel,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Did with her new companions daily dwell,</l>
               <l>Was in a rocke, whose head it selfe did shroud</l>
               <l>In mistie cloake of many a wandring cloud,</l>
               <l>And whose thicke mossie sides and hollow wombe</l>
               <l>To many a bird did yeeld much building roome,</l>
               <l>It seated was downe in a valley low,</l>
               <l>Where many a siluer gliding streame did flow,</l>
               <l>And leauie woods in arbor wise did stand,</l>
               <l>As made by art, and not by natures hand.</l>
               <l>From right side of this rocke, there issued out</l>
               <l>A crystall spring which slowed round about</l>
               <l>The bottome of the rock, whose vpper brim</l>
               <l>Thick set with hearbes and flowers smelt sweet and trim:</l>
               <l>In th'hollow of this rock the humming swarmes</l>
               <l>Of honie flies, whose bodies nature armes</l>
               <l>With biting stings did beare a murmuring base</l>
               <l>vnto the spring, that trickling downe apace</l>
               <l>From of the rock did meanely seeme to warbble</l>
               <l>Among'st the pibble stones vnto the trebble,</l>
               <l>Which many prettie birds did seeme to sing,</l>
               <l>Houering about the rocke with painted wing:</l>
               <l>This was the place of <hi>Philomels</hi> abode</l>
               <l>With her companions in the desert wood,</l>
               <l>Where all the time of those long lasting houres,</l>
               <l>When as the heauenly crab with his eight oares</l>
               <l>Doth in the starrie <hi>Zodiack</hi> softly row,</l>
               <l>Felicitie did in abundance flow,</l>
               <l>Whereby faire <hi>Philomel</hi> did find no misse</l>
               <l>Of wonted pleasure in the bower of blisse:</l>
               <l>For there where curious art her helpe denide,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:13532:18"/>There natures selfe, that want with store supplide:</l>
               <l>If <hi>Boreas</hi> did at any time offend her</l>
               <l>The hollow rock a remedie did lend her:</l>
               <l>If <hi>Phoe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> hurt her with his fierie rayes,</l>
               <l>She found redresse beneath the leauie spraies,</l>
               <l>To whose coole shades she safely might retreate,</l>
               <l>When earth did crack beneath heauens burning heate:</l>
               <l>If she did hunger after wonted baite,</l>
               <l>The goodly fruit of euery tree did waite</l>
               <l>Vpon her will: yea much varietie</l>
               <l>Of painted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lies for her sati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>tie</l>
               <l>At hand in this her dwelling place she found,</l>
               <l>So fruitfull was this pleasant plot of ground:</l>
               <l>If she did thirst, or heate did her annoy,</l>
               <l>What pleasure did she take, what gladsome ioy</l>
               <l>Vnto the siluer gliding streame to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lie,</l>
               <l>That rowled through the bordering wood fast by:</l>
               <l>For when she stooping steep'd her tender beake</l>
               <l>Into the waue, it oft would seeme to breake,</l>
               <l>And feeling her soft bosome pant and beate</l>
               <l>Would bid her bath and quench her boiling heate:</l>
               <l>Meane time flowers seem'd to laugh and buds to spring,</l>
               <l>Trees seem'd to bloome and blossomes sorth to bring,</l>
               <l>And winds to coole the scorching of the sun,</l>
               <l>While by the brinke the currant smooth did run,</l>
               <l>Which oft did please this prettie bird so well,</l>
               <l>That in that place she still desir'd to dwell.</l>
               <l>But long alas, thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> pleasure did not last;</l>
               <l>For long it was not, ere the earth defac'd</l>
               <l>By winters sad approch was forc'd to leaue</l>
               <l>That pompe, which from the spring she did receaue;</l>
               <l>For what thing is't subelementarie,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:13532:18"/>That still continues and doth neuer varie?</l>
               <l>What thing retaines one forme that euer liues</l>
               <l>And place vnto another neuer giues?</l>
               <l>Alas, nought permanent with vs doth stay:</l>
               <l>For end and ofspring haue successiue sway:</l>
               <l>Eternall time, that auncient enemie</l>
               <l>To vading natures prodigalitie</l>
               <l>Remorselesse of all things with Sithe cuts downe</l>
               <l>The growing glorie of this earthes renowne;</l>
               <l>And as he flies with swift wings to and fro</l>
               <l>By his decree, all things do come and go.</l>
               <l>And so at length, where <hi>Philomel</hi> did dwell</l>
               <l>Sad winter came, and sommer bad farewell.</l>
               <l>With cold th'ayres lower region gan to shiuer</l>
               <l>And daily to the earth did downe deliuer</l>
               <l>The fleece-like yuorie flakes of heauenly snow,</l>
               <l>Which from the neighbour region fast did flow:</l>
               <l>For then from heauens point perpendicular</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hyperion</hi> in his spheare o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>bicular</l>
               <l>Running his wonted race with oblique course,</l>
               <l>His repercusse beames beat with lesser force</l>
               <l>Vpon his butt, the ball of earth, whereby</l>
               <l>A weake reflection, to our aire did flie:</l>
               <l>Then did the fruitfull earth begin to faint,</l>
               <l>When that warme wonted comfort it did want,</l>
               <l>Which from the gentle breathing aire should come,</l>
               <l>To cherish vp the fruit of her bigge wombe,</l>
               <l>Whose sorrowes wrathfull winter to augment</l>
               <l>Did muster vp his forces with intent</l>
               <l>To spoile her daughter sweet <hi>Pomonaes</hi> loues</l>
               <l>With her <hi>Autumnus</hi> in the shadie groues,</l>
               <l>Whom to withstand bold <hi>Auster,</hi> that braue Knight</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:13532:19"/>Ioyn'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>orces with <hi>Autumnus</hi> for the fight,</l>
               <l>And oftentimes brau'd <hi>Boreas</hi> in the field</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pomonaes</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>uits from his proud blasts to shield:</l>
               <l>But raging <hi>Hyems</hi> to inforce the warre</l>
               <l>All his bold Legions did reuoke from farre,</l>
               <l>Which in three battailes he did thus diuide</l>
               <l>To quell stout <hi>Auster</hi> and <hi>Autumnus</hi> pride,</l>
               <l>The hidio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s stormes, that beate downe brazen wals</l>
               <l>And horrid tempests that make tennis bals</l>
               <l>Of mightie mountaines in the vauntgard went</l>
               <l>To giue the onset with bold hardiment,</l>
               <l>Who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e stubborne rankes with haileshot did abound</l>
               <l>And drifts of snow their foe-men to confound,</l>
               <l>Whom lustie <hi>Bore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> full of daunting dread</l>
               <l>Did vnto boisterous battaile boldly lead:</l>
               <l>The middle ward, great <hi>Hyems</hi> selfe did guide,</l>
               <l>Who to the field like great god <hi>Mars</hi> did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ide:</l>
               <l>For on a winged cloud he sate on high</l>
               <l>Deckt in strange armour dreadfull to the ei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Vpon his breast a curac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> he did beare</l>
               <l>Ofycie mettall made, which far more cleare</l>
               <l>Then crystall shone: for like the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ystall skie</l>
               <l>It could subdue the gazers greedie eie,</l>
               <l>Thereby his blade did hang in snow-white sheath,</l>
               <l>With which he vs'd t'imploy works of cold death</l>
               <l>Mong'st those, that needie were, and could not arme</l>
               <l>themselues to sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>n the stroke of his strong arme,</l>
               <l>His y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ie Helmet powdered with white snow</l>
               <l>Great terror and bright glory both did show,</l>
               <l>And in the steade of plume stood thereupon</l>
               <l>A bunch ofysacles by nature growen;</l>
               <l>Which with pure snow being sprinckled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:13532:19"/>Did seeme to daunce and leape for iollitie:</l>
               <l>His shield, which at his back parts he did settle,</l>
               <l>Was neatly fram'd of Diamondlike mettell,</l>
               <l>Hewen out ofycie rocks in Scythian land</l>
               <l>By nature wrought, and not by Artists hand,</l>
               <l>On which for badge did stand in ramping p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ide</l>
               <l>Cold <hi>Capricorne</hi> the shiue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ing winters guide.</l>
               <l>In such like armes was wrathfull <hi>Hyems</hi> clad,</l>
               <l>Whose lookes a terror to his armes did adde:</l>
               <l>His browes contract aboue his gloomie eies,</l>
               <l>On which the hoarie hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s did bristled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ise,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Ioue</hi>-like looke with grim stiffe buggle beard</l>
               <l>Made his owne powers, that marcht by him, affeard,</l>
               <l>To gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rd his person round about him stood</l>
               <l>Whole hoastes of mists and many a roaring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>loud<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>And thus to field the second battell went</l>
               <l>Vnder conduct of <hi>Hyems</hi> regiment.</l>
               <l>The third <hi>Battalion</hi> to the field did goe</l>
               <l>Beneath great <hi>Eurus</hi> standard 'gainst the foe,</l>
               <l>Who being Lord of th'Easterne parts, that lie,</l>
               <l>Where great <hi>Apollo</hi> first doth mount the skie:</l>
               <l>Many bold bands of souldiers brought from farre;</l>
               <l>To serue the mightie <hi>Hyems</hi> in this warre;</l>
               <l>In seruice with him for light horsemen came,</l>
               <l>Those light swift winged winds, that beare the name</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Boreas</hi> and of <hi>Eurus</hi> both; for whom</l>
               <l>To serue in these same warres they all were come,</l>
               <l>With these th'humerous vapors ioyn'd their powers</l>
               <l>The gloomie fogs, and duskie drizeling showers,</l>
               <l>Whole troopes of drowzie mistes, of dewe and frost,</l>
               <l>Who of themselues could make a mightie h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ast<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>And thus did <hi>Hyems</hi> his whole powers diuide,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:13532:20"/>Which winged were with clouds on either side;</l>
               <l>Of whose approch when <hi>Autumne</hi> first did heare,</l>
               <l>His heart stroke dead, began to faint for feare:</l>
               <l>Yet calling mightie <hi>Auster</hi> to his aide</l>
               <l>And gentle <hi>Zephirus,</hi> his part he made,</l>
               <l>As able as he could, and boldly went</l>
               <l>To frustrate winter of his proud intent;</l>
               <l>Vnto his aide the King of forrests all</l>
               <l>Came backt with his consorts, whom some do call</l>
               <l>The tree of <hi>Ioue,</hi> with whom there came from farre</l>
               <l>Fields, forrests, woods, and groues vnto this warre:</l>
               <l>Thus did both parts prepare with all their might</l>
               <l>To meete each other in th'appointed fight.</l>
               <l>The time being come, before the fight b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>gan</l>
               <l>Downe from the hilles the torrents swiftly ran,</l>
               <l>As scouts from <hi>Hyems</hi> campe to take suruey</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Autumnes</hi> host, that in the valleyes lay,</l>
               <l>Which all the birds about both neere and farre</l>
               <l>Tooke as a warning of th'approching warre,</l>
               <l>And for themselues prouided all in hast</l>
               <l>Vntill the danger of the warre were past:</l>
               <l>Mong'st whom the little Redbrest with great care</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Philomel</hi> her friend did make repaire</l>
               <l>Vnto the rock, where she and <hi>Philomel</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This dangerous time might both in safetie dwell:</l>
               <l>Then came proud <hi>Hyems</hi> forward to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ight</l>
               <l>Downe from the ayrie mountaines that are pight</l>
               <l>In th'articke side, whereas the Dragons traine</l>
               <l>Diuides the wrathfull beares by <hi>Charles</hi> his waine:</l>
               <l>The battels ioyn'd, and both the hosts did meet,</l>
               <l>Whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e lustie <hi>Auster</hi> cuffe for cuffe did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>reet</l>
               <l>The migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ie <hi>Boreas</hi> selfe, whose verie breath</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:13532:20"/>Did powder-like blast other foes to death:</l>
               <l>Then came the stormes and tempests to the fight</l>
               <l>In blacke, fresh, gloomie horror all bedight,</l>
               <l>With smouldering fume, thick driftes of drizeling raine,</l>
               <l>Commixt with haileshot, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ull of deadly bane,</l>
               <l>Who at the first their foes did soone confound,</l>
               <l>Rending vp woods and forrests from the ground,</l>
               <l>Whose leauie heads disperst about did flie,</l>
               <l>Tost to and fro, like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eathers in the skie:</l>
               <l>Then to the reskew with the westerne King</l>
               <l>Milde <hi>Zephirus,</hi> came <hi>Autumne,</hi> who did bring</l>
               <l>Many swift winged winds, who with great might</l>
               <l>At first in counter did renue the fight:</l>
               <l>For many iustling clouds, that came in course</l>
               <l>With bold intent to beare their violent force</l>
               <l>Being hem'd in round about, could not abide,</l>
               <l>But deadly wounded were on euery side,</l>
               <l>Who fearing in their cloudie shapes to die</l>
               <l>In humerous thin drops away did flie:</l>
               <l>But now to gaine the glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ie of the day,</l>
               <l>Loe, <hi>Eurus</hi> came, who at his first assay</l>
               <l>By violent force did end the doubtfull fight</l>
               <l>And turn'd his foes into inglorious flight.</l>
               <l>Meane time, great <hi>Autumne</hi> tooke his loue aside,</l>
               <l>His faire <hi>Pomonas</hi> selfe, whom he did hide</l>
               <l>In wooden walles of forrests, woods and groues,</l>
               <l>From mightie <hi>Hyems</hi> false inueigling loues,</l>
               <l>While he with <hi>Zephirus</hi> and <hi>Auster</hi> flew</l>
               <l>To <hi>Tytans</hi> Westerne house, there to renew</l>
               <l>Their powers 'gainst <hi>Aries</hi> should the yeare recall</l>
               <l>To free <hi>Pomona</hi> from great <hi>Hyems</hi> thrall:</l>
               <l>Meane time great winter in triumphant wise</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:13532:21"/>Ouer his captiue foes did tyrannize,</l>
               <l>The siluer brookes that sweetly wound about</l>
               <l>The pleasant bankes with wreathings in and out,</l>
               <l>With Adamantine-like strong ycie bands,</l>
               <l>He fast did bind within the hollow lands:</l>
               <l>The Crystall springs, that from the mountaines side</l>
               <l>With pleasing sound to ground did gently glide</l>
               <l>And brackish streames, that gushed from the rock</l>
               <l>With strong congealed frost he vp did lock:</l>
               <l>The slowring fields, woods, hilles and mountaines greene</l>
               <l>And valleyes, that before to laugh were seene,</l>
               <l>In stead of fresh greene colour, now were clad</l>
               <l>In h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>arie hue, that made them looke full sad;</l>
               <l>Yea euery thing, for want of heate halfe dead</l>
               <l>In winters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, droop't and hung the head:</l>
               <l>Yet all this time of winters wrathfull reigne,</l>
               <l>When all things did in deepe distresse complaine,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow in the bower of blisse did sing</l>
               <l>His ioyfull note, where dwels eternall spring:</l>
               <l>Where, while that he did liue both day and night</l>
               <l>Drencht in the daintie dregs of deepe delight,</l>
               <l>With little Redbrest forlorne <hi>Philomel</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In hollow rock in consolate did dwell,</l>
               <l>Where she poore bird in many a dolefull straine</l>
               <l>The Nymphes late vniust doome did much complaine,</l>
               <l>Which was the cause of all her miserie,</l>
               <l>That liu'd before in chiefe felicitie.</l>
               <l>The state, which fortune erst to her did giue</l>
               <l>Compar'd to this, in which she now did liue,</l>
               <l>Did trebble sorrow on her dying heart</l>
               <l>A fresh reuiuing her forgotten smart,</l>
               <l>For miserie to those most bitter is,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:13532:21"/>That tasted once the sweets of happie blisse,</l>
               <l>Which little Redbrest did perceiue right well</l>
               <l>In her companion gentle <hi>Philomel:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For once when <hi>Philomel</hi> and she together</l>
               <l>In hollow rocke sate shrowded from the weather</l>
               <l>Still as the Redbrest in sweet notes did sing</l>
               <l>A sad complaint for absence of the spring,</l>
               <l>So did poore <hi>Philomel</hi> her griefe to show</l>
               <l>In sad record recount her former woe:</l>
               <l>To whom the Redbrest mou'd with melting pitie</l>
               <l>To heare the sad tunes of her dolefull dittie,</l>
               <l>These words of comfort spake: (sister) quoth she,</l>
               <l>I see that winters blasts dispeasant be,</l>
               <l>And in your thoughts renewes the memorie</l>
               <l>Of your precedent liues felicitie,</l>
               <l>Whereby I know, your sorrow is the more,</l>
               <l>That haplesse now liu'd happie heretofore:</l>
               <l>But now vnto my words your listening lend,</l>
               <l>By which perhaps your sorrowes may haue end:</l>
               <l>Each yeare, when winter cause of all our woe,</l>
               <l>Vpon these woods with cold keene breath doth blow,</l>
               <l>From hence compeld I vsually do flie,</l>
               <l>To famous <hi>Trynobantum,</hi> here fast by,</l>
               <l>Whereas your sister <hi>Progne</hi> builds her bowers,</l>
               <l>Safe from the threates of winters stormie showers,</l>
               <l>For heauen that heere lookes grim with gloomie face</l>
               <l>With milde aspect beholds that happie place,</l>
               <l>There, not as heere th'inhabitants do know</l>
               <l>Cold winters rage, nor doth proud <hi>Bore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> blow</l>
               <l>So sharpe and keene: but in the welkin faire</l>
               <l>The milder windes do tosse the gentle aire;</l>
               <l>There also many gentle Nymphes do dwell,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:13532:22"/>That may compare with those that do excell</l>
               <l>In beautie bright; for eye did neuer see</l>
               <l>More faire then in great <hi>Trynobantum</hi> be,</l>
               <l>To whom I do not doubt, if that we go,</l>
               <l>But they to <hi>Philomel</hi> will fauour show,</l>
               <l>And though those Nymphes, that in the bower of blisse</l>
               <l>Haue their abode, 'gainst thee haue done amisse:</l>
               <l>Yet they no doubt will pitie thy complaint</l>
               <l>And driue <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow from great <hi>Trynobant;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And in our way, as we together slie</l>
               <l>Lest we be destitute of company,</l>
               <l>In this our iorney with vs well I know</l>
               <l>Our neighbours Titmouse and dame Wren wil go:</l>
               <l>Then be not sad, helpe neuer comes too late,</l>
               <l>And time perhaps may turne your froward fate.</l>
               <l>This said, sad <hi>Philomel</hi> no answere made</l>
               <l>But making doubt of that, which Redbrest said,</l>
               <l>Sometimes she thought it best to liue content</l>
               <l>In th'hollow rock all danger to preuent:</l>
               <l>But when proud <hi>Boreas</hi> blasts her heart did daunt,</l>
               <l>She thought it best to flie to <hi>Trynobant.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus diuers doubts did in her thoughts arise,</l>
               <l>Nor what was best to do could she deuise,</l>
               <l>Vntill her neighbours Wren and Titmouse came,</l>
               <l>Who with perswasiue speech her mind did frame</l>
               <l>To <hi>Trynobant</hi> with them along to go,</l>
               <l>Vnto the faire Nymphes there, her cause to show,</l>
               <l>To trie if they for <hi>Castaes</hi> sake would chase</l>
               <l>The vnchaste Cuckow from their dwelling place:</l>
               <l>Thus by perswasion of those prettie birds,</l>
               <l>The gentle <hi>Philomela</hi> soone accords</l>
               <l>To go with them, though, as it came to passe,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:13532:22"/>The sequell prou'd their labour fruitlesse was.</l>
               <l>For in their iourney loe, as they did flee,</l>
               <l>Taking their couert slight from tree to tree,</l>
               <l>Not daring to be seene in open skie,</l>
               <l>About great <hi>Trynobant</hi> they did espie</l>
               <l>The swift-wing'd swallow making her strong flight,</l>
               <l>Sister to <hi>Philomela, Progne</hi> hight;</l>
               <l>To whom right glad they tooke their ready way</l>
               <l>Each one recording her deligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>some lay,</l>
               <l>Which did so loudly echo in the ayre,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Progne</hi> heard it, as they came from farre,</l>
               <l>And drawing nie to know what it might be</l>
               <l>Staying her swift strong flight loe, she did see</l>
               <l>Her sister <hi>Philomel</hi> with other birds,</l>
               <l>To whom with wonderment she spake these words;</l>
               <l>(O heauens) what chaunce is this, what see I heere</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pandions Philomel,</hi> my sister deare?</l>
               <l>Alas, what sad mishap is now befell,</l>
               <l>That you haue left the place where you did dwell,</l>
               <l>Great perill, which I wot you little know,</l>
               <l>In comming hither, you do vndergoe.</l>
               <l>Sister, (said <hi>Philomel</hi>) no great mischaunce</l>
               <l>Hath happened vnto me, nor ignorance</l>
               <l>Of perill in the way hath made me bold:</l>
               <l>But forc'd by stormie winters bitter cold.</l>
               <l>My friends and I haue lately left our home</l>
               <l>And for reliefe to <hi>Trynobant</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e come,</l>
               <l>Where you do liue in chiefe felicitie,</l>
               <l>Free from the thrall of winters tyrannie.</l>
               <l>Alas, (good sister) <hi>Progne</hi> did replie,</l>
               <l>Let not that vaine opinion in your eie</l>
               <l>Go currant, which the idiot multitude</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:13532:23"/>Out of blind ignorance doth still conclude,</l>
               <l>That meane estate is greatest miserie</l>
               <l>And high esteeme the chiefe felicitie:</l>
               <l>For high or low, rich are not rich indeed,</l>
               <l>And great states still on discontent do feed.</l>
               <l>What dreadfull danger dogs him at the heele,</l>
               <l>That proudly vaunts on top of Fortunes wheele?</l>
               <l>What daunting dread his Stealing steps attend,</l>
               <l>Whose climing thoughts do ayme at honors end?</l>
               <l>Who feares to fall, but he that sits on high,</l>
               <l>Or feeles th'infection of an enuious eie?</l>
               <l>For enuy euermore her poison spits</l>
               <l>At those, that most in fortunes fauour sits,</l>
               <l>The heauie care, that wounds the mind with woe</l>
               <l>Seldome forsakes the giddie feet that goe,</l>
               <l>Where treades the steps of high authoritie,</l>
               <l>So fleeting is this earthes felicitie:</l>
               <l>For wauering chaunce about him still doth flie,</l>
               <l>That proudly seekes to build his hopes on high,</l>
               <l>Of which a president, I well may bee</l>
               <l>Vnto you all, such is my chaunce you see:</l>
               <l>For fate and nature hauing both decreed,</l>
               <l>That I in loftie tops of towers should breed,</l>
               <l>While you my happie sister <hi>Philomel</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Should in the woods and forrests safely dwell,</l>
               <l>About the bower of blisse once did not I,</l>
               <l>A long time safely build my bowers on high,</l>
               <l>Till by my foes, they all were ouerthrowne</l>
               <l>And young ones slaine, which I shall euer mone:</l>
               <l>For those false Nymphes which sentence gaue 'gainst thee</l>
               <l>On proud <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckowes side, did all agree,</l>
               <l>Because beneath the windowes of their towers</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:13532:23"/>My custome was to build my secret bowers,</l>
               <l>That I for euer should be chased thence</l>
               <l>To seeke my fortunes though for no offence:</l>
               <l>For loe no crime 'gainst me they could obiect,</l>
               <l>But that because, they said I did detect</l>
               <l>Their chamber sports, and truth to say mine eye</l>
               <l>Such obscene sports did oft times there espie,</l>
               <l>That very shame bids me forbeare to tell</l>
               <l>The nuptiall band-breake play, that there befell:</l>
               <l>Wherfore from thence long since they did me chase,</l>
               <l>Since when I liued haue in this same place,</l>
               <l>Whereas you say, I build my lowly bowers</l>
               <l>Safe from the threates of winters stormie showers:</l>
               <l>Yet in such feare of those, that vse to feed</l>
               <l>On beauties spoile, about whose bowers I breed:</l>
               <l>That would my fate had been to liue alone</l>
               <l>In forrests wide, though winter made me mone.</l>
               <l>She hauing said, this answere Redbrest made:</l>
               <l>Certes (dame <hi>Progne</hi>) you haue wisely said,</l>
               <l>For better 'tis to liue we all agree</l>
               <l>In meane estate content, from danger free,</l>
               <l>Then in the blind worlds deem'd felicitie</l>
               <l>In trouble, care and minds perplexitie;</l>
               <l>But we to <hi>Trynobant</hi> not only come,</l>
               <l>For that we grieue at winters blasts at home:</l>
               <l>But seeing many a bright cheek'd gentle dame</l>
               <l>Dwels heere in <hi>Trynobant</hi> we hither came,</l>
               <l>That so thy sister <hi>Philomel</hi> might trie,</l>
               <l>If they for loue to honor'd chastitie</l>
               <l>Would driue <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow from this place with shame</l>
               <l>And raise againe sad <hi>Castaes</hi> dying name.</l>
               <l>To this thus <hi>Progne</hi> did returne replie.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:13532:24"/>Alas (good Redbrest) thy fraile shallow eie</l>
               <l>Nought but th'externall <hi>species</hi> doth behold,</l>
               <l>Deeming all things that gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ster perfect gold:</l>
               <l>Each winter, when thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ither dost repaire</l>
               <l>Our Nymphes being spree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ly vigorous and faire,</l>
               <l>Thou deem'st their minds to be as wise and wittie,</l>
               <l>As in proportion, they be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>aire and prettie:</l>
               <l>But thou art blind; for do but marke with me</l>
               <l>Their witlesse actions, and thou soone shalt see</l>
               <l>Their faire but foule; their wit, but wanton will,</l>
               <l>Their wisedomes quintessence loues idle skill,</l>
               <l>For heere in <hi>Trynobant</hi> with their consent</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow sings his layes with meriment,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> no more on <hi>Ida</hi> hilles is seene,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Paphos</hi> temples, nor <hi>Cytheron</hi> greene:</l>
               <l>But long ago hath bid them all farewell</l>
               <l>Heere in great <hi>Trynobant</hi> with vs to dwell:</l>
               <l>For heere the lustie Queene of loue adornes</l>
               <l>The poore <hi>Cer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>stes</hi> with the welked hornes,</l>
               <l>Here the <hi>Propoetides</hi> deuoid of sense,</l>
               <l>Those women pictures of true impudence,</l>
               <l>By the great power of loues luxurious Queene</l>
               <l>Are turn'd to stones, women no more are seene.</l>
               <l>For which <hi>Pigmalion</hi> leads a single life</l>
               <l>And feares strange things, not daring weda wife.</l>
               <l>She <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> spoken, all the other birds</l>
               <l>Long sil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nt stood amaz'd at those her words</l>
               <l>Till I it mouse spake, quoth she, what you do tell</l>
               <l>Is verie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>range and we perceiue right well,</l>
               <l>That gentle <hi>Casta</hi> here shall find small <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Seeing such strange Nymphes do d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ll in this same place:</l>
               <l>But what doth cause them with such impudence</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:13532:24"/>In spite of modesties pure excellence,</l>
               <l>So much degenerate from heauenly kind?</l>
               <l>Sure pinching want doth much oppresse the minde:</l>
               <l>Or el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e with <hi>Danae</hi> for loue of g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ld</l>
               <l>They kindly suffer friends to be too bold.</l>
               <l>No certes (Titmouse) <hi>Progne</hi> did repli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Nor loue of gold, nor pinching penurie:</l>
               <l>But plentie, pleasure, ease and idlenesse,</l>
               <l>Is cause of their deare deem'd voluptuousnes,</l>
               <l>Whereby they oft times rather giue then take</l>
               <l>The golden gifts, that minds immodest make,</l>
               <l>Heere need not <hi>loue</hi> come take a sleepelesse nap</l>
               <l>With golden showers in <hi>Danaes</hi> louely lap.</l>
               <l>For heere our lustie <hi>Danaes,</hi> if he want</l>
               <l>Will shower downe gold on him, if he but graunt:</l>
               <l>In nights black vaile, he need not hide his head</l>
               <l>If he intend to got' <hi>Amphytrions</hi> bed,</l>
               <l>For th' <hi>Alcumenaes</hi> here both day and night</l>
               <l>Will meet him any where for loues delight,</l>
               <l>If <hi>Daphne</hi> heere do runne, she slackes her pace</l>
               <l>Till <hi>Phoebus</hi> catch her, whom she must embrace,</l>
               <l>And heere if louely <hi>Syrinx</hi> do intend</l>
               <l>To runne from rugged <hi>Pan:</hi> yet in the end</l>
               <l>She seeming faint her swifter course will stay,</l>
               <l>That she may be the pipe, when <hi>Pan</hi> doth play:</l>
               <l>For neither <hi>Pans</hi> high hornes nor rugged beard</l>
               <l>Can make the Nymphes in this same place affeard.</l>
               <l>Fie, fie (dame <hi>Progne</hi>) quoth the little Wren,</l>
               <l>In sooth 'gainst them, thou hast too bitter been,</l>
               <l>I do not thinke that such incontinence</l>
               <l>Can lurke beneath the glorious excellence</l>
               <l>Of such rare beautie, which doth seeme t'exce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:13532:25"/>In these faire dames, that in this place do dwell;</l>
               <l>Yet if in them such light demeanor be,</l>
               <l>Doubtlesse they do not make it knowne to thee,</l>
               <l>How then canst thou such things, as these relate</l>
               <l>With their close deeds not being intimate?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Progne</hi> replied; vnwisely haue you said</l>
               <l>Me with vntruth vngentlie to vpbraid;</l>
               <l>For know dame Wren, that what I late did show</l>
               <l>Is nothing in respect of that I know:</l>
               <l>For in my neast built wondrous by my wit</l>
               <l>Beneath their chamber-windowes I do sit,</l>
               <l>Where if your selfe were present but one day,</l>
               <l>You would speake more then lately I did say.</l>
               <l>For there oft times I do both see and heare</l>
               <l>Those things that shame to tell bids me forbeare.</l>
               <l>This said, the other birds all silent sate</l>
               <l>As modestly for bearing, t'aske of that</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Prognes</hi> selfe did seeme halfe sham'd to tell,</l>
               <l>Vntill at last spake gentle <hi>Philomel,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And said (deare sister) hide not what you know;</l>
               <l>Because the thing breeds shame which thou shalt show</l>
               <l>For to the author of the sin be shame,</l>
               <l>Not vnto him, that's guiltlesse in the same,</l>
               <l>Nor should examples of immodestie</l>
               <l>Offend the modest eares of chastitie,</l>
               <l>For vertues glorious shine, then shines most bright,</l>
               <l>When 'tis oppos'd to vice her opposite,</l>
               <l>As whitest things seeme fair<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>st to the eye,</l>
               <l>When they be match'd with blacke their contrarie.</l>
               <l>Wherefore (dearesister) speake and boldly tell</l>
               <l>The shamelesse deeds of dames that heere do dwell,</l>
               <l>So shall we sing about the world so wide,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:13532:25"/>That which their chamber wals now seeme to hide,</l>
               <l>Of which perhaps when they hereafter heare</l>
               <l>To do the like hence forth they will forbeare.</l>
               <l>She hauing said, thus <hi>Progne</hi> made replie:</l>
               <l>If that ye will (yebirds) that I descrie</l>
               <l>And draw the curtaines of the vnchaste bed,</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> hornes old <hi>Vulcans</hi> head,</l>
               <l>Come neare and listen, lest the obscene sound</l>
               <l>Of my strange speech do in the ayre abound,</l>
               <l>And in the same do breed corruption,</l>
               <l>From whence may spring a foule infection</l>
               <l>Of those hot furious, fierie, lustfull beasts,</l>
               <l>That toil'd with lust, do loath loues vulgar feasts,</l>
               <l>Whom nature cannot furnish with excesse</l>
               <l>In kind-like game: but that some monstrous messe</l>
               <l>They do affect, I will not heere speake much</l>
               <l>Lest I offend; my meaning is of such</l>
               <l>As imitate Romes <hi>Semiramida,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or that Italian <hi>Cortigiana,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And put in practise th'art of <hi>Aretine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>At which both heauen and nature doth repine,</l>
               <l>And with that Lybian lustfull foule <hi>Syrena,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That woman monster <hi>Dodecamechana</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In <hi>Venus</hi> act deuise twelue sundrie measures</l>
               <l>With lustie lads at full to take their pleasures;</l>
               <l>Nor will I tell, though many be of these</l>
               <l>That with <hi>Athlanta</hi> and <hi>Hyppomenes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Do <hi>Stalion</hi>-like run madding out of season</l>
               <l>To quench their lust, 'gainst nature and 'gainst reason;</l>
               <l>Nor here to shew to you is my intent</l>
               <l>That execrable squirtlike instrument,</l>
               <l>Which lust burnt, fierie, female monsters vse</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:13532:26"/>In fruitlesse lust, to natures vile abuse:</l>
               <l>For these are things not fitting speech of birds:</l>
               <l>But best befitting roughest <hi>Salyrs</hi> words.</l>
               <l>I only here intend to make report</l>
               <l>Of that same common counted cuckow sport,</l>
               <l>Which by our dames is deem'd a lawfull game,</l>
               <l>Though impudence it selfe blush at the same,</l>
               <l>(I meane of th'old <hi>Malbeccoes</hi> of our age)</l>
               <l>Who iustly beare <hi>Cornuted Vulcans</hi> badge.</l>
               <l>In <hi>Trynobant</hi> as to and fro I flie</l>
               <l>It hath been oftentimes my chaunce t'espie</l>
               <l>An old cold <hi>Ianuarie</hi> iet before</l>
               <l>A fresh young <hi>May,</hi> a spreetly <hi>Helinore,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Vnequall both in yeares and in affection,</l>
               <l>And also far vnlike in their condition;</l>
               <l>Yet to the blind-ey'd world it did appeare,</l>
               <l>That <hi>May</hi> did loue her <hi>Ianuarie</hi> deare;</l>
               <l>Which I scarse trusting with a curious eie</l>
               <l>Haue closely trackt their steps the truth to trie:</l>
               <l>And loe, while he hath set his thoughts vpon</l>
               <l>His horded heapes, his <hi>May</hi> being left alone,</l>
               <l>He being close at his accounts aboue,</l>
               <l>While she beneath sits longing after loue,</l>
               <l>In steps me <hi>March</hi> clad like a lustie Knight,</l>
               <l>Or pleasant <hi>Aprill</hi> full of sweet delight,</l>
               <l>Who in loues wanton art, not wanting skill</l>
               <l>Hath slights enow t'assault fresh <hi>May</hi> at will;</l>
               <l>But what needs long assault where none doth shield;</l>
               <l>For gentle heart she is as prone to yeeld,</l>
               <l>As he t'assault, which well this younker knowes,</l>
               <l>Though seeming strange a while with her he glose,</l>
               <l>For by her touching, stroking, gentle pressing,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:13532:26"/>Her rubbing, wringing, wrestling, wanton thrusting,</l>
               <l>Coy looking, culling and kind inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>taine</l>
               <l>He finds enough and knowes he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> meaning plaine:</l>
               <l>For gentle <hi>May</hi> no proffer'd time will lose,</l>
               <l>When as from home old <hi>Ianuar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> goes,</l>
               <l>And then the vnchaste kisses common flies,</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Hymens</hi> strongest nuptiall bands vnties,</l>
               <l>Then beautie sets the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>es of lust on fire,</l>
               <l>And fancie breakes forth into strong desire,</l>
               <l>And lastly lust doth in a moment space</l>
               <l>Make <hi>Ianuaries</hi> browes bud forth apace,</l>
               <l>Which neither he, nor any else do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Though it be commonly well knowne to me:</l>
               <l>For these be obiects common to my sight,</l>
               <l>As in my bowers I sit, both day and night.</l>
               <l>Then say ye birds, if in this place can dwell</l>
               <l>My sister <hi>Casta</hi> gentle <hi>Philomel.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ay me, quoth <hi>Philomel,</hi> the more my griefe,</l>
               <l>That I poore wretch can no where find reliefe:</l>
               <l>For where alas, shall <hi>Casta</hi> find a place,</l>
               <l>Where proud <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow sings not her disgrace?</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Phoebes</hi> name is now extincted quite,</l>
               <l>Whose fame whilom the golden starres did smite,</l>
               <l>Where else are her faire Nymphes, whose beauties blaze</l>
               <l>Did decke the world with like to <hi>Phoebus</hi> raies,</l>
               <l>Who with the slower of heauenly chastitie</l>
               <l>Their beauties garland did so dignifie,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Venus</hi> brat, though deem'd a god of power,</l>
               <l>With all his flames could neuer scorch their flower?</l>
               <l>But now alas, faire <hi>Phoebes</hi> daintie rose,</l>
               <l>Which many Nymphes did in their brests inclose,</l>
               <l>And with great care did tender it more deare,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:13532:27"/>Then dearest life, doth no where now appeare,</l>
               <l>Else why doth <hi>Casta</hi> suffer such disgrace,</l>
               <l>While that the Cuckow sings in euery place.</l>
               <l>As thus she spake, not far they did espie,</l>
               <l>How proud <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow to and fro did flie,</l>
               <l>Who vaunting in the ayre with outstretch'd wing</l>
               <l>His bastard note triumphantly did sing;</l>
               <l>At whom the Swallow, Robbin and the Wren,</l>
               <l>And Titmouse, as if they inrag'd had been,</l>
               <l>With eager thoughts did flie, whom they in chase</l>
               <l>A long time did pursue from place to place,</l>
               <l>Oft did they flap him with their feathered quils,</l>
               <l>And peckt and beat him with their tender bils,</l>
               <l>Vntill from out of sight he quite was fled</l>
               <l>And in some couert place had hid his head:</l>
               <l>But they returning backe, where making mone,</l>
               <l>They late had left poore <hi>Philomel</hi> alone,</l>
               <l>Loe, they beheld, how she poore bird did sit</l>
               <l>Halfe dead with torment of her wofull fit,</l>
               <l>To whom poore birds being mou'd with inelting pitie</l>
               <l>Each one did striue to tune her dolefull dittie,</l>
               <l>Long sate they sympathizing in their song</l>
               <l>The wofull record of poore <hi>Castaes</hi> wrong,</l>
               <l>Nor of sweet comfort could they ought partake,</l>
               <l>Vntill at length the little Wren thus spake:</l>
               <l>(My louing friends and fellow birds) quoth she,</l>
               <l>Great griefe doth vex your troubled thoughts I see:</l>
               <l>But fond it is in sorrow still to dwell</l>
               <l>And seeke no meanes sad sorrow to expell:</l>
               <l>For griefe, that breeds despaire, nere finds reliefe,</l>
               <l>When good aduice doth master greatest griefe;</l>
               <l>Then know, that though no Nymph of this same place</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:13532:27"/>Nor of the bower of blisse will take to grace,</l>
               <l>The forlorne <hi>Casta, Phoebes</hi> only bird,</l>
               <l>Yet meaner places may perchaunce afford</l>
               <l>Some gentle dame, although of meane degree,</l>
               <l>That vnto <hi>Philomel</hi> would gratious be;</l>
               <l>And well do I remember, in that place</l>
               <l>There wonnes a vertuous Nymph of goodly grace;</l>
               <l>Where I do safely build my lowly bowers</l>
               <l>To shrowd my selfe from winters stormie showers:</l>
               <l>In humble cottage she doth still remaine,</l>
               <l>The happie daughter of a countrie swaine,</l>
               <l>And though she liue vpon meane maintenance,</l>
               <l>Yet with such grace and goodly gouernance,</l>
               <l>She doth demeane her selfe, that many be</l>
               <l>Of greater state, that want her genterie,</l>
               <l>For little would ye weene, that such great grace</l>
               <l>Had any lodging in so meane a place,</l>
               <l>She hath to wit hight <hi>Virgina</hi> to name,</l>
               <l>Who though but meane, yet of exceeding fame:</l>
               <l>For loe, that Squier, that liues in deepe despaire</l>
               <l>Of gaining grace of <hi>Columbel</hi> the faire,</l>
               <l>Vnto an endlesse taske by her being ti'd</l>
               <l>To wander each where, through the world so wide,</l>
               <l>To proue how many damsels he could find,</l>
               <l>That chastely did retaine a constant mind,</l>
               <l>Did of three hundred dames find but this one,</l>
               <l>That vnto loues delight would not be wonne:</l>
               <l>Then (gentle <hi>Philomel</hi>) lay by thy griefe,</l>
               <l>And of this dame let vs go seeke reliefe,</l>
               <l>Vpon whose bosome thou maiest sit and sing</l>
               <l>The virgin beautie of her youthfull spring,</l>
               <l>Where proud <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow dares not come in place,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:13532:28"/>Much lesse dares sing his layes in thy disgrace.</l>
               <l>The Wren thus hauing spoke, the other birds</l>
               <l>With <hi>Castaes</hi> selfe did like well of her words,</l>
               <l>And with the Wren would straight vnto that wood,</l>
               <l>Where that same virgin dame had her abode:</l>
               <l>But gentle <hi>Progne</hi> she must stay behind,</l>
               <l>As being forbidden by the fates vnkind;</l>
               <l>Since her in shape of bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d they first did hide,</l>
               <l>Nere to frequent the woods and forrests wide;</l>
               <l>Parting therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rom her with weeping e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>es</l>
               <l>Her sister <hi>Philomel</hi> spake in this wise.</l>
               <l>Sister (quoth she) the stubbome fates decree,</l>
               <l>That from each other we must parted bee:</l>
               <l>For thou alas maiest not frequent the wood,</l>
               <l>Nor may I come, where thou hast thy abode:</l>
               <l>For now (aye me) hard hap doth me compell</l>
               <l>Vnto the bower of blisse, to bid farewell,</l>
               <l>And vnto <hi>Trynobant,</hi> where woe is mee</l>
               <l>My dearest sister thou shalt liue and see</l>
               <l>My hatefull foe, <hi>Dan</hi> Cuckow proudly sing</l>
               <l>In my dispight to welcome in the spring:</l>
               <l>But must we then alas, for euer part,</l>
               <l>The thought of which augments our wofull smart,</l>
               <l>Must thus <hi>Pandions</hi> daughters bid farewell,</l>
               <l>For euer in the world apart to dwell?</l>
               <l>We must alas: wherefore compel'd by fate,</l>
               <l>Whose malice heauen it selfe may not abate,</l>
               <l>Vnto the world and thee I bid farewell</l>
               <l>In desert woods for euermore to dwell.</l>
               <l>Thus hauing said, both did with wofull heart</l>
               <l>Each from the other heauily depart,</l>
               <l>Sad <hi>Progne</hi> back to <hi>Trynobant</hi> did flie,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:13532:28"/>And gentle <hi>Philomel</hi> in companie</l>
               <l>Of little Redbrest, Titmouse and the Wren,</l>
               <l>Did take her way far from the abodes of men</l>
               <l>Vnto that place, where dwelt that gentle dame,</l>
               <l>Of whom the Wren did speake: where when she came,</l>
               <l>Of that faire Nymph she found such intertaine,</l>
               <l>That neuer more she thence return'd againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
