<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle of the reuerend father in God Hieronymus Osorius Bishop of Arcoburge in Portugale, to the most excellent Princesse Elizabeth by the grace of God Quene of England, Fraunce, and Ireland, &amp;c. Translated oute of Latten in to Englishe by Richard Shacklock M. of Arte and student of the ciuill Lawes in Louaine</title>
            <title>Epistola ad serenissimam Elisabetam, Angliae Reginam. English</title>
            <author>Osório, Jerónimo, 1506-1580.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1565</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 85 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-03">2003-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08567</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18887</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101135</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836958</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836958</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1259</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A08567)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1259)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 968:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle of the reuerend father in God Hieronymus Osorius Bishop of Arcoburge in Portugale, to the most excellent Princesse Elizabeth by the grace of God Quene of England, Fraunce, and Ireland, &amp;c. Translated oute of Latten in to Englishe by Richard Shacklock M. of Arte and student of the ciuill Lawes in Louaine</title>
                  <title>Epistola ad serenissimam Elisabetam, Angliae Reginam. English</title>
                  <author>Osório, Jerónimo, 1506-1580.</author>
                  <author>Shacklock, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>78, [2] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ægidius Diest,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Antwerp :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno M. D. LXV. [1565]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by Richard Shacklock, of: Osòrio, Jerònimo.  Epistola ad serenissimam Elizabetam, Angliæ reginam.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A pearle for a prynce.</note>
                  <note>Errata of earlier edition, STC 18888, corrected.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Yale University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Elizabeth --  I, --  Queen of England, 1533-1603 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-12</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1259:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1259:1"/>
            <p>AN EPISTLE
of the Reuerend father in God
<hi>HIERONYMVS OSORIVS BISHOP</hi>
of Arcoburge in Portugale, to the most
excellent Princesse <hi>ELIZABETH</hi>
by the grace of God Quene of
England, Fraunce, and
Ireland. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Translated oute of Latten in to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glishe
by Richard Shacklock M. of
Arte and student of the Ciuill
Lawes in Louaine.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at Antwerp by Aegidius Diest,
Anno M.D.LXV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:1259:2"/>
            <head>THE TRANSLATOVR.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>SEYLAN</hi> an Ile of florishing fame</l>
               <l>VVith pretious pearles was wont to excell,</l>
               <l>But now it hath lost that notable name,</l>
               <l>And Portugale for pearles beareth the bell.</l>
               <l>All spirituall goldsmythes can wytnes this well,</l>
               <l>That this pearle sent from Portugale grounde,</l>
               <l>Surmou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth al pearles which in Seylan are fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This pearle of greate price <hi>Osorius</hi> hath sent</l>
               <l>To a pearlesse Princesse our excellent Quene</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>ELIZABETH</hi> of England most Royall regent,</l>
               <l>God grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t her grace take it as the giuer did mene.</l>
               <l>Th<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e pretious pearles plentie shall in England be sene,</l>
               <l>If counterfett pearles being sett a parte,</l>
               <l>This Catholyke pearle take place in her harte.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1259:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR so muche as it is the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
of euerye Christian man,
not only in hart to pray with
the Prophet Dauid, saying:
Deale mercifully O lord in thy good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
with Syan, that the walles of Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem
(that is of the churche) maye bee
builded vp agayne, but also to put to hys
helping hand so muche as he is able to the
repayring of it, I thought it to appertaine
to me, which am (I trust) a membre of
Christ hys Catholyke churche, to doo as
muche as in me lyeth, that the broken and
battred walles of it may be reedified. And
where as it passed my strengthe, to bryng
any principall beames, any corner stones,
by wrytyng newe workes of myne owne
inuention, rather then I would be an ydle
loker on, I thought it my part to be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior
laborer, to bryng morter, to carry
sand, and as it were beare baskettes, by
translatyng some worthy worke of some
other wryter. And although I dyd well
<pb facs="tcp:1259:3"/>
knowe, that there were many workes in
Latten, which beyng translated in to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glysshe,
myght helpe to rayse vp the ruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous
walles of Christ hys churche in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,
yet among so many, this one semed
to me to conteine moste spedy remedie and
reparation: whiche as it was of the first
author dedicated to a most excellent Prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cesse,
so of me the second translator (for
one before me hath tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>slated it into Fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che)
is named not without a cause, <hi>A PRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIOVS
PEARLE FOR A PRINCE.</hi> If any
man meruaile, what moued me to tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>slate
this Epistle,<note place="margin">3. causes of this trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</note> I do hym to vnderstand, that
three causes styrred and prouoked me.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The first is, that I myght moue all godly
Englishe hartes, to morne and lament, that
thei in England should be so blynded with
the smoke of ignorance, that they them sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues
coulde not see the greate flames of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resies,
which dayly burne theire sowles, but
were fayne to be warned of them which be
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> in farre countries. The second is, to gyue
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1259:3"/>
God thankes, that allthough the eyes of
them which dwel in England, can not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue
those furiouse fyars, for so muche
as they dwell in the mystie vales of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies,
yet that it hath pleased hym, to make
greate learned men, which dwell on the
hygh hylles of the Catholyke fayth, a farre
of to discrye the flames which dayly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume
England, and not onlye to discrye
them, but also to send holy water of moste
godly councell to quenche them.</p>
            <p>The third cause is, to styrr vp all deuoute <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
Catholykes not learned in the Latten ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue,
to pray to God for the Quenes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie,
that as she hath good councelloures
abroade in farr countryes, so she may haue
good councelloures at home in her courte,
which with <hi>Osorius</hi> may be <hi>osores</hi> of all
false doctryne and heresie: which with <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorius</hi>
maye persuade her to come oute of
the cockring bote of scismaticall noysom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
in to the stedfast arcke of Noy, that is
of holsome and catholyke vnitie: which
<pb facs="tcp:1259:4"/>
with Osorius may instruct her to gyue no
eare to theis deceptfull shypmen,<note place="margin">A mete metaphor for suche maryners.</note> whiche
clymyng vp in to theire pulpyttes, as in to
the topp of the mastes, crie to them which
be beneathe, that thei see the port and saffe
hauen of God his worde, when in deede
thei be in the mayne sea of their owne wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering
pha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tasies: which beare her in hand
that they sayle with a fore wynde of the
holy ghoste, when in deede they ryde with
a sydewinde of dyuellishe suggestion: which
make her beleue, that she hath with her the
warme southe wynde of charitie, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde,
when in deed thei leade her with the
colde Northewynde of dissention and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde:
which persuade her that thei goe
Eastewarde, where the bryght Sonne of
true doctrine doth ryse and appeare, when
to say the truthe, thei goe VVestwarde,
where the cleare beames of veritie doth
vanishe and shrynck oute of syght. Oh that
so noble a Princesse should be so abused by
them which crie against abuses. But to my
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1259:4"/>
purpose. These be the three causes, which
hartned me to translate this epistle, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstandyng
I knew I should displease
some, for God is to be pleased rather then
men: notwithstandyng I was not ignorant
that our base tounge coulde not atteine to
the maiestie of <hi>Osorius</hi> his Laten, for I
regarde not so much the fynes of wordes,
as the diuynenes of the matter: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing
this epistle of <hi>Osorius</hi> is after a
sorte answered à <hi>quoda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> osore veritatis,</hi>
who shall be nameles, for all the world can
wytness that the answer <hi>osoris illius</hi> is no
more to be compared to the epistle of <hi>Oso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi>
then the light of a lampe to the light
of a lynck, then the light of a lynck to the
light of the Sonne. Allthough being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
with other of his owne sect, I confess
hym to be as he is taken a man of handso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me
eloquence. But compare hym to the gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stryng
starres, which are this daye in the
catholike church, and namely to <hi>Osorius,</hi>
against whome he setteth hymselfe, he is
<pb facs="tcp:1259:5"/>
but a candle vnder a bushell, as he shall
well perceaue at <hi>Osorius</hi> next answer, if
so be <hi>Osorius</hi> thinck hym worthie to be
answered. But to leaue all comparisons, for
that thei be odious, I wishe to that answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer
not the eloquence of <hi>Osorius,</hi> which I
know he wold abuse in setting out the false
Churche, but the grace and spirit of <hi>Oso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi>
to be one of the true church. Then I
doubt not, but he will wishe when he made
that answer, he <hi>had don</hi> some other thing,
but I will say no more, for I almost <hi>had
don</hi> his name to be vnderstanded against
my will. Only, gentle Reader, I desire the,
diligentlye to reade this epistle, in reading
it to learne, in learning to lyue accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
as it doth councell. For I assure the
this is a pretiouse pearle, which held a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
the Sonne of good vnderstandyng,
casteth oute suche a glystring light, that
Princes thereby may learne to rule, sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes
may learne to obey, wauerers in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
may be stayed, wanderers may be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1259:5"/>
brought in to the right way. If thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite,
gyue God the cheife prayse: and if
thou thinck me worthie no thanke for that
I haue but declared and sette out in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish
an other mans his doing in Latten, I
am well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent. Yet remembre that many
tymes we see those men, which haue iewel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les
in keeping, which be none of theire
owne, to receaue greate thankes at
theire handes, to whome they
do shewe them.</p>
            <closer>Fare well,
<dateline>from Antwerp. <date>xiiij. of March.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>R. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1259:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1259:6"/>
            <head>A PEARLE FOR
A PRYNCE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> WAS, I assure you (moste
noble Princesse) here to
fore sufficientlie prouoked
to the loue of youre Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie
and highnes, when I herd say howe
muche you dyd preuaile in witte, how
greately you had profited in Greke and
Latten, and howe you did ioyne youre
Princely dignity with liberalle learning
and knowledge: But after that certaine
men brought me worde, that you wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
did reade my workes,<note place="margin">Hys booke intituled De vera nobilitate.</note> my former
good will was so muche increased to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde
you, as in wordes I am not able
to vtter. Whether thei tolde me that
vnfaynedly, or that they ment to curry
fauor with me, I am not able to say, but
this I am assured of, that I toke greate
pleasure at theire sayinges, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought
my selffe howe in writing I
might wytnesse my moste louing and
<pb facs="tcp:1259:7"/>
moste lowly hart toward you. For I
mistruste not, but with the same fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure
with which you reade my wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes
(if it be true, that you be not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell
delighted in reading them) you
will interteine these my letters.</p>
            <p>Specially, seing those other my wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes
doe concerne the common profit
of all men, but these my letters intend
cheifely the mayntenaunce of youre
estate, and the auauncement of youre
Royall Maiestie. The whiche thing,
thoughe I shall not be able to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>passe,
yet my good will is not to be displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>santly
taken of you. For why? mightie
Princes are wont not so much to haue
an eye to the worth of the thing which
is presented to them, as to weygh the
hart and the good meaning of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senter.
For seing the suerest defence
and furnyture of Princelye renome,
dothe stay vppon the frendeshipp and
trustines of men, howe can that be mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1259:7"/>
of them, which thei perceaue to
procede of a hartie loue and speciall
fidelitie? and that here I may make an
entraunce to my writing, I am wont
many tymes to merueil with my self at
the prouidence of God in appointing
kinges,<note place="margin">The mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilous prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God in kyngly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment.</note> that to a multitude of people al
most innumerable, made of so sondry
natures, greatly disagreing one with an
other, he hathe gyuen suche a mynde,
that it will haue an eye cheifely to one,
that it will be kept in awe at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundment
of one, that it will suffer
it self as it were to be tyed short with
the lawes and procedinges of one. In
so muche that whereas men often ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes
aboute other thinges, with dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
hatred do warr among them selues,
and outeragiously disagree, yet in this
one pointe (for the moste parte) with
greate consent of myndes, they cleaue
and holde together. And as I greatly
wunder at this, so I accompt those kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
<pb facs="tcp:1259:8"/>
which at the appointment of that
highe and euerlasting king, do execute
so worthie and paynefull an office,<note place="margin">The pree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence of kynges ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oue other persones.</note> to
be men farr surmounting in all kinde
of vertue, and all together indued with
godly perfection. For there is nothing
greater or more honorable, nothing so
hard and paynefull to attchyue, as to
brydell the affections of men, to cutt a
way filthie desires, to mainteine inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centie,
with rewardes to encorage ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,
with punishment to discorage syn,
and fynallie in establishing peace and
quietnes, to make the hole common
wealthe to florishe and abounde with
all commodities. Seing no man is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
to performe those thinges, but he
which is indued with heauenly grace,
surely they which worthily behaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
selues in theire kingly vocation, are to
be accompted in the number of the
heauenly citezins, and worthie to be
reuerensed as certeine godes among
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1259:8"/>
men. If so be notable men, when they
gyue them selues wholy to preserue the
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealthe, and do vprightly, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sely
and discretly rule their kingdome,<note place="margin">A woman wysely ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to be merueiled at then a man.</note>
be muche merueiled at, surely when a
woman shall do the like, she shall gyue
men greater occasion to merueile. For
what is more to be wondred at, then
to beholde in a woman a manly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantie,
in a virgin an horehedded pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
in greate abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance of richesse,
greate praise of temperaunce and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty?
What can soner astonish a man,
then to see the tendre and deintie na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
of a woman to be trimmed and
decked with so many vertues, that she
is able to vpholde the burden of the
whole realme, and to be haue her selfe
in that office with greate commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
which is scantly brought to passe
withe the aduise, prouesse, fidelity and
autority of many excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t men? Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
(as it is to be hoped) if you will
<pb facs="tcp:1259:9"/>
so ordre the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealthe, that you
will not swarue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vertue of youre
auncetoures, who only embraced god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes,
you shal so farre go beyond them
in greatnes of renome, as it is a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
matter for a young woman to rule
a Realme wyselie and stoutelye, then
for men whiche are strengthned with
rype yeares and experience. If there
were euer any woman of excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,
which with a noble corage hathe
bent her selfe to the care of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
wealthe, and by that carefulnes
and gouernement,<note place="margin">A wyder wyndowe of win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me opened to oure Quene of Englande then to any Prince here to fore.</note> hathe wonne great
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation, youre Kingdome hathe
happened to you in suche a tyme, and
you haue gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> suche a matter to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke
on, that if you will constantly take
in hand those affaires, which well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
that princelie disposition which
glistreth in you, with the brightnes of
youre noble prayse and worthie doin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
you shall ouershadowe and darcke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:1259:9"/>
the greate actes of moste mighty prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesses.
And that we may boldly warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
the whole Christian co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth,
thus muche of your grace,<note place="margin">Causes of good hope in oure no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble Quene.</note> many cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
do moue vs. For you are indued
with a singular wytte. You are learned
in the preceptes of moste noble scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:
you are praysed aboue all others
for gentlenes and mekenes, which well
beseme youre comelye bewtie: and as
for those prayses which are due to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stancie,
you well think, that you ought
not to denye them, or put them from
you. Therefore if you will not neglect
and forget youre selfe, you shall set a
good stay in the common weale, you
shall bring all those mischeifes, which
disquiet it,<note place="margin">Greate danger in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilful ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the ship of the Englishe common weale.</note> to an end: and you shall pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase
youre selfe euerlasting commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.
But on the other syde, if in su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
stormes and hurly burlies, you shall
go any thing a wrye, and shall vnskill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb facs="tcp:1259:10"/>
rule the stearne of youre charge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
it is an hundred to one (which God
forbid) but that the shyp of this youre
common wealthe, dashing against hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
and secret rockes, shal be all to bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken:
and the passingers which be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
to youre charge, shall vtterlye
perishe and be cast awaye. Therefore
seing you be in that taking, that either
you must wyn greate honour with the
safety of your whole realme, or become
a laughing stock with the ouerthrowe
of your common wealthe, I thinke
that no riches nor treasures ought to
be so deare vnto you,<note place="margin">No riches to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell</note> that you sholde
prefer them before faithfull councell,
which intendeth the staying and assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
of your kyngdome. But perchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
you will saye to me,<note place="margin">An obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> doe you thinke
me so ill bestead of frendes and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celloures,
that you neede nowe to tell
me what I sholde doe? or haue you so
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1259:10"/>
muche vacant tyme from the affaires of
Portugale<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that you can intend to take
care for the matters of England? I
thinke verily,<note place="margin">The aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer.</note> there be in England ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
wyse men, greately to be commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
for theyr vertue and godlynes, to
whome if you will gyue eare, you shall
prouide verye well for youre self and
youre realme, and trimlye mayntayne
youre princelye porte and estate.<note place="margin">A goodly similitude.</note> But
like as thei which be muche gyuen to
gather goodes, allthoughe they haue
greate riches layed vp in store at ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me,
yet for all that do not refuse golde
and siluer, which is brought vnto them
from other places, and loke howe ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher
they wax, so muche the more they
couet to haue theire good heaped and
encreased: euen so wyse Kinges, whose
treasure ought rather to consist in the
prudent aduise &amp; faythfulnes of good
men, then in the aboundaunce of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,
<pb facs="tcp:1259:11"/>
although they haue store of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell.
Yet if those riches, which they este<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me
aboue all other, by any meanes be
augmented, they ought not to sett it
light, or despise it. Nether neade they
to care, whether he which cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celleth
them, be a countrie man borne, or a
straunger, but of what intent he taketh
suche an office vpon hym. Beside this,
councells gyuen of forenners, many ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes
are least to be suspected. For ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
treasons are wrought against Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
of theire howseholde seruauntes,<note place="margin">Inimici ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minis do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mestici eiꝰ. Matth. 10.</note>
many craftie fetches are attempted in
the court for loue of lucre, many thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
are couered with the cloke of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>simulation,
partly to curry fauoure, and
partly for feare of falling in to daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouse
displeasure: so that there be very
fewe, whiche dare frelye speake their
mynde to Princes: last of al, I adde this,
that I think no Christian Prince a for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rener
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1259:11"/>
or a straunger, but I professe my
selfe to be beholding to all, but cheife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
to you, whome afore all other for
the hope which I haue conceaued of
your gentlenes, I haue sett before myne
eyes only to be worshipped and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rensed.</p>
            <p>But that I may come to that, which
I haue taken in hande, two thinges spe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cially
are to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>sidered of all Kinges,<note place="margin">2. thinges of Kynges to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered.</note>
first the worthines of the office which
thei beare, and seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly the weightynes
and paynefulnes in fullfilling that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.
As for the worthynes of it, it is so
greate,<note place="margin">The wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines of kingly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</note> as greater can not be imagined
in this lyfe. For all Kynges for theyr
owne parte, are the Vicares of God his
authority, for it is as it were the office
and roume of a God, that one man
among all the rest, sholde so farr excell,
that all with one agrement of mynde,
sholde yelde them selues to be ledd and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1259:12"/>
defended of hym, and that they sholde
beleue, that the strongest bulwarkes of
theyr life, welfare, and worshyp, doe
rest in his wysdome, manhode; and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestie.
Now, as touching the difficultie
of theyr office,<note place="margin">The diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culte of Kyngly office.</note> it is vnspeakable. For
if it be an hard matter to rule al affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
to brydle vnhonest desires, to
subdue the vnruly motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the mynd,
and to keepe the whole state of the
mynde in suche a frame, that nothing
arise, which with any boysterouse blast
may shake or disquiet it, then what a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>do
is it for one not only to wayne hym
selffe from his owne wyll, but also to
tame and qualifie the affections of the
whole people, after suche a sorte, that
no oute rage or vprore burst oute of
theyr vnruly myndes, which may set the
whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealthe oute of ordre?</p>
            <p>Therefore he which is charged with
such an office, as requireth first that he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1259:12"/>
sholde kepe hym selfe in ordre, (for it<note place="margin">☜</note>
can not be, that he sholde assuage other
mens lustes, which can not tempre his
owne,) and secondly, that with reason
he sholde alay the trobles of the whole
common wealthe, that as muche as in
hym lyeth, he sholde make all his sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes
sober and discrete, and that he
sholde warde them with the defence of
all vertues, I saye, suche a man is to be
aided and socored with the helpe, not
only of man, but also of God, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,
that the thing which he hath lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>styly
purposed, he may luckyly perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me.
But that I may first intreate of man
his helpe (which neuerthelesse is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined
in the ayde and assistaunce of
God) I think,<note place="margin">How necessary good men be for Kynges.</note> that all the riches &amp; pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessions
of Kinges, which with greate
indeuoure are to bee sought after,
ought to staye vpon the wysdome and
honestie of good men. For no Prince
<pb facs="tcp:1259:13"/>
is able by any meanes, either in warr to
get the victory, or in peace to mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
his honoure, either in his affai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res
to behaue hymself politikely, or in
his leasure continewe quietlye, which
is not as it were walled with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
of good men. For howe shall he
be able with his owne eyes to see to all
thinges, which Kinges ought to looke
to? Or howe with his owne eares can
he heare the complaintes of all clien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes?
Or with his owne mynde and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration,
studie for so many thinges,
as be requisite to preserue the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon
weale?</p>
            <p>Therefore many are to be called to
take parte in the ordring of the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,<note place="margin">what ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men kynges sholde call to theire councell.</note> whiche be men bewtified with
the iewells of kyngly qualities, that is
to say, iustice, temperance, manhode,
sagenes, stedfastnes, liberality, and wys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
in which one vertue, all thinges
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1259:13"/>
which are prayse worthie be contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.
Yea these men must be of suche
wysdome,<note place="margin">wise men.</note> that thei be able to trye oute
all thinges narrowly, and by former
causes long before to prouide, for thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges
which may ensue afterwarde.</p>
            <p>Theire trustines muste be suche,<note place="margin">Trustie men.</note> that
no bribes, or aduauntage, may leade
them a syde from doing their duty, and
maintayning the truthe. They ought
to be of so valyaunt a corage,<note place="margin">Stoute me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> that no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing
may dismay them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> sayng that
playnely, whiche may be healthfull to
the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale.<note place="margin">A trim si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude.</note> For like as sick men
often tymes lothe and abhorre holsom
medicyns, if thei be bitter and vntothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some,
and long after those thinges
which be enemies to theire healthe,
euen so nowe and then Princes being
sore sick and diseased in theire sowles,
refuse the phisick of true councell, and
are delighted with counterfet fynes of
<pb facs="tcp:1259:14"/>
lying, and deceaueable lickersomnes of
flatterie. So it cometh to passe, that
all be it in the beginning they take a
pleasure, yet in the end, they bye theyr
rashnes, and folly, with hartbreake and
sorowfulnes: and as nothyng is more
godly then truthe, so nothing is more
healthfull for the common weale. For
what other differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is there betwene
wyse men and fooles,<note place="margin">Difference betwene wyse men and fooles.</note> but that wyse
men with ernest trauaile, purchase to
them selues thinges which are good
in dede: but foles being beguyled with
false appearaunces, hunt after thinges
which haue a shewe of goodnes, and in
dede be very vaine trifles, and mocke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries:
and so at length whilst they couet
false worship, and seke after deceipt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
pleasures, they be branded with
the marck of fowle shame, and be tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented
contynually with the worme
of theire wicked conscience. Therefor
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1259:14"/>
all the trade of a blessed life consisteth
in truthe, and all wretchednes standeth
vpon lying and dissimulation. For
which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>syderation, all Princes which
doo wishe the safetie of theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon
weale, and desire to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinewe and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde
theyr honour, ought all wayes
to pretend this, bothe in worde and
worcke to wytnesse this, that nothing
is more deare vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then the bright
beames of veritie. So they shall set all
good men free from feare, and holde
shameles flaterers noses to the gryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone.
The which thing that they may
more easely compasse,<note place="margin">what Kynd of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces sholde banishe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them.</note> it is neadefull
that they enriche and highely aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
good and true meaning men, but as
for nawghtiepackes, coyners of lyes,
and forgers of flearing tales, thei ought
to abandon them farre from theyr ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaynetaunce,
and to think them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie
of any preferme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. For all flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers
<pb facs="tcp:1259:15"/>
be sworne enemies to the truth,
back frendes to all good men, verie
poison of Princes, and not only deadly
foes to the whole c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munaltie, but also
malishiously mynded against God hym
selffe. For he which wrastleth against
the truth, wrastleth against the mightie
ruler of all thinges, who is the only and
euerlasting veritie. Therefore these
naughtie and pestilent persones, are
to be put out of all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceipt, to be kept
a loofe from climing to honoure, to be
excluded from all companie and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaritie,
yea to be banished as farre as
there is any land, lest the infectyon of
theire myschefe, sholde spreade it selffe
to the vtter vndoing of Kinges, and
waste the whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealthe, with
a remedilesse consumption. But on the
other syde, thei which euer speake the
truthe, neuer double or dissemble, but
esteme true vertue more then worldly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1259:15"/>
ryches<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and drawe the lyne of theire
whole lyfe, by the square of wysdome
and honestie, they I say, if they kepe
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> selues secrete, be to be pulled oute
of theire prime closettes, will they nill
they, drawe they back neuer so muche,
they are to be brought acquaynted
with kinges, and to haue whole heapes
of ryches bestowed vpon them. For
those ryches of Kynges,<note place="margin">Fidelitie the suerest treasure howse of Princes.</note> be in better
assurau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which be laied vp in the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie
of good men, then those which
be horded and couched vp in theire
cofers. For beyng layd vp in the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
howse, thei breede the cancker of
enuye, but being sette a broade to the
vse of good men, they make the Kyng
to be well spoken of, and fortifie his
estate, with the faithful hartes of good
men. Beside this, riches closed and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted
vp, may ether be caried away of
theues, or be lasht oute and made ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uock
<pb facs="tcp:1259:16"/>
of, through the falshode of the
kepers. But the remembraunce of a
good turne, is rooted for euer in tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
myndes, &amp; can not be plucked out
by any mans pilfrie. More ouer, it is
to be consydered, that they which by
no false or sowle fetches; but by true
vertue and fayre conditions, cam to be
familiar with their Kinges, doe thinck
that of duetie they ought to bestowe
those riches which they receaued of
theyr Kynges<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to the profit of them by
whome they enioye them. But they,
whiche by hypocrisy,<note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perte of hy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pocriticall honor hun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters.</note> haue obteyned
great wealthe of Kinges, for so muche
as they gape al for gaines, as sone as
they spy, where more aduauntage is to
be gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they forsake theyr kinges, yea
they betray them, and some tyme byd
them battayle. Whereby we may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
howe mad all Princes be, which
not regarding good men, bestowe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1259:16"/>
riches and promotions vpon wicked
persones, and put all theyr honoure in
the credit of them, whome couetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
will not suffer to be trusty &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.
But they which be of suche wyse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
that displacyng naughtie men,
doo call good menne vnto them, and
make them partakers of theyr cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels
and charge, doe prouide very well for
theyr honoure and safetie. For it can
not be, that the Safegarde of Pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
shoulde be betrayed of them, who
holde fidelitie more deare, then all the
wealthe of the world: nether can theyr
honour be stayned with anie spotte of
reproche, when it shall appeare, that
they be fastned in the frendshippe and
familiaritie of vnculpable men. For as
nothing bringeth more shame to Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
then the companie and familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye
of rakehells, so the frendshippe
of good men, doth greatly increase
<pb facs="tcp:1259:17"/>
theire glory and renome.</p>
            <p>For we so iudge of them,<note place="margin">lyke loueth lyke.</note> as they be,
with whome they be moste familiar &amp;
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uersant. Whereby we may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude,
that those Kynges be not to be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
riche and puissant, which possesse
greate pyles of golde and syluer,<note place="margin">what Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are to be counted riche.</note> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouse
stones gloriously glystring, great
store of yuorie, many mynes of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall,
and be Lordes ouer manye landes:
but those rather, which be assisted with
a numbre of men excelling in honestie
and trustines, which be lincked in lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue,
and frendshippe of all good men,
so farre as shall become their Princely
person and Royall maiestie. For all
those thinges afore sayde, be seldome
obteined withoute vertue,<note place="margin">Vertue with oute riches is sufficient.</note> but thei be
neuer reteined withoute the succoure
of vertue. But turne vertue naked oute
of all the robes of riches, yet she will
holde her owne, and make her bright
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1259:17"/>
beames, be sene a great waye of. Beside
this,<note place="margin">Riches with oute vertue be impotent.</note> if riches haue not the ayde of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,
they can help nothing, but rather
stirr vp and kyndle the cole of couetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
in the hartes of many, to worke
treason agaynst them, whome they see
pufft vp with plentie of possessions.</p>
            <p>But vertue alone, many tymes without
reskue of ryches, preserueth the Prince
hys estate, and doth auoyde the daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
which hangeth ouer the common
wealthe. But this may suffice, which we
haue spoken, as concerning the healpe
of man: now it followeth in ordre, that
we sholde intreate of the ayde and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistaunce
of God.</p>
            <p>Therefore, if the honestie and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullnes
of good men be of suche force,
that withoute theyr healpe, no Kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
or common weale can long en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure,
then I praye you, what shall we
think of the healpe of God? For God
<pb facs="tcp:1259:18"/>
is he by whose Deitie, councell, wyll,
kingdomes doo begyn,<note place="margin">God is first to be sought for.</note> be enlarged, &amp;
mayntayned: by whose wisdome they
be kept in ordre, by whose helpe they
be vpholden, and finally, by whose dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure
they decay, ouerwhelme, and
vtterly come to naught. Therefore a
Prince, which will acquite hym selfe
well in his office, and comlyly handle
the rule committed to his charge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
all thinges must kepe religion pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely
and vndefyledly, and in his daylye
prayers desire God to prosper hym, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compting
al the happy successe in ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng
the realme, to stay vpon the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice
and pleasing of God. For first, if
wisdome be so necessarie for Kinges,
that without it, they can not haue so
muche as a pece of a common wealthe,
but they shall leaue all thinges topp fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turuy,
and seing wisdome borroweth
her light of none other, then of that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1259:18"/>
passing and vnspeakeable clearenes of
the wysdome and spirit of God, by the
which all thinges are led in the right
way, and lightned, vpon what thinges
sholde kinges more bestowe their stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,
then in ernest bendyng themselues
to religion, &amp; purely praying for God
his healpe and assistaunce? which thing
if they doo,<note place="margin">The effect which Kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges haue by seruing of God.</note> suche clearenes of Godly
wisdome, suche a brightnes of wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
vertue shall shoote oute of their
myndes, that they shall not onlye dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne
what is right, honest, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable,
and knowe to trye what diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
is betwene counterfet and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,
but looke what so euer they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue
to be right, that same they shall
stedfastlye put in practyse. For the
mercy and goodnes of God, worketh
bothe these thynges in vs. For first it
sheweth a moste cleare light to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his
mynde, and armeth hym with inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:1259:19"/>
valiantnes, so that by meanes of the
one, he neuer trippes or treades a wrye,
&amp; by reason of the other, is not abashed
of the daunger or troble, that the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting
of his office bringeth with it.</p>
            <p>For there is nothing so hard to come
by, nothing so cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tregarded with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynes,
which he shall not easely batter
and beate downe, which is indued with
Godly vertue. He must therefore spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily
asuage all the brutishe mocyons of
the mynde,<note place="margin">what a Prince shold do which seketh for god his help</note> he must wayne hymselfe of
his owne wyll, he must scrape oute all
the blottes and blemishes of vices, and
so lighten all the state of his mynde
with the brightnes of honestie, that a
meruaillouse amiablenes, bewtie, and
liuely image of God his holye spyrit,
may clearely appeare in it. For it can
not be, but he whiche in this lyfe so
muche as is in man hys powre<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with
cleare eyes doth behold God, &amp; dayly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1259:19"/>
doth vewe that pearlesse fayrenes and
bewtie, sholde be raueshed with the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue
of it, and force hym selfe ernestly to
be lyke vnto it: specially, seing he can
not attaine to resemble and be like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
it so muche by his owne labour and
trauaile, as by the goodnes and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnes
of God. And loe, oute of this
likelyhood of mens myndes,<note place="margin">The effect of the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hood of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s mynd with god</note> with the
spirit of God, there springeth an euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting
band of amitye, which causeth
God so to cleaue to mans sowle, that
he will vouchsafe a gyltles and deuout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
disposed mynde, plentifull to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take
of his Godly treasures. Therefore
suche a mynde, he enformeth with cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell,
he wardeth with vertue, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passeth
with conforte, and in all hasard
doth defend it with his godly presence.
Therefore they which be kyndled with
the loue of true vertue,<note place="margin">Vertue is ful of good hope.</note> being hartned
with this hope, though all the worlde
<pb facs="tcp:1259:20"/>
be togeather by the eares, thoughe the
grounde open with earthe quakes, yet
they be not dismayed, but then most of
all they trust God wyll succoure them:
and when in mans iudgement all hope
is past, they stand styffly in this belefe,
that God will saue them harmeles.</p>
            <p>Whereby we maye gather, that for so
muche as mans nature is so feble, and
that there ys no holde to be had in
these transitorie and glyding goodes
of the worlde, and that all oure lyfe
sta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth in the gunshot of dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiousnes
of mynd, and confidence
of vnprenable strengthe to be founde
in them only, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>syder that they
haue God on theyr syde. Therefore
seing no man can take vpon hym the
office of a Kyng, without wonderfull
wysdome, without a speciall token of
worthynes, without the stay of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conquerable
stoutenes, and none of all
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1259:20"/>
these laudable vertues, grow oute of
the grounde, but descend downe from
heauen by God hys inspyration, it is
playne that Kinges ought to employ
all theyr care and office, to be of an
holy and blameles religion. For they
and none other, are to be reckned wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se,
dyscrete, and stronge, which are
knyt with the knot of right religion to
God, who is the author, and cheife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne
of all wysdome, honestie, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantnes.</p>
            <p>But what shall we now say of iustice?
can any man ministre it, onles he cast
all his mynde vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the rule of the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting
lawe, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaue in his mynde,
the wel spring of righteousnes, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently
marcke the ordre and seme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes,
with the which that cheife ruler
setteth all thinges in frame? and last of
all, onlesse he gyue hym selfe wholy to
the studie of God his lawe? surely it is
<pb facs="tcp:1259:21"/>
impossible. For God only is the pythe,
wisdome, and rule of the lawe: he is the
beginning and rote of vpright dealing,
and father of all iustice. By whose gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,
all holsome and profitable lawes be
enacted, by whose procurement they
be kept and preserued. Hereby it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth,
that they only glystre with the
brightnes of iustice, which fix theyr
eye vpon that hyghe and euerlasting
light. Verily oute of this agrement of
mynde, by the which men resemble the
iustice of God, and stretch all the strin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
of theyr studie to profit the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon
wealthe, the loue and hartie good wyll
of men dothe growe, oute of this doth
issue the commendation of myldenes
and curtesie, oute of this (to be short)
doth procede all the swetenes of most
true pleasure and delight. For no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyly
pleasure is in any poynt to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
with the pleasure which cometh
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1259:21"/>
of vnfayned honestie. For the pleasure
of the bodye many tymes in a madnes
is desired,<note place="margin">The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the pleasure of the body &amp; the mynde</note> and in twinkling of an eye
vanisheth away, and afterward seareth
the mynde with sadnes, and leaueth a
print of shame behynde it. But that
pleasure which true vertue doth breed,
is chosen oute wisely, and is inioyed
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually, not able to be defyled with
any lewde affection, or defaced with
any villany, because it is farre from all
infectiue filthines, and ioyned with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
honestie and comlynes, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
of which, it cometh to passe, that
theyr lyfe, which be lincked in loue
with God, is not only adorned with
Godly vertue, indued with greate ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
and put in sure hope of euerlas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
glorie, but also is replenished with
stedfast and vnspeakeable ioy and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte,
so that they may lawfully crie
with that most fayntely Kyng, how
<pb facs="tcp:1259:22"/>
greate is the plenty of thy swete com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte,
o Lorde, which thou haste layed
vp for them which loue the? Therefor
the loue and carefulnes of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, doth
conteyne all these benefytes, with the
which the laboures susteyned in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouse
practise, are made more tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
and easie, and requited with a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne
exceding swetenes, and without
the which, the Kyngdome can not be
wel ordred. More ouer what a notable
thing is that? that all the subiectes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
suche which through myschefe are
growne to a monstrouse madnes and
crueltye,<note place="margin">Subiectes do loue &amp; wyllingly obey reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces.</note> will greatly loue those Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
and vse muche fidelitie towarde
them, if they se them deuoutely to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace
religion? For it must neades be,
that the picture of diuine fayrenes set
before mennes eyes, sholde make them
greately inamored, and cause euery bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye
to be much delighted with it: and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1259:22"/>
there is no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which wyll let this sinck
in his mynde, that he which feareth
God and casteth all to please hym, will
once forsake his fayth or shrinck from
his seruice. Therefore partely because
they perceaue hym learned in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes
and conncels of God, and to be
ernestly bent to care for the common
wealth, partly because thei mistrust not
his goodnes, and stand not in dought
that he wil forget publike profit, whilst
he licketh his owne fyngers, they wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
obey hym, &amp; in no wyse grudge
to bee vnder hym. Nowe then, if no
Realme, no Citie, yea no house can be
vpholden without it be ruled, and the
manner of ruling well, standeth in pure
and perfect religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, surely nothing may
be inuented more profitable or hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some
then religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to kepe a multitude
of men in awe, and good ordre. For
what can more strengthen a ruler, then
<pb facs="tcp:1259:23"/>
that all men may know and perceaue,
that all his delight and studie is, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale? for so it cometh
to passe, that the common wealth hath
him in admiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, loueth him, and with
hartie good wil dothe yeld to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedinges.
Otherwise they wil not long
leade in his lyne, but as much as lyeth
in them, they will striue to cut or snap
it a sundre: for no regiment can long
continew, which is rather established
with feare of punishment, then with
loue of vertue. If so be that agreement
doth preserue and encrease the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon
weale, but drawing diuerse wayes, doth
teare it and minsse it all to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mockes,
and the right religion of the Prince
doth as it were glue his subiectes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
with this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>corde, (for all with
one consent do shewe obeisaunce to a
religiouse Prince, and be redie at his
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement) then without perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1259:23"/>
all the saffegarde and suretie
of the common wealthe doth beare it
selfe vpon religion. Moreouer, that is
not to be lightly weyghed, that vntrue
subiectes will not be so bold to worke
treason against theyr Prince, on whose
syde they thincke God to be. Neither
doe his enemyes ventre so sone to bid
hym battell, whom they see to be way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
on with the trayne and garde of
God his healpe. For if they go aboute
to worke wyles, or offre warre, they do
it fayntly and fearefully, so that naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye
subiectes being taken with the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
may suffer for their offence, or for
feare be reclamed from theyr naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tienes,
&amp; enemies also may easily leaue
of to moue warre and disquietnes.</p>
            <p>For they willingly seke to be at one
with them whose strengthe in warre
they feare, whose fidelitye in peace
they loue, and whome they know to be
<pb facs="tcp:1259:24"/>
suche, that they neade not mystrust,
leaste they shoulde breake the truce,
which they haue well agreed vpon.</p>
            <p>Laste of all, seing euery common we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>althe
dothe frame it self to the Princes
fashio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, if the Prince be a worthy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipper
of godlynes and religion, the
whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealthe muste neades
lay fast holde vpon the same religion.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> effect of true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</note> And religion trulye dothe restrayne
naughtye desyres, it dothe kepe wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tones
vnder, it abateth pryde, it staieth
rashenes and folishe hardynes, it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
men discrete, and obedient, bothe
to the lawes, and also to them which
execute the lawes. For there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
of more powre then the feare of
God, to pull back out ragiouse desy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,
to cutt the combt of bragging and
lightnes. For when we call to mynde,
howe muche we be bounde to oure
highe and most holy father for his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1259:24"/>
bestowed vpon vs, and what
paynes be ordeined for them which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyle
the bewtie of their sowle with syn
and vncleanes, and when we conceaue
in oure vnderstandyng, that there be
no lurkyng holes whiche can hyndre
the sight of God, seing those thinges,
whiche Iye hyd vnder the yearth: yea
euen very hell it selfe, which is wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
with continuall darcknes, appeare
brightly in his sight, I saye, when we
weygh all these thinges with oure sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues
we breake &amp; disapointe our owne
will, partly least we sholde offend hys
eyes with fylthines, or shewe owre sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues
vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfull towarde hym (then the
which nothing is more greuouse) par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely
leaste we sholde shame oure sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues,
and worke owre euerlasting wo,
throughe owre owne abhominatyon:
and so being reskewed by the healpe of
God, we beare away the victorie van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quishing
<pb facs="tcp:1259:25"/>
and putting to flyght all kynd
of wickednes, for they whiche stand
in awe of God his iudgementes, and
feare to displease hym, be neuer forsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
of him, or left to shyft for them sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues.
Therefor being assured of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte,
they easely kepe of the assaulte
of concupiscens, from scaling and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uading
the mayne towre of reason. So
then, it is an easie matter, to lyue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drely,
to doo as a man ought to doo,
and to practyse all thinges which ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
dothe prescribe, when dyuellyshe
desyres be quenched and subdued.</p>
            <p>For who can auoide vncleanes, but he
whiche with vndesyled eyes beholdeth
that hyghe and euerlastyng honestie,
trymnes and neatenes, which is in the
bewtie of God? who shall be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les
in ministring iustice, but he which
dothe marke the fashion, ordre, and
comlynes with the which that mighty
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1259:25"/>
Lorde ruleth all thinges, fytly placeth
all thinges, and in their seuerall offices
appoynteth all thinges? who wyll not
sticke to put his lyfe in daunger, who
in battaile will fyght stoutely &amp; man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
for the mayntenaunce of iustice,
and in the common quarrell, but he
which trusteth that God wyll be euer
at his elbowe? and though he be slayne
in the felde, yet trusteth that God hath
not cast hym of, but rather beleueth for
this short and fading lyfe, to be rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
with an euerlasting lyfe, in which
he shall enioy all felicitie in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
of the blessed sayntes? Therefore
if religion in tyme of peace, doth make
men discrete and sobre, and merueil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously
agreing together in louable vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
willing and redy to obey the lawes,
and Princes procedinges, and in tyme
of warre doth harten them aboue the
common strength of men, and so ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uisheth
<pb facs="tcp:1259:26"/>
them with the loue of euerlas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng
lyfe, that they wyll spend theyr
blood and lyfe in theyr cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tryes cause,
to the intent they may wyn heauen: is
it not playne, that a King which hath
an ernest desyre to doo his dutie to the
vttermost, ought to set all hys care and
studie in the well disposyng of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?
For so he shall most royally abounde
with the riches and orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,
and shall flow on euery syde with
exceding glory which shall neuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay,
and in all doughtfull aduentures
shall be strenghtned with the ayde of
God, and shall receaue greate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte
of the remembraunce of so many good
dedes: neither shall he alone be in an
happye case, but he shall make all the
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to his charge,
partaker of hys happie and blessed lyfe:
<note place="margin">The charge of Kynges.</note> in the which all the dutie and office of
a Kyng doth consist. For what other
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1259:26"/>
charge hath a Kyng assygned hym ouer
the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealthe, then that he shold
make the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale florishe, and be
in a blessed state? which no other wyse
is brought to passe, but by a speciall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion
to vertue and religion.</p>
            <p>But loke how muche the more reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
surmou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth all other vertues, (for
they all be borne of her, caryed in her
armes, and dandled in her lap) so much
the more it is to be feared,<note place="margin">Heresye is an hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite.</note> least vice
take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it the name of vertue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
and vnder the pretence of holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
may ouerthrowe and vndermynde
all Godlynes. For as nothing is more
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to vertue then hypocrisye, so it
euidently doth bewray it selfe, in fayned
and counterfeyte religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For horrible
wickednes, cloking it selfe deceiptfully
with the name of vertue, myndeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
ells, but the rasyng of religion,
and scrapyng of the remembraunce of
<pb facs="tcp:1259:27"/>
God oute of mennes myndes. Here
most noble Quene,<note place="margin">Notable and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cel to our noble Quene.</note> I desyre you to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syder
the matter wysely: for seing you
be clogged with so many cares, that
by no meanes you be able by youre
owne wytte to auoide suche snares, and
so peryllous pytfals, whiche be layed
for you, &amp; all Christendome, and seing
all the swey of your Kyngdome stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
vpon this one poynt, that you
shold inbrace religion purely, that you
sholde be assysted with the healpe of
God, and that you shold kepe the real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me
assigned to you, in good estate and
prosperitye, nothing ought to be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
welcome to you, specially in suche
disagreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of religion, then to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertised
of matters of so greate impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce,
by a man which wysheth your
grace verye well, which is farre from
hope of all fylthie lucre, whiche also
knoweth what belongeth to true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1259:27"/>
I dare be bold to say thus muche
vnto youre grace, that if I had mistrus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
your wysdome and gentlenes, I
wolde not haue bestowed laboure in
writing these letters. For it had ben a
poynte of great madnes, to take that
in hand, which I haue vtterly dispaired
of. But when youre wytte, learning,
gentlenes, and good nature,<note place="margin">The spoile of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is not to be imputed to oure graciouse Quene</note> did bryng
me in greate hope of youre honorable
Maiestie, and when I vnderstode that
the spoyle of religion, which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
in your realme, is not to be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
to you, but to many men which
being verbes actiue I knowe not of
what mad moode, go about to pul in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sondre
the fences and inclosures of all
lawe and religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that it is no God
a mercye to them, but long of your
graciouse goodnes, that any sparcke
of Christian religion doth remayne, I
dought not but you will be well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb facs="tcp:1259:28"/>
to here me speake. Wherefore in
moste hartie manner,<note place="margin">3. Wyse and godly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>questes to our royall Quene.</note> I desyre you first
that you will take these my enterpryses
in good parte, (the which you shall do,
if you will looke in to my heart oute
of which proceadeth all that I doo:)
secondly that before you haue readen
all which I purpose to comprehend in
this epistle, you will not gyue youre
verdict either to the prayse or disprayse
of them: last of all, I request you by the
faythe which you owe to Christ, that
if by the craftye councel of others, you
haue conceiued any wrong opinion, if
ryght reason shall confound it, if eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
truthe shall bewray it, if godlynes
shall boult it oute, that you will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse
the good grace of God, but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyngly
gyue credit to those reasons
which you shall see to be more agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
to Christian religion. For it is the
poynt not only of a prowde and arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1259:28"/>
stomake, but also the token of a
dull and blockyshe wytte, (which faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
be very farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you) to be so ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted
to certayne chosen and singular
opinions, beaton in to the heade by
dayly crying and callyng on of wicked
persones, that it can not be remoued
from that opinion which it hath once
taken in hand to defend. which thyng
as in euery trade of lyfe, is beyond all
God hys forbode, so in wrong religion
which is taken of a heade, is most pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rylous
and daungerous. For the more
trymme, excellent, and profytable any
thing is in his right kynde, so the more
vyle, beggarly, and hurtfull it is, when
it is cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfeit.<note place="margin">Mark the manifolde miseries caused by the false preachers of oure tyme,</note> The which I wold God
we had not tryed in these troblesome
dayes. For after that by the naughtye
persuasyon, and bedlem boldnes of
some, men forsooke that religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which
fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Apostles tyme, euen to our age
<pb facs="tcp:1259:29"/>
hath continued inuincible, and many
being inuegled with paynted woordes,
haue strayed from that way which the
disciples of Christ dyd fyrst open, and
many holy men in whome the holy
ghost dwelled, dyd afterward enlarge,
that they might walcke in that pathe,
which with a shew of lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiousnes and
pleasure, dyd drawe folish and vnadui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
men vnto it, I saye, after that this
newe deuised religion was spredd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade
by meanes of many seditiouse
sermons, and erronyouse bookes, we
haue sene shamefastnes sodenly to be
shaken of, honestie to be chassed oute
of the countrie, man his lawe and God
hys lawe to be troden vnder fote, holy
thynges to be prophaned, godlynes to
be iested at, boldnes euery where to
scape skotfree, vnshamefastnes to be
mayntayned, many opinions contrary
one to the other, to bee scattered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade,
the vnity of Christ to be torne
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1259:29"/>
with sutes of dyuerse sectes, and in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
place where these mad men haue
come, the fyre of horrible discorde to
haue ben blowne vp. Out of this roote
haue spronge deadly displeasures, often
vprores, perylouse dagger drawinges:
hereof many blody battayles haue ben
fought, many slaughters done, many
spoyles co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, many mennes posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions
destroyed with fyre and sworde.
And now, I pray, you who is so blynde
which doth not see what crueltye ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth
in many of them, which haue
ben the authors of these opinyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, with
what disdaynefull arrogancye they do
iette vp and downe, with what maly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertnes
and cursed speaking they rayle
vpon good men? Adde now here vnto,
the breache of lawes, the contempt of
rule, the hatred of Kyngly authoritie,
the vnmercyfull treasons which these
men moste dyuelyshly deuyse agaynst
<pb facs="tcp:1259:30"/>
Princes. Recken here also, theyr se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crette
whysperynges, when they cast
theyr heades together how to destroy
and vndoo theyr Kynges, and whilst
most shamefully they worke theyr wo,
for whose wealth and good estate, they
ought to serue and call vpon God. For
who hath so littell wytte, that can not
perceaue, that this sect is alltogether
for the peoples to the, &amp; to feade theyr
humoure, and that it is more fyt to styr
vp &amp; increase, then to asuage and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minish
theyr folly and madnes? But all
these people pleasers, for so muche as
they be men of no wysdome or discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o,
but be led with an inordinate desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
of liberty, they loue not law, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye
iusticers, they wyshe in theyr hartes
that kinges were at the dyuel, that they
without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptrolme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t might liue as they
lyst. For they couet to be set free from
lawe and ordre, that they may be bond
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1259:30"/>
slaues to theyr owne wyl and naughtie
affecti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>os, is there any m<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a can deny this?
haue not we had the proofe of it by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples? doth not euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> see that
they shoote all at this marke, that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
being dispatched oute of the way,
there might none be left which shold
once say, black is theyr eye? Therefore
some Kinges they haue poysoned, some
they haue attempted to kyll with the
sworde, and haue cast many mysche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouse
fetches, how to pull them oute
of theyr seate. But peraduenture some
man wyll say,<note place="margin">An heretis cal obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> this hath not chaunsed
for any grudge which those good men
haue borne toward Kynges, but only
for the diuersytye and variance of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.
And that it were not to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
that the mad and mysheuouse mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude
myght worke them any displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure,
if Princes wold agree with them
aboute ordring and appointyng of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb facs="tcp:1259:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:1259:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:1259:32"/>
He which will say thys, of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessytie
he must graunt,<note place="margin">A Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer.</note> that it is the
intent and meaning of this newe deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
religion, by hooke or by crooke to
seke the death of those Prynces, which
will not forsake the religion in which
they haue ben vertuously and wysely
brought vp, to come to the lure of the
mad people. Againe, he doth not wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sely
weygh, how that the end of this
sect, is ouermuche libertye, which can
be kept in no ordre, then the which,
nothing can be more contrary to the
offyce and regiment of Kynges. For a
Kyng his offyce is, to cutte vp vice with
the knyfe of punishment, but the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brydled
people doo desyre to be dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered
from the feare of all punishme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.
A Kyng is the executor,<note place="margin">The office of a Kyng &amp; the will of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</note> keper, and
maintayner of the lawes, but the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
as muche as it is able, with rashnes
doth rent and al to teare them. A kyng
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1259:32"/>
studieth for peace and quietnes, but the
people all together vnruly, doth seke
troble and disturbaunce. Laste of all, a
king doth not think, that all thinges
are to be bestowed of euery man a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke,
but as euery man is more worthie
then an other, so he rewardeth hym af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
the rate of his desert. But the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
wolde not haue one better then an
other, and desyreth to haue heauen and
yearth mingled togeather. So that as in
no sauce it can abyde anie superiours,
so moost cheifely it hateth kinges to
the deathe. For it can not away with
any excellencie of more worthynes.
and it stryueth all to this end, either to
destroy Kinges vtterly, or els to bryng
them in to a trappe of trobles. This I
graunte doth not appeare at the fyrst,
but as sone as a company of madde
rakehels groweth to any strengthe or
powre, then theyr boldnes being enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged
<pb facs="tcp:1259:33"/>
with long sufferaunce, and winc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
at, bursteth oute to the vndoing
<hi>&amp;</hi> ouerthrowing of the Kynge his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie.
Therefore seing this is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
of the ignorant people,<note place="margin">The natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of the ignorant people.</note> so sone as
they haue gotten people pleasyng cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,
which with theyr railing sermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
may puff them vp as it were with
wyndy blastes, and rayse mightie waues
of foly and madnes, surely Princes doo
vnwisely which doo not nyp wycked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
in the hed, so sone as it doth begyn,
but cherishe it with theyr sofftnes, and
strengthen it with theyr bearing. For
they do not perceaue that they make a
rod for them selues, when they suffre
that to spryng and increase, which at
the last being growne to a hed, wil pul
them oute of theyr throne, and so when
it is to late, they shall se that they haue
bred theyr owne bane, which they shall
not be able to remedy when they wold.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1259:33"/>
Wherefore then they shall drynke of
the whyp for theyr madnes, as all other
Princes doo, which take vpon then to
further and mayntayne with publike
authoritie, the folish fansye of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
people. But peraduenture they
wyll deny that this is a people pleasyng
sect. Then what is a people pleasyng
sect if this be not? doth it not euery
where styrre vp sedityon?<note place="margin">A profe that this new lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is a people plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sing sect.</note> doth it not
breake the bandes of all iustice and
lawes? doth it not resist rule and kingly
regime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? doth it not put all men in hope
of to muche lewde libertie? For where
is rule moste dispysed? where are the
Princes had in most derisyon of the c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
people? surely in those places
where this pestilent learning doth gett
the vpper hand. Therefore if this mad
enterprise take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> myscheuousely in hand
of these people pleasers, and vnaduy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sedly
wynked at of Princes, shall grow
<pb facs="tcp:1259:34"/>
to a rypenes, which way so euer it ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth,
it wyll quyte ouerturne all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
and strengthe of kyngly estate.</p>
            <p>Beleue me (o Quene,) this sect which
for oure synnes hath ouer run many
partes of Christe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dome, is the vndoing
of common wealthes, the marring of
good ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners, the spoyling of kyngdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes,
and the destruction of all kyngly
honoure. But you will say, that you sett
not so muche by your reigne, that for
the loue of it, you wold lese the ryches
of the euerlasting kyngdome, and that
you wold willingly abyde any aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
that you might entre in to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
I will not meruaile if you will say this.
For it is the poynte of a noble mynd,
to despyse the fletyng pleasures of this
short lyfe, &amp; to be greatly in loue with
immortalitye. For what goodnes is in
thys lyfe? what part of it is quyt of
daunger? what is it which is not hemd
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1259:34"/>
in on euery syde with sorowfullnes?
as for laughinges, feastinges, mynstrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sye,
sportinges, dalyaunces, many gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes
do follow them, and al delightes are
ended often tymes with pitifull &amp; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable
mysfortunes. And put the
case, that all thinges chaunce as we
wolde haue them, yet we must abyde
the sharp shoure of death, which neuer
is farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, but alway is at our back,
and dayly pyncheth somethyng from
oure lyfe. For it is a folly to thynke
death then to drawe neare when it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
an end of oure lyfe, and not to fele
the force of it, when dayly it doth crop
and by littell and littell wasteth oure
lyfe. For euerye day, deathe dothe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croche
vpon vs, and what so euer parte
of oure age passeth away, it is deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
by the crueltie of deathe. Therfore
seing oure lyfe dothe so swyftly ebbe
away, and in so lyttell co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuaunce of
<pb facs="tcp:1259:35"/>
tyme, is subiect to so many grefes and
miseries, &amp; all greate possessions glyde
away in a minute of an howre, what
is a greater poynte of wysdome, then
to sett at naught all the tryfles of this
lyfe, and to gyue oure mynde to seke
after heauenly and euerlasting thinges?
Wherefore if this be your mynde, that
thoughe you sholde hazarde all youre
riches, you wolde not weygh it a straw,
so that by such meanes you might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare
youre selfe away to heauen, I can
neuer worthilye prayse the noble dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position
of your princely hart. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for
I gyue you councell, that if the ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers
of this newe religion, can fynde out
anye meanes, howe you maye come a
nearer way to heauen, although great
losse of goods shold follow you by their
doctrine, you notwithstanding sholde
make muche of them, and thynk them
worthy of all preferment. For small
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1259:35"/>
thinges are not to be compared with
greate, worldly thinges with heauenly,
transitorie thinges with euerlasting.</p>
            <p>Nowe then, what doe they bring with
them of suche force to get heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that
auncyent religion is to be forsake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that
the profit and highe estate of the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
is to be lyttell estemed? Perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture
some man wyll say:<note place="margin">An hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation.</note> O yes, they
bryng with them a great furtheraunce
to heauen, and wonderfully to be com
mended. For these men be not inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors
of nouelties as fond men do drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me,
but rather they laboure to restore
all thinges which were decayed, to the
perfection of theyre auncient and first
institution: for it muche greueth them
that the purenes of Christian religion,
which Christ and his disciples dyd lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue
behynde, is choked with many su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitions,
and corrupted with many
abuses: therfore they haue found out a
<pb facs="tcp:1259:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:1259:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:1259:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:1259:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:1259:38"/>
notable way, how they may put down
all superstition, and scoure oute all the
blottes of Christian righteousnes, that
so at the length, Christian religion may
recouer the light and purenes which it
had lost.<note place="margin">A catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like consy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning an excellent quyppe.</note> Surely this is a worthy act, and
deseruing immortall prayse. For what
can be inu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted either better, for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitablenes,
or more excellent, for the
worthynes, then in suche an infection
and decay of good manners, in suche a
spoyle and ouerthrow of all good thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
for one to step furth inspyred with
such vertue, that he can set a new glasse
vpon olde manners, that he can heale
thynges which are wounded, that he
can repayre thinges fallen in to ruine,
that he can clense religion fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all fylth,
and make all holye thinges perfect?</p>
            <p>Wherefore it is no meruayle, if many
which were hartily in loue with god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes,
dyd take the decay of true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1259:38"/>
heauely, and being intysed with
suche goodly promises, dyd willingly
follow whither those men dyd lead the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
But before they had lept so farre, they
shold haue looked, of what abylitye
these promysers had ben.<note place="margin">what shold haue ben co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>sydered ere credit had be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to these fayre pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misers.</note> For as mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunt
men do measure euery man his
fydelitye according to hys riches, for
they neuer credit hym whome they
think vnable to stand to his promyse,
so in suche greate vauntes, regarde was
to be had, not only with what woordes
they dyd warrant, but rather muchemore
it was to be weighed with discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
whether they were able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
and acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plyshe that which they
had spoken. Therefore it was requisyte,
that he which shold take vpon hym so
great &amp; notable an enterpryse, shold be
a man of a meruaylouse vpryghteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
sagenes, sobrietye, manly corage,
stedfastnes, rauished with the loue of
<pb facs="tcp:1259:39"/>
heauenly thynges, furnished and reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished
with greate gyftes of the holy
ghoste. More ouer thys is to be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,
for so muche as in tyme past, there
haue ben many most holye and wyse
men, excelling in all kynde of godlynes
and neuer any of them could fynde in
hys hart, to further thys good intent of
youres after suche sorte as these men
haue fyrst inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, that it standeth with
reason that these men which do take
vpon them to fullfyll your desyre, after
suche a newe and vnknowen fashyon,
shold so farre passe those excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies
in vertue, as thys maystrye which
they haue taken in hand, is more to be
praysed then all the thynges whiche
those holy men dyd in theyr lyfe tyme.
But I pray you, is there any of these
men, more holy, more sobre, more
stronge to godward, then Athanasius,
Basyll, Ambrose, Ierome, Augustyne, or
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1259:39"/>
other fathers of most excele<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wysdome
and religion? no doughtles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what then?
could such a greate matter be brought
to passe with meane and common ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue?
it is not to be beleued. But let vs
relent thus muche to them, and let vs
graunt that it might be, that God in
oure dayes wold reuele to them which
were of meane behauyoure,<note place="margin">Note.</note> that kynde
of doctrine inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to redresse and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which was hyd from the
holy fathers. Yet at the least, they must
graunte, that he whome the wysdome
of God wold set ouer suche an offyce,
ought to be a man of indifferent ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
and godlines. For God is not wont
to commit honorable offyces of holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
and honestie, to naughtie and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
persons, <hi>&amp;</hi> they can beare no sway
among wyse men whose lyues are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famed
with dishonestie. Therefore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
to the discharging of so weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:1259:40"/>
an offyce, I did require not without
a cause excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vertue and authoritie,
yet for all that, because it might seme
vnreasonable among suche dreggishe
doctoures, to looke for the examples
of vertue and honestie which was vsed
in olde tyme, I will now content my
selfe with meane vertue and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.
Tell me therefore, who was he so
discrete, so perfect of lyffe, and ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners,
that it was lyke that God dyd put hym
in trust with this offyce? who was the
beginner and founder of this learning?
<note place="margin">Luther the fyrst founder of this fond doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trine.</note>
who was the hedd carpenter of thys
goodlye buylding? forsothe Luther.
what ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner a fellow was this Luther?
surely that I may speake the best of
hym, he was a man neither sobre, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
discrete, but hedlong, rashe, mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheuous,<note place="margin">Luthers lewde scollers.</note>
seditious, and of all other the
greatest people pleasure, and what ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
of men were they which afterward
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1259:40"/>
sprange oute of hys scole as oute of a
well? vndoughtedly, bold, standing in
their owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceite, puft vp with pryde,
and (that I may say no wurse by them)
men not so indued with vertue, that
we being moued with their authoritie,
shold forsake the rules of the religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in
which we were brought vp. Therefor
how can it synk in to a wyse man his
hed, that oure most holy Lorde,<note place="margin">A questio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> insoluble and able to choke all heretykes.</note> which
allwayes hath imbraced symple, lowly,
and humble men, and hath lyghtned
with hys brightnes the myndes of such
as take nothing vpon them, now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
to his accustomed manner, shold
ouer hyp symple and humble men, and
shew them this new and strau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge light,
which haue no sparke of shamefastnes
or modestie? Now I say, how cometh
it to passe, that these fellowes who as
it appeareth by many tokens, be gyuen
to worldly delightes, haue only most
<pb facs="tcp:1259:41"/>
wittily spyed out that which was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
to so holy fathers, kyndled with
the loue of purenes, and as it were set
on fyre with the desyre of godly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge?
But now I reason not of what
authoritie they be. For it cometh to
passe through the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of many, that
men can not perceaue that they which
are not to be reuerensed for any nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
vertue,<note place="margin">Syn is the cause that men can not see the folly of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se teachers.</note> be not able to performe that
which they do pretend. Let vs therefor
graunt, if it please them, that it may be
by some meanes, that they which be
not to be praysed for any excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,
and go not beyond others in the
loue of Godlynes, may take in hande
and accomplysh that which men most
famouse for theyr vertue and Godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
were not able to bryng to passe.</p>
            <p>Therefor after what sort haue they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned
that?<note place="margin">An excuse commonly vsed of all heretikes.</note> Because (say they) those
men whome you meane, although they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1259:41"/>
dyd follow the spirite of God, and were
ernestly bent towarde the woorde of
God, yet they did leane to much to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
authority: but we thinck it vnseme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
for vs to stick to the authority of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
to be bound to the traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of men, to
weygh what is right &amp; honest according
to the reason and consyderatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of men.
we haue one only author and maister,
namely God, and we make our acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt,
that oure lyfe is to be drawen after the
rule of hys worde, and not after me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes
decrees, and ordynaunces.<note place="margin">A trymiro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nia against heritikes.</note> O these be
m<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e worthy to be wondred at, and with
cap and knee to be worshipped. For
they so speake as they now hadd not
one iote of man hys nature in them,
and as though they were not made of
fleshe and bone as other men be. For
they forsothe, haue mortifyed all theyr
sences with fayth, they haue parted the
soule fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the body, neither do they only
<pb facs="tcp:1259:42"/>
defy man hys nature, but also they dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyse
all the authorities of holy men.
For beynge losed from the lynkes of
nawghtie desyres, they be flowen vp in
to heauen, that they may behold none
other thynge but God, and that they
may make none other of theyr cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell
but the holy ghost. If it be so, I take
them in dede to be men of God, for as
S. Paule wytnesseth, they be the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
of God,<note place="margin">A strong profe that the hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of oure time be not men of god as they wold seme.</note> whiche bee led with the
spyrit of God, and they which bee the
children of God, questyonles bee fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyshed
with godlye vertues. But now
Syr, yf theyr shamfull doynges, do dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue
theyr shameles sayinges, shall
we beleue them, so often as they make
theyr vaunt that they followe only the
worde of God? for yf in all theyr do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges
they doe according to God hys
worde, then they follow not couetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
hatred, wrathe, ambityon, but they
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1259:42"/>
be all together made perfect with ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues
which spryng out of the worde of
God. If they be not indued with suche
heauenly vertues, then doe they lye in
saying, that they only and all to gether
do frame them selues to the worde of
God, for wyckednesses and the worde
of God can not dwell together. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
eyther they dyrect not theyr lyffe
after the worde of God, eyther they do
not commit any abhominable or sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mefull
syn, for if they syn shamefully,
and abhominably, vndoughtedly they
be not squared to the worde of God.
But they commyt many hyduouse of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences
and synnes, as al the worlde can
wytnesse, therfore it is false to say that
they be gouerned with God hys word,
and the inspiration of the holyghoste.</p>
            <p>But let vs leaue this darke kynde of
disputyng, and demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of them some
token of this worde of God, whiche
<pb facs="tcp:1259:43"/>
they all wayes be chatting on. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
you shal giue me leaue (o Quene)
that I maye searche and ransake all
this matter so farr, tyll it appeare howe
trymly these men do handle the Ghos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.<note place="margin">A chale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge chokyng al heritikes.</note>
Nowe then, I wolde willinglye
heare of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whether these many yeares
they haue wrought any notable feate,
which may inforce vs to confesse that
they grownde onlye vppon the worde
of God. Well sayde, (wyll they saye)
but you knowe that it is the office of
God his worde,<note place="margin">A common clok which heritikes vse.</note> (as it is written in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remye)
before it buylde newe, to pull
downe the olde buyldynges, before it
grafte frutefull trees, to pluck vp by the
rootes, those which be barren and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profytable.
I knowe it well: therefore
I looke and stand as it were in a mase,
to beholde what you pull downe, and
what you roote vp with this your good
ly attempt, that at the length I may see
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1259:43"/>
Christ his howse raysed vp, and his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyne
bewtifully set, with the heauenly
graftes of all manner of vertues. Go to
nowe, bestyrre you a pase, plye the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
tyll you sweate, that you may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
to fynyshe a worke of suche excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie.
Do as muche as in you lyeth, to
ouerthrowe the walles of Satan, to pull
downe pryde, to refrayne angre &amp; cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
speaking, to picke oute all the brys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles
of vncleane and fylthye desyres, to
plucke vp by the rootes all occasyon
of stryffe and debate, that so at the laste
you may laye the foundations of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
humilitye and lowlynes, and that
you may plant sobrietie of lyfe, &amp; cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitie,
ioyned with moste pure religyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
&amp; that you may set the graftes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stian
loue and charitie. You gyue good
councell say they: but before this, there
is an other thyng that we wyll destroy
and pull downe. In the name of God.
<pb facs="tcp:1259:44"/>
what thing is that so heynouse and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testable,
that you wyll fyrst endeuoure
youre selfe, to dispatche that oute of
the way, before you vtterly ouerthrow
these so pestilent poysons of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kynd?
O saye they, it is a greuouse thynge,
an vntolerable thing,<note place="margin">The fyrst spoyle of heretykes.</note> a secret myschefe,
and for the abhominablenes of it, to be
quyte rased out of all remembraunce.
For we wyll rushe in to those howses,
in which holye virgins being inclosed,
day and night do syng hymnes to the
glory of God, and praye to Christ for
the good estate of Kynges and Pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
and for the sauegarde of the whole
communaltie. We wyl pull downe the
fences of shamfastnes, we wyll breake
open the inclosures of chastitie, and we
wyll no longer suffer wel fauoured vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyns
to be barred of theire solace and
pleasures, to lack the comfort and ayde
of theire children, and to spend theire
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1259:44"/>
younge yeares in sorrowfull solytary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
and miserable vnfrutefullnes. In
faithe, I allowe this youre charitie and
louing kyndnes. What wyl you do mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re?<note place="margin">The seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d spoyle of heritikes.</note>
Then we will make a law for Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes,
or solitary lyuers, whose howses we
wyll pull downe lykewyse, or let them
oute to hyer, it skilleth not to what lay
men, and charge them vnder payne of
deathe, that here after, none presume
for religious sake, to wrastle co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynually
against his lecherouse lustes. For why?
It is an heynouse offence, and in no
sauce to be borne withall. What do I
heare? Doest thou reclame men to the
streightnes of religion,<note place="margin">Note a god ly defence of ppetuall chastitie.</note> which was in
the primitiue churche, which so busily
doest destroye that thing whiche was
muche to be merueyled at in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue
churche, and which contayned
the image of heauenlye purenes? For
what is more meruailouse, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> subduing
<pb facs="tcp:1259:45"/>
the lustes, which withdrawe the mynde
from contemplation of heauenly thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
to thincke wholy on the fayrenes
of God, &amp; to be rauished with the loue
of his diuinitie? It is an hard matter,
say you. Yea if you please, let it be of all
other most hard, so that we vnderstand,
that the harder it is, the more it auaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth
the glory of God, which hathe so
strengthened oure feble nature, that
for loue of purenes, it is able to resyst
that tickling pleasure, with which natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
we be intangled, and being wonne
with the swetenes of heauenly delight,
can forsake and lothe all bodyly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure.
Therfore if any man rauished with
the loue of godly lyfe, and to the intent
he may gyue hym selfe to the consyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
of heauenly thynges, shall kepe
hym self from the moste troblesome
cares of marryage<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if any virgyn infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
with the loue of euerlasting glory
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1259:45"/>
and honestie, with an ernest good will,
shall take that vppon her which is sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
sene and hard to performe, and
shall of her owne accorde, inclose her
selffe in a religyouse howse, that so be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
voyde of all other cares, she may be
coupled to Christ with a more streight
and holy band of professyon, and by
the spyrit of Christ, to whom she hath
offered her selffe, shall constantlye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayne
all vncleane and vnchaste desy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,
is there any man so farr from ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesty,
so muche an enimye to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
of God, that he wyll detest it as a
greuouse and abhominable offence?
Surely suche a man is to be suspected.
For euen so (as Athanasius and other
holy men do,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>A</hi> iuste cause to suspect the new teachers of oure tyme.</note> make mentyon) dyd the
heretikes of olde tyme. With the lyke
hatred, they did persecute chastitie: with
suche rage, they dyd disquyet the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasteries
of religyouse virgyns. And as
<pb facs="tcp:1259:46"/>
muche as lay in them, wolde not suffer
that ther shold be any, which according
to the councell of Christ, for the loue
and desyre of the heauenly kyngdome,
might forsake all carnall pleasure, and
by contynuall worshipping of God,
might in holynes bothe of bodye and
sowle, here in yearthe, followe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble
the conuersation of the sayntes
which be in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But now, I wyll stay
my selffe. For it is not reason that I
sholde bewayle that which is taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,
before I see what is set vp in the
place of that which is pulled downe.
For as yet there may be hope, that the
worthynes of the thing which shall be
brought in, may make amendes for the
thing which is put oute. Now then,<note place="margin">The third spoyle of heritikes.</note> go
on. What hathe this worde which you
bragg on so muche ouerthrowen, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syde
all this which we haue spoken of?
Forsothe all the pictures of Sayntes, all
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1259:46"/>
the signes of Christ his crosse, all payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
tables in the which any thing was
set oute, which might put vs in mynde
of the mercy of God, or of any notable
vertue. Neither hereafter wyll we in
any wyse suffer the image of oure Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyour
Christ, or symilitude of his holy
Sayntes, to be set in any open or secret
places. And this doing, certainlye cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth
me to suspect, that these men mynd
no lesse, but by lyttell and lyttell to pull
all remembraunces of Christ oute of
our myndes. For seing nothing is more
conuenient to quicken oure memorye
then sygnes and images,<note place="margin">A true de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of images.</note> and seing this
is oure especyall dutie, allway to think
on God, &amp; to remembre his benefytes
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually, and for so muche as in thys
lyfe we haue so many lettes, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke
oure myndes to stray from so godly
and necessary cogitations, I pray you
then, what offence is it to haue those
<pb facs="tcp:1259:47"/>
remembraunces euer before oure eyes,
which may often styrr vs vp to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
the mercye and kyndenes of God,
and make our myndes more sharpe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde
the loue of Godlynes? But we
may fynde faulte with this folly of thei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,
when we shall perceaue that they
bryng no better salue with them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy
the weakenes of man, which may
more depelye prynt the benefytes of
Christe in the hartes of the vnlearned
people,<note place="margin">The four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th spoyle of herety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes.</note> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this beholding (as they say)
of dome images. Is there any thing els
that your fyngers itche at, tyll you haue
it downe? Yea mary is there. We wyll
make hauock of churche goodes, of ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimonies,
and of all the sacramentes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
Loe also, thys is a thyng, which sholde
make a man quake for feare. wylt thou
(o heritike) abolyshe the holye ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces
which Christ hath ordeined?
which his Apostles haue appoynted to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1259:47"/>
be obserued? which holy churche hath
allowed? which do rote in our myndes
the remembraunce of Christ,<note place="margin">A Godly defence of the cerimo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies and sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cramentes.</note> by oft re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peting
his benefytes, with the which we
haue fastened our selues vnto hym as it
were with a true loue knott, by meanes
of the which we be clensed from syn,
we be hartned with heauenlye foode,
and be defended with the ayde of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible
vertue? For what other thing
wolde the Turcke and other infydells
doo? Oh it is a miserable, a greuouse,
a lamentable case, and not to be borne
withall of a Chrystyan man, to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reued
of such holy comfortes, through
which he remembreth that often tymes
he hath receaued the benefytes of God
his grace, and that which is more ody<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouse,
to be bereued of suche Christian
comfortes, by the councell, study, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement,
and endeuoure of Christian
men. Tushe you do but tryfle (say they)
<pb facs="tcp:1259:48"/>
which do thinke that our holynes and
ryghteousnes doth consist in these ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rymonies,<note place="margin">An heriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> whereas in deed, it all to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
resteth in the grace and mercy of
Christ. As who sholde say, we knewe
not that: as who sholde saye, we haue
readen nothing, we haue hard nothing,
no heauenlye bryghtnes at anye tyme
hath shyned vpon vs, or that this is the
fyrst tyme, that anye suche thing was
tolde vs. Beleue me,<note place="margin">A catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng oure iustificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> we neuer dough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
that all the cause of oure iustifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon,
was to be imputed to the mercy
of God, and the most holye merites of
Christ. Notwithstanding we defend
this, that we can not withoute greate
trespasse leaue those thinges vndone,
which the same author of our saluation
hathe ordeined, as meanes to make vs
more fyt to be partakers of his diuine
benefytes, and to strengthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
with all ayde and assistaunce.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:1259:48"/>
Moreouer we affirme, that so oft as we
duly ministre the holy sacramentes, we
do sensiblye perceaue, that those holye
mysteries were assigned and appoynted
of him, by the which, he wold often put
vs in mynde of hys greate goodnes, by
the which, he might in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
oure eyes, the paynes which he
fuffred for vs. By the which, he might
more ernestly styr vp oure faith, and to
be short, by the which, he might more
plentyfully styll in to oure hartes the
dewe of hys grace. we truly which do
receaue greate comforte of those thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
which the more we be occupied
in executyng of them, the more we fele
Godly deuotion to encrease in vs, do
worthily bewayle suche thynges to be
taken away of you, onlesse you, as of
duty you ought, do restore better thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
in theyr place. Is there any thyng
els, in pulling downe of the which, you
<pb facs="tcp:1259:49"/>
may brag of your dyligence? Yea cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teynely
very many. For where so euer
we come,<note place="margin">The fyft spoyle of heretykes.</note> we stretche all the strynges
of oure wyt to thys end, that we may
deface the autoritie of the Prestes and
Bishops, that we may delyuer the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
from thraldome of the Pope, and
that we may disanull all there lawes and
ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, that there may be nothing
to let a Christyan man of hys libertie.
And I pray you, what other thyng is
this, but to rypp Chryst hys cote, to
breake the ordre which he hathe made,
to disquyet the peace of hys churche,<note place="margin">4. notable argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes for the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacye.</note>
to cast innumerable bones of debate,
to set men to gether by the eares? For
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> as there is one faythe, one religion, one
churche, so is it nedefull that it be ruled
and gouerned chefely by the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
of one. Otherwyse, there shall ryse
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> manyfolde yea infinyte religyons one
contrary to the other, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1259:49"/>
shall be mayntayned, whiche may
not be nombred. For euery man wyll
inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t a churche, according to his owne
fantasye. Then the which thyng, what
can be imagined more confuse &amp; oute
of ordre, more contrary to the lawes
and commaundementes of Chryste?
More ouer lay to thys that when Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes
be dryuen oute and thrust from <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
their roumes, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the autoritie of the
Pope is despysed, and trodden vnder
foote, then temporall Prynces, agaynst
all God hys forbode, take vpon them
to rule matters of religyon, to medle
with holy thinges, and by suche sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
do heape vpon them God hys
heauye displeasure. Againe, who do the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
not see, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the religyouse rules which
be conteined in the Popes constituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
be taken away, that all feare is put
to flyght, and licentiouse liuyng dothe
raigne withoute comptrollement? As
<pb facs="tcp:1259:50"/>
who sholde say (say they) we shote at
any other marcke,<note place="margin">Mark this bragg of hereticall teachers co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning securitie.</note> then to pull all feare
oute of mens myndes? For we be the
patrones of perfect libertie, and it is so
farr of, that we wyl suffer those which
be our disciples, to stand in awe of any
thyng, that we will quyte set them free
from fearing of God. For the which
thing veryly our scollers are muche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdyng
to vs, for it was to sore an hart
breake day and night to feare God, and
by that meanes, to pyne away with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumyng
carefullnes. Therfore we haue
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded all those which beleue in
Christ, to set cocke on hoope, &amp; crye
care away. For we beare them in hand,
that fayth is of suche force, that laying
once hand of it, thoughe he be neuer
so mischeuouse a lym of the dyuell, yet
he may warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hymselfe the fauoure of
Christ, and blysse euerlasting. So that
there is nothing which sholde make a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1259:50"/>
man a fearde,<note place="margin">Note well this lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of securitie, with a stro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g profe that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian men ought to stand in feare, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Protesta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chinges.</note> if he be harnessed with
this faythe. What is this which sown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
in myne eares? Wylt thou take
awaye the feare of God? Wylt thou
shake of that awe which the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes
of God beate in to the hartes of men?
I pray the, whoeuer was suche a people
parasite, so seruiceable to please the
madnes of the common sorte, that he
durst be so bolde as to encorage men
from fearing of God? In deede, suche
people pyke thankes, haue often tymes
reiected the rule of Princes, haue disa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulled
lawes which abridged &amp; restrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
the people of their wanton wyshes,
with promisyng them to lyue as they
lyst, they wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne the greatest sorte vnto
them, that thei might make a way vnto
their tyrannicall and vsurped autoritie:
but that they sholde not feare the iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement
of God, none of them all dyd
once open his mouthe, or made anye
<pb facs="tcp:1259:51"/>
proffer to perswade the people. For
they dyd knowe well inoughe, that the
man which dyd not feare God, wolde
not abyde to be vnder the rule and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience
of any man. For take away the
feare of God, how coulde you knowe
a man fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a beaste? or that I may tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
the truthe nearer the quyck, what
beaste is so outeragyouse and horne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mad,
which is to be compared in mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
to suche a man, which hathe no
feare of God before hys eyes?</p>
            <p>But nowe mark,<note place="margin">Oure pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testantes wursse the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ethni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this opinion of securite.</note> howe greate oddes
is betwene these Bible bablers, &amp; those
men which being all together wyde of
true worshipping of God, in olde time
dyd ordeyne common wealthes? they,
forsomuche as they dyd wysely consy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre,
that with oute the feare of God,
the people coulde not be kept in law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
subiection, dyd institute false and
feyned religions: these men from true
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:1259:51"/>
religion, haue fylched all feare, which
myght kepe men with in the listes and
bowndes of their dutie. Those other,
which perhappes beleued not that God
had any regard to worldly affaires, yet
they dyd beate the feare of God in to
the hartes of the rude people: but oure
men, which crake that they came oute
of God his bosome, and knowe all hys
secretes, doo plye the box busyly, that
they may seale Christian men a Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
from al feare of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and so make
them lyke blynde bayardes boldely to
leape in to the myar of al mischefe.</p>
            <p>nowe for all this, I do not yet reason
how well they behaue them selues, but
I declare what cause they do gyue men
to thynk yll of them. For they seme to
haue thys dryft in theyr heades, that
they may stopp all the hyghe wayes of
healthe and saluation, that they which
be shackled with any syn, may haue no
<pb facs="tcp:1259:52"/>
saffe passage or entraunce. For if they
haue shaken of all feare, which of them
wyll syghe for his synnes? who wyll
bewayle his offences committed? who
wyll hartily hate &amp; abhorr his nawgh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynes?
who from the bothome of his
harte, wyll long after honestie and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes?
who falling groueling at Christ
his fete, with teares wyll aske forgyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
for his mysdoynges? who wyll go
aboute to take oute the stayninges of
his synnes with allmesse dedes,<note place="margin">An hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> &amp; other
workes of mercye? What (say they)
doest thou put the holynes of our iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifycation
in weping and wayling, in
sobbyng and syghing at the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce
of oure synnes? Yea surelye.
And that I sholde so doo,<note place="margin">A catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke answer.</note> I am not led
with any lyght autoritie, but with the
determination of holy scripture. And
that you be not of that iudgement also,
I doo not a lyttel meruail. O (say they)
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:1259:52"/>
wepyng is a wytnesse of the weakenes
of faythe:<note place="margin">An here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply.</note> and as for mennes workes,
thoughe they be done with neuer so
godly a zeale, yet as a man wolde say,
they be so rotten at the rote, and so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelye
stayned with sokynge fylthynes,
that they can neuer be scoured or made
cleane. We therfore consyderyng these
thinges wysely, by no meanes doo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
oure saluation to stand in
wepyng, or in dedes of charitye,<note place="margin">A catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like solu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> but in
fayth onlye. These sayinges make me
more to merueile the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I dyd before. For
this faythe, which by meanes of Christ
his merites, maketh vs to haue accesse
vnto God, dothe followe the lawe of
God, dothe cleaue to his wordes, and
dothe not say nay to the commaundy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of our master Christ. Therefore
for so muche as the lawe of God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
vs to wepe, so oft as we slyp in to
any syn, &amp; seing that all the Prophetes
<pb facs="tcp:1259:53"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:1259:53"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:1259:54"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:1259:54"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:1259:55"/>
with lowde voyces do crye vnto vs, that
we sholde clense oure spotted sowle
with sorrowing and sobbyng, with wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyng
and performyng mercyfull dedes
of charitie,<note place="margin">O Osorius if you we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re fellowe of Trinitie colledge in Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bridge, you shold lese your fellowship as I knowe who dyd, for saing so in a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</note> seing the sone of God hym
selfe dothe say playnelye, that all they
which refuse to do penaunce, shall vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlye
peryshe, and forwarneth vs, that
they which wyll do good workes, shall
entre in to euerlastyng lyfe, but they
which worke wyckednesse, shall be tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented
with euerlastyng fyar, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude,
that the office and dutie of fayth
is, to mourne, to lament, to conceiue
an ernest hatred agaynst the accouste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
synnes, with a burnyng desyre to
returne from the byway of wickednes,
to the hyghe way of honest and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
conuersation. Which all thynges
truly faythe doth worthylye performe,
so oft as it is quick and lyuely, and not
faynting or ouercharged with the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1259:55"/>
of bodylye and carnall desyres.
Not that she chalengeth any thing to
her selfe, but because she knoweth by
godlye inspiration, that they onlye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue
the greate mercye of God, which
repent them of their former fylthynes,
&amp; with ernest affection do rendre them
selues vp to the following of God his
lawe. Therefore that fayth, by persua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syon
of the which, any man warranteth
hym selfe euerlastyng blysse, setting a
parte sorrowfullnes for his synnes past,
leauyng of to doo good workes, and
hath the loue of charitye cleane quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
in hym, I say that fayth, is not wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy
the name of fayth, but rather to be
called folyshe hardynes, hedlong hasty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
and prowde presumptuousenes.
Moreouer, all men may see that the
profyte of holsome repentaunce, is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
away, that the ardent loue of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
is made key cold, when men take
<pb facs="tcp:1259:56"/>
thys for a sure staff to leane on, that
theyr synnes be not forgyuen, for theyr
mourning, for theyr Godly sorrowing,
for any holy workyng,<note place="margin">Luthers opinion.</note> but rather that
in so doing, they heape new synnes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
theyr olde. For they take it to be a syn
to lament for theyr syn, and they hold
that no good worke can be done with
out syn. Therfor this is a doctrine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
to be wondered at, which hath so
malypertly taken in hand to set furthe
suche incredible thynges, and yet wold
haue men to gyue them credit. Is there
yet any thyng ells, so much to be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiled
at? so muche quoth you? Yea
which wyl cast you in to suche a mase,
as the head of Medusa sene at vnwares
could not more quickly turne men in
to a flynt stone.<note place="margin">The sixth spoyle co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted of the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes.</note> I pray you, what is
that? forsothe they bynd ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes reason
as it were to a poste, they spoyle hym
of lyberty to take councell, they wrap
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:1259:56"/>
hys wyll in fatall fetters, they bereaue
man all together of iudgement, and all
perceauerau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and they strype hym so
cleane of all free wyll, that there is no
difference betwene hym and a stone.</p>
            <p>For of all those thynges, which men
cast in theyr mynde, take in hand and
put in practyse, whether they be aught
or naught, they make God the causer
of them, they impute it to fatall neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sytie,
and say that it was predestyned
that they shold so do before they were
borne. Which saying if it be true, then
is there no councell to be taken in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires
of thys lyffe, then there is no iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement,
no prayse to do well,<note place="margin">Note here a goodlye reprofe of fatall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie taught of oure Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testantes.</note> no shame
to syn, no vse of iustice, then with oute
a cause, any rewarde is apoynted for
honestie, and it is agaynst reason, that
theyr shold be ordeyned any punishme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
for syn. For what reason is it, that I for
the syn which I dyd not of myne owne
<pb facs="tcp:1259:57"/>
accorde (for I was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>streyned of neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sytye
to do it) shold suffer euerlastyng
paynes? or what ryght is there, that I
shold be rewarded with euerlasting ioy
for that fayth which I kept only enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
and spurred forward of God, with
oute any will or dyligens of my parte?
And that which is horrible, and to be
detested, if we will leane to these ioly
fellowes autoritie, all the cause of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie
is to be layde to God hys charge.
For so they reason, that he without any
choyse or respect, only because it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
hym so, before all worldes, hath
appoynted who sholde be hys, whome
he wolde crowne with euerlastyng glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
and who shold be cast awayes, which
he wolde torment with euerlastyng pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyshment.
In the which theyre asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
I fynde fault bothe with theyr
constancie, and also their wysdome.</p>
            <p>With theyre constancie, because whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reas
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1259:57"/>
they make theyre vaunt,<note place="margin">This doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie maketh against the protestan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes them selues.</note> that they
be the autors of libertye, they all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
take awaye libertye. Except they
wyll graunt that at the fyrst, they dyd
teach men lycentiouse lyuing, and not
libertie, and that afterwarde, they dyd
deny them libertye, but not to lyue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiously:
I allowe not their wysdome,
because they troble them selues very
greately, and neade not. For if before
all worldes, God hath enacted, that we
shold receaue that doctryne which they
teache, to what purpose is it, euerye
where to beate it in to mens heades
with so many bookes, preachinges, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putinges,
perylls, and greate trauayles?
Except they will also say, that they be
compelled with the selfesame necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
to laboure, to watche, to haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flyctes
with many men, and that to no
end, and withoute any profyte. There
be many other thynges whiche disgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth
<pb facs="tcp:1259:58"/>
thys worde of God, vnder whose
banner these doughtie and polytyke
souldyoures, do crake that they fyght.
For it were an endles worke, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge
necessary, if I sholde recken
all, seing that whiche I haue sayde, is
inowghe for oure purpose.</p>
            <p>Nowe you see (o Quene,) of what
force this Ghospell is, to throwe down
and ouerturne those thinges, which we
sely sowles dyd not onlye thinck to be
nothyng hurtfull, but also to be so ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary
proppes of religion, that in such
decay of al good thinges in these dayes,
godlynes dyd seme to staye vppon the
maintenaunce of them.<note place="margin">Here En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland can witnesse whether Osorius doth lye.</note> It hath broken
downe the howses of holye virgins, it
hath put out that wonderfull example
of continuall chastitye, it hath defaced
and broken the sygnes which dyd often
renewe the memory of God his good
gyftes bestowed vpon vs, it hath quyte
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:1259:58"/>
dispatched oute of the way holy orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes,
cerymonies, the sacramentes,
with the which many mortall men were
greatlye styrred vp to the loue of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalytie.
They haue also remoued
out of the way for stumblyng, all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destye
and obedyence, by the which all
Christian men dyd stand in awe of the
cheife ruler of the church: it hath made
all the lawes of the church of none ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect:
it hathe wyped away the feare of
God: it hath chased away saddnes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
for syn: it hath grated oute the
grefe which the gyltie conscyence dyd
smyte in to mennes myndes for theyr
offences: it hath made men slacke to
doo good workes: fynallye whereas it
dyd allure all men to lybertie, it hathe
taken away libertye. What remayneth
nowe? Forsothe that we may see, what
these conyng craftes men with theyr di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence
haue restored in the place of
<pb facs="tcp:1259:59"/>
those thinges, which they haue taken
away. For suche men of God, and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters
of his holy worde, because they
haue abolysshed those thinges, which
dyd some good, displeased as they say,
for that they had a smacke of supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
of necessitye must restore muche
better and more holye thinges, if they
wyll stand to theyre promysse.</p>
            <p>For we seeing what that word of God
which they preache, hath pulled down,
and rooted vp, is it not requisyte, that
we shold behold what it hath buylded
&amp; planted in steade of it? Now what is
it that they haue repayred &amp; renewed?
what is it that they haue sowne? what
profyte is there which the world doth
fele by them? surely none at all. I see
what is toppled ouer, but I see not
what is sett vp agayne. I see what is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,
but I see no good thing as yet ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed.
But (will they say) do you thynk,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:1259:59"/>
that it is but a smal matter, to restrayne
the wanton manners of men, with the
strayght disciplyne of the primityue
church, and to restore Christian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
with greate trauayle, to that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
from the which now of late for
the most parte it is flyded? Surely I
take that to be no small matter, but a
thyng of suche excellency, that if you
performe it, I will beleue verily, you be
men of God, and angels flowne down
from heauen. Therefore let vs see this.<note place="margin">A question to put the protesta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes to silence.</note>
haue you taken in hand to embr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ace
mekenes and humilitye with an ernest
and ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t affection? haue you cast far
from you the bytter gall of deadly ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred,
of rayling and cursed speakyng?
haue you crucifyed your fleshly desyres,
that they being quenched, you may
more easylye lyft vp youre mynde to
thyncke of heauenly thynges? haue you
shewed any meruaylouse token of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb facs="tcp:1259:60"/>
and godlynes, by the which we may
perceaue the auncyent bryghtnes of the
Ghospell, and the paterne of that most
pure holynes and charitye, vsed in olde
tyme? no, I assure you. But the more
any man doth apply hym selfe to thys
doctryne,<note place="margin">Howe the disciples of this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytt.</note> the wurser he waxeth, the
more he flowteth those which be playn
and ryght dealyng men, the more he is
set on fyre with hatred agaynst com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
peace and quyetnesse, and is puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed
vp with most fantastycall vanityes.
For he taketh that wysdome vpon hym
which neuer man could yet obteyne.
And so standyng in hys owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceite,
what so euer toy taketh hym in the
heade, that he so ernestly doth defend,
as if he shold alleadge any worde co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng
oute of God hys owne mouth,
with so headlong boldnes he disquye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
all thynges, as in dede he sholde
seme to couet nothyng more, then to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:1259:60"/>
see an hochepoche made of all the
world. Therefore which way so euer
they crepe in to mennes bosomes, that
they may vtter theyr Ghospel vnto the
vnlearned people, they are so farr from
mendyng mennes manners, that they
make all thynges in wurse case then
they found the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For they banish sham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fastnes,
and let carnalitie raunge lose
abroade, and takyng away the feare of
God, without punishment they gyue
men leaue to lyue so wyckedly as they
lyst. So it cometh to passe, that wylfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
doth more vehemently burst oute,
that lecherouse lyfe dothe more sone
consume mennes ryches, that boldnes
doth more bragg, and goeth aboute
more heynouse enterpryses. For what
shall I speake, how daungerouse tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaylyng
it is by the hyghe wayes for
feare of robbing? what shall I recken
the disagreinges and furyouse fallynges
<pb facs="tcp:1259:61"/>
oute which raygne euery where? what
shall I sett oute the conspiracyes, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,
and murders entreprysed agaynst
Princes? But you will say, these euells
were allway in all common wealthes.
no man sayth nay to that. But I wold
haue those myschefes redressed with
thys youre so holsome and profytable
doctryne. The which thing, because it
doth not bryng to passe, but rather the
more it encreaseth, the greater offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
are committed, and more vnshame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fastly
attempted euen of those which
desyre to be called the discyples of
such masters: it is a stro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that
they were not styrred vp to preache
by the secrete workyng and inspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the holy ghoste.<note place="margin">A notable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paryson betwene the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cient teachers, and oure new start<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vp Gho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spellers.</note> But consider
what difference is betwene the olde
professors of the Ghospell and these
which beare men in hand that thei fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe
theyr foote steppes. They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:1259:61"/>
of God the doctrine, with the
which they gaue lyght to the worlde:
these men leaning to theyr owne wit
and inuention, toke vpon them to be
doctors and teachers. They, brydled the
ryotouse manners of men with seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
punishement, gyuing also a meruai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louse
example of innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie and chas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titye:
these men with theyr naughtie
example and lycentiouse doctrine, do
set mennes tethe more on edge to all
kynde of vnhappynes. They, exhorted
men to humility, to lowlynes, mekenes
and pacyence: these men for the most
part doo teache theyr scollers, pryde,
crueltie, scolding and cursed speaking.
They, dyd aswage the oute ragyouse
desyres of men with puttyng them in
mynde to feare God, and councelled
them, which had fallen into any syn, to
weping, fasting, &amp; praying: these men
inioyning no penaunce or penaltie to
<pb facs="tcp:1259:62"/>
them which are lode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with syn, do harte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
&amp; encorage the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to all vnshamefastnes.
They, by all meanes possible, dyd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe
men from bodyly pleasures, that
they myght the more be inflamed with
the loue of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly thinges: these men
do surrender their scollers fast bounde
to bodyly delyghtes, to the intent they
may wayte, and gyue attendau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vpon
their lecherouse lustes: fynallye, they,
seing they were all of one mynde, for
so muche as they were the discyples of
one master, that is to say, of the holy
ghoste, so that one coulde not iarr fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
an other, dyd knyt men to gether with
the sure bond of peace, and dyd fasten
the good willes of all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with the glue
of mutuall loue and frendeshyp: But
these men, for so muche as euery one
of them according to hys owne fyckle
fansye, dothe blab oute &amp; tell for truth
what so euer he dothe dreame of, and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:1259:62"/>
by meanes of that are dispersed in to
diuerse and innumerable sectes, they
breake peace, they rayse vpp debates,
and procure bloody battailes. In olde
tyme none of those, whiche I haue spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
of, did minystre poysons, none wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyngly
did shake the sworde against his
country men, none did take councell
to destroy theire Princes, none did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue
hym selfe wantonlye or vndiscre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telye
vpon his ale benche. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
they did excell in all the prayses of
moste noble vertues, yet this vertue was
to be merueiled at in them, that they
wolde pray to God for the healthe and
wealthe of suche as did them greate
wronge: being rayled on, they did not
gyue fowle language agayne: when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury
was done vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, so sone as they
were able, they did a good turne to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
which harmed them: being cast in to
mysery<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they wyshed no euell to those,
<pb facs="tcp:1259:63"/>
which against lawe and conscience dyd
vnmercyfully handle them: seruauntes
dyd serue theyr masters with greate
trustines: souldyours in battayle for the
saffegarde of the common wealth, dyd
fyght manfullye, and in tyme of peace
they did not refuse the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundiment
of theyr Princes, so farr as they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded
nothing contrary to the lawe
of God: but rather obeyed all rulers, as
the ministres of God, allthough theyr
lyfe disagreed from Christian religion.
Therfore they so behaued themselues,
that nether in peace, nether in warr, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
when they were at leasure, nether
when they were occupyed, nether in
pryuate busynes, or in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon affayres,
they myght commyt any thyng which
myght set the common weale oute of
ordre, or gyue men occasyon to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended
through their synfull and wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
example. I let passe to speake of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:1259:63"/>
the fastynges, heare clothes, watchyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
with the which they dyd coole the
heate of theyr burnyng desyres, and
constreyned the body to be obedyent
to the fowle. I wyll saye nothing of
the ryches, whiche they dyd bestowe
on the releuyng of the poore. What
neade I make mentyon of theyr day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
prayers? What sholde I make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte
of that ernest zeale, with the
which theyr hole mynde was set so fast
vpon God, that althoughe bodyly they
dwelled here vpon yearth, yet spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
they were caryed vp in to heauen?
Who can expresse those teares, which
they did pore out longyng for the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye
kyngdome? Who can vtter in
wordes those syghes, which they did of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
drawe, from the bothome of theyr
harte, for that they were all togeather
rauyshed with the loue of God? I say
<pb facs="tcp:1259:64"/>
nothing of them which with an inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyble
corage for the honour of Christ
did suffer hangyng, burnyng, rackyng,
and other newe fownde tormentes.</p>
            <p>Also I ouerpasse them which to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
that they might better allway gyue
attendaunce vpon Christ, &amp; haue more
leasure to study heauenlye thinges, did
withdrawe them selues from mennes
company, and led theyre lyfe in soly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarye
and desert places among wylde
beastes, in such sharpnes, nedynes, and
pynyng dyet, that they made all men
astonished to see them, or here of them,
whereas notwithstandyng they being
comforted with the ioy of heauenlye
thinges, did easylye endure watchyng,
hungre, and nakednes. I speake of the
common godlynes of those Christians
whiche lyued next after the Apostles
tyme, in whome the most ernest loue
of vertue, honestye, charitye, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destye
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:1259:64"/>
did florishe. Let these godlye
Ghospellers restore these thinges,<note place="margin">How oure Ghospel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers might get them credit.</note> let
them reclayme men to these manners,
let them leade vs back to these rules,
for the moste parte left of these manye
yeares, &amp; let them bryng to passe both
that they them selues and all their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers
abstayne from vices, &amp; followe
those godly vertues in which holy men
of olde tyme did greatelye excell, and
then men may beleue that they be au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors
of the Ghospell. But if they be
not able to performe any of these thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
but rather they put out all shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fastynes
&amp; religion, and that they entre
no soner in to any place, but strayght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
contempt of lawes buddeth oute,
wantones, wylfullnes, madnes, crueltie,
and other myschefes do corrupt good
manners, and rayse vprores and hurly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burlyes
among men, haue they suche
brasen faces, that they dare once open
<pb facs="tcp:1259:65"/>
their mouthe, and speake of the Ghos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell?<note place="margin">The Gho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland at thys day is a wylye Ghospell.</note>
O wyly and deceitfull Ghospell.
For outewardly it pretendeth oure fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitye,
and priuilye it worketh oure
destructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It putteth vs in hope of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertye,
and in dede layeth vpon vs the
yoke of moste miserable bondage. It
allureth vs with the coloure of present
pleasure, and afterwarde freteth vs with
many cares and greate heuynes. It pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miseth
that it will shewe the ryght way
to heauen, and in the end it tumbleth
men which hope for help of it, hedlong
in to hell. For what other way is there
in to heauen, but that which is opened
with good workes, and with excellent
innocencye of lyfe? Therfore, he which
vnder the name of Godlynes, dothe
stryue against the exercise of Godlynes,
and dedes of charitye, dothe not leade
vs to euerlastyng lyfe, but bloweth the
coles of the vnquencheable fyar, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:1259:65"/>
to make vs roste meate for the dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell.
Marke I pray you,<note place="margin">Note here by what note you may know the true Ghospell from the false.</note> with what wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
by the Prophete Ieremy God tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth
vs to try, which is the true Ghos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,
and which is the false: Gyue no
eare (sayth he) to the Prophetes, which
prophecy vnto you pleasaunt thinges,
and in dede do deceaue you. For they
tell you but the dreames of their owne
head, and not of the worde of God.</p>
            <p>For thus they speake to suche as do dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoure
me. peace shall come vnto
you. and to them which walcke after
the wyckednes of their owne harte, no
harme or peryll dothe hang ouer your
heades. What shall we say now? Could
the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of these men be more play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely
set forth? coulde theyre vnshame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fastnes
be better discouered? For they
quite them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all feare, which be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyled
with fowle synnes, and they war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
all them which be at dagger dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing
<pb facs="tcp:1259:66"/>
with Godlynes, that all thinges
shall chaunce well and luckyly vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
He sayeth moreouer by the Prophete:
which of them was euer of cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell with
God, &amp; hath sene or hard hym speake?
It is certayne, that these wordes doo
marke oute the Prophetes of oure ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me,
which do tyckle mennes eares with
suche pleasaunte and delectable say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges.
For none of them hath lyued so
perfectly, that by any meanes we may
thynk that God hath made hym pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uye
of hys councel. For which of them
hath so refrayned hys luste, that no syn
dyd burst oute of it, to make men of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended?
which of them was euer of
thys mynde, that he thought God hys
wrathe to be appeased with fastyng,
with continuall praying, and dedes of
charitie? which of them to the intent he
might turne away the destructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng
ouer hys deare frendes, hath
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:1259:66"/>
with many teares bowed God to take
mercye? Fynally, which of them dyd e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
burne so with charitye that for the
lyffe of other he wold offre hym selfe
to death? and could fynde in hys hart
to suffre in hys owne body the punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
due for the offences of hys whole
countrye? For it is requisyte, that they
to whome we sholde beleue that God
hath opened all hys secretes,<note place="margin">what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretaryes.</note> shold be
men of no meane perfection, shold be
men not fellow lyke with the common
sorte, but that they should be men sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting,
and farre passing all others,
and for many co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>syderations to be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyled
at. For neyther the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,
neither the Apostles, neither other
most holy men, whome God dyd make
partakers of hys councells, haue come
to that degree of most hyghe perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
with leading theyr lyfe in suche plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure,
as these deyntie tothed and sugre
<pb facs="tcp:1259:67"/>
sop gentlemen be delyghted with all,
but rather in meruailouse and excellent
holynes of manners, in incredible shar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penes
of lyfe, in many laboures, wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynges
prayers, wepynges, in suche
egre desyre of heauenly thinges, in such
ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t charitye, that they desyred to be
kylled, and to be tormented with most
greouuse paynes, so that other might
be saued. Of the which vertues, where
as these men haue not one sparckle,
but lyue so, that it may appeare by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
tokens, that they take delyght in
those pleasures which the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon sorte
of men do couet,<note place="margin">A lykely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode that our protes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauntes be not men chosen of God to fynde oute the truthe not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne before.</note> and that they be gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
to those entyseme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, and prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations,
which naturall appetyte doth
greatelye desyre, yet they so talke, as
thoughe God had made them of hys
cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell, and as though not one worde
scaped them, which they hard not and
learned of God hym selfe. Therefore
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:1259:67"/>
God in the place aforesayd, doth wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily
curse such shameles chyldren, and
doth threate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them greuous destructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
And within a littell whyle after, he gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
vs a notable marke,<note place="margin">An other special no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te to know false pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>true.</note> how we shall
knowe the false prophetes from the
true, saying thus: if they had ben of my
councell, and had vttered my wordes
vnto the people, surely they shold haue
turned them from thyer synfull wayes,
and from theyr naughtye cogitations.
Therefore as it appeareth by this ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict,
whiche God gyueth, where true
prophetes take in hand to teache <hi>&amp;</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct
the people, many sodenly chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge
their myndes, and wax euery day better
and better, and for the desyr of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
glory, do forsake bodyly pleasures,
do set naught by the delyghtes of this
lyfe, and with a certayne cherefullnes
do applye them selues to the studye of
God his lawe. on the other syde where
<pb facs="tcp:1259:68"/>
so euer false prophetes treade, by and
by you shall see greater lycence to syn,
lesse shame to do amisse, more abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable
oute ragyng in all kynde of
fylthynes: so that you may easyly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue,
as the same Prophet in the same
place in the person of God at large
doth intreate, that theyr intent is to
bury the studye of God hys lawe, and
hys most holy relygion, in the graue of
euerlastyng forgetfulnes. And truly this
place of Ierymy is not heare alleadged
of me without a cause, for by it we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue
how we may knowe false and
forged doctrine, from holsom true and
vncounterfeyted doctrine. For if, synce
this newe learning was brought in to
Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, there was also brought in with
it, shamefastnes, honestie, and vpright
lyuyng, if graue manners, constancie,
strayght lyfe, laudable comelynes, and
vertuouse behauyoure, were brought
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:1259:68"/>
to lyght, if fydelytie towarde Princes, if
agreement and loueable vnitye, was
more assuredlye planted in subiectes
hartes one towarde an other, if men
be made more redye to practyse mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfull
&amp; charitable workes, if the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
be occupied with better or more
holy relygion, if the remembraunce of
Christ which dyed for vs vpon the cros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se,
be more depelye printed in mennes
myndes, so that manye for the loue of
Christ his crosse, do laye a crosse vpon
their owne neckes, to the end that they
may stay the rage of those lustes which
warre continuallye with the holynes
of Christ, fynallye if a newe lyght be
spronge oute, if a newe bewtie of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
vertues neuer sene before doth glys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre
in mennes eyes, then they whiche
haue followed theyr whystle, seme not
worthye so muche to be blamed.
But if so be by meanes of this religion,
<pb facs="tcp:1259:69"/>
none of all these thynges be brought
to passe,<note place="margin">what mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandise this scis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall ship hath brought in to Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</note> but rather by occasyon of it,
rashenes, vnshamefastnes, vncleanclines
of lyfe, doth more boldely flye rounde
aboute, if vntolerable pryde, and arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancye
be much more establyshed then
it was before, if seditions, contentions,
and fallinges oute, be more easyly styr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
vp, if traytours be more ventrouse
to lay violent handes vpon theyr Kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
and to laye wayte how to murdre
theyr Princes, if neither shame, neither
feare, neither awe of God hys displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure,
can holde them from doynge of
mischefe, which haue yelded them sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues
vp to this newe doctrine, if all this
synck or dunge hyll of myschefes, or at
leaste, an increase and newe heape of
euelles, be brought in with this lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
withoute doubte it is not esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyshed
by the worde of God as they
prate in theyr pulpytes, but by the craft
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:1259:69"/>
and subtylitye of our cruell enemy the
deuyll. For the worde of God, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth
shamefastnes and purenes of
lyfe. But this learnyng, suffreth the lus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
to run at ryot, &amp; that which is next
dore to it, prouoketh hedlong to all
kynde of wyckednes. The worde of
God,<note place="margin">A co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son betwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the true worde of God and the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantes worde.</note> do the abate all arrogancye, and
especially trayneth men vp in modestie:
but this puffeth vp mennes hartes with
pryde, and teacheth them to despyse all
antiquitye, auncyent religion, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes
of old tyme. The worde of God,
dothe make peace, and lyncketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
myndes in loue, makyng them par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teners
of all good thinges: but thys
learnyng, do the breake peace, and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
the bodye of Christ hys churche,
with inwardly consumyng &amp; wastyng
sedition. For how can they be autors
bothe of discorde and concorde, which
nether agree with them selues, nether
<pb facs="tcp:1259:70"/>
with other,<note place="margin">The inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancy of heretykes.</note> which wander oute of the
waye as well as they? which disagree
with themselues moste inconstantlye?
which to day hold one opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
an other, cleane co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary one to the
other, &amp; ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not rest long in one mynd?
Therefore seyng it is the propretye of
Christ (as he hym selfe doth wytnesse)
to gather in to one place those which
stray a broade,<note place="margin">The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene Christ his doctrine &amp; the dyuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les.</note> to ioyne those which be
of diuerse myndes, in an vniforme co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent,
mutuall beneuolence, and chary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye,
and that it is the dynells dutye, to
scatter and pull a sundre, those which
agree wel to gether, and to breake the
band of all faythfull and frendely fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweshyp,
and seyng the doctryne of
these goodly Ghospellers, dothe rayse
vpprores, dothe breake peace, dothe
spreade one sect in to innumerable sec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,
and causeth one sect to be at defy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce
with the other, is it not playne
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:1259:70"/>
that theyr religion is not drawen by
Christ hys rule, but all to gether is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented
according to the craftie deuyse
of subtyl Sathan? For what greater ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument
can we haue,<note place="margin">A greate argument of false doctrine.</note> then their dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
hatredes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> theire contentions, theire
scamblyng by the eares, theire taun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges
and rybauldry raylinges? Christ
doth not cause these euelles, but An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
For he is not the author of
dissention, but of peace. Nowe laste
of all, this is not to be passed ouer with
sylence, at what marke these sundrye
fectes &amp; licentiouse pratinges do shore.
Mary, they haue this fetche, that they
may quyte take away all the knowledge
of God. For seing that no religion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
them is so surely grounded,<note place="margin">At what mark he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritykes chefely shote.</note> but
it may easyly be ouerthrowen with the
argumentes of other sectaries, for so
muche as moste men be caryed aboure
with euery winde, and be diuersely tos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb facs="tcp:1259:71"/>
with doubtfull and wandryng opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,
and can stay themselues vppon
no certeine iudgement, when at the
lengthe many perceaue the fondnes &amp;
vanitye of theyr opinions, which they
once co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued, it cometh to passe that
they make but a ieste of all religion,
ether that they think, there is no God,
or ells, that he hath no regarde what
men doo here vpon earthe: then the
which thing what ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be sayd or thought
more beastelye, that they whiche once
had bequethed and offred them selues
vp to Christ, and were taught to know
God, euen by the verye sone of God,
after they had gone oute of the onlye
true and ryght way, sholde so far leape
ouer the lynes of all godlynes, that they
shold not only hate the crosse of Christ,
and in steade of God worshyp theyre
owne lustes and wyckednes, but also
beleue that the Lorde and Creator of
all thinges, whose powre and ryght iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gementes,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:1259:71"/>
euen the dyuelles in hell and
damned sowles do feare, ether not to
be at all, or ells not to rule and gouerne
the whole worlde? But you will perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenture
aske, who is so beastely <hi>&amp;</hi> past
all grace, that can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaue in hys mynd
so straunge and abhominable blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie?
Surely, if you will marke well, you
shall fynde,<note place="margin">Secres be the steppes to atheis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that is, of denying that there is any god.</note> that there hath bene many
whiche clymyng vp by these sectes, as
by certeine steppes and degrees, haue
at laste ascended to the top of thys vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable
abhomination. For as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
artes, no man can sodenly attayne
to that perfection, for the which he
myndeth to take paynes, but necessaryly
he must begyn with his principles, and
so ordrelye go one by lyttle and lyttle,
and at laste growe to a rypenes, so in
learning of naughtines, there be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine
begynninges, (and not Christ
crosse) but Christ curse rewes, which
<pb facs="tcp:1259:72"/>
if they be suffred to crepe forwarde,
they wyll induce men as farr as is pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syble,
to the full knowledge of that
vnspeakable myschefe. But who they
bee,<note place="margin">Our heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tykes be gyltie of atheisme.</note> whiche be gyltie of this greueous
syn, they them selues do wytnesse wel
inoughe by theyr workes. For if they
thought, that God dyd forsee and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde
all thinges, and sharpely punyshe
synnes vpon yearth, they wolde ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
haue wrought suche wylye wayes,
to seduce the people: But alas, they are
so farre gone in madnes, and tumbled
hedlong in to all folly, that so often as
it taketh them in the head, with wicked
wordes, they scoffe and mocke those
thinges, whiche be wryten of God hys
iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, as thoughe they were but
Caunterbury tales and grym vysardes
only deuysed to fray younge chyldren.
But I haue bene longer then I purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed.
Yet for so muche as myne intent
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:1259:72"/>
was to shewe you myne aduyse, howe
to prouyde for those helpes, with the
whiche you beyng assysted, you maye
more stronglye establyshe youre kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
&amp; that I myght declare vnto you
that the cheifest stay, and furnyture of
your Realme, consysted in the aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cement
and mayntenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of religion,
and that I myghte proue, that there is
no presenter poyson to the common
weale, then cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rerfeyted religion and
hypocrytycall holynes, I thought no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng
to be more agreable to my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose,
then to shewe certayne euydent
tokens, howe you myght discouer the
secrete deceptes, which lurcke vnder
the happ harlottes cloke of forged re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.
For if you haue in remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce
those frutes of religion,<note place="margin">A recapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulation of the frutes of true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and falfe.</note> whiche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
I haue rehersed, you shall easyly
perceaue, whiche is false religion. For
if true religion doe beare downe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancye,
<pb facs="tcp:1259:73"/>
ouercome angre, brydle fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye
defyres, restrayne intemperaunce,
scrape oute the spottes of the mynde,
preserue shamefastnes and modestye;
brede the feare of God, make sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes
faythfull to theyr Princes, esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyshe
peace, fasten mennes myndes in
amyty, and inflame them with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syre
of heauen, then certaynely that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
which causeth pryde, prouoketh
angre, letteth the lustes lose, defyleth
the sowle with syn, taketh away shame
fastnes, remoueth the feare of God,
worketh treason agaynst Kynges, tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon peace, bloweth the cole
of hatred, thrusteth oure myndes down
to the earthe warde, and drowneth
them in the seas of worldly trobles, is
no true religion, but false, pestilent,
and damnable. Furthermore, I haue
proued, that thys sect, (if so be, we may
call it one sect, which is not only doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:1259:73"/>
slyppery, but also diuerse, many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde,
and contaynyng in it innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
other sectes) is all to gether popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,
and for the peoples pleasure. For
alluryng the people with a ioly shewe
of to muche libertye, it armeth them
against Offycers, against their Kynges
autoritie and regiment, and hardneth
the hartes of the multitude with a false
persuasyon of religion. And if it dyd
onlye procure destruction of Kynges,
so that it brought no daunger and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
to the sowle, and by all meanes
dyd not ouerthrowe the law of God, it
were somethyng to be borne with all.
But this is greatly to be lamented, that
it putteth oute the loue of vertue, the
bryghtnes of honesty, the lyght of most
true religion and deuotion, defyleth all
commendable comlynes with vnpure
lyuyng, and vtterly stoppeth vs for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryng
in in to euerlastyng glory. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:1259:74"/>
what is it that may now deceaue
vs? Is it the autoritie of these teachers?
But I haue playnely declared,<note place="margin">The auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the protestan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes should not moue vs to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyte them.</note> how farr
the professors of thys learnyng be from
true vertue, grauitye, and constancie of
lyffe, and the perfection of moste pure
religion. What then? Is it the lose ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertye
of the people? But there is no
more sworne enymye to Princes,<note place="margin">the liberty of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple sholde disuade vs to beleue these new teachers.</note> then
that is: besyde that, it dothe vndoo the
people whiche whiche couet it, and spoyleth
them of al lyberty. For all thinges tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye,
be preserued with kepyng a meane,
and are destroyed with superfluitye &amp;
excesse. For as a Kyng, which not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentyng
hymselfe with his lawfull kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
desyreth to be lorde ouer all the
worlde, and dothe not only thinke to
rule the roste in worldlye matters, but
also casteth to haue thinges pertaynyng
to God, obedyent at hys becke &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundyment,
can not long enioy hys
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:1259:74"/>
leyngdome, for so much as he shall both
turne away from hym me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes hartes, by
reason of doing them manye iniuryes,
and also shall get God hys moste heauy
displeasure, euen so the people, which
is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented with the liberty which
the law gyueth them, and for that cause
breaketh all good ordre, moueth sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon,
and waxeth woode, of necessyty
at longthe, loseth that libertye whiche
it might haue styll enioyed, with many
other commodities and benefytes.</p>
            <p>Therfore what now? Shall we follow
this lore, because it leadeth vs to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lastyng
lyfe? But I haue playnely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,
that by meanes of this religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testantes promising vs euerlas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting lyfe ought not to wyn vs.</note> men
be intysed to wantones, tovnshamefast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
to vnlawfull lustes, that troblesome
tumultes and dissentions be styrred vp,
that many naughtye entrepryses be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
in hand, that inumerable myschefes
be forged, and last of all, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce
<pb facs="tcp:1259:75"/>
of godlynes is quyte blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
oute. The which thinges truly, do
not conducte vs to heauen, but pytch
vs hedlong in to the place of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall
mysery and wretchednes. In the which
thing trulye it appeareth, howe fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
these Euangelicall teachers haue
performed theyre promisse. For thys
they professed, thys they proclaymed,<note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testantes promise not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</note>
thys they promysed to bryng fullye to
passe, that they wolde call back corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
manners to the strayght rule of the
Ghospell, and that they wolde restore
that perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; purenes of lyfe which
was in the primityue churche.</p>
            <p>Nowe you vnderstand, o Quene<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
how well they haue kept touche. For
they haue not onlye left the Christian
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale vnhealed, but also where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer
they cam, they haue bestowed
their trauayle to this end, (that if there
were any healthe in it) to take it away,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:1259:75"/>
and to infect all the membres of Christ
his church with most vncurable diseases
and maladyes. Therefore, how coulde
any man farther ouer shote hym selfe,<note place="margin">A greate oure shote in them which we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re seduced by these new doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toures.</note>
then to be persuaded by these mennes
autority, to go from the most auncient
and holy religion, which was halowed
with Christ his bloode, sealed with the
torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of martyres, aduaunced with
the diuine workes of godly wryghters,
standing allway inuincible against the
wycked attemptes of heritikes, and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saultes
of cruell tyrauntes, hathe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned
in the same state euen vnto
these oure dayes, to imbrace a religion
which is to be suspected for the newe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
which is defamed with the wycked
lyuyng of the autors and teachers of it,
which is lamentable for the destruction
of all holy thinges, which is detestable
for the horrible end which is shooteth
at? The which religion truly, as it can
<pb facs="tcp:1259:76"/>
be taken in hand of no man,<note place="margin">The grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test plague for herisie, shall lyght vpon kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</note> withoute
miserable destruction, so kynges which
suffre them selues to be abused and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted
with it, shall be more greuousely
plaged for it. For they do not only put
theyr imperiall maiestie, the saffegarde
of the common wealthe, their lyfe and
theire honowre in greate hazarde, but
that which is muche more myserable,
and harmefull, they shall prouoke the
greuouse displeasure of God towarde
them, &amp; shall suffre much more payne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
punyshement worlde without end.
For the mo which following their euell
example fall in to the lyke damnation,
whome they ought to haue healed and
preserued, the more greuouse and pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefull
shall their tormentes be in hell
fyre.<note place="margin">A notable and terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of S. Paules wordes.</note> It is an horrible thyng, sayth saint
Paule, to fall in to the handes of thely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng
God. For to whome shall we run
for succoure, if God hym selfe be oure
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:1259:76"/>
enymye, in whose mercy all oure might
and trust is? whose healpe we defyre in
all aduersyty, and dystresse? on whome
only we fasten oure eye, lokyng to be
rescued, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we be assaulted on euery
syde? vnder whose buckler shall we
stand to anoyde his blowe? in what de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
or darcke dungeons shall we hyde
oure heades, that we may not beholde
his angry and displeased countenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce?
with the leaste: blaste of hys breathe
the whole yearth is shaken, the hylles
smoke beyng swyndged with the fyre
of his terrible lyghtnynge, the heauen
with greate thundre clappes sendyng
oute flying flames, ouershadowing the
yearthe with darcknes, shewing many
other fearefull and terrible syghtes, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comforteth,
amaseth, and astonisheth
mortall men.</p>
            <p>Therfore seeing he hath thus strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lely
weaponed nature to smyte feare
<pb facs="tcp:1259:77"/>
in to vs, and to fray men from doing of
naughtynes, what shall we thynke, he
will doo, when he hym selfe shall come
with all the hostes of heauen, and shall
appeare in the clowdes, gyrded with
iuste seueritye and indignacyon, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng
to take veng eaunce of the eny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes
of hys moste holy religion? when
with hys iudgement he shall treade vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
foote all pryde, and worldly pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe,
when he shall thruste oute of hys
presence those, whiche haue bene ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stynate
synners, to be tormented with
fyre, and moste cruell punyshementes,
which neuer shall cease. He fayth the
Scripture is the God of Goddes, the
Lorde of Lordes, strong, myghtye,
and terryble, whose iudgement nether
with fauoure can be bowed, nether
with rewardes or brybes be corrupted.
Shall we not therefore feare hys iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes?
shall we not quake at hys lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke?
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:1259:77"/>
shall we not for awe of hym shake
of all syn and inyquitye? More ouer,
what if long before we be warned of
hym with many sygnes,<note place="margin">Many sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes shewed vs to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</note> of the myseries
which for wicked lyfe and heynouse
offences<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hange ouer all oure heades?
shall we yet for all that not regarde
God hys warnyng toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and as a man
wold say hys watche wordes? notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standyng
these, shall we wallowe styll in
oure myary manners? Truly, God gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
(as Dauid recordeth) many syg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
the whiche also we see to happen
in oure dayes, beeing admonished with
the whiche, we may by chaungyng our
eonuersation, auoyde the shot of hys
bowe, which he hath bent agaynst the
enimyes of hys religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and by true and
syncere worshyppyng of hym, turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syde
hys deadely arrowes. The which
hys so greate mercye, if we shall with
more boldenes and vnshamefastnes,
<pb facs="tcp:1259:78"/>
abuse in contynuyng in oure naughty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
we shall as S. Paule sayth, heape vp
the ryches of God his angre, and bring
carte lodes of syn to encrease our euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lastyng
punysheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. Swete Iesu for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byd
thys pytyfull destructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from hys
Chrystyan flocke,<note place="margin">A Godly prayer.</note> and comforte hys
church so greuousely disquyeted with
controuersies, and at laste ioyne them
with it in vnity of mynd, which be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed
from it with contrary opinions:
and I besech hym, that he will not suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre
suche an occasyon of reioysyng, to
the mortall enymyes of hys name, with
the losse and castyng away of so many
sowles. For my parte truly, I thynk it
my dutye, all way to pray for the saffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
of all Christendome, which only
consisteth in the imbracyng of one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
in mutuall loue and agreement,
in the felloweshyp and partaking of all
God hys graces and holye blessynges.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:1259:78"/>
and whereas I am very sorye for other
countryes, which haue deuyded them
selues from the church, yet I am so tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
in mynde for the daunger which
hangeth ouer this Realme of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,<note place="margin">Alas that England shold be in such a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se, that fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renners sholde so pytye it.</note>
that I can not in wordes vtter the care
and thought, which I take in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe
of it. For I take it very heauyly,
yea it nyppeth me at the harte, that so
floryshyng a countrye, furnyshed <hi>&amp;</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plenyshed
with all thynges, more ouer
(if that make any thing to the purpose)
knit very fast to this oure kyngdome of
Spayne, both in nyghe kynred and also
confederacie of long continuaunce,
whiche hathe gyuen so many profes of
godlynes, and in olde tyme hathe not
shewed more notable feates of armes
in battayle, then it hathe set forthe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples
of religion and holynes, worthy
to be followed of the posterity, in these
dayes seduced with the deceptes and
subtyll suggestions of desperate doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours
<pb facs="tcp:1259:79"/>
is in diuerse poyntes fallen in to
folyshe and so dyuellyshe opinions.</p>
            <p>But in so greate vexation of mynde, a
certayne hope doth refreshe me, which
I haue conceaued of your syngular wyt
and especiall graciousnes. For it is the
poynte of a notable wyt, to take hede
before hand of eueles which may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue,<note place="margin">There is cause of good ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte in oure soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne Quene.</note>
to forsake the wrong opinion, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
the falsehode is discouered, wyllyngly
to receaue the truthe, when it is once
knowen and tryed oute, and to thynk
no honowre to consist in styff standyng
in wrong opinions, but to beleue that
it is moste honorable, easyly to bend &amp;
yelde to holsome cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell. Also it is the
dutye of excellent graciousnes, to haue
a care for the hole countrye, &amp; if neade
requyre, with ventryng the lyffe, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer
it from all pernitiouse erroures.
All the healthe of youre countrye stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
in youre handes. If you wyll take
vppon you to reuenge religions quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:1259:79"/>
if you wyll ioyne your selfe to the
consent of the Catholyke churche, if
you wyll mayntayne and cherishe aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
manners and good ordres, &amp; ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyshyng
naughtye men oute of youre
courte,<note place="margin">How oure gratiouse Quene may make an happy En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</note> and councell, shall intertayne
good and godly men to assist you, no
doubt by the healpe and furtheraunce
of Christ, but you shall set your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon
wealthe in a good ordre, and restore
healthe, wealthe, and happy lyfe to all
your subiectes. But if you wyll haue no
regarde to vnderset those thinges which
fall downe &amp; go to decay, I am a fearde<note place="margin">☜</note>
to tell you what wyll become of you,
and all youres. Also I wolde wyshe you
to recorde this with your selfe, that he
whiche preferreth hys owne honowre,
before the honowre of Christ, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuseth
to employ all his endeuoure,<note place="margin">Marck this and prayse God for suche hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell.</note> to
aduaunce Christ his glory, for feare of
indaungeryng hym selfe, dothe often
fall in to that myserye, which he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:1259:80"/>
to scape, by wynckyng at wycked
men, whiche robb and spoyle Christ of
hys honowre and glorye. For it is the
ryght iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, that he which
maketh more accompt of hys owne
glorye then of the glory of Christ, shold
end hys lyfe in greate shame and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honowre.
Contrarywyse, he which in
respect of Christ hys glorye, setteth
naught by hys owne ryches and estima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
attayneth to greate weathe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ourned
with all worshipfull preferment
and promotion. For suche a man get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
allmightye God to be hys patrone
and defendour, who neuer yet did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake
his seruauntes, so that he maketh
hys ryches &amp; hys honowre in more as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suraunce,
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if he were garded or way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
on with a mightye &amp; strong armye.
Therefor if you haue an ernest zeale to
defend and preserue youre kyngdome,
if you desyre to inioy immortall glory,
hercken not so much what men tyckle
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:1259:80"/>
you in the eare to be expedyent to
strengthen and assure you, as what the
lawe of God, the cause and considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of hys moste holy relygyon dothe
requyre of you. Cal to remembraunce
with what a goodlye wyt, God hathe
indued you, consydre with what lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng
and knowledge you be decked,
in what roume you be placed, what an
office and charge you haue taken vpon
you, and you shall vnderstand that all
those gracyouse gyftes,<note place="margin">God hath bestowed so many gyftes of grace vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Quene, to set oute his glory.</note> which you ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue
receaued of God, you ought to vse
and bestowe to the settyng forthe of
hys glorye. For he which hathe blessed
you with suche benefytes, if you wyll
wholy yelde vp your selfe to hym, wyll
assyste you with his grace, and wyl euer
be redy at youre ellbowe to helpe you.
For allthoughe you alone,<note place="margin">Our migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, able a lone to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</note> sholde take
in hand suche a greate entrepryse, to
reclayme England to the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cient fayth,
what were not you able to bryng to
<pb facs="tcp:1259:81"/>
passe, hauyng God before you, at your
<note place="margin">☞</note> backe, and on eche syde of you? Add
here vnto, that there be in thys youre
realme, mo which fauoure the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke
religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and which be redy to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre
extreme punyshement, in the holy
quarell of it, then there be which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clyne
to these newe fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de learnynges,
and late vp starte opynions. Therefore
there is no doubt, but what so euer you
wolde haue done in this behalffe, you
shall haue bothe God and man redy to
further you. Weygh allso with youre
selffe howe muche it shall redounde to
youre honoure, that thys youre realme
set oute of ordre &amp; for the moste parte
torne a sundre by the meanes of a fewe
myscheuous persones, sholde by youre
dylygence, returne to the auncyent
bewtye,<note place="margin">what an honorable thing it we re to oure puyssant Quene to rearesse religion in England.</note> and recouer the ornamentes of
godly conuersation, with the which in
olde tyme it was trymly set forthe and
decked. For all good men wyll speake
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:1259:81"/>
and wryght good of you, youre actes
shall be cronycled and regestred vp for
euer, they which be not yet borne shall
talke of you, and no age shall seace to
syng songes in prayse and commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of you. For what victoryes are to
be compared with so notable a dede?</p>
            <p>what is able to purchase greater prayse
and renowne? what more notable mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numentes
can be left to make youre
name allway to be remembred? for it is
not prayse worthie to kyll many thow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sandes
of men, but to put wyckednes
to flyght, vtterly to race oute and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face
syn, that is to be praysed, that is to
be exalted: not to worke men myschefe
and destruction, but to saue and dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
them, is the hyghe way to immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
glorye: not to ouerthrowe with
force of armes many Cyties of foren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enymyes,
but to preserue the natyue
countrye for beeing ouerflowne with
feaes of syn, or ouerrun with the run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng
<pb facs="tcp:1259:82"/>
campe of vngodlynes, dothe wyn
the golden spurres of glorye and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne.
For all other victories though
they be in God his appoyntement, yet
they be gotten with the dent of the
sworde and helpe of man: but this of
all other moste notable, is obteyned
with godly and spirituall weapons: &amp;
those other victoryes are not gotten
withoute bloodeshed, and a certayne
lyce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or warrant to syn, but thys which
I speake of, is gotten with the destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge
of syn, and the sauyng of men:
wherefore of necessytye this passeth in
worthynes all other, which be wonne
with worldely weapons, shrightyng of
souldyoures, &amp; force of men, so farr as
heauenly thynges excell thynges vpon
earthe. Which thynge truly shall cause
men so much more to meruayle, as it is
an harder matter for the Princes of dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes,
&amp; euerlastyng enymyes of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde,
to be vancquyshed of one wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:1259:82"/>
then one man to be conquered
of an other. Therfore so notable prayse,
shall not only allway be freshe in men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
memories, but also it shall be set
forthe and magnifyed of the blessed
sayntes in heauen. Wherefore (o most
noble Quene) euen for the bledyng
wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of our Redemer Iesu Christ,<note place="margin">A most ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement &amp; Godly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Quene.</note>
for hys bloode shed for vs vpon the
crosse, for his death &amp; bytter passyon,
by hys most gloryous victory, with the
which he tryumphed vpon death, des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troying
it and puttyng it to death, for
that contynuall fyar, which he hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closed
in the centre of theyearth, and
with the which he hath stirred the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
of his seruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes to the loue of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
and hatred of syn, for that moste
ryghtwyse iudgement with the which
he shall take vengeaunce of syn, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence
with euerlasting rewardes,
those which haue helde a sound faythe
and vndefyled religion, fynally for the
<pb facs="tcp:1259:83"/>
loue of all holy thinges in the worlde,
I pray and beseche you, seeing you haue
so many helpes and furtheraunces to
immortall glorye, that no let or hyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draunce
may be found in you. Fasten
youre eyes vpon Christ mangled with
woundes for youre sake, throwe your
selfe flat before hys fete, imbrace hys
crosse in your armes, and banyshe out
of your countrye, thys hatred agaynst
hys crosse,<note place="margin">Enimies of the crosse to be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished.</note> whiche thys newe fangled
fraternitye doth openly mayntayne.</p>
            <p>Follow the foote steppes of holy men,
and persuade your selfe that to be the
ryght way, which Godly men indued
with excellent vertue continencie, and
purenenes,<note place="margin">what fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners our most cleare Princes shold fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe and eschewe.</note> being hyghly in the fauour
of God, inspyred and taught with the
holy ghoste, haue troden before you:
not that which men blynded with selfe
loue, leanyng only to theyr owne wyt,
hedlong in folysh hardines, ouer whel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
with wyckednes, and dyuyded fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:1259:83"/>
the vnitie of Catholyke churche doo
persuade you to followe. The which
thyng if you wyll doo, you shall vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde
and encrease the ryches of your
Realme, and that which is much more
worthe, you shall with greate glory as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend
in to the Kyngdome of heauen.
IESVS CHRIST the fountayne of all
goodnes, the Lorde of all myght, long
preserue youre grace in healthe, with
increase of all honoure and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celye
aduancement.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="testimony">
            <p>Ex testimonio doctissimi cuiusdam viri
Anglicè periti, credimus praedictam epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolam
&amp; esse catholicam, &amp; bene versam.</p>
            <l>Ita esse testor Cornelius Iansenius</l>
            <l>S. Theologiae Louanij professor.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:1259:84"/>
            <head>To M. Doctor Haddon.</head>
            <p>VAlens the Emperour, as Nazianzenas
dothe wytnesse, beyng poysoned with
Arrius heresie, after he had wrytten
with his owne hand many wordes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning
the banishment of saynt Basill, yet coulde not
fynishe those wrytynges, for so muche as the
pen dyd thre tymes refuse to yelde yncke. Not
withstandynge, he beyng obstinae in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed
malyce, dyd not leaue of to wryte that
wycked Decree, and to subscribe vnto it when
it was wryten, tyll a greate cramp or palsye
dyd come in to his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, which dyd smyte such
a feare and terroure in to hys hart, that with
his owne hand he dyd teare that, which he had
once put in wrytyng. O terrible, o fearefull
example. For the loue of God remember this
history M. Doctor Haddon. And whereas it
dyd not feare you to wryte agaynst Osorius
at the fyrst, because peraduenture either you
knewe it not, or ells dyd forget it, nowe seyng
you do knowe it, and haue it freshe in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye,
despyse it not. But let it be a warnyng to
you, whether you be moued of youre owne
heade, or pricked forward with the suggestion
of other, whether you be in your priuate par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,
or publyke parlament howse, that you say
nothing, write nothing, subscribe to nothyng,
pertayning to the defacyng of the truthe, lest
<pb facs="tcp:1259:84"/>
suche a cramp take you in the hand, when you
sholde wryte, suche a palsye come in to youre
tonge when you sholde speake, that you be a
spectacle to all them which see you or heare
you. Entre in to an humble confession of your
owne imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that although in humanity
you can do very commendably, yet when you
come to declame in diuinitye, agaynst the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,
you can no more bestirre your selfe, then
young Dauid coulde in Saules heauie helmet,
and boysterouse armoure,<note place="margin">1. Re. 17.</note> with the which he
was neuer accustomed. VVherfor I pray you,
vse that, of which you haue some skyll, refuse
that, whereof you be all together ignorant. If
you wyll not ceasse, I assure you, you shall
styrre vp so many aduersaries agaynst you,
that whereas you be M. of the Requestes, and
for that cause, ought allway to be at leasure
to heare petitions, when sueters come to you,
you shall be fayne to make them answer: I
pray you, troble me not, I must go answer O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorius
of Portugall, I must answer Hosius in
Polonia, suche a man in such a countrie. &amp;c.
And if you wyll not make them suche an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer,
yet your brayne shall be busyed with so
many bookes and letters, from so many places
of youre betters, that your mynde shall not
<pb facs="tcp:1259:85"/>
be vpon youre charge. So that either you shal
be put oute of youre office for negligence, or
elles sent from the Court to Cambridge for
pitye, that you may haue more leasure to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer
youre aduersaries. VVhiche chaunge I
thinck you wolde not willyngly chose: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
I pray you, followe my former councell.
Stay your selfe, recompence your troblesome
eloquence, with charitable and quiet sylence.
But if you thinke, that I haue done you iniury
by tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>slatyng O forius, you may easily reuenge
me by translating youre answer, if you thynk
it to be truer. VVhether you do translate it or
no, because you be M. of the requestes, I pray
you, graunt me thys request: Increase not I
pray you your olde fault with a new offence,
make no new resistau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce against the auncyent
veritie. And that you may be the more a feard
hereafter to abuse youre hand in writyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynst
Osorius, or any other Catholyke, turn
the boke named Symbola heroica, heroicall
deuyses, where in among many pictures, you
shall fynde a shaking hand, with a pen lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng
oute of it, &amp; this posye wryten ouer it.
<hi>Vlterius ne tende odiis.</hi> Let this be in payn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted
tables euer before youre eyes, let this be
your heroicall deuyse, and I trust it shal feare
<pb facs="tcp:1259:85"/>
you from the lyke vyce. VVhich, I pray God,
you neuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit agayn, whose grace I wyshe
you, that you may worthily repent for that
which you haue done all redy. Amen.</p>
            <closer>Fare you well.
From Antwerp the .27. of Marche.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faultes escaped in
some Copyes.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>mans hys
arroganyce
wyll what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lypertnes</cell>
                     <cell>Reade</cell>
                     <cell>man hys.
arrogancye.
with what
malypert.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
