<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Aprill shower shed in abundance of teares, for the death and incomparable losse, of the right noble, truly religious, and virtuous, Richard Sacuile, Baron of Buckhurst, and Earle of Dorset. VVho departed this life vpon Easter day last, being the 28.th of March, at Dorset-House. By Henry Peacham.</title>
            <author>Peacham, Henry, 1576?-1643?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-01">2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09188</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19499</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S122559</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857682</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857682</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23451</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A09188)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23451)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1111:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Aprill shower shed in abundance of teares, for the death and incomparable losse, of the right noble, truly religious, and virtuous, Richard Sacuile, Baron of Buckhurst, and Earle of Dorset. VVho departed this life vpon Easter day last, being the 28.th of March, at Dorset-House. By Henry Peacham.</title>
                  <author>Peacham, Henry, 1576?-1643?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edw. Allde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Vpon the death of the Earle of Dorset.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dorset, Richard Sackville, --  Earl of, 1589-1624 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-03</date>
            <label>TCP Staff (Michigan)</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23451:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23451:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An Aprill Shower</hi> Shed in abundance of TEARES,</p>
            <p>FOR THE DEATH AND INCOMPARABLE LOSSE, OF THE RIGHT NOBLE, TRVLY RELIGIOVS, AND <hi>Virtuous,</hi> RICHARD SACVILE, Baron of BVCKHVRST, and Earle of DORSET.</p>
            <p>Who Departed this Life vpon <hi>Easter</hi> day last, being the 28.th of March, at DORSET<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>House.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Henry Peacham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>— <hi>Sublatam oculis p<gap reason="illegible: obscured" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rimus inuidi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON</p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>Edw. Allde.</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="coat_of_arms">
            <pb facs="tcp:23451:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CLaruit his armis viuus</hi> DORSETIVS <hi>Heros, Quêis ornarat auos</hi> NEVSTRIA <hi>terra suos. Nunc his</hi> ad postem fixis, latet abditus <hi>astris Hoste triumphato, nescius ipse mori.</hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:23451:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, RELIGIOVS, AND <hi>Nobly minded Lady,</hi> ANNE Countesse Dowager of DORSET.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAME:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am bolde; the first, to bewayle in publique, the Death of your deare Deceased Lord of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and Blessed memorie; not that hee can want Mourners, whose losse concernes so deepely our Religion, King, State, your Selfe, your Children, and thousands of true Louers and Friends in particular: But because I am loath (I must confesse truely) to be preuented in manifesting my affection vnto him dead, vnto whom
<pb facs="tcp:23451:3"/>
liuing I was more obliged then any other of his rancke in the Land. And although I am of least a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie in this kinde (since the most Learned Pens and skilfullest Pencils, must fall farre short of limning him to the Life, such were his excellent Parts) yet I had rather vndergoe any censure then be Ingratefull, or like an vnconscionable Debtor, refuse satisfaction when it will bee accepted for lesse then three in the hundred. It is too true, that the Zeale of the most, expires with their Friends liues or fortunes: vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Deuotion weares and waters their Tombes many yeares after: and so (Madame) shall I his, though I creepe thereto on my knees. For if euer Mortalitie clad true Honour, and Honestie of Heart, she veiled either in the Person of your Noble Lord and Husband; whose Pietie to GOD, Zeale to Religion, Loyaltie to his Soueraign, Loue to his Countrey, Courtesie and Affabilitie to all; set of with the rarest endowments of Body and Minde, (like so many Diamonds in Gold) drew all Hearts to his Loue, and Eyes to his Admiration. But hee is gone, and wee follow as fast as may bee: and as in Fruit the ripest; so with vs in the world, the rarest are soonest gathered for Heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Immodicis brevis est aetas &amp; rara Senectus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:23451:3"/>I dare not presume farther of your Honours pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, already Exercised and tryed euen to the height; onely I desire of the Almightie, who is hope and helpe of the Widdow, and Father of the Fatherlesse, to send you Comfort from Heauen, and his Blessing vpon those sweet Ladyes your hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Children, that they may liue many yeares to propagate your Names and happie Memories to all Posteritie for euer. I humbly take leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Aprill, 18.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Who is, and euer shall bee deuoted to your Honour, HENRY PEACHAM.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <pb facs="tcp:23451:4"/>
            <head>Epitaphium verè Honoratissimi, Nobiliss: pijs ac bonis, omnibus desideratissimi, D. RICHARDI SACVILE, Baronis de <hi>Buckhurst,</hi> ac <hi>Dorsetiae</hi> Comitis, <hi>Londo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nijs</hi> defuncti, &amp; <hi>Withihamis</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muni auorum <hi>Sarcophago</hi> in agro <hi>Sussexiensi</hi> sepulti.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>HIc situs ille tuus Comes est <hi>DORSETIA,</hi> nomen</l>
               <l>Qui clarum toto fecerat orbe tuum.</l>
               <l>Quem si Nobilit as generis, (nam Sanguine Regum</l>
               <l>Cretus,) si Pietas, cum genio ingenium,</l>
               <l>Census, honos, aut Musa potens valuisset ab vmbris</l>
               <l>Infernis, pretio vel reuocâsseprece;</l>
               <l>Non Caput exiguâ Sanctum latitâsset in vrna,</l>
               <l>Nestoreos dignum vel superâsse dies.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>His Monument to the Reader.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHo thinkes that DORSET lyes Interred</l>
                  <l>Here-vnder, thinke that they haue erred</l>
                  <l>For 'tis not hee, 'tis but the Case</l>
                  <l>Wherein this precious Iewell was,</l>
                  <l>Who seekes for him must aske of FAME,</l>
                  <l>Who registers his Honour'd name;</l>
                  <l>Or search the Hearts of Friends, where hee</l>
                  <l>Is lodg'd, and liuing like to bee:</l>
                  <l>And if not heere, to Heauen ascend,</l>
                  <l>There sure hee liues world without end.</l>
                  <l>For though with mee his dust doth lie,</l>
                  <l>Beleeue it, DORSET cannot Die.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:23451:4"/>
            <head>AN ELEGIE. Vpon the Death of the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, RICHARD SACVILE, Baron of <hi>Buckhurst,</hi> and Earle of DORSET.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>MY LORD! (so must I call that Honour'd mind</l>
               <l>And happie Soule of yours, which heere behind,</l>
               <l>Hath left her earthy Pawne; e're any knew</l>
               <l>Or could imagine DEATH would seeke his due.)</l>
               <l>Oh giue me leaue distractedly to rue;</l>
               <l>The first of many, our deare misse of you;</l>
               <l>Of you my Dearest LORD — </l>
               <l>But Sorrow duls my Stile, and teares mine Inke</l>
               <l>Discolour weeping. DORSET dead? Mee thinke</l>
               <l>Though Fame in mourning tells it, 'tis not so</l>
               <l>That such a Peere, but sewest dayes agoe,</l>
               <l>So Healthy, Young, so vsefull to the State</l>
               <l>In these weake Times, that doe importunate</l>
               <l>The Heauens themselues, for helpe of Heart, of Hand,</l>
               <l>Of Wisest and the ablest of our Land</l>
               <l>To her Support. Ah! would it were vntrue,</l>
               <l>And that mine Eyes not needed to bedew</l>
               <l>With Siluer-dropping <hi>Aprill</hi> his blacke Herse,</l>
               <l>Sad Subject now of euery Learned Verse.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:23451:5"/>For by the <hi>Genius</hi> (which I hold Diuine)</l>
               <l>Of each true Poët, (therefore none of mine)</l>
               <l>I heere professe, it is no by-regard,</l>
               <l>Or expectation of a slight reward</l>
               <l>Enforces me to weepe. The common losse</l>
               <l>Of KING, and COVNTREY, calls to beare their crosse</l>
               <l>And so I will; know then whom wee haue lost,</l>
               <l>Euen him, whom Artes and Armes may truely boast</l>
               <l>To bee their owne. Wee tricke not his Discent</l>
               <l>And Images, which in our<note n="*" place="margin">The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, a worke of the Author, wherein hee setteth down his Pedigree at large.</note> COMPLEMENT,</l>
               <l>Who list may view at large; nor say his Blood</l>
               <l>(Except the Royall) was as equall good</l>
               <l>As any else of NORMAN Race, sith none</l>
               <l>Can clayme their Grandsires Vertues for their owne.</l>
               <l>No, like a Diamond hee allur'd the sight</l>
               <l>T'admire his owne, and not a borrow'd light.</l>
               <l>For whatsoeuer could bee wish'd, that one</l>
               <l>Might make Complete and Absolute alone,</l>
               <l>It wanted not in him; For, first his <hi>Mind</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Was best compos'd, Religiously inclin'd,</l>
               <l>Not with the World, to winne an Aerie fame</l>
               <l>Of Singular, or vnderneath the same,</l>
               <l>To worke (as many) some malicious end</l>
               <l>While they the TRVTH and PIETIE pretend.</l>
               <l>Oh no! in him this Zeale was reall good</l>
               <l>And was the Ground, whereon the Modell stood</l>
               <l>Of that braue structure of his Noblest mind:</l>
               <l>For who more Zealous, Pitifull, and kind</l>
               <l>To heauenly TRVTH'S Professors? yee Diuines</l>
               <l>Of LONDON, SVSSEX, KENT, witnesse, my Lines</l>
               <l>Doe attribute vnto him, but his due.</l>
               <l>How was his Loue extended vnto you,</l>
               <l>By adding Stipends to your Liuings small,</l>
               <l>Maintaining many who had none at all?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:23451:5"/>Your Debts oft times (when least you thought) discharging</l>
               <l>Your bounds, and grounds from his owne meanes enlarging,</l>
               <l>Nor did this Bountie, stretch to you alone,</l>
               <l>But to <hi>Desert,</hi> in euery meanestone,</l>
               <l>That (as of TITVS) I may truely say;</l>
               <l>From him Sad-hearted none return'd away.</l>
               <l>And which his Bountie, yet did more endeare,</l>
               <l>And each reward made double to appeare,</l>
               <l>Was his Free-noble, Curteou entertayne,</l>
               <l>Deuoid of Pride, and haughte-brow'd Disdayne,</l>
               <l>Who did not (monstrous) wth his Honour swell,</l>
               <l>Hee knew that was but rin'd and outward shell</l>
               <l>Of Man, and best did with their humours sute</l>
               <l>Whose insides poore, could onely beg repute</l>
               <l>From Plumes and Tissue: or whose <hi>Honours</hi> cost</l>
               <l>The setting on, and must improoue them most.</l>
               <l>No, this as but the vinet of Boule</l>
               <l>That's emptie, whereuponthe thirstie Soule</l>
               <l>Commends, admires, the Grauers hand and wit,</l>
               <l>His thirst not quenched allthis while for it.</l>
               <l>'Twas hence wee knew hm affable and milde,</l>
               <l>Denying not accesse euer to the Childe.</l>
               <l>(Though Greatnesse alwayes cannot stand extent</l>
               <l>But Bowe-like sometimeit must lye vnbent.)</l>
               <l>An enemie to garish Pride and Fashion,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Epilepsie,</hi> of our English Nation,</l>
               <l>For with the plainest plaine, yee saw him goe</l>
               <l>In Ciuill blacke of Rash, of Serge, or so,</l>
               <l>The Liuerie of wise Stayednesse; Except when</l>
               <l>His Prince did call vpon his Seruice, then</l>
               <l>Stout DIOMEDE in Armes, not brighter shone,</l>
               <l>Or man more Glorious was to looke vpon:</l>
               <l>That had <hi>Death</hi> seene him at a Courtly Tilt</l>
               <l>Braue mounted, Plum'd, in Armes of Azure gilt</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:23451:6"/>Encountring Princely CHARLES, while splinters flie,</l>
               <l>And prayers of people, eccho in the skie,</l>
               <l>Hee would I know haue lent him longer date,</l>
               <l>Hee yet, not lost, and wee beene fortunate.</l>
               <l>What Cunning Artistes pencill may I borrow,</l>
               <l>Thrice-hopefull CHARLES, to limne thy griefe and sorrow</l>
               <l>For DORSETS losse, but there's no forme can fit,</l>
               <l>Or bee imagin'd to decipherit.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>"Light Cares may speake, the great amaz'd with wonder,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>"Themselues then vtter, sooner burst a sunder.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And hence proceeds the dulnese of each Pen</l>
               <l>Our hopes thus,<note n="*" place="margin">His Death immediately ensuing the Death of the worthy Prince <hi>Lodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke,</hi> Duke of <hi>Lenox,</hi> and <hi>Richmond.</hi>
                  </note> stricken downe and downe agen,</l>
               <l>Oh whither Heauens 'twere your immediate hand</l>
               <l>For his owne good, (though to afflict our hand)</l>
               <l>Or Hels deepe Hate wrought his vntimely end,</l>
               <l>Occasion'd by those rootes (whch God defend)</l>
               <l>I cannot say, but this I must professe</l>
               <l>The <hi>Non-pareil,</hi> Pearle, Earle of Noblenesse</l>
               <l>Is (fairest BRITANE) from thy bosome torne,</l>
               <l>And pawn'd by Death, though by another worne;</l>
               <l>Thou like one lately rob'd not knowest yet,</l>
               <l>What thou hast lost, or how to value it.</l>
               <l>Beleeue (all-dreaded Empresse) from thy KENT</l>
               <l>To ORKNEY, vtmost of thy large extent,</l>
               <l>NOBILITIE not bred a finer wit</l>
               <l>With better judgement to dispose of it.</l>
               <l>What various reading heigthned his Discourse</l>
               <l>At all occasions, putting to the worse</l>
               <l>A vulgar judgement by dispute, or whan</l>
               <l>H'encountred <hi>Papist,</hi> or the <hi>Puritan.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who better reis'd in Scriptures and the Text,</l>
               <l>The Ancient Fathers, and our Writers next,</l>
               <l>Mine eyes I heere a-vow did neuer read</l>
               <l>Lines sweeter, then did from his Pen proceed;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:23451:6"/>Rare Poet sure was DORSET, therefore hee</l>
               <l>Was great MOECENAS of all Poesie,</l>
               <l>What State, what Traine, what Order, House kept hee</l>
               <l>At his faire KNOWLE, <note n="*" place="margin">His House hard by <hi>Seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noke</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
                  </note> a Paradise to mee</l>
               <l>That seem'd for site, a Court for grearest Prince,</l>
               <l>The Home of <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>Magnificence;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where euery day a Christmasse, seem'd, that fed</l>
               <l>The neighbour Poore, that else had famished.</l>
               <l>How did his Loue and Noblest Care extend</l>
               <l>To all his followers, at his latter end</l>
               <l>I need not tell, themselues will say for mee,</l>
               <l>Men neuer seru'd a better Lord then hee.</l>
               <l>Ah dearest Lady, flower of the Stemme</l>
               <l>Of CLIFFORDS race, and Honours goodly Gemme</l>
               <l>His truest Spouse, with (whom hee lou'd so well)</l>
               <l>That Pearle your MARGARITE,<note n="*" place="margin">His onely Children li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret</hi> the eldest, a hopefull &amp; faire young Lady, <hi>Isabell</hi> an infant.</note> and young ISABELL.</l>
               <l>How doe I sorrow for your sake, whom Crosse</l>
               <l>(By Father, Mother, Sonne, now Husbands losse)</l>
               <l>On Crosse afflicts, of worldly helpe bereau'n,</l>
               <l>Except the helpe (that neuer failes) of Heauen:</l>
               <l>Oh let not griefe that many one hath slaine,</l>
               <l>Wherein not any profit doth remaine,</l>
               <l>(For Sinne except,) deject your soule a whit,</l>
               <l>But Palme-like grow, the more opprest by it.</l>
               <l>And since I now the Common losse haue showne,</l>
               <l>Oh let mee drop one teare, and shew mine owne,</l>
               <l>Who neuer found a minde more Nobly-free,</l>
               <l>Respectiue, Louing, Bountifull to mee.</l>
               <l>Yea Constant, (for no PYLADES could bee</l>
               <l>More faithfull, where he did affect, then hee;</l>
               <l>That euen in Child-hood, whom hee chose a Friend</l>
               <l>His Loue embraced to his latter end,</l>
               <l>Such was his Honour'd minde; but hee is dead,</l>
               <l>And with him Hopes of thousands buried.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:23451:7"/>Sleepe then in peace (Deare Lord) and lowly Dust,</l>
               <l>Till thou receiu'st thy Portion with the Iust;</l>
               <l>For while I liue, mine eyes shall neuer see</l>
               <l>A Man, a Peere, a Patrone like to thee.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="vision">
            <head>A double Vision vpon the Death of this Noble Lord.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>MEe thought I saw by DVROVERNVM,<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cantuaburie,</hi> So called in old time.</note> where</l>
               <l>Along the Siluer-streaming STOVRE doth slide</l>
               <l>A louely Nymph, her wiery-golden haire</l>
               <l>Sit rending, wayling that faire place beside,</l>
               <l>More beauteous Creature the worlds Compasse wide</l>
               <l>Ne had: her rayment white, her cheekes besprent</l>
               <l>With blubbred teares, and on a Crosse shee leant.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To whom, ah whom, shall now I make my mone?</l>
               <l>Or who (shee said) will pitie my distresse?</l>
               <l>Sith now my nearest dearest Friend is gone,</l>
               <l>Who shall RELIGION (wel-nie Comfortlesse)</l>
               <l>Commiserate? (yet many doe professe</l>
               <l>A seeming friendship) and her labours cherish,</l>
               <l>Or giue me Bread, that heere I may not perish?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I finde with many gratious entertaine</l>
               <l>(In <hi>Kentish</hi> soyle) yet DORVS was the man</l>
               <l>Whose loue I had, and hee my héart againe,</l>
               <l>Wonne by his Braue and Royall bountie, whan</l>
               <l>I deeply languish'd, that Physitian</l>
               <l>Of life dispaired, me hee then relieued,</l>
               <l>And gaue most Comfort, when I most was grieued.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:23451:7"/>
               <l>But hee is Dead; with that a sigh shee fetch'd,</l>
               <l>As mought haue torne an heart of steele in twaine,</l>
               <l>And said; blest Soule (with handes on high out-stretch'd)</l>
               <l>Where-euer thou in Heauen dost remaine,</l>
               <l>Enjoy thy Blisse, for hardly I againe</l>
               <l>Thy like shall finde, therewith I wak'd in bed,</l>
               <l>But Riuer, Nymph, and all were vanished.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="vision">
               <head>The second Vision.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I Saw a goodly Lawrell, streight and Greene,</l>
                  <l>Vpon whose top sweet singing Birds did build,</l>
                  <l>Whose like PERNASSVS Bay-bound head I weene,</l>
                  <l>Nor TEMPE, pride of THESSALIE, could yeeld,</l>
                  <l>Whereto repayr'd the Shepheard of the Field:</l>
                  <l>But Muses most heere-vnder did delight,</l>
                  <l>In Heate, their Hymnes and holy thinges endite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But sodainly the enuious owner came,</l>
                  <l>And at the roote did lay with all his might,</l>
                  <l>That downe it fell, together with the same,</l>
                  <l>The Nestes and tender Young, vnfit for flight;</l>
                  <l>That much my heart was grieued at the sight,</l>
                  <l>But more, because the Muse had lost her Freind</l>
                  <l>Whose armes from harmes her state did full defend.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>To the Deceased Lord.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>AS in that Royall Chappell, where</l>
               <l>Seauenth HENRIE lyes in <hi>Westminster,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From euery Windowes middle part;</l>
               <l>A line direct runnes to his Heart.<note n="*" place="margin">So was the Plot deuised, that from the Center of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery window a direct line came to the K hart, lying in his Graue.</note>
               </l>
               <l>So all our Loues by equall line</l>
               <l>From farre, concenter in thy Shrine.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="closer">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:23451:8"/>
            <l>NOblest DORSET, dead and gone,</l>
            <l>My Muse with Poësie haue done:</l>
            <l>And in his Graue, now throwne thy Pen,</l>
            <l>Sit downe and neuer rise agen.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
