<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sonnets to the fairest Coelia</title>
            <author>Percy, William, 1575-1648.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1594</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-11">2004-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09307</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19618</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110392</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845946</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845946</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10879</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A09307)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10879)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 348:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sonnets to the fairest Coelia</title>
                  <author>Percy, William, 1575-1648.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[26] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Adam Islip, for W[illiam] P[onsonby?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1594.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: W. Percy.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Publisher's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ D²  (-D2).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10879:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10879:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SONNETS
TO THE FAIREST
<hi>COELIA.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Parue, nec inuideo, sine me liber ibis ad illam,</l>
               <l>Hei mihi quòd domino no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> licèt ire tuo. </l>
               <bibl>Trist. 1.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>stylized fleur-de-lis</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed by Adam Islip,
for W. P.
1594.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:10879:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10879:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, whereas I was
fullie determined to haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed
my Sonnets, as thinges
priuie to my selfe, yet of courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie
hauing lent them to some,
they were secretlie committed to the Presse,
and almost finished, before it came to my
knowledge. Wherefore making, as they say,
<hi>Vertue of necessitie,</hi> I did deeme it most
conuenient to praepose mine Epistle, onely to
beseech you to account of them as of toyes and
amorous deuises, and ere long, I will impart
<pb facs="tcp:10879:3"/>
vnto the world another Poeme which shall be
both more fruitfull and ponderous. In the
meane while I commit these as a pledge
vnto your indifferent cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures.
London,
1594.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. Percy.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sonnets">
            <pb facs="tcp:10879:3"/>
            <head>COELIA.</head>
            <div n="1" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonnet I.</head>
               <l>IVdg'd by my goddesse doome to endlesse paine,</l>
               <l>Lo here I ope my sorrovves passion,</l>
               <l>That eu'rie sillie eye may vievv most plaine,</l>
               <l>A sentence giuen on no occasion.</l>
               <l>If that by chaunce they fall most fortunate,</l>
               <l>Within those cruell hands that did enact it,</l>
               <l>Say but, alas he vvas too passionate,</l>
               <l>My doome is past, nor can be novv vnactit.</l>
               <l>So mayst thou see I vvas a spotlesse louer,</l>
               <l>And grieue vvithall that ere thou dealt so sore.</l>
               <l>Vnto remorse vvho goes about to moue her,</l>
               <l>Pursues the vvinged vvinds, and tils the shore.</l>
               <l>Louelie is her semblance, hard is her hart,</l>
               <l>Wauering is her mind, sure is her dart.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10879:4"/>
               <head>Sonnet II.</head>
               <l>Oh happie houre, and yet vnhappie houre,</l>
               <l>When first by chaunce I had my goddesse vievved,</l>
               <l>Then first I tasted of the svveetest soure,</l>
               <l>Wherevvith the cup of <hi>Cypria</hi> is embrevved.</l>
               <l>For gazing ferme vvithout suspition,</l>
               <l>Loue coopt behind the charet of her eye,</l>
               <l>Iustly to schoole my bold presumption,</l>
               <l>Against my hart did let an arrovv flie:</l>
               <l>Faire sir, quoth he, to practise haue you nought</l>
               <l>But to be gazing on deuinitie?</l>
               <l>Befo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e you part, your leare you shall be tought,</l>
               <l>With that attonce he made his arrovves hie:</l>
               <l>Imperious God, I did it not to loue her,</l>
               <l>Ah, stay thy hand, I did it but to proue her.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10879:4"/>
               <head>Sonnet III.</head>
               <l>Proue her? Ah no, I did it but to loue her:</l>
               <l>Then shoote amaine, drad liege, I stand vnarmed,</l>
               <l>Altho no hope that any thing may moue her,</l>
               <l>Some ease it is to be by beautie charmed.</l>
               <l>Then quicke, my liege, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quicke, &amp; end thy game,</l>
               <l>That all the vvorld may see hovv thou hast plagu'd vs,</l>
               <l>Then cruell she shall vievv vnto her blame,</l>
               <l>That all men be not fickle as they'ue term'd vs:</l>
               <l>May be, my vvords may vvinne contrition;</l>
               <l>If not my vvords, my sobs; if not my sobs,</l>
               <l>My teares may moue her to compassion;</l>
               <l>If teares do faile, my tears, my vvords, my throbs,</l>
               <l>Ay me, Ah no, teares, vvords, throbs all in vaine,</l>
               <l>She scornes my dole, and smileth at my paine.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10879:5"/>
               <head>Sonnet IIII.</head>
               <l>Oh heauenly <hi>Coelia,</hi> as faire as vertuous,</l>
               <l>The only mirrour of true chastitie,</l>
               <l>Haue I beene gainst thy godhead impious,</l>
               <l>That thus am guerdond for my fealtie?</l>
               <l>Haue I not shed vpon thine yu'rie shrine,</l>
               <l>Huge drops of teares vvith large eruptions?</l>
               <l>Haue I not offred eu'ning and at prime</l>
               <l>My sighs, my Psalms of inuocations?</l>
               <l>VVhat be mens sighs, but cals of guilefulnesse?</l>
               <l>They shevv, deare loue, true proofs of fermitie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>What be your teares, but meere vngratiousnesse?</l>
               <l>Teares only plead for our simplicitie:</l>
               <l>VVhen all strike mute, she saies it is my dutie,</l>
               <l>And claimes as much as to her deitie.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10879:5"/>
               <head>Sonnet V.</head>
               <l>Faire Queene of <hi>Gnidos</hi> come adorn my forehead,</l>
               <l>And crovvne me vvith the lavvrell emperor,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I'ó</hi> thrise sing <hi>I'ó</hi> about thy Poet,</l>
               <l>Loe on my goddesse I am conqueror.</l>
               <l>For once by chaunce, not sure, or vvittingly,</l>
               <l>Vpon my foot, her tender foot alighted,</l>
               <l>With that she pluckt it off full vvimbely,</l>
               <l>As though the verie touch had her afrighted:</l>
               <l>Deere mistresse, vvill you deale so cruelly,</l>
               <l>To priue me of so small a benefit?</l>
               <l>What? do you iert it off so nimbely,</l>
               <l>As though in verie sooth a snake had bit it?</l>
               <l>Yea bit perhaps indeed: Ho, Muses blab you?</l>
               <l>Not a vvord Pieannets, or I vvill gag you.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10879:6"/>
               <head>Sonnet VI.</head>
               <l>Good God hovv sencelesse be vve paramours,</l>
               <l>So proudly on a nothing for to vaunt it?</l>
               <l>We cannot reape the meanest of all fauours,</l>
               <l>But by and by vve thinke our sute is grauntit.</l>
               <l>Had ye obseru'd tvvo planets vvhich then mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted,</l>
               <l>Tvvo certaine signes of indignation,</l>
               <l>Ye vvould haue deemed rather both consented,</l>
               <l>To turne all hopes to desperation.</l>
               <l>Then can you vvauer so inconstantly,</l>
               <l>To shevv first loue, and then disdainfulnesse?</l>
               <l>First for to bring a dramme of courtesie,</l>
               <l>Then mix it vvith an ounce of scornfulnesse?</l>
               <l>No, no, the doubt is ansvver'd, certainlie</l>
               <l>She trod by chaunce, she trod not vvittingly.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10879:6"/>
               <head>Sonnet VII.</head>
               <l>If it be sin so dearely for to loue thee,</l>
               <l>Come bind my hands, I am thy prisoner,</l>
               <l>Yet if a sparke of pittie may but moue thee,</l>
               <l>First sit vpon the cause commissioner.</l>
               <l>The same vvell heard may vvrest incontinent</l>
               <l>Tvvo floods from foorth those rocks of adamant</l>
               <l>Which streaming dovvne vvith force impatient,</l>
               <l>May melt the brest of my fierce <hi>Rhadamant.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Dearest cruell the cause I see dislikes thee,</l>
               <l>On vs thy brovves thou bends so direfully;</l>
               <l>Enioine me pennaunce vvhatsoeuer likes thee,</l>
               <l>What e're it be Ile take it thankefully.</l>
               <l>Yet since for loue it is I am thy bondman,</l>
               <l>Good <hi>Coelia</hi> vse me like a Gentleman.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10879:7"/>
               <head>Sonnet VIII.</head>
               <l>Strike vp, my Lute, and ease my heauie cares,</l>
               <l>The onely solace to my passions,</l>
               <l>Impart vnto the aires thy pleasing aires,</l>
               <l>More svveet than heauenly consolations.</l>
               <l>Rehearse the songs of forlorne amot'us</l>
               <l>Driv'ne to despaire by dames tyrannicall,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Alpheus</hi> losse, of vvoes of <hi>Troilus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of <hi>Rowlands</hi> rage, of <hi>Jphis</hi> funerall.</l>
               <l>Ayme, vvhat vvarbles yeelds mine instrument?</l>
               <l>The bases skrieke, as though they vvere amis,</l>
               <l>The Meanes, no meanes, too sad the meriment,</l>
               <l>No, no, the musicke good, but thus it is,</l>
               <l>I loath both Meanes, meriment, Diapasons,</l>
               <l>So she and I may be but Vnisons.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10879:7"/>
               <head>Sonnet IX.</head>
               <l>Whilst others vveene sole hopes to be a sauue,</l>
               <l>Sole hopes I find to be my corosiues:</l>
               <l>Whilst others found in hopes an harbour haue,</l>
               <l>From hopes I feele a sea of sorrovves rise:</l>
               <l>For vvhen mild hopes should ease my raging fires,</l>
               <l>They fester more, in that they are but hopes:</l>
               <l>Then vvhilst I touch the port of my desires,</l>
               <l>A storme of hate doth burst mine anchor ropes.</l>
               <l>Were I but once resolued certainly,</l>
               <l>Soon should I knovv vvhich point my helme to stere,</l>
               <l>But she denies my sute most vvomanly,</l>
               <l>As hidden documents for vs to heare.</l>
               <l>Loe this the cause my hell forsakes me neuer.</l>
               <l>Tell me, (deare svveet) thus shal I liue for euer?</l>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10879:8"/>
               <head>Sonnet X.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶A MYSTERIE.</head>
               <l>To vvinne the Fort hovv oft haue I assayd,</l>
               <l>Wherein the heart of my faire mistresse lies?</l>
               <l>What Rammes, vvhat mines, vvhat plots haue I not layd?</l>
               <l>Yet still am frighted from mine enterprise.</l>
               <l>First from the leads of that proud citadell,</l>
               <l>Do foulder forth tvvo fierie culuerines,</l>
               <l>Vnder tvvo red coates keepe the Larum bell,</l>
               <l>For feare of close or open venturings.</l>
               <l>Before the gates Scorne, Feare, and Modestie,</l>
               <l>Do tosse amaine their pikes, but boue them all</l>
               <l>Pudic'itie vveilds her staffe most manfullie,</l>
               <l>Garded vvith blocks that keepe me from the vvall,</l>
               <l>Yet if this staffe vvill ford me cleare the vvay,</l>
               <l>In spite of all I'le beare my Dame avvay.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10879:8"/>
               <head>Sonnet XI.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶TO POLYXENA.</head>
               <l>Of all the vvomen vvhich of yore haue beene,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alcest</hi> for vertue may be glorify'd,</l>
               <l>For courage <hi>Teuce',</hi> for features <hi>Spartaes</hi> queene,</l>
               <l>For all in one <hi>Polyxen'</hi> deify'd.</l>
               <l>If true it be by old Philosophie,</l>
               <l>These soules to haue since destin entered,</l>
               <l>To other bodies of like simpathie,</l>
               <l>Thou art the last of these Metemps'chosed.</l>
               <l>Thy courage vvoonderous, thy vertues peerelesse,</l>
               <l>Thy features haue the fairest Ladies blamed,</l>
               <l>Then if thou scorn'st not such a Monarchesse,</l>
               <l>Henceforth by reason good, thou shalt be named,</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Teuce',</hi> nor <hi>Alcest,</hi> nor faire <hi>Helena,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou shalt be nam'd my deare <hi>Polyxena.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10879:9"/>
               <head>Sonnet XII.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Coelia,</hi> of all svveet courtesies resolue me,</l>
               <l>For vvished grace, hovv must I novv be doing,</l>
               <l>Since <hi>Ops</hi> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plet'st frame vvhich did absolue thee,</l>
               <l>Hath made each parcell to my sole vndoing?</l>
               <l>Those vvires vvhich should thy corps to mine vnite,</l>
               <l>Be raies to daze vs from so neere approch,</l>
               <l>Thine eyne vvhich should my nighted sailers light,</l>
               <l>Be shot to keepe them off vvith foule reproch.</l>
               <l>Those ruddie plummes embrevv'd vvith heauenly foods,</l>
               <l>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I vvould sucke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> turne to driest currall,</l>
               <l>And vvhen I couch betvveene her lillie buds,</l>
               <l>They surge like frothie vvater mounts aboue all:</l>
               <l>Surelie they vvere all made vnto good vses,</l>
               <l>But she them all vntovvardly abuses.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10879:9"/>
               <head>Sonnet XIII.</head>
               <l>With greeuous thoughts &amp; vveighty cares opprest,</l>
               <l>One day I vvent to <hi>Venus</hi> Fanacle,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Cyprian</hi> dreames vvhich did me sore molest,</l>
               <l>To be resolv'd by certaine oracle.</l>
               <l>No sooner vvas I past the temples gate,</l>
               <l>But from the shrine vvhere <hi>Venus</hi> vvont to stand,</l>
               <l>I savv a Ladie faire and delicate,</l>
               <l>Did beckon to me vvith her yu'rie hand.</l>
               <l>VVeening she vvas the goddesse of the Fane,</l>
               <l>VVith cheerefull lookes I tovvards bent my pace,</l>
               <l>Soone vvhen I came, I found vnto my bane,</l>
               <l>A Gorgon shadovv'd vnder <hi>Venus</hi> face,</l>
               <l>Whereat afright, vvhen backe <hi>I</hi> vvould be gone,</l>
               <l>I stood transformed to a speechlesse stone.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10879:10"/>
               <head>Sonnet XIIII.</head>
               <l>When once <hi>I</hi> savv that no intreats vvould moue her,</l>
               <l>All means I sought to be deliuered,</l>
               <l>Against vvhite <hi>Cupid</hi> and his golden mother,</l>
               <l>In hie contempt base vvords I vttered;</l>
               <l>When both from clouds of her bright firmament,</l>
               <l>With heauie griefes and strong disdaine surmounted,</l>
               <l>Vpon my thoughts and me did shoot reueng'ment,</l>
               <l>Whilst in our highest prides vve vvere amounted.</l>
               <l>Nor be they pleas'd to giue vs all these vvounds,</l>
               <l>To make me languish as a dying liuer,</l>
               <l>But from her orbes they fling their fiarbronds,</l>
               <l>Thereby to quite consume both hart and lyuer:</l>
               <l>Pardon, drad povv'rs, pardon my rash offence,</l>
               <l>By heauens bright vaile, t'vvas gainst my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>science.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10879:10"/>
               <head>Sonnet XV.</head>
               <head type="sub">ECHO.</head>
               <l>What is the faire to vvhom so long I plead? <hi>Lead,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What is her face so Angell like? <hi>Angellike.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then vnto saints in mind sh'is not vnlike. <hi>Vnlike,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What may be hop'd of one so euill nat'red? <hi>Hatred.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O then my vvoes hovv shall I ope best? <hi>Hope-best</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then she is flexible. <hi>She is flexible.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fie no, it is impossible. <hi>Possible.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>About her straight then only our best. <hi>You're best.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hovv must I first her loues to me approue? <hi>Proue.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hovv if she say I may not kisse hir? <hi>Kisse hir.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For all hir bobs <hi>I</hi> must then beare, or mis hir? <hi>Yes sir,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then vvill she yeeld at length to Loue? <hi>To loue.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Eu'n so? <hi>Eu'n so.</hi> By <hi>Narcisse</hi> is it true? <hi>True.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of thine honestie? <hi>J.</hi> Adieu. <hi>Adieu.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10879:11"/>
               <head>Sonnet XVI.</head>
               <l>What may be thought of thine vntovvardnesse,</l>
               <l>That moouest still at euerie motion?</l>
               <l>What may be hop'd of so strange vncouthnesse,</l>
               <l>That scornes all vovves, scornes all deuotion?</l>
               <l>If I but sue, thou vvouldst releeue myne anguish,</l>
               <l>Tvvo threatning arcks thou bendest rig'rously;</l>
               <l>Then if <hi>I</hi> svveare thy loue doth make me languish,</l>
               <l>Thou turn'st avvay, and smilest scornfully;</l>
               <l>Then if I vvish thou vvould'st not tyrannise,</l>
               <l>Of Tyrannie thou makest but a mock'ry,</l>
               <l>And if I vveepe, my teares thou doost despise,</l>
               <l>And if I stir, thou threatenst battery:</l>
               <l>Froune on, smile on, mocke me, despise me, threat mee,</l>
               <l>All shall not make me leaue for to intreat thee.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10879:11"/>
               <head>Sonnet XVII.</head>
               <l>Relent my deere, yet vnkind <hi>Coelia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>At length relent, and giue my sorrovves end,</l>
               <l>So shall I keepe my long vvisht holy day,</l>
               <l>And set a trophey on a frovvard frend,</l>
               <l>Nor tributes, nor imposts, nor other duties,</l>
               <l>Demaund I vvill as lavvfull conqueror;</l>
               <l>Duties, tributes, imposts vnto thy beauties,</l>
               <l>My selfe vvill pay, as yeelded seruitor.</l>
               <l>Then quicke relent, thy selfe surrender vs:</l>
               <l>Braue sit and vvhy, quoth she, must I relent?</l>
               <l>Relent, cry'd I, thy selfe doth conquer vs,</l>
               <l>VVhen eftsoons vvith my propper instrument,</l>
               <l>She cut me off, ay me, and ansvvered,</l>
               <l>You cannot conquer and be conquered.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10879:12"/>
               <head>Sonnet XVIII.</head>
               <l>I cannot conquer and be conquered:</l>
               <l>Then vvhole my selfe <hi>I</hi> yeeld vnto thy fauor,</l>
               <l>Behold my thoughts flote in an ocean battered,</l>
               <l>To be cast off, or vvafted to thine harbor:</l>
               <l>If of the same thou vvilt then take acceptance,</l>
               <l>Stretch out thy fairest hand as flag of peace,</l>
               <l>If not, no longer keepe vs in attendance,</l>
               <l>But all at once thy firie shafts release.</l>
               <l>If thus I die, an honest cause of loue,</l>
               <l>Will of my fates the rigor mittigate,</l>
               <l>Those gratious eyne vvhich vvill a <hi>Tartare</hi> moue,</l>
               <l>Will proue my case the lesse vnfortunate,</l>
               <l>Altho my friends may rue my chaunce for ay,</l>
               <l>It vvill be said, he dy'de for <hi>Coelia.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10879:12"/>
               <head>Sonnet XIX.</head>
               <l>It shall be sayd I dy'de for <hi>Coelia;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then quicke thou grieslie man of <hi>Erebus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Transport me hence vnto <hi>Proserpina,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To be adiudg'd as vvilfull amot'us:</l>
               <l>To be hong vp vvithin the liquid aire,</l>
               <l>For all the sighs vvhich I in vaine haue vvasted,</l>
               <l>To be through <hi>Lethes</hi> vvaters clensed faire,</l>
               <l>For those darke clouds vvhich haue my lookes or'eca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted,</l>
               <l>To be condemd to euerlasting fire,</l>
               <l>Because at <hi>Cupids</hi> fire I vvilfull brent me,</l>
               <l>And to be clad for deadly dumps in mire:</l>
               <l>Among so manie plagues vvhich shall torment me,</l>
               <l>One solace I shall find vvhen I am ouer,</l>
               <l>It vvill be knovvne I dy'de a constant louer.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10879:13"/>
               <head>Sonnet XX.</head>
               <l>Receaue these vvrits, my svveet and deerest frend,</l>
               <l>The liuelie patterns of my liuelesse bodie,</l>
               <l>VVhere thou shalt find in Hebon pictures pend,</l>
               <l>Hovv I vvas meeke, but thou extreamlie blodie.</l>
               <l>I'le vvalke forlorne along the vvillovv shades,</l>
               <l>Alone complaining of a ruthlesse dame;</l>
               <l>VVhere are I passe, the rocks, the hilles, the glades,</l>
               <l>In pittious yelles shall sound her cruell name.</l>
               <l>There I vvill vvaile the lot vvhich fortune sent me,</l>
               <l>And make my mones vnto the sauage eares,</l>
               <l>The remnant of the daies vvhich nature lent me,</l>
               <l>Ile spend them all, conceald, in ceaselesse teares.</l>
               <l>Since vnkind fates permit me not t'enioy her,</l>
               <l>No more, burst eyes, I meane for to annoy her.</l>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="madrigal">
            <pb facs="tcp:10879:13"/>
            <head>To Parthenophil vpon his Laya and
Parthenophe.</head>
            <head type="sub">MADRIGALL.</head>
            <l>When first I heard thy loues to <hi>Laya,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>I wisht the gods to turne it to good hap,</l>
            <l>Yet since I heare thy blessed flight away,</l>
            <l>I ioy thy chaunce for feare of afterclap.</l>
            <l>Vnwily man, why could'st not keepe thee there,</l>
            <l>But must with <hi>Parthenoph'</hi> thee'gaine entrap?</l>
            <l>I litle rue thy well deserued teares,</l>
            <l>The beast once scap't will euer shun the trap.</l>
            <l>What tel'st thou me by spels th'hast wonne thy deare?</l>
            <l>Beleeue her, friend, no more then <hi>Laya</hi> past,</l>
            <l>Charm'd loue endures but whilst the charme doth last.</l>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
