<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Digitus Dei. Or, Good newes from Holland Sent to the wor. Iohn Treffry and Iohn Trefusis. Esquires: as allso to all that haue shot arrows agayst Babels brats, and wish well to Sion wheresouer.</title>
            <author>Peters, Hugh, 1598-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1631</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-11">2004-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09517</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19798.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101483</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837297</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837297</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1613</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A09517)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1613)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 998:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Digitus Dei. Or, Good newes from Holland Sent to the wor. Iohn Treffry and Iohn Trefusis. Esquires: as allso to all that haue shot arrows agayst Babels brats, and wish well to Sion wheresouer.</title>
                  <author>Peters, Hugh, 1598-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Abraham Neringh, printer in Rotterdam, by the ould Head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Rotterdam] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1631.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: H.P. (i.e. Hugh Peters.--Halkett and Laing).</note>
                  <note>"Relates to a victory gained by the British forces under Sir Horace Vere and the Earl of Oxford in Holland."--Folger Shakespeare Library Catalogue.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 19066.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 19066 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ (-B4, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Yale University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1613:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1613:1"/>
            <p>DIGITVS DEI.
OR GOOD NEWES FROM HOLLAND.</p>
            <p>Sent to the wor.<hi rend="sup">ll</hi>
IOHN TREFFRY.
AND IOHN TREFVSIS.
ESQVIRES:</p>
            <p>As allso to all that haue shot arrows agaynst Babels Brats, and wish well to Sion wheresouer.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <head>NON NOBIS DOMINE</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed By Abraham Neringh, Printer in Rotterdam, by the ould Head.</p>
            <p>ANNO. 1631.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1613:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1613:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>S<hi rend="sup">RS</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince my condition &amp; lot fell in these parts of the world which for a long time haue beene Sedes belli: I haue not bin altogether negligent in taking up such observations as might either draw mee to a more serious consideration of Gods prouidence, dispensing it selfe into many particulars, some more secret, &amp; some open to euery eye: or such as might by their presentment unto mee of the worlds vanity &amp; turnings, make mee see the glassie brittlenesse &amp; shiftlesnesse of the creature, &amp; so perswade to a stronger dependance uppon the creator, a Being that hath happinesse in it selfe. Not hath it bin the least of my care to cast an especiall eye uppon the seuerall victories, &amp; vnparaleld deliuerances (if wee take up all circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) which this state hath bin honored with. In the compasse of three yeares or there about, I haue seene strange turnings &amp; returnings of prouidence, ebbs of State that left vs (at least the wise-hearted) hopelesse of a flood: and then agayne high waters, that haue left many thoughtesse yea carelesse, of an ebb: heere haue I seene an enemy slighted at a great distance, &amp; too much feared neerer hand, many mountainous designes which haue prooued mole hills in execution, heere haue wee seene men looking one way &amp; the Lord bringing the thing about another, sometimes God destraining for his glory where men would not giue it him other wayes: In a word heere hath bin imploiments for all kinds of spirits, all kinds of men, heere the sad heart hath had matter to feed those black vapors that cherish melancholy, &amp; heere the freer spirit might h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue a time to lauish it selfe out in warrantble ioyes &amp; refreshments, heere the magistrate hath had worke enough to aduise, &amp; the people to bring in their assistances, the souldier hath had enough how to deuise &amp; how to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute to his greater advantage, and those that waite vppon the tabernacle haue had no reason to bee idle, where dayes of attonement, as well as the dayly sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice were to bee attended on: sometime wee haue bin slipping with Dauid beside our selves and our comforts, while wee fretted at the foolish, and saw the prosperity of the wicked, sometimes with the same good-man wee were as those that dreamed, to see the downe-fall of the vngodly, &amp; what chaff they were before the wind. Truly (S<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>) wee haue seene much of Gods faythful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse &amp; sufficiency, &amp; wee ar to bee blamed if wee have not also seene our owne inability &amp; nothingnesse.</p>
            <p>But whiles I haue let my meditations travel from one place to another they haue lodged longer in these two, viz: first in the consideration of our selues 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> of the enemy: in the former whereof wee may take up matter of wonder, that the Lord continues vs instruments of his glory, &amp; the subiect of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb facs="tcp:1613:3"/>
&amp; bounty, who may iustly take shame to our selues that wee ar no more sanctified in our drawing neare unto him, or doe sanctifie him soe little: alas (S<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>) strangers that looke uppon us may thinke that wee are his onely iewell, since wee are kept so safely: but the truth is our beauty is but black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, our deformities are the speech of neighbor nations, &amp; by the openesse of our folly wee make the daughters of the Philistims reioyce. Nor haue wee lesse worke in the contemplation of the enimy, being the center to which subtilty, cruelty, dilligence in euell, with many other the like, as so many lines haue their confluxe. What great cost haue they byn at in the not yet subdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a handfull of people nay (which is admirable) that which hath bin the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mon breake-back to other states &amp; countryes, hath bin the supplying of their treasures heere, &amp; filling of their Magazins, I meane their Army. They haue had heere many plowers plowing uppon their back, &amp; yet there remaines noe signe of a furrow, I wish wee saw noe steps of their sin. I will not heere dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusse in what coyne the Lord hath bin paid for his kindnesse, nor what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ede they haue returned of their talents concredited to them. I haue inioyed this common ayre with them, and haue had my share in their particular mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, I cannot bee silent. What a hand wee saw out of heauen by the surprize of Wesel, and the Bosch following that, as if the former mertie had not bin enough for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Heere I will not treate, I haue formerly advertisd about them: what mertie the Lord hath sent them from the sea, &amp; what siluer trophees from the enimy hath bin brought, is not now my purpose to speake: But since the Lord by an especiall hand led me to looke vppon the beginning &amp; end of this late deliuerance, I shall aduertise therein according to truth, in which I may not seeme (it may bee) soe particular as some may expect, because I dare not call Opinion, Fayth: nor so exact in tearmes, because a stranger to the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage though a freind to Souldiery: but this I shall doe, I will labor to shew truth in her nakednesse, or at least in her owne apparell; and the order I shall propose will bee this; First I shall present the bare history 2,<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> some obserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from it, 3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> I shall add some vses wee may make of it: and first for the history.</p>
            <p>Whilst the Illustrious Prince of Orange after a triple victory, viz: Groll, Wesell, and the Bosch, had sate downe the last summer to refresh him-selfe euen la den with honnor; Sanballat and Tobiah, I meane they of Spayne and Flaunders rose early, &amp; went to bed late, eating the bread of carefulnesse, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plottiug the raising their honnor out of the dust, where Hee had buried it, as an instrument in Gods hand the yeares before: and surely if strength had answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their reuengefull spirits, the mischeife had had wings, before wee should haue knowne it was hatchd; For heerein they far outstrip their enimies, that their waters run deepely and silently. Now that you may vnderstand what
<pb facs="tcp:1613:3"/>
they had in their eye, that should exhaust so much of their treasure this yeare, and perswade with their cleargie like the neighboring channels soe f<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eely to emptie themselues into the common sea; I shall acquaint you with Marques Spinolaes last will and testament left in the hands of the Infanta at his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur out of these wars. Two things hee aduised out of his lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g experience &amp; best observations, that might infest the States, whereof the first was, that the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of their commerce with forreine parts might be stoppd, or at least lesse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, &amp; therfore would that from Dunkerk, Osten, &amp; other parts ships should bee set forth for the intercepting them in the narrow seas, which counsaile the world obserues hath bin taken, &amp; that with noe ordinary successe: that to this day Dunkerk a meane Dunghill hauen, dare write her selfe a M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>. The 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> was this, that they should not spend themselues thus yeare after yeare, in the beseiging, beleaguring, &amp; taking in of any one towne, which did spend them much treasure, &amp; could not much disaduantage the enimy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but that they should (though with double cost) attempt the diuiding of the Provinces, especially Holland &amp; Zeeland, which hee demonstrated to bee feasable. And for the better understanding the way, may it please you to take notice that about two or three houres sailing from Dort, there lies a village calld the Plate, with a conuenient hauen able to receiue many smal vessels: this village with the whole Iland uppon which it stands is all together vnfortified, &amp; soe are all places about it: this hauen lookes right against Princeland a place of the same strenght with the Plate, betwixt these two passe all our shipps to Zeland, Bergen, Ter Goose, Tertoll, Zeerikze<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: ect.</p>
            <p>This yeare about the time of this attempt their army entred Princeland<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing remained but that they might make themselves M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> of the Plate, &amp; soe <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> once cut of the passage to Zeland, &amp; the parts aboue said, &amp; soone put Dort &amp; Roterdam the Hart of the land in feare, from whence likewise they might haue an easie way to Dunkerk, &amp; they recourse to them agayne. This with the consequences being vnderstood I shall labor to show yow what faythfull ouerseers the Marquese had to his wil, and how tender they are on the other side to follow the mind of the dead. After the Prince of Orange had retreated out of fflaunders, &amp; (whether through the foreslowing of time, or too many loope holes made in their counsails or unfaithfulnesse in men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trusted, or correspondence by any false heart with the enimy) he had lost his designe, &amp; inquartered himselfe at Drunen, neare Huisden, little other ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings came to vs, but the constant and extraordinary prouisions of the enimy by land &amp; water, especially concerning certaine sloopes, &amp; flat bottomed boates, &amp; an engeneering Preist, who should haue spent much oyle &amp; can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in the advancing of a strange designe. The tidings whereof comming thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, &amp; the child being neere the birth the towne of Bergen petition the
<pb facs="tcp:1613:4"/>
ayde, who with that part of his army that lay at Drunen, being about 12 or 14000. foot beside horse, set forward for Bergen the 25. of August, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in 3. or 4, dayes was inquartered on the North-side of the towne, Sargeant Maior Cary being sent before with diuers companies for a safegard to those parts by which these shalloopes might passe, as also 15. or 17. men of war, that vsually waite uppon the In-land waters.</p>
            <p>Vppon the 11. of Septem: being thursday at 4. or 5' of the clock at night wee heard shooting from Falconesse, and the Doel, and there-abous, and saw shipping, but did generally conceiue that the enemy had made an attempt to come forth and was beaten back by our men, when as it appeared otherwise t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e next day for the next morning being friday wee discerned vppon the wals of Bergen a fleete of 80. sayle or more comming towards the towne, and farther off some greater shipps in an other fleete: It is strange to see &amp; heare how hardly men were drawne to beleeve that the enemy was so neare, nor was there much credit giuen to it till they were before the very towne of Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen: where my-selfe being a spectator amongst the rest, could tell above 80. sayle, who as it seemes came the day before from Antwerpe, &amp; soe past by our shipping (as wee saw over night) &amp; onely changd a few shot without far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Danger, Sargeant Maior Cary carefully attending vppon the chardge com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him, they bent their course toward Tertoll land, &amp; about 8. or 9. in morning 22. saile of their Reregard comming on ground, the rest stayed for them betwixt Rommers-wali &amp; Tertoll, till the returning of the next tide, which was at 3. in the afternoone: and thus they lay this whole day in the sight not onely, of Berghen, but of the Princes whole army: mee thought this time was alotted us from heaven, as if a voice had cried and bid vs yet try what prayer will doe: and if I should bee playner with you, &amp; open you a window into my owne heart, mee thought this stopp was the time wherein Iustice &amp; Mercy compeered before the great God of heaven &amp; earth (as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it was a time for our saddest thoughts) Take Vengeance cries Iustice Oh spare sayes Mercy: Kill cries the one, Saue the other: There are no sins like theirs, cries Iustice: No God like theirs sayes Mercy: Give successe to this designe cries the One, Lord they are Thy enemies sayes the Other: Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land is p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oud &amp; secure sayes Iustice, But they may amend by this diliuerance: They haue not improoued former kindnesses, But they may bee tried by one more: Reuenge thy Sabbaths &amp; let them haue noe rest that neglect this day of rest, heere Mercye paused, at lentgh charging their teachers with this &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusing the poore people that knew noe better. You shall see what followed, and whic<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> preuayled</p>
            <p>The Prince perceiuing that it was now no time to aske, what shall we doe, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut to bee doing, vnder command of Generall Morgan sent 3. Regements <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>oll, to guard those parts from the incursion, &amp; landing of the enemy, who went to their worke with no ordinary resolution, &amp; came close by
<pb facs="tcp:1613:4"/>
those partes where the enemy lay, &amp; onely gave them notice by some shot that they there attended them, with which troopes the Prince went in person: In the meane time Count Ernest advised for the cutting off the Reregard, that lay on ground, &amp; to that purpose commanded such warlike shipping as lay at Bergen to be made ready, &amp; 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> musketteres out of every companie of the army, to bee imployed in the designe, which came to 1200 or there abouts, the commander in cheife of our nation, was the noble &amp; valiant Earle of Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford Lieutenant Collonel to my Lord Generall Vere, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e were added Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant Maior Hollis. Captaine. Dudly, Captaine Skippon, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Thomas Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peper, Captaine Iackson, with some other officers: and this I must say, my hart wittnesseth I flatter not I never saw men hugg an enterprise so, the common souldier even beseeching their captaines with teares that they might bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor were they without the company of diuers Noble volunteers amongst whom that Noble Gentle-man my Lord Crauen, (who hath much honored his nation abroad) must not be forgotten, who with the first presented him-felfe with his musket, ready to share in the common condition, whether good or bad. But as great bodyes mooue slowely, so these, tfor they set not forth till the enemie floated, who with the comming of the tide were soone at worke, &amp; as before hauing a small boate with them, sounding the way ouer the many sands they were to passe, made toward Zerickzea hauing gotten their whole fleete together; about 4. of the clock ours followd them, &amp; had the Princes owneship to leade them the way, about 4, came some of our fleet that lay by Falconesse, &amp; followed them &amp; made in all about 25. saile, they passed betweene Tertol &amp; Tergoose, on the one side whereof a godly minister before General Morgan came had wi<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h much &amp; earnest persuasions drawne this neighbors into a reasonable order for their owne defence, on the other side not only 20, companies of the Princes awaited them, but also the Boores or country people were in great readinesse being generally men of very good abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities in point of souldierie;</p>
            <p>But it seemes that was not the white they shot at, wherefore they past on beyoud Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reikzea, before our ships could come neere shot of them: about 9' of the clock at might the friday aforesaid, the Princes ship shot by a village calld Ould Kerke, &amp; in short time brought her peeces to beare vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, in so much as wee haue it by credible testti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, that with one broade side shee killd 23. men, other ships of ours came vp with them like wise, &amp; gaue &amp; received such rough intertainement as passeth among men at such times: a ship of Zeland had by one shot from the enimy 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> men slayne, &amp; 4. hurt: our musketeres came not up to doe much seruice, for these reasons, 1 in such a hurry of businesse, &amp; uppon the water command could not so easily passe, &amp; besides that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand they had, was to seconde the ships that were prouided to fight at length, &amp; more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer the worke continued not so loug as to make vse of all our men: The Princes ship receiued shot: 2. in the sayles &amp; 1, in the midship, &amp; quitted herselfe well, some 5. or 6. more did the like: but it playnely appeared the enimy seemed not much to regarde fighting, rather longing &amp; striuing to bee M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> of his designe, &amp; therfore continually steered of their course, till towards morning the whole night being exceeding fayre
<pb facs="tcp:1613:5"/>
for one houres space &amp; noe more the Lord east a mist uppon them, by which (they themselues confessing it) they were much distracted, lost their way, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of them came on ground, and the most of them at Muschle-creeke not far from Steenbergen, the vangard being at this time, within one houres time, or two at the most, of the place they aimed at: diuers of them blame Fortune and their pilots, but in truth (as some of them accknowledgd to my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe) the blow was from heauen. and to proceede, this confusion taught vs who was their Generall, viz: Count Iohn of Nassau, who would rather venture the Infantaes displeasure, then pay soe deare for his entertainment heere againe, as hee had lately done at Wesell: Insomuch that hee with Prince Brabenson and some other cheifes left the fleete, and heere I must remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber a complement was put vppon Count Iohn at his departure from Ant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werp, and embarquing, after many benedictions from the Infanta, and (ques<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionlesse) much water sprinckled uppon him and his company, to praeserue him from the displesure of S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Neptune etc. The Liuetenant Generall of the horse had a cringe with him to this purpose, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> (quoth hee) the designe you are ingaged in, is weightie, the cost hath bin great for the aduancing of it, and it will require a whole man, but I must tell you I conceiue not Count Iohn to bee That Man, and so they parted. And since wee haue spoken of Muschle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creeke, I must tell you of a passage that concernes the said Generall of theirs, where by I may put you in mind how fooles oracles may prooue wise-mens truths: not long before this attempt Count Iohn sending a Trumpet to our army, wished him if the Prince should aske what became of their shallopes, to answer that they meant shortly to come eate some Muscles: hee came to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> place indead, but I suppose hee had not time to fill his belly, or if hee tasted them I thinke hee hath not yet disgested them, that he cannot much reioyse at his banquet. Some other sloopes followed their Generall to Prince-land, and fired them at landing, so that betwene Willemstadt and Musclecreeke I saw diuers of the hulls of them lying by the shore; the rest quirred their boates with what speede they could, feare giuing them wings, and confusion and distraction taking away their wits: the reason they giue for making this great haste to the land is, because on these in-land waters they could expect noe quarter, and euery worme will reade us a lecture of the sweetenesse of life, 1400. seing a horse-man vppon a dike gaue themselues to him: a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest for one man! Divers in landing were drowned, many stript them selves to swim and so came naked to our army, most of their ships by the morning light were found in new Fosse-mere where they lay that day with our ships by them. Wee shall not neede to write what they returned the Preists for their benedictions, but certainely many Tuns of diuels, and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to the Preist who had the cheife hand in the plot, and did boaste great
<pb facs="tcp:1613:5"/>
of carriing shipps under water and promising to bring their souldiers into Berghen, which hee did truly performe: You must conceiue what a suddayne change heere was, when our men came to take possession of their vessels, &amp; they scrambled away in the mud, which mynds me of a merry answere of the Prince to one that told him the Preist would bring their men vnder the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, hee sayd he then must send to Zeland for some fishermen to prick them vp vpon their Eel-speares. By 8. in the morning newes came to the Prince of their forfaking their boates, whereupon he commanded diuers companies to march towards Steen-berghen to enconter them supposing they might make head, but before our men were vpon their march, tidings came that most of them had giuen them selues prisoners; &amp; by 11. of the clock the first sight of them wee saw was 4, or 5. Captaynes with 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Capuchins presented to the Prince, with whome hee enterayned neere an houres talke, who all blamed Count Iohn for his starting at a pinch: The Capucians were presently begd by the Duke of vensdome, into whose tuition and fauor they were soone retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: the next sight that was presented to vs was a fat trumpetter of Count Iohns in a carr there followed him the Captaine of the Princes ship on horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe behinde a Gentleman, with the colours of the Admirall of their fleete, being a Burgoignian crosse which hee presented to the Prince; after him fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in two diuifions the prisoners, garded by a troope of the Duke of Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, which were betweene 2. and 3000. before the last diuision was a wagon laden with their Officers; and this was obseruable, that among all these, and 900. more wich lay at Steen-bergen there was no English at all, but they were all Dutch, and Wallons; these were sent to such places, as the towne of Berg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hen had to entertaine them in, especially an old peice of a Church receiued most. Thus the saterday was cheerefully spent in veiwing these liuely tokens of Gods fauor, on the day following command was giuen that publike thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing should bee rendred both in the towne and army in which (I blesse God) I had a share: and on Munday-night (with 3. volleyes af<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er the manner heere) it was made knowne very cleerely to Antwerpe, and the enemies army (some of our cannon hauing very wide mouthes) vppon the sabbath was brought in Dulken the once Gouernour of Grol, &amp; a Iesuite with him &amp; so dayly diuers prisoners who had come on shore on diuers parts. Nor did wee at this time thinke our labor ill bestowed to ride from place to place to looke on either their Punts &amp; sloopes, or our men bringing in the spoyle, som telling their freinds how hardly they had escaped, and shewing their chayne &amp; gnawne bullets, som with rapiers, som scarfes, one with Count Iohns leading stasse, another with a buffcoate, &amp; most laden with Antwerpes beere: Amongst diuers other things there came to my hande a knife of the keur lings who are som of their company about Bridges, that ne<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her giue nor take
<pb facs="tcp:1613:6"/>
quarter, vpon which was engraven in Dutch Rithme.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Make hast from Bridges Prince of Aurania:</l>
               <l>Honnor your M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> the king of Hispania:</l>
               <l>Let our flaunders alone, come not heere to pillage:</l>
               <l>For wee haue for you, nor citty, nor village.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>vnder which was pictured the towne of Bridges, &amp; the Prince running from it on horse-back, -Surely as the deliuerance was great, so the purchase especially of amunition was not a little, as wee shall shew by the particulars following: And now mee thinkes by this time I saw the mother of Sisera loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out of a window, &amp; crying through the lattesse, why stay his chariot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wheeles so long? Iudg: 5. 28. etc. surely shee is much deceiued if she thinke they are deuiding the spoyle: Thus the Lord ouerthrew Pharow &amp; his host in the red sea, for his mercy indureth for ever. The weeke following the Prince commanded most of the prisoners to bee set vppon ships without fayle or rudder, by the head at Berghen, till order should bee taken for ransome: the poore women at Antwerpe who had their husbands in the Service, with their heauy complaynts at Bergen gates made vs know how welcome those tidings were at Antwerpe: the last weeke the Drossart of Breda treated for their deliuery, and so they are departing home, you may iudge with what ioy they shall bee intertained; and presently vppon the miscarriage of the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise their army marcheth both from Prince-land, and Rosendale, whereof 32. companies of foote are gone for Breda, and 10. of horse.</p>
            <p>Vpon Thurs-day wee had generall thanksgiuing in our churches &amp; expressing our ioy by fires, guns etc.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>The sum of the officers taken by vs.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Colonels, Lieuten: Col: Sargeant Maiors, &amp; men of great note.—</cell>
                     <cell>19.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Captaines.—</cell>
                     <cell>26.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lieutenants.—</cell>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ensignes.—</cell>
                     <cell>28.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sargeants.—</cell>
                     <cell>23.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Officers about the Canon.—</cell>
                     <cell>6.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Som other officers, &amp; Church men.—</cell>
                     <cell>11.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Land souldiers.—</cell>
                     <cell>3151.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>Sea men.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Captaines.—</cell>
                     <cell>12.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lieutenants.—</cell>
                     <cell>15.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Quarter Masters.—</cell>
                     <cell>7.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Shippers.—</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sailors.—</cell>
                     <cell>820.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Coming out of Antwerpe in all they were mustered aboue.—</cell>
                     <cell>6000.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>The number of the shipping come to our hands.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Shalloopes whose provision generally was 6. brasse Peeces, 8. Murtherers, 4. Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der busses, besides Lether Peeces.—</cell>
                     <cell>36.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <pb facs="tcp:1613:6"/>
Punts with one halfe Canon and two three quarter Canon.—</cell>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Pleyts whose lading was Lope-staues, Nayls, Ice-spurs. 10 Horses, Hardles, Bees<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridges etc.—<g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>—<g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>—</cell>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Other Amunition ships whose lading was Powder, Beere, Deales—</cell>
                     <cell>7.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>That which I offer by way of observation cannot bee much: Time wyll not afford it: Yet these things briefly take notice of.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That Reuenge is no Sluggard, Malice is vnwearyed: For wee vnderstand this worke &amp; practise haue bin vnder hand these 6 yeares.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Reuolters from Religion prooue her sharpest enemyes: witnes (besides Iulian) Count Iohn, who will bee the Ring-leader in any designe that may make nothing of what hee formerly profest.</p>
            <p n="3">3 To expect better then Stratagems tending to ruine from a popish enemy, doth argue either ignorance of their courses, or groundles Confidence,</p>
            <p n="4">4 Security (hauing lost the vse of reason) will deny the Conclusion, rather then beleeue the danger. As wee saw when our people could hardly beleeue the enemy to be the enemy, though he lay before the Ports.</p>
            <p n="5">5. High men are Vanity, &amp; Low men are a Lye: which was playne when wee saw neither the great Commander, nor the comon souldier could helpe vs, the enemy out-brauing vs the whole day.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The Creature cannot bee sufficient for our succor, for he is not allwayes a present helpe in trouble: wee could neither command wind nor tide, where as either of them might haue done vs much good.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The Lord often layes the reine on the neck of his enemyes, they goe long vncontrold: these went all day in the face of our Army vntouched.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Sudden Prosperity is no signe of lasting Happynesse: These Spiders had no sooner framed their web, but it was swept downe.</p>
            <p n="9">9. The Lord brings his greatest workes about by Accident, the tide not ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vng, which wee longd for, our ships could not come vp with them by day, &amp; so escapt a scowring. Their Admirall putting out a light when he was on ground, brought the rest into the same net: they seeking a neerer way by the Fosse-mere, lost their way. with many such like.</p>
            <p n="10">10. A poore creature is many times made the Lords great host, as Pharaohs Lice agaynst him, and a hand full of mist throwne amongst these.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Feare vnfits a man to know what hee should doe, &amp; disinables him to doe what hee knowes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> otherwise they might haue made head vpon the water or the shore, &amp; gotten good quarter, for ought wee perceiue.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Cruell men haue often their punishments giuen them out in proportion they devising new boates, they shall perish in their boates, they will bring hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars
<pb facs="tcp:1613:7"/>
for others which may serue them selues, the gallowes set up for Mordecay serues Haman.</p>
            <p n="13">13. The Lord answers his servants some times in the very thing they aske, in our fast before the Prince went into the field wee made vse of that text &amp; that petition of Dauids Psal: 83. 15. So persecute them with they tempest &amp; make them afrayd with thy storme: &amp; behold wee haue our answere.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Outward strength &amp; humane policyes are no sufficient Bul warks aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynst Battryes from heauen: it was easily seene here was no want of skill in this designe the preparations were not ordinary, but what are Tifney-walls to a Canon-shot? or their plots to Gods mist?</p>
            <p n="15">15. Feare is an ill guide though a quick post, many hundreds of them lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing their owne strength &amp; betaking them selves to the mercy of an enemy.</p>
            <p n="16">16. God like an Indulgent Father striues to reforme by shewing a rod: Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid had the same measure when hee Confesseth, Lord thou hast shewn me affliction. we saw what might haue bin our portion; wee felt not what the enemy intended, &amp; wee deserued.</p>
            <p n="17">17. Diuine Providence (which fooles call Foutune) will serve it selfe vpon Let vs sleepe &amp; the enemy wake, let them attempt, &amp; let vs study to prevent, let them bee strong &amp; many, wee weake &amp; few, let them goe on, &amp; wee looke on, let them deuide the spoyle to euery one a damosell, an office before they come where they are; yet Prouidence will serue it selfe vpon all this.</p>
            <p n="18">18. It is remarkable that the Lord doth sadly make the servants of Idolls to know that ther Maisters or Gods are nothing. In this attempt they will set forth vpon Saint Crosses day (it being by their Almanack the eleuation of the holy Crosse) their Generall of all their Army being called by that name, and Count Iohn the Leader of the Nauall troopes being free of that Company, Such Crosses let the enemyes of God euer carry with them. hee had one he wore on his brest before, he hath now another for his back: I wish i may doe him good at his hart,</p>
            <p n="19">19, The Lord doth not bind himsele to any particular meanes that wee many times vse &amp; to often trust vnto, either for our deliuerance, or the confusi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of our enemies: wee iudged of one meane, he vsed another in this great work, as was playne to be seene.</p>
            <p n="20">20. It is admirable to see what a man or people may receiue in poynt of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor &amp; doe like wise in matter of Action, if the Lord goe out with them; as this is notable, this Prince of Orange neuer yet (since hee had the command) went out, but hee returued triumphing. the Lord euer make him triumphing &amp; victorious in his cause.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1613:7"/>
The Vses wee may make in a word are these</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let vs euer heereafter learne to know the creature by their owne names, &amp; not to call a horse or a man a God, or a water or fort a Sauiour: wee may take vp <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he words of the repenting church Hos 14. The more fatherles the more merry, or the lesse wee Idolize vpon our selves the greater succor we may looke for from heauen.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Since the Lord can rule &amp; guide, dispatch &amp; ouercome workes of this nature so well; since hee hath thus graciously appeared in 31. as formerly in 88. let both England &amp; Holland bee willing to giue him the helme into his owne hands for euer. I wish his quarrell agaynst vs all bee not that wee haue vsed him too much like a Comon-man. wee see (though wee had never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued his word) that his place is at the sterne, let not Religion lackquey to Policy: Kisse the sonne least hee bee angry. Psal 2.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Giue him (who hath done all, &amp; deserueth all) all the glory: Ioseph may haue any thing in Potiphars house but his wife, &amp; in Pharaohs but his throne: as tender is the Lord of his honor &amp; glory as they of either. Shall wee euen greiue his good spirit more. shall wee euer slight his sabbaths? can it bee?</p>
            <p n="4">4. See that prosperity s<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay not our foolish harts: the skill will bee how to improoue the mercy. Sisera is then vndone when hee his careles in Iaels tent, who was a Neutrall: &amp; such is outward prosperity, good &amp; bad may share in it, the wisdome is how to vse it; hee need walke warily that goes on a glassy sea with iron shooes. But the wind is fayre, the sea-men call, the Dutch printer is weary hee craues pardon for his faults, I must end before I am halfe way the mayne. This at least may saue the writing many letters: You may trust the Intelligence for the Truth: &amp; to the God of Truth I commend You.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>In whome I am your lo. kinsman.
H. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
