<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A solemne contestation of diuerse popes, for the aduaunsing of theyr supremacie: quoted and collected faithfully out of their own canon law, according to the very wordes, stile, and tenor of the same theyr own canons, decres, decretales, clementines, extrauagantes, bulles, epistles, and commen glose vpon the same. Histories and stories of Romane bishops [et]c. In forme and wordes, as their are to be seane, and found by the quotations here vnto annexed</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1560</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-01">2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09849</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20114</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114968</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850189</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850189</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15376</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A09849)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15376)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1580:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A solemne contestation of diuerse popes, for the aduaunsing of theyr supremacie: quoted and collected faithfully out of their own canon law, according to the very wordes, stile, and tenor of the same theyr own canons, decres, decretales, clementines, extrauagantes, bulles, epistles, and commen glose vpon the same. Histories and stories of Romane bishops [et]c. In forme and wordes, as their are to be seane, and found by the quotations here vnto annexed</title>
                  <author>Foxe, John, 1516-1587, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Catholic Church. Pope.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[104] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Daye, dwelling ouer Aldersgate. Cum gratia &amp; priuilegio Regiæ Maiestatis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[26 Sept. 1560?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Compilership attributed to John Foxe in an MS. note in the University of Durham copy.</note>
                  <note>The Eton copy is dated 26 Sept. 1560 in MS.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F G⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Popes --  Primacy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-03</date>
            <label>TCP Staff (Michigan)</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15376:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15376:1"/>
            <p>A SOLEMNE Contestation of diuerse Popes, for the aduaunsing of theyr supremacie: quoted and col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected faithfully out of their own Canon law, according to the very wordes, stile, and tenor of the same theyr own Canons, Decres, Decretales, Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentines, Extrauagantes, Bulles, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistles, and commen Glose vpon the same. Histories and stories of Romane Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops &amp;c. Informe and wordes, as their are to be seane, and found by the Quotations here vnto annexed.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Iohn Daye, dwelling ouer Aldersgate. Cum gratia &amp; priuilegio Regiae Maiestatis.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15376:2"/>
            <head>To the Christen Reader.</head>
            <p>IN reading this Boke vndersta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d (gentle Reader) nothing here to be feyned or forged of vs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise than the Popes themselfes in theyr owne Persones speake and write in theyr owne Lawes and Canones, accordyng as their wordes and sentences shall declare, if thou please to searche them and to conferre the quotationes here in the Margent, with their writynges as they stand in theyr owne Bokes. Wherein, if thou shalte finde any line or sentence through this whole Boke alteryng or vareyng from their wordes and truth of their writynges: then iudge and wey not so much our labour in gathering, as marke the matter &amp; maner of their hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and then be not asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to confesse the truth.</p>
            <closer>Vale.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:15376:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Solemne Contestation of diuers Popes.</head>
            <p>F<note n="A" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facius</hi> 8. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trauag. de Maiorit. &amp; obed. c. Vna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note> Or as much as it standeth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site of saluation, for euery humane crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to bee subiecte vnto me, the Pope of Rome, it shalbe therefore requisite and neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary for all men that will be saued to learne &amp; knowe the dignitie of my sea, and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of my domination, as here is set forth accordyng to the truth and very wordes of mine owne lawes, in style as foloweth. <note n="B" place="margin">
                  <hi>Distinct.</hi> 28<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ca. Decretis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> First my institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion began in the old Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; was consumate and finished in the newe: in that


<pb facs="tcp:15376:3"/>
my pristhode was prefigured by Aaron: And other bish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shopes vnder me were prefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured by the sonnes of Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were vnder him. <note n="C" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope pelagius Distinct.</hi> 21. <hi>c. Qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uis.</hi>
               </note> Nether is it to be thought that my church of Rome hath ben pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ferred by any general cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>sell, but obtained y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> primacie only by the voyce of the gospell, &amp; the mouth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> sauiour.<note n="D" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pelagius ibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem.</hi>
               </note> And hath in it neither spotte nor wrincle, nor any suche like thing. <note n="E" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Nicolaꝰ Dist.</hi> 21. <hi>cap. Inferior.</hi>
               </note> Wherefore as other seates be all inferiour to me, &amp; as thei can not absolue me: so haue they no power to binde me, or to stand against me, no more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the axe hath power


<pb facs="tcp:15376:3"/>
to sta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or presume aboue him that heaweth with it, or the sawe to presume against him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ruleth it. <note n="F" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Lucius</hi> 24. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>cap. a. Recta.</hi>
               </note>This is the holy &amp; apostolike mother church of all other churches of Chryst, <note n="G" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Calixtus Dist.</hi> 12. <hi>cap. Non decet.</hi>
               </note> From whose rules it is not mete that any person or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons should decline, but like as the sonne of God came to do the will of his Father, so muste you do the will of your mother, the church of Rome, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head whereof am I. <note n="H" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius. Distinct.</hi> 11. <hi>cap. Quis.</hi>
               </note>And if anye other person or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones shall erre from the said church, eyther let them be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monished, or els their names taken, to be knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who they


<pb facs="tcp:15376:4"/>
be that swarue from the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes of Rome. <note n="I" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Stepha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus Distinct.</hi> 19. <hi>ca. Enim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ero.</hi>
               </note> Thus the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for asmuch as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy churche of Rome, wherof I am gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour, is set vp to the whole worlde for a glasse or exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, reaso<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wold, that what thing so euer the sayd church deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myth or ordeneth, that to be receaued of all men for a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall &amp; a perpetuall rule for euer. <note n="K" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Bonifa.</hi> 8. <hi>Extrauag. c. vna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> sancta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Item Pope Ioannes.</hi> 22. <hi>Extrau. cap. Super ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes.</hi>
               </note> Wherevpon we se it now veryfide in this church, that was forprophesied by Ieremy, saing: behold I haue set thee vp ouer nations and kingdomes to plucke vp, and to breake down, to build, and to plante &amp;c. <note n="L" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiui</hi> 3. <hi>art. de maior &amp; obe. c. Solitae.</hi>
               </note> Who so vnder


<pb facs="tcp:15376:4"/>
standeth not the prerogatiue of this my Priesthode let him loke vp to the Firmament, where he may see two great lightes, the sunne &amp; the mone, one ruling ouer the daye, the other ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night. So in the firmament of the vniuersall churche. <note n="M" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Gelasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us distinc.</hi> 96 <hi>cap. Duo.</hi>
               </note> God hath set two great dignities, the autoritie of the Pope, and of the empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ij. this our dignitie is so muche more weightier, as we haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter charge to geue accompt to god, for kings of the earth &amp; the lawes of men. <note n="N" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note>Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be it knowne to you em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, which knowe it also


<pb facs="tcp:15376:5"/>
right well, that you depende vpon the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of vs, we muste not be brought and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to your will. <note n="O" place="margin">
                  <hi>Innocentius De Maior. et obed. c. Solitae.</hi>
               </note> For, as I sayd, loke what difference there is betwixt the Sunne and the Mone, so great is the power of the Pope ruling o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the daye, that is ouer the spiritualtie, aboue emperours and kinges rulinge ouer the nyght that is ouer the laitie. <note n="P" place="margin">
                  <hi>Glosa ibide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note> Now seyng then the earth is seue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times bigger then the Moone, and the sunne eight times gretter than the earth, it foloweth that the Popes dignitie 47. times dothe sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounte the estate of Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.


<pb facs="tcp:15376:5"/>
               <note n="Q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note>Upon consideracion wherof I saye therfore &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that Constantine the Emperour did naught, in set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the patriarch of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople beneth him on his left ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. <note n="R" place="margin">
                  <hi>Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tius Glosa ibidem.</hi>
               </note> And although the said Emperour wrote to me alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes of saint Peter commaundyng vs to submit our selfs to euery humane cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ature, as to kings, dukes and other for the cause of God. &amp;c. 1. <hi>Peter</hi> .2. yet in aunswering agayn in my decretall, I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded the minde and the wordes of s. Peter to pertain to his subiectes, and not his successors, willinge the saide


<pb facs="tcp:15376:6"/>
emperour to consider the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the speaker, &amp; to whom it was spoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For if the mind of Peter had ben there to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>base the order of pristhod and to make vs vnderlinges to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye humane creature, than euery Iacke might haue do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion ouer prelates whiche maketh against the example of Christ, setting vp the order of presthod to bere dominion ouer kinges, beyng said to <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy</hi> the Prophet: beholde I haue set the vp ouer kinges &amp; nations. &amp;c. <note n="S" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</hi> 5. <hi>Cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. de iureiurando c. Romani.</hi>
               </note>And as I feared not than to write this boldly to Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>stantine, so now I say to al other emperours, that thei


<pb facs="tcp:15376:6"/>
receiuing of me there appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, vnction, consecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; croune imperiall, muste not disdaine to submit there hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des vnder me, and swear vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me there allegeance. <note n="T" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Ioa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes. Dist.</hi> 96. <hi>c. Nunquam.</hi>
               </note>For so you reade in the decree of pope Iohn, howe that prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces heretofore haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wont to bowe and submitte there heades vnto bishops, and not to procede in Iudgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the heades of bishops. <note n="V" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</hi> 5. <hi>clement. de Sente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iud, c. Paestos ralis.</hi>
               </note>yf this reuerence &amp; submis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion was wont to begeuen to Bisshops, howe muche more ought they to submitte there heades to me beyng superior not only to kinges, but Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours,


<pb facs="tcp:15376:7"/>
and that for two causes, firste for my title of successio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that I pope of Rome haue to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> empire, the roume standinge vacant. Also for the fulnesse of power that Christe the kinge of Kinges, and lorde of Lordes hath ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to me in the person of Peter. <note n="X" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> 3. <hi>De iudiciis cap. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit.</hi>
               </note>By reason where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, seyng my power is not of man but of God, who by his celestiall prouidence, hath set me ouer his whole vniuersall Churche maister and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, it belongeth therfore to my office to loke vpon euery mortal sinne of euery Christe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>


               <pb facs="tcp:15376:7"/>
man: <note n="Y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note> Wherby all criminall causes as well of kinges, as all other, be subiecte to my censure, <note n="Y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Iulius. Caus.</hi> 2. <hi>q.</hi> 6. <hi>c. Ad Romana<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note> in suche sorte, that in all maner of pleadyng if any maner of person at any time eyther before the sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence giuen, or after shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pele to me, it shalbe lawfulfor him so to do. <note n="Z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Innocentius Ibidem.</hi>
               </note> Nether must Kinges and Princes thinke it muche to submitte them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfes to my Iudgement for so did <hi>Valentinianus</hi> the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Emperour, so did <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dosius,</hi> and also <hi>Carolus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="A" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bonifacius Dist.</hi> 40. <hi>cap. Si papa.</hi>
               </note> Thus you see all muste be iudged by me, &amp; I of no man,


<pb facs="tcp:15376:8"/>
yea and thoughe I Pope of Rome, by my negligencie or euill demanner befound vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, or hurtfull other to my self, or to others, yea, if I should draw with me innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable soules by heapes to hell, yet no mortall manne so hardy, so bold, or presumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to reproue me, <note n="B" place="margin">
                  <hi>Glosa. Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uag. de sede vacant. Ad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolatus.</hi>
               </note> or to say to me: <hi>Domine cur ita facis?</hi> 
               <note n="C" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope leo. cau.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>q.</hi> 7. <hi>c. No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note>for although you reade that <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam</hi> was rebuked of his asse, by the whiche Asse our sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, by <hi>Balaam</hi> we prelates are signified: yet that ought to be no example to our sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes to rebuke vs. <note n="D" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gregorius</hi> 2. <hi>q.</hi> 7. <hi>c. petr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note>And though we reade in the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture


<pb facs="tcp:15376:8"/>
that Peter, who recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the power of kyngdome, and beyng chiefe of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stels, might by vertue of his office controlle all other, was content to come, and giue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere before his inferiours, obiecting to him, his goyng to the gentiles, yet other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours muste not learne by this example to be chekmate with their prelates, bycause that Peter so toke it at there handes, shewyng therby ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a dispensation of humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, than the power of his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, by the whiche power he might haue saide to them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in this wise, it beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth


<pb facs="tcp:15376:9"/>
not shepe, nor belongeth to their office to accuse or carpe theyr sheapherd, &amp;c. <note n="E" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Nicolaꝰ Dist. 21. cap. In tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note> For els why was <hi>Dioscorus</hi> patriarch of <hi>Alexandria</hi> condemned and exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate at Chalcedon? not for any cause of his faith, but only for that he durst sta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d against pope Leo, and durst exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate the Bisshop of rome, for who is he that hath autoritie to accuse the seat of saint Peter.<note n="F" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hiero. Caus.</hi> 2 <hi>q.</hi> 7. <hi>cap. Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus.</hi>
               </note> Albeit I am not ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t what saint Hieromy writeth, that Paule would not haue reprehendid Peter, vnlesse he had thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe equale vnto him: <note n="G" place="margin">
                  <hi>Glosa Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiani ibidem.</hi>
               </note> yet Hieromy muste thus be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundid


<pb facs="tcp:15376:9"/>
by my interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that this equalitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Peter and Paule con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth not in like office of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnitie, but in purenes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersation. <note n="H" place="margin">
                  <hi>Glosa. in Dist.</hi> 11. <hi>c. Quis.</hi>
               </note>For who gaue Paule his licence to preache but Peter, and that by the autoritie of God, sayng, sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate to me Paule and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas. &amp;c. <note n="I" place="margin">
                  <hi>Caus.</hi> 2. <hi>q.</hi> 7. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o beati.</hi>
               </note> Wherefore be it knowen to all men that my Churche of Rome is prince &amp; head of al nations, <note n="K" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Nicolaꝰ Dist.</hi> 22. <hi>c. oe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</hi>
               </note>the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the faith,<note n="L" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Anacle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus. Dist.</hi> 22. <hi>c. Sacrosa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cta.</hi>
               </note> the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion cardinall, wherupon all churches do depende as the dore dothe depende by the hinges: <note n="M" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope pelagius Dist.</hi> 21. <hi>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis.</hi>
               </note> the first of al other


<pb facs="tcp:15376:10"/>
seates, without al spot or ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish: <note n="N" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Nicolaꝰ Dist.</hi> 21. <hi>cap. Deni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>.</hi>
               </note>Lady mistres and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structor of all Churches. <note n="O" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Stepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus. Dist.</hi> 19. <hi>Enimuero.</hi>
               </note> a glasse and spectacle to al men, to be folowed in all, what so euer she obseruith. <note n="P" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Lucius.</hi> 24. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rect.</hi>
               </note> Whiche was neuer founde yet to slide or decline from the pathe of apostolicke tradition, or to be inta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gled with anye newnes of Heresy. <note n="Q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Nicolaꝰ Dist.</hi> 22. <hi>Oe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</hi>
               </note>Agaynst which church of Rome who so euer speaketh any euill, is forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with an heritike: <note n="R" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius. Dist.</hi> 81. <hi>cap. Siqui.</hi>
               </note> yea a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pagane a witch and idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or infidele. <note n="S" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Leo. Caus.</hi> 3. <hi>q.</hi> 6. <hi>cap. Multu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note> Hauinge ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of power onlye in her owne handes in rulyng,<note n="T" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dist.</hi> 20. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretales.</hi>
               </note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisinge, absoluinge, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,


<pb facs="tcp:15376:10"/>
casting out, or receiuing in,<note n="V" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Iulius. Caus.</hi> 2. <hi>q.</hi> 6. <hi>Qui se.</hi>
               </note> albeit I deny not but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Churches be partakers with hyr in laboring and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng. <note n="X" place="margin">
                  <hi>Caus.</hi> 2. <hi>q.</hi> 6. <hi>Arguta. ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> c. Ad Romana<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note>To the which church of Rome it is lawfull to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale for remedy, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al other Churches.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caus.</hi> 2. <hi>q.</hi> 6. <hi>cap. Placuit.</hi>
               </note> Although it was otherwise concluded in the generall cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell of Carthage, that no man shoulde appeale ouer the sea, vnder paine of ex communication, yet my glose commeth in here with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Glosa. Gratiani.¶ Nisi.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nisi forte Romanam se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem appellauerint</hi>: 1. Except the appeale be to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> sea of Rome, &amp;c. <note n="Y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Gelasiꝰ.</hi> 25. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>cap. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidimus.</hi>
               </note>By the autoritie of whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che Churche of Rome, all si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodes,


<pb facs="tcp:15376:11"/>
and decrees of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels stande confirmed. <note n="Z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Vrbanꝰ.</hi> 25. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>c. Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi>
               </note> And hath alwaies full autoritie in hyr handes to make newe Lawes and decrementes:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> 25 <hi>q.</hi> 2. <hi>ca. posteaquam.</hi>
               </note> And to alter statutes priuile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, rightes or Documentes of churches to separate thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ioyned, &amp; to ioyne things seperated vpon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>sideration eyther in whole or in parte, personally, or generally. <note n="A" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bulla Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis. Dist.</hi> 96. <hi>c. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>stant.</hi>
               </note>Of the whiche Church of Rome I am heade as a king is ouer his iudges, <note n="B" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope paschalis Dist.</hi> 63. <hi>cap. Ego.</hi>
               </note>the vicare of S. Peter. <note n="C" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> 5. <hi>Cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. c. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani. Glosa.</hi>
               </note>yea not the vicare of Peter properly, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vicare of Christ properly, and succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor


<pb facs="tcp:15376:11"/>
of Peter. <note n="D" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Bonifacius</hi> 8. <hi>Sext. Decretal. cap. vbi.</hi>
               </note> vicare of Iesus christ,<note n="E" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note> Rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the vniuersall churche: Director of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde his vniuersall flocke: <note n="F" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Bonifacius. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem. Sext. Decretal. ib. Sacro sancta.</hi>
               </note> Chiefe magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate of the whole worlde. <note n="G" place="margin">
                  <hi>Anacletus. Dist.</hi> 22. <hi>cap. Sacro sancta.</hi>
               </note> 1. <hi>Cephas. i. caput,</hi> the head and chiefe of the Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Churche. <note n="H" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pope Bonifacius</hi> 4. <hi>Sext. Decret. de paenit. &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miss. cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Glosa.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Item Alexander</hi> 4. <hi>Sext. Decre. c.</hi> 4. <hi>in Glosa.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall Pope, And diocesane in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces exempt as well as euerye Bisshoppe is in places not exempt. <note n="I" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope hilarius.</hi> 25. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>Nulli.</hi>
               </note> most mightie Priest. <note n="K" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sext. Decret. cap. Ab ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitris. Glosa.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lex animata in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</hi> 1. <note n="L" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Bonifa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciꝰ. Sext. Dec. De co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>st. cap. licet.</hi>
               </note> a liuing lawe


<pb facs="tcp:15376:12"/>
lawe in the earth hauing all lawes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiste of my breste <note n="M" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiꝰ.</hi> 3. <hi>De tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>sl. c. Quanto.</hi>
               </note> bering y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> person of no pure ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <note n="N" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prohaem. Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Glosa. Papa Stupor mundi &amp;c. Nec Deus es nec homo, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>si neuter es in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>.</hi>
               </note>beyng nether God nor man, but the admiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world, and a midle thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixte both: <note n="O" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Bonifa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius. Extr. De Maiorit &amp; obed. ca. vna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dist.</hi> 22. <hi>c. Oe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</hi>
               </note> Hauing both swordes in my power bothe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> spirituall, &amp; temporall iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <note n="P" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sext. Decret. De sente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. &amp; re. c. Ad Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolicae. ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Glosa. ibide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note>so far surmou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> autoritie of the emperour, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I of mine owne power alone without a councell haue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torite to depose him, to trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre his kyngdome, and to giue a new election, as I did to Frederick &amp; diuers other. <note n="Q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Nicolaꝰ Dist.</hi> 22. <hi>cap. Oe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</hi>
               </note>What power than or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>estate in al the world is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable


<pb facs="tcp:15376:12"/>
to me: who haue auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to binde and lose both in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; earth.<note n="R" place="margin">
                  <hi>Glosa. ibide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note> That is, who haue power both of heauenly thinges, and also of temporal thinges?<note n="S" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Gelasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us. Dist.</hi> 96. <hi>c. Duo.</hi>
               </note> To whom Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and kinges be more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leade is inferiour to Gold.<note n="T" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Gelasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us. ibidem.</hi>
               </note> For do you not see the neckes of great kinges &amp; princes be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vnder our knees, yea &amp; thynke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>selfes happy &amp; well defensid, if they maye kisse our ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des?<note n="V" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dist.</hi> 96. <hi>cap. Illud.</hi>
               </note> Wherfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> sawsines of <hi>Honorius</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour is to be reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>did, &amp; his constitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abolished, who w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his laitie would take vpon him to intermedle not onl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>


               <pb facs="tcp:15376:13"/>
with the temporall order, but also with matters ecclesias<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike, and elettion of the pope. <note n="X" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex citatione Hier. Marij.</hi>
               </note> But here percase some will obiect the examples &amp; words of Christ, saing, that his king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dom is not of this world, and where he beyng required to deuide betwixt two brethren there hereditage, did refuse it but that ought to be no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice to my power. <note n="Y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Hilde bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dus, called Gregorius</hi> 7. <hi>Ex platina, in Vita Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rii.</hi>
               </note>For if Peter, and I in Peter, if we I saye, haue power to binde &amp; loose in heauen, how much more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is it to be thought, that we haue power in earth to loose and take awaye im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peres, Kyngdomes, Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes,


<pb facs="tcp:15376:13"/>
and what els so euer mortall men maye haue, and to giue them where we will? <note n="Z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hildebrandus ibidem.</hi>
               </note>And if we haue autoritie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Angels, which be the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernors of princes, what the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maye we do vpon theyr infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours and seruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes? <note n="A" place="margin">
                  <hi>Antonius in Tertia parte Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mae maiori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> And for that you shall not meruel, that I say, Angels be subiect to vs, you shal here what my blessed clerke <hi>Antoninus,</hi> wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of that matter, saying, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our power, of Peter &amp; me, is greater then the Angels in .4 thynges: In iurisdiction, 2. in administration of sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: 3. in knowlege, 4. and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. &amp;c. <note n="B" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bulla Cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note>And again in <hi>Bulla


<pb facs="tcp:15376:14"/>
Clementis,</hi> do not I there com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde in my Bull, the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of Paradise to absolue the soule of man oute of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory and to bringe it into the glory of Paradise? <note n="C" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius. De ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione c. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erabilem.</hi>
               </note>And now besides my heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to speake of mine earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iurisdiction, who did first translate the Empeire from the Grekes, to the Almanes, but I?<note n="D" place="margin">
                  <hi>Extrauagan. De praeben. et dig. c. Execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis.</hi>
               </note> And not only in the Empyre am Emperour, the place being emptie, but in all ecclesiasticall benefices haue full right and power to giue, to translate, and to dispose af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my arbitreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. <note n="E" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ias. Caus.</hi> 15 <hi>q.</hi> 6. <hi>c. Ali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> Did not I <hi>Zacharias</hi> put downe <hi>Hilde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke</hi>


               <pb facs="tcp:15376:14"/>
the olde king of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and set vp <hi>Pipinus</hi>? <note n="F" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Hilde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand. called Gregorius.</hi> 7. <hi>Cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. c. pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storalis.</hi>
               </note>Did not I <hi>Gregorius sept.</hi> set vp <hi>Robert VVysarde</hi> and made him kyng of <hi>Sicilia</hi> &amp; Duke of <hi>Capua</hi>? &amp;c. <note n="G" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex Gestis Hildebrandi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> Did not I the same <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> also sette vp <hi>Rodulphus</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Henricus</hi> themperour? <note n="H" place="margin">
                  <hi>Baptista Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius.</hi>
               </note> And thoughe this <hi>Henricus</hi> was an Emperour of moste stoute courage, who stoode, 62. times in ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fielde against his enemies. <note n="I" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Platina Benno.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nauclerus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </note>yet did not I <hi>Gregorius</hi> bring him, <hi>coram no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis,</hi> and made him stande at my gate three dayes and iij. nightes barefote &amp; barelegge with his Wife and Childe, in the depe of winter, bothe in


<pb facs="tcp:15376:15"/>
froste and snowe entreating for his absolucion and after did exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate him again, so was he twise excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate in my daies?<note n="K" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Platina Egnatius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Benno.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> Again did not I <hi>Paschalis</hi> after <hi>Gregory,</hi> set vp the Sonne of the said <hi>Henricus,</hi> against his Father in warre, to possesse the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere, and to put down his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and so he did? <note n="L" place="margin">
                  <hi>Polido. Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius. Historia Iornalensis de rebus Anglo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
               </note> Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did not I pope <hi>Alexander</hi> brynge vnder <hi>Henry</hi> the second king of England, for the death of <hi>Thomas Becket,</hi> and caused him to goe barefote to his tombe at Canterburie with bleding feete? <note n="M" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chronica ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>acula.</hi>
               </note> Did not I <hi>Innocentius</hi> the thirde, cause kinge <hi>Iohn</hi> to


<pb facs="tcp:15376:15"/>
knele downe at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fete of <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolfus</hi> my legate, and offer vp his crowne to his handes? al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so to kisse the fete of <hi>Steuen La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ghton</hi> bishop of Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terbury, and besides marsid him in a M. Markes by yeare? <note n="N" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Vrbanꝰ. Caus.</hi> 15. <hi>q.</hi> 6. <hi>cap. Iuratos.</hi>
               </note> Did not I <hi>Vrbanus</hi> 2. put downe <hi>Hugo</hi> erle in <hi>Italy,</hi> discharging his subiectes from their othe and obedience to him? <note n="O" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pope Pasch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis. Carsulani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Platina.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vincentius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Stella.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Antoninus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Matheus pari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>siensis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> Did not I <hi>Paschalis</hi> exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate also his Sonne <hi>Henricus</hi> 5. and gate out of his handes al his right and title of electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and donacions of spirituall promotions? Did not I <hi>Gela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sius</hi> .2. bring the captaine <hi>Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> vnder,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Gelasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> .<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> vnto the kissing of


<pb facs="tcp:15376:16"/>
my fete? And after <hi>Gelasius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Calix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note> did not I <hi>Calixtus</hi> 2. quale the for said emperour <hi>Henricus</hi> 5. &amp; also did bring in subiection <hi>Gregorie</hi> whom the sayd Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour had set vp against me to be Pope,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Platina de vitis pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note> bringing him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Rome vpon a Camell, his face to the horse taile, making him to hold the horse taile in his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in steade of a bridle? <note n="P" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> .2. <hi>Platina.</hi>
               </note> Further did not I <hi>Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> 2. set vp and made <hi>Lotha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> to be Emperour for dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing out Pope <hi>Anacletus</hi> out of Rome. <note n="Q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nauclerus.</hi>
               </note>Dyd not I the said <hi>Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tius</hi> take the Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Sicile</hi> from the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere, &amp; made <hi>Roger</hi> to be king


<pb facs="tcp:15376:16"/>
thereof, wherby afterwarde the kingdome became the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie of <hi>s. Peter</hi>? <note n="R" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> .3. <hi>De spo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal. &amp; matr. c. Non e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t.</hi>
               </note> Did not I <hi>Alexander</hi> .3. suspende al the realme and Churches of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande for the Kinges mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age. <hi>Anno</hi> 1159. <note n="S" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nauclerus. Acta. Rom. pontificum.</hi>
               </note>But what do I speake of kings? did not the said <hi>Alexander</hi> bringe the valiant Emperour <hi>Fredericke</hi> the firste to <hi>Venece,</hi> by reason of his sonne <hi>Otho</hi> there taken prisoner, and there in <hi>s. Marke</hi> his Churche made him fall downe flat vpon the ground, while I set my fote vpon his necke, sayng the verse of the Psalme. <hi>Super a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pidem &amp; basi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liscum ambulabis &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note n="T" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Adria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus. Vitae Ro. pontificum.</hi>
               </note>Did not


<pb facs="tcp:15376:17"/>
I <hi>Hadrianus</hi> pope and an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish man borne excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate William King of Sicile, and refused his peace, which he offerid. And had not he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome me in plaine fielde, I would haue shaked him out of his kingdom of Sicile and Dukedome of <hi>Apulia</hi>? <note n="V" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>entino.</hi>
               </note> Also did not I the saide <hi>Adrianus,</hi> controlle and correct the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saide <hi>Fridericus</hi> emperour for holding the lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te sturrup of my horse wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he should haue holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the right? <note n="X" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ulla Adriani <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Caesare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note> And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde did excomunicate and curse him, for that he was so sawsie, to set his owne name in writing before mine? <note n="Y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acta Rom. pontifi.</hi>
               </note> And


<pb facs="tcp:15376:17"/>
although a pore flie after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ouercame &amp; strangled me, yet I made kynges and Emperours to stope. <note n="Z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> 3. <hi>Ex vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis &amp; Actis Rom. pontifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note> Dyd not I <hi>Innocentius</hi> .3. deiect <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippus</hi> brother to <hi>Fridericus</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the emperiall crowne beyng electid withoute my leaue, and after set him vp agayne? And also set vp <hi>Otho</hi> of Bru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex Abbate Vrspergense.</hi>
               </note> and after did exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate &amp; also depose the same 4. yeares, setting vp the fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch kyng to warre against hym? <note n="A" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex eodem.</hi>
               </note> Then was <hi>Fridericus</hi> .2. by me sette vp and reigned .37. yeares, and yet fiue yeares before he died. <note n="B" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Honoriꝰ</hi> 3. <hi>Ex Mario.</hi>
               </note> Did not I <hi>Honorius</hi> interdicte him, for


<pb facs="tcp:15376:18"/>
not restoring certaine to their possessions at my requeste? <note n="C" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius.</hi> 9. <hi>Ex eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem.</hi>
               </note> Whom also <hi>Gregorius</hi> .9. dyd excommunicate twise toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and raised vp the <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> agaynst him. <note n="D" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> .4. <hi>Hiero<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nimus Mariꝰ Petrus de Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neis.</hi>
               </note> And at length <hi>Innocentius</hi> spoiled him of his empere, after that cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed hym to be poysoned, at length to be strangled by one <hi>Manfredus,</hi> and did excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate his sonne <hi>Conradus</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, not only depreuing him of his right inheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but also caused him, with <hi>Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick</hi> Duke of Austria to be beheaded. <note n="E" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex Chronic. Car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onis.</hi>
               </note> Thus then dyd not I exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose all these Emperours in


<pb facs="tcp:15376:18"/>
order. <hi>Henricus</hi> .4. <hi>Henricus</hi> .5. <hi>Fridericus</hi> .1. <hi>Philippus Otho</hi> .4. <hi>Fridericus</hi> .2. and <hi>Conradus</hi> his sonne? <note n="F" place="margin">
                  <hi>Historia An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note>Did not I interdicte kyng <hi>Henry</hi> the eyght? <note n="G" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem.</hi>
               </note> And all his kingdome of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d? <note n="H" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem.</hi>
               </note>And had not his prudence and power preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tid my prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, I had displaced him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his kingdome also? briefly who is able to comprehend the greatnesse of my power &amp; of my seat? <note n="I" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellus. Dist.</hi> 17 <hi>cap. Synodu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note>for by me only generall councels take theyr force and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmation, <note n="K" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dist.</hi> 20<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>les.</hi>
               </note>and the interpretacion of the said consels, and of al other causes hard and doubtfull ought to be referred and stande to my


<pb facs="tcp:15376:19"/>
determination. <note n="M" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Nicolaꝰ Dist.</hi> 19. <hi>Si Romanoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note> By me the workes of all wryters what so euer they be, eyther be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued or allowed. <note n="N" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note> Then howe muche more ought my wrytinges and decrees to be preferrid before al other?<note n="O" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dist.</hi> 20. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretales.</hi>
               </note> In so muche that my letters and epistels decretall be equiua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent with generall councels. <note n="P" place="margin">
                  <hi>Symmachus Pope.</hi> 9. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <hi>Alioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note>And wher as God hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denid all causes of men, to be iudged by men, he hath only reseruid me, that is, the Pope of Rome, without all questio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of men, vnto his own iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <note n="Q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius.</hi> 6. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <hi>c. Nemo.</hi>
               </note>And therfore where all other creatures be vnder theyr iudge, only I which in


<pb facs="tcp:15376:19"/>
earth am the iudge of all can be iudged of none, nether of Emperour, nor the whole Clergye, nor of Kynges, nor yet of the people. <note n="R" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note> For who hath power to iudge vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Iudge? <note n="S" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Gelasiꝰ</hi> .9. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <hi>cap. Cuncta.</hi>
               </note> This iudge am I, &amp; that alone, without anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther assistance of any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouncel ioyned to me. For I haue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer vpon councels, councels haue no power vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me. But yf the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell determe amisse, it is in my autoritie alone to infringe it, or to condemne whome I luste without any councell. <note n="T" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note>And all for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of my predecessor bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed saint Peter, which by the


<pb facs="tcp:15376:20"/>
voyce of the lord, he receuid, and euer shall retene. <note n="V" place="margin">
                  <hi>Anastasius pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>triarch. D. q.</hi> 3. <hi>c. Antiquis Item.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <hi>cap. Quamuis.</hi>
               </note> Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore and where as al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sentences and iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts both of cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels person or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones maye and oughte to be examined,<note n="X" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> .2. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <hi>c. Quatuor.</hi>
               </note> for that, thei may be corrupted foure wayes, by feare, by giftes, by hatred, by fauoure: only my sente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and iudgement muste stande, <note n="Y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Agatho. Dist.</hi> 19. <hi>cap. Sic oe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</hi>
               </note>as gyuen out of Heauen by the mouth of Peter himself whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che no manne must, <note n="Z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Nicola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> .9. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <hi>cap. Patet.</hi>
               </note>breake, nor retract.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="A" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Innocentius</hi> 2. <hi>Art.</hi> 17. <hi>q.</hi> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Si quis.</hi>
               </note>No man muste dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute or doubt of. <note n="B" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dist.</hi> 19. <hi>cap. In me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriam.</hi>
               </note> yea &amp; if my iudgment statute or yock seame scarsly tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,


<pb facs="tcp:15376:20"/>
yet for reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of s. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it must be humbly obeyd. <note n="C" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sextꝰ Decret. Tit.</hi> 7. <hi>De re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciat. Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Glosa.</hi>
               </note>yea and moreouer obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is to be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not only to such decrees sette forthe by me in time of my Popedome, but also to suche as I do foresey &amp; commit to writing, before I be Pope.<note n="D" place="margin">
                  <hi>Of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ic. l.</hi> 1.</note> And although it be thought by some writers, to be giuen to all men to ere, and to be deceauid, <note n="E" place="margin">
                  <hi>Glosa. Extra. De verb. sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nif. cap. Ad.</hi>
               </note> yet nether am I a pure man, <note n="F" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius. Caus.</hi> 35. <hi>q.</hi> 9. <hi>Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licae.</hi>
               </note>and again the sentence of my Apostolike seat is alwaies co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceauid with such moderation, is concocte and digestid with suche paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and rypenes, and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out with such grauitie of


<pb facs="tcp:15376:21"/>
deliberation, that nothing is thought in it necessary to bee alterid or retractid. <note n="G" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Symma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus. Caus.</hi> 9. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <hi>Alioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is manifest, &amp; testified by the voyce of holy bishops, that the dignitie of this my seat is to be reuerenced tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the whole world, in that all the faithfull submit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfes to it, as to the head of the whole body: <note n="H" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note> Wherof it is spoken to me by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, speaking of the arche: if this bee humiled, whether shall you runne for succour, &amp; wher shal your glory become? Seyng then this is so, that so holy Bishops &amp; scriptures do witnesse with me, what


<pb facs="tcp:15376:21"/>
shall we saye then to suche as wil take vpon them to iudge of my doynges, to reprehend my procedinges, or to require homage and tribute of me, to whome all other be subiecte: <note n="I" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Grego<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rius.</hi> 6. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <hi>Scriptu est.</hi>
               </note> Againste the firste sorte the Scripture speaketh <hi>Deutero.</hi> thou ought not to putte thy sithe in an other mans corne. Whiche thinge to attempt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst me what is it but plain sacrilege. <note n="K" place="margin">
                  <hi>Caus.</hi> 17. <hi>q.</hi> 4. <hi>Sacrileg. Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sa.</hi>
               </note> Accordinge to my canonists, which thus define sacrilege to consiste in three thinges, eyther when a man iudgeth of his princes iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: or whan the holy daye is prophaned, or when reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence


<pb facs="tcp:15376:22"/>
is not giuen to Lawes and Canons. <note n="L" place="margin">2. <hi>q.</hi> 7. <hi>cap. Plaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sema Gratia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni. ¶. Item.</hi>
               </note>Agaynste the second sort maketh the place of the boke of kinges, where we reade, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> arch of God was brought from <hi>Gabaa</hi> to Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem, and in the waye the Arch inclinyng by reason of the vnruly oxen, <hi>Ozias</hi> the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite put to his hand to help, and therefore was stroken of the Lord. By this Arch is si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnified the Prelates, by the inclination therof, the fall of Prelates,<note n="M" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note> whiche also be si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnified by the Angels, that <hi>Iacob</hi> did see goyng vp &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming doune the lader. <note n="N" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note> Also by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet, wher he saith:


<pb facs="tcp:15376:22"/>
He bowyd down the Heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and came down &amp;c: By <hi>Ozias,</hi> and by the vnruly Oxen are mente our subiectes. <note n="O" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note> Then like as <hi>Ozias</hi> was strucken for putting his hand to the Arch inclining, no more must sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes rebuke there Prelates, goynge awry, <note n="P" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ibidem.</hi> ¶.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>His itae.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> Albeit here may be answered again, that all be not Prelates whiche so be called, for it is not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name that maketh a bishop, but his life. <note n="Q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Vrbanꝰ.</hi> 23. <hi>q. Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note>Agaynst the thirde sort of suche as would brynge vs vnder the tribute and exac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of seculare men, maketh the newe Testament, where <hi>Peter</hi> was bid to giue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grot


<pb facs="tcp:15376:23"/>
in the Fishes mouthe but not the head, nor the body of the fishe: No more is the heade or body of the Churche subduid to Kings, but only that, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is in the mouthe, that is, the externe things of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church And yet nor they nether: <note n="R" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ibidem.</hi> ¶</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quamuis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> For so we reade in the booke of <hi>Genesis,</hi> that <hi>Pharao</hi> in time of darth subduyd all the land of thegiptians, but yet he mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistred to the Priestes, so that he toke nether there possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from them, nor there li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie. If then the prelates of the Churche muste be nether iudged, nor reprehendid, nor exacted, howe muche more


<pb facs="tcp:15376:23"/>
ought I to be free from the same,<note n="S" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictus. Extr. De aut. et. vs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pallij. c. Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>sta.</hi>
               </note> which am the Bishop of bishops, &amp; head of prelates For it is not to bee thought that the case betwixt me and other prelates, betwixte my sea,<note n="T" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Stepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus. Dist.</hi> 19. <hi>Enimuero.</hi>
               </note> &amp; other churches be like. <note n="V" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us. Dist.</hi> 21. <hi>Quamuis.</hi>
               </note>Although the whole catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and apostolike Churche make one brydechamber of christ: yet the cathol. &amp; Apost. church of Rome, had the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence giuen ouer al other, by the mouth of the lord him self sayng to Peter: Thou art Peter. &amp;c?<note n="X" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dist.</hi> 21. <hi>De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cretis.</hi>
               </note> Thus a discretion and difference must be had in the church, as it was betwixt <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Children,<note n="Y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Anaclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus. Dist.</hi> 21. <hi>in non<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt


<pb facs="tcp:15376:24"/>
72. disciples, &amp; the 12. Apostels: betwixt thother a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postels and Peter.<note n="Z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Bonifa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius &amp; Greg. Dist.</hi> 89. <hi>Ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oc.</hi>
               </note> Wherfore it is to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cludid, that their must be an order &amp; difference of degrees in the Churche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt powers, superiour and inferiour, without which or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the vniuersite of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole can not consist.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="A" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note>For as amongst the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall creatures aboue in heauen there is set a differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and inequalitie of powers &amp; orders, some be Angels, some Archangels, some Cherubin Seraphines:<note n="B" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dist.</hi> 89. <hi>cap. Singula.</hi>
               </note> So in the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall Hierarchie of the Church militant in the earth


<pb facs="tcp:15376:24"/>
priestes must not be equall w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Bishops. Bishops must not be like in order with Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishops with Patriarches or Primates.<note n="C" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex Citatione Bull. Decr.</hi> 5. <hi>Ser.</hi> 3.</note> Who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them three Archbishops, as a Kynge conteineth three Dukes vnder him. In the whiche nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of patriarches cometh in the state also of <note n="D" place="margin">
                  <hi>De officio Archipres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. in Glosa.</hi>
               </note> Cardinals or Principales, so called bicause as the dore tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth by his hinges, so the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuersall churche ought to be ruled by them. <note n="E" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: left blank" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> The nexte and hiest order aboue these is mine, whiche am Pope, diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng in power and maiorite, and honor reuerentiall from


<pb facs="tcp:15376:25"/>
these and al other degrees of men.<note n="F" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex</hi> 3. <hi>Parte. Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mae maio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris. b. Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nini.</hi>
               </note> For the better declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof, my Canonistes make 3. kindes or power in earth, <hi>Immediata,</hi> whyche is mine immediatly from God. <hi>Deriuata,</hi> which belongeth to to other inferiour prelates fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me. <note n="G" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> 3. <hi>De sacra vnctione. Qui venisset.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ministralis,</hi> belongyng to Emperours and Princes to minister for me, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which cause the anointing of princes and my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>secration doth dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer: for they are anoynted on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the arme or shoulders, &amp; in the head to signify the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of power betwixt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and me.<note n="H" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Nicolaꝰ Dist.</hi> 22. <hi>cap. Oe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</hi>
               </note> This order ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore of Priestes, Bishoppes,


<pb facs="tcp:15376:25"/>
Archbishops, Patriarches &amp; other, as a thyng moste con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, my churche of Rome hath set, &amp; institute through all churches folowing therin not onlye the example of the Angelicall army in Heauen, but also of the Apostels.<note n="I" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Dist.</hi> 80. <hi>cap. In illis.</hi>
               </note> For amongst them also ther was not an vniforme equalite or institution of one degree, <note n="K" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Anacle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tꝰ. Dist.</hi> 22. <hi>c. Sacrosancta.</hi>
               </note> But a diuersitie or distinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of autorite and power, albeit they were all Apostels toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet it was graunted not withstanding to Peter, (the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfes also agreyng to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> same) that he should beare dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and superioritie ouer all the


<pb facs="tcp:15376:26"/>
other apostels.<note n="L" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quasi vero Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trꝰ no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Petra, sed <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> ducatur.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> And therfore had his name giuen him <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas,</hi> that is, head or begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apostelhode.<note n="M" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dist.</hi> 21. <hi>cap. In nouo.</hi>
               </note> wher vpon the order of Priesthod first in the newe Testament began in Peter, to whome it was said, Thou arte Peter, &amp; vpon thee I will builde my church. <note n="N" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note>And I will giue the keys of the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. And thou beyng conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tid confirme thy brethern. <note n="O" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dist.</hi> 21. <hi>cap. Decretis.</hi>
               </note> I haue prayed sor thee, that thy faith shal not fayle. Wherfore seyng such power is geuen to Peter, <note n="P" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Leo. Dist.</hi> 19. <hi>c. Ita Dominus.</hi>
               </note> and to me in Peter, beyng his successor,<note n="Q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Nicolaꝰ In ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Dist.</hi> 22.</note> who is he then in all the world, that


<pb facs="tcp:15376:26"/>
ought not to be subiect to my decrees, which haue such po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in hell, in earth, with the quicke and also the dead,<note n="R" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. in Bulla Vie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae, in scruiiis priuilegioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manding and grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in my Bulle of leade sent to <hi>Vienna,</hi> vnto all suche as died in there peregrinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Rome, that the payne of hell should not touche them: And also that all suche as toke the holy crosse vpon them should euery one at his requeste not only be deliuerid himself, but also deliuer three or iiij. soules whome so would, out of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory. <note n="S" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dist.</hi> 21. <hi>cap. Decretis.</hi>
               </note>Agayn hauing such promise and asserance, that my faith shall not fayle, who


<pb facs="tcp:15376:27"/>
then wil not beleaue my doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine? For did not Christ him selfe firste pray for Peter that his faithe shoulde not fayle. <note n="T" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pope Anacle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tꝰ. Dist.</hi> 22. <hi>c. Sacrosancta.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Scripture well aplied, and like a Clerke.</p>
               </note>Also haue not I a sure pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise of Paul his own mouth, writinge to my Churche by these wordes. God is my wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes whom I serue in my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, in the gospel of his sonne, that without ceasing I make mention of you alwayes in my prayers? <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <note n="V" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pope Dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus.</hi> 25. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>c. Omnia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Item, Pope Gregor. Dist.</hi> 19. <hi>Nulli.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as I condemne all suche worthely, whiche will not obey my decrees, to be dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessid of al their honour with out restitution: <note n="X" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Nicolaꝰ Dist.</hi> 22. <hi>cap. Oe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</hi>
               </note> So all they that beleue not my doctrine,


<pb facs="tcp:15376:27"/>
or stand agaynst the priuilege of the church especially of the Church of Rome, I pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce them heretikes. <note n="Y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note>And as the other before is to be called vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iust, so this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is to be called an heretike. <note n="Z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note>For why he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth against the faith, whiche goeth against hyr, who is the mother of faith.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="A" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dist.</hi> 20. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretales.</hi>
               </note>But here may rise percase a doubt or scruple, that if my faith and knowlege stand so sure by the promise of Christ, and by the continuall prayer of s. Paul: whether is it trew, or is to be graunted, that any other shuld excel me in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege or interpretation of holy


<pb facs="tcp:15376:28"/>
scripture. <note n="B" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note>For looke whose knowlege is grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>did of most reason, his wordes shoulde seame to be of more autorite. <note n="C" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note>Wherunto I aunswere, and graunt, that manye there be and haue ben more abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly indued with fuller grace of the holy gost, and greater ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence of knowlege, And therfore that the tractationes of <hi>Augustine, Hierome</hi> &amp; others ought to be preferrid before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> constitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of diuerse popes: yet I saye in determinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of causes, bicause they haue not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertue &amp; height of that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie, which is giuen to me, therfore in expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures


<pb facs="tcp:15376:28"/>
they are to be prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but in dissising of matters they sta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d inferiour to my au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie. By vertue of whiche autoritie, <note n="D" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dist.</hi> 19. <hi>Si Romanoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note> bothe they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfes be alowed for doctors, and there workes approued, and also all other matters be ruled, through the power of the keyes whiche be giuen to me immediatly of Christ. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I denye not but the same keyes be also co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to other Prelates, as they were to other Apostels, besi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des Peter:<note n="E" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gabriel Biel. li.</hi> 4. <hi>Dist.</hi> 19.</note> yet it is one thing to haue the keyes, an other thing to haue the vse of the keyes. <note n="F" place="margin">
                  <hi>Petrus de Palude.</hi>
               </note> Wherefore here is to


<pb facs="tcp:15376:29"/>
be noted, a distinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of keys, after the mind of my Schole-doctors, one key which is cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led <hi>Clauis ordinis,</hi> hauing auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to bind &amp; lose, but not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the persones whom they binde &amp; lose, &amp; this autoritie they take not immediatly of Christ, but mediatly by me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vicare of Christ. The other keye is called <hi>Clauis iurisdictio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> which I y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vicare of Christ take immediatly of him, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge not onlye autoritie to bind &amp; lose, but also Dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on whom this keye is exercised. By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iurisdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of whiche key, the fulnesse of my power is so greate, that


<pb facs="tcp:15376:29"/>
where as all other are subie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes, <note n="G" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dist.</hi> 96. <hi>cap. Si Imperator.</hi>
               </note> yea and Emperours themselfes oughte to subdue there executions to me. Only I am a subiect to no creature, <note n="H" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gabriel. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Dist.</hi> 19.</note> no not to me self, except if I liste, <hi>In foro paenitentiae,</hi> to my Gostlyfather submitting me selfe as a sinner, but not as Pope, so that my Papall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie euer remayneth vnmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished, Superior to all men, <note n="I" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Nicolaus. Dist.</hi> 19. <hi>cap. Si Romano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Glosa.</hi>
               </note> whome all persones ought to obey, <note n="K" place="margin">
                  <hi>Item.</hi> 24. <hi>q.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Hae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> est.</hi>
               </note> and folowe, <note n="L" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dist.</hi> 40. <hi>cap. Si Papa.</hi>
               </note> no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> must iudge, nor accuse of any crime ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Murder, Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, Symone, or suche like. <note n="M" place="margin">2. <hi>q.</hi> 7. <hi>Nos si. in Glosa.</hi>
               </note> No man depose


<pb facs="tcp:15376:30"/>
but I me selfe. <note n="N" place="margin">
                  <hi>Extrau. De e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. Innotuit.</hi>
               </note> No man can exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate me, yea though I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate with the exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, for no Canon bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth me. Whom no man must ley to. <note n="O" place="margin">
                  <hi>De penite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia. Dist. i. c. Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in Glosa.</hi>
               </note>For he that leyth to me is a churchrobber. <note n="P" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dist.</hi> 19. <hi>cap. Nulli.</hi>
               </note> And who obeyth not me is an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike, and an exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate perso<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note n="Q" place="margin">
                  <hi>August. de Ancho.</hi>
               </note> For like as al Iewes were commandid to obey the hey priest of Leuiticall order, of what state or condition so euer they were: So are all Christen men more and lesse bounde to obeye me Christes Leauetenant in earth concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the obedience of whom or disobedience we haue in


<pb facs="tcp:15376:30"/>
               <hi>Deuter.</hi> 17. <note n="R" place="margin">
                  <hi>Glosa Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naria.</hi>
               </note> Where the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men glose saieth that he who denieth to the hey priest <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientiam,</hi> leyth vnder the sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation, as much as he that denieth God his <hi>Omnipotentiam.</hi> Thus then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth the greatnesse of my Priesthod, <note n="S" place="margin">
                  <hi>Antoninus.</hi>
               </note>begon in <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sedech,</hi> solemnized in <hi>Aaron.</hi> Continued in the Children of <hi>Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi>: perfectionated in Christ: Representid in <hi>Peter</hi>: Exalted in vniuersall iurisdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, And manifestid in <hi>Syluester. &amp;c</hi>? So that throughe this <hi>Praee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miance</hi> of my pristhod, hauing all thinges subiect to me, <note n="T" place="margin">
                  <hi>Antoninus.</hi>
               </note>it maye seame well verified in


<pb facs="tcp:15376:31"/>
me, that was spoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Christ.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Summae Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ris.</hi> 3. <hi>part. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ist.</hi> 22.</note> 
               <hi>Psal.</hi> 8. <hi>Omnia subiecisti sub pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus eius, oues, &amp; boues, &amp; vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sa pecora campi. Volucres caeli &amp; pisces Maris. &amp;c. i.</hi> Thou haste subduyd all things vnder his feete, Sheape and Oxen, and all cattell of the fielde: The birdes of Heauen, and Fish of the sea &amp;c. <note n="V" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note>Where it is to be noted, that by oxen Iewes and Heretikes, by Cattell of the fielde, Paganes, be si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnified. For although as yet they be oute of the vse of my keyes of binding and losing, yet they be not out of the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction of my keyes, but yf they returne, I maye absolue


<pb facs="tcp:15376:31"/>
them.<note n="X" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note> By sheape and all ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, are ment al Christen men both great and lesse, whether thei be Emperours, Princes, Prelates or other. By byrdes of the ayer you maye vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande the Angels and pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states of Heauen, who be all subiecte to me, in that I am greater than the Angels, and that in foure thinges as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore declared, &amp; haue power to binde &amp; lose in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note n="Y" place="margin">23. <hi>q.</hi> 5. <hi>cap. Omnium.</hi>
               </note> and to giue heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fight in my warres. <note n="Z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Antoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i.</hi>
               </note>Lastly by the Fishes of the sea are signified the soules departid in peyne or in purgatory, as <hi>Gregory</hi> by his prayer deliuered the soule


<pb facs="tcp:15376:32"/>
of <hi>Traianus</hi> out of hell, and I haue power to deliuer out of purgatory whome I please. <note n="Z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note>Lastly by the Fisshes of the sea are signified suche as be in purgatory. In asmuche that they stande in neade and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie of other mens helpe, &amp; yet be in their iorney <hi>Viatores, &amp; de foro papae, i.</hi> passingers, &amp; belong to the court of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope, therfore they may be relieued out of the storehouse of the church, by the participatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of indulge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antoninus. August. de Ancho. Thomas. Parte.</hi> 4.</note> And for asmuch as some do obiect, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my pardons ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not extende to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be departed, for that it was said to <hi>Peter</hi>: what so euer thou


<pb facs="tcp:15376:32"/>
shalt lose vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth, &amp; therfor seyng thei are not vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth, they can not be losed of me. Here I aunswere agayne by my Doctors, that this worde <hi>Super terram, i.</hi> vpon the earth may be referred two manner of wayes, first to him that is the loser, so that he whiche shal lose shal be vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth. And so I grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that the pope beyng dead can loose no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Also it may be referrid to him that is losed, so that who so euer is loosed must be vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth or about the earth. And so the soules in Purgatorye maye be losed whiche albeit they are not vpon the earth


<pb facs="tcp:15376:33"/>
yet they are about the earth, at lest they be not in heauen. And bycause oft times one question may rise vpon an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>August. de Ancho.</hi>
               </note> and heades of men now a dayes are curious, a manne hearyng nowe that I can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer out of Purgatory, will aske here a question,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>An papa pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sit totum pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorium ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poliare.</hi>
               </note> whether I be able also to emptie all purgatory at once, or not? To whom my Canonist <hi>August. de Ancho.</hi> doth answer by a triple distinction, <hi>Quantum ad absolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meam iurisdictionem, quantum ad ordinatam executionem, quantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad diuinam acceptationem</hi>:<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Absoluta Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdictio.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> Firste touchyng my absolute iuris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction he saith I am able to


<pb facs="tcp:15376:33"/>
ride out all purgatory toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for as many as be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my iurisdiction, as be all, except only infantes vnbap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tised <hi>In limbo,</hi> And menne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted only <hi>cum baptismo flami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</hi> That is with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Baptisme of spirit. And such as haue no frendes, to do for them that, wherfore pardones be giuen. These only exceptid, for all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther besides, the pope, he say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, hath power to release all purgatory at once, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching his absolute iurisdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Albeit <hi>Thomas Aquine part</hi> .4. denieth the same, for asmuche as Christ him selfe, he sayth, when he came downe did not


<pb facs="tcp:15376:34"/>
vtterly at once release al pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory.<note place="margin">Doctors dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agre in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory.</note> As touching my ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary execution this they hold that I maye if I will,<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>August. De Ancho. Antoninus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>nata ex <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Diuina ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptatio.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> but I ought not to do it. Thirdly as concernyng the diuine ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation, that is, how God wold accept it if I did it, that they say, is vnknown to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to euery creature, yea &amp; to the pope himself.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="A" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Antoninus in Summulis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Augustinus de Ancho. in Decret.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Astesanus Minorita.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note>And to the intent I wold all men to se and vnderstand that I lack not witnesis moo besides these, if I liste bringe them out,<note n="B" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Baptista de Salis. in sua</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Batistiniana.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bonauetura.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> you shall heare the whole queare of my diuine Clergy broughte out with a full voice testifiyng in my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half,


<pb facs="tcp:15376:34"/>
in theyr bokes, tractati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Distinctions, Titles, Gloses, and Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mares,<note n="C" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Campe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>sis. lib.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouersiaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Coclaeus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> as by theyr owne wordes here fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth. The Pope, say they, beyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vicare of Iesu Christ thorow out the whole world,<note n="D" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Durandus, in Speculo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dreido, de ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris &amp; Dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> steade of the liuing God, hath that Dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe, whiche Christ here in earth woulde not haue, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he had <hi>in habitu,</hi> but gaue item to <hi>Peter in Actu</hi>
               <note n="E" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Edoardus Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uellus, Anglꝰ co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra Lutheru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ecchius i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Enchirid.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> that is the vniuersal iurisdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both of spirituall thinges and also of temporall, which doble iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was signified by the two swordes in the Gospell: And also by offering of the


<pb facs="tcp:15376:35"/>
wiseme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note n="F" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Franciscus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fulgo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> who offered not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Incense, but also God, to signify not only the spirituall Dominion,<note n="G" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gabriel Biel. ex Spica.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gaspar.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gratianus in Decr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gerson doctor Illuminatissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mꝰ. De ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astica pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> but also y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral to belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to Christ &amp; to his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care. For as we reade, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth is the Lordes, and the fulnes therof, and as Christ sayth al power is giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to him both in heauen, and earth, so it is to be affirmed, <hi>Inclusiuè,</hi> that the vicare of Christ hath power on things celestiall,<note n="H" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hugo Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalis in postil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hostiensis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Holkot.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hosius.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> terrestial, and infernall. Which he toke immediatly of Christ, al other take mediatly by Peter and the Pope. Wherfore suche as saye that the Pope hath Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion onlye on Spirituall


<pb facs="tcp:15376:35"/>
thinges in the world,<note n="I" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ioannes An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreae.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Innocentius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ioa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. de Turr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Cremata de ecclesia S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> and not of temporall, may be likened to the counsellors of the king of <hi>Syria</hi> .3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 20. Which said, The Godes of the mounta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce be theyr Godes, and therfore they haue ouercome vs,<note n="L" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lanfrancu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra Wiclef.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ius Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus. Anglus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lapus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Laurentius.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> but let vs fighte agaynst them in the lowe medowes, and in valles, where they haue no power, &amp; so we shall preuaile ouer them: So euill counsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors nowe a dayes throughe there pestiferous flattery de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue Kinges and Princes of the earth, sayng:<note n="M" place="margin">
                  <hi>Magister Sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note> Popes &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates be Gods of Montance, that is, of spirituall thinges only, but they be not Godes


<pb facs="tcp:15376:36"/>
of valles, that is, they haue no dominion ouer temporall thinges,<note n="N" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nicolaus.</hi>
               </note> And therefore let vs fight with them in the valles that is, in the power of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall possessions, and so we shall preuaile ouer them.<note n="O" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Okam in Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logo, parte.</hi> 1. <hi>lib.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Oytanus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> But what sayeth the sentence of God to them let vs heare. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause, sayth he, the Syrians say, that the God of Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is there God, and not the God of valles,<note n="P" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Petrus de Palude.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Petrus de Tharam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Petrus de Aliaco.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Panormitanꝰ.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> therfore I will giue all this multitude into your hande, and ye shall knowe that I am the Lorde. What can be more effectually spoken to set forthe the maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie of my iurisdiction whiche


<pb facs="tcp:15376:36"/>
I receaued immediatly of the Lord, of the Lord I saye, and of no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Alexander de A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es.</hi>
               </note> For where as Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine themperour gaue to Siluester, induyng him with this possession and patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,<note n="R" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Raymu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dus in Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma de Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>sibus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Richardus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rabanus su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Math. cap.</hi> 16.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rupertus Tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>itiensis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> that is so to be expoundid and taken not so muche for a Donatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as to be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted for a restitution made of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, which tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nously was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him before. And agayn where as I haue giuen at sondry times to <hi>Ludouicus</hi> and other Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of my temporall landes and possessions, yet that was donne, not so muche for anye recognising of homage to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as for keping peace with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.


<pb facs="tcp:15376:37"/>
For I owe to Emperours no dewe obediance that they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cleame,<note n="S" place="margin">
                  <hi>Scotus Doctor Subtilis.</hi>
               </note> but they owe to me as to theyr superiour. And therefore for a diuersitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt there degree and mine, in theyr consecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they take theyr vnction on the arme, I on the head.<note n="T" place="margin">
                  <hi>Thomas A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin.</hi>
               </note> And as I am su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour to them, so am I su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior to all Lawes, and fre from all constitutions. Which am able of my self, and by my interpretation to preferre e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite beyng not wryten, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the lawe wryten.<note n="V" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vlricus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Waldemꝰ co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessionate, &amp; De Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge all lawes within the chiest of my breste, as is afore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sayd. And what so euer this


<pb facs="tcp:15376:37"/>
my sea shal inacte, approue or disproue all men ought to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue or reproue the same, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out either iudging, disputing, doubting, or retracting. Such is the priuilege giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Christ in behalf of Peter to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of Rome, <note n="X" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan. Dreido. De Dogmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iis, lib.</hi> 4.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what Countre so euer, kingdom or prouince, cheusing to them selfes Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops &amp; ministers, although they agree with al other chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes faithful people in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Iesu, that is, in faith and charitie, beleuing in the same God, and in Christ his trewe sonne, and in the holy gost, hauyng also the same Crede, the same Euangelistes and


<pb facs="tcp:15376:38"/>
scriptures of the Apostels, yet not withsta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding vnlesse their Bishops and Ministers take theyr origine and ordination from this Apostolike seate, they are to be counted not of the Churche. So that succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of fayth only is not suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to make a church, except the Ministers take theyr or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whiche haue there successio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stels. So theyr fayth, supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie, the chayre of Peter, keyes of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, power to bind and loose, all these be insepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the church of Rome, so that it is to bee presumed, that God always prouiding,


<pb facs="tcp:15376:38"/>
and sainct Peter helpyng the bishoprike &amp; diocese of Rome shal neuer defayle from faith. And likewise it is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed &amp; presupposed that the bishop of that Churche is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes good and holy. yea &amp; though he be not alwayes good, or destitute of his owne merites, yet the merites of S. Peter predecessor of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> place be sufficient for him, who hath bequethed and lefte a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall dewrie of merites, with inheritance of innocencye to his posteritie. <note n="Y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hugo. in Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sa. Dist.</hi> 40. <hi>c. Non Nos.</hi>
               </note> yea &amp; though he fall into Homicide or adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, he may sinne, but yet he can not be accused, but rather


<pb facs="tcp:15376:39"/>
excused by the Murders of Sampson, the theftes of the <hi>Haebrues,</hi> the adultery of <hi>Iacob.</hi> 
               <note n="Z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Glos. in Caus.</hi> 11. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <hi>cap. Ab sit.</hi>
               </note> And likewise if any of his clergy should be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing a woman, it muste be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>did and presupposed that he doth it to blesse hyr.</p>
            <p>Furthermore the Pope, say they, hath all the dignities &amp; all power of all Patriarches. In his primacie he is Abell, In gouermente the Arche of Noe, In Patriarchdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, In order Melchisedech, In dignitie Aaron, In auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie Moses, In seat iudiciall Samuel. In zeale Helias, In mekenes Dauid, In power


<pb facs="tcp:15376:39"/>
Peter, In vnction Christ. <hi>(Du bist das Antichrist.)</hi> My power they saye is greater than all the sainctes. For whome I confirme no manne maye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme. I maye fauour &amp; spare whome I please,<note n="A" place="margin">
                  <hi>Glosa. in c.</hi> 11. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <hi>Si inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</hi>
               </note> to take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one, and to giue to an other. And if I be ennemy to anye man, al men ought to eschew that person forthewith, and not to tary and loke whyle I bid them so to do. All y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth is my diocese, and I the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie of al meune, hauing the autoritie of the Kinge of all kinges vpon subiectes. I am all in all &amp; aboue all, <note n="B" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hostiensis in cap. Qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>sl. praeb.</hi>
               </note> so that God him selfe &amp; I the vicare


<pb facs="tcp:15376:40"/>
of God haue both one Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storie, <note n="C" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex summa ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suum fratris Baptistae.</hi>
               </note>and am able to do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moste all that God can doe, <hi>Claue non erra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te.</hi> 
               <note n="D" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ex Citatione Hen. Bulling. De fine seculi. Orat. Prima. Item ex cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione Iacobi Andreae, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersus Hosiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. lib.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Item ex cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione Hierom. Marij. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis</hi> 2. <hi>Diei.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is said of me, that I haue an heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly arbitrement, and therfore am able to chaunge nature of thinges, <hi>Substantialia vnius ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicando alteri.</hi> And of nothing to make thinges to be, and of a sentence that is nothing, to make it stande in effect. In all thinges that I liste, my wyll to stand for reason. For I am able by the lawe, to dispense aboue the lawe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cessione praeb. ca. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posuit.</hi>
               </note> and of wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to make Iustice, in correcting Lawes, &amp; chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. You haue herd hytherto sufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly


<pb facs="tcp:15376:40"/>
out of my Doctors, nowe you shal heare greater things oute of mine owne decrees. <note n="E" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Nicol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Dist.</hi> 96. <hi>c. Satis.</hi>
               </note> Reade there <hi>Dist.</hi> 96. <hi>c. Satis.</hi> 
               <note n="F" place="margin">11. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotibus.</hi>
               </note> also, <hi>Caus</hi> 11. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>ca Sacerdoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</hi> 
               <note n="G" place="margin">12. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>c. Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam.</hi>
               </note>Also, 12. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>cap. Futura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Do not you finde there ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed how Consta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinus the Emperour sitting in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councel of Nice, called vs Prelates of the Churche all Gods. <note n="H" place="margin">
                  <hi>Decretal. De Transl. episc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cap. Quanto.</hi>
               </note>Agayn reade my Canon <hi>Decretal. De transl. episc. cap. Quanto.</hi> Doe you not see theyr manifestlye expressed, howe not manne, but God alone separateth that which the Bisshoppe of Rome doth dissolue &amp; separate. Wherfore


<pb facs="tcp:15376:41"/>
if those thinges that I do be said to be done not of manne, but of God, what canne you make of me but God? Agayn if Prelates of the Churche be called and counted of Consta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus for Gods, I then beyng aboue all Prelates,<note place="margin">Thus ye may se i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ide that s. Paul pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesieth of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> aduersarye settyng in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple as God, &amp; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>styng him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue al that is named God. &amp;c. 2. <hi>Thess.</hi> 2.</note> seame by this reason to bee aboue all Gods. Wherefore no meruell, if it be in my power to chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge time and times, to alter and abrogate Lawes, to dispense with al thinges yea with the precepts of Christ. For where Christ biddeth Peter put vp his sworde, monishyng his disciples not to vse any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward force in reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues,


<pb facs="tcp:15376:41"/>
               <note n="I" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Nicolaꝰ Caus.</hi> 15. <hi>q.</hi> 6. <hi>c. Autoritate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note> do not I pope Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus wryting to the Bishops of Fraunce, exhorte them to drawe oute there materiall swordes in persuyng theyr e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and recouering theyr possessions, setting agaynste the precept of Christ, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet sayng:<note place="margin">The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets minde well expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did.</note> 
               <hi>Dissolue colligatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes impietatis &amp;c?</hi> Item where Christ was present himself at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mariage in <hi>Cana Galileae,</hi>
               <note n="K" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus. Dist.</hi> 34. <hi>cap. Lector.</hi>
               </note> do not I Pope Martinus in my distinctions inhibite the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall clergye to be present at mariage feastes, and also to mary the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>selues? Item where matrimonie by Christ ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be losed but only for horedom


<pb facs="tcp:15376:42"/>
               <note n="L" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Iunior.</hi> 32. <hi>q.</hi> 7. <hi>cap. Quod propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suisti.</hi>
               </note> Do not I Pope <hi>Gregorius Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior,</hi> wrytynge <hi>ad Bonifacium,</hi> permitte the same to be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for impote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie or infirmite of bodye? <note n="M" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius.</hi> 4. <hi>Sext. Decretal. De sente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. cap. Dilecto.</hi>
               </note>Item against the expresse caution of the Gospel doth not <hi>Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tius</hi> 4. permitte <hi>vim vi repellere?</hi> 
               <note n="N" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Alexander.</hi> 3. <hi>De Decimis. cap. Ex parte.</hi>
               </note> Likewise a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the olde testament I do dispense in not gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing tithes.<note n="O" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Nicolaus.</hi> 15. <hi>q.</hi> 6. <hi>Autoritatem.</hi>
               </note> Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> against the newe Testament in swearing, &amp; that in these sixe causes:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <note n="P" place="margin">
                        <hi>De elect. &amp; elect. Potesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. Significasti in Glosa.</hi>
                     </note> Pax, &amp; fama, fides, reuerentia cautio Damni</l>
                  <l>Defectus veri, poscunt sibi magna caueri.</l>
               </q>
Wherin two kindes of othes


<pb facs="tcp:15376:42"/>
is to be noted whereof some be <hi>promissoria,</hi> some be <hi>asserto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria. &amp;c?</hi> 
               <note n="Q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Baptista de Salis. in Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma casuum ex Pauormitano</hi>
               </note>Item in <hi>voues</hi> &amp; that <hi>ex toto voto.</hi> Where as other Prelates can not dispense <hi>ex toto a voto,</hi> but I can deliuer <hi>ex toto a voto,</hi> like God himselfe. <note n="R" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius.</hi> 4. <hi>De e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilem.</hi>
               </note>Item in periury if I absolue my absolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> sta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dith. <note n="S" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ext. De Iure iurando. cap. Venientes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. De Elect. Significasti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in Glosa.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> Where also note that in al swearing, alwayes the autoritie of the superiour is excepted. <note n="T" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Martin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 5. <hi>Extra. cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Regimini V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuersalis ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>siae.</hi>
               </note>More ouer where Christ biddeth to lende without hope of gaine, do not I pope Martinus giue dispensation for the same, not withstanding the councell of Thuron enactid the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, yet with two Bulles I disa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>millid


<pb facs="tcp:15376:43"/>
that decreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. <note n="V" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Vrbanꝰ</hi> 2. <hi>Caus.</hi> 23. <hi>q.</hi> 5. <hi>c. Exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicatorum.</hi>
               </note> What shoulde I speake of Murder makynge it no Murder nor homicide, to s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aye them that be exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate. <note n="X" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Nicolaꝰ Caus.</hi> 15. <hi>q.</hi> 6. <hi>Autoritate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note> Likewise againste the lawe of nature, <note n="Y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note>Item agaynste the Apostle, <note n="Z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Distinct.</hi> 82. <hi>c. Presbyter.</hi>
               </note>also againste the canones of the Apostels I can and do di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>se. For where they in their Cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a priest for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication to be deposed, I tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> autoritie of Siluester alter y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> rygor of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> constitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <note n="A" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Pelagiꝰ. Dist.</hi> 34. <hi>cap. Fraternitatis.</hi>
               </note> Considering the mindes &amp; bodies also of men now to be weaker than thei were then. <note n="B" place="margin">
                  <hi>Baptista de Salis. fol.</hi> 184.</note> Briefly against the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall state of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church I haue


<pb facs="tcp:15376:43"/>
dispensation, <hi>sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quando status ecclesiae non decoloratur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note> And for mariage in the second degree of consanguinite and affinite, <hi>In collateralibus aequali linea,</hi> that is betwixt brethern children: although not <hi>inaequali linea,</hi> so that the vncle may not mary his nice, vnles for an vrge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; weyght cause. As for all such co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tractes betwixt party and party, where that matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie is not yet consummate by carnall copulation, it is but a small matter for me to dispe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>se with all. <hi>In summa,</hi> if ye liste briefly to here the whole nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of al such cases as proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apperteine to my Papall


<pb facs="tcp:15376:44"/>
dispensation, whiche come to the number of one and fiftie pointes, that no manne maye meddle with all, but onlye I my selfe alone, I will receite them firste in Latin, then in English, as they be set forthe in my Canonicall Doctors.</p>
            <div type="cases">
               <head>
                  <hi>Casus Papales</hi> .51. <hi>Apud Fratrem</hi> Astesanum, sine de Ast. Doctore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> solemnem in Summa confessionis. Item apud Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em. De offic. legat. reperti &amp; his versibus comprehensi.</head>
               <l>SI sit catholicus papam non iudicat vllus.</l>
               <l>Erigit, &amp; subdit cathedras, Diuidit, vnit</l>
               <l>Mutat vota crucis,<note place="inline">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i. votu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terrae sanctae.</hi>
                  </note> Restituit, Eximit.<note place="inline">
                     <hi>.i. degradatos .i. ep<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>os et alios.</hi>
                  </note> Ad se</l>
               <l>Maiores, causae referuntur. Legitimatqúe.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15376:44"/>Promouet,<note place="inline">
                     <hi>.i. insufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes.</hi>
                  </note> Appellare vetat, Prohibet profiteri<note place="inline">
                     <hi>.i. intra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes religione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Deponit, transfert, suppletque,<note place="inline">
                     <hi>.i. defectu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> regi vacante regno.</hi>
                  </note> Renunciat illi</l>
               <l>Praesul, &amp; exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptus. Simon, Iurans, Anathema,<note place="inline">
                     <hi>Symonia, Iurame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municatio</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Vel proprium,<note place="inline">
                     <hi>a papa facta</hi>
                  </note> vel legati, vel lex vtriusq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="inline">
                     <hi>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> papae <abbr>q</abbr> legati</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neque participans, Etfi que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> sponte salutat,<note place="inline">
                     <hi>i. soluitur papa</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Canon damnat, Sibi soli quando reseruat,</l>
               <l>Soluitur a papa: nec non que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> regula damnat.<note place="inline">
                     <hi>qui irregularitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> incurrit.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Addas suspensu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Causam,<note place="inline">
                     <hi>sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. addas.</hi>
                  </note> cum fertur ad ipsum.</l>
               <l>Rescriptum,<note place="inline">
                     <hi>i. addas</hi>
                  </note> fidei dubium. Confert bona plura<note place="inline">
                     <hi>i. pluralitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beneficioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Irritat infectu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Legem co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dit generalem.</l>
               <l>Approbat imperiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="inline">
                     <hi>i. imperatorem.</hi>
                  </note> firmat, Deponit, &amp; vngit.</l>
               <l>Consilium generale facit. Sacrat quoq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctos.<note place="inline">
                     <hi>canonizat.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Eus non esse facit.<note place="inline">
                     <hi>de aliquo facit nihil.</hi>
                  </note> Non eus fore.<note place="inline">
                     <hi>de nihilo aliquid.</hi>
                  </note> Pallia semper<note place="inline">
                     <hi>i. palliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15376:45"/>Portat.<note place="inline">
                     <hi>i. palliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                  </note> Concedit, Legi non subiacet vlli.</l>
               <l>Appellatur ad hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c medio sine,<note place="inline">
                     <hi>i. immediatà</hi>
                  </note> Iudiciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Est pro lege suu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Monachu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reuocat renuentem,<note place="inline">
                     <hi>de monacho no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> monachu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> facit.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Maius adulterio soluit generaliter.<note place="inline">
                     <hi>i. incestu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> Arctat</l>
               <l>Et laxat quicquid sponsis nocet.<note place="inline">
                     <hi>i. impedimen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tum matrimonia</hi>
                  </note> Ordinat extra</l>
               <l>Tempora da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do sacru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="inline">
                     <hi>i. extra</hi> 4. <hi>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pora.</hi>
                  </note> Promotu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> promouet ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</l>
               <l>Ordinat atque die qua consecratur &amp; ipse</l>
               <l>Viue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tisq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> locu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cedit,<note place="inline">
                     <hi>i. sacerdotiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> confert nondu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vacans.</hi>
                  </note> Iureq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> priuat.</l>
               <l>Insignit.<note place="inline">
                     <hi>insignia episcopalia co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cedit .i. a decimis eximit .i. praesbyter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> concedit infantes vngere</hi>
                  </note> Laieo sacra donat. Chrisma ministro.</l>
               <l>Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma sede sedet, plenusq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vicarius extat.</l>
               <l>Si sit catholicus papam non iudicat vllus.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="cases">
               <pb facs="tcp:15376:45"/>
               <head>Cases Papale, to the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of one and fiftie, wherin the Pope hath power only to dispense and none els besides. Except by a speciall licence from hym.</head>
               <p>FIrst Determination of doubtes and que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions belonging to fayth.<note place="margin">24. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Translatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a Bishop,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slat. c. Inter.</hi>
                  </note> elect, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed: likewise of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>botes exempted.</p>
               <p>Deposition of Bisshops.<note place="margin">3. <hi>q.</hi> 6. <hi>Quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>The taking of resignation of Bishops.<note place="margin">9. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <hi>Deniq.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Exemption of Bisshops,<note place="margin">16. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
                  </note> not to be vnder Archbishops.</p>
               <p>Restitution of suche as be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posid<note place="margin">2. <hi>q.</hi> 6. <hi>Ideo.</hi>
                  </note>


                  <pb facs="tcp:15376:46"/>
from there order.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutione cap. Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> venissent.</hi>
                  </note>The iudicial definition, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uileges.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">7. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</hi>
                  </note>Chaunging of Bishoprickes, or dimission of Couents &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">16. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>Felix.</hi>
                  </note>New erectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of bishopsseats, or institutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of new religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">16. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>Et Christus.</hi>
                  </note>Subiection or diuision of one bisshoprike vnder an other.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. Ex multa.</hi>
                  </note>Dispensation for vowiug to go to the holy land.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu monachi. c. Cum ad.</hi>
                  </note>Dispensation for the vowe of chastitie, or of religion, or of holy orders.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to. cap. Venientes.</hi>
                  </note>Dispensation against a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful othe, or vowe made.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicio. c. At si clerici.</hi>
                  </note>Dispensation agaynst diuerse erregularities, as in crimes


<pb facs="tcp:15376:46"/>
greatter than adultery, &amp; in suche as be suspendid for si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie.</p>
               <p>Dispensatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in receuing into orders him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had ij. wiues.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamia. c. Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Dispensing w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> such as beyng within orders,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rico non ord. ministra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te.</hi>
                  </note> do y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche is aboue there order, as if a Deacon should saye Masse, beyng not yet Priest.</p>
               <p>To receaue into orders suche as be blemished or maymed in body.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore vitiatis. &amp; Dist.</hi> 55.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Dispensatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with murder,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dist.</hi> 50. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.</hi>
                  </note> or with such, as willing cut of any me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of a mans body.</p>
               <p>Dispensing to giue orders to<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ca. Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> illo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                  </note> such as haue ben vnder the sentence of the greater curse


<pb facs="tcp:15376:47"/>
or excommunication.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
                  </note>Dispensatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with such as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng suspe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>did with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter curse, do minister in any holy order.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De filijs praesbyt. c. Is qui.</hi>
                  </note>Dispe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>sation w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> such as beyng vnlawfullye borne, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue orders, or benefices.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ext. De prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bend. c. De <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ulta.</hi>
                  </note>Dispensatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for pluralites of benefices.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extra. De e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. cap. Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nobis.</hi>
                  </note>Dispensation to make a man Bishop before he be thirty yeare olde.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De aeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te &amp; qualit. Generale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                  </note>Dispensation to gyue orders vnder age.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dist.</hi> 15. <hi>Per totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                  </note>The Pope only hath power to make and call a generall councell.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">9. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <hi>c. Per principale.</hi>
                  </note>The Pope onlye hath power


<pb facs="tcp:15376:47"/>
to depriue an ecclesiasticall person, &amp; giue away his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice beyng not vacant.</p>
               <p>The pope alone is able to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solue him that is excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>De elect. cap. Venerabile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                  </note> by name.</p>
               <p>The pope only is able to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solue him whom his legate doth excommunicate.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio legati. c. Quaere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>The Pope both iudgeth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> causes of them that appele vnto him,<note place="margin">9. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <hi>Alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
                  </note> And were he iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth none may appele from him.</p>
               <p>Onlye he hath autoritie to make Deaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pli ordine. c. Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Distrib.</hi>
                  </note> &amp; prist, whom he made subdeacon, either vpon sondayes, or vpon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feastes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15376:48"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De vsu pallij. cap. Ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>onorem.</hi>
                  </note>Only the pope, and none els, at all times, and in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces weareth the palle.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. c. Dudu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                  </note>The Pope only dispensith w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a manne, eyther beyng not within orders, or beyng vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>worthy, to be made bishop.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. c. Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabilem.</hi>
                  </note>He only either confirmeth, or deposith themperour whan he is chosen.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tractatu. De censuris.</hi>
                  </note>A man beyng exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate, and his absolution referrid to the Pope, none maye ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solue that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but the Pope alone.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. c. Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uit.</hi>
                  </note>The same hath autoritie in anye election, before it bee made, to pronounce it none, whan it is made.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15376:48"/>He doth canonise sanctes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gione et vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ct. cap.</hi> 1.</note> and none els but he.</p>
               <p>Dispensation to haue manye dignities or personages in one Churche and without charge and cure of soule,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. cap. De multa.</hi>
                  </note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth onlye to the Pope.</p>
               <p>To make that effectual whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is of no effecte,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. Qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i. sint leg. cap. Tanta.</hi>
                  </note> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarywise, belongeth only to the Pope.</p>
               <p>To plucke a Monke oute of his cloister both against his owne will &amp; the Abbates,<note place="margin">9. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <hi>cap. Vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timo.</hi>
                  </note> perteyneth only to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope.</p>
               <p>His sentence maketh a lawe.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. et re Iudic. c. In causis.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>The same daye in which the pope is consecrate,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. cap. Quod sicut.</hi>
                  </note> he maye giue orders.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15376:49"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. De re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stit. spo. Lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras.</hi>
                  </note>He dispenseth in degrees of consanguite and affinite.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ext. De prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>script. c. Vlt. &amp; De Iudicio c. Nouit.</hi>
                  </note>He is able to abolishe lawes, <hi>quoad vtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> foru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> that is both ciuile &amp; canon, where daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is of the soule.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Thomas.</hi>
                  </note>It is in his dispe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>satio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to giue generall indulgences to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine places, or persons.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extr. Qui fi. sint legit. c. Per venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilem.</hi>
                  </note>Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to legitimate what per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones so euer he please, as touchyng spiritualties? in al places, as touchyng tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralties, as honors, inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Petrus de Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude. lib.</hi> 4.</note>To erecte newe religions, to approue, or reproue rules, ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, and Ceremonies in the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15376:49"/>He is able to dispense with al the preceptes and statutes of the Church.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Secundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in</hi> 4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Item to dispense and to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge any subiect from the bonde of allegance or othe made to any maner person.<note place="margin">9. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <hi>Per principalem.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>No man maye accuse him of anye crime,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dist.</hi> 40. <hi>Si Papa.</hi>
                  </note> vnlesse only of heresy, and that nether, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he be incorrigible.</p>
               <p>The same also is fre from all lawes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
                  </note> so y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not incurre into any sentence of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, suspension, ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regularitie, or into the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie of any crime, but into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> note of crime he may wel.</p>
               <p>Finally he by his dispensa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Distinct.</hi> 32<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>c. Praeter hoc. ¶. Veru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                  </note>


                  <pb facs="tcp:15376:50"/>
maye graunt, yea to a simple priest, to minister the Sacrament of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmation to infantes, also to gyue lower orders, &amp; to hallowe Churches, and virgins &amp;c.</p>
               <p>These be the cases wherin I only haue power to dispe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>se, and no man els, nether bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop, nor Metropolitane, nor legate, without a speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all licence from me.</p>
               <p>After that I haue now suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently declared my power in earth, in heauen, &amp; in purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, how great it is, &amp; what is the fulnes thereof, in bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, losing, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting, electing, confirming,


<pb facs="tcp:15376:50"/>
deposing, dispensing, doyng, and vndoyng &amp;c.<note place="margin">The riches and possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Pope.</note> I will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate now a litle of my riches likewise and great possessio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, that euery man may se by my wealth and aboundance of al thinges, rentes, tythes, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, my silkes, my purple, Miters, Crownes, Golde, sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, Perles &amp; Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes, Lands, &amp; Lordships, howe God here prospereth &amp; magnifieth his vicare in the earth. For to me pertaineth firste the imperiall citie of Rome, the Palace of Lateren, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdom of Sicile is proper to me, Apulia, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pua be mine. Also y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdome of England and Ireland be


<pb facs="tcp:15376:51"/>
they not or ought to be tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries to me?<note n="A" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dist.</hi> 96. <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>inus.</hi>
                  </note> To these I ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ioyne also, besides other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces and countries bothe in the occident and orient, from the Northe to the Southe, these dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s by name, <note n="B" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ex Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rijs Theodorici Niemi. quem citat Illyricus in catalogo te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. fol.</hi> 228.</note>as <hi>Surrianum, Montembordon, &amp; lunae insula<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icae regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Paruam Mantua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Montense<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lete, Insulam venetiaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Ducatum ferrariae, Canellum, Canioda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Ducatum Histriae, Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiam, Exarchatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Raue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nae, Faue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiam, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senam, Castru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Tiberia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us, Rocca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Mediolanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Castru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ceperianum, Castrum Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ianu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Terr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Cornularia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Ducatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Arimini, Conta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Monte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ferretum, Montem Capiniae, seu Olympicum, Castru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exforij, Robin, Eugubin, V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bin, foru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sempronij, Galli, &amp; Senogalli, Ancona<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sam, Ducatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perusij, Vrbeneta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; Tudertu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Castru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Cinianu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Ducatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Spoletanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Theanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Calabria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Ducatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Neapolim, Ducatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti, Salernu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Sorre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti insula<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Cardinia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> insula<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Anciae insula<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Territorium Cutisan, Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium praene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>inum, Terra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Silandis, Terra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>


                     <pb facs="tcp:15376:51"/>
Clusiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Terra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fundan, Terra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vegetan, Terr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Claudiana<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Terra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> camisina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Terram Fabine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sem, Terra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Siram, Terra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> portue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>sem, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> insul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Archis. Terra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ostiensem cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maritimis, Ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem Aquine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>sem, Ciuitatem lamentum, &amp; Sufforariam, Ciuitatem Falisena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Fidenam, Feretrum, Cliterna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Neapolim, Galiopolim,</hi> with diuerse mo <note n="C" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dist.</hi> 96. <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant.</hi>
                  </note>which Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinus the emperour gaue vnto me, not that they were not mine before he did giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <note n="D" place="margin">
                     <hi>Antoni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us in Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iore.</hi> 3. <hi>Parte.</hi>
                  </note> For in that I toke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of him I toke them not as a gifte, as is afore mentioned, but as a restitution. And that I renderyd them agayne to Otho, I did it not for anye dutye to him, but onlye for peace sake. What shoulde I speake here of my dayly reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of my first fruites Anna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,


<pb facs="tcp:15376:52"/>
palles, indulge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, bulles, confessionales, indultes &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scriptes, testaments, dispensa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, priuilegis, elections, prebendes, religious houses and such like whiche come to no small masse of money. In so muche that for one palle to the Archebishoppe of <hi>Mentz,</hi> whiche was wont to be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ten thousande <note n="E" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ex libr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicae.</hi>
                  </note>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orence, nowe it is groune to xxvij. thousand florence, whiche I receiued of Iacobus the arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop not long before Basell councell. Besides the fruites of other bishoprickes in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,<note place="margin">Aboue fiftie bishoprikes in Germany</note> comming to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of fiftie, whereby what


<pb facs="tcp:15376:52"/>
va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mith to my coffers,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>AEneas Sylui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</hi>
                  </note> it maye partly be coniectured. But what should I speake of Germany, <note n="F" place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sext. Decret. De penis. cap. Felicis in Glosa.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, De priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legijs. c. Auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Glosa.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whole worlde is my diocese, as my Canonistes do say, and all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to beleue, <note n="G" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pope Bonifa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius.</hi> 8. <hi>Extr. De Maio. &amp; obed. c. Vnam sanctam.</hi>
                  </note> excepte they will imagine (as the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niches do) ij. begi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nings which is false &amp; hereticall. For Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses saith: In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning god made Heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and Earth, &amp; not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginnings.<note n="H" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible: left blank" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Wherefore as I begon, so I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, declari<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, &amp; pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, to sta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpon necessitie of saluation, for euery humane creature to be subiect to me.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="I" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Datum laterani.</hi> 14. <hi>Dece<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b. An. pont. nostri</hi> 8.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
