<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lucius Annæus Seneca, the philosopher, his booke of the shortnesse of life translated into an English poem.</title>
            <title>De brevitate vitae. English</title>
            <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus, ca. 4 B.C.-65 A.D.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-12">2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11901</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22215.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3838</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33151062</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33151062</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28897</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A11901)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28897)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1883:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Lucius Annæus Seneca, the philosopher, his booke of the shortnesse of life translated into an English poem.</title>
                  <title>De brevitate vitae. English</title>
                  <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus, ca. 4 B.C.-65 A.D.</author>
                  <author>Freeman, Ralph, Sir, fl. 1610-1655.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Daniel Frere, at the red Bull in little Britaine,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1636.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation attributed to Sir Ralph Freeman--Cf. Wing and STC (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Life --  Poetry.</term>
               <term>Longevity --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-01</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:28897:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28897:1"/>
            <p>LUCIUS, ANNAEUS,
SENECA
THE
PHILOSOPHER: <hi>HIS BOOKE OF THE
Shortnesse of LIFE.</hi> Translated into an ENGLISH
<hi>Poem.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Multum ille ad bonam mentem profecit, cuj
<hi>Seneca</hi> placere caepit. </p>
               <bibl>Lipsius.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at <hi>London</hi> for <hi>Daniel Frere,</hi>
at the red Bull in little Britaine.
1636.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:28897:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28897:2"/>
            <head>TO THE LEARNED AND
Iudicious, Sir Henry Wotton.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Approbation of some wandring Papers,
brought casually to your sight, and whisper'd to
be mine, inuites me to owne this, and send it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad
secur'd by the Safe Conduct of Your Iudgment: I ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
to transforme a <hi>Stoick</hi> into one of the <hi>Muses,</hi> to reduce
to Harmony a rigid peice of <hi>Philosophy;</hi> and because an
Imperiall Envy, and therefore the highest, (that which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd
the suppression of <hi>Homer, Virgil,</hi> and <hi>Livie,)</hi>
censur'd the Authors Workes, to be but <hi>Arena sine calce,</hi>
I have without any violence knit up <hi>His short Booke of
the Shortnes of Life,</hi> into a naturall <hi>Poem;</hi> which
may bee thus farre usefull, that the Readers memory may
retaine his Acute and Redundant witt with more facillity:
I make the addresse to you, thereby to prefixe a President,
that wisely spins out this narrow Thread of Life in the way
prescrib'd; which Remarkeable Example (that being all
the Addition I make) must needs contribute no small vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour
to the Precepts of <hi>Seneca.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:28897:3"/>
            <head>In Senecae de brevitate vitae Librum Elegan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tissime
Translatum.</head>
            <l>OBstruitur tanto mortalis vita dolore,</l>
            <l>Taedeat ut longae semita ducta viae.</l>
            <l>Tam suavis <hi>Senecae</hi> stilus, et Translatio libri</l>
            <l>Vt placeat multas ferre relecta vices</l>
            <l>Esse brevem cuperem misero sub tempore vitam</l>
            <l>Sed longum vitae de brevitate librum.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. A.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <head>Metaphrasti Dignissimo.</head>
            <l>TO Translate <hi>Seneca,</hi> and to obserue</l>
            <l>His Brevity, and from his sence not swerue,</l>
            <l>Require's a Learned Iudgement ev'n in Prose;</l>
            <l>But him in Verse to render, and yet lose</l>
            <l>Neither his Quicknes, nor his Eloquence,</l>
            <l>Shew's both great Skill and our Tongu's Excellence;</l>
            <l>Thus by this happy Version may we see,</l>
            <l>That the Acutest Prose is <hi>Poetry,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And may beleeve that <hi>Seneca'</hi> as in name</l>
            <l>Both <hi>Poet</hi> and <hi>Philosopher's</hi> the same.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:28897:3"/>
            <head>L. A. SENECA OF THE
Shortnes of Life.</head>
            <lg>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cha. </seg>1</label>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost men <hi>(Paulinus)</hi> make it Natures crime,</l>
               <l>That we are borne to a small part of time,</l>
               <l>Which doth so speedily, so swiftly run,</l>
               <l>That life with most is in the entrance done;</l>
               <l>Nor doe the Rude and Ignorant alone</l>
               <l>Vnder this common conceiv'd evill groane;</l>
               <l>But it hath drawne (out of an inward sence)</l>
               <l>Complaints from men of greatest Eminence;</l>
               <l>Hence did the chiefe Physitian exclaime,</l>
               <l>That Art is long, Life short to learne the same;</l>
               <l>And <hi>Aristotl'</hi> expostulate with Nature</l>
               <l>(More then a Wiseman ought) to the brute creature</l>
               <l>As most indulgent, since some kind appeares</l>
               <l>To live five hundred, some a thousand yeares,</l>
               <l>Whilst man to High and Noble things design'd</l>
               <l>Is to a farre lesse terme of life confin'd.</l>
               <l>The time we have's not short; but much we lose,</l>
               <l>Our life, if of the whole we well dispose,</l>
               <l>Is long enough, and of a large extent</l>
               <l>To bring great things to their accomplishment:</l>
               <l>But when it is not vertuously imploy'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>But with excesse or idlenes destroy'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Death vs at length surprising, life is spent</l>
               <l>Before we have perceived how it went;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:28897:4"/>
Life is not given, but made short; nor poore</l>
               <l>Can we be said, but prodigall of store;</l>
               <l>For as great Riches falling in the power</l>
               <l>Of a lewd Spend-all vanish in an houre,</l>
               <l>And meanes though small, committed to the care</l>
               <l>Of a good Husband, soone increased are;</l>
               <l>So life well us'd is long enough;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cha. </seg>2</label>
               <l>Why then</l>
               <l>Is Nature charg'd to have dealt ill with men?</l>
               <l>Some to infatiat Auarice are bent;</l>
               <l>Others to fruitlesse labours are intent;</l>
               <l>This drenched is with Wine; that, dull'd with Sloth,</l>
               <l>This mans ambiton leaves him to the Wrath</l>
               <l>And will of others; that, in hope of gaine</l>
               <l>Seekes Lands, and Seas his Traficke to maintaine;</l>
               <l>Some take delight in Warre, busy'd about</l>
               <l>Other mens Ruines, while their owne they doubt;</l>
               <l>Some into willing servitude are brought,</l>
               <l>Which an ingrate dependency hath wrought;</l>
               <l>Many doe either earnestly affect</l>
               <l>Other mens fortunes, or their owne neglect;</l>
               <l>Most, unresolv'd whereto themselves t' apply,</l>
               <l>Through vaine and selfe displeasing levity</l>
               <l>Fall still upon new proiects; some againe</l>
               <l>Misliking every course of life, remaine</l>
               <l>Yawning till death; so that, what hath beene said</l>
               <l>And as an Oracle delivered</l>
               <l>By that great Poet, we for truth may give,</l>
               <l>'Ts the least part of Life that wee doe live:</l>
               <l>The rest is onely Time not Life; they're ty'd</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:28897:4"/>
And compassed by vice on every side,</l>
               <l>They cannot raise themselves, nor lift their eyes</l>
               <l>To behold truth, and from their strong Lusts rise;</l>
               <l>They never will find leasure to retire</l>
               <l>Into themselves; or if some good desire</l>
               <l>They chance to have, 'tis like, but at the best</l>
               <l>The Sea, that though Winds cease, is not at rest;</l>
               <l>Their passions will afford them noe repose;</l>
               <l>Nor would I have thee thinke I speake of those</l>
               <l>Notoriously bad; they whom the World</l>
               <l>Calls happy, are into like evils hur'ld;</l>
               <l>How many mens great Riches have beene found</l>
               <l>An heauy weight to presse them to the ground?</l>
               <l>Many to boast their Eloquence so strayne</l>
               <l>Themselues, they dye by Rupture of a Veine?</l>
               <l>How many have we seene grow pale and wan</l>
               <l>With their continuall pleasures? many a man</l>
               <l>Compass'd with troopes of Suiters, is thereby</l>
               <l>Deprived quite of his owne liberty;</l>
               <l>Nay run through all degrees; one goes to law,</l>
               <l>Another Pleades the cause; this stands in awe</l>
               <l>Of Power which threatens death, that him defends</l>
               <l>An other will be Iudge, and make them friends;</l>
               <l>But none doth to himselfe himselfe redeeme;</l>
               <l>We mutually are wasted; those that seeme</l>
               <l>Of greatest note, doe with a fond respect</l>
               <l>Court one another, and themselves neglect;</l>
               <l>It is a folly therefore beyond Sence,</l>
               <l>When great men will not give us Audience</l>
               <l>To count them proud; how dare we call it pride</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:28897:5"/>
When we the same have to our selves deny'd</l>
               <l>Yet they how great, how proud so ere, have bin</l>
               <l>Sometimes so courteous as to call thee in,</l>
               <l>And heare thee speake; but thou couldst nere afford</l>
               <l>Thy selfe the leasure of a looke or word<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cha. </seg>3</label>
               <l>THou shouldst not then here in another blame,</l>
               <l>Because when thou thy selfe do'st doe the same</l>
               <l>Thou wouldst not be with others, but we see</l>
               <l>Plainely, thou canst not with thine owne selfe be;</l>
               <l>Not all the wits that are, should they conspire,</l>
               <l>This humane blindnes could enough admire;</l>
               <l>They will have none to meddle with their Farmes,</l>
               <l>And if their bounds be question'd are in Armes;</l>
               <l>But yet will suffer others to incroach</l>
               <l>Vpon their lives, and to their great reproach,</l>
               <l>They will not sticke officiously to call</l>
               <l>Such as will at the length be Lords of all;</l>
               <l>To share his money no man can abide;</l>
               <l>Their lives twixt many all men will devide;</l>
               <l>In keeping their Estate strict care they use;</l>
               <l>But, come t' expence of time, th'are most profuse;</l>
               <l>Of what alone (though in it selfe a vice)</l>
               <l>Is an especiall vertue, Avarice;</l>
               <l>With some old man let's thus expostulate;</l>
               <l>Thou hast, we see, run through lifes u<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>most date,</l>
               <l>Attain'd perhaps, an hundred yeares or more,</l>
               <l>But tell us now; how much from that great store</l>
               <l>Thy Creditor hath got, thy Mistris, Friend,</l>
               <l>Thy Clients, or the Iarre (that hath no end)</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:28897:5"/>
Betweene thy wife and thee? how much is spent</l>
               <l>In chastising thy Slaves? in Complement,</l>
               <l>And Visits through the towne? adde here the cure</l>
               <l>Of maladies, thou didst thy selfe procure,</l>
               <l>Time lost in doing nothing; and behold</l>
               <l>Thou hast farre fewer yeares then thou hast told:</l>
               <l>Consider well what day hath beene imploy'd</l>
               <l>As thou determin'st, how thou hast enioy'd</l>
               <l>Thy selfe, or hast beene constant to thy ends,</l>
               <l>Kept thy mind right, what good thine age pretends</l>
               <l>T'have ever done, how many have bereav'd</l>
               <l>Thee of thy life when thou hast not perceiv'd,</l>
               <l>When foolish ioy, vaine hope, greedy desire,</l>
               <l>And flattering company their shares require,</l>
               <l>But a small part will to thy selfe belong,</l>
               <l>And then thou must confesse thou dyest yong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cha. </seg>4</label>
               <l>BVt what's the cause? we live, as if for ever</l>
               <l>We were to live, minding our frailties never?</l>
               <l>We husband not our time, but let it fly</l>
               <l>As if we had a Store-house to supply,</l>
               <l>When as perhaps, that day set to be past</l>
               <l>Vpon that thing, or man, will be our last;</l>
               <l>As Mortall, all things sordidly we feare,</l>
               <l>And as Immortall, our Ambitions reare:</l>
               <l>At fifty Yeares some say they will retire,</l>
               <l>And at threescore beleeve they shall desire</l>
               <l>To quit their offices: but who can give</l>
               <l>Assurance, that we shall to that time live</l>
               <l>T'effect our purpose? what vain thought us driues</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:28897:6"/>
To give our selves the Reliques of our lives;</l>
               <l>And that time onely unto goodnesse lend,</l>
               <l>That otherwise we know not how to spend?</l>
               <l>That man hath certainly too late begun</l>
               <l>To live, that onely lives when life is done;</l>
               <l>What madnesse is it to defer our rest.</l>
               <l>Till fifty 'or threescore yeares? and thinke it best</l>
               <l>Then to begin our life, when onely some,</l>
               <l>And perhaps few, will unto that age come?</l>
               <l>The greatest Princes oft have words let fall</l>
               <l>Wherein they wish, commend, prefer 'bove all</l>
               <l>A quiet life; and (might it safely bee)</l>
               <l>Would be content to quit their dignity</l>
               <l>For though no outward danger should assaile,</l>
               <l>Yet fortune will against her selfe prevaile.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Chap. </seg>
               </label>
               <l>DIvine <hi>Augustus</hi> (t'whom the <hi>Gods</hi> gave more</l>
               <l>Then any mortall man) would oft deplore</l>
               <l>The misery that waites upon a Crowne,</l>
               <l>And still desire to lay the burthen downe,</l>
               <l>His chiefe discourse to this did ever tend,</l>
               <l>That in a privat life his cares should end;</l>
               <l>This hope, though vaine, did sweete contentment give,</l>
               <l>That at the length he to Himselfe should live:</l>
               <l>In an Epistle to the Senate sent,</l>
               <l>Where he desir'd to let them know, hee ment</l>
               <l>That his so often mentioned retreat,</l>
               <l>Should be with reservation of his state,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Such words I find.</hi> But these things rather ought</l>
               <l>Be done, then said; yet so farre hath the thought.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:28897:6"/>
Of that wisht time prevaild, that though the glad</l>
               <l>Fruition of the thing hee yet not had,</l>
               <l>Yet I, in the discourse I thereof make</l>
               <l>Doe in the meane time no small pleasure take:</l>
               <l>So did he value rest, that when he could</l>
               <l>Not compasse it in deede, in thought he would;</l>
               <l>He that saw all depend upon his will,</l>
               <l>And unto men and Nations, good or ill</l>
               <l>Gave as he list, thought gladly on that day</l>
               <l>Wherein his greatnesse he should put away;</l>
               <l>He found what secret cares, and how much sweat</l>
               <l>Such farre-renowned Honour did beget;</l>
               <l>When first by Citizens, by Collegues next,</l>
               <l>And lastly by his Kindred deepely vext,</l>
               <l>He was compeld (so powerfully withstood)</l>
               <l>By land and Sea, to try it out with blood;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Through</hi> Macedonia, Aegypt, Cicily,</l>
               <l>Through <hi>Asia, Syria,</hi> and the coast thereby</l>
               <l>He led his Armies forth to forraigne warrs</l>
               <l>Weari'd with slaughter in our <hi>Roman</hi> iarres;</l>
               <l>While he the <hi>Alpes</hi> appeas'd, did such reduce</l>
               <l>As in the Empire liv'd in doubtfull truce;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>While beyond</hi> Rhene, Danubius, Euphrates,</l>
               <l>He did his bounds remove, in midst of these</l>
               <l>Great acts, in <hi>Rome</hi> it selfe did <hi>Lepidus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Muraena, Caepio, <hi>and</hi> Egnatius</l>
               <l>Whet all their Swords against him; and before</l>
               <l>This threatning danger he had well past ore,</l>
               <l>His daughter, with so many Nobles bound</l>
               <l>B'Adultry, as by vow, sought to confound</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:28897:7"/>
His yet unbroken age; that once more hee</l>
               <l>Might feare a woman with her Anthony:</l>
               <l>And though these ulcers with the members two,</l>
               <l>He quite cut off, yet others quickly grew;</l>
               <l>So bodies still breake out, that are opprest</l>
               <l>With too much blood; he therefore sought for rest;</l>
               <l>There dwelt his thoughts, to that his hopes aspir'd,</l>
               <l>That could give others all that they desir'd.</l>
               <l>When <hi>Cicero</hi> by the malitious fewde</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Catalines,</hi> and <hi>Clodians</hi> persude,</l>
               <l>By <hi>Pompey</hi> and <hi>Crassus</hi> greiv'd, those foes profest,</l>
               <l>These doubtfull friends, could not find any rest</l>
               <l>In the perplexed State, which he desir'd</l>
               <l>To save from ruine, he at length retir'd;</l>
               <l>No lesse inconstant in adversity</l>
               <l>Then he was active in prosperity;</l>
               <l>His Consulship that he did so commend,</l>
               <l>Though not without a cause, yet without end,</l>
               <l>How did he then detest? what heavinesse</l>
               <l>Writing to <hi>Atticus</hi> did he expresse?</l>
               <l>Old <hi>Pompey</hi> vanquisht, and his Sonne in <hi>Spaine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His broken troopes now gathering up againe,</l>
               <l>Dost thou demand what I doe heere? (quoth hee)</l>
               <l>In <hi>Tusculanum</hi> I remaine halfe free:</l>
               <l>He further addes where he bewailes time past,</l>
               <l>Condemnes the present, and despaires at last</l>
               <l>Of what's to come; did <hi>Cicero</hi> but call</l>
               <l>Himselfe halfe free? a Wise man never shall</l>
               <l>Descend so low; but halfe he cannot be,</l>
               <l>Vnbound, intirely himselfe, hee's wholy free;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:28897:7"/>
For being above fortune, nothing can</l>
               <l>Be ever thought to be above that man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cha. </seg>6</label>
               <l>WHen <hi>Livius Drusus</hi> one of a bold spirit,</l>
               <l>Did strive the <hi>Grachi's</hi> mischiefe, to inherit</l>
               <l>And to obtrud new Lawes, followed by all</l>
               <l>Th' <hi>Italian</hi> rout, scarce weighing what might fall,</l>
               <l>Finding no hope to compasse his designe,</l>
               <l>Which he with safety could not then decline,</l>
               <l>He curs'd his life, who (as he oft would say)</l>
               <l>Was th' onely boy that nere had leave to play;</l>
               <l>He durst presume though yet but one of those,</l>
               <l>That wore the Robe of Youth, to interpose</l>
               <l>For guilty men, and in such earnest sort</l>
               <l>That he did many sentences extort;</l>
               <l>What would not that ambition undergoe?</l>
               <l>Such forward impudence brings certaine woe,</l>
               <l>Private and publique; therefore he too late</l>
               <l>Complain'd of want of play-daies, whom the state</l>
               <l>And Iustice, from a boy pernitious found;</l>
               <l>Some thought he slew himselfe, for of a wound</l>
               <l>Peircing his Groyne he dyde, the means unknown,</l>
               <l>But the act thought unseasonable by none.</l>
               <l>Twere vaine to speake of more, whom vulgar fame</l>
               <l>Hath happy call'd, since selfe-convincing shame</l>
               <l>Their whole life past hath taught them to condem;</l>
               <l>But these complaints nor others chang'd, nor them</l>
               <l>For though such words brak from them, yet the wil</l>
               <l>And the affections have remained still;</l>
               <l>A Life so led, although a thousand yeares,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:28897:8"/>
Seemes to best raightned much and short appeares;</l>
               <l>Such things devoure an Age; though nature run</l>
               <l>Her course, lengthned by Art, yet life's soone done;</l>
               <l>For men observe not, nor give timely stay</l>
               <l>To what's most swift, but let it passe away</l>
               <l>As needlesse, or to be regain'd at pleasure;</l>
               <l>I name those first that can afford no leasure</l>
               <l>To any thing but Wine, and Lust, such time</l>
               <l>Is vildly spent: Others, although they climbe</l>
               <l>With a vaine glorious hope, more brauely' offend,</l>
               <l>The Couetous, the Wrathfull, they that bend</l>
               <l>Their actions to uniust revenge, or warre,</l>
               <l>Have more pretence, Their crimes more manly are,</l>
               <l>The sins of Lust are base; doe thou suruay</l>
               <l>The actions of most men, they spend the day</l>
               <l>Onely in counting money, plotting still</l>
               <l>How to deceive, or fearing the like ill,</l>
               <l>Giving or taking favours, waging law,</l>
               <l>Or making feasts, which custome now doth draw</l>
               <l>As duties on them, betweene good and bad</l>
               <l>They're so turmoyl'd, no breathing can be had;</l>
               <l>And 'tis confest by all; that they that dwell</l>
               <l>In too much businesse, can doe nothing well;</l>
               <l>Nor Eloquence, nor liberall Arts can find</l>
               <l>Any admittance, when the busied mind</l>
               <l>Not able to looke up, with care is cloyd,</l>
               <l>They that continually are so imployd,</l>
               <l>Doe nothing lesse then live, a thing discernd</l>
               <l>By very few, and hardly to bee learnd</l>
               <l>Of other Sciences, professors are</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:28897:8"/>
In every place; yea boyes have prou'd so rare</l>
               <l>They have beene teachers; but we must apply</l>
               <l>Even all our life to live, nay all to dye:</l>
               <l>Which many Wise men quitting both their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures</l>
               <l>Their worldly affairs, their offices, their pleasures,</l>
               <l>And ready to depart hence, have profest</l>
               <l>Not yet to know; how short then are the rest?</l>
               <l>We may (beleeve me) truely thinke a man</l>
               <l>Rais'd above humane errour, when he can</l>
               <l>So keepe his time, that it be shard by none;</l>
               <l>Life then is long, when it is all our owne.</l>
               <l>No part will to the owner uselesse be,</l>
               <l>Nor subiect to an others will; for he</l>
               <l>That knowes to husband time, think's nothing fit</l>
               <l>Nor worthy heere, to be exchang'd for it:</l>
               <l>He therefore hath enough, while they that spend</l>
               <l>It on the people, quickly find an end;</l>
               <l>Nor can we therefore thinke from hence that such</l>
               <l>Know not their losse, how many with too much</l>
               <l>Felicity opprest, amidst the Rout</l>
               <l>Of Suitors, their law cases, or about</l>
               <l>Some other honest misery, have cride</l>
               <l>That time to live was unto them denide?</l>
               <l>Which we may well beleeve, since all that make</l>
               <l>Vse of thy helpe, doe something from thee take;</l>
               <l>How much hath he whom thou defend'st? or hee</l>
               <l>That by thy helpe expects some dignity?</l>
               <l>Or that old Woman, that with clamour fils</l>
               <l>Thine eares, with proving many Husbands wills?</l>
               <l>How much hath hee that sicknesses doth faigne</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:28897:9"/>
And by deluding others hopes makes gaine?</l>
               <l>Or that great friend, by whom th'art onely sure;</l>
               <l>To be regarded as his Furniture?</l>
               <l>Recount (I say) thy daies, and thou shalt find</l>
               <l>Onely the reffuse to thy selfe assign'd:</l>
               <l>This gets the Consulship so much desir'd,</l>
               <l>And then askes when the yeare will be expir'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>That provids publique sports, obtain'd with large</l>
               <l>Expence, and straight growes weary of the charge:</l>
               <l>This Lawyer hurried to every barre</l>
               <l>By troupes of Suiters, with more causes farre</l>
               <l>Then can be heard, growne weary, doth pretend</l>
               <l>That he could wish the Terme were at an end;</l>
               <l>They their owne Lives precipitate, that both</l>
               <l>Desire things future, and the present loath;</l>
               <l>While he that suffers none his time to borrow,</l>
               <l>But makes each present day his life, the morrow,</l>
               <l>Nor feares, nor wishes; for what houre can bring</l>
               <l>New ioy to him, that knowing every thing</l>
               <l>Hath Master'd all his thoughts? let Fortune vse</l>
               <l>Her pleasure, he his constant life persues:</l>
               <l>Something may added be perchance, although</l>
               <l>Nothing diminished, but yet added so</l>
               <l>As Meate to a full stomacke, neither sought,</l>
               <l>Nor yet digested. Let none then be thought</l>
               <l>Old for their wrinckles, or gray-hairs, 'twere wrong</l>
               <l>To say hee liv'd, hee onely hath beene long:</l>
               <l>We cannot truely say that Ship hath saild,</l>
               <l>On which fierce stormes have from the port pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaild,</l>
               <l>And driving too and fro, the voyage crost,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:28897:9"/>
That hath not sayled much, but beene much tost:</l>
               <l>I oft have wondred with my selfe to heare,</l>
               <l>Some demand time, and others not forbeare</l>
               <l>To grant it straight, both looke upon the cause</l>
               <l>Why it is ask'd, the thing from neither drawes</l>
               <l>Regard, but as nothing were sought, or given;</l>
               <l>That which should be in most esteeme, is even</l>
               <l>A trifle made; the errour hence doth spring,</l>
               <l>Because it is an incorporeall thing,</l>
               <l>Not subiect to the sence, tis therefore brought</l>
               <l>Into contempt, or rather nothing thought.</l>
               <l>Our Great men yearly New-yeares Gifts receive,</l>
               <l>For which they give by way of contract leave</l>
               <l>To use their labour, diligence, and paines,</l>
               <l>That which costs onely time, is counted gaines:</l>
               <l>But if such once be sick, and think, Death neare</l>
               <l>How are Physitians hugg'd? or if they feare</l>
               <l>To loose their lives for some notorious crime,</l>
               <l>What bounteous offers are then made for time?</l>
               <l>So various are their thoughts; could men but tell</l>
               <l>The number of their yeares to come, as well</l>
               <l>As what are past, how would they then both make</l>
               <l>Spare of the one, and at the other quake?</l>
               <l>What certaine is (though small) we may devide;</l>
               <l>We must more wary be of what may slide</l>
               <l>So suddainly from us; nor can we suppose</l>
               <l>They know not what a precious thing they loose,</l>
               <l>Because when they their loves would most expresse,</l>
               <l>Part of their yeares to give, they will professe,</l>
               <l>They give, tis true, but so, that what they leave</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:28897:10"/>
Others, to whom they give, doe not receive,</l>
               <l>Nor they themselves take notice of the losse;</l>
               <l>A hidden damage seemes an easie crosse.</l>
               <l>But none thy yeares will render, none restore</l>
               <l>Thee to thy selfe; what order'd was before</l>
               <l>Must be continued in the course begun;</l>
               <l>Time gives no warning, but doth flyly run:</l>
               <l>Nor peoples favour, nor the Princes power</l>
               <l>Can alter, lengthen, or retard one houre;</l>
               <l>Thou busy'd art, life hastneth away,</l>
               <l>Death comes at length, and thou must needs obay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cha. </seg>9</label>
               <l>CAn any that to Wisedome would pretend,</l>
               <l>Be better busy'd, then to learne to mend</l>
               <l>His present life? it is a vaine pretence</l>
               <l>To thinke to order time, with times expence;</l>
               <l>And to defer our purpose, when we know,</l>
               <l>Life's greatest damage from delay doth grow.</l>
               <l>Th'expectance of an other daies event,</l>
               <l>Is nothing but a present detriment;</l>
               <l>For to omit a day, is to dispose</l>
               <l>Of what is fortunes, and our owne to lose:</l>
               <l>Why stay'st thou then? whereon dost thou relye?</l>
               <l>No future thing is sure; live presently.</l>
               <l>Heare how the Poet in a Rapture cries,</l>
               <l>Each best day first from wretched Mortalls flyes.</l>
               <l>Let's not deferre (said he) for if wee stay</l>
               <l>'Tis gone, though we lay hold it runs away;</l>
               <l>We therefore of swift time swift use should make,</l>
               <l>And as it were from a quicke Torrent, take;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:28897:10"/>
And to reprove our thoughts, he doth not say</l>
               <l>The best Yeare soonest flyes, but the best day;</l>
               <l>Why are we then so slow in such a Flight</l>
               <l>Of time, as if we could pretend a Right</l>
               <l>To Moneths, or Yeares, or to the longest date</l>
               <l>That our vast minds could ere desire of fate?</l>
               <l>He speakes but of a day now fleeting; then</l>
               <l>Why marvaile we, if wretched mortall men</l>
               <l>(That is, such as be buside) ever find</l>
               <l>Their best daies soonest gon, whose childish mind</l>
               <l>Age undiscern'd invades; for no man keepes</l>
               <l>Any accompt, by what degrees that creepes:</l>
               <l>As they, whom some tale told, or serious thought</l>
               <l>Deceiving, to their Iournies end are brought,</l>
               <l>Before they thinke them neere; so we that make</l>
               <l>This speedy Iourney' of Life, both while we wake</l>
               <l>And sleepe, by reason of our too much care,</l>
               <l>Doe find it done before we be aware.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cha. </seg>10</label>
               <l>SHould I in parts devide what I propose,</l>
               <l>I easily then might prove the lives of those</l>
               <l>That so much mind the World, to be most short:</l>
               <l>Old <hi>Fabianus</hi> (none of that odde sort</l>
               <l>Of Chaire-philosophers, but Morrall, grave;)</l>
               <l>Was wont to say, that vices must not have</l>
               <l>A slight encounter, the'are (quoth he) our Swords,</l>
               <l>That must repell such Enemies, not words;</l>
               <l>Yet that men may their errours more refraine,</l>
               <l>'Ti better to instruct, then to complaine,</l>
               <l>These three degrees of time make up lifes summe,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:28897:11"/>
What is, what was, and what is yet to come,</l>
               <l>The present transient is, and cannot last,</l>
               <l>The future doubtfull; onely what is past</l>
               <l>Is certaine: fortune heere all right doth lose,</l>
               <l>Not any other can thereof dispose;</l>
               <l>This Worldly men have lost, nor can they find</l>
               <l>Leasure enough, their former deedes to mind;</l>
               <l>Or if they could, 'twere an unpleasant thing,</l>
               <l>To thinke of that which must repentance bring:</l>
               <l>Men care not to looke backe on time ill spent,</l>
               <l>For that remembrance needes must represent</l>
               <l>The shame, when they shall truely ponder it,</l>
               <l>Of what they tooke such pleasure to commit,</l>
               <l>Such onely as by reasons rule direct</l>
               <l>Their actions, can upon time-past reflect;</l>
               <l>He that hath oft ambitiously desir'd,</l>
               <l>Proudly contemn'd, with insolence requir'd</l>
               <l>His captives thraldome; he that hath deceiv'd</l>
               <l>Perfidiously, extortingly bereav'd,</l>
               <l>Or hath profusely spent, can hardly be</l>
               <l>Content to have recourse to memory;</l>
               <l>Whereas that onely is the Sacred time,</l>
               <l>That doth above all power of fortune clime:</l>
               <l>No sicknesse can disturbe, nor feare, nor want,</l>
               <l>The firme fruition of the same supplant:</l>
               <l>The present is but every single day,</l>
               <l>Which passeth in a moment, but we may</l>
               <l>At our owne pleasure all time past revive,</l>
               <l>Whereof the busy'd doe themselves deprive:</l>
               <l>It is the quiet mind, that can revoke</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:28897:11"/>
All parts of life, whereas a heavy yoake</l>
               <l>Imposed is upon the labouring thought,</l>
               <l>That to looke backe it hardly can be brought:</l>
               <l>Such lives are swallow'd up; and as tis vaine</l>
               <l>To seeke to fill what nothing can retaine,</l>
               <l>So is it bootlesse store of time to give</l>
               <l>To them, whose minds are like a leaking sive:</l>
               <l>Time present is so short, that 'tis by some</l>
               <l>Thought nothing, gone ere it be fully come,</l>
               <l>And stoppes no more then the Celestiall speare,</l>
               <l>Which never can its constant course forbeare,</l>
               <l>Yet that to busy'd men is onely left,</l>
               <l>Whereof they at the instant are bereft.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cha. </seg>11</label>
               <l>BVt wouldst thou know how short a time they have?</l>
               <l>Then doe but see how long a time they crave;</l>
               <l>How earnestly doe old men begge t'obtaine,</l>
               <l>Some yeares addition to their small remaine;</l>
               <l>Who feigning themselves younger doe belye</l>
               <l>Their age, and are deceiv'd so willingly,</l>
               <l>As if the fates they also could delude;</l>
               <l>But by some deadly sicknesse be'ng pursu'd,</l>
               <l>How fearefully they draw their latest breath,</l>
               <l>And goe not, but are haled unto death;</l>
               <l>Then they repent, and vow if they recover</l>
               <l>Their health's, their wonted courses to give over;</l>
               <l>Finding their labour to small use imploy'd,</l>
               <l>When what is gotten cannot be enioy'd:</l>
               <l>Whereas a life from worldly troubles free</l>
               <l>Is long enough, and cannot subiect be</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:28897:12"/>
To Fortune, Riot, or an others will,</l>
               <l>Tis all our owne, and turnes to profit still;</l>
               <l>Though it be short, it doth cententment find,</l>
               <l>A Wise man dyes with an assured mind:</l>
               <l>But thou, purhaps wouldst be informed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whom</l>
               <l>I meane by buside men; not such as come</l>
               <l>Early into the Pleading place, and stay</l>
               <l>So late, that barking Dogges drive them away;</l>
               <l>Nor those, whom either their own Clients smother</l>
               <l>Bravely, or else by following an other</l>
               <l>Contemptuously are trod on; nor yet those</l>
               <l>That for base Lucre, their Estates expose</l>
               <l>To sordid out-cries; or whom flattery</l>
               <l>Drawes from their owne, at others gates to lye;</l>
               <l>Some mens repose is busines; in their Beds</l>
               <l>And Houses of retirement, are their Heads</l>
               <l>Still vainely troubled; such cannot be said</l>
               <l>To be at rest, but Idely busied.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cha. </seg>12</label>
               <l>THink'st thou them quiet, that with so much care,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Corinthian</hi> rusty Medalls will compare,</l>
               <l>That from the false they may discerne the true,</l>
               <l>Made pretious by the Folly of some few?</l>
               <l>Or those that goe to see (for loe we groane</l>
               <l>Not under Roman vices now alone)</l>
               <l>Youths with Oil'd-bodies wrastle on the Stage,</l>
               <l>Bred up on purpose of like shape and age?</l>
               <l>Think'st thou Him quiet, that spends halfe the day</l>
               <l>To have the tedious Barbour take away</l>
               <l>What grew the night before, that time can spare</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:28897:12"/>
To call a Councell upon every haire</l>
               <l>How it must lye; what Choller will he vent</l>
               <l>If once the Barber seemes but negligent?</l>
               <l>Who to displease him is as much afeard</l>
               <l>As if he cut the man, and not his beard;</l>
               <l>When by a Per'wigg th'haire's restor'd that's shed,</l>
               <l>Or growing thinne is o're the Fore-head spred;</l>
               <l>Into what passion will he straight be put</l>
               <l>If any part of his Deare maine be cut,</l>
               <l>Or if the same be discompos'd; he frets</l>
               <l>If all be not reduc'd to Annulets;</l>
               <l>May we not well beleeve he takes lesse care</l>
               <l>To have the State disordred, then his haire;</l>
               <l>Who rather to be spruce, then honest strives;</l>
               <l>Such are more curious of their lockes, then lives.</l>
               <l>Are they at rest, who their whole time doe passe</l>
               <l>But onely with a Combe, and Looking-glasse?</l>
               <l>That Songs doe either make, or sing, or heare;</l>
               <l>When as the voice, that to the naturall eare</l>
               <l>In the plaine note sounds best, is taught to run</l>
               <l>Wanton division with writh'd Faces done;</l>
               <l>Who on their Fingers measure verses feet,</l>
               <l>And though with serious, or sad things they meet,</l>
               <l>Yet are they ever warbling; such as these</l>
               <l>In Lazie businesse live, and not in ease:</l>
               <l>Nor have they vacant time, that feasts doe make;</l>
               <l>Because we se what curious paines, they take</l>
               <l>T'adorne with Plate their Cupboards, and devise</l>
               <l>To put their Pages in quaint Liveries;</l>
               <l>How carefull are they least the Cooke neglect</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:28897:13"/>
To send the Bore in dress'd as they expect?</l>
               <l>With what a quicknesse doe the servants fall</l>
               <l>Vnto their busines, when they heare the call?</l>
               <l>How neatly doth the Carver play his part,</l>
               <l>In cutting up the fowle with so much art?</l>
               <l>And after their full Cups spewing about,</l>
               <l>How soone th'unhappy boyes will wipe it out?</l>
               <l>In these respects, they covet to be thought</l>
               <l>Magnificent, and bounteous, and are brought</l>
               <l>In every course of life, to this condition</l>
               <l>They cannot eate or drinke, but with ambition:</l>
               <l>Nor have they quiet lives, that up and downe</l>
               <l>Are born in Chairs, and Litters, through the towne;</l>
               <l>For which they have their certain hours, when they</l>
               <l>That are their Bearers, dare not be away;</l>
               <l>Who must by other men be put in mind</l>
               <l>To Bath, to Swimme, to Sup, and are inclin'd</l>
               <l>To such a negligence, that they scarce know</l>
               <l>Themselves, whither they hungry be, or no;</l>
               <l>One of the nicer sort (if so it be,</l>
               <l>Nicenesse to loose humane society,)</l>
               <l>Lifted by men from forth a Bath all wet</l>
               <l>Into a Chaire, said to them, am I set?</l>
               <l>So strange a question made, can it be guest</l>
               <l>He knowes he lives, or sees, or is at rest?</l>
               <l>'Tis doubtful, which most wretchednes doth show</l>
               <l>To know it not; or to faine not to know;</l>
               <l>Some things we doe forget, and some we faine,</l>
               <l>Some errours we are willing to retaine,</l>
               <l>As Arguments of Greatnes: 'tis for love</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:28897:13"/>
And Abiect persons to know what they doe.</l>
               <l>Goe then, and blame the Players bold abuse<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>More Follies they omit, then they traduce:</l>
               <l>So Copious is vice growne in this our age,</l>
               <l>Witty in ill alone, that we the Stage</l>
               <l>May rather taxe of negligence; can one</l>
               <l>To such a sensuality be growne</l>
               <l>That he by others must be told he fits?</l>
               <l>He is not quiet, that such things forgets;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cha. </seg>13</label>
               <l>WE rather must some other word devise,</l>
               <l>That he is sicke, yea dead will but suffice;</l>
               <l>He is at rest, that doth his rest discerne,</l>
               <l>This halfe-alive, that must from others learne</l>
               <l>His bodies posture, never can be thought</l>
               <l>Of time to make advantage as he ought;</l>
               <l>Twere long to reckon them that spend the day</l>
               <l>At <hi>Chesse,</hi> at <hi>Ball,</hi> or at some other play</l>
               <l>Are roasted in the <hi>Sun;</hi> such men can spare</l>
               <l>No time, whose pleasures tedious businesse are;</l>
               <l>Nor can we doubt, but they laboriously</l>
               <l>Performe iust nothing, who themselves apply</l>
               <l>To fruitlesse Studies, frequent now in <hi>Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Twas a disease that first from <hi>Greece</hi> did come,</l>
               <l>To make it a rare peece of skill, to know</l>
               <l>How many in <hi>Vlisses</hi> Ship did Rowe;</l>
               <l>Th' <hi>Iliads</hi> or the <hi>Odisea,</hi> whether</l>
               <l>Were written first; or from the stile to gather</l>
               <l>If one compos'd them both; with such as these,</l>
               <l>Which if conceal'd, cannot the mind displease,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:28897:14"/>
And utter'd, we thereby are not become</l>
               <l>More learned, but perhaps, more troublesome;</l>
               <l>Behold the <hi>Romans</hi> also have affected</l>
               <l>These needlesse Studies, formerly neglected;</l>
               <l>I knew a Wise man of these times would run</l>
               <l>Through every Act, and by what Captaine done,</l>
               <l>Affirming that <hi>Duillius</hi> first assail'd</l>
               <l>Our foes at Sea, and prosperously preuail'd;</l>
               <l>That <hi>Curius Dentatus</hi> was the first</l>
               <l>Led <hi>Elephants</hi> in Tryumph; these at worst,</l>
               <l>Examples are of ciuill Actions, though</l>
               <l>True Glory nothing to such things doth owe,</l>
               <l>Such knowledge profits little, though there bee</l>
               <l>Therein a kind of specious vanity;</l>
               <l>Let them that will have also leave t'enquire</l>
               <l>Who first possess'd the <hi>Romans</hi> with desire</l>
               <l>To build a Ship; 'twas <hi>Claudius,</hi> therefore he</l>
               <l>Was called <hi>Caudex,</hi> by which word we see</l>
               <l>The Ioyning fast of many Boords is meant,</l>
               <l>Whence publique Tables are by one consent</l>
               <l>Call'd <hi>Codices,</hi> and Boates of <hi>Tyber</hi> fram'd</l>
               <l>For Publique use, are <hi>Caudicariae</hi> nam'd;</l>
               <l>And let this knowledge not be needles thought,</l>
               <l>That first <hi>Valerius Corvinus</hi> brought</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Messana</hi> in Subiection, and thereby</l>
               <l>Added that Surname to his Family;</l>
               <l>Which from <hi>Messana,</hi> by corruption came</l>
               <l>To be <hi>Messalla,</hi> but was still the same;</l>
               <l>And it is not a knowledge of much use,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Sylla</hi> in the Cirque let <hi>Lions</hi> loose?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:28897:14"/>
Whereas before they tyed were together,</l>
               <l>And that King <hi>Boccus</hi> sent Dart-flingers thether</l>
               <l>T'encounter them? yet these we may remit;</l>
               <l>But how can this for any use be fit,</l>
               <l>To know that <hi>Pompey</hi> in the peoples sight</l>
               <l>First brought the Eighteene <hi>Elephants</hi> to fight</l>
               <l>With men condemn'd? a Prince of High esteeme,</l>
               <l>And whom Fame for Humanity might seeme</l>
               <l>To rancke with Auncient Worthies, to devise</l>
               <l>New deaths for men, and ther'with feed his eyes?</l>
               <l>They fight, they goared are, at length they dye,</l>
               <l>And under those Huge Monsters buried lye;</l>
               <l>Surely this ought t'have beene forgotten quite,</l>
               <l>That so no great man after might delight</l>
               <l>To Imitate such an inhumane thing,</l>
               <l>And enuy that should detestation bring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cha. </seg>14</label>
               <l>O, How doth Greatnes blind mens Iudgments! he</l>
               <l>Thought himselfe rais'd above Mortality,</l>
               <l>When he so many wretches did ordaine</l>
               <l>To be by beasts bred in farre Countries slaine,</l>
               <l>Devising a strange Combat betweene Creatures</l>
               <l>Of so vnequall strength, and different natures,</l>
               <l>And in the <hi>Romans</hi> sight shedding such store</l>
               <l>Of Blood; (compell'd soone after to shed more,)</l>
               <l>He was at length perfidiously betray'd</l>
               <l>When his owne Slave rude hands upon him layd,</l>
               <l>And Murdred him, letting him plainly see</l>
               <l>That his proud Sur-name was but vanity.</l>
               <l>But to returne to my discourses and thence</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:28897:15"/>
To shew another fruitlesse diligence,</l>
               <l>The same man of <hi>Metellus</hi> said, when he</l>
               <l>The <hi>Carthaginians</hi> in <hi>Cicily.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Had vanquish'd, that he onely Triumphed</l>
               <l>With Sixscore <hi>Elephants,</hi> as Captives lead;</l>
               <l>That <hi>Sylla</hi> first had leave to amplifie</l>
               <l>The Citty bounds for forraigne Victory,</l>
               <l>A thing allowed Aunciently to none</l>
               <l>But Conquerours in <hi>Italy</hi> alone;</l>
               <l>This is more worth our knowledge, then t'have found</l>
               <l>The Aventine to be without that bound,</l>
               <l>Because the people when they did dissent,</l>
               <l>So mainely from the Senate, thether went;</l>
               <l>Or that the Birds at <hi>Remus-Augury</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Were not observ'd about that place to fly:</l>
               <l>These and a thousand more they doe devise,</l>
               <l>Which either are, or else resemble lyes;</l>
               <l>But let us on their Credits now relie,</l>
               <l>And thinke them true, whose errours are thereby,</l>
               <l>Whose Lust suppress'd? whom may we therefore call</l>
               <l>More Iust, more Valiant, or more Liberall?</l>
               <l>Our <hi>Fabianus</hi> said, he doubted much</l>
               <l>Whether no knowledge better were, or such:</l>
               <l>They onely quiet are that Wisedome mind,</l>
               <l>They onely live; nor doe they thereby find</l>
               <l>Their lives in firme security alone,</l>
               <l>But every age they adde unto their owne:</l>
               <l>What ever hath beene acted heretofore</l>
               <l>Belongs to them; yea, that unvalued store</l>
               <l>Of Sacred Writers, for our use were borne,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:28897:15"/>
Who ready are our present lives t'adorne:</l>
               <l>Thus we by others industry are taught,</l>
               <l>Great and rare things from darke oblivion brought,</l>
               <l>And are not limited, but uncontrould</l>
               <l>The secrets of all ages may behold;</l>
               <l>And if the greatnesse of our minds would climbe</l>
               <l>Above all humane frailty, we have time</l>
               <l>Enough, t'enquire out truths with <hi>Socrates,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To propound questions with <hi>Carneades,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To rest with <hi>Epicurus,</hi> to suppresse</l>
               <l>With <hi>Stoickes</hi> our affections vast excesse,</l>
               <l>And with the <hi>Cynickes</hi> to subdue them so,</l>
               <l>That we with Fate even hand in hand may goe:</l>
               <l>Why doe we then in this short time neglect</l>
               <l>These divine things, that all good men affect?</l>
               <l>Such as have daily offer'd up and downe</l>
               <l>Their meritorious Service in this towne,</l>
               <l>As vast in sensuall pleasures, as extent,</l>
               <l>That both themselves and others doe torment,</l>
               <l>When they have shew'd folly enough, and bin</l>
               <l>At every house that would receive them in;</l>
               <l>How have they beene put of by Luxury?</l>
               <l>Or Sleepe? or great mens Incivillity?</l>
               <l>Who having tortur'd them with long delay,</l>
               <l>Then pretend businesse, and make hast away;</l>
               <l>Or else to shun the place filled with store</l>
               <l>Of Suiters, have slunke forth at the backe Doore,</l>
               <l>As if it were not farre lesse barbarous</l>
               <l>To deny entrance, then t'abuse them thus:</l>
               <l>How have they courted him, whose sleepy head,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:28897:16"/>
Shewes he hath yet scarse well recovered</l>
               <l>His last nights surfit, making others keepe</l>
               <l>Ill houres, to waite on his disorder'd fleepe,</l>
               <l>Who being often told the Suiters name,</l>
               <l>With a proud yawning will repeate the same.</l>
               <l>They are imploy'd to purpose, that doe passe</l>
               <l>Their time with <hi>Zeno</hi> and <hi>Pythagoras;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That often to <hi>Democritus</hi> resort,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Aristotl'</hi> and <hi>Theophrastus</hi> Court,</l>
               <l>With other Authors of good Learning; they</l>
               <l>Bid all men welcome, sending them away</l>
               <l>Not empty, but more pleas'd, more happy farre;</l>
               <l>They, day and night at equall leasure are;</l>
               <l>They'll not compell, but teach us, how to dye;</l>
               <l>They'll not consume our yeares, but will supply</l>
               <l>Ours with their owne; their Friendship is to us</l>
               <l>Not costly, their discourse not dangerous.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cha. </seg>15</label>
               <l>FRom these men we may carry what wee will,</l>
               <l>And having gotten much may get more still;</l>
               <l>What happines, what Reverend Age shall hee</l>
               <l>Obtaine, that is of their societie?</l>
               <l>There hath he those with whom he may advise</l>
               <l>What he should doe when any doubts arise;</l>
               <l>There he the truth without Reproach shall heare,</l>
               <l>And being prais'd, no flattery needes feare:</l>
               <l>By their Example he his life may frame,</l>
               <l>And strive like them to gaine a vertuous name:</l>
               <l>The choyce of our owne Parents did not lie</l>
               <l>In our owne Power, <hi>Chance</hi> gave them; but hereby</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:28897:16"/>
We may be borne, as we our selves shall please;</l>
               <l>The Families of Noble wits are these;</l>
               <l>Choose then in which thou wilt thy Race advance,</l>
               <l>And bee intitled to th' inheritance,</l>
               <l>Not the bare name; to wealth that must not be</l>
               <l>Hoorded up, basely, or malitiously,</l>
               <l>But bountifully spent; men grow not poore</l>
               <l>By such expence, those goods increase the more:</l>
               <l>These shall thy way t'Eternity prepare,</l>
               <l>And fixe thee there, from whence none can, or dare</l>
               <l>Thinke to remove thee; they alone can teach</l>
               <l>Mortality, Immortalitie to reach:</l>
               <l>Great Honours, Monuments, or what beside</l>
               <l>In strength of Law or structure is by pride</l>
               <l>Devis'd, shall soone decay, time doth invade</l>
               <l>That soonest, which the World hath Sacred made:</l>
               <l>Onely true Vertue can resist the rage</l>
               <l>Of present, and of future time, by Age</l>
               <l>That gaines esteeme; things neere them men enuy,</l>
               <l>But on remote looke with Impartiall eye:</l>
               <l>A Wisemans life is therefore large, not bound</l>
               <l>To those strict tearmes that Nature doth propound</l>
               <l>To others, Lawes, which mankind doth deplore;</l>
               <l>All Ages, like a God, doe him adore;</l>
               <l>He in the thought to time past takes content,</l>
               <l>Makes use of what is now, and doth prevent</l>
               <l>That which shall be; thus ioyning all in one</l>
               <l>His constant life can shortned be by none;</l>
               <l>Whereas their time must short and sad appeare,</l>
               <l>Who all these three forget, neglect, or feare;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:28897:17"/>
And when death commeth, they too late begin</l>
               <l>To know how idly they imploy'd have bin.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cha. </seg>16</label>
               <l>NOr is this any Argument at all</l>
               <l>That they live long, because for death they call;</l>
               <l>Their Folly workes on their affections so,</l>
               <l>That they, on what they feare, themselves do throw;</l>
               <l>Thus they seeke death, because they feare the same;</l>
               <l>Nor yet can we from hence a reason frame,</l>
               <l>Because the day seemes sometimes long, for they</l>
               <l>Repine that houres so slowly passe away</l>
               <l>Ere it be Supper time; if they remaine</l>
               <l>But a short while unbusy'd, they complaine,</l>
               <l>And not well knowing how the time to spend,</l>
               <l>Their thoughts to some new Vanity they bend:</l>
               <l>How tedious seemes that time, when they expect</l>
               <l>Some Sword-play, or some Masque that they affect?</l>
               <l>And yet how short is that they like? and short</l>
               <l>Because they like not long, but still resort</l>
               <l>To new delights, so that their daies become</l>
               <l>Not long at all, but rather wearisome;</l>
               <l>Those Nights seeme ever quickly at an end,</l>
               <l>That men in drinking, or with Harlots spend;</l>
               <l>Hence Poets in their Raptutes, to disguise</l>
               <l>And cherish humane errours, did devise</l>
               <l>That <hi>Iupiter,</hi> to lengthen the delight</l>
               <l>He with <hi>Alcmena</hi> tooke, doubled the night:</l>
               <l>But what can this be else, but vice t'enflame,</l>
               <l>To make the Gods the Authors of the same?</l>
               <l>And to Divinity ascribe th'excesse</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:28897:17"/>
Of Mortall mens Licentious wickednes?</l>
               <l>How can those nights seeme short? that cost so deare?</l>
               <l>They lose the day, that wish the night were neare;</l>
               <l>And lose the night with a desire of day;</l>
               <l>So much their feares their pleasures doe dismay;</l>
               <l>The thought of these two slender words, <hi>(How long)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Can turne all mirth into a mournefull song:</l>
               <l>From this affection Kings their Powre lament,</l>
               <l>And in their Greatnes find but small content;</l>
               <l>As being Frighted often with this thought,</l>
               <l>That it must one day to an end be brought.</l>
               <l>When that proud <hi>Persian</hi> King o're vast Fields spred</l>
               <l>His spacious Army not then numbered,</l>
               <l>But in the view admir'd, He there shed teares,</l>
               <l>To thinke that but within on hundred Yeares,</l>
               <l>Not any one thereof should be alive;</l>
               <l>When he that wept, soone after did deprive</l>
               <l>By Sea and Land, by Fight, and Flight all those</l>
               <l>Of Life, which he with greife, did then suppose</l>
               <l>Would dye within one hundred Yeares.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cha. </seg>17</label>
               <l>How then?</l>
               <l>Comes it to passe, that feare possesseth men</l>
               <l>In mid'st of Ioy? because their Ioyes rely</l>
               <l>On nothing, but the selfe same vanity</l>
               <l>That gave them being: what may we then gesse,</l>
               <l>Of that, which to be wretched they confesse,</l>
               <l>When the felicity through which they beare,</l>
               <l>And lift their thoughts so high, is not sincere?</l>
               <l>Great fortunes are accompany'd with care,</l>
               <l>And of all others, least assured are;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:28897:18"/>
They stand in neede of other Happines</l>
               <l>To keepe their Happines, &amp; new successe</l>
               <l>To guard their old; all things that come from Chaunce</l>
               <l>Vnstable are; yea that which doth advance</l>
               <l>It selfe the Highest, soonest falls to Ground;</l>
               <l>Then what true Pleasure can therein be found?</l>
               <l>Needs must their Life both short and wretched be,</l>
               <l>VVhen what they get with so much Misery,</l>
               <l>They keepe with more, and doubtfully maintaine</l>
               <l>VVhat formerly acquired was with Paine;</l>
               <l>In the meane while, but small account is made</l>
               <l>Of unrecouer'd time; new things invade</l>
               <l>The old, hope stirres up hope, desire desire,</l>
               <l>They change the matter, not the end require:</l>
               <l>Doe we our selves cease to be Candidate?</l>
               <l>VVee give our suffrages to others streight;</l>
               <l>If we give over our owne suites, we then</l>
               <l>Are hir'd to follow suites for other men;</l>
               <l>No sooner doe we leave of to accuse,</l>
               <l>But to be Iudges instantly we choose;</l>
               <l>Hath <hi>Marius</hi> left the VVarres? He shall receive</l>
               <l>The Consulship; did <hi>Quintius</hi> strive to leave</l>
               <l>The charge of the Dictatourship? he now</l>
               <l>Shall bee againe call'd to it, from the Plough;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Scipio,</hi> too yong for so great things, shall goe</l>
               <l>Against the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> and o're-throw</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hanniball,</hi> and <hi>Antiochus</hi> subdue;</l>
               <l>The glory of our Consuls, and the true</l>
               <l>Pledge of his Brothers Honour, who unlesse</l>
               <l>Himselfe gaine-say it, shall with <hi>Iove</hi> po<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>esse</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:28897:18"/>
An equall place; and when all this is done</l>
               <l>He the preserver with sedition</l>
               <l>Shall be provok'd, and having quight refus'd</l>
               <l>Such Honour as unto the Gods is us'd,</l>
               <l>He at the length growne old, shall take content</l>
               <l>To goe into a willfull Banishment:</l>
               <l>Thus happy or unhappy causes will</l>
               <l>Be never wanting to breede trouble still;</l>
               <l>Variety of busines hindereth rest,</l>
               <l>A thing desir'd by all, by few possest.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cha. </seg>18</label>
               <l>EXempt thy selfe then from the multitude</l>
               <l>My deare <hi>Paulinus,</hi> having beene pursude</l>
               <l>By stormes, which might more years then thine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire,</l>
               <l>Into a quiet Harbour now retire;</l>
               <l>Thinke but what privat blasts thou hast endur'd,</l>
               <l>What Publique tempests to thy selfe procur'd;</l>
               <l>Thy Vertue hath sufficiently bin try'd</l>
               <l>In Rough Affaires; now let it be apply'd</l>
               <l>To Calmer Waies; the most (at least, the best)</l>
               <l>Part of thy life, hath solely beene possest</l>
               <l>By the Republique; let then some be spent</l>
               <l>To thine owne use; nor is it my intent</l>
               <l>To call thee to a dull and lazie Ease,</l>
               <l>To drowne that vigour in delights that please</l>
               <l>The vulgar People; this gives no repose</l>
               <l>To any; there are greater things, then those</l>
               <l>Thou hast already done, that may by thee</l>
               <l>In thy retirement safely acted be;</l>
               <l>Th'Accompts of all the World thou managest</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:28897:19"/>
With temperance, as an others interest,</l>
               <l>With Fore-sight, thine owne, and with a zeale,</l>
               <l>As things that much concerne the Publique-weale:</l>
               <l>In doing this thy duty, thou gayn'st love,</l>
               <l>Wherein an other hardly could remove</l>
               <l>A generall hatred; it is better though</l>
               <l>To take accompt of thine owne life, then know</l>
               <l>What store of Graine there is; that strength of wit,</l>
               <l>That vigour of thy mind, for great things fit,</l>
               <l>From a charge (Honourable I must confesse,</l>
               <l>But not conducing unto happines:)</l>
               <l>Call home to thee; and think not thou wert borne</l>
               <l>And trayn'd in famous Arts, to lay up Corne;</l>
               <l>Thy Noble Education promis'd then</l>
               <l>Things of a Higher straine; there want not men</l>
               <l>That moulded are for labour, and can be</l>
               <l>Exact in matters of frugality;</l>
               <l>Dull Iades great Burthens fitter are to beare</l>
               <l>Then generous Horses; what a pitty 'twere</l>
               <l>Their stately backes with heavy loades to presse?</l>
               <l>Thinke also with thy selfe, to what excesse</l>
               <l>Of envy th'art expos'd; thou hast to doe</l>
               <l>With hunger, and the common people too:</l>
               <l>No reason workes, no equity prevailes,</l>
               <l>No Prayers move, when hunger them assailes.</l>
               <l>In <hi>Caius Caesars</hi> time, (who now at least</l>
               <l>If Sence of things abide in Soules deceast</l>
               <l>Is grieu'd to find the <hi>Roman</hi> people left</l>
               <l>In safety, and himselfe of life bereft,)</l>
               <l>The Store-howses so empty were of graine</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:28897:19"/>
That scarce a weekes Provision did remaine;</l>
               <l>While he with ioyned Ships large Bridges made,</l>
               <l>And with the forces of the Empire plaide,</l>
               <l>The worst of evills (Famine) was at hand,</l>
               <l>And that which followes, Ruine of the land;</l>
               <l>And this th'example of a Forreigne King,</l>
               <l>Vnfortunately proud and mad, did bring;</l>
               <l>What thoughts had they that then imployed were?</l>
               <l>Did they not Stones, Fire, Sword, and <hi>Caius</hi> feare?</l>
               <l>They all their Art (as they had cause) applide,</l>
               <l>The ill that in their Bowells lurk'd, to hide;</l>
               <l>For some are cur'd, ere they their Sicknes know;</l>
               <l>While others Deaths from such a knowledge grow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cha. </seg>19</label>
               <l>FOr these things then doe thou thy selfe prepare,</l>
               <l>Which more secure, more calme, more Noble are;</l>
               <l>Is it all one (think'st thou) thus to take thought</l>
               <l>That Corne be cleane into the Garner brought,</l>
               <l>And layd up dry, least it grow Musty streight,</l>
               <l>And heat, and that it answer the iust weight?</l>
               <l>Or to search out the highest Misteries,</l>
               <l>To know the Nature of the Deities,</l>
               <l>Their Will, their Forme and their Condition?</l>
               <l>To learne what manner of conclusion</l>
               <l>Waites on our Soules, where Fate will them bestow</l>
               <l>So soone as they forth of our Bodies goe?</l>
               <l>To understand what holds the heavier things</l>
               <l>Firme in the mid'st, and what the lighter brings</l>
               <l>To hang aboue, what highest beares the fire,</l>
               <l>And doth the motions of the Starres inspire,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:28897:20"/>
With all <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hings else, that are by Nature sent</l>
               <l>To strike the wilest with astonishment.</l>
               <l>Wouldst thou from Earth to these things raise thy mind?</l>
               <l>Doo't while thy blood is warme; the Sprightful find</l>
               <l>Easi'st Aecesse, this course of life imparts</l>
               <l>These things unto thee, Love of all good Arts,</l>
               <l>True Vse of uerrue, Courage to defie</l>
               <l>The Powre of Lusts, Skill how to live and dye;</l>
               <l>Together with a firme and constant rest</l>
               <l>Whereof thou never canst be dispossest;</l>
               <l>All busy'd men are wretched; but yet none</l>
               <l>Like them that toyle, not onely in their owne</l>
               <l>Frequent affaires, but sleepe while others sleepe,</l>
               <l>And when they walke the Pace of others keepe,</l>
               <l>That eate with others appetites, and waite</l>
               <l>To be commanded; both to Love and hate</l>
               <l>Of all things the most free; their lives seeme short</l>
               <l>That thus unto anothers Will resort;</l>
               <l>They doe not envy him that gets Renowne</l>
               <l>By Pleading, or that weares the Purple Gowne,</l>
               <l>He ventures his life for it, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'have men call</l>
               <l>But one yeare by his Name, he wasteth all;</l>
               <l>Some, having stretched their ambitions wide,</l>
               <l>Dye yong, and in the midst of all their pride;</l>
               <l>Others, that have great Dignities obtain'd</l>
               <l>By many Indignitie, find they have gain'd</l>
               <l>But Titles to their Tombes; some, their last Age</l>
               <l>Fed with new hopes, like their first youth ingage</l>
               <l>In great and wicked Proiects, when they see</l>
               <l>Nothing but Death in their Infirmity,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:28897:20"/>
               <l>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Cha. </seg>20</label> HE sordid is, that catch'd with rude applause,</l>
               <l>Grown old, dies wrangling in a worthles cause,</l>
               <l>Like him, that weary lesse of toyle, then life,</l>
               <l>Faints in the mid'st of his officious strife;</l>
               <l>Or him, whom dying mid'st his heapes of Gold,</l>
               <l>His long-fed Heire with laughter doth behold:</l>
               <l>I cannot an Example here let passe</l>
               <l>That comes into my mind; <hi>Turanius</hi> was</l>
               <l>An aged man, exactly diligent,</l>
               <l>Who after Ninety yeares, a good part spent</l>
               <l>As Procuratour, willing to desist,</l>
               <l>By <hi>Caius Caesar</hi> was at length dismiss'd;</l>
               <l>But comming Home, he laid him on his Bed,</l>
               <l>Bidding his Servants Mourne as he were dead,</l>
               <l>Who standing round about him, did expresse</l>
               <l>Sorrow for their old Master's Quietnesse,</l>
               <l>Nor would his Family their griefe refraine,</l>
               <l>Till to his labour he were call'd againe:</l>
               <l>Is it such pleasure then to dye in cares?</l>
               <l>So are the thoughts of most bent to affaires,</l>
               <l>Their Bodies sooner then their minds doe faile,</l>
               <l>Thus they their owne infirmities assaile,</l>
               <l>And Age in no respect more Irkesome proves</l>
               <l>Then that from busines it them removes;</l>
               <l>Law doth not force a Souldier to Fight</l>
               <l>At Fifty Yeares, nor after Three-score cite</l>
               <l>A Senatour, men doe more hardly draw</l>
               <l>Leave from themselves to rest, then from the Law;</l>
               <l>In the meane time, while one anothers peace</l>
               <l>They daily interrupt, and never cease</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:28897:21"/>
To hurry, and be hurry'd; while they lye</l>
               <l>Together in a mutuall misery,</l>
               <l>Their life is without Fruit, without delight,</l>
               <l>Or any thing that should the Soule invite:</l>
               <l>No man makes Death his Obiect; to their hope</l>
               <l>All men desire to give the largest scope;</l>
               <l>Yea many contrive busines beyond Death,</l>
               <l>Resolue of stately Monuments, bequeath</l>
               <l>Great Guifts for Funerall Triumphs, and devise</l>
               <l>Workes to be talk'd of, with proud Obsequies;</l>
               <l>But these, like such as dye to soone, should have</l>
               <l>Torches, and Lampes, to light them to their Grave.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:28897:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
