<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe and learned treatise, conteining a true description of the Antichrist, who was foretold by the prophets and apostles And an evident proofe that the same agreeth vnto the Pope. Written in Latin by M. George Sohn Doctor of Diuinitie, and publike professor thereof at Heidelberg, and translated into english.</title>
            <author>Sohn, Georg, 1152?-1589.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1592</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 112 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-10">2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12577</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22891</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114124</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849352</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849352</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14493</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A12577)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14493)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1497:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe and learned treatise, conteining a true description of the Antichrist, who was foretold by the prophets and apostles And an evident proofe that the same agreeth vnto the Pope. Written in Latin by M. George Sohn Doctor of Diuinitie, and publike professor thereof at Heidelberg, and translated into english.</title>
                  <author>Sohn, Georg, 1152?-1589.</author>
                  <author>N. G., fl. 1592.</author>
                  <author>Grimald, Nicholas, 1519-1562, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 8, 8-18, 18-38 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Legate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Cambridge :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1592.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: N.G.</note>
                  <note>N.G. has been misattributed to Nicholas Grimald.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Antichrist --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Papacy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14493:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14493:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE AND LEARNED TREATISE, conteining a true deſcription of the Antichriſt, who was foretold by the Prophets and Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>AND AN EVIDENT PROOFE that the ſame agreeth vnto the <hi>Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WRITTEN IN LATIN BY M. <hi>George Sohn</hi> Doctor of Diuinitie, and publike profeſſor thereof at <hi>Heidelberg,</hi> And tranſlated into engliſh.</p>
            <p>Printed at Cambridge by IOHN LEGATE.</p>
            <p>1592</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:14493:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>coat of arms or blazon</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14493:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE AND VERTVOVS Ladie,</hi> Katharine <hi>Counteſſe of</hi> Huntingdon, his especiall <hi>good Ladie, Grace</hi> and peace in Chriſt <hi>Ieſus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die: whoſoeuer is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graffed into the bodie of Chriſt, and duely conſidereth the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold ſtratagems of the olde ſerpent, and his wicked inſtruments, muſt needs be mooued with mutuall compaſſion, to pitie their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and with all abilitie receiued from God, to preuent their ſubtilties, and to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their malicious proceedings. For if Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than continually doe compaſſe the earth like a roaring lyon, ſeeking to deuoure: if
<pb facs="tcp:14493:3"/>
his children (hauing their fathers nature) doe compaſſe ſea &amp; land, to withdraw from the faith: if both children and father, with all his angels of darkeneſſe, doe transforme them ſelues into Angels of light, to deceiue ifit were poſſible, he very elect: how much more ought wee to regarde our brethren, the children of God, leaſt they become the children of Hell, be deuoured of the great àragon, and be drawne to haue pleaſure in vnrighteouſneſſe, and to worſhip the beaſt. Beholde howe they hazard their goods, their landes, their libertie, and their liues, and being, as it were, inflamed with the fire of hell, they come amongst vs to ſet on fire the Temple and citie of our God, to burne vp the corne, the oliues, and the vineyard of the Lord of hoſts; that is to ſay, more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; theſe Romiſh and Rhemiſh foxes ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour by all means to poyſon our youth with the leauen of popiſh opinions, to confirme the aged in their olde ſuperſtitions, and to withdraw all men as well from the holy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of Chriſt, as from their loyal obedience to their gracious ſoueraigne. Therefore it is full time, that wee ſhould all ſay with the ſpouſe in the Can. Take vs the foxes, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the greateſt, but eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the litle foxes which deſtroy our vines: and further to afford all
<pb facs="tcp:14493:3"/>
that litle helpe we can, for the quenching of theſe Antichriſtian firebrands. This moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the author of this treatiſe, * <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doctor</hi> Sohn <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie at</hi> Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delberg. <hi>The matter of this booke.</hi>
               </note> as diuers other very godly and learned men, to write diuers books for the benefit of the Church: amongst which, this ſeemeth very worthie both his paines of writing, and our deligence in reading thereof. For here is deliuered a aplain and ſound deſcription of Antichriſt, and the ſame ſo mightily applied and ſurely faſtned vpon the Pope, that he muſt either change his nature, which is vnpoſſible, or elſe be enfolded within this concluſion, <hi>The Pope is Antichriſt.</hi> Here he is moſt liuely painted foorth vnto you by his name, quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and progenie: by his doctrine, miracles, and authoritie: by his life, his habitation, and the time of his reuelation, continuance, and vtter deſtruction: here the doctrine of Chriſt is oppoſed to that of Antichriſt, and ſoundly confirmed, not with the weake reede of humane conſtitutions, nor with the ſand of mans traditions and authoritie, but with the ſacred rock of Chriſt, his Apoſtles, Euangeliſts, and Prophets: ſo that though the windes blowe, and the raine fall, and the floods be at, and the gates of hell be opened a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſame, yet it ſhall not fall: for it
<pb facs="tcp:14493:4"/>
is grounded vpon this rocke, <hi>The word of the Lord endureth for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore who ſoeuer pleaſeth to ſee the truth of this great controuerſie, may within fewe houres know (and that out of the word of God) what we ought to iudge concerning the <hi>Pope;</hi> namely that hee is <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> Whereupon it will follow, that as the Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon of Antichriſt is not the Ieruſalem of Chriſt, nor the religion of the beaſt, the worſhip of the Lamb: ſo the Popiſh Church is not <hi>Bethel</hi> but <hi>Beth-auen,</hi> not the Church of Chriſt but the ſynagogue of Satan: and the religion of the <hi>Pope,</hi> is not the religion of Chriſt, but the ſuperſtitious homage of the curſed beaſt. So that it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be but a lewde practiſe of them, who ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to make an vnion of two religions, <note place="margin">No vnion of the two religions.</note> which differ in them ſelues as light and darkeneſſe, who doe altogether forget that heauenly voyce, <hi>Reuel. 18. 4.</hi> Goe out of her my people, that ye be not partakers in her ſinnes, and that ye receiue not of her plagues.</p>
            <p>Nowe that many may be benefited by this learned treatiſe, beeing earneſtly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated and greatly vrged by a good friende of mine: I haue aduentured to expreſſe
<pb facs="tcp:14493:4"/>
my authors meaning, after a plaine manner in our owne language, and to commit the ſame to the bleſſing of God, and the friendly acceptation of the Chriſtian Reader.</p>
            <p>And theſe my firſt fruits of this kinde, I am bolde to dedicate vnto your Honour, moſt Honourable Ladie, beſeeching you to accept of this as of a ſmall, yet a publike te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of my bounden duetie, thankefull remembrance, and heartie affection, which I can not any way expreſſe, but doe entirely beare toward your Honour, and the reſt of your moſt Honourable name and alliance. Whoſe Honourable fauour and goodneſſe, (the fruit of true faith, ſyncere loue, and pure religion) as it hath beene comfortable to many of Gods children, and especially vouchfafed to my Father, my ſelfe, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther friendes, ſo is it a worke which God him ſelfe will regard and reward in mercy, with an immortall crowne of euerlaſting glorie: Who keepe, direct, and bleſſe your Honour, with the right Honourable my good Lorde, and all yours in Chriſt Ieſus, that beeing furniſhed with all spirituall graces and temporarie benefits, needefull for this life and the life to come, you may continually walke in the waies of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb facs="tcp:14493:5"/>
and enioye at the length the incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible ioyes of the kingdome of heauen, the end of your hope, the ſaluation of your ſoules, through Christ Ieſus.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours
moſt humble bounden in the Lord.
N. G.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14493:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE POPE OF Rome is that Antichriſt</hi> OF VVHOME THE <hi>Prophets and Apoſtles</hi> haue Prophecied.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing heretofore diſcourſed concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that is, the perſon, the office, and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> we will now entreate concerning <hi>Antichriſt:</hi> that the glorie of Chriſt maie be ſomewhat the better vnderſtood: becauſe, that (according to the common ſaying) <hi>Things contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie appeare more euidently by their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <hi>Antichriſt</hi> in generall is hee, who <note place="margin">The definitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Antichriſt in generall.</note> doeth any waie oppoſe him ſelfe to the
<pb facs="tcp:14493:6"/>
doctrine of Chriſt, whome in word he profeſſeth to follow: or, who doeth op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne <hi>Chriſt,</hi> vnder the name and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Chriſt: for thus he is deſcribed vnto vs, 1. Ioh. 2. 18. &amp; v. 22. Chap. 4. v. 3. &amp; 2. Ioh. 7.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is of two kindes: for <note place="margin">There be two kinds of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtes.</note> either hee is aduerſarie onelie to one parte of the doctrine of Chriſt, or elſe almoſt to the wholl bodie thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Of the firſt ſorte are all heretikes, which haue beene euer ſince the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles <note place="margin">1</note> times, and yet continue vnto this daie: as were <hi>Cerinthus, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentinus, Marcion, Sabellius, Arius, Neſtorius, Eutiches, Pelagius,</hi> and the reſt: who haue oppoſed themſelues againſt either the perſon, or office of Chriſt: and of this kinde ſpeaketh 1. Ioh. 1. 2, 18.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Of the ſecond kinde is ſome one <note place="margin">2</note> notable and principall aduerſarie of Chriſt, who is called <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> by way of primacie, ſuperioritie, or princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palitie: and vnto whome the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtes, which are of the former ſorte, haue onely (as it were his forerunners) paued and prepared the way 2. Theſ. 2. 7. 1. Ioh. 4. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:14493:6"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
6 And what this <hi>Antichrist</hi> is, and who hee ſhould be, is now chiefelie to be enquired, becauſe at this preſent, the controuerſie betwixt vs and the Papiſts concerneth him: wherein we will eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie declare, what is that which wee defend.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Now let it not ſeeme ſtrange to any, that we doe ſomwhat diſſent from ſome of the ancient fathers in former times. For before ſuch time, as Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt was come into the world, and before hee was reueiled: the interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of that prophecie, which was not then fulfilled, was verie hard. But now ſeeing he is come into the worlde, and remaineth and reigneth in the ſame: in ſo much, that the euent &amp; the experience of the thing it ſelfe, is verie anſwerable to the prophecies of the Prophets and Apoſtles: it is more eaſie to determine thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Firſt therfore, this Antichriſt (who is ſo termed by the way of excellencie, both in the ſcripture and in the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the fathers) is alſo called by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">The names of Antichriſt.</note> names in the holie ſcripture: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, <hi>The man of ſinne, the ſonne of perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14493:7"/>
               <hi>the Adverſarie: Abaddon, Apolly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>the king of Locuſts: the beast: the whore: the dragon: the falſe prophet: the Angell of the deepe,</hi> and ſuch like, as ye maie find in the 2. Theſſalonians and the ſecond chapter: as alſo in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation. Furthermore, there haue beene, as it were, certaine Types or fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures of him in the olde Teſtament: <note place="margin">The types.</note> as namely, <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes,</hi> by whome <hi>Daniel</hi> deſcribeth Antichriſt (whoſe Prophecie extendeth euen to theſe laſt daies) and diuers other, who were the principall and capitall enemies of the auncient Church, and people of God, Zachar. 11. v. 15, 16, 17, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> But thus hee is defined in the Scripure: to witte, that hee is a man, <note place="margin">The deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt in speciall.</note> who vſurpeth a kingdome, who profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the name of Chriſt, but yet oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him ſelfe vnto Chriſt, and to the doctrine of Chriſt, who hath a double authoritie, and both of them ſupreme: the one ſpirituall or eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall, the other ciuill or ſecular, who vaunteth of himſelfe as God, with ſignes, and miracles, (though
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14493:7"/>
altogether falſe and deceitfull) hee is an idolater, an hypocrite, a blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, hee is ambitious, proude, and not vnder lawe, hee is a ſingle man, and vnmarried, but yet a filthie forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator: hee refraineth from certaine meates, but yet aboundeth with all exceſſe, riotte, and deliciouſneſſe: hee is couetous, craftie, vaine, falſe, and cruell: who after the ruine and deuiſion of the fourth I meane the Romane) Monarchie, by little and little ariſing, euen out of the rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh and reliques thereof, is to bee ſituated at Rome, euen in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God (that is, in the Church) by the power and effectuall operation of Sathan: finallie, he is to be reueiled in the laſt times of the worlde, and at the length to be vtterlie aboliſhed at the glorious comming and appearance <note place="margin">The declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the deſcription.</note> of Chriſt Ieſus. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> This is the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or deſcription of that Antichriſt: which wee will briefelie declare by te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of the ſcriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> Wherefore to proue that this Antichriſt is a man, the ſcripture wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth it, 2. Theſ. 2. 3. Dan. 7. 6. where
<pb facs="tcp:14493:8"/>
he is verie expreſſelie called a man. <note place="margin">A man.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> And that he is not ſimplie any one perſon alone, nor any particular or ſingular man, but one ſort or kinde of men, which (as one man, or as a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine order, or companie and ſtate of <note place="margin">A kingdome or ſtate.</note> men) gouerneth and executeth the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the kingdome, it appeareth plainelie in the 2. Theſſ. 2. 3. Dan. 7. 8. Revel. 17. 1. &amp; 18. 3. In which places in truth, this Antichriſt is deſcribed, not as any one perſon or particular man, &amp; (as the Logitians ſpeake) an <hi>Individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um:</hi> but as a corporation of men, and <note place="margin">That is, a proper and ſingular perſon, as Leo, Pius, Iohn, Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</note> as it were, a certaine kingdome: wherein yet, there is alwaie ſome one, who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celleth and ruleth ouer the reſt, who <hi>ſetteth his owne marke vpon them,</hi> Reuel. 13. 17. For firſt Paul mencioneth <hi>an Apostacie,</hi> that is, a generall depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, &amp; reuolting from the faith, which indeed maketh one bodie or corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and one kingdome: this is a matter which can not be effected ſuddenlie, but requireth many yeeres thereunto. Further he proueth verie clearely, that the miſterie of iniquitie, ſhould be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded and conſiſt of manie errours,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14493:8"/>
&amp; grow by little and little. Thirdlie he affirmeth, that the kingdome ſhould continue and endure a long ſpace, to wit, vntill it ſhould be vtterlie aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, by the comming of the Lorde at the end of the world.</p>
            <p>This kingdome is ſignified by the <hi>cruell beaſt and by Babylon,</hi> Reuel. 13. 11. &amp; 18 Chapter, as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> witneſſeth in his fift booke, and the thirteenth chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: and <hi>Ierome</hi> is of the ſame minde; and <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his 20 booke <hi>De Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitate Dei,</hi> and the 19 chapter. <hi>Beda</hi> alſo and diuers others did ſee the ſame. Further it is ſignified by manie waters, Reuel. 17. 1. And <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh of the chiefe and principall citizens, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of his kingdome, ſaying after this maner, <hi>There ſhalbe Locuſts, having vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their heades crownes like to gold.</hi> Reuel. 9. 3, 7. And againe, <hi>there ſhall be three vncleane ſpirites proceeding out of his mouth.</hi> Reuel. 16. 13. Finally, <hi>all both great ond ſmall, rich and poore, bonde and free, ſhall receiue the marke of the beaſt in their right handes, and in their foreheads,</hi> Reuel. 13. 16.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> Further, that which followeth,
<pb facs="tcp:14493:9"/>
that he is aduerſarie to Chriſt, that hee <note place="margin">Aduerſarie to Chriſt.</note> denieth him in deed, whome in worde hee profeſſeth, and that he corrupteth almoſt all the doctrine of Chriſt, or at the leaſt defendeth very ſtoutly the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolting from the doctrine of Chriſt, (for which verie cauſe he is an Arch-here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, or rather, the Patriarke and prince of heretiques) is witneſſed by the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> chap. 7. ver. 25. ſaying, <hi>Hee ſhall speake wordes againſt the moſt High.</hi> And by Saint <hi>Paul</hi> 1. Theſſ. 2. 3. Where he foretelleth, <hi>that there ſhuld be firſt are volting before that the Antichriſt ſhould come:</hi> Adding further, <hi>that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ ſhould ſit in the temple of God:</hi> that is, in the Chriſtian Church. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Antichriſt profeſſe himſelfe a friend and diſciple vnto Chriſt, yet ſhall hee ſet him ſelfe againſt Chriſt, as it were in the name of Chriſt, or vnder colour and pretence of the profeſſion of Chriſtianitie: That is more plainelie thus: Though he doe not openlie op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne and reſiſt the doctrine of Chriſt, but maketh profeſſion thereof, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing both the titles and names: yet ſhall he bring impietie into the roome
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14493:9"/>
of the doctrine of pietie, which hee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembleth, and ſhall drawe men by little and little, out of the Kings high waie of faith, by his ordinations and traditions. And of this iudgement is <hi>Hilarie,</hi> who thus writeth againſt <hi>Auxentius: Hee ſhalbe contrarie vnto Chriſt, vnder the ſhowe of preaching the Goſpell: that our Lord Ieſus Chriſt may then be denied, when men ſuppoſe that he is preached.</hi> And <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> alſo is of the ſame minde, in his 49. <hi>Homilie</hi> vpon <hi>Matthew.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> As for his double authoritie, <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Twofold au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie.</note> and <hi>Temporall,</hi> it appeareth by the two kinds of his names: as, firſt that he is called a <hi>king</hi> by <hi>Daniel,</hi> and is recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned amongſt thoſe ten earthlie kings (of whome conſiſteth the <hi>Romane</hi> Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie) and muſt ſpring vp in the midſt of them, ariſing vp fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a very low degreee, till at length hee ſubdue all the other <hi>kings vnto him ſelfe,</hi> Dan. 7. 24. &amp; cap. 8. 11. &amp; cap. 11. 36. Secondly, this is he whom <hi>Zacharie</hi> calleth the <hi>fooliſh ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard,</hi> cap 11. 15. And whome <hi>Iohn</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <hi>a falſe prophet,</hi> Reuel. 16. 13. &amp;c. 19. 20. &amp; chap. 20. 10.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> Touching his ſignes and <hi>miracles,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Miracles.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:14493:10"/>
the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> is witnes, 2. Theſ. 2. 9. &amp; Chriſt, Mat. 7. 22. &amp; Iohn, Reuel. 13. 13. &amp; 16. 14.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> And that he vaunteth himſelfe as <note place="margin">A vaunt as God.</note> God, it is taught vnto vs, Dan. 7. 8. <hi>The mouth speaking preſumptuous words:</hi> &amp;c. 11. 36. <hi>He ſhal aduance &amp; extoll himſelfe aboue euery God.</hi> &amp; 2. Th. 2. 4. <hi>He ſhal ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt himſelf aboue al that is called God, or is worſhipped.</hi> And to conclude, in Dan. 7. 25. <hi>He ſhall imagin that he is able to cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge both times and lawes, at his owne pleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> For his idolatrie, it is taught by Dan. 11. 36. <hi>He ſhall doe worſhip vnto the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">His Idolatry.</note> 
               <hi>god Maozim,</hi> that is, <hi>the god of defences, &amp;c:</hi> as alſo Reuel. 17. 2. &amp; 18. 3. 9.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> What his hypocriſie is, we learne <note place="margin">Hypocriſie.</note> Da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 7. 8. <hi>His eyes are as the eyes of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> &amp; v. 25. <hi>He ſhal speake words againſt the moſt high:</hi> &amp; Reuel. 13. 11. <hi>He ſhall haue two hornes of a lamb, but ſhal speake like a dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon:</hi> that is, he ſhal couer a woolfe vnder a ſheeps skinne: &amp; 2. Tim. 3. 5. <hi>Hauing a forme or ſhew of godlines, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> Further, his pride &amp; ambition is <note place="margin">Pride.</note> manifeſt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. 20. <hi>He had a mouth ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king preſumptuouſly:</hi> &amp; ch. 8. 25. <hi>He ſhall extoll himſelfe, &amp;c.</hi> 1. Tim. 3. 2. <hi>There ſhal</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:14493:10"/>
               <hi>be men both arrogant and proud:</hi> &amp; 2. Pet. 2. 10. <hi>They ſhall deſpiſe gouernment</hi> (that is, <hi>the ciuill magiſtrate, ordeined by God) bold, and preſumptuous, and ſuch as ſtande in their conceit:</hi> in which manner alſo <hi>Iude</hi> writeth, verſ. 8.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> His blaſphemie: that is to ſay, that <note place="margin">Blaſphemie.</note> he ſhould be a blaſphemer &amp; anatheiſt; we ſee it, Dan. 11. 39. <hi>He ſhall speake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the God of gods:</hi> &amp; Reuel. 13. 6. <hi>He ſhall ſpeake blasphemie againſt God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> His licentiouſnes, to wit, that hee <note place="margin">Licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> ſhould be aboue all, lawleſſe, making &amp; breaking lawes at his pleaſure, is taught vs, 2. Theſ. 2. 4. Dan. 7. 25. <hi>He ſhal ſuppoſe that he is able to change both times &amp; laws:</hi> &amp; chap. 11. 3. <hi>He ſhall doe euen what he list.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> His ſingle life is ſetdown, Dan. 11. 37. <note place="margin">Single life.</note> 
               <hi>He ſhall not regard nor vnderſtand the deſires of women:</hi> where is ment, as <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> ſaith, that vnder pretence of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, he ſhould be an enemie vnto mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage: ſo in the 1. to Tim. 4. 3. <hi>He ſhal for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid to make marriages.</hi> As for his filthie fornication, and licences to vſe and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low outragious and diſſolute luſts, wee finde it, 2. Pet. 2. 10, 14.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14493:11"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/>
24 Concerning his abſtinence from certaine meats, and his faſts, wee haue <note place="margin">Abſtinence.</note> that alſo, 1. Tim. 4. 3. <hi>They ſhall command to abſteine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meats.</hi> Where the meaning is not ſimplie to be vnderſtood of abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence from all kind of meats: (for this would neuer haue beene effected, nor yet could poſſiblie be obſerued) but onely of making ſome choice and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of meates. Yet of his exceſſe and effeminate and daintie life, wee are taught, Reuel. 18. 3, 9. and in 2. Pet. 10. and in the Epiſtle of <hi>Iude</hi> and the 8. verſ.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> Touching his couetouſnes and his riches, we may read Dan. 1. 1. 39. <hi>He ſhall deuide the earth for gaine:</hi> as alſo Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel. 18. 3. 2. <note place="margin">Couetouſnes.</note> Pet. 2. 3. 14.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> Of his craftines, vanitie, lying, and impudencie, is mention made in the 8. of Dan. 25. <hi>Deceit ſhal proſper in his hand,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Craft.</note> 
               <hi>and hee ſhall extoll him ſelfe in his heart:</hi> and in the 23. verſe of the ſame, it is ſaid that <hi>he is of a fierce, impudent, and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe countenance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> His crueltie (which is eſpecially bent againſt the Saints) is taught, Dan. 7. 21. <hi>I ſaw that horne make warre againſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Crueltie.</note> 
               <hi>the Saints:</hi> and in the 25. verſe. <hi>Hee ſhall</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:14493:11"/>
               <hi>grind to powder the Saints of the moſt high:</hi> and chap. 8. 24. &amp; 11. Reuel. 11. 7. &amp;c. and chap. 17. 6. &amp; the 19. 19.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> Concerning his founder &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall author, to wit, that he was to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by little &amp; little, by the craft of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan; <note place="margin">His author.</note> who hath thought of this myſterie, and hath had it in hande, euer ſince the Apoſtles time, we doe learne in the 2. to the Theſſ. 2. where it is ſaid, <hi>Whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming is by the operation and working of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than:</hi> and in the 1. Tim. 41. where the doctrine of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is called <hi>the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of deuils:</hi> and in the 13. of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel. 4. where the <hi>dragon</hi> is called <hi>author</hi> and <hi>cauſe</hi> of the whole ſtate of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> which is conueyed into the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Empire: and in the 18. where Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, that is, the ſeat and kingdome of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> is called <hi>the habitation of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, the houſe of foule spirits, and a cage of euery vncleane and foule bird,</hi> chap. 18. 2. The which the Lord will ſuffer and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſo to be, till his wrath be accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, Dan. 11. 36. <hi>The faithfull be tried, and they which are tried, be made manifeſt,</hi> Dan. 12. 10. &amp; 1. Ioh. 2. 19. and that the contempt of the earth may thus be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed,
<pb facs="tcp:14493:12"/>
according to that of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2. Theſ. 2. 10, 11.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> Now for the time, to wit, that he ſhould then appeare, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Romane <note place="margin">The time of his appeara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</note> Empire ſhould be diſtracted &amp; diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, it is taught, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. 8. 24. &amp; 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 7. For both <hi>Tertul.</hi> &amp; <hi>Ierome,</hi> &amp; others more, doe interpret that place of <hi>Paul</hi> of the diuiſion and ruine of the Romane Empire: as alſo Reuel. 13. 11. 12. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the myſterie of iniquitie began to worke, as yet ſecretly vnder-hand, &amp;, as it were, by vndermining, euen from the daies of the Apoſtles, 2. Theſ. 2. 7. 1. Ioh. 2. 18. yet afterwards <hi>Antichriſt</hi> was to iſſue &amp; break forth with full ſtreame, &amp; euidently to ſhew himſelfe, as it were, proceeding out of the ruines of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Empire, 2. Theſ. 2. 7. And this time <hi>Iohn</hi> ſeemeth to note, Reuel. 13. 18. whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee faith, that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhould come 666 yeeres after, to wit, after the birth of Chriſt: His words are theſe, <hi>Let him that hath wiſdom count the number of the yeres: for it is the number of a man, &amp; it is</hi> 666.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> Concerning the place, that he was <note place="margin">His place.</note> to ſpring out of the ruines of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Monarchie, &amp; ſo ſhould appeare in the <hi>Romane Empire;</hi> it appeareth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by <hi>Daniel</hi> &amp; <hi>Paul,</hi> as we haue touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14493:12"/>
heretofore: as alſo by the 17. of the Reue. 3. where the <hi>purple whore,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth the people, is ſaide, <hi>to ſit vpon the beaſt with ten hornes.</hi> For that beaſt with ten hornes ſignifieth the fourth Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, to wit, that of <hi>Rome,</hi> Dan. 7.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/> As for his <hi>throne</hi> &amp; ſeat, to wit, that <note place="margin">His throne.</note> he ſhal ſit in the city of <hi>Rome:</hi> firſt, <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> witneſſeth the ſame, when as he pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth this ſeat betwixt 2. ſeas, (for <hi>Rome</hi> &amp; <hi>Italy</hi> are ſituated twixt 2. ſeas) <hi>Adri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aticu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> &amp; <hi>Tyrrhenu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly <hi>Iohn,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he maketh mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> as Rev. 14. 8. &amp; 16. 19. &amp; 18. 2. By which places the ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t doctors of the Church (&amp; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>Ierome)</hi> do vnderſtand <hi>Rome,</hi> as alſo by that place, 1. Pet. 5. 13. &amp; further, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> doth cal it the <hi>citie with</hi> 7. <hi>hils,</hi> &amp; the <hi>queen of al,</hi> as it is Rev. 17. 9. 18. For <hi>Rome</hi> was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> called by thoſe names, euen by profane writers. Finally, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he ſaith, Rev. 17. 1. that <hi>the whore ſhal ſit vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many waters</hi> (that is, <hi>aboue much people &amp; many nations,</hi> as him ſelfe in the 15. verſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf) &amp; in <hi>the great city which hath the rule ouer the kings of the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="32"/> Now that he ſhould ſit <hi>in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">He ſits in the Church.</note> 
               <hi>God,</hi> that is, in the Church, it is taught vs, 2. Th. 2. 4. for by this ſitti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g here, is not me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t corporal &amp; bodily placing, but a certain
<pb facs="tcp:14493:13"/>
dominion: and by <hi>temple</hi> is ment, neither that of Ieruſalem (which long ago was ouerthrown &amp; raſed, &amp; which is neuer again to be repaired, according to that prophecie in the 9. of Dan. 27.) nor yet any other externall building, but onely the Church, which is the <hi>temple &amp; houſe of God.</hi> 1. Tim. 3. 15. And therefore herby is ſignified, that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhould pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely vſurp the chiefe juriſdiction &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in the Church of God; yet ſhuld he not profeſſe any open &amp; flat denial of Chriſt, but onely he ſhould bring in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame impietie, vnder the pretence of the doctrine of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="33"/> Further, that he is to continue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til <note place="margin">His conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance.</note> the very laſt end &amp; day of the world, it is taught 7. <hi>Dan.</hi> 26. &amp; 8. 25. &amp; 11. 45. &amp; 12. 1, 2. Rev. 19. 21. &amp; 20. 10. In which places ſo ſoone as the end of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is rehearſed, immediatly followeth me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the laſt reſurrection, and not a word of any other worldly kingdome.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="34"/> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or iſſue, to wit, <note place="margin">The event or his reuelation</note> that he ſhould be reueled &amp; diſcouered in the laſt times of the world, &amp; that his kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is to be battred &amp; thrown down by the preaching of the Goſpell, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14493:13"/>
witneſſeth 2. <hi>Th.</hi> 2. 3. &amp; <hi>Iohn</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the ſame thing, by the ruine &amp; fall of Babylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Reuel. 14. 8. &amp; 16. 19. &amp; 18. 2. And to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude, Iohn prophecied the ſame of him, Reu. 14. where three An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, that is, three Teachers, are appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to reueile Antichriſt, to whome are added other two in the 18 of the Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, as alſo in the 17. verſ. 16. 17. where he ſaieth, <hi>The tenne hornes which thou ſaweſt &amp;c.</hi> that is, manie Princes and Eſtates of the Romane Empire, ſhall reuolt from the whore, and ſhall giue her kingdome vnto the beaſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="35"/> For although at all times, there ſhall alwaies be ſome, who ſhall op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelues to Antichriſt, to his corruptions and idolatrie, and ſpeake againſt the ſame, Reuel. 10. 11. &amp; 11. 3. &amp; 12. 7. Yet here by is inſinuated, that in this laſt time of the worlde Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt was more fullie and clearelie to be reueiled by the great and ſingular goodneſſe of God: by men endued with the ſpirit of <hi>Elias</hi> and <hi>Enoch:</hi> and that the doctrine of Chriſt ſhould be brought to light, and Antichriſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly tormented.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14493:14"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="36"/>
36 Finally, touching his deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">His deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> and ende, that is, that he ſhould bee vtterly aboliſhed by Chriſt himſelfe at the laſt day, at his glorious and royall appearance, (who is now indeede re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiled to be the Antichriſt) and be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed eternallie, is taught vs, 2. Theſſ. 2. 8. and may be gathered out of the 7. chap. of Dan. 26. &amp; 8. 25. &amp; 11. 45. and 12. 1. and out of the Reuelat. chap. 19. 20, 21. &amp; 20. 10. as we alſo ſpake a little before, touching the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the kingdome of Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="37"/> For although the kingdome of Antichriſt ſhalbe ſhaken before the laſt day and comming of Chriſt, and ſhall be pulled downe, as it were, by piecemeale, by reaſon of thereuolting of Prouinces: yet there ſhall alwaie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine a ſtate and forme thereof: but euen this alſo ſhall be vtterly aboliſhed, in the laſt time of the worlde.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="38"/> This is our definition of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and the declaration of the ſame definition out of the old &amp; new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But the Papiſtes define it after a <note place="margin">The Papiſtes deſcription of Antichriſt.</note> farre other manner: to wit, that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt is one ſingular &amp; particular man,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14493:14"/>
who ſhoulde ariſe of the Tribe of <hi>Dan,</hi> and be circumciſed: who (being accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the Iewes for the Meſſias) ſhould reigne and tyrannize at Ieruſalem the ſpace of three yeeres and ſixe moneths, and whome Chriſt ſhould at the length kill in mount Oliuet, whileſt he enten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to aſcend vp into heauen: Which definition of theirs will be more exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in our diſputations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Pope is Antichriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="39"/> HItherto wee haue declared, what Antichriſt is: now wee will ſhewe who he is, and to whome this definition before ſet downe will beſt agree.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="40"/> Therefore wee affirme, that the Pope of Rome is that Antichriſt: &amp; thus <note place="margin">The proofe that the Pope is Antichriſt.</note> we prooue it. For to whomſoeuer the definition of Antichriſt doeth agree, it neceſſarily followeth, that hee is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt: but this definition of Antichriſt hath agreed fitly to the Pope of Rome, euer ſince the death of <hi>Gregorie</hi> the great, and the ſlaughter of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Mauritius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14493:15"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="41"/>
41. For the Pope of Rome (euer ſince the death of <hi>Gregorie</hi> and <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricius)</hi> is the man, who by continuall ſucceſſion and ſet order, hath bene pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The proofe of the aſſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption by view in particular.</hi> 1 <hi>Aman,</hi> 2 <hi>Whoruleth a ſtate.</hi>
               </note> to a certaine bodie or ſtate of men, and hath giuen them his marke: wherein the Monkes and Cleargie ſhauelings, (like vnto the crowned lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtes) haue their ſhauing as crownes vpon their heads, that they might ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thereby, that they are kings and prieſtes, and their routes diſperſed and ſpread in all places of Chriſtendome, and thoſe many waters, vpon which the great whore the mother of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications of the earth, ſeemeth both to ſit and reigne, Reuel. 18.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="42"/> The Pope alſo profeſſeth Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie, <note place="margin">3 <hi>The Popes profeſſion of Chriſtianitie, to which hee is indeede an aduerſarie.</hi>
               </note> ſaying, that he is the follower and the Vicar of Chriſt: as doe alſo his chiefe ſeruants at this day, who giue themſelues a newe name, <hi>Ieſuites:</hi> hee alſo retaineth the Bible, that is, the ſcriptures written by the Prophets and Apoſtles; and the Sacraments alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by Chriſt, and yet hee is an aduerſarie to Chriſt and to his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:14493:15"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="43"/>
43 For though Chriſt alone be the heade of the Catholique or vniuerſall <note place="margin">1 <hi>He challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Chriſt.</hi>
               </note> Church, beeing alwaies preſent to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne the ſame, Epheſ. 1 21, 22. &amp; 4. 15<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; 5, 23. Coloſſ. 1. 8, Though he be alſo the onely ſpouſe of the Church. 2. Cor. 11, 2. Epheſ, 5. 29, Finally, though hee bee alſo the onely prince, the chiefe ſhephearde, and the high prieſt vnto his Church. 1. Pet. 2. 5. and chap. 5. 4. Heb. 6. 20. &amp; chap. 7. 26. &amp; chapt. 9. 11. <hi>Alway liuing to make interceſſion for vs.</hi> Rom. 8. 34. Heb. 7. 25. Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Pope of Rome doeth arrogate this office, and theſe proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties vnto himſelfe, and vaunteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that hee is the chiefe head, high prieſt, and ſacrificer, and the Oecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menicall and generall Biſhop, Paſtour and doctour of the whole Church here vpon earth. For ſo ſaith <hi>Clement, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoralis, de Sentent. &amp; re Iudic. A paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall charge is enioyned to vs of God over all Nations of Chriſtendome, &amp;c. C.</hi> 1. <hi>extravag. de empt, &amp; vend. We being go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verners of the vniuerſall Church by the Lords appointment &amp;c. &amp;c. reg. extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vag. de prebend. Beeing called to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14493:16"/>
               <hi>of the vniuerſall Church by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie ordinance. &amp;C.</hi> 1 <hi>de treuga &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce. Being called to the gouernment of the vniuerſall Church by the mercy of God, ſo dispoſing it. C.</hi> 3. <hi>de Elect. The holy Church of Rome, which (by the Lords appointment, being as it were the mother and mistreſſe of all the faithfull, which belong to Christ) hath obtained of God ſuperioritie ouer the reſt. &amp; diſtinct.</hi> 22. <hi>Sacroſancta. This Apoſtolicallchayre, to wit, Rome, is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the head and principall, and as it were, the Hinge: for as the doore is turned and gouerned vpon the hinge; ſo all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are to bee ruled by the authoritie of this. &amp; Cap. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nam ſanctam, extravag. de mator. &amp; obed. Therefore there is one bodie of one and the ſame onely Church, &amp; one bead, not two, far that were monſtrous, to wit, Chriſt and the vicar of Chriſt, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Peters ſucceſſour. &amp; Cap. funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. de elect.</hi> 6. So likewiſe at this day, the Pope in his bulles challengeth au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie ouer all Churches of euerie people and nation. So alſo doeth hee call the Church his ſpouſe and bride. <hi>C. quonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de imminut. in</hi> 6. ſaying after this manner, <hi>Wee being loth to neglect the</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:14493:16"/>
               <hi>righteouſneſſe of our ſelues, &amp; the Church our ſpouſe.</hi> In like maner alſo hee ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, <hi>cap. inter corporalia &amp;c. licet in tantum de tranſlat. Epiſc.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="44"/> Secondly, the Pope hath viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and corrupted almoſt all the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine <note place="margin">2. <hi>The Pope hath corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by the oppoſition of theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</hi>
               </note> of Chriſt, ſo that he is not onely an heretike, but an Archheretique, the ringleader, and the Patriarke of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes: for hee hath not onelie main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained one errour onely againſt the foundation, but hath heaped vp manie one vpon the necke of another, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended them with might and maine, as may bee plainely vnderſtoode by this compariſon and oppoſition of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt and the Pope.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="45"/> The ſcripture, or rather Chriſt <note place="margin">Voluntarie worſhip.</note> in the ſcripture teacheth, that <hi>God is in vaine worſhipped with the precepts of men,</hi> Matth. 15. It condemneth <hi>voluntarie ſeruice.</hi> Col. 2. 2, 3. Further it declareth, that al things neceſſary to ſaluation, are committed to writing by the Apoſtles, &amp; are to be ſought for in theit writings, 2. Tim. 3. 6. &amp; that he is <hi>Anathema,</hi> that is, accurſed, who teacheth or bringeth any other doctrine. Gal. 18. But the <hi>Pope</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14493:17"/>
doeth vrge the traditions of men, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth in a will-worſhip, and letteth not to ſay, that the ſcripture is obſcure, maimed, and imperfect: as it is in the counſell of <hi>Trident. Seſſ.</hi> 4. 1. and elſe where.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="46"/> The ſcripture teacheth, that there <note place="margin">2. <hi>One God.</hi>
               </note> is but one onely God, who knoweth all things, is almightie. and the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of the worlde, and all thinges therein, Deut. 6. 4. Mark. 12. 29. 1. Kings 8. 39. 2. Cron. 6. 30. Eſa. 40. 13. Rom. 16. 27. 1. Tim. 6. 15. and in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places beſides. But the Pope, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king as it were, a diuiſion of the diuine Maieſtie, doeth transferre the ſame vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to certaine petie gods, and aſſociates vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. For looke how many he hath canonized for ſaintes, ſo manie hath he erected to bee gods, and lordes, and rulers of the worlde. Amongſt which, one is ouer the raine, another is for faire weather: one for diſeaſes, another for health: finallie, one for this cauſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother for that, they hauing their taskes and offices aſſigned ſeuerally vnto them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="47"/> The ſcripture teacheth, that God
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14493:17"/>
alone is to be called vpon, Deut. 6. 13. <note place="margin">3. <hi>Invocation of God.</hi>
               </note> Math. 4. 10. Act. 10. 25. &amp; 14. 11. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel. 19. 10. &amp; 22. 9. But the <hi>Pope,</hi> hee prayeth vnto the deade, and teacheth that they are to be prayed vnto.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="48"/> The Scripture teacheth, that we <note place="margin">4. <hi>Idols.</hi>
               </note> ſhould abhorte idols, Exod. 20. 4. Deut. 4. 23. 1. Ioh. 5. 21. Reuel. 18. 4. But the <hi>Pope</hi> doeth erect and ſet vp idols euery where to be worſhipped.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="49"/> The Scripture teacheth, that <note place="margin">5. <hi>One high Prieſt.</hi>
               </note> now there is one onely high Prieſt and Sacrificer, to wit, Chriſt; and that there is but one onely Oblation, Heb. 6. 20. and 9. 26, 28. and chap. 10. 12. But the <hi>Pope</hi> hath ſubſtituted an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in ſtead of Chriſt, who doe euerie day offer to God a reall and propitiato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſacrifice, to wit, the bodie and bloode of Chriſt in the Maſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="50"/> The Scripture teacheth, that <note place="margin">6. <hi>One Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour.</hi>
               </note> there is one onely Mediatour and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour <hi>betwixt God and man,</hi> to wit, <hi>the man Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> 1. Tim. 2. 5. 1. Ioh. 2. 1. Rom. 8. 34. Heb. 7. 24. and 9. 24. But the <hi>Pope</hi> hath ſuborned almoſt an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite number of dead men, to be media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, interceſſours, and ſpokeſmen, and
<pb facs="tcp:14493:18"/>
eſpecially the Virgine <hi>Marie</hi> in ſtead of Chriſt, as is in the Councill of <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="51"/> The Scripture teacheth, that all <note place="margin">7. <hi>Chriſts power.</hi>
               </note> power in heauen and earth is giuen and graunted vnto Chriſt, and that he is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted aboue all principalities, and is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Lord of all things, Math. 28. 18. Act. 2. 36. Epheſ. 1. 21. Further, that he is the head of the milita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Church here vpon earth, as was ſaide before. Whereupon <hi>Gregorie</hi> the great ſaith, <hi>That he is the forerunner of Antichriſt, who ſoeuer ſhould challenge vnto him ſelfe the title of generall Biſhop: who (that hee might leaue vnto his ſucceſſours an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of humilitie) was the firſt that called him ſelfe the ſeruant of the ſeruants of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And likewiſe the Councill of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage,</hi> and <hi>Pelagius</hi> the Pope, were of the mind, <hi>diſt.</hi> 96. <hi>can. Nullus.</hi> But the Pope, he placeth Chriſt (who is now in heauen exalted vnto the right-hand of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) not onely inferiour to his Father (with the <hi>Arrians)</hi> but alſo ſomewhat inferiour to his mother, and willeth that ſhee ſhould by her mortherly authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14493:18"/>
and priuiledge, to commaund her Sonne, &amp;c. And for him ſelfe hee ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vpon it, that he is the vniuerſall Biſhop here vpon earth, and the head of the whole Church.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="52"/> The Scripture teacheth, that a <note place="margin">8. <hi>Free-will.</hi>
               </note> man beeing deade in his ſinnes, is not able ſo much, as to vnderſtande any thing of him ſelfe, that is, hath no free-will in thoſe matters that be ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, and appertaine to ſaluation, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ. 2. 1. Coloſ. 2. 13. Roman. 8. 6. 1. Corinth. 2. 14. 2. Corinth. 3. 5. 2. Tim. 2. 15. 1. Ioh. 13. But the Pope, he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributeth ſo much vnto free-will, that he ſeemeth to come very high to the hereſie of <hi>Pelagius;</hi> as may be gathered out of the 28. chap. of <hi>Auguſtins</hi> booke, <hi>de Hereſibus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="53"/> The Scriptures teach, that Chriſt <note place="margin">9. <hi>Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
               </note> onely hath ſatisfied for our ſinne. 1. Ioh. 2. Roman. 3. 25. and 5. 8. Ioh. 1. 29. Math. 20. 28. Hebr. 10. 14. But the Pope teacheth, that wee muſt by our abilitie, merite, ſatisfie, and anſwer the iuſtice of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="54"/> The Scripture teacheth, that
<pb facs="tcp:14493:19"/>
we are onely iuſtified by faith in Chriſt, and that freely, vnto life eternall, and that our ſaluation is to be accounted and eſteemed as obtained by the onely mercie of God, Eſay 43. 25. Ioh. 3. 6. Act. 10. Eph. 2. 8. Heb. 24. But the <hi>Pope,</hi> hee teacheth that wee not onely haue not our ſaluation by faith alone, but that wee may merit and deſerue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life by our workes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merits.</p>
            <p>Further, that there is in the maſſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication <note place="margin">10. <hi>Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </note> made of all Chriſtes benefits, <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> that is, by the deede done, or for the workes ſake. Finally, that the maſſe beeing applied in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of others though they be vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons (ſo that them ſelues put no barre, and be no hinderance of the ſame) doeth merite the remiſſion both of the guilt, and of the puniſhment thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="55"/> The Scripture teacheth, that iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying <note place="margin">11. <hi>Iuſtifying faith.</hi>
               </note> faith is a ſure confidence repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Chriſt, or els thus, a ſure confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the remiſſion of our ſinnes, for Chriſts ſake, Rom. 4. 19. &amp;c. But the <hi>Pope,</hi> he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth that faith is nothing, but a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14493:19"/>
of the hiſtorie, and a doubtfulnes of the remiſſion of ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="56"/> The Scripture teacheth, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <note place="margin">12. <hi>Obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the law.</hi>
               </note> the regenerate man, whileſt he is in this life, can not perfectly obſerue and fulfill the Lawe of God, Roman. 7. Luk. 17. 10. Philippian. 3. 12. Act. 15. 10. But the <hi>Pope</hi> affirmeth, that hee is able: conſenting with the <hi>Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="57"/> The Scripture teacheth, that <note place="margin">13. <hi>The king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt.</hi>
               </note> the kingdome of Chriſt is not of this world. Further, that the miniſterie of the Apoſtles and their calling, is not ciuill and worldly, Ioh. 18. 36. Mark. 20. 25. Luk. 22. 25, 27. In like manner the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the Apoſtles commaund, that hee ſhould be remooued and depoſed from his office, who ſo euer ſhould beare both ciuill and eccleſiaſtical iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. But the <hi>Pope</hi> who boaſteth that he is the Vicar of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour</hi> of <hi>Peter,</hi> doth arrogate to him ſelfe both ciuill and eccleſiaſticall authority, as hereafter we will ſhew more at large.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="58"/> The Scripture ſaith, there are <note place="margin">15. <hi>The two Sacraments.</hi>
               </note> onely two Sacraments of the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, properly ſo called: Baptiſme,
<pb facs="tcp:14493:20"/>
and the Supper of the Lord: of which the one is ordained, Math. 28. and Mark. 16. The other, Math. 26. Mark. 14. Luk. 22. 1. Cor. 11. But the Pope holdeth that they be ſeuen.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="59"/> The Scripture teacheth, that <note place="margin">15. <hi>The vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar tongue to be vſed in the Church.</hi>
               </note> the vulgar tongue with an euident, ſignificant, a loud and diſtinct pronun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation is to be vſed in the Church, or the meetings of the godly, that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, might be eaſily vnderſtood, and approoued by the people. 1. Cor. 14. 9. And <hi>Luſtinian</hi> doeth make a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree very agreeable to the Scripture in this behalfe, in <hi>Conſtit.</hi> 123. <hi>&amp;</hi> 146. But the Pope will haue all things read in the latine tongue.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="60"/> The Scripture teacheth, that men <note place="margin">16. <hi>Who are to be baptized</hi>
               </note> are to be baptized for the remiſſion of ſinnes. Mat. 28. 19. not bruit creatures, and things without life. But the Pope doeth not onely baptize men, but alſo wood, and ſtones, and bells, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="61"/> The Scripture teacheth, that the bread both is, &amp; remaineth in the Lords <note place="margin">17. <hi>the bread in the Lordes Supper.</hi>
               </note> Supper. 1. Cor. 10. 16. &amp; 11. 26, &amp;c. But the Pope teacheth, that it is tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated, and chaunged into the bodie
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14493:20"/>
of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="62"/> The Scripture teacheth, that <note place="margin">18. <hi>The lords ſupper is no ſacrifice.</hi>
               </note> bread in the Lords Supper is a token of remembrance, or a ſigne of the bodie of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> once offred vp as a ſacrifice for vs, and that the body of Chriſt once giuen for vs, and his blood ſhed, is not offered againe vpon the alter by vs in the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, but is eaten and drunken for the confirmation of our faith in Chriſt, and for to ſtirre vp thankeſgiuing in vs, Hebr. 9. 28. and 10. 12. Make 26. 26. Luke 22. 19. But the Pope conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth this Sacrament into a ſacrifice, externall, reall, and propitiatorie: And hee daylie in his maſſe offereth vp this breade, turned into the bodie of Chriſt vpon the alter, for the quicke and the deade: and beeing offered, hee ſhuts it vp in a boxe, and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it about and worſhippeth it. <hi>Cap. peract. diſt.</hi> 2. <hi>de Conſecrat.</hi> and as in the Councill of <hi>Trident,</hi> and the Ieſuites Catechiſme is to be ſeene. Further, hee offereth this ſacrifice, or permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it to be offered for corporall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities: Whereupon it is, that there bee Maſſes for them that
<pb facs="tcp:14493:21"/>
ſayle vpon the ſea, or trauell vpon the lande, either on foote, or horſebacke, women with childe and in trauell, for them which are barren, or are ſicke of tertian or quartern agues, for mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants that they may haue proſperous traffique.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="63"/> The Scripture teacheth, that Chriſt in the inſtitution and celebrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">19. <hi>Chriſts bodie.</hi>
               </note> of the holie Supper, had and retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and ſtill hath and retaineth, a true bodie of the ſame ſubſtance with ours, Matth. 26. 26. Luk. 24. 39. 1. Cor. 11. 26. But the <hi>Pope</hi> feigneth, that the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Chriſt is inuiſible, and inſenſible, and ſo altogether diuerſe and vnlike vnto ours, and ſuch a one as may be in many places at one time, that is to ſay, that a bodie is preſent, but not as a bodie in deede.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="64"/> The Scripture teacheth, that not <note place="margin">20. <hi>All ought to take, eate, and drinke.</hi>
               </note> onely the Miniſters of the worde, but others alſo which be faithfull, ought to take, eate, and drinke, the breade and wine in the Lordes Supper, Luk. 22. 17. 1. Corinth. 11. 20. But the <hi>Pope</hi> will, that onely the Prieſtes ſhall take, eate, and drinke, the reſt are
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14493:21"/>
onely to be ſpectatours, and to looke on; as in the priuate Maſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="65"/> The Scripture teacheth, that in the Lords ſupper the wine as well as the <note place="margin">21 <hi>The bread and wine are to be diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to all.</hi>
               </note> bread is to be adminiſtred and diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, 1. Cor. 11. 26. But the Pope bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the laytie from the vſe of the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and of the wine, as in the Councill of Conſt. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="66"/> The ſcripture teacheth, that there be onely two places appointed for the <note place="margin">22 <hi>Two pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for the ſoules,</hi>
               </note> ſoules of the dead after this life: to wit, heauen for the faithfull, hell for the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeuers. Mark. 16. 16. Luc. 16. 22. Ioh. 3. 18. &amp; 4. 36. &amp; 5. 24. &amp;c. But the Pope hee feigneth a thirde place, where the ſoules of them that are defiled with veniall, that is, with ſmall ſinnes, are to be purged before they aſcende vp into heauen: which for this cauſe he calleth the fire of purgatorie. Concil. Trident. Seſſ. 6. cap. 30. &amp; Seſſ. 22. cap. 2. &amp; cap. 3. &amp; Seſſ. 25.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="67"/> The ſcripture teacheth, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage <note place="margin">23. <hi>Mariage honourable for all men.</hi>
               </note> is not onely ſeemely and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable for all ſorts of men; but alſo euen almoſt neceſſarie for the auoiding of fornication. Heb. 13. 4. 1. Cor. 7. 2. &amp; 9.
<pb facs="tcp:14493:22"/>
Againe, it woulde haue a Biſhop to be the husband of one lawfull wife &amp; not to haue concubines. 1. Tim. 3. 2. But the Pope forbiddeth mariage to his clergie &amp; Nuns, &amp; bindeth them with an othe vnto perpetuall ſingle life.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="68"/> The ſcripture teacheth, that the vſe of all meates is now free, Col. 2. 16. <note place="margin">24. <hi>Meates are free.</hi>
               </note> Rom. 14. 1. Tim. 4. 3. &amp;c. and that alſo there is fleſh of fiſhes, 1. Corinth. 15. 39. But the Pope teacheth that the eating fleſh vpon certaine daies is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden ſince the comming of Chriſt. Diſt. 35. And that they doe not eate fleſh who doe eate fiſh. Further he do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth (as did <hi>Montanus</hi> the heretique) appoint lawes concerning certaine fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting daies, and that without eyther prayer or repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="69"/> To conclude, hiſtories doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, <note place="margin">Popes haue erred.</note> that Pope <hi>Honorius</hi> fell into the hereſie of the <hi>Monothelites.</hi> 2. Tom. Con. 8. Syn. Conſtant. act. 17. that <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſeuenth fell from the true faith. <hi>Lib.</hi> 1 <hi>Alphonſi de Caſtro Minonta contra Hereſ.</hi> in the Cronicle of <hi>Abbas Vrbergenſ.</hi> that Pope <hi>Liberius</hi> was an <hi>Arrian.</hi> And that Pope <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:14493:22"/>
fauoured the <hi>Neſtorians,</hi> and erred from the faith. <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Alphonſi de Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro. Minonta contra Hereſ.</hi> That <hi>Iohn</hi> the 22 helde and maintained that the ſoules were mortall, and died with the bodies, vntill the daie of the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in <hi>Sermone quodam paſcali Ioh. Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> For which cauſe that Pope is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a deuill incarnate. <hi>In Concil. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant. Seſſ.</hi> 7. Laſtly, that <hi>Marcellinus</hi> the Pope ſacrificed vnto Idols. <hi>C. nunc autem. diſt.</hi> 21.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="70"/> Furthermore, the Pope is the <note place="margin">4. <hi>The Pope hath two ſwordes.</hi>
               </note> man who vaunteth vpon his twofolde ſupreme authoritie, ſpirituall and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, and of both his ſwords, ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and temporall or materiall: and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth arrogate vnto himſelfe both Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions. As touching them both, thus they are ioyntly proued by that which is ſaid. <hi>C. vnam ſanctam extra vag. de maior &amp; obed. Wee are instructed by the worde of the Goſpell that there be two ſwordes, the one spirituall, the other tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall; in this power and authoritie of the Pope.</hi> Againe, <hi>therefore both the ſwords are in the power of the Church, that is, both the ſpirituall and the materiall</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14493:23"/>
               <hi>ſword, &amp;c. Fundament. de elect in</hi> 6. <hi>The Pope of Rome hath the Monarchie or ſole gouernment of both the Iuriſdictions spirituall and temporall.</hi> Whereof wee haue a notable example in <hi>Boniface</hi> the 8. who in the firſt yere of his Iubile in the yere of our Lorde 1300, hauing vpon him both the Emperours robe, and the Prieſtes attyre, and ſhewing himſelfe openly in the Church of Peter and Paul, and hauing both a key and a ſword, hee cried as loude as he coulde, <hi>Beholde, here bee two ſwordes. c. vnam ſanct. Extravag. de maiorit. &amp; obed.</hi> as alſo in <hi>Iulius</hi> the ſecond, who was a better ſouldier then a Prieſt, and of whom <hi>Mantuan</hi> writeth thus:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Enſepotens gemino, cuius veſtigia adora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</l>
               <l>Caeſar, &amp; aurato veſtiti muricereges.</l>
            </q>
            <p>which is in Engliſh.</p>
            <q>
               <l>He powrefull is by twofold ſword,</l>
               <l>to him all men doe ſtoupe;</l>
               <l>Both Emperour and ſtately kings,</l>
               <l>with all their glorious troupe.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Concerning his ſpirituall authoritie, <note place="margin">Spirituall.</note> are theſe teſtimonies, <hi>Clement. in Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. deſent. &amp; re Iud. &amp;c. Primum extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vag.</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:14493:23"/>
               <hi>de empt. &amp; vend.</hi> and others, of which we ſpake before: &amp; for the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Iuriſdictions, theſe are witneſſes <note place="margin">Temporall.</note> ſufficient, as <hi>Cap. Conſtan. diſt.</hi> 96. where the enſignes, titles, pallace, citie, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, right and power of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours are beſtowed vpon the Pope of Rome: that hee hath the rule of all the Weſt partes. <hi>Et cap.</hi> 1. <hi>in fine extravag. de matorit. &amp; obed.</hi> Where it is ſaid with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt, whoſoeuer denieth that the temporall ſword is in the power of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> doeth giue ſmall heede vnto the word of the Lord, which ſaith, <hi>Put vp thy ſword into the ſheath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="71"/> Hee alſo vaunteth of himſelfe, with ſignes and miracles, as is well <note place="margin">5. <hi>The Popes miracles.</hi>
               </note> knowne both by the bookes and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the Papiſtes, but they are lying &amp; deceitfull, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, and are wrought to ſeduce and drawe men into errour and ſuperſtition: and further they are either meere fables, or elſe, iuggling ſleights: Fables, as thoſe which are reported of <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Lauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane,</hi> as they call her, which a certaine Ieſuite hath declared to bee falſe and feigned in a certaine booke, ſet foorth
<pb facs="tcp:14493:24"/>
at <hi>Lipſia</hi> after that hee had denounced Ieſuitiſme: ſo alſo they which are reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the bookes of the <hi>Franciſcans</hi> &amp; <hi>Dominicans,</hi> &amp; eſpecially in the bookes which are of the conformities of the <hi>Franciſcans.</hi> Iuggling ſleights; as thoſe which are wrought, either by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion of Sathan, or by the cloſe and craftie conueyances of the Monkes: as in the apparitions of ſoules, which made report of purgatorie, and deſired that Maſſes might be ſaid and celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for them, and in the healing of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes at the Chappels I or images of ſaintes, and in coniurations. For Sathan (God in his iuſt iudgement ſo permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it to be) afflicted men with pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar diſeaſes, and againe ceaſed to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict them, when they were making their vowes at the Chappels or images of ſaintes, ſo that they were ſuppoſed to bee cured by the making of their vowes, and deliuered by the helpe of the ſaintes. And thus hee, playing with the exorciſtes, doeth voluntarilie yeeld vnto them, though he ſeeme to be caſt out by force, and hee ceaſeth to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a man, who is bodily poſſeſſed,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14493:24"/>
that by this meanes (theſe errours bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing confirmed) he may inſtead of their bodies beſiege, win, and poſſeſſe their ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="72"/> He boaſteth himſelfe as God, <note place="margin">6. <hi>The Pope as God.</hi>
               </note> whileſt that hee chalengeth vnto him ſelfe the name and authoritie and the workes which are proper vnto God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="73"/> Hee arrogateth to himſelfe the <note place="margin">He chalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth Gods owne name.</note> name of God, <hi>Cap. ſatisf. diſt.</hi> 96. where he ſaieth, It is euident enough that the Pope neither is as all, neither can be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther freed or bounde by any temporall authoritie, who (as it is verie mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt) was caled God by the godly prince <hi>Conſtantine:</hi> Sith that it is euident, that God can not bee iudged of men. <hi>Et cap. quanto. &amp; ſeq. extr. de tranſlat. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopi.</hi> For no man but God doeth ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate them, whome the Pope of Rome doeth ſeparate, not by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, but rather by diuine authoritie. So likewiſe the Pope is God on earth, according as <hi>Baldus</hi> hath it, hee is a certaine diuine power, and hath, as it were, the reſemblance of a viſible God; and what he doeth, he doeth it as God, not as man according to
<pb facs="tcp:14493:25"/>
               <hi>Gomazius:</hi> of which there is a more large diſcourſe in the booke which is called <hi>Recuſatio concilij Trident.</hi> publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the name of the proteſtant princes and ſtates. Anno 64.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="74"/> Furthermare, he doeth chalenge the power and the workes of God: as <note place="margin">2. <hi>Gods pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie.</hi>
               </note> he will be both indeed and eſtimation as hee is alſo accounted of verie many, not only the head of the whole Church as was before ſaide: but alſo the head and lord of all kings and Monarches <note place="margin">Head of the Church.</note> of the worlde. <hi>Extravag. de maiorit. &amp; obed.</hi> in the end. Moreouer, we declare to euerie humane creature, that hee is ſubiect to the Pope of Rome: this wee doe profeſſe, determine, &amp; pronounce, that it is altogether a matter neceſſarie to ſaluation. <hi>Cap. ſuper gentes extra. de conſuet.</hi> The Biſhop of Rome is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Lorde aboue all nations and kingdomes. <hi>Cap. ſi Imperatore diſt.</hi> 96. Gods will is, that the powers ſecular ſhould be ſubiect vnto the Church, or the Prieſts. <hi>Cap. nunquam eadem. diſt.</hi> 96. It is a cuſtome, that princes ſhoulde ſubmit their heads vnto the Biſhops girdle, and not iudge of their liues. <hi>Cap.</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:14493:25"/>
               <hi>ſolita. de maiorit. &amp; obed.</hi> God made two great lights in the firmame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the greater light to rule the day, &amp; the leſſe light to rule the night: both of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great, but the one greater. Therefore hath God made two great lightes for the firmament of heauen, that is, the vniuerſall Church, to wit, he hath appointed two high ſtates or dignities, which are theſe, the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the <hi>Pope,</hi> &amp; the power of the king. But that which ruleth the day, that is, in matters ſpiritual, is the greater: that which gouerneth carnall affaires, that is, the leſſe: That it may appeare, that looke what difference there is betwixt the ſunne &amp; the moone, ſo great oddes there is betwixt Popes &amp; Kings. <hi>C. fundament. de elect. in</hi> 6. <hi>Papa nulli homini ſubeſt.</hi> Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, the Emperour is bound to take an oath of alegiance &amp; obedience vnto the Pope: the forme whereof is extant, <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>de jurejurando. &amp;c. tibi domino. deſt.</hi> 63. <hi>&amp; clement. vnica. de jurejurando.</hi> And ſo it is ſaid <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>ceremoniarum Pontificia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium. cap.</hi> 7. The Pope in the night of the birth of our Lorde doeth hallowe the ſword, which he afterward giueth vnto ſome Prince, in token of the infinite
<pb facs="tcp:14493:26"/>
power which is giuen vnto the Pope, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that ſaying, <hi>All power is giuen vnto me in heauen &amp; in earth:</hi> &amp; that alſo, <hi>He ſhal rule fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeato ſea, &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the riuer to the ende of the earth.</hi> So it is alſo in the Gloſſe of the Canon law, to wit, that the Pope is al things, &amp; aboue all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs: that he is the lord of lords, &amp; hath the right of the king of ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs ouer his ſubiects: that he may turn rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d into ſquare: that he is the cauſe of cauſes; &amp; therfore no inquirie is to be made into his authoritie, becauſe there is no cauſe of the firſt cauſe, that the whole world is the Popes dioceſſe: that his authority exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth vnto things in heauen &amp; earth, and vnder the earth: that he may command the Angels: that he hath ſo great power both in Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie &amp; alſo in hell: that hee can by his pardons, deliuer as many ſoules as hee will which are in thoſe places, &amp; place them preſently in heauen, &amp; in the ſeats of them which be bleſſed: as it is ſaide in the Bull of <hi>Clement</hi> the ſixt: that hee hath ſuch power in heauen, that hee may canonize whome hee will that is dead for a ſaint, though all Byſhops and Cardinals were againſt it. And who can
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14493:26"/>
recken vp all his blaſphemies? To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, <hi>Sixtus quintus,</hi> to omit the reſt, doth at this day thus begin in one of his Bulles. <hi>The authoritie graunted to bleſſed Peter, and to all his ſucceſſours, by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite power of the everlaſting King, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celleth the power of all earthly kings and Princes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="75"/> Secondly, for that he will be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the higheſt iudge, who neither <note place="margin">2 <hi>The Pope the higheſt Iudge.</hi>
               </note> can erre in making decrees concerning faith, or lawes concerning manners: neither yet ought to be iudged of any. And for that hee ſetteth vp himſelfe aboue all euen the generall councels, and ordaineth new ſacraments, and transformeth and altereth thoſe which Chriſt did inſtitute. He impoſeth new lawes vpon mens conſcienees, as for thoſe which Chriſt made, hee doeth ratifie and repeale at his pleaſure. as <hi>Cap. nunc autem. diſt.</hi> 21. The chiefe ſeate, that is, the chayre of Rome, is not indeede of any. <hi>Can. ſi Papa. diſt.</hi> 40. If the Pope ſhould drawe by heapes innumerable people with him into hell, no mortall man preſumeth or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vpon him to reprehend his faults:
<pb facs="tcp:14493:27"/>
for that he is to iudge all men, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be iudged of none. <hi>Can. cuncta. &amp; ſeq.</hi> 9. <hi>q.</hi> 3. Euery Church in the worlde knoweth, that the holy Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath authoritie to iudge of all perſons, &amp; no man may cenſure her iudgement. <hi>Can. nemini.</hi> 17. 4. It is permitted to no man to iudge of the Apoſtolicall ſeat, or to retract that ſentence, becauſe of the primacie of the Church of Rome. <hi>cap. propoſuit. de concept. praebend.</hi> According to the largenes of our authority, we may diſpenſe with &amp; aboue law. <hi>cap. ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti. de elect. &amp; elect. poteſt.</hi> Al councils both are called, &amp; haue their ſtrength by the authoritie of the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> &amp; the authoritie of the Biſhop of Rome is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly excepted in their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. <hi>cap. regula. diſt.</hi> 17. No council is, or ſhal euer be eſtabliſhed, which ſhall not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med &amp; ſupported by the Popes authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And ſo the Gloſſe ſaith again, that the Popes pleaſure is heauenly: and for this cauſe, he may cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the nature of thigs, by applying thoſe things which are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial in one thing, vnto another. That he hath allaws in the cloſet of his breſt: that he hath the ſame conſiſtory, which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14493:27"/>
God hath, and the ſame iudgement ſeat with Chriſt: that he can make any thing of nothing, and make that to be a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence or iudgement, which is none: that in what ſo euer he pleaſeth, his will is to him in ſteade of reaſon, and yet no man may ſay: <hi>Why doſt thou thus?</hi> that he may diſpenſe beyond law, &amp; make iuſtice of iniuſtice, by concealing and altering the laws: that he can do all things (ſinne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) whatſoeuer God himſelf ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do: that he muſt be iudged of none: that if he ſhould throw downe heaps of ſoules into the hels, yet none may demand of him, <hi>Why doeſt thou it?</hi> that he may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe againſt both Apoſtle, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall Canon: that he is aboue lawe: that what ſoeuer is done of the Pope, is to be ſuppoſed is done of God: that he is all, and aboue all: that hee may doe all things aboue law, contrarie to law, and without lawe. <hi>ad cap. quanto de tranſlat. Epiſcopi, &amp; cap. propoſuit. de conceſſ. praeb.</hi> and elſe where, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="76"/> Thirdly, for that he taketh and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpeth <note place="margin">3. <hi>He diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes.</hi>
               </note> power &amp; authoritie, to transferre kingdoms, which is the onely worke of God as <hi>Clement. vnica de jureiur ando, in priu.</hi> The Romane Emperours haue the
<pb facs="tcp:14493:28"/>
approbation of the B. of Rome, for the perſon which is to be preferred vnto the dignity of the Emperiall M<hi rend="sup">ie</hi>: as alſo the anointing, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the crown of the Empire. <hi>Clem. Past. de ſent. &amp; re iudic. in fine.</hi> The Pope hath ſuperiority ouer the Empire, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Empire is void ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cee deth the Emperour. <hi>C. venerabile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de elect.</hi> The right &amp; authoritie to chooſe a king to be Emperor, appertaineth vnto the Biſhop of Rome. <hi>&amp; cap.</hi> 2. <hi>de ſent. &amp; re iudic. in</hi> 6. The Pope may depoſe the Emperour. <hi>Can. alius</hi> 15. <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 6. <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> the Pope depoſed the <hi>French</hi> king from his kingdome, &amp; ſubſtituted <hi>Papin</hi> into his roome. So Pope <hi>Hadrian</hi> ſaith as <hi>Arentinus</hi> reporteth, <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>in Epiſt. ad Archiepiſc. Trevicenſ. Mogunt. &amp; Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nienſ.</hi> From whence hath the Emperour his Empire vnleſſe it be fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs? therefore he ruleth by vs. <hi>Againe,</hi> whatſoeuer the Emp. hath, he hath it wholly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. <hi>Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> behold, the Empire is in our power to giue it, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſoeuer we wil. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are we appointed of God, aboue nations &amp; kingdoms, that we may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy &amp; pull down, build &amp; plant. And thus ſay the Canoniſts, that the Emp. is the Popes vaſſall, and that hee hath the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14493:28"/>
Empire of him in name of Homage.</p>
            <p>The acts of the Biſhops of Rome af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford vs plentifull exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples; who haue ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proclaimed as depoſed &amp; at their <note place="margin">Examples.</note> pleaſure tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their thrones, or elſe crowned Emperors, &amp; kings, and princes. So dealt <hi>Innocentius</hi> with <hi>Otho</hi> the 4 Emperour of that name: <hi>Gregorie</hi> the 7 with <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. <hi>Paſchalis</hi> the 2 with <hi>Henry</hi> the fift: <hi>Hadrian</hi> the 4 and <hi>Alexander</hi> the 3, with <hi>Frederick</hi> the firſt: <hi>Innocentius</hi> the 3 with <hi>Philip</hi> the ſon of <hi>Frederick: Gregory</hi> the 9 with <hi>Frederick</hi> the 2: <hi>Innocentius</hi> the 4 with <hi>Conrad</hi> the 4: <hi>Alexander</hi> the 2 with <hi>W. king</hi> of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: Boniface</hi> the 8 with <hi>Philip Pulcher</hi> the K. of <hi>France:</hi> whom they did excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, &amp; either did depoſe, or labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to depoſe them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their Empire &amp; kingdoms. And at this day <hi>Sixtus</hi> the 5 doeth depriue the king of <hi>Navar</hi> and prince of <hi>Condie</hi> of their kingdome, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue, &amp; all hope of ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolueth the ſubiects from the oth of alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; inciteth the <hi>French</hi> king to perſecute them with violence, fire, and ſworde. So <hi>Leo</hi> the third cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated <hi>Charles</hi> the great Emperour, hee annointed him, and ſate the diademe
<pb facs="tcp:14493:29"/>
vpon his head, &amp; ſo transferred the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire vnto the <hi>Frenchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Grecians,</hi> among who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued 500 yeres. <hi>Iohn</hi> the ninth, made three Emperours one after another, &amp; gaue the Emperiall crown vnto <hi>Carolous, Calons,</hi> to <hi>Ludovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Bulbus</hi> his ſonne, and to <hi>Charles</hi> the third, ſonne to <hi>Ludovicus Germanicus. Iohn</hi> the thirteenth, created <hi>Otto;</hi> and <hi>Clement</hi> the fift created <hi>Henry</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour &amp; called him <hi>Auguſtus.</hi> But aboue all, the acte of <hi>Gregorie</hi> is famous, who tooke away the Empire from <hi>Henricus</hi> the Emperour, &amp; gaue it to <hi>Rodolphus,</hi> adding this verſe,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Petra dedit Patro, Petrus diadema Rodolpho.</l>
               <l>This diademe the Rocke to Peter gaue,</l>
               <l>And Peter graunts that Rodolph ſhall it haue.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="77"/> The ſame Pope is an idolatour, <note place="margin">He is an ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latour.</note> worſhipping ſtrange gods, that is, ſuch a thing for God, which is no God. Firſt, in the bread of the <hi>Euchariſt:</hi> where <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius</hi> the fourth, was the firſt who eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed tranſubſtantiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the worſhip of that bread. <hi>Honorious</hi> the 3, vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed it a peculiar place where it ſhould be ſet, that the God of bread might haue a <note place="margin">Breaden God.</note> temple &amp; palace. To conclude, leaſt any thing ſhould be wanting vnto idolatrie, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbanus</hi> the fourth, <hi>Anno Chriſt.</hi> 1263.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14493:29"/>
appointed a feaſt vnto the body of Chriſt, and the carying about of the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt in proceſſion, and gaue verie large indulgences there withal. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in the calling vpon the ſaintes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted. For he perſecuteth the ſaintes whileſt they liue on earth, and killeth them, whom being dead, hee worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth in heauen. Wherein he is like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hunters, who do therefore hunt that they may kill and eate, and eating doe commend the meate, and are encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to follow their game againe. And alſo he is like to eraftie and cloſe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, who whileſt they are to buy, diſpraiſe that which afterward they do commend, when they haue bought it, according as it is ſaid, Prov. 20. 14. It is nought, it is nought, ſaith euery buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Finally, he is like to the Scribes and Phariſes of whome mention is made, Mat. 23. 29. 30. Thirdly, in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of images and monuments &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes of Chriſt, and the ſaintes, in that which they call holy water: in the hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and conſecrated oyle, and waxe candles: in the ſigne of the croſſe: in the baptizing of belles: in Amulets
<pb facs="tcp:14493:30"/>
&amp; Pomanders, &amp; ſuch like. The which Idolatrie is gone ſo farre, that there hath not bin greater, no not amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="78"/> The Pope is alſo an hypocrite, worſhipping the true God indeed; but <note place="margin">His hypocriſy</note> onely in externall rites, perfourmed <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> by the worke done, and inſtituting new kinds of worſhip: as in the ſacraments, in the ſacrifice of the Maſſe, in the vigils or ſaintes euens, in Canonicall houres, in chaunting in the Church, in faſtes, in choice of meates, ſingle life, religious pilgrimages, anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, the order of Monaſticall life, (whereof there be more kindes (if they were tolde) then there are of fowles (which yet alſo haue differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce by their colours, &amp; ſo great multitudes (if they were muſtered together) that they wold ſeeme to bee the armie of <hi>Xerxes)</hi> In workes of ſupererrogation, in almes, in mumbling of praiers, and in the number of them, in their apparell, or holy ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites, in the ſhauing their haire, their burning tapers, the ornaments of the Churches, the multitude of feaſts, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there is neither meaſure nor end. But yet he is indeed prophane, wicked, &amp; an Atheiſt, becauſe he getteth this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14493:30"/>
by magique or Symonie, or elſe by threats, ſedition, and tumult, &amp; both he himſelfe beareth &amp; alſo ſuffereth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to beare the titles &amp; names of holy offices, without the thing itſelfe. For if you do take a view either of the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the word &amp; ſacraments, or of the whole gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Church, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth that the biſhops &amp; others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, doe not execute any part of their owne function, but are wholly emploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about temporall affaires, contrarie to the word of God &amp; the ancient canons.</p>
            <p>We haue exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples herof in <hi>Gregory</hi> the 5, who being caried with a deuiliſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of authority, did firſt by bribes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Rhenes,</hi> and afterwarde got by the deuils aſſiſtance the Popedome itſelfe: on this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition, that after his death the deuil ſhoulde wholly haue him, as <hi>Platina</hi> recordeth. In <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7, who being a Magitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, cauſed that ſtones fell downe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue when <hi>Henry</hi> the 3 Emperor was pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple: &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was ſeeking anſwers from God againſt the Emp. he caſt the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the body of the lord into the fire, as <hi>Platina</hi> doeth witneſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:14493:31"/>
In <hi>Iohn</hi> the eight, or rather <hi>Ione,</hi> a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who diſſembling her ſexe, obtained and exerciſed the Popedome, vntil ſuch time, as her tranell did bewray what ſhee was: as againe <hi>Platina</hi> and verie manie others doe witneſſe. In <hi>Iohn</hi> the thirteene who gaue himſelfe vnto Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than corporally, as it is regiſtred in <hi>Faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciculo Temporum.</hi> In <hi>Sylvester</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, of whome <hi>Iohannes Stella</hi> the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netian</hi> writeth, that hee was appointed Pope by the aſſiſtance of the deuill, on this condition, that after his death hee might haue him whollie, both ſoule &amp; bodie, by whoſe ſubtiltie he attained to ſo great promotion. In <hi>Benedictus</hi> the ninth and <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſixt: and moreouer in <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth (as the ſaid Cardinall <hi>Benno</hi> witneſſeth) who being at <hi>Florence</hi> in the Church, when (after a watch word giuen) the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt was taken away, hee would (by his conſpiratours) haue killed the two bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren <hi>Iulianus</hi> and <hi>Laurentius Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:</hi> and did indeede ſlay the one and wound the other: as <hi>Raphael Volateran</hi> recordeth in the 5 of his <hi>Geographie.</hi> In <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth, who is reported to haue
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14493:31"/>
anſwered vnto <hi>Peter Bembus,</hi> when hee alledged a ſaying out of the Goſpell: What doeſt thou alledge or tell me of that fable?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="79"/> Hee is alſo blaſphemous, in that he claimeth for his owne that which <note place="margin">His blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.</note> is Gods, doeth ſpeake againſt God: namely, when he ſaieth, that he is God, and of equall power with Chriſt, &amp; the head and ſpouſe of the Church: the which we haue more fully opened be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Further, when he affirmeth that the Scripture is obſcure, and imperfect, and doubtfull: and that hee may inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete it as he liſteth, and may make new articles of faith, and yet he neither er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth herein nor is to be controlled by any, As alſo when he boaſteth, that he can graunt indulgences and pardons, and remiſſion of all ſinnes to whom ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he will.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="80"/> He is alſo ambitious and proud, both in his wordes and deedes, becauſe <note place="margin">His ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> hee, beeing euen ſicke of an vnſaciable thirſt after honour, and vnlawfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of lordlineſſe, doeth ſet vp himſelfe aboue the Church, aboue councils, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all magiſtrates, and accounteth
<pb facs="tcp:14493:32"/>
all Emperours, kings and princes which are in Europe, to be but his vaſſals, his tenauntes, and almoſt his ſlaues and drudges hee treadeth them vnder his feete. Of which pride and arrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of his, we before brought teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies euen out of the Canon lawe: but nowe wee will bring others like vnto them, out of the booke which is called <hi>Liber ceremoniarum Romanae curiae:</hi> Where it is ſaide, that all men of what honour or preheminence ſoeuer they be, ſo ſoone as they come within the ſight of the Pope, ought to bowe their knees thriſe, obſeruing equall diſtance of pace, and to kiſſe his feete. Further, when the Pope doeth get vp on horſe-backe, the greateſt prince of them which be preſent though he be a king or Emperour muſt hold the Popes ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup, &amp; then lead the horſe by the bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle a little on the way. But if that the Pope be not carried on horſebacke but on his chaire, whether hee be king or Emperour that is preſent it skilleth not, they muſt cary the ſeate it ſelfe with the Pope in it, a while vpon their ſhoulders. Againe, that the prince of the city (into
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14493:32"/>
which the Pope ſhall enter) though he be a king, ſhall leade the popes horſe by the bridle: or if the pope be caried in his chaire, ſhall (together with the chiefe of his Nobles) carry the ſame a good way: then, when the pope com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth him, the king ſhall take his horſe &amp; ride according vnto his place. Further, the Emperor muſt at the baket holde water for the pope to waſh his hands. And moreouer, when the pope hath a feaſt, the Emperor or els the king of the Romans muſt cary the firſt meſſe or ſeruice. And to conclude, the pope doth no reuerence at all to any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, only he raiſeth vp himſelfe when the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour kiſſeth him. For examples theſe are chiefly to be noted: firſt of the pope in generall, who offreth his feet to be kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the Emperor, kings princes, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, <note place="margin">Examples of his ambition.</note> biſhops, &amp; the reſt. Then ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of pope <hi>Sylveſter</hi> of whome it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported that (for the honour of <hi>S. Peter) Pſeudoconſtantinus</hi> or that feigned <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tine</hi> helde his horſe bridle in his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d when he tooke horſe and plaid the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman vſher or ſergeant before him. <hi>Diſt.</hi> 96. Thirdly of pope <hi>Hadrian</hi> the fourth, who was very angry with
<pb facs="tcp:14493:33"/>
               <hi>Fredericke</hi> the Emperour, and did in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch obiect vnto him, that when as hee woulde haue helde his ſtirrup at his lighting downe from his horſe, he came and helde not the further ſtirrup as hee ſhould, but the other. And that he alſo had ſet the Emperours name before the popes in certain letters which were ſent vnto him. Fourthly of <hi>Alexander</hi> the third, who ſet one foote in the necke of <hi>Fredericke</hi> the Emperour, when he was proſtrate and ſuppliant at his feet in the Cathedrall Church of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enice,</hi> that he might haue his excommunication re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed, and commanding, that the verſe of Pſalme ſhould be ſong of his prieſts, <hi>Thou ſhult walke vpon the Serpent, and the Baſiliske: thou ſhalt tread vnder foote the Lyon and the Dragon.</hi> Fiftly, of <hi>Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> the eight, Anno 1300, who ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelfe at Rome in a great aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the people (by reaſon of a Iubile then ſolemnized) the firſt day of the ſolemnitie with all the ornaments of the Pope, and the next day hee came foorth clad with the Emperours robe, or coate armour, and commaunded a drawne ſword to be caried before him,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14493:33"/>
himſelfe crying with a loud voice, I am both Pope, &amp; Emperor, &amp; haue autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie both in heauen &amp; earth: &amp; within few dayes after did proudly reiect <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus,</hi> who was created Emp. by the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectours of the Empire, &amp; deſired to be confirmed by him: Affirming moreouer that no election could be authenticall, which was made without his authority, ſith that he alone had the authoritie of both the ſwords, which when <hi>Albertus Crautzius</hi> ſuperintendent of the church of <hi>Hanburgh</hi> reciteth, hee maketh this exclamation; O <hi>Peter,</hi> behold thy ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour, &amp;, O Sauiour Chriſt, behold thy Vicar: beholde the pride of the feruant of thy ſeruants, vnto what height he is now come.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="81"/> He is alſo lawleſſe, becauſe hee doeth what he liſteth, he aboliſheth the <note place="margin">The Pope is lawleſſe.</note> lawes which Chriſt hath made, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth new at his owne pleaſure: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he will be iudged of no man but aduanceth himſelfe aboue lawe, as wee ſhewed heretofore. Whereof we haue example in the forbidding of the mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of Prieſtes, and certaine meats, &amp; of the chalice in the Lords ſupper, which
<pb facs="tcp:14493:34"/>
is contrary vnto the reuealed will of God and of Chriſt our Lord. Further, in diſpenſing with degrees contrarie to the lawe of God and nature: as that Pope <hi>Martin</hi> the fift gaue diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that a man might take his owne ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to wife: And that others haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed, that any man might mary two ſiſters, his fathers ſiſter, or his mothers, or any woman two brethren, her vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle by her fathers ſide or by her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and that (which ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the ſchoolemen doe teach vpon the 4. <hi>ſent. diſt.</hi> 34. <hi>&amp; Caietan ſecunda ſecundae. Thomae. quaeſt.</hi> 154 <hi>Art.</hi> 9. (to wit that the Pope may diſpenſe with all degrees, excepting the mariage of the father and the ſonne, with the daughter and the mother.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="82"/> He is alſo a ſingle man but yet a filthy fornicatour, becauſe that, hee in forbidding mariage vnto his clergie, &amp; the Nuns, commandeth ſingle life. The authous &amp; defenders of the which law, are theſe eſpecially. <hi>Siricius</hi> the pope. <hi>C. plurimos. diſt.</hi> 82. <hi>Greg.</hi> 7. <hi>Calixtus</hi> 6. <hi>Presbyteris. diſt.</hi> 27. <hi>Leo. diſt.</hi> 32. <hi>per totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Innocentius c. propoſuiſti. diſt.</hi> 82. <hi>&amp;c. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdoticus.</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:14493:34"/>
               <hi>&amp; ſeq. diſt.</hi> 31. <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth &amp; other more. But on the contrary, hee permitteth concubines, brothel houſes, whoredomes, &amp; filthie luſtes, or at leaſt doeth tollerate them, &amp; filleth all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome with whores, with Baſtards, with buggerers, and others more of the ſame ſtampe, as it is knowne full well, and yet further by giuing diſpenſation, he permitteth inceſtuous mariages: and that which is more then all the reſt, he maketh a gaine and raiſeth a yerely rent of the common ſtewes.</p>
            <p>So <hi>Iohn</hi> 13 being found with a queane was run through of the husband of the ſame harlotte. Further, how great was the chaſtitie and honeſtie of <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt, it appeareth by this epitaph made for his daughter.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hic iacet in tumulo Lucretia nomine, ſedre</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thaïs, Alexandri ſilia, ſponſa, nurus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Here lyes entombd <hi>Lucretia</hi>
               </l>
               <l>by name: but wee her ſawe</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thais</hi> in life; <hi>Alexanders</hi>
               </l>
               <l>childe, ſpouſe, daughter in lawe.</l>
            </q>
            <p>So <hi>Iohn Caſus</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventum</hi> the popes legate among the <hi>Venetians,</hi> hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended &amp; publiſhed in print that horrible kind of luſt and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerie,
<pb facs="tcp:14493:35"/>
which is not at all to be reported: yea, &amp; that who is called P. <hi>Iohn</hi> the 8, was both a woman and an harlot, &amp; as ſhe went to the palace of <hi>Laterane,</hi> ſhee traueiled in the third yere of the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, &amp; died of that trauell in the ſame place, whereupon <hi>Mantuan</hi> in his time writeth after this maner:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Jpudor in villas, ſi non patiantur eaſdem</l>
               <l>&amp; villae vomicas, Roma eſt iam tota lupanar.</l>
               <l>O ſhame to village packe away</l>
               <l>If it may be found deere,</l>
               <l>Rome is a stewes: now chaſtitie</l>
               <l>hath no abiding there. <note place="margin">His abſtine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and riot.</note>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="83"/> He alſo abſtaineth from certain meates, &amp; yet exceedeth in all kinde of exceſſe: becauſe he forbiddeth fleſh &amp; all things which haue generation by ſeede, or doe ſauour of fleſh, as milke, cheeſe &amp; egges to be eaten on ſet daies, vnderpain of deadly ſinne, to ſatisfie for ſinne, &amp; to deſerue the grace of God, &amp; life euerlaſting: but he granteth all the dainties &amp; delicates whatſoeuer, <hi>de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſec. diſt.</hi> 3. <hi>de eſu carnium. &amp; diſt. quia. &amp; eadem diſt.</hi> 5. <hi>quadr. &amp; diſt.</hi> 4. <hi>c. deni<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> &amp;c. &amp;</hi> 13. <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 2. <hi>animae.</hi> And yet he will for mony diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe for the ſelf ſamething.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="84"/> He is couetous, becauſe he vſeth <note place="margin">He is cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous.</note>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:14493:35"/>
Symonie, that is, buying, ſelling, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a marchaudiſe of things ſpirituall: he giueth nothing, but ſelleth al things, as, the grace of God, the ſacraments, good works, heauen, &amp; life euerlaſting, &amp; out of all of them he piketh out gold and ſiluer, and raiſeth his gaine for hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, hell, the earth, yea time itſelfe, and all creatures whether they haue life or be without life, as wine, bread, oyle, lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen, milke, butter, cheeſe, water, ſalt, fire, perfumes, the ſtewes, &amp;c. So that, there was neuer hearde of either any greater, or more abominable marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe. Whereupon his marchants &amp; bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, that is, the Monkes, the Biſhops, &amp; Cardinals, are not onely become rich, but are euen princes vpon the earth. So likewiſe doeth he make a gaine of Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſatisfactions, pardons, burials, and Church liuings: to wit, by ſelling of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, annats, or vacations: preuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, reſignations for fauour, commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datus, diſpenſations for age, for orders, for irregularity, for blemiſh of body, for redemptions of the Biſhops pall and the Bulls. Further, by reſeruation of caſes, by mariage cauſes, by ſinnes and offences,
<pb facs="tcp:14493:36"/>
to wit, when as licenſe for ſinnes and all kind of miſchiefes are bought and ſold after a certaine price and rate: and by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſes and cauſes of the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: which, if wee ſhoulde recken vp one by one, would be very tedious, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they want both meaſure and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie: and there is no great neceſſitie ſo to doe: for that there is a booke extant of theſe things, which hath this title. <hi>Taxae Cancellariae Apostolicae, &amp; Taxae ſacrae Poenitentiariae, itidem Apoſtolicae cum not abilibus iuxta ſtylum hodiernum curiae Romanae.</hi> In which book thus there is a ſentence worthy the remembrance ſet downe in theſe wordes. <hi>And marke this diligently, that ſuch immunities and dispenſations are not graunted vnto them which be poore: For they, becauſe they bee not rich, can not be comforted.</hi> Hereof commeth it to paſſe, that an infinite maſſe of gold and ſiluer is brought vnto Rome, which afterward the Pope, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, and the reſt of the ſame rable do conſume in their ſtewes and brothel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, and doe riotouſlie ſpend, as it were in the bottomles gulfe of their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaciable gluttonie &amp; ſenſualitie, to the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14493:36"/>
great ſhame &amp; ignominie of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: So <hi>Franciſcus Petrarch</hi> hath left it in record, that in the treaſure houſe of Pope Iohn the 22, there was founde (when hee was dead) by his heires, 25 thouſand thouſand crownes, that is, 250 tunne of gold. And of <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight (who was taken priſoner &amp; ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at the commandement of <hi>Philippus Pulcher,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King) wee finde it regiſtred, that all the kings of the world were not able to disburſe ſo much out of their treaſurie within the compaſſe of one yere, as was taken and caried out of the Popes palace: wherefore there haue alwaies beene ſome at all times, who both deteſted that in ſatiable hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and vncontented deſire, and gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines of riches, and alſo lotted not to enueigh againſt the ſame: hereupon <hi>Mantuan</hi> ſaith thus:</p>
            <q>
               <l>—venalia Romae.</l>
               <l>Templa, Sacerdotes, Altario, Sacra, Corona,</l>
               <l>Jgni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, thura, preces, Coelum eſt venale, Deuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>.</l>
            </q>
            <p>which is in Engliſh thus.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Churches and Prieſtes, Altars and Princes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>at</hi> Rome <hi>are to be ſolde.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Kingdomes and rites, incenſe and heauen.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>yea, God,</hi> Rome <hi>is ſo bolde.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14493:37"/>
And another thus.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Curia Romana non carpit ovem ſine lana</l>
               <l>Dantes exaudit, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dantibus oſtia claudit.</l>
            </q>
            <p>which may be thus tranſlated.</p>
            <q>
               <l>The Romiſh court doeth make no pay</l>
               <l>Of ſheepe that fleece doe want:</l>
               <l>No man can ſpeed vnleſſe he pray,</l>
               <l>Bring giftes and take our graunt.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And againe another ſpeaketh after this manner: The treaſure houſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall is like vnto the ſea, into which all flouds doe runne, and yet it doeth not ouerflowe: for euen ſo thouſand waightes of golde are brought into this out of diuers partes of the worlde, and yet it is not filled.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="85"/> Hee is alſo craftie, deceitfull, <note place="margin">His craftines and falſe dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</note> falſe, and giuen to lying: craftie hee is, for that hee blindeth trueth and falſhoode together: deceitfull and a lyar hee is, in that his feigned ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, to witte, when as hee entituleth his lordlineſſe with a name of ſeruice, (that is, when hee calleth himſelfe the ſeruant of ſeruants) vnder pretence of humilitie, according to the example
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14493:37"/>
of <hi>Gregorie</hi> the great, who for this ende called himſelfe the ſeruant of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God, that hee might giue his ſucceſſours a patterne of lowli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and yet in words and deede, hee proudely exalteth himſelfe aboue all kings and princes, deſiring to bee the lorde of lordes, as wee declared at large heretofore: in ſo much, that hee indeede retaineth the bare name and title, but vſurpeth a ſtatelineſſe, alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether diſagreeing from the title: ſo further in the fained donation of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> as is mentioned in <hi>Cap. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinus, diſt.</hi> 96. hee produceth a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged inſtrument of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> his deede of gift, in which hee affirmeth, that the citie of <hi>Rome,</hi> with <hi>Italie, Sicilie, Sardinia, Spaine, Germanie,</hi> and <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,</hi> were giuen vnto him by that Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour.</p>
            <p>Againe, he is taken in manifeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, in that hee ſometime af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, <note place="margin">His lying and contradictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s The deede of gift for his Iuriſdiction and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note> that the ſame deed of gift was made vnto <hi>Sylvester</hi> the Pope by <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> ſometime before <hi>Sylveſter</hi> by the ſame <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> ſometime by <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dovicus Pius</hi> ſonne to <hi>Charles</hi> the great,
<pb facs="tcp:14493:38"/>
               <hi>cap. Conſtantinus. diſt.</hi> 96. <hi>&amp; cano. futu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> 12. <hi>quaeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In that he ſaith, ſometime that <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> ſometime that Chriſt, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time that <hi>Peter,</hi> gaue vnto him that power and authoritie, as in the ſame place. <hi>cap. Constant. diſt.</hi> 96. <hi>&amp; cap. ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croſancta. diſt.</hi> 22. <hi>&amp;c. vnam ſanctam. extrav. de maiorit, &amp; obed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In that ſometime he auoucheth, that principalitie is graunted vnto him by <note place="margin">Primatie.</note> 
               <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> that he ſhould be the head ouer all Churches and Prieſtes: <hi>cap. Conſtantinus. diſt.</hi> 96. Sometime hee affirmeth, that no man is to be called the prince of the Prieſts, or high prieſt, or vniuerſall biſhop. <hi>Cap. multi diſt.</hi> 40. <hi>&amp; cap. primae ſedis, &amp; duobus. ce. ſeqq. diſt.</hi> 99. In that ſomtime he ſaith, that Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and eſpecially <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> are equall and alike, 2. <hi>q.</hi> 7. <hi>Can.</hi> 33. <hi>&amp; can.</hi> 37. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>can.</hi> 18. Sometime that both he preferreth <hi>Peter</hi> before the reſt of the Apoſtles, and aſcribeth the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie to him alone, <hi>&amp; cap. ſacroſancta. diſt.</hi> 22. and elſe where.</p>
            <p>In that hee ſaieth, that the election <note place="margin">Dignitie.</note> of the Pope ought to be made by the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14493:38"/>
conſent and approbation of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and that the Pope is in ſubiection to the Emperours lawes and ſtatutes, and that the Emperour excelleth him in temporalities, <hi>c.</hi> 22. &amp; 22. <hi>diſt.</hi> 63. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 9. &amp; 3. <hi>diſt.</hi> 10. &amp; 2. <hi>q.</hi> 7. <hi>can.</hi> 1. <hi>Nos ſi incompetenter,</hi> &amp; 25. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>ſat agendum,</hi> &amp; <hi>c. ſolitae de mai orit. &amp; obeà.</hi> Sometime he ſubiecteth the Emperour vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, aduanceth himſelfe aboue him, &amp; aboue all kings, &amp; exempteth himſelfe from all iudgement of men, as was ſaid before.</p>
            <p>In that hee ſometime denieth, that <note place="margin">Succeſſion.</note> ſucceſſion is ordinarie &amp; tyed to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine place, bringing this place out of <hi>Ierome:</hi> They are not the ſonnes of the ſaintes, who poſſeſſe the places of the ſaintes, but they which doe the workes of the ſaintes, &amp;c. <hi>c.</hi> 1, 3, &amp; 4. <hi>diſt.</hi> 40. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2. Sometime he auoucheth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, as <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>diſt.</hi> 40.</p>
            <p>In that ſomtime he wils, that prieſts &amp; biſhops ſhuld only be occupied in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <note place="margin">The matters in which hee dealeth.</note> ſpiritual, not te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral. <hi>diſt.</hi> 36. &amp; 38. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manding alſo, that he ſhuld be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his functio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who bereth both ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil &amp; Eccleſiaſtical magiſtracy, at one &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:14493:39"/>
the ſame time in <hi>Can. Ap. quos approbat, Can.</hi> 8. Sometime he chalengeth both the powers, and both the ſwordes vnto himſelfe and to his Biſhoppes, as was ſhewed heretofore.</p>
            <p>In that he graunteth ſometimes, yea commaundeth mariage vnto Prieſtes. <note place="margin">Mariage of Prieſtes.</note> 
               <hi>C. ſi quis docuerit. diſt.</hi> 28. <hi>&amp;C. quoniam Diſt.</hi> 31. <hi>&amp;C. ſi quis nuptias. dist.</hi> 3 Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times hee doth altogether forbid them mariage, as we ſhewed before.</p>
            <p>In that ſometime hee commandeth the entire and perfite vſe of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">Vſe of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament in both kinds.</note> of the ſupper of the Lord: excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating them alſo which otherwiſe ſhall doe. <hi>De Conſec. c. comperimus. diſt.</hi> 2. Sometimes hee forbiddeth the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to receiue the Cuppe. <hi>In Concil. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. ſeſſ.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>In that he willeth ſometime, that all <note place="margin">Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> ſhould communicate in the ſupper of the Lorde, that is, ſhould take, eate, and drinke, and doeth excommunicate them who doe otherwiſe. <hi>De conſecrat. c. per Acta diſt.</hi> 2. ſometimes hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barreth the Laity, and defendeth, that this is onely lawfull for the prieſts, <hi>vt inprivata Miſſa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:14493:39"/>
In that he ſaith, that the Pope is to be iudged of no man, vnleſſe he be founde <note place="margin">The Pope not to be iudged.</note> to erre from the faith. <hi>c. ſi papa. diſt.</hi> 40. Sometimes he ſaith, that the Pope <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corus</hi> is excommunicate, though hee hath not erred in the faith. <hi>Quaeſt.</hi> 2. <hi>Can. ſane profertur. verſ. item Romanoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Furthermore, in that hee maketh his <note place="margin">Promiſe breaking.</note> promiſe, but keepeth it not: ſaying, that promiſe is not to bee kept with here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, as <hi>in concil. Conſtant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In that he ſometime affirmeth, nowe <note place="margin">Of Pope Ioan</note> denieth verie impudently by the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites and others, that Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> the eight was a woman, &amp; that the chaire of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirie, (by which the Pope created is <note place="margin">Sedes teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culatrix.</note> pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced capable or vncapable) was vſed ſince that time, which is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vnto ſo many euident teſtimonies of Hyſtoriographers, (and euen of them who haue bene Papiſts) both olde and newe: as <hi>Marianus Scotus, Anno</hi> 1080 orthereabout, <hi>Sigebert</hi> the Monke. <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1110. <hi>Martinus</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Polonus, Anno</hi> 1278. <hi>Martinus Minorit. Anno</hi> 1350. <hi>Franciſcus Petrarch, Anno</hi> 1370. <hi>Iohannes Bocatius,</hi> who liued at the ſame time. <hi>Raphael <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>olateran. Anno</hi> 1490
<pb facs="tcp:14493:40"/>
or there abouts. Further, of <hi>Platina, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellicus, Aeneid.</hi> 9. <hi>Tritem. in hiſt. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſter. Hirſaugienſis. Iohan. Stella</hi> of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice, Nauclerus, Albertus, Crantzius,</hi> and the authour of <hi>Faſciculus Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Baptiſta, Mantuan, Caelius Rhodig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> and of others, who doe beare witneſſe of this feminine or woman Pope, whoſe entire recordes are not long ſince put forth into print.</p>
            <p>In that he hath not onely put coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeits in ſtead of the right bookes (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in the Monuments of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) but doeth alſo corrupt, cancell, chop and change them, as may appeare both in that hee corrupteth the Latine Bible, and obſtinately defendeth the corruptions: which do many times diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agree from the Hebrewe and Greeke copies: and in that he now altereth and changeth the writings of the fathers, which being thus made vnperfect, hee ſetteth foorth, and alledgeth them <hi>as they are ſet forth</hi> according to theſe Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Example wherof (to omit others, which might plentifully be brought in this place, and haue bene alſo alledged by others heretofore) wee haue affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14493:40"/>
vnto vs by <hi>Iohn Gibbons</hi> an Engliſh Ieſuite doctour of diuinitie, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour at <hi>Triens, in diſputatione de ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis. Theſ.</hi> 207. alledging a place out of <hi>Auguſtine, Lib.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 27. <hi>de civitate Dei.</hi> for his owne purpoſe, but as it ſeemeth out of an imperfect and counterfeit copie: in this manner. <hi>Wee appoint Churches, and orders of Prieſtes, and holy rites, and ſacrifices vnto the martyrs, not for that they be good, but becauſe their God is ours, &amp;c.</hi> Whereas other editions are thus. <hi>Yet doe not wee appoint temples, orders of Prieſtes, holy rites, and ſacrifices vnto the ſaintes, &amp;c.</hi> And the ſcope and drift of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> will not admit of that ſenſe which the Ieſuite woulde haue: but doeth neceſſarily require this which is all in all our Copies.</p>
            <p>Further, in that hee feigneth many reliques of the ſaintes, which neither are nor poſſibly can be true, vnleſſe we would graunt that there be many bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, many heades, many armes, of one ſaint or holie man. For if ſo bee that all the reliques of the Saintes
<pb facs="tcp:14493:41"/>
were brought together, the bodies of the ſaintes would not be onely verie vaſte for their quantitie of huge big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and verie monſtrous for the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the members: but alſo often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times there woulde bee more bodies then one of one and the ſame Saint.</p>
            <p>In that hee counterfaiteth miracles, which neither are, nor haue beene wrought, as was ſhewed before.</p>
            <p>In that hee pretendeth the name of Chriſt &amp; the ſaluation of the Church: But indeede doeth ſeeke his owne ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and commoditie. For he calleth them the Riches of the Church, and Patrimonie of Chriſt. But did Chriſt poſſeſſe any ſuch things? Thou beareſt the name and title of Biſhops, but alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether voide of the ſubſtance. Thou heareſt the name of Patriarkes, Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendentes, Abbats: but if thou take away the outwarde viſard and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, what will remaine? Thou heareſt the names of the Fraternities: and they are ſchiſmes or diuiſions. Thou heareſt of the orders and contemplatiue life: what is it but confuſion and ſenſeleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? Thou heareſt of continencie:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14493:41"/>
and it is nothing but riotouſneſſe. Thou heareſt of the pouertie, eſpecially of the Monkes, and what is it but delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes? Thou heareſt of chaſtitie and ſingle life, and what is this but filthie lecherie? Thou heareſt of humilitie, and it is pride and arrogancie. Finally thou ſeeſt the ſheepes skinne, but there is a wolfe lurking within it. For hee indeed profeſſeth humilitie, but exalteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe aboue all others: hee voweth cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie, but vſeth adulterie: yea and more is further from all honeſtie: no man (as it is full well knowne vnto all men) doth more defile himſelfe with all kinde of villanie: hee celebrateth a feaſt, and yet he playeth the glutton in the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="86"/> Againe, hee is cruell, as thoſe terrible excommunications and edicts do ſhew, which <note place="margin">His crueltie.</note> he maketh againſt Emperors, kings, &amp; others: as do alſo his factions, his warres, his butcherly maſſacres, with the perſecutions and moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme torments of the faithfull: which are in truth more then I am able to rehearſe in any ſhort ſpace. For how many factions, warres, &amp; maſſacres hath the Pope of Rome cauſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſtian princes, in all partes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom within theſe 500 yeres, for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance &amp; encreaſe of his power? How much blood hath he ſhed? when as he in the meane
<pb facs="tcp:14493:42"/>
ſeaſon like to a Fencer hauing ſet others togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the eares, is a beholder of theſe bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſports: Or as another <hi>Nero,</hi> beholding in his turret the citie ſet on fire, which himſelfe had fired, doth feede and pleaſe his mind, and delight his eies with ſuch a hidious and pitiful ſpectacle. What miſchiefe did he work in that voyage to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> for the recouerie of the ſepulchre of the Lorde, the citie <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and the holy lande? which was firſt begun by <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie</hi> the 8: one, who was more cruell and abominable then <hi>Nero</hi> himſelfe: and after pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted by <hi>Vrbanus,</hi> the deare and moſt neare friend which <hi>Gregorie</hi> had: wherein the Weſt fought againſt the Eaſt verie dangerouſlie, &amp; the Chriſtian ſouldiers ſo vſed the matter by ſpoiling &amp; killing Chriſtians, Iewes, &amp; others, &amp; by committing other outrages, that all the warres which were made by the Romanes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gentiles, may (in compariſon of that) bee called Chriſtian, godly, and holy.</p>
            <p>Howe madly and furiouſly haue the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter popes raged together, euen that they might diſpatch one another, onely to ſerue their owne ambition? To conclude, how many and how great perſecutions hath the Pope cauſed within this 60 yeeres? what torments hath he inflicted vpon men faithfull, and holy, whome he proclaimed as heretiques, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in France, and the low Countries. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that he is cruell, he doeth perſecute the ſaintes, but he worſhippeth them when they be placed in heauen. For this is the propertie
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14493:42"/>
of a bloody and cruell man, to iniurie thoſe which are his equals, or them who are his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours &amp; whom he may hurt: but as for them who are his betters, &amp; whom he can not hurt, but feareth leſt himſelfe be hurt by them, theſe he reuerenceth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="87"/> He alſo appeared by little &amp; litle by the <note place="margin">His appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note> craft of the deuill, which mingleth truth and falſhood together, which is a cunning coze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and ſophiſticall ſubtilty. For a lie is weake of it ſelfe &amp; can not ſtand: therfore theſe coze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning mates do vnderprop their lies with ſuch propoſitions &amp; aſſertions, as be either true, or els haue a ſhew of trueth. Therfore ſathan by litle &amp; litle brought in the corruptions of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine &amp; maners, &amp; confirmed them more and more by ſophiſtrie &amp; hypocriſie, till at length this kingdome did fully appeare.</p>
            <p>Hee alſo hath bin extant ſince the diuiſion <note place="margin">His time.</note> &amp; ouerthrow of the Romane Monarchie, and ſince the expiring &amp; date of thoſe 666 yeeres: that is ſince the death of Mauritius the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour: when the Emperour Phocas (who ſlewe his father) made this decree, that the Church of Rome ſhould be head ouer all other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and that the Biſhop of Rome (who then was <hi>Boniface</hi> the third) ſhould be head ouer all Biſhops, &amp; be the Catholique and general Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop. And alway ſince, eſpecially ſince the time of <hi>Charles</hi> the great, hee hath gotten ſtrength and growne greater and greater.</p>
            <p>He appeared in the temple of God. that is, in the Churches, and there he ſtill ſitteth and <note place="margin">His place.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:14493:43"/>
ruleth, feigning that hee is the Vicar of Chriſt and the ſucceſſour of <hi>Peter:</hi> for there was the true Church where the Pope of Rome firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared as Antichriſt, and afterward there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained the name, the title, &amp; the print of the Church, there was the bible, that is, the booke of the Prophets &amp; Apoſtles, there remained the true doctrine concerning God, concerning the trinitie of the deuine perſons, &amp; concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the perſon of Chriſt, there remained bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme together with the creed of the Apoſtles: and though the Popedome was not then, no more then in trueth it is now the Church, yet the Church was, and did as it were, lie hid in the Papacie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="90"/> He ſitteth at Rome betwixt two ſeas, <hi>Tyrrhenum</hi> &amp; <hi>Adriaticum,</hi> for here is the ſeate of the Pope, wherein oftentimes, (for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the place is changed) he dwelleth bodily.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="91"/> He is diſcouered in theſe laſt daies of the world, firſt by <hi>Iohn Hus,</hi> ſecondly by <hi>Martin Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the pope.</note> &amp; other excellent men, whom God raiſed vp, who hauing found out Antichriſt euen in the time of his marchandiſe, and as we ſay, with the manner, haue put him to ſhame, by ſhewing his impietie and indeauour againſt Chriſt, and haue kindled the light of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell in all places, eſpecially in <hi>Germany</hi> though the Pope &amp; other the Lords of Chriſtendom, being vtterly againſt it, haue threatened ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, puniſhments, warres and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe: who would not ſuffer the religion (which had continued ſo many ages) to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14493:43"/>
be ouerthrowen, to the great trouble &amp; deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of all Europe. For ſo ſoone as men which were not giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto pleaſures (as Epicures are) did ſee but a ſpark of light ſhining vnto them, they being verie much grieued with that dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; ſeruitude (wherewith they had beene ſo manie yeres oppreſſed) and being intiſed with the beautie &amp; ſweetnes of trueth, they ioyned themſelues vnto the ſincere teachers of truth, not hauing regard of other matters whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. By which meanes, the puritie of doctrine was euerie where propagated &amp; ſpred abroad, the Churches were eſtabliſhed &amp; reſtored vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their former beautie, firſt in <hi>Germanie, Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerland,</hi> then in <hi>England, Scotland, France, Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Denmarke,</hi> &amp; other prouinces. And though that vnluckie contention concerning the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lorde, did ſtraightwaie beginne, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the preachers of the Goſpell, euen in the beginning thereof, and continueth alſo vnto this day (Satan endeauouring thereby to hinder and ſtaie the cauſe of the goſpell) yet we are to thinke thus: Firſt, that Sathan hath not now begun, but hath practiſed long agoe, to ſet at variance the holy ſeruants of God, as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> and againe the ſame <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> with others more: ſecondlie, that as concerning the foundation of the doctrine &amp; religion of Chriſt, &amp; all things neceſſarie vnto ſaluation, there hath alwaies bene and ſtill is, an agreement betwixt thoſe men, who are the reſtorers of this goſpell which now beginneth to take life againe. For hauing conſuted merit,
<pb facs="tcp:14493:44"/>
and truſt repoſed in workes wherwith miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men were bewitched in time of Poperie, both parties agreed, that our whole ſaluation conſiſteth in the merites of Chriſt: onely the difference is in the ſupper of the Lorde, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the corporall preſence, and the bodily eating, and that the ſame is common vnto the godlie and the wicked (as the one part defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth) and ſo not neceſſarie vnto ſaluation. Thirdly, it is no great maruell, if in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of reformation, &amp; as it were, in the daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the day, all things were not at the firſt well conſidered: for it can ſcarſely be declared what a deep gulfe of ignorance was in popery, and what an horrible darkeneſſe by reaſon of errours. And doubtleſſe, it was a verie great miracle wrought by God, that thoſe firſt do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours of the goſpell could ariſe from thence, in ſo litle and ſhort ſpace. And although the Ieſuites which are lately ſprong vp, indeauour to heale this wounde of Antichriſt, yet ſhall they neuer fullie cure the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="93"/> Finally, he ſhalbe deſtroied in the laſt daie of Chriſt, when he returneth to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <note place="margin">The deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Pope.</note> and ſhalbe caſt into the lake of fire and brimſtone according vnto the prophecie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore declared. In the meane ſeaſon, we are pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently to beare that perſecution wherwith he oppreſſeth vs, and we muſt not for his tyranie leaue or forſake the profeſſion of the truth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="94"/> Which things ſith they are all true, it followeth, that the Pope ſince the death of <note place="margin">The concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
               <hi>Gregorie</hi> the great, and the murther of <hi>Mauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:14493:44"/>
the Emperour, is that Antichriſt whome we haue before deſcribed out of the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the Prophets and Apoſtles. For whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they conſider the doctrine or behold the maners and actions of the Pope, they all agree vnto theſe prophecies: and though heretofore there were controuerſie touching primacie, &amp; there were diuers errours (and they not ſmall) concerning the doctrine: yet afterwarde, the deſire of bearingſway, did more breake forth, Idolatrie, and impietie was encreaſed, and at the length <hi>Boniface</hi> the third obtained of <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas</hi> the Emperour, that whoſoeuer ſhould be the Biſhop of auncient Rome, ſhould alſo bee eſteemed as vniuerſall Biſhop, that Rome ſhoulde be accounted the heade of all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and that this priuiledge might be tradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to their ſucceſſours: and within a while after, others of them chalenged both the ſwords for themſelues, eſtabliſhed this by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, that the Maſſe was a ſacrifice propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie for the liuing and the dead: and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, they made Rome a ſanctuarie for Idols.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="95"/> Hitherto wee haue ſhewed, who this great Antichriſt is. But as in the former que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, the Papiſtes doe differ from vs, what Antichriſt ſhould be, ſo likewiſe in this latter, who Antichriſt ſhould be: for as they doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine Antichriſt otherwiſe then we, ſo doe they vtterly denie that the Pope of Rome is that Antichriſt. For the Pope with his adherents (now playing the part of Antichriſt) doeth feigne another Antichriſt, and teacheth that
<pb facs="tcp:14493:45"/>
he is yet to come, leaſt he himſelfe ſhould bee thought to be the Antichriſt indeed. Of whoſe opinion and their reaſons we will ſay more as occaſion ſhall be offered: for the manner of our poſitions will not now permit vs to ſpeake of the ſame.</p>
            <p>God the Father graunt for our Lorde Ieſus Chriſtes ſake, that men may learne to knowe and to abhorre that Antichriſt, the moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous enemie of Chriſt and the Church: and may likewiſe learne more and more to loue and worſhip Chriſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:14493:45"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
