<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sir Gregory Nonsence his newes from no place Written on purpose, with much study to no end, plentifully stored with want of wit, learning, iudgement, rime and reason, and may seeme very fitly for the vnderstanding of nobody. Toyte, Puncton, Ghemorah, Molushque, Kaycapepson. This is the worke of the authors, without borrowing or stealing from others. By Iohn Taylor.</title>
            <author>Taylor, John, 1580-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-01">2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13499</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23795</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101248</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837064</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837064</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1370</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A13499)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1370)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 977:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sir Gregory Nonsence his newes from no place Written on purpose, with much study to no end, plentifully stored with want of wit, learning, iudgement, rime and reason, and may seeme very fitly for the vnderstanding of nobody. Toyte, Puncton, Ghemorah, Molushque, Kaycapepson. This is the worke of the authors, without borrowing or stealing from others. By Iohn Taylor.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, John, 1580-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By N[icholas] O[kes]] and are to bee sold betweene Charing-Crosse, and Algate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed in London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700 [i.e. 1622]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's initials and actual publication date appear in colophon; printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B (-A1, B8).</note>
                  <note>Margins cropped, affecting imprint date.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-08</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1370:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1370:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>SIR</hi>
Gregory Nonsence
His Newes from no place.</p>
            <p>Written on purpose, with much study to
no end, plentifully stored with want of
wit, learning, Iudgement, Rime and
Reason, and may seeme very fitly
for the vnderstanding of
Nobody.</p>
            <p>Toyte, Puncton, Ghemorah, Molushque,
Kaycapepson.</p>
            <p>This is the worke of the Authors, without bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing
or stealing from others.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Iohn Taylor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in <hi>London,</hi> and are to bee sold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<hi>Charing-Crosse,</hi> and <hi>Algate.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1370:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1370:2"/>
            <head>To the (Sir Reuerence) Rich
Worshipped, Master Trim Tram Senceles,
great Image of Authority and Hedgborough
of the famous City of Goteham, and to the rest of
that admired and vnmatchable Senate, with
their Corruptions and Families.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost <hi>Honorificicabilitudinitatibus,</hi>
I hauing studied the seuen Lub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly
Sciences (being nine by
computation) out of which
I gathered three coniunctions
foure mile Asse-vnder, which with much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,
and great ease, to little or no purpose,
I haue Noddicated to your gray graue and
grauelled Prate ection. I doubt not but I
might haue had a Patrone neerer hand, as the
Deane of Dunstable, or the Beadle of Layton
Buzzard, but that I know the p<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rase, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod
<pb facs="tcp:1370:3"/>
and Stile, is not for euery mans vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing,
no my most renowned Pythagor-Asses,
for you this Hogshead of inuention
was brewed and broched, for I am ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
perswaded that your wisedome, can pick as
much matter out of this Booke in one day as
both the Vniuersities can in twelue moneths,
and thirteene Moones, with sixe times foure
yeeres to boot. I know your bounties too ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
for as old mother <hi>Baly</hi> said, the wit of
man was much when she saw a dog muzzled.<note place="margin">I haue Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story for this our of an Illite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate well printed Poem in Prose, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, the wise men of Gotha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of much antiquity.</note>
Euery man is not borne to make a Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
for the Cuckoo; to send a Trifoote
home alone, to driue sheepe before they haue
them, or to Trundle Cheeses down a hill. So
saluting you with more prespect then the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior
of <hi>Loo,</hi> did the Queenes Ape, I take leaue
to leaue you, and rest yours to bid you wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come,
if you came within a mile of my house
to stay all night.</p>
            <signed>Yours Rolihayton.</signed>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1370:3"/>
            <head>To Nobody.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Vpon a Christmas Euen, som what
night Easter, anon after Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sontide,
walking in a Coach from
London to Lambeth by water, I o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertooke
a man that met me in the
morning before sunne set, the wind being in <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricorne,</hi>
the Signe <hi>Southwest,</hi> with silence I
demanded many questions of him, and hee with
much pensiuenesse did answere me merrily to the
full, with such ample and empty replications, that
both our vnderstandings being equally satisfied,
we contentiously agreed to finish and prosecute the
narration of the vnknowne Knight Sir <hi>Gregory
Nonsence,</hi> so sitting downe vpon our shoulders,
resting vneasily on a banke of Sicamores vnder a
Tree of odoriferous and contagious Camomile,
after three sighs, smilingly vttered in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew
Character, two grones from the Chaldean
Dialact, fiue sobs from the Arabian Sinquapace,
sixe dumps from Germane Idiome, nine Moodes
<pb facs="tcp:1370:4"/>
of Melancholly from the Italian tongue, with one
hub hub from the Hiberbian outcry. And last he
laughed in the Cambrian tongue, and beganne to
declare in the Vtopian speech, what I haue heere
with most diligent negligence translated into the
English Language, in which if the Printer hath
placed any line, letter or sillable, whereby this
large volume may bee made guilty to bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood
by any man, I would haue the Reader not to
impute the fault to the Author, for it was farre
from his purpose to write to any purpose, so ending
at the beginning, I say as it is applawsfully writ|
ten and commended to posterity in the Midsom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
nights dreame. If we offend, it is with our
good will, we came with no intent, but to offend,
and shew our simple skill.</p>
            <signed>Rolihayton.</signed>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_authors">
            <pb facs="tcp:1370:4"/>
            <head>The names of such Authors Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabetically
recited as are simply
mintioned in this Worke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>A Madis de Gaul.</item>
               <item>Archy Arms.</item>
               <item>Beuis of Hampton.</item>
               <item>Boe to a Goose.</item>
               <item>Charing Crosse.</item>
               <item>Coakley.</item>
               <item>Dunsmore Cow.</item>
               <item>Dauy Wager.</item>
               <item>Euanwich Muffe.</item>
               <item>Frier and the Boy.</item>
               <item>Fubs his Trauels.</item>
               <item>Garagantua.</item>
               <item>Gammon of Westphallia.</item>
               <item>Grigs Granam.</item>
               <item>Hundred merry tales.</item>
               <item>Huon of Burdeux.</item>
               <item>Iacke Drum.</item>
               <item>Knight of the Sunne.</item>
               <item>Knaue of Diamonds.</item>
               <item>Lanum.</item>
               <item>Long Meg.</item>
               <item>Mad Mawdlin.</item>
               <item>No body.</item>
               <item>Otoole.</item>
               <item>Proofes of OOOO.</item>
               <item>Quinborough Osters.</item>
               <item>Ready mony.</item>
               <item>Shooters Hill.</item>
               <item>Singer.</item>
               <item>Sir Thomas Parsons.</item>
               <item>Tarleton.</item>
               <item>Tom Derry.</item>
               <item>Tom Thumbe.</item>
               <item>Vnguentum Album.</item>
               <item>Will Summers.</item>
               <item>Wit whither wilt thou.</item>
               <item>Woodcocke of our side.</item>
               <item>Xampelloes Quiblines.</item>
               <item>Yard of Ale.</item>
               <item>Zany on tumbling.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:1370:5"/>
            <head>Faults escaped in the Printing,
which a wise Reader may mend
when he sees them.</head>
            <p>IN the 25. page. 44. line, for <unclear>a</unclear> 
               <hi>Friers mouth</hi> read a <hi>Pudding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the 170. page 53. line, for a <hi>foole</hi> read a <hi>Bable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 90. page, 27. line, for <hi>friend</hi> read <hi>rare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 30. page 6. line 78. for a <hi>Whore</hi> read a <hi>Bridewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 100. pace, line 40. for a <hi>Bawd</hi> reade a <hi>Cart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 12. page 11. line, for <hi>noone</hi> read <hi>dinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 16. first, and all the Pages following for <hi>Tobacco</hi> read a
<hi>Witch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 40. page, and 80. line, for a <hi>Calues head</hi> read <hi>Bacon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 37. page, and 1. line, for <hi>vice</hi> read <hi>plenty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 000. page, and 3. line for <hi>money</hi> read <hi>scarce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the last Page, for <hi>conscience,</hi> read <hi>none.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In euery page for <hi>sence</hi> read <hi>nonsence.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poems">
            <pb facs="tcp:1370:5"/>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Sir Gregory Nonsence his newes
from no place.</head>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was in Iune the eight and thirtieth day,</l>
               <l>That I imbarked was on highgate Hill,</l>
               <l>After discourteous friendly taking leaue:</l>
               <l>Of my young Father <hi>Madge</hi> and Mother <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Wind did ebbe, the tide flou'd North South-east,</l>
               <l>We hoist our Sailes of Colloquintida,</l>
               <l>And after 13. dayes and 17. nights,</l>
               <l>(VVith certaine Hiroglyphicke houres to boote)</l>
               <l>We with tempestuous calmes, and friendly stormes,</l>
               <l>Split our maine top-mast, close below the keele.</l>
               <l>But I with a dull quick congruity,</l>
               <l>Tooke 19. ounces of the Westerne winde,</l>
               <l>And with the pith of the pole Artichocke,</l>
               <l>Saild by the flaming Coast of Trapezond,</l>
               <l>There in a Fort of melting Adamant,</l>
               <l>Arm'd in a Crimson Robe, as blacke as Iet,</l>
               <l>I saw <hi>Alcides</hi> with a Spiders thred,</l>
               <l>Lead <hi>Serberus</hi> to the Proponticke Sea,</l>
               <l>Then cutting further through the marble Maine,</l>
               <l>'Mongst flying Buls<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and 4. leg'd Turkicocks,</l>
               <l>A dumbe faire spoken, welfac'd aged youth,</l>
               <l>Sent to me from the stout Stimphalides,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1370:6"/>
With tonguelesse silence thus beganne his speech.</l>
               <l>Illustrious flapiack, to thy hungry doome,</l>
               <l>Low as the ground I eleuate my cause,</l>
               <l>As I vpon a Gnat was riding late,</l>
               <l>In quest to parley with the Pleiades,</l>
               <l>I saw the Duke of Hounsditch gaping close,</l>
               <l>In a greene Arbour made of yellow starch,</l>
               <l>Betwixt two Brokers howling Madrigales,</l>
               <l>A Banquet was serued in of Lampraies bones,</l>
               <l>Well pickel'd in the Tarbox of old time,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Demogorgon</hi> saild to <hi>Islington;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which I perceiuing with nine chads of steele,</l>
               <l>Straight flew vnto the coast of Pimlico.</l>
               <l>'Tinforme great <hi>Prester Iohn,</hi> and the <hi>Mogull,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What exlent Oysters were at <hi>Billingsgate.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Mogull</hi> (all enraged with these newes,</l>
               <l>Sent a black snaile post to <hi>Tartaria.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To tell the Irishmen in <hi>Saxony,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The dismall downefall of old Charing Crosse.</l>
               <l>With that <unclear>nine</unclear> butter Firkins in a flame,</l>
               <l>Did coldly rise to Arbitrate the cause:</l>
               <l>Guessing by the Sinderesis of wapping,</l>
               <l>Saint <hi>Thomas Watrings</hi> is most ominous,</l>
               <l>For though an Andiron, and a paire of Tongs,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1370:6"/>
May both haue breeding from one teeming wombe,</l>
               <l>Yet by the Calculation of Pickt-hatch,</l>
               <l>Milke must not be so deere as Muskadell.</l>
               <l>First shall Melpomene in Cobweb Lawne.</l>
               <l>Adorne great <hi>Memphis</hi> in a Mussell boate,</l>
               <l>And all the Muses clad in Robes of Ayre,</l>
               <l>Shall dance Leuoltoes with a Whirligig,</l>
               <l>Faire <hi>Pluto</hi> shall descend from Brazen dis,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Polipheamus</hi> keepe a Seamsters shop,</l>
               <l>The Ile of <hi>Wight</hi> shall like a diue dapper,</l>
               <l>Deuoure the Egyptian proud <hi>Piramides,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whilst <hi>Cassia Fistula</hi> shall gurmundize,</l>
               <l>Vpon the flesh and bloud of Croydon cole dust,</l>
               <l>Then on the Bankes of Shoreditch shall be seene,</l>
               <l>What 'tis to serue the great Vtopian Queene.</l>
               <l>This fearefull period with great ioyfull care,</l>
               <l>Was heard with acclamations, and in fine,</l>
               <l>The whilst a lad of aged Nestors yeeres,</l>
               <l>Stood sitting in a Throne of massy yeast,</l>
               <l>(Not speaking any word gaue this reply.</l>
               <l>Most conscript Vmpire in this various <unclear>Orbe</unclear>.</l>
               <l>I saw the Ceaders of old <hi>Lebanon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Read a sad Lecture vnto <hi>Clapham</hi> heath,</l>
               <l>At which time a strange vision did appeare,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1370:7"/>
His head was Buckrum, and his eyes were sedge,</l>
               <l>His armes were blew botiles, his teeth were straw,</l>
               <l>His legges were nine well squard Tobacco Pipes,</l>
               <l>Cloath'd in a garment all of Dolphins egges,</l>
               <l>Then with a voyce erected to the ground,</l>
               <l>Lifting aloft his hands vnto his feete,</l>
               <l>He thus beganne, cease friendly cutting throtes,</l>
               <l>Clamor the promulgation of your tongues,</l>
               <l>And yeeld to Demagorgons pollicy.</l>
               <l>Stop the refulgent method of your moodes,</l>
               <l>For should you liue old <hi>Paphlagonias</hi> yeeres,</l>
               <l>And with <hi>Sardanapalus</hi> match in vertue.</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Atropos</hi> will with a Marigold,</l>
               <l>Runne through the Mountaines of the Caspian Sea,</l>
               <l>When you shall see aboue you, and beneath</l>
               <l>That nothing kils a man so soone as death.</l>
               <l>This period finished, ere it was begunne,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aquarius</hi> ioyn'd with <hi>Pisces,</hi> in firme league,</l>
               <l>With Reasons and vindictiue Arguments,</l>
               <l>That pulueriz'd the King of Diamonds,</l>
               <l>And with a diogoricall relap's,</l>
               <l>Squeaz'd through the Sinders of a Butterflye,</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Oboron</hi> was mounted on a Waspe,</l>
               <l>To signifie this newes at Dunstable.</l>
               <l>The Weather-cock at Pancrage in a fume,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1370:7"/>
With Patience much distracted hearing this,</l>
               <l>Repli'd thus briefely without feare or wit,</l>
               <l>What madnesse doth thy Pericranion seaze,</l>
               <l>Beyond the Dragons taile A<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tophilax.</l>
               <l>Think'st thou a Wolfe thrust through a sheep skin gl<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e,</l>
               <l>Can make me take this Goblin for a Lambe:</l>
               <l>Or that a Crodadile in Barly broth,</l>
               <l>Is not a dish to feast don Belzebub,</l>
               <l>Giue me a Medler in a field of blue,</l>
               <l>Wrapt vp stigmatically in a dreame,</l>
               <l>And I will send him to the gates of Dis,</l>
               <l>To cause him fetch a sword of massie Chalke,</l>
               <l>With which he wan the fatall Theban field<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>From Romes great mitred Matropolitan.</l>
               <l>Much was the quoile this brauing answere made,</l>
               <l>When presently a German Coniurer,</l>
               <l>Did ope a learned Booke of Palmistry,</l>
               <l>Cram'd full of mentall reseruations:</l>
               <l>The which beginning with a loud low voyce,</l>
               <l>With affable and kind discourtesie,</l>
               <l>He spake what no man heard or vnderstood,</l>
               <l>Words tending vnto this or no respect,</l>
               <l>Spawne of a Tortoyse hold thy silent noyse,</l>
               <l>For when the great Leuiathan of Trumps,</l>
               <l>Shall make a breach in <hi>Sinons</hi> Tennis Court.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1370:8"/>
Then shall the pigmey mighty <hi>Hercules,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Skip like a Wildernesse in Woodstreet Counter.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Taurus</hi> shall in league with <hi>Hanniball,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Draw <hi>Bacchus</hi> dry, whilst <hi>
                     <unclear>Boreus</unclear>
                  </hi> in a <unclear>heate</unclear>,</l>
               <l>In<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>op'd, in a Gowne of Isicles:</l>
               <l>With much discretion and great want of wit,</l>
               <l>Leaue all as wisely as it was at first,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>fed much how those things could be done<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>When straite a water Tankerd answer'd me,</l>
               <l>That it was made with a Parenthesis,</l>
               <l>With thirteene yards of Kersie and a <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Made of fine flaxe which grew on <unclear>Goodwin</unclear> sands,</l>
               <l>Whereby we all perceiu'd the Hernshawes breed,</l>
               <l>Being trusted with a charitable doome,</l>
               <l>Was neere Bunhill, when staite I might descry,</l>
               <l>the Quintesence of Grubstreete, well disti<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Through Cripplegate in a contagioas Map.</l>
               <l>Bright <hi>Phaeton</hi> all angry at the sight,</l>
               <l>Snatch't a large Wool-packe from a Pismires mouth.</l>
               <l>And in a Taylors Thimble boil'd a Cabbage.</l>
               <l>Then all the standers by, most Reueterend, Rude,</l>
               <l>Iudg'd that the case was most obscure and cleere,</l>
               <l>And that three salt Enuigmates well appli'd,</l>
               <l>With fourescore Pipers, and <hi>Arions</hi> Harpe,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1370:8"/>
Might catch <hi>Garagantua</hi> through an augor-hole,</l>
               <l>And twas no doubt but mulley <hi>Mahamet,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Would make a quaffing bole of <hi>Gorgons</hi> skull,</l>
               <l>Whilst gormundizing <hi>Tantalus</hi> would weepe,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Polipheme</hi> should kisse <hi>Auroraes</hi> lips,</l>
               <l>Triformed <hi>Cinthis</hi> in a sinkefoile shape,</l>
               <l>Met with the Dogstarre on Saint <hi>Dauids</hi> day,</l>
               <l>But sad <unclear>Grimalkin</unclear> mumbling vp the Alpes,</l>
               <l>Made fifteene fustian fumes of Pasticrust.</l>
               <l>This was no sooner knowne at <hi>Amsterdam,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But with an Ethiopian Argosey,</l>
               <l>Man'd with <unclear>Flap-dragons</unclear>, drinking vp sifreeze,</l>
               <l>They past the purple gulfe of Basingstoke.</l>
               <l>This being finisht, scarce to any end,</l>
               <l>A full od number of iust sixteene dogs,</l>
               <l>Drencht in a sulpher flame of scalding Ice,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ung the Besonian W<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> pooles of <hi>Argeire,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Mixt with <unclear>pragmaticall</unclear> potato Pies,</l>
               <l>
                  <unclear>With</unclear> that I turn'd mine eares to see these things,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd on a Christall wall of Scarlet dye,</l>
               <l>with mine eyes began to heare and note,</l>
               <l>
                  <unclear>What</unclear> these succeding Verses might portend,</l>
               <l>
                  <unclear>Which</unclear> furiously an Annabaptist squeak'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he audieace <unclear>deaflly</unclear> listning all the while.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:1370:9"/>
               <head>A most learned-Lye, and Illite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
Oration, in lame galloping Rime,
fustianly pronounced by Nimshag, a Gimno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophicall
Phoolosopher, in the presence of Achit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophell
Smel-smocke, Annani-Asse Aretine, Iscariot
Nabal, Fransiscus Ra-viliaco, Garnetto Iebusito, Guido
Salpetro Fauexit Powderio, and many other graue
Senators of Limbo. Translated out of the vulgar Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage,
of Terra Incognita, and is as materiall as
any part of the Booke, the meaning where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
a blind man may see without Spectacles
as well at midn<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ght, as at
noone day.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe Story of <hi>Ricardo,</hi> and of <hi>Bindo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Appear'd like <hi>Nylus,</hi> peeping through a Windo:</l>
                  <l>Which put the wandring Iew in much amazement,</l>
                  <l>In seeing such a voyce without the Cazement.</l>
                  <l>When loe a Bull (long nourish'd in <hi>Cocitus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With sulphure hornes, sent by the Emp'rour <hi>Titus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ask'd a stigmatike <hi>Paraclesian</hi> question,</l>
                  <l>If <hi>Alexander</hi> euer lou'd <hi>Ephestion.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I seeing each to other were much aduerse,</l>
                  <l>In mirth and sport set downe their minds in sad verse,</l>
                  <l>Which as my braines with care haue coin'd &amp; minted</l>
                  <l>With plenteous want of iudgement here tis printed,</l>
                  <l>But if <hi>Grimalkine</hi> take my line in dudgion,</l>
                  <l>The case is plaine, I pray good Readers iudge ye on,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:1370:9"/>
That <hi>Esop</hi> that old fabulisticke <hi>Phrigian,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From the Nocturnall floud, or lake cal'd <hi>Stigian,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Came to the Court at <hi>Creete,</hi> clad like a Legate,</l>
                  <l>The Porter kindly to him open'd the-Gate,</l>
                  <l>He past through <hi>Plutoes</hi> Hall in Hell most horrid,</l>
                  <l>Where gnashing cold mixt with combustious torid,</l>
                  <l>Where all things that are good, and goodnes wanted,</l>
                  <l>Where plants of mans perdition still are planted,</l>
                  <l>Where Ghosts and Goblins all in sulphure suted,</l>
                  <l>And all the fiends like Cuckolds were cornuted.</l>
                  <l>At last he audience got in <hi>Plutoes</hi> presence,</l>
                  <l>And of his whole Embassage this was the-sence.</l>
                  <l>To thee Tartarian Monarch now my Rime-is,</l>
                  <l>And therefore marke my Prologue, or <hi>Imprimis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thou that in <hi>Limbo</hi> art as 'twere <hi>Rex Regnant,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Beare with my wit, which is not sharpe or pregnant,</l>
                  <l>I come from Houndsditch, Long-lane, &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Bridewel,</l>
                  <l>Where all that haue liu'd ill, haue all not dide well,</l>
                  <l>Where as the Vices shew like Vertues Cardinall,</l>
                  <l>Where's mony store, and conscience very hard in all,</l>
                  <l>Through thy protection they are monstrous Thriuers,</l>
                  <l>Not like the Dutchmen in base Doytes and Stiuers,</l>
                  <l>For there you may see many a greedy grout-head,</l>
                  <l>Without or wit, or sence, almost without-head,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:1370:10"/>
Held and esteem'd a man whose zeale is feruent,</l>
                  <l>And makes a shew as he were not your seruant.</l>
                  <l>To tell this newes I came from many a mile hence,</l>
                  <l>For we do know ther's ods 'twixt talke and silence,</l>
                  <l>With that the smug-fac'd <hi>Pluto</hi> shooke his vestment,</l>
                  <l>Deepe ruminating what the weighty Iest ment,</l>
                  <l>Calling to mind old <hi>Dodonaeus</hi> Hearball,</l>
                  <l>With Taciturnity and Actions verball,</l>
                  <l>Quoth he, I care for neither Friend or Kinsman,</l>
                  <l>Nor do I value honesty two pinnes man:</l>
                  <l>But 'tis a Maxime Mortals cannot hinder,</l>
                  <l>The doughty deedes of Wakesields huffe cap Pinder,</l>
                  <l>Are not so pleasant as the faire <hi>Aurora,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When <hi>Nimrod</hi> rudely plaid on his Bandora.</l>
                  <l>For 'tis not fit that any Turke or Persian,</l>
                  <l>Should in a Cloke-bag hide a feauer Tertian,</l>
                  <l>Because the Dog-starre in his cold Meridian,</l>
                  <l>Might arme himselfe in fury most quotidian.</l>
                  <l>With that most quicke a Pettifoggers tongue went,</l>
                  <l>(Well oild with <hi>Aureum, Argent,</hi> or such <hi>Vnguent,</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Is't fit (quoth he) here should be such incroachment,</l>
                  <l>By such whose fathers nere knew what a Coach ment,</l>
                  <l>Or shall their Scutchions fairely be endorsed,</l>
                  <l>Who riding backward iadishly were horsed,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:1370:10"/>
For though in <hi>India</hi> it be rare and frequent,</l>
                  <l>Where to the wall most commonly the weake went,</l>
                  <l>Yet neither can the <hi>Soldan</hi> or the <hi>Sophy,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shew any Presidents for such a Trophy.</l>
                  <l>By Rules of Logicke, he's a kinde a Catiue,</l>
                  <l>And makes no reckning of his Country natiue,</l>
                  <l>That doth with <unclear>feeble</unclear> strength, loue with derision,</l>
                  <l>And without bloudshed makes a deepe incision.</l>
                  <l>Why should a man lay either life or lime ny,</l>
                  <l>To be endangered by a falling Chimney.</l>
                  <l>For though the prosecution may be quaintly,</l>
                  <l>Yet may the execution end but faintly,</l>
                  <l>Lets call to mind the famous acts of <hi>Hector,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When aged <hi>Ganimede</hi> carousing <hi>Nectar,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Did leaue the Greekes much matter to repine on.</l>
                  <l>Vntill the Woodden Horse of trusty <hi>Sinon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Foald a whole litter of mad Colts in Harnesse,</l>
                  <l>As furious as the host of <hi>Hollophernes.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But to the purpose here's the long and and short ont,</l>
                  <l>All that is said, hath not beene much important,</l>
                  <l>Nor can it be that what is spoke is meant all,</l>
                  <l>Of any thing that happens accidentall,</l>
                  <l>We will examine wisely what the Foe sent,</l>
                  <l>And whether he be innocent or nocent.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:1370:11"/>
In weighty matters lets not be too serious,</l>
                  <l>Ther's many an Eunuch hath bin thought venrious,</l>
                  <l>And 'tis a thing which often hath bin heard on,</l>
                  <l>That he that labours doth deserue his Guerdon,</l>
                  <l>Let vs the first precadent time examine,</l>
                  <l>Youle finde that hunger is the cause of famine,</l>
                  <l>The Birds in Summer that haue sweetely chirped,</l>
                  <l>Ere winter hath beene done haue beene extirped.</l>
                  <l>He may weare Robes, that nere knew what a Rag ment,</l>
                  <l>And he that feasts may fast without a fragment,</l>
                  <l>The end proues all, I care not for the Interim,</l>
                  <l>Time now that summers him, wil one day winter him.</l>
                  <l>To outward view, and Senses all exterier,</l>
                  <l>Amongst all fooles I neuer saw a verier,</l>
                  <l>Then he that doth his liberty prohibit,</l>
                  <l>To fall in danger of a fatall Iibbit.</l>
                  <l>Nor for this purpose here to talke come I,</l>
                  <l>How siluer may be mock't with Alcamie,</l>
                  <l>I oft haue heard that many a Hawke hath muted,</l>
                  <l>Whereby the Faulkners Clothes hath beene poluted.</l>
                  <l>This may be auoyded if the Knight <hi>Sir Reuerence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Be wary with a negligent perseuerance:</l>
                  <l>For men of Iudement neuer thinke it decent,</l>
                  <l>To loue a stinking Pole-cat well for the sent.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:1370:11"/>
But if a man should seriously consider,</l>
                  <l>Where Charity is fled, or who hath hid her,</l>
                  <l>He in the end would giue this worthy sentence,</l>
                  <l>The earth hath beene accursed since she went hence.</l>
                  <l>The Times are biting, and the dayes Caniculer,</l>
                  <l>And mischiefe girds about the Globes orbiculer,</l>
                  <l>How from the Country all the plaine Rusticity,</l>
                  <l>Liues by deceit, exiling plaine simplicity.</l>
                  <l>A face like Rubies mix'd with Allablaster,</l>
                  <l>Wastes much in Physicke, and her water-caster,</l>
                  <l>That whosoe're perceiues which way the stinke went,</l>
                  <l>May sent and sensure shee's a great delinquent.</l>
                  <l>Why should a Bawd be fur'd with Budge &amp; Miniuer,</l>
                  <l>As if she were a Lady, or Queene <hi>Guiniuer?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When as perhaps ther's many a modest Matron,</l>
                  <l>Hath scarcely meate, or money, clothes or patron,</l>
                  <l>And wherefore should a man be growne so stupid,</l>
                  <l>To be a slaue to <hi>Venus</hi> or to <hi>Cupid,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hee's but a foole that hoping for a vaine prize,</l>
                  <l>Being captiu'd can haue no baile or maine prize.</l>
                  <l>For he that hath no shift let him determine,</l>
                  <l>He shall be bitten with Fleas, Lice, or Vermine.</l>
                  <l>This being all his speeches <hi>Pia Mater,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He cal'd a Sculler, and would goe by water:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:1370:12"/>
When straite the Stigian Ferriman a rare one,</l>
                  <l>Old amiable, currish curteous <hi>Caron,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Row'd with a whirle-wind through the <hi>Acheron</hi> ticke</l>
                  <l>And thence vnto the Azure Sea proponticke.</l>
                  <l>There <hi>Neptune</hi> in a burning blue Pauillion,</l>
                  <l>In state did entertaine this slow Postilion,</l>
                  <l>There <hi>Proteus</hi> in a Robe of twisted Camphire,</l>
                  <l>With a graue beard of monumentall Samphire,</l>
                  <l>Quoth he, shall we whose Ancestors were warre-like,</l>
                  <l>Whose rich Perfumes were only Leekes and Garlike,</l>
                  <l>Whose noble deedes nocturnall and diurnall,</l>
                  <l>Great Townes and Towers did topsie turuy turne all.</l>
                  <l>Shall all their valour be in vs extinguish'd,</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Ioue</hi> forbid there should be such a thing wish'd,</l>
                  <l>Though <hi>Cleoprtra</hi> was <hi>Octauia's</hi> riuall,</l>
                  <l>It is a thing that we may well conniue all,</l>
                  <l>Amongst the Antients it is vndisputable,</l>
                  <l>That women and the winds were euer muteable,</l>
                  <l>And 'tis aprou'd where people are littigious,</l>
                  <l>There euery Epicure is not religious,</l>
                  <l>Old <hi>Oceamus</hi> knowing what they ment all,</l>
                  <l>Brought <hi>Zephirus</hi> vnto the Orientall,</l>
                  <l>And he by Argument would proue that loue is,</l>
                  <l>A thing that makes a wise man oft a Nouice:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:1370:12"/>
For tis approu'd a Greyhound or a Beagle,</l>
                  <l>Were not ordain'd or made, to hunt the Eagle,</l>
                  <l>Nor can the nimblest Cat that came from <hi>Gottam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Search the profundity of <hi>Neptunes</hi> bottom.</l>
                  <l>Let roaring Cannons with the Welkin parley,</l>
                  <l>It's knowne good liquer may be made with Barley<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>And by experience many are assured,</l>
                  <l>Some grounds are fruitfull if they be manured.</l>
                  <l>For in the rudimens of health or sanity,</l>
                  <l>An arrant Whore is but a price of vanity:</l>
                  <l>Some men with fury will procrastinate,</l>
                  <l>And some with leaden speede make hast in at<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>But in conclusion many things impurely,</l>
                  <l>Dye in the Birth, and neuer end maturely,</l>
                  <l>The man that seeketh straying minds to weane all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>From veniall vices, or offences penall:</l>
                  <l>Had he the forces of the Turkish Nauy,</l>
                  <l>He would lye downe at last and cry pecauy.</l>
                  <l>Of one thing I haue oftentimes tooke notice,</l>
                  <l>The foole that's old, and rich, much apt to dote is,</l>
                  <l>And by the light of <hi>Polux</hi> and of <hi>Castor,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A Woolfe in Shepheards weedes is no good Pastor,</l>
                  <l>Those that do liue a Commicke life by Magicke,</l>
                  <l>Their Sceanes in their Catastraphes are tragicke.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:1370:13"/>
And that ore the World would be chiefe Primate,</l>
                  <l>May giue occasion for wise men to rime at,</l>
                  <l>Before men fell to wrangling disagreement,</l>
                  <l>A Lawyer vnderstood not what a fee meant:</l>
                  <l>It was a time when Guilt did feare no censure,</l>
                  <l>But loue, and peace, and charity was then sure.</l>
                  <l>Now fathers (for their bread dig and delue it,</l>
                  <l>The whilst the Satten Sonnes are lin'd with Veluet.</l>
                  <l>Thus do I make a hotch potch messe of <hi>Nonsence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In darke Enigmaes, and strange sence vpon sence:</l>
                  <l>It is not foolish all, nor is it wise all,</l>
                  <l>Nor is it true in all, nor is it lies all.</l>
                  <l>I haue not shew'd my wits accute or fluent,</l>
                  <l>Nor told which way of late the wandring Iew went,</l>
                  <l>For mine owne part I neuer cared greatly,</l>
                  <l>(So I farewell) where those that dresse the meate lye.</l>
                  <l>A miserable Knaue may be close fisted,</l>
                  <l>And prodigall expence may be resisted,</l>
                  <l>I neither care what <hi>Tom,</hi> or <hi>Iacke,</hi> or <hi>Dick</hi> sed,</l>
                  <l>I am resolu'd, and my mind is fixed,</l>
                  <l>The case is not as he, or I, or you sed,</l>
                  <l>Truth must be found, and witnesses produced,</l>
                  <l>My care is, that no captious Reader beare hence,</l>
                  <l>My vnderstanding, wit, or reason here hence.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:1370:13"/>
On purpose to no purpose I did write all,</l>
                  <l>And so at Noone, I bid you here good night all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>THen with a tuchbox of transalpine tarre,</l>
                  <l>Turning thrice round, and stirring not a iot,</l>
                  <l>He threw fiue tunne of red hot purple Snow,</l>
                  <l>Into a Pigmeis mouth, nine inches square,</l>
                  <l>Which straite with mellancholly mou'd,</l>
                  <l>Old <hi>
                        <unclear>Bombus</unclear>
                     </hi> Burgomaster of <hi>Pickthatch,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That plunging through the Sea of <hi>Turneball streete<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He safely did ariue at <hi>Smith field Barres.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then did the Turnetripes on the Coast of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Catch fifteene hundred thousand Grashoppers,</l>
                  <l>With foureteene Spanish Needles bumbasted,</l>
                  <l>Poach'd with the Egges of fourescore Flanders Mares,</l>
                  <l>Mounted vpon the foote of <hi>Caucasus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They whorld the footeball of conspiring fate,</l>
                  <l>And brake the shinnes of smugfac'd <hi>
                        <unclear>Mulciber</unclear>,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With that grim <hi>Pluto</hi> all in Scarlet blue,</l>
                  <l>Gaue faire <hi>Proserpina</hi> a kisse of brasse,</l>
                  <l>At which all Hell danc'd Trenchmore in a string,</l>
                  <l>Whilst <hi>Acheron,</hi> and <hi>Termagaunt</hi> did sing,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:1370:14"/>
The Mold-warpe all this while in white broth bath'd,</l>
                  <l>Did Carroll <hi>Didoes</hi> happinesse in loue,</l>
                  <l>Vpon a Gridiron made of Whiting-mops,</l>
                  <l>Vnto the tune of <hi>Iohn</hi> come kisse me now,</l>
                  <l>At which <hi>Auernus</hi> Musicke gan to rore,</l>
                  <l>Iuthron'd vpon a seate of three leau'd grasse,</l>
                  <l>Whilst all the Hibernian Kernes in multitudes,</l>
                  <l>Did feast with Shamerags stew'd in Vsquebagh.</l>
                  <l>At which a banquet made of Monopolies,</l>
                  <l>Tooke great disaste, because the Pillory</l>
                  <l>Was hunger-staru'd for want of Villaines eares,</l>
                  <l>Whom to relieue, there was a Mittimus,</l>
                  <l>Sent from <hi>Tartaria</hi> in an Oyster Boate,</l>
                  <l>At which the King of <hi>China</hi> was amaz'd,</l>
                  <l>And with nine graines of Rewbarbe stellified,</l>
                  <l>As low as to the altitude of shame,</l>
                  <l>He thrust foure Onions in a Candle-case,</l>
                  <l>And spoild the meaning of the worlds misdoubt,</l>
                  <l>Thus with a Dialogue of crimson starch,</l>
                  <l>I was inflamed with a num-cold fire,</l>
                  <l>Vpon the tenterhookes of <hi>Chalemaine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Dogstar howl'd, the Cat a Mountaine smil'd,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Sisiphus</hi> dranke Muskadell and Egges,</l>
                  <l>In the horn'd hoofe of huge <hi>Bucephalus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:1370:14"/>
Time turn'd about, and shew'd me yesterday,</l>
                  <l>Clad in a Gowne of mourning had I wist,</l>
                  <l>The motion was almost too late they said,</l>
                  <l>Whilst sad dispaire made all the World starke mad,</l>
                  <l>They all arose, and I put vp my pen,</l>
                  <l>It makes no matter, where, why, how, or when.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:1370:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Some sence at last to the learned.</head>
               <l>YOu that in <hi>Greeke</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> learned are,</l>
               <l>And of the ancient <hi>Hebrew</hi> haue a share:</l>
               <l>You that most rarely oftentimes haue sung,</l>
               <l>In the <hi>French, Spanish</hi> or <hi>Italian</hi> tongue,</l>
               <l>Here I in <hi>English</hi> haue imploid my pen,</l>
               <l>To be read by the learnedst Englishmen,</l>
               <l>Wherein the meanest Scholler plaine may see,</l>
               <l>I vnderstand their tongues, as they do me.</l>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>N. O<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
1622.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1370:15"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
