<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A memorial of all the English monarchs being in number 151, from Brute to King Charles. In heroicall verse by Io. Taylor.</title>
            <author>Taylor, John, 1580-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 105 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-01">2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13472</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23774</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118225</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853433</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853433</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18816</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A13472)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18816)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1611:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A memorial of all the English monarchs being in number 151, from Brute to King Charles. In heroicall verse by Io. Taylor.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, John, 1580-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[112] p. : ports. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Beale, for Iames Bowler,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last two leaves are blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A memoriall of monarchs from Brute to King Charles.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliography.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>With added frontispiece portrait of King Charles. Some print faded and show-through; some pages creased, torn, and tightly bound.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-09</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-09</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:18816:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18816:1"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18816:2"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>CAROLUS STUART.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Koningk van Engelandt. Schotlandt, En Irlandt, Gebooren A<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1600.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Binnen Londen onthalst, A<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1649. in't 24 Iaer zyner Regeeringe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> van Dyck pinxit. Ioost Hartgers excud. S. Savery f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tt</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18816:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A MEMORIAL</hi> OF ALL THE <hi>English Monarchs</hi> being in number 151, from BRVTE to King CHARLES. <hi>In Heroicall Uerse by</hi> IO. TAYLOR.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by IOHN BEALE, for <hi>Iames Bowler,</hi> 1630</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:18816:3"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18816:3"/>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18816:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18816:4"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> TO THE RIGHT Honourable, LIONEL Lord <hi>Viscount Cranefield,</hi> Earle of Middlesex, &amp;c.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y humble Muse, in lofty manner sings</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">
                     <hi>The 7 Kingdomes were,</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. Kent.</item>
                        <item>2 South-Saxons, Sussex <hi>and</hi> Surry.</item>
                        <item>3 East-Angles, Norfolke, <hi>and</hi> Cambridge-shire.</item>
                        <item>4 West Saxon, Barkshire, Deuonshire, Somersetshire, <hi>and</hi> Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</item>
                        <item>5 Mertia, Glostershire, Herefordshire, Worcester, Shropsh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>re, Scaffor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>shire, Cheshire, Warwike, Leycester, Noreb, Oxford, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham, Bedford, <hi>and halfe</hi> Hartfordshire.</item>
                        <item>6 East-Saxon, Essex, Middlesex, <hi>and halfe</hi> Hartfordshire.</item>
                        <item>7 Northumberland <hi>diuided to two Kingdomes,</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>nd Bernicia, <hi>all brought to one Monarchy by</hi> Egler<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> West-Saxons, <hi>and called</hi> England, 196<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>yee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap>s after</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</item>
                     </list>
                  </note> A Catalogue of Englands mighty Kings:</l>
               <l>At first I do begin with Troian <hi>BRVTE,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And following Chronicles I do dispute,</l>
               <l>Proceeding briefely with their Raignes and Names,</l>
               <l>Till these <hi>blest</hi> dayes of our <hi>best</hi> Monarch <hi>IAMES,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:5"/>
Tis but an Argument thats written here,</l>
               <l>That in such time such and such Princes were:</l>
               <l>But he that meanes their Actions more to know,</l>
               <l>May read <hi>Boetius, Hollinshed,</hi> or <hi>Stow,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or our true labouring Moderne Master <hi>How,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which Authors, Learned Iudgement do allow:</l>
               <l>Or if youle see how former times doe runne,</l>
               <l>Reade the laborious paines of <hi>Middleton.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>We haue had Kings since <hi>Brute,</hi> of royall Blood,</l>
               <l>One hundred forty sixe, some bad, some good,</l>
               <l>Foure Queenes in all, this time did only Raigne,</l>
               <l>Whose Memories in Histories remaine.</l>
               <l>So in two thousand and seuen hundred yeeres,</l>
               <l>We had thrice 50 Princes it appeares.</l>
               <l>This Kingdome here was fiue times won and lost,</l>
               <l>And Kings (as God decreed) oft chang'd and tost.</l>
               <l>Sometimes one swaid the Scepter, sometime twaine,</l>
               <l>And sometime seuen at once did rule and raigne,</l>
               <l>Till sixe (by bloudy warres) lost life and throne,</l>
               <l>And valiant <hi>Egbert</hi> ioyn'd them all in one.</l>
               <l>But since (through Heauens high prouidence) I see,</l>
               <l>Tis growne more great, and greater like to be:</l>
               <l>Long may He liue, by whom in <hi>one</hi> 'tis guided,</l>
               <l>And may they sinke that wish't againe diuided.</l>
               <l>Then (Noble Lord) with good acceptance take</l>
               <l>This Poem, for the Royall Subiects sake,</l>
               <l>And though it be not compleate as it should,</l>
               <l>Beare with it, and accept of what I could,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:5"/>
The matter's worthy, though the manner poore,</l>
               <l>VVhich makes me heere your Patronage implore,</l>
               <l>And may you be externall and internall,</l>
               <l>Blest and aduanc'd to happinesse eternall.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Your Honours in all obseruance to be commanded,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Taylor.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="B.C." type="period">
            <head>Yeeres before Christ.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:6"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Medulla Historioe Anglicanoe</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <div n="1" type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:6"/>
                     <head>BRVTE, THE FIRST KING OF <hi>BRITTAINE,</hi> began his Reigne,</head>
                     <head>1. BRVTE.</head>
                     <head type="sub">Anno mundi, 2858. Before Christ, 1108.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>AENEAS</hi> from subuerted <hi>Troy</hi> exilde,</l>
                        <l>In <hi>Tuscan</hi> wedded King <hi>Lati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap>s</hi> childe:</l>
                        <l>By whom the Realme of <hi>Italy</hi> he gain'd,</l>
                        <l>And after he had 3 yeeres fully raign'd,</l>
                        <l>He died, and left <hi>Ascanius</hi> in his stead:</l>
                        <l>To whom <hi>Sil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap>s Post<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap>s</hi> did succeed.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:18816:7"/>
From which <hi>Posthumus</hi> Royall loynes did spring,</l>
                        <l>
                           <note n="*" place="bottom">
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Brute</hi> being of the age of 15 yeeres, as he shot at a wild beast, the arrow glanced vnfortunately and slew his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Siluius Aeneas,</hi> for the which he was exilde, and came into this Land, then called <hi>Albyon.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>I follow the common opinion: for many Writers doe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther write or allow of <hi>Brutes</hi> being here, accounting it a dishonor for our Nation, to haue originall from a Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                                    <desc>•…</desc>
                                 </gap>ide, and one that deriued his descent from the Goddesse <hi>(alias</hi> strumper) <hi>Venus.</hi> Howsoeuer, Histories are obscured and clouded with ambiguities, some burnt, lost, defaced by anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; and some abused by the malice, ignorance, or partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of Writers, so that truth is hard to be found. Amongst all which variations of Times and Writers, I must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude there was a BRVTE.</p>
                           </note> Great <hi>Brutus,</hi> Brittaines first commanding King:</l>
                        <l>The people then were (here) all voyd of pride,</l>
                        <l>Borne Naked, Naked liu'd, and Naked dy'd.</l>
                        <l>Three Sonnes <hi>Brute</hi> left, <hi>Locrinus</hi> was his Heire</l>
                        <l>To <hi>England, Cambria</hi> (Wales) was <hi>Cambers</hi> share,</l>
                        <l>To <hi>Albanact</hi> (the youngest) 'twas his lot,</l>
                        <l>To sway the Scepter of the valiant <hi>Scot.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Thus 'mongst his Sonnes this Ile he did diuide,</l>
                        <l>And after twenty foure yeeres Reigne he dy'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:7"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Locrine</hi> 20. yeeres, 1084.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>LOcrinus,</hi> Eldest of old <hi>Brutus</hi> Sonnes,</l>
                        <l>By Valour vanquisht the inuading <hi>Hunnes:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>He chas'd them, &amp; their power did quite confound,</l>
                        <l>And their King <hi>Humber</hi> was in <note n="a" place="bottom">The Riuer of <hi>Humber</hi> tooke the name from the drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap>d King of the <hi>Huns,</hi> now <hi>Hungarians.</hi>
                           </note> 
                           <hi>Humber</hi> drownd:</l>
                        <l>This <hi>Locrine</hi> had a Queene, faire <note n="b" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Guendoline</hi> was daughter vnto <hi>Corineus,</hi> Duke Cornewall. <hi>Estrild</hi> was a beautious Lady of King <hi>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                                    <desc>•…</desc>
                                 </gap>umbers,</hi> whom <hi>Locrinus</hi> tooke prisoner.</note> 
                           <hi>Guendolin,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Yet folly led him to the Paphaean sinne,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>esotted sence, and blood with lust inflam'd,</l>
                        <l>He lou'd a beautie, Beautious <hi>Estrild</hi> nam'd,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>y whom he had a Daughter, <hi>Sabrin</hi> hight,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> whome the King had whole and sole delight:</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>or which the Queene made war vpon her Lord:</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>nd in the Fight she put him to the Sword;</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>nd after a reuengefull bloody slaughter,</l>
                        <l>Queene <hi>Guendoline</hi> tooke <hi>Estrild</hi> and her daughter,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>nd drownd them both (to que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch her ielous flame)</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>nd so from <hi>Sabrine, Seauerne</hi> got the name.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:8"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:8"/>
                  </div>
                  <div type="queen">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:9"/>
                     <head>Q. <hi>Guendoline,</hi> 1064.</head>
                     <figure/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>About this time</hi> Saul <hi>was King of Israel.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>VVHen 15. yeeres this Queen had wisely raign'd,</l>
                        <l>She dy'd, &amp; then her Son the kingdome gain'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Queene</hi> Guendoline <hi>was allowed the gouernment in her Sonne</hi> Madans <hi>minority, whose p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>dent reigne is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>fully recorded in histories.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Madan, 1009.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>VVHen forty yeers this King had rul'd this Ile,</l>
                        <l>(As Stories say) he died a death most vile:</l>
                        <l>The wide-mouth'd <hi>Wolfe,</hi> and keene-tusk'd brutish <hi>Bore</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Did eate his Kingly flesh, &amp; drinke his gore.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Madan <hi>was a vicious and wicked Prince, the Sonn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18816:9"/>
                        <hi>of</hi> Locrine <hi>and</hi> Guendoline. <hi>Hee was a great Tyrant. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> built the To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ne of</hi> Doncaster. <hi>Hee had two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>nes,</hi> Mempricius <hi>and</hi> Mannus.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Mempricius</hi> raigned 20. yeeres, 991.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>MEmpricius</hi> base, his brother <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> slew,</l>
                        <l>And got the Crowne, by murder, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> as d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>e:</l>
                        <l>Maids, wiues and widdowes, hoby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> deflowr'd:</l>
                        <l>He liu'd a Beast, and dy'd, by a Beast, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>uour'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hee killed his elder brother tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> sly as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ee was parlying with him. Hee was eaten of Wolues as hee was hunting. Hee was so beastly, that he was ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>din histories to be a</hi> Sodomite <hi>with Beasts in his time.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:10"/>
                     <head>Ebranke, 989. King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> reigne ouer Israe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>AT <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the Castle he did found,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Alcluid</hi> &amp; <hi>York,</hi> he built new from the ground</l>
                        <l>He builded <hi>Bambrough,</hi> and reigned sixty yeeres,</l>
                        <l>Belou'd, as it in Chronicles appeares.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Ebranke <hi>had</hi> 21. <hi>wiues, by whom he had</hi> 20. <hi>Sonnes and</hi> 30. <hi>Daughters; hee inuaded</hi> Gallia, <hi>now</hi> France <hi>He was the Sonne of</hi> Mempricius. <hi>In his Reigne reigne King</hi> Salomon. Alcluid <hi>is Dumbreton in</hi> Scotland.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Brute</hi> the second, 929.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>IF any noble act <hi>Brute Greeneshield</hi> did,</l>
                        <l>Hee's wrong'd, because from Histories th'are hid:</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:18816:10"/>
Twelue yeeres he rul'd, that's all I of him read,</l>
                        <l>And how at <hi>Yorke,</hi> hee Iyeth buried.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This</hi> Brute <hi>was the Sonne of</hi> Ebranke <hi>and some histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries write doubtfully, that he conquer'd</hi> France, <hi>and that after he receiued a great foyle in field by</hi> Brinchild, <hi>or</hi> Brinchillus, <hi>Prince of</hi> Henoway, <hi>or</hi> Henault.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Leil. 917.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>LEil Carleile</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>t, and raign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>d yeeres twenty fiue,</l>
                        <l>And as Fame still keepes dead mens acts aliue:</l>
                        <l>So <hi>Leil</hi> (though dead) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> euer liue by Fame,</l>
                        <l>He lyes at <hi>Carleile,</hi> which himselfe did frame.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Leil <hi>was the Sonne of</hi> Brute Greeneshield. <hi>It is also written that he bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> of</hi> Chester. Lud, <hi>or</hi> Rud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hudibras <hi>was the Sonne of</hi> Leil, <hi>a religious Prince in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>s superstitious way of Paganisme, for in these</hi> 3. <hi>Townes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ich he built, hee erected</hi> 3. <hi>Temples, and placed</hi> 3. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> or Pagan Bishops in them.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:11"/>
                     <head>Rudhudibrasse, 892.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THis King built <hi>Canterbury, Winchester,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> he from the ground did reare:</l>
                        <l>And after twenty nine yeeres reigne was past,</l>
                        <l>At <hi>Winchester</hi> sore sicke, he breath'd his last.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Bladud</hi> reign'd 20. 863.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>BAathe</hi> was by <hi>Bladud</hi> to perfection brought,</l>
                        <l>By Necromanricke Arts, to flye hee sought:</l>
                        <l>As from a Towre he thought to scale the Sky,</l>
                        <l>He brake his necke, because he soar'd too hig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This</hi> Bladud <hi>had beene a st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> in</hi> Ather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>id: <hi>whence hee brought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ny learned men: hee bui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> elue ford, <hi>a Colledge I thinke, the first in</hi> England:
<pb facs="tcp:18816:11"/>
                        <hi>play the fowle or the foole, he brake his necke on the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of</hi> Apollo <hi>in</hi> Troynouant.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Leire, 844.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>LEire</hi> (as the Story saies) three daughters had,</l>
                        <l>The youngest good, the other two too bad:</l>
                        <l>Yet the old King lou'd the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wrong'd him most,</l>
                        <l>She that lou'd him, he banisht from his Coast.</l>
                        <l>False <hi>Gonorel</hi> and <hi>Ragan,</hi> he betweene</l>
                        <l>Them gaue the Kingdome, making <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ach a Queene.</l>
                        <l>But young <hi>Cordeilla</hi> wedded was by chance,</l>
                        <l>To <hi>Aganippus,</hi> King of fertile <hi>France:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>The eldest Daughters did reiect their Sire,</l>
                        <l>For succour to the young'st hee did retire,</l>
                        <l>By whose iust aide the Crowne againe he gain'd;</l>
                        <l>And dyed when he full forty yeeres had reign'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Leire <hi>built</hi> Leicester <hi>and was a good Prince. At</hi> Ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester <hi>he built a Temple to</hi> Ianues <hi>Bifrons, or</hi> Ianues <hi>with two faces.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="queen">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:12"/>
                     <head>Qu. <hi>Cordeilla,</hi> 805.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>MAd <hi>Morgan,</hi> and vnmanner'd <hi>Cunedague,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Their Au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Cordeilla</hi> with fierce war did plague:</l>
                        <l>They vanquish'd her, and her in Prison threw:</l>
                        <l>And hauing reign'd fiue yeeres, her selfe she slew.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>She reigned with her Husband</hi> Aganippus <hi>till he dyed, and then in her widowhood her cruell kinsmen opprest her. Shee stabb'd her selfe in prison, being tyrannously vsed, in despaire of her liberty.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Morgan Cunedagu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>, 800.</head>
                     <figure/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THen <hi>Morgan</hi> did 'gainst <hi>Cunedague</hi> contend,</l>
                        <l>And at <hi>Glamorgan, Morgan</hi> had his end.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:18816:12"/>
Then <hi>Cunedagus</hi> sole King did abide,</l>
                        <l>Full three and thirty yeeres, and then he dyed.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Morgan <hi>was the Sonne of</hi> Gonorel, Leires <hi>eldest Daughter, and</hi> Cunedagus <hi>his kinsman, was the Sonne of</hi> Ragan.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Prophet</hi> Esay <hi>prophesied about this time.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Riuallo,</hi> before Christ, 766.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THree daies it rain'd blood, when <hi>Riuallo</hi> reign'd,</l>
                        <l>And great mortalitie the Land sustain'd;</l>
                        <l>Hee forty six yeeres rul'd in Kingly State,</l>
                        <l>And then surrendred to all humane Fate.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This Land in this Kings reigne was almost vnpeopled with dearth, death and desolation. In his time</hi> Rome <hi>was builded,</hi> 356. <hi>yeeres after</hi> Brute: <hi>Innumerable multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of Horse-flyes or Hornets sprung out of the blood that raind, which flyes stung many people to death.</hi> Riual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo <hi>was buried at</hi> Yorke.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:13"/>
                     <head>Gurgustus, 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Scicillius, 684.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A Common Drunkard was this wicked King,</l>
                        <l>Which vice did many other vices bring,</l>
                        <l>Yeeres thirty eight, the Diadem he wore,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Scicillius</hi> next raignd nine and forty more.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Gurgustus <hi>and</hi> Scicillius <hi>were brethren. I finde little mention of any good they did, though they reigned long: They were both the Sonnes of</hi> Riuallo.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="kings">
                     <head>Iago, 636.</head>
                     <head>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, 612.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>OF these two Kings, small mention I doe finde,</l>
                        <l>They left bare Names (for me hori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>) behinde;</l>
                        <l>One twentie fiue yeeres: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> other fifty foure,</l>
                        <l>Had in this Land Commanding Regall power.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Iugo <hi>was a kinsman to</hi> Gurgustus, <hi>and by his vicious</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18816:13"/>
                        <hi>life, he got a sleepy disease called the Lethargy, whereof he dyed. These two Kings were both buried at</hi> Yorke.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Gorbodug, 559.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>GOrbodug</hi> next did in the Throne succced,</l>
                        <l>Was sixty three yeeres King, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ast decreed,</l>
                        <l>'Twixt his two Sonnes this Kingdome to diuide,</l>
                        <l>At <hi>Yorke</hi> hee's buried, where in peace hee dy'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Some write that he reigned but 42. yeeres, and that he was buried at</hi> Troynouant.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Ferex, <hi>and</hi> Porex, 496.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>POrex,</hi> in Fight his brother <hi>Ferex</hi> kil'd,</l>
                        <l>For which their mother, <hi>Porex</hi> heartblud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:18816:14"/>
These murthers mercilesse, did quite deface,</l>
                        <l>These Princes, last of Royall <hi>Brutus</hi> Race.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Ferex <hi>and</hi> Porex <hi>were the sonnes of</hi> Gorbodug. <hi>Their mother and her maides chopped</hi> Porex <hi>in pieces, in reuenge of her sonne</hi> Ferex: <hi>they reigned fiue yeeres: after whose death the Land was a long time diuided into fiue Kingdomes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Mulmutius Donwallo. 441.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THe Land vnguided, Kinglesse did remaine,</l>
                        <l>Till great <hi>Mulmutius</hi> did the Wreathe obtaine:</l>
                        <l>He builded Temples, made Lawes, Ploughs, high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies,</l>
                        <l>And 40. yeeres he liu'd in fame and praise.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Mulmutius <hi>slew</hi> Pinnar, Slater, <hi>and</hi> Rudack, <hi>three Kings of seuerall parts of this Ile, and at last brought the Kingdome to his sole obedience. He was the Sonne of</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>lotten, <hi>Duke of</hi> Cornewall: <hi>He was the first of all the Kings of this Land that wore a crowne of Gold.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:14"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Bellinus</hi> and <hi>Brennus</hi> reigned 26. yeeres. 401.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THese brethren did diuide the Realme in twaine,</l>
                        <l>But Kings can brooke no partnership in reigne;</l>
                        <l>They fell at oddes, and <hi>Brennus</hi> fled, subdude</l>
                        <l>With slaughter of his warlike multitude.</l>
                        <l>To <hi>France</hi> he scap'd, and was receiu'd in State,</l>
                        <l>In <hi>London, Belline</hi> builded <hi>Bellins-gate</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Braue <hi>Brennus</hi> conquer'd <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Bellinus</hi> lies heere in an honour'd Tombe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Brennus <hi>slew himselfe with the sword, at the fiedge of</hi> Delphos <hi>in Greece.</hi> Bochas. <hi>They were the sonnes of</hi> Mulmutius Donwallo. Belinus <hi>brought Denmarke to be tributary to Brittaine: they were a paire of worthy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:15"/>
                     <head>Gurguintus, 373.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>GVrguintus,</hi> was <hi>Belinus</hi> first-borne sonne,</l>
                        <l>Victorously <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>e <hi>Denmarke</hi> ouer-runne:</l>
                        <l>He the vnpeopled <hi>Ireland</hi> did supply,</l>
                        <l>Reign'd nineteene yeeres a King, and then did dye.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This King gaue leaue to a company of stragling distressed Spaniards to possesse themselules in Ireland, hee lyeth buried at Carelion.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Guinthelinus, 456.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>HE married <hi>Mercia</hi> a renowned Dame,</l>
                        <l>From whom the iust, wise, <hi>Mercian</hi> Statutes came:</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:18816:15"/>
He sixe and twenty yeeres the Scepter swaide,</l>
                        <l>And then with honour in his Tombe was laide.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>He was the sonne of</hi> Arguintus, <hi>he builded Warwick and lyeth buried at London.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Cecilius, 330.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Kimarus, 223.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Seuen yeeres <hi>Cecilius</hi> kept the Regall Chaire,</l>
                        <l>Three yeeres <hi>Kimarus</hi> rul'd as his sole Heire;</l>
                        <l>The Syre with loue did well and iustly reigne,</l>
                        <l>His sonne <hi>Kimarus</hi> was a hunting slaine.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>About this time, a sauage people called the Picts, beg'd habitation of the King of</hi> Scots, <hi>and liued in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes betweene</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland. Kimarus <hi>was a vicious Prince, and killed by wild Beasts as hee was hunting: he was the sonne of</hi> Cecilius. Cecilius <hi>was buried at</hi> Carelion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:16"/>
                     <head>Elanius, 321.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>ELanius</hi> (as most Histories agree)</l>
                        <l>Was King of <hi>Brittaine</hi> yeeres iust three times three:</l>
                        <l>What Acts he did, or what Lawes he decreed,</l>
                        <l>They are vnwrit, and therefore are vnread.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Elanius <hi>was the sonne of</hi> Kimarus.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Morindus</hi> reigned 8 yeeres. 311.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THis King <hi>Morindus,</hi> valiant more then wise,</l>
                        <l>A ran'ning Monster from the Sea did rise:</l>
                        <l>Which many people to destruction brought,</l>
                        <l>Who kil'd this braue King as he brauely fought.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>He killed the Monster, after the Monster had deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18816:16"/>
                        <hi>him, for he was in the belly of it liuing, and found dead with his dagger in his hand.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Gorbomanus. 303.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THis King eleuen yeers wore the Brittain crown.</l>
                        <l>He founded <hi>Cambridge,</hi> &amp; built <hi>Grantham</hi> Town;</l>
                        <l>His subiects peace, past Kingdomes he prefer'd,</l>
                        <l>Lou'd and bewail'd, at London was inter'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>He built the Townes of Cambridge and Grantham.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Archigalo, <hi>and</hi> Elidurus. 392.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THese brothers were not Kings both at one time,</l>
                        <l>But for extortion (an vnkingly crime,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:18816:17"/>
The Eldest hauing gaind his Subiects hate)</l>
                        <l>Depos'd, and <hi>Elidurus</hi> got the State.</l>
                        <l>But he (not greedy after worldly reigne)</l>
                        <l>To <hi>Archigalo</hi> gaue it vp againe.</l>
                        <l>Rul'd tenne yeeres more: thus twenty yeeres in all,</l>
                        <l>His State Maiesticke, did twice rise and fall.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Archigalo <hi>put away from him and reiected the true and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> Nobility and Gentry: and in their roomes was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>pplyde with the counsels of flatterers and parasites, which was his downefall.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Elidurus, 272. Vigenius, Peredurus, 270.</head>
                     <figure/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THen <hi>Archigale</hi> beeing dead and gone,</l>
                        <l>Good <hi>Elidure</hi> two yeers kept Brittaines Throne.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Vigenius, Peredurus</hi> two yeeres more,</l>
                        <l>Thrust <hi>Elidure</hi> from all the sway he bore,</l>
                        <l>But they both dy'd the third time he was crown'd, <hi>Elidurus,</hi> 261.</l>
                        <l>And reigned foure yeeres more, belou'd, renown'd.</l>
                        <l>Once subiect, twice a slaue, and thrice a King;</l>
                        <l>Thus <hi>Fortunes</hi> fauours vp and downe did fling.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>In these often changes of Princes estates, this Land was miserably vexed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18816:17"/>
Heere because Hystories make little or no mention of any the doings of the Kings, from the reigne of <hi>Elidurus</hi> to King <hi>Lud,</hi> I thinke it fit, onely to insert their names, and the times of their reignes, with their yeeres before Christ.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>258. <hi>Gorbonian</hi> reigned ten yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>248. <hi>Morgan</hi> foureteene yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>234. <hi>Emerianus</hi> seuen yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <p>This King was deposed from all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall gouernment for h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> tyranny.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:18"/>
                     <head>227. <hi>Iuall</hi> twenty yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <p>This King was a iust and prudent Prince.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>207. <hi>Rimo</hi> sixteen yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <p>His reigne was blest with abundance of Peace and Plenty.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>191. <hi>Geruncius</hi> twenty yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>171. <hi>Catillus</hi> ten yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <p>Catillus caused all the oppressors of the poore to be hanged vp: but since his time they are doubly increased.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:18"/>
                     <head>161. <hi>Coylus</hi> twenty yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <p>A peaceable King, and a quiet reigne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>141. <hi>Porrex</hi> fiue yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <p>A good Prince.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>136. <hi>Chirimus</hi> one yeere.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <p>Chirimus <hi>through excessiue drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king gat his death.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>135. <hi>Fulgon</hi> two yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:19"/>
                     <head>133. <hi>Eldred</hi> one yeere.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>132. <hi>Androgius</hi> one yeere.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>131. <hi>Varianus</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>re.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <p>Varianus <hi>giuen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>to lust, purchsed himselfe a short reigne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> and it may bee perceiued, that all these Prince: either by treason, or their ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> bad liues, were soon brought to their ends, for 25 of them did not reign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> aboue 62 yeeres.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>129. <hi>Fliud</hi> fiue yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:19"/>
                     <head>120. <hi>Dedamius</hi> fiue yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>118. <hi>Gurginius</hi> three yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>115. <hi>Mercianus</hi> two yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>113. <hi>Bladunus</hi> two yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:20"/>
                     <head>110. <hi>Cupenus</hi> three yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>108. <hi>Quinus</hi> two yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>106. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ius</hi> two yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>94. <hi>Bledgabredus</hi> ten yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A great louer of Musicke, and a good Patron to Musician<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:20"/>
                     <head>92. <hi>Archemalus</hi> two yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>90. <hi>Eldolus</hi> two yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>88. <hi>Rodianus</hi> two yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>86. <hi>Redargius</hi> three yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:21"/>
                     <head>84. <hi>Samullius</hi> two yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>81. <hi>Penisellus</hi> three yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>78. <hi>Pirrhus</hi> two yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>76. <hi>Caporus</hi> two yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:21"/>
                     <head>74. <hi>Dinellus</hi> foure yeeres.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A Noble and vertuous Prince.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>70. <hi>Hellius</hi> one yeere.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Ile of</hi> Ely <hi>tooke the nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from this Prince. There hee built a Palace, and there he dying was buried.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Lud</hi> reigned 11. yeeres, 66.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A Long time after <hi>Troynouant</hi> was fram'd,</l>
                        <l>It was by <hi>Lud, Kair-Lud,</hi> or <hi>Lud-stone</hi> nam'd,</l>
                        <l>He made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> strong with Battlemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>s and Towres,</l>
                        <l>Defensiue against foes inuasiue pow'rs.</l>
                        <l>Of free Stone for Free-men <hi>Ludgate</hi> hee founded,</l>
                        <l>Where freemen (wanting freedom) are confounded.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:18816:22"/>
He dy'd and left two Sonnes, too young for reigne,</l>
                        <l>Wherefore his brother did the Crowne obtaine.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Some Writers doe affirme, that this King b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ilded</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <hi>from</hi> Ludgate <hi>to</hi> London-stone, <hi>and that the stone in memory thereof was called</hi> Luds <hi>stone.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Cassibelan,</hi> 17. yeeres. 58.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>LVd</hi> deed, the Nobles crown'd <hi>Cassibelan,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>In whose reigne her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> the <hi>Romane</hi> conquest <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>an,</l>
                        <l>Great <hi>Iulius Caesar</hi> sailed out of <hi>France,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And in this Land his <hi>Eagle</hi> did aduance.</l>
                        <l>But <hi>Brittaines</hi> bold scorn'd base at first to stoope,</l>
                        <l>Twice <hi>Caesar</hi> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ed, before their warlike troope.</l>
                        <l>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>iuill warres, this Kingdome ouer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</l>
                        <l>Betwixt <hi>Cassibelan,</hi> and <hi>Luds two</hi> Sonnes,</l>
                        <l>Whilst they (vnnaturall) sought each others fall,</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Romanes</hi> tooke aduantage, conquer'd all:</l>
                        <l>Where <hi>Caesar,</hi> by his high Imperiall doome,</l>
                        <l>Made <hi>Brittaine</hi> Tributary vnto <hi>Rome.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Nennius <hi>a valiant Duke of this Kingdome, receiued his de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ths <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>und of</hi> Caesar: <hi>Yet after that he tooke</hi> Caesars
<pb facs="tcp:18816:22"/>
                        <hi>Sword from him, and with the same kil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>d</hi> La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ianus <hi>a</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Tribune, <hi>and lastly, ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ld and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> Caesar <hi>built the Castles of</hi> Dou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>, Canterbury, <hi>and the Tower of</hi> London.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Theomantius, 37.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THen <hi>Theomantius</hi> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> all blood)</l>
                        <l>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> Sonne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> his Father <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Reign'd three and twenty yeeres, a King in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>Whose Picture stands on <hi>Luds</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> gate.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Cimbelinus.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>IN this Kings reigne, (the glorious King of Kings</l>
                        <l>In person came, and mans saluation brings)</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:18816:23"/>
When through the world all bloody wars did cease,</l>
                        <l>(For our soules peace) then came the Prince of peace.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Our Sauiour</hi> Iesus Christ <hi>was borne in his reigne, in the 42. yeere of</hi> Augustus Caesar, <hi>then being Emperour of</hi> Rome: Cimbelinus <hi>was the Sonne of</hi> Iheomantius,</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="A.D." type="period">
            <head>Yeeres after Christ.</head>
            <div n="1 (cont.)" type="part">
               <div type="subpart">
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Guiderius, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, 21.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THis King and Sub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>cts, brauely, nobly ioyne,</l>
                        <l>To hold from <hi>Rome</hi> the tributary Coyne:</l>
                        <l>But <hi>Claudius Caesar</hi> with an Army came,</l>
                        <l>The <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap>t</hi> bold rebellious hearts to tame;</l>
                        <l>One <hi>Hamon</hi> there (a <hi>Romane)</hi> di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</l>
                        <l>Himselfe like to a <hi>Britaine</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Guiderius</hi> brauely cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>de his fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>s amaine,</l>
                        <l>Was by disg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ifed <hi>Hamon</hi> falfely slaine.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When</hi> Guiderius <hi>was King of</hi> Britaine, <hi>our Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer suffered vnder</hi> Claudius Tiberius Caesar, <hi>being the Romane Emperour.</hi> Guiderius <hi>was a valiant Prince.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:23"/>
                     <head>Aruiragus, 44.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>STout <hi>Aruiragus</hi> being in the fight,</l>
                        <l>The Kings death added fury to his might:</l>
                        <l>Perceiu'd the <hi>Britaine</hi> Host, almost dismaide,</l>
                        <l>In's brothers Armour hee himselfe array'd,</l>
                        <l>The Souldiers thought the King againe suruiu'd.</l>
                        <l>With co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>rage new through euery veine deriu'd,</l>
                        <l>Braue <hi>Aruiragus,</hi> like a Tempest goes,</l>
                        <l>And pell mell topsieturuy throwes his foes.</l>
                        <l>Grear <hi>Caesar</hi> with his <hi>Romane</hi> army fled,</l>
                        <l>The King tooke <hi>Hamon,</hi> and cut off his head,</l>
                        <l>And more, with sharp reuenge his wrath t'appease,</l>
                        <l>Hew'd him piece-meale, and cast him in the Seas,</l>
                        <l>The place long time, this name did then allow,</l>
                        <l>Of <hi>Hamons hauen,</hi> or <hi>Southampton</hi> now.</l>
                        <l>The Emperour would quite the tribute free,</l>
                        <l>If <hi>Brittaines</hi> King his Sonne in law would be.</l>
                        <l>Then <hi>Aruarigue</hi> did faire <hi>Genisse</hi> marry,</l>
                        <l>And <hi>Claudius Caesar</hi> heere a while did tarry,</l>
                        <l>He builded <hi>Gloster,</hi> whil'st he heere remain'd:</l>
                        <l>The King dyed hauing twenty eight yeeres reign'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:24"/>
                     <head>Marius, 73.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>IN this Kings reigne the lawlesse proling <hi>Pict,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>(A Nation strange) did the North part afflict:</l>
                        <l>But <hi>Marius,</hi> in a battell slew their King,</l>
                        <l>And all their power did to subiection bring.</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Picts</hi> from <hi>Scythia,</hi> into <hi>Scotland</hi> came,</l>
                        <l>Rude, barbarous, ingratefull, hard to tame:</l>
                        <l>For by the <hi>Scotsh</hi> Kings fauour hauing got</l>
                        <l>Possession, they oft warr'd vpon the <hi>Scot.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And more and more that Kingdome they annoy'd,</l>
                        <l>Till <hi>Kennith Scotlands</hi> King, them all destroy'd:</l>
                        <l>Yeeres fifty three reign'd <hi>Marius</hi> iust and wise,</l>
                        <l>Dyed: and at <hi>Carleile</hi> his Corps royall lies.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Much about this time,</hi> Ioseph <hi>of</hi> Arimathea, <hi>after he had buried Christ (being hated for it of the mis-beleeuing</hi> Iewes) <hi>came into this Land, and first planted Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity heere, built a Chappell at</hi> Glastenburgh: <hi>Some wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters say, that he repaired</hi> Chester, <hi>and was buried there.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:24"/>
                     <head>Coylus, 124.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>IN <hi>Rome</hi> this King was fostred all his youth,</l>
                        <l>He lou'd Peace, Iustice, Fortitude and Truth:</l>
                        <l>He builded <hi>Colchester,</hi> and did suruiue,</l>
                        <l>Till he had reign'd a Kings yeeres, fifty fiue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Coylus <hi>was the Sonne of</hi> Marius, <hi>hee was buried at</hi> Yorke.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Lucius, 179.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THe first of Kings that was a Christian nam'd,</l>
                        <l>Was <hi>Lucius</hi> (with the spirit of God inflam'd)</l>
                        <l>The Bread of life he did receiue with ioy,</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Pagan</hi> Idols hee did all destroy,</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Flamines</hi> and <hi>Archflamines</hi> he downe cast,</l>
                        <l>And Bishops and Archbishops here he plac'd,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:18816:25"/>
He lou'd and fear'd th'eternall <hi>Three in one,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And dyed when he had 12 yeeres kept the Throne.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This was the first Christian King of</hi> Brittaine, <hi>he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed twentie eight Idolatrous Temples of the</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>agan <hi>gods to be made Cathedrall Churches, for the seruice of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> God;</hi> Elutherius <hi>was then Bishop of</hi> Rome, <hi>King</hi> Lucius <hi>was buried at</hi> Glocester: <hi>hee dyed leauing no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>, so that this Land was in a burly-burly</hi> 15. <hi>yeeres, through want of a King.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Seuerus, 194.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THis was a <hi>Romane</hi> Emperour, and was slaine</l>
                        <l>At <hi>York</hi> the eighteenth yeere of his proud reigne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>Hee was an <hi>Alien</hi> and a stranger heere,</l>
                        <l>And therefore bought his vsurpation deare:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Seuerus <hi>was</hi> 60. <hi>yeeres old when hee tooke the crowne, and caused a wall of Turfe to be made betwixt</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland <hi>to kepe this Land from the incursions of the</hi> Scots <hi>and</hi> Picts: <hi>the wall reached from Tyne to the</hi> Scottish <hi>Seas,</hi> 112. <hi>miles.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:25"/>
                     <head>Bassianus, 212.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>SEuerus</hi> here did wed a <hi>Brittish</hi> Dame,</l>
                        <l>By whom this King (their Son) the Crowne did claime.</l>
                        <l>But after sixe veeres time, he left this Land,</l>
                        <l>And had the <hi>Romane</hi> Empire at's command.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Bassianus <hi>was brought from</hi> Rome <hi>by his Father</hi> Seuerus.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Carausius, 290.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When</hi> Carausi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>reigned,</hi> Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesian <hi>was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>mperor.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Alectus, 292.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THis King (of meane birth) did the Crown attain</l>
                        <l>After seuen yeeres, was by <hi>Alectus</hi> slaine:</l>
                        <l>Thre yeeres <hi>Alectus</hi> did in state recide,</l>
                        <l>Our Protomartyr then Saint <hi>Alban</hi> dyde.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Dioclesian <hi>and</hi> Maximilian <hi>ruled the</hi> Romane <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18816:26"/>
                        <hi>when Saint</hi> Albane <hi>suffered;</hi> Alectus <hi>was sent from</hi> Rome <hi>against</hi> Carausius: <hi>this</hi> Alectus <hi>was a cruell Tyrant, and was also slame by</hi> Asclepiodatus.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Asclepiodatus, 299.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>ASclepiodatus,</hi> (in a mortall Fight)</l>
                        <l>Suodude the <hi>Romane</hi> Generall <hi>Gallus</hi> might,</l>
                        <l>Kil'd him, and cast him head-long in a Brooke,</l>
                        <l>Whence <hi>Gallus</hi> or <hi>Wallbrooke,</hi> for name it tooke,</l>
                        <l>And as <hi>Alectus</hi> did <hi>Carausius</hi> kill,</l>
                        <l>So did this King <hi>Alectus</hi> life bloud spill,</l>
                        <l>And after two yeeres reigne in mortall strife,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Asclepiodatus</hi> slaine lost Crowne and life.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Gallus <hi>Brooke or</hi> Wallbrooke <hi>tooke the name from</hi> Gallus <hi>a</hi> Romane <hi>Captaine, slaine by</hi> Asclepiodatus, <hi>and throwne into that Brooke.</hi> Asclepiodatus <hi>was after slaine by</hi> Coil <hi>Duke of</hi> Colchester. <hi>Some write that</hi> Asclepiodatus <hi>reigned</hi> 30. <hi>yeeres.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:26"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Coil</hi> raigned 14. yeeres. 301.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>COlchesters</hi> Duke <hi>Coil</hi> in the Throne inuested,</l>
                        <l>Was by <hi>Constantius Caesar</hi> much molested:</l>
                        <l>Till <hi>Coil</hi> gaue's Daughter to him for his Bride,</l>
                        <l>And paid <hi>Romes</hi> tribute, that was long denide.</l>
                        <l>The Lady was of beauty most diuine,</l>
                        <l>Faire <hi>Hellen,</hi> Mother to great <hi>Constantine.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>The King at <hi>Colchester,</hi> dead, laide in's Tombe,</l>
                        <l>His Sonne <hi>Constantius</hi> did supply his roome.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This Hellen reedified</hi> Ierusalem, <hi>and adorned it with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>oodly Churches. She also walle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> London and Colchester.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Constantius, 305.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>SPaine, Italy, France, Britaines</hi> Emperor,</l>
                        <l>Foure yeeres he raign'd heere, with Maiesticke power,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:18816:27"/>
True Honour was the ayme at which he shot.</l>
                        <l>Iust, Valiant, these reports his Actions got.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This</hi> Constantius <hi>was Grandfather to</hi> Constantine <hi>the Great: he came from</hi> Rome <hi>to this Ile, and was bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried at</hi> Yorke.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Constantine, 306,</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>GReat Emp'ror <hi>Constantine,</hi> surnam'd the Great:</l>
                        <l>In all respects a worthy Prince compleate,</l>
                        <l>The glorious Gospell, he ador'd, and fear'd,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Constantinople</hi> famously he rear'd,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Maxentius, Romes</hi> great Tyrant, (most abhor'd)</l>
                        <l>He made him flie from his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> sword.</l>
                        <l>Belou'd, be wail'd, high honor'd and admir'd,</l>
                        <l>In grace with God and men, his dayes expir'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This worthy Prince</hi> Constantine <hi>was borne in this Land, the Sonne of</hi> Constantius <hi>and</hi> Hellen. <hi>After</hi> Constantius <hi>decease, our Land was molested by</hi> Octaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Maximus <hi>and others for many yeers. These times are so diuersly written of in Histories, that a man knowes not which to beleeue most.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:27"/>
                     <head>84. Constantinus, 337.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>85. Constans, 340.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THese two were Brothers of the Royall line,</l>
                        <l>And Sonnes vnto the Emperour <hi>Constantine:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Ambition and debate for Kingly Raigne,</l>
                        <l>Was the vnnaturall cause they both were slaine.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Kings and Louers can brook no partners: for these two brothers were each others destruction.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>86. Octauius, 345.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>87. Traherus, 349.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>OCtauius</hi> Duke of <hi>Windsor</hi> to oke the Crowne,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Traherus</hi> came from <hi>Rome</hi> and put him downe:</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:18816:28"/>
The Land was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ull with hurly-burlies fild,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Traherus</hi> by <hi>Octtauius</hi> last was kild.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Theodosius <hi>was Emperour of the East <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>d</hi> Macri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>of the West: Some write that</hi> Octauius <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> 54. <hi>yeeres</hi> Noncredo.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>88. <hi>Constantius</hi> the third. 353.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The <hi>Romane</hi> Empire he did closely sway,</l>
                        <l>And as a King this Land did him obay:</l>
                        <l>Th' Apostate <hi>Iulian</hi> was the Emp'rour next,</l>
                        <l>By whom the Christians all were slaine, or vext.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Constantius <hi>was a victorious Prince, and triumphed in</hi> Rome: <hi>yet a cruell oppressor, and an Arian hereticke.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>89 Maximinianus. 375.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>NExt <hi>Iulian,</hi> raigned <hi>Valentinian,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And after him, succeeded <hi>Gratian</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:18816:28"/>
                           <hi>Maximi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap>nus</hi> was of life depriu'd,</l>
                        <l>'Cause he with <hi>Gratian</hi> for the Empire striu'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>How like</hi> Bauius <hi>these tyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ts confi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>med one another; these were all Emperours of Rome, &amp; Kings of Brittaine,</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>90. Gratian. 376.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THen <hi>Gratian</hi> claim'd this Kingdome as his right<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>But hauing gain'd it, he was slaine in fight:</l>
                        <l>Fierce warres the <hi>Romane</hi> Empire did deuide,</l>
                        <l>And <hi>Caesars</hi> and their <hi>Viceroyes</hi> fought and dyde.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Honorius</hi> Romes Tribunall did obtaine,</l>
                        <l>Next after him did <hi>Theodosius</hi> raigne,</l>
                        <l>Then did the <hi>Scot</hi> ioyne with the barbarous <hi>Pict,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>This headlesse, Kinglesse Kingdome to afflict.</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Romane</hi> Scepter we had long obayd,</l>
                        <l>Foure hundred eightythree yeeres Tribute payd;</l>
                        <l>And now this land shook off their wrongd comand</l>
                        <l>When Ciuill discord had neer spoyl'd this Land.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In one battell the whole nation of the</hi> Piets <hi>were quite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>xtinguished about this time the</hi> Romanes <hi>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>uernement <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>nded here. Gratian was a Brittaine Emperour but foure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:29"/>
                     <head>91 Vortiger. 447.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THis King through murder did the Throne ascend,</l>
                        <l>And had a troublous Raigne, and murdrous end:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Constanes (Constantines)</hi> lawfull Heyre and Sonne,</l>
                        <l>By <hi>Vortigers</hi> false meanes to death was done.</l>
                        <l>For which (to keepe the Crowne vniustly gain'd)</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Saxons</hi> for his ayde he entertain'd.</l>
                        <l>Then <hi>Hengist,</hi> with his Brother <hi>Horsus</hi> crue,</l>
                        <l>In <hi>Britaines</hi> best bloud did their blades embrew.</l>
                        <l>King <hi>Vortiger</hi> with doting loue inthral'd,</l>
                        <l>Match't <hi>Hengists</hi> daughter, beauteous <hi>Rowan</hi> cal'd:</l>
                        <l>But <hi>Saxons</hi> troopes, on troopes came in so fast,</l>
                        <l>That <hi>Britaines</hi> did depriue the King at last.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hee murdered his lawfull Prince, and vsurping the Throne, was enforced to haue ayd of the</hi> Saxons, <hi>who at the last almost ouer-ran this Kingdome, but the</hi> Brittaines <hi>deposed</hi> Vortiger, <hi>and crowned his Sonne</hi> Vortimer.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:29"/>
                     <head>92. Vortimer. 454.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THen <note n="a" place="inline">On the Plaine of <hi>Salisbury</hi> at <hi>Stonehing</hi> (where the Stones are to be seene at this day.)</note> 
                           <hi>Vortimer,</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Vortiger,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Vpon the <hi>Saxons</hi> made successfull warre:</l>
                        <l>Till he by <hi>Rowan</hi> was by craft o'r-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ane,</l>
                        <l>From whose false hands, he dy'd by poys'nous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>Deposed <hi>Vortiger</hi> (his Sonne once slaine)</l>
                        <l>His ill gain'd, ill kept Crowne he gain'd againe:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hengistus</hi> with his <hi>Saxon</hi> fresh supplies,</l>
                        <l>The Plaines of <hi>Salisbury</hi> did all surprize.</l>
                        <l>The King tooke counsell of his <hi>Brittaine</hi> Lords,</l>
                        <l>And all in generall to a Peace accords.</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Saxons</hi> and the <hi>Brittaines</hi> did agree,</l>
                        <l>That at this meeting all vnarm'd should be:</l>
                        <l>But traitrous <hi>Hengist</hi> did a watch-word speake,</l>
                        <l>Which did the Law of Armes, and Honour breake,</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Saxons</hi> vnsuspected drew forth Kniues,</l>
                        <l>Foure hundred, threescore Lords, all lost their liues,</l>
                        <l>All <hi>Brittaine</hi> Nobles, then the <hi>Saxons</hi> there,</l>
                        <l>Surpris'd the King, constraining him through feare</l>
                        <l>To giue <hi>Kent, Sussex, Suffolke, Norfolke,</hi> and</l>
                        <l>That <hi>Hengist,</hi> King should in those Lands command,</l>
                        <l>But after nineteene yeeres were quite expir'd,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:18816:30"/>
                           <note n="*" place="inline">The King &amp; Queene burnt to death. Vortiger married his owne daughter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> his third wife.</note> Reuenging Fire, the King in's Castle fir'd.</l>
                        <l>And thus the <hi>Saxons,</hi> and Great <hi>Hengists</hi> Heyres,</l>
                        <l>Won Shire to Shire, till <hi>Brittaine</hi> all was theirs.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>93. Aurelius Ambrose. 466.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>IN honour of the Nobles basely slaine,</l>
                        <l>This King set vp the Ston<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>s on <hi>Saru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap> 
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>The <hi>Gospell</hi> with great zeale he dignifi'd,</l>
                        <l>Raign'd thirty two yeeres, and by poyson dy'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This King was a Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ne, and brother to Vter Pendra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon that succeeded him.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:30"/>
                     <head>94. <hi>Vter Pendragon</hi> raigned 18 yeeres. 498.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THis King (by <hi>Merlins</hi> meanes a skilfull man)</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Igrene,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Cornewals</hi> Dutchesse wan:</l>
                        <l>On her he got, (though illegittimate)</l>
                        <l>The Christian Worthy, <hi>Arthur,</hi> stilde the Great.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Vter Pendragon <hi>poysoned by the</hi> Saxons, <hi>after he had reigned</hi> 18. <hi>yeeres.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>95. Arthur. 516.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>OF the nine Worthies was this Worthy one,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Denmarke,</hi> and <hi>Norway,</hi> did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>y his Throne:</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:18816:31"/>
In twelue set Battels he the <hi>Saxons</hi> beat,</l>
                        <l>Great, and to make his Victories more great,</l>
                        <l>The Faithlesse <hi>Sarazons</hi> he ouercame,</l>
                        <l>And made them honour high <hi>Iehonah's</hi> Name.</l>
                        <l>The Noble order of the <hi>Table round,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>At <hi>Winchester,</hi> his first inuention found.</l>
                        <l>Whilst he beyond Sea fought to win Renowne,</l>
                        <l>His Nephew <hi>Mordred</hi> did vsurpe his Crowne,</l>
                        <l>But he return'd, and <hi>Mordred</hi> did confound,</l>
                        <l>And in the fight great <hi>Arthur</hi> got a wound,</l>
                        <l>That prou'd lo mortall, that immortally</l>
                        <l>It made him liue, although it made him dye.</l>
                        <l>Full sixteene yeeres the Diadem he wore,</l>
                        <l>And euery day gaind Honour more and more.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Arthur the great was buried at</hi> Glastenbury.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>96 Constantine, the fourth. 542.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>97 Aurelius Conanus. 545.</head>
                     <figure/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>COnstantine</hi> was by King <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> kil'd:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Aurelius (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>)</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> yeeres held,</l>
                        <l>Seuen Kingdomes heere at once the <hi>Saxons</hi> held,</l>
                        <l>And slaughter launc'd, when proud ambition sweld.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This</hi> Constantine <hi>was kinsman to King</hi> Arthur, <hi>and</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18816:31"/>
                        <hi>was slaine by</hi> Conanus. Constantine <hi>was a wicked Prince, and slaine in battell by his kinsman</hi> Conanus, <hi>when he had reigned neere</hi> 3. <hi>yeeres. Of the tyme of this</hi> Aurelius Conanus <hi>his reigne, there is much variation in Histories.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Heere beganne the Heptarchy, or</hi> 7 <hi>Kingdomes in this Land, namely,</hi> Kent, South-Saxons, West-Saxons, East-Saxons, Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland, Mercia, and East-Angles: <hi>which diuision continued more then</hi> 600. <hi>yeeres, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was all vnited into one Monarchy the names of the Kings, &amp; times of their reignes, and limits of their Kingdomes, are hereunder expressed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1 <hi>KEnt</hi> was only a kingdome which had 17 Kings, namely, 1 <hi>Hengist,</hi> 2 <hi>Eske,</hi> 3 <hi>Octa,</hi> 4 <hi>Ymerick,</hi> 5 <hi>Ethelbert,</hi> who was the first Christian King of <hi>Kent,</hi> hee was an ayde and helper of <hi>Sebert,</hi> King of the <hi>East-Saxons,</hi> in the famous and memorable buildings of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Pauls Church in <hi>London,</hi> and Saint Peters at <hi>Westminster.</hi> 6 <hi>Eabald,</hi> 7 <hi>Ercombert,</hi> 8 <hi>Egbert,</hi> 9 <hi>Lother,</hi> 10 <hi>Edrick,</hi> 11 <hi>Withred,</hi> 12 <hi>Edbert,</hi> 13 <hi>Edelbert,</hi> 14 <hi>Alick,</hi> 15 <hi>Ethilbert,</hi> 16 <hi>Cuthred,</hi> 17 <hi>Baldred.</hi> These Kings reigned in <hi>Kent</hi> 372. yeeres, from the yeere of Grace 455. till the yeere 827.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <pb facs="tcp:18816:32"/>
2 The kingdome of the South-Saxons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Counties of <hi>Sussex</hi> and <hi>Surrie,</hi> it continued from the yeere 488. vntill the yeere 601. being 113 yeeres: they had three Kings, namely, 1 <hi>Ella,</hi> 2 <hi>Cissa,</hi> 3 <hi>Ethelwolfe</hi> a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an King, 4 <hi>Berthrum,</hi> 5 <hi>Authum.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3 The West-Saxons kingdome, whose be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning was in the yeer 519. and ended, Anno. 166. lasted 561 yeeres, hauing 17 Kings, namely, 1 <hi>Cherdick,</hi> 2 <hi>Kenrick,</hi> 3 <hi>Chequilin,</hi> 4 <hi>Cealick,</hi> 5 <hi>Chelwold,</hi> 6 <hi>Kingils, a Christian,</hi> 7 <hi>Kenwald,</hi> 8 <hi>Eskwin,</hi> 9 <hi>Kentwin,</hi> 10 <hi>Ceadwald,</hi> 11 <hi>Inas,</hi> 12 <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi> 13 <hi>Cuthred,</hi> 14 <hi>Sigebert,</hi> 15 <hi>Kenwolfe,</hi> 16 <hi>Brightrik,</hi> 17 <hi>Egbert,:</hi> These Kings had vnder their gouernments, the Counties of Cornewall, Deuonshire, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mersetshire, Wiltshire, Hampshire and Bark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire.</p>
                     <p n="4">4 The East-Saxons reigned 281 yeeres, beginning, Anno. 527, and ending in the yeere 827. Their bounds were Essex and Middle-Sex, and their Kings were in number 14, namely, 1 <hi>Erchenwin,</hi> 2 <hi>Sledda,</hi> 3 <hi>Sebert</hi> a Christian King, that assisted <hi>Ethelbert,</hi> King of Kent, in the building of the Churches of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and Saint <hi>Peter</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said. 4 <hi>Seward,</hi> 5 <hi>Sigebert,</hi> 6 <hi>Sigibext,</hi> 7 <hi>Swithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line,</hi> 8 <hi>Sighere,</hi> 9 <hi>Sebba,</hi> 10 <hi>Sigherd,</hi> 11 <hi>Seo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frid,</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18816:32"/>
12 <hi>Offa,</hi> 13 <hi>Selred,</hi> 14 <hi>Suthred.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5 Northumberland was sometimes diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into two kingdomes. It contained the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ties of <hi>Yorkshire, Durham, Lancashire, West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merland, Cumberland</hi> and <hi>Northumberland:</hi> this Kingdome beganne in the yeere of our Lord, 547. and expired in 926. continuing 379. yeeres vnder 23 Kings, whose names were, 1 <hi>Ella,</hi> 2 <hi>Adda,</hi> 3 <hi>Theodwald,</hi> 4 <hi>Frethulse,</hi> 5 <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odrick,</hi> 6 <hi>Ethelrick,</hi> 7 <hi>Ethelfrid,</hi> 8 <hi>Edwin,</hi> 9 <hi>Os<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wald,</hi> 10 <hi>Oswy,</hi> 11 <hi>Egfrid,</hi> 12 <hi>Alkfrid,</hi> 13 <hi>Ofred,</hi> 14 <hi>Kenred,</hi> 15 <hi>Oswicke,</hi> 16 <hi>Ceolnuph,</hi> 17 <hi>Egbert,</hi> 18 <hi>Oswolfe,</hi> 19 <hi>Edilwald,</hi> 20 <hi>Alured,</hi> 21 <hi>Ethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> 22 <hi>Alswald,</hi> 23 <hi>Osr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>d.</hi> Amongst these, Edwin was their first Christian King.</p>
                     <p n="6">6 The East Angles vnder 15 seuerall Kings, continued 353 yeeres, beginning in <hi>Anno,</hi> 575. and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> III 914. their Territories were Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> Nor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>olk, Cambridgeshire and the Ile <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, Ely, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ir Kings names were, 1 <hi>Vffa,</hi> 2 <hi>Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>us,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Red<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ald</hi> their first Christian King, 4 <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi> 5 <hi>Sigebert,</hi> 6 <hi>Egrik,</hi> 7 <hi>Anna,</hi> 8 <hi>Ethelbert,</hi> 9 <hi>Ethwald,</hi> 10 <hi>Aldwol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>e,</hi> 11 <hi>Aswald,</hi> 12 <hi>Beorn,</hi> 13 <hi>Ethelred,</hi> 14 <hi>Ethelbert,</hi> 15 <hi>Edmund.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="7">7 The seuenth Kingdome were the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, who had 20 Kings and 17 shires vnder their command: their Kings were, 1 <hi>Creda,</hi> 2 <hi>Wibba,</hi> 3 <hi>Cheorle,</hi> 4 <hi>Penda,</hi> 5 <hi>Peada</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18816:33"/>
their first Christian King, 6 <hi>Wolfere,</hi> 7 <hi>Ethelred,</hi> 8 <hi>Kenred,</hi> 9 <hi>Chelred,</hi> 10 <hi>Ethebald,</hi> 11 <hi>Offa,</hi> 12 <hi>Egfrid,</hi> 13 <hi>Kenwolfe,</hi> 14 <hi>Kenelme,</hi> 15 <hi>Chelwolse,</hi> 16 <hi>Bernulfe,</hi> 17 <hi>Ludecan,</hi> 18 <hi>Whitlafe,</hi> 19 <hi>Bertwolfe,</hi> 20 <hi>Burdred.</hi> Their bounds and dominions were 17 Counties, as of Northampton, Leister, Darby, Lincolne, Huntington, Rutland, Notingham, Ches<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire, Oxfordshire, Staffordshire, Worcester<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire, Glostershire, Shropshire, Warwicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire, Bedfordshire, Buckinghamshire, and Hartfordshire.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>98 Vortiporus. 578.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>99 Malgo. 581.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THis <hi>Vortipore</hi> from good Kings did decline,</l>
                        <l>Kept his wiues Daughter as his Conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ine:</l>
                        <l>And <hi>Malgo</hi> put his Wife to bloudy slaughter,</l>
                        <l>To liue in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ncest with his brothers Daughter.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>About this time <hi>Augustine</hi> the Monke, <hi>Mellitus, Iustus</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> all learned men, came from <hi>Rome,</hi> and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:18816:33"/>
the Gospell to the English men. <hi>Vortipore</hi> reigned 4. yeeres. <hi>Malgo,</hi> his raigne was short and wicked.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>100. Careticus. 586.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>GVrmundus</hi> hither out of <hi>Ireland</hi> came,</l>
                        <l>And with the <hi>Saxons</hi> ioyn'd with sword and flame:</l>
                        <l>The King to <hi>Wales</hi> did flye, his life to saue,</l>
                        <l>Whereas he chang'd his Kingdome for a Graue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>He reigned 3. yeeres: and now the Saxons had all Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, the Brittaines and their Kings being expulsed and chased to the West sides of the Riuers Seauerne, and Dee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Cadwane. 613.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THis <hi>Cadwane</hi> did the <hi>Saxon</hi> force withstand,</l>
                        <l>Of <hi>Ethelfridus</hi> of <hi>Northumberland:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:18816:34"/>
And made him to intreate and sue for peace:</l>
                        <l>Raign'd two and twenty yeeres, then did decease.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>102. Cadwallin. 635.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>CAdwallin</hi> slew King <hi>Edwin, Egfrids</hi> Sonne,</l>
                        <l>He <hi>Penda Mercias</hi> King did ouer-runne:</l>
                        <l>He neuer fought but Conquest home did bring,</l>
                        <l>And eight and forty yeeres did raigne a King.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Cadwallin <hi>was buried at</hi> London <hi>in Saint Martins Church neere Ludgate.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>103. Cadwallader. 685.</head>
                     <figure/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THis King renowned was both neere and farre,</l>
                        <l>The last of <hi>Brittaines</hi> Kings, <hi>Cadwallader,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:18816:34"/>
The name of <hi>Brittaine</hi> was quite alterd then,</l>
                        <l>The Kings of <hi>England,</hi> subiects, Englishmen.</l>
                        <l>Then in this Land, of Kings there raign'd so many,</l>
                        <l>That Subiects knew not to obey all, or any:</l>
                        <l>Their names and times of raigne I meane to tell,</l>
                        <l>Should I write more, my Book too big would swell.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Here the inhabitants lost the name of <hi>Brittaines,</hi> the land being called <hi>Anglia,</hi> or <hi>England,</hi> and the people Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishmen.</p>
                     <p>687. <hi>Cadwallader</hi> left his Crowne, went to <hi>Rome,</hi> and dyed there.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="Kings of the West Saxons" type="subpart">
                  <head>These Kings following were <hi>of the West Saxons.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>726 <hi>Ethelard</hi> was King of the <hi>West Saxons.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>740. <hi>Cuthred</hi> succeeded him.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:35"/>
                     <head>757. <hi>Sigebert</hi> next him, was slaine by a Swineheard.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>758. <hi>Kenulphus</hi> was slaine by a kinsman of <hi>Sigebert.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>786. <hi>Brithricus.</hi> In his time it rained blood.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IN the 800. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>re of Christ, the</hi> Danes <hi>landed at</hi> Port<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>but</hi> Brithricus <hi>beat them backe, and afterwards was poysoned by his wife</hi> Ethelburga.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>Eghricus, <hi>King of</hi> West-Saxons.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:35"/>
                     <head>839. <hi>Adelnulphus</hi> ouercame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Danes,</hi> that came to inuade the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome with 350. ships.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>857. Athelbald.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>860. Athelbrict.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>866. Etheldrid.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:36"/>
                     <head>872. Aelfred.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>900. Edward <hi>surnamed</hi> Senior.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <p>Heere end the Kings of the <hi>West-Saxons,</hi> now fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Kings of <hi>Britaine.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="Kings of Britain" type="subpart">
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>104. <hi>Athelstane</hi> reigned 15. yeeres. 905.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THis King did tame the <hi>Welsh,</hi> the <hi>Danes</hi> sub du'd,</l>
                        <l>He conquerd <hi>Scotland</hi> and the <hi>Marches</hi> rude:</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Danish</hi> Gyant <hi>Colebrand</hi> in <hi>Hyde-meade,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>By <hi>Guy</hi> the Earle of <hi>Warwicke</hi> was strucke dead.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>King</hi> Athelstane <hi>was crowned at</hi> Kingstone, <hi>hee brought this Land againe to one sole Monarchy, he was buried at</hi> Malmsbury.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:36"/>
                     <head>105. Edmund. 940.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>106. Eldred. 946.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>EDmond,</hi> reigned next his brother <hi>Athelstane,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And after fiue yeeres was vntimely slaine:</l>
                        <l>Nine yeeres was <hi>Eldred Englands</hi> King inst<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>d,</l>
                        <l>Th'insulting <hi>Danes,</hi> he from this Realme exilde.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Edmund <hi>was buried at</hi> Glastenbury. Eldred <hi>was brother to</hi> Edmund, <hi>he was crowned at</hi> Kingstone, <hi>he expelled the</hi> Danes, <hi>and was buried at</hi> Winchester.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>107 Edwin. 955.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>108 Edgar. 959.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THen <hi>Edwin</hi> (as his right) obtain'd the Crowne,</l>
                        <l>For Rape, and brutish Iust he was put downe,</l>
                        <l>His brother <hi>Edgar</hi> a man iust and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>se,</l>
                        <l>By <hi>Edwin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> fall, vnto the Throne did rise.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:18816:37"/>
The <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Commonweale</hi> (long time deform'd)</l>
                        <l>He by his Iustice and good Lawes reform'd.</l>
                        <l>Raign'd sixteen yeeres, and then by death assail'd,</l>
                        <l>As he had liu'd belou'd, he dy'd bewail'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Edwin <hi>was</hi> Eldreds <hi>kinsman crowned at</hi> Kingstone: <hi>he defloured his owne kinswoman and slew her husband, for which odious acts hee was deposed of all Kingly dignity, and his brother</hi> Edgar <hi>was in his stead crowned at</hi> Bathe. Edgar <hi>had</hi> 3600 <hi>ships to withstand the inuasion of his enemies, hee founded and repaired</hi> 47. <hi>relligious houses, hee was buried at</hi> Glastenbury.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>109 Edward. 975.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>110 Etheldred. 978.</head>
                     <figure/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>EDward</hi> was slain by his accurst Stepmother,</l>
                        <l>Ayded by <hi>Etheldred</hi> his cruell brother.</l>
                        <l>This <hi>Etheldred</hi> caus'd all the <hi>Danes</hi> be slaine:</l>
                        <l>And dyed the thirty eight yeere of his raigne.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>He was crowned at</hi> Kingstone: <hi>he reigned</hi> 3 <hi>yeeres, and was buried at</hi> Shaftsbury.</p>
                     <p>Etheldred <hi>was buried in S.</hi> Pauls <hi>Church in</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:37"/>
                     <head>111 Edmond Ironside. 1016.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THe <hi>Danes</hi> came to reuenge with sword and fire,</l>
                        <l>Both Kings to Combat single did desire:</l>
                        <l>On equall termes, their valours both were tride,</l>
                        <l>In loue the Realme betwixt them they deuide.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Edricus <hi>a traitor murdered King</hi> Edmond Ironside, <hi>for the which</hi> Canutus <hi>the</hi> Dane <hi>caused him to bee tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented to death grieuously as he deserued.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>112 Canutus. 1018.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THis mighty <hi>Danish</hi> King foure Kingdomes hel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Danes, Norway, England, Scotland</hi> he compeld,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:18816:38"/>
Taxes and toles he rais'd in <hi>England</hi> here,</l>
                        <l>And dyed when he had gouern'd twenty yeere.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In</hi> Canutus <hi>his raigne the</hi> Danes <hi>possessed all</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: <hi>he lies buried at</hi> Winchester.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>113 Harold. 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>8.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>114 Hardicanutus. 1041.</head>
                     <figure/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>HArold</hi> from <hi>England</hi> did exile his Mother,</l>
                        <l>And kild <hi>Allured</hi> his King and his Brother:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hardicanutus</hi> then the Crowne obtain'd,</l>
                        <l>Who quaffing died, when he 3. yeeres had raig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>'d.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Harold <hi>was a</hi> Tyrant: <hi>hee was called</hi> Hartfoote <hi>for his swift running: he murdered Prince</hi> Allured <hi>hee raign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed three yeeres, and was buried at</hi> Westminster.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hee caused the body of</hi> Harold <hi>to be digged out of the graue, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ast into the</hi> Thames, <hi>in reuenge of his brother</hi> Allureds <hi>death: he was buried at</hi> Winchester.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:38"/>
                     <head>115. Saint Edward. 1043.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="king">
                     <head>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>6. <hi>Harold</hi> the second. 1066.</head>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>SAint <hi>Edward</hi> from the <hi>Danes</hi> this Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>gdom freed,</l>
                        <l>And for he had no Heyre, he heere decreed,</l>
                        <l>That <hi>William</hi> Duke of <hi>Normandy</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>hou'd be</l>
                        <l>Next King, but <hi>Harold</hi> seeming to agree,</l>
                        <l>Assoone as <hi>Edward</hi> was laid in his Toombe,</l>
                        <l>This hasty <hi>Harold</hi> mounted in his roome,</l>
                        <l>But <hi>William</hi> came from <hi>Normandy</hi> amaine,</l>
                        <l>By whom King <hi>Harold</hi> was vnking'd and slaine.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <trailer>The end of the first part.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:18816:39"/>
               <head>The second part.</head>
               <div type="king">
                  <head>
                     <hi>William</hi> Conquerour. <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1066.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVHen <hi>Britains, Romanes, Saxons, Danes</hi> had done,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Normans</hi> (fiftly) <hi>Englands</hi> glory won,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>w Lords brought in new Lawes incontinent,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>nd all were Conquer'd but the County <hi>Kent.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>King <hi>William</hi> (after he had all surpriz'd)</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>lted, domineer'd, and tyranniz'd,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Englishmen (like slaues) their doores must lock,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> paine of death, each night at eight of clocke.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>English</hi> from all Office were disgrac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>d,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> in their places the proud <hi>French</hi> were plac'd.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> beating down the right, with wrong on wrong,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>aining men should speake the English tongue.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> so to bring o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>r memory to naught,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Grammar</hi> and the <hi>Lawes</hi> in French were taught,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> Sonnes, with <hi>Danes</hi> a mighty band,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> in <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>umber</hi> to inuade the Land,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18816:39"/>
Then <hi>Yorke</hi> was burnt, the wealth away was borne</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Danes</hi> on Composition home did turne.</l>
                     <l>A dearth in England was so great, that heere</l>
                     <l>Cats, Dogs, and mans flesh, was our wofull cheere.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Mercians</hi> and <hi>Northumbers</hi> they rebel'd,</l>
                     <l>Strong warres the <hi>Scots</hi> within our Country held:</l>
                     <l>The Ile of <hi>Ely</hi> did the King surprize,</l>
                     <l>He caus'd the Rebels lose hands, feet, and eyes.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Normans</hi> did rebell and were subdu'd,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Danes</hi> came and fled, with all their multitude.</l>
                     <l>The Kings sonne <hi>(Robert)</hi> by the French Kings ayd,</l>
                     <l>Did diuers parts of <hi>Normandy</hi> inuade.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Scots</hi> spoild <hi>England,</hi> with all might and maine,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Durhams</hi> Bishop in a broyle was slaine,</l>
                     <l>Heere euery Acre of mens Lands were measur'd.</l>
                     <l>And by a heauy taxe the King was treasur'd:</l>
                     <l>Slaine by a Deere the Kings sonne lost his life,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Glassenbury</hi> Monkes were kill'd in strife.</l>
                     <l>The English Nobles almost were decay'd,</l>
                     <l>And euery place of rule the <hi>Normans</hi> swai'd.</l>
                     <l>And all mens goods and lands, and coyn were rated</l>
                     <l>Through England, and vnto the King related.</l>
                     <l>The French mens pride did England ouerwhelme,</l>
                     <l>And grieuous tributes did oppresse the Realme.</l>
                     <l>Churches and Chappels were throwne down with speed,</l>
                     <l>To make <hi>New Forrest</hi> as the King decreed:</l>
                     <l>Who hauing rul'd in trouble, toyle and care,</l>
                     <l>And tryannously pol'd this Kingdome bare,</l>
                     <l>Neere twenty one yeeres, death was then his bane:</l>
                     <l>He lyes in <hi>Normandy,</hi> enterr'd at <hi>Cane.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>William Conquerour <hi>was crowned on Christmas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> 1067. <hi>the yeere then beginning on that day. In the</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:40"/>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Forrest in</hi> Hampshire <hi>called New Forrest, where this King had defased many Churches (wherein the name of God was called vpon) and placed wild Beasts for his disport: in the same Forrest two of his owne sonnes were slaine, Prince</hi> Robert <hi>killed by a Deere, and</hi> William Rufus <hi>by a Knight shooting at a Deere.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="king">
                  <head>William Rufus. An. Dom. 1087.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>WIlliam</hi> the cruell Conquerours second Sonne,</l>
                     <l>With ease, got what his Fathers paines had won,</l>
                     <l>Oppressed <hi>England</hi> he opprest and prest,</l>
                     <l>And great Exactions wrongfully did wrest.</l>
                     <l>For Symony, and base corrupting gold,</l>
                     <l>The King most Churches and Church-liuings sold,</l>
                     <l>And more, (his Subiects vilely to abuse)</l>
                     <l>Against them he in armes did arme the Iewes,</l>
                     <l>And swore if they the victory did gaine,</l>
                     <l>That he their faithlesse faith would entertaine.</l>
                     <l>Vpon his eldest brother hee rai'sd warres,</l>
                     <l>His youngest brother troubled him with iarres.</l>
                     <l>At <hi>London,</hi> such a furious winde did blow,</l>
                     <l>Which did sixe hundred houses ouerthrow.</l>
                     <l>The City <hi>Gloster</hi> was by <hi>Welshmen</hi> sack'd.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Northumberland</hi> was by King <hi>William</hi> wrack'd:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>William</hi> de <hi>Oue,</hi> and <hi>William</hi> de <hi>Aluery,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18816:40"/>
In cruell torments dyed at <hi>Salisbury.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Duke <hi>Robert</hi> laid all <hi>Normandy</hi> to gage</l>
                     <l>Vnto the King, warres with the <hi>Turkes</hi> to wage.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Westminster</hi> Hall was built, the <hi>Danes</hi> came in,</l>
                     <l>And th' <hi>Orchades,</hi> and the Ile of <hi>Man</hi> did win.</l>
                     <l>But as the King was hunting in <hi>Hampshire,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Sir <hi>Walter Tirr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ll</hi> shooting at a Deere,</l>
                     <l>The Arrow glauncing'gainst a Tree by chance,</l>
                     <l>Th'vnhappy King kild, by the haplesse Glaunce.</l>
                     <l>A Colliers Cart to <hi>Winchester</hi> did bring</l>
                     <l>The Corps, where vnbemoand they laid the King.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Rufus. <hi>In the</hi> 8. <hi>yeere of his reigne, the Christian Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my went to</hi> Ierusalem <hi>vnder the conduct of</hi> Godfry <hi>Duke of</hi> Bulleine, <hi>in which warres serued</hi> Robert <hi>Duke of</hi> Normandy <hi>the Kings eldest brother, who pawned his Dukedome for</hi> 16666 <hi>pounds weight of siluer. In the</hi> 11. <hi>yeere the Lands of the late Earle</hi> Godwine <hi>sunk in the sea, and are to this day called</hi> Godwine <hi>sands. This King died the</hi> 2. <hi>of</hi> August 1100. <hi>he reigned</hi> 12. <hi>yeeres,</hi> 11. <hi>moneths, and was buried at</hi> Winchester.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="king">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> the first. <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1100.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THis <hi>Henry</hi> (for his wisedome <hi>Beuclarke</hi> nam'd)</l>
                     <l>Th'vnlawfull Lawes and measures he reclaim'd.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18816:41"/>
The <hi>Norman</hi> Duke, eld'st Brother to the King,</l>
                     <l>To claime the Crowne a mighty Hoast did bring.</l>
                     <l>Saint <hi>Bartholomewes</hi> was founded and Saint <hi>Gyles,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And <hi>Henry</hi> stop'd Duke <hi>Roberts</hi> mouth with wiles.</l>
                     <l>Then peace was made; but after, warres did rise,</l>
                     <l>The King tooke's brother, and put out his eyes.</l>
                     <l>Here <hi>Windsor</hi> Church and Castle were erected,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Wales</hi> (rebeld) most sharpely was corrected.</l>
                     <l>All the King's Sonnes and eight score persons more,</l>
                     <l>Were drown'd by tempest neere the <hi>Norman</hi> shore.</l>
                     <l>Thus all his Ioy in Childrens losse bereft,</l>
                     <l>Saue onely <hi>Maud,</hi> the Widdow Empresse left,</l>
                     <l>Whom <hi>Geffrey Anioy's</hi> Earle to wife did get,</l>
                     <l>From whom did spring the name <hi>Plant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>genet.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The King proclaim'd his Daughter, or her seede,</l>
                     <l>After his death should in the Realme succeede,</l>
                     <l>And after thirty fiue yeeres time was past,</l>
                     <l>King <hi>Henry</hi> by a surfet breath'd his last.</l>
                     <l>Much trouble in his dayes this Kingdome wearied,</l>
                     <l>He dyed, and dead, at <hi>Redding</hi> he lies buried.</l>
                     <l>Thus God that lifts the low, casts downe the high,</l>
                     <l>Caus'd all the Conquerors sonnes vntimely dye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Henry <hi>the</hi> 1. <hi>He held the Crowne wrongfully from his elder brother</hi> Robert <hi>Duke of</hi> Normandy, <hi>and ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming him in battell, most vnnaturally put out his eies: he reigned</hi> 35. <hi>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>res, his braines, eyes and bowels were buried at</hi> Roane <hi>in</hi> France, <hi>and the rest of his body at</hi> Redding: <hi>his Phisician that opened his head, was killed suddainely with the stench of his braines.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="king">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:41"/>
                  <head>King Stephen. An. Dom. 1135.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>STephen</hi> Earle of <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>loign,</hi> (th'Earle of <hi>Bloys</hi> his son)</l>
                     <l>From th' <hi>Empresse Maud</hi> this famous Kingdome won.</l>
                     <l>Domestike, forraigne, dangerous discords,</l>
                     <l>'Twixt factions f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ctions, of the King and's Lords,</l>
                     <l>Wars 'twixt the <hi>King</hi> and th' <hi>Empresse</hi> for the crown,</l>
                     <l>Both tasted Fortunes fauours, and her frowne,</l>
                     <l>Now vp, now downe, like balles at Tennis tost,</l>
                     <l>Till <hi>Stephen</hi> gain'd the goale, and th'Empresse lost.</l>
                     <l>And after eighteene yeeres were come and gone,</l>
                     <l>The King not hauing any lawfull Sonne,</l>
                     <l>He dyed, and chang'd his Kingdome &amp; his strength,</l>
                     <l>For a small Sepulcher of sixe foote length.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <hi>King</hi> Stephen. <hi>He was noble, valiant, liberall, and poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique, and almost in continuall trouble. In the</hi> 1. <hi>yeere of his reigne a fire burnt all the streete, from</hi> London-stone East, <hi>to</hi> Pauls, <hi>and</hi> West, <hi>to Algate, and within</hi> 2. <hi>yeeres after, the ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ties of</hi> York, Rochester, <hi>and</hi> Bathe, <hi>were burnt. Hee reigned</hi> 18. <hi>yeeres,</hi> 10. <hi>moneths, and was buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at</hi> Feuersham.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="king">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:42"/>
                  <head>Henry the second. An Dom. 1154.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THis King vnto the Empresse <hi>Maud</hi> was Heyre,</l>
                     <l>And lawfully obtain'd the Regall Chayre,</l>
                     <l>He was couragious, and yet most vnchaste,</l>
                     <l>Which Vice, his other Vertues all defac'd.</l>
                     <l>He lou'd faire <hi>Rosamond,</hi> the worlds faire <hi>Rose,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For which his wife and children turn'd his foes.</l>
                     <l>He made his sonne Copartner in his Crowne,</l>
                     <l>Who rais'd strong warres to put his Father downe.</l>
                     <l>Faire <hi>Rosamond</hi> at <hi>Woodstock</hi> by the Queene</l>
                     <l>Was poyson'd, in reuengefull-iealous spleene.</l>
                     <l>In toyle, and trouble, with his Sonnes and Peeres,</l>
                     <l>The King raign'd almost fiue and thirty yeeres.</l>
                     <l>Hee neere his death did curse his day of birth,</l>
                     <l>Hee curst his Sonnes, and sadly left the earth,</l>
                     <l>Hee at <hi>Founteuerard</hi> in his Tombe was laid.</l>
                     <l>And his Son <hi>Richard</hi> next the Scepter swaid.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Henry <hi>the</hi> 2. <hi>In the</hi> 12. <hi>yeer of this King an earthquake in</hi> Norfolk, Suffolk, <hi>and</hi> Elye, <hi>that made bels ring with shaking the steeples, and ouerthrew men that stood on their feete.</hi> Nicholas Breakespeare, <hi>an Englishman was Pope of</hi> Rome, <hi>and was named</hi> Adrian <hi>the fourth, hee gaue the Lord-shippe of</hi> Ireland <hi>to King</hi> Henry.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="king">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:42"/>
                  <head>Richard Cordelion. An. Dom. 1189.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THis braue victorious Lyon-hearted Prince,</l>
                     <l>The foes of Christ, in <hi>Iury</hi> did conuince:</l>
                     <l>Whilst at <hi>Ierusalem</hi> he wan Renowne,</l>
                     <l>His Brother <hi>Iohn</hi> at home vsurp'd his Crowne.</l>
                     <l>And as he home return'd, (his owne to gaine)</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Austria's</hi> Duke the King was Prisoner tane.</l>
                     <l>His ransome was an hundred thousand pound,</l>
                     <l>Which paid, in <hi>England</hi> he againe was crown'd.</l>
                     <l>Yet after nine full yeeres, and 9. months raigne,</l>
                     <l>Hee with a Shot was kild in <hi>Aquitane,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>His buriall at <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>hought meet,</l>
                     <l>At his dead Fathers, second <hi>Henries</hi> feet.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Richard <hi>the</hi> 1. <hi>he conquered the kingdome of</hi> Cypresse, <hi>and he tooke from the Infidels the Cities of</hi> Acon, <hi>&amp;</hi> Iop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa, <hi>and deliuered them to Christians. In his</hi> 2. <hi>yeere, the bones of the renowned King</hi> Arthur <hi>were found at</hi> Gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stenbury. <hi>King</hi> Richards <hi>bowels were buried at</hi> Chalne <hi>Castle in</hi> Aquitane, <hi>his heart at</hi> Roane, <hi>and his body at</hi> Founteuerard.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="king">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:43"/>
                  <head>King Iohn. An. Dom. 1199.</head>
                  <figure/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>John</hi> Earle of <hi>Morton</hi> tooke the regall Seate,</l>
                     <l>His state, his toyle, his pompe, his cares, all great:</l>
                     <l>The <hi>French,</hi> the <hi>Welsh,</hi> the <hi>Scotsh,</hi> all prou'd his foes,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Pope</hi> King <hi>Iohn</hi> did from his Crowne depose.</l>
                     <l>His Lords rebel'd, from <hi>France</hi> the <hi>Dolphin</hi> came,</l>
                     <l>And wasted <hi>England</hi> much with sword and flame.</l>
                     <l>And after seuenteene yeeres were full expir'd.</l>
                     <l>King <hi>Iohn</hi> being poysoned, to his graue retir'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <hi>King</hi> Iohn. <hi>In the</hi> 8. <hi>yeere many men, Women, and cattell were slaine with thunder, and many houses burnt, and the corne was beaten downe with haile as bigge as goose egges.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Some say, the King was po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>son'd by a monke, and others write that he died of a surfeit at Newark, but his life was full of troubles, and after his death he was by base villaines rob'd and left naked without any thing to couer the corpes, hee was buried at</hi> Worcester.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="king">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:43"/>
                  <head>Henry the third. An. Dom. 1216.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WArs, bloody wars, the <hi>French</hi> in <hi>Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> made,</l>
                     <l>Strong holds, Towns, Towres &amp; Castles they inuade.</l>
                     <l>But afterwards it was K. <hi>Henries</hi> chance,</l>
                     <l>By force perforce to force them backe to <hi>France.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Great discord 'twixt the King and Barons were,</l>
                     <l>And factions did the Realme in pieces teare.</l>
                     <l>A world of mischiefes did this Land abide,</l>
                     <l>And fifty sixe yeeres raign'd the King, and dy'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Henry <hi>the</hi> 3. <hi>This King was born at</hi> Winchester, <hi>crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at</hi> Glocester, <hi>&amp; buried at</hi> Westminster. <hi>In the</hi> 17. <hi>of his reigne on the</hi> 8. <hi>of</hi> Aprill 1233. <hi>there were</hi> 5 <hi>Sonnes in the firmament, and the naturall Sun was as red as blood.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="king">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:44"/>
                  <head>Edward Long-shanks. An. Dom. 1272.</head>
                  <figure/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THis was a hardy, wise, Victorious King,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Welshmen</hi> he did to subiection bring:</l>
                     <l>He <hi>Scotland</hi> wan, and brought from thence (by fate)</l>
                     <l>Their <hi>Crowne,</hi> their <hi>Scepter, Chaire,</hi> and <hi>Cloth</hi> of <hi>state,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That Kingdome with oppression sore he brusde,</l>
                     <l>Much tyranny and bloodshed there he vsde.</l>
                     <l>When thirty fiue yeeres he the Crowne had kept,</l>
                     <l>At <hi>Westminster,</hi> he with his Father slept.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Edward <hi>the</hi> 1. <hi>In the</hi> 13. <hi>yeere his sonne</hi> Edward <hi>was borne at</hi> Carnaruan, <hi>who was the first sonne of any King of</hi> England <hi>that was Prince of</hi> Wales.</p>
                  <p>An. 17. <hi>Wheat at</hi> 3. <hi>pence the Bushell.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="king">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:44"/>
                  <head>Edward <hi>of Carnaruan.</hi> An. Dom. 1307.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THe hard mis haps that did this King attend,</l>
                     <l>The wretched life, and lamentable end,</l>
                     <l>Which he endur'd the like hath ne'r bin seene,</l>
                     <l>Depos'd, and poyson'd by his cruell Queene.</l>
                     <l>Which when the poyson had no force to kill,</l>
                     <l>Another way she wrought her wicked will.</l>
                     <l>Into his Fundament a red hot Spit</l>
                     <l>Was thrust, which made his Royall heart to split.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In his</hi> 8. <hi>yeere such a dearth, that dogges and horses were good food, many ate their owne children, and old prisoners tore such as were newly committed in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and deuoured them halfe liuing. The King reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> 19. <hi>yeeres</hi> 6. <hi>moneths.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="king">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:45"/>
                  <head>Edward the third. An. Dom. 1316.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>IN Peace and warre, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>his King was right, &amp; good,</l>
                     <l>He did reu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>nge his murdred Fathers blood:</l>
                     <l>Hee, and the blacke Prince, his most valiant Sonne,</l>
                     <l>The field at <hi>Cress<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> and at <hi>Poytiers</hi> wonne,</l>
                     <l>At first and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>st in his victorious raigne,</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Scots,</hi> were six score thousand slaine.</l>
                     <l>And more, (his glory further to aduance)</l>
                     <l>He tooke the Kings of <hi>Scotland</hi> and of <hi>France.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The noble order of the <hi>Garter,</hi> he</l>
                     <l>At <hi>Windsor,</hi> instituted caus'd to be.</l>
                     <l>When fifty yeeres this Land had him obaid,</l>
                     <l>At <hi>Westminster</hi> he in his tombe was laid.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In his</hi> 12. <hi>yeere he quartered the Armes of England and France, as they are at this day.</hi> Henry Pichard <hi>Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>tner, in his Maioralty feasted at once,</hi> Edward <hi>King of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Dauid <hi>King of</hi> Scotland, Iohn <hi>King of</hi> France, <hi>the King of</hi> Cypres, <hi>the Prince of</hi> Wales, <hi>the</hi> Dolphin <hi>of</hi> France, <hi>with many other great Personages of Honour and Worship.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="king">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:45"/>
                  <head>Richard <hi>the second.</hi> An. Dom. 1377.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>YOng King, rash cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>sell, lawes &amp; right neglected,</l>
                     <l>The good put downe, the bad in State <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>rected:</l>
                     <l>The Court with knaues &amp; flat'rers here did swarm,</l>
                     <l>The Kingdome, (like a Farme) was let to Farme.</l>
                     <l>The Commons rose in Armies, Rou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>es, and throngs,</l>
                     <l>And by foule treason, would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> foule wrongs.</l>
                     <l>In this Kings raigne, began the Ciuill warre,</l>
                     <l>(Vnnaturally) 'twixt <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Lancaster.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Oppression on oppression, breedes Confusion,</l>
                     <l>Bad Prologue, bad Proceeding, bad Conclusion:</l>
                     <l>King <hi>Richard,</hi> twenty two yeeres raign'd, misse-led,</l>
                     <l>Deposed and at <hi>Pomfret</hi> knock'd ith'head.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This King was Grandchild to</hi> Edward <hi>the</hi> 3. <hi>and sonne to the black Prince, he was borne at</hi> Burdeux <hi>in</hi> France, <hi>and was but</hi> 11. <hi>yeeres old when he was crowned, so that all his miserable calamity may be imputed to his not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing or not regarding good counsell.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="king">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:46"/>
                  <head>Henry <hi>the fourth.</hi> An. Dom. 1399.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THe Crown wrong got fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wrong' doing king,</l>
                     <l>More griefe then ioy did to King <hi>Henry</hi> bring:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>France, England, Scotland, Wales,</hi> arose in Armes,</l>
                     <l>And menac'd <hi>Henry,</hi> with most fierce Alarmes:</l>
                     <l>Hot <hi>Percy, Dowglas, Mortimer, Glend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>wre,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>At <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> the King or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>threw their power,</l>
                     <l>He fourteene yeeres did raigne, and then did dye,</l>
                     <l>At <hi>Cant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>rbury</hi> buried, he doth lye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Henry <hi>the</hi> 4. <hi>Hee began his reigne the</hi> 29. <hi>of Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> 1399. <hi>and the</hi> 14. <hi>of February following, King</hi> Richard <hi>the</hi> 2. <hi>being in prison at</hi> Pomfret-Castle, <hi>was murdered. The raigne of King</hi> Henry <hi>was a continuall warre and trouble.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="king">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:46"/>
                  <head>Henry <hi>the fift.</hi> An. Dom. 1412.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THis was a King Renowned n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ere and farre,</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Mars</hi> of men, a Thunderbolt of warre:</l>
                     <l>At <hi>Agencourt</hi> the French were ouerthrowne,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Henry</hi> heyre proclaim'd vnto that Crowne.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ine yeeres raigne this valiant Prince wan more,</l>
                     <l>I hena<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> the Kings did after or before.</l>
                     <l>Intomb'd at <hi>Westminster</hi> his Carkas lyes,</l>
                     <l>His soule did (like his Acts) ascend the skies.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Henry <hi>the</hi> 5. <hi>In his</hi> 3. <hi>yeere hee past the sea with</hi> 1000. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> of Ships and Vessels into</hi> France. <hi>His tombe or statue was couered with siluer, but this yron age hath deuoured</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="king">
                  <head>Henry the sixt. An. Dom. 1422.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THis Infant Prince scarce being nine moneths old,</l>
                     <l>The Realmes of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England</hi> he did hold</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18816:47"/>
But he vncapable through want of yeeres,</l>
                     <l>Was ouer-gouern'd by mis-gouern'd Peeres.</l>
                     <l>Now <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Lancaster,</hi> with bloudy wars,</l>
                     <l>Both wound this kingdome, with deep deadly scars.</l>
                     <l>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>st this good King by <hi>Yorke</hi> oppos'd, depos'd,</l>
                     <l>Expos'd to dangers, is captiu'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>'d,</l>
                     <l>His <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>xilde, his sonne and many friends,</l>
                     <l>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>d, murdred, slaughtred; lastly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ate contends</l>
                     <l>To crowne him once againe, who then at last</l>
                     <l>Was murdred, thirty nine yeeres being past.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <hi>King</hi> Henry <hi>the fixt, being</hi> 10. <hi>yeers old, was crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned King of</hi> France <hi>in</hi> Paris, <hi>but with the strife betwixt the Nobility, and the Commons in</hi> England, <hi>the most part of</hi> France <hi>was lost againe, which was neuer recouered since.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="king">
                  <head>Edward the fourth. An. Dom. 1460.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>EDward,</hi> the 4 the house of <hi>Yorks</hi> great heire,</l>
                     <l>By bloudy wars attain'd the Regall Chair<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>,</l>
                     <l>The poore King <hi>Henry</hi> into <hi>Scotland</hi> fled,</l>
                     <l>And foure yeeres there was royally cloath'd and fed,</l>
                     <l>Still good success<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> with him was in the wane,</l>
                     <l>He by King <hi>Edwards</hi> power at last was tane.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18816:47"/>
But yet before the tenth yeere of his reigne,</l>
                     <l>Hence <hi>Edward</hi> fled, and <hi>Henry</hi> crown'd againe.</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Warwicks</hi> meanes sixe moneths he held the same,</l>
                     <l>Till <hi>Edward</hi> backe in armes to <hi>England</hi> came,</l>
                     <l>And fighting stoutly, made this kingdome yeeld,</l>
                     <l>And slew great <hi>Warwicks</hi> Earle at <hi>Barnet</hi> field.</l>
                     <l>Thus Ciuill wars on wars, and broyles on broyles,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>England</hi> against <hi>England</hi> spils and spoyles,</l>
                     <l>Now <hi>Yorke,</hi> then <hi>Lancaster,</hi> then <hi>Yorke</hi> againe</l>
                     <l>Quels <hi>Lancaster;</hi> thus ioy, griefe, pleasure, paine,</l>
                     <l>Doth like inconstant waters ebbe and flow:</l>
                     <l>Ones rising is the others ouerthrow.</l>
                     <l>King <hi>Edward,</hi> twenty two yeeres rul'd this Land,</l>
                     <l>And lies at <hi>Windsor,</hi> where his <hi>Tombe</hi> doth stand.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Edward <hi>the</hi> 4. <hi>In the first yeere on</hi> Palme-sunday, 1460. <hi>there was a battell fought betwixt King</hi> Edward <hi>and King</hi> Henry, <hi>neere</hi> Todcaster, <hi>wherein were slaine of English-men on both sides</hi> 53000, 700, <hi>and</hi> 11. <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons: The bloudy victory fell to King</hi> Edward. <hi>In the</hi> 10. <hi>yeere of his reigne, he was forced to forsake this Land, whereby King</hi> Henry <hi>was restored againe to the Crowne. But shortly after,</hi> Edward <hi>returned, and</hi> Henry <hi>was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>urthered.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:48"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:48"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
               <div type="king">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:49"/>
                  <head>Edward the fifth. An. Dom. 1483.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>HIgh birth, blood, state, and innocent in yeeres,</l>
                     <l>Eclips'd, and murdred by insulting Peeres:</l>
                     <l>This King was neuer crown'd, short was his raigne:</l>
                     <l>For to be short, hee in short space was slaine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Edward <hi>the</hi> 5. <hi>Within</hi> 3. <hi>moneths after the death of his father, hee and his brother</hi> Richard <hi>Duke of Yorke, were depriued both of their liues, and he of the Crowne, by their tyrannous Unkle</hi> Richard, <hi>Duke of</hi> Gloster.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="king">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Richard</hi> the third. <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1483.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>BY reason, mischiefe, murder and debate.</l>
                     <l>Vsurping <hi>Richard</hi> wonne the royall state:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18816:49"/>
Vnnatnrally the children of his brothe.</l>
                     <l>The King, and Duke of <hi>Yorke</hi> he caus'd to smother.</l>
                     <l>For Sir <hi>Iames Tirrell, Dighton</hi> and <hi>Blacke Will,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Did in the Tower these harmlesse Princes kill,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Buckinghams</hi> Duke did raise King <hi>Richard</hi> high,</l>
                     <l>And for reward he lost his head thereby.</l>
                     <l>A fellow to this King I scarce can finde.</l>
                     <l>His shape deform'd, and crooked like his minde.</l>
                     <l>Most cruell, tyrannous, inconstant, stout,</l>
                     <l>Couragious, hardy, t'abide all dangers out,</l>
                     <l>Yet when his sinnes were mellow, ripe and full,</l>
                     <l>Th'Almighties Iustice then his plum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>s did pull:</l>
                     <l>By bloudy meanes he did the kingdome gaine,</l>
                     <l>And lost it so, at <hi>Bosworth</hi> being slaine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This</hi> Richard <hi>was neuer a good subiect; but wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> he had got the Crowne, he striued by all meanes to be a good King, for in his short reigne of two yeeres, two mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>s, he made very profitable Lawes, which are yet in force: by which it may be perceiued how willing he was to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> his mis-spent time.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="king">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> the seuenth. <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1485.</head>
                  <figure/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVHen Ciuill wars, full fourescore yeers &amp; more,</l>
                     <l>Had made this kingdome welter in her Gore:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18816:50"/>
When eightie of the royall blood were kild,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Lancasters</hi> crosse faction held,</l>
                     <l>Then God in mercy, looking on this Land,</l>
                     <l>Brought in this Prince, with a triumphant band,</l>
                     <l>The onely Heire of the <hi>Lancastrian</hi> line,</l>
                     <l>Who grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ously consented to combine,</l>
                     <l>To ease poore <hi>England</hi> of a world of anone,</l>
                     <l>And make the red Rose and the white but one,</l>
                     <l>By Marriage with <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the faire,</l>
                     <l>Fourth <hi>Edwards</hi> daughter, and <hi>Yorks</hi> onely heire.</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Margret Burgunds</hi> Lancaster storm'd &amp; frown'd,</l>
                     <l>That th'heire of <hi>Lancaster</hi> in state was crown'd.</l>
                     <l>A counterfeit, one <hi>Lambert</hi> she suborn'd,</l>
                     <l>(Beign with Princely ornaments adorn'd)</l>
                     <l>To claime the State in name of <hi>Cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ce</hi> sonne,</l>
                     <l>Who in the Tower before to death was done.</l>
                     <l>Wars' gainst the French King <hi>Henry</hi> did maintaine,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Edward</hi> braue Lord <hi>Wooduil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> there was slaine.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Northumberlands</hi> great Earle (for the Kings right)</l>
                     <l>Was slaine by Northerne rebels in sharpe fight.</l>
                     <l>The King besiedged <hi>Boloigne,</hi> but a Peace</l>
                     <l>The French king sought, and so the siedge did cease.</l>
                     <l>Still <hi>Burgunds</hi> Dutchesse, (with inueterate hate)</l>
                     <l>Did seeke to ruine <hi>Henries</hi> Royall state:</l>
                     <l>She caus'd one <hi>Perkin Warbecke,</hi> to put on</l>
                     <l>The name of <hi>Richard, Edwards</hi> murdred sonne,</l>
                     <l>Which <hi>Richard,</hi> was the youngest of the twaine</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Edwards</hi> sonnes that in the Tower was slaine.</l>
                     <l>The King at last these traitors did confound,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Perkin</hi> for a counterfeit was found.</l>
                     <l>Sir <hi>William Stanley,</hi> (once the Kings best friend)</l>
                     <l>At <hi>Tower</hi> hill, on a Scaffold had his end.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18816:50"/>
On <hi>Blacke Heath Cornish</hi> rebels were o'rthrowne,</l>
                     <l>A Shoomaker did claine King <hi>Henries</hi> Crowne.</l>
                     <l>The Earle of <hi>Warwicke</hi> lost his haplesse head,</l>
                     <l>And Lady <hi>Katherine</hi> did Prince <hi>Arthur</hi> wed.</l>
                     <l>But ere sixe moneths were fully gone and past,</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Ludlow</hi> Castle, <hi>Arthur</hi> breath'd his last.</l>
                     <l>King <hi>Henry</hi> built his Chappell from the ground,</l>
                     <l>At <hi>Westminster,</hi> whose like can scarce be found.</l>
                     <l>Faire <hi>Margret</hi> eldest daughter to our King,</l>
                     <l>King <hi>Iames</hi> the fourth of <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> home did bring,</l>
                     <l>Where those two Princes, with great pompe and cheare,</l>
                     <l>In State at <hi>Edenborough</hi> married were.</l>
                     <l>But as all Mortall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>hings are tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ory,</l>
                     <l>So to an end came <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>nrie</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>arthly glory.</l>
                     <l>Twenty three yeeres, and 8. months here he swaid,</l>
                     <l>And then at <hi>Westminster,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>s Tombe was laid.</l>
                     <l>He all his Life had variable share,</l>
                     <l>Of Peace, Warre, Ioy Griefe, Royaltie and Care.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In his</hi> 1. <hi>yeere in</hi> 7. <hi>weekes space, there dyed in</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don 2. <hi>Masors, and</hi> 6. <hi>Aldermen, besides many hundred others of a strange sweating sicknesse,</hi> 1485.</p>
                  <p>Anno Reg. 12. <hi>at Saint Needs in Bedfordshire, there fell bail-stones</hi> 18. <hi>inches about.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>King</hi> Iames <hi>the</hi> 4. <hi>of</hi> Scotland, <hi>married</hi> Margret, <hi>eldest daughter to</hi> Henry <hi>the</hi> 7. <hi>from whom our gracious Soueraigne is lineally descended.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="king">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:51"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> the eight. <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1509.</head>
                  <figure/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>FRom both the Lines, and both the loynes did spring</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>York</hi> &amp; <hi>Lancaster,</hi> this mighty King:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Katherine</hi> that was his brothers wife of late,</l>
                     <l>He tooke to wife, and crown'd her Queene in state.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Empson</hi> and <hi>Dudley</hi> lost their heads at Tower,</l>
                     <l>For racking the poore Commons by their power.</l>
                     <l>Warres, dreadfull wars, arose 'twixt vs and <hi>France,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Lord <hi>Edward Howard,</hi> drowned by mis-chance</l>
                     <l>At <hi>Brest,</hi> he was high Admirall in fight,</l>
                     <l>Cast ouerboord, dy'd like a valiant Knight.</l>
                     <l>In England <hi>Suffolks</hi> Duke did lose his head,</l>
                     <l>The King to <hi>Tur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>in</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>d an army lead,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Turney</hi> he wonne with his victorious blade,</l>
                     <l>King <hi>Iames</hi> of <hi>Scotland, England</hi> did inuade:</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Surries</hi> Earle, the <hi>Sco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>sh</hi> King ouercame,</l>
                     <l>Who lost life there, but wonne immortall fame.</l>
                     <l>Now Cardinall <hi>Wol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ey,</hi> in the Kings high Grace,</l>
                     <l>Was rais'd to honours, from great place to place,</l>
                     <l>Lordship on Lordship laid vpon his backe,</l>
                     <l>Vntill the burthen was the bearers wracke.</l>
                     <l>The Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> his head did lose,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Luther</hi> stoutly did the <hi>Pope</hi> oppose,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18816:51"/>
Blinde ignorance that long had look'd awry,</l>
                     <l>Began to see Truth with a clearer eye,</l>
                     <l>And then the King (inspir'd with feruent Zeale)</l>
                     <l>Reformed both the Church and Common weale,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iehouah</hi> with his power Omnipotent,</l>
                     <l>Did make this King his gracious instrument,</l>
                     <l>T' vnmaske his Truth from Antichristian fables,</l>
                     <l>And purge this wofull Land from <hi>Babel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> bables.</l>
                     <l>This King at <hi>Boloigne</hi> was victorious;</l>
                     <l>In peace and warre, Magnifique, Glorious;</l>
                     <l>In his rage bounty he did oft expresse,</l>
                     <l>His Liberality to bee excesse,</l>
                     <l>In Reuels, Iusts, and Turnies he spent more,</l>
                     <l>Then fiue of his Fore-fathers did before,</l>
                     <l>His Auarice was all for Noble fame,</l>
                     <l>Amongst the Worthies to inrole his Name,</l>
                     <l>A valiant Champion for the <hi>Faiths defence,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Was the great Title of this mightie Prince.</l>
                     <l>Sixe wiues he had, 3. <hi>Kates,</hi> 2. <hi>Annes,</hi> one <hi>Iane,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Two were diuorc'd, two at the blocke were slaine:</l>
                     <l>One sonne and two faire daughters he did leaue,</l>
                     <l>Who each from other did the Crowne receiue:</l>
                     <l>The first was <hi>Edward; Mary</hi> next, whose death</l>
                     <l>Left State, and Realme, to Queene <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>He thirty eight yeeres kept this Royall Roome,</l>
                     <l>At <hi>Windsor</hi> hee's enter'd without a Tombe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Leeth, Edenbourgh, <hi>and diuers other parts of</hi> Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>were spoyled by Sir</hi> Iohn Dudley, <hi>Lord</hi> Viscount Lisle, <hi>Lord high Admirall of</hi> England, <hi>with a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy of</hi> 200. <hi>tall Ships.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Anno 1544. <hi>King</hi> Henry <hi>went to</hi> Boloigne, <hi>hee</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:18816:52"/>
                     <hi>entred</hi> France <hi>the</hi> 13. <hi>of</hi> Iuly, <hi>and into</hi> Boloigne <hi>the</hi> 25. <hi>of</hi> September, <hi>in which yeere were taken</hi> 300. <hi>French Ships for prizes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="king">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Edward</hi> the sixt. <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1546.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>HAd this Kings reigne bin long, as it was good,</l>
                     <l>Religion in a peaceable state had stood,</l>
                     <l>What might haue his age bin, when his blest youth,</l>
                     <l>So valiantly aduanc'd Gods sacred truth?</l>
                     <l>At nine yeeres age, the Crowne on him hee tooke,</l>
                     <l>And ere sixteene, he Crowne and life forsooke.</l>
                     <l>Too good for earth, th' Almighty tooke his spirit,</l>
                     <l>And Westminster his Carkas doth inherit.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In his</hi> 5. <hi>yeere a strange Earth-quake did much harme in diuers places of</hi> Surry, <hi>and a sweating sicknesse gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ouer</hi> England, <hi>that dispatched those that were in good health, in</hi> 12. <hi>houres, or</hi> 24. <hi>at the most. In one weeke there dyed of it in</hi> London 806. <hi>the most of them being men of best strength.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="queen">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:52"/>
                  <head>Queene <hi>Mary. An. Dam.</hi> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </head>
                  <figure/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>AFter a while this Queene had worne the Crown,</l>
                     <l>Idolatry was rais'd, and Truth put downe,</l>
                     <l>The Masse, the Images, the Beades and Altars,</l>
                     <l>By tyrannie, by fire, and sword and Halters,</l>
                     <l>Th' vngodly bloudy Antichristian sway,</l>
                     <l>Men were force, perforce forced to obey.</l>
                     <l>Now burning <hi>Bonner, Londons</hi> Bishop, he</l>
                     <l>Was from the <hi>Marshal-sea</hi> againe set free:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iohn Dudley,</hi> great Duke of <hi>Northumberland,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And Sir <hi>Iohn Gates</hi> dyed by the Headsmans hand.</l>
                     <l>With them Sir <hi>Thomas Palmer</hi> likewise dy'd.</l>
                     <l>Hoping for heau'n, through Iesus Crucified.</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Latine</hi> Seruice must be sung and said,</l>
                     <l>Because men should not know for what they prai'd.</l>
                     <l>The Emp'rors sonne, great <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Spaine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A marriage with Queene <hi>Mary</hi> did obtaine:</l>
                     <l>Against which match, Sir <hi>Thomas Wyat</hi> rose,</l>
                     <l>With powers of <hi>Kent</hi> the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to oppose.</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Wyat</hi> was or'throwne, his armie fled,</l>
                     <l>And on the Tower hill after lost his head.</l>
                     <l>Lord <hi>Gray</hi> the Duke of <hi>Suffolke</hi> also dy'd,</l>
                     <l>An Axe his Corps did from his head diuide,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18816:53"/>
A little after, the Lord <hi>Thomas Gray,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Dukes owne brother went that headlesse way.</l>
                     <l>A Millers sonne asl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>m'd King <hi>Edwards</hi> name,</l>
                     <l>And fa sely in that n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>me the Crowne did claime,</l>
                     <l>But he was tane and iustly whip'd and tortur'd,</l>
                     <l>And claiming it once more, was hang'd &amp; quarterd.</l>
                     <l>King <hi>Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>lip</hi> won Saint. <hi>Quintins</hi> with great cost.</l>
                     <l>But after to our shame was <hi>Callice</hi> lost,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Calli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>e</hi> was lost, which threescore yeeres and ten,</l>
                     <l>Had beene a Garrison for <hi>English men.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thus by Gods mercy <hi>Englands</hi> Queene did dye,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>England</hi> gain'd much ease and rest thereby.</l>
                     <l>Fiue yeeres and 4. months was her bloudy reigne,</l>
                     <l>And all her glory doth one graue containe.</l>
                     <l>Though of her selfe this Queene was well inclin'd,</l>
                     <l>Bad-minded counsell al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>red much her minde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <hi>She married</hi> Philip <hi>King of</hi> Spaine, <hi>on Saint</hi> Iames <hi>his day,</hi> 1554. <hi>at</hi> Winchester.</p>
                  <p>Callice <hi>was won by</hi> Edward <hi>the</hi> 3. <hi>in the</hi> 21. <hi>of his reigne,</hi> 1347. <hi>and it was lost the</hi> 1. <hi>of Ianuary</hi> 1557. <hi>after the English-men had possest it</hi> 210. <hi>yeeres.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>August 7. 1558 <hi>a tempest neere</hi> Nottingham, <hi>beat damne</hi> 2 <hi>Townes and Churches, and cast the Bels to the further side of the Church-yard, threw whole sheetes of Lead</hi> 400. <hi>foot into the fields, where they were crumpled together like burnt parchment: the streame and mud of the K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>er of</hi> Trent <hi>was blowne a-land a quarter of a mile: a childe blowne out of a mans hand</hi> 100. <hi>foot and kild, there fell hayle</hi> 15. <hi>Inches about.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="queen">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:53"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queene</hi> Elizabeth. An. Dom. 1558.</head>
                  <figure/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A <hi>Debora,</hi> a <hi>Iudith,</hi> a <hi>Susannae,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A <hi>Virgin,</hi> a <hi>Virago,</hi> a <hi>Diana:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Couragious, Zealous, Learned, Wise and Chaste,</l>
                     <l>With heauenly, earthly gifts, adorn'd and grac'd,</l>
                     <l>Victorious, glorious, bountious, gracious, good,</l>
                     <l>And one, whose vertues dignifi'd her bloud,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Muses, Graces,</hi> Armes, and liberall Arts,</l>
                     <l>Amongst all <hi>Queens,</hi> proclaim'd her <hi>Queen</hi> of hearts,</l>
                     <l>She did repurifie this Land once more,</l>
                     <l>From the infection of the Romish whore.</l>
                     <l>Now Abbies, Abbots, Fri'rs, Monks, Nuns &amp; Stews,</l>
                     <l>Masses, and Masse-priests, that mens soules abuse,</l>
                     <l>Were all cast downe, Lamps, Tapers, Relikes, Beads,</l>
                     <l>And Superstitions that mans soule misse-leads,</l>
                     <l>All Popish pardons, Buls. Confessions, </l>
                     <l>With Crossings, Christening bels, Saints Interces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions,</l>
                     <l>The Altars, Idols, Images downe cast,</l>
                     <l>All Pilgrimage, and Superstitious Fast,</l>
                     <l>Th' acknowledging the Pope for supreme head,</l>
                     <l>The holy water, and the god of bread,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18816:54"/>
The mumbling Mattins, and the pickpurse Masse,</l>
                     <l>These bables this good Queene did turne to grasse.</l>
                     <l>She caus'd <hi>Gods</hi> seruice to be said and sung,</l>
                     <l>In our owne vnderstanding English tongue.</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Scotland</hi> and in <hi>France,</hi> fierce warres she held,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Irish</hi> she subdu'd when they rebeld,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Netherlands</hi> her name doe still admire,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Spaine</hi> her like againe doth not desire.</l>
                     <l>When forty foure yeers reigne was past and gone,</l>
                     <l>She chang'd her earthly for a heauenly Throne,</l>
                     <l>At <hi>Greenwich</hi> she was borne, at <hi>Richmond</hi> dy'd,</l>
                     <l>At <hi>Westminster</hi> she buried, doth abide;</l>
                     <l>And as the fame of this Imperiall Maide,</l>
                     <l>Is through the world, (by the foure winds) displaid,</l>
                     <l>So shall her memory for euer grace</l>
                     <l>Her famous birth, her death, and buriall place.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <hi>At</hi> Teuxbury <hi>Anno</hi> 1574. <hi>the</hi> 24. <hi>of February, being a hard frost, the Riuer of Seuerne was couered with Flies and Beetles, so that it was thought, within the length of a paire of Buts, to be</hi> 100. <hi>quarters of them the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ils were stopped with them, but from whence they came, is vnknown.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1582. <hi>A piece of Land of three Acres in Dorsetshire, in the Parish of Armitage, was suddenly remooued</hi> 600. <hi>foot from the place where formerly it stood.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="king">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:54"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>King</hi> Iames. An. Dom. 1601.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVHen as <hi>Elizaes</hi> wofull death was act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>d:</l>
                     <l>When this lamenting land was halfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>:</l>
                     <l>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tears e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ch loyall heart with grief had drownd,</l>
                     <l>Then came this King and made our ioves abound,</l>
                     <l>Ordain'd for vs by heauenly power diuine,</l>
                     <l>Then from the <hi>North</hi> this glorious starre did shine,</l>
                     <l>The Royall Image of the Prince of Peace,</l>
                     <l>The blest <hi>Concorder</hi> that made warres to cease;</l>
                     <l>By Name a S T E V V A R D, and by Nature one,</l>
                     <l>Appointed from <hi>Iehonahs</hi> sacred Throne,</l>
                     <l>And by th'almighties hand supported euer,</l>
                     <l>That Treason or the Diuell should hurt him neuer:</l>
                     <l>And as his Zeale vnto his God was great,</l>
                     <l>Gods blessings on him were each way compleat,</l>
                     <l>Rich in his Subiects loue (a Kings best treasure)</l>
                     <l>Rich in content, (a Riches aboue measure)</l>
                     <l>Rich in his Princely Issue, and in them,</l>
                     <l>Rich in his hopefull Branches of his stemme;</l>
                     <l>Rich in Munition and a Nauy Royall,</l>
                     <l>And richer then all Kings in seruants Loyall.</l>
                     <l>When <hi>Hell</hi> and <hi>Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> together did conspire,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>o blow him and his Kingdome vp with fire,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18816:55"/>
Then did the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> preserue our King,</l>
                     <l>And all the Traytors to confusion bring.</l>
                     <l>And whoso reckons vp from first to last,</l>
                     <l>The many hel-hatch'd dangers he hath past</l>
                     <l>Through all his daies, he will beleeue (no doubt)</l>
                     <l>That he with heauenly pow'rs was wall'd about.</l>
                     <l>All Christian Princes held his friendship deare,</l>
                     <l>Was fear'd for loue, and not belou'd for feare:</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Pagan</hi> Monarchs were in L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ague combin'd</l>
                     <l>With him, as farre as is the Easterne <hi>Ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And like a <hi>flame</hi> a midst a Riuer fix'd,</l>
                     <l>So was his <hi>Iustice</hi> with his m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>rcy mix'd:</l>
                     <l>He striu'd to imitate his Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>er still,</l>
                     <l>And clemency preseru'd where Law <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>:</l>
                     <l>He hath cur'd <hi>England</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> wounds,</l>
                     <l>And made them both <hi>great</hi> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>) <hi>Britains</hi> bounds</l>
                     <l>All bloudy deadly fewds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>And canker'd hate he turn'd to Christian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</l>
                     <l>The mouth of warre he muzzled mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</l>
                     <l>He still'd the roaring Cannon and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Secure in peace, his people sup and dine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>With their owne fig-trees shaded and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whilst in an vprore most of Christendome,</l>
                     <l>One Nation doth another <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                     <l>Vnto the King of Kings let's praises sing.</l>
                     <l>For giuing vs this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>appy peacefull King.</l>
                     <l>None know so well how they should peace prefer,</l>
                     <l>As those that know the miseries of warre:</l>
                     <l>Tis true (though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>) and must not be forgot,</l>
                     <l>The warres are sweet to such as know them not.</l>
                     <l>Peace (happy peace) doth spread tranq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>illity,</l>
                     <l>Through all the bounds of Britaines Monarchy;</l>
                     <l>And may we all our actions still addresse,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18816:55"/>
For peace with God, and warre 'gainst wickednesse.</l>
                     <l>Vnto which peace of God this King's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</l>
                     <l>To reigne in glory that shall ne'r be ended.</l>
                     <l>His mortall part at Westminster enter'd,</l>
                     <l>His soule and Fame immortally prefer'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God did wonderfully preserue him (vpon two seuerall Tuesdaies) from</hi> 2 <hi>most dangerous treas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>, the one at the Towne of</hi> Saint Iohnston <hi>in</hi> Scotland, <hi>on Tuesday the</hi> 5. <hi>of</hi> August, 1600. <hi>where the Earle of</hi> Gowry <hi>attempted to kill his Maiesty. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>her was in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>in that fearfull treason and deliuerance from the Powder-plot, on Tuesday the</hi> 5. <hi>of Nouember.</hi> 1606.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="king">
                  <head>King CHARLES.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>TWo <hi>Williams, Henries</hi> 8. 1. <hi>Steuen,</hi> 1. <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Sixe <hi>Edwards, Richards</hi> 3. and 1. Queene <hi>Mary:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and <hi>Iames,</hi> all dead and gone,</l>
                     <l>Our gracious <hi>Charles</hi> doth now the Scepter carry;</l>
                     <l>And may they liue and dye of God accurst,</l>
                     <l>Who wish the pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>dice of <hi>Charles</hi> the first.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iust</hi> 25. <hi>Kings and Queenes of</hi> England <hi>since the Norman Conquest.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="catalogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:18816:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18816:56"/>
            <head>THIS AVTHOR HATH newly caused all his works (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aboue 60.) to bee printed into one Volume, the Names of all which Works are set downe in this following Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue.</head>
            <list>
               <item>TAylors Vrania.</item>
               <item>The life and death of the Virgin Mary.</item>
               <item>The whip of Pride.</item>
               <item>Against cursing and swearing.</item>
               <item>The fearefull Summer.</item>
               <item>Christian Admonitions.</item>
               <item>The trauell of tweluepence.</item>
               <item>The Armado.</item>
               <item>The Begger.</item>
               <item>Taylors Goose.</item>
               <item>Iacke a Lent.</item>
               <item>Taylors peninlesse Pilgrimage,</item>
               <item>The Sculler.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:57"/>
The Dolphins danger.</item>
               <item>The Cormorant.</item>
               <item>A sea-fight by Captaine Wedall.</item>
               <item>The praise of Hempseed.</item>
               <item>Taylors Pastorall.</item>
               <item>Prince Charles his welcome from Spaine.</item>
               <item>An English mans loue to Bohemia.</item>
               <item>Three weeks and three daies trauels</item>
               <item>Taylors farewell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>o Bohemia.</item>
               <item>Sir Gregory Nonsence.</item>
               <item>A very merry Whir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y voyage.</item>
               <item>The great O Tnole.</item>
               <item>A voyage to the West.</item>
               <item>The scourge of basenesse.</item>
               <item>Taylors Motto.</item>
               <item>Odcombs complaint.</item>
               <item>Coriats resurrection.</item>
               <item>Laugh and be fat.</item>
               <item>Coriats newes.</item>
               <item>A Bawd.</item>
               <item>A Whore.</item>
               <item>A Thiefe.</item>
               <item>A Hangman.</item>
               <item>The vnnaturall Father.</item>
               <item>Taylors reuenge.</item>
               <item>Fenners defence.</item>
               <item>A cast ouer the water.</item>
               <item>The praise of cleane Linnen.</item>
               <item>The Water-mans suit.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18816:57"/>
Wit and mirth.</item>
               <item>A Dogge of Warre.</item>
               <item>The world runs on Wheeles.</item>
               <item>The nipping or snipping of abuses.</item>
               <item>A Chronicle from Brute.</item>
               <item>A Briefe from the conquest.</item>
               <item>A Farewell to the Towre bottles.</item>
               <item>The marriage of the Princesse Elizabeth.</item>
               <item>An Elegie for King Iames.</item>
               <item>An Elegy for the Earle of Nottingham.</item>
               <item>An Elegy for the Earle of Holdernesse.</item>
               <item>An Elegy for the Bishop of Winchester.</item>
               <item>An Elegy for the Duke of Richmond.</item>
               <item>An Elegy for Iohn Moray Esquire.</item>
               <item>The summe of the Bible in verse.</item>
               <item>The sum of the Booke of Martyrs in verse.</item>
               <item>The Churches deliuerances.</item>
               <item>Archies making peace with France.</item>
               <item>The Acts and exployts of Wood the great</item>
               <item>Eater, in Kent.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
