<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>True louing sorow, attired in a robe of vnfeigned griefe presented vpon occasion of the much bewailed funerall of that gracious and illustrious prince Lewis Steward, Duke of Richmond and Linox, Eearle [sic] of Newcastle and Darnely ... who departed this life at White-Hall on the Thursday the 12 of February ... / [by] John Taylor.</title>
            <author>Taylor, John, 1580-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-01">2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13514</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23808.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3373</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33143382</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33143382</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28432</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A13514)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28432)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1885:48)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>True louing sorow, attired in a robe of vnfeigned griefe presented vpon occasion of the much bewailed funerall of that gracious and illustrious prince Lewis Steward, Duke of Richmond and Linox, Eearle [sic] of Newcastle and Darnely ... who departed this life at White-Hall on the Thursday the 12 of February ... / [by] John Taylor.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, John, 1580-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Gosson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: faded, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Society of Antiquaries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Richmond, Ludovic Stuart, --  Duke of, 1574-1624 --  Death and burial.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James I, 1603-1625.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  London (England) --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="elegiac_poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:28432:1"/>
            <head>True louing Sorow, attired in a Robe of vnfeigned Griefe, presented vpon occasion of the much bewailed Funerall of that Gracious and Illustrious Prince <hi>Lewis Steward</hi> Duke of <hi>Richmond</hi> and <hi>Linox,</hi> Eearle of <hi>Newcastle</hi> and <hi>Darnely,</hi> Lord of <hi>Torbolton</hi> and <hi>Methuen,</hi> Baron of <hi>Settrington,</hi> Knight of the noble order of the Garter, Lord high Admirall, and great Chamberlaine of <hi>Scotland,</hi> Lord high Steward to the Kings most excellent Maiesties most Honourable Houshold, Gentleman of his Maiesties Bed-Chamber, and one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuy Councell for <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> Who departed this life at <hi>White-Hall</hi> on Thursday the 12. of February, whose Obsequies were solemnly and Princely Celebrated, on Munday the 19. of April, described in forme as f<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lloweth. Dedicated generally to all his worthy Friends, and louing Seruants; and particularly to that trusty and well-beloued Seruant of his <hi>Arthur Neassmith.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>ANd first my Muse findes, that his Graces name</l>
               <l>Significantly makes an Annagram.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>LEWIS STEWARDE,</hi> Annagram <hi>VERTV IS WEL EAS'D.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His Vertues such continuall paines did take</l>
               <l>For King and Country, Church and peoples sake:</l>
               <l>That for Earths courtly toyle, to him 'twas giuen</l>
               <l>His <hi>UERTU IS WEL EAS'D</hi> i'the Court of Heauen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>GReat <hi>God,</hi> that to thyselfe wilt take thine owne</l>
               <l>By sundry wayes, and meanes to <hi>Man</hi> vnknowne,</l>
               <l>Whose <hi>Eye</hi> of prouidence doth still perceiue</l>
               <l>When, where, why, who to take, or else to leaue,</l>
               <l>Whose mercy, and whose Iustice equall are,</l>
               <l>Both Infinite, to punish or to spare,</l>
               <l>All men doe know, that men to dye are borne,</l>
               <l>And from the Eearth, must to the Earth returne.</l>
               <l>But Time and Circumstance coniecture may,</l>
               <l>For some great cause thou took'st this Duke away.</l>
               <l>Amongst vs lurkes so many a foule offence,</l>
               <l>Which giues thee cause to take good men from hence:</l>
               <l>And that this <hi>Prince</hi> was <hi>Good</hi> as well as <hi>Great,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His life and timelesse losse doth well repeat.</l>
               <l>Deuout and zealous to his God aboue:</l>
               <l>True to his King, as did his seruice proue:</l>
               <l>Discreet in Counsell, Noble in his minde,</l>
               <l>Most Charitably, Honourably kinde.</l>
               <l>So Affable, so Hopefull vnto all,</l>
               <l>And so Repleat with vertues generall,</l>
               <l>That we may say, this Land in losing <hi>Him:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hath lost a gratious Peere, a prop, a limbe.</l>
               <l>It must be true, that well he spends his dayes,</l>
               <l>Whose actions doe attaine all peoples praise:</l>
               <l>And surely I suppose he doth not liue,</l>
               <l>Who of this Duke a bad report can giue.</l>
               <l>So full endu'd he was of all good parts,</l>
               <l>With noble Courtesie he wan all hearts,</l>
               <l>To loue and honour his admired minde</l>
               <l>So well adicted, and so well enclinde,</l>
               <l>That as a Diamond in Gold transfixt</l>
               <l>His vertues with his Greatnesse was so mixt,</l>
               <l>That he as one of an immortall Race</l>
               <l>Made Vertue vertuous, and gaue Grace to grace.</l>
               <l>Then since his goodnes, was so generall,</l>
               <l>The losse of him is Gen'rall vnto all:</l>
               <l>This being true, let's recollect our spirits</l>
               <l>And weigh his worth, with our vnworthy merits;</l>
               <l>And then our frailties truly will confesse</l>
               <l>God tooke him hence for our vnworthinesse:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Death</hi> was in Message from th'Almighty sent</l>
               <l>To summon him to <hi>Heau'ns</hi> high <hi>Parlament,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He chang'd his <hi>Gracious</hi> Title transitorie,</l>
               <l>And (by the grace of God) attain'd true Glory;</l>
               <l>And as his King had his integritie;</l>
               <l>So did the Commons share his Clemency,</l>
               <l>Which was so pleasing to his Makers sight,</l>
               <l>That Bounteously he did his life requite</l>
               <l>That Lambe-like, mildely hence he tooke him sleeping,</l>
               <l>To his Eternall euer-blessed keeping.</l>
               <l>Thus as his name includes, so God is pleas'd</l>
               <l>(From worldly sorrowes) <hi>VERTV IS WEL EAS'D.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No sicknesse or no phisicke made him languish,</l>
               <l>He lay not long in heart-tormenting anguish,</l>
               <l>But as Gods feare was planted in his brest,</l>
               <l>So at his Rest, God tooke him to his Rest.</l>
               <l>When like a good Tree, laden full of fruit,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Grace,</hi> of Vertue, Honour, and Repute:</l>
               <l>Euen in his best estate, too good for Earth,</l>
               <l>Then did his soule put on a second Birth.</l>
               <l>And though his part of fraile mortality,</l>
               <l>In Monumentall Marble here doth lie:</l>
               <l>Yet thousands weeping soules, with deepe laments,</l>
               <l>As his most wofull mourning Monuments,</l>
               <l>I daily see, whose visages doe show</l>
               <l>That He's inter'd within their hearts below;</l>
               <l>Whose faces seemes an Epitaph to beare,</l>
               <l>That men may Reade who is <unclear>intombed</unclear> there.</l>
            </lg>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="unk">
                  <body>
                     <div type="epitaph">
                        <head>Epitaph.</head>
                        <l>GOod, Gratious, Great, <hi>Richmond</hi> and <hi>Linox</hi> Duke,</l>
                        <l>God, King, and Countries seruant here doth lye;</l>
                        <l>Whose liuing Merits merit no rebuke,</l>
                        <l>For whose liues lesse lamenting Memory,</l>
                        <l>Our hearts are groning Graues of grieses and cares,</l>
                        <l>Which when we die, wee'le leaue vnto our heires.</l>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <lg>
               <l>Me thinkes the Sable Mourners did appeare,</l>
               <l>As if in forme they numbring Figures were;</l>
               <l>As 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9.</l>
               <l>Whilst all that view'd, like Ciphers did combine</l>
               <l>Their mourning with the Mourners to vnite,</l>
               <l>Which made their Lamentations infinite.</l>
               <l>And Infinite are now his Ioyes Aboue</l>
               <l>With the Eternall God of peace and loue:</l>
               <l>Where for a mortall Dukedome he hath wonne,</l>
               <l>(Through boundlesse merits of th'Almighties Sonne)</l>
               <l>A Kingdome that's immortall, where he sings</l>
               <l>Perpetuall praise vnto the King of Kings.</l>
               <l>Thus what the Earth surrendred, Heau'n hath seaz'd</l>
               <l>Most blest <hi>LEWIS STEWARDE, UERTU IS WEL EAS'D.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The manner of the Funerall.</head>
               <p>Eight Conductors with black staues, and poore Gownes, 100.</p>
               <p>Seruants to Gentlemen and Esquires in Cloakes 50.</p>
               <p>Seruants to Knights, 46.</p>
               <p>Seruants to Baronets, 10.</p>
               <p>Three Trumpeters.</p>
               <p>Then came the Standard borne by Sir <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard <unclear>Samms</unclear>
                  </hi> Knight, accompanied with an Officer of Armes.</p>
               <p>The first Horse couered with blacke cloth garnished with Scutchions, Shaffron and Plumes led by a groome.</p>
               <p>Here went Seruants to Barons youngor Sons, and some others of like qualitie in number 15.</p>
               <p>The seruants to Knights of the priuy Councell, 30.</p>
               <p>Seruants to Earles younger sonnes, 24.</p>
               <p>Seruants to Viscounts eldest Sons, 6.</p>
               <p>Then the Schollers of <hi>Westminster</hi> in Gownes and Surplises, their Masters fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in mourning Gownes.</p>
               <p>Three <unclear>Trumpeters</unclear>.</p>
               <p>The Guidon borne by Sir <hi>Andrew Boyd</hi> Knight, accompanied with an Officer of Armes.</p>
               <p>The second Horse led by a Groome, and furnished as the former.</p>
               <p>Barons seruants 60.</p>
               <p>Bishops Seruants 10.</p>
               <p>Earles eldest Sonnes seruants, 15.</p>
               <p>Viscounts Seruants, 10.</p>
               <p>Marquesses eldest Sonnes seruants.</p>
               <p>3. Trumpers.</p>
               <p>The Banner of the augmentation borne by a Knight, accompanied with an Officer of Armes.</p>
               <p>The third Horse led by onother Groome of his Graces Stable furnished as the others. Earles seruants: Marquesses and Dukes ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, The Lord Priuie-Seales seruants.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>President of the Councel,</cell>
                        <cell rows="4">Seruants.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Lord Thresurors,</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Lord Keepers,</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>And Lord Archbishops,</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>3. Trumpets. The, Banner of <hi>Steward,</hi> borne by Sir <hi>Iohn Steward</hi> accompanied with an Officer of Armes.</p>
               <p>The 4. Horse led by a Yeomen of his Graces Stable furnished as the other.</p>
               <p>Seruants to his Grace in Cloakes: Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers to his Grace in Gownes.</p>
               <p>3. Trumpeters.</p>
               <p>The <unclear>Banner</unclear> of <hi>Steward</hi> and the augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation quartered with it borne by a Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net accompanied with a Herald of Armes.</p>
               <p>The fist Horse led by a Yeoman of his Graces Stable furnished as the former.</p>
               <p>Serieants of seuerall Offices in his Maiesties House, and other Esquires, his Maiesties Seruants of good quality. The Gentlemen of his Maiesties Chappell in Surplices and rich Copes, the Sergeant of the Vestry accompaning them. Chaplaines. Doctors of Physicke. Doctors of Diuinity. Knights. Gentlemen of the Priuie Chamber. Gentlemen of the Bed-Chamber to the Prince. Baronets. Barons younger Sonnes. Knights of the Priuie Councell. Viscounts eldest Sonnes. A veluet Cushen carried by an Esquire, The Comptroller, Treasurer, Steward, and Chamberlaine to his Grace, bearing white Staues. Barons of <hi>Ireland, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>England.</hi> Bishops. Earles eldest Sonnes Viscounts. Earles of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and <hi>England.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Lennox</hi> eldest Sonne. The Arch-Bishop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> The Mace, The Purse, The Lord Keeper Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher. Sergeant Trumpetter, and foure Trumpets. The Great Banner borne by an Earles Sonne, accompanied with an Herald. The chiefe Mourning Horse couered with blacke Veluet, and garnished with Eschochens of Taffata, with Shaffron and Plumes led by Mr. <hi>
                     <unclear>Hatton</unclear> Clauell.</hi> His Graces Hatchiuements borne as followeth. The Gauntlets and Spurres, the Helme and Crest, and the Sword borne by three Heralds. The Targe and <unclear>Coat</unclear> of Armes, borne by two Kings of Armes. Then the liuely Effigies or represention of his Grace, drawne in a Chariot by sixe goodly Horses garnished as the former, couered with a Canopie of blacke Veluet, the Pall supported by two Earles Sonnes, and two Marquises Sonnes. The Footmen going on each side the Chariot and likewise to small Banners, carried by to Knights, 5. of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and 5. of <hi>England</hi> round about the Chariot, two principall Gent. riding at his head and feet in the said Chariot. Then followed <hi>Garter</hi> principall King of Armes accompanied with a Gent. Vsher who went bare headed. The Duke of <hi>Lennox</hi> chiefe Mourners. The L. Treasurer, &amp; L. President of the Councell, his supporters. 10. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther assistants. The L. Priuie Seale, and D. of <hi>Buckingham.</hi> The Marquis <hi>Hamilton,</hi> and Earle Marshall. The L. Chamberlaine of his Maiest. House, and the E. of <hi>Sussex.</hi> The E. of <hi>Southampton,</hi> and E. of <hi>Essex.</hi> The E. of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and E. of <hi>Exceter.</hi> The Mr. of the Horse to his Grace in close mourning, leading the Horse of Honor, most richly furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed. Thus past, this sad Shew from his Graces House in <hi>Holborne</hi> to <hi>Westminster,</hi> where the Funerall Rites being solemnly ended, his Graces liuely <unclear>Effiges</unclear>, was left in the Abbey of St. <hi>Peter</hi> vnder a Rich Hearse.</p>
            </div>
            <signed>Iohn Taylor.</signed>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed for <hi>Henry Gosson.</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
