<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A very Christian, learned, and briefe discourse, concerning the true, ancient, and Catholicke faith, against all wicked vp-start heresies seruing very profitably for a preseruatiue against the profane nouelties of papists, Anabaptists, Arrians, Brownists, and all other sectaries. First composed by Vincentius Lirinensis in Latine, about twelue hundreth yeares ago. And now faithfully translated into English, and illustrated with certaine marginall notes. By Thomas Tuke.</title>
            <title>Pro catholicae fidei antiquitate libellus. English</title>
            <author>Vincent, of Lérins, Saint, d. ca. 450.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 96 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-12">2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14435</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24753</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102090</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837890</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837890</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2237</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A14435)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2237)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1043:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A very Christian, learned, and briefe discourse, concerning the true, ancient, and Catholicke faith, against all wicked vp-start heresies seruing very profitably for a preseruatiue against the profane nouelties of papists, Anabaptists, Arrians, Brownists, and all other sectaries. First composed by Vincentius Lirinensis in Latine, about twelue hundreth yeares ago. And now faithfully translated into English, and illustrated with certaine marginall notes. By Thomas Tuke.</title>
                  <title>Pro catholicae fidei antiquitate libellus. English</title>
                  <author>Vincent, of Lérins, Saint, d. ca. 450.</author>
                  <author>Tuke, Thomas, d. 1657. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 71 [i.e. 83] leaves.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for Leonard Becket, and are to be sold at his shop in the Inner Temple,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by Thomas Tuke, of: Saint Vincent of Lérins. Pro catholicae fidei antiquitate libellus.</note>
                  <note>Title on A2r; A1r contains only printer's device and imprint.</note>
                  <note>Printed by N. Okes. Cf. colophon.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:2237:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2237:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Leonard Becket,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in the Temple neere the Church, 1611.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2237:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2237:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VERY CHRIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIAN, LEARNED, and briefe Diſcourſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the true, ancient, and Catholicke Faith, againſt all wicked vp-ſtart <hi>Hereſies:</hi> Seruing very profitably for a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruatiue againſt the profane No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelties of Papiſts, Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, Arrians, Browniſts, and <hi>all other Sectaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt compoſed by <hi>Vincentius Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinenſis</hi> in Latine, about twelue hundreth yeares ago.</p>
            <p>And now faithfully tranſlated into Engliſh, and illuſtrated with <hi>certaine Marginall Notes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By THOMAS TVKE.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London for <hi>Leonard Becket,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in the Inner Temple. 1611.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2237:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2237:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT worſhipfull, Sir IOHN LEVENTHORPE knight, and to the right vertuous Lady <hi>Ioanna, his wife, all happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe earthly and heauenly.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worſhipfull, great is the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſeneſſe of Mans nature, as may appeare by the multitude of errors, and falſe religions, of the which the world is now ſicke euen vnto death. For the Iewe hath his, the Turke his, the Indians theirs, the Papiſt his:
<pb facs="tcp:2237:4"/>
yea and almoſt euery man is ready to turne his fanſy into faith (ſo common is this kind of Alchymie) and to make doctrines of his owne deuiſes; ſo fond we are by reaſon of ſelfe-loue, and the blindneſſe of our minds.</p>
            <p>But (as <hi>Eli</hi> ſayd) <hi>this is not well.</hi> For there is but <hi>one true</hi> Religion, and as <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>In Natiu. Dom. Ser.</hi> 4. <hi>Niſi vna eſt, fides non eſt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Leo</hi> ſaith, <hi>Faith is either One, or None.</hi> Now becauſe there are ſo many religions in the world, therefore ſome will be of none, but ſtand as it were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed, not knowing what courſe to take, like the <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10. 15.</note> fool, that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeakes of, which knowes not the way into the Citty. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooues
<pb facs="tcp:2237:4"/>
vs therefore ſeeing ſuch variety of profeſſions to looke before we leape, &amp; to ſound the waters before we hoyſe vp our ſailes (for heauen is no harbor for he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes, no common Inne for all kinds of Trauellers) I meane afore all to conſult with the written word of God, the oracle of truth, the ground of faith, <hi>a</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 105.</note> 
               <hi>lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne to our feet, &amp; a light vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our path, &amp; is</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16</note> 
               <hi>profitable to teach, to conuince, to correct and instruct in righteouſneſſe, that the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God maybe abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute. Heare</hi> (ſaith S. <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. ep.</hi> 48. <hi>Audi dicit Dominus, non dicit Don<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſtin) Thus ſaith the Lord:</hi> not, <hi>thus ſaith, Donatus, or Rogatus, or Vincentius, or Hilary, or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2237:5"/>
but, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord.</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Iſ. 8. 20.</note> 
               <hi>To the Law, and to the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony</hi> (ſaith <hi>Eſay:) if they ſpeake not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them. By the Scripture God ſpeaketh his whole will,</hi> ſaith <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Per Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam Deus loquitur omne, quod vult. Moral. l.</hi> 16. <hi>c.</hi> 16.</note> 
               <hi>Gregory.</hi> If therefore men would in the true feare of God and lowlineſſe of ſpirit deſire diuine directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and attend vnto the word, vndoubtedly they ſhould ſee their way before them, and could not be ſo tranſported of Impoſtors, as they vſe to be. For <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25. 9. 12. 14.</note> 
               <hi>them that be meeke, will he guide in iudgement, and teach the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble his way. What man is he, that feareth the Lord? Him
<pb facs="tcp:2237:5"/>
will he teach the way, which he ſhall chuſe. The ſecret of the Lord is reuealed to them, that feare him; and his couenant, to giue them vnderſtanding.</hi> And as our Sauiour ſpeaketh, <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16. 23.</note> 
               <hi>Whatſoeuer ye ſhall aske the Father in my Name, he will giue it you.</hi> So then, if we will not giue eare vnto Man, but vnto God, if we will not truſt vnto our owne wings, but ſeeke for aide of him, we may boldly expect aſſiſtance of him according to his word. And becauſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin a courſe well is nothing, vnleſſe a man continue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in it; therefore it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houes vs to cleaue faſt vnto the faith, auoiding all impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures
<pb facs="tcp:2237:6"/>
of Heretickes whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer. For the furtherance hereof, this Treatiſe was firſt written in Latine aboue a thouſand yeares agoe, by a learned and godly French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whoſe authority is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe to be reſpected for his Monaſticke kinde of liuing, conſidering that our moderne Monkes haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt nothing of Antiquity beſides their name. And for the ſame purpoſe we haue turn'd it into Engliſh, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Almightie to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dew the ſame with the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of his grace. My labour I account as due to the Church in generall, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly deſerued of you
<pb facs="tcp:2237:6"/>
both in particular: if there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ſhall accept it, I ſhall haue my full deſire.</p>
            <p>The God of heauen and earth preſerue you by his grace, that after this life on Earth ye may be preſented to Ieſus Chriſt to liue in heauen with him in eternall glory.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <closer>
               <dateline>London S. Clem. <date>April 14. 1611.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your VVorſhips in Chriſt Ieſus to be commanded,
<hi>Thomas Tuke.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2237:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2237:7"/>
            <head>To The Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE are three ſorts of men, for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated this little booke. The firſt are they, that heare their fathers inſtruction, and deſpiſe not the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their mother: whom I deſire God vpon my knees to keepe free from the poyſon, and peruerſneſſe of all Heretickes, and Schiſmatickes whatſoeuer. The ſecond are they, that are miſ-led by <hi>Romiſh</hi> Impoſtors into many groſſe and nouell er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours,
<pb facs="tcp:2237:8"/>
ſuch as the Scriptures and antient Doctors vtterly condemne, as may eaſily be ſeene by viewing ſundry workes of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers learned men amongſt vs, either written, or turned into <hi>Engliſh.</hi> The chiefeſt cauſe of of whoſe erring, partly conſiſts in an incredible credit, which they giue vnto their Teachers, and partly in their owne won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull ignorance of the holy Scriptures, which might inligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten their eies, and informe their iudgements. It is written of <hi>Naaſh,</hi> that he would make a couenant with the men of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſh Gilead</hi> vpon condition <note place="margin">1. Sam. 11. 2.</note> that he might thrust out all their <hi>right eies:</hi> euen ſo ſurely the Diuell delights in nothing
<pb facs="tcp:2237:8"/>
more, then in putting out mens eyes, and in captiuating their vnderſtanding (which is as the <hi>right eye</hi> of the ſoule) that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing blinded, he may leade them at his pleaſure. But if it would pleaſe them to ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures <note place="margin">Iohn. 5. 39.</note> (as Chriſt exhorteth) and to conſider of the Catholicke do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the antient Church e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the times, wherein this our Author liued, I doubt not, but that the ſcales of ignorance would fall from their eyes, and that thoſe mists would be ſoone diſperſed, which Satan caſts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. The third are ſuch, as are not much offended at the doctrines of the Church, but condemne her gouernment, and ſtumble at her Ceremonies,
<pb facs="tcp:2237:9"/>
which yet are neither vndecent, nor ſuperſtitious, or numerous, and ſuch as neither Gods word forbiddeth, nor any approued Church in the Chriſtian world condemneth, <hi>as they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by this Church, &amp; entertained.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſee heere what ſtrange conceipts and doctrines are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed, and defended of them, ſuch as haue no foot-step in the <hi>Scripture,</hi> no fellowſhip with <hi>Antiquity, 1.</hi> It is affirmed that <hi>The true and right go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the Chriſtian Churches is a certaine De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocratie. 2.</hi> That a prouinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Church is <hi>Contrary</hi> to the teſtament of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Hereupon <hi>Henry Iacob</hi> in an Epiſtle pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed
<pb facs="tcp:2237:9"/>
to a booke lately printed at <hi>Leyden,</hi> labours for a <hi>Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 3.</hi> That humane ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies being once abuſed, cannot bee purged but by vtter aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion. <hi>4.</hi> That <note n="o" place="margin">Indeede Chriſt lay at the Paſſ. but that he did ſo at the laſt Supper, the Scripture ſayes not.</note> it is out of all doubt, that Chriſt ſate or lay at his laſt Supper: or thus, that it is not only poſsible or probable, but <hi>certaine</hi> that he vſed a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble gesture at that his laſt Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. <hi>5.</hi> That becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a table gesture; therefore it is vnlawfull for vs to vſe any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then a table gesture. <hi>6</hi> That to receiue the bread and wine kneeling is vnlawfull, is <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Kneeling at Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, as it is required of the Church of England, lawfull.</note> Which me thinkes is very strange. For what is the <hi>Idoll?</hi> wee kneele not vnto the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but vnto God, in teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
<pb facs="tcp:2237:10"/>
of reuerence and humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſpirit. Secondly if wee <hi>Muſt</hi> receiue the Sacrament with reuerence and humility of heart (as who dare gainſay?) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vndoubtedly wee <hi>May</hi> receiue it with a reuerend and humble gesture. Thirdly, if our kneeling be idolatry, then are wee idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (as if oppreſsion bee theft, and oppreſsors are <hi>Theeues:</hi> if to take the <hi>Cure</hi> of ſoules, and to take no <hi>Care</hi> of ſoules be murder, then they, that take the <hi>Cure</hi> of ſoules, and take no <hi>Care</hi> of ſoules are <hi>Murderers)</hi> yea and <hi>reſolute</hi> Idolaters: for we do not onely kneele, but ſtand to defend it, and we practiſe it daily, yea and charge them with ignorance that do condemne it
<pb facs="tcp:2237:10"/>
as vnlawful. Now what wil fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low? If we be idolaters, then they must not eate with vs. <hi>If any,</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul) that is called</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 5, 11.</note> 
               <hi>a brother, bee an Idolater, with ſuch one eate not.</hi> And againe, If wee be Idolaters, how dare they communicate with vs? What? with Idolaters? Either therefore theſe conceits must be for ſaken, or elſe I ſee not how wee can but ſwarme with <hi>Iacobites.</hi> But I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded better things of many of them: ſuch as accompany <hi>Saluation,</hi> and tend not to <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration. A. Fuluius</hi> once ſayd to his ſonne: <note n="*" place="margin">Ego te non Catilmae ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus patria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſed patriae ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſus Cauli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam gonui.</note> 
               <hi>I begat thee not for Catiline againſt thy Country, but for thy Country againſt Catiline:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2237:11"/>
ſo may I ſay, they were not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by the Goſpel, for <hi>Iohn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> for <hi>Iacob,</hi> for any turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and phantaſticke Doctor againſt the Church, but for the Church againſt them. And be they well aſsured that this ſleight stuffe will ſhrinke when it comes to wetting, this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit coine will not indure tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. The greatneſse of men, their learning, their godlineſſe, are no arguments to moue vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue their owne conceipts for doctrines. No, an Angell muſt not be heard againſt the truth. But mee thinkes I heare ſome <note place="margin">Queſt.</note> man ſay, How may I be reſolued in this difference of opinions? what ſhall I doe to finde out the truth? I anſwer. Firſt giue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent <note place="margin">An.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:2237:11"/>
care to the voyce of God in the Scriptures: what it ſaith, that receiue, though it croſse thee neuer ſo much, and where it hath no tongue, haue thou no care. Do not firſt entertaine a conceit, and then look out Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to draw it by the haire to thee. Secondly, be not ouercari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with any preiudicate opinion of thine <hi>Oppoſite:</hi> neither let the reuerend conceit of thy Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, that hath taught thee ſuch a doctrine, couer thine eye from beholding reaſon: and do not thinke that, becauſe hee is a good man, therefore all muſt needes bee good, that hee hath taught thee; or that his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines are ſounder the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another mans, becauſe his life is better.
<pb facs="tcp:2237:12"/>
Thirdly, be not proud, or <hi>ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceited,</hi> For <note n="*" place="margin">Iam. 4. 6.</note> 
               <hi>God reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth the proud.</hi> God and Pride (ſaith <hi>Bernard)</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not dwell together in the ſame heart, which could not dwell in the ſame heauen. And the Hiſtory of the Church ſheweth that <hi>Arrius</hi> of very pride fell into wicked and open hereſie. But the Lord <note n="*" place="margin">1. Pet 5. 5. Pſal. 25. 9.</note> giueth grace to the humble, and teacheth him his way. <hi>If yee aske</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine) what is the firſt ſtep in the way of truth? I anſwer Humility. If yee aske what is the ſecond? I ſay Humility, If yee aske, what is the third? I ſay the ſame, Humility.</hi> fourthly, pray earneſtly with <hi>Dauid</hi> that
<pb facs="tcp:2237:12"/>
God would bee pleaſed to <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 119. 34. 66.</note> 
               <hi>Giue thee vnderſtanding, and to teach thee good indgement and knowledge.</hi> Finally, bee not eaſily perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to beleeue Doctrines ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally against the vnanimous conſent of a true Church, which neither the ancient ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, neither are allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by any preſent <hi>approoued</hi> Church, but are the conceipts of ſome particular perſons. In one word, I pray thee diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to read this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> ouer. For it teacheth how to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the faith, againſt all the fraudes and fallacies of Imposters. It is not great, but good: learned, though but litle: and as ſweete to them,
<pb facs="tcp:2237:13"/>
that are intelligent, as ſhort. The Lord bleſſe it to thee, and giue thee an vnderſtanding head, and an obedient heart.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>April. 14. 1611.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Thine in Chriſt,
THOMAS TVKE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2237:13"/>
            <head>A TREATISE, OR Diſputation of VIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CENTIVS <note n="*" place="margin">So called of <hi>Lerme,</hi> or <hi>Lerina,</hi> an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land in the <hi>Mediterranea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> ſea, where he liued.</note> LIRINEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIS, for the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of the <hi>Catholicke faith,</hi> againſt the profane <hi>Nouelties</hi> of all <hi>Hereſies.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="preface">
               <head>The Preface.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>ORASMVCH as the Scripture ſpeakes, and warnes vs thus; <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut</hi> 32. 7</note> 
                  <hi>Aske thy Fathers, and they will ſhew thee thine El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and they will tell thece.</hi> And againe, <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 22. 17. &amp; 3. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Apply thine eare to the words of the wiſe.</hi> In like manner alſo, <hi>My Son, forget not theſe ſayings, and let thine heart keepe my words?</hi> It ſeemeth
<pb facs="tcp:2237:14"/>
to me <note n="o" place="margin">This word ſignifies a pilgrime, or ſtranger: a word befit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting al Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian men: &amp; vnder this name our Author puts forth his Booke, concealing his owne proper name, leaſt the Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary ſhould reiect the worke for the worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans ſake. Or it may be a read peregrin, a pilgrime or a ſtranger.</note> 
                  <hi>Peregrinus,</hi> the leaſt of all the ſeruants of God, that it will not be a little pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, through the Lords aſſiſtance, if I ſhall ſet downe thoſe things in writing, which I haue faithfully receiued of the holy <hi>Fathers;</hi> ſure I am, very neceſſary for mine owne infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, ſeeing I may haue in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe, whereby the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my memory may bee relieued with continuall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Vnto which taske, not only the benefite of the work doth mooue me, but the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration alſo of <hi>time,</hi> and the oportunity of <hi>Place.</hi> The <hi>time;</hi> for ſeeing all things are carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away therewith, it beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs alſo to catch ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing therefrom againe, which may further vnto eternall life: eſpecially becauſe the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2237:14"/>
of Gods terrible iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment requireth the ſtudies of Religion, and the ſubtilty of nouell Heretiques, asketh much care and diligence. The <hi>Place</hi> alſo, becauſe auoiding the throngs &amp; multitudes that are in Citties, we liue in a little Village more remote, and are there incloſtred in a <hi>Monaſtery,</hi> where without great diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we may do that, which the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſings of; <hi>Be ſtill and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>know that I am God.</hi> But indeed the reaſon of our purpoſe is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable thereunto, as who, becauſe wee haue ſome while bene toſſed with diuers and grieuous troubles of a ſecular warfare, haue at the length through the fauour of Chriſt hidden vs within the hauen of Religion, moſt faithful alwaies vnto all: that there the blaſts
<pb facs="tcp:2237:15"/>
of vanity and pride being laid downe, and appeaſing God <note n="a" place="margin">By, not For: the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients knew no merits, but Chriſts, They prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched mercy, not merit.</note> by the ſacrifice of Chriſtian humility, we might eſcape, not onely the Ship-wracks of the life preſent, but the flames alſo of the future.</p>
               <p>But now will I <hi>in the</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">That is with the helpe of God, for to do a thing in the name of God, is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to doe it to Gods glory: or by his power &amp; authority: or elſe, as here, by his grace, or with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of his aſſiſtance, as <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 20. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>name of the Lord,</hi> ſet vpon this buſineſſe; to wit, ſet downe in writing, the things that haue ben deliuered from our <hi>Elders,</hi> and committed to our kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, intending to be a faithful <hi>Relator</hi> of them, and not preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to be their <hi>Author.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meane I to ſet downe <hi>all,</hi> but to touch thoſe onely, that are neceſſary: &amp; that not in any poliſhed and curious ſtile, but in a plaine and familiar ſpeech, that the moſt of them may ſeeme to bee pointed at rather then vnfolded. Let them write
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2237:15"/>
delicately and with accurate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that are led thereunto through confidence of their wit, or by reaſon of their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: but for me it ſhall be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, that I haue prepared a <hi>Remembrancer</hi> for my ſelfe, to helpe my memory, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to preuent my forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the which yet I will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour through the Lords aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance to mend, and perfite dayly, by reuoluing and calling to mind the things that I haue <note n="c" place="margin">Not which himſelfe hath forged vpon the anuill of his owne wit.</note> 
                  <hi>learned.</hi> And this I haue ſaid before hand, that if happily ought of ours ſhall come into the hands of the <note n="*" place="margin">He meanes eſpecially ſuch as are Saints not in reſpect, of grace onely, but of place, as Biſhops &amp; other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, whoſe office is holy.</note> 
                  <hi>Saints,</hi> they would repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend nothing therein raſhly, which they may ſee by promiſe yet to be amended.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2237:16"/>
               <head>CHAP. 1.</head>
               <p>INquiring therefore often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with great care and very ſingular diligence, of very many excellent men, both for holineſſe and learning, how I might by ſome certaine, and as it were generall and regular way, diſcerne the truth of the <hi>Catholicke faith,</hi> from the falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of <hi>wicked hereſies,</hi> I recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued this anſwere alwaies from them all almoſt; That if either I, or any other would finde out the wiles of <hi>vpſtart Hereticks,</hi> and eſcape their <note n="d" place="margin">That is their deceit full reaſons, wherby they ſeeke to catch &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle men.</note> 
                  <hi>ſnares,</hi> and continue ſound and whole in a ſound faith, he muſt fortifie his faith through the Lords aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance with a two-fold fence; namely <hi>firſt</hi> with the <hi>authority of Gods word:</hi> and <hi>then</hi> alſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2237:16"/>
with the <hi>tradition</hi> of the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 2.</head>
               <p>HEre, it may be ſome man will aske; Seeing the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> of the Scriptures is perfect, and that it is aboundantly ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient of it ſelfe to all things, what need is there that the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Churches vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding <note place="margin">Queſt.</note> ſhould be ioyned therunto? Surely, becauſe al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do not after one manner vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <note place="margin">Anſ.</note> the holy Scripture, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the height thereof; but diuers men interpret the ſentences thereof diuerſly, that there may ſeeme to be as many meanings thereof almoſt, as men. For <hi>Nouatian</hi> expounds it one way, <hi>Photinus</hi> another way, <hi>Sabellius</hi> thus, <hi>Donatus</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:2237:17"/>
                  <hi>Arrius, Eunomius, Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donius</hi> other waies, <hi>Appollinaris</hi> &amp; <hi>Priſcillianus</hi> by themſelues, <hi>Iouinianus, Pelagius, Celeſtius</hi> another way, and finally, <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorius</hi> hath a ſence by himſelfe, And therefore by reaſon of ſo great deceipts, and windings of ſo different errours, it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neceſſary that a man ſhould interpret the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> according as the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church</hi> doth vnderſtand them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 3.</head>
               <p>IN like manner, euen in the <hi>Catholike Church</hi> wee muſt haue a ſpeciall regard, that we hold that which is, <hi>Euery where beleeued alwaies &amp; of all:</hi> for this is truly and properly <hi>Catholike</hi> (as the very force &amp; reaſon of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2237:17"/>
the name declareth) which comprehendeth al things truly vniuerſally. Now this we ſhall doe, if we follow Vniuerſality, Antiquity and Conſent. And wee ſhall follow <hi>Vniuerſality</hi> thus, namely if we do confeſſe this one faith to be true, which the <hi>whole Church through out the world</hi> confeſſeth. We ſhall fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Antiquity,</hi> if by no meanes we reiect thoſe interpretations, which we know to haue bene vſed and eſteemed of our holy <hi>Elders</hi> and <hi>Forefathers.</hi> And <hi>Conſent</hi> in like ſort alſo, if euer in <hi>Antiquity</hi> we follow the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations and iudgements of all, or ſurely of almoſt all <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Doctors.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2237:18"/>
               <head>CHAP. 4.</head>
               <p>VVHat then ſhal a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Queſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Catholicke</hi> do, if ſome few members of the Church ſhall cut themſelues from the fellowſhip of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Faith?</hi> Surely what elſe, but preferre the ſoundneſſe of <note place="margin">Anſ.</note> the <hi>whole body</hi> before a noyſom and corrupt <hi>member?</hi> And what <note place="margin">Quest.</note> if ſome new contagion ſhall indeuour the corruption, not of ſome ſmall part of the Church onely, but euen of the whole body thereof alſo? In like manner then he ſhall bee <note place="margin">Anſ.</note> carefull to cleaue faſt vnto <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity,</hi> which cannot now wholly be ſeduced by any no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell deceipt. And what if euen <note place="margin">Queſt.</note> in Antiquity it ſelfe the errour of two or three, or of a Citty,
<pb facs="tcp:2237:18"/>
or of ſome Prouince be found out? Then his whole care ſhall <note place="margin">Anſ.</note> be to prefer the decrees of the <hi>Vniuerſal Church,</hi> vniuerſally of <hi>old</hi> maintained, to the raſhneſſe or ignorance (if any ſuch be) of ſome <hi>few</hi> perſons. But what if ſome ſuch thing breake out, <note place="margin">Quest.</note> where nothing of that nature may be found? Then ſhall hee <note place="margin">Anſ.</note> compare the ſentences and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions of the <hi>Fathers</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and take Counſell of them: of thoſe <hi>Fathers</hi> or <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> (I meane) <note n="*" place="margin">Or eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, duntaxat.</note> onely, which though they liued not in one age and place, did yet continue in the fellowſhip and faith of <hi>one Catholicke Church,</hi> &amp; were <hi>laudable Teachers:</hi> and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he ſhall perceiue that not one or two alone, but that all alike with <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>ſame</hi> conſent did <hi>openly, commonly, and
<pb facs="tcp:2237:19"/>
conſtantly</hi> hold, write and teach, let him know that the ſame of him alſo is without any ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to bee beleeued. But that thoſe things, which wee ſay may be made more plaine, they are each of them to be cleered by examples, and to be a little more enlarged, leaſt through affectation of too much bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity, the weight of things bee not perceiued, by reaſon of paſſing ſo ſwiftly ouer them in our ſpeech.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 5.</head>
               <p>IN the time of <hi>Donatus,</hi> from whom ſprang the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> when as a great part of <hi>Aphrica</hi> had throwne themſelues head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into his furious errours, and when vnmindfull of their honour, religion and profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2237:19"/>
they did preferre the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious headines of one man to the Church of Chriſt, then thoſe <hi>Africans</hi> could of them all alone be ſafe within the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuaries of the Catholicke faith, which hauing that wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Schiſme in deteſtation, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned themſelues to all the Churches of the world; lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in truth a notable paterne to them that ſhould come af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, namely <hi>how,</hi> and that alſo <hi>well,</hi> the ſoundneſſe of <hi>all</hi> might be preferred before the fury of <hi>one,</hi> or but a <hi>few.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 6.</head>
               <p>IN like manner, when as the poyſon of the <hi>Arrians</hi> had now corrupted not ſome fewe, but almoſt all the world, ſo as that well neere all the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Latini ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monis,</hi> that ſpake the Latine tongue.</note> Latine
<pb facs="tcp:2237:20"/>
Biſhops being deceiued, partly by force and partly by fraude, knew not well, by reaſon of a certaine kinde of blindneſſe, which had inuaded their vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, what courſe they were beſt to follow, when things were ſo confuſed: then whoſoeuer was a true <hi>Louer</hi> &amp; <hi>worſhipper</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the ſame by making more accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient-faith,</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>nouel-falſhood,</hi> was preſerued from all infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of that contagious do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. The danger in truth of which time hath aboundantly ſhewed what great calamity the bringing in of that vpſtart doctrine cauſed. For then were ſhaken not ſmall things onely, but euen the greateſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. For not onely alliances, kindreds, friendſhips, and hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were diſſolued, but alſo Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2237:20"/>
People, Prouinces, Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yea, and the whole <hi>Romane Empire</hi> was vtterly ſhaken, and put out of order. For when that profane <hi>noueltie</hi> of the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> as a certaine <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellona,</hi> &amp; <hi>Furia</hi> were two heathen god deſſes: the one was ouer war, the other was the mother of fury.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellona</hi> or <hi>Furia,</hi> had firſt captiuated the <note n="c" place="margin">He means <hi>Conſtantius</hi> or <hi>Valens,</hi> or both: who were <hi>Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> both.</note> 
                  <hi>Emperour,</hi> and then brought all the <note n="f" place="margin">Or princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</note> 
                  <hi>chiefest</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him vnder new lawes, it ceaſed not afterwards to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; diſorder all things, priuat and publicke, facred and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane, and to haue no regard of that, which was good and true, but whomſoeuer it liſted, to ſmite them downe, as from ſome place on high. Then were wiues defiled, widdowes robd, Virgins deflowred, Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries demoliſhed, Cleargy-men diſturbed, Leuites beaten, Prieſts baniſhed, priſons, gaoles and mynes filled with
<pb facs="tcp:2237:21"/>
the <note n="g" place="margin">Antiquity acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth men li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to bee Saints: &amp; not dead men onely, as ſome do,</note> Saints: the greateſt part of whom being driuen out of Citties forbidden to them, and exiled, were euen broken and conſumed with na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, hunger, and thirſt, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt deſerts, dens, wild beaſts and rockes. But all theſe things did they for no other cauſe befall, but euen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſuperſtitions of mans inuentions were taught for heauenly doctrine, becauſe well-grounded antiquity was vedermined by wicked nouel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, becauſe the ordinances of the <hi>Elders</hi> were violated, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the decrees of the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> were repealed, becauſe the determinations of the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient</hi> were diſanulled, and for that the luſt of profane and <hi>vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtart</hi> curioſity contained not it ſelfe within the moſt <note n="h" place="margin">Heretiks break from their tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitate, &amp; go an whoring after the idols of their owne braines.</note> 
                  <hi>chaſte
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2237:21"/>
limits</hi> of ſacred and vncorrupt Antiquity?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 7.</head>
               <p>BVt (it will bee thought) perhaps wee faine theſe things through hatred of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelty and loue of Antiquity. Whoſoeuer iudgeth this, let him giue credit at the leaſt to bleſſed <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> who in his ſecond book to the Emperour, <hi>Gratian,</hi> himſelfe bewailing the bitternes of the time, ſaith: But now, almighty God, quoth <note n="*" place="margin">In ſine cap. vlt.</note> he, we haue beene ſufficiently pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by our owne deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and bloud-ſhed for the ſlaughters of the Confeſſours, the baniſhments of the Prieſts, and for ſuch wicked villany. It is cleare enough that they, which violated the faith, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb facs="tcp:2237:22"/>
be ſafe. In like manner, in the third booke of the ſame worke: Let vs, therefore keepe (ſaith he) the commandements of the Elders, that wee be not bold through vnciuill raſhneſſe to breake the ſeales, that are hereditary. Neither the Elders, nor the Power, nor the Angels, nor Archangels durſt open that ſealed booke of prophecy: the prerogatiue of explaning that <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reu.</hi> 5. 3. 5.</note> was reſerued for Chriſt alone. Which of vs dares vnſeale the <note n="i" place="margin">That is, the holy Scriptures: ſo called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them to keep, and teach: I meane Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtets, which book is then ſaid to be vnſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in our Authors ſenſe, when it is viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted.</note> 
                  <hi>Sacerdoticall Booke,</hi> ſealed of Confeſſours, and conſecrated now with the martyrdome of many? which they, that haue bene compelled to vnſeale it, yet afterwards haue ſealed, when the fraud was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: they that durſt not violate it, were Confeſſours and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs. How can wee deny their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2237:22"/>
faith, whoſe victory we do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll? Wee praiſe them I ſay, O venerable <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> wee praiſe them indeed, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing wee wonder at them. For who is he, that is ſo mad, who though he be not able to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them, yet would not wiſh to follow, whom no violence hath driuen from defending of the faith of the <hi>Elders?</hi> Not threatnings, not flatterings, not life, not death, not the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, not Sergeants, not the Emperour, not the Empire, not men, not diuels, Whom (I ſay) the Lord, for their conſtant im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing of holy Antiquity, deemed meete for ſo great an office, as by them to repaire Churches ruinated, to quicken ſpirituall people extinguiſhed, to put on the Crownes of Prieſts, that were deiected, to
<pb facs="tcp:2237:23"/>
deface (a fountaine of vnfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned teares being infuſed from heauen into the Biſhops) thoſe wicked (I ſay) not letters, but <hi>litures</hi> (blots or daſhes) of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell impiety, and finally, to call back now almoſt all the world being ſtrucken with the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt of ſuddaine hereſie: (I ſay to call it backe) to the <hi>ancient faith,</hi> from <hi>vp-ſtart falſhood:</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ancient ſoundneſſe, from fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and vnſound newneſſe, and to the ancient light, from the blindneſſe of nouelty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 8.</head>
               <p>BVt in this certaine Diuine vertue of Confeſſions, that we are alſo euen moſt of all to mark, that then in the very An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity of the Church, they vndertooke the defence, not of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2237:23"/>
ſome part; but of the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. For it was not lawful for me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo great, and of ſuch quality, to mantaine with ſo great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention &amp; indeauour, the ſtrag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling &amp; ſelfe-thwarting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectures of one or two, or to ſtriue for the raſh conſent of ſome little Prouince: but fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the decrees and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of Apoſtolique and Catholicke truth, made by all the <note n="k" place="margin">That is, the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpell: ſo called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did offer the people to God, as a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice: kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling their fleſh with the Word, as with a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifycing Knife.</note> 
                  <hi>Prieſts</hi> of the holy Church, they chooſed rather to betray themſelues, then the faith which was held of old v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſally. Whereby they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained alſo ſo great a degree of glory, as that they were right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and worthily counted not Confeſſours only, but the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall of Confeſſours alſo. It behoueth therefore all true Catholikes <hi>vnceſſantly</hi> to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate
<pb facs="tcp:2237:24"/>
on this notable, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede diuine enſample of thoſe ſame bleſſed men: who ſhining like the <note n="l" place="margin">He alludes to the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſticke in Exod. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>ſeuen headed Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke,</hi> with the ſeuenfold light of the holy Spirit, haue ſhewed their poſterity a moſt euident way, how the boldneſſe of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane nouelty may in all the vaine bablings of errours bee <note n="m" place="margin">Or ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen, quaſht, ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, broken, c<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nteratur.</note> hence forth cooled with the authority of ſacred Antiquity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 9.</head>
               <p>NEither is this a new thing truly: for this cuſtome was alwaies vſed in the <hi>Church,</hi> that the more any man flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in religion, the more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy he was to withſtand nouell deuices. The world is full of ſuch examples. But, for breuity ſake, wee will make choyce of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2237:24"/>
ſome one, and this eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the Apoſtolicke Sea. In times paſt therefore <hi>Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinus,</hi> of venerable memory, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Carthage, held rebap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tization firſt of all men, againſt the Canon of the <hi>Word,</hi> againſt the <hi>Rule</hi> of the <hi>Uniuerſall</hi> Church, againſt the iudgement of all his <hi>Fellow-prieſts,</hi> againſt the <note n="n" place="margin">Or againſt the cuſtome &amp; ordin an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>contra morem &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituta.</hi>
                  </note> manner and cuſtomes of the <hi>Elders.</hi> The which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption cauſed ſo great a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, as that it miniſtred a forme of ſacrilege, not onely to all heretickes, but gaue oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of error to ſome Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes alſo. When as all men therefore euery where vpon the nouelty of the thing cryed out againſt it, &amp; all the Prieſts on euery ſide, did euery one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to reſiſt it, then Pope <hi>Stephen,</hi> of happy memory, <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2237:25"/>
of the <hi>Apoſtolike See,</hi> with the reſt of his <hi>Fellowes,</hi> but yet aboue the reſt withſtood it; deeming it, as I ſuppoſe, a thing beſeeming, if hee did excell all the reſt as much by deuout af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the faith, as hee did ſurpaſſe them by the authority of place. Finally, in an Epiſtle which was ſent into <hi>Affrica,</hi> the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apud Cypri. Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Ep.</hi> 7.</note> ſaid <hi>Stephen</hi> ordeined in theſe words: <hi>That nothing ſhould bee renewed, but that which is deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi> For that holy and wiſe man knew, that piety doth nothing elſe allow of, but that all things ſhould with the ſame faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe bee reteined for the <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> with the which they were receiued of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> and that we ought to follow religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not which way wee would lead it, but rather by that way it would lead vs, and that that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2237:25"/>
is the propertie of <hi>Christian</hi> modeſty and grauity for men not to deliuer their owne deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to them, that ſo come af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but to keepe the things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of their Elders. What therefore was the iſſue then of all the matter? Surely what elſe, but that, which was vſuall, and accuſtomed? <hi>Antiquity namely reteined, and nouelty ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploded.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 10.</head>
               <p>BVt peraduenture then that <note place="margin">Obiect.</note> new deuiſe was deſtitute of means to defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; beare it out. Yea verily, there was for it ſo <note place="margin">Anſ.</note> great acutenes of wit, ſo great aboundance of eloquence, ſo great a number of maintainers, ſo great likelihood of truth, ſo many Oracles of Gods word,
<pb facs="tcp:2237:26"/>
but indeede after a new and naughty manner vnderſtood, that me thought all that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy could by no meanes be deſtroyed, vnleſſe that ſelfe ſame vndertaken, defended, &amp; commended profeſſion of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelty, had forſaken the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone cauſe of ſo great an enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe.</p>
               <p>To conclude, what force had that Affrican Councell or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree? Truly none, through the gift of God: but all things were aboliſhed, made void, and tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vnder foot, as dreames, as fables, as things ſuperfluous.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 11.</head>
               <p>AND ô the wonderfull change of things! The Authors of the ſame opinion are accounted <hi>Catholickes:</hi> but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2237:26"/>
the <hi>Followers</hi> are iudged <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes.</hi> The <hi>Maiſters</hi> are abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, the <hi>Schollers</hi> are condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. The writers of the bookes ſhall bee the children of the Kingdome, but Hell ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the <hi>Defenders.</hi> For who would doubt that moſt bleſſed <hi>Cyprian,</hi> the <hi>Light</hi> of all the Saints, both Biſhops and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, together with the reſt of his fellowes, ſhall reigne eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally with <hi>Chriſt?</hi> Or who on the contrary is ſo ſacrilegious, as to deny that the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> &amp; thoſe other peſtilent wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, which doe bragge that they rebaptize by the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of that Councell, ſhall burne for euer with the <hi>Diuell?</hi> Which iudgement truly to me ſeemeth to bee promulged of God, for their craftineſſe eſpecially, who when they go about to forge
<pb facs="tcp:2237:27"/>
an hereſie vnder another bodies name, do commonly lay hold of the writings of ſome ancient man ſomething too couertly ſet out, which in reſpect of their darkneſſe, doe as it were, ſerue for their owne opinion: that that, which, I know not what, they doe bring forth, they may ſeeme to thinke, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>firſt,</hi> nor <hi>all-alone.</hi> Whoſe wickedneſſe I iudge worthy double hatred: either therfore, becauſe they are not afraid to proffer the poyſon of hereſie vnto others: or therefore alſo, becauſe they do with a wicked hand blow vp, and winnow the memory of euery holy man, like aſhes now raked vp, and diffame thoſe things with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiued opinion, which ought in ſilence to be buried; altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther following the foote-ſteps
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2237:27"/>
of their father <hi>Cham,</hi> who not onely neglected to couer the nakedneſſe of venerable <hi>Noah,</hi> but told it alſo to the reſt, that it might be mocked. Whereby hee did ſo grieuouſly ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt child-like piety, as that his very poſterity became ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to the curſes of his ſin: thoſe brethren being bleſſed, and farre vnlike, who would neither diſtaine the nakedneſſe of their reuerend father with their owne eies, nor haue it lye open vnto other mens, but co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered him, as it is written, <hi>with their faces backward:</hi> which is neither to approue, nor diſcloſe <note place="margin">Gen. 9.</note> the error of the holy man: and therefore are they bleſſed in their poſterity. But let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne vnto our purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2237:28"/>
               <head>CHAP. 12.</head>
               <p>WE ſhould therefore great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feare the grieuous ſinne of <hi>changing</hi> the <note n="o" place="margin">By faith is not meant, the gift of faith, but the doctrine: not by which, but which wee do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue.</note> 
                  <hi>Faith, and of ſtairing Religion:</hi> from the which wickedneſſe wee are deterred, not onely by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution,</hi> but alſo by the cenſure of <hi>Apostolicall authority.</hi> For all men know how grauely, how ſeuerely, and how earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the bleſſed <note n="a" place="margin">Gal. 1.</note> Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> inueigheth againſt ſome, that were too ſoone through their owne lightneſſe, <hi>tranſlated from him, who had called them to the grace of Chriſt, vnto another Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, which is not another:</hi> who had heaped to themſelues Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers after their <hi>owne</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">2. Tim. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>deſires,</hi> turning their eares from the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2237:28"/>
truth, and turning themſelues to fables, hauing damnation, <note n="c" place="margin">1. Tim. 5.</note> becauſe they haue broken the firſt faith. Who were by them deceiued, of whom the ſame Apoſtle writeth to the <hi>Romane</hi> brethren: <hi>Now I beſeech you</hi> 
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 16. 17</note> 
                  <hi>brethren, marke them, that cauſe diſſentions &amp; offences other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then the doctrine which yee haue learned, and auoyd them. For ſuch ſerue not the Lord Chriſt, but their owne belly: and by faire ſpeeches, and flattering ſeduce the hearts of the ſimple:</hi> which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into houſes, and lead <hi>captiue</hi> 
                  <note n="e" place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>ſilly women</hi> laden with ſinnes and led with ſundry luſts, euer learning, and neuer coming to the knowledge of the truth, <note n="f" place="margin">Tit. 1. 10. 11</note> 
                  <hi>Uaine-talkers,</hi> and <hi>Seducers,</hi> which ſubuert whole houſes, teaching things which they ſhould not, for <hi>filthy Lucre ſake.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2237:29"/>
Men of corrupt mindes <note n="g" place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate</hi> concerning the faith: proud, and knowing nothing: but <note n="h" place="margin">1. Tim. 6. 4, <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>doting about questions,</hi> and ſtrife of words, deſtitute of the truth, imagining that gaine is godlineſſe. Likewiſe alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>idle</hi> 
                  <note n="i" place="margin">1. Tim. 5. 13</note> they learne to goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout from houſe to houſe, yea they are alſo bablers, and buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodies, ſpeaking things, they ought not. <hi>Who</hi> 
                  <note n="k" place="margin">1. Tim. 1. 19</note> 
                  <hi>repelling a good conſcience, as concerning faith, haue made ſhip-wracke.</hi> Whoſe prophane bablings fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther much vnto impiety, and their <note n="l" place="margin">2. Tim. 2. 17</note> 
                  <hi>word fretteth like a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.</hi> And it fitteth well which is alſo written of them: <note n="m" place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 9</note> 
                  <hi>But they ſhall preuaile no further: for their madneſſe ſhal be manifeſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all, as theirs alſo was.</hi> When therefore ſome ſuch wandring vp and downe Countries and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2237:29"/>
Cities, &amp; carrying about their <note n="o" place="margin">He alludes to Pedlars that go vp and downe to ſell their Wares.</note> 
                  <hi>Pedlary</hi> errors, had come al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to the <hi>Galatians:</hi> and when as the <hi>Galatians</hi> hauing heard the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, being now affected with a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine loathing of the truth, and caſting vp the <hi>Manna</hi> of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicke and Catholicke do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, delighted themſelues in the filthineſſe of hereticall nouelty, the Apoſtle did ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe his Apoſtolicall autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as that with all ſeuerity he did decree: <hi>But though either we</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>or an Angel from</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 1. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Heauen preach vnto you otherwiſe then we haue preached, let him bee accurſed.</hi> What is that which he ſaith, <hi>But though wee?</hi> Why does hee not rather ſay, <hi>But</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Queſt.</note> 
                  <hi>though I?</hi> The meaning here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> is this: Though <hi>Peter,</hi> though <hi>Andrew,</hi> though <hi>Iohn:</hi> Laſtly, though the <hi>whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2237:30"/>
ſhold preach to you other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then we haue preached, <hi>Let him bee accurſed.</hi> A terrible <hi>Curſe,</hi> that to maintaine the conſtant embracing of the firſt <note n="o" place="margin">He means not Faith, whereby we do beleeue, but which we doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue, that is, the doctrine of Faith, which was once for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Saints, as in Iud. 3.</note> faith, he neither ſpared <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,</hi> nor the reſt of his <hi>Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apoſtles.</hi> Yet this is but little, <hi>Although</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>an Angell ſhould from heauen preach vnto you, otherwiſe then wee haue prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, let him be accurſed.</hi> It ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced not for the keeping of the faith, once deliuered to haue mentioned the nature of <hi>Man,</hi> vnleſſe hee had comprehended alſo the excellency of <hi>Angels.</hi> Though <hi>We</hi> (ſaith he) or an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell from heauen. Not becauſe the holy and heauenly Angels can now offend: but this is his meaning: <hi>If alſo</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>that ſhould bee, which cannot be, Whoſoeuer hee be, that ſhall aſſay
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2237:30"/>
to change the faith, that was once deliuered, let him bee accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 13.</head>
               <p>BVt hee ſpake, it may bee, <note place="margin">Obiect.</note> theſe things without due regard, and vttered them in an humane paſſion rather, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> decreed them with Diuine reaſon. Farre bee it from him, for hee goes on, and preſſeth <note place="margin">Sol.</note> this ſame point with a very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt repetition: <hi>As wee haue</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>ſaid before,</hi> quoth he, <hi>ſo ſay I now againe, If any preach vnto you otherwiſe, then that yee haue receiued, let him be accurſed.</hi> He ſaid not: If any preach vnto you beſides that which ye haue receiued, let him bee bleſſed, praiſed and entertained: but let him be, quoth he, <hi>accurſed,</hi> that
<pb facs="tcp:2237:31"/>
is ſeparated, put from the flock and excluded, leaſt the curſed contagion of one Sheep ſhould corrupt the harmeleſſe flocke of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by a <note n="*" place="margin">Or infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</note> venemous mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with them. Yea, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps theſe precepts belong on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the <hi>Galatians.</hi> Then theſe <note place="margin">Obiect.</note> things alſo are commanded to <note place="margin">Sol.</note> the <hi>Galatians</hi> onely, which are mentioned in the ſame Epiſtle after: ſuch as are theſe; <hi>If wee liue in the Spirit, let vs alſo walk in the Spirit, let vs not be deſirous of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal</hi> 2. 25. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>vaine glory, prouoking one another, enuying one another:</hi> and the reſt. Which if it bee againſt ſenſe, and if they be commanded vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all alike, it ſtandeth with good reaſon that, as theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements concerning man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ſo thoſe alſo concerning <hi>faith</hi> ſhould equally belong to <hi>all.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:2237:31"/>
               <head>CHAP. 14.</head>
               <p>ANd as no man may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke, or enuy one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo no man may receiue ought beſides that, which the Catholike Church doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way preach. or elſe perhaps <note place="margin">Obiect.</note> it was at that time inioyned: that if any did preach other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then was already prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, hee ſhould bee accurſed: but not at this time there is no ſuch commandement. Then that alſo, which hee likewiſe <note place="margin">Sol:</note> ſpeaketh in the ſame Epiſtle, <hi>And I ſay, walke in the Spirit, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>ye ſhall not fulfill the lust of the fleſh,</hi> was at that time onely commanded, and is not now inioyned. But if it be both im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious and pernicious ſo to thinke, it doth neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb facs="tcp:2237:32"/>
that, as theſe things ought to be obſerued of all ages, ſo thoſe things which are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed concerning the keeping of the faith without alteration, are commanded alſo to all ages. To preach any thing therefore to <hi>Chriſtian</hi> 
                  <note n="o" place="margin">There are now two ſorts of Catholiks, Chriſtian, &amp; Antichriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the former are reall, the other (as the Ieſuits) are nominall &amp; titular.</note> Catholikes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, which they haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, was neuer lawfull, is no where lawfull, and neuer ſhall be lawfull: and to accurſe them, which preach any thing beſides that, which was once receiued, hath beene euer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoouefull, is euery where be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoouefull, and ſhall alwaies be behoouefull: Which things ſeeing they thus ſtand, is there any man either ſo bold, as to preach otherwiſe, then hath ben preached in the Church, or ſo light as to receiue otherwiſe, then that hee hath receiued of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2237:32"/>
the Church? Let <hi>him</hi> cry, and cry againe, and againe, let him in his letters cry both vnto <hi>all,</hi> and <hi>alwaies,</hi> and <hi>euery where,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">He allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to that in <hi>Act.</hi> 9. 15.</note> euen <hi>that veſſell</hi> of election, that teacher of the Gentiles, that Apoſtolique Trumpet, that Preacher of Men, and who knew the will of God, <hi>That if any one preach a new doctrine hee ſhall be accurſed,</hi> On the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry alſo certaine <hi>Frogs,</hi> and <hi>Gnats,</hi> and <hi>Flies,</hi> that ſhall periſh, ſuch as are the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> cry out againſt him, and that vnto Catholikes. We, ſay they, being Authors, Leaders, and interpreters, <hi>Condemne</hi> ye thoſe things, which yee did hold, <hi>hold</hi> yee thoſe things, which yee did condemne, <hi>Reiect</hi> yee the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent faith, the Fathers ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and thoſe things which the Elders haue committed to
<pb facs="tcp:2237:33"/>
your truſt and <hi>Receiue</hi> ye, <hi>What things I pray you?</hi> I tremble to ſpeake them: for they are ſo inſolent, that mee thinkes they <note n="*" place="margin">This he ſaith to ſhew the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of their errours.</note> cannot be without ſome vile offence affirmed, no nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth ſomuch as refelled.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 15.</head>
               <p>BVt ſome man will ſay. Wherefore then doth God <note place="margin">Queſt.</note> very often ſuffer certaine excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent perſons in the Church to broach new matters vnto Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes? It is a good queſtion, and worthy to be diligently &amp; <note place="margin">Anſ.</note> largely anſwered. Which yet we muſt make anſwere to, not of our owne head, but by the authority of Gods word, and by the inſtruction of an Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Teacher. Let vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore heare holy <hi>Moſes,</hi> and let
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2237:33"/>
him teach vs, wherefore lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, and ſuch as by reaſon of the grace of knowledge be called alſo <hi>Prophets</hi> of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, are ſometimes permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to publiſh new doctrines, which the old Teſtament vſeth allegorically to call <hi>Strange Gods;</hi> to wit, becauſe Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques worſhip their owne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, as the Gentiles doe their gods. Bleſſed <hi>Moſes</hi> therefore in <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. 1. 2'</note> 
                  <hi>If there ariſe among you a Prophet, or which ſaith hee hath ſeene a viſion:</hi> that is to ſay, a Teacher conſtituted in the Church, who is thought of his Schollers and Hearers to teach by ſome reuelation. What fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth? <hi>And ſhall giue thee a Signe or Wonder, and the Signe or Wonder, which he hath ſpoken of ſhall come to paſſe.</hi> Doubtles
<pb facs="tcp:2237:34"/>
ſome great, I know not what, Teacher is vnderſtood, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with ſuch knowledge, as who may ſeeme to his owne followers not onely to know things, that are within the reach of man, but alſo to <hi>fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>know</hi> things, which are aboue him, ſuch almoſt as <hi>Ualentinus, Donatus, Photinus, Appollinaris,</hi> and the reſt of that rabble, were by their Diſciples crakt of to haue bene. But what followes, <hi>And ſhall ſay,</hi> quoth <hi>Moſes? vnto thee,</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Let vs go and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after other gods, which thou knoweſt not, and let vs ſerue them.</hi> What are thoſe ſtrange Gods but ſtrange <hi>errours,</hi> which thou haſt not knowne, that is to ſay, <hi>new,</hi> and <hi>not-heard-of?</hi> And <hi>let vs ſerue them,</hi> that is, let vs beleeue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, follow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But what ſaies he laſt of all? <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2237:34"/>
hearken,</hi> quoth hee, <hi>vnto that Prophet, or dreamer of dreames,</hi> And why, I pray thee, doth not God <note n="c" place="margin">Or inhibit, hinder, let.</note> prohibite that to bee taught, which hee doth forbid to be receiued? <hi>Becauſe,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>the Lord your God prooueth you, that it might appeare whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you loue the Lord your God, withall your heart, and withall your ſoule.</hi> The reaſon is clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer then the light, why the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God doth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſuffer certaine Teachers of the Churches to broach ſome new doctrines: <hi>that the Lord your God,</hi> quoth he, <hi>might try yee.</hi> And indeed it is no ſmall temptation, when as he, whom thou counteſt a Prophet, the Diſciple of the Prophets, and a teacher and defender of the truth, and whom thou doſt exceedingly reuerence &amp; loue,
<pb facs="tcp:2237:35"/>
Shall on the ſuddaine cloſely bring in ſome hurtfull errours, which thou art neither able quickly to perceiue, as long as thou art led by a fore-ſtalled iudgement, concerning his old maiſterlike authority: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doſt thou eaſily thinke it lawfull, to condemne them, whilſt thou art hindred by thine affection towards thine ancient Maiſter <note n="*" place="margin">Or tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher.</note>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 16.</head>
               <p>HEre ſome man may, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps deſire that thoſe things, which are in the words of holy <hi>Moſes</hi> affirmed, may be by ſome Eccleſiaſticall En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamples cleered. The deſire is iuſt, and not long to be put off. For that we may beginne with the neereſt, and thoſe, that are
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2237:35"/>
manifeſt: what a temptation was that of late ſuppoſe wee, when as that wretch <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> being ſuddenly turned from a <hi>Sheepe</hi> to a <hi>Wolfe,</hi> had begun to rend the <hi>Flocke</hi> of <hi>Chriſt?</hi> At <note place="margin">Falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers are called Wolues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they bite and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure the Sheep of Chriſt with their wicked errours: and like Wolues they are not of the Sheepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, but his foes.</note> which time the very ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whom he did teare: for a great part of them as yet did verily think him to be a ſheep, and therefore lay the more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to his teeth. For who would eaſily imagine him to erre, whom he ſaw choſen with ſuch iudgement of the Empire, and ſo highly fauoured of the Prieſts? Who being continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honoured with the great loue of the Saints, and very great good will of the people, did openly preach the word of God, and confute alſo the hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full errours of <hi>Iewes,</hi> and <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles.</hi> By the which meanes I
<pb facs="tcp:2237:36"/>
pray you, would hee not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſsade any man that hid do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, preaching, and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were right and ſound? Who to make way for his one hereſie inueighed againſt the blaſphemies of all hereſies. But this was that, which <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> ſaith; <hi>The Lord your God proueth you, whether yee loue him or no.</hi> And that we may paſſe by <hi>Nestorius,</hi> in whom there was alwaies more wonderment then profite, and more fame then experience: whom the fauour of men, rather then of God, had for a while aduanced in the opinion of the common people: let vs rather ſpeake of thoſe, who hauing profited well and being full of induſtry became no ſmall temptation to Catholike men.</p>
               <p>As in <hi>Hungarie,</hi> in the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2237:36"/>
of our Anceſters <note n="e" place="margin">He was Biſhop of the <hi>Sirmitan</hi> Church: But a Galatian borne: skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the Greeke and Latine tongues: he foſtered a blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous error againſt Chriſt: and being a man of good parts other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with pride, (a moath that frets the cuſhion in which it bred) as ſome Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents ſay.</note> 
                  <hi>Photi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> is ſaid to haue tempted the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Sirmion.</hi> Where whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as with the great liking of al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee was called vnto the prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and had executed his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for a time, like a <hi>Catholike,</hi> ſuddenly, like that <hi>euil Prophet,</hi> or <hi>Dreamer,</hi> which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of, hee began to perſwade the people of God, committed to his truſt, to follow after <hi>ſtrange gods,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>ſtrange errours,</hi> which before they knew not. But this is vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and that dangerous, becauſe hee was furniſhed with no meane helpes to ſo great a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. For hee had a good wit, and hee was an excellent Scholler, and very eloquent, or powerfull in ſpeech; able in both languages to diſpute and write eloquently and ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally:
<pb facs="tcp:2237:37"/>
as appeareth by the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of his bookes, which hee hath written, partly in <hi>Greeke,</hi> and partly in <hi>Latine.</hi> But it was well, that the Sheepe of Chriſt committed to him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very watchfull and wary for the Catholicke Faith, had quicke regard to the words of <hi>Moſes,</hi> who did forewarne them, and that, although they did admire the eloquence of their Prophet and Paſtor, yet notwithſtanding, they were not ignorant of the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before they follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed as the <note n="f" place="margin">Such an one is euery godly and orthodoxall Biſhop, and Paſtor: who goes before his fellowes the Sheepe of Chriſt in life and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the word of God in their eares: &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the controll of the chiefe Sheepheard, as well as the meaneſt in the flock.</note> 
                  <hi>Bel-weather</hi> of the <hi>Flocke,</hi> euen him they fled fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> afterwards, as from a <hi>Wolfe,</hi> Neither do wee come to know the perill of this Eccleſiaſticall temptation by the example of <hi>Photinus,</hi> but of <hi>Apollinaris</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and are therby alſo admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2237:37"/>
to the more diligent kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the faith, which is to be kept. For he made his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers to haue much a doe, and brought them into great ſtraites. For whereas the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Church drew them one way, the cuſtome or conuerſation &amp; acquaintance of their Maiſter drew them backe another way: and ſo wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, and wauering betwixt both, they ſee not which way they ſhould rather chuſe. But it may be he was a man, that might eaſily bee contemned. Yea verily, he was ſo worthy a man, and ſo qualified, as that he might in the moſt things be too ſoone beleeued. For who ſurpaſt him in acutenes of wit, practiſe, and in Schollerſhip? How many hereſies hee hath ouerthrown in many volumes,
<pb facs="tcp:2237:38"/>
how many errours contrary to the faith hee hath confuted, that moſt excellent and very huge worke, conſiſting of no leſſe then thirty bookes, doth witneſſe, wherein he hath with a great maſſe of argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded the furious cauils of <hi>Porphiry.</hi> It is too long to recko<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp all his workes, for the which he might intruth be matched, with the chiefeſt builders of the Church, had he not through that wicked luſt of hereticall <note n="g" place="margin">Humility is the nurſe of verity, pride &amp; cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity be the founders of hereſie.</note> curioſity found out what nouelty I wot not, by the which he might both defile all his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, as with the mixture of a certaine leproſie, and ſhould haue his doctrine ſaid to be not ſo much an edification, as an <hi>Eccleſiaſticall tentation.</hi> Heere perhaps ſome may require at my hands, that I would ſhew
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2237:38"/>
them the hereſies of theſe men, of whom we ſpake before; to wit, <hi>Neſtorius, Apollinaris,</hi> and <hi>Photinus.</hi> But this is nothing to the matter; which now wee are in hand with. For our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is not to ſet downe the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of all, but to ſhew the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of a few, whereby that may euidently and plainely be cleered, which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaketh: Namely that, if at any time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Eccleſiaſticall Teacher, and hee a Prophet by reaſon of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting the myſteries of the Prophets, ſhal attempt to bring in ſome new point of doctrine into the Church of God, the Diuine prouidence <hi>doth ſuffer it</hi> to be done, that <hi>We might be proued.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2237:39"/>
               <head>CHAP. 17.</head>
               <p>IT will not therefore bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe by way of digreſſion briefly to ſhew the opinions of the fore-named heretiques, that is, <hi>Photinus, Apollinaris,</hi> &amp; <hi>Neſtorius.</hi> This is then the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Photinus:</hi> that God is <hi>ſingle</hi> and <hi>alone,</hi> and to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed after a <hi>Iudaicall</hi> manner: he ſaith that there are not full three perſons, neither doth he thinke, that there is any perſon of the <note n="a" place="margin">Chriſt is called the Word: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is begotten of the Father, as words are of the mind: and becauſe hee ſhewes his Fathers mind vnto vs.</note> 
                  <hi>Word</hi> or <hi>Son</hi> of God, or any of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt:</hi> he doth alſo ſay that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is a <hi>meere</hi> man <hi>only,</hi> to whom he aſcribeth a beginning from <hi>Mary:</hi> and this he teacheth by all meanes for a doctrine, <hi>That we ought to worſhip onely, the perſon of God the Father, and onely Chriſt the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2237:39"/>
Man.</hi> Theſe things therefore held <hi>Photinus. Apollinaris</hi> alſo doth as it were glory that hee doth conſent vnto the vnity truly of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> and that with perfect ſoundnes of faith: but he doth by open profeſſion blaſpheme againſt the <hi>Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the Lord. For hee ſaith, that the ſoule of a man was ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not at all in the fleſh of our Sauiour, or elſe ſurely that there was ſuch a one, as wanted vnderſtanding and reaſon. Yea and he ſaid, that the very fleſh of our Lord was not of the fleſh of the holy Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> but that it came downe from heauen into the Virgin: and alwaies ſtaggering and doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, he ſaid ſometimes that it was coëternall with the God, the <hi>Word,</hi> ſometimes that it was made of the Diuinity of the
<pb facs="tcp:2237:40"/>
                  <hi>Word.</hi> For he would not that two ſubſtances ſhould bee in Chriſt, one <hi>Diuine,</hi> and another <hi>Humane,</hi> one of a father, the other of a mother: but he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined that the nature of the <hi>Word</hi> was diuided, as though a part thereof remained in God, and the other had bene turned into the fleſh: that, whereas the truth ſaith, that of two ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces there is one <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he being oppoſite to the truth might af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that of one Diuinity of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> there are two ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Theſe then are the errours of <hi>Apollinaris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now <hi>Nestorius</hi> being ſicke of a contrary diſeaſe to <hi>Apolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naris,</hi> whiles he makes fare, as if hee did diſtinguiſh two ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in Chriſt, all on the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den hee brings in two perſons: and with incredible wickednes
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2237:40"/>
will haue <hi>two Sons</hi> of God, <hi>two Chriſts:</hi> One of them God, the other Man: one that is begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of a Father, the other ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated of a Mother: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee doth affirme that holy <hi>Mary</hi> is not to bee called the <note n="e" place="margin">Non The<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t ocos<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoto<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>os.</note> 
                  <hi>Mother of God,</hi> but the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Christ:</hi> to wit, becauſe of her came not Chriſt, who is God, but he, which was man. If ſo be that any man thinke, that hee ſaith in his letters, that Chriſt is one, and that hee ſpeaks of one perſon of Chriſt, let him not eaſily giue credit to him. For either hee hath deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed this ſhift through his skil to deceiue, that by good things he might the more eaſily perſwade men alſo vnto euill: as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith: <hi>It wrought death</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>vnto me by that, which was good.</hi> Either therefore (as wee ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:2237:41"/>
before) to the end that hee might deceiue, he doth in ſome places of his writings glory that he doth beleeue on Chriſt, &amp; one perſon of Chriſt: or elſe ſurely hee ſaith that <hi>two perſons</hi> now after the <hi>Virgins</hi> deliuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce did ſo meete and knit in one <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that yet he holds there were <hi>two Chriſts</hi> at the time of her conceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or deliuering, &amp; a little afterwards. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as intruth <hi>Chriſt</hi> was at the firſt borne an <note n="i" place="margin">Lo the fond co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceit of this here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique! The Colt ruins if he haue the reines.</note> 
                  <hi>ordinary</hi> and <hi>meere</hi> man, and not yet partaker of the vnity of the perſon of God the <hi>Word,</hi> afterwards the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the <hi>Word</hi> aſſuming him deſcended into him. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though now being aſſumed he do remain in the glory of God, yet it ſeemeth to him that for ſome ſpace there was no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt him, &amp; other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:2237:41"/>
               <head>CHAP. 18.</head>
               <p>THeſe things therefore <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorius, Apollinaris,</hi> &amp; <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus</hi> like <note n="o" place="margin">Not rage but zeale makes him thus to ſpeake. A dog will bawle &amp; bite: a mad dog will not ſtick to bite his maiſter, and that which he ſhould not; &amp; ſuch are falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers.</note> 
                  <hi>madde dogs</hi> doe barke againſt the Catholicke faith; <hi>Photinus</hi> by not confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the <hi>Trinity: Appollinaris</hi> in ſaying that the nature of the <hi>Word</hi> is conuertible, &amp; not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging two ſubſtances in Chriſt, and by denying either the whole ſoule of Chriſt, or at the leaſt, the minde &amp; reaſon in the ſoule, and by affirming that the Word of God was in ſtead thereof: &amp; <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> by auou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching either that there are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies two Chriſts, or that there were two ſome while. But the Catholike Church iudging rightly both of God and of our Sauiour, blaſphemeth neither againſt the myſtery of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
<pb facs="tcp:2237:42"/>
nor againſt the Incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt. For it worſhippeth both one Diuinity in a perfect <hi>Trinity,</hi> and the equality of the Trinity in one and the ſame Maieſty, and acknowledgeth one <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> not two, and that ſame is both <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man.</hi> It beleeueth indeed that there is <hi>one</hi> perſon In him, but <hi>two</hi> ſubſtances: it beleeueth there are two ſubſtances, but one perſon; two ſubſtances, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, the <hi>Word</hi> of God is not changeable, that it ſhould be turned into fleſh: and one perſon, leaſt by profeſſing <hi>two</hi> Sons, it may ſeeme to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip a <hi>Quaternity</hi> (or Foure) &amp; not a <hi>Trinity,</hi> or Three.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:2237:42"/>
               <head>CHAP. 19.</head>
               <p>BVt it is worth our labour to lay open this point with diligence more diſtinctly, and more plainly. In God there is <hi>one</hi> ſubſtance, but <hi>three</hi> perſons. In Chriſt there be <hi>two</hi> ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but <hi>one</hi> perſon. In the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity there is <note n="o" place="margin">Alius &amp; alius, non ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ud &amp; aliud.</note> diſtinction of perſons, but no diuerſity of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. In our Sauiour there is diuerſity of <hi>nature,</hi> but no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of <hi>perſon.</hi> How is there <note place="margin">Queſt.</note> in the Trinity diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but no difference of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? Namely, becauſe there is <note place="margin">Anſ.</note> one <hi>perſon</hi> of the Father, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Sonne, and another of the holy Ghoſt: but yet the <hi>nature</hi> of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the holy Ghoſt, is <hi>not diuers,</hi> but <hi>one</hi> &amp; the <hi>ſame.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2237:43"/>
How is there in our Sauiour <note place="margin">Quest.</note> differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of natures, but not of perſon? Surely becauſe there is one <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of the <hi>Diuinity,</hi> &amp; <note place="margin">Anſ.</note> another of the <hi>Humanity:</hi> but yet the <hi>God-head</hi> and <hi>Manhead</hi> are not <hi>two perſons,</hi> but <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>ſame Chriſt,</hi> one &amp; the ſame Sonne of God, and <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>ſame perſon</hi> of one and the ſame Chriſt, and Sonne of God. As in a man the <hi>Fleſh</hi> is one nature, and the <hi>Soule</hi> another: but the ſoule and the fleſh is <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>ſame</hi> man. In <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; <hi>Paul</hi> the ſoule is one nature, and the fleſh another: but yet the fleſh and ſoule are not two <hi>Peters,</hi> neither is the ſoule one <hi>Paul,</hi> and the fleſh another <hi>Paul;</hi> but one and the ſame <hi>Peter,</hi> and one and the ſame <hi>Paul,</hi> ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of the double and diuers nature of the ſoule and of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2237:43"/>
body. So then in one and the ſame Chriſt there are <hi>two ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances:</hi> but one is <hi>diuine,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is <hi>humane:</hi> one of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God, the other of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Virgin: one coëter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and equall to the Father, the other conſubſtantiall to the Mother: yet <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>ſame Christ,</hi> in both the ſubſtance. There is not therefore one Chriſt God, and another Man: not one vncreated, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther created: not one that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſuffer, and another, that can ſuffer: not one equal to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, another leſſer then the Father, another of the mother: But one and the ſame Chriſt is God and Man: the ſame is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created, and created: the ſame could not bee changed, and could not ſuffer, the ſame was changed, and did ſuffer: the
<pb facs="tcp:2237:44"/>
ſame is equall to the Father, &amp; inferiour: the ſame was begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of the Father <hi>before</hi> time, &amp; the ſame is borne of his Mother <hi>in</hi> time: perfect God, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Man: in God is the ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne <hi>Diuinity,</hi> in Man the whole <hi>Humanity:</hi> I ſay the <hi>whole Humanity,</hi> which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth both the <hi>Soule</hi> and the <hi>Fleſh:</hi> yea true fleſh, our fleſh, and the mothers fleſh: a ſoule alſo indued with vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, furniſhed with iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; reaſon. There is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Chriſt, the <hi>Word,</hi> a <hi>Soule,</hi> and <hi>Fleſh:</hi> but all this is one <hi>Chriſt,</hi> one <hi>Sonne</hi> of God, and one <hi>Sauiour</hi> and Redeemer of vs. And <hi>one,</hi> not by I wot not what corruptible confuſion of the God-head and Man-head, but by a certaine entire and <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular vnity of perſon.</hi> For that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2237:44"/>
coniunction doth not conuert and change the one into the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (which is an errour proper to the <hi>Arrians)</hi> but hath ſo conioyned both the natures in one, that the ſingularity, or vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of one &amp; the ſame perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding alwaies in Chriſt the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of either nature remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth alſo for euer: ſo that verily the body doth neuer at any time begin to be God, nor ceaſe at any time to bee a body: which is alſo made manifeſt by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of an humane caſe. For neither for the preſent onely, but for the future alſo, euery man ſhall conſiſt of body and ſoule: yet neither ſhall the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy euer bee changed into the ſoule, or the ſoule into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: but euery man being to continue euer, the difference of both the ſubſtances ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:2237:45"/>
continue for euer in euery man: euen ſo in Chriſt alſo the property of both the ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces is to bee reteined of them both for euer, but yet the vnity of the perſon being preſerued ſafe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 20.</head>
               <p>BVt whereas wee doe often name this word Perſon, and ſay that God in perſon was made man, wee muſt greatly feare, that we do not ſeeme to ſay this, That God the <hi>word</hi> did onely by the <hi>reſemblance of acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> take vpon him thoſe things, that appertaine to vs, and that hee wrought whatſoeuer belonged to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation of a man, as it were <hi>in ſhew,</hi> and not as a <hi>true Man:</hi> as is wont to be done on the ſtages, where
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2237:45"/>
one man doth ſuddenly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent many perſons, of the which himſelfe is none. For as often as there is made a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of another mans action, the duties and deedes of others are ſo done, as that yet theſe men, that act them, are not the very ſame men, whom they do act, or counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit. For, that we may for illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration ſake vſe the enſamples of things ſecular, and which are vſed of the <hi>Manichees,</hi> whenas a Tragicall Player doth counterfeit a Prieſt, or a King, hee is neither a Prieſt, nor a King: for the action ceaſing, thoſe things alſo ceaſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which that perſon had repreſented.</p>
               <p>But from vs farre bee this curſed &amp; wicked mockery. Let this madneſſe be the <hi>Manichees,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2237:46"/>
who being phantaſticall Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, affirme that the Sonne of God, who is God, was not a man truely and ſubſtancially, but that hee reſembled man by a certaine imaginary act and conuerſation. But the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke faith doth ſo ſay that the <hi>Word</hi> of God was made Man, that hee tooke vpon him our nature and properties, <hi>not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully,</hi> and in ſhew, but <hi>truly,</hi> and liuely: and that he did not reſemble thoſe things, which belong to the nature of man, as not his owne, but that hee did ſuſtaine them rather, as being <hi>his owne:</hi> and that hee was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together alſo the <hi>very thing,</hi> which hee did <hi>reſemble.</hi> Euen as we our ſelues alſo in that we ſpeake, vnderſtand, liue, and ſubſiſt, wee doe not repreſent men, but wee are men. For
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2237:46"/>
neither <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> (that we may eſpecially ſpeake of them) were men by imitating, but by ſubſiſting. In like maner <hi>Paul</hi> did not counterfeit an Apoſtle, or reſemble <hi>Paul:</hi> but hee was an Apoſtle, and <hi>Paul</hi> indeede: Euen ſo alſo God the <hi>Word</hi> by aſſuming and hauing the fleſh, and by ſpeaking, doing, and ſuffering by the fleſh, yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any corruption of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, vouchſafed verily to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme this, that hee might not reſemble or counterfeit a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect man, but exhibite, that hee might not ſeeme, or be thought to bee a true man, but that hee might ſubſiſt, and bee one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede. Therefore as the ſoule vnited to the fleſh, but yet not turned into fleſh, doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble a man, but is a man, &amp; is a man not in ſhew, but in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance:
<pb facs="tcp:2237:47"/>
ſo alſo the <hi>Word</hi> God by vniting himſelfe vnto man without any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſion of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was made man not by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, not by imitation, but by ſubſiſting. Let vs therefore vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly reiect all conceipt of that perſon, which is vſurped by counterfeiting, &amp; reſembling: where alwaies one thing <hi>is,</hi> and another thing is <hi>counterfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted:</hi> where hee that doth act or repreſent, is neuer he whom he doth act. For farre bee it from vs to thinke, that God the <hi>Word</hi> hath taken vpon him the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of man in this deceiptfull manner: but rather ſo, as that his ſubſtance continuing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable, and by taking vpon him the nature of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect man, he might himſelfe be fleſh, a man, the perſon of a man: not counterfeit, but true:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2237:47"/>
not by reſemblance, but in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. To conclude, not ſuch a one as ceaſeth with the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or repreſentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but which alway abideth in the ſubſtance. This vnity therefore of perſon in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> was not made and perfected <hi>after</hi> the Virgin had brought him forth, but <hi>in the very wombe of the Uirgin.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 21.</head>
               <p>FOr we muſt be very wary that we doe confeſſe, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> not onely is one: but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that he <hi>was</hi> alwayes <hi>one:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is intolerable blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, though thou ſhouldeſt grant him to be one (perſon) now, yet to auouch that he was ſometime not one, but two; to wit, one after the time of his <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> but two at the
<pb facs="tcp:2237:48"/>
time of his <hi>Birth.</hi> Which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great ſacriledge ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we ſhall not be able other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to auoid, but by confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that man was vnited to God in the vnity of perſon, not at his aſcenſion, or reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Baptiſme: but euen now in his mother, euen in the wombe, yea, euen in the very conception of the <hi>Virgin:</hi> by reaſon of which vnity of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thoſe things, that are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per vnto God, are indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and in common giuen to him being man, and thoſe things, that are proper to the fleſh, are aſcribed vnto God. For thence it is that the holy Scriptures ſay, both that the Sonne of Man came downe from heauen, and that the Lord of glory was crucified vpon earth. Thence alſo it is that,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2237:48"/>
becauſe the fleſh of the Lord was made, becauſe the fleſh of the Lord was created, the very <hi>word</hi> of God is ſaid to be made, the <hi>wiſedome</hi> of God is ſayd to be filled, the <note n="o" place="margin">Or thus, &amp; is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to knowledge ſayd to be created: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as in, &amp;c</note> 
                  <hi>Science</hi> or knowledge of God is ſayd to be created: euen as in reſpect of fore-knowledge his <hi>hands</hi> &amp; his <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>feet</hi> are ſayd to be <hi>peir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</hi> In regard, I ſay, of this v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of perſon that alſo hath by reaſon of the like myſterie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, that becauſe the <hi>Fleſh</hi> of the <hi>word</hi> was borne of his <hi>Uirgin-mother,</hi> that therefore God the <hi>word</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſhould be moſt catholick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeued to be borne of the Virgin, and moſt wickedly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied. Which things ſeeing they thus are, God forbid that any man ſhould go about to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue holy <hi>Mary</hi> of the priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges
<pb facs="tcp:2237:49"/>
of diuine fauour, as a ſpeciall glory. For ſhe is through a certaine ſingular be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of our Lord and God, and her owne Sonne, to be moſt truly and moſt happily confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dei non Deitatis:</hi> of God, not of the God head: for ſo hee had no mother.</note> 
                  <hi>Mother of God.</hi> But ſhe is not ſo the mother of God, as a certaine wicked he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie ſurmiſeth, which affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that ſhe is to be ſayd to be the mother of God in name onely, as who forſooth did bring forth that man, which was afterwards made God; as we call one the mother of a Prieſt, or the mother of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, not becauſe ſhe did bring forth one, that was at his very birth a Prieſt or Biſhop, but for that ſhe brought one forth, that was afterwards made a Prieſt or Biſhop. <note n="e" place="margin">She was holy not by generation, but by rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: her Sonne, that tooke fleſh of her, gaue grace to her.</note> Holy <hi>Mary</hi> is not, I ſay, ſo to be called the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2237:49"/>
mother of God: but therefore rather, becauſe, as hath beene ſayd before, that holy myſtery was accompliſhed euen in her ſacred wombe, ſince by reaſon of a certaine ſingular and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiduall vnitie of perſon, as the <hi>Word</hi> in the fleſh is fleſh, ſo man in God is God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 22.</head>
               <p>BVt now according to thoſe things, which haue beene briefly ſayd before concerning the foreſayd hereſies, and the Catholicke faith; let vs for the refreſhing of memory make a briefer and ſhorter rehearſall: to the end verily, both that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing repeated they might be better vnderſtood, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſſed they might more ſurely be remembred. Accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:2237:50"/>
therefore be <hi>Photinus</hi> for not acknowledging three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct perſons, &amp; for affirming Chriſt to bee no more then a bare man. Accurſed be <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linaris,</hi> that affirmeth the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of the Diuinitie chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in Chriſt, and denieth the property of a perfect man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head. Accurſed be <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> which denieth that God was borne of the Virgin, and affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth there are two Chriſts, &amp; reiecting the faith of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, bringeth in amongſt vs a <hi>quaternity.</hi> But bleſſed be the <hi>Catholicke Church,</hi> which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippeth one God in a perfect Trinity, and the equality alſo of the Trinity in one Diuinitie: ſo as that neither the ſingulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the ſubſtance confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the propertie of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons nor the diſtinction of the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2237:50"/>
Trinitie ſeparate the vnitie of the Deity. Bleſſed, I ſay, be the Church, which beleeueth that there are two true and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſubſtances in Chriſt, but yet one perſon of Chriſt: ſo that neither the diſtinction of the natures diuideth the vnitie of the perſon, nor the vnitie of the perſon confounds the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the ſubſtances. Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, I ſay, be the Church, which that it might acknowledge that Chriſt both <hi>is</hi> &amp; <hi>was</hi> euer one, confeſſeth that man was vnited to God, not after his birth, but now euen <hi>in the mothers wombe.</hi> Bleſſed, I ſay, be the Church, which vnderſtandeth that God was made man, not by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of nature, but in regard of perſon; perſon, I ſay, not counterfeit and tranſient, but ſubſtantiall and permanent. I
<pb facs="tcp:2237:51"/>
ſay, bleſſed bee the Church, which affirmeth that this vnity of perſon is ſo effectuall, as that by reaſon thereof the things of God are by a wonderfull and vnſpeakable myſterie aſcribed vnto man, and the things of man aſcribed vnto God. For, becauſe of that vnitie it doth not deny that <hi>man</hi> deſcended from heauen in reſpect of the <hi>God-head,</hi> and hath belieued, that <hi>God</hi> was <hi>made</hi> vpon earth, that he ſuffered, and was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified in regard of the <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head.</hi> To conclude, by reaſon of that vnity ſhe doth acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Man to be the Sonne of God, and God to be the Sonne of the Virgin. Holy therefore and venerable, bleſſed and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiolable, and to that celeſtiall praiſing, performed of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, altogether comparable
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2237:51"/>
be this confeſſion, which glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifies God with a threefold ſanctification. For therefore it doth eſpecially <note n="*" place="margin">Or preach.</note> tel and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the vnitie of Chriſt, leaſt the myſterie of the Trinity ſhould exceed. Be theſe things ſpoken by way of digreſſing, elſe where (if God ſhall pleaſe) they are more largely to be treated of, and vnfolded. Let vs now returne vnto our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 23.</head>
               <p>VVE ſayd therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that in the Church of God the <hi>Teachers error was the peoples temptation:</hi> and that the tentation was ſo much the greater, by how the the learneder he was, that did erre. Which we taught firſt by the authority of Scripture, and
<pb facs="tcp:2237:52"/>
then by Eccleſiaſticall exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; to wit, by reckoning vp them, that though they were for a time accounted ſound in the faith, yet at the laſt did ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fall into the ſect of ſome other, or elſe deuiſed an hereſie of their owne. A matter doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of great moment, &amp; both commodious to learne, and neceſſary to be thought of and remembred, the which wee ought diligently to illuſtrate and inculcate with the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of enſamples: that all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes for the moſt part may know, That they ought with the Church to receiue teachers, and not that they ſhould with teachers forſake the faith, that the Church embraceth.</p>
               <p>But in my conceit, though we might recken vp a number in this kind of tempting, yet
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2237:52"/>
was there almoſt none, that was ſo great a temptation, as was <hi>Origen:</hi> in whome there were many things ſo excellent, ſo ſingular, and ſo admirable, that any man might eaſily iudge <note n="*" place="margin">At the firſt ſight, before matters were ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> at firſt that all his aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were to be belieued. For if the life doth win authority, his induſtry, his chaſtity, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ſufferance was not ſmall: if either kindred or lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Who more noble then he, who at the firſt was borne in that <note n="a" place="margin">He was the ſonne of <hi>Leonides,</hi> who dyed a Martyr vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Seuerus.</hi>
                  </note> family, which was made illuſtrious by Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? And afterwards hauing for Chriſt loſt not his father onely, but all his ſubſtance al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, he did profit ſo much with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſtraites of <hi>holy pouerty,</hi> he did often, as they ſay, ſuſteine afflictions for confeſſing the <note n="e" place="margin">For his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers goods were conſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerus.</hi> He cals his pouerty Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: becauſe it befel him by tyranny for religion ſake.</note> Lord. Neither indeed were
<pb facs="tcp:2237:53"/>
theſe things onely in him, all which might afterwards proue a tentation: but hee had alſo ſuch a notable wit, ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found, ſo acute, and ſo fine, that he did much and farre ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe almoſt all: and ſo great was the skill of this notable man in all knowledge and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as that there were but few things in diuine philoſophy, &amp; of humane it may be almoſt none, which hee did not tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly vnderſtand. Who when he had atteined to the learning <note place="margin">Cuius ſcientiae um Graeel encederent.</note> of the Greekes, he gaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, alſo to the ſtudy of the Hebrew.</p>
               <p>But why ſhould I ſpeake of eloquence? whoſe ſpeech was ſo pleaſant, ſo delectable, and ſo ſweete, that not words me thinkes ſo much, as hony ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to flow out of his mouth.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2237:53"/>
What incredible things did he bolt out and cleer by the force of diſputation? What things ſeeming hard to be done, did not he make that they ſhould ſeeme moſt eaſie? But he woue <note place="margin">Obiect.</note> his aſſertions, it may be, onely with the knots of arguments. Yea doubtleſſe there was neuer <note place="margin">Sol.</note> any Teacher, which vſed more examples or proofes of <hi>holy writ.</hi> But he wrote, I beleeue, <note place="margin">Obiect.</note> but little. No man writ more: <note place="margin">Sol.</note> that I thinke all his works can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not onely not be read ouer, but indeede not ſo much as found. And who alſo, that he might not want any helpe to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, was furniſhed with ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of age. But perhaps he <note place="margin">Obiect.</note> was not very happy in Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. Who euer more happy? For out of his boſome ſprang innumerable Teachers, an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb facs="tcp:2237:54"/>
of Prieſts, Confeſſors and Martyers. And now what man is able to conceiue in what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, in what renowne and grace he was in with all men? What man a little more deuout then ordinary did not with ſpeed reſort vnto him from the fartheſt quarters of the world? What Chriſtian did not reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence him almoſt as a <hi>Prophet,</hi> what Philoſopher honor'd him not as a <hi>Maiſter?</hi> And how re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend he was accounted, not onely among priuate men, but euen of the chiefeſt in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, the Stories doe declare, which ſay that he was ſent for by the <note n="n" place="margin">Mammaa.</note> mother of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Emperour, intruth becauſe of heauenly wiſedome, which alſo he did much affect &amp; loue. But the epiſtles alſo of the ſame ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beare witnes, which he wrot
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2237:54"/>
by the authority of Chriſtian Teacher to Emperour <hi>Philip,</hi> who was the firſt Chriſtian of all the <hi>Romane</hi> Princes. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning whoſe incredible knowledge, if any man beleeue not a Chriſtian teſtimony, we being the relators, let him at the leſt receiue a <hi>Pagan</hi> confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the Philoſophers being the witneſſes. For that wicked <hi>Porphicie</hi> ſaith that being mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with his fame, he went, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a manner but a boy, to <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and that he ſawe him there being now an olde man: but indeede ſo notably qualified, as one that had attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the height of all lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. The day would ſooner faile me, then I ſhall be able to touch euen the ſmalleſt part of thoſe excellent things, which were in that man: which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:2237:55"/>
did not only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine to the glory of religion, but alſo to the greatneſſe of <hi>temptation.</hi> For what man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong a thouſand would eaſily caſt off from him a man of ſuch an excellent wit, ſo great a ſcholler, and of ſo great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and not rather vſe that ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, <note n="o" place="margin">So <hi>Cicero</hi> of <hi>Plato</hi> l. 1. Tuſc. quaeſt.</note> 
                  <hi>That he had rather erre with Origen, then iudge truly with other men?</hi> But what ſhould I make many words? It ſo fell out, that not ſome humane, but (as the euent declared) a too dangerous temptation made by ſo great a perſon, ſo great a <hi>Teacher,</hi> ſo great a <hi>Prophet,</hi> did draw very many fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the <hi>Faith.</hi> Wherefore this <hi>Origen</hi> ſo great and ſo well qualified, whiles he doth inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently abuſe the grace of God, whiles he makes too much of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2237:55"/>
his own wit, and thinks ſo well of himſelf, whiles he conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth the ancient ſimplicity of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> religion, whiles he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes he is wiſer then all men, and whiles that contemning the traditions of the Church, and the <note n="u" place="margin">He mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth their authority.</note> maiſterſhips of the <hi>Elders</hi> he doth after a new man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner expound certaine places of the Scriptures, he hath deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that it ſhould be ſayd vnto the Church of God concerning him alſo; <hi>If there ariſe among you a Prophet.</hi> And a little after, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not,</hi> quoth he, <hi>listen to the words of that Prophet.</hi> And againe, <hi>Becauſe the Lord your God,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>tryeth you, whether ye will loue him, or no.</hi> It was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed not onely a temptation, but euen a great temptation to remoue the Church, being <note n="*" place="margin">Or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted, bent.</note> giuen vnto him, and depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:2237:56"/>
vpon him, and through wondring at his wit, learning, eloquence, conuerſation and reputation ſuſpecting him not, nor fearing him (to remoue the Church, I ſay) all vpon the ſudden by little and little from the ancient Religion to nouell profaneneſſe.</p>
               <p>But ſome man will ſay that the bookes of <hi>Origen</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">S. <hi>Ierome</hi> thinkes not ſo: <hi>vide Epiſ. ad Panima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chium, et Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum.</hi>
                  </note> are cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted. I gain ſay it not, but had rather too it were ſo. For that is both deliuered and written of ſome, not onely Catholikes, but alſo Heretiques. But that is it, which now we are to marke, that although he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe bee not, yet the bookes, which are publiked vnder his name, are a great temptation, which being peſtered with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wounds of blaſphemies are both read &amp; embraced, not as
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2237:56"/>
other mens, but as his owne: ſo that although <hi>Origen</hi> did not conceiue the error, yet <hi>Origens</hi> authority may ſeeme power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to perſwade the error.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 24.</head>
               <p>BVt <hi>Tertullians</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition alſo is euen the ſame. For as he among the <hi>Greekes,</hi> ſo this man among the <hi>Latines</hi> is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt to bee reputed the chiefeſt of all our men. For who more learned then this man? who more exerciſed in diuinity, and in humanity? For verily he did with a certaine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable capacity of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, vnderſtand &amp; compaſſe al <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> and all the ſects of the <hi>Phyloſophers,</hi> the authors &amp; abettours of the ſects, and all their doctrines, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſtories and ſtudies. And did hee not excell for a wit ſo
<pb facs="tcp:2237:57"/>
graue and vehement, as that he propounded almoſt nothing to himſelfe to vanquiſh, which he did not either breake into with acuteneſſe, or ſtrike out with weightineſſe.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, who can expreſſe the praiſes of his ſpeech? which was repleniſhed with ſuch, I wot not what, vrgent argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as that whom he could not perſwade, he forced to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto him: whoſe ſentences were almoſt as many as words: and as many victories as <note n="*" place="margin">Or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts and opinions. <hi>ſenſus.</hi>
                  </note> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. This knew the <hi>Martio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, Apelles,</hi> the <hi>Praxeans, Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogenes,</hi> the <hi>Iewes, Gentiles, Gnoſtickes,</hi> and the reſt, whoſe blaſphemies he ouerthrew with his manifold &amp; great volumes, as with certaine <hi>lightenings.</hi> And yet this man alſo, I ſay, this <hi>Tertullian</hi> being vnmind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2237:57"/>
of the <hi>Catholicke doctrine,</hi> that is, the vniuerſall and anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent faith, and much more elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> happy, changing his iudgment afterwards wrought that at laſt, which the bleſſed Confeſſour <hi>Hilarie</hi> writeth of him in a certaine place; <hi>By the error</hi> (quoth he) <hi>which he fell af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards into, he made the workes, which he wrote well, to looſe their reputation. And hee himſelfe was alſo a great temptation in the Church.</hi> But of him I will ſay no more. This thing I will onely mention, that, becauſe hee did againſt the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Moſes</hi> affirme that the new braine-ſicke doctrines of <hi>Montanus</hi> ariſing in the Church, and that thoſe madde conceits of <note n="a" place="margin">He mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <hi>Priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilla,</hi> and <hi>Maximil a,</hi> two Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts.</note> mad <hi>women,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the dreames of an vpſtart doctrine, were true prophecies,
<pb facs="tcp:2237:58"/>
he did deſerue that it ſhould be ſaid of him alſo and of his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings; <hi>If a Prophet ſhall ariſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you.</hi> And againe. <hi>Thou ſhalt not heare the words of that Prophet.</hi> Why ſo? <hi>Becauſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Lord your God tryeth you,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>whether you will loue him, or not.</hi> By theſe therfore ſo many, and ſo great examples in the Church, and by the reſt of that nature, we ought euidently to marke, and to know more clearely then the light, that if euer any teacher in the <hi>Church</hi> ſhall wander from the faith, the prouidence of God doth <note n="e" place="margin">Not cauſe, but ſuffer.</note> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it to be done for our tryall to proue, whether we loue the Lord our God with <hi>all</hi> our heart, and with <hi>all</hi> our ſoule, or no.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:2237:58"/>
               <head>CHAP. 25.</head>
               <p>VVHich things, ſeeing they ſo ſtand, he is a true and right Catholicke, who loueth the truth of God, the Church, the body of Chriſt, and who preferres nothing to <hi>Gods</hi> Religion, nothing to the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke</hi> faith, not the authority, not the loue, not the wit, not the eloquence, nor the philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy of any man: but contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all theſe things, and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding firme and ſtedfaſt in the faith, doth iudge that, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he ſhall vnderſtand to bee vniuerſally held of old of the <hi>Catholicke Church,</hi> himſelfe ſhould hold and beleeue alone: but whatſoeuer <hi>nouell</hi> and <hi>ſtrange</hi> doctrine hee ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue to bee priuily brought in
<pb facs="tcp:2237:59"/>
after by any one beſides, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the iudgement of all the Saints, hee knowes that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs not to religion, but rather to tentation. And is alſo eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by the ſpeeches of the bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> inſtructed: for this is that, which hee wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in his firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthes: There muſt bee,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>hereſies euen among you, that they, which are approued among you, might be knowen.</hi> As if hee ſhould ſay; for this cauſe the Authors of hereſies are not preſently rooted out by God, that they, which are approued, might be ſeene: that is, that it might appeare, how ſure, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and conſtant a louer of the <hi>Catholick faith</hi> euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is. And in truth, when euery <hi>nouelty</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vp, the weightineſſe of the <hi>Corne,</hi> and the lightneſſe of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2237:59"/>
the <hi>Chaffe</hi> is preſently percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: at which time that is eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhaken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Floore,</hi> which was held with no weight with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Floore.</hi> For ſome doe forthwith flye quite away, but others being onely driuen out, doe both feare to periſh, and bluſh to returne, being woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, halfe dead, and halfe aliue: as haiung drunke ſuch a quantity of poyſon, as neither kild them, nor was digeſted, as would neither make them dye, nor ſuffer them to liue. Oh mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable condition, with what waues of care, with what whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winds are they toſſed! For ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, which way the wind ſhal driue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they are carried with a violent error: ſometimes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to themſelues, they are beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> back like co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary waues: ſomtimes by raſh preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they
<pb facs="tcp:2237:60"/>
allow of thoſe things, which ſeeme vncertaine: ſometimes alſo through a reaſonleſſe feare they are afraid of thoſe things, that are certaine: being vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine which way to go, which way to returne: what to follow, what to fly, what to hold, what to let go. Which afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> verily of a doubting &amp; wauering hart is the medicine of Gods mercy towards them, if they would be wiſe. For therefore are they toſſed, beaten, and almoſt kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with ſundry tempeſts of thoughts, out of the moſt <note n="i" place="margin">A quie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hauen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: for out of this har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour men are either toſſed vpon the waues of errour, or ſwallowed vp.</note> 
                  <hi>quiet hauen</hi> of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like faith, that they might let downe the ſailes of a proud ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſpread out on high, which they did wickedly ſpread open to the winds of nouelties, and that they might retire and keep themſelues within the moſt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2237:60"/>
faithfull ſtation of their gentle and good mother, and firſt vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit vp thoſe bitter and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled waters of errours, that they might bee able <note n="o" place="margin">For a veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell is not capable of wine, till the water or dregs, that filled be emptied out.</note> 
                  <hi>after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> to drinke of the ſtreames of liuing and ſpringing water. Let them vnlearne that well, which they did not well to learne: and let them receiue by the vniuerſall doctrine of the Church, what may bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood: and what may not, let them beleeue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 26.</head>
               <p>WHich things ſeeing that they are thus, reuoluing and recounting the ſame things oftentimes, I cannot ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wonder that the madneſſe of ſome men, that the vngodlines of their blinded vnderſtanding,
<pb facs="tcp:2237:61"/>
and laſtly, that their luſt of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring is ſo great, that they are not contented with the rule of beleeuing, which of old was once deliuered and receiued, but that they do dayly hunt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter change of nouelties, &amp; euer delight to put ſome new matter to religion, to change &amp; take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: as though it were not an heauenly doctrine, which ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth to haue beene once reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, but an earthly inſtitution, which could not otherwiſe bee perfited, but by continuall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, or rather reprehenſion: albeit the <hi>Oracles</hi> of God cry out; <hi>Thou ſhalt not remoue the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 22. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>ancient bounds, which thy Fathers haue ſet:</hi> And, <hi>Thou ſhalt not iudge aboue,</hi> or more then <hi>the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccles.</hi> 8. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Iudge:</hi> And againe, <hi>Hee that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ecc.</hi> 10. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>breaketh the hedge, a Serpent ſhall bite him:</hi> And that of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2237:61"/>
wherewith all the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked nouelties of all hereſies are often cut in peeces, as with a certaine ſpirituall ſword, and are alwaies to be diſmembred; <hi>O</hi> 
                  <note n="u" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 20. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Timotheus, keepe that which is committed to thee, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid profane</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Cainopho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias, ſiue Cene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonias.</note> 
                  <hi>nouelties of words, or vaine bablings, and oppoſitions of knowledge falſely ſo called: which while ſome profeſſed, they haue erred about the Faith.</hi> And for all this are there ſome found of ſuch a marble fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, ſo impudent without all ſhame, and of ſuch an ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant like obſtinacy, as which would not yeeld to ſuch hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly ſpeeches of ſo great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce? which would not faint vnder ſuch heauy weights? which would not be broken in peeces with ſuch mighty ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers? finally, which would not
<pb facs="tcp:2237:62"/>
be bruiſed with ſo great light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings? <hi>Auoid,</hi> quoth he, <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane nouelties of words.</hi> He did ſay <hi>Antiquities,</hi> hee ſaid not <hi>old:</hi> Yea hee doth plainely ſhew, what ſhould follow on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, For if <hi>Nouelty</hi> muſt bee auoided, then <hi>Antiquity</hi> is to be maintained. And if <hi>Nouelty</hi> be <hi>profane,</hi> then <hi>Antiquity</hi> is <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred.</hi> And <hi>oppoſitions,</hi> quoth he, <hi>of knowledge ſalſly ſo named.</hi> A falſe name indeed is vſed among the doctrines of heretiques, that ignorance might bee coloured with the name of knowledge, and myſtineſſe with the name of cleereneſſe, and darkneſſe with the name of light. <hi>Which,</hi> quoth hee, <hi>while ſome profeſſed, they haue erred concerning the faith.</hi> What was that, which whiles they did profeſſe, they fell away, but a new, I wot not
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2237:62"/>
what, and vnknowne doctrine? For you might heare ſome of them ſay: Come, O yee fooliſh and wretched men, who are commonly called Catholicks, and learne the true faith, which none, but we, doth vnderſtand, which many by-paſt ages hath ben concealed, but was of late reuealed &amp; diſcloſed: but learne ye by <hi>stealth,</hi> and <hi>ſecretly,</hi> for it ſhall delight you. And in like manner, when ye haue learned it, teach it cloſly, leaſt the world doe heare it, leaſt the Church take knowledge of it. For it is granted but to a few to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the ſecret of ſo great a myſtery. Are not theſe the words of that <hi>Harlot,</hi> which in the <hi>Prouerbs</hi> of <hi>Salomon</hi> calleth them that paſſe by the way, which goe right on their way? <hi>Who ſo is,</hi> quoth ſhee, <hi>the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſt <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pron.</hi> 9. 15. 16.</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2237:63"/>
among you, let him turne into me. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that, are voyd of ſenſe, ſhe exhorteth, ſaying: do yee glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touch hidden bread, and drinke ye ſweete water</hi> 
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Furtim.</note> 
                  <hi>by ſtealth.</hi> And what followes? <hi>But hee knowes not,</hi> quoth he, <hi>how that</hi> 
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Terrigenae.</note> 
                  <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings do periſh at her houſe.</hi> And who are thoſe earthly men? Let the Apoſtle declare, euen they, ſaith he, <hi>which haue</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red about the faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 27.</head>
               <p>BVt it is worth the labour diligently to entreate of all that place of the Apoſtle. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>O Timotheus,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>keepe that, which is committed to thee, auoiding profane nouelties of words. O:</hi> this exclamation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokens, both foreknowledge, and charity alſo: for hee did
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2237:63"/>
                  <hi>Foreſee</hi> the errours, that were to be, for the which he was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>Grieued</hi> aforehand. Who is <hi>Timotheus</hi> now at this day? but either the Vniuerſall Church, or ſpecially the whole compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Prieſts or Biſhops, who ſhould either haue themſelues, or inſtill and teach vnto others the whole knowledge of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine worſhip. But what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth this, <hi>keepe that,</hi> which is committed to thee? Keepe it, ſaith he, for feare of Theeues, for feare of enemies: leaſt, whiles men do ſleepe, they ſhould ſow their darnall vpon that good ſeede of wheate, which the Sonne of man had ſowne in his Field. <hi>Keep,</hi> quoth he, <hi>that which is committed to thee.</hi> What is that, which was <hi>Committed?</hi> That is to ſay, that wherewithall thou art put in
<pb facs="tcp:2237:64"/>
truſt, not that which thou haſt deuiſed; that, which thou haſt receiued, not that, which thou haſt inuented: a matter not of wit, but of doctrine: not of priuate vſurpation, but of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique tradition: a thing, that was brought vnto thee, and not which commeth from thee: as in which thou muſt not bee an <hi>Author,</hi> but a <hi>Keeper:</hi> not an <hi>Ordainer,</hi> but a <hi>Follower:</hi> not a <hi>leader,</hi> but one that is <hi>led.</hi> Keep, ſaith he, that which is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: keepe the Talent of the Catholicke Faith, inuiolated &amp; vncorrupted. That which is committed to thy truſt, let it remaine in thy poſſeſſion, let it be deliuered of thee. Thou haſt receiued Gold, repay Gold: I will not that thou ſhouldeſt bring mee one thing for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: I would not that inſtead
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2237:64"/>
of gold thou ſhouldeſt either impudently put lead, or deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully braſſe: I reſpect not the colour of the gold, but the nature ſurely. <hi>O Timotheus,</hi> O Prieſt, O Treatiſer, O Teacher, if the gift of God ſhall make thee fit, be thou for wit, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, and doctrine a <hi>Bezaleel</hi> of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 36. 1.</note> the ſpirituall Temple, in graue the precious gemmes of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine doctrine, fit them faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, adorne them diſcretly, adde luſtre, fauour and comlineſſe. Let that bee through thine expoſition vnderſtood more cleerely, which was before be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued more obſcurely. Let the poſterity reioyce that that was vnderſtood by the meanes of thee, which antiquity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did reuerence being not vnderſtood: the ſame things which thou haſt learn'd, do thou
<pb facs="tcp:2237:65"/>
teach ſo, that, although thou ſpeakeſt <note n="*" place="margin">Or after a new faſhion: <hi>Noue, non noua.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>newly,</hi> yet not <hi>new things.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 28.</head>
               <p>BVt it may be ſome ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaies: what? ſhall there then bee <note place="margin">Quest.</note> no progreſſe made of religion in the Church of Chriſt? Let there bee made verily, and as <note place="margin">Anſ.</note> much as may be. For who is he, that is ſo ſpitefull to men, and ſo hatefull to God, as that goes about to prohibite that? But yet let it be ſo, that it may be indeed a proceeding, &amp; not a <hi>changing,</hi> of the <hi>Faith.</hi> For that is to <note n="o" place="margin">To pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed or make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe.</note> 
                  <hi>profite,</hi> that euery thing bee increaſed in it ſelfe: but that is <hi>changing,</hi> when a thing is altered from one thing to another. It behoueth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that the vnderſtanding,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2237:65"/>
knowledge, and wiſedome, as well of each as of all, as well of one man as of the whole Church ſhould by the degrees of ages and times increaſe, and profite much and greatly: but yet in their owne kind one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: to wit, in the ſame doctrine, in the ſame ſenſe, and in the ſame iudgement.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 29.</head>
               <p>LEt the religion of ſoules reſemble the ſtate and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of bodies, which although in the proceſſe of yeares they declare and finiſh their propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and degrees, yet do they continue ſtill the <hi>ſame,</hi> which they were at firſt. There is much difference betwixt the flower of <hi>Child-hood,</hi> and the ripeneſſe of <hi>Old-age:</hi> but yet
<pb facs="tcp:2237:66"/>
the very ſelf-ſame men become old, which had bene yong: that albeit the very ſtate and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of one and the ſame man bee altered, yet is he neuertheleſſe one and the ſame nature, one and the <hi>ſelfe-ſame</hi> perſon. The members of ſucking children are ſmall, but of young men great: yet are they the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſelfe-ſame. As many as are the ioynts of little ones, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are there of men: and if thoſe be any which come forth in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per yeares, they be now alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy planted in the nature of the ſeede: ſo that no new thing comes out in old men after, which did not now before lye within them hid in their child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.</p>
               <p>Whence it is manifeſt, that this is the lawful and <hi>right Rule</hi> of profiting, that this is the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:2237:66"/>
and moſt excellent order of increaſing: if ſo be that the number and degrees of age do alway diſcouer thoſe parts and formes, when wee are greater, or elder, which the wiſedome of our Creator did forme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when wee were little. If that the ſhape of man ſhould afterwards be changed into the ſhape of another kinde, or if at the leaſt wiſe the number of the members ſhould be increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or decreaſed, the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy muſt of neceſſity either pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, or become monſtrous, or at the leaſt be weakened. So al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it is fitting that the doctrine of Chriſtian religion ſhould follow theſe rules or faſhions of increaſing: namely, that it ſhould bee ſtrengthened by yeares, inlarged by time, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolled with age: but yet remain
<pb facs="tcp:2237:67"/>
incorrupted and pure, and bee compleat and perfect in all the meaſures of her parts, and in al her owne members, as it were, and ſenſes: as which more ouer admitteth no change, no loſſe of property, nor indureth any variety of definition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 30.</head>
               <p>FOr examhle ſake: our <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> ſowed of old the <hi>Whea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſeedes</hi> of the faith in this <hi>Corne field</hi> of the <hi>Church:</hi> it is vniuſt, and vnbeſeeming, that wee their <hi>Poſterity</hi> inſtead of the naturall and true <hi>Wheate,</hi> ſhould make choice of the <hi>Cockle</hi> of errour put into the roome thereof. But this rather is right and agreeable, that the beginnings and the endings being correſpondent to each
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:2237:67"/>
other, we ſhould reape and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy of the increaſings of a wheaten inſtitution the fruit or graine alſo of wheaten do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: that whenas ſomthing out of thoſe beginnings of the ſeeds is by proceſſe of time ſhot vp, it may now both <note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Laetetur,</hi> be manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: for <hi>lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamen</hi> is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure, which being layd on the ground, doth make it flouriſh. <hi>Pallad. lib.</hi> 1. vſeth this word: <hi>In lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandis, inquit arboribus crs tes facicmus.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>flouriſh,</hi> and be trimmed vp by husbanding: yet ſo as that nothing of the property of the ſprout bee changed: though forme, ſhape, and diſtinction bee added, that yet the nature of euery kinde abide the ſame. For God forbid, that thoſe <hi>roſy</hi> plants of Catholicke iudgment ſhould bee turned into <hi>Thiſtles</hi> &amp; <hi>Thornes.</hi> Farre be it, I ſay, that in this ſpirituall Paradiſe <hi>Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell</hi> and <hi>Woolfe-bane</hi> ſhould all vpon the ſudden come from the ſets and ſhootes of <hi>Cynna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> and <hi>Balme.</hi> Whatſoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:2237:68"/>
therefore is faithfully ſowen of the Fathers in the Church, which is Gods <note n="u" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 9.</note> Husbandry, it behooueth that by the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of the children the very ſame ſhould be husbanded and lookt vnto: it is fitting that the very ſame ſhould flouriſh and ripen, that the ſame ſhould grow, &amp; come to perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For it is lawfull that thoſe ancient doctrines of heauenly Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, ſhould in proceſſe of time bee exactly handled, trimmed, and poliſhed but it is vnlawful that they ſhould be changed, it is vnlawfull to mangle and to maime them. They may lawfully receiue cleareneſſe, light, and diſtinction: but it is needfull that they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine fulneſſe, ſoundneſſe, and property.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:2237:68"/>
               <head>CHAP. 31.</head>
               <p>FOr if this licentiouſneſſe of wicked deceit be once per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, I tremble to vtter what great danger may enſue of roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out, and aboliſhing of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. For when any part of the Catholicke doctrine ſhall be reiected, others alſo, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers after them, one after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, will now as it were by cuſtome and lawe be reiected and done away. Moreouer al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, when the parts are each of them ſeuerely reiected, what will follow at the laſt, but that the whole ſhould in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner be refuſed? Yea, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, if <hi>nouelties</hi> ſhall begin to be mingled with <hi>antient</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, and <hi>forreine</hi> with <hi>dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall,</hi> and <hi>profane</hi> with <hi>ſacred,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2237:69"/>
it cannot be but that this faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will ſpread it ſelfe ouer all, that nothing in the Church wil hereafter bee left vntouched, nothing ſound, nothing vncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted: but that the <note n="a" place="margin">An errour ſtifly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined is a filthy har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot.</note> Stewes of wicked and filthy errours ſhould afterwards be there, where there was aforetime the Sanctuary of the chaſt and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled truth. But let godly deuotion driue this wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe from mens minds, and let this rather bee the fury of the wicked.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 32.</head>
               <p>BVt the Church of Chriſt, being a diligent and wary Keeper of the Doctrines, that are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to her, doth alter nothing in them at any time,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2237:69"/>
diminiſheth nothing, addeth nothing: ſhee cuts not off things, that are neceſſary, ſhe ads not things ſuperfluous, ſhe looſeth not her owne, ſhe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurps not ſtrangers: but this one thing ſhe ſtudies with all diligence, namely, that by handling the antient doctrines faithfully and diſcreetly, ſhe might perfit and poliſh thoſe, if any, that haue bene ſhaped and begun of old: and if any be already perfectly declared and made manifeſt, that ſhe might confirme &amp; ſtrengthen them: and that, if any be now confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and defined, ſhe might conſerue and keepe them. To conclude, what elſe did ſhe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer labour by the Decrees of Councels, then that the ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame thing, which was <note n="*" place="margin">Or barely.</note> ſimp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeued afore, might more
<pb facs="tcp:2237:70"/>
carefully bee beleeued after? that the very ſame thing, which was more ſlackly preached be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, might be more diligently preached after? that the very ſame thing, which was more careleſly kept before, might more carefully be husbanded after?</p>
               <p>This thing, I ſay, ſhe hath ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at alwayes, and at nothing elſe, being ſtirred vp with the nouelties of Heretiques. The Catholicke Church be the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of her Councells hath done nothing, but that, what ſhe had receiued before of the Elders onely by tradition, ſhe might moreouer ſet the ſame thing downe in hand-writing for thoſe alſo, that ſhold come after: comprehending a great deale of matter in a few words, and commonly expreſſing the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:2237:70"/>
thing by ſome conuenient new tearme for the clearenes of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and not for any new meaning of the Faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 33.</head>
               <p>BVt let vs returne vnto the Apoſtle: <hi>O Timotheus,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>keepe that, which is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>to thee, auoiding the profane nouelties of words:</hi> Auoid them ſaith he, as a <hi>Viper,</hi> as a <hi>Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion,</hi> as a <hi>Cockatrice:</hi> that they may not ſmite thee, not onely by touching, but by ſight alſo, and by breathing. What is it <note place="margin">1. Cor. 5. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>to auoid?</hi> Not to eate meate with ſuch an one. What mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth this, <hi>Auoide thou?</hi> If there come any vnto you, ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn, and bring not this doctrine.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. Ioh. 10.</note> What doctrine meanes he, but
<pb facs="tcp:2237:71"/>
the Catholicke and vniuerſall, which both continueth by an vncorrupted tradition of the truth one &amp; the ſame through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all ſucceeding ages, and ſhall continue for euer and for euer, without end? But what followeth? <hi>Do not,</hi> quoth he, <hi>receiue him to houſe, neither bid</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11.</note> 
                  <hi>ye him God ſpeede. For he, that biddeth him, God ſpeed, is parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of his euill deeds.</hi> Profane nouelties of words, ſaith <hi>Paul.</hi> What is profane? Such as are altogether voyde of holineſſe and <note n="o" place="margin">Porrò, fiue procul a ſano</note> religion: vtterly ſtrange from the boſome of the Church, which is the temple of God. Profane <hi>nouelties of words,</hi> ſaith he: nouelties of words, that is, of doctrines, <note n="*" place="margin">Or opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning things or matters.</note> things, opinions: which nouelties are contrary to antientneſſe, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:2237:71"/>
Which if they ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, it cannot bee, but that the <hi>Faith</hi> of the bleſſed <hi>Fathers</hi> ſhould be violated either <hi>all,</hi> or for a <hi>great part</hi> thereof at leaſt: it muſt needs bee, that all the faithfull of all ages, all the Saints, all the chaſte <note n="*" place="margin">Or the continent, the virgins.</note> the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent virgines, that all the Cleargy, Leuites, and Prieſts, that ſo many thouſands of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors,</hi> ſo great armies of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,</hi> ſo great an aſſembly and multitude of cities and people, that ſo many Iſlands, Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Kings, Nations, kingdoms, countries, and finally, that now almoſt all the world, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated into <hi>Christ</hi> the <hi>Head</hi> by the Catholicke faith, it muſt needs bee, I ſay, that all theſe aforeſaid, ſhould be ſaid to haue beene ignorant for ſo long continuance of time, to
<pb facs="tcp:2237:72"/>
haue erred, to haue blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed, and not to haue kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen what they ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 34.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AUoid,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>profane no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelties of words:</hi> which to receiue and follow was neuer the propertie of <hi>Catholickes,</hi> but alwayes of <hi>Heretickes.</hi> And in truth, what hereſie was there euer, which did not ſpring vp vnder a certaine name, in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine place, and at a certaine time? Who euer brought vp hereſies, but which firſt ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated himſelfe from the viuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall and antient conſent of the Catholicke Church? Which that it was ſo, examples ſhew moſt cleerely. For who euer before that prophane <hi>Pelagius</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:2237:72"/>
preſumed that the power of <hi>Free-will</hi> was ſo great, that hee did not thinke that the grace of God was neceſſary to helpe it in good thngs in euery act? Who euer before <hi>Celeſtus</hi> his prodigious diſcipline denyed that all mankind was guilty of <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſſion? Who before ſacrilegious <hi>Arrius</hi> da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to diuide the vnity of the Trinity, who durſt confound the Trinity of vnity before wicked <hi>Sabellius.</hi> Who before moſt cruel <hi>Nauatianus</hi> affirmed that God was cruell, for that he had rather the death of him, that dyeth, then that he ſhould returne and liue? Who before <hi>Simon</hi> the Magitian, whom the Apoſtle <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 21.</note> curſed, from whom that <hi>whirle-poole</hi> of fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſes flowed by a continual and hidden ſucceſſion, euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:2237:73"/>
                  <hi>Priſcilianus</hi> the laſt and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermoſt, (who I ſay, before that <hi>Simon)</hi> durſt affirme that God the Creator is the author of euils, that is, of our abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable acts, impieties, and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked enormities? For he did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouch, that God himſelfe did with his owne hands create the nature of men ſo, as that by reaſon of a certaine proper mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or impulſion of a certaine neceſſary will, it could doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, it could will nothing elſe, but commit ſin: becauſe it being chafed and inflamed with the furies of all vices, it is carried by an vnſaciable deſire, into all the gulfes or whirle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits of diſhoneſt and filthy facts. Innumerable examples there are of the like nature, which for breuity ſake we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termit: by al which yet we haue
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2237:73"/>
euidently and clearely inough ſhewed, that this with almoſt all hereſies, is <hi>ſolemne,</hi> as it were, and <note n="i" place="margin">That is, Heretickes count is a Law, and make it as a Trade.</note> 
                  <hi>according to Law,</hi> to delight alwaies in prophane nouelties, to contemne the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Antiquity, and through oppoſitions of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, falſly ſo tearmed, to make ſhip-wracke from the faith. On the contrary alſo, this is almoſt proper vnto Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes to keep thoſe things, <note n="*" place="margin">Or which the holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers left in their cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, <hi>Dipoſit<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> patrum.</hi>
                  </note> which were left in the cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the holy Fathers, and were committed to them, and to condemne prophane nouel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and, as the Apoſtle ſayd, and ſayd againe: <hi>If any ſhall</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 1. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>preach otherwiſe then that which was receiued, to Anathematize</hi> or <hi>curſe him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2237:74"/>
               <head>CHAP. 35.</head>
               <p>HEere ſome man perhaps may aske, whether Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes <note place="margin">Queſt.</note> alſo do vſe the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the holy Scripture. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <note place="margin">Anſ.</note> they vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and in truth with vehemency: for you may ſee the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> flie through all &amp; euery booke of the word of God, through the bookes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and of the <hi>Kings,</hi> through the <hi>Pſalmes, Apoſtles, Goſpels, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</hi> For whether it bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt their owne Followers, or with others: whether pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately, or publickly: whether in <hi>Sermons,</hi> or in <hi>Bookes:</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at <hi>Banquets,</hi> or in the <hi>ſtreetes:</hi> they neuer almoſt vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter any thing of their owne, which they labour not alſo to ſhadow with their words of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:2237:74"/>
the Scripture. Reade the pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets of <hi>Paulus Samoſatenus,</hi> of <hi>Priſcillian, Eunomius, Ioui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> and the reſt of thoſe <note n="o" place="margin">So he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and pernicious Teachers: whoſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors are as plague-ſoares, rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious.</note> 
                  <hi>Plagues:</hi> you may ſee an infinite maſſe of examples, that no page welneere eſcapes, which is not painted and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lored with the ſentences of the Old, or New Teſtament. But they bee ſo much the rather to bee taken heede of, and feared, by how much the more cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they lurke vnder the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of Gods word: For they know, that their ſtinking er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours would not quikly bee pleaſing almoſt vnto any man, if they ſhould bee vented bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and as they are in their owne nature: and therefore they beſpice them (as it were) with the word of God, that he, which would eaſily deſpiſe the
<pb facs="tcp:2237:75"/>
errour of man, might not eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contemne the Oracles of God. They doe therefore, as thoſe are wont, which being to giue ſome bitter potions to children for to drinke, doe firſt rub their mouthes about with honey: that the ſilly little ones, hauing before felt the ſweete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, might not be afraid of the bitterneſſe. Which thing they alſo are carefull of, which ſet the names of medicines vpon ill hearbes and hurtfull <note n="u" place="margin">Or drugs.</note> ſyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rops: that almoſt no body would ſuſpect poyſon, where he read a remedy written ouer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 36.</head>
               <p>FInally, our Sauiour alſo cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out for the ſame thing. <hi>Beware yee of falſe Prophets,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 7. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>which in ſheepes cloathing come
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2237:75"/>
vnto you: but inwardly they are rauening Wolues.</hi> What is <hi>ſheepes cloathing,</hi> but the ſentences of the Prophets and Apoſtles, which they with a certaine ſheepe-like ſincerity haue wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as certaine fleeces for that <hi>immaculate Lambe,</hi> which ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away the ſinnes of the world? Who are rauening Wolues, but the ſauage and rauening opinions or conceits of heretickes, which alwaies annoy the Foldes of the Church, and rend aſſunder the Flocke of Chriſt, on what part ſoeuer they are able. But that they may ſteale more ſlily vpon the vnwary ſheepe, retaining ſtill their woluiſh cruelty they lay aſide their ſhape of a <hi>Wolfe,</hi> and wrap themſelues within the ſentences of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as it were, within cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb facs="tcp:2237:76"/>
                  <hi>Sheepe-skinnes:</hi> that when a body hath felt afore the ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the wooll, hee might not bee afraid of the bitings of the teeth. But what ſaith our Sauiour? <hi>Yee ſhall know</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 7. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>them by their fruits.</hi> That is, when they ſhall begin not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly now to vtter thoſe ſayings, but alſo to expound them: nor as yet to cracke of them only, but alſo to interpret them: then that bitterneſſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſoure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and madneſſe is percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, then this new deuiſed poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon will bee breathed out, then are prophane nouelties diſclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, then may ye ſee the bounds of the Fathers to be remoued, the Catholicke faith to be then but chered, and the doctrine of the Church torne in peeces.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="chapter">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:2237:76"/>
               <head>CHAP. 37.</head>
               <p>SVch were they, whom the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> reproueth in his ſecond Epiſtle to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthes,</hi> ſaying: <hi>For ſuch falſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>are crafty, workmen, transforming them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into Apoſtles of Chriſt.</hi> What meaneth this transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming themſelues into the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of Chriſt? The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles alledged examples of the <note n="o" place="margin">Or word</note> Law of God, and ſo did they: The Apoſtles cited the authorities of the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> and ſo did they: the Apoſtles pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the ſayings of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> euen ſo did they too, not a iot the leſſe. But when they had begun to expound thoſe ſentences diuerſly, which they had alike alledged: then were
<pb facs="tcp:2237:77"/>
the ſimple Apoſtles diſcerned from the ſubtill Apoſtles, the ſincere from the counterfeite, the right from the peruerſe, and finally, the true from the falſe. And no wonder, quoth he: <hi>For</hi> 
                  <note n="u" place="margin">verſ. 14. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Sathan himſelfe tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth himſelfe into an Angel of light: it is no great thing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though his Miniſters bee transformed as Miniſters of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</hi> Therefore by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Pauls</hi> doctrine, ſo often as euer either falſe Apoſtles, or falſe Prophets, or falſe Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers all edge the ſentences of Gods word, with the which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnderſtood amiſſe, they ſeeke to maintaine their owne errors, there is no doubt but that they follow the crafty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes of their <hi>Author:</hi> which he would neuer without doubt deuiſe, but that hee knowes,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:2237:77"/>
that there is no way at all more ready to deceiue, then that, where the deceit of a wicked errour is vnderhand introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, There the authority of Diuine ſentences ſhould bee pretended.</p>
               <p>But ſome man will ſay: how <note place="margin">Queſt.</note> is it proued, that the Diuell is wont to vſe proofes of holy Scripture?</p>
               <p>Let him read the Goſpels, <note place="margin">An.</note> in the which it is written; <hi>Then the Diuell tooke him,</hi> that is, the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. 5. <hi>Luk.</hi> 4. 9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91. 11.</note> Lord and Sauiour: <hi>and ſet him vpon a pinacle of the Temple, and ſaid vnto him, If thou be the Son of God, caſt thy ſelfe downe: For it is written, that hee hath giuen his Angels charge ouer thee (to keepe thee</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Theſe words are not in the Goſpell, though in the Pſalme.</note> 
                  <hi>in all thy waies:) and with their hands they ſhall lift thee vp, least it may bee thou ſhouldeſt daſh thy foote againſt a ſtone.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2237:78"/>
What will this Fiend do to ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men, that ſet vpon the Lord of glory with teſtimonies of Scripture. <hi>If,</hi> quoth hee, <hi>thou be the Son of God caſt thy ſelfe downe.</hi> Why ſo? <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>it is written,</hi> The doctrine of this place is to bee diligently marked, and reteined of vs, that, when we ſhall ſee ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the words of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles or Prophets, againſt the Catholicke Faith, we ſhould in no wiſe doubt: conſidering ſuch a remarkeable example of Euangelicall authority, that the Diuell ſpeaketh by them. For as then the <note n="c" place="margin">That is, the Diuell to Ieſus, and Hereticks to true Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes.</note> 
                  <hi>Head</hi> ſpake to the <hi>Head,</hi> ſo now alſo the <hi>Members</hi> ſpeake vnto the <hi>Members:</hi> to wit, the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Diuell, to the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, the vnfaithfull to the faithfull, the ſacrilegious
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:2237:78"/>
to the religious<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> finally, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques to Catholickes. But what I pray you, ſaith hee? <hi>If,</hi> quoth he, <hi>thou bee the Sonne of God, caſt thy ſelfe downe.</hi> That is to ſay, thou wilt be the Son of God, and wilt receiue the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance of the kingdome of heauen, <hi>Caſt thy ſelfe downe:</hi> that is, throw thy ſelfe off from the doctrine and tradition of this high Church, which is alſo counted the <hi>Temple of God.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1, <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And if any man ſhould aske ſome hereticke which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades him to doe thus: How doſt thou prooue, vpon what ground doſt thou teach, that I ought to forſake the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall and ancient faith of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Church? Hee would preſently anſwer: <hi>For it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</hi> And forthwith hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares a multitude of teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,
<pb facs="tcp:2237:79"/>
examples, and authorities, from the Law, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Pſalmes, from the Apoſtles, from the Prophets, through the which being after a new and naughty manner interpreted, the vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſoule might bee plunged headlong into the gulfe of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie. And now with thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes following the hereticks are wont to deceiue vnwary men. For they preſume to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and to teach. That in their Church, that is, in the conuenticle of their commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, there is a great, and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial, and in truth a certaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall grace of God, ſo as that they, whoſoeuer they bee, that are of their company, without any labour, without any ſtudy, without any trauell, though they neither ſeeke, nor aske, nor knocke, are yet for all that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2237:79"/>
ſo ordered by God, that being lifted vp in the hands of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, that is, being preſerued by Angelicall protection, they can neuer daſh their foote againſt a ſtone, that is, they can neuer be ſcandalized, or offended.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 38.</head>
               <p>BVt ſome man doth ſay; If <note place="margin">Quest.</note> the Diuel and his Diſciples do vſe Diuine ſpeeches, ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and promiſes, amongſt whoſe Diſciples ſome are Falſ-apoſtles, &amp; Falſe-prophets, and Falſe-teachers, and all of them generally heretiques: what ſhal Catholicke men, and the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Church our <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> do? How ſhall they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the truth in the holy Scriptures from falſehood?</p>
               <p>Surely they ſhall haue ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <note place="margin">Anſ.</note> care to doe this, which wee
<pb facs="tcp:2237:80"/>
haue in writing ſet downe in the beginning of this <hi>aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to haue beene deliuered vnto vs by holy and learned men: namely, that they doe interprete the holy Scriptures according to the traditions of the vniuerſall Church, and by the rules of Catholicke do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: wherein alſo it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that they follow the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſality, antiquity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Catholique and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolique Church. And if at any time a part ſhall rebell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the whole, if nouelty ſhall thwart antiquity, if the diſſention of one, or of ſome few erronious perſons, ſhall croſſe the conſent of all, or ſurely of the greateſt number of Catholickes, let them pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the ſoundneſſe of the whole to the corruptneſſe of a
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:2237:80"/>
part: in the which ſame vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall body, let them make more account of religious antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, then of profane nouelty: &amp; in like manner in the ſame an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, let them firſt and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, afore all thinges preferre the generall decrees, if there be any, of an vniuerſall counſell, vnto the raſhneſſe of one, or of ſome very few. Then ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if that be not, let them fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, which is the next thing to it, the iudgements of many &amp; great Teachers, that are agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able one vnto another: the which being faithfully, ſoberly, and carefully obſerued by the Lords aſſiſtance, we ſhall eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceiue all the hurtfull er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of the heretickes, which riſe vp.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2237:81"/>
               <head>CHAP. 39.</head>
               <p>HEre now I ſee it meete, that I ſhould ſhew by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, how the profane no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelties of Heretickes may bee both found out, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, when the iudgements of ancient Teachers, agreeing one with another, are produced and compared. Which ancient conſent of the holy Fathers wee ſhould with great labour ſearch out and follow, yet not in all the petty queſtions of Gods word, but onely, at the leaſtwiſe eſpecially, in the rule of faith. But neither are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies alwaies, nor all of them thus to be impugned, but thoſe onely that are new and freſh: namely when as they doe firſt ariſe, before they falſifie the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2237:81"/>
Rules of the ancient faith, whiles they bee let with the ſtraitneſſe of the time it ſelfe, and before that, the poyſon ſpreading it ſelfe farther about, they do attempt to corrupt the writings of the Elders. But hereſies that haue gathered much ground, and are waxen old, muſt not this way be aſſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, becauſe that by reaſon of long continuance of time, they haue had opportunity offered them, a great while to <note n="*" place="margin">He is ſaid to ſteale the truth, which writhes the Scriptures to his owne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion or er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their meaning.</note> ſteale the truth. And therefore it behooueth vs either to confute thoſe more ancient wicked Schiſmes or Hereſies by no meanes, but by the ſole autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Scriptures, if neede be, or elſe verily to auoid them, being now of old confuted &amp; condemned by the generall Councels of Catholike Prieſts.
<pb facs="tcp:2237:82"/>
Therefore ſo ſoone as the rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſſe of euery wicked er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour beginnes to breake out, and to ſteale for the defence of it ſelfe certaine ſentences of Gods word, and to expound them falſely and deceitfully: the ſentences or iudgements of the Elders are preſently to bee gathered together for to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret the <note n="*" place="margin">Or Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> 
                  <hi>Canon,</hi> by the which that nouell, and therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane opinion, whatſoeuer it be which ſhall ſtart vp, may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any coyle preſently be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcried, &amp; without any retracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion condemned. But the iudgements of thoſe Fathers onely are to be compared toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which liuing, teaching &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing, holily, wiſely, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly in the Catholike Faith and Fellowſhip, obteined either to dye faithfully in Chriſt, or
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2237:82"/>
to be ſlaine happily for Chriſt. Whom to notwithſtanding we muſt giue credit with this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that, that be accounted vndoubedly true, certaine, and ſure, whatſoeuer either all of them, or the moſt, haue mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly, commonly, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly with one and the ſame meaning, as in a certaine vnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Councell of Teachers, confirmed and eſtabliſhed by receiuing, holding and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it. But whatſoeuer any man ſhall conceite or thinke otherwiſe then all men, or elſe contrary to all men, though he be (o) holy and learned, though <note n="*" place="margin">For the perſon doth not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the faith, but faith the perſon.</note> he be a Biſhop, though he bee a Confeſſour and Martyr, let it be put apart from the authority of the commune, publicke and generall iudgement, amongſt proper, hidden and priuate opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions:
<pb facs="tcp:2237:83"/>
and let vs not with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great hazzard of our ſoules, after the wicked faſhion of Heretiques, &amp; Schiſmatiques, follow the nouell errour of one man, forſaking the truth of Catholike doctrine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 40.</head>
               <p>THE holy and Catholicke conſent of which bleſſed Fathers, leaſt any man ſhould vnaduiſedly, it may be, thinke for to contemne, the Apoſtle ſaith in the firſt epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians: And God indeede hath ordeined ſome in the Church:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>as firſt Apostles,</hi> of which ranke he himſelfe was one: <hi>ſecondly Prophets,</hi> as we reade in the Acts of the Apoſtles that <hi>Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> was: thirdly <hi>Teachers,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 11. 27. 28.</note>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:2237:83"/>
which are now called Treati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers, Tractators, which by this ſame Apoſtle are ſometimes called Prophets, becauſe they open the myſteries of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets to the people. Whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer therefore doth contemne theſe men, being ſet by God in ſundry ages and places in the Church of God, whiles in the name of Chriſt they do deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine or iudge ſome one thing according to the meaning of the Catholicke doctrine, he doth not contemne <hi>Man,</hi> but <hi>God.</hi> And from whom, that no man ſhould diſſent, whiles with one conſent they ſpeake the truth, the ſame Apoſtle doth very earneſtly deſire, ſaying: <hi>Now I beſeech you, Brethren,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>that ye All ſpeake one thing, and that there be no Schiſmes</hi> or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions <hi>among you: but be ye
<pb facs="tcp:2237:84"/>
knit together in the ſame mind, and in the ſame iudgement.</hi> If ſo be that any man ſhall goe from their commune iudgement, he ſhal heare what the ſame Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith; <hi>God is not the God of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>diſſention, but of peace:</hi> that is to ſay, he is not his God, which departeth from them, that doe ioyntly conſent vnto the truth, but theirs, that continue peac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably conſenting with them: <hi>as,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I teach in all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Saints,</hi> that is, of the Catholickes: which Churches are therefore holy, becauſe they abide in the fellowſhip of the faith. And leaſt any perhaps, the reſt beeing vnregarded, ſhould arrogate to bee heard himſelfe alone, and that he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ſhould be beleeued, he ſaith a little after: <hi>Came the word of God out from you? either</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Uerſ.</hi> 36.</note> 
                  <hi>came it vnto you onely?</hi> And leaſt
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:2237:84"/>
this ſhould as it were for faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſake be receiued, he hath added, ſaying, <hi>If any man thinke</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 37.</note> 
                  <hi>himſelfe to be a Prophet, or Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall,</hi> that is, a teacher of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall things, <hi>let him be with all diligence a louer of equality and vnitie:</hi> that in truth he do nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preferre his own opinions to the reſt, and that he go not from the iudgements of all. <hi>The commaundements of which things he which knowes not,</hi> ſaith <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Uerſ.</hi> 38.</note> he: that is, hee which either learnes them not beeing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne, or which contemnes them being knowne, <hi>he ſhall not be knowne,</hi> that is, he ſhal be counted vnworthie to be by God reſpected among them, that are knit together in the faith, and made equall by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie: then which euill I wot not whether any ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be thought to be more grieuous. Which
<pb facs="tcp:2237:85"/>
yet we ſee to haue befallen, as the Apoſtle threatned, that <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagian Iulianus,</hi> who either neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to agree in iudgement with his Fellows, or elſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to diuide himſelfe from them.</p>
               <p>But it is now time, that we ſhould produce that example promiſed, wherein and after what manner the iudgements of the Fathers are gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, that by them the Rule of eccleſiaſticall faith might be eſtabliſhed by the decree and authority of a Councel. Which that it may be done more hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely, let this be the end now of this Aduertiſement: that we may begin the reſt of the things that follow with another be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. The ſecond Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement hath fallen betweene, neither hath any thing more
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2237:85"/>
thereof remained, then the laſt parcell, that is, onely a briefe rehearſall of that, which hath bene more largely handled, which is alſo added after.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 41.</head>
               <p>THe which things ſeeing they thus ſtand, it is nowe time, that we ſhould rehearſe the ſumme of thoſe things in the end of this ſecond Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement, which haue ben ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in theſe two. We haue ſayd before that this hath euer bene, and is alſo at this day the cuſtome of Catholickes to proue the true ſaith theſe two wayes: Firſt, by the authority of Gods word: Secondly, by the tradition of the Catholike Church: not becauſe the word alone is not ſufficient of it ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:2237:86"/>
for all matters, but becauſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, whiles they expound the Scriptures, as they liſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, they conceiue ſundry o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, and errors. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that it is neceſſary, that the interpretation of the heauenly Scripture ſhould bee directed by the alone Rule of Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical iudgement or vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: eſpecially, in thoſe que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions at leaſt, on which the grounds of all the Catholicke doctrine are layed. In like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner we haue ſayd, that we ſhould againe haue regard in the Church her-ſelfe vnto the conſent of <hi>All</hi> in generall, and alſo of <hi>Antiquity,</hi> leaſt we ſhould either bee broken off from the whole body (of the Church) being vnited and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled together, and ſo become Schiſmatickes, or elſe be caſt
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2237:86"/>
head-long from the antient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion into nouell hereſies. We haue alſo ſayd, that in the very antiquity of the Church, two certaine things are earneſtly and carefully to be obſerued, to which all, that would not be Heretiques, ſhould throughly cleaue: firſt, if any thing hath bene of antient time decreed of all the Prieſts of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church by the authority of a generall Councell: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, if any ſtrange queſtion ſhould ariſe, when that in no wiſe might be found, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ſhould be had to the iudgements of the holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, of thoſe onely, which in their times and places contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all of them in the vnity of fellowſhip and of the Faith, were commendable Teachers. And that, whatſoeuer they
<pb facs="tcp:2237:87"/>
ſhould be found to haue held with one meaning and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, that it ſhould without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſcruple be iudged of the Church to be true and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 42.</head>
               <p>VVHich-leaſt we ſhould ſeeme to ſet abroach through our owne preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on rather, then by Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call authority, we haue vſed the example of an holy Councell, which was held almoſt three yeares ſince at <hi>Epheſus</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> thoſe moſt excellent men <hi>Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> and <hi>Antiochus</hi> being Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls. Where when there was diſpute about the confirming of the Rules of Faith, leaſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps any profane noueltie ſhould ſteale in there after the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2237:87"/>
manner of the (o) <hi>Ariminian</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued <hi>Ua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens</hi> the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian,</hi> hauing before con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned him.</note> Councels vnfaithfull dealing, this ſeemed to all the Prieſts, which had come thither to the number almoſt of two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth, to be a thing moſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke, moſt commodious, and beſt to be done, that the iudgements of the holy Fathers ſhould be brought foorth and ſhewed, of whom it ſhould be manifeſt that ſome were Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, others Confeſſors, but that all had bene and had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Catholicke Prieſts: that ſo by their conſent and decree the religion of the ancient do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine might well and ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be confirmed, and the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy of wicked nouelty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned. Which when it was ſo done, then was that foreſaid <hi>Neſtorius</hi> iudged contrary to Catholicke Antiquity, but
<pb facs="tcp:2237:88"/>
bleſſed <hi>Cyril</hi> to conſent <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ad verb.</hi> to ſacred Antiquity.</note> vnto it. And that the truth of thoſe things might in no wiſe be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into queſtion, we haue alſo ſhewed the names and number (though we had forgotten the ranke) of thoſe Fathers accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to whoſe order therein concording and vnanimous iudgement both the ſentences of holy Writ were expounded, and the rule of diuine doctrine eſtabliſhed. Whom for the ſtrengthening of our memorie it is not ſuperfluous here alſo to recite.</p>
               <p>Theſe therefore are the men, whoſe writings, either as of Iudges, or as it were of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, were in that Councell ſhewed and recited; S. <hi>Peter</hi> of <note n="*" place="margin">Perhaps it ſhold be read Biſhop of <hi>Alex.</hi> for the Comma is wanting in ſome bookes.</note> 
                  <hi>Alexandria,</hi> a Biſhop, a moſt excellent Teacher, and a moſt bleſſed Martyr: S. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:2237:88"/>
a Prelate of the ſame Citty, a moſt faithfull Teacher, and a moſt worthy Confeſſor: Saint <hi>Theophilus,</hi> a Biſhop of the ſame Citie too, a man very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for his religion, life, and learning, whom worthy <hi>Cyril</hi> did ſucceed, who doth at this time make the Church of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria</hi> famous. And leaſt it ſhould perhaps be thought to be the doctrine of one City &amp; Prouince, there were ioyned alſo thoſe <hi>Lights</hi> of <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> S. <hi>Gregory</hi> Biſhop and Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of <hi>Nazianzum:</hi> S. <hi>Baſil,</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and Confeſſor of <hi>Caeſarea</hi> in <hi>Cappadocia:</hi> as alſo the other S. <hi>Gregory</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Nyſſe,</hi> and for his faith, conuerſation, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe, and wiſedome, a man moſt worthy of his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Baſil.</hi> But that it might be proued that not <hi>Greece</hi> alone,
<pb facs="tcp:2237:89"/>
or that the <hi>Eaſt</hi> onely, but that the <hi>Weasterne</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> world was alwayes alſo of that iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, certaine Epiſtles alſo were there read, written to certaine men by Saint <hi>Foelix,</hi> a Martyr, and S. <hi>Iulius,</hi> Biſhops of the City of Rome. And that not only the <hi>head</hi> of the world, but that the <hi>ſides</hi> alſo might giue teſtimony to that iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there was taken from the <hi>South</hi> moſt bleſſed <hi>Cyprian,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> and a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr; and from the <hi>North</hi> Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Millaine.</hi> All theſe <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ad verb.</hi> of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Decalogue.</note> 
                  <hi>ten</hi> therefore were at <hi>Epheſus</hi> produced as Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, Counſellers, Witneſſes and Iudges: whoſe doctrine, counſell, witneſſe and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that bleſſed Synode main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teining, following, crediting, and obeying, did readily, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:2237:89"/>
&amp; vnpartially giue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence concerning the <hi>Rules</hi> of Faith. Although a farre grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter number of Elders might haue bene ioyned to theſe, yet it was not needfull: becauſe it was not ſitting that the time allotted for that buſineſſe ſhould be taken vp and ſpent with producing of a multitude of Witneſſes, and for that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man is perſwaded that thoſe ten did differ nothing in a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in iudgement from all their other fellowes.</p>
               <p>After all which things we haue alſo annexed the holy iudgement of <hi>Cyril,</hi> which things are conteined in the ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall acts. For after that the Epiſtle of S. <hi>Capreolus,</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Carthage</hi> was read, who laboured and intreated no other thing, but that <hi>Noueltie</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2237:90"/>
being conuinced <hi>Antiquity</hi> might be beleeued, Biſhop <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril</hi> ſpake and defined to the ſame effect: the which it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not vnfitting for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in hand here alſo to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
               <p>For hee ſaith in the end of the Acts; <hi>And this Epiſtle which was read,</hi> quoth he, <hi>of the reuerend &amp; very religious Biſhop of Carthage, Capreolus, ſhall bee faithfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded, whoſe iudgement is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest: for hee would haue the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of the ancient faith confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but nouell conceipts, and ſuch as are ſuperfluouſly deuiſed, and wickedly publiſhed, to bee reiected, and condemned.</hi> All the Biſhops cryed together in ſigne of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation; <hi>Theſe are the words of vs all,</hi> we do <hi>all</hi> affirme theſe things, this is the wiſh of vs <hi>all.</hi> And what, I pray you, were the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:2237:90"/>
words and the wiſhes of <hi>all,</hi> but that <hi>That ſhould bee embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, which was anciently deliuered,</hi> and that <hi>That ſhould be baniſhed, which was newly deuiſed?</hi> After which things we wondred at &amp; told of the great humility and holineſſe of that Councell, and what a number of Prieſts there were, the greater part welneere being <hi>Metropolitanes,</hi> of ſuch knowledge, and ſo well lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as that almoſt all of them were able to diſpute of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines. Whom when the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation being aſſembled all together might ſeeme to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage, to vndertake and to determine ſomething of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, yet would they giue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, preſume nothing, arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate nothing to themſelues at all: but by all meanes proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>that they might not deliuer
<pb facs="tcp:2237:91"/>
any thing to their poſterity, which they themſelues had not receiued of their Fathers,</hi> and that they might not only order the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter well for the preſent, but giue example alſo to them, that ſhould ſuceede, that they alſo might embrace the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of ſacred Antiquity, and condemne the deuiſes of prophane Nouelty. Wee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueighed alſo againſt the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked preſumption of <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> becauſe he boaſted that he did <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>onely</hi> vnderſtand the holy Scripture, and that all thoſe whatſoeuer were ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of it, which being teachers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him had handled the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of God; to wit, all Prieſts, all Confeſſors and Martyrs: ſome of which had explained Gods word, and others had conſented or giuen credit to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2237:91"/>
the Explainers of it: and laſtly, becauſe he did affirme that the whole Church doth now erre, and that it hath alwaies erred, <note n="*" place="margin">That is, the whole Church.</note> which, as to him ſeemed, had both alwaies followed, and did (now) follow ignorant and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous Teachers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 43.</head>
               <p>ALl which things, though they cannot plentifully &amp; aboundantly ſuffice to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme and extinguiſh all prophane nouelties, yet leaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing ſhould ſeeme to bee lacking, where there is ſuch plenty of proofe to cleare this point, we haue in the laſt place added a double authority of the Apoſtlicke See; namely one of the holy Pope, or <note n="o" place="margin">For <hi>Papa,</hi> Pope, is Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theria name of old gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to other Biſhops, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Romane.</hi>
                  </note> Father <hi>Xistus,</hi> who like a reuerend
<pb facs="tcp:2237:92"/>
man doth at this preſent ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> and the other of his Predeceſſor of bleſſed memory Pope <hi>Cale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi> whoſe authorities wee haue deemed needfull heere al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to interpoſe. Pope <hi>Xiſtus</hi> then ſaith in an Epiſtle, which he ſent to the Biſhop of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och,</hi> about the cauſe of <hi>Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius.</hi> Therefore, quoth he, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>there is one Faith,</hi> which hath eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 5.</note> preuailed, let vs hold thoſe things that are to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued, and let vs beleeue thoſe things that are to bee held. At the length hee ſheweth the things, that are to bee held and beleeued, and ſaith; <hi>Let no li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie</hi> (quoth he) <hi>bee giuen at all to Nouelty, becauſe it is fitting that nothing ſhould be added to Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. Let the manifeſt faith and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:2237:92"/>
credulity of the Elders be troubled with no mixture of</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">All cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceits of men are no better then mud, or mine: they are foule &amp; filthy: and therefore to be ſhunned of ſuch as would not be deſiled.</note> 
                  <hi>mire.</hi> Spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches altogether Apoſtolical, in that hee adornes the credulity or faith of the Elders, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring it to the <hi>Light,</hi> for the manifeſtneſſe or cleareneſſe of it, and deſcribes nouell profani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, (or prophane nouelties) by likening them to the mixture of mire. But Pope <hi>Caeleſtine</hi> alſo deales in the like manner, and is of the ſame iudgement. For he ſaith in an Epiſtle which he ſent to the <hi>French</hi> Miniſters, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing their conniuencie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they <note n="*" place="margin">Or forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through ſilence.</note> letting the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent faith to be iniured through their ſilence, did ſuffer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane nouelties to ſtart vp. Iuſtly, quoth hee, the matter concernes vs, if we ſhall nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh an error with holding our peace. Let ſuch men therefore
<pb facs="tcp:2237:93"/>
be rebuked, let them not haue liberty of ſpeech at ſuch their pleaſure. Some man here may <note place="margin">Queſt.</note> peraduenture doubt, who thoſe may be, whom hee forbids that they ſhould haue libertie to ſpeake what they liſt, whether the Preachers of Antiquity, or the Deuiſers of Nouelty. Let him ſpeake himſelfe, and anſwer the doubting of the <note place="margin">Anſ.</note> Readers. For it followeth: Let Nouelty ceaſe, ſaith hee, if the caſe ſtand thus, that is, if it bee ſo, that ſome accuſe your Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Prouinces to me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you make them to giue conſent to certaine Nouelties through your dangerous win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king at them. Let Nouelty therefore ceaſe, ſaith hee, if the matter ſtand ſo, to inuade and incroach vpon Antiquity. This then was the bleſſed iudgment
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2237:93"/>
of bleſſed <hi>Celeſtine,</hi> not that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity ſhould ceaſe to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw Nouelty, but rather that Nouelty ſhould ceaſe to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ground vpon, and inuade Antiquity.</p>
               <p>Which Apoſtolicke and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke decrees whoſoeuer doth gaineſay, hee muſt needs firſt of al triumph ouer the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of Saint <hi>Celeſtine,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined that Nouelty ſhould ceaſe to vexe and inuade Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity: and in the ſecond place ſcorne the decrees of holy <hi>Xy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> who iudged that no liberty at all ſhould be granted to No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelty, becauſe it is meete that nothing ſhold be added to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity: yea &amp; contemne the determinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of bleſſed <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> who did greatly extoll the zeale of reuerend <hi>Capreolus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee deſired that the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines
<pb facs="tcp:2237:94"/>
of the ancient Faith ſhould be confirmed: and that <hi>nouell deuiſes ſhould be condemned:</hi> and deſpiſe the Counſell of <hi>Epheſus</hi> alſo, that is, the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the holy Biſhops almoſt of all the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> whom it pleaſed by Gods direction to determine that the Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhould beleeue no other thing, but that <note n="*" place="margin">That is, which the holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Chriſt held of old before.</note> which the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and in Chriſt vnanimous Antiquity of the holy Fathers had held, and who alſo with their cryes and exclamations witneſſed with one conſent, that theſe are the words of all, that they did all wiſh this, that they were all of this iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: that as almoſt all Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes before <hi>Nestorius,</hi> deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Antiquity, and deſending nouelty ſhould be condemned, euen ſo <hi>Neſtorius</hi> himſelfe alſo
<pb facs="tcp:2237:94"/>
ſhould be condemned as an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of Nouelty, and an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugner of Antiquity, whoſe conſent being inſpired by an holy gift and of heauenly grace to whom it is diſpleaſing. What elſe doth follow, but that he ſhould affirme that the wickedneſſe of <hi>Neſtorius</hi> was not iuſtly condemned, and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alſo contemne the whole Church of Chriſt and his Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, Apoſtles, and Prophets; but yet eſpecially the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> as certaine filth or off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourings? <hi>Her,</hi> becauſe ſhe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the religion of the ſaith once deliuered vnto her to be husbanded &amp; careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lookt vnto: and <hi>Him,</hi> becauſe he hath written; <hi>O</hi> Timotheus <hi>keep that which is committed vnto</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>thee, auoiding profane nouelties of words:</hi> And alſo, <hi>If any one ſhall <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2237:95"/>
preach vnto you otherwiſe then that yee haue receiued, let him be accurſed.</hi> If ſo be that neither Apoſtolicall ordinances, nor Eccleſiaſticall decrees be to be broken, by the which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſacred conſent of the vniuerſall and ancient Church all Hereticks alwaies, and laſt of all <hi>Pelagius, Celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and <hi>Neſtorius</hi> haue ben iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and worthily condemned, it is neceſſealy doubtleſſe for all Catholickes hereafter, which ſtudy to ſhewe themſelues the lawfull Children of the Church their <note n="o" place="margin">Hee that hath not the Church for his mother, hath not God for his father, nor Chriſt for his brother.</note> 
                  <hi>Mother,</hi> that they ſhould ſticke and cleaue vnto, and dye in the holy faith of the holy Fathers: and that they ſhould deteſt, abhorre, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueigh againſt, and perſecute the profane Nouelties of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane perſons. Theſe are well
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2237:95"/>
nigh the things, which being more largely handled in the two Aduertiſments are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted as a recapitulation ought to be, that my memory, for the helping whereof we haue done theſe things, might bee both <note n="*" place="margin">Or men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired.</note> refreſhed by being continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally put in minde, and not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with wearineſſe, cauſed by long diſcourſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Trin-vni Deo Gloria.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:2237:96"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2237:96"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by NICHOLAS OKES, for LEONARD BECKET, and are to be ſold at his Shop, neere the Church, in the Inner Temple. 1611.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
