<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vvorlds svveet-heart vvhereby it is shewed that mistris Money, is the worlds sweet-heart and hony. To the tune of, The begger boy.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15710</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25984</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103649</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839398</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839398</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3814</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A15710)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3814)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1264:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vvorlds svveet-heart vvhereby it is shewed that mistris Money, is the worlds sweet-heart and hony. To the tune of, The begger boy.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for Tho: Lambert, at the signe of the Horshoo in Smithfield,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1634]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse - "Sweet Mistris money I here will declare,".</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>In two parts; woodcuts at head of each part.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ballads, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="ballad">
            <pb facs="tcp:3814:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 7 -->
            <head>The VVorlds Svveet-heart: VVhereby it is ſhewed that Miſtris <hi>Money,</hi> Is the worlds Sweet-heart and Hony.</head>
            <opener>To the tune of, <hi>The Begger Boy.</hi>
            </opener>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>SWeet Miſtris <hi>Money</hi> I here will declare,</l>
                  <l>thy beauty which euery one adoreth,</l>
                  <l>The loft y gallant and beggar ſo bare,</l>
                  <l>ſome help and comfort from thée imploreth:</l>
                  <l>For thou art become the worlds ſwéetheart,</l>
                  <l>while euery one doth make thée their honey,</l>
                  <l>And loath they are from thée to depart,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>ſo well they doe love ſweet Miſtris Money.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Money is that which all men obey,</l>
                  <l>the wealthy rich miſer doteth upon it,</l>
                  <l>He puts her to trading vntill ſuch a day,</l>
                  <l>and is very carefull in parting from it:</l>
                  <l>It joyes him to ſée a great heap of wealth,</l>
                  <l>and Lady <hi>Pecunia</hi> is his deare honey,</l>
                  <l>While he is content for to ſtarue himſelfe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>even for the love of Miſtris Money.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Citty of London doth take great care,</l>
                  <l>to gaine her fauour by ſome new faſhion,</l>
                  <l>And for her ſake they will giue you ſuch ware,</l>
                  <l>as there is not better in any Nation:</l>
                  <l>For euery ones heart is now ſet vpon her,</l>
                  <l>and ſhe is become their onely deare Honey,</l>
                  <l>Where euer ſhe goes her ſteps they doe honour</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>ſo well they doe love ſweet Miſtris Money.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though Moneys complexion be very white,</l>
                  <l>yet I doe thinke there was neuer yet any</l>
                  <l>Could equall her beauty which is ſo bright,</l>
                  <l>ſo that ſhe hath friends and louers many.</l>
                  <l>Each one will lend her a helping hand,</l>
                  <l>to carry abroad their deareſt honey,</l>
                  <l>And they will be ready at her command,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>even for the love of Miſtris Money.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Your Country men to the Market will goe,</l>
                  <l>with corne and ſuch other like prouiſion,</l>
                  <l>And to procure money ſometimes you do know</l>
                  <l>they will ſell it off vpon any condition:</l>
                  <l>To cure their hearts of ſorrow and care.</l>
                  <l>the ſauour of coyne is as ſwéet as honey,</l>
                  <l>And they are glad to ſell off their ware,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>even for the love of Miſtris Money.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Shepheard that lyeth abroad in the ſield,</l>
                  <l>and neuer careth for wind or weather,</l>
                  <l>Doth hope that his ſhéepe ſome profit wil yéeld,</l>
                  <l>which makes him to kéepe them all together:</l>
                  <l>For he wil ſit on the ſide of a Rock,</l>
                  <l>or elſe lye vpon a gréen banke that is ſunny,</l>
                  <l>And there he will kéepe his poore little ſtock,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>even for the love of Miſtris Money.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:3814:1"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 7 -->
               <head>The ſecond part,</head>
               <opener>To the ſame tune.</opener>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN City and Country and euery place,</l>
                  <l>tis money that is ſo much reſpected,</l>
                  <l>For ſhe can neuer receiue diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>ſince many deuiſes are ſtill projected</l>
                  <l>By thoſe which ſéeke her fauour to gaine,</l>
                  <l>and make her their onely delight and honey,</l>
                  <l>For they will refuſe no labour and paine,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>in hope for to get ſweet Miſtris Money.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I thinke the world ſhall come to an end,</l>
                  <l>before that Money ſhall be deſpiſed,</l>
                  <l>For in euery corner ſhe hath a cloſe friend,</l>
                  <l>and by euery one ſhe is highly priſed:</l>
                  <l>In euery country where euer you ride,</l>
                  <l>the ſauour of coyne is ſweet as the hony,</l>
                  <l>And all the Inns on the roade doe prouide,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>to entertaine ſweet miſtris Money.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now <hi>Cupid</hi> may lay by his quiuer and bow,</l>
                  <l>whereby ſometime much loue was procured,</l>
                  <l>Since now to marry they are very ſlow,</l>
                  <l>vnleſſe that a portion may be aſſured:</l>
                  <l>For that doth carry their fancy away,</l>
                  <l>ſo that young men doe make it their honey,</l>
                  <l>And many a wedding without all delay.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>is made up for the love of money.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Mark where you doe come &amp; you ſhal ſtill find,</l>
                  <l>that for your money you ſhal be attended,</l>
                  <l>My Hoſt and my Hoſteſſe will be very kind,</l>
                  <l>but when that your ſiluer and coin is ſpended</l>
                  <l>Faith then you may goe with much grief &amp; woe</l>
                  <l>becauſe you haue parted from your deare hony;</l>
                  <l>For that reſpect which to you they did ſhow;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>was for the love of miſtris Money.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>At Rome the prieſts doe make her a Saint,</l>
                  <l>who cheat the people by fond deluſion,</l>
                  <l>And if that you no mony doe want,</l>
                  <l>you ſhall for your ſins haue an abſolution:</l>
                  <l>Thus in forraine countries whereuer you goe,</l>
                  <l>this Mammon is counted their onely hony,</l>
                  <l>And vnto you much kindneſſe they'l ſhew,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>even for the love of miſtris Mony.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Seaman likewiſe will trauaile abroad,</l>
                  <l>in ſtorms &amp; in tempeſts his heart nere faileth</l>
                  <l>Vntill with commodities he be wel ſtor'd,</l>
                  <l>and then through the Ocean he luſtily ſaileth</l>
                  <l>He cares not if that he méet with ſome blowes,</l>
                  <l>for he ſo eſteemeth his deareſt hony,</l>
                  <l>That he ſpreadeth his ſayls and away he goes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>&amp; ſometimes he bringeth home gold &amp; Mony.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus all mens affections are equally bent,</l>
                  <l>to Money, which maketh them ful of mettle,</l>
                  <l>And when they doe want it they are diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>becauſe their loue on it they doe ſettle:</l>
                  <l>Yet I would not haue you to ſet your heart</l>
                  <l>on worldly treaſure to make it your hony,</l>
                  <l>But to buy this ditty before you depart,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>if that you doe love ſweet Miſtris Mony.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed at London for <hi>Tho: Lambert,</hi> at the ſigne of the Horſhoo in Smithfield.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
