<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The pilgrimage to paradise Compiled for the direction, comfort, and resolution of Gods poore distressed children, in passing through this irkesome wildernesse of temptation and tryall. By Leonard Wright. Seene and allowed.</title>
            <author>Wright, Leonard, b. 1555 or 6.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-11">2004-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15762</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26032</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102797</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838559</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838559</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2941</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A15762)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2941)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1125:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The pilgrimage to paradise Compiled for the direction, comfort, and resolution of Gods poore distressed children, in passing through this irkesome wildernesse of temptation and tryall. By Leonard Wright. Seene and allowed.</title>
                  <author>Wright, Leonard, b. 1555 or 6.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 58, [2] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wolfe, and are to be solde at his shoppe against the broad south doore of Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a final index leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2941:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2941:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Pilgrimage to Paradise. Compiled for the direction, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and resolution of Gods poore distressed children, in passing through this irkesome wildernesse of temptation and tryall.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Leonard Wright.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Acts. 14.22.</bibl>
               <p>Through much tribulation must wee enter into the kingdome of God.</p>
               <bibl>Matth. 7.14.</bibl>
               <p>Straight is the gate, and narrowe is the way that leadeth vnto life, and fewe there be that finde it.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Seene and allowed.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>Iohn Wolfe,</hi> and are to be solde at his shoppe against the broad South doore of Paules. 1591.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2941:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2941:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable and my very good Lord, Ihon, Lord Saint-Ihon, Baron of Bletso: L. Wright wisheth increase of honour and temporall prosperitie: and after death, to ioy with Christ in eternal felicitie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Patriarkes in olde time co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plained (right Honorable) that the dayes of their pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage were short &amp; tedious:<note place="margin">Genes. 47 Iob 14. 2. Tim. 3.1.</note> but we may truly say, that the days of our crooked aged are most wretched and dangerous.<note place="margin">Apoc. 12.12</note> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Satan (whose wrath being great because he knoweth his time but short) is transformed into an Angel of of light: and his peeuish Ministers fashio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned like to the Apostles of Christ,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11 13 14.</note> hauyng their heads so fraught with nouelties, their harts so ful of hypocrisie, and their toongs so smooth, eloquent and plausible: as by the persuadable words of mans wisdome, they are able to deceiue (if it were possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) euen the very elect.<note place="margin">Mat. 24.24</note> They fil our eares with vaine iangling, striuing and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding about Church-plots and principles of doctrine (euer learning,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.7.</note> and neuer able
<pb facs="tcp:2941:3"/>
to come to the trueth) as though Religion consisted onely in speculation, wythout action, hearing, without doing, or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, without execution To the great dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging and amazing of many a simple soule. Who though in zeale of conscience very careful to please God, and feareful to offend him: yet by reason of ignorance vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to discerne medicine from poison, or Religion from Superstition. For whose comfort and directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the way of truth, godlinesse and vertue, I haue penned this litle volume. Which, as a true testimony of a thankefull minde, for those fauourable courtesies your Lordship hath vouchsafed to shew me, I haue presumed to dedicate vnto your Honor: in hope, that in passing vnder your good name, the people shal the rather be moued to take the same in good part, and apply it to their profit. Humbly beseeching you to pardon my boldenesse, and accept it as willingly, as I offer it faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. And as duety bindes me, my dailie prayers to the Almightie for your Honour shal not cease during life.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2941:3"/>
            <head>The Author to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a true saying (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) man doth purpose, but God doth dispose. For I had no sooner determined in discharge of my dutie to frame this litle volume: but that vpon speciall occasion offered by some of Satans broode (who vnder an hipocriticall shew of Religion, sought to corrupt the pure doctrine of the Gospell, deface the ministerie, and subuert the state of Ecclesiasticall gouernement:) I was moued in zeale of conscience to stay my former pretence. And rather (as time then required) to apply my indeuours to the preuenting of eminent daungers: as in my late published labour intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>A Sommons for sleepers: A Patterne for Pastors: A Display of dutie: and The Hunting of Anti-christ: with A friendly admonition to Martin Marprelate, and his Mates,</hi> may plainely appeare. Tending chiefely to awake and stirre vp to repentance and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life, such wicked and notorious offenders as are most grieuous to the Church, and noysome
<pb facs="tcp:2941:4"/>
to the common wealth. And to put all states and degrees of people in minde of their office and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to God, their Prince and countrie. And now to proceede as one alwayes willing and desirous what in me lyeth, to further the glorie of God, and profite his children: I haue at length fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed this my first pretended worke: as a meane to incourage, strengthen &amp; direct in the right path to eternal felicity, such weary wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dring Pilgrims: as yet are weake in faith, doubtfull in conscience, or distressed in minde. Crauing thus much at thy handes (courteous Reader) that if it shall please the Lorde in mercie so effectually to blesse and fructifie these my simple trauailes, as by the helpe and meanes thereof, thou shalt conceiue in thy soule that spirituall comfort and heauenly conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, which in heart I wish thee: then yeelde dutifull thankes to the highest, and charitably pray for me.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>vale in Christo. L. Wright.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="tcp:2941:4"/>THE PILGRIMAGE to Paradise.</head>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>Chapter 1. He that in Paradise wil taist the fruites of Diuinity, must first learne to know himselfe in the schole of humility.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Vmility is a vertue sprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging from the feare of God: the mother of meekenesse: and sister of deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which no man can at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the knowledge and feeling of his owne misery in <hi>Adam: &amp;</hi> felicity in Christ. A Birde, except her winges be mooued down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, can not flye vp to the top of an hill: nor man, except the affections of his hart be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled downwards: mount vp to the towre of diuine vnderstanding. And therfore that god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father S. <hi>Augustine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Augustin de ciuitate Dei.</hi>
               </note> compareth heauen vnto a faire stately Pallace, with a litle dore: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at no man can enter, except he stoupe very low.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2941:5"/>
As who should say, God reiecteth the proude, and giueth grace to the humble and lowlye.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psalm.</hi> 51.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The true wisedome of a Christian Pilgram, consisteth espetia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly, in the knowledge of his owne imperfections. Then are we said to bee righteous (saith <hi>Ierom</hi>) when we acknowledge our selues to be wicked transgressors.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierom</hi> in his first B. against <hi>Pelagius. Augustin.</hi>
               </note> He hath much profited in this life (saith <hi>S. Augustin</hi>) that hath learned how farre he is from perfection of righteousnes.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15</note> For the lesse opinion a man hath of himselfe: the more trust he hath in God. And the more he feeleth in his conscience, the horror of hell:<note place="margin">Those that feel not the horror of hell, passe litle for the ioyes of heauen. <hi>Psal.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.17.</note> the nearer he is to the ioyes of Heauen. None so neare, as the humble penitent, whose hart is most deepely wounded with the gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uousnes of sinnes: nor none so farre from true religion, as he who thinketh himselfe most per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and very religious.</p>
            <p>The ioyes of Paradise are prepared, not for proud presumptuous Pharasyes, who seeme in their owne Eyes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.</note> most iust, pure and perfect: but poore humble Publicans, that iustly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne, themselues, as most vile, miserable and wretched. The Sunne of man came not to call the righteous:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 5.32.19, 10.15 23.24</note> but sinners to repentance. To seeke vp none, but those that do acknowledge themselues to bee lost. To comfort and to raise vp none with his Gospel: but those which bee discomforted, and cast downe by the law. Nor to annoint and heale none with his oyle of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2941:5"/>
gladnes, but such broken and contrit hartes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esi.</hi> 61.</note> as (for griefe of synnes) are sicke and mourne in syon.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>Chapter II. Of the lothsome deformity of nature through A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams fall.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Naturall man consisteth of three partes The spirit,<note place="margin">As <hi>Adam</hi> in Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed</note> or immortall soule, endued with reason, will,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Th.</hi> 5.23. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11.</note> and diuine vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing. The naturall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, or powers of the soule: as indifferent spurres to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke, stirre vp, and pricke forward vnto vertue,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 8.5.13.</note>
               <figure/>
or vice: and the terrestriall body,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 7.23. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Gala.</hi> 5.17.</note> wherein Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan (by tempting of <hi>Adam</hi>) hath written the law of sinne.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:2941:6"/>All which parts of man (at the fyrst) were in such perfect order and conco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, framed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: as nether the immortall spirit did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue any thing: the naturall powers of the soule desyre any thing: nor the terrestriall body, execute any thing, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the wil of God. All creatures vnder heauen, being obedient to the body of man: as the subiects to the Prince. The naturall body, obedient to the reasonable soule: as the seruant to the maister. And the reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble soule, with his affections, obedient to God the Creator: as the child to the father: till that cursed serpent our mortall enemie, found means to set them at variance,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.41.</note> and discord. Synce which time, the nature of man became so fraill and weake: the occasions vnto euill, so many: and the illusion of Satan,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.</note> so prompt, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: that except, Gods special grace preu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt him: he is apt and prone vpon euery light occasion, to yeeld vnto sinne, and wickednes. Being more easily brought to con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaue an error, by one little word: then the truth by a long tale. And sooner seduced to consent vnto vice, by one small exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: then conuerted vnto vertue, by many vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment perswasions.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.17.24</note>And as the Iewish Church was likened vnto a garden Oliue tree: whose branches in time, growing baren: were cutt off, as vnprofitable. And the gentles though by nature wild oliues: yet being grafted in the same, were by grace,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2941:6"/>
made fruitfull. So is euery naturall man very aptly compared vnto a wild &amp; bitter crab-tree. And as Abraham was remoued from the forest of <hi>Babilonia</hi>:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.</note> and replanted in the fruitfull gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of Canaan.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Moses</hi> from the wood of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raos</hi> court: to the fieldes of Madian hils. And the Israelites from their hellish bondage in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt, through the red sea:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. <hi>Psal.</hi> 80.8.</note> to the florishing land of promise. So must euery child of <hi>Adam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.5.6 <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.13. <hi>Colo.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14 <hi>Titus</hi> 2.15.</note> bee remoued from the wild Wood of nature: And (by baptim) replanted in the fruitfull orchard of grace: regrafted with the sweete Garden imps of true christian doctrine: and (with the pruning knife of ecclesiasticall discipline) haue thei superfluous branches of sinne and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, daily clensed and cut away:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 3.10.</note> or they cannot bring forth true spirituall fruits, acceptable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gods diuine tast.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>Chapter 3. Of the miserie of Adams brats, and vanitie of the world.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuch as (of all other vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) that olde rooted infection of pride, vaineglorie, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption, is most vniuersallie grafted in man: there is no thing more necessarie or profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to suppresse and subdue his hautie affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2941:7"/>
then continuall remembrance what he is: from whence he came: and whether hee shall. That in calling to minde,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 7.</note> his base mettall: his wretched condition: and mortall generation: he may the rather be moued, more humblie, and lowlie, to conceiue and esteeme of himselfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality.</note>What is man? <hi>telluris inutile pondus</hi>: an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable lump of earth: like as one might saie to a peece of yse: thou wast water: thou art wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: and to water thou shalt turne againe. So man was earth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</note> he is earth: and to earth hee shall turne againe. Thou hast fashioned mee of mould and earth (saith <hi>Iob</hi>:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 10.30.</note>) and I am become like dust and ashes. <hi>Oh homo</hi> (saith <hi>Chriso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome) si consideras, quid per o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, quid per nares, quid per ceteros meatus egrediatur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chrisost.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>nunquam vilius ster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilium inuenisti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is man? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is matter is base, slime, and clay: his nature weake, and feeble: his birth paine, and sorow: his life vaine, and miserable: his state sliperie, &amp; vncertaine: his time short, and tedious: his sinnes horrible, and filthie: and his ende, greeuous and lothsome.</p>
            <p>What is man? A mirror of miserie: a play of fortune:<note place="margin">He is born in teares, groweth vp in sighs, liueth in paine, and dyeth in griefe.</note> and a pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y of death. He is borne weping and wailing, to shew his wretchednes: he liueth laughing and toying, to bewraie his folly: and dieth sighing, and sob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, to declare his weake infirmitie.</p>
            <p>What is man? <hi>Appulius</hi> a Philosopher, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2941:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
scholler to <hi>Plato</hi>: describeth him in this wise. Me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (saith he:) are liuing creatures, dwelling vpon the earth: hauing soules immortall: brutish ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile bodies, subiect to death: light careful minds apt to errour: vaine in labours: diuers in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions: long or they bee wise: their time but short: and during life neuer content.</p>
            <p>What is the state of man? Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> describeth it in this maner. There commeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thine eies (saith he) a man, poore, naked, and miserable: mourning that he is a man: blushing that he is naked: weeping for that he is a wretch replenished with miserie and feare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ull for that his t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me is but sho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t. A great part of his life pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth away in doing that is euill: a greater part in doing nothing: and the greatest part, in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thinges to small purpose.</p>
            <p>And as the life of man is vaine, transitorie, and miserable: euen so is the world: with all thinges else, wherein humaine nature taketh pleasure and delight: as health, wealth, honor,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 39.6. <hi>Preach.</hi> 2.</note> wisedome, strength, beautie, or whatsoeuer.</p>
            <p>What is the world? A vaile of miserie: A sinck of sinne: a mould of mischiefe: a den of theeues: a court of Satan: a purgatorie of paine: a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the wicked: and a stepdame to the good. Where the proud and vitious are daily advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced without desert: and the humble and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous oppressed without cause: the weiwarde and seditious befrended, and the quiet and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2941:8"/>
molested: the ignorant and foolish permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to speake: and the wise and discreete put to silence: crafty dissemblers extolled: and simple in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siocents dispised.</p>
            <p>What is the world? A second hell: full of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious desires: couetuous conceates: carefull studies: wicked willes: and diuelish intents. A cruell serpent that biteth vs with her teeth: scratcheth vs with her nailes: and swelleth vs with her poison. Much like the deceitful <hi>Laban.</hi> Who made poore <hi>Iacob</hi> serue seauen yeares for faire <hi>Rachell</hi>: and in the ende, deceiued him with foule <hi>Lea.</hi> Euen so the world promiseth health, wealth, and long life: and in the ende, deceiueth vs with pouertie, sicknes, and death.</p>
            <p>What is the world? Her mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th is but sorow: her pleasure, but paine: her wisedome but foolish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: and her wealth but misery. Where nothing is to be looked for, but euen a rancke of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, one folowing in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>others necke. A great trauell is created for all men, (saith <hi>Iesus Sirach</hi>) and a heauie yoake vpon all mens c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ildren.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccles.</hi> 40.</note> Some so p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nched with pouerty &amp; oppressed with miserie: Some tossed and turntoiled with strife, and contention: some tormented with sickenes, sores, and contagious diseases: that if an olde man shoulde set forth the tragidie of his life, from the daie of his birth,<note place="margin">As yeares diminish. so troubles increase.</note> till his departure to the graue: a man would wonder that the bodie could suffer, and the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>art could beare, so paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2941:8"/>
and dolorus a pilgrimage.</p>
            <p>All the godly from the beginning haue tasted the troubles of their time. Adam felt his part of miserie: when his children did one kill an other, and saw the fall of his posterity, 900. yeares. <hi>Abraham</hi> felt his part of miserie: when at Gods commaundement he wandred into a straunge countrie, and suffered great troubles.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>Iob</hi> felt his part of miserie: when hee sawe the spoyle and hauocke of all his goods: the distruction of his children: and his owne bodie (from toppe to toe) tormented with botches and sores: hauing nothing remaining but his wicked wise: who seemed to be left of the deuill: not to comfort, but vexe and tempt him, to blaspheme God. <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seph</hi> felt his part of miserie:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 38.</note> when he was solde of his brother, and impr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>soned without cause. <hi>Noah</hi> felt his part of miserie: being grieuouslye mocked and persecuted of the wicked. Poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> was both sicke, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, hungry and thirsty.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.</note> Father <hi>Iacob.</hi> complayned that his daies were fewe and euill. <hi>Dauid</hi> said hee was a worme, and no man. <hi>Solomon</hi> was weary of his life: because all that euer he saw vnder the Sunne: was nothing but vanitie, miserie, and vexation of minde. Father <hi>Ierom</hi> complayned, that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan sought to ouerthrowe him: and that his weake fleshe was readie to consent.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 15.20.</note> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremy</hi> cursed the daye of his birth. <hi>Ionas</hi> said, it was better for h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m to die, then liue.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2941:9"/>
               <hi>Chrisostome</hi> called the daies of his life, the daies of his sorrowe. <hi>Naziensen</hi> wept that his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had brought him forth, to see such misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble daies. Such trauell hath God giuen vnto men vnder the sunne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Preach.</hi> 1.</note> to be exercised therin.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>Chapter IIII. Of the breuitye of mans life, and certaintye of Death.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd as the dayes of this our painefull pilgrimage, are vayne, and miserable: so are they short and tedious. The one foote no sooner on the ground: but the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther readie to slip into the graue. Man that is borne of woman (saith <hi>Iob</hi>) hath but a short time to liue,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 14.</note> and is full of miserie. He springeth as a flower: fadeth like a shadowe: and neuer continueth in one state.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 9.</note> My daies (saith he) are more swifte then a runner. We bring our yeares to an ende (saith <hi>Dauid</hi>) as it were a tale that is tolde. We are dying con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually all our life long: euery yeare, day, and houre. Our infancie lasteth a small while, and dyeth. Our youth florisheth a time, and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth. Our manhood a time, and departeth. Our age a time, and by and by it is gone. The dayes<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 90.</note> of our life (saith the Psalmist) are three-score
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2941:9"/>
yeares and tenne: and though men bee so strong, that they rubbe out till foure score: yet is their strength then but labour, and sorrow: so soone passeth it away, and we are gone. The life of man is aptly compared to a vapour: to the trace of a cloude:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>VVis.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> to a shippe passing ouer the waues of the sea,<note place="margin">Vpon this condition we came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world to leaue it againe.</note> tossed and beaten with tempest: to a birde that flyeth in the aire: or a shaft that is shot at a marke, and neuer staieth till it light vpon the ground. Euen so, man, assoone as he is borne, beginneth immediately, to draw to his ende.</p>
            <p>The godly Patriarkes who liued in the firste age of the world, saw many yeares: yet at last the dyed. Death was alwaies the ende of their song. <hi>Adam</hi> lyued 930-yeares: <hi>Seath</hi> 912: <hi>Enoch,</hi> 905: <hi>Kenan</hi> 910: <hi>Mahelaell,</hi> 895: <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> 962: <hi>Mathusala,</hi> 969: <hi>Lamech,</hi> 777: <hi>Noah,</hi> 950: and they died saith the text. <hi>ABraham,</hi> the father of the faithfull: <hi>Dauid,</hi> a man according to Gods owne hart: <hi>Iohn Baptist,</hi> of whom our Sauiour Christ said, there hath not risen a greater amongst the children of women: y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t they dyed. All the Prophets, Apostles, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly martires, were greatly in Gods fauour: yet they died. Rich and poore, wisemen and fooles: learned and ignorant: godly and vngodly: all must follow the dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of death. Many are gone before: the rest must followe after: when God doth call nature must obey. Wise <hi>Salomon,</hi> rich
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2941:10"/>
               <hi>Iob,</hi> strong <hi>Sampson,</hi> and faire <hi>Absolon,</hi> haue trode the path of all flesh. Great <hi>Alexander</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered the whole world: yet could hee finde no weapon to conquer death. The stiffest steele yeeldeth to the hammer: the strongest oake to the axe: and the stoutest heart vnto nature. And therefore, king <hi>Phillip</hi> of <hi>Macedonia</hi> wallowing in worldly wealth, and prosperity: commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his chamberlaine, euery daye at his vp ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing: sadly to repeate vnto him these wordes. Remember king <hi>Phillip,</hi> and forget not, that thou art a man, subiect to mortality. All flesh is grasse: and euerye man, the flower of the grasse: the grasse shall be withered, and the flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer shall fall away.</p>
            <p>And as death is a thing of all other most cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and sure: so is the time of d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath most vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine and doubtfull.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Preach.</hi> 9.13</note> The Lord in his word hath reuea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed vnto man, many notable lessons, touch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng the knowledge of his w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll: yet not the day of death: b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cause he would haue vs liue so, as euery day mig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t be the day of death. Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that as the course of this life, is the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death: so is death the gate to eternal life. And therefore, as at night, we do willingly put of our garments: in hope the next morning to put them on againe:<note place="margin">He that wil liue, must learne to die.</note> so ought wee willingly to put of these our mortall bodies: assuring our selues that after we haue slept a while in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e dust: to receiue them againe immortall.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:2941:10"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>O homo Nosce Teipsum</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Behold thy selfe by me, such one was I as thou, &amp; thou in time shalt be euen dust as I am now.</note>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:2941:11"/>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.24</note>The wheat and other seede, though it dye and rot in the ground: yet springeth vp more beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful then before It is written how certain sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer birds lye dead all winter,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plinie.</hi>
               </note> and reuiue in the spring.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lactantius.</hi>
               </note> The Phenix being burnt vnto ashes, yet of the same ashes is bred to liue againe.
<q>
                  <l>So though our bodies layd shall be, to rot in lothsome graue:</l>
                  <l>Yet afterwards in glorious state, more bewty they shall haue:</l>
                  <l>When death hath held them downe awhile.</l>
                  <l>Anon they shall arise,</l>
                  <l>Eternally in ioy to liue</l>
                  <l>With Christ aboue the skyes.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>Chapter V. The passage to Paradise is aptly compared to a warfare.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Lato</hi> calleth a Philosophers life, a meditation of death. But it may truly be said, that the whole race of a Christian mans life: is nothing else, but a continuall warfare.<note place="margin">Beginning and ending in the hart.</note> For as the Israelites by bodily resistance, did assaile, fyght against, and ouercome seuen Nations, before they could ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a temporall inheritance, in the land of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan: so must Gods children, by spirituall resis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.1.</note> assaile, fight against, and ouercome their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2941:11"/>
lewd lustes, wicked, appetits,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11</note> and fleshly affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, with the hole host of vic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s: enemies most odious to God, and dangerous to man:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames</hi> 4.1.</note> before they can come to inioy their eternall inheritance in the kingdome of heauen.<note place="margin">The more contrary man is to himself, the more agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the will of God.</note>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>The chiefe Captaine generall</hi> in this conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall conflict, is the mighty Lion of the tribe of Iuda: the prince of peace: the conqueror of death, hell, and sinne: the great Iudge of the world, and bishop of our soules: which is Christ himselfe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:2941:12"/>
               <hi>The grande Captaine of our ennemyes part:</hi> is the great red Dragon: the old crafty serpent: the deceauer of the world: accuser of his brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren: and gouernor of darknes: which is Satan himselfe. Mighty in power: subtil in pollicy: &amp; skilfull in war. Apt and ready (what in him ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) to hinder the glory of God, and saluation of man.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.</note> Who (like a ramping and roring lyon, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king continually whom he may deuoure) know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth how to vse both riches and pouerty, prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and aduersity health and sicknesse: strength and weakenes, bewty and deformity, as instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and weapons, to serue his purpose. Hee tempted <hi>Adam,</hi> to eate the forb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fruit: <hi>Aaron,</hi> to make the golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Calfe: <hi>Dauid,</hi> to commit adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and murther: <hi>Iudas,</hi> to betray Christ: &amp; <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> to forsweare him.</p>
            <p>He is the prince of this world: hauing all those which are without or against Christ: either by ignorance, not knowing him: or by heathenish life, not following him: or by violence resist<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng him: at his b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cke, to take part against vs, with tooth and naile.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lieutenants of the field:</hi> are fleshly sensu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality, against spir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tuall reason.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Sargeants of the band</hi>: the cursed children of darknes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6 12.</note> against the faithful ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ldren of light.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The common souldiers</hi>: the law of our mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, against the law of our mind: the effectes of the flesh, ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e fruites of the spirite:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2941:12"/>
oppression and wrong, against right and iustice: subtill craft, and deceit,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gala.</hi> 5.</note> against true simple mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: pride and presumption, against humility and lowlines: and all other vice against ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>Chapter VI. The armour and weapons of a Christian Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow forasmuch as our enimies, the children of the world: are more subtill, craftie, and poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke in their generation, then the children of God:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.24.</note> able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue (if it were possible) euen the very elect. Satan can transfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me himselfe into an Angell of light. <hi>Pharaos</hi> sorserers could work maruelous strange wonders:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 7.</note> turne a rod to a Serpent: water into bloud: and make quick Frogs. It is written that <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> could by sorserye flye in the aire: turne stones into bread: make quicke Serpents of brasse: sicles to rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e corne without hands: Images of stone to laugh: and dogges to sing.</p>
            <p>And being so many in number, as which way soeuer we turne, be sure to haue one enimie or other to incounter with vs. At our right hand, the world, the flesh, and the deuill watcheth to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2941:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
intice vs to our vtter distruction. At our left hand, aduersitie, pouertie and affliction of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die is readie to cast vs downe, into the dunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of dispaire. Behinde vs, our sinnes are at hand, to bewray vs. Within vs, our owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, belaieth to accuse vs. Before vs, are Gods iudgements read<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to condemne vs: and hell mouth open to deuour vs.</p>
            <p>And seeing also that the soldiours of Satan, are so mightie in force, and strongly armed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst vs: hauing on the brest plate of iniury: the girdle of falshood: the shoes of discord: the sheeld of infidelity: the helmet of mistrust: the pearcing dartes of crueltie: the cannon shotte of spitefull reproches: the arrowes of lying slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: and the sworde of the flesh, which is the doctrine of man: seeking continually to tempt, peruert, and vtterly confound vs.</p>
            <p>To resist their tyranny therefore, it standeth vs in hand to be also well and strongly armed, with the brestplate of equitie: the shielde of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted faith in Christ: the helmet of assured hope:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6.</note> the shoes of knowledge, and peace in the holy Ghost: the girdle of truth, well buckled with patience, and constancie: the cannon shotte of deepe sighes proceeding from a true penitent heart: the arrowes of bitter teares, brought forth by remorse of conscience: the pearcing dartes of humble fasting: deuout praying, chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table giuing, and vertuous liuing: and the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2941:13"/>
two edged sworde of the eternall word of God: which is liuely in operation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12.</note> &amp; entreth through euen to the diuiding of the soule, and the spirite: and the ioyntes, and the marow. Mighty and strong to cast downe holdes, and ouerthrow the imaginations of euerye thing that exalteth it selfe against the knowledge of God:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.41.5</note> and bring into captiuity euery thought to the obedience of Christ.</p>
            <p>In which spirituall conflic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, are three kinds of soldiours. Some painefull warriours: placed for a time, to be tryed in this irkesome vale of miserie, on earth. Some triumphat conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours: for whom is appointed a crowne of vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, in the glorious kingdome of heauen. And some cowardly fugitiues: for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are reserued most greeuous torments, in the lothsome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of hell. For as that professed soldiour,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esay</hi> 24.</note> which in time of battaile doth flye the field: and suffer his captaine amongst his enimies, to be buffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and beaten downe: is but a dastardlye co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, worthy of death: so that professed christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, which in time of persecution, and trouble,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 10.28.32. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.9.10.</note> doth flye the spirituall combat, and suffer Christ his louing redeemer, amongst his enimies, to be buffited, and borne downe: is but a dastardly hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, worthy of eternall torments.</p>
            <p>Forasmuch therefore, as he is nowe readie comming in mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>stie, and honor to muster,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.37. <hi>Math.</hi> 25.3</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and crowne with glorie his conquering
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2941:14"/>
soldiours: and punish with seuerity, all coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fugitiues: whose signes and tokens (as mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sengers) being alreadie come before: to shewe that himselfe is not farre behind. It standeth vs vpon, to keepe our battle ray orderly: fight valiantly: watch carefully: pray hartily: belieue faithfully: hope assuredly: indure constantly: and march on charitably: to stand fast: perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and quite our selues like men: the quarrell is Gods:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.13.</note> the victorie ours: the ende, the salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our soules. Let vs keep am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ane course: as it were betwixt <hi>Silla</hi> and <hi>Caribdes:</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption, and desperation: traueling our paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full pilgrimage in humble obedience,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12.</note> with feare and trembling: alwaies ready to do our best, and trusting in Christ to performe the rest.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>Chapter VII. He that in Paradise will come to ioy with Christ, must trauell with patience vnder the crosse of Christ.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the Israelits could not come to the land of promise,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.</note> but by long painefull trauell through the wildernes: no more can we come to the promised land of rest:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 14.22.</note> but by long painefull trauel through the wildernes of tribulation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:2941:14"/>The law of <hi>Adams</hi> children, is to liue in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</note> and the curse of <hi>Eues</hi> brats to suffer afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: yea all mankinde do feele the biting of the serpent.</p>
            <p>Our elders in times past,<note place="margin">Though these &amp; such other familiar ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples may profitably bee vsed, to helpe the weake ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of the simple: yet no man ought to ground his conscience vpon the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention of man, which may erre: but the truth of God which can not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue.</note> before they learned their A B.C. (to put them in mind of their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) began alwaies their fyrst lesson with Christs crosse. Who in building their churches, did imitat the fashion of <hi>Salomons</hi> temple: so as the bodies thereof, might seeme to represent the church militant: and the chancell, the church triumphant. And in the time of ignorance, was placed right ouer the doore betweene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a Rood, or crosse of wood: to signify, that there is no way left vs to passe from the one to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but onely vnder the crosse of our louing Redeemer.</p>
            <p>He that will tast of his glory in heauen, must first be partaker of his cuppe vpon earth. Hee that after death will reioyce at his presence,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.3.</note> must first in his life time mourne for his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence. Hee that will imbrace him in his diuine robes of honor, must thinke no skorne of his earthly ragges of contempt.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.26.</note> Whosoeuer is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shamed of his crosse in this life,<note place="margin">Hee that will be crowned, must not grudge to be crossed.</note> he will bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shamed of him in the life to come. Hee can not passe from ioy to ioy, but ether from earthly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sery, to heauenly felicity: or else from earthly fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity, to infernall extremity. There is no other way left for the members,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.27.</note> then to follow their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2941:15"/>
head.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.24.25.</note> The Disciple is not aboue his maister: nor the seruant aboue his Lord. Seeing the good man of the house hath beene called Belsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bub,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.34.</note> glutton, and a companion of the wicked: how can the seruants looke for better entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
            <p>If the Prophets, Apostles, and godly Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirs of the primitiue Church, (who suffred so pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently the persecutions and troubles of their time) might haue come to the ioyes of heauen, by liuing here at ease in sensual pleasure and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity: they were madde men so to dispise the world, and afflict their bodies as they did. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>say</hi> had his carkas cut a sunder with a woodden saw.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>Amos</hi> thrust into the temples with a naile. <hi>Iohn Baptist,</hi> beheaded. <hi>Daniel</hi> condemned to be eaten of Lyons.<note place="margin">All that will liue godly in Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, must suffer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12.</note> The three Israelites, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the flam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng fyre. <hi>Ieremie</hi> and <hi>Steeuen</hi> stoned to death. <hi>Paul,</hi> beh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aded. <hi>Thomas</hi> (prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Ghospell in India) slaine with a Dart. And <hi>Symon Zelots</hi> preaching in Britany, was there crucifyed, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But these valiant and victorious conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, were w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll assured, that prosperity and aduersity, riches and poue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty, life and death, are all Gods giftes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames</hi> 1.3.4</note> to trye, the hartes of men.</p>
            <p>That godly and valian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p on <hi>Ignatius,</hi> scholler to <hi>Iohn,</hi> and Byshop of Antioch, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing condemned for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Gospell, to be torne and deuoured of wild <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sses:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ignatius an. dom.</hi> 80.</note> brast sodenly out in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2941:15"/>
these words. So I may finde Christ (saith he) I passe neyther for beastes, teeth, fyre, Iebet, crashing my bones, renting my body, nor all the cruell torments, the Deuill and his instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments can inuent.. Who in the middest of his greeuous panges, did valiantly comfort him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, saying: <hi>Iam incipio esse discipulus Christi.</hi> For as a Noble mans seruant is knowen by his maisters cognisance:<note place="margin">Let no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> count that a greeuous misery, which Christ hath left as a badge of his bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing.</note> so is a faithfull Christian by bearing his crosse with patience.</p>
            <p>It is written how a certaine Pagan on a time vsyng great iniury and outrage against a godly christ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an, asked him in great disdaine, what fruit or profyt he receiued by his Christ. Is not this a singuler profyte (quoth he) that for all the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tants cruell in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urie,<note place="margin">An exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> and grieuous outrage against mee, yet I do patiently suffer, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly pardon thee without reuenge?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>Chapter VIII. Of true repentance with her inseperable furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Epentance is an inward sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, compunction, and mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the hart,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 51.17. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10</note> and conscience for sinnes committed: and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth three partes. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition of heart, confession of mouth, and reformation of life.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.8.9.10.</note> Lyke as a man feeling his body greeuously<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 3.8.</note>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:2941:16"/>
infected with sicknes doth first acknowledge his disease: secondly, seeke to the Phisition for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie: and thirdly, being cured, is carefull to temper his diet, and keepe his body from surfet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againe. So is it the manner and duty of euery christian Pilgram, feeling his soule sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feted with sinnes: first by earnest repentance to acknowledge his owne wickednes: secondly by humble, faithfull, and deuout praier to seeke vnto Christ for pardon: and thirdly by restrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and subduing his fleshly appetits and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly affections, to keepe himselfe from falling againe. And as when the aire is one cast with stormes, the Sunne darkened with tempest, the clowds torne with thunder, and the ground bed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wed with raine, straight followeth calme and faire wether. So when a penitent christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, feeling his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>science burthened with sinnes, doth humbly bewaile and confesse his faultes: the teares (like drops of raine) trickling downe his cheekes, with groning, sighing and sobbing vnto God for mercy: at last, by earnest, faithful, and deuout praier, being easily entreated and wonne: straight followeth pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Christ com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of conscience, and quietnesse of mind.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psalm.</hi> 40.</note>In this manner the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> confessed his sinnes to be more in number, then the hairs of his head.<note place="margin">4 <hi>Kings.</hi> 20</note> 
               <hi>Manasses</hi> bowing the knees of his hart vnto God, confessed his faultes to be more then the sandes of the Sea. <hi>Ezechias</hi> turned
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2941:16"/>
his face to the wall, and mourned heauily. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Magdalyn</hi> fell downe behinde Iesus,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented pitifully. <hi>Peter</hi> remembring the words of Christ, after he had for sworne him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.71.</note> went out and wept bitterly. Which godly conuersion (for that it seemeth greeuous and painfull to flesh and bloud, so to resist and striue against the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of nature) is of some called penance. For Christ neuer assigned any other penance or satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for synnes:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 8.11.</note> but goe thy way and synne no more.</p>
            <p>Thus wheresoeuer true repentance with her inseperable furniture (as humble confession: faithfull prayer, and amendment of life) goeth before: their remission of sinnes (belonging only to penitent synners) do alwaies follow after. And wher acknowledging of sinnes leadeth not the way:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.3.</note> there the gates of Gods mercy is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes shutte.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>Chapter IX. Of Confession of sinnes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here be foure manner of confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions allowed before God.</p>
            <p>The fyrst is publike: as when for some notorious crime com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted) the church is greeuously offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded: the gilty offender ought then to come forth in open assembly, and there
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2941:17"/>
(with an vnfained shew of repentance,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.3.9</note> and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest desire of pardon) to make confession of his fault. Humble thy selfe (saith sainct <hi>Ambrose</hi>) and intreat thy mother,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ambrose</hi> in his 2. B. of repentance Chap. 10.</note> the church of GOD to weepe for thee, and wash away thine offences with her teares.</p>
            <p>The second is, when one priuate person (by word or deede) hath done iniury, hurt, or wrong vnto an other: the party offender ought then in charitable maner to come vnto him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames</hi> 5.16. <hi>Math</hi> 5.23.24.</note> confesse his fault, desyre a brotherly reconcillatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and make satisfaction for the iniurie committed. <hi>Non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitur peccatum</hi> (saith <hi>S. Augustine) nisi resti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuatur ablatum</hi>:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>August.</hi>
               </note> that is to say, the fault is not pardoned, without restitution (ether in effect, or affect) to the party offended.</p>
            <p>The third, when a man is distressed in mind, or troubled in conscience, he ought then to resort vnto his pastor, or else some other learned man, whose office and duty is by the word of God,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16 17. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.4.</note> to instruct his mind, resolue his conscience, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort his weaknesse</p>
            <p>The fourth is a daily opening of our hartes in secret before God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 24.</note> The iust man (saith <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>) falleth seauen times, and riseth againe. Who so hideth his sinnes (saith he) shal not pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 28.</note> but he that confesseth and forsaketh them, shall haue mercie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chrisost.</hi> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the 30. Psalm. ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mili. 2.</note>Confesse thy synnes in this life (saith <hi>Chriso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome</hi>) that thou maist haue rest in the life to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2941:17"/>
come: not vnto the Preest,<note place="margin">Auricular confession was fyrst compelled by Pope Innocent. <hi>an. dom.</hi> 1198. <hi>Psalm.</hi> 32.6. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.9.</note> who is but thy felow seruant, but vnto God himselfe, who is able to heale them.</p>
            <p>I sayd I will confesse my sinnes vnto the Lord (saith <hi>Dauid</hi>) and thou forgauest the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednesse of my fault. If wee acknowledge our sinnes (saith the Apostle) God is mercifull and iust to forgiue vs our synnes, and clense vs from all vnrighteousnes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>Chapter X. Of faith, hope, and charity.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Aith is a certainty of thinges, which are not seene:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebru.</hi> 11.1</note> a sure per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion and stedfast consent of the hart and conscience: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with man beleeueth that, which his dull capacity ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend: and is deuided into three kindes.</p>
            <p>The first is called a dead or fruitlesse faith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames.</hi> 2.19.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred only to Deuils &amp; reprobats: who though they beleeue the story of the Bible, and all the articles of the common Creede, except remission of sinnes: yet remaine still in their damnable state.</p>
            <p>The second is to worke miracles:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.6. <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.23.11, 23.</note> as with a certaine assured perswasion, to beleeue that a thing shall come to passe:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 3.16.</note> whereby the Apostles
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2941:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:2941:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:2941:19"/>
did cast out Deuils and heale diseases: Which kind, is common as wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the reprobate as to the elect.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22.23.</note> But the true, liuely, and iustifying faith:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.43.</note> whereby Gods wrath is pacifyed: our sinnes pardoned: our minds lightned: our harts strengthened:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames</hi> 1.6. <hi>Ro.</hi> 8.14.15. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.15.19.</note> our praye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s heard: our requestes granted: and we adopted the children of God, members of Christ, and Temples of the holy ghost:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebru.</hi> 11.6. <hi>Math.</hi> 16.17. <hi>Ro.</hi> 10 17. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.45. <hi>Ro.</hi> 10.10.1.16.</note> without which it is not possible to please him: is a syngular gift of God, whereby his holy spirit (by the preaching of his word and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments) doth seale and conforme in the harts and conscience of his elect, a certaine assured trust:<note place="margin">Which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seedeth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the hart, then the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing of the braine. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.16.</note> that onely by and through the conception, byrth, merits, death, passion, resurrection, assen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; intercession of that pure innocent Lambe Christ Iesus: to haue free pardon &amp; remission of synnes, both originall, and actuall, and raigne with him in glory for euer.</p>
            <p>Pope is an assured, constant, and vnmooua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble expectation: which as an inseperable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 15.4.8.24.</note> doth stedfastly looke and long for the perfourmance of those things,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Titus</hi> 2.13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10, 21.</note> which faith belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to be true: and is therefore called the bloud of faith, and anker of saluation.</p>
            <p>Loue in generall, is a common effect of fauor and affection: and charity is loue, reduced in due order, the handmaid of faith, and mistres of all other vertues.</p>
            <p>And as faith beleeueth the word, and hope
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2941:19"/>
waiteth for the promised reward: so charity see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to helpe, comfort, and releeue her neigh:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 7.12. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4.7.</note> hour. To profit and do good vnto all: and to hurt or hinder none. To loue all men in Christ, and for Christes sake: and to hate none but sin,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.10. <hi>Math.</hi> 5.44. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.35.</note> and for sinnes sake.</p>
            <p>And as the spirite of life, descending from the head, disperseth into euery part of the bodie: so that if any member shall not be partaker there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it cannot liue, but perish terrestrially: euen so the spirite of Christ, (being the head of his Church) so disperseath into euerye member thereof, quickning, knitting, and ioyning them together, by the vertue of concord, loue,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.12. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.35.</note> and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: that if any part, or member shall bee sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, or cut from the same: it cannot liue but pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish eternally.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>Chapter XI. Of prayer and meditation.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S amongst the Iewes in olde time, those beastes onely,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leu.</hi> 11. Prayer must be grounded vpon faith, and faith vpon the word of God.</note> which chew the endde, were counted cleane, and meete for the suste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of man: so those men one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which (by faithfull prayer, and meditation) chew the cudd of their minds: are counted righteous, and meete for the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2941:20"/>
of heauen.</p>
            <p>Meditation is the keye of conscience, which openeth the closet of the heart: and the eye of the soule, whereby she seeth her whole estate, defect, and danger.</p>
            <p>Prayer is an humble lifting vp of the minde vnto God: the fruits of repentance, and foode of faith:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Colo.</hi> 4.2.</note> consisting of two partes: inuocation, and thanksgiuing. Which Christ himselfe, hath not onely in mercy ordained, as the chiefest part of Diuinity: profitably appointed it, as the surest staffe for a christia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pilgrim to s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay vpon:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.38. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1.</note> straight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commaunded it, as the strongest defence for his poore distressed children to flye vnto: and by his owne example confirmed it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.40.41.</note> as the onely meane to obtaine all thinges meete for the vse and profite of man:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 7.8. <hi>Math.</hi> 6.9.</note> but hath also prescribed, an ordinary rule, and firme (as it were his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon store house of wealth and vertue) to direct our praiers according to his owne diuine wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Wherein is contained all thinges necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, both concerning his owne glory: the health of our soules: and preseruation of our bodies. Adding thereunto, a certaine assured promise, confirmed with an othe, and sealed with his owne bloud: that whosoeuer do faithfully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in him: put their trust in his mercy: and depend wholy vpon his prouidence:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.30. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.43. <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.47. <hi>Mark.</hi> 11.34 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.23.</note> shall haue cleane remission of sinn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, and eternall life. And whatsoeuer they shall profitably aske in his
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2941:20"/>
name: he will assuredly here them, and graunt their requestes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 50.</note> Call vpon me in the daye of trouble (saith the Lord:) and I will heare thee, and thou shal praise me. This is the trust that we haue towardes him (saith the Euangelist) that if we aske any thing according to his will,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.14.</note> he heareth vs. If you abide in me, and my wordes abide in you (saith our Sauiour) aske what you will, and it shall be done vnto you.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.7.</note> Whatsoeuer you shall aske in prayer, if you do beleeue (saith he) you shall receiue it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 21, 22.</note> The Lord is nigh vnto all that ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l vpon him (saith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi>) Yea vnto all such as call vpon him faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. I will heare before you call,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 145.</note> yea while you are but euen thinking to speake, saith the Lord.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esay</hi> 65.</note>
            </p>
            <p>As truely as hee heard <hi>Iobes</hi> prayer in the dunghill: <hi>Ieremy,</hi> in the clay p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tte:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 42. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. <hi>Daniel</hi> 6.3. <hi>Ionas</hi> 2. <hi>Act.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>Daniell</hi> in the Lyons denne: the three children, in the flaming fire: <hi>Iona<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in the whales bellye: and <hi>Steuen</hi> vnder the stones: so truely will he heare the rest of his obedient children,<note place="margin">All times, in al places and for all persons. <hi>Iames</hi> 1.6.7</note> that call faithfully vpon him in distresse, and mistrust him not. But hee that doubteth (saith the Apostle) is like a waue of the sea, tost w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th the wind, and carried with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. Neither let that man thinke, that he shall receiue any thing of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Some are not heard,<note place="margin">Like a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per that plaieth one tune and singeth an other.</note> because they pray with lippes onely, without the affections of the hart. Some for vngratefully abusing Gods bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites, as though got by their owne policie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:2941:21"/>Some in praying for superfluity, are iustlye denyed things necessarie. You receiue not (saith the Apostle) because you aske not.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames</hi> 4.2.3</note> And you aske and receiue not: because you aske amisse.</p>
            <p>The matter in prayer lyeth not in much saying, but well saying. It is not in the number of words,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 6.6.7</note> or lowdnesse of voice: but the zealous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of an humble penitent heart:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esay.</hi> 57. <hi>Psal.</hi> 31.</note> and the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent groning desire of a troubl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d spiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e: that as most delicate musicke, pearceth the heauens, and soundeth in Gods sacred eares: as daintie meate pleaseth his diuine tast: and as sweete incence, delighteth his heauenly smell.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Anna</hi> (a figure of the Church) did pray in the Temple:<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 1.</note> her hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t and lippes did moue: but her voyce was not heard: and yet God hard her. So was <hi>Moises</hi> saide to be vehement in prayer,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.</note> when he spake not one word.</p>
            <p>It is moreouer to be obserued: that our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for spirituall giftes, pertaining to the soule, ought alwaies to be absolute, without conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: as well assured of rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on of sinnes, and eternall saluation in Christ, according to his promise. But for temporall thinges pertaining to the bodie: to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e alwaies ioyned with this condition: that if it sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l please his fatherly goodnes, to graunt our petitions. Because wee are ignorant, what is most meete, and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for vs.</p>
            <p>When it pleaseth the Lord to bestowe a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of his children: his custome is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13.</note> first to sti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2941:21"/>
vp their mindes: moue their heartes: and open their lippes, humbly to pray vnto him.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13.</note> And then (as a louing father) so farre as shall further his owne glorie, and their saluation: to graunt their requestes. For whatsoeuer is contrarie, is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t for him to giue: and hurtfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l for vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue.</p>
            <p>And though our prayers be but weake, faint,<note place="margin">For if God shoulde straightly measure mans im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections by the straight rule of his word, the most righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man vpon earth should not be able to stand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him. <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.24. <hi>Math.</hi> 7.6.15 29. <hi>VVisd.</hi> 1.</note> and full of wandring fantasies: y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t in stirring vp our selues, what in vs lyeth: hee will no doubt, put to his helping hand: sharpen our dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s: strengthen our weakenes: pardon our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections: and accept our obedience. But contrariwise: as he is mercifull, so is he iust. As he is liberall, so is he wise. He appeared not vnto <hi>Moises,</hi> before he had runne out of Egypt, vnto the hilles of Madian. Neither will he endewe the hartes of such, with his heauenly consolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: as are yet possessed with worldly vanities. He will not cast pearles before swine: not the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens bread vnto dogges; Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther giue a tast of his treasure where there is no will to receiue it. He will be found of those (saith the wise man) that tempt him not.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:2941:22"/>
            <head>Chapter. XII. Of true abstinence or fasting.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Asting serueth especiallye to three endes. First, to mortify, and subdue the lustes of the flesh. Secondlye, to stirre vp more feruent aptnesse,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tob.</hi> 12.9. <hi>Psal.</hi> 35.13.</note> to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and prayer. And th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rdly, to be a testimony of our inward humility, and duetifull obedience to the will of God.</p>
            <p>We ought to fast (saith S. <hi>Ambrose</hi>) to keepe our bodies from surfetting:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ambrose.</hi>
               </note> and our soules from sinning.</p>
            <p>The diseases of the minde (saith S. <hi>Ierom</hi>) are to be healed with praying:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierom.</hi>
               </note> and the lustes of of the body, with fasting. For euen as a wanton pampered horse, doth striue to cast his rider: so doth a wanton pampered bodie, by nature, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist against reason, and vertue. And as a fat foule with few fethers, is vnapt to flye in the aire: so our praiers (as it were the wings of the soule) without abstinence of bodie:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.37. <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.21.</note> are vnapt to fly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heauen.</p>
            <p>The bodie of an obedient Christian, is the meetest temple wherein the holy Ghost deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to dwell.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19 <hi>Psal.</hi> 51.17.</note> An humble penitent hart, the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2941:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
altar, whereon the Lord taketh pleasure, to receiue our offerings: and the mortifying of our flesh, the most acceptable sacrifice,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.12. <hi>Colo.</hi> 3.5.6</note> to appease the honorable maiestie of our God.</p>
            <p>Yet alwaies prouided, that as he is well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with the abstinence of the godly: so much more with the conuersion of a sinner. Hee is greatly moued with the prayers of the iust: but much more, with the restitution of the iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. He is greatly delighted with the patience of the sicke,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames</hi> 1.3.4 <hi>Iames</hi> 2.15</note> but much more with the charitable hospitality of those that be whole.</p>
            <p>It is good to fast (saith S. <hi>Augustine</hi>) but better to giue almesse.<note place="margin">Augustine in his 64. sermon of time.</note> When the lustes of the flesh are mortifyed: our wronged brother satisfied: and our needy neighbour releeued: then God with our fast is well pleased.</p>
            <q>
               <l>The sicke for lacke of stomach fast </l>
               <l>the poore for want of meate,</l>
               <l>The couetuous chuffe to spare his purse <note place="margin">Augustine in his 41 sermon, in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note>
               </l>
               <l>the glutton more to eate.</l>
               <l>The apish hipocrite for praise </l>
               <l>a good man for his soules health alwaies.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:2941:23"/>
            <head>Chapter XIII. A briefe summe of Christian religion.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the wise men of the East did offer vnto Christ their costlye presents of gold,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 2.11.</note> frankensence, and mirre:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Thes.</hi> 3.8 <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.15 <hi>Act.</hi> 10.4 <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.24. 1. <hi>Thes</hi> 4.3 <hi>Math.</hi> 7.12 6.31.33.</note> so the most pretious thing that we can present vnto him, is the golde of faith, and sure hope: the franckensence of zeale, and true deuotion: and the mirre of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, &amp; charitable liuing. To honor him with due obedience: and depend wholy vpon his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Ioyning alwaies practice with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge deedes, with wordes: keeping, with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: walking with talking: and expressing, with professing.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.13.</note> Knowing that not the hearers of the word, but the doers, shall be iustified. Not euery one that saith vnto me Lord, Lord, shall enter into the kingdome of heauen:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.21. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.17. <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.28.</note> but he that doth the will of my father, which is in heauen. If you vnderstand these things (saith our Sauiour) happy are you if you do them. Blessed are they that heare the word of God, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eepe it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Christian duetie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth in knowledge of the truth, faith in Christ, and obedience to his will.</note>He that heareth the word willingly: vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standeth it rightly: belieueth it faithfuly: learneth it perfectly applyeth it profitably: and keepeth it diligently: shall ioy with Christ assuredly.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2941:23"/>
And this is religion, or godlines, the ground of conscience, and true deuotion.</p>
            <p>The word of God propoundeth; repentance seeketh: prayer findeth: faith apprehendeth: hope assureth: and charity perfourmeth. And where faith neuer doubteth: nor hope neuer shrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth: nor charity neuer ceaseth: there God ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer faileth. And this is the golden chaine of saluation: the true pilgrimage to Paradise, and right ladder to heauen. To know and beleeue the truth, are two winges to flye vnto ioy: and to resist vice, and practise vertue, two legges to walke to felicity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn</hi> heard a voice from heauen saying: bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed are the dead which die in the Lord:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 14.13</note> euen so sayth the spir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, that they rest from their labors, &amp; their works follow them. And he that will die in the Lord, must be carefull to liue in the Lord.</p>
            <p>It is an infallible rule, <hi>qualis vita, finis ita</hi>: to him that liueth vertuously. God doth alwayes giue grace to dye faithfully. A ioyful death fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth a charitable life: and a happy life insu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth such a death. So as hee that liueth to dye well, shall surely die to liue better: whereas he that will not frame himselfe to honor and obay the giuer of his life: is vnworthy to haue or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy his life. And as God in olde tune,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi> 21.</note> was not contented to be serued with the blind, lame, and maimed of the flock: so he that carelesly imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the bewty and strength of his youth, in vice,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2941:24"/>
vanity, and seruice of the Deuill: as though old rotten bones, and dregs of age were good y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to vse in the seru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce of God: he seldome granteth either time to liue long, or grace to dye well. Such as liue like wolues, do often dye like swine. Commonly after a dissolute life without feare of death, followeth a desperat death, without hope of life. And it agreeth with all equity, right, and reason, that such as in lewd behauiour haue passed their time:<note place="margin">A wicked life deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth a shamefull death.</note> should by ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of iustice receiue their end.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <head>Chapter XIIII. An exhortation to indure constant in time of try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is required in a true chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Pilgram, to be wel and strongly armed with patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and girt with constancy, to abide firme and stable in the time of temptation and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 8.36.38 39.</note> so as nether prosperity, nor aduersity, well, nor woe, life nor death, can once moue, quaile, or discorage him.</p>
            <p>Worldly riches are subiect to many mishaps: bodily strength is taken away by sicknes: and by age that dayly cree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es on, bewty is soone consumed: but a true constant mind, comforted
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2941:24"/>
by Gods holy spirit: no chance or misfortune can alter or quall. <hi>Elias</hi> in the desert, <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> in the wildernesse, and <hi>Peeter</hi> in prison with the rest of the Apostles in time of their pilgrimage, had but simple clothing, but the loines of their minds were we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l &amp; surely gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t. Whose commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of Christ himselfe are very great: yet not so much for leauing their parents, frendes, goods, and countrie to followe him: nether for their strait kinde of liuing, or valiant corage in preaching: as for that they continued constant to the end. You are they that haue byden with mee in my temptation (saith he) and I will giue you a kingdome: bee faithfull to the end,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.29.</note>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.7.</note> and I will giue you a crown of life. He that ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, shall possesse all thinges, and I will be his God, and he shall be my sonne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.7.</note> and shall eate of the tree of life, which is in the middest of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise of God. But hee that taketh the Plough in hand, and looke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h back,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.62. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> is vnmeete for the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen. Not euery one that runneth: but he that commeth to the end of the gole,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.24 25.</note> hath the garlande. Not euery one that worketh in the vine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ard: but he that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinueth vntil night,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 20.</note> hath the penny. Not euery one that fighteth: but he that getteth the victory, hath the crowne of triumph. Not euery one that beginneth wel,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.22</note> and doth good for a time: but hee that indureth to the end shall be saued.</p>
            <p>When the Angell had wrestled and night with<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:2941:25"/>
               <hi>Iacob</hi>: at last because it drue neere day, desyred to depart: (no quoth <hi>Iacob</hi>) I will not let thee go before thou blesse me. <hi>Iacob</hi> by faith preuailed, and was therefore called Israel (that is to say) one that preuaileth with God: so all that wil be taken at the last day for true christia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Israelites: must by faithfull prayer, patience and constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, preuaile with God.</p>
            <p>To become a Citizen of heauen, is an office of great honor: and no small matter to obtaine so high a calling. We may not thinke to haue that at the fyrst chop, which all the godly before vs haue obtained in long time: with great trobles, greeuous crosses, and many tears. An Oke springeth vp by litle and litle in great space of yeares: and cut downe againe by many small strokes. The soft drops of water, by often fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, do pierce through the hardest stone. By continuall perswasion, the hardnes of mans hart is molifyed: and by continuall prayers our God is easily intreated. Without great labor and long sute, a worldly benefyte is not obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at an earthly kings hands: so many we think our selues most happy and blessed: if (when we haue paciently waited in hope, with cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nuall praying and intr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ating all the dayes of our life) we may yet at length obtaine our long desired ioyes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 10 20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Happy and blessed is hee whom the father of mercy endueth with his interior grace: so to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2941:25"/>
worke, runne, and perseuer: as in the ende hee may say with the Apostle:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7.</note> I haue fought a good fyght: and got the victory. I haue finished my course: and woon the prise. Christ is to me life: and death to mee aduantage. To him with the Father, and the holy Ghost, be all honor, glory, and thankes for euer.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <head>Chapter XV. A comfortable consolation to the faithfull troope of Christian Pilgrams.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Lucke vp thy hart, and reioice,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sach.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Psal.</hi> 6.2.9. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.32. <hi>Ihon.</hi> 16.20 33.</note> litle poore dispised flocke: for the Lord hath heard the voice of thy weeping: whose will and pleasure is to giue thee a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>Great are the troubles of the righteous:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psalm.</hi> 33.107.</note> but the Lord himselfe is the defender of their cause, and will deliuer them out of all. One haire of their head shall not perish:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math</hi> 10.30</note> for they are dearely bought. Euen as a Father pittieth his owne sonne:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 103.</note> so is our God mercifull vnto them that feare him. The naturall infirmities of man, are not hid from his eies: he knoweth whereof we are made: he remembreth that we are but dust.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 116.13.</note> Right deare in the sight of the Lord is the death of his Sainctes. He that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2941:26"/>
toucheth one of his obedient Children, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the apple of his owne eie.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 2. <hi>Esay</hi> 49.</note> Will a wife forget the child of hir wombe, or the sonne that shee hath borne: and though shee do forget, yet wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l not I forget thee, saith the Lord. I haue bene younge,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psalm.</hi> 37.</note> and now am olde (sayth <hi>Dauid</hi>) yet saw I neuer the righteous forsaken: nor his Children begge their bread. Yea, rather then <hi>Helias</hi> shall die for foode: he will prepare the Rauens to feede him.<note place="margin">3 <hi>King.</hi> 17.</note> Rather then <hi>Sampson</hi> shall decay for drinke,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 15.</note> hee will bring water out of an Asses Iawe bone, to refresh him. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then Israell shall starue for hunger: He wil send Manna from Heauen, to norish them. rather then his people shall perish for thirst:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.</note> hee will turne the hard Rocke into a standing water,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deutr.</hi> 8.</note> to comfort them. Rather then any harme shall come vnto his chosen: hee will set his Angels to keepe and preserue them: and carry the poor begger into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Math.</hi> 18.10. <hi>Psalm.</hi> 34. <hi>Euk.</hi> 16.22. <hi>Esay.</hi> 54.</note> The Mountaines shall moue, and the hilles shall fall downe: but my louing kindnes, shall neuer moue, nor fall, saith the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 12.5.1.</note>They that put their trust in him (saith the Prophet) shall be euen as mount Sion, which may not bee remoued, but standeth fast for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor,</hi> 11.32 Not barre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> trees, but fruitful are yerely bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</note>And though our louing Father, whose will and pleasure is, not to cocker his children in this life: but rather to punish their sinnes, that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2941:26"/>
they should not be condempned in the world to come) do feede them for a time,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esay</hi> 30.</note> with the sowre bread of heauinesse, and bitter water of afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: to try them in the fournace of aduersitie:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou</hi> 17.</note> as the potters vessell in the ouen: or gold in the fyer:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 3.11.</note> yet the time of refreshing (no doubt) is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen at hand. He will come shortly, and will not tary: to wipe all teares from their eies: and turne their sorrow,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 7.17. <hi>Esay</hi> 61 <hi>Math.</hi> 16.20</note> and miserie into ioy and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity for euer.</p>
            <p>Whom the Lord loueth, him hee chaste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 3. <hi>Tob.</hi> 12</note> and yet delighteth in him as a father in his sonne. Because thou wast beloued of God (saith the Angell to <hi>Tobias</hi>) it was necessary that temptation should trye thee.</p>
            <p>Lyke as the Heards-man, when any of his flocke are vnruly, and straye from their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes: sendeth forth his dogge not of mallice to hurt on deuoure them: but of loue to saue and refourme them. Euen so our heauenly Shepheard; when his sheepe goe astray, and offende him: hee sendeth out his dogge of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation: not of e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uye to hurt or distroy them: but of fauor to correct and am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd them.</p>
            <p>And as the skilfull Phisitian prescribeth not one manner of dyet, nor one kinde of mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, to all his patients: but onely that which he knoweth most meete for their bodily health, according to the complection of the man, and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2941:27"/>
quality of the disease: so where as God our on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sailfull Phisitian, knowing best what is meet and expedient for the health of all men, both bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and soule: doth giue vnto some prosperity, some aduersity, some health, some sicknes, some quietnes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iams.</hi> 1 12. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.11.</note> and some troubles: it is our duty to rest contented with his will: knowing that hee neuer faileth his children in necessity: nor suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freth them to bee tempted aboue their power.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13</note> Though he maketh a wound (sai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h <hi>Iob</hi>) hee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th a plaister,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 5.</note> and though hee smite, hee maketh hole.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.</note> As in wrastling with <hi>Iacob</hi> with one hande: he did comfort and strengthen him to ouercome with the other.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> So will hee ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther strengthen the rest of his obedient Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13</note> to indure and ouercome their troubles: or else open a way whereby to auoide them. And often times those thinges, which are taken for punishmentes, are rather profitable medecins. For euen as the Nurse, by annointing her brest with Aloes, doth weane hir Infant from suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: so doth God by tribulation and aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity: weane his Children from sensuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deutr</hi> 1.</note>And as <hi>Moses,</hi> by striking the hard stonie Rocke, with his Rodde: brought forth plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Water: euen so GOD by stryking the stony Hart of Man with affliction: bringeth foorth teares of contrition. And as in the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2941:27"/>
Gold-smithes Forge, the golde is fined, while the Coales are burned: so in the Forge of temptation and trouble: the faithfull are try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and fined: while the wicked are hardned and consumed.</p>
            <p>And as the seed, which is cast vpon the land: vnlesse it indure the coldnesse of raine, frost, and snowe: can bring forth no fruit: no more can man:<note place="margin">He that so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in teares shall reape in ioy. <hi>Prou.</hi> 10. <hi>Esay</hi> 51.4.5 52.4.</note> vnlesse he do patiently beare the crosse of tribulation and aduersity: bring forth true fruites of the Gospell. The patient abiding of the righteous (saith <hi>Salomon</hi>) shall be turned into gladnesse. The Lorde correcteth all those whom he loueth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.6. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 3.19.</note> and scourgeth euery sonne that he receiueth. So as there is no greater temptation, then neuer to be tempted: nor sorer whip, then neuer to be scourged.</p>
            <p>Yet such is the naturall infirmitie of man: that it God beginne a little to chastice: wee so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and lament, as though there were none other hell. And if we florish a little in prosperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: we laugh and sing, as though there were none oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r heauen. Hauing more respect, how the world is inclined: then what the Lorde hath commaunded. Whereas wee shoulde not so much regard what we are here: as what here after wee shall bee. Not what we haue now: but what we shall haue, in time to come. For all that Christ dyed for, is yet behinde. His kingdome is not of this world.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2941:28"/>
The effect of his death, is not to make vs flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish in this life. The ioy of Gods children, and sorrow of his enimies, beginneth not till after death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hoc momentum, vnde pendet eternitas.</hi> This is a place of temptation and triall: a moment of time, whereof dependeth eternity of life to come. The figure of this life: withall the glory pompe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.31. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13.</note> and vanity thereof: shall vanish and passe away, and all thinges must be new. New heauen: new earth: new bodies: new mindes: and all thinges new: such as neither eye hath seene: eare hath heard: nor heart hath vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand before.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <head>Chapter XVI. Of the ioyfull state of Gods children after the laste iudgement.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the worlde had a beginning: so shall it haue an ending. The heauens (saith the Apostle) shal passe away in manner of a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.</note> the eliments shall melt with heat: and the earth with all thinges therein contained shall burne with fier, and be consumed. But the Lord will crea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e newe heauens,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esay</hi> 51.8.</note> and a new earth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esay</hi> 65.17.</note> and the former (saith the prophet)
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2941:28"/>
shall not bee remembred nor come to minde.</p>
            <p>I saw (saith the Euangelist) a newe heauen. and a newe earth: for the first heauens,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.</note> and the first earth were passed away, and there was no more sea.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>And I saw the holy citie new Ierusalem,<note place="margin">All things shall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed and restored to the most excellent state of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, as in paradise be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Adams fall.</note> come downe from God, out of heauen, prepared as a bride, trimmed for her husband. And I heard a great voyce out of heauen saying:
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2941:29"/>
beholde the tabernacle of God is with men: and he will dwell with them: and they shall be his people: and he himselfe shall bee their God with them: and shall wipe awaye all teares from their eies. And there shall bee no more death: neither sorrow: neither crying: neither shall there bee any more paine: for the first things are gone. And there shall be no night there:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.5.</note> and they neede no candle, neither light of the sunne, for the Lorde God giueth them light: and they shall raigne for euermore. Thy sonne shall neuer go downe (saith the Prophet) and thy name shall not be taken away:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esay</hi> 60.</note> for the Lorde himselfe shall be thine euerlasting light: and thy sorrowfull daies shall be ended.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esay</hi> 30.</note> The moue (saith he) shall then be as light as the sunne: and the sunne light shall be increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, seauen folde: and haue as much shine as in seauen daies besides.</p>
            <p>And as the newe heauens, and newe earth which I will make,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esay</hi> 66.</note> shall remaine before mee (saith the Lorde) so shall your seede, and your name continue: and from moneth to moneth: and from Saboth to Saboth: shall all fleshe come and worshippe before me (saith the Lord) and they shall go forth, and looke vpon the kar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cases of the men which haue transgressed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst me: for their worme shall not die neither shall their fire be quenched: and they shall be an abhorring vnto all flesh.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:2941:29"/>As the gold is desolued in the fire (saith S. <hi>Augustine</hi>) not to perish,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Augustine de ciuitate dei.</hi>
               </note> but to make it more fine, and pure: so the first heauen, defiled with the pride of Angels: and the first earth cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with the wickednesse of man: shall va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish, passe away, and be no more seene. Not altered in verity, and substance: but changed in fashion, forme, and shape.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.31</note> So as the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, qualitie, and complexion, of corruptible Elemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, agreeable to these our mortall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: shall then be transformed, to agree with our immortall, and purified bodies:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Thes.</hi> 4.16</note> and so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine for euer.</p>
            <p>And as we are now clothed, with the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of <hi>Adams</hi> corruptible bodie,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.48.49.</note> subiect to death and miserie:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.52.53.</note> so shall wee then bee clothed with the Image of Christes glorified bodie, chaunged into perfection and sincerity. When Christ shall appeare (saith the Apostle) wee shall be like vnto him, and see him as he is.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.2.</note> And though wee shall not then, as now:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierom. Mat.</hi> 22.30. <hi>Psal.</hi> 78.25. <hi>Iob.</hi> 19.</note> bee main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and fed with elimentall foode, but as the Angels in heauen:<note place="margin">Not airie spitits but incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bodies. Theodoret in his 2. dialoge. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.38.44. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.39</note> Yet our bodies of the same humaine nature, shape, and fashion, of flesh and bones, with all partes and members of a man, as in this life. Not altered in substance: but chaunged in property. Behold my handes and my feete (saith our Sauiour his Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples) for it is euen I my selfe: handle mee and see: for a spirite hath not flesh and bones as you
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:2941:30"/>
see me haue.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.19 <hi>Anselm. in lib. de simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, Chap.</hi> 48.49.</note>Yet such was his bodie, as he entred the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber where they were assembled, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e dores being shut. <hi>Anselmus</hi> affirmeth that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorifie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to ies of the iust: shall be so pure, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rfect, as may easily pearce or penitrate,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.43. <hi>Daniel</hi> 12.</note> any other body, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out resistance, or danger: and in beaut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e shall shine, as the sunne.</p>
            <p>And as we shall be new men: so shall we haue new sences to vnderstand thinges, not as they seeme:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12.</note> but as they are in deede: And beholde the diuine mysterie of God, face to face. The fruition of whose glorious presence (as the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall fountaine from whence, all wisedome, gladnes, ioye, vertue, and true felicitie, do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede) shall so rauish, content, and satisfie, euery member,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.28. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9.</note> power, and sence of bodie, and minde, with fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l perfection, of pleasure and delight: as neither eie hath seene: eare hath heard: tongue can expresse: nor heart imagine. In compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison whereof: all the va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne pleasures of this world, are but fained shewes, or darke sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes.</p>
            <p>There was in the temple at Ierusalem, and so in the tabernacle, two vales. The first in the sanctuarie: and the second in <hi>sanctum sanctorum.</hi> The outward vale did signifye the couering and concealing of those mysteries, glad tydings, of the Gospell, or doctrine of grace: pertaining to the church militant.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.13.14.18.</note> Which at the death of christ
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2941:30"/>
(to shewe that the same was then reueiled: the fierie sword, which kept the gate of Paradise remoued: and the way to God the Father, vnto all true beleeuers, laid open) did rent and teare in sunder.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.51</note>
            </p>
            <p>The inwarde vale, did signify the couering and concealing of those diuine mysteries, which after the generall iudgement shall bee reuealed: when we shall see his glorious maiestie face to face, as he is. Which vale had foure colours,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12</note> signifying the foure Elements: being impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and lets, to keepe vs from the sight of those heauenly substances, which our immortall and glorifyed bodies, shall then behold.</p>
            <p>And as our Sauiour Christ,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.</note> laide aside the pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of maiestie: tooke vpon him the forme of a seruant: and hauing performed due obedience, and subiection vnto his father: is now aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the highest dominion, and crowned with honor and glorie, that all knees shall bow vnto him. So after the last day,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.11</note> when he hath perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the offic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of a mediator: hee shall yeelde vp into the handes of his Father,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24.25.</note> both the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, name, and crowne of glorie:<note place="margin">Maister Caluin in his insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions.</note> and bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with that same glorie which he inioyed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the creation of the world: that God may be all in all.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:2941:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:2941:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:2941:32"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:2941:32"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:2941:33"/>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>A Meditation of the Lords prayer.</head>
               <q>
                  <p>Our Father which art in heauen: halowed bee thy name.</p>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hy sacred word (oh heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) wherby thou art knowne, the onely Lorde of mercy and iudgement:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ro.</hi> 12.1.2. 1. <hi>Thes.</hi> 4 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.17 <hi>Psal.</hi> 19.111.</note> bee halowed, and sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctified in vs. That by meanes of hearing thine euerlasting truth: And viewing thy wondrous wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, most glorious in their kind: all states, and degrees of people, may continually be moued (with hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, thankfull, and obedient heartes) to ext<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll, praise, and magnify thy infynite goodnes for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. That all may turne to thy glory, and our saluation.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Thy kingdome come.</p>
               </q>
               <p>INcrease (most louing Father) thy faithfull family vpon earth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gala.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.20 <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.31. 1. <hi>Thes.</hi> 4.17</note> and make hast to deliuer vs, from this present euill world. Come Lord quickly, to shorten these our sinfull daies, and bring our miserable pilgrimage to an end. That all may turne to thy glorie, and our saluation.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:2941:33"/>
               <q>
                  <p>Thy will be done in earth, as it is in heauen.</p>
               </q>
               <p>OH mercifull God, whose eternall will and pleasure is, to glorify them that glorify thee in themselues.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.10 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 6.20. 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 4 3.</note> We beseech thy father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goodnes, so to frame our hartes in due obedience, to thy heauenly wil: as our cheefe stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy care, and delight, may be wholly applyed to the suppressing of falshod and vice: th' aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of truth and vertue:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.27.</note> and bearing with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience the crosse of our louing Redeemer after him. That al may turn to thy glory and our sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Giue vs this day, our daily bread.</p>
               </q>
               <p>OH most bountifull and gratious Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne: at whose mercyes seat, all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind must call, and cry for grace:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 7.7</note> at whose almes-basket, both King and Keaser are driuen to begge their bread: at whose bountifull handes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Psalm.</hi> 145.</note> all liuing creatures (in due season) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r food. We humbly beseech thee: so to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, norish, and releeue our soules with thy true and holesome bread of life:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6.58.</note> as the promise of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission of sinnes, and redemption in Christ, may assuredly bee sealed in our hartes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science. And at thy good will, and pleasure, giue vs thy daily blessing of food and raiment:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.31.33.</note> with all thinges needfull for our bodily sustinance in
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2941:34"/>
this life.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Da mihi Do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. hodie quod suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, &amp; eras plurima pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sost.</hi>
                  </note> Not desyring with couetous world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, to wallow in superfluity: but with <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> a meane contented liuing, to aide necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. That all may turne to thy glory and our saluation</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Forgiue vs our trespasses, as wee forgiue them that trespasse against vs.</p>
               </q>
               <p>OH mercifull Father, who hast promised free pardon and forgiuenes of synnes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditionally, that we do humbly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our faultes:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioel.</hi> 2. <hi>Luk.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Math.</hi> 6.14.15.</note> amend our liues: and shew like pity and compassion, to our bretheren that offend vs. We humbly beseech thee, so to relent and mollify, our hard stony harts, with the piercyng oile of thy interior grace: as our loue and charity towards them,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.3.4.</note> may declare the same promise to bee thankfully receiued of vs. That all may turne to thy glory, and our salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Lead vs not into temptation: but deliuer vs from euill.</p>
               </q>
               <p>WE pray and beseech thee most gratious Soueraigne to bridle and restraine the furious rage of Sathan, our mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall enemy. Who like a ramping and roring Lyon,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 8.5.9.</note> seeketh continually to seduce and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2941:34"/>
lead vs into err<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, sinne, and vtter distruction. Strengthen our weakenesse:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.30</note> quicken our dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our negl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gence: increase our faith: and keepe vs in all truth godlinesse, and vertue. That we may alw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies render vnto thy glorious maiesty (w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thout beginning, change, or end) all honor, power, and dominion for euer, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A most godly and comfortable prayer in time of aduersity.</head>
               <p>OH eternall and most louing father, thou God of mercy and iudgement: to whom all thinges in heauen and earth, do bow and obay. At t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e countinance of whose glorious maiesty, the whole wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld doth tremble and quake. Who hath fashioned man of slime &amp; earth, couered him in his mothers wombe: and redeemed him from death and hell. Who seeth the very secrets of mans harte: vnderstandeth his thoughtes: and spiest out all his wayes. To thee, oh heauenly king, I humbly bowe the knees of my hart: beseeching thy fatherly good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes (in Iesus Christ) to heare me poore wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched child of <hi>Adam:</hi> begotten and borne in sin: disquieted with troubles: wrapt in aduersity, &amp; oppressed with misery. Yet by thy secret purpose pertaine to thy kingdome. An vnruly sheepe of thy fold, by election and calling: an vnprofitable seruant of thy houshold by obedience and duty.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2941:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:2941:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:2941:36"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:2941:36"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:2941:37"/>
And vnworthy sonne of thy family, by adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and grace.</p>
               <p>I will call mine owne waies to remembrance: confesse mine iniquities against my selfe: and power out my complaint before thee. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue eare to my prayer O Lord: consider my distresse: and ponder the voice of my humble desires. Let the words of my mouth, and the meditation of my hart, be alwaies acceptable in thy sight: O Lord my strength and my redemer. I haue sinned most greeuously (Oh mercifull God) against heauen, and before thee. I haue sore prouoked thyne anger, oh Lord: thy wrath is waxen hot, &amp; thy heauy displeasure is sore kindled against me. And now in the vexation of my spirit: and the anguish of my soule (Remembring thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly kindnes towards penitent sinners) I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to thy eternall mercy: acknowledge my wickednes: and lament my greuous offences. My hart is broken with sorrows: my life waxe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> old with heauines: and my yeares with mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. How long wilt thou be angry with thy seruant to Lord: how lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g shall I seeke counsell in my soul: and be so vexed in my spirit? How long shall I (poore sinfull wretch) be tossed in these troublesome floods of mortality: beway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the tediousnes of this my yrksome pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. The infant ouercommeth his mother with crying: the child his father with weeping: and the seruant his maister with submission.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2941:37"/>
and wilt thou be no more intreated? Oh Lord, where are thy tender mercies, and louing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which hath bin euer of old? our Fathers hoped in thee, and were deliuered: they put their trust in thee, and were not confounded. Thou art the father of the fatherlesse: and the helper of the frendlesse. Thou hast alwaies heard the humble desire of the poore: thou preparest their hart to call vppon thee: and thine Eares har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken thereunto. Thou deliuerest them from wronge: and right deare is their bloud in thy sight. Why art thou so full of heauines then, oh my soule: &amp; why art thou so disquieted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in mee? Oh put thy trust in God: for I will yet giue him thanks, which is the helpe of my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinance, and my God. Yea though hee kill me: yet will I trust in him. I will sing vnto the Lord, so long as I liue: and will praise my God while I haue any being. He hath chastened, &amp; corrected me: but not giuen me ouer vnto death. And therefore my hart daunceth for ioy: my flesh shall rest in hope: and in my song will I praise him. I will honor him with due obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: serue him in feare: and reioice vnto him with reuerence. Rebuke me not in thyne anger oh Lord; neither chasten me in thy heauy dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure. Forsake me not in mine old age, when my strength faileth me: but comfort my heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: pitty my misery: and releeue my necessity. Clense me from my secret faultes: and pardon
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:2941:38"/>
the sinnes of my youth. Grant me a new hart: a new mind: a new spirit: and a new life. And I wil offer vnto thee the sacrifice of thankes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and reioyce in thy saluation, oh thou most highest. Thy testimonies shal delight my soule, in the dayes of my trouble: thy statutes shall be my songes, in the house of my pilgrimage: and thy law shall be dearer vnto me: then thousands of gold and siluer. To thee oh heauenly Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghost: three distinct persons in Trinitie: and one God in power, might, and maiesty: be euerlasting glory, perpetual praise: and eternall thanks for euermore, world without ende: Amen,</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:2941:38"/>
               <head>The Table of the Chapters, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this booke.</head>
               <item>Chapter I. He that in Paradise wil taist the fruites of Diuinity, must first learne to know himselfe in the schole of humility. fol. 1.</item>
               <item>Chapter II. Of the lothsome deformity of nature through A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams fall. fol. 3.</item>
               <item>Chapter III. Of the miserie of Adams brats, and vanitie of the world. fol. 5.</item>
               <item>Chapter IIII. Of the breuitye of mans life, and certaintye of Death. fol. 10.</item>
               <item>Chapter V. The passage of Paradise is aptly compared to a warfare. fol. 14.</item>
               <item>Chapter VI. The armour and weapons of a Christian Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. fol. 17.</item>
               <item>Chapter VII. He that in Paradise will come to ioy with Christ, must trauell with patience vnder the crosse of Christ. fol. 20.</item>
               <item>Chapter VIII. Of true repentance with her inseperable furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. fol. 23.</item>
               <item>Chapter IX. Of Confession of sinnes. fol. 25.</item>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:2941:39"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2941:39"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2941:40"/>
               <item>Chapter X. Of faith, hope, and charity. fol. 27.</item>
               <item>Chapter XI. Of prayer and meditation. fol. 29.</item>
               <item>Chapter XII. Of true abstinence or fasting. fol. 34.</item>
               <item>Chapter XIII. A briefe summe of Christian religion. fol. 36.</item>
               <item>Chapter XIIII. An exhortation to indure constant in time of try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. fol. 38.</item>
               <item>Chapter XV. A comfortable consolation to the faithful troupe of Christian Pilgrims. fol. 41.</item>
               <item>Chapter XVI.<list>
                     <item>Of the ioyful state of Gods children, after the last iudgement. fol. 46.</item>
                     <item>A meditation of the Lords prayer. fol. 52.</item>
                     <item>A most godly and comfortable prayer in time of aduersity. fol. 55.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:2941:40"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
