<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The art of giuing Describing the true nature, and right vse of liberality: and prouing that these dayes of the gospell haue farre exceeded the former times of superstition in true charitie and magnificence. By Thomas Cooper.</title>
            <author>Cooper, Thomas, fl. 1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 142 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-11">2004-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19280</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5692</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118543</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853750</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853750</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19145</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A19280)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19145)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 577:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The art of giuing Describing the true nature, and right vse of liberality: and prouing that these dayes of the gospell haue farre exceeded the former times of superstition in true charitie and magnificence. By Thomas Cooper.</title>
                  <author>Cooper, Thomas, fl. 1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 116 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by T. Snodham] for T. Pauier, and are to be sold in Iuy Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Dedication to Sir J. Rotherham and others.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-09</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-09</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19145:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19145:1"/>
            <p>THE
ART OF
Giuing. Describing the true Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
and right vse of
Liberality: And prouing
That these dayes of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell
haue farre exceeded the
former times of Superstition
in true Charitie and
Magnificence.</p>
            <p>BY
THOMAS COOPER.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed for <hi>T. Pauter,</hi> and are
to be sold in Iuy Lane. 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19145:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19145:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT
VVorshipfull, Sir Iohn Rothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram,
and Sir Gilbert Wakering,
Knights, and their vertuous La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,
especiall Patrons of my
studies, T. C. wisheth all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease
of the blessings of
Heauen and Earth.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worshipfull:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He occasions that hath
moued mee to treate of
this subiect of true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficence
in these latter
dayes are First, to propose
it as a liuely Touchstone
for the triall of our holy entertainment of the
glorious Gospell of Iesus Christ: Secondly, to
confound hereby the vaine confidence of
this deceitfull generation, which seeme to be
somewhat herein, when indeed they are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;
deceiuing themselues, euen as clouds
<pb facs="tcp:19145:3"/>
without water, in their false liberality. And
so to conuince the Atheist, that saith, where is
the promise of his comming? seeing this very
decay of true loue, is among other, one of those
pregnant signes, that the day of the Lord Iesus
is neere at hand, that so the wise in heart may
see the plague, and hide himselfe. And seeing
he that is comming will come quickly, with
his reward with him, to giue vnto euery one
according to his work, yea, will come sodainly
in an houre, that no man knowes of, ought we
not alwaies to haue Oyle ready in our Lamps,
that so we may enter in vnto our masters ioy?</p>
            <p>Surely were there nothing else to moue vs
hereunto, but the commandement of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly
Master, this should prouoke vs to loue
one another, this should adiure vs to abound
in Charity, that so we might auoid eternall
vengeance, seeing all the commandements are
fulfilled in this, that we loue each other, &amp; to
faile in one duty is guilty of the breach of all.
But behold what loue the Father hath shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
vs, that, what was impossible to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement
in regard of the transgression,
whereby sin reuiued &amp; became <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
sinfull: and so the hatred increasing, we
had no hope, but were as water spilt vpon the
ground, that we could not be gathered vp
<pb facs="tcp:19145:3"/>
againe: Our God which is rich in mercy
through his great loue, wherewith he loued
vs, supplied by a most gracious and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
remedy, namely, the pretious bloud of his
deere sonne, as of a Lambe vndefiled &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
spot. This is that bloud that hath spoken
better things for vs then the bloud of <hi>Abel,</hi>
not only stopping that loud crie of Vengeance
which our sinnes called for, but opening vnto
vs the gates of righteousnesse, and enabling
vs to walke in the similitude of the death
and resurrection of Iesus Christ, that so we
might be partakers with him of eternall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.
And this is that blessed Lord Iesus, who
hath not beene a stranger vnto vs, or soiour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
with vs for a season, but hath beene
liuely described in our sight, and euen cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
among vs, in the glorious and constant
publishing of the Gospell of Peace. And could
greater loue be shewed to vs by any then that
the sonne of God should lay downe his life
for his? And if the Lord so loued vs, ought
we not to loue one another? Is not this our
euidence that we loue God whom we haue
not seene, in that we loue our brethren whom
we see daily? Is not this our warrant that we
are translated from death to life, because we
loue the brethren?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19145:4"/>
Behold then our triall of the right enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment
of the Gospell. And haue wee
brought forth this fruit to repentance and
amendment of life?</p>
            <p>Surely we must needs acknowledge that our
glorious God can truly iustifie him against
vs: What could he haue done vnto vs which
he hath not done? Enquire we, in the name
of God, of the dayes that are past, which were
before vs, since the day that God created
man vpon the earth, and aske from one end
of heauen to the other; if there came to
passe such a great thing as this, or whither
any such like thing hath beene heard: What
nation is so great vnto whom the Gods come
so neere as the Lord our God is neere vnto
vs in all that we call vnto him for?</p>
            <p>Had euer nation the Gospell of Iesus
Christ so long continued with such constant
outward peace and prosperity for the better
entertainment thereof? Was euer nation de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered
out of so horrible a pit, as was the
Gunpowder treason? Thus may the Lord
iustifie himselfe against vs, but how haue we
iustified our God in a conscionable embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
of so great saluation, bringing forth fruit
answerable thereunto?</p>
            <p>That we haue a name to be aliue, who
<pb facs="tcp:19145:4"/>
may deny vs? Is not yet the Gospell preached
in our streets? Doe we not draw forth with
ioy out of these fountaines of saluation? How
is it then that we bring forth wilde grapes?
are we not for all this euen now dead, and
pluckt vp by the rootes? Yea, if we may be
beleeued our selues, we say that we are rich,
and encreased with goods, and haue neede
of nothing? But is not this because wee
know not that we are poore, and lame, and
blinde, and miserable? Are we not willingly
ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the truth of our estates, iudging of
the same by false rules, as Opinion, Custome,
Estimation, Multitude, and such like: and so
are deceiued in our imagination, esteeming
our selues to be somewhat, when we are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
at leastwise nothing to what we should
be? Haue we brought forth fruit answerable
to the time of our visitation?</p>
            <p>Surely, if there were nothing else to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince
our barrennesse &amp; vnprofitablenes in
the entertainment of so great saluation, the
very bleating of the Sheep, and lowing of the
Oxen; the cries and complaints of the poore,
ringing daily, and piercing the heauens for
their contempt, and des<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lations: the diuisions
of <hi>Ruben,</hi> should cause great sorrow of heart;
this might iustly challenge a great decay of
<pb facs="tcp:19145:5"/>
vnfained loue. Is not <hi>Ephraim</hi> against <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasses,</hi>
and <hi>Manasses</hi> against <hi>Ephraim,</hi>
and both against <hi>Iuda?</hi> Hath not the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
of selfe-loue eaten out all hearty and
true affection to each other, while euery
one seekes his owne, and not that which
may concerne the common good: nay, with
the generall wracke of the publike weale?
And if wee thus bite and teare one another,
shall we not be deuoured of each other?</p>
            <p>Learne we hence, in the name of God, to
see the plague, and hide our selues. Is it not
already begunne; shall I say in the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most
part of the hoast, or not rather in
the hoast and eyes thereof? And is not the
Kite ready to seaze vpon both? The Lord
giue vs vnderstanding in all things. Is not
this the day of <hi>Iacobs</hi> trauaile? Doth not
the Iudge stand at the doore? Will not the
Master come in an houre which that ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant
dreameth not of, and giue him his por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
with Hypocrites, where shall be wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
and wayling, and gnashing of teeth?
Surely, were it not that the Lord had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued
a remnant of the holy seed among
vs, we had long since beene as <hi>Sodome</hi>
and <hi>Gomorrha:</hi> And is not the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
daily taken from the euill to come? Is
<pb facs="tcp:19145:5"/>
not <hi>Ezekiell</hi> daily made a signe to the
house of <hi>Israell?</hi> And is not the hand of
the Lord stretched out still? Who so is wise
let him vnderstand these things, and to
whom the Lord shall reueale them; for the
wayes of God are holy and righteous, and
the iust shall walke therein, but the w<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
shall fall in the same. Must not the
Gospell be a stumbling-blocke to the Iew,
and foolish to the Graecians? Doe any of the
Rulers beleeue in him? nay, is it not an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
that the poore receiue the Gospell? And
shall not the Lord stay his hand till <hi>Lot</hi>
be remoued out of <hi>Sodome?</hi> shall not the
Gospell be continued till the remnant be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered
in? And may we not daily obserue
a great Haruest abroad, euen the barraine
and desolate corners of the Land, hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring
after the Word, and catching the
Kingdome, with all holy violence? And
why then stand wee idle in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-place?
Why helpe wee not the Lord
against the mighty? Is not the Canaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite
yet in the Land? Hath hee not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased
by our contentions and securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie?
Why ioyne wee not together against
the common enemy? Doth he not beast
<pb facs="tcp:19145:6"/>
of false liberality? Doth not the harlot begin
to encroach vpon vs by her offerings of Peace
and pretences of reconciliation, by her glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
shewes, and sugred greetings, entending
more desperately to kill, when she kisseth and
croucheth, that heapes of men may fall by
her might? Can we euer forget that hidden
Mine? Shall we not euer suspect such faw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<hi>Absalons,</hi> and deepe <hi>Achitophels?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is not this the age of complements, and
formalities, vanishing meerely in shewes and
bodily worships? Was euer deadly hatred car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
more cunningly vnder sugred words,
and fayned deuotions? Is not our friendship
turned into flattery, our hospitality to stately
houses, and gay cloathes, our Beneficence to
vaine boastings, and cold words: Nay, to euill
deeds? Witnesse our enclosures and turning
out of our brethren from their ancient habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,
and placing in their roomes heards
of beasts: Were it not better to be such Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemens
sheepe then their Tenants? Were it
not better that such great ones had not a foot
of the earth, then that hereby they should en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger
the losse of heauen? What shall wee
thinke of that innaturall encroaching and
vndermining of each other in their callings
and liuelihoods? Tradesman eating out
<pb facs="tcp:19145:6"/>
Tradesman, Merchant supplanting Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant,
one Brother vndermining another, the
common wisedome and misery of the times?
Doe not they argue that both conscience
and charity is dead among vs? And ought
we not then to strengthen the things that are
ready to die, that so wee may recouer our
first loue? Surely what these poore labours shall
come short of herein, that shall I not fayle to
make vp with my best desires: All which I
doe here, with whatsoeuer I humbly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
vnto your Worships good acceptance in
Iesus Christ, as acknowledging hereby my
selfe, and all mine deepely indebted vnto your
Worships for your fatherly loue vnto vs in
our afflictions, and binding my selfe hereby
in all hearty affections and endeauours, at
least to take away iust imputation of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefulnesse.
And thus commending your
Worships to the grace of God in Iesus Christ,
I euer rest:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worships poore kinsman, euer
bounden in Iesus Christ
THOMAS COOPER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:19145:7"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>FIrst, it is declared what Giuing is, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally.
Chap. 1</item>
               <item>The kindes of Liberality described.
Chap. 2</item>
               <item>Is discouered who is the true giuer.
Chap. 3</item>
               <item>The true nature of Liberality is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.
Chap. 4</item>
               <item>Together with the properties thereof,
as that, first, it must be free. Chap. 5</item>
               <item>Secondly, we must giue of our owne.
Chap. 6</item>
               <item>Thirdly, we must be wise in our boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.
Chap. 7</item>
               <item>First prouiding for our selues. 2 Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
where there is most need. 3. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding
that wee may be still able to
giue. Yet, 4. Keeping within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe
of our ability. 5. Not endam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maging
<pb facs="tcp:19145:7"/>
any by our bounty. 6. Wee
must giue in faith, that is, 1. Beleeuing
that our persons are accepted, and so
are our endeauours. 2. Not looking
for recompence againe. Where espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
is taught that wee must loue our
enemies, and how farre. Chap. 8</item>
               <item>We must giue out of a louing and
affectionate heart. Chap. 9</item>
               <item>We must giue constantly. Chap. 10</item>
               <item>Wee must propose right ends in our
giuing, which are: 1. Assurance of salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
to our selues. 2. Benefit to others
in soule and body. 3. The good of
the Church. 4. Furtherance of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine
worship. 5. The glory of God.
Chap. 11</item>
               <item>The vices contrary to Beneficence
are laid downe generally, both such
as hinder altogether, as also such
as corrupt the sinceritie thereof, both
on the left hand, and on the right.
Chap. 12</item>
               <item>Certaine motiues are laid downe to
prouoke to bounty. Chap. 13</item>
               <item>And so are commended diuers
helpes and preparatiues to Liberality.
Chap. 14</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19145:8"/>
As also it is obserued what punishments
are due, and haue beene inflicted vpon
the breach of this duty, and exercise of
cruelty and vnmercifulnesse. Chap. 15</item>
               <item>Together with the vse of these punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.
Chap. 16</item>
               <item>The seuerall lets and rentations against
beneficence are laid open in their places,
As, 1. Because they are our owne. 2. All
little enough for our selues. 3. We shall
be soone emptied, and become beggers.
These are vrged and answered. Cha. 17</item>
               <item>Other lets are proposed, as 1. Care of
posterity. 2. Marriage of daughters,
&amp;c. Chap<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 18</item>
               <item>A third sort of Tentations, arising from
the vnworthinesse of such as neede, and
little good redounds thereby. These are
answered, and in speciall is declared how
Witches may be relieued, &amp; though the
poore be vnthankfull, yet wee must re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue
them; yea, though dissemblers, yet
must not be neglected. Chap. 19</item>
               <item>Other Tentations discouered, whereby
liberality is excused, as charge for the
common-wealth, layes for the Church,
maintenance of the Ministery and such
charges, for the Sacrament, assessings for
<pb facs="tcp:19145:8"/>
the poore, &amp;c. these are remoued.
Chap. 20</item>
               <item>A fift sort of Tentations proposed for
the hinderance of bounty, namely,
Christmas-feasts: these are answered.
Chap. 21</item>
               <item>Diuers speciall practises of Satan are
further detected, whereby he hath and
doth hinder Beneficence. As 1. Enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
of land, together with the remedy
thereof. Chap. 22</item>
               <item>2. Excesse in diet, with the remedie
thereof. Chap. 23</item>
               <item>3. Pride, and excesse in apparrell, with
the remedy thereof. Chap. 24</item>
               <item>4. That excessine hunting is an enemy
to bounty, with the remedy thereof.
Chap. 25</item>
               <item>Of feare to be accounted Papists, that
it is an enemy to liberality, with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy
thereof. Chap. 26</item>
               <item>The tentation, that we sinne in the best,
and will doe no good least wee should
sin, discouered and remoued. Chap. 27</item>
               <item>That idlenesse is an enemy to true
bounty, and that it abounds in this age,
with the remedy thereof. Chap. 28</item>
               <item>The last and maine enemy to liberality
<pb facs="tcp:19145:9"/>
is vnthrifty and vnlawfull games. Here
is first proued, that they are vnlawfull.
As namely, <list>
                     <item>Dicing.</item>
                     <item>2 Carding.</item>
                     <item>3 Cock fighting and Bearebayting.</item>
                     <item>4 Stage-Playes and Enterludes.</item>
                     <item>5 Dancing. Chap. 29</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Certaine generall remedies are propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,
and commended against these vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull
delights. Chap. 30</item>
               <item>Conclusion of the whole. Chap. 31</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19145:9"/>THE ART OF
Giuing.</head>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. I.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>What Giuing is in generall, namely:</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N imparting of what the
Lord hath giuen vs, as
eyther cast vpon vs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily
by his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence,
or obtayned
by ordinary meanes of
our labour and industry.</p>
            <p>2 To the necessitie of our poore
brother, as he is neerest vnto vs in the
Lord: And that both willingly, and
bountifully, to his sound comfort<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And
wisely also, prouiding especially and
principally for our selues. <hi>And that,</hi> in
all holinesse and humility vnto God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19145:10"/>
Giuing him the glory of what hee hath
enabled vs to giue vnto others, and lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
vp thereby a good foundation, by
making vs friends of this vnrighteous
Mammon, against the day of Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus,
that we may be receiued into euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting
habitations. 1 <hi>Tim. 6. 19. Luke</hi> 16
11. 12. &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. II.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Obserue we the diuers kindes of Liberality,
and that to good ends.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THe first and speciall worke of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
is to prouide for the saluation of
the soule.<note place="margin">Sect. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To this end serue,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Prouision, that it be instructed by
the word of God. <hi>Rom</hi> 10. 10.</p>
            <p>2 Reproofe for sinne, and plucking
it out of the fire. <hi>Iud.</hi> 2. 2.</p>
            <p>3 Comfort, and consolation, raising it
vp out of the deepe and pit of despayre.
<hi>Gal. 6. 1. Iam.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>4 Chastisement, and humbling of the
flesh, that the soule may be saued. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>5 To this end serues the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
of the Ministry, as a speciall worke
of bounty, as also 1 <hi>Cor. 9. 2. Cor.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:19145:10"/>
6 The erecting and maintayning of the
Vniuersities, and Free-schooles, for the
instructing of youth, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A second and next worke of Beneficence is,<note place="margin">Sect. 2.</note>
to relieue the body of our poore Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:
And this is properly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
Almes: this is done;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 By giuing freely vnto him to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
his want. <hi>Hebr. 13. Math.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>2 We must also lend vnto him, which
steeds him more sometime then giuing.
<hi>Deut. 5. 8. Luke 6. 35. Exod.</hi> 22. 25.</p>
            <p>3 We must remit due debt, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
lent, if the party be not able to repay.
<hi>Exod. 22. 26. Nehem.</hi> 5, 11.</p>
            <p>4 We are to hinder and put off such
wrongs as may be done vnto him. <hi>Pro. 24
10.</hi> 11. 12. As also, as our callings will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,
to right him therein, and to be auen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
of those that offer them.</p>
            <p>6 Yea, to this end we are to prouoke o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
to tender his case, by making it
knowne.</p>
            <p>7 Hitherto serue set contributions,
and treasuries for the poore.</p>
            <p>8 By conscionable selling, we performe
true bounty.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:19145:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A third kinde of Beneficence is where
gifts are giuen betweene parties
for ciuill respects.<note place="margin">Sect. 3.</note>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Are gratulatory, such as <hi>Gen.</hi> 45. 23</p>
            <p>2 Or placatory to appease wrath, as
<hi>Iacob</hi> to <hi>Esau, Gen.</hi> 34.</p>
            <p>3 Some for reward, as those of the
Prince to the Subiect. <hi>Dan. 2. 48. Hest.</hi> 6. 2.</p>
            <p>4 Or to procure fauour of those of
the meaner to the superiour.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Pro.</hi> 21. 14.</p>
            <p>5 Some to helpe and promote iust
causes as <hi>Iacob</hi> to his sonne <hi>Ioseph. Gen.
43.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>6 And also to maintayne mutuall
loue and friendship. <hi>Nehem. 8. 1 Reg. 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
11.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>7 To the aduancing of the worship
of God. 1 <hi>Chron. 19. Exod.</hi> 35. 20.</p>
            <p>8 By thankfulnesse we are giuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
God.</p>
            <p>9 Also gifts are giuen in signe of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage
and subiection. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. 27.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly some are to euill ends.<note place="margin">Sect. 4.</note>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 As to the erecting of Idolatry.
<hi>Exod.</hi> 32.</p>
            <p>2 To the coruprting and enthral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19145:11"/>
of the soule. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>3 To the corrupting of iudgement
and iustice. <hi>Pro. 17. 23. 2 Sam. 16.
Pro.</hi> 17. 8.</p>
            <p>4 To the ensnaring, and entrapping
into danger. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.</p>
            <p>5 To the enthralling and abasing
of men to serue the worlds turne.</p>
            <p>6 To obtaine greater benefits againe,
fishing with a Gudgeon to catch a Pipe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. III.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Of the true Giuer.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>1 GEnerally onely the regenerate
man may truly giue,<note place="margin">Sect. 1.</note> because he
onely hath right in what he hath. The
wicked being no better then theeues.</p>
            <p>2 Particularly the rich are bound to
giue. 1 <hi>Iohn. 3. 17.. 2 Cor.</hi> 8. 14.</p>
            <p>3 The poore euen of that little that
they haue, are also bound to giue. <hi>Ioh. 13.
29. Eph.</hi> 4. 28. As the widow must giue her
mite, seruants must giue of their wages.</p>
            <p>4 Yea we must empouerish our selues
in some cases, to giue to others in cases of
necessitie. <hi>Act. 5. Nehem.</hi> 5.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19145:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Exception.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Those that are in paricular subie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
to others,<note place="margin">Sect. 2.</note> as Seruants to Masters;
these may not giue in selling, &amp;c. vnlesse
it be out of their wages.</p>
            <p>2 Subiects cannot giue, but from that
generall authority committed by the
lawes of the land, vnto them, answerable
to the lawes of God, concerning relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
of the poore, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>3 The Wife may not giue in some ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,
vnlesse it be of such things as are
common to both. 2 As also of that
which she hath excepted from man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage.</p>
            <p>3 And that with the consent of her
Husband, eyther expressed, or presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
from the generall liberty giuen to
her.</p>
            <p>4 In a case of extremitie, when all
is like to be lost, and the Husband vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
to gouerne the family. 1 <hi>Samuel 25.
19.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:19145:12"/>
            <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Obserue more especially what true giuing
is, as it properly belongeth to the elect
of God, and of the seuerall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties
thereof:</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>Namely:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Most free, franke, and liberall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting
some meet and conuenient
portion of that wherewith God of his
goodnesse hath blessed euery man.</p>
            <p>1 To the maintenance and aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of Gods pure religion and worship.
<hi>Hebr.</hi> 8. 3.</p>
            <p>2 To the mercifull relieuing, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting,
and succouring of all such as we
see: or for want of such, of those whom
we doe by credible report vnderstand at
any time, to be in any present necessity
and neede. And that in such manner as
God himselfe would haue his owne wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship
to be vpheld and furthered: And
the poore among his people in all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
Churches, to be comfortably relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
and succoured.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:19145:13"/>
            <head>CHAP. V.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Of the conditions and propertie, of true
liberality, gathered out of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
difinition.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>1 IT must be free,<note place="margin">Sect. 1.</note> and from a franke
minde,<note place="margin">First it must be free.</note> 
               <hi>Luke 6. 33. 34. 35. Prou. 25.
21.</hi> 22. euen to our enemies. <hi>Math.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>2 To those that cannot requite vs
againe. <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 12. 13 14.</p>
            <p>3 And that not sparingly and grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gingly,
but bountifully. 2 <hi>Cor. 9. 5. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.
14. Luke 19. 1 Pet.</hi> 4. 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Because.<note place="margin">Reason.</note>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 It must be from the heart. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 7.</p>
            <p>2 This is it that God loueth and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.
2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 12.</p>
            <p>3 <hi>Yea, though the gift be small, yet
the heart makes it acceptable.</hi> Luke 21.
Act. 9. 36. 1 King. 18. 3. 4. Obadiah and
Lydia, Act. 16. Exod. 35. 20. 2 Chron. 39.
31. 36. <hi>&amp;</hi> 35. 8. sub Hezekiah and Iosiah,
Deut. 20. 8. Exod. 36.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:19145:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Markes of this free giuing:<note place="margin">Sect. 2.</note> Are,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 To giue bountifully of a little, so
the widow. <hi>Luke</hi> 21.</p>
            <p>2 To straine our selues euen aboue
our ability. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 4.</p>
            <p>3 To preuent importunate asking.</p>
            <p>4 Not to defer and put off til to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.
<hi>Pro.</hi> 3. 28.</p>
            <p>5 To giue with ioy and gladnesse of
heart. 1 <hi>Chron. 19. Deut.</hi> 26. 10. 11. 14.
yea, to reioyce theerein as well done.</p>
            <p>6 To giue of the best, and costliest,
as is fitting to the party. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 12. 3.</p>
            <p>7 And that accordingly as God hath
blessed vs. 1 <hi>or.</hi> 16. 2.</p>
            <p>8 Yea, according as hee hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined
in his heart 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 7.</p>
            <p>9 Not to tie our liberality strictly to
the law of men, but besides that, to doe
ouer and aboue according to our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prouided.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 That others be eased, and wee our
selues not grieued. 2 <hi>Cor. 8. 13. Pro. 5. 16.
17. Luke</hi> 3. 11.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:19145:14"/>
2 In a case of extreamity to relieue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
we must sell euen our possessions,
<hi>Luke 12. 33. Psa.</hi> 112. 9. of which more
afterward.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now that we may giue cheerefully,<note place="margin">Sect. 3.</note> these
things are required;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 A delight in the thing to whom
we shew our beneficence.<note place="margin">Helpes hereunto.</note> 
               <hi>Psa. 131. 2.
1 Chro. 29. 2 Sam. 6. Psa.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>2 Faith: both that we are perswaded
that this wel-doing is acceptable to God,
<hi>Heb. 13. 16. Phil 4. 18. Hose</hi> 6. 2. That
God also wil blesse and prouide for those
that are liberall, notwithstanding the
feare of after wants.</p>
            <p>3 A third helpe is Humility, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
our selues vnworthy of those bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings
which yet our gracious God hath
made vs stewards of, to giue to others.
<hi>Gen. 32. 10. 1 Tim.</hi> 6. 17. 18. 19.</p>
            <p>4 Consider we the vncertainty of our
life, that if we neglect to day wee may
be cut off tomorrow. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 10.</p>
            <p>5 Meditate we daily on the free and
and vndeserued bounty of our God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
vs, how seasonably it commeth,
how plentifully aboue our desires.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:19145:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Considerations and motiues to giue
bountifully and freely:<note place="margin">Sect. 4.</note> Are,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Heereby we come neerest the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
of God.</p>
            <p>2 We prouide wisely for our selues, as
vndoubtedly being assured that we shall
be plentifully rewarded. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 10. 11. of
the Lord.</p>
            <p>3 Wee make vs more friends of our
vnrighteous Mammon in the world.
<hi>Luke</hi> 16. to further vs to heauen.</p>
            <p>4 We giue sound contentment to the
receiuer hereby: whom if we should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer,
wee prouoke to despayre, murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,
&amp;c.</p>
            <p>5 Wee turne that which is vsually a
snare, hereby to be a blessing and good
foundation against the life to come.
<hi>Luke 16. 1 Tim.</hi> 6. 19.</p>
            <p>6 Whatsoeuer we giue vnto the poore,
wee giue it vnto Christ Iesus himselfe.
<hi>Math.</hi> 25. 44. 45.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:19145:15"/>
            <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>A second thing in beneficence is, that we
must giue of our owne, that wherewith
God hath blessed vs.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>That is:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVe must giue in righteousnesse,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sect. 1:</note>
Psal. 106. Deut. 24. 13. Dan. 4. 24.
Psal. 112. vers. 2. 2 Cor. 9. 9. Mat. 6. Pro.
5. 25. 1 Chron. 21. 24. Luke 19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And that because.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 It is approued hereby of God: as
being the liuely fruit of faith. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 6.
without which all liberality is theft, &amp;c.
<hi>Esay. 61. 8. Deut.</hi> 23. 18.</p>
            <p>2 Hereby onely it will prosper, and
benefit the giuer.</p>
            <p>3 Yea, hee to whom it is giuen can
haue no assurance of blessing and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,
but that it may be a snare vnto him,
vnlesse it be giuen in righteousnesse, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
he is the receiuer to a Thiefe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This condemneth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Those that rob the poore, to grease
the rich.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:19145:15"/>
2 That hope to make amends for
their ill gotten-goods, by a little charity
at their deaths.</p>
            <p>3 Colour their iniustice with cloaks
of authority, necessity; &amp;c.</p>
            <p>4 As also such receiuers, as indeed
are no better then brokers, and sharers
with those theeues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now we giue in righteousnesse.<note place="margin">Sect. 2.</note>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 When we giue of our owne, that
is, what we haue gotten by holy and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scionable
labour.</p>
            <p>2 What comes vnto vs by inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
gift, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>3 And that is then truly our owne
which we doe sanctifie both by the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance
of our persons in the sight of
God, as also by daily prayer for the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
of God vpon it: vnlesse these latter
be added nothing is truly our owne.</p>
            <p>4 Then also a thing is our owne tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
when as we haue gotten it honestly,
or it comes to vs by inheritance, &amp;c.
so wee imploy it faithfully in some ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest
calling.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:19145:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And this,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Reproueth Gentlemen and others,
that hauing goods &amp; possessions, eyther
gotten, or come vnto them by inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
thinke their onely end is to spend it
in housekeeping, and worse, neuer respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting
the poore, otherwise: neyther wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
in any calling, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>2 Generally the prophanes of all
that make no conscience of sanctifying
the blessings of God, nothing regard
how their persons are accepted, onely
stand vpon the credit of these things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We give in righteousnesse when we giue
where there is best desert,<note place="margin">Sect. 3.</note> and more
bonds to tye vs thereto: Heere then,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Wee must giue to the household of
faith. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 10. and Church of God. And
that not for any by-respects, but euen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
they are beloued of God. <hi>Mat. 10.
41.</hi> 42. 43.</p>
            <p>2 To our country &amp; common Parent.</p>
            <p>3 To our naturall parents and kinse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folkes.
1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 4.</p>
            <p>4 Leauing these, we may make a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
giuing one more then the other, as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19145:16"/>
they are purest in religion, or likeliest in
condition, or neerer in bloud. So <hi>Iacob</hi>
loued <hi>Ioseph, Ioseph Beniamin, &amp;c. Gen. 37
Gen.</hi> 43. 44, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But our Sauiours lesson is, we must
loue our neighbor as our selues: therfore
ther must be no difference in our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
Againe this may seeme to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> There may be degrees in loue, &amp; yet
all may be loued truly: our Sauiour bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
that we loue our brother; it hinders
the quality of our loue, not the quantity.</p>
            <p>5 Next these are our friends.</p>
            <p>6 Then our neighbours.</p>
            <p>7 Strangers.</p>
            <p>8 Our enemies <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 24.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>A third point in beneficence is Wisedome:<note place="margin">Sect. 2.</note>
wherein obserue,<note place="margin">Psal. 112.</note> that first I must prouide
for my selfe before others.<note place="margin">Pro. 20.</note> Here then is condemned,<note place="margin">Pro. 5. 15.</note>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>1 COmmunity of goods,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.</note> as if all should
be common, none should haue any
propriety in any thing, compare the 19.
of <hi>Mat.</hi> with the 5 of <hi>Acts.</hi> &amp; the 4. vers.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:19145:17"/>
2 Giuing of our patrimonies, and
whole estates to the maintenance of idle
Monkes and Friers: which is the best
charity of the Papists.</p>
            <p>1 As being <hi>vnfit</hi> for such men to
manage.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Vnconscionable</hi> for any to giue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
he robs his present issue, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity
of what the Lord hath cast vpon
him.</p>
            <p>3 He renounceth <hi>his right</hi> in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly
possession: wherof the earthly was
a signe. And therefore wee shall finde
that the Lord gaue straight charge that
the Iewes should at no hand part with
their possessions: if for want they were
compelled to sell them, yet they were
to redeeme them after, if they were able:
if not, they were freely to be restored,
and returne vnto them at the yeere of
Iubily. <hi>Leuit. 25. 23. 24. 25. 26. 27. 28.
1 Reg.</hi> 21. 3.</p>
            <p>4 He maintaynes idlenesse, and so all
kinde of wickednesse.</p>
            <p>3 This also condemneth that vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious
and foolish charity of many,
who to bee counted maintayners of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19145:17"/>
others emptie themselues, and so bring
vntimely and vniust misery: yet most
iustly vpon themselues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A second poynt of wisedome is,<note place="margin">Sect. 2.</note> that we
must giue where there is most neede
presently, so that without our
helpe, life will perish. And that because,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 This is most impartiall; when we
simply respect our owne flesh, and are
not led with any more speciall circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances.
<hi>Esay.</hi> 58.</p>
            <p>2 This is most seasonable, because
now it doth good: <hi>And,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3 Generally euery one beareth the
Image of God, and so we are to relieue
him, least in him we reiect God himselfe.
<hi>Math.</hi> 25.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And this condemneth:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Those that neglect well-doing in
such extremities, vpon pretence that
such are forsaken of God, and so to be
left to his iustice; as presuming that if
they were Gods they should not be left
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19145:18"/>
to such extremity: whereas the Lord
doth this eyther to trie our charity, or
shew his extraordinary mercy, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>2 Those, that cast water into the Sea,
powring in where there is no want.</p>
            <p>3 Those, that because they feare they
may bestow amisse, therefore they will
not relieue at all, much lesse in this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A third poynt of this wisedome is,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That we not onely giue as present oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion
is offered,<note place="margin">Sect. 3.</note> but, That we set apart
a moitie of our substance, as the Lord en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaseth
it, to be as a Treasurie continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,
as occasion is offered to draw forth
for the poore. <hi>Pro.</hi> 5. 15. To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose
compared to a Cesterne, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.
16. 2. For</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Hereby we shew our determinate
purpose to giue. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. which is
discouered by actuall giuing vpon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions.</p>
            <p>2 We prouide for constancy, and sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonablenesse
of bounty, as hauing some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
alwayes ready, and so continue to
such end.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:19145:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And this serueth,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 To reproue those that among their
bagges haue forgotten this: <hi>Or,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2 Thinke so of themselues, as
that they ought not to let their stocke
lie dead, and thinking, whereas they
may imploy their stocke for the further
maintenance of the poore.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hereunto appertayneth,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 The appoynting of set officers,<note place="margin">Sect. 4.</note> for
the distribution of the Almes vnto the
poore. These in the Primitiue Church
were called Deacons, and are vsed in all
reformed Churches; like vnto which are
our Collectors for the poore.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whose office was.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 To haue a particular Catalogue of
the names of the poore.</p>
            <p>2 To discerne the measure of their
pouerty, and to this end to ouersee them
weekely, <hi>And,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3 So to distribute the reliefe of the
Church among them, by such portions
as may not linger them in a pinching
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19145:19"/>
famine, but indeede cheere them, and
make them seruiceable to God, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth,
or both.</p>
            <p>4 That they should giue an account
of this their distribution to the Pastors
and gouernours of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2. To this purpose ought there a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
Treasury to be prouided.<note place="margin">Sect. 5.</note>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Not only of those weekely contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
which are ministred by the Saints:</p>
            <p>2 As also of those pledges of thankfulnes
which are giuen at the Sacrament: <hi>But,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further, euery man is monethly, or
quarterly, as he is able, to cast in his mite
into the Treasurie, for the increase and
continuance of the common Treasurie,
not onely to relieue their owne poore,
but if occasion shall serue, to comfort o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Churches in their afflictions and
wants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A fourth poynt of wisedome in giuing,
is to keepe within the bounds
of our abilitie. That is,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 First to prouide necessary things
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19145:19"/>
for our selues, and so consequently to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stribute.</p>
            <p>2 To measure our ability, not by what
may be, as fearing by giuing to diminish
it, but by what is; so depending vpon
the prouidence of God for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease
of our estate, if we bestow on our
Brother. <hi>Pro.</hi> 11. 24.</p>
            <p>3 If the case of the Church so require,
our ability must come within a narrower
compasse: not onely not to respect the
time to come, but so farre to enlarge our
selues for the time present, as to part
with the inheritance of our Fathers, and
to sell our possessions, for the reliefe of
the Saints, reseruing some part for our
necessary reliefe: and herein also for the
time to come resting on the prouidence
of God.<note place="margin">Luke. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Luke 21. Widow. 2 Chron. 31. 3. 4.
Hezekiah. Nehem. 10. 32. 33. Num. 31.
25. Act.</hi> 4. 32.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reasons,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Because, as it is a triall of our faith
to Godward, if we will lay downe our
liues for his sake: so, if the Lord doe
spare vs herein, yet seeing we must suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
with our brethren, therefore wee
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19145:20"/>
must manifest our loue by parting with
our possessions to their reliefe.</p>
            <p>2 If we ought to part with our liues
for our brethren sake, then much more
with our goods. 1 <hi>Iohn 3. 16. Rom.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>Prouided that this be in times extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary,
and cases of extremity, otherwise
we are not bound to diminish our estates.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Reproueth all Popish charity and
profession of wilfull pouerty.</p>
            <p>2 As also those that onely of their
superfluity doe bestow, thinking it in no
sort lawfull to impart their patrimonies
to this end, whereas such will make no
bones to sell away whole Lordships, &amp;c.
to maintayne dicing, whoring, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>3 Hereby the loue of the Saints may
be tried abundantly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Apoynt of wisedome is,<note place="margin">Sect. 7.</note> That none
may be any way dammaged or
hindred by our benefice. This may be,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 When sinne is manifested by the
same: As in the maintenance of Rogues
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19145:20"/>
and idle Beggars, which though they can
yet will not worke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest.</hi> Are not these then to be relieued?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> Yes, if they begin extreame ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitiy.</p>
            <p>2 And be first punished for the breach
of the Law.</p>
            <p>3 And so tied to worke when they
are able, that so they may liue of their
owne: otherwise both the giuer sins in
breaking the law, 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 2. 12. and the
receiuers sinne is maintayned, by nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing
idlenesse, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>4 If they be impotent, they are to be
relieued at their houses, and not suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
to wander. 2. When our estates are
lauished and consumed hereby,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To this end we must giue: Ordinarily</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 As God encreaseth our estate.</p>
            <p>2 As may satisfie onely the present ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity
of our brother, that so he may as
well depend vpon the prouidence of
God as wee.</p>
            <p>3 When Superstition and Idolatry is
maintained therby. <hi>Exod.</hi> 23. such is the
Popish charity, in maintaining Iesuits, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:19145:21"/>
4 When idlenesse and vanity is thereby
maintayned, and this is the vsuall bounty
of our land: whose house-keeping and
excesse, what else doth it maintayne, at
solemne times, but gaming, and all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse
of sinne; tending to the hurt both
of the giuer and receiuer?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>A fourth circumstance and condition of
Beneficence, that it to be done in Faith:</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>That is,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 THe person that performeth it;
must beleeue in the sonne of God.<note place="margin">Sect. 1.</note>
because whatsoeuer is not of faith is sin,
<hi>Rom. 14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2 Cor.</hi> 8. 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And this,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reproueth the liberality &amp; munificence
of all Atheists, Papists and prophane
persons whatsoeuer, yea, the hypocrites
Almes is heere condemned. <hi>Math.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>2 It must be done according to the
word,<note place="margin">Sect. 2. Leuit. 19. 2 Deut. 24. 19.</note> and so all voluntary and conceited
charity is also reproued, as also that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends
onely on mans law.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:19145:21"/>
3 We must giue with assurance that
though man doe forget, yet God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence,
and aboundantly repay both
in this life, and the life to come.</p>
            <p>4 To this end we are to ioyne prayer
with our liberality.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And this condemneth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The infidelity of beleeuers,<note place="margin">Sect. 3.</note> that doubt
of this. As also the prophanes of the
world, that expects it not.</p>
            <p>Another note of faith in giuing, is,
that we giue, looking for no recompence
againe from man, yea, there cast our
bread, where there is no likelihood, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
vpon the waters. <hi>Eccles. 5. This we
shall performe</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If we giue,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 To the poore, &amp;c. that are not
able to recompence vs. <hi>Math.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>2 To our enemies, and such as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steed
of good, vsually recompence euill
vnto vs. <hi>Math. 5. Rom. 12. Pro.</hi> 25. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And that because,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Herein we come neerest vnto God,
who loued vs when we were his enemies.
<hi>Rom. 5. 6. Math.</hi> 5. 45.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:19145:22"/>
2 We obtayne a most glorious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest
ouer our owne corrupt nature
mastering heereby the pride of ou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
hearts; whose fruit is anger; and effec<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
reuenge. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>3 We attaine not onely the spiritua<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
meaning, but the most difficult practis<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
of the law of God, and so hasten to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            <p>4 Heereby also we may winne them
or make them inexcusable, or bridl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
them at the least. <hi>Pro. 25. Pro.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now the loue that we ought to shew to
our enemie, Is,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 In heart louingly and heartily to
affect him, so far forth as that we desir<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
euen the saluation of his soule, and s<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
consequently of his body, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Secondly in speech.</hi> Math. 5. 21
Blesse them that curse you. 1 Sam. 24. 7.</p>
            <p>3 <hi>In action, &amp;c.</hi> Doe good to them
1 Iohn. 3. 18. Exod. 23. 4. Prou. 25. 21
2 Reg. 6. 14. 19. 21.</p>
            <p>4 Yea, in that action which may mos<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
benefit their soules, namely Prayer
<hi>Luke 23. 34. Act.</hi> 7. 60.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:19145:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Exception.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 We must put a difference betweene
the cause and the person, the person we
must loue, but hate the cause. <hi>Psal. 139.
21.</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>2 Some enemies are publisht and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest
against God and his truth: Others
priuate to our selues and secret, these
we must loue, the other we may hate.
1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 22.</p>
            <p>3 Publike enemies are either cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
such as will receiue instruction, &amp;c.
these we must pray for, &amp;c. or incurable,
such as scorne instruction and prosecute
the meanes; these to be prayed against:
and so <hi>Dauid</hi> &amp; <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 109. 10.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> prayed against
Gods enemies, as hauing a speciall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight
into their finall estates,<note place="margin">Act. 8. 19.</note> by extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
illumination,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 14.</note> and spirit of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy,
which because wee haue not,
therefore we are 1. not to pray peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily
against them, as if we did iudge
them finally, 2. but conditionally, &amp; one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
respecting their present estate, where
in they do desperately oppose the truth:
3. yea rather praying that by some tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall
iudgement the LORD would
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19145:23"/>
crosse their purposes, and bring them
to repentance, then that they might be
left to finall vengeance. So these places
are to be expounded. 1 <hi>Ioh. 5. 16. Deut.
7.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And this reproueth</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 The Popish loue,<note place="margin">Vse.</note> which hold, that we
are bound not to hate, but not alwaies
to loue our enemies, saue in two cases:
1. When he is in necessity.<note place="margin">Note.</note> 2. In the case
of scandall; we giue offence to others in
not relieuing him.</p>
            <p>2 The practise of the world, which
rendreth what euill it may, and preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
cause.</p>
            <p>3 Though it forgiue, yet it will not
forget.</p>
            <p>4 We must not professe enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
any.</p>
            <p>5 Nor speake euill of them, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>A fift point in Beneficence,<note place="margin">Sect. 1.</note> is, that it
be done in loue: </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>That is,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THat my bounty proceede from a
tender heart, in true compassion of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19145:23"/>
my neighbours estate,<note place="margin">Mat. 15. 3<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and hearty desire,
to giue him sound comfort hereby:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This shall appeare,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 If I principally respect his soule,
and in all my bounty labour the good
thereof.</p>
            <p>2 When together with my outward
reliefe I ioyne louing speech, and sweete
behauiour, and make my selfe equall
with him of low degree. <hi>Esay. 58. 7. Hide
not thy selfe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3 When together with my well-doing
I preuent such euils as are inward: by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe,
exhortation, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>4 And doe it, also to that end, that
God may enlarge his bounty ouer him,
not to hinder him from further com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts,
eyther from God or man.</p>
            <p>5 And be not weary hereof, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
prouoke to aske, then denie being
asked.</p>
            <p>6 To this end ioyne we prayer to
our bounty, that God may blesse it; else
it may proue a curse to our selues, and to
the receiuer. <hi>Pro.</hi> 12. 10.</p>
            <p>7 And be wee not driuen off from
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19145:24"/>
well-doing, eyther by the malice of the
world, or vnthankfulnesse of receiuers,
or hardnesse of the times, or example
of oppressors, but know we that true
loue respects none of these.</p>
            <p>8 And to testifie our loue herein, we
are bound not onely to giue when it is
demanded, but euen priuately to enquire
and seeke out the poore among vs, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
the most honest poore will
hardly discouer their wants) and so ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly
minister vnto them.</p>
            <p>9 To this end it is not amisse, euen
with our owne hands to distribute what
God hath enlarged vs to, to the greater
comfort of the poore, and better securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
of our Almes: not to reserue it to the
end of our liues, when wee must part
with it, whether we will or no, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>10 Yea hitherto appertayneth, that
we receiue such small tokens as the
poore offer vs, to testifie their thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
&amp;c.</p>
            <p>11 Then also doe I giue in loue when
I so prouide that my charity may doe
good.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:19145:24"/>
            <p>
               <hi>To this purpose is required.<note place="margin">Sect. 3. Charitie when it doth good.</note>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 That I giue not niggardly, to linger
them in misery, but plentifully, that so I
may recouer them out of the estate of
pinching famine, and so enable them to
strength, and labouring for themselues.</p>
            <p>2 As I relieue them thus farre; so here
I must not cease, least health not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed
make way for idlenesse, and so
for all manner of sinne. And therefore
now I must prouide that idlenesse be
preuented, by seeing them imployed in
some handie-craft, or such like, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto
they are fittest, and if they will
not labour not to relieue them.</p>
            <p>3 I am bound to testifie this loue by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing
them for their idlenesse, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering
them by the helpe of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate
to punishment, if neede be, for
the same; yea, I am to supply them with
some stocke as their trustinesse shall be,
and to watch ouer them brotherly, that
they may follow their callings, taking
some account of them, and withall adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
them as occasion shall serue.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:19145:25"/>
            <head>CHAP. X.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>A sixt Circumstance in Beneficence is,
that it be constant, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable:</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>As Pro. 5. 15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>HErein, best resembling the mercy of
God, which is continuall.</p>
            <p>2 Best trying our faith: <hi>And,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3 Seruiug most for the comfort, and
occasions of the poore, who if they shall
be alwaies with vs, then we must not
omit to relieue them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is seene,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 In relieuing him so often as his oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion
shall require, if wee be able; not
putting him off with this; that he must
now seeke elsewhere, but reioycing that
we haue still this meanes to sanctifie our
estate; and being glad herein to preuent
others. <hi>Math. 26. 11. Pro. 22. 2. Rom. 12.
13. Gal.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Because,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Our God deales so with vs, as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
as we seeke, he supplies; and we must
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19145:25"/>
be mercifull as our heauenly Father is
mercifull.</p>
            <p>2 Hereby we preuent much distra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
and endlesse labour, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
we put him to, in putting him ouer
to others.</p>
            <p>3 The Church is freed from inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
and idle persons, by this constant
contribution. 2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 3. 6. 7. 8. 9.</p>
            <p>4 To this end serues that common
treasury, to be leauied and stored vp for
the poore, of which before.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>A seauenth thing to be considered in
Beneficence is the ends thereof,</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>Which are,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 THe assurance of saluation to the
giuer, who testifieth hereby the
truth of his faith. 1 <hi>Iam. 23. And layeth
vp a good foundation against the day of
Christ 1 Tim.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>2 Is the benefit of the party, both in
soule and body, to whom he giueth.</p>
            <p>3 The good of the Church of God
which is hereby both honoured by the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19145:26"/>
maintenance of her members.<note place="margin">Leuit. 25.</note> 2. And
prouoked to the like by such examples.<note place="margin">Deut. 15. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>3 And 3. hereby enabled and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly
preserued, when the word and
meanes thereof are maintained.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hence followeth the</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Necessity of the maintenance for
Ministers, 1 <hi>Cor. 94. Gal.</hi> 6. 6.</p>
            <p>2 The equity of Tithes to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose.
<hi>Deut. 16. 16. 12. 19. Act.</hi> 21. 24.
not as a matter of Almes, but due, <hi>Luke
10. 7. 1 Tim.</hi> 5. 3.</p>
            <p>4 This Beneficence hath good place
in the solemne duties of Gods worship,
as a part and inseparable companion
thereof, <hi>So</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 It is a part of the sanctifying of the
Sabbath in generall. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 1.</p>
            <p>2 A necessary companion of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
Thankesgiuings. <hi>Hest. 9. Nehem.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>3 As also publike fasts are not well
solemnized without it. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 25.</p>
            <p>4 It doth accompany the Ministerie
of the word. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>5 Hitherto also belongeth those re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenewes
which haue beene giuen to the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19145:26"/>
maintenance, and repayre of the house
of God. Which howsoeuer in some part
to superstitious vses, yet by the godly
haue beene well conuerted, and esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished
to such good ends.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And so are to be continued and increased,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 So that we remember we are in the
time of the Gospell, where lesse outward
pompe is required<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then vnder the law.
<hi>Exod. 36. 5. 6. Hagg. 1. Mala. 1. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2 Where the Lord is to be worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
in spirit and truth, and not in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
ceremonies &amp; vnnecessary vanity.</p>
            <p>3 Where we are sometimes to remit of
our right, rather then to stand vpon vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necessary
and superfluous maintenance.
<hi>Ezra. 8. 22. Act. 20. 33. 34<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1 Cor. 4. 12.
2 Cor. 12. 13. 1 Thessa. 2. 3. 4. 5. 17. 9.
2 Thess.</hi> 3. 8.</p>
            <p>1 As when the Church is in some ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary
persecution and difficulty.</p>
            <p>2 To stoppe the mouth of false Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
and accusers, that condemne the
Ministery as mercenary, and that they
doe all for what will you giue.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:19145:27"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And this</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Condemneth the vnsatiable ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
and couetousnesse of the Church of
Rome.</p>
            <p>2 And generally all such as would
bring religion from the heart to the eye,
and set vp a pompous and carnall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship.</p>
            <p>3 It teacheth all faithfull Pastors to
be content with a sober maintenance, and
to beare a part of the burthen of the
Church in all the difficulties &amp; streights
thereof.</p>
            <p>5 And lastly and especially, as aboue
all, the maine end is, The glory of God.
1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 31.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which we wholy respect by,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Priuate &amp; secret liberality, not blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
a trumpet, &amp;c. but so that our right
hand may not know what our left hand
doth, <hi>Math.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>2 This principally reports the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility
of the heart, which if it be free
from hypocrisie and vaine-glory, it skills
not though the gift be open.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:19145:27"/>
3 By thankefulnesse vnto God that
hath made vs, not onely able, but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to part with our owne, and that in
such good order and measure as that we
may be perswaded of the acceptance
thereof. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. 14.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Now because things will better appeare by
comparison of their contraries, therefore ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
shewed, the good properties belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to Beneficence; let vs now in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
place consider of such Vices as
are contrary to godly and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
Beneficence.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>These are of two sorts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 SVch as hinder the same altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.<note place="margin">Of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficence.</note>
            </p>
            <p>2 Such as corrupt and peruert the
power and sincerity thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Those which hinder altogether are,<note place="margin">Sect. 1.</note>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Couetousnesse, whereby we thinke
we neuer haue enough for our selues.
<hi>Haba.</hi> 2. 2. And so in steed of giuing, rake
what we can from others.</p>
            <p>2 Churlishnesse, whereby we cannot
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19145:28"/>
endure to doe good to others, as neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting
society, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>3 Pride, as thinking our selues worthy
of all things, and therefore wee will not
part with any thing.</p>
            <p>4 Enuy, as not enduring the good of
another, and therefore wee will rather
choake our selues then others shall haue
good by vs, nay we will hurt our selues,
that we may hurt others.</p>
            <p>5 A base account of God and his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,
and his seruants. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. Who is
<hi>Dauid?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>6 Distrust in Gods prouidence, as if
we should want our selues if we should
distribute to others.</p>
            <p>7 Confidence in riches which hath so
possessed and forestalled our hearts, as
that they haue no corner to admit com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion
to others.</p>
            <p>8 Selfe-loue, as if all were too little for
vs, &amp; we could not bestow too much cost
on our selues, being onely borne for our
selues.</p>
            <p>9 Voluptuousnes which so imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
our state, and drowneth vs in
pleasure, as that wee regard not the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19145:28"/>
of <hi>Ioseph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>10 Atheisme, thinking this life to be
onely our happinesse, and therefore wee
will take our fill, &amp; wholy possesse it our
selues, &amp; none shall share with vs therein.</p>
            <p>11 Vnnaturalnesse, as hauing broken
the bands of nature, and so neglecting
all duties thereto. 1 <hi>Rom. 27. 2 Tim. 3.
5.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Those which seeke to corrupt our
Beneficence are,<note place="margin">Sect. 2.</note>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>1. On the left hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Hypocrisie, whereby we make shew
of what we meane not to doe.</p>
            <p>2 Vaine-glory, doing it to be magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
of men.</p>
            <p>3 Conceit of merit, as if God were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding
to vs, and we did a worke of su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererogation.</p>
            <p>4 Iniustice, giuing of ill gotten goods.</p>
            <p>5 Superstition, when we doe good to
maintayne Idolatry, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>6 Pollicy, when we do good for a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
hurt, or to procure vnto our selues
some greater benefit of men.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:19145:29"/>
            <p>
               <hi>2 On the right hand,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>7 Prodigality, giuing beyond our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility.</p>
            <p>8 Presumption of Gods prouidence
hence.</p>
            <p>9 Neglect of spirituall and ciuill
meanes to vphold our estates.</p>
            <p>10 Vnthankefulnesse vnto God for
enabling vs hereto.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Further consider we such Motiues as
may stirre vs vp to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance
thereof:</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>These are,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 THe commandement of God, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly
enioyning the same. <hi>Galat.
10. Math.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>2 The examples of the Saints that
haue beene plentifull herein. Our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
himselfe though he liued of Almes,
yet he gaue bountifully. <hi>Math.</hi> 15. 32. so
<hi>Abraham, Lot, Iacob, Ioseph, &amp;c. Gen. 18.
Gen. 19. Gen. 47. Exod. 2. Exod. 18. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,
&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:19145:29"/>
3 The benefits that doe redound to
Gods children hereby, which are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifolde.</p>
            <p>1 What we doe here inconscionably,
it is accepted as done to God, and Christ
themselues. <hi>Math. 10. 40. 41. Math.</hi> 25.</p>
            <p>2 The Lord will recompence it, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the excellency of the occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
which he vouchsafeth to giue, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
greater or lesser, and according to
the greater, or lesser measure of saith and
loue, wherein the same duties are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed:
yet so as the least kindnesse
done in truth, shall be requited with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifolde
aduantage. <hi>Gal. 6. 6. 1 Tim. 6. 1.
Hagg.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>3 This will be a great comfort vnto
vs in the time of trouble. <hi>Iob.</hi> 30. As also
a pledge of our recouery out of the
same.<note place="margin">Esay. 58.</note> 2 <hi>Chron. 31. 1 King. 18. 13. Psal.
37. 25. 26. Pro.</hi> 13. 22.</p>
            <p>4 Yea, hereby the Saints are prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
and emboldned to pray for mercy
for others: and so cannot be denied it.
2 <hi>Tim. 1. 16. 17. 18. Phil. 4. 17. 18. 19. 10.
1 Reg. 17. 15. 2 Reg.</hi> 48.</p>
            <p>5 The very wicked haue beene blessed
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19145:30"/>
for their beneficence to the Saints. <hi>Act.
28. Gen.</hi> 42. 43. 44. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>6 It is a meanes to establish and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
our estates for euer. <hi>Psal. 122.
6.</hi> 9. 10. to our posterity. &amp;c. <hi>Pro. 13.
22.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>7 Yea, an vndoubted pledge of our
right, and enioying of euerlasting happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.
<hi>Math. 25. 40. Pro.</hi> 11. 17.</p>
            <p>8 The more we scatter, the more we
encrease our estate in this life. <hi>Pro. 11.
24. 25. Pro.</hi> 28. 27.</p>
            <p>9 We make the Lord hereby a deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor
vnto vs. <hi>Pro.</hi> 19. 17.</p>
            <p>10 Hereby ill gotten goods are san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified.
<hi>Ezech. 18. 7. 8. Luke.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>11 It is the meanes to make our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
accepted of God. <hi>Esay.</hi> 58. 7. 8. 9.</p>
            <p>12 Yea, hereby we haue receiued An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels
into our houses. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>13 Obserue we how <hi>Iob, Ezechiah</hi>
and others, were abundantly recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.
<hi>Iob.</hi> 42.</p>
            <p>14 Hereby wee gather much assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
that we are in the fauour of God
1 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3. 14.</p>
            <p>15 We approue our selues to be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19145:30"/>
and true members of Iesus Christ.
1 <hi>Cor. 12. Iohn.</hi> 15.</p>
            <p>16 And manifest our selues to be like
vnto our heauenly Father. <hi>Iam. 1. 5. 6.
Math.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>17 And doe witnesse that we are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers
of the holy Ghost.</p>
            <p>18 We adorne and beautifie our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession.</p>
            <p>19 And make our calling sure. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 9</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Motiues hereto,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4 Weigh we the vncertainty &amp; danger
of riches, and thinke we how by libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
we make them durable and eternall.</p>
            <p>5 By liberality to the poore all super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous
expences are cut off in Diet, and
Apparrell, and the like, Buildings, Plate,
and so, much sinne preuented.</p>
            <p>6 Hereby we shew our selves faithfull
Stewards vnto God in a right bestowing
of the blessings hee hath put vs in trust
withall. <hi>Math.</hi> 25.</p>
            <p>7 VVe make the liues of the Saints
comfortable, and ease them of many
grieuous burthens.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:19145:31"/>
            <head>CHAP. XIIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Consider we wisely some helpes and
preparatiues to Beneficence:</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>And for our better encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
herein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 VVE must consider wisely of the
poore and needy, that is, Iudge
charitably of them. <hi>Psal.</hi> 41. 1. 2.</p>
            <p>2 Hereupon will follow: a taking to
heart of their estate, and true compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
thereof.</p>
            <p>3 This will be furthered by conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
that it may be our case, and so as
we would be comforted our selues, we
are moued to comfort them.</p>
            <p>4 Hereupou yet to moue compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
more, we proceed to take notice of
their misery, to reason with them of it,
to enter into the house of mourning;
and discerne the particulers thereof.</p>
            <p>5 Hereupon we con<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ue the necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
and equity of doing good, and so
are conuinced in conscience, that it
must be done.</p>
            <p>6 And so as we are perswaded in our
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19145:31"/>
hearts, we proceede to seasonable boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
and so cause the loynes of the poore
to blesse vs. <hi>Iob.</hi> 30.</p>
            <p>7 To this purpose consider we, that
the poore in their neede are true ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
of what God hath made vs Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
of. <hi>Pro.</hi> 3. 27.</p>
            <p>8 And that wee may be willing to
powre out to others, set wee not our
hearts vpon these things. <hi>Psal.</hi> 62.</p>
            <p>9 Consider that these blessings are
burthens vnto vs, and therefore by
giuing to the poore, we ease our selues
of this burthen, and goe lightlier to
heauen.</p>
            <p>10 Yea, wee ease them of their bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
of pouerty, that they may also be
more cheerefull companions in our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly
iourney with vs.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:19145:32"/>
            <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Obserue we the punishments that are due
and haue beene inflicted vpon such as haue
fayled in this duty of Beneficence, and
exercised the contrary sinne
of Cruelty and Vnmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>1 <hi>THe neglect of this duety hath
been punished with famine.</hi> Hag.
2. Esr. 7. 23. Mal, 3. 8. 9. 11. Pro. 20. 25.</p>
            <p>2 The vnmercifull man is vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued
of all comfort in his soule, from
God, of all his riches. <hi>Eccl. 6. 1. &amp;</hi> 59.</p>
            <p>3 God esteemeth these as vsurpers
of such blessings which they doe not san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie
through liberality.</p>
            <p>4 God takes away riches when they
are not thus imployed. <hi>Pro.</hi> 11. 24.</p>
            <p>5 <hi>Yea, when they are in need he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuseth
to succour them.</hi> Pro. 13. 21. Zac.
7. 8. Mich. 3. 1. 2. 3. 4.</p>
            <p>6 If we doe not hinder what we may
the cruelty of others, there is grieuous
punishment threatned. <hi>Pro. 24. 10. 11.
12. 1 Sam.</hi> 14. 45.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:19145:32"/>
7 This want of bounty is a meanes to
shorten the dayes of men, as <hi>Pro. 55. 23.
Psal. 140. 11. 12. Psal.</hi> 11. 26.</p>
            <p>8 Heereby men doe expose them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
to the curses of the poore. <hi>Pro. 11.
26. Exod.</hi> 22. 23. 24. which God will take
notice of and auenge.</p>
            <p>9 Yea, this is the meanes to bring a
curse, not onely on themselues, but
on their posteritie. <hi>Psalm. 109. 6. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem.
5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>10 Sodaine death is likewise a fruit of
this sinne. 1 <hi>Sam 25. 9. Psal.</hi> 73. 19. 20.</p>
            <p>11 Yea, it is the cause of a most shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
and dishonourable death. <hi>Ierem. 22.
13. Esay.</hi> 14. 3. 4. 5. 6. and that such shall
become a prouerbe, and by-word to all
posterity. <hi>Abac<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 2. 6.</p>
            <p>12 This was one of the sinnes, for
which Sodom was so destroyed. <hi>Ezec. 16.
49.</hi> &amp; the old world drowned. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 13.</p>
            <p>13 The vnmercifull person is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
then a rotten braunch cut off from
the true Communion of Christ, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer
hee be in the Church, and in shew
a member thereof. 1 <hi>Cor. 11. 1 Tim.</hi>
6. 5</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:19145:33"/>
14 <hi>The couetous person shall not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit
the Kingdome of heauen.</hi> 1 Cor. 6.
10. Ephes. 5. 5. Psal. 17. 14. 1 Tim. 6. 9. 10.
Psal. 69. 22. Iam. 2. 13. <hi>iudgement merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse.</hi>
Math. 25. 41. 42.</p>
            <p>15 Hereby a wicked man doth most
resemble his father the diuell; <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. and
so hath his condemnation already.</p>
            <p>16 It transformes men into bruite
beasts: so the holy Ghost calls oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors.
<hi>Amos 4. Psal.</hi> 10. to a Lion, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XVI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Heere then is a Glasse for diuers sorts
of men to looke their faces in.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>1 FOr those that rob their Ministers
in tithes and offerings.<note place="margin">The vse to be made of these pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishments.</note> 
               <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>2 That deny contributions to the
poore, and enlarge not towards them.</p>
            <p>3 For Officers in corporations, who
are put in trust with Legacies giuen to
the poore, that they imploy them to the
best aduantage.</p>
            <p>4 For such ouerseers of Testaments,
that they licke not their owne fingers,
but faithfully distribute.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:19145:33"/>
5 For masters of Hospitals, that they
make not their places matter of prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
but indeed, as they were first in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended,
places of bounty, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>6 For Almoners, &amp;c. that they beare
not the bagge as <hi>Iudas</hi> did, and thinke
the cost ill bestowed that is imployed
on Christs poore members.</p>
            <p>7 For euery priuate Christian to make
him friends of his Mammon, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XVII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Lastly obserue we such Lets and Tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
as Satan vseth to hinder this
duety,<note place="margin">Sect. 1.</note> and how we are to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
the same.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>Of Tentations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 COncerning their owne estate:<note place="margin">Tent.</note> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan
alledgeth, that they are our
owne, and therefore we may dispose
them as we list: and why not wholly for
our pleasure and profit?</p>
            <p>2 They are no otherwise our owne,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> then
that wee are Gods Stewards to dispence
them according to his word, which see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
it commandeth vs to imploy them
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19145:34"/>
on the poore, therefore we may not lay
them all on our owne backes and bellies,
least they proue nothing lesse then
goods vnto vs.</p>
            <p>But all is little enough for my selfe,<note place="margin">Sect. 1.</note>
(may the miser reply,)<note place="margin">Tent.</note> charges are so
great, and gettings so rare: and therefore
though I haue more then many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands,
yet I haue enough to doe for my
selfe.</p>
            <p>1 If thou which hast such abundance,<note place="margin">Conquest.</note>
hast tittle enough for thy selfe, how little
then haue they, that haue nothing to
take to?</p>
            <p>2 If God then will prouide for these,
doest thou doubt, by obeying Gods
commandement in relieuiug these, to be
scanted?</p>
            <p>3 Who hast already experience of
Gods mercy aboue these, and if thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuest
shalt see greater things then these.</p>
            <p>4 And hast this abundance giuen
thee, to impart vnto these, that by this
means thy store may be increased. Feare
not thou want where God commands
to distribute, and beleeue the promise,
that thou shalt haue plenty.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:19145:34"/>
5 And as God restrayneth his hand
in such scarce and miserable times, so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straine
thou thy vnnecessary expence in
apparrell and diet, and so thou shalt haue
yet to spare, for thy needfull brother.</p>
            <p>6 And liue here by faith, and not by
sence, so shalt thou be encreased, though
thou mayest feare the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If I should giue to euery one,<note place="margin">Sect. 1.</note> I may soone
giue all away, and so I shall make
my selfe a beggar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 God would haue thee in giuing first
to prouide for thy selfe, and therefore
thou maist not giue to all. <hi>Neither</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2 God hath so enlarged thee, as that
thou canst giue vnto all, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
he requires no more then for what
he giues.</p>
            <p>3 Thou art to giue onely to such, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
whom present occasion is offred,
in discouering their present necessity, and
so much onely as in good discretion is
meete, vpon such speciall occasion.</p>
            <p>4 Thy rule here must be thy ability,
and from thy loue to thy selfe must pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
thy loue to thy neighbour.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="chapter">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:19145:35"/>
            <head>CHAP. XVIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Of Tentations concerning care of
our Posteritie.<note place="margin">Sect. 1.</note>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>I But (saith Satan) thou must prouide
for thy posterity.<note place="margin">Tent.</note> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. to leaue
them portions, they are neerest thee,
&amp;c.</p>
            <p>1 Thou shalt best prouide for them
by sanctifying thine estate,<note place="margin">Conquest.</note> and lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
vp for them in the Treasurie of the
poore.</p>
            <p>2 As also by leauing the care of them
to God, in the obedience to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement:
who eyther will so blesse
thy beneficence that thou shalt be able
to leaue them sufficient: or if necessary
occasion require thy further employing,
or the Lord hereby haue a purpose to
try thy faith: know thou, that the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity
of the faithfull are the Lords por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
and he will see them prouided for
abundantly.</p>
            <p>3 No Scripture enioyneth vs to
leaue a set portion to our children: that
which is implyed thereby is, that wee
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19145:35"/>
be not guiltie of neglect and carelesnesse
herein.</p>
            <p>4 The best patrimony Parents can
leaue their children is true Godlinesse.
<hi>Psal. 37. 26. Psal.</hi> 112. 2.</p>
            <p>5 And therefore so to prouide for
our children, as that wee neglect this
principall duety of charity, is to betray
our children, and expose them to all
misery. <hi>Psal.</hi> 109.</p>
            <p>6 Yea, hereby Parents commit a
double sinne. First in not taking a right
course for the prouision of his children.
Secondly, hereby also he prouoketh his
children to esteeme more their earthly,
then their heauenly Patrimony, and so
with the Cadarens, to preferre their
Swine before Iesus Christ.</p>
            <p>7 Because the children of rich men
are vsually gracelesse, &amp;c. therefore it is
farre better to be a father to many Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes,
or fatherlesse children, in feeding
and cherishing them, of Christian loue
and pitie, for the Lords sake, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesseth
himselfe a father vnto them, then
to leaue the greatest abundance that may
be to such children of a mans owne, as
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19145:36"/>
for want of grace shew themselues so
lewdly minded, that they will wantonly
and vnthriftily spend all that shall be left
vnto them. And therefore it hath beene
the practise of many godly Christians to
supply for the present, where there
hath beene neede in Gods Church. As
for their children, they haue rather in
their life time put them to honest trades,
whereby they might be able to liue of
themselues, then to leaue them any
great portion after their deaths.</p>
            <p>8 The summe is, that we know the
commandements of God are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
to each other: as if because the
Lord bids vs prouide for our families,
this did contrary that other commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement,
to distribute to the poore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
But rather that the one is a meanes to
the performance of the other. They
both implying frugality, and conscio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
cariage in our ciuill callings:<note place="margin">Note.</note> by
which wee shall be inabled to both these
duties, and each of them furthering
the other: namely, that in pitying the
poore, wee shall prouide for our fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
because there is an extraordinary
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19145:36"/>
promise of God to such beneficence, and
in carefull prouiding for our family,
we shall also be moued to relieue the
poore: because they are our flesh al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so,
<hi>Esay.</hi> 58. So that in trueth he doth
not prouide truely for his children that
respects not the poore: Neyther doth
he wisely respect the poore, that is not
moued to begin at home, because he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
continue herein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But yet Satan replyes further.<note place="margin">Sect. 2.</note>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou hast Daughters as well as
Sonnes:<note place="margin">Tent.</note> these will not be preferred
without portions, their bringing vp will
becostly, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>My Daughters vertue and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
shall be her best portion,<note place="margin">Resist.</note> which
that she may be furnished withall. Her
education shall be such, as may hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
her, and subdue the corruption
of nature: little cost will serue this
turne. As for a portion of goods,
hee that will haue my Daughter shall
giue mee somewhat for her. So was it
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19145:37"/>
among the Iewes, so it was among the
Saints. If her vertue will not marry her,
a portion will rather marre her marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age:
for so long as it lasts, so long shall
my daughter be beloued, and it is not
my daughter, but her portion that shall
be maried.</p>
            <p>And seeing my purpose is that my
daughter shall haue the blessing of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage,
therefore I will rather make choice
of a man who will take my daughter for
loue, and if there be loue, there will be
no lacke: and what neede then my por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?
Notwithstanding I will respect my
daughter in her place. My God shall
first be honoured with my substance, and
next his poore Saints, my daughter if
she stand more in neede then they, shall
not want necessary comfort; otherwise
she shall depend on the prouidence of
God, as I haue done, and what is her por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
she shall haue it in her place.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="chapter">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:19145:37"/>
            <head>CHAP. XIX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Other Tentations there are in regard of
the pretended vnworthinesse of
those that stand in need to
be relieued.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>1 SAtan obiects:<note place="margin">Tent.</note> That hereby many
shall be, first maintayned in their
idlenesse. Secondly, Which will be
hurtfull to the common-wealth.</p>
            <p>1 Though it be a sinne for the poore,<note place="margin">Reply.</note>
&amp;c. to liue idlely, yet my entent is not
by my liberality to maintayne them in
sinne, but relieue their want, and so to
obey the commandement of God. If
they abuse my mercy, it is their greater
sinne.</p>
            <p>2 Yet that they may not abuse it,
I will see they shall be set on worke, if
they be able, if not I will relieue them
that they may be able, and then if they
will not worke, they shall not eate.</p>
            <p>3 Because I haue not authority to set
them on worke, therefore I will acquaint
the Magistrate, who will supply in this
behalfe.</p>
            <p>4 And what is in my power shall not
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19145:38"/>
be wanting: Namely, godly exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
and admonition to leaue their sinne,
as also more sparing reliefe, as a kinde
of punishment of their idlenesse. By
this meanes I shall performe reliefe
both to soule and body.</p>
            <p>Seeing some poore folkes are suspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
of witchcraft,<note place="margin">Ob.</note> and some conuinced,
shall I therefore giue to those?</p>
            <p>If they be but suspected,<note place="margin">Answ.</note> then they are
to be relieued, because Charity is not su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spicious.
If conuinced, yet I am to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue
them, because hereby I shall heape
coales on their head: And still they are
my flesh, yea hereby I may be a meanes
to bring them to repentance.</p>
            <p>But if I giue them,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> they by this means
haue power ouer me, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If I accept of their company,<note place="margin">Answ.</note> and yet
suspect them to be such, and so for feare,
that they may not hurt me, doe giue
them, then it is iust with God to punish
my infidelity. But if they haue extreame
neede, and so are relieued not of feare
but loue, because my flesh, I shall ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
preuent their malice, or all will be
for the best.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:19145:38"/>
            <p>
               <hi>But Satan replies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though thou giue them neuer so
much,<note place="margin">Tent. 3.</note> they are neuer the better, for it
all goes downe the throat, it is little seene
on them, they haue still as much neede
as euer they had, and therefore it may
seeme that God doth not blesse it vnto
them: and therefore secretly seemes to
forbid thy charity towards them.</p>
            <p>1 Indeede to giue vsually, as the
world, doth sparingly and miserable, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
to linger on a pining state then to
set the poore on their feete, as wee say,
that they may be able to worke for
themselues: this as it doth them little
good, so it is not accepted of God, who
willeth vs to giue, not sparingly, but plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully.</p>
            <p>2 And therefore I will giue, that it
may doe good, with a large hand, as God
hath giuen, to set them vp, and prouide
them of some stocke, and withall to see
to their following of their calling, and
thriuing therein.</p>
            <p>3 If for all my paines and cost I yet
see them neuer the better: yet heere is
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19145:39"/>
my comfort: that God accepteth my
purpose, and my faith is heereby more
tried: that I cast my bread vpon the
waters.</p>
            <p>4 Yet if still I see that no good will
follow, but rather my bounty is wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
abused, to be a cloake for sinne; here
I may lawfully change my soyle, and
sow my seede where there is better
hope.</p>
            <p>5 And yet rather then the vilest should
perish, I am bound and wil relieue them,
though he sinne in receiuing; yet I shall
not sinne in giuing: and my well-doing
shall returne into mine owne bosome.</p>
            <p>Oh but (saith Satan) the poore are the
most vnthankfull wretches that may be,<note place="margin">Tent. 3.</note>
and therefore what comfort canst thou
haue in relieuing them?</p>
            <p>1 I doe not relieue them,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> that they
may be thankefull, but because God hath
commanded so, and promised to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence,
whose faithfulnesse shall content
mee, notwithstanding mans vnthanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse.
<hi>And</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2 If I should seeke praise of men, I
should dishonour my God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19145:39"/>
it is his mercy that men should be
vnthankefull, that so I might giue him
the whole glory of the worke. <hi>Yet</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3 Though I finde men vnthankfull,
yet let me not cease to doe good: for
hereby I shall in the end ouercome euill
with good. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>Seest thou not (saith Satan) what dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblers
these professors are,<note place="margin">Tent. 4.</note> while they
haue neede of thee, who so holy as they,
but yet when their turne is serued, they
embrace the world. And therefore, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
thou knowest not who are the hous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
of faith: nay indeede; canst haue
little hope, but rather to maintaine
hypocrisie, cast not away thy mony, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>1 Though men may deceiue mee,
yet my God will not.</p>
            <p>2 And therefore my well-doing is
not cast away, though the person may
be a cast-away.</p>
            <p>3 It may be I may win him hereby:
If not, I make him without excuse.</p>
            <p>4 And what know I whether I may
not adde sinne to sinne: First in not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieuing
him: Secondly, in iudging him
an hypocrite, seeing the sinne of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19145:40"/>
is so hardly discerned?</p>
            <p>5 Howsoeuer, the person may be:
yet will I not be cast off from doing
good vnto him, because it is not for his
sake, but for the Lords cause, that
I doe it, who will accept my single heart
herein, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owsoeuer he may punish the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
hypocrisie.</p>
            <p>6 Lastly, if I should play the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite,
in not giuing where God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,
vpon such and the like pretences,
where as indeede my wretched and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous
heart is the cause thereof: What
will it aduantage mee to complayne of
the hypocrisie of others, seeing therein
I doe condemne my selfe? And this will
be the issue, that hee will one day con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne
me of hypocrisie for not giuing,
who now pretends his hypocrisie, as not
worthy to receiue.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="chapter">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:19145:40"/>
            <head>CHAP. XX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Other tentations whereby couetous
men would excuse one charge
with another.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>Hearken I pray how Satan assa<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ts
them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 VVHat art thou not charged suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently
with expences for the
Common-wealth,<note place="margin">Tent. 4.</note> and to the Prince,
how many occasions are offered to draw
mony from thee? Is not this sufficient for
one, are not these to goe for beneficence:
and may they not excuse thee to be more
sparing another way? Nay, doest thou
not giue (as thou art ceased,) weekely
contributions? doest thou not more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer
giue some Almes at thy doore, and
what more can they require at thy
hands?</p>
            <p>I call to minde my offences this day:<note place="margin">Answ.</note>
indeede it is vnmercifulnesse that is the
especiall meanes to draw downe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
vpon the land, as famine, wars, &amp;c.
and I cannot excuse my self herein: And
shall I seeke to remoue the iudgement
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19145:41"/>
by the encrease of my sinne? shall I help
forward he affliction by my vnmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse?</p>
            <p>2 If God hath enabled mee to doe
the greater good, namely, to relieue my
Prince and Country, shall I disinable my
selfe to doe the lesse, seeing the char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
of the Prince are so moderate and
conscionable?</p>
            <p>3 If my Prince be partaker of my
goods, &amp;c. is it any more then is due
vnto him? Nay, owe I him not my body
goods and all? And doth not he plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
make me amends by the benefit of
the law? May I not ease my selfe? nay, do
not rich men beare least of this burthen?
Is not the protection of the Prince a suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
recompence hereof? Am I not
hereby better enabled to doe good to
others?</p>
            <p>4 Besides, what triall is this of my
bounty to doe that which is due? Nay
what will be exacted of mee whether I
will or no? Ought I not therefore to
doe good otherwise, where it is in my
choyce?</p>
            <p>5 If the Lord offer extraordinarie
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19145:41"/>
publike occasions: this shall not hinder
me to shew my willing minde: what I
am able (God willing) I will beare a part
in the burthen, and ease the affliction.</p>
            <p>6 As for determining what is suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
it is not in my choyse where God
commands the contrary, and therefore
I may not neglect the poore, though I
thinke I am sufficiently charged else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where,
seeing the same God that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,
will enable me to performe.</p>
            <p>7 And what if I giue weekely to the
poore? this I am compelled to: and
what triall is heere? this I may doe of
vaine-glory: and where is then my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward?
doth not my God daily giue?
doth hee stint his mercies? Is not his
hand continually enlarged? and shall I
shut my bounty? where he offers occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion?</p>
            <p>8 As for the Almes that is giuen at my
doore, this is wrung from me, and done
vsually for custome: I must moreouer
visite the fatherlesse, if I will be truely
religious: and seeke out where I may
doe good, not onely be sought to
for it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:19145:42"/>
9 It is not what man may require
or be contented withall, but what my
God requires and enables me to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme,
my conscience witnessing here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto,
and occasions offered to manifest
the same.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A second Tentation that sets vpon
vs, in this kinde, is drawne
from</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Such contributions and layes as
are leauied about the Church, for repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
            <p>2 That which goes out towards the
maintenance of the Ministery.</p>
            <p>3 For Bread and Wine at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,
&amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hereupon Satan vrgeth thus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God is a Spirit, and he will be worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
in Spirit, what then neede so much
about outward decencie and comeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse?</p>
            <p>1 Why should the Ministers take
Tythes in these dayes? This is Iudaisme,
which they say, is abolished; 2. Why
ought they not to labour with their
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19145:42"/>
hands, as the Apostles did, to ease the
charge of the people.</p>
            <p>3 Why will not a reading Minister
serue the turne, who will serue for lesse?
Seeing thou mayest as well edifie by
him, as by a Preacher, whom thou canst
not vnderstand, who will seeke to curbe
thee, and crosse thee in thy pleasures?
And if I must needs be charged with all
these, is not this great liberality? Can
you require more at my hands?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For answere hereunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Know wee that spirituall worship
cannot be performed publikely without
the helpe of the body:<note place="margin">Answ.</note> for which, seeing
there must be a set place of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship;
therefore it is fit it be so prouided,
that not onely the body be sheltred from
iniury and danger, but fitted also by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency
and order to the seruice of God.</p>
            <p>2 Which seeing it may be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
excessiue charge, therefore much
the rather ought conuenient cost to be
bestowed hereupon.</p>
            <p>3 And if the Lord be at the cost to
bestow his sonne vpon vs, is it not reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19145:43"/>
that we should be at the charge of
such sacramentall signes as may repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
and seale vp the benefit of our sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation
vnto vs?</p>
            <p>4 As for Tithes due to the maintenance
of the Ministery, howsoeuer they were
inioyned by the ceremoniall law, yet the
equity of them is morall, and so to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
for euer.</p>
            <p>1 Because they were paid by the law
of Nature, before euer the Ceremoniall
law was instituted. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 9. 10.</p>
            <p>2 They are not now required to be
paid in any ceremonious or figurate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect,
but as a morall duty, to the vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
and maintenance of the diuine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,
according to the affirmatiue part of
the second commandement, of the first
Table: And as a duty of ciuill honour
and iustice, according to the fift &amp; eight
commandement of the second Table.</p>
            <p>3 As the Sabbath remaynes, though
the Ceremony be changed, so ought
Tithes to remayne for the maintenance
of the ministery, to the sanctifying of
the Sabbath, the Ceremony being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:19145:43"/>
4 Vnlesse the Christian Magistrate
(in whose hands the ordering of such
things doth lie) shall determine of a like
bountifull and constant course for the set
maintenance of the Ministery.</p>
            <p>As for the example of the Apostle
<hi>Paul</hi> in working with his owne hands.</p>
            <p>1 There was no other of the Apostles
but he, that did so.</p>
            <p>2 He presseth none to doe the like by
his example, vnlesse vpon very speciall
and extraordinary occasion as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.
7. 8. 9. 10.</p>
            <p>3 Nay as allowing a certayne and set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
course of maintenance, he preuents
&amp; meets with this vnkinde obiection of
this kinde of people, as 1 <hi>Cor. 9. 1 Tim.
5.</hi> 17. 18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>4 Besides the times then and now
are different.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Then the Church was in her cradle,
now shee is in her growth, then not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stablished
by the Magistrate, who is the
approuer and confirmer of the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
of Ministers, as now it is. 2 Then
the Apostles were furnished with extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary
gifts of miracles, &amp;c. to procure
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19145:44"/>
and compel extraordinary maintenance.
<hi>Act.</hi> 5. Now these gifts are ceased.</p>
            <p>3 Then mens hearts were inflamed
with the power of godlinesse. For then
happy was hee that could lay downe
his possessions at the feete of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles.
<hi>But</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the forme of Godlinesse hath
bred coldnesse of compassion, so that
glad is hee that can withdraw from the
Ministery.</p>
            <p>4 There the zeale of teaching sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued
men to the Church. Now the zeale
of teaching, because the Haruest is well
in, driues hypocrites out of the Church.
And winnowes the Wheat into a narrow
compasse. And therefore if the Ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
should not haue a set maintenance,
seeing it necessarily prouokes enmitie,
and maintaynes such opposition against
the world, little voluntary deuotion
would appeare.</p>
            <p>Lastly, let these consider what their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers
haue parted with to the Queene
of heauen, and the Golden Calfe, &amp;c.
<hi>Ier. 44. Exod.</hi> 32. And see whether their
blinde deuotion will not condemne this
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19145:44"/>
repining of their children to maintaine
the sinceritie of Gods worship.</p>
            <p>Nay let them wisely consider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
they spend not more vnnecessarily
and wickedly vpon the idols of their
belly and backe, then vpon the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
of the worship of God.</p>
            <p>And if they can content themselues
with a Leuite that wil serue for ten Shec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kels,
and a suite of rayment, because they
will not be at the charge of the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of the Gospell, let them looke to be
serued as <hi>Micha</hi> was, their Leuite will be
the man to betray their soules, through
ignorance, prophannesse and the like,
and if he can finde a better Master, their
hireling will shew them a fayre payre of
heeles.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XXI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Another tentation which Satan hath
to hinder true bounty and libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
to the poore, Is</p>
            </argument>
            <p>FRom pretence of such expences as
are wastfully imployed in keeping
great excesse at Christmas, &amp;c. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19145:45"/>
he inferreth that the poore being
fufficiently relieued the in, they may
be excused all there yeere after: and so
hath brought it to passe among great
ones generally, that so they keepe iolly
rout and riot at that time, they priuiledge
themselues from further hospitality.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the encountring of which Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Know they, that this solemnity of
feastings at that time, is one of those
works of supererogation which one day
will be brought within the compasse of
that Quere. <hi>VVho required these things
at their hands. Esay.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>2 Admit it were lawfull to vse such
excesse at that time, yet is it farre from
true bounty.</p>
            <p>1 Because the poore haue least part
thereof, they are no fit guests at these
times, especially religious poore will
marre the sport.</p>
            <p>2 What they haue is not wholesome
and of the better, but the refuse, that
which the Dogs and Swine doe leaue.</p>
            <p>3 They haue it also with sauce of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19145:45"/>
swearing and cursing, and that is farre
from sanctifying the deuotion vnto
them.</p>
            <p>4 The glut that they haue at such
times, makes them more greedy &amp; dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
yea, more idle, and vnfit for their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
and spare diet all the yeere after.</p>
            <p>5 That which they then haue, will
not maintayne them all the yeere, as
they must be relieued. <hi>Nay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>6 Vsually to maintayne such <hi>Bacchus</hi>
feasts, the poore are racked, and fined
and grinded to powder.</p>
            <p>7 And this Charity is also subiect to
such vanity and ostentation, as that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
it is, if it hath it reward in this life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing what is wastfully spent at such
times would maintayne many poore,
euen a whole yeere, it were much better
to abate such vnnecessary expences, and
so at conuenient times to distribute to
the necessity of the Saints.</p>
            <p>Besides these tentations, consider we
certain maine pollicies of Satan, whereby
he hath in these late daies, euen stockt vp
liberality, and vtterly abolished the same.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="22" type="chapter">
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:19145:46"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The first maine pollicy which Satan hath
vsed in these latter dayes to preuent
liberality, is, Enclosing of
grounds, &amp;c.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>BY which his drift is, that the people
of God being turned out of their
dwellings might so perish through the
vnmercifulnesse of the weather, &amp; so the
Land being dispeopled, these cormo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants
might riot freely, no more might
be troubled with the cries of the poore,
might themselues wholly consume, that
they call, their owne, without enuy or
controulement, and so fat vp themselues
against the day of slaughter. <hi>Ier.</hi> 12. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For remedy of which mischiefe I would
such did consider these things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 That the rich and the poore goe
together, the Lord is the ordayner of
them both. If the Lord had not seene
it fit they should be together, he might
and would, no doubt, haue made all rich.
<hi>Pro.</hi> 22. 2. But as our Sauiour saith, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19145:46"/>
the poore wee shall haue alwayes
with vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To what end I pray you with vs? surely,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 That the poore might be a means
to humble the rich: <hi>And</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2 The rich might be a meanes to
comfort the poore.</p>
            <p>3 That so the loynes of the poore
might blesse the rich.</p>
            <p>4 And the fleece of the rich might
cloth the poore: And so of either, such as
doe belong to God might by this means
further each other vnto God. <hi>And</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for such as doe not belong to the
Election, the Lord hath also appointed
this mixture of the poore with the rich,
for the contrary end: <hi>Namely,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 That the estate of the poore might
breede contempt and hardnesse of heart
in the rich. <hi>And</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The oppression of the mighty might
nourish discontentednesse and worldly
sorrow in the poore.</p>
            <p>That the poore hereby being often
prouoked to spoyle the rich.</p>
            <p>The rich might be enraged to make
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19145:47"/>
hauocke of the poore, and so the iustice
of God wonderfully accomplished in
making each other the instrument of
their destruction. And yet all for his
glory and good of his children in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
a Land hereby of much corrupt
bloud, and out of euill manners esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishing
good lawes, yea hereby procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
for the better execution of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Know we that they which by enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures
would roote and weary out the
poore.</p>
            <p>1 They fight against Gods ordinance,
and therefore they shall not prosper; as
may appeare by the visible iudgements
of God daily brought to light vpon such
<hi>Nimrods</hi> and deuourers. <hi>Habac.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>2 They are enemies to Religion, and
the worship of God, being occasions that
the houses of God are laid waste &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted
to Barnes, Stables, and kennels
for hounds, whereby Atheisme &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanenesse
is set in the seat of the scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
            <p>3 They are also enemies to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths:
First, in decaying tillage,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19145:47"/>
which maintains labour, and so keepes in
humility: so that in steede therof, idlenes
and pride is maintained. Secondly, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying
the people, which are the glory of
the Prince, &amp; strength of the land where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon
the land is exposed to the spoyle
of the enemy, as also ciuill wars are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
oft times occasioned, &amp; the Famine,
Pestilence, &amp;c. procured. Thirdly, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
also the estate of Princes is endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered:
In that great ones hauing now
no inferiours to be humbled by, through
the insatiablenesse of pride and ambition
grow to enuy, and so to leauy at the
highest: whereupon proceeds treasons,
and subuersion of Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>4 Our neighbour is many wayes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly
iniuried.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And that</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 As being outlawed, and depriued of
the common benefit of habitation.</p>
            <p>2 Driuen most inconscionable to the
cursed estate of beggery. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>3 Compelled euen to steale, and so
the Author of his owne destruction.</p>
            <p>4 Depriued of the publike benefit of
Gods worship.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:19145:48"/>
5 Forced to a most discontented and
desperate estate.</p>
            <p>5 The greatest wrong of enclosing,
redounds to the Authors themselues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Because,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 They exclude themselues out of
Gods protection, in excluding the poore
out of their protection.</p>
            <p>2 They lye open to Gods heauy curse
in this oppression of the poore.</p>
            <p>3 They depriue themselues of the vse
of Charity, whereby they argue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
to be no better then infidels.</p>
            <p>5 As also they strip themselues of the
vse of society, and so grow sauage and
brutish.</p>
            <p>6 They also exclude themselues from
the necessary protection of their owne
flesh.</p>
            <p>7 And arme the same with crueltie
against them.</p>
            <p>8 Hereby they make way to pride,
and all kinde of impiety.</p>
            <p>9 As also they doe expose themselues
to beggery, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>10 And not onely so, but their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19145:48"/>
is lyable to the curse, and so to
desolation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And that we may grow to an healing of
this euill: Consider we wisely the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
hereof, which are:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Atheisme and contempt of God,
for if wee were contented to be vnder
God, and did acknowledge we held of
him, we would then suffer others to liue
both by vs and vnder vs.</p>
            <p>2 Pride, which cannot endure eyther
equall or inferiour.</p>
            <p>3 Couetousnesse, as if all were too
little for our selues.</p>
            <p>4 Distrust of Gods prouidence, as if
God were not able to prouide for vs, if
so be that others liued by vs.</p>
            <p>5 Hatred of mankinde, in that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
endure his presence and society.</p>
            <p>6 Inordinate loue of this world, and
these corruptible things.</p>
            <p>7 Setting vp our rest in the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
of this life.</p>
            <p>8 As also a secret renouncing of the
heauenly blisse.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:19145:49"/>
9 Enuy of Superiours and disconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tednesse,
which are forerunners of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,
&amp;c.</p>
            <p>10 A bloudy and cruell minde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyd
of all remorse and pitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3 Obserue we the particular reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
of the same,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhich are eyther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Inward, concerning the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the minde.</p>
            <p>2 Outward, reforming the party.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Outward are these,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Sincere loue of God, whom wee
haue not seene.</p>
            <p>2 Consideration of our wants and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
occasions, and then wee shall see
that he is a very meane one, whom wee
may not stand in neede of, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
despise we none.</p>
            <p>3 Contentednesse with our estate,
and so shall we endure the poore to liue
vnder vs.</p>
            <p>4 Remember we the day of account,
that as now we would haue all, so we
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19145:49"/>
must giue vp the larger account, and
thinke we if it were not much better to
haue others to ease vs?</p>
            <p>5 Know wee that so much as we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
in enclosing and coueting, so much
we doe detract from the holy vse of
Gods blessings, and so shall be guilty of
cruelty against our selues, because wee
shall want whereon to imploy them.</p>
            <p>6 Meditate we on death, &amp;c. when all
our glory shall be confounded, that
seauen foote long at most must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne
vs.</p>
            <p>7 Record we the curses of God which
are threatned and executed against ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
of house to house, &amp;c. <hi>Esay. 5. Hab.
2. Mich.</hi> 3. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The outward Remedies are,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Frugality in apparell and diet,
whereby being good examples to those
with whom we liue, as wee shall not be
driuen to spoyle them, so not vsing them
as instruments of our lusts, they shall
not lye open to our cruelty.</p>
            <p>2 Care, that wee and our Tenants
prosper in religion and honesty, for the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19145:50"/>
neglect of these, and contrary, bolstering
of them in sinne, is an occasion to make
vs tyrannise ouer them.</p>
            <p>3 Conscionable obedience in our
owne persons to those that are set ouer
vs, so shall wee continue mercifull to
those that are vnder vs.</p>
            <p>4 Conuersing louingly, &amp;c. with those
of the lower sort, inuiting them to our
society, Tables, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>5 Maintenance of Tillage.</p>
            <p>6 Moderation of hunting, and such
outward pleasures.</p>
            <p>7 Necessary prouision by Musters
and trained Souldiers, against the dayes
of warre.</p>
            <p>8 Progresse of Princes, to view their
people, and reioyce them by seeing their
faces.</p>
            <p>9 Wholesome lawes against depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,
and conscionably executed.</p>
            <p>11 The estimation of the subiect with
the Prince, and pretiousnesse of the life of
man is a speciall meanes hereto, whose
example will be the best law to those
great ones that are vnder him.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="23" type="chapter">
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:19145:50"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>A second enemy to Charity is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse
in Diet: eyther by</p>
            </argument>
            <p>1 GLuttony, <hi>or</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2 Drunkennesse: <hi>Whereby</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Selfe-loue being nourished, <hi>And</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2 The flesh pampered, <hi>And</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3 Sinne growing insatiable.</p>
            <p>4 And so others drawne into the same
excesse.</p>
            <p>5 And our estate wasted, &amp;c. <hi>Hereby</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 The loue of our brother groweth
cold.</p>
            <p>2 Their bellies are pinched.</p>
            <p>3 And all being thought too little for
our selues, euery thing is thought too
much for others.</p>
            <p>4 And that which wee impart to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
as the intent is to draw them into
fellowship of sinne; so hereby not onely
they become thieues to their families,
but draw downe the iudgements of God
vpon them, as famine, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>6 Yea, in that hereby our estates are
wasted and consumed: are not great
ones hereby driuen to the spoyle? and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19145:51"/>
who more likely to be spoyled, then
those that haue beene instruments in
sinne?</p>
            <p>7 Carnall loue doth most vsually
end in extreame hatred. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14. And
so the weakest goeth to the wall.</p>
            <p>8 And how can we but be cruell vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
others, when we are not mercifull to
our owne soules.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 In vaine doe Epicures boast of
false liberality.</p>
            <p>2 And extreame cruelty is the best
fellowship of drunkards.</p>
            <p>3 Little comfort in that speech, that
a belly-god is no mans foe but his
owne, seeing he is an enemy to God, to
his neighbour, to the creatures, and his
owne soule and body.</p>
            <p>4 Lesse warrant therein, that they
spend but of their owne, seeing their
spending is abuse, and abuse makes it
not their owne.</p>
            <p>5 And for the cloake of hospitali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
what shall it auaile, seeing the poore
are more pinched: and fat hogs are
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19145:51"/>
onely fed vp to the slaughter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Learne we in the second place to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie
this euill: And that</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 By enforming the iudgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right,
concerning our liberty in these
things.</p>
            <p>Here first know we that what liberty
and Lordship we had ouer these things,
was vtterly lost in <hi>Adam,</hi> so that by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
the best are slaues to the creatures:
being so farre off from any right ouer
them, or ability to vse them well, as that
our best right in them is, that they are
executioners of the diuine vengeance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
vs, and our best vse is by abusing
them to prouoke them to a more spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
and sharpe execution thereof.</p>
            <p>2 Consider we hence that it is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
we haue most of them cast vpon
vs, therefore we deserue them, and so
haue power to vse them well, seeing v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sually
they are the wickeds portion in
this life, to fatten them vp to the day of
slaughter. <hi>Psal. 17. 14. Ierem.</hi> 12. 3.</p>
            <p>3 Neyther if we are scanted of them,
ought we to flatter our selues, that wee
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:19145:52"/>
are beloued of God, in that he diets vs
of these things: seeing it is a punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of sinne to be stripped of these
comforts. <hi>Deut. 28. Ioel. 1. Psal.</hi> 107.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That we may vse them aright, wee
are to seek for the recouery of our right
in Iesus Christ, who being giuen vs of
the Father, doth giue vs with him all
good things else: so that in Iesus Christ
we are restored againe both to our Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship
ouer the Creature, and holy liberty
also to vse them aright for Gods glory,
and our eternall saluation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now being restored to an holy Liberty in
these things, we are to know in the second
place, that this liberty is bounded
within these limits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 We must in all these things ayme
at Gods glory. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 30. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
so to vse our liberty in Diet, as first,
may especially further the sanctifying of
the Sabbath: Secondly, and fit vs to all
holy duties: Thirdly, may empty vs of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:19145:52"/>
carnall loue to, and confidence in, the
creature: fourthly, may keepe still our
power and liberty ouer the same.</p>
            <p>2 In the vse of these outward things,
we must haue respect to the saluation
of the soule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We must first sanctifie them vnto vs,
that the soule may haue aright in them,
and grace to vse them holily. 1 <hi>Tim.
4.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>2 Wee must discerne that in the
vse thereof, the soule be especially fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered.</p>
            <p>1 As discerning insufficiency in them
to satisfie the soule, and therefore being
weaned from the loue of them, euen by
the vse thereof.</p>
            <p>2 And yet discerning in the least of
them, a pledge of Gods loue, &amp; so being
contented with our owne, and returning
the strength vnto our God in more
conscionable obedience.</p>
            <p>3 Still being prouoked by experience
of Gods prouidence in these things, to
hunger after the best graces.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:19145:53"/>
4 And communicating, euen of our
<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ittle, to the good of others. <hi>Iob</hi> 31.</p>
            <p>5 Abstayning from our liberty here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
that wee may be fitter for heauenly
duties.</p>
            <p>6 Seeking rather to satisfie necessity
then the eye or palate.</p>
            <p>7 And still when the body is satisfied,
discerning the soules want. <hi>And</hi>
            </p>
            <p>8 Redeeming wisely the one with the
losse of the other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3 We must in the vse of these things,
respect a common good: And therefore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 To be ordered herein for the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
of our diet, by the authority of the
Magistrate, <hi>As also,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2 As occasions shall serue for the
measure thereof.</p>
            <p>3 Vsing that which our owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
best affords, and most cheape. And
lastly being lawes vnto our selues, where
otherwise we may exceed, not conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
what our purse can doe, or our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings
will allow, but wherein we may
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19145:53"/>
best be examples of frugality to others,
and best able to maintaine the common
charge; especially may be a meane to
stand in the gappe to keepe out the
common scourge.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="24" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XXIIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>A third enemy to Bounty is, Pride,
and excesse of Apparrell.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>AS not onely exceeding herein our
callings.</p>
            <p>But also stretching beyond our abilities,
Putting euen whole Lordships not so
much vpon our backes, as vpon our
shoes, yea sometimes our very garters
and shoes-strings.</p>
            <p>And so hence follow racking and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
out of Tenants. Eating out of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spitality.</p>
            <p>Running deepe into the Tradesmens
bookes, yea, vndoing of them. Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
of all riot and excesse in sinne, &amp;c.
In fine, the Prison, and beggery.</p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:19145:54"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Remedy is partly, as before in Diet, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
the generall: Vnto which we may adde these follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
in particular.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First that we vse such apparell as may
best serue to expresse and adorne our
Christian callings, furthering to morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication
and abasing of the flesh.</p>
            <p>And secondly such as may serue to
maintaine humaine society, by keeping
the common fashion of the Country,
and such as beseemes our seuerall places,
in the common-wealth. <hi>Esay 3. Zeph.</hi> 1.
Wisely admitting such ciuil distinctions,
as by the wisedome of state are deuised,
both for ornament, and difference of
callings.</p>
            <p>Auoyding, as on the one side slouenly
and brutish attire, so on the other, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riosity
and precisenesse.</p>
            <p>And reiecting all diuices, to adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
nature; making vs faire; straigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
&amp;c. as painting, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And so endeauouring to expresse all
modesty and grauity therein.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="25" type="chapter">
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:19145:54"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXV.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Of Hunting, that it is an Enimy to Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality:
And how many waies.
With the Remedy thereof.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>And first, that Hunting is an enemy to Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality
appeares, Because,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 IT entendeth too much the satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying
of our owne pleasures, and
so hindereth from respecting the nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssities
of others, 1 <hi>Cor. 13. 2 Tim.</hi> 3. 2.
Louers of pleasures, and without natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
affection, goe together.</p>
            <p>2 It with-draweth naturall affection
from our owne flesh: and conuerteth it
to dogs, so that it were better to be a
huntsmans dog, then his poore neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
            <p>3 It breedeth vnnaturallnesse and
cruelty, in that the sport thereof is in
shedding of bloud, and bathing their
hands therein, wherevpon it commeth
to passe, that by degrees the blood of
the poore is as little regarded, as the
blood of a beast, yea it maketh more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light
in the company of beasts, then to
conuerse with men.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:19145:55"/>
4 Hereby Gentlemen are prouoked
to racke their Tenants and spoyle the
poore, to turne them out, &amp;c. euen to
maintayne stables for their hunting hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,
and kennels for their hounds.</p>
            <p>5 Also much good ground is restray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
for the maintenance of such wilde
game, which otherwise might be conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
to tillage for the relief of the poore.</p>
            <p>6 Much good graine is consumed in
maintenance of Deare, and Dogs, which
the poore ought to be relieued with.</p>
            <p>7 Yea, Gentlemen thinke themselues
excused from reliefe of the poore, in that
so many quarters of graine goes out to
such pleasurable prouision.</p>
            <p>8 Yea, much graine is spoyled on the
ground by the vnreasonable pursuit of
this vnbridled sport.</p>
            <p>9 Herein also much precious time
is so wasted and rioted, that the estate of
the poore cannot be entended, and loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
into: much lesse relieued.</p>
            <p>10 For this abuse of creatures, the Lord
many times punisheth a Land with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,
and so the poore are further pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
for the offence of the great ones.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:19145:55"/>
11 Yea, the poore hereby are so grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
and enraged many times, that being
thus despised aboue wilde beasts, they
grow wilde and outragious, and so giue
such bloudy hunters euen their fill of
blood.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Remedies hereof is,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 That we be able to discerne of the
true bounds of our Christian liberty:
that so wee doe not turne the same; as
an occasion of wantonnesse. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 11.</p>
            <p>2 That wee consider of the pretious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
of time, and so learne to redeeme it,
in making sure our election. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5. 16.</p>
            <p>3 Consider wee wisely whether wee
can make one corne, &amp;c. or hayre, &amp;c.
and then lay we it to our hearts, what a
grieuous sinne it is to riot and wast out
so many creatures of God: yea wilfully
to kill such seruiceable horses, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>4 Know wee that hunting is a recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation
to make our selues and other fitter
for our better callings: not to rob our
selues and others of health and meanes
of life: not to cut off imployment in
more serious affaires.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:19145:56"/>
5 Resolue wee that our priuate plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures
must be submitted to the publike
good, so that both expediency must be
respected, aswell as what is lawfull: yea
wee must in no case offend the weake
brother, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. least otherwise while
we satisfie our lusts without respect of
offending others, wee loose our naturall
affection, and so loose the affection of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p>6 Expect wee vndoubtedly that if
wee neglect our owne flesh, and set our
affections vpon brute beasts: wee shall
make our flesh sauadge against vs, either
the Lord for our vnnaturallnesse, shall
make man pretious, as the gold of <hi>Ophir;</hi>
so that for want of help, wee may be
exposed to be a pray vnto the beasts;
or the rage of our enimes shalbe so great
that no gold shalbe ble to redeeme vs
out of their hands. <hi>Esay 13. 12. 13.
Pro.</hi> 11. 8.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="26" type="chapter">
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:19145:56"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXVI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>A fift Policie, whereby Sathan keepes men
from charity and true bounty, is a foolish
feare that they may be esteemed Papists, and
therefore they will doe no good workes,
because the Papists glory therein, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
this is a marke (as they
say) of their Religion.</p>
            </argument>
            <l>Yea, are they not hereby condemned; as me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit-mongers?
&amp;c.</l>
            <l>Are not their goodly monuments cast downe
and demolished?</l>
            <l>Are we not taught iustification by Faith, so
that good workes may seeme to be thrust
out of doores?</l>
            <p>
               <hi>The Remedy hereof is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 TO consider, that the Lord hath
commanded vs to abound in
good workes, and therefore wee should
(not casting these feares) be obedient
to his will.</p>
            <p>2 Wee teach iustification by Faith,
which worketh by loue, so that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer
by faith in Iesus Christ we iustifie
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:19145:57"/>
Gods righteousnesse in pardoning our
sinnes through Christ his merit, in whom
wee apprehend the acceptance and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification
of our persons, as standing
righteous through him in the sight of
God. So by the vertue of Christ his
righteousnes, wee are inuested with a true
inherent righteous, whereby first in
thankefulnes vnto our God, we abound
in good workes: secondly, to declare
that wee are iustified, both to our owne
consciences: thirdly, and also vnto
men. <hi>Iames</hi> 2. fourthly, to approue
our conformitie vnto our head Christ,
as liuing members: fiftly to be made
meet for that glorious inheritance with
the Saints in light.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee condemne the Papists, and
haue demolished their glorious Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchers:
that their rotten and stin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
bones being discouered, their
faces may be couered with shame, that
they might seeke the face of God in
Christ Iesus, whom they did daily crusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
by their abhominable Masses, Hori|
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:19145:57"/>
Murthers of infants, Thefts, Rapines,
which were discouered in the demolish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of those abhominable sinkes and
cages of all vncleannesse.</p>
            <p>And though we haue conuerted some
few of those houses to be places of Gods
worship, purging them of the idolatrous
vse and end, by which they were abused.
Yet haue wee wisely defaced the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
of them, as being altogether vnne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary,
to cut off the hope of nurcing
Popery againe.</p>
            <p>To restore to the Common-wealth,
what hath vniustly beene extorted from
thence, by the couetousnesse and fayned
deuotions of those Abbey-lubbers.</p>
            <p>To roote out idlenesse, and such other
mischiefes as were nourished in those
abhominable Stewes.</p>
            <p>To restore the people to their liberty,
who were very fearefully enthralled, not
onely in their soules, but euen in their
bodies, by those towers of Babell.</p>
            <p>Specially to make free way to the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution
of Iustice which was defeated by
such sinfull Sanctuaries. And to restore
the Tithes for the maintenance of a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:19145:58"/>
Ministery which we wish may (as in
part it hath bin begun) be further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted
to that end. And haue we not since
the time of the gospel restored, exceeded
them notwithstanding, in true bounty?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yea surely:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Blessed be God, in Iesus Christ, that
hath confounded the false charity of the
Papists, by discouering the rotten foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
and cruell ends thereof: Blessed
be the name of his Maiesty for euer, that
hath confuted their slaunderous impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations
against the glorious Gospell of
his Sonne Iesus, as if it abolished good
workes, had banished all true loue and
charity. Hath not the glorious Lord ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced
and iustified the power of the
Gospell, in kindling the hearts of the
true professors thereof to performe such
renowned and glorious workes as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
be matched in any age of Popery?
Hath not these times of the Gospell
yeelded the supply of foure new stately
and magnificent Colledges in the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersities,
very richly endowed for the
maintenance of true religion and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
to all posterity?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:19145:58"/>
Haue they not furnished the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
Citie of <hi>London</hi> with a most ample
and worthy Colledge, endowed with
constant and sufficient mayntenance
both for a Reader of Diuinity, as also
with seuerall Readers of the seauen libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
Sciences, to prepare the better for the
Vniuersities, and so to ease such of that
iourney which will receiue their seaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
heere?</p>
            <p>And are not the foundations laid of
another famous Colledge, by the pious
and magnificent authority of our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
Lord King <hi>Iames,</hi> the most con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant
enemy of Antichrist, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender
of the true Christian, ancient,
and Apostolike faith, for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
of such worthies of our Church,
to employ their studies in refuting the
aduersary, and iustifying the truth of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus
Christ?</p>
            <p>Is not a good part of that Colledge
alreadie erected? Is it not still fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered
and vndertaken by the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne
Maiesty, who for the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
of GOD will finish that glorious
worke?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:19145:59"/>
What should wee speake of those
hundreds of free-Schooles, that haue
beene erected since the dayes of glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> of happy memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
for the rooting out of ignorance; the
very nurse of Popery, and trayning vp of
youth in Learning and Religion? Shall we
not euer remember, not only how many
sinkes of Antichrist were conuerted to
Hospitals, for the cure of the diseased, and
nourishing of Orphanes in the Citie of
London,<note place="margin">By king <hi>Edward.</hi>
               </note> and elsewhere, and haue not
their reuenewes beene much encreased
by worthy Citizens from time to time?</p>
            <p>Haue there not beene scores of new
Hospitals erected and endowed in each
part of the land, for the reliefe of decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
and decrepet persons?</p>
            <p>Shall not the memory of <hi>Sutton</hi> be
glorious to posterity, for that his mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent
Colledge, so stately for the
House, so bountifull for the Reuenue
of at lest sixe thousand pound by the
yeere, for the sustentation of decayed
Souldiers, Scholers, Citizens, &amp;c. to
continue for euer?</p>
            <p>And hath not the streame of this
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:19145:59"/>
bounty, yet flowed more boundantly to
our Vniuersities?</p>
            <p>Is there any Colledge almost in the
Vniuersities, which hath not receiued,
euen new glory from thes<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> times of the
Gospell, not onely by enlarging of
the buildings and beautifying there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
but by addition of large mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
for the encrease of their Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowship
and Scholers-places, to continue
for euer?</p>
            <p>It not that glorious Library, excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
the Vatican, or any now extant in
the World, furnished with all sorts of
bookes, and constant mayntenance
for a Keeper therof, and continuall sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
for the same, a very true and blessed
monument of the bounty of these
times, a very liuely fruit of the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
of Iesus Christ? Shall not the
memory of deuout <hi>Bodley</hi> be blessed
for euer?</p>
            <p>And can wee forget what is now
by Gods mercy euen finished, that
magnificent building of the Vniuersitie
Schooles, so stately for the structure,
so sufficient for mayntenance, begunne
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:19145:60"/>
euen from the foundation, and finished
by the procurement and charge, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,
of those most worthy instruments:
The Right Reuerend Father in God, the
Lord Bishop of <hi>London,</hi> a true Kingly
and Hieroicall Spirit; and that illustrious
Sir <hi>Iohn Bennet,</hi> both liuing members of
the Church of Christ Iesus, both some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
brought vp in that magnificent
Colledge of Christ Church.</p>
            <p>Surely if we shall adde vnto these, the
multitude of new Bridges, erected substan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially
in the needfull places of the Land
of free stone &amp;c. The building of many
Gates in the C<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tie of London, &amp;c. It may
appeare that the Gospell of Christ hath
beene most fruitfull in good workes.</p>
            <p>Especially if we be wise to distinguish of
the times, it will appeare that the char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
of such great buildings and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments
doe in these dayes farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede
those of former ages, though
of the like bulke and quantity. Both
in that the Land doth now much
more abound with people then in
former ages, in regard of the long
peace our good God hath vouchsafed.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:19145:60"/>
And so in regard heereof the prices of
all things being much enhansed, charges
of building must needs be so much the
greater.</p>
            <p>And this the rather, because the wise
and gracious Lord, hath also furnished
the Land with more abundance of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
then formerly: which as it is an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion
to make things deerer, in that
men are better enabled thereby to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
their necessaries: so doth this serue
for the great enriching and contentment
of the Land.</p>
            <p>That our inbred commodities shall
passe at a round price, as hath else-where
beene truly and sufficiently proued: see
my Lord <hi>Cokes</hi> preface to his Reports.</p>
            <p>Lastly, if we shall consider, that as the
doctrine of the Gospell teacheth what
is the nature and property of true boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
so also it enableth to an holy practise
of well-doing. It will easily appeare, that
though it should be granted that the
former times hath exceeded vs in the
outward worke, yet seeing they fayled
in the true vse and end of well-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
they cannot iustly compare herein,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:19145:61"/>
with the times of the Gospell. And that
well manifestly be discouerd by these
differences.</p>
            <p>1 Because the good workes of popery
were done in darknesse; refused the light
and true touchstone thereof, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
wanting knowledge wherefore, and
faith to make the person acceptable, they
could not be good in the sight of God.</p>
            <p>Whereas the Gospell teacheth to doe
all things by a good warrant from the
Word, and in the faith of IESVS
CHRIST, doing all things in thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse
vnto God for his loue vnto vs in
Iesus Christ, informing vs, first to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
the acceptance of our persons, in
the Lord Iesus, and so through him to
offer vp this sacrifice.</p>
            <p>2 Popish workes, as they wanted a
good foundation, so they fayled in the
manner and meanes.</p>
            <p>Either doing euill that good might
come thereof, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>Or being stinted in well-doing, not
by the word, but by the orders of their
superiours, and seuerall rules of their
professions.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:19145:61"/>
Whereas the Gospell teacheth, to doe
good by good meanes, not according to
the will of man, in a voluntary deuotion
&amp; imitation of angelicall perfection, but
according to the blessed will of God,
each keeping him-selfe within the
bounds of his calling. Whereas in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,
either the calling is not lawfull at
all, and so no good can truely be there
done; or else liberty is taken to vsurpe
an other calling, as that of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate:
or else they presume of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary
calling, as the best ground
of all their heroicall and great exploits,
as they call them, indeed, their diuelish,
and monstrous enterprises vpon States,
Princes, whosoeuer stands in their way.</p>
            <p>3 Popish workes faile in the true
end, which is to giue glory vnto God,
and procure saluation to the soule, as
being done, first, to merit by them and
so to rob God of the glory of his free
mercy, and Christ Iesus of the efficacie
of his all-sufficient merit: secondly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
done to depriue the soule of it salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
as teaching it; first, to rest in the
outward workes, without faith: secondly,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:19145:62"/>
by outward workes to excuse and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie
for any grose and notorious wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
and so giues the bridle to all sinne,
with greedinesse, and vtterly excludes
true repentance.</p>
            <p>3 By their good workes to merit
heauen, and so to depriue themselues of
the onely true way thereto.</p>
            <p>4 Onely tending to the maintenance
of present credit and profit, and so to
build vp an imaginary happinesse in
this life, and thereby to exclude them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
eternall happinesse.</p>
            <p>But the Gospell teacheth to ayme
in all things at Gods glory. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 13.
To propose saluation not any present
respect onely as the marke of well-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
3 <hi>Phil.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>Not to rest in the thing done but in
the acceptance thereof.</p>
            <p>To labour perfection of well-doing,
not by Euangelicall councels, but by the
warrant of the word. And in this, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding
all Popish well-doing, that we
especially ayme at the sincerity of the
heart, and yet deny still our owne righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse,
that wee may be found in
Christ Iesus.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:19145:62"/>
And that, wherein the Papists doe
well, therein wee may be like vnto
them, and haue exceeded them: but we
must not be stinted by their measure, nor
misled by their ends.</p>
            <p>They doe well without knowledge,
without Faith, to merit thereby, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusing
hereby their ignorance, Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latries,
and all other kinde of abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>We doe good workes out of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
of the will of God, out of Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
to obey Gods will, as true branches,
deriuing our goodnesse from the Vine
Christ Iesus, performing and brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
forth fruit onely as we are engrafted
in the Vine, and daily receiue vertue
and sap from thence to enable thereto;
hauing the imperfection of our good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
daily couered with the righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
of Christ, that we may be accepted
of our God, &amp;c. By the power of Christ
dwelling in vs; we are daily led on to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,
daily ascribing our righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
to our maker.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="27" type="chapter">
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:19145:63"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXVII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Hereunto appertayneth that Tentation.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>That because,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 VVE sinne in the best wee doe,
Stherefore we will doe no good
at all, least we should sinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To which we may answere,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 That it is a sinne to omit wel-doing,
as well as to doe euill.</p>
            <p>2 That sinne which accompanies well-doing
shall not be imputed, if there be a
willing minde.</p>
            <p>3 Our persons are accepted in Christ,
and therefore our faylings are couered
with his righteousnesse.</p>
            <p>4 This life is not a time of perfection,
but of growing and hastening thereto,
and therefore though we be not perfect
without sinne, yet if we doe it truly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
hypocrisie, it shall be accepted.</p>
            <p>5 The sinne which accompanies wel-doing
is not ours, and therefore we shall
not answere for it.</p>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:19145:63"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And yet by</hi>
            </p>
            <p>6 Sinne we are still humbled to giue
glory vnto Christ.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="28" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XXVIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>A seauenth deuice to draw men from true
bounty, is by nourishing them in Idlenes,
and so disinabling thereto.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>And that this sinne abounds in this
age is manifest.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 BY the generall pouerty of the
Trades-man and Artificer, each
labouring onely from hand to mouth,
to maintaine life and soule together
(as wee say:) the rest of the time
being spent in idlenesse and vnthrifty
sports, &amp;c. Whereas the hand of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent
might haue plenty.</p>
            <p>2 By that ordinary sleightnesse to
which all Trades are growne, each ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
things onely saleable to the eye,
without substance, &amp;c. Idlenesse, hauing
found out a neerer way to deceiue it
selfe and others.</p>
            <p>And is it not iust with God to giue
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:19145:64"/>
vp the deceiuer, to be deceiued? Is not
the deceitfull Artificer, that workes
sleightly, because hee loues idlenesse,
and cannot, through his pouerty, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare
payment; is hee not, I say, met
with all by as cunning as himselfe? Hath
not idlenesse bred vp the Cony-catcher
to strip him of his deceitfull gaine.</p>
            <p>Hath not idlenesse fostred and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed
the slye and deceitfull game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,
to fleece him thread-bare?</p>
            <p>Is not the Stage-plaier, a right bird
of this idle neast, ready to entice him yet
to more idlenesse? Is not the Tauerne
and Alehouse dore open to receiue such
a guest? Is not the bawdie house readie
to send home this Prodigall by wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping-crosse,
that hee may crie late
repentance?</p>
            <p>Doth not the abundance of these nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series
of idlenesse, conuince the raiging
of this sinne in these times? would not
the fire be quenched, if there were not
such fuell?</p>
            <p>What should wee speake of those
swarmes of sturdy roagues, and Idle beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,
whose meat is for the most part ease
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:19145:64"/>
and idlenesse, who had rather starue then
be set a worke?</p>
            <p>And are not such vsually forced to
steale, that they may not starue? doe not
the abundance of these conuince the
Land to swarme with idlenesse?</p>
            <p>And by your leaue, is it not now a
fashion to liue in idlenesse? My high
borne younger-Brothers, because they
haue no lands, therefore they haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
to doe what they should; they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
digge, to begge they are ashamed:
meete the enemy they dare not, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
they wil be meet with their friend, if
they can, by cheating, if not by plain cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
and so they will doe what they
should not, and so in the end suffer what
they would not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Well then it is apparant that idlenesse
abounds. Learne we now in the next place, the
remedy hereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Labour we to get grace in our hearts,
for he that is in Christ wil be alwaies brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
forth fruit in due season, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:19145:65"/>
be idle that hath the spirit working
in him.</p>
            <p>2 And therefore let vs stir vp the spirit
by prayer and holy duties, that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer
the world count, the seruice
of God idlenesse, yet wee may finde,
that when our God is honoured he will
honour vs before men, in giuing vs di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence,
that we may stand before Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
and giuing vs wisdome and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse
in the least.</p>
            <p>3 And giue wee not our hearts to
pleasures and delights, abuse we not our
liberty in the creatures of God, for these
will draw on and confirme in idlenesse.</p>
            <p>4 Consider wee how the creatures
are in continuall imployment.</p>
            <p>5 And obserue wee that the diuell is
neuer idle to hurt vs.</p>
            <p>6 Remember wee how vnprofitably
wee haue spent the time past, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider
wee what warrant wee haue for the
time to come.</p>
            <p>7 And know wee that the minde can
neuer be idle, if not working for good,
then certainely for euill.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="29" type="chapter">
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:19145:65"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXIX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>An eight practise of Satan to hinder
bounty is, by enticing men to exhaust
their estates in vnlawfnll
recreations.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>As</hi>
            </p>
            <p>DIcing.</p>
            <p>Carding.</p>
            <p>Cock-fighting.</p>
            <p>Beare-bayting.</p>
            <p>Stage-Playes, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Being the common Recreations of
the time.</p>
            <p>2 Taken vp not by the basest, but
euen by the best, and so countenanced
by example.</p>
            <p>3 Hauing some pretence of Christian
liberty.</p>
            <p>4 Hauing also some sweete baites of
profit and pleasure.</p>
            <p>5 And being good meanes to passe
away the time.</p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:19145:66"/>
            <p>
               <hi>For the remedy of this euill know we,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 That these recreations are vtterly
vnlawfull. <hi>As</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>1 Dicing. Because</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It consists in hazard and casting of a
Lot, which being a religious ordinance,
appointed of the Lord in waighty euasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
to determine the doubtfulnesse
thereof, ought not to be transferred to
matter of recreation. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>2 It is performed by many cunning
and deceitfull sleights, not so much
depending vpon the bare chance, as by
aduantage of dice, &amp;c. intending to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-rule
the hazard, and by the chance
to rob and spoyle others.</p>
            <p>3 And so, besides the occasions of
swearing, losse of time, corruption of
manners accompanying these sports.
Is not satisfied vsually without spoyle
of estate, yea, many times of liues
also.</p>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:19145:66"/>
            <p>
               <hi>2 Carding vnlawfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 And that because it partly consists
of hazard, and therefore is an abuse of
diuine ordinance.</p>
            <p>2 The skill thereof consists in couse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage
and out-facing trickes.</p>
            <p>3 It maintaynes Couetousnesse, and
hunts after gaine by vnlawfull sleights.</p>
            <p>4 And so in steade of recreating the
minde, doth much distract the same
with hopes to winne, and feare to loose.</p>
            <p>5 It steales away our pretious time,
and nourisheth in idlenesse and effemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
delights.</p>
            <p>6 And is not vsually performed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
blasphemies against God, and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings
of each other.</p>
            <p>7 At the best, it is but an indifferent
thing, and therefore being more subiect
to abuse, is wisely to be auoyded.</p>
            <p>8 Especially seeing it is a sport of no
good report, vsed especially by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane,
and by them grossely abused, and
taken vp to ease a troubled spirit.</p>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:19145:67"/>
            <p>
               <hi>3 Cocke-fighting and Beare-baiting
vnlawfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Because the ground of them is the
enmity of the creature, which was the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment
of sinne.</p>
            <p>2 They prouoke to cruelty, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifulnesse.</p>
            <p>3 And withdraw the minde from the
right vse of the creature, which is to
contemplate the iustice and mercy of
God in the preseruation and gouernment
thereof.</p>
            <p>4 It is contrary to the nature of a iust
man, who is mercifull to his beast.</p>
            <p>5 By this vnmercifulnesse to the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
vnnaturalnesse, and brutish tyranny
is oft-times discouered and maintayned.</p>
            <p>6 And the creature eft soones pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked
to crie quittance with man.</p>
            <p>7 Besides, the prophanation of the
Sabbaths, blasphemies &amp; whoredomes,
the drunkennesse, &amp;c. that accompany
these games.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>4 That Enterludes, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>First because,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 They are expressely forbidden by
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:19145:67"/>
the Lord, who hath commanded tha
we should not imitate the heathen in
their sports and pastimes.</p>
            <p>2 They were first inuented and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted
by the Diuell,<note place="margin">Tit. Liu. Decad.</note> to pacifie his
wrath in the time of a famine, as if hee
were the author of the iudgement of
God: <hi>And so</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3 They were inuented to the high
derogation of the power and Maiesty of
God.</p>
            <p>4 They are the teachers of sinne, yea,
enemies to Repentance, as both expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
sinne liuely, and making a mock<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
of it.</p>
            <p>5 They are the very bands to all hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie
and dissimulation, as making
shew of what they are not, and expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
vice vnder the habite of vertue.</p>
            <p>6 They alter the order that God hath
placed in his creatures, changing the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>4 Stage-Playes are vnlawfull
and abhominable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of men into women, a thing expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
forbidden by the law of God. <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>They are meanes to exclude the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:19145:68"/>
preaching of the Gospell, as contenting
the people with such formall shewes,
and so thereby perswading them, that
because they can learne more at a play,
then at a Sermon, therefore, the play is
better, the Sermon needlesse.</p>
            <p>And seeing the people can endure sin
to be reproued in a play, which they will
not abide in the Pulpet: This causeth
not onely to despise the power of the
word, but euen to make a mocke of
sinne.</p>
            <p>And so are the meanes to nourish
Atheisme, and all desperate impiety.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of dancing: That it is an enemy to libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality,
and vtterly vnlawfull as it is
now vsed generally.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Howsoeuer the Scripture doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
vnto vs some kindes of dancing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Namely,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That of <hi>Dauid,</hi> to shew his ioy and
thankfulnesse vnto God for the redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
of the Arke: as also 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>Those holy dancings of <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam,</hi>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:19145:68"/>
in thankfulnesse vnto God for their
great deliuerance. <hi>Exod.</hi> 15. 1. 2.</p>
            <p>Yet are those no warrants to iustifie the
prophane and lasciuious dancing of
these ages.</p>
            <p>1 These were performed in an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
manner: namely, in modesty, and
great wisedome, to auoid occasion and
appearance of euill, the men by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues,
and the women also together.</p>
            <p>2 These dancings, of old, were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
to holy ends, namely, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse
thankfulnesse vnto God for his
mercies vouchsafed vnto them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But as for the dancings of these times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They are both occasions of euill in
regard of the promiscuous dancing of
men and women together, as also, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
of those lasciuious gestures and
behauiours that accompany the same.</p>
            <p>Especially they entend most wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
ends; as vncleannesse, wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
effeminatenesse, &amp;c. if not mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
and adultery followes the same.
And are they not also maine enemies
against liberality?</p>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:19145:69"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Yea certainly,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As not onely exhausting our estate in
vanity of apparrell; maskings, &amp;c. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
we are vsually disenabled from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming
this duety.</p>
            <p>But by these vaine recreations enfla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
the heart with pride, &amp;c. whereby
it is alienated from the poore. Yea nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing
in idlenesse, and prouoking
thereby to all excesse of lust, whereby
still the estate is more emptied, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sery
hastened.</p>
            <p>And so exposing oft-times to the iust
scorne of the world, and necessity of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe
from others.</p>
            <p>And thereby thrusting forward to shif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
and spoyling of our brethren, whom
we should and might relieue. And doth
not open robbery and murthers vsually
hence ensue? Will such gallants labour?
are they not ashamed to begge, and must
they not liue? Will they not haue it by
hooke or by crooke, as we say? must they
not cut it out of the hides of others?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="30" type="chapter">
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:19145:69"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>How to abstaine from these delights.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>1 COnsider wee that at the best they
are subiect to much abuse: And
therefore choose we rather such recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
as may turne good to the soule, may
prouoke to see our vilenesse, and humble
to repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If we will needs try conclusions in
these sports,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2 Then resolue we to play freely, and
so we shall shortly play alone: secondly, if
we play for ought, let vs then vse our
selues to giue a way whatsoeuer we win,
and to pay of our owne what we loose,
and this will also quickly end vs of our
company, and ease vs of our labour.</p>
            <p>3 Insteed of these, we choose such
as are of honest report, as shooting, &amp;c.
Secondly such as are not so subiect to
sleights and aduantages to deceiue: such
as may further the health of the body,
as exercises of running, wrestling, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Such as may fit vs the better to the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:19145:70"/>
seruice of our country, as handling the
Pike, feates of actiuity, and such as are
performed laudably in the Artillery gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den;
shooting with the Peece.</p>
            <p>And such as in generall may further to
spirituall duties of Prayer, thankesgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing,
may prouoke to contemplate the
power and wisedome of God, in the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety
of his worke, and such as may
serue to humble the flesh, and may
enable vs the better to this grace of
liberality, as tillage of the earth, graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
and may imitate euen childish
simplicity.</p>
            <p>But especially labour we to weane our
soules from these delights.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That our hearts may be weaned by
degrees from these perillous vanities.</p>
            <p>1 Let vs consider, not so much how
we may passe away the time present, as
how we haue mispent the time past, and
therefore haue deserued that time should
be no more, and this wil euen worke this
conclusion, that it is sufficient that wee
haue spent time past after the manner
of the Gentiles, that it is the mercies of
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:19145:70"/>
the Lord, that wee haue not beene ouer
taken in our foiles, that it now stands
vs vpon to walke more circumspectly,
redeeming the time, because the daies
are euill.</p>
            <p>2 Consider wee what fruit wee haue
in those things whereof wee are now
ashamed, at the best, no better then
vanity and vexation of spirit.</p>
            <p>3 Obserue wee the reason and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
ground of these sports, namely, to
ease a troubled minde: and iudge wee
wisely what vnfit and desperate Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke
this proues thereto; seruing at
the best to dead the conscience, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
Repentance, to encrease sinne:
and so to hasten to vengeance.</p>
            <p>4 Consider wee that the practise of
these sports tends not onely to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaning
of the Sabbath, but to iustifie
this prophannesse, vnder pretence of
Christian liberty, and recreation.</p>
            <p>5 And so consider wee wisely the
companions of these games, as who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,
drunkennesse, murther, cousenage,
and swearing.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:19145:71"/>
6 Resolue we daily to reckon with our
selues for the expence of time, and then
we shall be ill apaid to bring any such
stuffe into reckoning.</p>
            <p>7 We shall haue enough to doe to
account for ordinary escapes, and sins
that hangs so fast vpon vs, so that wee
shall haue little need, to draw on sinne
with cart-ropes, to make a sport of it.</p>
            <p>And therefore in all these recreations
labour we to become fooles, not affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting
any extraordinary skill in them,
neyther seeking for masteries by them,
vnlesse they be such as may make vs ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable
to the common good, obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
daily the vanity of them, or at least
their insufficiency to giue content to the
pure minde: and considering the short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
of our liues, and suddennesse of
Christs comming to iudgement, imagine
we whether these will proue Oyle in our
Lampes, to meete the Bridegroome
withall, or not rather stubble to helpe to
kindle the fire of Gods iealousie, to
burne vs vnquenchably?</p>
            <p>And learne we to make God our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light,
by walking alwayes in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:19145:71"/>
Reioycing in his word.</p>
            <p>Meditating of his admirable power and
wisedome in all his workes, especially re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freshing
our soules in the beauty of his
face in Iesus Christ. And reioycing in
the hope of that loue that shall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed.</p>
            <p>Delighting in the excellent that ar<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
earth. <hi>Psal.</hi> 16. and labouring to ma<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tayne
the fellowship by walking as lights
amidst the darknesse of this world, sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
some by feare, plucking out of the
fire. <hi>Iud.</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>Exhorting each other daily, that wee
be not hardned by the deceitfulnesse of
sinne. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 3. 13.</p>
            <p>And waiting for the glorious reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the sonnes of God.</p>
            <p>Labouring especially to auoid the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
and occasions of these vanities.</p>
            <p>Namely, pretence of Christian liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
as before.</p>
            <p>2 Idlenesse. Being diligent in our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings,
and committing the issue to God.</p>
            <p>3 Security, as because wee are safe, all
is well, therefore wee may be merry, wee
may take our fill of pleasure.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:19145:72"/>
4 Atheisme, as thinking all our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse
consists in this life, and that this
happinesse appeares in the satisfying of
the flesh, and therefore let vs eate and
drinke, play and sport, for to morrow we
shall die. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>5 Lastly, consider we that these sports
<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the most part, as they were banished
by the wiser heathen out of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths,
so they are also condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
by the lawes of our land.</p>
            <p>The parties vsing many of them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted
no better then common rogues,
as Players, Bearewards, &amp;c. And so
as Rogues to be dealt
withall.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19145:72"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
