<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Canaans calamitie Ierusalems misery, or The dolefull destruction of faire Ierusalem by Tytus, the sonne of Vaspasian Emperour of Rome, in the yeare of Christs incarnation 74 Wherein is shewed the woonderfull miseries which God brought vpon that citty for sinne, being vtterly ouer-throwne and destroyed by sword, pestilence and famine.</title>
            <title>Canaans calamitie Jerusalems misery</title>
            <author>T. D.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-05">2003-05 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19754</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6181.2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105234</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840963</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840963</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5511</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A19754)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5511)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 380:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Canaans calamitie Ierusalems misery, or The dolefull destruction of faire Ierusalem by Tytus, the sonne of Vaspasian Emperour of Rome, in the yeare of Christs incarnation 74 Wherein is shewed the woonderfull miseries which God brought vpon that citty for sinne, being vtterly ouer-throwne and destroyed by sword, pestilence and famine.</title>
                  <title>Canaans calamitie Jerusalems misery</title>
                  <author>T. D.</author>
                  <author>Deloney, Thomas, 1543?-1600, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Dekker, Thomas, ca. 1572-1632, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by W. Jones] for Thomas Bayly, and are to be sould at the corner-shop in the middle rowe iu [sic] Holborne, neere adioyning vnto Staple Inne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: T.D. Sometimes attributed to Thomas Dekker; attributed with more probability to Thomas Deloney.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The destruction of Ierusalem.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 6494 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jerusalem --  Siege, 70 A.D. --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-01</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5511:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5511:1"/>
            <p>CANAANS CALAMITIE Ierusalems Misery, OR The dolefull destruction of faire Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem
by <hi>TYTVS,</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Vaspasian</hi> Emperour of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the yeare of <hi>Christs</hi>
Incarnation 74. Wherein is shewed the woonderfull miseries which
<hi>God brought vpon that Citty for sinne, being vtterly</hi>
ouer-throwne and destroyed by Sword,
<hi>pestilence and famine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AT LONDON, ¶Printed for <hi>Thomas Bayly,</hi> and are to be sould at
the corner-shop in the middle rowe in <hi>Holborne,</hi>
neere adioyning vnto <hi>Staple Inne.</hi>
1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5511:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5511:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL
<hi>M. Richard Kingsmill</hi> Esquier, Iustice of peace
and Quorum in the Countie of Southampton, and
Surveyer of her Maiesties Court<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of Wardes
and Liveries. All prosperitie and happines.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing (Right worshipfull) often heard of your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary
favour, shewed in the depth of extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie,
to some poore freindes of mine, remayning
in your pleasant Lordship of <hi>High-cleere:</hi> by
meanes whereof, they haue had no small comfort for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerie
of their wished desire: I haue been studious how I
might in some measure declare both their thankfulnesse and
mine owne for so great a good. But such <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our weake abillity
that we cannot requite the least poynt of that life prolonging
kindnes, which the riches of your courtesie did yeeld: never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse
to make apparent, that our poore estates shall not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure,
or clowd with ingratitude, the well intending thoughts
of our hearts: I haue presumed to present to your worship
this little booke, an vnfaigned token of our good affection,
hoping that like the Princely <hi>Pertian</hi> you will more respect
the good will then the gift, which I confesse farre vnworthy
so worthy a Patron in respect of the simple handling of so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
a matter: But a playne stile doth best become plaine
truth, for a trifling fable hath most neede of a pleasant pen.
Wherefore if it shall please your Worship to esteeme of my
simple labour, and to let this passe vnd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r your favorable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection,
I shall haue the end of my desire. And resting
thus in hope of your worships courtesie I cease wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing
you all hearts content in this life, and
in the world to come eternall felicitie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worships most humblie affectionate:
T. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:5511:3"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Three stately walles begirt this Citty round,</l>
               <l>Strongly raild vp of gallant squared stone,</l>
               <l>Vnpossible in fight foes should them confound,</l>
               <l>By warlike Engines seized therevpon.</l>
               <l>The spacious gates most glorious to behold,</l>
               <l>Were all gilt ouer, with rich burnisht gould.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Aud round abo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t <hi>Ierusalem</hi> likewise.</l>
               <l>Were pleasant walkes prepard for recreation,</l>
               <l>Sweet daintie gardens feeding gazers eyes,</l>
               <l>With workes of wonder and high admiration,</l>
               <l>Where in the midst of sweetest smelling flowers,</l>
               <l>They built for pleasure, many pleasant bowers.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In treasures store this Citty did excell,</l>
               <l>For pompe and pride it was the onely place,</l>
               <l>In her alone did richest Marchants dwell,</l>
               <l>And famous Princes sprung of Royall race:</l>
               <l>And fairer Dames did nature neuer frame,</l>
               <l>Then in that Citty dwelt and thither came.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Christs Prophesie of the destruction
of this Cittie and how it came to passe accordingly
within Forty yeares after, shewing the cause that
mooued the Emperour to come against it.</head>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:3"/>
               <l>OVr Sauiour Christ tracing the bordring hilles,</l>
               <l>When he on this faire Cittie cast his eye</l>
               <l>The teares along his rosia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l cheekes dist<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>les.</l>
               <l>Mourning for their destruction drawing nie.</l>
               <l>O <hi>Ierusalem Ierusalem</hi> quoth hee,</l>
               <l>My heart bewailes thy great calamitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The time shall come and neere it is at hand,</l>
               <l>When furious foes shall t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ench thee round about,</l>
               <l>And batter downe thy Towers that stately stand,</l>
               <l>All thy strong holds within thee and without:</l>
               <l>Thy golden buildings shall they quite confound,</l>
               <l>And make thee equall with the lowly ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O woe to them that then giues sucke he sayes,</l>
               <l>And lulles their Infants on their tender knees,</l>
               <l>More woe to them that be with child those dayes,</l>
               <l>Wherein shalbe such extreame miserye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</l>
               <l>Thou mightst haue shund these plagues hadst thou bin wise</l>
               <l>Which now for sinne is hidden from thy eyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This dreadfull Prophesie spoken by our Lord,</l>
               <l>The stubborne people naught at all regarded,</l>
               <l>Whose Adamantine heartes did still accord,</l>
               <l>To follow sinne, whhich was with shame rewarded:</l>
               <l>They flouted him for telling of this storie,</l>
               <l>And crucifide inspite the Lord of glorie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:4"/>
               <l>Reprochfully they fleered in his face,</l>
               <l>That wept for them in tender true compassion,</l>
               <l>They wrought his death and did him all disgrace,</l>
               <l>That sought their life, and waild their desolation:</l>
               <l>Their hardened heartes beleeu'd not what was said,</l>
               <l>Vntill they saw the siege about them layd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Full fortie yeares after Christes passion,</l>
               <l>Did these proud people liue in peace and rest,</l>
               <l>Whose wanton eyes seeing no alteration,</l>
               <l>Christs words of truth, they turned to a iest:</l>
               <l>But when they thought themselues the surest of all,</l>
               <l>Lo then began their neuer raised fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Their mounting minds that towred past their strength</l>
               <l>Scorning subiection to the <hi>Romaine</hi> state,</l>
               <l>In boyling hatred loath'd their Lords at length,</l>
               <l>Dispis'd the Emperour with a deadly hate:</l>
               <l>Reiecting his authoritie each howre,</l>
               <l>Sought to expell the pride of forraine power.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which foule conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt the Emperours wrath inflam'd,</l>
               <l>Mightie <hi>Vespatian</hi> hot reueng did threat,</l>
               <l>But all in vaine they would not be reclaim'd,</l>
               <l>Relying on their strength and courage great:</l>
               <l>And hereupon began the deadly iarre,</l>
               <l>And after followed bloody wofull warre,</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:5511:4"/>
            <head>The sign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and tokens shewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the destruction, alluring the Iewes to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
and their little regard thereof, interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
all things to be for the best, flattering
themselues in their sinnes.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>YEt marke the mercy of our gracious God,</l>
               <l>Before the grieuous scourge to them was sent,</l>
               <l>That they might shun his heauie smarting rod,</l>
               <l>And hartely their filthy faultes repent:</l>
               <l>Strange signes and wonders did he shew them still,</l>
               <l>Fore-runners of their ruine woe, and ill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For one who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e yeare as well by day as night,</l>
               <l>A blazing starre appeared in the skie,</l>
               <l>Whose bushie tayle was so excelling bright,</l>
               <l>It dim'd the glory of the sunns faire eye,</l>
               <l>And euery one that on this obiect gazed,</l>
               <l>At sight thereof stood wonderous sore amazed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In right proportion it resembled well,</l>
               <l>A sharp two edged sword of mighty strength,</l>
               <l>The percing poynt a needle did excell,</l>
               <l>And sure it seem'd a mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cle for length:</l>
               <l>So strange a starre before was neuer seene,</l>
               <l>And since that time the like hath neuer been.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:5"/>
               <l>And ouer right that goodly famous Cittie,</l>
               <l>Hung still this dreadfull apparition,</l>
               <l>Which might haue mou'd had they bin gracious wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</l>
               <l>For outward follies, inward hearts contrition:</l>
               <l>And neuer did that wonder change his place,</l>
               <l>But still <hi>Ierusalem</hi> with woe menace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The wondring people neuer lookt thereon,</l>
               <l>But their mistrusting heart suspected much,</l>
               <l>Saying great plagues would follow thereupon,</l>
               <l>Such priuie motions did their conscience touch:</l>
               <l>But other-some would say it was not so,</l>
               <l>But signe that they their foes would ouerthrow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thinke not quoth they that Iacobs God will leaue,</l>
               <l>The blessed seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> in distresse,</l>
               <l>First shall his Sword the heathens liues bereaue,</l>
               <l>As by this token he doth plaine expresse,</l>
               <l>His fierie sword shall shield this holy towne,</l>
               <l>And heaw in heapes the proudest <hi>Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ins</hi> downe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus flattered they themselues in sinfull sort,</l>
               <l>Their harts were hard, their deepest iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts blinded</l>
               <l>What godly teachers did to them report,</l>
               <l>They soone forgot, such things they neuer minded:</l>
               <l>Their chiefest study was delight and pleasure,</l>
               <l>And how they might by all meanes gather treasure</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:5"/>
               <l>Men would haue thought this wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ning had bin faire,</l>
               <l>When God his standard gainst them did aduance,</l>
               <l>His flagge of Iustice waued in the ayre,</l>
               <l>And yet they count it, but a thing of chance:</l>
               <l>This bad them yeild, and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om their sinnes con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>art,</l>
               <l>But they would not till sorrow made them smart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then in the ayre God shewed another wonder,</l>
               <l>When azurd skies were brightest faire and cleere,</l>
               <l>An hoast of armed men, like dreadfull thunder,</l>
               <l>With hidious clamours, fighting did appeare:</l>
               <l>And at each other eagerly they ran,</l>
               <l>With burnisht Falchions murdering many a man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And marching fiercely in their proud aray,</l>
               <l>Their wrathfull eyes did sparkle like the fier,</l>
               <l>Or like inraged Lyons for their pray,</l>
               <l>So did they striue, in nature and desire:</l>
               <l>That all the plaine wherein they fighting stood,</l>
               <l>Seem'd to mens sight all staind with purple blood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This dreadfull token many men amazed,</l>
               <l>When they beh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld the vncouth sight so strange,</l>
               <l>On one another doubtfully they gazed,</l>
               <l>With fearefull lookes their coulour quite did change:</l>
               <l>Yet all, they did interpret to the best,</l>
               <l>Thinking themselues aboue all other blest.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:6"/>
               <l>The conquering sort that did with warlike hand,</l>
               <l>Suppresse the other in the bloudy field,</l>
               <l>Declares quoth they that <hi>Iudaes</hi> sacred band,</l>
               <l>Shall make vnhallowed <hi>Romaines</hi> die or yeeld:</l>
               <l>And ouer them we shall haue honour great,</l>
               <l>That proudly now vsurpes King Davids seat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>See how the Divell doth sinfull soules beguile,</l>
               <l>Filling the same with vaine imagination,</l>
               <l>Thinking themselves cock-sure, when al the while,</l>
               <l>They stand vpon the brink of desolation:</l>
               <l>All faithfull Christians warning take by this,</l>
               <l>Interpret not Gods fearfull signes amisse.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet loe the Lord would not giue ouer so,</l>
               <l>But to convert them, if that it might bee,</l>
               <l>Hee doth proceed more wonders yet to show,</l>
               <l>All to reclayme them from iniquitie:</l>
               <l>That so he might remoue his plagues away,</l>
               <l>Which threatned their destruction every day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Temple gates all made of shining brasse,</l>
               <l>Whose massie substance was exceeding great,</l>
               <l>Which they with yron barres each night did crosse,</l>
               <l>And lockt with brazen bolts, which made them sweat,</l>
               <l>Did of themselues start open and vndoe,</l>
               <l>Which twenty men of might could scant put to.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:6"/>
               <l>Vpon a day most high and festiuall,</l>
               <l>The high Priest went after a sacred manner,</l>
               <l>Into the glorious Temple most maiesticall,</l>
               <l>To offer sacrifice their God to honour:</l>
               <l>What time the Lord a wonder did declare,</l>
               <l>To all mens sight, prodigious, strange, and rare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A goodly <hi>Calfe</hi> prepar'd for sacrifice,</l>
               <l>And layd vpon the holy Alter there,</l>
               <l>Brought forth a <hi>Lambe</hi> most plaine before their eyes,</l>
               <l>Which filled some mens hearts with sodaine feare:</l>
               <l>And sore perplext the passions of their mind,</l>
               <l>To see a thing so farre against all kind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Soone after this they heard a wailefull voice,</l>
               <l>Which in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Temple shreeking thus did say,</l>
               <l>Let vs go hence, and no man heere reioyce,</l>
               <l>Thus figuring foorth their ruine and decay,</l>
               <l>All men did heare these speeches very plaine,</l>
               <l>But saw nothi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g, nor knew from whence it came.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And foure yeares space before the bloody fight,</l>
               <l>One <hi>Ananias</hi> had a youthfull sonne,</l>
               <l>Which like a Prophet cried day and night</l>
               <l>About the streets as he did go and runne:</l>
               <l>Shewing the people without dread at all,</l>
               <l>Most wofull plagues should on the Cittie fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:7"/>
               <l>And in this sort began his dolefull cry:</l>
               <l>A fearefull voyce proceedeth from the East,</l>
               <l>And from the West, as great a voyce did fly,</l>
               <l>A voyce likewise from blustering winds addrest:</l>
               <l>A voyce vpon <hi>Ierusalem</hi> shall goe,</l>
               <l>A voyce vpon the Temple full of woe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A mournefull voyce on wretched man and wife,</l>
               <l>A voyce of sorrow on the people all,</l>
               <l>Woe and destruction, mortall war and strife,</l>
               <l>Bitter pinching famine, misery and thrall:</l>
               <l>In euery place these threatnings still he had,</l>
               <l>Running about like one distraught and mad.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With lofty voyce thus ran he through the towne,</l>
               <l>Nor day and night did he his clamours cease,</l>
               <l>No man could make him lay these threatnings downe</l>
               <l>By no intreaty would he hould his peace:</l>
               <l>Although he was in Dungeon deeply layd,</l>
               <l>Yet there his cryes did make them more afraid.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Maiestrates that most forbad his crie:</l>
               <l>And saw his bouldnesse more and more arise,</l>
               <l>With grieuous scourges whipt him bitterly,</l>
               <l>Yet came no teares out of his pleasant eyes:</l>
               <l>The more his stripes, the higher went his voyce<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>In sorest torment did he most reioyce.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:7"/>
               <l>But when the <hi>Iewes</hi> perceau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d how he was bent,</l>
               <l>And that their eares were cloyed with his cries,</l>
               <l>They counted it but sportfull merriment,</l>
               <l>A nine dayes wonder that in short time dyes:</l>
               <l>So that a fresh their fol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies they begin,</l>
               <l>And for his speech they passed not a pin.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But as the holy Scriptures doe bewray,</l>
               <l>To dainty cheere they iocondly sat downe,</l>
               <l>And well refresht, they rose againe to play,</l>
               <l>In smiling sort when God did fircely frowne:</l>
               <l>And neuer more to mirth were they diposed,</l>
               <l>Then when the Lord his wrath to them disclosed.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶The tydings brought of the enimies appoach, and the feare
of the citizens: their provisio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of victuals for twenty yeares
burnt in one night, by one of their owne captaines, of meere
malice, which caused a sodaine dearth to follow: their seditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
and diuisio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> betweene the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>selues while the cittie was besieged.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>BVt whilst that they their sugred Iunkets tasted,</l>
               <l>Vnto the Citty came a tyred post,</l>
               <l>Full weake and wearie, and with trauell wasted,</l>
               <l>Who brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> word their foes were on their coast:</l>
               <l>Which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they knew, their merriments were dashed</l>
               <l>These dolefull newes made them full sore abashed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:8"/>
               <l>Three Cipres Tables then to ground they throw,</l>
               <l>Their siluer dishes, and their cups of gould,</l>
               <l>For haste to meet the proud inuading foe,</l>
               <l>Feare ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es them mad, but courage makes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bould:</l>
               <l>And to defend the brunt of future harmes,</l>
               <l>They leaue their Ladies and imbrace their Armes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Instead of Lutes and sweete resounding Vials,</l>
               <l>They sound the Trumpet and the ratling drum,</l>
               <l>Their barbed Steeds they put to diuers tryals,</l>
               <l>How they can manage, stop, carrie, and run:</l>
               <l>Their cunning harpers now must harnesse beare,</l>
               <l>Their nimble dauncers war-like weapons weare,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ere their wrathfull foes approached neere,</l>
               <l>The store-houses the Gouerners did fill,</l>
               <l>With wholsome victuals which for twenty yeare</l>
               <l>Would serue two hundred thousand cast by bill,</l>
               <l>But all the same by one seditious Squire</l>
               <l>Was in one night consum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d with flaming fire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For why the Cittizens to discord fell,</l>
               <l>So giddy headed were they alwaies found,</l>
               <l>And in their rage like furious fiends of hell,</l>
               <l>In murdering sort they did each other wound:</l>
               <l>And when they entred in this diuellish strife,</l>
               <l>They spared neither Infant, man, nor wife.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:8"/>
               <l>Into three parts the people were deuided,</l>
               <l>And one against an other hatred bore,</l>
               <l>The chiefest sort sediciously were guided,</l>
               <l>Whereby vnciuell mutines vext them sore:</l>
               <l>So that the sorrow of the forr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine warre,</l>
               <l>Was nothing to their bloody ciuill iarre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And so malicious did their rancor rise,</l>
               <l>That they the holy Temple did defile,</l>
               <l>All such as came to offer sacrifice,</l>
               <l>They murdered straight, remorce they did exile:</l>
               <l>The Sacrificer with the sacrifice,</l>
               <l>Both bath'd in blood, men saw before their eyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus did they make the sacred Temple there,</l>
               <l>The slaughter house of many a humane soule,</l>
               <l>So that the marble pauement euery where,</l>
               <l>was blacke with blood like to a butchers bowle:</l>
               <l>And with the fat of men so slippery made,</l>
               <l>That there for falling, none could goe vnstayd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And by this wicked meanes it came to passe,</l>
               <l>The streets and temple full of dead-men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay,</l>
               <l>With wounds putrified, where buriall was,</l>
               <l>Which rais'd a grieuous pestilence that day:</l>
               <l>So hot, and fell, that thereof dyed a number,</l>
               <l>Whose foule infection all the towne did cumber.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:9"/>
               <l>And that which was more heauie to behold,</l>
               <l>As men and woemen past along the street:</l>
               <l>Their weeping eyes did to their hearts vnfold,</l>
               <l>A mappe of Murder at their trembling feete</l>
               <l>Some saw their Fathers fetching deadly groanes,</l>
               <l>Some their Husbands braines scattered on the sto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here lay a woman stabbed to the heart,</l>
               <l>There a tender Infant one a souldiers speare,</l>
               <l>Strugling with death, and sprawling with each part:</l>
               <l>The channels ran with purple blood each wheare</l>
               <l>A thousand persons might you daily see,</l>
               <l>Some gasping, groaning bleeding fresh to bee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Lo, all this mischiefe was within the towne</l>
               <l>Wrought twixt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>selues in wonderous hatefull sort,</l>
               <l>While noble <hi>Tytus</hi> beat their bulwarkes downe,</l>
               <l>And at their walles did shew them warlike sport:</l>
               <l>But by distresse to bring them vnto thrall,</l>
               <l>He brake their pipes, and stopt their cundits all.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:5511:9"/>
            <head>¶A descriptio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the horrible Famine within
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Cittie of Ierusalem.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>FOr true report r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g in his royall eares,</l>
               <l>That bitter Famine did afflict them sore,</l>
               <l>Which was the cause of many bitter teares,</l>
               <l>And he to make their miserie the more,</l>
               <l>Depriu'd them quit of all their water cleere,</l>
               <l>Which in their want they did esteeme so deere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Alack, what pen is able to expresse?</l>
               <l>The extreame miserie of this people then?</l>
               <l>Which were with Famine brought to great distresse,</l>
               <l>For cruell hunger vext the welthiest men:</l>
               <l>When night approacht, well might they lye &amp; winke,</l>
               <l>But cold not sleepe for want of meat and drinke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For by this time full Fourteene monthes and more,</l>
               <l>Had warlike <hi>Titus</hi> sieg'd that famous towne,</l>
               <l>What time the <hi>Iewes</hi> had quite consum'd their store,</l>
               <l>And being staru'd, like Ghosts went vp and downe:</l>
               <l>For in the markets were no victuals found,</l>
               <l>Though for a <hi>Lambe,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey might haue twenty pound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:10"/>
               <l>When bread was gone, then was he counted blest,</l>
               <l>That in his hand had either cat or dogge,</l>
               <l>To fill his emptie maw: and thus distrest,</l>
               <l>A dozen men would fight for one poore frogge,</l>
               <l>The fairest Lady lighting one a mouce,</l>
               <l>Would keepe it from her best friend in the house.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A weazell was accounted daynty meate,</l>
               <l>A hissing snake esteem'd a Princes dish,</l>
               <l>A Queene vpon a moule might seeme to eate,</l>
               <l>A veanom neawt was thought a wholesome fish:</l>
               <l>Wormes from the earth, were dig'd vp great &amp; small,</l>
               <l>And poysoned spiders eaten from the wall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A hundred men vnder this grieuous crosse,</l>
               <l>With hunger-starued bodies wanting food,</l>
               <l>Haue for a morsell of a stinking horse,</l>
               <l>In deadly strife, shed one an others blood.</l>
               <l>Like famisht Rauens, that in a shole doe pitch,</l>
               <l>To seaze a caryon in a noysome ditch.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But when these things, were all consumed quite,</l>
               <l>(For famines greedy mawe destroyeth all,)</l>
               <l>Then did they bend, their study day and night,</l>
               <l>To see what next vnto their share might fall:</l>
               <l>Necessitie doth seeke an hundred wayes,</l>
               <l>Famines fell torment from the heart to rayse.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:10"/>
               <l>Then did they take their horses leather raignes,</l>
               <l>And broyling them suppos'd the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wonderous sweete,</l>
               <l>A hungry stomack naught at all refraines,</l>
               <l>Nor did they spare their shooes vpon their feete:</l>
               <l>But shooes, and bootes, and buskins, all they eate,</l>
               <l>And would not spare one morsell of their meate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But out alas my heart doth shake to show,</l>
               <l>When these things fail'd, what shift these wretches made,</l>
               <l>Without salt teares how should I write their woe,</l>
               <l>Sith sorrowes ground-worke in the same is layd:</l>
               <l>All English hearts which Christ in armes doe hem</l>
               <l>Marke wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the woes of fayre <hi>Ierusalem.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When all was spent, and nothing left to eate,</l>
               <l>Whereby they might maintaine their feeble life,</l>
               <l>Then doth the wife her husband deere intreat,</l>
               <l>To end her misery by his wounding knife:</l>
               <l>Maides weepe for foode, &amp; children make their moa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e,</l>
               <l>Their parents sigh when they can giue them none.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some men with hunger falleth raging mad,</l>
               <l>Gnawing the stones and timber where they walke,</l>
               <l>Some other staggering, weake and wonderous s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d,</l>
               <l>Dyes in the streetes, as with their friends they talke?</l>
               <l>And other some licks vp the vomit fast,</l>
               <l>Which their sick neighbours in their houses cast.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:11"/>
               <l>Nay more then this, though this be all to much,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iosephus</hi> writes, that men and maidens young</l>
               <l>The which of late did scorne brown-bread to touch,</l>
               <l>Sustain'd themselues with one an others doong.</l>
               <l>Remember this you that so dainty bee,</l>
               <l>And praise Gods name for all things sent to thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All things were brought by famine out of frame,</l>
               <l>For modest Chastitie to it gaue place,</l>
               <l>High honoured Virgins that for very shame,</l>
               <l>Would hardly looke on men with open face,</l>
               <l>One bit of beead neuer so course and browne,</l>
               <l>Would winne them to the foulest knaue in towne.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶The seditious Captaines Schimion &amp; Iehocana<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> search
all the houses in the Citty for Victuals, they take from a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Lady al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her prouision, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>auing her and her Sonne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortlesse,
shewing the great moane she made.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THe curst seditious Captaines and their crue,</l>
               <l>When they perceiu'd the famine grow so great,</l>
               <l>In all mens houses would they search, and view,</l>
               <l>In euery corner both for bread and meat:</l>
               <l>If any did their bould request denie,</l>
               <l>On murdering swords they were right sure to dye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:11"/>
               <l>Among the rest where they a searching went,</l>
               <l>Vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gallant Ladyes house they came,</l>
               <l>And there before her victuals quite was spent,</l>
               <l>With hardened hearts, and faces void of shame:</l>
               <l>They tooke her store with many a bitte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> threat,</l>
               <l>And left her not one bit of bread to eate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The noble Lady on her tender knees,</l>
               <l>With floods of teares distilling from her eyes,</l>
               <l>Their crueltie when she so plainely sees,</l>
               <l>In mournefull sort vnto them thus she cries:</l>
               <l>Vpon a wofull Lady take some pittie,</l>
               <l>And let not famine slay me in this Cittie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of all the store which you haue tooke away,</l>
               <l>Leaue on browne loafe, for my poore child and me:</l>
               <l>That we may eat but one bit in a day,</l>
               <l>To saue our liues from extreame misery.</l>
               <l>Thus holding vp her lillie hands she cried,</l>
               <l>The more she crau'd the more she was denied.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If you quoth she cannot a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>orp me bread,</l>
               <l>One dried stock-fish doe one me bestow,</l>
               <l>For my poore Infants life I greatly dread,</l>
               <l>If thus distrest you leaue me when you goe:</l>
               <l>Braue men of might, shew pittie for his sake,</l>
               <l>And I thereof a thousand meales will make.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:12"/>
               <l>O call to minde my childe is nobly borne,</l>
               <l>Of honorable blood and high degree,</l>
               <l>Then leaue vs not braue Captaines thus forlorne,</l>
               <l>Your countries f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iend one day this child may bee:</l>
               <l>O let me not this gentle fauour misse,</l>
               <l>I may one day requi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e far more then this.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then answered they in harsh and churlish sort,</l>
               <l>Tut tell not vs of honourable state,</l>
               <l>And if thou wilt we'l cut thy Infants throat,</l>
               <l>So shall he neede no meate, then cease to pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e:</l>
               <l>Men must haue meate, let children dye and s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arue,</l>
               <l>Yf we want foode, in warres how can we seru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With bended browes they s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>roue to get away</l>
               <l>But she vpon her knees did follow fast,</l>
               <l>And taking hould on their confus'd aray,</l>
               <l>This sad complaint from her hearts pallace past:</l>
               <l>Renouned Lords, our Citties sure defence,</l>
               <l>O let me speake once more, ere you goe hence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yf you lack money, see I haue good store,</l>
               <l>Wherein great <hi>Cesars</hi> Image is portrayde,</l>
               <l>Therefore of gift, I will demaund no more,</l>
               <l>To buy me some foode, let me not be denayd.</l>
               <l>For fiue red herriugs, ten Crownes shall you haue,</l>
               <l>Ile pay it downe, with vantage if you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:12"/>
               <l>That damned coyne quoth they wee doe de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>est,</l>
               <l>And therewithall thy selfe, which all this while,</l>
               <l>Has<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> kept our foes foule picture in thy chest,</l>
               <l>Which seekes this holy Citty to de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e:</l>
               <l>Thou getst no foode, and therefore hold thy toungue</l>
               <l>Hang, starue, &amp; dye, thou canst not dye more young.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O pardon yet (quoth she) my earnest speech,</l>
               <l>Doe not my words to poyson so conuert,</l>
               <l>Take heere my chaine, I humbly doe beseech,</l>
               <l>Of pearle and Diamonds for one silly sprat:</l>
               <l>One sprat (sweete men) cast vpon the ground,</l>
               <l>For this faire chaine, which cost a thousand pound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Talke not to vs, quoth they of Iems and chaines,</l>
               <l>Of Diamonds, Pearls or precious rings of Gould,</l>
               <l>One sprat to vs is sweeter gotten gaines,</l>
               <l>Then so much siluer, as this house can hold:</l>
               <l>Gould is but drosse, where hunger is so great,</l>
               <l>Hard hap hath hee, that hath but gould to eate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With that the testie Souldiers get them out,</l>
               <l>Proud of the purchast pray which they had got,</l>
               <l>The woefull Lady e did they mocke and flout,</l>
               <l>Her plaints and teares regarding not a iott:</l>
               <l>Shee sighes they smile, she mournes, and they reioyce,</l>
               <l>And of their pray they make an equall choyce,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:13"/>
               <l>But Megar famine couetous of all,</l>
               <l>Enuying those that should thereof haue part,</l>
               <l>In sharing out there purchasse bread a brawle,</l>
               <l>Wherein one s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abd the other to the heart:</l>
               <l>This fellow said the other did deceiue him,</l>
               <l>He swore againe enough they did not leaue him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Lo thus about the victuals they did fight,</l>
               <l>Looke who was strongest bore away the prize,</l>
               <l>And for a crust of bread, in dead of night,</l>
               <l>They cut their Fathers throats in wofull wise:</l>
               <l>The mother would her childrens victuals snatch,</l>
               <l>And from his wife, the husband he did catch.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶How the noble Lady and her young S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nne went to
out the dung of beasts to eate, being ready to dye with hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
and could finde none: shewing what moane they
made comming home without,</head>
            <lg>
               <l>BVt now of <hi>Miriams</hi> sorrow will I speake,</l>
               <l>Whom the seditious Souldiers so distrest,</l>
               <l>Her noble heart with girfe was like to breake,</l>
               <l>No kind of foode had she, then to reliue her,</l>
               <l>With gnawing hunger was she, sore opprest</l>
               <l>Nor for her child: which most of all did grieue her.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:13"/>
               <l>Alas quoth shee that euer I was borne,</l>
               <l>To see these gloomie daies of griefe and care,</l>
               <l>whome this false world hath mede an open scorne,</l>
               <l>Fraught full of miserie passing all compare:</l>
               <l>Blest had I been if in the painefull birth,</l>
               <l>I had receiu'd sweete sentence of my death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Why hath the partiall heauens prolong'd my life,</l>
               <l>Aboue a number of my deerest friends,</l>
               <l>Whose blessed soules did neuer see the strife,</l>
               <l>How happy were they in their happy ends:</l>
               <l>Great God of <hi>Abraham</hi> heare my mournefull crie,</l>
               <l>Soone rid my life or end this miserie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With that her little sonne with eager looke,</l>
               <l>Vnto his wofull mother crying came,</l>
               <l>His pretty hands fast hold vpon her tooke,</l>
               <l>Whose presence brought, her praying out of frame:</l>
               <l>And to his Mother thus the child did say,</l>
               <l>Giue mee some meate, that eat nothing to day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I am (deere Mother) hungry at the heart,</l>
               <l>And scalding thirst, makes me I cannot speake,</l>
               <l>I feele my strength decay in euery part,</l>
               <l>One bit of bread, for me good Mother breake,</l>
               <l>My lesson I haue learnd, where you did lay it,</l>
               <l>Then giue me some what: you shall heere me say it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:14"/>
               <l>The sighing Ladie looking quite a-side,</l>
               <l>With many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>obs sent from her wofull soule,</l>
               <l>Wroung both her hands, but not one word replide,</l>
               <l>Sighes stopt her toung, teares did her tongue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>troul,</l>
               <l>Sweete Lady mother, mother speake (quoth he?)</l>
               <l>O let me not with hunger murdered bee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Deere child she said, what wouldst thou haue of me?</l>
               <l>Art thou a thirst, then come and drinke my teares,</l>
               <l>For other succour haue I none for thee,</l>
               <l>The time hath been, I could haue giueu thee peares:</l>
               <l>Rose coulered apples, cherries for my child,</l>
               <l>But now alas, of all wee are beguild.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But come quoth she, giue me thy little finger,</l>
               <l>And thou and I will to the back-yard goe,</l>
               <l>And there seeke out a Cow-cake For thy dinner,</l>
               <l>How saist thou sonne art thou contented so?</l>
               <l>The ioyfull child did hereat giue a smile,</l>
               <l>When both his eyes with water ran the while.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then vp and downe with warie s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arching eye,</l>
               <l>In euery place for beasts dung doth she seeke,</l>
               <l>As if a long lost Iewell there did lye,</l>
               <l>Clo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e hidden in some narrow chink or creeke:</l>
               <l>When she lookt and nought at all had found,</l>
               <l>Then downe she coucheth on the sluttish ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:14"/>
               <l>And with her faire white fingers fine and small,</l>
               <l>She scrapes away the dust and draffe togeather,
and so doth search through out the Oxes stall,</l>
               <l>For dung or hoofes, or some old peece of leather:</l>
               <l>But when in vaine her paines she did bestow,</l>
               <l>She paid her heart the interest of her woe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And lifting vp with sorow her bright eyes,</l>
               <l>She cald her little Sonne to come away,</l>
               <l>Who sought as fast for spiders, wormes and flies,</l>
               <l>As she for Ordure mongst the mouldy hay,</l>
               <l>O stay a while good mother did he cry,</l>
               <l>For heere euen now I did a maggot spie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At which sweete sight my teeth did water yet,</l>
               <l>Euen as you cald, she fell her in the dust,</l>
               <l>An hower were well spent, this prize to get,</l>
               <l>To let her slip, I thinke I was accurst:</l>
               <l>My hungry stomacke, well it would haue stayd,</l>
               <l>And I haue lost her I am sore affraid.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I, I, my Sonne, it may be so (quoth shee,)</l>
               <l>Then come away: let vs togeather dye,</l>
               <l>Our lucklesse starres alots it so to be,</l>
               <l>Peace my sweete boy, alack why dost thou cry,</l>
               <l>Had I found any thing, thou shouldst haue seen,</l>
               <l>That therewithall we would haue merry been,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:15"/>
               <l>Then be thou still (my sonne) and weepe no more,</l>
               <l>For with my t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ares, thou kilst my wounded heart,</l>
               <l>Thy neede is great, my hunger is as sore,</l>
               <l>Which grieues my soule, and pinches euery part:</l>
               <l>Yet hope of helpe alack I know not any,</l>
               <l>Without, within, our foes they are so many.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Deare mother heare me one word and no moe,</l>
               <l>See heere my foote so slender in your sight,</l>
               <l>Giue me but leaue to eate my little toe,</l>
               <l>No be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter supper will I aske to night:</l>
               <l>Or else my thumbe: a morsell small you see,</l>
               <l>And these two ioynts, me thinks may spared be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My sonne quoth she great are thy cares God wot,</l>
               <l>To haue thy hungry stomack fil'd with food,</l>
               <l>Yet all be it we haue so hard a lot,</l>
               <l>Dismember not thy selfe for any good:</l>
               <l>No brutish beast, will doe so foule a deede,</l>
               <l>Then doe not thou gainst nature so proceed,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But O my sonne, what shall I doe quoth she<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>My griefe of hunger is as great as thine,</l>
               <l>And sure no hope of comfort doe I see,</l>
               <l>But we must yeild our selues to starue and pine:</l>
               <l>The wrath of God doth siege the Citty round,</l>
               <l>And we within fell famine doth confound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:15"/>
               <l>The sword without, intends our desolation,</l>
               <l>Consuming pestilence destroyeth heere within,</l>
               <l>Ciuell dissention breedes our hearts vexation,</l>
               <l>The angry heauens, the same hath sent for sinne,</l>
               <l>Murders, and ruine through our streete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> doe run,</l>
               <l>Then how can I feede thee, my louing sonne?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yf pale fac't famine take away my life,</l>
               <l>Why then, with whome should I trust thee my sonen</l>
               <l>Far heer's no loue, but hate and deadly strife,</l>
               <l>Woe is that child, whose parents dayes are done:</l>
               <l>One thee sweete boy no person would take pitty,</l>
               <l>For milde compassion, hath forsooke the citty.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Once I retaynd, this ioyfull hope of thee,</l>
               <l>When ripened yeares, brought thee to mans estate,</l>
               <l>That thou shouldst be a comfort vnto me,</l>
               <l>Feeding my age, when youthfull strength did bate:</l>
               <l>And haue my meate my drinke and cloth of thee,</l>
               <l>Fit for a <hi>Lady</hi> of so high degree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And when the span length, of my life was done,</l>
               <l>That God and nature, claim'd of me their due,</l>
               <l>My hope was then, that thou my louing Sonne,</l>
               <l>In Marble stone, my memorie should renew:</l>
               <l>And bring my corpes, with honour to the graue,</l>
               <l>The latest dutie, men of children crau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:16"/>
               <l>But now I see (my sweete and bonny boy)</l>
               <l>This hope is fruitlesse, and these thoughts are vaine,</l>
               <l>I see grim death, hath seaz'd my earthly ioy,</l>
               <l>I or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amines dart hath thee already slaine:</l>
               <l>Thy hollow eyes and wrinckled cheekes declare,</l>
               <l>Thou art not markt, to be thy Fathers heire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Looke on thy legges, see all thy flesh is gone,</l>
               <l>Thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ollie thighes, are fallen quite away,</l>
               <l>Thy a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mes and handes, nothing but skin, and bone</l>
               <l>How weake thy heart is, thou thy selfe canst say:</l>
               <l>I haue no foode, to strengthen thee (my child,)</l>
               <l>And heere thy buriall would be too too vilde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wherefore my Sonne least vgly Rauens and Crowes,</l>
               <l>Should eate thy carcas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in the stincking streetes,</l>
               <l>Thereby to be a scorne vnto our foes,</l>
               <l>And gaule to me, that gaue thee many sweets:</l>
               <l>I haue prepaird, this my vnspotted wombe,</l>
               <l>To be for thee an honourable Tombe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then sith thou canst not liue to be a man,</l>
               <l>What time thou mightst haue fed thy aged mother,</l>
               <l>Therefore my child it lyes thee now vpon,</l>
               <l>To be my foode, because I haue no other:</l>
               <l>With my one blood, long time I nourisht thee,</l>
               <l>Then with thy flesh, thou oughtst to cherish mee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:16"/>
               <l>Within this wombe thou first receiuedst breath,</l>
               <l>Then giue thy mother, that which she gaue thee,</l>
               <l>Here hadst thou life, then lye here after death,</l>
               <l>Sith thou hadst beene, so welbeloude of me:</l>
               <l>In spight of foes, be thou my dayly food,</l>
               <l>And saue my life, that can doe thee no good,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In blessed <hi>Eden</hi> shall thy soule remaine,</l>
               <l>While that my belly is thy bodyes graue,</l>
               <l>There is no taste of famine woe or paine</l>
               <l>But ioyes eternall, more then heart can craue:</l>
               <l>Then who would wish, in sorrow to perseuer,</l>
               <l>That by his death might liue in heauen for euer.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The Lady with hunger is constrayned to kill her best
beloued and onely Sonne, and eate him:
whose body she Roasted.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>VVHen this was said, her feeble child she tooke,</l>
               <l>And with a sword which she had lying by,</l>
               <l>She thrust him through turning away her looke,</l>
               <l>That her wet eyes might not behold him die:</l>
               <l>And when sweete life was from his body fled,</l>
               <l>A thousand times she kist him being dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:17"/>
               <l>His mil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e white body staind with purple blood,</l>
               <l>She cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nsd and washt with siluer dropping teares,</l>
               <l>Which being done, she wipte it as she stood,</l>
               <l>With nothing else, but her faire golden haires:</l>
               <l>And when she <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aw, his litle lims were cold,</l>
               <l>She cut him vp, for hunger made her bold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In many peeces did she then deuide him,</l>
               <l>Some part she sod, some other part she rosted,</l>
               <l>Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neighbours sight she made great shift to hide him,</l>
               <l>And of her cheere, in heart she greatly bosted:</l>
               <l>Ere it was ready, she began to eate,</l>
               <l>And from the spit, pluckt many bits of meate.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The smell of the meate is felt round about: the sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Captai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> therevpon came to the Lady, and threatens
to kill her for meate. Wherevpon the Lady, sets
part before them.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THe sent thereof was straight smelt round abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>The neighbour then out of their houses ran,</l>
               <l>Saying, we smell roast-meat out of all doubt,</l>
               <l>Which was great wonder vnto euery man:</l>
               <l>And euery one like to a longing wife,</l>
               <l>In that good cheer did wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h his sharpest knife.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:17"/>
               <l>This newes so swift, in each mans mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th did flie,</l>
               <l>The proud seditious, heard thereof at last,</l>
               <l>Who with all speed, vnto the house did hye,</l>
               <l>And at the doores and windowes knocked fast:</l>
               <l>And with vilde words &amp; speeches rough and great,</l>
               <l>They askt the Lady, where she had that meat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou wicked woman how comes this quoth they?</l>
               <l>That thou alone hast roast-meat in the towne?</l>
               <l>While we with griping famine dye each day,</l>
               <l>Which are your Lords, and leaders of renowne:</l>
               <l>For this contempt, we thinke it right and reason,</l>
               <l>Thou shouldst be punisht as in case of treason.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The louely Lady trembling at their speech,</l>
               <l>Fearing their bloody hands and cruell actions,</l>
               <l>With many gentle words, did them beseech,</l>
               <l>They would not enter into further factions:</l>
               <l>But listen to her words and she would tell,</l>
               <l>The certaine truth, how euery thing befell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Be not she said, at your poore hand-maid grieued,</l>
               <l>I haue not eaten all in this hard case,</l>
               <l>But that your selues might something be relieued,</l>
               <l>I haue kept part to giue you in this place:</l>
               <l>Then sit you downe, right welcome shall you be,</l>
               <l>And what I haue, your selues shall tast and see.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:18"/>
               <l>With diligence the Table then she layde,</l>
               <l>And siluer trenchers, on the boord she set,</l>
               <l>A golden salt, that many ounces wayde,</l>
               <l>And Damask napkins, dainty, fine, and neate:</l>
               <l>Her guests were glad to se this preparation,</l>
               <l>And at the boord they sat with contentation,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In massie siluer platters brought she forth,</l>
               <l>Her owne Sonnes flesh whom she did loue so deere,</l>
               <l>Saying my maisters take this well in worth,</l>
               <l>I pray be merry: looke for no other cheere:</l>
               <l>See here my childs white hand, most finely drest,</l>
               <l>And here his foote, eate where it likes you best.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And doe not say this child was any others,</l>
               <l>But my owne Sonne: whome you so well did know,</l>
               <l>Which may seeme strange, vnto all tender Mothers,</l>
               <l>My owne childes flesh, I should deuoure so:</l>
               <l>Him did I beare, and carefully did feed,</l>
               <l>And now his flesh sustaines me in my need.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet allbeit this sweet relieuing feast,</l>
               <l>Hath dearest beene to me that ere I made,</l>
               <l>Yet niggardize I doe so much detest,</l>
               <l>I thought it shame, but there should some be layde,</l>
               <l>In store for you: although the store be small,</l>
               <l>For they are gluttons which consumeth all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:18"/>
               <l>Herewith she burst into a flood of teares,</l>
               <l>Which downe her thin pale cheekes distilled fast,</l>
               <l>Her bleeding heart, no sobs nor sighes forbeares,</l>
               <l>Till her weake voyce breath'd out these words at last:</l>
               <l>O my deere Sonne, my pretty boy (quoth she)</l>
               <l>While thou didst liue, how sweet wast thou to me?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet sweeter farre, a thousand times thou art,</l>
               <l>To thy poore mother, at this instant howre,</l>
               <l>My hungry stomake hast thou eas'd of smart,</l>
               <l>And kept me from the bloody Tyrants power,</l>
               <l>And they like friends doe at my table eat,</l>
               <l>That would haue kild me for a bit of meate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When this was said, wiping her watery eyes,</l>
               <l>Vnto her self, fresh courage then she tooke,</l>
               <l>And all her guests, she welcom'd in this wise,</l>
               <l>Casting on them, a courteous pleasant looke:</l>
               <l>Be mery friends, I pray you doe not sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>In all this towne, is not such noble fare.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:5511:19"/>
            <head>The Captaines and their company were so amazed
at sight of the childs limbes being by his mother set vpon
the table in platters, that wondring thereat, they
would not eat a bite, for the which the Lady
reproues them.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THE men amazed at this vncouth sight,</l>
               <l>One to another cast a steadfast eye,</l>
               <l>Their hard remorcelesse hearts full fraught with spight</l>
               <l>Were herewithall appalled sodenly,</l>
               <l>And though their extreame hunger was full great,</l>
               <l>Like sencelesse men they sat and would not eate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O why quoth she doe you refraine this food,</l>
               <l>I brought it forth vnto you for good wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>corne it not (deere friends) for it is good:</l>
               <l>And I euen now did thereof eate my fill:</l>
               <l>Tast it therefore and I dare sweare you'l say,</l>
               <l>You eate no meate, more sweete this many a day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hard hearted woman, cruell and vnkind</l>
               <l>Canst thou (quoth they) so frankly feed of this?</l>
               <l>A thing more hatefull did wee neuer finde,</l>
               <l>Then keepe it for thy tooth, loe there it is.</l>
               <l>Most vild and odious is it in our eye,</l>
               <l>Then feed on mans flesh, rather would wee dye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:19"/>
               <l>Alack quoth she, doth foolish pitty mooue ye,</l>
               <l>Weaker then a womans, is your hearts become,</l>
               <l>I pray fall too, and if that you doe loue me,</l>
               <l>Eate where you will, and ile with you eat some</l>
               <l>What greater shame to Captaines can befall,</l>
               <l>Then I in courage should surpasse you all,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Why, wast not you, that did with many a threats,</l>
               <l>Charge me with eager lookes to lay the cloth:</l>
               <l>And as I lou'd my li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to bring you meate,</l>
               <l>And now to eate it doe you seeme so loath?</l>
               <l>Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e fit I should, then you, heerewith be moued,</l>
               <l>Since twas his flesh whom I so deerly loued.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It was my sonne and not yours that is slaine.</l>
               <l>Whose roasted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imbes lies here within the platter,</l>
               <l>Then more then you I ought his flesh refraine,</l>
               <l>And ten times more be greeued at this matter,</l>
               <l>How chance you are more mercifull then I,</l>
               <l>To spare his flesh, while you for hunger dye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet blame not me for this outragious deed,</l>
               <l>For wast not you that first did spoyle my house?</l>
               <l>And rob me of my food in my great need,</l>
               <l>Leauing not behind a ratt or silly mouse:</l>
               <l>Then you alone are authors of this feast,</l>
               <l>What n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed you then this action so detest?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:20"/>
               <l>The starued <hi>Iewes</hi> hearing this dolefull tale,</l>
               <l>Were at the matter smitten in such sadnesse,</l>
               <l>That man by man with visage wan and pale,</l>
               <l>Dropt out of dores, accusing her of madnesse,</l>
               <l>And noting we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l, their famine, warre and strife,</l>
               <l>Wisht rather death, than length of mortall life.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And hereupon, much people of the Citty,</l>
               <l>Fled to the <hi>Romaines</hi> secret in the night,</l>
               <l>Vpon their knees desiring them for pitty</l>
               <l>To saue their liues, that were in wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ull plight,</l>
               <l>And finding mercie, tolde when that was done<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>How famine forc't a <hi>Lady</hi> eate her <hi>Sonne.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Tytus the Romaine Generall wept at the report of
the famine in Ierusalem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> especially when he heard
of the Mother that did eate her Childe.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THe Romaine Generall hearing of the same,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tytus</hi> I meane, <hi>Vespasians</hi> famous Sonne,</l>
               <l>So grieu'd thereat, that griefe did teares constraine,</l>
               <l>Which downe his manly cheekes did streaming runne</l>
               <l>And holding vp to heauen his hands and eyes</l>
               <l>To this effect, vnto the Lord he cries.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:20"/>
               <l>Thou mighty God, which guides this mortall round,</l>
               <l>That all hearts secrets sees, and knowes my heart,</l>
               <l>Witnesse thou canst, I came not to confound,</l>
               <l>This goodly Cittie: or to worke their smart:</l>
               <l>I was not author of their bloudie iarrs,</l>
               <l>But offred peace, when they imbraced wars.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>These eighteene moneths, that I with warlike force,</l>
               <l>Besieged their Cittiy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (Lord thou knowest it well,)</l>
               <l>My heart was full of mercy and remorce,</l>
               <l>And they alwayes did stubbornely rebell:</l>
               <l>Therfore good Lord, with their most hatefull rage,</l>
               <l>And wondrous deeds do not my conscience charge</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My eyes doe see, my heart doth likewise pity,</l>
               <l>The great calamitie that they are in,</l>
               <l>Yet Lord, except thou wilt yeeld me the Cittie,</l>
               <l>I'le raise my power, and not behold more sinne:</l>
               <l>For they with famine are become so wilde,</l>
               <l>That hunger made a woman eate her childe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When Noble <hi>Titus</hi> thus had made his moane,</l>
               <l>All those that from <hi>Ierusalem</hi> did fly:</l>
               <l>He did receaue to mercy every one,</l>
               <l>And nourisht famisht men at poynt to dye:</l>
               <l>But cruell <hi>Schimion</hi> that seditious <hi>Iewe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And Proud <hi>Iehocanan,</hi> more mischiefe still did brew.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:21"/>
               <l>For albeit braue <hi>Tytus</hi> by his power,</l>
               <l>And warlike Engines, brought vnto that plece,</l>
               <l>Had layde their strong walles, flat vpon the flower,</l>
               <l>And done their Citty, wonderfull disgrace.</l>
               <l>Yet stubbo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nly they did resist him still,</l>
               <l>Such pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce they gaue, to their seditious will.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Tytus ouerthrowing the walls of Ierusalem enters the
Cyty and Temple with his power burning downe the silue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
gate thereof, which led the way to the Sanctum Sanctoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:
and setteh Souldiers to keepe it from further hurt.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>ABout that time with wonderous dilligence,</l>
               <l>They rais'd a wall, in secret of the night,</l>
               <l>Which then was found their Citties best defence,</l>
               <l>For to withstand the conquering <hi>Roma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nes</hi> might:</l>
               <l>which once rac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tty needs must yeeld,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Iewes</hi> giue place to <hi>Romaines</hi> sword and shield,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Reno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ned <hi>Tytus</hi> well perceiuing this,</l>
               <l>To his best proued Captaines, gaue a charge,</l>
               <l>That new rais'd wall, the <hi>Iewes</hi> supposed blis,</l>
               <l>Should scattered be, with breaches wide and large:</l>
               <l>And hervpon, the troopes togither met,</l>
               <l>And to the walles, their battering Engines set.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:21"/>
               <l>The feare of this, mademany a <hi>Iewish</hi> Lord,</l>
               <l>That ioynde themselues with the seditious traine,</l>
               <l>To steale away, and all with one accord,</l>
               <l>At <hi>Tytus</hi> feete, sought mercie to obtaine:</l>
               <l>Whose milde submission, he accepted then,</l>
               <l>And gaue them honour, mong'st his noble men.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By this, the mellow wall was broke and s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aled,</l>
               <l>With fierce allarms, the holy towne was entred,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Romaines</hi> tooke courage, but the <hi>Iewes</hi> harts failed,</l>
               <l>Thousands lost their liues, which for honour ventred:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Schimion, Iehocanan,</hi> all did flie for feare,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iewes</hi> mournd, and <hi>Romaines</hi> triumpht euery where,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The faire Temple, Gods holy habitation,</l>
               <l>The worlds <hi>non pareli,</hi> the heathens wonder,</l>
               <l>Their Citties glory, their ioyes preseruation,</l>
               <l>To the Romaine power, must now come vnder:</l>
               <l>There many <hi>Isralites</hi> for liues defence,</l>
               <l>Had lockt themselues, &amp; would not come from thence</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The famous Citty being thus subdued,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Romaines</hi> heads, with glad-so<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e baies wer crowned</l>
               <l>For blesfull victory on their side ensued,</l>
               <l>While on the <hi>Iewes</hi> the worlds Creator frowned:</l>
               <l>The Captaines of the foule seditious rout,</l>
               <l>To hide their heades did seeke odd corners out,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:22"/>
               <l>The <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>maines</hi> resting in triumphant state,</l>
               <l>Vnto the holy Temple turned their course,</l>
               <l>And finding shutthe siluer shining gate,</l>
               <l>They fir'd it, retayning no remorce:</l>
               <l>And when the fiers flamde did sore abound,</l>
               <l>The melting siluer streamd along the ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Their timber worke into pale ashes turning,</l>
               <l>Downe dropt the goodly gate vpon the flower,</l>
               <l>What time the wrathfull <hi>Romaines</hi> went in running,</l>
               <l>Shouting and crying with a mighty power:</l>
               <l>The glory of which place, their bright sight drew,</l>
               <l>To take thereof a wondring greedy view.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet did that place but onely lead the way,</l>
               <l>Vnto the holyest place, where once a yeare,</l>
               <l>The high Priest went, vnto the Lord to pray,</l>
               <l>The figure of whose glory, did there appeare:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum</hi> so that place was called,</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Tytus</hi> wondring mind the most appalled.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which holy holyest place, when <hi>Tytus</hi> sawe,</l>
               <l>Hauing a view but of the outward part,</l>
               <l>So glorious was it that the sight did draw,</l>
               <l>A wounderous reuerence in his soule and heart:</l>
               <l>And with all meeknesse on his Princely knees,</l>
               <l>He honors there the Maiestie he sees.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:22"/>
               <l>This place was closed in with goulden gates,</l>
               <l>So beautifull and super excellent,</l>
               <l>That Princely <hi>Tytus</hi> and the <hi>Romaine</hi> states,</l>
               <l>Said sure this is Gods house omnipotent:</l>
               <l>And therefore <hi>Tytus</hi> who did loue and feare it,</l>
               <l>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded straightly, no man should come nere it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And through his Camp he made a proclamation,</l>
               <l>That whosoeuer did come neere the same,</l>
               <l>He should be hanged vp, without compassion,</l>
               <l>Without respect of birth, desert, or fame:</l>
               <l>And more, a band of men he there ordained,</l>
               <l>To keepe the Temple not to be prophaned.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The seditious set vpon the Romaine guard that kept
the Temple, and sodenly slew them: whereupon the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine
souldiers set fire on the golden gate of Sanctum
Sanctorum and spoyled the holy place with fire. Titus
sought to quench it but could not, for which he made
great lamentation.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>VVHile qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et thus the <hi>Romaine</hi> prince did ly,</l>
               <l>Without mistrust of any bloudy broyle,</l>
               <l>Proclaiming pardon, life and liberty,</l>
               <l>To euey yeelding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ule, in that faire soyle:</l>
               <l>A crew of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rayt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rous <hi>Iewes,</hi> of base condition,</l>
               <l>Assayled the <hi>Romaine</hi> guard, without suspition.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:23"/>
               <l>All <hi>Tytus</hi> gallant Souldiers which he set,</l>
               <l>So carefully, the Temple gates to keepe,</l>
               <l>Vpon a sodaine, they against them get,</l>
               <l>In dead of night, when most were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alne a sleepe:</l>
               <l>And there without all stay, or further wordes,</l>
               <l>Each man they murdered on their drawn swordes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not one escap'd their bloody butchering hands,</l>
               <l>Which noble <hi>Tytus</hi> hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing, grieued sore,</l>
               <l>And thereon rais'd, his best prepared bandes,</l>
               <l>Slaying those <hi>Iewes,</hi> and many hundreds more.</l>
               <l>And with such fury, he pursu'd them still,</l>
               <l>That who escapt, fled vp to <hi>Syon</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But yet the <hi>Romaines</hi> full of hot reuenge,</l>
               <l>For this vilde deede, by wicked <hi>Iewes</hi> committed,</l>
               <l>Troopt to the Temple, with a mighty swinge:</l>
               <l>And hauing all things for their purpose fitted:</l>
               <l>Did in their rage, set on fiers flame,</l>
               <l>Those goodly goulden gates, of greatest fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And as the flaming fier gather'd strength,</l>
               <l>Great spoyle was practisd by the Romaine rout,</l>
               <l>The melting gould that streamed downe at length,</l>
               <l>Did gild the marble pauement round about:</l>
               <l>The gates thus burned with a hidious din,</l>
               <l>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctum Sanctorum Romaines <hi>entred in.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:23"/>
               <l>Who hauing hereby won their hearts desier,</l>
               <l>With mighty shootes they shewed signes of ioy,</l>
               <l>While the holy place burnt with flaming fier,</l>
               <l>Which did, earthes heauenly paradice destroy:</l>
               <l>This woefull sight when <hi>Tytus</hi> once did see,</l>
               <l>He sought to quench it: but it would not be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For many wicked hands had busie beene,</l>
               <l>To worke that holy house all foule disgraces,</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Tytus</hi> would haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>au'd as well was seene,</l>
               <l>But it was fier'd in so many places:</l>
               <l>That by no meanes the spoyle he could preuent,</l>
               <l>Which thing he did most grieuously lament.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He ran about and cri'd with might and main<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>O stay your hands, and saue this house I charge yee,</l>
               <l>Fetch water vp, and quench this fire againe,</l>
               <l>Or you sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l smart, before I doe enlarge yee,</l>
               <l>Thus some he threatned, many he intreated:</l>
               <l>Till he was hoarse, with that he had repeated.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But when his voyce was gone with crying out,</l>
               <l>He drew his sword, and slew the disobedient,</l>
               <l>Till faint and weary, running round about,</l>
               <l>He sat him downe, as it was expedient:</l>
               <l>And there twixt wrath and sorrow he bewayled,</l>
               <l>With froward Souldiers, he no more preuayled.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:24"/>
               <l>The Priests &amp; <hi>Iewes</hi> that earst themselues had hidden</l>
               <l>Within the compasse of that holy ground,</l>
               <l>Against the Romaines fought: and had abidden,</l>
               <l>For to defend it many a bleeding wound:</l>
               <l>But when they saw, there was no way to fly,</l>
               <l>They lept into the fier, and there did die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So long they fought, vntill the parching fier,</l>
               <l>Did burne the clothes, from their sweating backes,</l>
               <l>The more they fought, the more was their desier,</l>
               <l>For to revenge the Temples wofull wrackes:</l>
               <l>They layd about, as long as they could stand;</l>
               <l>Or moue a legge, or lift a feeble hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And all this while did noble <hi>Tytus</hi> mourne,</l>
               <l>To see <hi>Sanctorum</hi> spoyled in such sort,</l>
               <l>Layde on the ground, there did he tosse and turne:</l>
               <l>And smote at such as did to him report,</l>
               <l>The woefull ruine of that holy place,</l>
               <l>And from his sight, with frownes he did them chace</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:5511:24"/>
            <head>Titus with great reverence, entred into the Sanctu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
Sanctorum, and greatly wondred as the beautie
thereof, affirming it to be the house
of the God of heauen.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THe cruell fire having wrought her worst,</l>
               <l>When that at length the fury thereof ceast,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Titus</hi> arose, all open and vntrust,</l>
               <l>Of many teares vnburdned and releast:</l>
               <l>With head vncouered, mild and reverently,</l>
               <l>Into <hi>Sanctorum</hi> humbly entred he.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And seeing the glorie and magnificence,</l>
               <l>The wondrous beautie of that sacred place,</l>
               <l>Which there appeared, for all the v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hemence,</l>
               <l>The flaming fier made, so long a space:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tytus</hi> did stand amazed at the sight,</l>
               <l>When he considered euery thing a right.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And therevpon into this speech he broke,</l>
               <l>How came I in this Paradice of pleasure,</l>
               <l>This Place Celestiall, may all soules Prouoke,</l>
               <l>To scorne the world, and seeke no other treasure:</l>
               <l>Doe I from ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th ascend by eleuation?</l>
               <l>Or see I heauen by divine revelation?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:25"/>
               <l>Vndoubte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly the mightie God dwolt here,</l>
               <l>This was no mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> creatures habitation,</l>
               <l>For earthly Monarkes, it was all to dee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</l>
               <l>Fit for none, but h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m who is our soules saluation:</l>
               <l>O ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thly heauen or heauenly Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntes receauer,</l>
               <l>Thy sweete remembrance shall I keepe for euer.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now well I wot, no maruell t'was indeed,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Iewes</hi> so stoutly stood in fence of this:</l>
               <l>O who could blame them, when they did proceed,</l>
               <l>By all deuices to preserue their blis:</l>
               <l>Since first I saw the Sunne, I neuer knew,</l>
               <l>What heauens ioy ment, till I this place did view.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nor did the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> without speciall cause,</l>
               <l>From fardest partes both of the East and West,</l>
               <l>Send heapes of gold by straight commaund of lawes,</l>
               <l>This sacred place with glory to inuest:</l>
               <l>For rich and wounderous is this holy seat,</l>
               <l>And in mans eye the Maiesty is great.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Far doth it passe the <hi>Romaine</hi> Temples all,</l>
               <l>Yea all the Temples of the world likewise,</l>
               <l>They seeme to this like to an Asses stall,</l>
               <l>Or like a stie where swine still grunting lies:</l>
               <l>Great God of heauen, God of this glorious place,</l>
               <l>Plague thou their soules that did thy house deface'</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:25"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tytus,</hi> thus wearied, gazing vp and downe,</l>
               <l>Yet not satisfied, with the Temples sight,</l>
               <l>Departed thence, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>odge within the towne:</l>
               <l>Things out of frame, to set in order right,</l>
               <l>Where while he stayd the stubborne harted <hi>Iewes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Did there most wicked actions dayly vse.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For when they saw that fier had so spoyled,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum</hi> in such pitious sort,</l>
               <l>Their diuillish harts that still with mischiefe broyled,</l>
               <l>The treasure houses all, they burnt in sport,</l>
               <l>And precious Iewells wheresoeuer they stood.</l>
               <l>With all things else that should doe <hi>Romaines</hi> good.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The rest of the Temple, likewise did they burne,</l>
               <l>In desperàt manner, without all regard:</l>
               <l>Which being wrought, away they did returne,</l>
               <l>But many scapt not, without iust reward<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Romaine</hi> Souldiers, quickly quencht the fier,</l>
               <l>And in the Temple wrought their heartes desire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where they set vp, their heathen Idolls all,</l>
               <l>Their sence-lesse Images, of wood and stone,</l>
               <l>And at their feete, all prostrate did they fall,</l>
               <l>Their offering sacrifice to them alone:</l>
               <l>In plaine derision of the conquered sort,</l>
               <l>Of whom the <hi>Romaines</hi> made a mocking sport,</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:5511:26"/>
            <head>A false Prophet arose among the Iewes, telling them
that the Temple should againe be builded by it selfe, with
out the helpe of mans hand, willing ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fore to destroy
the Romaines: which they going about to doe, brought
further sorrow vpon themselues.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>A False and lying Prophet then arose,</l>
               <l>Among the <hi>Iewes,</hi> at faire <hi>Ierusalem,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which then an absurd fancie did disclose,</l>
               <l>Among them all, who thus incourag'd them:</l>
               <l>Most valiant <hi>Iewes</hi> play you the men and fight,</l>
               <l>And God will shew a wonder in your sight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Against the cursed Romaines turne againe,</l>
               <l>And beate the boasting heathen to the ground,</l>
               <l>For God will shew vnto your sights most plaine,</l>
               <l>His mightie power: if you doe them confound,</l>
               <l>The Temple by it selfe shall builded be,</l>
               <l>Without mans hand or helpe, most gloriously.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That <hi>Iacobs</hi> God, thereby may shew his power,</l>
               <l>To those proude <hi>Romaines:</hi> which doe glory so,</l>
               <l>In there one strength: tryumphing euery hower,</l>
               <l>In this our spoyle, and wofull ouerthrow:</l>
               <l>Then fight O <hi>Iewes,</hi> the temple sanz delay,</l>
               <l>Shall by itselfe be builded vp this day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:26"/>
               <l>The wilde seditious beleeuing this lye.</l>
               <l>Did set a fresh vpon the <hi>Romaine</hi> band,</l>
               <l>In such fierce sort, that many men did dye,</l>
               <l>But yet the <hi>Romaines</hi> got the vpper hand:</l>
               <l>Who in new wakened wrath, that late did sleepe</l>
               <l>Slew downe the <hi>Iewes</hi> like to a sort of sheepe.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Schimion and Iehocanan come to seeke peace with Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,
but refuse to be in sub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ection to the Romaines: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon
Tytus will shew them no fauour, but presently assayled
them with his power, whereupon Schimion and I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nans
followers by some, and some forsake them, leauing
them in distresse: who there-vpon hid them-selues in
Caues.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THen came false <hi>Schimion</hi> and <hi>Iehocanan,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Chiefe Captaines, to the seditious trayne,</l>
               <l>With many followers, weapned euery man,</l>
               <l>Requiring peace, if peace they could obtaine:</l>
               <l>To whome Prince <hi>Tytus</hi> with his chiefest state,</l>
               <l>Did thus reply you seeke this thing to late.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:27"/>
               <l>How comes it now that yee intreate for life.</l>
               <l>After so many mischeiefes by you wrought,</l>
               <l>When you haue slaine and murthered man and wife,</l>
               <l>And thousand thousands to destruction brought:</l>
               <l>Who then as faint as euer he could stand,</l>
               <l>Came to submit himselfe, to <hi>Tytus</hi> hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How oft haue I intreated you to peace,</l>
               <l>And offered mercie, without all desert,</l>
               <l>When you refusing it, did still increase,</l>
               <l>Your trayterous dealings, your chiefest smart:</l>
               <l>It pitt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed me to see your woefull case,</l>
               <l>With your innumerable men dead in each place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How can I pardon these outragious acts,</l>
               <l>Your many murders and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alse sedition,</l>
               <l>With diuers other abhominable facts,</l>
               <l>For which I see in you, no hearts contrition:</l>
               <l>You seeke for peace, yet armed do you stand,</l>
               <l>You craue for pardon, with your swords in hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>First lay a side your swords and weapons all,</l>
               <l>And in submiss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue manner ask for grace,</l>
               <l>So shall you see what fauour may befall,</l>
               <l>Perhaps I may take pitty on your case:</l>
               <l>And graciously withall your faults suspence,</l>
               <l>And giue you pardon, ere you goe from hence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:27"/>
               <l>With bended browes proud <hi>Schimion</hi> then did looke,</l>
               <l>On gentle <hi>Tytus: Iehocanan</hi> likewise,</l>
               <l>In scornfull manner all his speeches tooke,</l>
               <l>And both of them disdainefully replies:</l>
               <l>By heauens great God, we both haue sworne quoth they</l>
               <l>To make no seruile peace with thee this day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For neuer shall earths misery prouoke,</l>
               <l>Our vndaunted heartes to stoope vnto thy will,</l>
               <l>Orbend our neckes vnto the <hi>Romaine</hi> yoake,</l>
               <l>While vital breath our inward parts doth fill:</l>
               <l>Then vnto vs this fauour doe expresse,</l>
               <l>To let vs part and liue in wildernesse.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At this contempt was <hi>Tytus</hi> greatly moued,</l>
               <l>And doth your pride continue yet quoth he?</l>
               <l>Will not your impudency be yet reproued?</l>
               <l>Nor yet your stubborne heartes yet humbeld be?</l>
               <l>And dare you say that you will sweare and vow,</l>
               <l>That to the <hi>Romaine</hi> yoke you will not bow,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At this his wrath was wounderous sore inflamed,</l>
               <l>Who herevpon gaue straight commandement,</l>
               <l>By strength of sword to haue those rebels tamed,</l>
               <l>On whom the <hi>Romaines</hi> set incontinent:</l>
               <l>Who chac'd the Iewes and scattered them so sore,</l>
               <l>That they were found to gather head no more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:28"/>
               <l>For secretly the Iewes from <hi>Schimion</hi> fled,</l>
               <l>By some and some they all forsooke him quite,</l>
               <l>With false <hi>Iehocanan</hi> which so misled,</l>
               <l>And for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gainst them selues to murderous fight:</l>
               <l>Who leauing them, to noble <hi>Tytus</hi> came,</l>
               <l>Desiring grace, who graunted them the same.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iehocanan</hi> and <hi>Schimion</hi> seeing this,</l>
               <l>They were forsaken, and left post alone,</l>
               <l>In their distresse lamented their amisse,</l>
               <l>Closse hid in caues, they lay and made their mone:</l>
               <l>Where they remained perplext with famine great,</l>
               <l>Till they were ready, their owne flesh to eate.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Iehocanan inforced by hunger comes out of his caue &amp;
submits him-selfe to Tytus, who caused
him to be hanged.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>AT length out of a deepe darke hollow caue,</l>
               <l>With bitter hunger <hi>Iehocanan</hi> was driuen,</l>
               <l>Like to a Ghost new risen from his graue,</l>
               <l>Or like Anotamy of all flesh beryuen:</l>
               <l>Who then as faint as euer he could stand,</l>
               <l>Came to submit himselfe, to <hi>Tytus</hi> hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:28"/>
               <l>Into this Princely presence when he came,</l>
               <l>With all submission fell he at his feete,</l>
               <l>Saying, O King of most renouned f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me,</l>
               <l>Here am I come as it is right and meete:</l>
               <l>To yeeld my selfe into thy Princely hand,</l>
               <l>Whose life doth rest, vpon thy great command,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My disobedience, doe I sore repent,</l>
               <l>That euer I, refus'd thy offered grace,</l>
               <l>Bewayling my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ewd life, so badly bent,</l>
               <l>And my foule actions, gainst this holy place:</l>
               <l>Yet with thy mercy shadow my amisse,</l>
               <l>And let me tast what thy compassion is,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not from my selfe, did all my sinne proceede,</l>
               <l>Though I confesse, my faults were too too many,</l>
               <l>But was prouokt to many a bloody deede,</l>
               <l>By him that yet was neuer good to any:</l>
               <l>Blood-thirsty <hi>Schimeon,</hi> led me to all en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll,</l>
               <l>Who doth in malice, far exceed the Diuell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Too long alasse, he ouer-ruld my will,</l>
               <l>And made me actor, of a thousand woes,</l>
               <l>What I refus'd his outrage did fulfill,</l>
               <l>And his deuise, did make my friends my foes:</l>
               <l>Then worthy Victor, mittigate my blame,</l>
               <l>And let thy glory, ouer-spread my shame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:29"/>
               <l>No more quoth <hi>Tytus,</hi> stay thy traiterous tounge,</l>
               <l>Infect vs not with thy impoysoned breath,</l>
               <l>Ile doe thee right that hast done many wrong,</l>
               <l>Thy end of sorrow, shall begin thy death:</l>
               <l>And by thy death, shall life arise to such,</l>
               <l>To whom thou thoughtst, a minutes life too much.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With that he wild his Captaines take him thence,</l>
               <l>When he with yron chaines was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ettered fast,</l>
               <l>And afterward (meete meed for his offence)</l>
               <l>Through all the Campe they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed him at the last,</l>
               <l>That he of them, might mockt and scorned be,</l>
               <l>And then in chaines they hanged him one a tree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This was the end of proud <hi>Iehocanan,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That in <hi>Ierusalem</hi> did such harme,</l>
               <l>And this likewise was that accursed man,</l>
               <l>That in his malice with a fierce alarme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Burnd all the Victuals laide in by the Peeres,</l>
               <l>That was inough to serue them twenty yeeres.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which was the cause, that in so short a space,</l>
               <l>So great a famine fell within the towne;</l>
               <l>Yea this was he burnt, King <hi>Agrippaes</hi> place,</l>
               <l>And in the temple slew so many downe:</l>
               <l>But not long after he was gone and dead,</l>
               <l>Out of his den did <hi>Schimion</hi> shew his head.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:5511:29"/>
            <head>SCHIMION in like sort being driuen with hunger out
of his den, apparelling himselfe in princely attire, desired
to be brought before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itus, supposing he would haue sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
his life: but he commanded his head to be stricken off,
and his body to be cut in peces and cast to the dogges.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHo staring vp and down with feareful lookes,</l>
               <l>Least any one were nigh to apprehend him,</l>
               <l>Like to a Panther doubting hidden hookes,</l>
               <l>That any way might lye for to offend him:</l>
               <l>Driuen out with famine, hungry at the hart,</l>
               <l>He sought for succour of his earned smart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And hauing drest himselfe in Kingly tire,</l>
               <l>In richest manner that he could deuise,</l>
               <l>That men at him might wonder: and desire,</l>
               <l>To know what Monarke did from earth arise,</l>
               <l>Farre off he walked as it were in boast,</l>
               <l>And shewd himselfe vnto the Romaine hoast.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For his great heart could not abid to yeeld,</l>
               <l>Though gnawing hunger vext his very sou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e:</l>
               <l>Thus faintly walkt he vp and downe the field</l>
               <l>With lofty thoughts: with famine did controule,</l>
               <l>Supposing firmely, though he liu'd in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>He should finde fauour, for his high estate:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:30"/>
               <l>For though (quoth he) I did the <hi>Romaines</hi> wrong,</l>
               <l>Yet in my deeds, I shewed Princely courage,</l>
               <l>Bearing a heart, that did to honour throng,</l>
               <l>And there vpon their Campe so oft did forage,</l>
               <l>To haughty acts all Princes honour owes,</l>
               <l>For they must thinke that war hath made vs foes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Considering this, Prince <hi>Tytus</hi> may be proude,</l>
               <l>To such an enemie he may fauour shew,</l>
               <l>And herein may his action be allowd,</l>
               <l>That magnanimitie he will nourish so:</l>
               <l>And by his mercie make a friend of him,</l>
               <l>That in his warres so great a foe hath beene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which in this honour, hee himselfe did flatter,</l>
               <l>Of him the <hi>Romaines,</hi> had a perfect sight,</l>
               <l>And round about him, they themselues did scatter,</l>
               <l>Yet were afraid, to come within his might:</l>
               <l>And that they fear'd this was the onely reason,</l>
               <l>They knew his craft, and doubted hidden treason.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But <hi>Schimion</hi> seeing, that they shund him so,</l>
               <l>He cald vnto them in couragious wise,</l>
               <l>Maiestically walking to and fro,</l>
               <l>And in this sort, his speech to them applies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>If any gallant Captaine with you be,</l>
               <l>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t him approch, and talke one word with me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:30"/>
               <l>With that stept out a braue couragious Knight,</l>
               <l>With weapons well prouided euery way,</l>
               <l>A noble <hi>Romaine</hi> of great strength and might,</l>
               <l>Who with his weapon drawne these words did say</l>
               <l>Tell me, who art thou that in such attire,</l>
               <l>Walkes in this place, and what is thy desire?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I am (quoth he) vndaunted <hi>Schimeon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The wrathfull Captaine of seditious <hi>Iewes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That slew the <hi>Romaines,</hi> in their greatest throng,</l>
               <l>The deed whereof I come not to excuse:</l>
               <l>Nor doe I passe what you can say thereto,</l>
               <l>I am the man made you so much a doe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet let me thus much fauour craue of thee,</l>
               <l>As to conduct me to great <hi>Tytus</hi> sight,</l>
               <l>Thy noble friend: but enemie to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Yet doubt I not, but he will doe me right:</l>
               <l>Bring me to him, what chaunce so ere I finde,</l>
               <l>That he may heare, and I may shew my mind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Romaine</hi> Captaine his request fulfild,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Tytus</hi> royall presence was he brought,</l>
               <l>Whose hatefull person, when the Prince beheld,</l>
               <l>He did refuse to heare him speake in ought,</l>
               <l>Away with him he sayd, let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im be bound,</l>
               <l>For of all woe this villaine was the ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:31"/>
               <l>And like a Captiue first let him be led,</l>
               <l>About the Camp to suffer scoffes and scornes,</l>
               <l>And after that strike of his hatefull head,</l>
               <l>The mansion house of mischiefes pricking thornes:</l>
               <l>And let his carcase be in peeces torne,</l>
               <l>And every gobbet vnto dogges be throwne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What <hi>Titus</hi> charg'd was put in execution,</l>
               <l>And in this sort was <hi>Schimio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> hatefull end,</l>
               <l>Who went to death with wonderous resolution,</l>
               <l>Not like a man, but like an hellish fiend:</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Titus</hi> conquer'd that most pretious Iem,</l>
               <l>The beautious Citie faire <hi>Ierusalem.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The number of those that had bin slaine at the siege
of Ierusalem, and the number of the Prisoners that
Titus caried with him to Rome.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THE perfect number of the people there,</l>
               <l>The which with hunger &amp; with sword was slaine</l>
               <l>A leauen hundred thousand did appeare,</l>
               <l>As bookes of records did declare it plaine:</l>
               <l>Beside all such as did vnburied lye,</l>
               <l>And diuers moe that did in fier dye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5511:31"/>
               <l>And when to <hi>Rome</hi> the Conquerer went his way,</l>
               <l>The number of his prisoners were full great,</l>
               <l>Full sixteene thousand men that instant day,</l>
               <l>Were carried captiue to the <hi>Romaine</hi> seate:</l>
               <l>Among the rest the man that wrot this story,</l>
               <l>Who by his wisedome purchast endlesse glory.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus Christs prophesie truely came to passe,</l>
               <l>Which Forty yeares before he had expressed,</l>
               <l>But with the <hi>Iewes</hi> of small account it was,</l>
               <l>Till they did finde themselues so sore distressed:</l>
               <l>He soght their life, his death they wrought with spite.</l>
               <l>Wishing his blood on them and theirs to light.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The which according to their owne request,</l>
               <l>The Lord in wrath did perfectly fulfil,</l>
               <l>There channels ran with blood and did not rest,</l>
               <l>Their blood was spilt, that <hi>Iesus</hi> blood did spill:</l>
               <l>God grant we may our hatefull sins forsake,</l>
               <l>And by the <hi>Iewes</hi> a Christian warning take.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
