<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaracion of the seremonies a nexid, to the sacrament of baptyme [sic] what they sygnyffie and how we owght to vnderstande them</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1537</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-03">2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20015</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6455</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109520</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845167</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845167</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10053</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A20015)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10053)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 34:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaracion of the seremonies a nexid, to the sacrament of baptyme [sic] what they sygnyffie and how we owght to vnderstande them</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>T. Gibson],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1537.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A (-A8, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10053:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10053:1"/>
            <p>¶ A declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the Seremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies a nexid, to the Sacrament of Baptyme, what they ſygnyffie and how we owght to vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de them (:) 1537.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10053:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10053:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>han a chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis chylde is born<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into this worlde it is brought to chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che and .iii. witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes comyth with, hym that is God fader and godmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be a greed what name ſhalbe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyld, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſt makyth a ſigne of the croſſe i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed of the chyld &amp; ſeyth thus. A toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the holy croſſe of our lorde. Ieſu chriſt I ſet in thy forhed and ſo at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breſte in lyk manere, &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſt ſeith many oriſons ouer the chylde comaundynge the deuel to knolech hys ſentenſe and gyue worſhipe to the lyuynge god and trewe and to Ieſu chriſt and to the holy ghoſt and departe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god &amp; than he puttyth ſalt in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth of the chyld &amp; ſeith thus <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. Thou
<pb facs="tcp:10053:3"/>
ſalt of wyſdom y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god be mercyfull to the in to euerlaſtynge lyfe. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This ſalt of wyſdom vnderſtande goddꝭ word whiche ſhulde be ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the mouth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde whan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne it begynneth to ſpeke as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtel ſeith be our word ſauord w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſalt euermore in grace than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſt weetyth his tho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpotil and tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyldꝭ eere &amp; ſeith. Be thou openyd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is vnderſtande in alle thy fyue wittys to here &amp; ſpeke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of god with loue &amp; drede and holy deuocion. For the Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god ſhall touche in whiche we ſhulde yelde acount of euery ydel word al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the preſt toucheth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> noſe thrylles of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyld for it ſhold ſmylle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> odour of ſwetnes of heuenly thyngis, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re than euery ertly thynges. Sone after this the preſt biddith alle the peple y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther be, to ſeye a. Pater no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb facs="tcp:10053:3"/>
and an. Aue and a. Credo byſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng god that the child may right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully take his chriſtendom, &amp; well kepe it to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> endyng of his lyfe. And thanne the preſt takyth the chyld by the right hande and callyth his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and ſeyth come thou in to the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of god that thou may haue euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng lyfe and lyue i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to worlde of worldis. Amen. Thanne the chylde is brought to the fonte and the preſt callyth it by name and ſeyth. Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuucio ſatane &amp; omnibus operibus eius et omnibus pompis eius that is. I for ſake ſatanas that is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyl and alle his werkis &amp; alle his pompis or prydes and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godſibbis ſayth. Abranuncio that is I for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke Therfore wher he is not a fals chriſten man that kepith not the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenaunt of theſe wordis but after ward wrappyth hym in the fendis
<pb facs="tcp:10053:4"/>
pryde in hert and i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clothyng and in wycked worckynge for yf this coue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunt ſhuld be trewly kept, all the tokenes of pryde i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man muſt be don a way ſeyng eche token of pryde, is a pompe of the fende. After ſeyth the preſt to the chylde by leueſt thou in god the fader almyhgty maker of he uene and erthe The chyld is dombe and may not ſpeke but and yt were of age and myght ſpeke yt ſhuld a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were for it ſelf therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godſibbis anſwere ſeyng. Credo. that I bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue. Efte axith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſt, &amp; beleueſt thou i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſu chriſt his only ſone our lord born and ſufferd &amp; they ſaye I bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue. The thride tyme areth the preſt. And beleueſt thou in the holy ghoſt in holy churche fayth in communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſaintes for geuenes of ſynnes the ryſyng of fleſhe and after the euer laſtynge lyfe. And they ſaye
<pb facs="tcp:10053:4"/>
I beleue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſt. Quid pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis what axiſt thou they ſey baptim wold thou be baptiſed ſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſt and they ſay, Volo I wole than the preſt takyth the chylde and ſayth. I Baptiſe the in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of the father and of the ſone and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt Amen. And ſo he plungyth it in the water and commaundyth the goſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis to ley ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyldes heed for they ben wytneſſes of his Baptim &amp; receue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> charge to teach it and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trewthe of his beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementis &amp; the domes of god, and to flee the pompis and prydes of the fend, for the comen peple &amp; all men ſhuld knowe and kepe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dementis of god. And preſtis his holy counſeyles. And Lordis his iuſt domes, and yf they do not this: they be wrongfully called chriſten men. And thus blinde preſtis bere
<pb facs="tcp:10053:5"/>
fals wytneſſes of yong chyldren chriſtened, that after warde ſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuel whome they for looke ſeying Abronuncio After theſe thyngis the preſt a noyntyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde wyth oyle and lappyd in his criſome &amp; takith yt a candele brinnyng in his hond, and ſeyth. Accipe lampadem arden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem irriprehenſibilem cuſtodi Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſmum tuum ſerua mandata vt cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>venit dominus ad nuptias poſſis occurrere ei vna cum ſanctis in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la celeſtis vt habeas vita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eternam et viuas in ſecula ſeculorum. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. That is to ſey. Haue thou a bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nynge lampe vnreprouable. Kepe thou thy baptym &amp; kepe thou y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis that wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lorde cometh to the weddyngis thou mayſt renne agenſt hym as one wyth ſeyntis in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heuenly halle y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haue euer laſtynge lyfe and lyue i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world
<pb facs="tcp:10053:5"/>
of worldꝭ. am<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Here endith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reulys of bapti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But alle chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> folk ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de beſily lerne to know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gretnes of charge whiche they receue i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther baptym. For wyth .iiii. thyngis we be chargyd in our Bapti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al though blinde preſtis knowe yt not, whan they geue to vs iiii. Elamentis in tokenyng of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is ſalt, &amp; wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and oyle, &amp; fier. The fyrſt charge is that we take ſalt of wyſdom of goddꝭ word and rewle our lyfe ther after and ſalt our ſoules that they ſtynk not in ſynne. For and thys he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenly ſalt fayle fro men they ſhulde be caſt out as chriſt techyth in the goſpel. The .ii. charge is, that our eeris be openyd euer more redy to here chryſtes goſpel and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de yt. For chriſt ſeyth. He that hath eerys of herynge, Let him here &amp; he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> redyth let him vnderſtande. The
<pb facs="tcp:10053:6"/>
iii. charge is this that we kepe our Baptym that is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> couenaunt of our Baptym and trew beleue in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the ſone and the holy ghoſt as the preſt appoſith vs whan we ſaye. Credo. The .iiii. charge is this that we kepe the commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis of god, as the preſt commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dith vs at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fonte puttyng a candel bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge in our hand, for as a candille brennynge is waſtyd by fyer: ſo ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes in our ſoul ſhulde be waſtyd and deſtroyed wyth kepyng of the commaundementis of god, hauyng deuout loue to hym and to our euen chriſten. And this is the ſeconde Baptym, that ſaynt Iohn. techyth whan he ſayth I Baptyſe in water but a nother ſhall come after me ſtrongir than I and he ſhall Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe you in the holy ghoſt and fyer and wyth out this ſeconde. Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tym
<pb facs="tcp:10053:6"/>
may no man be ſaued, as chriſt ſeyde to Nichodeme truly I ſaye to the: But a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be born a gen of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and of the holy ghoſt he may not enter in to the Kyngdom of god. Al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo Paul techyth that the fyrſt Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tym in water only, makyth vs not ſaef, But the axinge of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god &amp; fayth not fayned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> worckyth by charite for chriſt ſayth. He that beleuyth in me flodis of quyk water ſhulde flow fro hys wombe that is the holy ghoſt that chryſt callyth the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortour, whyche flowyth euer in to the hertis of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke men that make them redy to die, for that man that ſhall dwelle by fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re the bleſſed face of god in heuene, ſhall receue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erneſt of the holy goſt here in erthe. And this is the ſecond Baptym that fleſhely preſtis and ſwynyſh peple knowyth not, for
<pb facs="tcp:10053:7"/>
ther hertis be ſtoppyd wyth fleſhly luſt, that the flodis of the holy ghoſt may not entre in to them, and there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore preſtis be i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perel that teach not the ſecounde Baptym. For yt ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyth not to ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe his body in water of Baptym and ſuffre his ſoule to ſtynk in ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne thorow brekyng of the commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis of god, for thus preſtis rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in the holy Pſalm. Increpaſti ſuperbos maledicti qui declinant a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>datis tuis, That is to ſeye thou blameſt the proude they be a curſyd that bow a wey fro thyn heſtis. And thus god ſhall blame proude preſtis for they purſewe powre men for the lernynge of the commaundementis the whyche they charge them to ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe in the our of ther. Baptym and all that bere the name of chryſten men ſhulde crie agenſt this errour
<pb facs="tcp:10053:7"/>
For what errour is more vyle in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyght of god than to byende men to alawe and afterwarde purſue them for the ſame lawe and thus for drede of euel preſtis men dar not kepe chryſtis heeſtis and the ghoſtly byrth of our mother holy chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is deſpyſed of proude men that knowe not the bond of ther Baptym. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:10053:8"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10053:8"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
