<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Greene in conceipt New raised from his graue to write the tragique historie of faire Valeria of London. Wherein is truly discouered the rare and lamentable issue of a husbands dotage, a wiues leudnesse, &amp; children of disobedience. Receiued and reported by I.D.</title>
            <author>Dickenson, John, romance writer.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1598</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-01">2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20408</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6819</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105352</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841081</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841081</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5640</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A20408)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5640)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 217:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Greene in conceipt New raised from his graue to write the tragique historie of faire Valeria of London. Wherein is truly discouered the rare and lamentable issue of a husbands dotage, a wiues leudnesse, &amp; children of disobedience. Receiued and reported by I.D.</title>
                  <author>Dickenson, John, romance writer.</author>
                  <author>Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 63, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Richard Bradocke for William Iones, dwelling at the signe of the Gunne neare Holborne conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1598.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Iohn Dickenson.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-05</date>
            <label>TCP Staff (Michigan)</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5640:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GREENE IN CONCEIPT.</p>
            <p>New raised from his graue to write the Tragique Historie of faire <hi>Valeria</hi> of London.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN IS TRVLY DISCOVERED the rare and lamentable issue of a Hu<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bands do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, a wiues leudnesse, &amp; childrens disobedience.</p>
            <p>Receiued and reported by I. D.</p>
            <q>Veritas non quaerit angulos, vmbra gaudet.</q>
            <figure/>
            <p>Printed at London by RICHARD BRADOCKE for <hi>William Iones,</hi> dwelling at the signe of the Gunne neare Holborne conduit. 1598.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5640:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5640:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To my deare friend, Master <hi>Thomas White</hi> of Corffe in Dorsetshire.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough in the spring-time of cur liues yeare, there bee no depth nor durance of resolution, because sound iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t our reasons ripenes, is then but in the budde; yet the affection which I beare you, wherto your owne hopefulll forwardnesse did first giue life, and your many courtesies adde strength, albeit it were the childe of my childhood, conceiued where we both recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the first grounds of learning, was euen then so deepely rooted, that neither length of time, distance of plase, nor discontents of minde, haue beene able, I will not say to abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish, but to diminish it: for an instance whereof, I haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled to your name this naked humor, a Present not so wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy as I would, or as perhaps I could affoord if some clouds were cleared: Yet howsoeuer this toy may prooue, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume, of your acceptance, both in regard of that affection that (I hope) you still d<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e beare me, which may impetrate a toleration wh<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re no liking may bee looked for: or of that well-meaning wherewith I offer it vnto you, sith strangers
<pb facs="tcp:5640:3"/>
of strangers, and greatest Princes of meanest peasants haue taken in good worth as worthlesse things, because presented with good will. And I would that I might but halfe so far<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>uaile with others, of whome some (I seare) will not onely charge me with that which iustly they may, but also aster t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>eading of my title and <hi>Proemium,</hi> deeme me one of those against whome <hi>Horace</hi> doth well exclaime, <hi>Oimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatores servum pecus,</hi> yet I protest that neuer anything was further from my thoughts, and that the rest was fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed before that humor was suggested But I should grossely offend in troubling you with a long Epistle, whome I trouble with so long a toy. I will therefore conclude with this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall promise, wherein I ioyne with you the courteous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whose patience I vrge too much with my youthes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, that if my life be capable of riper yeeres, and my state of better fortune, my labours shall not be wholly barren of dese<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t: till when, and euer I rest,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours assured, Iohn Dickenson.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:5640:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An aduertisement to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen night (f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>iend to melancholly) had runne the third part of her cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>se, besp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>inkling the drowsie earth with <hi>Lethes</hi> dew, I sitting solitary in my cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, reading with some pleasure <hi>Luc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ans Timon,</hi> on a sodaine f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>lt mine eies heauie, and immediatly all my powers were violently surprised by a slumber; whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>into I was no sooner entred, then me thought I saw standing before me, the shape of a well-proportioned man su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in deaths liuery, who seemed to write as fast as I could read. This gastly obiect did much astonish me, and (as fancie in such cases is a fruitfull nource of superstitious feares) my amazeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: being thus taken in the reading of that Authour, who, besides his other impieties, is the greatest <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ffer of apparitio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s. But when I had well noted the others mild countenance, my courage did soone recall it selfe, and I growing somwhat bold, demanded both who he was, and why he came: whereto hee gently answered thus I am hee, whose pen was first emploied in the aduancement of vanitie, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward in the discouering of villanie. Ioyne these two, and they will serue thee for the <hi>Periphrasis</hi> of my name. In the former of which, I confesse I haue offended, yet who knoweth not, that Fiction the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother of Poësie makes her the shadow of Philosophie; which if not sweetned by this heauenly mixture, may well haue reuerence, but small regard. This mooued the Poet to write, and me to vse for my familiar <hi>mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>to</hi> that que<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t verse, <hi>Omne tulit punctu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, qui misc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>it vtile dul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> But admit it as the most will haue it, yet dare I boldly affirme, that my later labours haue made a large part of amends for those former vanities. Here (me thought) I could no longer containe my selfe f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> going to imbrace him, as both reason and humani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e required.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Sod frustr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nsa manus eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>git imago</l>
               <l>Par levibus ven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>olucr qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>simillim a somno.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Whereat beeing no lesse amazed then before, and casting backe mine eies, I espied him standing in like order at the othet end of the chamber, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a criticall smile he thus proceeded: Hast thou tost ouer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o many Authors, &amp; knowest not yet that ghostes are shadowes? But to omit this which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>impute to thine astonishment, and to answer the other part of thy demand, first, for thy better conceiting of my intent, know, that it is my wont to walke much from <hi>Elysium</hi> towardes the mouth of <hi>Or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>us,</hi> the cause whereof is this: <hi>Diogenes, Menippus,</hi> &amp; all the ancient Cynicks, with as many of our moderne humorists as haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>umpt with them in their soure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ain, do mightily frequent that place, who though of seuerall countries and times, yet are so throughly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>h with other as if they had liued all togither. Their order is, when any ghosts ariue, to run presently vnto them, peere in their
<pb facs="tcp:5640:4"/>
f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ces and boord them currishly with a question touching their estates and fortunes while they liued: if they gather by their answeres that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them haue florished in the world for pompe, wealth, beauty, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer other like transitory gift, &amp; that therein they haue reposed their sole delight, oh then they soundly frumpe and baite them for their wélcome with such bitter scoffes, that this new corrosiue added to their other yet-bleding sorrowe, makes them altogither impatient but if they finde that their liues greatest part hath beene d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>stresse and care, then they comfort them, bidding them reioyce in death. Marry this their comfort serues to small purpose, for <hi>I</hi> haue heard the chiefe Seniors of this societie oft solemnly protest, that for <hi>I</hi> know not how many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares, not three of all those wretches (though the number hath bene infinite) haue thanked them for their comfort but all bitterly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamed on death, and wished themselues againe aliue, with thrice as many miseries as they had endured: yet many of them dyed so olde, that their sighte, their tast, and generally all their sences and powers had of themselues failed them; so that the weaknes of their spent nature could no longer haue bin capable of any pleasure: others so poor, that for pure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; no deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they had fasted to death: som so grieued with Aches that they had longlaine bed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>idden, or so peppered with diseases, that in many yeares they could reckon few daies of rest: some had beene rotted in prison, some new skipt from the gallowes; others blinde, many cripples, all miserable, which caused me deepely to meruaile what se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret deceipt of nature made men thus dote on life. <hi>Sed ad propositum.</hi> walking there not long since, while those aforesaide odde companions were questioning with other ghosts, <hi>I</hi> sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>one (&amp; it was a womans Ghost) pacing demurely, and with so se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>led a countenance, that as it argued no ioy, so it made shewe of little sorrow. Wondering at such moderation in so fraile a sexe, I went towards h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>r, and in going eyed hir so exactly, that in the end, though death had much desaced her, <hi>I</hi> knew who she was, and remembred that when I dyed, she liued at London in florish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing estate &amp; as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ewde a dame, as any in that Citye. This much increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed my former admiration, who demde it rare, that any of that sexe, wealth, and wantonnesse could with such patience brooke the losse of life. Being in this humor I discouered my selfe vnto her, and earnestly requested her to shew me the cause of this her more then manly cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage: whereto she ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly replyed, that since my death her fortune cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged by hir folly had quited the former ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty &amp; pleasures that she had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> enioyed, with a farre greater measure of want and woe; and for she sawe mee extremly desirous to heare the maner of this change and sequell, shee imparted that likewise vnto mee, concluding that sith death had ridde s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ir from distresse, it were madnesse to lament, much more to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire life. this saide, shee lef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e mee in a strange humor: for <hi>I</hi> wished my selfe aliue againe, were it but for two daies.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5640:4"/>Laughest thou? So mightest thou well haue done, if this my wish had beene the Ape of common error: but the onely ayme and end of my desire, was the good of tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e that liue; for whose admonition, euen in so small a time (for my witte was neuer long in performing such a taske) <hi>I</hi> would haue pende in maner of a caueat, alarge discourse both of hir former lewdnesse which my selfe had knowne, and of her following miseries which she had then related. But finding my desires full accomplishment herein impossible, after long thought I conceip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a likely course, for the effecting thereof in parte; and this it was<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> To sue to <hi>Mercury</hi> that by the vertue of his charming rodde <hi>qua manes euocat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>co,</hi> this my bodies bloudlesse remnant might reuisite the earth, to finde some one who receiuing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mee the plott and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke of this rare subiect, might performe thereon in my behalfe, that which by reason of deaths defects my selfe now ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not. In this reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution I gaue long attendance, before the leysure of that busie God, (which as thou knowest is heauens Herald, and hels carrier,) did afford me any opportunity: But in the end hauing purchased ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse and audience, I preuailde so farre with him, that either for his good opinion of my intent, or for the loue he beares vnto Poetry wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in himselfe, as he is the God of eloquence, hath no small interest, hee fully graunted my desire, but with this <hi>prouiso,</hi> that I should dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch within an houre, by which time he will haue readye a fresh <hi>conuoy</hi> of ghosts for his returne. To be short; I was with a tryce in sight of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, whether running for ioy in headlong hast as the way ledde mee, I haue by chance lighted on thee, and thereby know that this subiect is reserued for thy penne. Listen then to my relation. Heere he som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what pawsde: then with a deepe sigh sorrowes true preface, he began his sadde discourse therein comprising the seuerall branches that I haue handled; this done, hee thus concluded: Thou hast now hearde the summe of all, which I had once begunne to write, meting by good happe with penne, incke and paper on the way; but the shortnesse of my time warns me to resigne the office of my penne vnto my tongue. Suffice it that <hi>I</hi> despeire not of thy memory, nor doubt thy forwardnes. This only I will add, let the world know it coms fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, that they who since my death haue vnkindly blamd me, may henceforth ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>sure more charitably of me. Hereto (me thought) I thus replyed: The chargethat thou imposest, is (I feare) greater then I can well discharge: for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the nature of my veine is like to thine, neither is it <hi>in suo genere</hi> so sufficient. Besides none will beleeue this, but rather deem it a blinde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise of mine to begge a title for my booke, &amp; to picke vp some crummes of credit from anothers table. Some againe will charge me that I haue stolne this conceipt out of <hi>Lucian.</hi> And many maruaile, that I who haue a while forborn the presse (saue only in some sleight tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>slations of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb facs="tcp:5640:5"/>
nouelties.) because iustly sea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ing the ouer deep &amp; piercing censures of this iudiciall age, should now in so bold an humor grow thus confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Lastly there are sundry others both better known to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ee and of far more sufficiencie. Tush (quoth he) thou art too scrupulous; this is not mod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y, but mopishnesse: leauing therfore these vai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e excuses, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>equest: and thereto I coniure thee by the reuerence thou bear'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> vnto the sacred Mules. Well (quoth I) sith thou hast so deepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charged mee, I will performe it, and doe thou likewise in requitall graunt mee one demaunde, that I will make. <hi>I</hi> meane: nay (quoth hee) I know thy meaning and the humor that boyles now to thy bra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>es, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> dare not play the blab againe: for who would willingly fry in Phle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geton? Besides, the time do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>h fly and the power of <hi>Mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s cadu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eus</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>rawes me hence, farewell and faile not in thy promise: with these words mee thought he vanished, leauing mee extreamely discontented; for I had ready a mint of questions. As first, how each hagge and fiend doth take his place, when they are summond to any assembly, <hi>Al rauco suon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>a tar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>area tromba.</hi> How <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>erberus</hi> in these late yeares of dearth hath shifted for his diet, comming so ost short of his fee: for it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likly that they which being aliue could not get the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>selues a dry crust, but sterued miserably, for want of foode, can after death be able to giue him a soppe: Whether the gredy Corne-hoorders be not generally cursed, euen there also, for pluming so the silly ghosts before hand, that when they come thither they are not able to discharge the dueties of the house, viz. to the Ferriman, the porter &amp;c. VVhether <hi>Charon</hi> doe still cry out against gonnes for determining the fortune of battailes before they co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e to hand-strokes, and thereby cutting of the best part of his doings; whether <hi>Democritus</hi> do laugh still, &amp; whether it be true that <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> who while he liued, wept for the vanities of men, do now laugh at hims<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>lfe for hauing beene so foolish; whether it be likewise true that <hi>Aretine</hi> hangs by the tongue for haui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>g blab'd abroade the secrets of dame Lecheries dearlings, what monsters were brought sorth of late, &amp; which of the olde haggs, are most in fauour with <hi>Hecat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> These &amp; infinite other demands I would haue made, had not his sodaine vanishing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented me, whereat in a rage I clapt my hand on the table and theré<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with did awake, hauing my braines so set on worke by this strange slum. ber, that I could sleepe no more all that night. The next morning, the plot being fresh in my memory, I went in hand with it, proceeding ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in at times of leasure till <hi>I</hi> had finishedit, which (Gentlemen) Inow pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent vnto your fauours the only wished harbor wherein this my weathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> bearen vessell may rest safely shrowded from the tempest of disgrace.</p>
            <p>Besides sundry seapes of the Presse in Orthography, and some more extraordinary of whole wordes mistaken, though in the fewest coppies; these foure are generall: secrets for sorrowes. p. 18. these, for those, p. 20. intent, for content. p. 21. deem' for doom'd. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:5640:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>GREENE IN CONCEIPT: New raised from his graue, to write the <hi>Tragique storie of faire Ualeria of London.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Eace fraught with plentie, waiting on the Scepter of a gratious Soueraigne, had nowe seated her selfe in <hi>Albion,</hi> whence at her ariuall, rough-fac'd <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lona</hi> the nursse of broyles, writing in blood, her bailefull tryumphes, fledde disconsolate to forraine coasts, and there sounded hir Tragique summons. At whose departure all things recouered their former quiet: As when the yeare haueing shaken of stormie winters Ice badge, growes young againe, greeting the earth with gladsome tidings of the Flower-clad springes approach. Sillie Sheepeherdes haunted securely with their harme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse flockes, the westerne plaines, chanting by turnes sweete Roundelayes, or tyring with long play their Oa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten pipes: Toyling husbandmen ioyde freely in the issue of their hopes, reaping haruests plenty the guerdon of their winters paines. Each season had his successe, each state his solace. In which tranquillitie of time and truce of fortune, their liued in the famous citie of <hi>Troinouant</hi> an ancient gentleman, sonne to a wealthie Citizen, who dying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ulde, lefte him not younge, his onely childe, sole heire of his goodes, which, (besides money &amp; other moue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables)
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5640:6"/>
yealded him an ample reuenue of yearely rents. <hi>Giraldo,</hi> (so was he named) haueing enough, deemed it follye to toyle for super fluous store, or not to vse, what his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ncestors succesfull industrye had alreadie afforded him.</p>
            <p>Hee therefore conform'd his life to luch a course, as might equall his calling, and not Impaire his credit, or procure his discontent. Liuing thus at quiet (the more to Augmeut his ease,) loue he esteemed so little, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage lesse, that he passed y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> most part of his time without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> wife, in which Stoicall humor he determined to persiste, stiffely refusing many great offers, mou'd to him by sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye of good account and knowne sufficience; whether the care of housekeeping and feare to match with a mate of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like conditions, had dismaide him; or the sweetenesse of a single life through long vse besotted him; Howsoeuer this resolution seemd easie in regard of his yeares, yet did the sequell largely shewe, that no time, no temperature is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from loues tyranny; nor ought lesse to be trusted, then affections try all: The Sunne ofte shines not, til nere his setting. <hi>Cinthia</hi> filles not her circle, til fardest from hir brothers Sphere. Smothered Cinders may breed a flame, where we least suspect a fire; and winter fruites in growth lesse forwarde, are in lasting most forceable. The purest goulde hath his drosse; the clearest Wine his dregges; sweetest Roses their prickes; sowrest Stoickes their passions. Loue hath his change of Arrowes, his choyce of obiectes, to intice euery eye, to intangle euery Age.</p>
            <p>It chanced in a fatall ho <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>er, that <hi>Giraldo</hi> with sundry his familiers was inuited by a gentleman of the country (his dead Fathers approued friende.) to accompany him home, &amp; passe with him some daies of pleasure at his howse, scituate in a gallant soyle fruitefull of all delightes. They agreeing to his friendly motion, lefte the Citie, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riuing where he dwelt, found there such entertainement, as might assure their welcome, and warrant his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5640:6"/>
They were richly feasted, and frollike royally in all gentlemanlike disportes, hunting, hauking, with what soeuer pleasant recreation their thoughts could ayme at, and the countrye yealde. Thus farre lasted <hi>Giraldos</hi> comedie: but heere (though in a borrowed hue) stept in his Tragedies sad Proem masking his following sorrows in outward semblance of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>luring sweetnesse: Such are the wiles of loue and fortune, there first to smile, where they intend last and most to lower. This gentleman be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides two sonnes of rare towardnesse, had one daughter, hir name <hi>Valeria,</hi> young and fayre, in discourse witti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, but in life wanton; the fault and cause thereof, her edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: for being the fathers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>oy the Mothers Jewell, their last borne, and therefore most beloou'd, she was trained vp by her parents in all libertie, and taught, not that which best beseem'd, but which most delighted hir; In steade of sowing, shee could sing, write, daunce, and sweetly touch hir Iuory Lute, with whose weltuned stringes, hir fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers were more acquainted, then with hir needle: Breefely what could shee not, which least she should, and all more exquisitly, then was meete for a modest virgine? If then the strongest Marble bee in time worne by weake droppes of raine, the hardest <hi>Adamant,</hi> (though otherwise impene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trable) pearc'dby Goats warme blood: what maruel is it, that these so mightie inforcements, wrought so effectually on hir, whose fewe years, fraile sex, and sleight education made the couquest easie? Yet rau he headlongforward, not heeding howe she was inclined, nor weighing as he should haue done, the issue of his attempt, which these so many, and so manyfest likelihoodes did forethreaten: Such was his blindnesse enen when he first behelde her, to whom na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had leut a looke so alluring, a tongue so inchanting, that it restes doubtfull, whether hir countenance could more intrappe, or hir wordes entangle. To those that neuer sawe the Ocean, narrowe straights may seeme large
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5640:7"/>
seas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>he which till now had neuer view'd with curious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde, any such besotting obiect, demed <hi>Valeria</hi> the west<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erne prragon. His greedy euer gazing eyes, fed like hungry Guestes en hir faces beautie, yet neuer glutted; for the more he looked, the more he looued; Affection was no sooner bred, then wing'd; no soner warme, then flaming; (a thing in nature maruelous, but in loue no miracle,) she was the onely subiect of his conceipt, the onely ayme of his content: If she spake, his partiall eares deem'd hir voice more then Angelicall; if she smil'd, he was rauisht: if shee frown'd, euen frowning shee seem'd fairer, and hir anger a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>iable. Thus were hir wordes his eares musique, her faire countenance his eyes harbor, hir selfe, his transported sowles supposed solace, while he though olde, yet a Nouice in the schole of fancie fed his vaine thoughtes, with vainer hopes: But when beginning his wooing with signes, he sawe portraide on hir lookes, a deepe misliking of his age, threatning a sequell of many sorrowes, a Centurie of sowl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyring passions, then somewhat rowsing his charm'd sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, he began sadly to conferre his former course of life, with his present crosses in loue, weighing howe before he ioy'd in content, nowe ioylesse through discontent, then free from faucie, now slaue to beautie: And so farre he wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in this pensiue meditation, that sealing with manye sighes, each clawse of his complaints, he wished too late, than he had not come, or comming, had not seene; or seeing, had not affected; or affecting, had not so extreamly do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. But finding mone a bootlesse methode, a sleight me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine to cure harts maladye, he resolued to seeke some su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer remedie: which, (as he thought) was immediatly to depart; hoping that absence should worke his ease, and that his eyes not hauing whereon to gaze, his thoughtes should want wherewith to greeue him.</p>
            <p>In the heat of which humor, he abruptly tooke his leaue of the gentleman his friend, and the other his familiars, fei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5640:7"/>
sodaine and extraordinary occasions of busines, which drewe him thence. They no lesse beleening his wordes, then loath to hinder his waightie affaires, did not importune his tariance, yet vrged with much entreatie his spedy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torne, which he promising, though then not entending, lefte them; bnt could not leaue so his sorrowe, for in him selfe he caried his owne wounde, the euer-fresh and perfect Idea of <hi>Valerias</hi> farre peircing beautie, a more inseperable companion to his thoughts, then the shadowe to his bodye: the one waiting without, the other working so forceably within, that by how much the more he stroue to alay his passions, by so much the more hee encreased his paines: concluding by his owne experience, that to attempt the quenching of loue with absence, is to cherish fire with oyse. For as the course of a stronge currant, counterchekt by a barre of earth, seekes with greater violence another issue, and hauing past his boundes, tornes the pleasant medowes, into vnpleasant marishes: As the slowest flame, somwhat dau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ted by water, gathers immediatly double force and brightnesse: so the frenzie of a louers fancie, is then most outragious, and feeles greatest lacke of wonted ease, when the eyes do want their wonted obiect. <hi>Giral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi> therefore finding in the citie lesse comfort then in the contrye content, wandered in this labyrinth of woe, fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his soules agonie howerly augmented: In the daie, he could not rest; in the night, he could not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>leepe; if he sat, he sighed; but sighes yealded him no solace: ofte he walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to out we are his sorrowe, but oft walking could not worke it: At the table he sat a cypher; nor is it maruel, for how could he haue any stomacke to disgest his meat that wanted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>rength to disband his melancholie, which was so frutefull in afflicting him, that not <hi>Hydra,</hi> foggie <hi>Lernas</hi> fowle guest, could faster renue hir seauen heades, with seauenfoulde encrease, then his each-passion doubled his perplexitie, making his vnquiet life, the perfect ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:5640:8"/>
of a louers miserie: His friendes and neighbours mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed much what might be the cause of his discontent, suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siug nothing lesse, then that loue had bene the occasion.</p>
            <p>Among this number, one of like yeares &amp; long acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, did on a time so farre importune him, that <hi>Geraldo</hi> (though loath to vtter his affection, yet able to denie him nothing, because he lou'd him dearely) discoursed the whole at large, peremptorily concluding to hast with all speede possible (if his speding might bee possible) a maryage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Valeria</hi> and himselfe: For (quoth hee) as <hi>Telephus</hi> wounded by <hi>Achilles</hi> speare, could not be cured but by the rust of the same speare: And they which are stunge by the Serpent <hi>Dipsas,</hi> feele an vnquenchable thirst in the midst of water: so standes it with me, which haue surfeted, yet am not satiate: but being wounded with <hi>Telephus,</hi> must like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise with him deriue my helpe, whence I receiued my hurt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> which word he had no soner vttered, then his amazed friend deeming this humor in those yeares, the eight miracle; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drest himselfe to diuert him from so fonde a thought, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter some pawse began thus: Were I as wise, as I am wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to discharge the duety of a friende, then would I with mightie Arguments disswade you from a purpose so il be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeming: Can it be y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
               <hi>Geraldo</hi> so stale a batcheler, so strict a follower of the Stoichs philosophie, is in the wain of his age become a woer? He which laught at loue, and scornd fancy, nowe droupe for loue, and dote through folly: resembling in repugnance to nature, the stone <hi>Gagates,</hi> whereon if wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be powred it kindles fyer, if oyle, it doth quench the flame: Two things I haue noted in many, and finde both in you: the first rare and commendable, the second ridieulous, yet common: A young man wise, an old man wanten. Weigh yet with your sefe, what your friends will say, and the worlde censure, hearing of this so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine change: If mariage be a course so requisite, they will demaunde why you haue so long defer'd it; if not to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5640:8"/>
be respected, why you shoulde nowe determine <hi>it?</hi> know you not that loue in olde men is no lesse vnsermely and vnseasonable, then frost in Aprill, snowe in Sommer, Ice in the entering of Autumne? But admit it necessary, yet this hast is needlesse: Rash beginnings haue ruful ends: ripe counsailes right successe. The <hi>Elephant</hi> breedes not oft in age: The <hi>Phenix</hi> (as some affirme) takes life from Ashes, but once in sixe hundred and sixtie yeares: the one how mightie a beast? the other how matchlesse a birde? In <hi>Samos</hi> stoode a Temple of <hi>Hymen,</hi> ouer whose dore, on the outside, was set the portrature of a Snayle, to admonishe the beholders, that with slowe pace and deepe aduice they should proceede to a matter of such waighte, importing their extraordinarye weale or woe, <hi>Apelles</hi> drawing the picture of Folly, gaue hir winges, but not eyes; hir eares stopt, thereby intimating, that fonde men runne headlong forwarde, not seeing what they do, nor hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring others, which fortell them, the issue of their vnheed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full actions. It greeues me <hi>Geraldo</hi> to thinke, that fondly gazing on fayre lookes, which do commonly shroud false hearts, you are taken in beauties trappe, entangled like y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> fishe, which leaping at the Sunne beames, gilding the waues, playes therwith, vntill the net haue made him pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soner. Had you fancied some modest Matron, not for beauty a fading blisse; but for vertue a lasting value, your hast had bene yet more hopefull; nor might any iustly haue accused your abstinence in youth, or your affection in age. But at these years, when the prime of fancy is past, to be won by a want on glance, to dote on a silly Gerle, whose continence or constancy you know not, how farre vnfit? The <hi>Cretans</hi> had a lawe made by <hi>Minos</hi> their iust Kinge, that if a youngman matcht with an olde woman, or an olde man wedded a young mayde, they both should forfet whatsoeuer they possessed, and the elder of either sexe so offending, lose the reuerence due to their age. Well sawe hee, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5640:9"/>
true affection could finde no residence, where the desires wereso different; the one ayming wholy at youths delights, the other dull to wonted daliance, whence followes breach of wedlocke. What is your <hi>Valeria</hi> that you so dote on hir? say you shee is young? then wauering: grauitie is seldome in greene yeares. But were shee well enclin'd, yet might ill companie corrupt hir: Earely buddes are soone blasted; young sprigs do with the winde bende euery way. The flower-rith spring is natures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>thorne, but not heire of Autumnes ripenesse. Say you she is faire? then prowde, for as the herbe <hi>Fesula</hi> taken in wine, causeth the vaines to swell: so beautie in women doth enhance the thoughtes. I omitte to inferre hir store of fauorits, which will not faile to seduce hir, if coyne or counsaile may sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due hir. Is she wittie? then wilie; fraught still with new deuices to circumuent you. But shee can daunce, singe, finger a Lute, and all excellently: doe not these argue hir wanton education, or can you for these so highly fancie hir? then what other instance neede I saue your selfe, to prooue that loue is blinde? Loue, which hath the power of Lethe to induce obliuion, the windinges of a Labyrinth to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trappe the minde, the shape transforming iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e of <hi>Circes</hi> in chanting cuppes, to change thoughtes, as shee could al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bodies: Loue which for a minute of pleasure, yealdes a million of paines; for a dramme of Hunny, an ounce of gall, resembling that tree in <hi>America,</hi> whose Apples are to the sight exceeding faire but to the tast, deathes foode. Cease then betimes friende <hi>Giraldo,</hi> least you repent to late, and sigh in vaine, to thinke on my sayings, when your supposed ioyes shalbe smothered in surmising Ielousie. There is for euery sore prouided a salue, yet no simple for hartes sorrow: But as the bay tre alone is neuer hurt by lightning, so wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome euer vnstain'd by wantonnesse, which is in you the ground of that woe. Against poysons we haue preserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues: Storme-beaten seamen, wrestling with the furye
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5640:9"/>
of windes aud waters, ioy in the sight of <hi>Ledas</hi> twinnes: but thought sicke louers haue onely reason their soueraigne refuge: deuine reason the sole phisicke to cure loues follye, which straies from it so farre, that where the one raignes, the other cannot rest: For <hi>Amare</hi> &amp; <hi>sapere vix deo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceditur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heere he paws'd and <hi>Geraldo</hi> thus replide: your counsaile sauours much of good will, little of conceipt: yet for your curtesie I thanke you, and for your kindnesse, I wil think of you, as of a well entending friend. You deeme it strange that I thus olde, (though not so olde as you vrge) should now resolue on mariage, haueing before shaped a contrary course of life. True it is, that whilome my sole delight was to liue single, but who knowes not, that ould opinions are ofte concealed by new occasions? Must I be etter ill ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uised, because once not well aduertised? Is loue in oulde men so vnseasonable, in youth onely, (yf at all) commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable? or rather as the herbe <hi>Moly</hi> tempered with newe wine doth much distemper the braines, and infeeble the whole bodye; the same mingled with olde wine, doth soner effect the contrary, and releeue the ouer charged sences: So is affection in greene yeares full of perils, vrging young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to extremes, which cannot moderate their passions; but in riper yeares doth cheer the thoughts, glad the hart, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake the sences halfe dul and drooping. Admit the wants, the weakenesse, and whatsoeuer disabling defects incident to age. Tell mee (I pray you) who more needes comfort then they which want it; or what greater comforte to men then kinde women? How can you then with reason de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that to age; which doth ease the toylfull burthen of age, or terme that needlesse, which is so necessarie, but you growing to farther dislikes, condemne myne haste, which resolue with speede to dispatch my purpose, know you not that delay is fraught with daungers, that occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion is balde behinde? that they which deferre, are ofte
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5640:10"/>
preuented, and so circumuented? Such as obserue not there times, do iustly faile in there deserued cryalles. On the lilie-garnisht bankes of <hi>Cephisus</hi> there springes a flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of rare effectes, yet merely forcelesse, if not applide at the instant, when <hi>Phebus</hi> do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>h in fiery maiesty touch the meridian. In like sort, young virgines fancies, prone to affection by yeares and nature, must be assailed while time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>oth serue: for their fauour once rooted (a thinge easily performed) can neuer bee recal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e by threates of parents, or worldes of pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ffers. Speaking then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, I may perhaps speede: but deferring the one, I must dispaire of the other. Good wine needes no Juic bush: Faier women want no woers. hereto you reply that you condemne not so much my age as <hi>Valerias</hi> youth: to haue wo ed and wedded an auncient woman, had bene a match more meet: and this equalitie of yeares, caried more likelyhood of mutuall loue. For answere to which obiection, I cra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e no greater instance then your owne experience, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> widowes are wily and wilfull; that many scarse holsome morsels, do often vsurpe the attyre and gestures of honest matrons: heer is a Lerna of euils, a sea of dangers; which to encounter, I haue no courage: to conquer, no fortune: But in one yet neuer matched, how can deceipt be setled, or how is shee acquianted with wiles, which throughly knowes not the world? That <hi>Valeria</hi> is young, I yealde, nor am I very ould: but you will say that though a while I may entertaine hir with delight, yet I shalbe past beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, when she is in the prime of bearing: hereon you vrge, that giftes and pleasures are mighty tempters, women and they young, fraile vesseles, and therefore weake re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisters. Yet doubt not I, that with a gentle minde, the knowen kindnesse of a louing husband, shall more preuaile, then the doubtfull counsailes of deluding stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. That shee is fayer, I graunt also; that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore prowde, I deny. It suffiseth not with <hi>Ouid</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:5640:10"/>
to say partially, <hi>fastus inest pulchris, sequitur que superbia formam,</hi> vnlesse you learne of <hi>Aristotle</hi> to proue the consequence, by a stroug coherence: It followes not that all are faultie, because some offend: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as the birde <hi>Rintaces</hi> bred in <hi>Persia,</hi> liueing by ayre and deawe onely, hath no excrements: so natures perfections polished by vertuous education, brooke no excesse.</p>
            <p>For where shoulde inwarde graces be more resident, then where outwarde giftes are most resplendent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> That shee is wittye, in discourse, expert in daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, singing, and well fingering of a Lute, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse: that therefore wilye, or more apt for wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonnesse, I may in no sort graunt. The best things may be wrested to bad vses: Such recreations not misintended, hinder melancholy, and hurt not modesty. Thus haue I answered what you obiected, shewing reason the ground of my affection. Say then my friendes what they list, censure the world what it will, I am resolute to attempt, nor doubt I to attaine that, for which my<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> soule doth long, and my heart languish. Stoicks are stockes; sencelesse teachers that publish their owne follies, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying that to wise men which the sences worke in all men. Till now I knewe not what it was to liue, because I felt not the power of loue. Haue not Planets their con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>uncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the elements their mixtures, both their cooperant mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which argue that nothing can be of it selfe sufficient? Say that sicknesse should enfeeble me, who coulde so kindly comfort me, or would so willingly attende mee, as a louing wife: which would sit by me, sigh for mee, share with me my sorrowes, and vse all meanes to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure my safety? If death should seaze on mee wiuelesse as I am, and childelesse, leauing my goodes to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, or vnknowne heires, with what discontent shoulde
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5640:11"/>
I breath out my drooping spirit? But to your selfe I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale which haue in part experemented this facilitie, what ioye it were, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>uen in death, to behoulde, the fruite of my owne bodie, the continuer of my name, liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to possesse what I leaue: knowe you not that beastes voide of reason doe perpetuate, their seuerall kindes by procreation? and shall men iuriched by reason, be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in exceeded by beastes? if all were such as you counsaile mee to continue, where were the hope of posteritie: And that taken away, where the spurre of vertue? deserts guer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, the taske of fame, sounding to succeding times true honours trophes in euerliuing notes? I omit to alledge, that nature, and my countrye claime mariage of me as a debt: The Sparta ns among other lawes made by <hi>Licur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus,</hi> had this one, that the younger sorte should at all times and in all places, reuerence there elders: But to those of great Age wanting yssue, this preueledg was not due: So that <hi>Brasidas</hi> a valient chiefetaine neuer maried, laden with many yeares, but honored through more victories, passing by a young man, which sat still, not vsing to haue any shewe of reuerence, by mouing his bodie, or his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, and deeming it a great indignitie, receiued this answere: Thou hast not quoth he a sonne which may doe the like to me, if liuing to thy age. But whether runne I, in so large a fielde of mightie reasons, warranting my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution beyond all compasse of contradiction? Sith then to marry it is not onely seemely for any, but likewise ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary for all: in disswading mee from it, you highly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury mee. That I haue hetherto abstained, it was my fault; To persist in like humor, were deeperfolly, Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is little, then nothing; late then neuer; not to bee, then in vaine to bee. <hi>Nascitur is frustra, per quem non nascitur alter.</hi> Hauing thus said and fearing to bee vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with a fresh reply, he brake of there conference, by a feined occasion of businesse, leauing his well wishing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:5640:11"/>
friende in a deepe amasement, no lesse petying his daunger, then wondering at his do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>age. But no soner had <hi>Aurora</hi> in her next vprise moystn'd with her earely teares, transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m'd <hi>Adonis,</hi> and cherisht the forward springing of other flowers, then <hi>Giraldo</hi> mounting on his horsse, gallopt on the spurre in that gladsome season of the yeare, toward his harts wished harbor, where <hi>Valeria,</hi> (whom leauing, he so languished,) made hir residence: By whose father (his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured friend) he there alighting, was by so much the more louingly welcomed, by how much the lesse, his coming was then lookt for, which yealded in outwarde shewe, no other likelihoode of coniecture, but to be a bare iourney of recreation: till he impatient of all delay did fully (though in feawe wordes,) deliuer the soomme of his desire, which was to espowse <hi>Valeria;</hi> whereto the soner to induce hir fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to whom onely he now communicated his affectious secrets, he promised to make hir a large ioynter, craue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him no other dowery, then what himselfe would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly assigne. <hi>Theodoro</hi> (such was the others name) haue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much vsed-the father, and long knowne the sonne; of whose vertue, (besides his breath,) he was no lesse cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, then of his wealth assured: and perhappes somewhat mou'd by the voluntary offer of so large a ioynter: yealded him his full consent: promising moreouer, to worke herein so effectually with his daughter, (adding to his words the weight of a fathers authority) that shee likewise, whom it most concerned, should grant his demaunde, or deny hir due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: Which promise he faild not to performe, moueing the matter to <hi>Valeria</hi> in such sort, that the wily gerle which could by little gather much, and by a sillable co nceiue a sentence, was nothing ignorant of his entent herein, whom fearing to displease, &amp; hoping by this match to raign as Mistrisse of all (for well she knew the myldnesse of <hi>Geraldos</hi> nature) though at the first for fashions sake somwhat sticking at his age, concluded hir answere with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5640:12"/>
the offer of her obedience, in yeelding her selfe wholly to her fathers disposing. To bee shorte, <hi>Giraldo</hi> and shee were solemnly contracted, <hi>Valerias</hi> dowrie assigned, her ioynter set downe, all things confirmed, and they soone after openly espoused. Now seemed hee to himselfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely happie, solacing in an earthly heauen of imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie ioyes, a Paradise of thought-exceeding pleasures. But between seeming and beeing, there hath euer beene a large difference: <hi>Cadmus</hi> seemed happie, but his liues se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quell dasht his felicities vaine Hourish with a <hi>Chiliade</hi> of crosse Fortunes. <hi>Ante obitum nemo supremaque funera foelix.</hi> Had great <hi>Pompey</hi> with his third triumph finished his then-victorious life, hee had not famous'de <hi>Pharsalia</hi> through his foile, nor made Egypt fatall through his fall. Had <hi>Giraldo</hi> beene extinct in this the prime of his see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming happinesse, hee had not afterwarde dyed most happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse. But to proceed, the Nuptials beeing ended, and <hi>Giraldo</hi> on his returne vnto the Citie (whither hee pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to take with him his beauteous Bride) at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant of their departure, <hi>Theodoro</hi> (whose misgiuing heart did make him heauie) taking aside his daughter, thus grauely bespake her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Valeria,</hi> thou now must leaue mee, and learne with all another course of life then thou hast ledde with mee: thou must with thy estate change thy thoughtes, no lesse earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nowe endeauouring to please thy husband, then earst warily shunning to displease thy father. Oh let it not be saide of thee, which is too truely saide of many, That li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vnder their parents awe, they make shewe of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable vertue, but beeing exempted from that obedience, they vnmaske their abhorred vices, resembling in this change the Corall, which growing vnder the water, is of exceeding softnesse; but taking once the Aire, takes therewith a stone-like hardness. These may to their shame learne duetye of sillie creatures wanting rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5640:12"/>
Young Storkes feede their olde dammes, which else should famish: The Turtle hauing lost her mate by death, ioyes not in the companie of any other. Lo, in the one a precept of pietie to the parents; in the other, a myrrour of loue and loyaltie towarde the husband. And thinke withall, that naked beautie not adorned by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, is like the Tree <hi>Daphnoides,</hi> whose leaues are white, but the berries beeing ripe, are blacke. Presume not then on the fairenesse wherewith GOD hath suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently graced thee: that must fade, beeing onely the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies gift: but if, while it flourish, it be ill applyed, what more is it then a painted tombe, a golden sheath closing a leaden Sword, or wherein is it more esteemed by the wise, then wisdome by the foolish; From the Countrey (a place of small resort) thou must now into the Cittie, where thou shalt finde sundry sortes of companie and customes, as in a large plot among wholesome hearbes, vnholesome weedes: The wounded Hart flyes to the Forrest, crop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping <hi>Dictamnum</hi> to cure his hurt, knowing it by the smell among infinite other plantes. The little Bee (Natures great miracle) can sucke sweete Hony out of the most vnlikely flowers. I coulde wish in thee such distingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing skill and knowledge, in discerning and vsing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie; nor doubt I it, yet giue mee leaue euen without cause to feare, for therein likewise am I a father. All young Eagles can not steadfastly beholde the Sunne: All that seeme vertuous, are not so: whome though by their lookes thou caust not knowe, yet if for a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all thou temporize a while, the issue of their actions shall discouer them. Shunne these <hi>Valeria,</hi> least they shame thee: Joyne acquaintance and vse familiaritie with them onely, whose company may aduance, or at least not impeach thy credite: And striue thou rather to merite this rare tytle of extraordinarie praise, that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5640:13"/>
being young in yeares, thou art old in maners, then to be noted of this common imperfection, that thy manners are as thy years, light I meane, what more should I say then this only, that on the hope of thy behauiour, my life and ioyes depend: So that in thee it restes by thy well doing to cherish them, or by thy ill demeanor to cut them off: if thy entent be good, then may these words suffize, if otherwise farre more should be to fewe. This said, he ofte kist hir, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de wing plentionsly hir faire cheekes with fathers teares; then committed hir to hir husbands gouernment, and both to the almighties guidance, through whose fauour, they with their traine, after some smale iorney ariued insafetye at <hi>Troinouant:</hi> Aske not whether <hi>Giraldos</hi> friendes and neighbours mused to see him thus married: They were all in an extaste of admiration: but the roughest tempest is ouer blowne: the greatest wonder lastes but nine daies, and when the date of this was cleene expired, he not feeling the least scruple of discontent, liu'd in the pleasures of loue, seeking by all means to content his young wife, which hetherto rendered him like kindnes, whether hir thoughts were yet pure, vntill corrupted through bad company, or hir naturall humor of wantonnesse slept only, vntill awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by ill counsaill, (a thing to common in our age:) she bare him some prety children, a deper pledge of her yet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during loyalty: But alasse it had to sleight a permanence, for no sooner were three yeares past, then this vaine flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish became frutles, and she contemptuously neglecting or burying in carelesse obliuion, hir fathers counsaile, was throughly setled in forbiden acquaintance. Pitch if touched defiles, Bad company corrupts good condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: warme wax is apt for any impression, greene thoughts soone led to any opinion, but most commonly to imbrace the worst, for where vertue hath one affecter, vice hath many factors.</p>
            <p>Among sundry of hir owne sex, with whom <hi>Valeria</hi> did
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:5640:13"/>
a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t conuerse, there was one which in wit and wickednesse did farre exceed. Shee thought it not enough her selfe to offend, vnlesse through her, others also became faultie. So that (as making a conscience of imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>etie) shee stroue more earnestly to seduce the simple, then many to reduce the sinfull: and shee had so cunningly demeaned her selfe, that <hi>Giraldos</hi> wife (circumuented by her ouer-reaching wiles) deemed her a deare friend, communicating with her the chiefest of her thoughts. They had many mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, especially at gossips feasts, where alwaies (the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket beeing ended) while others held chat in common, they (somewhat withdrawing themselues) conferred in secret: and whereon soeuer they discoursed, this one point of her discontent, through daily feeling of more defect in her husbands declining yeares, was by <hi>Valeria</hi> sleightly tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched; yet so touched, that the other might well conceit her intent. Euen to be absolutely wicked, it requires time and vse. No maruaile then that shee hauing not yet ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into an habit of sinne, was not so wholly impudent as to expresse her meaning in plaine tearmes, though still ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting when the other would take the occasion by hér pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented. They oft met, oft talkt, and <hi>Giraldos</hi> wife woulde still harpe somewhat on that string: and hauing scarse be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, with a sleight sigh, abruptly ceasde. Now was the path well troden, and they meeting soone after in like place, on a day of great solemnitie, vsed like matter of discourse, with the same occasion againe offered. The other knowing her time, would not omit the aduantage, but ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king firme holde thereof, thus whispered to <hi>Valeria</hi> a Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens tale. Should it then be thus, or haue I thus deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that languishing through want of solace, you conceale from mee your hidden secrets? I haue often heard, that f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> euery sore, Nature hath planted a simple; that against e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie sicknesse, Phisicke hath possibilitie of expulsiue force. But well I wot, that reason containes no remedie
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5640:14"/>
for car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and discontent, saue onely the companie and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saile of a friend: such am I to you, and more I am, for your disease is to me knowen, though not by you disclosed: I know your youth, your husbands many yeeres; your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, his inclination; your desires, his defeets; your losse of time, his abuse of time. This onely I feare, least your faint courage barre you from accomplishing what you most couet. But listen with attention to my discourse, setting light by such suggestions: What is beautie, the sweetnesse thereof not tasted? What more is it to those which hauing it, can not vse it, then to <hi>Tantalus</hi> the decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing fruit and food: what more is it to those which admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it, can not enioy it, then musicke to the deafe, pictures to the blind, delicious meat vnto the dead? Beautie is no eternall blisse: but as the spring hath his date, so hath shee her durance limited by time: and (aye mee) too short a time. Sweetest flowers, if not gathered, wast or wither euen on the ground, whence they were cherished. These glories which now doe grace vs, must (if we liue) receiue the disgracious impression of wrinckled age: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore twice-rauisht <hi>Tindaris</hi> the wracke of Troy, long after her last recouerie, beholding in a glasse her aged face, did iustly sigh, witnessing in her teares, how transitorie a flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish her bodies late fairenesse did containe. To the Sunne, the measurer of time, Poets haue assignd a charriot drawn by foure winged horses; thereby intimating, that our liues daies poste on each minute with irremorable precipitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Time the father of Occasion, is (as his daughter) bald behinde, and hath one onely locke before, whereon vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse yon speedily lay holde, you shall for euer misse your holde. But why doe I tearme it yours, which if not vsed by you, can not be yours? Hereto you reply, that <hi>Giraldo</hi> is your husband, and you bound to him by the lawes of God and men. True it is, had you bound your selfe: but as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced oathes are by many deemed meerely forcelesse, so
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:5640:14"/>
compelled matches are not by fewe thought nothing so materiall, as where both parties yeelde a mutually free consent. Oh how preposterous is the care of parents, which ayming more at goods then at their childrens good, weigh not on what rockes of daunger through in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continencie and reproch they cast them whome they cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with those that abound in coine, though hauing nought else of worth: Farre more nobly minded was <hi>Themistocles,</hi> which in bestowing his daughter, preferred the vertuous and able poore, before the sottish impotent rich: whereof being demanded the cause, he made this generous answer: I had rather (quoth hee) choose a man without mony, then money without a man: wherein doubtlesse, hee meant not onely, that he is worthie the name of a man which imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth vertue, but also that hee is not to be thought a man, which can not performe the act of a man where it iustly is required.</p>
            <p>What can be more vnnaturall, then such inequalitie of yeeres and inclination? which granted, howe (I pray you) can that be pleasing to God, which is so directly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the course of nature, whome hee at first created in most absolute perfection of proportionall regarde, and hath euer since, and will till the ende of this worldes times, preserue fron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> confusion by vpholding this equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie? Thinke you that <hi>Myrobolan</hi> Trees, brought from Sunne-scorcht Susa, can prosper, if planted in frozen Scythia: or that the Northern pride of <hi>Flora</hi> can dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the Southerne fieldes? Would you deeme that gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diner skilfull, whome you should see setting Colewortes neare the vine, which shunnes them so much by nature, that it windes another way and soone doth wither? Can that match bee lesse vnmeete, where greene youth is yoakt with groning age? I haue hearde that <hi>Licur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> the Spartane Lawgiuer, did not ouely permitte, but commaund it (as a seruice much meritorious to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:5640:15"/>
the Common-wealth) that a vigorous man knowing an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble woman matcht with an husband impotent through yeares or some naturall defect, might lawfully demaund and no lesse lawfully vse her companie to raise vp issue in the others behalfe, which he must acknowledge as his own. Had <hi>Giraldo</hi> and you been Spartans, liuing in these times, then had you enioyed this pleasing priuiledge, your hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band beeing now past procreation: and hee, if discontent, in vaine had muttered: who if hee would needes marrie, should haue wedded some ancient matrone, the widow of two or three husbands, which might by custome knowe how to fitte the humour of his yeares, and brooke quietly the loath some accidents of his age, by feeling in her selfe like insufficiencie, baiting his eares with counter-coughes, and presenting to his eyes like nastie obiects of filth and flegme. Breach of medlocke had beene in her a crime in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expiable: but where the state and person of the offendour is changed, there likewise the qualitie of the offence is alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: nor can the crime bee so directly pertinent to you, (which being a child must obey) as to <hi>Theodoro,</hi> which (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your father) might and did commaund.</p>
            <p>Bethen couragious boldly to imitate the infinite exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of former times: nor are you now alone, which haue for presidents me, and such my friends, as seeke with mee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad what is not afforded vs at home: If herein you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sort with vs, you shall likewise share with vs your part of pleasures; you shall be furnisht with store of fauorites, ech of gallant &amp; goodly personage, and (which most is) of rare agilitie in acting that secret sweet seruice, which wee most affect. This onely is required, that you remunerate with coine the authours of your intent, bolstring vp with your bags their impouerishing braueries.</p>
            <p>Here <hi>Valeria</hi> halfe weeping, halfe wishing her self vnwed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, seemd doubtful wheron to resolue: but the other follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her aduautage, gaue not ouer till she had assured y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:5640:15"/>
To be short, there was a time &amp; place determined for entering <hi>Valeria</hi> into y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> order: meane while the whole crue was summoned, there to assemble at the day appointed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing likewise throughly acquainted with the cause. The meetest corner for this couent was thought a gardin-house, hauing round about it many flowers, and within it much deflowring. Were not this age fruitfull in stranger mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, I should haue deemd this an high maruell, that so small a plot of ground, could be so deuowring a gulfe of some mens gettings: yet who knowes not that extortions fruite hath seldome fayrer ende? But I procede; the day presign'd being come, no default was through absence made by any: there met they with their mynions, each hauing stopt hir husbands mouth with a feined talc, coynd <hi>extempore, Valeria</hi> not slacke to such deuotion, came with the first, seeming to her selfe most fortunate, in becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a sister of that society: They had there a costly banquet made at their common charge, so fraught with dainties, so furnisht with varietie of choycest delicates, that by their diet, there dispositions might bee well discerned; for this is the fewell which feedes and cherisheth the fyer of lust: <hi>Sine Cerere &amp; Libero friget Venus,</hi> When they had stoutly ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowsed and throughly pampered themselues, with these prouoking preparatiues, the table being now vncouered, they fell from quaffing to discoursing; then one of the dames and shee most impudent, (if this their excesse admitted any such degree of difference) calde for her lute, which finge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring too fitly, for so vnfit a purpose, shee accorded thereto with hir voice, and bewrayed (as followes) in a Canzon, the occasion of there meeting.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Happie lot to men assign'd</l>
               <l>Hartes with harts in loue combinde:</l>
               <l>Loue the some of earthly sweetes,</l>
               <l>Where with mutuall loue it meets:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:5640:16"/>
               <l>Not consisting all in lookes,</l>
               <l>Like to Idols, lay-mens bookes;</l>
               <l>But who tryes, this true shall proue;</l>
               <l>Action is the life of loue.</l>
               <l>Why slacke we then to bath in sweet delight,</l>
               <l>Before our day be turn'd to endlesse night?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fairest things, to nothing fade,</l>
               <l>Wrapt in deaths eternall shade:</l>
               <l>Hence I proue it beauties crime,</l>
               <l>Not to reape the fruits of time;</l>
               <l>Time which passeth swift as thought;</l>
               <l>Time whose blisse is dearely bought;</l>
               <l>Dearely bought so soone to faile vs;</l>
               <l>Soone, that should so long auaile vs.</l>
               <l>Why slacke wee then to bath in sweete delight,</l>
               <l>Before our daye be turnd to enlesse night?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Loue and beautie fade together,</l>
               <l>Fickle both as changing weather:</l>
               <l>Age or sicknes wastes the one,</l>
               <l>That doth faile, when this is gone:</l>
               <l>Let vs then while both doth last,</l>
               <l>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e them both, eare both be past.</l>
               <l>Sport we freely while wee may,</l>
               <l>yet a while it will be daye.</l>
               <l>Oh but this day drawes on to endlesse night,</l>
               <l>And with our life, still weares our loues delight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Soone ah soone was <hi>Adon</hi> slaine,</l>
               <l>Bashfull boy how faire in vaine!</l>
               <l>Fram'd by nature to be loou'd:</l>
               <l>Fram'd, but why, himselfe not mou'd?</l>
               <l>Dide hee not in prime of youth,</l>
               <l>Prime of beautie, pray to ruth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:5640:16"/>
               <l>Dye he did, himselfe preuenting;</l>
               <l>Sorte, vnworthy all lamenting.</l>
               <l>Oh thinke on him which changing safe delight,</l>
               <l>For certaine danger, turn'd his day to night.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But me thinks I talking see,</l>
               <l>How each minute slippes from me.</l>
               <l>Losse I deeme the least delay;</l>
               <l>Hast we then to this sweete play,</l>
               <l>Whence is suckt the sappe of pleasure,</l>
               <l>Such as loue by time doth measure:</l>
               <l>Loue that gardes his mothers forte,</l>
               <l>Peeping oft to see the sport:</l>
               <l>A sport how rare, how rich in sweete delight?</l>
               <l>But we how dull, how nere our day to night!</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Scarce had she ended, when they began, whose courages too prompt by custome, were by wine whet on to wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tonnes. <hi>Caetera quis nescit?</hi> we may more then guesse what was the sequell, by noting the precedence, both bad, but the latter a wrong inexpiable to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> right of wedlocke: a matter so offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siue to modest ears, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> euen impudence might blush relating it: but thoughts blush not to whom I referre it. Lust staine to loue, bane to beautie, path to shame, wanted here no effects: for <hi>Valeria</hi> thus entered into this exercise, like the game so well, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> thenceforth she could neuer leaue it. Boldnesse bred by vse grewe so absolute, in being dissolute, that it seemed in hir a second nature: who committing sinne with gredines, by offen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ing in one, became faulty in many. For most vices are linked together in such an vnion of affinity, &amp; cleaue so sister-like in one knot, (each mutually depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding on y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> other) that neuer any is imployed alone. This lustful dame not liking hir natiue beautie (though sufficient) would needes augment it with artificiall braueries, leauing no deuice vnplotted, no deceipt vnpractised, to make gratious hir
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5640:17"/>
gracelesse selfe: And I feare she hath herein too many fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, which spoyle there stommacks with vnsauory myx<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures thereby to seeme eye-sweete, though scarce hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sounde; or repaire their ruinous faces, by ouerlaying them with a false glosse of adulterine fayrenesse, whereas chaste beautie scorns acquaintance with Apothecaryes boxes. But why talke I of chastity, treating of a subiect so vnchast; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in whatsoeuer conceipt, or custome might afforde, shee faild not to apply effectually: And y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> more to garnish these bastard glories, she ware alwaies such ouersu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptuous attyre, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in desert, and dignitie farre exceding hir, were in this, as farre behind hir. No common fashion could please hir fancie, but it mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t be strange, and stately, drawing many eyes to gaze on hir, which ayi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>'d wholly at singularitie, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying to bee peerelesse in hir pompe, Neuer was any to hir power more lauish in varietie of wastefull vanities: neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny so peruerse in pride, and with such difficulty to be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed: For were the least stitch in hir Atyre not as shee would haue it, though the garment most fayre and costly, the Tai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor most rare and cunning, yet would shee furiously fling it from hir, with purpose neuer to weare it; so that the sillye workeman set at his non plus, lost both hir custome and the creedit of his workmanshippe. Next I note hir glutt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous appetite, not in the quantitie, but in the qualitie of of hir fare, which was so delicate and ouer daintie, that this lust-pampering diet, was no <hi>decorum</hi> in hir husbandes state. To preuent ill smelles, shee alwaies furnisht hir howse and garments with choyce perfumes, hir eyes deig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned no tryuiall obiects: without musicke no meat woulde downe, so mightily was this modest creature troubled (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sooth) with melancholy. Thus euery sence, had his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse, and (which more is) hir gylefull lookes shareing with the Adamant his attractiue power, could by an odde tricke whereto shee had inured them, worke petty won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5640:17"/>
If pacing in the streets she had seene any, whose outward semblance, might argue his inward sufficience, she would court him with a glance, whereto if he answered with the like, then was the match halfe made, and they neded but one meeting to assure the bergaine. Deeme you this not wonderfull, to pleade passion in dumbe action; to speake in silence, and speede by signes? oh why was sinne thus In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious, to excogitateso close a method for the furtherance of misdoing, or why should wantons exceede in wit, therby to spurre on there vnbridled wills? Thus you see that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wanted, saue only the cloking of hir crime, with the shew of holynesse and religio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, whose outward pretext is now a practise of great import, and a mightie piller of such carnall deuotion. Sinne appearing in his owue collors, should soone be knowen. A smoth habit of hipocresie is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finde by some, an intellectuall vertue, though a morall vice. But the hanting of priuate conuenticles being then not heard of, this pollicy could haue no ground. Yet <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leria</hi> though wanting, so great an helpe, wanted no fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorites, whose number by other meanes she still augmented: they strayning lustely their power in all sorts possible, (if any possible at full to please hir) were oft inforced for supply of their exhausted pith, to diet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>selues with drugs, and trot dayly to th'apoticaries for such trash. Of this crue the chiefe competitor was named <hi>Arthemio,</hi> whose aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage the wily Dame dissembling, did so temper hit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate lookes, and thereby held him in such suspence, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> though she so<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>what gracd him aboue the rest, because loath to leaue him; yet could he not gather by hir countenance any assurance of his content. Hir pollicie was, by concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his prerogatiue, to retaine hir soueraintie: Hir feare, that by disclosing it, she should arme his thoughts with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solencie, and he shake off that subiection wherein now shee had him: <hi>Arthemio</hi> which looked for a better market by <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raldos</hi> death, then present maintenance in his life, failde not
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:5640:18"/>
to imbrace all likely meanes, to make vse of all occasions, to applye cach opportunitie for the attaining and assuring of <hi>Valerias</hi> fauour to himselfe; still doubting his desires ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishment, because not priuie to his owne desart. After many thoughtes, hee deem'd this course the best, to seeme rauished by hir beauti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>; for well hee knewe, that herein to flatter women was highly to please them: In effecting which resolution, he did so quaintly counterfeite the drou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping louer, both in his lookes, and other gestures, that her witte bli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ded thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ugh selfe-concei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t, was by his wiles farre ouer reacht. At sight of hir hee would seeme so fillde with ioy, as if hir presence, weare his onely pleasure. when shee left him, he would sigh, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>aine such sorrow, as if his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort began and ended with hir company.</p>
            <p>Thus had he his sookes at such conunaundment, as wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men haue their teares: when shee talked he listued with such attention, as if hir voice had beene inchantingly melodious: ofte, (but on purpose when shee fawe him) he would steale a broken loke on hir: then (as loath that shee shoulde note hint) cast downe his eyes, and fourthwith raise them to reuewe hir. Hee would inuite hir to sumptuous banquets, ofte so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licite hir with amorous couceipts, of which so many, I haue related two as instances of the rest, wherein you may cleerely see hir blindnesse, with his bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ldnesse.</p>
            <p>In the prime of their acquaintance it chanced that Arthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mio was earnestly intreated to make one in a maske, for the gracing of a mariage; which request he sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e granted, knowing that <hi>Valeria</hi> (though with hir husbande) should be there a guest, to whom intending some odde toy in writing, because assurd that without suspicion he coulde not there im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy his tongue, and for that cause would not presume to much on his visard, he pende immediatly some feawe extemporall lines, with purpose there to deliuer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which might fully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate his forg'd affection. The time came; the maskers in their disguise appeard, when <hi>Arthemio</hi> hauing first taken
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:5640:18"/>
his mystris to the measures, and then withdrawing hir the daunce being ended, briefely whispered in hir eare his name, and conueyed in to hir hande these lines: which done, he left her. Shee finding that night an opportunitie (for shee could commaunde occasions, haueing hir husbande at controlement) perused his slight passion which followes thus.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>As when a waue-bruisd barke, long tost by the winds in a te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest</l>
               <l>Straies on a forraine coast, in danger still to be swallow'd,</l>
               <l>After a world of feares, with a winter of horrible obiects,</l>
               <l>Heau'n in a weeke of nights obscur'd, day turnd to be darknes,</l>
               <l>The shipmans solace, faier <hi>Ledas</hi> twinnes at an instant,</l>
               <l>Signes of a calme are seene, and seene are shrilly saluted:</l>
               <l>So to my drooping thoughts, when sorrow most doth await me</l>
               <l>Your subduing lookes in fayrenesse first of a thousand,</l>
               <l>(Staine to the brightest star, that gildes the roofe of Olimpus)</l>
               <l>Calm'd with a kind of aspect, vouch safe large hopes to releue me:</l>
               <l>Such is your bewty, which makes your bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty so powrful;</l>
               <l>Such to mee your beawty, which makes your bounty so blis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful;</l>
               <l>Whose each worth to relate, my worthlesse pen is vnable:</l>
               <l>Haires of a goldlike hewe; (not purest gould so refulgent)</l>
               <l>Pearle-like piercing eyes (not purest pearles so relucent)</l>
               <l>Cheekes of a maiden dye, with a snow white circle adorned:</l>
               <l>That rosy-redde as a rose, this Lillie white as a lillye;</l>
               <l>Not such a red, such a white, to be seene in a Rose or a Lillie.</l>
               <l>Euery part so repleat with more then could be required,</l>
               <l>That to behold hir worke, eu'n Natures selfe was amased.</l>
               <l>Muse not then that I loue, but muse that I liue, if I loue not:</l>
               <l>Muse that I draw my breath, mine eyes, not drawne by thy bewty.</l>
               <l>Yet, shal I loue in vain, in vain such bewty beholding,</l>
               <l>Deem'so to loue, so to looke, that lok<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s &amp; loue be rewardles:</l>
               <l>Better it is to be dead, by death from cares to be cleered;</l>
               <l>Cares the records of loue, sowre loue when slightly regarded.</l>
               <l>Grant me then (o fayrest) assurance so to be fancied,</l>
               <l>That nor I droope dismaide, nor doubt, not fully resolued.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:5640:19"/>
               <hi>Valeria</hi> hauing red this toy, smilde to thinke how hee which had on hir so mighty a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> aduantage, was held by hir at such a bay, because not priu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o his owne prerogatiue. Thus did they both dissemble; hee in feining great affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on where little was, she in making shewe of little, where much was. Upon occasion of this toye <hi>Valeria</hi> at thier next meeting thus saluted him. Seruant you are welcome from the Sea: what newes (I pray you) among shipmen? <hi>Arthemio</hi> smelling hir drift, and liking well the motion, but dissembling it, replyde thus: Mistres it were strange hee shoulde be welcome from the sea, which neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>aw the sea: But more strange (quoth shee) that land men should in stormes be driuen to expect ayde from starres; sith to them the greatest tempestes are meere trifles, if we weigh the seas huge tossing. Yet (quoth <hi>Arthemio</hi>) such may the storms be, &amp; such the starres, that the one may be as ruth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and the other as requisite: That you meane (quoth shee) by the sandy sea, where men are oft drownde in dust, and their bodies remnants become drugges. But it seems by your short returne, and sound complexion, that you were not a passenger in those pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s.</p>
            <p>Hereto <hi>Arthemio</hi> thus answere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>: the sea wherein I yet do saile, readie still to sinke, if not supported by your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, is no lesse strange then that of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>and; for amidst the flambe I freise: (such are my feares) amidst the floode I flame (such is the feruor of my affection,) my shippe floats, yet not on water; the waues which beat on it are sobbes: It sailes, yet on no fea; the windes which breath on it are sighes. But by your leaue (replyed <hi>Valeria</hi>) are you still a sea-man, and not yet o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> shore? then was my welcome ill bestow'd, before your selfe were well arriu'd: but to vnmaske this misterie, me thinks your sea is very me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>aphoricall, &amp; I muse that where the lymi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s are so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>raight, the danger can be so extreame: It is (quoth hee) generally obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that the floode is roughest, where most restrained.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5640:19"/>
And no lesse generally noted (quoth shee) that the Sea is of Elements the most vncertaine, whose waues are by each gale of wind raisde in billowes. If then your application hold as generall, I rather commend your Metaphors con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, their your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> constancie. But it were (said hee) iniustice to charge the Patient with the Agents fault. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though my thoughtes (my fancies Sea) tost twixt vaine hopes and feares, plunge my heart in dire perplerities: yet that my sillie shippe, ranging in this rockey Ocean of des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire, though not hauing still one Current, striues still to keepe one course: and amidst so many changes, remaines vnchanged, though tirde with troubles, which are (some say) loues surest trialls. Accuse not then, much lesse con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne that of dissoyaltie, whereto life shall sooner faile then it to loue: and which sooner may by death be broke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, then breake those <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> bondes, wherein your beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie making through mine eyes a breach, holdes it inthrald. But why talke I as if in me it rested to repeale my passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which doe share with the stone Abeston his retentiue vertue? For as that being once hote is neuer after colde, so my fancie fettered in affections chaines by your soule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intangling fairenesse, is now not capable of libertie. Or rather (quoth <hi>Valeria</hi>) your thoughtes masked vnder your deceiuing lookes disguise, resemble the Camelion; and as that can in a moment be clad with any colour, but retaines none; so your fancie can at the view of euery pleasing face, forge new passions, but persist in none.</p>
            <p>Hereat <hi>Arthemio</hi> guiltie to himselfe, did bite the lippe, because knowing she spa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the truth; yet comforted, in that shee meant it not a truth, but onely as tearmes of course, whereto as he would haue answered, other companie brake off their conference: and they with the rest fell from loose talke to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> toying: dreading nothing lesse, then that their leudnesse could be discouered.</p>
            <p>His second humour was this: Against <hi>Valerias</hi> birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:5640:20"/>
hee had of purpose pend this following Dittie, and on the verie day sent it her by that trull, through whose coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell shee was first seduced, and into whose familiaritie hee had of late insinuated, because knowing how much <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leria</hi> did loue and trust her. Shee comming as a friend and neighbour, and beeing with all a notable hypocrite, had both easie accesse and priuat conference without suspition: for it seemd a thing not to be doubted of, that the subiect of their talke was onely some gossips matter, as among wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men it is ordinarie. Beeing thus alone with her, after a large preface of <hi>Arthemios</hi> deepe affection (for so had he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore concluded) shee deliuered her on his behalfe this wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comepresent, which <hi>Valeria</hi> forthwith vnfolding, read as followeth.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Let others vse what Calenders they please,</l>
               <l>And celebrate their common holidayes;</l>
               <l>My rules for time, my times of ioy and ease</l>
               <l>Shall in my zeale blaze thy perfections praise:</l>
               <l>Their names &amp; worth they fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy worth shal take;</l>
               <l>And highly all be honoured for thy sake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That day shall to my thoughts still holy be,</l>
               <l>Which first vouchsafde thy beautie to mine eyes;</l>
               <l>That day when first thou deigndst to fauour me,</l>
               <l>And each from some peculiar grace arise:</l>
               <l>But mongst them all, my dutie shall attend</l>
               <l>This more then all, on which they all depend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Haile happie day, to whome the world doth owe</l>
               <l>The blissefull issue of that influence,</l>
               <l>Which from the force of best aspects did growe,</l>
               <l>In luckiest house of heau'ns circumference:</l>
               <l>Haile happie day that first didst shewe this aire,</l>
               <l>To her whom Fairenes self doth yeeld more faire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:5640:20"/>
               <l>Nere be thy brightnes dimd by wind or raine;</l>
               <l>No cloud on thee forestall <hi>Hyperions</hi> light;</l>
               <l>On thee no doome pronounc'd of death or paine;</l>
               <l>No death or paine endurde; no bloudie fight:</l>
               <l>But be thou peacefull, calme, and cleare for aye;</l>
               <l>Let feasts and triumphes choose thee for their day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>On thee I vowe to rest from all affaires,</l>
               <l>To giue large almes to poore distressed men;</l>
               <l>Not to profane thy ioy by fretting cares;</l>
               <l>To send my saint some tribute of my pen;</l>
               <l>And when thou dawn'st, deuoutly still to say,</l>
               <l>Haile happie, holy, high, and heau'nly day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such and so long may be to me her loue,</l>
               <l>As Ile this vow religiously maintaine;</l>
               <l>So may my plaints her heart to pittie mooue,</l>
               <l>As from my heart I speake: let false hearts faine.</l>
               <l>Haile happie day; but then how happie shee,</l>
               <l>Who makes this day thus happie vnto me!</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Gentlemen, you need not doubt that <hi>Valeria,</hi> whose o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersoothing humor made her interprete flatterie for truth, was no lesse proude of this then of the former, howsoeuer she dissembled her inward content, euen to her sinnes owne secretarie and chiefe directour, least <hi>Arthemio</hi> should by her meanes lay holde on that assurance, which by himselfe hee could not gather. But marke (I pray you) how thicke a mist of dotage <hi>Giraldos</hi> good nature had cast before his eyes. As the trull was readie e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> depart, he would neede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> force her to tarrie dinner, telling her merily that this was his wiues birth-day, whereon he had prouided an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie dish, and thought none so meete as her selfe to taste
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:5640:21"/>
thereof, beeing so kinde and louing a neighbour, requesting her withall to repayre oftener to his house, to visit and passe away the time with his wife, and when she walked abroad, to beare her company. They hearing these wordes, did in their lookes argue each to other their high content, groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding (though falsly) on his simplicitie, the safe continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of their delights, as being thereby exempted from all dread and danger os discouerie. But the highest flood hath the lowest ebbe, the hottest Sommer pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ignifies the coldest winter; tempestes in the prime of Autumne, are least drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but most dangerous. Shame sinnes guerdon, is then nearest, when through selfe-soothing securitie, the feare thereof is fardest. And as the fish <hi>Remora,</hi> though little, can stay the greatest shippe: and the Crocodile though in the shell one of the least, prooues afterwarde the greatest Serpent that haunts the shore os <hi>Nilus:</hi> so not seldome in this worldes accidentes the detecting of deepest crimes, springs from the lightest and most vnlikely occasions: for proofe of which assertion, I neede no farther instance than this subiect whereon I intreat.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Giraldo</hi> among other seruants, had one named <hi>Iockie,</hi> a sillie boy borne in the North of <hi>Albion,</hi> and employed in basest errands, such commonly as concerned the kitchen: It chaunced on a time, that as Valeria had left the house, gone foorth of purpose to sport with her companions, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly after her departure, this <hi>Iockie</hi> was sent abroad, when (straying in a boyish humor to gaze on the gayest ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects in some other street) hee espied suddenly his Mistresse before him, and stept backe as halfe amazed; but recalling forthwith his courage, and noting more exactly one of her company, whose lewde and dissolute life was commonly known, he began knau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hly to suspect, that eeh of her other mates were likewise of the same mould. To confirme or confute which imagination, he followed them aloofe; yet so warily, that hee saw them housde, himselfe not seene: and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:5640:21"/>
closely houering neere the dore, espied their minions ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in order, with other such apparant likelihoods, as hee now no longer suspected, but certainely beleeued, that <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raldo</hi> his master was as soundly armde for the head, as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Capricorne or the stoutest hornd signe in the Zodiacke. Hauing made this triall, he departed, doubtfull what to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine: for on the one side, hee foresawe his owne most as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured daunger, in reuealing what hee had discouered, sith well hee knewe that one of his mistres wordes could ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weigh, one of her teares wipe out a volume of accusati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by him produc'd: which graunted, what then might follow but this, that the guerdon of his tongues lauishnes, should be laide on his shoulders? Besides, his Mistresse by this meanes irreconciliable, for women which by nature imbrace extreames, beeing therein onely constant, persist not so in any as in malice: and what mischiefe that might effect, he though young, had for his owne part experience enough. But on the other side well hee sawe, that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters credite alreadie stainde, and his disgrace daily aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, would spread so it selfe, still gathering force by going forward, that if not now restrained, it must needs at last to his then greater shame, and incurable sorrowe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by others be detected, or of it selfe breake forth: for neuer yet was sinne long in league with secrecie. Tender twigges may with ease be bowed: the full growen tree soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner broken, then bent. The now-detecting of <hi>Valerias</hi> crime, might recall her, and preuent <hi>Giraldos</hi> future reproch, but her offence if longer cherished by sin-noursing silence, would in the end become inexpiable. In regard hereof <hi>Iockie</hi> cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiously resolu'd to ouerpeaze the feare of danger with the care of dutie. In which vaine returning home, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>eeing accusde of loytering by such as sent him, he appealed to his master, by whome likewise being sharply demanded y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> cause of his long taria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, he reuealed to him in secret what he had seene, &amp; proou'd to himselfe a true prophet, in receiuing for
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:5640:22"/>
his thanklesse seruice, that guerdon which before hee iustly feared. For <hi>Giraldo</hi> ayming amisse at his inclination, dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med this a villanous deuice forg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e by the boy to breed dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord between him and his wife: wherof this was no sleight presumption, in that <hi>Valeria</hi> was euer sharpe to him. But when <hi>lockie</hi> (which would not cowardly giue ouer hauing thus entred) continued his discoueries, still furnisht with more friendly opportunities, &amp; did oft constantly offer vpon the hazard of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whip, to make his master eye witnes of that, whereof his eares deignd no accepta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; <hi>Giraldo</hi> at last deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reuoluing in his pensiue thoughts the boies large proffer, and much desirous to know at full the state of his own fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, wherein he seemd to feele alreadie some alteration, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed to his request, waiting a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient time; &amp; being then by him conducted, saw what hee sigh d to see, &amp; for euer sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row'd to remember. Now iealousie (of all hags most hellish) whose neuer closed eies in number infinite, shun truce with sleep, whose tongues &amp; eares equalling her eyes are still im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploid, these in listning, they in whispering. This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>end (I say) shedding her selfe into his thoughts, and pouring into euery vaine her venime, did by continuall torturing of his care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired soule, gather vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> losses other long delay: now wrought she on his intangled wits as on an anuill, hatching in his brains vnw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nted horrors. He y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> earst weighed not his friends words dissuading him from mariage, did now more then ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire his truth presaging wisdom, &amp; much bewaild his own folly, in not crediting such good counsell: he that earst doted in blindnes, seemd now as cleere-sighted in discouering <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerias</hi> fault, as far-seeing <hi>Linceus</hi> in discrying the <hi>Punique</hi> fleet. He that earst deemd all gospell which his wife spake, did now dread deceit in euery sillable, &amp; mistrusted her each step, ech looke, ech sigh, ech smile: briefly, whatsoeuer by her was done, he deemd misdon. But how in nature could earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incinerating <hi>Aetnas</hi> wombe big swolne with flames, brooke inclosure, nor enforce an issue through violent eruption?
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:5640:22"/>
The world circling Ocean, threatning in his fomie source a seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d deluge, if not let blood in hollow <hi>Cauernes,</hi> &amp; thence suckt vp by the thirstie earth, would ouerflow the contiue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: aire restraind breakes forth in whirlwinds: wrong'd loues restles (if once raisd) suspicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the thoughts burning <hi>Aetna,</hi> boyling Ocean, &amp; euer-blustring whirlwind, piercing tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ough the eares vnto the heart, must be in words exprest, or the drooping mind by wosupprest <hi>Giraldo</hi> therfore, that he might disburden his ouerburdened selfe, no longer able to sustaine his sorowes weight, faild not to imbrace y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> first oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>asion; chose his time, made his triall, and thus sadly brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king silence he bespake <hi>Valeria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wife, I had thought vntil experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce proou'd it false, that outward gifts were euer linkt with inward graces; but now I find, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> in the sweetest fruits wormes are soonest bred; that the finest cloth is so onest eaten with consuming mothes; the freshest colours soonest tainted by defacing spots; euen front fairest roses, spiders suck their fatall poison. Trothles <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leria</hi> (but I want a sharper Epithet) when first I saw thee, I affected thee, my loue taking life from thy looks fairenes, yet well hop'd I of thy then seeming vertues forwardnes, which hope long I held; but it now hath left me, &amp; I too late haue learnd, that as Iris hath many colours but none conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing, <hi>Proteus</hi> at his pleasure any shape, but none certaine; the sea many calmes, but yet the wary shipma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neuer secure; so thy wit wrested by wantonnes, made, how faire a shew of vertue, thy selfe still nothing lesse then vertuous! But when the substance failes, needs must the shadow fade. Time the father of truth, drawing from before mine eyes the vaile of dot age which closde them as in a cloud, hath vnclaspt the legend of thy liues shame, to we are out my life with sorow. Shame (I say) which neuer shall haue end; sorrow, which death alone may end. Muse not if that for which I still haue lou'd thee, be now to me barren of delight, sith y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> which long I hopte in thee, had neuer harbor in thy thou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hts. O thou of women the most vnwomanly, say &amp; sigh (if not all shameles)
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:5640:23"/>
wherein haue I deseru'd this iniury? or by what wrong prouokt (if any wrong sufficient to prouoke an honest mind) hast thou yeelded that to others which by the lawes of God &amp; men thou owest to me alone? Did I euer countermand thy desires, euer contradict thy designments; euer crosse thee, or vnkindely thwart thee in thy commandements? didst thou not alwaies go when thou wouldst, whither and with whome thou wouldst, spend what thou wouldest, rule with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controlment, disposing all things at thy pleasure? Oh therein I wrought thy wracke, strengthening thy corrupt nature with corrupting libertie. But aye mee, my wordes work in thy countenance no change. What? haue thy cheeks forgot to blush, thy heart to feele compunction, thine eies to shed due teares? Teares they shed such as the Crocodill, to ensnare the silly passenger, not tears to argue thy contritio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thou which art for sinne too fleshly, for repentance art too stonie. Oh if thou wouldst but sigh, I should hope of thy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: but sigh thou wilt not, or thou canst not: wilt not, in that thou art too wilfull; canst not, because long custome hath wholly corrupted thee. Here hee pausd; for to proceede griefe would not permit him: but <hi>Valeria</hi> though not loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for such a lesson, yet bearing it out with a bold face, wherein impudencie was throughly setled, after a tempest of rough termes, vrged him to produce the authors of his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusation: which when he had done, naming <hi>Iockie</hi> &amp; himself, she standing stoutly in <unclear>defiance</unclear> of them both, &amp; renewing her railing vaine, would in the heat of her womanish fury, haue sillie <hi>Iockie</hi> thrust out of the house, as the breeder of their discord: But herein he withsta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding her, began now in vain to vse that which of right to him belonged, I meane, the husbandes soueraigntie, by her sere so much affected, by her still vsurpt with most aduantage: for how could he now reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer what his long sufferance had to her confirmed? The fault whereof resting wholly in himselfe, the effect thereof did likewise to himself wholly redou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: which in ouer-fondly manifesting his entire affection! a secret by husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds warily
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:5640:23"/>
to be handled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> arm'd hir im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>etie with impudencie, hir impudence with impunitie. But while nature slept that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>elosie might awake, there followed a mightie change: for the mildnesse in him so much commended, which appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from his birth, wanne to him the mindes of all those which conuerst with him, was now vanquisht by mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyrage; nor such rage to be condemned, if we weigh the ground whence it arose, They had therefore nought to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile at, which sawe their former discord, dasht by fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing disagrement, his loue now, conuerted to loathing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>th hir louc peruerted by lust, or his wonted kindnesse dying in vnkinde vpbradings: the cause amply warants the effect. <hi>Giraldo</hi> ofte inueighing, because seeing in hir no amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet had euer the disaduantage: For shee openly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying and denying what soeuer he ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ected, hoping to bear out hir crime with bouldne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e, thought it not enough hir selfe to ouer match him wearying his eares with outragious scoulding (for with hir tongue shee was as tall a warriou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resse as any of hir sex:) but which is worst, set on his owne children, to reuile their silly father: they though traind vp from their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>adle in all bouldnesse and neglect of duety, were herein impiously obedient, too promptly conceauing and practising their wicked mothers death-worthie doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. Like examples fewe ages can afforde, feawe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes yealde, much lesse should <hi>Albion</hi> (pollished so with ciuilitie, and natiue mildenesse of well ordered manners) harbor such vnheard of heinousnesse, which is rare euen to the barbarous <hi>Getes. Giraldo</hi> haueing till then helde out in changing bitter termes with hir, was hereat so a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated, that he now no longer wished to liue: In his howse he had no ioy, sith there bayted thus by them, which from his bowells had their beeing. But when shunning ofte his home, he strayed abroade reuoluing in himselfe with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny sighes his infinite fore-passed cares, present corrosiues, and likelihoode of farre greater ensuing griefe; <hi>Iockey</hi> in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:5640:24"/>
his absence neuer wanted blowes, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a cause, though faulse, yet seeming iust haueing a witte so rich to coyne occasions, power so absolute, and a will so much inflamed with wrath to vse them. Thus both the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>er and the man, the one in minde, the other in bodie by this Ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse outragiously afflicted, wished the first neuer to haue weded hir; the second y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his master had herein likewise been by hir ouer-mastred, when to thwart hir fury, he would needs retaine him stil in seruice; But she not moued by hir crimes discouery, proceeded dayly in misdoing, with so sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne vnrelenting wilfulnesse, that soner might the sunne melt with his beames, the euer ysie bulke of waylesse <hi>Caucasus,</hi> ouer whose snow manteled shoulders they glance without reflection; Then hir sinfrozen thoughts melt with true sorrowe, or (which is lesse) hir he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse eares, admit (though sleightly) holsome counsailes; eares more deafe to friendes repro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>uinges, then are the wrack rich <hi>Libique</hi> rocks, or the guestlesse ship swalow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Sirtes,</hi> to the cries of dying marriners: such force hath custome euen against nature: Then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>cible where backed (as here it was) by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap>? When <hi>Vlisses</hi> matesturn'd from men to beastes through the taste of <hi>Circes potions,</hi> had it afterwarde in their owne choyce, whether they would so remaine, or reasuming their former shapes, returne from beastes to men againe; they would in no sort be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, aleadging, that in this there brutishe state, they were farre more exempted from hart-gnawing greefe, farre more secure, then when their bodies were with humane shape inuested: which fiction moralized as <hi>Homer</hi> ment it, doth not onely note our liues troubles fraught with infinite distressing dangers, but likwise, that when reason is by affection ouerruled, and the soule our better parte, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to the bodies tyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ye, our baser parts, such as are charmed with the loue of sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all delights (wherein we wholly communicate with beasts
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:5640:24"/>
&amp; degenerating from our states <hi>decorum,</hi> participate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their nature, which is altogether led by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>-bred appetits) are then so deeply be witcht w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wantonnes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they will soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner dye for loue of it: then while they liue, in any sort assent to leaue it: but as the byting of the Aspicke, brings death as in a slumber, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ult thereof not being felt; so where defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling lust doth raigne at full, they whose thoughtes it hath polluted, haue no feeling of their destroying follyes, till plungd in the mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>st of their desorued paines. When the stoode is at his highest source then takes the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his turne, <hi>Valerias</hi> crime fostered through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ing, was nowe subiect to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> desteny <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is, to bee as openly discouered, as it was before closely couered: Hir offence earst priuately reueald to hir wrong'd husbande, did soone after become publique; &amp; with hir, the partnours of hir im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyetie shard like fortune, for what can be more iust, then that they which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> together, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> participate the shame therof together? And thus it was; After many meetinges, many mischiefes perpetrated by that troope of trulles, it chanced that in one of their fleshly synods, newes were toul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of a great solemnitie, which within fewe dayes was to bee celebrated, with much royalty at the courte: whereupon at <hi>Valerias</hi> motion, they immediatly resolu'd, that suted in mens attyre, they would meete there in a maske, there fauorits; which promis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> without farle there to finde them, and after one sporte acted by themselues, to act on them another, with so much the more safetie, by how much the farder they should bee from their husbandes: whose noses growing now with their hornes somwhat longe, coulde smell shrowdly any thing at hande. Was then there laying out of curled hear, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>uing oft the wants of their almost hearelesse scalpes) so light a crime? their buskes, and that great humme of <hi>Paris,</hi> that vaile of lechery, so slight a sinne, (beeing so soueraigne a remedy for bigge bellyes, which ofte at a pinch helpe forwarde the worldes increase
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:5640:25"/>
with swelling zeale,) were there other former faults such veniall offences, that to exceede them all, and hererein on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly able to exceede them, they must thus disguise there sexe? But why maruell I at their desire to seeme men, sith they so mightily affected men? yet could they not conueigh their ill contriu'd intent with such secrecie, but that sundry knewe thereof (for amongst so many how coulde all be silent?) passing thus from one mouth to an other it came in the ende to the heering of certaine courtiers, of which one, the greatest in account, deepely abhorring so odyous an enterprize bouldly reueald it to the prince of those times, who desiring to see the issue of their impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, (though deeming it almost impossible, that anye of that sex should be so shamelesse) commanded generall si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and such semblance, as if nothing were discouer'd. They going forward with their attempt, fayld not to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble at the day assigned, each being cas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> in hir mynions best attyre: then vsing the benefite of the darke, which is gilty of many mischiefes, they came to the court, and there suing for farther accesse, obtain'd it, thinking of nothing lesse, then that they were intrapt: But to dispatch the matter breefely; In the midst of their iolitie, they were by the princes commaundemente all forceably <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, standing then before hir, as stony Images, not blushing ought at this bewraying of their lewdnes, though enuirond, and like monsters gazd on by many eyes, nor making a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny shewe of sorrowe, for their soueraigns sharpe rebukes, which conceiuing no hope of their amendment, seut them home with open shame vnto their husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds. The griefe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of pinched <hi>Giraldo</hi> so nere the heart, that he fell through sorrow into a greeuous sicknesse, which wasted so his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feebled body, that all remedies fayling, his last musique was the sertons vnison, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him with a dolefull sounde, to make ready for his longest home. When no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>esse defirous of death, then disparing of life, he causd all
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:5640:25"/>
in the chamber to withdrawe, (<hi>Valeria</hi> excepted) whom calling to him, he thus bespake: Might these last wordes worke that remorse in thee, which my former speeches ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer could effect: I should deeme my selfe not wholly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie. That I am sicke, thou seest: that dangerously sick, I feele: the cause thy folly: long haue wee liu'd together, in litle ioy, lesse agreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; our iarring grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded on thy falshood, not my fault; vnlesse it were a fault, with too much loue to foster thy too much libertie: But I cease to relate former iniuries, at thought whereof I may iustly wish with <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustus,</hi> that I had liu'd wiuelesse, and died childlesse: bee it a full amendes for all these misdemeanors, heedfully to obserue and followe, that which I nowe shall speake, not as a husband, (though in that name I should commaund) but as a friend, no lesse carefull of thy soule, then thou carelesse of my safety: First, if thou caust conteine thy lust, liue still a widowe; for who heareing of thy loosenesse, wil mary thee for loue; and to whom is not thy shame knowen? if then hee wed thee for wealth, finding (as needes he must) thy sinne grounded on my too much sufferance; how slauish shall thy life be vnder him? I omit to vrge thy childrens hinderance by an vnaduised match. Next I counsell thee in no sort to change thefeat of thy aboade; for what else should that argue, then a meer dispayre of recouering thy lost good name? continue then where now thou art, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly endeauouring to wipe out the blemish of thy former leawdnesse, by imbraceing henceforth, and persisting to the ende, in an honest course of life: so shall the same place and persons that sawe thee vicious, see likewise thy returne to vertue; the report whereof receiued from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers might iustly be doubted, but their owne witnesse to themselues must needes bee authenticall. Beleeue me <hi>Valeria</hi> thou canst not otherwise weare out the impres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of thy shame; nor can it in such sort bee so curde, that no scarre will remaine: This for thee: and thus breefely
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:5640:26"/>
for thy ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ren? sith the shortnesse of my time, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nes mee likewise to be short in talke: God lent vs three all sonnes, one of which he hath taken againe vnto himselfe: that the happiest: Two he hath left to vs, and I leaue to thee: Reforme them with thy selfe; see them well instructes, taught to imbrace vertue, and abhorre vice: Such hether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their education, that I greeue to remember it: but thou maiest ioy to better it: Libertye is the bane of youth; not for a time, as the honny of <hi>Colchos,</hi> which doth inebriate those that taste it, &amp; distract with one dayes mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness those that greedelye doe eate it: But this soule-contami natinge poysson, strengthned by custome, growes incurable: Purge then from this infection their tender thoughts, while they yet are each way flexible. That thou louest the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I doubt not, but that thy loue will cherish their leawd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, I iustly dread, and therefore do thus warily admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish thee; bee thou as wary and willing to performe what I requier, tending so greatly to their good: In hope whereof I leaue to thee, aud after thee to them what so euer I possesse: And on condition heereof I forgiue both them and thee all the wronges which you haue doone mee: But if you f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ile heerein; then, when my soule shall at the seauenth Angels sounde, take againe this my bodie and you be cited before the impartiall Tribunall of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> deuine maiesty, I wil accuse you as guiltie of them all chiefely of my death, whereof you ioyntly are the causers; death which I imbrace so willingly, that could Nature for my wordes disclame hir due, and the inexorable desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, for my laments reuerse their dome, limiting to my dayes a longer date; yet woulde I inforce death, by not suing for longer life: And dye I must, for now I fainte euen vnto death; nowe faile my powers: nowe doth each sence denye his seruice; And gratious heauen seeming to exhale my soule, will resume it
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:5640:26"/>
whence I receiued it: farewell <hi>Valeria,</hi> thinke on my wordes, as God shall thinke on thee. This saide hee, and seald it with a sigh; then after many groanes yeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the ghost: rendring his spirit to his maker.</p>
            <p>But his body was no sooner <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>thlesse, then <hi>Iockey</hi> was turned to his shiftes: whose good seruice, had not his kinde maister secretly guerdonized before his death, doubtlesse his estate had beene very harde. <hi>Valeria,</hi> though hauing cleene forgotten hir husbandes wordes, which shee markte no longer, then while hee spake them, prouided yet for his buriall in the best sorte; and so much the rather, because in his decease shee io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the fulnesse of hir own desires.</p>
            <p>His corpes was with funerall pome conueyed to the Church: And there sollemnly enterred; nothing omitted which necessitie or custome coulde claime; A sermon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> banquet, and like obseruations. Haueing thus laide him, where shee wisht him long before, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hee was nowe a lustie widowe, and courted by that crue of gallantes, whose braueries in hir husbands lifetime shee had vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held, dreining out the quintessence of his bagges to gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishe with gay robes their backes. But <hi>Arthemio</hi> whose haruest of farre greater hopes then these, was nowe come, which he so long had loockt for, and in regarde thereof woulde not with the rest make profit of hir for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer prodigalitie: seeing nowe time and occasion smy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>acked not his affayres, but to preuent the first in forwardnesse, and sooner then in reason he should, immediatly on <hi>Giraldos</hi> buriall, sued for accesse, which finding as hee expected, and for his more incoragement veweing in his mistris countenance, no cloudes of discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, he thus began his wooing.</p>
            <p>It is a custome still in vse with christians, to attend the funerall of their deceased friendes with whole
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:5640:27"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of choyce quire-men, singing solemnly before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but behinde followes a troope all clad in blacke, which ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues mourning: much haue I marueled at this ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, deeming it till now, some hidden paradox, confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thus in one, things so opposite as these signes of ioy and sorrowe. But your late good fortune, inforst me to cancell this fond opinion: for if singing do with most right belong to ioying, who may then so iustly as your selfe, set on worke a world of fingers, to celebrate the day of your recouered liberty, from the tirannous controlement of a ielous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>? To gratulate which your good happe, I haue thus aduentured, nor lesse to prosecute my owne hopes, doom'd to liue or dye at your disposing; herein resembling transformed <hi>Clitie,</hi> which as the angry Sunne doth rise or set, opens or shuts (silly Nimph) hir saffron-coloured brest: Sith then the making or marring of my hopes, doth wholly rest in you: deigne rather to quicken them by a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious regard, then to kill them by a disgratious repulse: make me rather the mirror of your clemency, then the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre of your cruelty. If you fancye any worthier then my selfe, I shall droope for my defects: yf any meaner then my selfe, you shall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> from my deserts: But ay mee, what deserts haue I to alleadge, if true affection be no deserte? This saide, he pawsd, as feeling some deeper passion: but <hi>Valeria</hi> no longer able to dissemble, thus with a smile re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plide (for weeping was alreadie out of season) Seruant (quoth she) that true affection merits fauour, reason grants; that not euer barren of desert, thy fortune shall yealde suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient proofe; whose desires I haue hitherto dieted with dismaying doubts, thereby to make tryall of thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancie: which finding each way faultlesse, I will not that through me it should be frutlesse: But to make amends for tyring so thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with long suspence, and to remu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate thy fancies loyalty, with more then lookes, I yeald wholly to thy disposing, my selfe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> substance, &amp; whatsoeuer
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:5640:27"/>
to me is deerest: Thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming was to speake, thy good hap to speede both of loue and liuing, largely able to equall thy desires with thy deserts, and be this the earnest of my true intent: here she concluded her words with kisses, sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on his lippes her loues assurance: which kindnesse he requiting, did answer them with tenfold interest: Thence stept they to the next degree of louers daliance, and so for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward while lust had force. But hauing finisht, and <hi>Valeria</hi> being now in the veine, <hi>Arthemio</hi> deeming it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to strike when the iron was hote, least fortune should not euer rest so friendly, left her not, till before sufficient witnesses, they had each to other solemnly made themselues sure: Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly after which contract, their mariage was in a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning betimes, hastily hudled vp at a lawlesse Church: whose leaning Pulpit (a monument of many yeares, but of lesse vse then a Cipher in Arethmetique) had fallen so farre at oddes with preaching, that, whether through age or igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance I knowe not, it had long beene like a bell without a clapper. The wedding thus dispatcht, shee vaunting to her selfe, her soules delightes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this her Comedies Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strophe, changing all former discontents into the fulnesse of her desires accomplishment. But how much she was decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, let the sequell shewe. Fame the swiftest euill and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uish spreader of most vnwelcome newes, had now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>Theodoros</hi> eares <hi>Giraldos</hi> death, his daughters lewdnes, her late publike infamie and second match: The hearing of which report pearsed so his heart, that he likewise full of so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, yeelded his care-weakened bodie to the bed, and thence breathlesse to the graue: when at the instant of his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, he employed some friend in writing, what himselfe thus with a fainting voice did vtter, and as his last to her, intend.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <p>DOuble murderesse, earst of thy husband, now of thy father, read what I write, and may thy heart be rent with reading, as mine through thee is rent with ruth. Is this the memorie
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:5640:28"/>
which thou wilt leaue, wherein thy name shall liue to et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall obloquy? Is this the issue of my hope when last I left thee; or of thy mothers ioy, when she had borne thee? Oh what flouds of tears would she haue shed, had she liu'd to haue seen thy leudnesse? or if the dead know what the liuing doe, how doth her soule mourne for thy sinnes excesse! deeply art thou bound to Nature which shortened herdaies by death, and so preuented thy causing likewise of her vntimely end. Hadst thou an infant suckt some fierce Hircanian Tygresse, or bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> fostered on the ridge of Pholoe by some rauenous Liones, yet couldst thou not haue thus degenerated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy kind, in more then brutish misdemeanour. Vipers dig their way to life, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the bowels of their dams, &amp; of them the females do in conception kill the males; both which to do, it is their nature. But thou against the rites of nature, &amp; thereinfar worse then vipers, quitst him with death, to whome thou owest thy life: &amp; hast likewise before brought to his end thy harmles husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, to take into thy bosome the defiler of his bed: fatall to you both be your imbraces, &amp; thou in thy g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>eatest need enforst to relie on those for succour, whom thy present iniuries do most iustly exasperate against thee: Oh whether hath passion caried me? It beseemes not dying men to ban, much lesse fathers: yet how canst thou tearme me herein cruell, being thy selfe my deaths contriuer? But whereto wast I my wordes in vaine, which will slightly passe thine ears like the weightles <hi>Cumaean</hi> writings tost each way by the dallying windes? striuing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme an hopeles reprobate, I sow with succesles labor on the sand, and will therefore refer the issue to heauens execution, whose iustice, in making him the instrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of thy wo, whom thy selfe hast made the subiect of thy lust, is now imminent &amp; will fall with greater force, then had it been before inflicted: yet wish I as a father thy speedy amendment or speedy end, that thy euils may be the lesse. And so I leaue thee to thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serts, if thou leaue not thy leud desires.</p>
                  <signed>Thy dying father slaine by thy fault, Theodoro.</signed>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:5640:28"/>This subscription himselfe did write, whose <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hand another guided: scarse had he written what he would, when hee breathed out his enfranchised soule, ending almost at one instant his life and letter: which <hi>Valeria</hi> receiuing, read without remorse, hearing likewise the manner of his death by the messenger discourst at large, yet were her eyes still tearelesse: much it was that this could worke in her one houre of melancholly, for she deemd it no <hi>decorum</hi> to blemish her yet-during pleasures with not auailing sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. But had <hi>Theodoros</hi> life beene longer and his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting later, then coulde not his wordes haue perisht thus wholly without effect: for soone after the receiuing of this letter, her preimagined ioyes failing by degrees, grewe daily lesse: and shee too late, seeing in the present issue of <hi>Arthemios</hi> former promises, nought but deceit, wished her selfe againe at her owne will, which now shee iustly wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: nor so staid her fortunes change, for to haue wanted onely herein her wish, it had beene well; or howsoeuer, not wholly ill: But (which was worse) shee beheld apparant likelihoode of farre greater imminent distresse, then were her woonted outward delights. Hee knowing well her humour by his owne so long experience, thought it better to graffe hornes on anothers head, then himselfe to beare the impression: in preuenting which misfortune hee vsde this method: To reforme her leudnesse, he restraind her li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie.</p>
            <p>That was a day of fauour wherein shee might freely walke about the house, for commonly shee was mewde vp in her chamber: her loose-taild gossips which first intic't her to folly, were warnde from approach: especially that arch-queane her greatest counsellor, to whose kindnes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe also had been indebted. Those gallant yonkers which long had fed her humor, by seruing her insatiate lust, were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ard from accesse. This was some corosiue to a wilfull wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>on, whose desire could erst brook no contradictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but these
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:5640:29"/>
are trifles, if we note her following troubles, so many and so mightie, that it past a womans patience to indure them, if any way able to redresse them. Although her walks were watcht thus narrowly (as many eyes attending her steppes as had <hi>Argus</hi> guarding transformed <hi>Io</hi>) yet he most lauish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly addicted to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, romd abroad at pleasure, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting his owne bodie and her substance on troupes of truls, whome he gorgeou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y maintained. Riches lightly gotten, are soone leudly gone, for who weighes aright the worth of them, being not wearied with paines in gathering them? Pearles did then grow most in price, when they were first purchased with the daungers of many stormes. His minde beeing thus wholly on feasting his Minions with sumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bankets, it needes must followe, that Gluttonie made way and worke for her sister Lecherie, which without her furtherance were almost forcelesse. They hauing Sirens tongues and Crocodiles teares, thereby entic'd him to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle him, and preuailed: for as the Hemlocke of Attica tempered with wine, is of all compounded poysons the most deadly: so of all enticements that is most dangerous, where wit and beautie lodg'd both in one subiect, are so employed.</p>
            <p>All this while sate poore <hi>Valeria</hi> at home, surcharg'd with sorrow, not ruminating as yet, so much on repentance of former wantonnes, as drooping through despight of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent wants: for now wrathfull heauen setting wide open the gates of vengeance, showrd downe on her sinfull head heapes of deserued euils, infinitely exceeding the number of her yeares, yet not equalling her dire-offences, whose e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state was not herein onely haplesse to be (as earst) restrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from companie, and from the libertie of her woonted walkes, but likewise in each respect most abiectly misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: her allowance in attire, and at the table, scarse the sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of what it was, and hardly fitting the basenesse of her present fortune, her lust dieted with troubles leauings: her
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:5640:29"/>
earst-imperious humor set all on soueraigntie, stoopt to the lowest steppe of slauerie; and shee that whilome control<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the master, was now subiect without redresse, to the checks and taunts of her owne seruants, which thereto authorised by <hi>Arthemios</hi> order, limited so straightly her very lookes, that had she glanc'd her eye on any, though the meanest ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, it forth with bred suspition; and that no small com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, yet must she in no sort (if louing her owne case) cast on them an angry countenance to argue her offended mind, much lesse bewray in wordes her deepe-setled discontent, least he in a fitte of furie thundering forth an Alphabet of vgly othes, should amaze her with his affrighting menaces: nor did he so containe his outrage, but oft martyring with blowes her tender bodie, left on her bruised limmes for lasting monuments the irremooueable characters of his barbarous crueltie; so to verifie the tenour of his threates, and repay with heaped measure those her markes of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse remembrance, which shee (earst-mercilesse) had lent, and laid on silly <hi>Iockies</hi> shoulders. I omit the daily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecting of former leudnesse, and <hi>Giraldos</hi> death continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally vpbraided. At the memorie of which so many mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, the silly wretch did in sighes and teares discourse her sorrowes, lamenting iustly the fortune of her change, but more the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>lly of her second choice. Now thought shee on her husbands wordes which then she weighed not, when hee spake them. Now felt shee in her selfe the issue of his too true prediction: and as the wearie Mariner seeing from farre a storme, knowen by the seas loud rore, and flocking togither of birds, prepares himselfe with courage and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to entertaine the perill: so she, whose mind weande thus from wantonnesse, reuolu'd with restlesse motion fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passed woes, and in her fortunes mappe viewd the yet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clouded tracts of following troubles, addressed her selfe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>eare quietly these deserued crosses, and made nature schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler to necessitie, but as yet womans frailty could not fully
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:5640:30"/>
digest the sower precepts, of such saint-like patience, which that she might the lesse endure, he slackt not his indeauour, still deuising by what meanes he most might vexe her; and had therefore changde his former custome into an order far more impudent: for in stead of banketting his harlots a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, he now <unclear>feastes</unclear> them at home. She was the drudge to prepare their dainties, and scarse thought worthy of the lowest roome, when all their delicats were seru'd in. Then would hee in her sight kisse his queanes and toy with them, thus daring her to impatience, that thereon he might coine some seeming cause to tyrannize with his fist: for well hee knewe, that the tongue the hearts herald, womens chiefe instrument of reuenge and ease, could then hardly or not at all by her be bridled. Continuing this custome, he once in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uited his most affected Trull, to feast her priuatly with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie cost; when after the banquet ended and the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vncouered, taking his Lute, he sang to a pleasing note this following dittie, more to crosse his wife, then to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent his wanton Mistresse.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Waue-tossing windes characterizing feare</l>
               <l>On marblefurrowes of the threatfull deepe,</l>
               <l>Rousde from their caues the lowring aire to teare,</l>
               <l>And force the welken floods of showers to weepe:</l>
               <l>(Though stormie blastes doe scatter common fire)</l>
               <l>Burne midst their stormie blastes in hote desire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wind-tossed waues which with a gyring course</l>
               <l>Circle the Centers ouerpeering maine,</l>
               <l>And dare heau'ns star-bright turrets in their source,</l>
               <l>Can yet not ease their finnie regents paine:</l>
               <l>But though the floud, the fire in nature quench,</l>
               <l>They burne amidst the flouds which them do drench.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh whereto then in drooping hearts distresfe,</l>
               <l>Shall I a silly man my thoughts conforme,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:5640:30"/>Which can no more themselues, themselues redresse,</l>
               <l>Then may some guidelesse Pinnace in a storme</l>
               <l>Encounter safely barking <hi>Scillas</hi> rocke,</l>
               <l>And safely dare <hi>Chari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> to the shocke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where force doth faile, the weaker needs must yeeld,</l>
               <l>Seing submissiue that his smart may cease:</l>
               <l>Yet maist thou gaine a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>arre more glorious field,</l>
               <l>Deigning to graunt my care-fraught hearts release.</l>
               <l>The conquest this, t'excell in sauing one,</l>
               <l>Loues irrelenting God, which saueth none.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Here <hi>Valeria</hi> all enragde and scarse able to forbeare so long, flew on y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> others face, taking with her hands such sure hold, that the bloud trickled down amaine: which seeing &amp; at sight there of insulting, she addes this bitter scorne. Now iolly mistres vanc if you list your beauties conquest. Are you that daintie peece the riuall of my right? this the face that hath wrested my husbands fancie? Then turning to <hi>Arthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mio</hi> shee thus proceeds. Bonster of inhumanitie, speake (if thou canst without remorse) wherein haue I deserued these many iniuries, this of all the most intollerable? was it for louing thee? yea therein chiefly haue I deserued them, yet not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee, which hast thence receiued thy making. Canst thou: but here <hi>Arthemio</hi> interrupted her words with blows: then pausing hee thus replide. Slanderous strumpet, say if thou canst without blushing (but that thou canst too well) what greater wrong herein sustainst thou, then thou hast of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferd to thy other husband? How then darst thou terme iustice iuiurie: but sith this sight is so offensiue, Ile hereafter to greeue thy heart, glut thine eies w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> more abhorred obiects, &amp; now tame so thy tongue &amp; deuilish fingers, that henceforth thou shalt haue cause to curse the vse of them. This said, hee fell againe to blowes, nor ceast he from beating, till shee had ceast from shrewish answering. Soone after, to effect his first menace, &amp; therin to effect the second, he proceeded more insa tiatly in heaping wrong on wrong, euen to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> carnal vsing of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:5640:31"/>
his wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> before her face, whose presence hee enforc't, making her the vnwilling baud vnto their beastlines: yet shee remembring his late outrage, the markes whereof she had yet still to shewe, bare more quietly this the greatest iniurie, then those other which he before had offered. Now had shee learnd to smooth her lookes with signes of mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, although her care-worne heart were big with malice: now did she account patience her only gaine, knowiug well that by speaking she could not only not purchase any reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, but rather make her sorowes thereby more remedilesse, his delight beeing still in doing that which most did vex her, beside the penaltie of her prating, set by him soundly on her shoulders. Loe here an instance proouing it not wholly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible to ouer-master for the time the miraculous valubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of a womans tongue: which though not fearing a bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uado of blowes, yet shuns the brunt of a maine reuenge. But howsoeuer <hi>Valeria</hi> bridling nature by necessity, could in her husbands sight dissemble her deepe sorowes, yet being alone she could not so containe her passions, but at thought of this so dire a wrong (matter enough to haue moou'd a saints pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience) she would oft thus vnrip them. O <hi>Valeria,</hi> of all the vnhappiest, thouwantest many tongues to expresse the many torments which weare thy body &amp; weary thy mind: did thy starres bode thee these miseries, or thine owne amisse breed thee these misfortunes: ah blame not them, accuse not hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of iniustice, but blame thy selfe, thy sinne, thy vicious liuing; accuse thy selfe, thy lust, thy vnlawful louing: weigh wretched woman with thy distresse, thy deserts: in the one thou shalt find thy sorows inerplicable, thy shame infinite: both knowen, neither pitied: thy selfe pointed at by passers by, if thou be seene abroad: baited with rebukes &amp; blowes, if thou remain at home: thy goods lauishly wasted to maintain the braueries of truls vsurping thy right, &amp; insulting on thy ruth: thy childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> likewise sharing with thee their portion of deserued punishme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: but in the other thou shalt see these thy miseries far lesse then thy misdeedes: what then maist thou
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:5640:31"/>
expect: ease of these euils? no no <hi>Valeria;</hi> but till death, think that thy cares shall neuer ende: And that they then may cease, nor thou bee doom'd to eternall woe, sue while thou liuest with ceaselesse intercession, else shall thy sute bee vaine: remission, if not purchast eare life be past, is sought too late.</p>
            <p>The bodyes each-sicknesse may be expelled by choyce of symples: mercy only saught with true penitence, can salue the sin-sicke soule. But what talkest thou of penitence which nere wouldst lend one minuts listning to those that thereto would perswade thee; nere humili ate with harts contrition, thy mindes hawtinesse? Nowe is the morning past, the sunne declining, the euening shadowes haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>set thee: Oh but dispaire not, leaue that to those whose hopes haue left them; Thy hopes are many; Hadst thou liued and died in wonted ease, lulde so in deepe securitie, then had thy state beene wholly desperate: But these cros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses are gentle summons to recall thee, directions to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce thy straying steppes, woundes which heale and so en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended: Learne then thy vse of these afflictions, sith to be happie, thou must be haplesse. Tufh fonde <hi>Valeria</hi> thy talke is vaine; wilt thou preach of abstinence to pyning <hi>Tantalus,</hi> of welth and pleasure to dyiug men, of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to thy impatient selfe: Thinke on thy husband and on thy father, dead through thee: on thy kindre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> iustlye hateiug thee: on thy children which still doe liue, but through thee haue nothing left: After these thinke on thy selfe, thy sinnes, thy sorrowes: Sinnes and sorrowes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable, infinite, intollerable: What is now thy Theam of patience? Where thy hopes, or whence thy helpe? Heer would shee stoppe amidst dispaire, making that hir passions periode, then in the silence of teares and sighs, act anew hir soules distresse. Once in the depth of hir meditation, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to recreate hir care-duld spirits, shee tooke hir Lute, and therto warbled with a fainting voice, this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>eight ode.</p>
            <lg>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:5640:32"/>
               <l>Hauing long reuolu'd in thought,</l>
               <l>Long vnto my selfe lamented,</l>
               <l>Since I first to sinne assented,</l>
               <l>All the ill my sinne hath wrought;</l>
               <l>Enforc'st I am with sighes to say,</l>
               <l>Myne eyes did plot my soules decay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>These all heedelesse of the harmes,</l>
               <l>Guilfull Sirens had intended,</l>
               <l>In like saults with them offended,</l>
               <l>Listning to their luring charmes:</l>
               <l>Whereby inforst, with sighes I say,</l>
               <l>Mine ears did first my soule betray.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then began each other sence,</l>
               <l>Taught by them to wrest his vse,</l>
               <l>Reauing me of all excuse,</l>
               <l>Sought to shadow sinues pretence,</l>
               <l>Whereby enforc'st with sighes I say,</l>
               <l>Mine ears did first my soule betray.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Instruments of griefe and shame,</l>
               <l>Sundering <hi>Isthmus</hi> of true pleasure</l>
               <l>Chast delights vnspotted treasure,</l>
               <l>Wracke and death of my good name;</l>
               <l>Why force you me with sighes to say,</l>
               <l>That you did first my soule betray?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But oh cease fond wretch t'accuse,</l>
               <l>Done, vndon things cannotbee:</l>
               <l>More it now concerneth thee,</l>
               <l>Other minde and means to vse:</l>
               <l>Least thou too late with sighes do say,</l>
               <l>Thy sinnes haue wrought thy soules decaye,</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:5640:32"/>Thus did shee then expresse hir humor, and ofte i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> other sorte: mean while <hi>Arthemio,</hi> which set not his minde on mourning. kept on his ryot after such a rate, that <hi>Giraldos</hi> substance was sone consum'd; and had his power matcht y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> hugenesse of his desires, not an India of wealth might haue suffizd. Now were his lands all morgag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> which with the fairest and most worth of his houshould furniture, as also his owne, and hir attyre, fell through forfeits into the hands of brokeing Usurers. Oh what a banquet was this for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whose chiefe making, springs from the marring of such vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrifts; their rising, from the ruines of silly men! These are they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hom (to omit their other titles) we may iustly terme the deuils forerunners, preparing his waies before him. For when they haue left a man as bare, as hee lefte <hi>Iob,</hi> of whose goods by Gods permission, hee made large hauocke, then takes hee his turne of entrance, to dispatch the tragedie, which these his factors (coheirs of his infernall kingdome) haue set so forward. His first plotte is to induce the sillie wretches thus turnd out of all, to doubt of diuine prouidence. Heereon hee sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestes motions of dispaire, teaching them to number their crosses with curses, and in this humor packes them away, some to the beame, some to the water, each to a desperate end. If hee meete with lighter spirits, not thus incombred through melancholly, nor setting their misfortunes so neer the heart, but resolute to liue maugre fortunes frownes, These he fashions for his purpose in another mould, fitting them with a method for vnlawfull shiftes: vnder such a Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor working wonders euen on leaden wits, how can there bee a dearth of bad directions, or not plenty of deuillish practises, whereto he sharpens their conceipts and corages beyond their naturall promptnesse? of this seconde forte <hi>Arthemio</hi> within fewe monethes became a member; Loe here the issue: for sone after, his house growing queasie sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macht through a long consumption of the moueables,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:5640:33"/>
did in a generall vomit spewe out the master, the mystris, and all their traine, Oh whereto in this distresse should poore <hi>Valeria</hi> betake hir selfe? Mony shee had none, shoulde shee borrowe, who would lend hir, or vouchsafe hir one nights lodging? such was y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> rumor of hir leauonesse: should shee begge? who would giue hir? I omit her natiue hautinesse, hir education and former state, all abhorring so abiect a profession. But necessitie which tames the mightiest, had sone mastered hir afflicted minde, inforcing hir to craue of those, which before had crau'd of hir: yet found shee none, which would in wordes, pitie hir woes; A slender comfort, but such as other wretches haue. O you whome sinne charming with securitie, veiles from your eyes the sequels of your shame and sorrow: you which trace <hi>Valerias</hi> steppes in all lasciuiousnesse, hether I summon you to read with sighs, in these hir fortunes sad recordes, your owne fore-threatned ruine. This is the looking glasse which more beseemes you, then that whereon you daylye poore, practising your alluring lookes, and marshalling your bodies pride, thereby toattract more gazers on your garishnesse. Had I the mellisluous veine of <hi>Orpheus,</hi> rich in deuine conceipt; and garnisht with the spoyles of <hi>Helicon,</hi> whose rauishing vertue, he helde prisoner to his inchanting Hymnes and harmony: Then should I with sweete pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion treat this subiect, and, or winne your from your wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonnesse by displaying to the full <hi>Valerias</hi> woes: or prooue your hartes to be more frozen then the winter mantle of <hi>Thracian Hebrus,</hi> melting through his melodie; more stob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne then the loftie trees baring <hi>Hemus</hi> and highe <hi>Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dope</hi> to waite on him; more brutish then the sauage beasts attending him, more stony then theflinty rockes which follow'd him, for all these hee mou'd: but moue he could not those brain-sicke beldames of your sexe; which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding his harmonyous notes, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>owling noyse, tare peecemeale the sillie Poet: These only in not relenting
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:5640:33"/>
should you resemble. Looke on the crosses of this wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed creature, &amp; by them looke to your selues, turning so hir euill to some good: Weigh in what mizery shee needes must liue, whose costly robes were now changd to ragges, hir dainty fare to hard crustes, hir chambers richly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisht, to base corners, hir beauties florish blasted, more by cares then yeares. Shee which whilome scornd to looke, and almost to tread vpon the grounde; Now durst not raise thence hir blubbred eyes, fearing to looke to wards heauen, such was hir sinne: blushing to looke on men, such was hir shame. Shee which earst on highest dayes woulde keepe the house, iudging hir attyre for such times to meane (how costly soeuer) did now shame to bee seene on any day. But when night (the veile of earthes vanities) had drawne hir sable curtaines ouer the welkin, in this generall hue of horror, bereauing eyes and ears of daies obiects: See of all the most vnhappie and now wholly the guest of darknesse. wander<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> alone making musicke to hir mones, with deepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetche sighes: nor bewaild shee onely hir owne estate, but lamented likewise hir childrens distresse, iustly feard al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not knowen: for they not accompanying their care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mother, shifted for themselues, but where or how, she knew not. After many dayes of such distresse many wekes of woe, many monthes worne out in misery, it was hir hap to heere of hir man <hi>Iockeys</hi> aboade and fortune, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing maried a pore widow, kept a simple victualling house in an out part of the city: At the heereing of which newes shee was long and much perplexed, wauering in vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of resolution: For when shee weighed the caussesse wronges, which shee had offered him in wordes and blows: Howe shee had ofte incenso hir husband, ofte others, iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously to reuile and beat him, nor euer granted him one hower of quiet; See could no lesse then feare that hir repaire to him, should rather aggrauace hir present griefe, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauing some reprochfull answere, then any way attaine
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:5640:34"/>
desired case. But weighing the extreamity of hir neede, and well knowing that not imploring his reliefe, she could not any way better hir estate, but that it still grewe worse, the silly woman thus on all sides beset with sorrowes, chose rather to prosecute the slightest hope, then to continue the certainty of hir ill happe: Hauing thus resolu'd she went to seeke him, and sue to him for succor; him whom shee so much had i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ured: Loe heere the issue of hir dying fathers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ecration; which by the way calling to minde, at thought thereof, shee stream'd downe from hir pyned cheekes, show<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of salt teares.</p>
            <p>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming &amp; finding him, (which greeued to see hir in such a plight turned somwhat aside his troubled countenance) she thus bespake him. Ah <hi>Iockey</hi> deigne yet to looke on mee, and in one vewe, take thy full reuenge of all the wronges that I haue done thee: See hir miserable, which was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modest: See hir humbled at thy feete, acknowledging with teares hir causlesse fury <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ft inflicted on thy giltlesse body: ah shunne me not: I was thy mistrisse, nor scorne me that once gaue thee bread, though nowe thou seest mee baser then the meanest seruant, nor refuse I that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree if thou vouchsafe so to receaue mee. What greater tryumph on such a foe canst thou desire, then to haue hir subiect to thy checkes, and within the compasse of thy controlles, which with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> controlles and checkes (those the lightest iniuries) hath ofte wearied thy glowing eares? But sith heauen doth thus auenge on mee thy cause, let that suffice thee: oh adde not to my ruth thy rancour, Cut not my heart with dire reproches, hart so already cut with deepe cares, that almost nothing may bee added to my woes. If tyme or troubles haue not wrested from out thy memory <hi>Giraldos</hi> name, then for his sake deigne thou to suc cour me, and by his example, whose kinde affection my faults could neuer so extinguish, but that it lasted while hee liu'd. Wretch as I am, how am I blinded thus to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:5640:34"/>
plead against my selfe? louing him, thou needes must loath mee, through whom hee led a ioylesse life, and dyed sorrowing for my sinne: Whereon then shall I relye, but on the mildnesse of thy nature? If this hope doe likewise fayle mee, then whereto liue I? why are my dayes prolonged to drawe on my liues distresse. In vttering these last wordes, shee cast downe hir countenance, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hir eyes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>dfastly on the earth: but <hi>Iockey</hi> vnable to conteine his teares, therein shewing how deeply hir plaints had pierced him with remorcefull passion, did thus gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comfort hir.</p>
            <p>Had mine eares receiued from the report of others, that which mine eyes do now assure me of, I should neuer haue beleeued it. Good God, could such former wealth ende in such present want? such plenty in such penury, such bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery in such basenesse, such pleasure in such pinching woe? O Lord how righteous are thy iudgements: Yet Mistris, (for so Ile still call and accompt you, nor shall your fortune, or former iniuries cancell my duetye) I coulde wish, (if I might wish it without impiety) that this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Gods iustice had beene shewed on any other: But wee must thinke that whatsoeuer hee in his wisdome doth determine is doubtlesse for the best If you can make true vse of his correction, you shalbe happie in your vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse and these your miseries be a steppe to your fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie.</p>
            <p>That I am fory to see you in this state, my wordes and countenance may witnesse, and my greeued heart doth fele: But sith it is so, I yet reioyce that I am able by relee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing you, to shewe how deare to mee the name and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of my deceased master is: I accept you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as a welcome guest, assuring you of such enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement as I can afforde; and touching the wronges that you haue done me, I will striue so to forget them, as if I neuer had sustained them.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:5640:35"/>
This saide hee, nor saide hee more, then he perform'd, for immediatly he tooke hir into his house, where all the time of hir aboad with him (which was so long as hir selfe would tary) shee had such reliefe as his poore estate could yealde, afforded without grudging: nor did hee euer greeue hir, with the least vpbraiding of former wrongs, nor suffer, (while hee was present or knewe of it,) that shee shoulde take the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>eightest paines, more then in her owne affaires: But in his absence oft, to ease and please his wife, she would playe the tapster, and voluntarily addresse hir selfe to helpe hir in all kinde of drudgeries. While in this sort shee li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u'd, not altogether so haplesse asbefore, <hi>Arthemio</hi> no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger able to continue his shifting, sith he had thereby indan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered his life, made this his last shifte, closely to shifte him selfe away: sence when he was neuer seene about the cytie, nor almost heard of; Only some obscure reports haue past, of his long scouring the westerne plaines for pursses, and that being afterwarde apprehended, hee dyed miserably in a common <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> before his publique araignment, so pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenting the open scandall of an ignominious death. Howe so euer this bee likely in regarde of his former wicked life, yet not being thereof assured, I will suspend my censure, nor presumptuously descant of the vnknowen proceedings of the almighty. But <hi>Valeria</hi> after long residence with <hi>Iockey,</hi> at last, whether hoping on some better place, or loath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually to trouble him, sith no way able to requite his kindnesse, fondly left him and thereby rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ung'd hir selfe into hir former miseryes, falling in the ende to lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle better then open beggery: from which so abiect state of life, shee nere recouered till death gaue truce to hir di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresses: death wherein only shee was not haplesse; But if to wretched people the preuenting of any sorrow may bee term'd good happe, then so was hirs, in notsecing hir suruiuing childrens miserable endes, such as their disso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute bringing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y, did euer threaten, and their leaud cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:5640:35"/>
iustly merit: of these the elder flying for some offence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the seas, and there following armes in the ciuill tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults of distracted <hi>Belgia,</hi> but soone staining the most ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable profession of a souldier by playing the traitour, had his deserts paide with the halter, and therein leaping desperately from the ladder, he tooke his iourney into the other world. The yonger confirmd so in the loue of head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strong libertie through his corrupt education, that hee could not long brooke any seruice: succourd by none, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>sdaining subiection to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>l; died in the fieldes, and there lay a loathsome spectacle; for his stinking car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kasse had no other couerture then he auens vast circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, and his vnburied limmes were seazed on by raue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous birdes, who therewith glutted their carrion gorges. Somewhat before his last gaspe with an oft interrupted voice, he faintly groned out these bitter mones. O whither shall I turne me, whereon shall I hope, or what shall I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire? my bones ake, my bowels gnawe, my feet rot, each limme doth shiuer, and my whole bodie is full of paine: life I loath thee, life when lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> thou me? death why dallie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> thou with these delaies? why commest thou in such de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s of torments? thy messengers are more terrible then thy selfe: yet come not death, least in exchange of these my present wees, thou plunge me in eternall woe.</p>
            <p>O sinne, how sweet is thy beginning, how sower thy end? O father, but enough of thee, for thy name doth cut my soule anew. O mother, but too much of thee, cruell through immoderate kindnes: O vnhapie brother, but happie in respect of me: for though thy end were likewise shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, yet was thy carcasse couered with earth: but mine must lie still in this stinking place, to pollute the aire, and feed the rauenous foules: yet helpe me some good man who passing by may heare my mones: giue me at least some shelter from this iniurie of the weather; vnkind men, will none relieueme? yet not vnkind, because Gods iustice
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:5640:36"/>
hardens their heartes: oh that is it, whereon when I doe thinke, I wish that I had beene borne a beast, that with my life all my miseries might ende: yet helpe mee, O my God, sith men forsake me: though hell looke for me, and I dare not looke on heauen: though my offences be innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, yet is thy mercie infinitely greater: mercie sweete Lord, father of mercie, mercie it selfe: O that my mother had taught mee to pray, when shee taught me to reuile my father: Alas, I knowe no forme of praier, saue this onely which my heart laden with anguish doth thus endite. Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie sweete Lorde, let my soule imbrace thy mercie, let thy mercie imbrace my soule. But aye me, my paines increase, life and death doe combat in my breast: this their strife doubles my torments: ah, but helles torments are farre greater. From them and these, sweet Lorde deliuer me, for in thee: Here as he faine would haue proceeded, life failing, made these his last wordes vnperfect, with whose death I end this dolorous discourse.</p>
            <p>THus (Geutlemen) haue you heard briefly related the the Tragique issue of <hi>Giraldos</hi> wooing in age, and <hi>Valerias</hi> wantonnesse in youth: Had I intituled this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, <hi>A looking Glasse,</hi> the Metaphor had not been whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly immateriall: for herein may all sortes of readers note sundry points of weight: husbandes, the daunger of too much doting: wiues in her fall, the end of lustfull follie: parents, the mightie perill of soothing their children in check-free licentiousnesse: children, the fruit of disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and vndutifull dem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>r: rash proceeders, the great difference of good and bad counsell, of honest and dishonest companie: with the danger of not imbracing the one, and not shunning the other: and that the rather, sith the force of compante, hath in the effecting of either such excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding force, according to the Italian prouerbe, <hi>Dimmi con chi tu vai, &amp; saprò quel che fai. Ictus piscator sapit,</hi> but if wee
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:5640:36"/>
account him wise, which being once hurt, doth shunne a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond hazard: how much more iustly may wee commend their wisdome, who beeing not hurt at all, but learning heedfulnes at others costes, gouerne warily themselues by noting the issue of their indiscretion: which fore-sight and good fortuue I wish vnto you all.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
