<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Teares on the death of Meliades</title>
            <author>Drummond, William, 1585-1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-05">2003-05 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20880</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7257</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105422</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841150</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841150</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5712</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A20880)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5712)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1572:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Teares on the death of Meliades</title>
                  <author>Drummond, William, 1585-1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Andro Hart, and are to be sold at his shop on the north-side of the high streete, a litle beneath the Crosse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: W. Dr., i.e. William Drummond.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>On the death of Henry Frederick, Prince of Wales.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]⁴ B² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry Frederick, --  Prince of Wales, 1594-1612 --  Death and burial --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5712:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5712:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TEARES ON THE DEATH of <hi>Meliades.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>EDINBVRGH, Printed by Andro Hart, and are to be sold at his shop on the North-side of the high streete, a litle beneath the Crosse, 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_author">
            <pb facs="tcp:5712:2"/>
            <head>To the Author.</head>
            <l>IN waues of Woe thy sighes my Soule doe tosse,</l>
            <l>And doe burst vp the Conduits of my teares,</l>
            <l>Whose ranckling wound no smoothing Baume long beares,</l>
            <l>But freshly bleedes when ought vpbraides my losse.</l>
            <l>Then thou so sweetly Sorrow makes to sing,</l>
            <l>And troubled Passions dost so well accord,</l>
            <l>That more delight thy Anguish doth afford,</l>
            <l>Then others Ioyes can satisfaction bring.</l>
            <l>What sacred Wits (when rauish'd) doe affect</l>
            <l>To force Affections, Metamorphose minds,</l>
            <l>Whilst numbrous powre the Soule in secret binds,</l>
            <l>Thou hast perform'd transforming in effect.</l>
            <l>For neuer plaints did greater pittie moue,</l>
            <l>The best applause that can such notes approue.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. W. ALEXANDER</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:5712:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TEARES ON THE DEATH of <hi>Meliades.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>O Heauens, then is it trew that thou art gone,</l>
            <l>And left this wofull Ile her losse to mone,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Meliades,</hi> bright day-Starre of the West,</l>
            <l>A Comet blazing terrour to the East:</l>
            <l>And neither that thy Spirit so heauenly wise,</l>
            <l>Nor Bodie [though of earth] more pure then Skies,</l>
            <l>Nor royall Stemme, nor thy sweete tender Age,</l>
            <l>Of cruell Destinies could quench the rage?</l>
            <l>O fading hopes! O short-while-lasting joy</l>
            <l>Of earth-borne man, that one houre can destroy!</l>
            <l>Then euen of <hi>Vertues</hi> spoyles Death Trophees reares,</l>
            <l>As if he gloried most in many teares.</l>
            <l>Forc'd be hard Fates, doe Heauens neglect our cryes?</l>
            <l>Are Starres set onely to act Tragedies?</l>
            <l>And let them doe their worst, since thou art gone;</l>
            <l>Raise whome they lift to Thrones, enthron'd dethrone,</l>
            <l>Staine Princely Bowres with blood, and euen to <hi>Gange,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In Cypresse sad, glad <hi>Hymens</hi> torches change.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Ah</hi> thou hath left to liue, and in the time,</l>
            <l>When scarse thou blossom'd in thy pleasant Prime.</l>
            <l>So falls by Northen blast a virgin Rose,</l>
            <l>At halfe that doth her bashfull bosome close:</l>
            <l>So a sweete Flourish languishing decayes,</l>
            <l>That late did blush when kist by <hi>Phoebus</hi> rayes.</l>
            <l>So <hi>Phoebus</hi> mounting the Meridians hight,</l>
            <l>Choak't by pale <hi>Phoebe,</hi> faints vnto our sight:</l>
            <l>Astonish'd Nature sullen stands to see</l>
            <l>The Life of all this All, so chang'd to be,</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:5712:3"/>In gloomie gownes the Starres about deplore,</l>
            <l>The Sea with murmuring mountaines beates the shore,</l>
            <l>Blacke Darkenesse reeles o're all, in thousand shoures</l>
            <l>The weeping Aire on Earth her sorrow poures,</l>
            <l>That in a palsey, quakes to see so soone</l>
            <l>Her Louer set, and Night burst forth ere Noone.</l>
            <l>If Heauen alas ordaind thee yong to die,</l>
            <l>Why was't not where thou mightst thy valour trie?</l>
            <l>And to the wondring world at least set forth</l>
            <l>Some litle sparke of thy exspected worth?</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Meliades,</hi> O that by <hi>Isters</hi> streames</l>
            <l>Mong sounding trumpets, fierie twinckling gleames</l>
            <l>Of warme vermilion swords, and cannons roare,</l>
            <l>Balls thicke as raine powr'd by the <hi>Caspian</hi> shore;</l>
            <l>Mong broken speares, mong ringing helmes &amp; shieldes,</l>
            <l>Huge heapes of slaughtred bodies long the fieldes,</l>
            <l>In Turkish blood made red like <hi>Marses</hi> starre,</l>
            <l>Thou ended had thy life and Christian warre!</l>
            <l>Or as braue <hi>Burbon,</hi> thou had made olde <hi>Rome</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Queene of the world, thy triumph and thy tombe.</l>
            <l>So Heauens faire face to comming worlds which reedes,</l>
            <l>A booke had beene of thy illustrous deedes.</l>
            <l>So to their nephewes aged Syres had told</l>
            <l>The high exploits perform'd by thee of olde;</l>
            <l>Townes raz'd, and rais'd, victorious, vanquish'd bands,</l>
            <l>Fierce Tyrants flying, foyl'd, kild by thy hands.</l>
            <l>And in deare Arras, Virgins faire had wrought</l>
            <l>The Bayes and Trophees to thy countrie brought:</l>
            <l>While some great <hi>Homer</hi> imping wings to fame,</l>
            <l>Deafe <hi>Nilus</hi> dwellers had made heare thy name.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:5712:3"/>That thou did not attaine these honours spheares,</l>
            <l>Through lacke of power it was not, but of yeares.</l>
            <l>A brauer youth, pale <hi>Troy</hi> with trembling walls</l>
            <l>Did never see, nor she whose name appalls</l>
            <l>Both <hi>Titans</hi> golden bowres, in bloodie fights</l>
            <l>Mustring on <hi>Marses</hi> field, such <hi>Mars</hi>-like knights.</l>
            <l>The Heauens had brought thee to the highest hight</l>
            <l>Of wit and courage, showing all their might</l>
            <l>When they thee fram'd. <hi>Ayme</hi> that what is braue</l>
            <l>On earth, they as their owne so soone should craue!</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Meliades</hi> sweete courtly Nymphes deplore,</l>
            <l>From ruddy <hi>Hesp'rus</hi> rising to <hi>Aurore.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>When <hi>Forth</hi> thy nurse, <hi>Forth</hi> where thou first did passe</l>
            <l>Thy tender dayes, [who smylde oft on her glasse,</l>
            <l>To see thee gaze] Meandring with her streames,</l>
            <l>Heard thou had left this round, from <hi>Phoebus</hi> beames</l>
            <l>She sought to flie, but forced to returne</l>
            <l>By neighbour brookes, she gaue her selfe to mourne:</l>
            <l>And as she rush't her <hi>Cyclades</hi> among,</l>
            <l>She seem'd to plaine, that Heauen had done her wrong.</l>
            <l>With a hoarse plaint, <hi>Cleyd</hi> downe her steppie rockes,</l>
            <l>And <hi>Tweid</hi> through her greene mountaines cled with flocks,</l>
            <l>Did wound the <hi>Ocean,</hi> murmuring thy death;</l>
            <l>The <hi>Ocean</hi> that roar'd about the earth,</l>
            <l>And to the <hi>Mauritanian Atlas</hi> told;</l>
            <l>Who shrunke through griefe, &amp; down his white haires rold</l>
            <l>Huge streames of teares, which changed were in floods,</l>
            <l>Wherewith he drown'd the neighbour plaines &amp; woods.</l>
            <l>The lesser brookes as they did bubling goe,</l>
            <l>Did keepe a consort vnto publicke woe.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:5712:4"/>The Shepheards left their flockes, with downe cast eyes</l>
            <l>Sdaining to looke vp to the angrie Skyes:</l>
            <l>Some brake their pipes, and some in sweete-sad layes</l>
            <l>Made senslesse things amazed at thy praise.</l>
            <l>His reed <hi>Alexis</hi> hang vpon a tree,</l>
            <l>And with his teares made <hi>Doven</hi> great to be.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Meliades</hi> sweete courtly Nymphes deplore</l>
            <l>From ruddy <hi>Hesp'rus</hi> rising to <hi>Aurore.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Chast Maids which haunt faire <hi>Aganippe</hi> Well,</l>
            <l>And you in <hi>Tempes</hi> sacred shade who dwell,</l>
            <l>Let fall your harpes, cease tunes of joy to sing,</l>
            <l>Discheueled make all <hi>Parnassus</hi> ring</l>
            <l>With Antheames sad, thy Musicke <hi>Phoebus</hi> turne</l>
            <l>In dolefull plaints, whilst Ioy it selfe doth mourne.</l>
            <l>Dead is thy Darling who decor'd thy Bayes,</l>
            <l>Who oft was wont to cherish thy sweete layes,</l>
            <l>And to a trumpet raise thy amorous stile,</l>
            <l>That flotting <hi>Delos</hi> enuied might this Ile.</l>
            <l>You <hi>Acidalian</hi> Archers breake your Bowes,</l>
            <l>Your bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dons quench, with teares blot Beauties snowes,</l>
            <l>And bid your weeping Mother yet againe</l>
            <l>A second <hi>Adons</hi> death, nay <hi>Marses</hi> plaine.</l>
            <l>His Eyes once were your darts, nay euen his Name,</l>
            <l>Where euer heard, did euery heart inflame.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Tagus</hi> did court his loue with Golden streames,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Rheine</hi> with his Townes, faire <hi>Seine</hi> with all she claimes.</l>
            <l>But ah (poore Louers) Death them did betray,</l>
            <l>And not suspected made their Hopes, his Pray!</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Tagus</hi> bewailes his losse with Golden streames,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Rheine</hi> with his Townes, faire <hi>Seine</hi> with all she claimes.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:5712:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Meliades</hi> sweete courtly Nymphes deplore</l>
            <l>From ruddy <hi>Hesp'rus</hi> rising to <hi>Aurore.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Faire Meades amidst whose grassie velvet springs</l>
            <l>White, golden, azure flowres which once were kings,</l>
            <l>In mourning blacke, their shining colours dye,</l>
            <l>Bowe downe their heades, whiles sighing <hi>Zephyrs</hi> flye.</l>
            <l>Queene of the fieldes, whose blushes staines the Morne</l>
            <l>Sweete Rose, a Princes death in purple mourne.</l>
            <l>O Hyacinthes for ay your <hi>Al</hi> keepe still,</l>
            <l>Nay, with moe markes of woe your leaues now fill.</l>
            <l>Your greene lockes Forrests cut, in weeping Mirres,</l>
            <l>The deadly Cypresse, and inke-dropping Firres,</l>
            <l>Your Palmes and Mirtles turne; from shadowes darke</l>
            <l>Wing'd <hi>Syreins</hi> waile, and you sad <hi>Echoes</hi> marke</l>
            <l>The lamentable accents of their mone,</l>
            <l>And plaine that braue <hi>Meliades</hi> is gone.</l>
            <l>Stay Skye thy turning course, and now become</l>
            <l>A stately Arche, vnto the Earth his tombe;</l>
            <l>Ouer which ay the watrie <hi>Iris</hi> keepe,</l>
            <l>And soft-eyed <hi>Pleiades</hi> which still doe weepe,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Meliades</hi> sweete courtly Nymphes deplore</l>
            <l>From ruddy <hi>Hesp'rus</hi> rising to <hi>Aurore.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Deare Ghost forgiue these our vntimely teares,</l>
            <l>By which our louing mind, though w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ares.</l>
            <l>Our losse, not thine [when we complaine] we weepe,</l>
            <l>The glistring walls of Heauen for thee doe keepe,</l>
            <l>Beyond the Planets wheeles, boue highest source</l>
            <l>Of Spheares, that turnes the lower in his course.</l>
            <l>Where Sunne doth neuer set, nor vgly Night</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:5712:5"/>Euer appeares in mourning garments dight:</l>
            <l>Where <hi>Boreas</hi> stormie trumpet doth not sound,</l>
            <l>Nor clowdes in lightnings bursting, minds astound.</l>
            <l>From cares cold climates farre, and hote Desire,</l>
            <l>Where Time's exild, and Ages ne're expire:</l>
            <l>Mong purest spirits enuironed with beames,</l>
            <l>Thou thinks all things below, t'haue bene but dreames;</l>
            <l>And joyes to looke downe to the azur'd barres</l>
            <l>Of Heauen, poudred with troupes of streaming starres:</l>
            <l>And in their turning Temples, to behold</l>
            <l>In siluer robe the Moone, the Sunne in gold,</l>
            <l>Like yong eye-speaking louers in a dance,</l>
            <l>With majestie, by turnes retire, aduance.</l>
            <l>Thou wonders th'Earth to see hang like a ball</l>
            <l>Closd in the gha<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ly Cloister of this All:</l>
            <l>And that poore m<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> should proue so madly fond,</l>
            <l>To tosse themselues for a small foote of ground.</l>
            <l>Nay, that they euen dare braue the pow'rs aboue,</l>
            <l>From this base stage of change, that cannot moue.</l>
            <l>All worldly pompe, and pride thou seest arise</l>
            <l>Like smoake thats scattred in the emptie skies.</l>
            <l>Other Hills and Forrests, other sumptuous Towres</l>
            <l>Amaz'd thou finds excelling our poore Bowres;</l>
            <l>Courts voyd of flatterie, of malice Minds,</l>
            <l>Pleasures which last, not such as reason blinds.</l>
            <l>More sweeter songs thou heares and carrollings,</l>
            <l>Whilst Heauens do dance, and quire of Angells sings,</l>
            <l>Then moldie minds could faine, euen our annoy</l>
            <l>[If it approach that place] is chang'd in joy.</l>
            <l>Rest blessed spirit, rest, satiat with the sight</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:5712:5"/>Of him whose beames (though dazeling) doe delight,</l>
            <l>Life of all liues, Cause of each other cause,</l>
            <l>The Spheare and Center where the mind doth pause:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Narcyssus</hi> of himselfe, himselfe the Well,</l>
            <l>Louer, and Beautie that doth all excell.</l>
            <l>Rest happie Ghost, and wonder in that Glasse,</l>
            <l>Where seene is all that shall be, is, or was,</l>
            <l>While shall be, is, or was, doe passe away,</l>
            <l>And nothing be, but an Eternall day.</l>
            <l>For euer rest, thy praise Fame may enroule,</l>
            <l>In golden Annales, while about the Pole</l>
            <l>The slow <hi>Boötes</hi> turnes, or Sunne doth rise</l>
            <l>With scarlet scarfe to cheare the mourning Skies.</l>
            <l>The Virgins to thy tombe may garlands beare</l>
            <l>Of flowres, and with each flowre let fall a teare.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Meliades</hi> sweete courtly Nymphes deplore</l>
            <l>From ruddy <hi>Hesp'rus</hi> rising to <hi>Aurore.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. Dr.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:5712:6"/>
            <l>OF IET, </l>
            <l>Or <hi>PORPHERIE,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Or that white stone</l>
            <l> 
               <hi>PAROS</hi> affoordes alone,</l>
            <l> Or these in <hi>AZVRE</hi> dye,</l>
            <l> which seeme to scorne the <hi>SKYE</hi>:</l>
            <l> Here <hi>Memphis</hi> Wonders doe not set,</l>
            <l> Nor <hi>ARTEMISIAS</hi> huge frame,</l>
            <l> that keepes so long her Louers Name:</l>
            <l> mak no great marble <hi>Atlas</hi> tremble with gold</l>
            <l> To please a vulgar eye that doth beholde.</l>
            <l> 
               <hi>Phoebus,</hi> the Muses, Loue, hath raised of their teares</l>
            <l> A Chrystal tombe to him where through his worth appears.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:5712:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>STay Passenger, see where enclosed lyes,</l>
            <l>Wits Paragone, and Natures daintiest frame,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Vertues</hi> faire Temple, Wonder vnto Fame,</l>
            <l>In whome was found the best Heauen could deuise:</l>
            <l>At least that part the Earth of him could claime,</l>
            <l>Of Elements combind that did arise,</l>
            <l>For as to his braue Spirit, and glorious Name,</l>
            <l>The one the World, the other fills the Skyes.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Arabian</hi> odours, Mirtles youthfull Bayes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>Roses, and that sweet floure <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ares,</l>
            <l>Spred on this stone, while I these dolefull layes</l>
            <l>Sigh forth, and wash it ouer with my teares.</l>
            <l>Then goe and tell from <hi>Gades</hi> vnto <hi>Inde,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Thou saw where Earths perfections were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>finde.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:5712:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5712:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
