<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To our very louing friends the iustices of assize for the counties of Northampton, Warwicke, Leicester, Derbie, Nottingham, Rutland, and Lincolne after our very heartie commendations, whereas His Maiestie was mooued for diuers iust and waightie considerations, to grant foorth his letters pattents for a generall collection to made within the kingdome of England, and dominion of Wales, towards the repairing of the ancient hauen of the port townes of Dunwich, Southwold, and Walberswicke in the countie of Suffolke ...</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 3 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21445</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7754.4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S794</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22410113</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22410113</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25507</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A21445)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25507)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1775:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To our very louing friends the iustices of assize for the counties of Northampton, Warwicke, Leicester, Derbie, Nottingham, Rutland, and Lincolne after our very heartie commendations, whereas His Maiestie was mooued for diuers iust and waightie considerations, to grant foorth his letters pattents for a generall collection to made within the kingdome of England, and dominion of Wales, towards the repairing of the ancient hauen of the port townes of Dunwich, Southwold, and Walberswicke in the countie of Suffolke ...</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Privy Council.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 broadside.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Barker, and Iohn Bill ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Second part of title from first five lines of text.</note>
                  <note>Signed: G. Cant., Fr. Verulam Canc., E Worcester., [and 9 others].</note>
                  <note>Dated: From Whit-hall this 12. of Iuly. 1620.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Collecting of accounts --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James I, 1603-1625.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1603-1625.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <pb facs="tcp:25507:1"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->
To our very louing friends the Iuſtices of Aſsize for the Counties <hi>of Northampton, Warwicke, Leicester, Derbie, Nottingham, Rut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and Lincolne.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter our very heartie commendations. Whereas his Maieſtie was mooued for diuers iuſt and waightie conſiderations, to grant foorth his Letters Pattents for a generall Collection to be made within the Kingdome of England, and dominion of Wales, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the repairing of the ancient Hauen of the Port Townes of Dunwich, South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wold, and Walberſwicke in the Countie of Suffolke: which being likewiſe recommended by Letters from this Board, to your beſt furtherance as a worke of great conſequence for the ſafety, and defence of that Coaſt. Information is now made vnto vs, that there are diuers ſummes of money collected in the ſeuerall Counties of England and Wales: which are detained by the Clerkes of the Peace, Church-wardens, and Conſtables, vnto whoſe hands the ſame are come. And foraſmuch as the foreſaid worke of repairing that Hauen being alreadie begunne, and with much labour and expence of great ſummes of money put in good forwardneſſe, will be in danger to be all loſt, and waſhed away with the Sea, vnleſſe ſome courſe be taken for a ſpeedie ſupplie of money to perfect the ſame: We haue thought good to pray, and require you, at the next Aſſiſes in each Countie throughout your Circuite, to giue publike and ſtrict Command to the Clerkes of the Peace, High Conſtables, and all others to whom it ſhall or may appertaine, that they faile not, at their perill, to returne, and pay in, at Fiſhmongers Hall in London, all ſuch moneys as are collected for this ſeruice, together with all the Briefes deliuered vnto them for collecting the ſame, betweene this and the end of Michaelmas Tearme next. Further, willing and requiring, all Maiors, Sheriffes, Iuſtices of Peace, Bailiffes, and all other his Maieſties Officers, to affoard their beſt aſſiſtance for the due performance of theſe directions. Of the accompliſhment wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we purpoſe to take ſuch notice, as the neceſſitie and importance of the ſeruice requi<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth. And ſo we bid you very heartily farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From Whit-hall <date>this 12. of Iuly. 1620.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your very louing friends,
<list>
                     <item>G. Cant.</item>
                     <item>Fr. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erulam Canc.</item>
                     <item>E. Worcester.</item>
                     <item>Th. Arundell.</item>
                     <item>H. Southampton.</item>
                     <item>Kellie.</item>
                     <item>Robert Naunton.</item>
                     <item>Geo. Caluert.</item>
                     <item>Fulke Greuyll.</item>
                     <item>Iul. Caeſar.</item>
                     <item>Edw. Coke.</item>
                     <item>Lyonyll Cranfielde.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed at London by Robert Barker, and Iohn Bill, Printers to the Kings moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Maieſtie. 1620.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
