<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the King, a proclamation to restraine the planting of tobacco in England and VVales</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-07">2003-07 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22216</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8622</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1566</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">20213730</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 20213730</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23832</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A22216)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23832)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1709:20, 2371:58)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the King, a proclamation to restraine the planting of tobacco in England and VVales</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Barker, and Iohn Bill ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XIX [1619]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>"Giuen at our palace of Westminster the thirtieth day of December, in the seuenteenth yeere of our reign ..."--P. [2].</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery (1709:20) and Queen's College (University of Oxford). Library (2371:58).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tobacco --  Law and legislation --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Proclamations --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James I, 1603-1625.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1603-1625.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:23832:1"/>
            <head type="illustration">
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <unclear>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</unclear>
                  </head>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>By the King.</head>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>A Proclamation to restraine the planting of Tobacco in England and Wales.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not vnknowen what dislike Wee haue</hi> euer had of the vse of Tobacco, as tending to a generall and new corruption, both of mens bodies and manners: Neuertheles it is of the two, more tolerable, that the same should bee imported amongst many other vanities and superfluities which come from beyond the Seas, then permitted to be planted here within this Realme, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to abuse and misimploy the soyle of this fruitfull Kingdome: For which purpose by Our direction, Letters of late haue bene addressed from our Councell of State, prohibiting the plantation thereof within a certaine distance of Our City of London: But entring into further consideration of the manifold inconueniences of suffering this nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishment of vice (and nothing else) as a noysome and running Weede, to multiply and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spread within this Our Kingdome, Wee are resolued vpon many and weightie reasons of State, to make the sayd Prohibition generall.</p>
            <p>For first, Wee are informed, That whereas the vse of forreine Tobacco was chiefly vented, and receiued in Cities and great Townes, where riot and excesse vseth to take place, it is now by the Inland plantation become promiscuous, and begun to be taken in euery meane Uillage, euen amongst the basest people.</p>
            <p>Secondly, We are giuen to vnderstand from diuers persons of skill and experience, That the English Tobacco, howsoeuer some doe presume or imagine by industrie and experience to rectifie it, and make it good (wherein it is easie for opinion to doe mischiefe) yet it is certeinly in it selfe more crude, poysonous and dangerous for the bodies and healths of Our Subiects then that that comes from hotter Climates; So that the medicinall vse of Tobacco (which is that that is only good in it, and to be approued) is in this kind also corrupted and infected.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Whereas Our Colonies and Plantations in <hi>Virginia</hi> and the <hi>Sommer Ilands,</hi> (being proper and naturall Climates for that plant, and the true temper thereof) receiue much comfort by the Importation therof into this Kingdome, (which is to be respected at least in the <hi>Interim,</hi> vntill Our said Colonies may grow to yeeld better and more solide commodities) Now the said Trading from thence is and will be by the Plantation within this Realme, choaked and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:23832:2"/>Fourthly, Wee doe find also, that the reason that mooued Us to interdict the planting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of neere the Citie of London, (which was in regard of the conuersions of garden grounds, and rich soyled grounds from diuers Roots and Herbes, fit for victuall and <unclear>sustenance</unclear>, vnto this harmefull vanity) extendeth likewise vnto all Cities, Townes and Uillages, and rather more, by how much the pouertie is greater there, then here aboue.</p>
            <p>And lastly, for that it doeth manifestly tend to the diminution of Our Customes, which is a thing, that although in case of good Manufactures, and necessary commodities Wee doe little esteeme, Yet where it shall be taken from Us, and no good but rather hurt thereby redound to Our people, Wee haue reason to preserue.</p>
            <p>Wee therefore intending in time to prouide a remedie for this spreading euill, which hath in a very few yeares dispersed it selfe into most parts of Our Kingdomes, doe heereby straightly charge and command all and euery person and persons of what degree or condition soeuer, That they or any of them, by themselues, their seruants, workemen or labourers, doe not from and after the second day of February next, presume to sow, set, or plant, or cause to be sowen, set or planted within this Our Realme of England, or Dominion of Wales, any sort or kinde of Tobacco whatsoeuer; And that they or any of them, shall not, or doe not hereafter main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, or continue any old stockes, or plants of Tobacco, formerly sowen or planted, but shall foorthwith vtterly destroy and roote vp the same, conuerting and imploying the ground and soyle thereof to some other lawfull vses and purposes, as to them shall seeme best, vpon paine of contempt of Our Royall commaundement, to be proceeded with according to Our Lawes, and Prerogatiue Royall with all seueritie.</p>
            <p>And therefore, for the more due execution of the premisses, Wee doe further will, require and command all Mayors, Sheriffes, Iustices of Peace, Bayliffes, Constables, and other Officers and ministers, to whom it shall or may appertaine, That they and euery of them, shall from time to time diligently and carefully intend the due and exact obseruation of this Our Royall pleasure, And that they permit not, nor suffer any thing to be done, contrary to the true intent and meaning of this Our Proclamation, but withstand the same to their vttermost power, as they tender Our seruice: And further that they take order that such offendors, labourers, or workemen, as shal persist in the sowing or planting of Tobacco, in this Our Realme or Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Wales, or in the maintaining or continuing any old stocks, or former plantations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hereafter, may be called before them, &amp; be bound in Recognizances of good summes of Our vse, to appeare in Our Court of Starrechamber, there to be prosecuted by Our Attourney ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, as contemners of Our expresse Commandement, Proclamation, &amp; Prerogatiue Royall, wherein (especially in a cause of this nature) Wee will expect, and require of all Our Subiects, their due conformitie and obedience.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at Our Palace of Westminster <date>the
thirtieth day of December, in the seuenteenth yeere of Our Reigne of Great Britaine, France and Ireland.</date>
               </dateline>
God saue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>Imprinted at London by Robert Barker, and Iohn Bill, Printers to the Kings most Excellent Maiestie.</p>
            <p>ANNO DOM. M.DC.XIX.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
