<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the King at White Hall on Sunday Nov. 17, 1667 by Richard Allestree ...</title>
            <author>Allestree, Richard, 1619-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-03">2005-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23771</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A1167</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15229</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12854681</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12854681</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94587</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A23771)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94587)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 705:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the King at White Hall on Sunday Nov. 17, 1667 by Richard Allestree ...</title>
                  <author>Allestree, Richard, 1619-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Flesher, for James Allestree ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  James IV, 7 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Temptation --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-01</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94587:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94587:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>
SERMON
Preached before
THE KING
AT
<hi>WHITE HALL</hi>
On Sunday <hi>Nov.</hi> 17. 1667. BY
<hi>RICHARD ALLESTREE,</hi> D. D.
Chaplain then in Attendance. Published by His Majestie's Command.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed by <hi>J. Flesher,</hi> for <hi>James Allestree</hi> at the <hi>Rose</hi> and
<hi>Crown</hi> in <hi>Duck-lane, Anno Dam.</hi> 1667.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:94587:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94587:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>S. JAMES IV. 7.</bibl>
               <q>Resist the Devil, and he will flee from you.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HESE words are easily resolv'd
into two parts: the <hi>first,</hi> a Duty;
and the <hi>second,</hi> to incourage the
performance, an assurance of an
happy issue in the doing it. The
1. the Duty in these words, <hi>Resist
the Devil;</hi> the happy issue in those other, <hi>he will
flee from you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the more practical and usefull handling
of these parts, I shall endeavour to doe these three
things.</p>
            <p>1. View the Enemy we are to resist, <hi>the Devil;</hi>
fee his Strengths, and what are his chief Engines,
his main instruments of battery, whereby he shakes,
and does endeavour to demolish the whole frame of
Vertue in mens lives, shatters and throws down
all Religious, holy Resolutions, and subjects men
to himself and Sin.</p>
            <p>2. See what we are to doe in opposition to all
this; and how and by what means we must <hi>resist.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:94587:3"/>
3. Prove to them that do <hi>resist,</hi> the happy issue
which the Text here promiseth.</p>
            <p>First of the first.</p>
            <p>Though no man can be <hi>tempted,</hi> (so as to be foil'd
by the temptation) but <hi>he that is drawn away by
his own Lust, and enticed,</hi> James I. 14. and all the
blandishments of this world, all the wiles and arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices
of the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>God</hi> of it, the <hi>Devil,</hi> are not
able to betray one into sin, till his <hi>own</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Lust con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive</hi>
that sin, and <hi>bring it forth;</hi> Man must be <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken</hi>
first <hi>in his own nets,</hi> and <hi>fall into that pit himself
hath digg'd,</hi> before he can become the <hi>Devil's prey:</hi>
yet Satan hath so great an hand in this affair, that
<hi>the Tempter</hi> is his <hi>name</hi> and <hi>office,</hi> Matt. IV. 3. and
the warre which is now before us is so purely his,
that we are said to fight<note n="b" place="margin">Ephes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 12.</note>, <hi>not against flesh and bloud,</hi>
(those nests and fortresses of our own Lusts) <hi>but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
Principalities and Powers, against the Rulers of
the darkness of this world, against spiritual wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses
in high places;</hi> that is, against the Enemy
here in the Text, the <hi>Devil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to bring about his ends upon us he hath
several means. The first that I shall name is</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Infidelity.</hi> With this he began in Paradise, and
succeeded by it; for he had no sooner told the
woman that she should<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. III. 6.</note> 
               <hi>not surely die,</hi> and so made
her <hi>doubt of,</hi> not <hi>believe,</hi> and consequently not <hi>fear,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:94587:3"/>
that which <hi>God</hi> had threatned, but <hi>she took of the
forbidden fruit, and she did eat, and gave it to her
husband</hi> too, <hi>and he did eat.</hi> Now if a Serpent si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
with her inclination could so quickly stagger
and quite overthrow her Faith; if she, because she
<hi>sees</hi> and <hi>likes</hi> a pleasing Object, can, in mere defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
of her own assured conviction, when the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi>
look'd her in the face, and <hi>God</hi> himself was
scarce gone out of sight, straight give credit to a
<hi>Snake,</hi> that comes and confidently gives the lie to
<hi>God</hi> her <hi>Maker,</hi> offers her no proof at all of what he
says, but onely flatters her desires with promises
and expectations of she knows not what,<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. III. 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>Ye shall
not die, but ye shall be as Gods;</hi> if in spite of
Knowledge she turn Infidel so soon and easily: 'tis
no great wonder if that Serpent do, at this distance
from Revelation, prevail on men, whose conversati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
being most with Sense, (their satisfactions also
consequently gratifying of their Sense) they do not
willingly assent to any thing but that which brings
immediate evidence and attestation of the Senses,
which the objects of our Faith do not, (especially
if it give check to and restrain those satisfactions,
as those do;) on such men, I say, that do not care,
nor use, in things that are against their mind, to
apply the Understanding close and strongly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect
on those considerations which should move
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94587:4"/>
assent, and work belief. Considerations which I
dare affirm, if with sincerity adverted to, (if there
be no improbity within to trash their efficacy, no
fensual inclination cherish'd that must hinder their
admittance, as not being able to endure to lodge in
the same breast with those persuasions,) would make
Disbelief appear not onely most <hi>imprudent,</hi> but a
thing next to <hi>impossible.</hi> But in those that give
themselves no leisure, have no will thus to advert,
'tis not strange if, <hi>through Satan's arts,</hi> in things of
this remote kind they have onely <hi>languid opinions,</hi>
which sink quickly into <hi>doubts,</hi> and by degrees into
flat <hi>Infidelity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S. <hi>Paul</hi> does fetch the rise of unbelief of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity
from hence, II Cor. IV. 3, 4. <hi>If our Gospel
be hid, it is hid to them that are lost; In whom the
God of this world hath blinded their minds:</hi> that
is, If the Christian Doctrine do not appear to be
the truth of God to any, 'tis to obstinate persons
onely, whom the Devil hath besotted so with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages
and pleasures of this world, that their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections
to these will not let the other be admitted.
For,</p>
            <p>That Carnal prejudice can cast a mist before the
mind, or that a bright and glittering Temptation of
this world may dazle it so as that it cannot see that
which is most illustriously visible, we have this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstration.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:94587:4"/>
Those <hi>Works</hi> which <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apostles</hi>
wrought, which made the whole <hi>World,</hi> that was
<hi>Heathen</hi> then, so many <hi>Millions</hi> of such distant Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
as could never meet together to conspire an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal
change in their <hi>Religions,</hi> made them yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree
to lay aside their <hi>dear Gods</hi> and their <hi>dearer
Vices,</hi> and doe that to embrace a <hi>Crucified Deity,</hi> a
<hi>God</hi> put to a vile ignominious death, as one <hi>worse</hi>
then the <hi>worst of men,</hi> and a <hi>Religion</hi> that was as
much <hi>hated,</hi> counted as <hi>accursed</hi> as that <hi>God</hi> of it,
<hi>He</hi> and his <hi>Doctrine</hi> crucified a like, and a <hi>Religion</hi>
too that had as great severities in its <hi>Commands</hi> as
in its <hi>Persecutions,</hi> that did it self <hi>enjoyn</hi> as hard and
cruel things to flesh and bloud as they that hated it
<hi>inflicted,</hi> the <hi>duties</hi> and the <hi>punishments</hi> equally seem
<hi>executed</hi> on its followers, and a <hi>Religion,</hi> whose per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances
had no retributions <hi>here</hi> but <hi>fatal</hi> ones,
no otherwise <hi>rewarded</hi> but with <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>faggot,</hi> and
whose <hi>after-promises</hi> were most <hi>incredible:</hi> Those
<hi>Works</hi> that could produce all this had certainly <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent
conviction</hi> in them; sure we are there must
be <hi>prodigie</hi> of <hi>Miracle</hi> either in the <hi>causes,</hi> or in the
<hi>effect.</hi> And yet the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pharisees</hi> are not
wrought on by them. Their carnal Prejudices would
not be removed, not by the <hi>Finger of God:</hi> the
mean and despicable, and, as to all their worldly
expectations and affections, the unsatisfying con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94587:5"/>
of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> had so clouded all his works,
and their own pride so blinded them, that they could
see no <hi>argument</hi> in <hi>Miracle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now 'tis the <hi>Devil,</hi> that <hi>God of the World,</hi> that
hath the <hi>power</hi> of its <hi>Glories,</hi> and the <hi>managery</hi> of its
<hi>temptations,</hi> who, by raising these affections, dazles
so and blinds the minds of men, that they should
not believe. S. <hi>Paul</hi> affirms it: and 'tis plain that
<hi>Vnbelief</hi> is no one's <hi>Interest</hi> but <hi>Satan</hi>'s. For it is not
<hi>Man</hi>'s. Not the <hi>Vertuous</hi> man's certainly: He's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd
as much as Happiness amounts to, to believe
there is a <hi>God,</hi> whose <hi>Cares</hi> and <hi>Providence watch</hi>
over him, whose <hi>Ears</hi> and <hi>Arms</hi> are <hi>open</hi> to him,
whose <hi>Bowells yearn</hi> for him, whose <hi>Bloud</hi> did <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase</hi>
him, whose everlasting Blessednesses do await
him. 'Tis <hi>his</hi> Interest to trust that <hi>Vertue,</hi> which
the World so scorns or pitties, was yet worthy <hi>God</hi>
should be <hi>incarnated</hi> to <hi>teach</hi> it, <hi>die</hi> to <hi>purifie</hi> us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
it, and will <hi>raise</hi> us up again to <hi>cro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> it. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
is this Unbelief <hi>Man's real Interest,</hi> abstracting
from these prejudices of Religion. For if it were
<hi>Man's real Interest,</hi> then it were every man's wisest
course to pursue that Interest. But if every man
did so, and should persuade himself into <hi>Infidelity,</hi>
and that Religion and a Deity were but <hi>dreams</hi> or
artifices, and so arrive so farr as to have <hi>no fear of
God,</hi> nor <hi>sense of Honestie</hi> or <hi>Vertue,</hi> the whole world
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94587:5"/>
must needs return into the first confusions of its
<hi>Chaos: Villany</hi> and <hi>Rapine</hi> would have <hi>right.</hi>
When those Mounds are thrown down, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
that can hinder but that <hi>every</hi> man may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<hi>break in upon</hi> and <hi>invade every thing.</hi> There is
no fence to guard thy <hi>Coffers</hi> nor thy <hi>Bed,</hi> no nor thy
very <hi>Breast:</hi> rather indeed there can be <hi>nothing</hi>
thine. This is, 'tis true, <hi>Leviathan</hi>'s <hi>state of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi>
and 'tis so indeed with the <hi>Leviathans</hi> of
Sea and Land, the wilde Beasts of the Deep and of
the Desert. But to prevent the necessary and es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sential
mischiefs of this state amongst us Men, He
will have Nature to have taught us to make <hi>Pacts</hi>
and <hi>Oaths:</hi> but if there's no such thing as <hi>Vertue</hi>
or <hi>Religion,</hi> then there is no obligation to <hi>keep</hi> Pacts
or Oaths. And <hi>why</hi> should he observe them that
can <hi>safely</hi> break them? <hi>Here</hi> it is indeed that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<hi>ends;</hi> to <hi>this</hi> their <hi>Infidelity</hi> does tend. And
therefore 'tis no Interest of <hi>States</hi> or <hi>Princes.</hi> This
the <hi>Atheist</hi> will confess; <hi>Gods</hi> and <hi>Religions</hi> were
invented for the mere <hi>necessities</hi> of Governours,
who could not be <hi>secure</hi> without those higher Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations,
and these after-fears. And are they not
<hi>kind. Subjects</hi> then who, by promoting Atheism,
labour to break down that fence which <hi>themselves</hi>
account <hi>necessary?</hi> Or are they not good rational
Discoursers too, who labour to throw out a thing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94587:6"/>
as <hi>false</hi> and <hi>vain,</hi> because 'tis <hi>necessary?</hi> So neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary
sure, that they who weaken these bonds of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi>
quite dissolve those of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> all whose
Sinews are made of those Sacred Ties, which if
you untwist, the other Cords are burst as easily as
<hi>threads of Cobweb.</hi> Nay these Doctrines lay Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples
that justifie <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>King-killing.</hi> For
if there's no such thing as <hi>Vertue</hi> or <hi>Religion,</hi> then
those are no <hi>Crimes.</hi> And it is no wonder <hi>Treason</hi>
hath been lov'd, when <hi>Blasphemy</hi> hath been so.
They that hear men <hi>droll</hi> on <hi>God Almighty, raille</hi>
their <hi>Maker,</hi> and <hi>buffoon</hi> with <hi>Him,</hi> will quickly
learn to speak with little reverence of their <hi>Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours.</hi>
There's no <hi>Kingdome</hi> but the <hi>Devil</hi>'s that
can have support from <hi>Infidelity;</hi> 'tis the Interest
of <hi>that</hi> indeed. His work goes more securely on,
when there are no religious apprehensions to check
it: <hi>allow'd Vice</hi> cannot be at ease if it but think those
things are true. It is the infinite concern of <hi>Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness,</hi>
that the Laws of Vertue and Religion should
be onely <hi>Spiders webs,</hi> Snares for <hi>innocent</hi> and <hi>lesser</hi>
flies, while <hi>venimous Spiders</hi> can pass safely
through them, and the <hi>Wasps</hi> can burst them; are
Entanglements onely for the <hi>weak,</hi> the <hi>Phlegma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi>
and <hi>Hypochondriack:</hi> and that there should be
<hi>no God</hi> that can bring them to an after-reckoning.
They that <hi>flatter</hi> and <hi>betray,</hi> that <hi>hugg,</hi> and then
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94587:6"/>
               <hi>trip up,</hi> or that plot <hi>villanies</hi> and <hi>ruines</hi> under <hi>fair</hi>
and <hi>godly vizards;</hi> must needs be unwilling to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
that there is one who<note n="a" place="margin">Jet. XVII. 1</note> 
               <hi>tries the reins,</hi> and
<hi>sea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hes hearts,</hi> and <hi>that will render every one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to his works.</hi> The <hi>Drunkard,</hi> who nor
must nor can keep the <hi>remembrance</hi> of his Cups,
cannot endure to apprehend he must be call'd to
an <hi>account</hi> of them. The man whose Lust prevents
the Grave, that putrefies alive, and drops by piece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meal
into rotten dust ere he return to earth, must
needs be loth that there should be a Resurrection,
to collect the scatter'd, the foul atomes of his Sin
and his Disease, and shew them at that dread Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal,
before <hi>God,</hi> his <hi>Holy Angels,</hi> and <hi>Mankind.</hi>
Such as these are the onely men that are <hi>concern'd</hi>
against Religion. Here we see whose Interest such
promote who promote Infidelity. And truly 'tis
so much the Devil's Interest, that by those very
measures that he weakens Faith, he strengthens eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
sort of Wickedness: by the steps and degrees
of Infidelity men ascend towards the heights of
Sin: and when they have surmounted all Religious
apprehensions, then they are upon the Precipice of
Vice. When the Floud-gates are removed, the
Torrent must break impetuously. For what is
there that can hinder? Nothing certainly, if <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
Interest</hi> be not able: But 'tis plain that <hi>Thieves,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:94587:7"/>
and <hi>Murtherers,</hi> and <hi>Rebells,</hi> in fine, every one
whom we <hi>call Sinners,</hi> do pursue that which they
account their <hi>present Interest:</hi> that therefore, if
there were no other, would not be sufficient, since
the Devil does make use of that to work with under
Infidelity. <hi>This</hi> indeed he <hi>batters,</hi> makes his
<hi>spreading ruines</hi> with: therefore S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls him
<note n="a" place="margin">Ephes. II. 2.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the spirit that works</hi> in
filiis diffidentiae, saith the Vulgar: in the <hi>unbeliev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi>
so it bears: in filiis insuasibilitatis, <hi>in the men</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oh. III. 36.</note>
               <hi>that will not be persuaded to believe.</hi> In these
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> they are his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Possest</hi> and <hi>agitated</hi>
by <hi>him:</hi> 'tis <hi>he spirits</hi> what <hi>they</hi> doe: <hi>their</hi> actions
are <hi>his</hi> incitations and motions: In summe, as to
wickedness, they are mere <hi>Demoniacks.</hi> This there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
is his chief and the first Engine.</p>
            <p>2. The second Instrument by which he does de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molish
whatsoever hopes of Vertue we are built up
to is <hi>Want of Imployment:</hi> and in order to this, he
hath so far prevail'd on the opinions of the world,
that they believe some states of men not onely have
no obligation to be busied, but to have <hi>no Calling</hi> is
essential to their <hi>condition;</hi> which is made more
eminent upon this account that they have <hi>no busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</hi>
Wealth, how great soever, if with an imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
or profession, makes a man onely a more <hi>gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile
Mechanick:</hi> But Riches and nothing to doe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94587:7"/>
make a <hi>Person of quality.</hi> As if God had made
that state of men, far the most generous part of
the whole kinde, and best appointed for the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blest
uses of the world, to serve no other ends but
what the <hi>Grashoppers</hi> and <hi>Locusts</hi> do, to sing and
dance among the Plants and Branches, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
the fruits; and Providence had furnish'd them
with all advantages of plenty for no better pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses.
Such persons think not onely to reverse
<hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Curse,</hi> and <hi>In the sweat of others faces eat their
bread,</hi> but reverse <hi>Nature</hi> too; for <hi>Job</hi> saith,<note n="a" place="margin">Job V. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Man
is born to labour, as the sparks flie upwards;</hi> in his
making hath a principle to which <hi>Activity</hi> is as es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sential
as it is to fire to <hi>mount;</hi> from which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
else but force can hinder it: As if man did
<hi>doe violence</hi> to his making when he did <hi>doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;</hi>
and it were his hardest work and pressure,
not to be imploy'd; it were like making <hi>flame go
downwards.</hi> I am sure, it is one of the busiest ways
of doing <hi>Satan</hi>'s work. Our Saviour in a Parable
in the XII. Ch. of S. <hi>Matt.</hi> from the 43. v. saith,
<hi>When the unclean spirit is gone out of a man, he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
through dry places, seeking rest, and findeth
none:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 44.</note> 
               <hi>Then he saith, I will return into my house
from whence I came out; and when he is come, he
findeth it empty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">45.</note> 
               <hi>swept, and garnished. Then goeth
he, and taketh with himself seven other spirits more
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94587:8"/>
wicked then himself, and they enter in and dwell
there.</hi> Where, under the Similitude of a man cast
out of his habitation, who, while he wanders
through none but desert places seeking for a dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
he is sure to meet with none; but if he finde
an house that's empty, swept and garnish'd, he hath
found out not a receptacle onely, but an invitation,
an house drest on purpose to call in and to detain
inhabitants: He signifies, that when a Temptation
of the Devil is repell'd, and himself, upon some
working occasion, by a resolute act of holy courage
thrown out of the heart; as he finds no rest in this
condition, every place is <hi>desert</hi> to him, but the
Heart of man is indeed <hi>Hell</hi> to him, for he calls it
<note n="a" place="margin">Matt. VIII. 29.</note> 
               <hi>torment</hi> to be cast out thence, yea he accounts
himself bound up in his eternal chains of<note n="b" place="margin">Luk. VIII. 31.</note> darkness,
when he is restrain'd from working and engaging
man to sin; so, while he goeth to and fro, seeking
an opportunity to put in somewhere, if he finde
that heart from which he was cast out, or any other
heart, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (so the word is,) idling, not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd
or busied, (so it signifies,) such an heart is
<hi>empty, swept,</hi> and <hi>garnish'd</hi> for him, 'tis a dwelling
that's drest properly to <hi>tempt</hi> the Devil, fitted to
receive <hi>him</hi> and <hi>his forces</hi> too, prepar'd for him to
<hi>garrison,</hi> and make a <hi>strong hold</hi> of, whence he
cannot be remov'd; <hi>for he takes unto him seven
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94587:8"/>
other spirits more wicked then himself, and they enter
in and dwell there.</hi> No doubt they are the <hi>Patron-Guardian
spirits</hi> of the seven deadly sins, their <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telary
Devils.</hi> Some of those good qualities that are
the attendants of Idleness you may finde decy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher'd
in the Scripture. S. <hi>Paul</hi> says, when people
<note n="a" place="margin">I Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> V. 13.</note> 
               <hi>learn to be idle,</hi> they <hi>grow tattlers, busie-bodies,
speaking things which they ought not.</hi> 'Tis strange
that Idleness should make men and women <hi>busy-bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi>
yet it does most certainly in other folks af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs.
<hi>Faction,</hi> then which nothing in the world
can be more restless, is nurst by it. Where are
States so censur'd, so new-modell'd, as at certain
of our <hi>Refectories,</hi> places that are made merely for
men to spend their time in which they know not
what to doe with? At those Tables our Superiours
are dissected; Calumny and Treason are the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,
are indeed the more peculiar entertainments
of the places. In fine, where persons have no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
employment for their time but <hi>talking,</hi> and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
have not so much Vertue as to finde delight in
talking good things, or not so much skill as to
speak innocent recreation, there they <hi>talk of others,
censure,</hi> and <hi>back-bite,</hi> and <hi>scoffe.</hi> This is indeed
the onely <hi>picquant</hi> conversation; <hi>Gall</hi> is <hi>sawce</hi> to
all their entertainments: and that you may know
these things proceed from that <hi>old Serpent,</hi> they doe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94587:9"/>
nothing else but <hi>hiss</hi> and <hi>bite.</hi> 'Tis the<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>I. 13.</note> 
               <hi>poison of
Asps that is under their lips</hi> which gives <hi>relish</hi> to
their discourses; 'tis the <hi>sting</hi> that makes them
<hi>grateful, veni ne</hi> that they are <hi>condited</hi> with.</p>
            <p>More of the brood of this want of Imployment
you may finde at <hi>Sodome;</hi> namely, <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ury:</hi>
for saith <hi>Ezekiel,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Ezek. XVI. 49.</note> 
               <hi>This was the iniquity of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome;</hi>
               <hi>Pride, fulness of bread, and abundance of Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
was in her and in her daughters.</hi> And indeed
the idle person could not possibly know how to
passe his hours, if he had not <hi>Delicacies</hi> to <hi>sweeten</hi>
some, <hi>Wine</hi> to <hi>lay</hi> some <hi>asleep,</hi> and the solicitous
deckings of <hi>Pride</hi> to take up others: But the stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious
gorgings of the inside, and the elaborate trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings
of the outside, help him well away with
them.</p>
            <p>Good God! that for so many hours my morning
eyes should be <hi>lift up</hi> to nothing but a <hi>Looking-glass!</hi>
that that thin <hi>Shadow</hi> of my self should be
my <hi>Idol,</hi> be my <hi>God</hi> indeed, to which I pay all the
devotions I perform! And when with so much care
and time I have array'd and marshall'd my self, that
I should spend as much more too in the compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencies
of viewing this! with eager eyes and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite
surveying every part, as if I had set out, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd
them to my self alone, and onely drest a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect
for my own sight! and since Nature, to my
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94587:9"/>
grief, hath given me no eyes behinde; that I should
fetch reliefs from Art, and get vicarious sight, and
set my back parts too before my face, that so I may
enjoy the whole scene of my self! And why all
this? for nothing but to serve vain <hi>Ostentation,</hi> or
negotiate for <hi>Lust,</hi> to dress a <hi>Temptation,</hi> and start
<hi>Concupiscence.</hi> And that the half of each day should
be spent thus! the best part of a reasonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture's
and a Christian's life be laid out upon
purposes so farr from Christian or reasonable!</p>
            <p>And truely <hi>Luxury</hi> will easily eat the remainder
up, that sure companion of Idleness. For when
the <hi>Israelites</hi> were in the Wilderness, where they
could not <hi>eat</hi> but by <hi>Miracle,</hi> and the <hi>Rock</hi> must
give them <hi>drink;</hi> yet, having no imployment,
they <hi>made Feasls:</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Exod. XXXII. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>They sate down to eat and drink,
and rose up to play.</hi> Nor would eating to the uses
of their <hi>nature</hi> serve them, but they must have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainments
for their wantonness. Had they been
imploy'd to get their bread, their labour would
have made their morsells sweet: but since <hi>God,</hi> as
the Wise-man saies, <hi>sent them from Heaven bread
prepar'd without their labour,</hi> they must have va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties
to sweeten it; they require <hi>him</hi> to<note n="b" place="margin">Psal. LXXVIII.</note> 
               <hi>prepare
a Table</hi> also <hi>in the wilderness,</hi>
               <note place="margin">19.</note> and furnish them with
choice.<note place="margin">25.</note> And although they had the <hi>food of Angels,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Wised. XVI. 20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>able to content every man's delight, and agreeing to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94587:10"/>
every tast, and serving to the appetite of the eater,
it temper'd it self to every man's liking,</hi> and what
could they fansy more? the latitude of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
the whole Universe of Luxury could doe
nothing else; in every single morsell they had sorts,
Variety, all choice; as if that <hi>Desert</hi> had been
<hi>Paradise,</hi> that <hi>Wilderness</hi> the <hi>Garden of the Lord:</hi>
Yet so coy is Idleness, so apt to nauseate, that they
abhor the constancy of being pleas'd. And though
they were not sated neither,<note n="a" place="margin">Exod. XVI. 18.</note> 
               <hi>he that gather'd much
had nothing over,</hi> onely <hi>to his eating,</hi> God as well
providing for their <hi>Health</hi> and <hi>Vertue,</hi> as <hi>necessity,</hi>
and dieting their <hi>Temperance</hi> as he did their <hi>hunger:</hi>
yet their very <hi>liking</hi> does grow <hi>loathsome</hi> to them.
When their bodies were thus excellently well provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
for, having no imployment, nothing to take up
their <hi>minds</hi> and entertain their <hi>Souls,</hi> they require
<note n="b" place="margin">Psal. LXXVII. v. 18.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>meat for their Souls,</hi> meat not to serve
the uses of their <hi>bodies,</hi> but to feed their <hi>fancies,</hi>
their extravagant <hi>minds.</hi> Thus <hi>Idleness</hi> requires to
be <hi>dieted.</hi> And all this but to pamper and feed
high mens inclinations, so to make Temptations
<hi>irresistible,</hi> and by consequence <hi>Vice necessary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It were easie to recount more of those ways by
which the Devil does make use of mens <hi>want of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment</hi>
to debauch their lives, and ruine all the
hopes of Vertue in them. S. <hi>Jude</hi> finds more of its
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94587:10"/>
effects at <hi>Sodome:</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Ver. 7.</note> 
               <hi>They gave themselves over to
Fornication, and went after other flesh, and are set
forth for a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> example, suffering the vengeance of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
fire.</hi> Indeed these are most certain consequents
of not being imploy'd: <hi>Quaeritur Aegysthus</hi>—is
too known an instance: and<note n="b" place="margin">II Sam. XI. 1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>great, Holy David</hi>
is another. But its dire influence is sufficiently vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible
in that which it rain'd down upon those Cities.
Since it did fulfill the guilt of <hi>Sodome,</hi> and made
<hi>Heaven</hi> furnish <hi>Hell</hi> for it, and <hi>God</hi> himself turn
Executioner of <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>brimstone</hi> to revenge it;
this shall serve to prove it is one of the Devil's
Master-pieces.</p>
            <p>3. Next succeed his<note n="c" place="margin">Ephes. VI. 16.</note> 
               <hi>fiery darts,</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls
them, namely, <hi>Persecutions,</hi> or <hi>Calamities</hi> of any
kind: which he manageth either by inflicting pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures;
and he was so confident of the force of those,
that he did tell <hi>God</hi> he would make<note n="d" place="margin">Job I. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Job curse him
to his face</hi> with them: or if he find men in necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
and pressures, then by tempting them to get
from under them by methods which he shall direct;
and he had such assurance of the strength of this
Temptation, that by it he try'd our Saviour, to find
out whether he were the<note n="e" place="margin">IV. Matt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Son of God</hi> or no, belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
none but he that was so would be able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist
it.</p>
            <p>Indeed the trials are severe which this Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94587:11"/>
does present, to draw men from their Duty, and
to overcome their Constancy: whether it solicite
by inflicting punishment, (as on the Mother and
her Children, II <hi>Maccab.</hi> VII.) or by offering to
withdraw it, if they will submit to their unlawfull
terms, (and so they try'd her youngest son there,
ver. 24.) or at leastwise by some feigned act, some
ambiguous words or practices, will pretend compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
(so they dealt with <hi>Eleazar,</hi> Chap. VI. 21.
whom they would have had to bring flesh of his
own provision, such as he might use without offence,
and so onely seem to eat forbidden meat.) Each of
which is as great a trial also, and to stand against
them reckon'd up amongst as vigorous acts of
Faith, as those that held out in the greatest tortures
persecuting malice could invent: <hi>Heb.</hi> XI. 37. <hi>They
were ston'd, sawn asunder, were tempted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to fetch an instance of the sad success of
these, I shall not need to go so farr as to those Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions
of <hi>Antiochus:</hi> nor those of the <hi>primitive times
of Christianity;</hi> when they had no other choices but
these, to deliver up their <hi>Bibles</hi> or their <hi>Lives;</hi> either
to <hi>sacrifice</hi> to <hi>Idols,</hi> or at least procure a <hi>Ticket</hi>
which should certifie that they had done it, or to
be themselves an <hi>Holocaust,</hi> and give those Idols a
<hi>Burnt-offering</hi> with their <hi>martyr-flames.</hi> Which
made the <hi>Traditores, Lapsi,</hi> the <hi>Thurificati</hi> and the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94587:11"/>
               <hi>Libellatici</hi> to be so numerous. Through God's
blessed mercy there is no use of such instances, as
there is no fear of such a trial; 'tis not death to be
a Christian now: For if the <hi>Son of man</hi> or <hi>Satan's</hi>
self should come to try us at those rates, 'twere a
great doubt whether the one or other would<note n="a" place="margin">Luke XVIII. 8.</note> 
               <hi>find
Faith upon the earth;</hi> whether they would sacrifice
a <hi>life</hi> to our Religion, who are not content to sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
a little <hi>interest</hi> or <hi>pleasure</hi> to it; whether they
are likely to<note n="b" place="margin">Heb. XII. 4.</note> 
               <hi>resist unto bloud fighting against sin,</hi>
who will not resist to <hi>tears</hi> nor <hi>sober resolutions.</hi>
Alas! what Religion should we be of, if God should
raise a <hi>Diocletian,</hi> come to tempt us with the <hi>fiery
trial? Martyrs</hi> as we are to nothing but our <hi>Passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
and our <hi>Lusts!</hi> Nor shall I produce more
known and near experiences, when, by reason of
such <hi>storms</hi> of Persecution, men <hi>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e shipwreck,</hi> if
not <hi>of their Faith,</hi> yet of good Conscience. When
by order or permissions of Providence they were
brought to such a streight, that either they must let
goe their <hi>possessions</hi> or their <hi>honesty,</hi> acting against
Principles, and conscience of Duty; I shall not
remember, how, when <hi>God</hi> did shake his angry hand
thus over them, they fled to the <hi>Devil</hi>'s kindness,
and made <hi>Hell</hi> their refuge, to save them from their
<hi>Father's rod:</hi> how they grew so <hi>Atheistical,</hi> as to
believe a Perjury or other crime greater security,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94587:12"/>
that would preserve their selves and their condition
better then all God had promis'd; were such <hi>infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels,</hi>
that they did rather trust their being here to
the commission of a sin, then to the Providence and
the Engagements of the Almighty. For indeed
what need I instance in these greater cases, where
the trial was so sharp, as not to offer any easier
choice then this, either to part with <hi>Conscience</hi> or
with <hi>all they had?</hi> God knows, we find less Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rests
will doe: The Devil by no more then this,
driving the <hi>Gadarens swine</hi> into the Sea, was able to
drive <hi>Christ</hi> out of their coasts. You have the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
VIII. <hi>Matt.</hi> from the 28 ver. A legion of those
evil spirits did possess two men; and finding <hi>Christ</hi>
would cast them out, and by that Miracle so farr
shew forth his power, that in probability the whole
Countrey would believe on him, they fall upon this
project to prevent it; they besought him, if he would
cast them out, to suffer them to goe into an herd of
swine there feeding; hoping by destroying them
to incense the owners against <hi>Christ:</hi> and, to try
them, he permitted this. The possess'd swine ran
violently down into the Lake, and perish'd. Now
a man would think the virulency of these Devils,
which were so destructive when they were at liberty
and not restrain'd, would have endear'd the mercy
that had cast them out of the poor men, and came
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94587:12"/>
to dispossess the Countrey of them; and that their
astonishment at so great a Miracle would possess
them all with reverence and belief of him; and
that they would therefore seise and possess him also,
and not let the mercy goe: But, on the contrary,
the whole City and Countrey came out to meet <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus,</hi>
and, in consideration of the loss of their swine,
desire him to depart out of their coasts. Lo here an
equal enemy to <hi>Christ</hi> and all his Miracles, that was
indeed too hard for them. The Senate of Hell had
no project to keep out Religion like to this, to make
Religion thwart an Interest. Rather no Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
then lose an Earthly satisfaction by it: <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
have the swine then Christ himself.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. But if he chance to fail in this Assault, (as by
our Saviour he was beaten off) he hath yet a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve,
in which he places his last, strongest confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence;
with which he ventured to charge <hi>Christ,</hi>
when it is probable he knew He was the <hi>Son of God.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">IV. Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>He takes him up into an high mountain, and
shews him all the Kingdomes of the earth in the
twinkling of an eye, and the glory of them, and
says, All these things will I give thee.</hi> He thought
it was impossible for such a prospect not to make
impression on the appetite, raise some desire, or stir
one Covetous or Ambitious thought: which if it
could but doe, he made no scruple then to clog the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94587:13"/>
Gift with such conditions as that there, <hi>All these
things will I give thee, if thou wilt fall down and
worship me.</hi> 'Tis said indeed, the<note n="a" place="margin">Eph. V. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Covetous man
is an Idolater:</hi> and here we see the <hi>God</hi> he does doe
<hi>homage</hi> to, and <hi>worship.</hi> The <hi>Devil</hi> does require,
that those whom he gives wealth to, (now 'tis <hi>he</hi>
that gives it to the <hi>Covetous,</hi> to all indeed that get it
with <hi>injustice</hi> or with <hi>greediness;</hi>) he requires, I
say, that these should pay all their Religion to Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self:
and the <hi>Ambitious,</hi> in however high a place
he sets them, must <hi>fall down to him.</hi> And truly
these two dispositions can give worship to no other
God but such an one as is<note n="b" place="margin">Revel. X. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Abaddon,</hi> the Destroyer
of Mankind. For all the great Commotions of the
world, all those Convulsions that tear Provinces
and Empires, all Seditions and Rebellions, with
those armies of iniquities that attend them, and that
wage their designs, which are upheld by legions of
villanies as well as men, all the Disturbances of
States and Church, are but attempts of Covetous
and Ambitious spirits, men that are unsatisfied with
their condition, and desire a change, and care not
how they compass it: they can charge through
seas of bloud and sin, over the face of men and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science,
to get out of that condition, which they
therefore are not well content with, because some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
they like better beckens their ambitious and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94587:13"/>
their covetous desires. Would you see what one
of these will venture at? When <hi>Christ</hi> our Saviour
was to be betray'd, when a Person of the Godhead
was to be deliver'd up and crucified, the Devil had
no passion to imploy on that design so fit as the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire
of getting money;</hi> and when that desire was
once entertain'd, we see he enters<note n="a" place="margin">John XIII. 2, 27.</note> 
               <hi>really</hi> in <hi>person,</hi>
and <hi>possesses</hi> such a soul; and when he is there, he
designs no farther but to warm and stir that passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
'tis sufficient fruit of his <hi>possession,</hi> he hath
done enough in such an heart wherein he <hi>dwells,</hi> if
he but keep alive that desire of money: for he
knows that will make the man adventure upon any
guilt; for it made <hi>Judas</hi> undertake to betray <hi>Christ.</hi>
And as for the other passion which the Devil did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign
the glories of his prospect to give fire to, though
he could not stir it in our Saviour, yet he knew it
vanquisht him himself when he was <hi>Angel.</hi> What
height is there which <hi>Ambition</hi> will not flie at, since
it made this Spirit aim at an equality with the
<note n="b" place="margin">Isa. XIV. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Most High?</hi> Heaven it self was not sufficient to
content him, while there was a God above him in
it. And since this affection peopled Hell with
<hi>Devils,</hi> 'tis no wonder if it people Earth with <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series</hi>
and <hi>Vices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. The remaining Trial with which Satan did
assault our Saviour, when he tempted him with
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94587:14"/>
               <note n="a" place="margin">IV. Matt. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>God's Promises,</hi> and sought to <hi>ruine</hi>
him with his <hi>own Priviledges:</hi> with that also</p>
            <p>6. His being a <hi>lying spirit in the mouth of all the
Prophets;</hi> by which long ago he did destroy an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab,</hi>
in the I <hi>Kings</hi> XXII. 22. But since by sad expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience
we know, he ruin'd the best <hi>King,</hi> purest
<hi>Church,</hi> and most flourishing <hi>State,</hi> by the same
stratageme. But these, with those other which
S. <hi>Paul</hi> does call his<note n="b" place="margin">Eph. VI. 11.</note> 
               <hi>wiles,</hi> I must omit; suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
hath been said already to inforce the necessity
of <hi>resisting,</hi> which is the <hi>Duty,</hi> and the next con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Resist the Devil:</hi> that is, do not you consent to
his Temptations: for there is no more requir'd of
us, but this onely, not to be willing to be<note n="c" place="margin">II Tim. II. 26.</note> 
               <hi>taken,</hi>
and <hi>led captive by him.</hi> For let him <hi>suggest, incite,
assault</hi> and <hi>storm</hi> us, no impression can be made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
us till we <hi>yield,</hi> and till we <hi>give consent</hi> no hurt
is done. It is not here as in our other warrs: In
those no resolution can secure the victory, but not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding
all resistence possible, we may be van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisht;
yea, sometime men are overprest and die
with conquering, and the Victor onely gains a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument,
is but buried in the heaps of his slain Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies.
But in these warrs with the <hi>Devil,</hi> who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever
is <hi>unwilling</hi> to be vanquisht, <hi>never can</hi> be:
for he must first <hi>give consent</hi> to it, and <hi>will</hi> the ruine:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94587:14"/>
for men do not sin <hi>against their wills.</hi> Onely here
we must distinguish betwixt <hi>Will,</hi> and then <hi>Velleity</hi>
and <hi>Woulding.</hi> For let no man think when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits
deliberate iniquity with averseness and relu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctancy
of mind, allows not what he does, but does
the evil that he would not, what he hates that he
does; that this is not to be imputed to the Will,
that in this case he is not willing, but here the <hi>spirit
is willing, but the flesh is weak,</hi> and yields through
mere infirmity: For, on the contrary, the Devil
finds the flesh so strong in this case, that with it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone
he does assault the mind, and breaks through
its reluctancies and aversations, bears down all its
resolutions, triumphs over all that does pretend to
<hi>God</hi> or <hi>Vertue</hi> in him. Where 'tis thus, let no man
flatter or persuade himself he <hi>does what he would
not,</hi> when it is plain he does impetuously <hi>will the
doing it.</hi> Let him not think that he <hi>allows not,</hi> but
<hi>hates</hi> that which he does; when it is certain, in that
moment that he does commit, not to <hi>allow</hi> that
which he does <hi>resolve</hi> and <hi>pitch upon</hi> and <hi>chuse,</hi> to
<hi>hate</hi> what with <hi>complacency he acts,</hi> or to <hi>doe</hi> that
<hi>unwillingly</hi> which he is wrought on by his own <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiscence</hi>
to doe, and by his <hi>inward incitations,</hi> by
the mutiny of his <hi>own affections,</hi> which the Devil
raises, and when it is the mere <hi>height</hi> and <hi>prevalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie
of his appetite</hi> that does make him doe it, (as it
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94587:15"/>
must be where there is reluctancy before he doe it,
his desires and affections there are evidently too
strong for him,) or at last, to <hi>hate</hi> the <hi>doing</hi> that
which 'tis his <hi>too much love</hi> to that makes him <hi>doe;</hi>
are all impossibilities, the s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me things as to <hi>will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
the will, desire against appetite.</hi> But do but keep
thy self sincerely and in truth from being willing,
and thou must be safe: For God expects no more
but that we should not voluntarily yield to our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing.
He hath furnisht us with his own com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat
armour for no farther uses of a warre, but to
encourage us to <hi>stand.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Eph. VI. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Take unto you the whole
armour of God, that ye may be able to stand against
the wiles of the Devil:</hi>
               <note place="margin">13.</note> and again, <hi>Put ye on the
whole armour of God, that ye may be able to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand
in the evil day, and having done all, to stand.</hi>
There is no need to doe more then this, not to be
willing and consent to fall; for no man can be
beaten down but he that will fall.</p>
            <p>It were very easie for me to prescribe you how
to fortifie against those Engines of the Devil's bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery
which I produc'd to you. But that I may not
stay upon particulars, directing those whom he
prevails upon through <hi>want of imployment</hi> to find
out honest occasions not to be idle; (and here it
is the most unhappy thing in the whole world, for
any man to be necessitated to be vicio as by his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94587:15"/>
nothing else to doe, and because, while the
world accounts it a <hi>Pedantick</hi> thing to be brought
up by rules and under discipline, he cannot learn
how to imploy himself to his advantage) to pass by
these, I say, the universal strength against this ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie
is <hi>Faith.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">I Pet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 9.</note> 
               <hi>Your adversary the Devil, like a
roaring Lion, goeth up and down seeking whom he
may devour; whom resist steadfast in the Faith.</hi> And
that not onely as it frustrates all that he attempts by
means of <hi>Infidelity,</hi> but it also<note n="b" place="margin">Eph. VI. 16.</note> 
               <hi>quenches all his
fiery darts;</hi> whatsoever bright Temptation he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents
to draw us from our Duty, or whatever fiery
triall he makes use of to affright and martyr with.
For the man whose Faith does give him<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. XI. 1.</note> 
               <hi>evidence</hi>
and <hi>eye-sight</hi> of those blessed Promises <hi>eye hath not
seen,</hi> and gives<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Heb. XI. 1</note> 
               <hi>substance, present solid being</hi> to his
<hi>after hopes,</hi> and, whose heart hath swallow'd down
those happy expectations which <hi>have never entred
in the heart of man to comprehend;</hi> what is there
that can <hi>tempt</hi> or <hi>fright</hi> him from his station? To
make all that which Satan gave the prospect of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail
on such a Soul, the <hi>Kingdoms of the earth</hi> must
out-vie <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and their <hi>Gauds</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shine
his <hi>Glory,</hi> and the <hi>twinkling of an eye</hi> seem
longer then <hi>Eternity:</hi> for nothing less then these
will serve his turn, all these are in his expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
Or what can fright the man whose heart is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94587:16"/>
set above the sphere of terrours? who knows ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity,
how great soever, can inflict but a more
sudden and more glorious blessedness upon him;
and the most despiteful cruel usage can but perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute
him into Heaven. 'Tis easie to demonstrate
that a Faith and expectation of the <hi>things on earth,</hi>
built upon weaker grounds then any man may have
for his belief of <hi>things above,</hi> hath charg'd much
greater hazards, overcome more difficulties then
the Devil does assault us with. For sure none is
so <hi>Scepticall,</hi> but he will grant that we have firmer
grounds to think there is <hi>another world</hi> in Heaven,
then <hi>Columbus</hi> (if he were the first Discoverer) had
to think there was <hi>another Earth;</hi> and that there
are far richer hopes laid up there in that other
world, for those that do deny themselves the sinful
profits and the jollities of this, and force them from
their inclinations, then those Sea-men could expect
who first adventur'd with him thither. For they
could not think to gain much for themselves, but
onely to take seisin of the Land (if any such there
were) for others covetous cruelty; cold get little
else but onely <hi>richer graves,</hi> and to lie <hi>buried</hi> in
their <hi>yellow earth.</hi> Nor are we assaulted in our
voyage with such hazards, as they knew they must
encounter with; the <hi>path of Vertue</hi> and the <hi>way to
Heaven</hi> is not so beset with difficulties as theirs
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94587:16"/>
was; when they must cut it out themselves through
an unknown new world of Ocean, where they could
see nothing else but swelling gaping Death, from
an abysse of which they were but weakly guarded,
and remov'd few inches onely: and as if the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerousest
shipwrecks were on shore, they found a
Land more savage and more monstrous then that
Sea. Yet all this they vanquisht for such slender
<hi>hopes,</hi> and upon so uncertain a <hi>belief.</hi> A weak
Faith therefore can doe mighty works; greater
then any that we stand in need of to encounter with
our enemy: It can remove these mountains too;
the golden ones that Covetousness and Ambition do
cast up; yea more, it can remove the <hi>Devil</hi> also,
for if you <hi>resist</hi> him <hi>stedfast in the faith,</hi> he <hi>flies,</hi> which
is the <hi>happy Issue,</hi> and my last part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Resist the Devil, and he will flie from you.</hi> And
yet it cannot be deny'd but that sometimes when
the <hi>messenger of Satan</hi> comes to <hi>buffet,</hi> though
S. <hi>Paul resist</hi> him with the strength of <hi>Prayer,</hi>
(which when <hi>Moses</hi> manag'd he was able to prevail
on <hi>God</hi> himself, and the <hi>Lord</hi> articled with him,
that he might be<note n="a" place="margin">Deut. IX. 14.</note> 
               <hi>let alone,</hi>) yet he could not beat
off this assailant, II <hi>Cor.</hi> XII. 7, 8, 9. When God,
either for prevention, as 'twas there, <hi>v.</hi> 7. or for
exercising or illustrating of Graces, or some other
of his blessed ends, gives a man up to the assaults
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:94587:17"/>
of Satan, he is often pleased to continue the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation
long; but in that case he does never fail
to send assistences and aids enough against it. <hi>My
grace is sufficient for thee,</hi> saith he to S. <hi>Paul</hi> there.
And when he will have us tempted for his uses, (if we
be not failing to our selves) he does prevent our
being overcome; so that there is no danger on those
Trials from their stay. But yet it must not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd
but that the Devil does prevail sometimes by
importunacy, and by continuance of Temptation;
so that <hi>Resistence</hi> is not always a <hi>Repulse,</hi> at least
not such an one as to <hi>make him draw off</hi> and <hi>flie.</hi>
It is not strange to find him siding with a <hi>natural
inclination,</hi> with the <hi>bent of Constitution,</hi> still pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting
Objects, laying Opportunities, throwing
in Examples, and all sorts of invitation, always
pressing so, that when a man hath struggled long he
does grow weary of the service, not enduring to be
thus upon his guard perpetually, watching a weak
heart which strong inclinations, busie Devils do lay
siege to; and so growing slack and careless, he is
presently surpris'd: or else, despairing that he shall
be always able to hold out, lays hold upon a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pting
opportunity, and yields; by the most un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable
and basest cowardice that can be, yields,
for fear of yielding; lest he should not hold out,
he will not, but gives up; and puts himself into
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94587:17"/>
that very mischief which he would avoid, merely
for fear of coming into it. For which fear there is
no reason neither: for 'tis not here as in our other
Sieges, where, if it be close, continuance must re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
men to necessity of yielding, strengths and
ammunitions will decay, provisions fail, and, if the
Enemy cannot, their own hunger will break through
their walls, make avenues for conquest, time alone
will take them; but in these Spiritual Sieges, one
Repulse inables for another, and the more we have
resisted, the Temptation is not onely so much slat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
and more weak and baffled, but the inward man
is stronger; Victory does give new forces, and is
sure to get in fresh and still sufficient supplies. For
<note n="a" place="margin">Jam. IV. 6.</note> 
               <hi>God giveth more grace,</hi> saith S. <hi>Ja<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es:</hi> and, <note n="b" place="margin">Matt. XXV. 29.</note> 
               <hi>they
shall have abundance,</hi> saith our Saviour. So that
where the Devil after several repulses still comes on
with fresh assaults, we may be sure he does discern
there is some treacherous inclination that sides with
him: and although the man refuse himself the satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
of the sin, he sees he hath a minde to it, his
refusalls are but saint, not hearty; though he seem
afraid to come within the quarters of the Vice, he
keeps, it may be, correspondence with the incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives
to it, entertains the opportunities, plaies with
the objects, or at best he does not fortifie against
him. Now this gives the Tempter hopes, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:94587:18"/>
his assaults, and does expose the person to be
taken by him.</p>
            <p>But where he sees he is resisted heartily, his offers
are received with an abhorrency, discerns men are
in earnest, watch to avoid all opportunities and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions,
and prepare, and fortifie, and arm against
him, there he will not stay to be the <hi>triumph of their
Vertue.</hi> We may know this by his <hi>Agents,</hi> those
that work <hi>under the Devil,</hi> whom he hath instructed
in the <hi>mysteries of waging his Temptations.</hi> Where
they are not like to speed; (and as to this they have
<hi>discerning spirits,</hi>) they <hi>avoid,</hi> and <hi>hate,</hi> and <hi>come
not near,</hi> but study <hi>spite</hi> and <hi>mischief</hi> onely there.
The intemperate men are most <hi>uneasie</hi> with a person
whom they are not able to engage in the debauch;
the <hi>rudeness</hi> and <hi>brutality</hi> of their excesses are not
so offensive to the sober man, as his <hi>stayd Vertue</hi> is
to them; they do not more avoid the crude egesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
shamefull spewings of their overtaken fellows
riot, then they do the shame and the reproch that
such a man's strict conversation casts on them,
which does in earnest make them look more foul
and nasty to themselves. In fine, every sinner shuns
the company of those whom he believes Religious
in earnest; 'tis an awe and check to them; they
are afraid, and out at it, as their <hi>Great Master</hi> also
is, who when he is resisted must be overcome: and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:94587:18"/>
as they that are beaten have their own <hi>fears</hi> also
for their enemies, which are sure to charge close,
put to flight, chase and pursue them; so it seems he
also is afraid of a sincere and hearty Christian, for
he flies him: so he did from <hi>Christ,</hi> IV. <hi>Matt.</hi> ver. 11.
and so the Text assures, If you <hi>resist</hi> him, <hi>he will fly
from you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, although we all did once <hi>renounce the
Devil and his works,</hi> were listed Souldiers against
him, took a <hi>Sacrament</hi> upon it, and our Souls,
the immortality of life or miserie, depend upon our
being true and faithfull to our selves and oaths, or
otherwise; nor is there more requir'd of us but <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution</hi>
and <hi>fidelity,</hi> onely not to be <hi>consenting</hi> to
our Enemies conquest of us, not to will captivity
and servitude. Yet as if, in mere defiance of our
vows and interests, we not onely <hi>will'd</hi> the ruine,
but would <hi>fight for it,</hi> we may find, in stead of this
<hi>resisting</hi> of the <hi>Devil,</hi> most men do<note n="a" place="margin">Acts VII. 51.</note> 
               <hi>resist the Holy
Ghost; quench</hi> not <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Ephe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. VI. 16.</note> 
               <hi>fiery darts of Satan,</hi> but the
<note n="c" place="margin">I Thess. V. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Spirit</hi> and his flames, by which he would enkindle
love of God and Vertue in them. If he take advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
of some warm occasion to inflame their cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
against former fol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies, heat them into resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
of a change; as soon as that occasion goes off,
they put out those flames, and choak these heats un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til
they die. If he come in his <hi>soft whispers,</hi> speak
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:94587:19"/>
close to the heart, suggest, and call them to those
joys of which himself is <hi>earnest;</hi> to all these they
shut their ears, can hear no whispers, are not sensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
of any sounds of things at such a distance,
<hi>sounds</hi> to which they give no more regard, then to
things of the same extravagance with the <hi>Musick of
the Spheres.</hi> Nay, if he come with his more active
methods, as the <hi>Angels</hi> came to <hi>Lot,</hi> send <hi>mercy</hi> to
allure and<note n="d" place="margin">Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>IX. 16.</note> 
               <hi>take them by the hand,</hi> as they did, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite
and lead them out of <hi>Sodome;</hi> if that will not,
<hi>judgements</hi> then to <hi>thrust them out,</hi> as they did also,
come with <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>brimstone</hi> to affright them; they
not onely, like the men of <hi>Sodome,</hi> do attempt a
<note n="b" place="margin">Ver. 4, 9.</note> 
               <hi>violence and rape upon those very Angels,</hi> but they
really debauch the mercies, and profane the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
having blinded <hi>their own eyes,</hi> that they might
see no <hi>hand of God</hi> in either: using thus unkindly
all his blessed methods of reclaiming them, till they
have<note n="c" place="margin">Ephes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 30.</note> 
               <hi>grieved him</hi> so that he forsake and leave them
utterly. As if they had not heard that when the <hi>Holy
Spirit</hi> is thus forc'd away, the <hi>evil spirit</hi> takes his
place, I <hi>Sam.</hi> XVI. 14. As if they knew not that to
those who <hi>close their eyes</hi> and <hi>stop their ears</hi> against
the Holy Spirit's motions, till they are grown <hi>dull
of hearing</hi> and <hi>blind</hi> to them, God does send a <hi>spirit
of slumber, that they should not see nor hear;</hi> and that
for this dire reason, <hi>that they may not be converted,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:94587:19"/>
nor be sav'd.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Isa. VI. 9. Matt. XIII. 14, 15.</note> Five times he affirms it in the
<hi>Scripture.</hi> Yea, once more, in words of a <hi>sad Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phasis,</hi>
II Thes. II. 12, 13. <hi>He sends them strong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lusions</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. XII. 40. Act. XXVII. 26. Rom. XI. 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>
               <hi>that they may believe a ly, that they all may
be damn'd who believe not the truth, but have plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
in unrighteousness:</hi> and that, <hi>because they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
not the love of the truth, that they might be
sav'd.</hi> Blessed God! Is it so easie for such sinners
to <hi>believe</hi> and be <hi>converted,</hi> that thy self shouldst in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpose
to hinder it, and hide the possibilities of
mercy from their eyes, that they may never see
them, nor recover! What can then become of those
for whom God does contrive that they shall not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scape?
when instead of those bowels that did make
him<note n="b" place="margin">Ezek. XXXIII. 11.</note> 
               <hi>swear he would not have the sinner die, but
would have him return and live,</hi> he puts on so
much indignation at such sinners, as to take an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
they shall not repent, and take an order that
they shall be damn'd.</p>
            <p>And yet all this is onely to those men, who, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<hi>dull of hearing</hi> the suggestions of the Spirit,
and not willing to give entertainment to his holy
motions, <hi>grieve</hi> him so, that they repell and drive
him quite away; and so by <hi>consequence</hi> onely
make way for the Devil: Whereas there are others
that <hi>directly call</hi> him, <hi>force</hi> him to them, <hi>ravish</hi>
and <hi>invade</hi> occasions to serve him. Some there are
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:94587:20"/>
that <hi>study</hi> how to <hi>disbelieve,</hi> and with great labour
and contrivance <hi>work</hi> out <hi>arguments</hi> and <hi>motives</hi>
to persuade themselves to <hi>Atheism:</hi> Others <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise,
discipline,</hi> and <hi>exercise</hi> themselves to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd
in <hi>Vice.</hi> Some <hi>dress</hi> so as to <hi>lay baits, snares,</hi>
to <hi>entrap Temptation,</hi> that they may be sure it may
not pass them: Others <hi>feed high,</hi> to <hi>invite,</hi> and
<hi>entertain</hi> the <hi>Tempter,</hi> doe all that is possible to
make him come, and to assure him that he must
prevail, when they have made it most impossible
for themselves to stand and to <hi>resist.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some there are indeed whom he does not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
so easily, but is put to <hi>compound</hi> with them,
takes them upon <hi>Articles:</hi> for when he would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage
them to a sin to which he sees they have great
<hi>inclinations,</hi> with some <hi>fears,</hi> he is fain to persuade
them to <hi>repent</hi> when they have done; to lay hold
upon the present opportunity, and not let the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction
escape them, but be forry after, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend.
For where these resolutions of Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
usher in transgression, there we may be sure
it is the Devil that suggests those resolutions. But
if he can get admittance once thus, by prevailing
with a person to receive him upon purposes of
<hi>after-Penitence;</hi> he is sure to prosper still in his
attempts upon the same condition: for Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
will wash out another sin, if he commit it;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:94587:20"/>
and so on. And it is evident that by this very
train he does draw most men on through the whole
course of sin and life: for never doe they, till they
see themselves at the last stage, begin repenting.
When they are to grapple with <hi>Death's forces,</hi> then
they are to set upon <hi>resisting of the Devil:</hi> and
when they are grown so weak that their whole soul
must be employ'd to muster all its spirits, all their
strength, but to beat off one little spot of phlegm,
that does besiege the <hi>avenues of breath,</hi> the <hi>parts of
life,</hi> and <hi>sally</hi> at it, and <hi>assault</hi> it, <hi>once, again,</hi> and
a <hi>third, many times,</hi> and yet with all the fury of its
might cannot break through, nor beat off that little
clot of spittle; when it is thus, yet then are they
to<note n="a" place="margin">Eph. VI. 12.</note> 
               <hi>wrestle</hi> with, and conquer <hi>Principalities and
Powers, all the Rulers of the utter darkness</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">II Cor. X. 4, 5.</note>, <hi>pull
down the strong holds of</hi> sin within, <hi>cast down imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations,
and every high thing that did exalt it self
against the knowledge of God, and bring into capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity
every thought to the obedience of Christ;</hi> and
with those feeble hands that they are scarcely able
to lift up in a short wish, or prayer, they must doe
<hi>all this, resist the Devil,</hi> and take Heaven by force.</p>
            <p>Now sure to put it off to such a fatal season is a
purpose of a desperate concern. In God's Name
let us set upon the doing it while there is something
left of <hi>Principle</hi> and vigour in us, ere we have so
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:94587:21"/>
               <hi>griev'd God's Spirit,</hi> that he do resolve to leave us
utterly, and before the Devil have so broke us to
his yoke, that we become content and pleas'd to doe
his drudgery. We deceive our selves if we think
to doe it with more ease when Constitution is grown
weaker; as if then Temptations would not be so
strong: for the Habits will be then <hi>confirm'd,</hi> Vice
grown <hi>Heroicall,</hi> and we wholly in the<note n="a" place="margin">Act. XXVI. 18.</note> 
               <hi>power of
Satan,</hi> dead and senseless under it, not so much as
stirring to get out. But if we strive before he have
us in his clutches, we have an enemie that can van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quish
none but those who consent to, and comply
and confederate with him, those that will be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come:
so that if <hi>we resist,</hi> he must be conquer'd;
and Temptation must be conquer'd too, for <hi>He will
flie,</hi> and then by consequence must cease to trouble
and molest us. This is the sure way to be rid of
Temptations, to put to flight the great <hi>Artificer</hi> and
<hi>Prince</hi> of them, subdue and overcome <hi>Him</hi> and <hi>our
selves: To</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Rev. III. 21.</note> 
               <hi>him that over cometh thus Christ will
grant to sit with him on his Throne, as He also over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came,
and sat down with his Father on his Throne.</hi>
To which, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
