<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Abstract of severall letters from Hull, York, and Beverly of His Majesties proceedings as also the carriage and behaviour of the Cavaliers, with the number of those that were slain and taken prisoners by Sir John Hotham : whereunto is added a true relation of the provision in Hull.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2006-02">2006-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23815</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A121</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6567</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11966594</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11966594</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51726</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A23815)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51726)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 46:15 or 246:E108, no 34)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Abstract of severall letters from Hull, York, and Beverly of His Majesties proceedings as also the carriage and behaviour of the Cavaliers, with the number of those that were slain and taken prisoners by Sir John Hotham : whereunto is added a true relation of the provision in Hull.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ben. Allen ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>August the second, 1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title on added t.p.: A true relation of the proceedings from York and Beverley shewing the great power and strength there raised against the Parliament and Hull. London : Printed for Iohn Iohnson, Aug. 3, 1642.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hotham, John, --  Sir, d. 1645 Jan. 2.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-12</date>
            <label>Andrew Kuster</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-12</date>
            <label>Andrew Kuster</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-01</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51726:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51726:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN
ABSTRACT
OF SEVERALL LETTERS
from <hi>Hull, York,</hi> and <hi>Beverly,</hi> of his
MAJESTIES proceedings.</p>
            <p>As alſo the carriage and behaviour of the
<hi>Cavaliers,</hi> with the number of thoſe that were
ſlain and taken priſoners by Sir <hi>John Hotham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto is added, A true Relation of the
proviſion in HULL.</p>
            <p>LONDON:
<hi>Printed for</hi> Ben. Allen <hi>in</hi> Popes-Head Alley.
Auguſt <hi>the ſecond.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb facs="tcp:51726:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51726:2"/>
            <head>An Abtract of ſeverall Letters from Hull,
York, and Beverly.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y love and reſpect unto you. I have col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected
ſome materiall paſſages as I have
writ you before, Captain <hi>Piggot</hi> hath
redeemed his credit, and took a Bark
with 3 great guns, alſo many Muskettiers which
fled aſhore; and now the ſaid Captain and 2 other
ſhips lieth upon Linconſhire ſhore ſide, ſo that no
Fortifications can be made there as hath been at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted,
to hinder paſſage up to <hi>Hull.</hi> And as I have
writ you, we have taken many Cavaliers and brave
horſes, and ſome money, we took one horſe worth
an 100. l. Our townſmen ſtand all bravely to their
buſineſſe; and thoſe that were malignants before,
are now cured, and ſee their former error, and now
ſtrive who ſhould be moſt forwards and valiant: at
firſt theſe things were ſomething troubleſome unto
us, and moſt to our women, but now God be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
we have better ſpirits, and the truth is, if Sir
<hi>John</hi> would give way, we would ſallie forth upon
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51726:3"/>
them, and (my life for it) we remove the ſiege, for
the Countrey have no mind to fight againſt us, and
the peoples hearts of the Countrey do much incline
to us, and divers would come into our town to help
us, if they could come ſafely; but if any come, they
ſeaſe upon their means. We have information of
their proceedings every night; they have robbed Mr
<hi>Leggeds</hi> houſe, and taken away all he hath; and they
have robd Mr <hi>Hothams</hi> houſe, and have taken a
brave horſe from him which he is troubled for, but
he hath a brave horſe in liew of him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they have
rob'd Sir <hi>John Hothams</hi> houſe which is about eight
miles from our Town.</p>
               <p>The Countrey people complain miſerably that
they injoy nothing that they have, that <hi>Candebed</hi>
men and <hi>Cotingham</hi> men and <hi>Newland</hi> men they ſay
they dare not be ſeen to read a good book, but he
that doth not baniſh God and good men, he is no
companie for the Cavaliers.</p>
               <p>Not to omit the Cavaliers have planted 3 peices
of Ordnance at <hi>Haſſel</hi> to hinder any paſſage by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
and a Keel coming towards us, the principall
gunner ſhot at her and miſſed, he ſwore God damne
him if he did not ſink her the next ſhot: and the
Peice brake in peeces and killed the Gunner and
ſome others.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51726:3"/>
They have of late ſent to Sir <hi>John</hi> for the horſe
and men he had taken, but he returnd anſwer that
upon good and fair terms he would deliver them,
that was horſe for horſe, and man for man; and to
begin, if they would be pleaſed to ſend the horſe
that was taken from his ſonne, he would ſend any
horſe for him. And ſo Mr <hi>Hothams</hi> horſe was ſent
him, and the brave horſe I writ you of, was ſent in
exchange.</p>
               <p>There hath ſince a Knight been ſent from the
King to Sir <hi>John,</hi> that offereth a generall pardon if
he will deliver the Town<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But Sir <hi>John</hi> ſaith he wil
not betray the truſt repoſed in him: if the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
order him to deliver up the Town he will
deliver, otherwiſe he cannot.</p>
               <p>We manned out of our Town ſome fire-locks
and ſome ſmall Barks with 150 Muskettiers, and
they went to viſit the Cavaliers at <hi>Berton,</hi> and at the
landing of our men the watch fled away, ſo they
took away all the boats out of Harbour, and what
elſe was there, and came away.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:51726:4"/>
               <head>Beverly, <date>the 29 July. 1642.</date>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOu being ſo affectionately compaſſionate with our
friends in <hi>Hull,</hi> I could not but <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cquaint with my firſt
intelligence of their good ſucceſſe. This laſt week they iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued
out upon their beſiegers about ſome 500. which when
they ſaw they began to prepare themſelves for an encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
exhorting each other to ſtand to it and look to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves;
The Countrey people bid the Cavaliers look to
themſelves, theſe (ſay they) are our friends will not hurt us:
which ſo amazed the Cavaliers and deſperadoes, that they
thought their beſt weapons were their heels, and fairly run
away to <hi>Beverly.</hi> But for all their haſt, Sir <hi>John</hi> took 30.
and killed two. The King preſently call'd a Councell of
War to treat that he would purſue no further: who gave
him anſwer he muſt do as he ſaw convenient: then the King
and Cavalry laying the fault upon the unskilfulneſſe of the
Countrey Captains, thought to remedie the buſineſſe by
ſending an <hi>Iriſh</hi> old Captain to command them, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to the Souldiers with the Kings pleaſure that he ſhould
lead them, they asked whether he were a <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> man, and
he ſaying no; they asked him what he had to do to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
them, ſo beat him and ſent him back again. I ſhould
have writ you that in this skirmiſh they took Captain <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cucoms</hi>
Colours from him, and ſet them upon a Turret in the
Town. This is all, I reſt,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your affectionate friend.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>VVE have no good news ſave onely good help comes
from you: ſince a few men came from London, Sir
<hi>John</hi> hath ſent the Kings Army a Meſſage that cauſed the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51726:4"/>
moſt of the Leaguer to run away, at leaſt 21. ſlain, and 15.
taken priſoners. The Kings Magazine was fired at the ſame
broyl, at a part of the Leaguer called <hi>Ayuelebie,</hi> within 3.
miles of <hi>Hull.</hi> This diſaſter happened to the great amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of the Cavaliers: yea they who were ſo confident of
their victory againſt <hi>Hull,</hi> who moſt bitterly curſed Sir <hi>John
Hotham,</hi> and in conceit would cut him in ſippits, within 3.
dayes theſe brave or rather baſe ſpirits are now forced to
ſay, that Sir <hi>John</hi> is worthy commendations for his fidelity.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>York
<date>29 July. 1642.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
               <p>The King hath beat up his Drums but none cometh in
here, he beats his Drums, but not a man: and of late the
King hath ſent for to view our Army, and that he may have
80. Muskettiers to guard his perſon, but it was anſwered
they could not go out of the City. You ſhall have incloſed
the note of the proviſion in <hi>Hull.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>York <date>29. of July. 1642.</date>
               </head>
               <p>YOur Letter I received and books, for which I thank
you: news here upon Wedneſday at night laſt, Sir <hi>John
Hotham</hi> ſent out 300. foot Souldiers and ſome 60. horſe
unto a place called <hi>Aulbe</hi> 3. miles of <hi>Hull,</hi> where Captain
<hi>Dunkam,</hi> lay with his Company, where Sir <hi>John Hothams</hi>
men ſet on fire a barn wherein was ſome gunpowder and
other materials: this day Sir <hi>Henry Slingsbe</hi> took the view
of our Arms in the City both common and private, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires
80. Muskettiers for the Kings guard: this night the
Earl of <hi>Leiſter</hi> is come to Town with a great Company, we
live in great fears: and in this Citie many are grown care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51726:5"/>
in the worſhip and ſervice of God. The Lord in mercy
think thoughs of mercy to our Kingdom. The next Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day
the Gentry is to come in, and the Papiſts to bring in
their horſes: but not to find themſelves as is ſaid. So deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
to be remembred of you as is our duty one for another,
will reſt yours.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A true relation of that Proviſion in Hull moſt neceſſarie.</head>
               <p>Rye 14 thouſand quarters, beſides private proviſion.</p>
               <p>Wheat 500. quarters, beſides the Kings and private proviſion.</p>
               <p>Beans, 7000. quarters at leaſt, beſides private proviſion.</p>
               <p>Oates 7000. quarters, beſides private.</p>
               <p>Mault 200. quarters beſides private proviſion.</p>
               <p>Oatmeal 80. quarters, beſides private.</p>
               <p>Fiſh as much as will ſerve this ſeven yeers.</p>
               <p>Wine 1000. Tun. Beare proviſion for 12. Moneths.</p>
               <p>Water as much as is needfull, one Well in twelve houres time
ſprung ten foot water; alſo divers Wels diſcovered that hath not
been uſed this 39. yeers, ſo that there is no want of freſh water, not
hath there been the leaſt complaint as yet of one poore man, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
or child in the Town for want of proviſion; God hath mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly
provided ſtore of freſh water (beſides the Wels in the
Town, and the freſh River at low water) eſpecially in a place with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
their out-works, without the wals, ſo that there is a place called
Buſh-dike being ſixtie yards in length, and ten yards broad, the
which hath in one night ſprung a foot plumme height, and was
never known to ſpring before.</p>
               <p>This is a true Relation.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:51726:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
