<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Account of a vindication of the English Catholicks from the pretended conspiracy against the life and government of His Sacred Majesty undertaking to discover the chief falsities and contradictions contained in the narrative of Titus Oates, &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 128 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2006-06">2006-06 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A24391</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A194</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6713</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11612198</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11612198</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47905</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A24391)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47905)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Account of a vindication of the English Catholicks from the pretended conspiracy against the life and government of His Sacred Majesty undertaking to discover the chief falsities and contradictions contained in the narrative of Titus Oates, &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for James Vade ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 36.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
                  <note>Errata : p. 36.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Oates, Titus, 1649-1705.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47905:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ACCOUNT OF A VINDICATION OF THE Engliſh Catholicks From the Pretended CONSPIRACY AGAINST THE LIFE and GOVERNMENT OF HIS Sacred Majeſty, UNDERTAKING To Diſcover the chief FALSITIES and CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TRADICTIONS contained in the Narrative OF TITUS OATES, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Etſi coram <hi>Hominibus</hi> dura fit <hi>Frons</hi> veſtra; erubeſcit, coram <hi>Deo, mens</hi> veſtra.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>James Vade,</hi> at the <hi>Cock</hi> and <hi>Sugar-Loaf,</hi> near S. <hi>Dunſtan's</hi> Church in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="tcp:47905:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:47905:2"/>AN ACCOUNT OF THE VINDICATION OF THE Engliſh Catholicks, &amp;c. The Introduction.</head>
         <div n="1" type="section">
            <head>SECT. I.</head>
            <p>WEre the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> &amp;c. who ſtand thus poſitively charged with projecting againſt their Prince and Country (and that under the Maſque of <hi>Religion</hi> too) ſuch monſtrous, helliſh <hi>Villains</hi> as are not to be thought of without an extremity of horror and aſtoniſhment, and even capable of forcing a <hi>Bluſh</hi> from the very <hi>Sun</hi> it ſelf; were theſe (I ſay) a ſort of people who either by their principles or practices had ever approved themſelves equitable to <hi>Monarchichal</hi> (to any kind of <hi>Civil) Regiment,</hi> or
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47905:3"/>
reſpectful to the common Offices and Obligations of humane <hi>Society:</hi> It would then have been ſevere to have refuſed them ſuch a proportion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>Charity</hi> as might have ſuſpended an abſolute concluſion upon their <hi>Guilt</hi>; or at leaſt, in contemplation of our <hi>frailty,</hi> have engaged a compaſſionate regret for their misfortune, and ranſack'd ancient and modern <hi>Story</hi> in queſt of Preſidents to inſinuate that even <hi>Good</hi> Men have many times been over-ſet, upon the encounter of a powerful and artificial <hi>Temptation.</hi> But if, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſtrict enquiry into their ways of <hi>Acting</hi> (And how can man judge of man but by his <hi>Doings?</hi>) the <hi>world</hi> findeth ſo little reaſon to che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh a favourable opinion of their Inclination to cultivate ſuch ſacred <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſes,</hi> as ſtrongly diſpoſe us toward the comporting our ſelves ſuitable to the Rules of <hi>Morality,</hi> and the Dignity and Excellence of our Chriſtian <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion</hi>; that on the contrary they appear to it only <hi>famous</hi> for their <hi>Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> for embroiling and over-turning Kingdoms and States, for violating and trampling upon all things holy and profane, that ſtand in competition with their <hi>ambition</hi> or <hi>avarice</hi>; for pouring forth innocent Blood like water, waſhing their hands in the tears of Widows and Orphans; and in a word, for propagating Feuds, Seditions, Rapines, Rebellions, Murthers, Maſſacres, and the like Barbarities, where-ever they once ſet their foot: If (I ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain) the <hi>world</hi> does or has diſcovered them to be joyntly and ſeverally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in a <hi>Bed-roll</hi> of ſuch ſtupendious <hi>wickedneſſes,</hi> (and what Corner of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe</hi> is not by ſad experience qualified to bear witneſs againſt them to this <hi>Truth?</hi>) they muſt excuſe <hi>Mankind</hi> in <hi>general,</hi> for looking upon them as <hi>Locuſts</hi> and <hi>Caterpillars,</hi> fit to be extirpated and ſwept away from off the face of the Earth: and they muſt alſo excuſe <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> in particular, if, after ſo many Providential Deliverances from their <hi>Plots</hi> upon our Religion, Lives and Liberties, from the very <hi>dawning</hi> of the bleſſed <hi>Reformation</hi> upon our then benighted Iſland, down to this inſtant, we ſtand fairly warn'd and premoniſh'd to beware of their <hi>Malice,</hi> and, upon the leaſt rumour of their being crept in among us, to provide againſt the <hi>worſt</hi> that <hi>Hell</hi> and ſuch its miſcreant <hi>Agents</hi> can deviſe againſt us: and they muſt not think hardly of the <hi>Law</hi> neither if, after a fair Tryal by their <hi>Peers,</hi> and full conviction upon ſuch credible evidence as, were the <hi>Tables</hi> turn'd, is compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to <hi>caſt</hi> the nobleſt <hi>Proteſtant Subject</hi> in any Roman Catholick Court of Judicature in <hi>Europe,</hi> it do condemn every ſhavling traiterous wretch of them taken in the <hi>manner.</hi> Not that I do hereby aim at the encouraging or abetting of a popular, and undue Inquiſition after <hi>Blood,</hi> (it being incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the Grandure and Elevation of a True <hi>Engliſh Spirit</hi> to be ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, or to reject the petition for life even of the bittereſt <hi>Enemy,</hi> that lies diſarm'd and at mercy) but would imply thus much only: that if they will continue to make ſo bad an uſe of the <hi>Time</hi> and other <hi>Indulgences</hi> granted to their importunities, in order to the capacitating them to be their own
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47905:3"/>
Compurgators in a fair and Legal Way, as ſtill to employ them toward the ſupport of their evil Deſigns upon the Lives and Credits of their Accuſers, toward the abuſing and inflaming the people with an uninterrupted courſe of ſcandalous and flagitious Impoſtures, toward the arraigning the Wiſdom, Honour, and Juſtice of the Kingdom, and toward the rendring the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Nation odious and contemptible in the eyes of other Countries; in the name of <hi>Goodneſs</hi> let them have all the fair Play, and other advantages that the Law of the Land can allow them; and we ſhall then ſee whether their clamorous pretences of Innocence, or the tender and merciful <hi>Nature</hi> of their Soveraign, will prove their ſureſt <hi>Sanctuary.</hi>—But to come a little nearer the matter in hand. Although I well remember'd how feeble and obnoxious theſe men had approved themſelves in their former <hi>Nibblings</hi> at ſome ſpecial Branch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the Evidence againſt them; yet the <hi>Pamphlet</hi> I now came to examine, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing under the Pompous <hi>Title</hi> of <hi>A Vindication of the Engliſh Catholicks from the pretended Conſpiracy againſt the Life and Government of his ſacred Majeſty, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering the chief Falſities and Contradictions contained in the Narrative of</hi> Titus Oates, I read it over with much attention, as expecting from it ſuch an ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſubſtantial <hi>Confutation</hi> of the Narrative in queſtion, as might hold pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion with the Parts, Pains and Promiſes of the Perſons intereſted in the compiling of it, and be able to abide the Teſt of a <hi>Parliament,</hi> or a Court of <hi>Judicature:</hi> but, not to anticipate, or prepoſſeſs the Readers Judgment by calling it a Compound of unjuſt Surmizes, immoral Reflections, unmanly and inſipid Scoffs, egregious Sophiſtries and Prevarications, Illogical Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, fallacious Reaſonings, and Proofs, weak, unſatisfactory, and child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhly extravagant, to the higheſt degree imaginable; I found it not a jot <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe</hi> then in the Curſory, but impartial <hi>Notes</hi> enſuing, is Repreſented.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="section">
            <head>SECT. II.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>HE</hi> begins his previous Addreſs to the <hi>Courteous Reader, (pag.</hi> 1.) with an aſſurance, that the <hi>Narrative</hi> here in debate is an <hi>Original,</hi> becauſe the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer of it found none to <hi>Copy</hi> by; and yet in the next <hi>Line</hi> unbethinks himſelf that <hi>Lucian's True Hiſtory</hi> (rather than the <hi>Golden Legend</hi>) might furniſh the Preſident; and, upon this <hi>Preſumption,</hi> proceeds (in regard few <hi>Compariſons</hi> are able to run upon <hi>all four</hi>) mathematically to ſtate the <hi>Breadth</hi> and <hi>Depth</hi> of the <hi>Differences</hi> between them; winding them all up with this doughty <hi>Remark,</hi> that whereas <hi>Lucian in that intended</hi> (a hopeful beginning to pronounce upon the <hi>Intention</hi> of a man that died ſo many hundred years ſince) <hi>only to recreate thoſe, who never did him any good,</hi> Oates (on the other ſide) <hi>in this deſigns the ruine of thoſe who never did him any hurt,</hi> (excepting only a refuſing him <hi>Holy Orders, back</hi> and <hi>belly-beating</hi> him, <hi>&amp;c.) but intended him much good,</hi> (at <hi>Latter-Lammas</hi>; for in their Liſt of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47905:4"/>
               <hi>Aga's</hi> I find not <hi>Titus Oates</hi> prick'd down for the <hi>Reverſion</hi> of a <hi>Cure</hi> in any of the pooreſt Country-Village:) <hi>If his bad nature</hi> (his <hi>Tongue) had been ſuſceptible of good advice</hi> (could have kept within his <hi>Teeth,</hi> and told no Tales of the mighty preparations of the <hi>Holy Legions.</hi>)</p>
            <p>Then he confeſſes he <hi>never ſaw the man, and ſo can know nothing of him, but by hear-ſay.</hi> To which he gives a more poſitive and implicit Faith, thoroughout the whole courſe of his <hi>Obſervations,</hi> than his own <hi>Ears</hi> and <hi>Eyes</hi> could ever expect from him: and ſo preſently lays the <hi>courteous Reader</hi> abord with a pretty <hi>Third-hand</hi> Story of a certain <hi>Dignitary,</hi> who was ſo deadly cunning at ſeeing a man's <hi>Heart</hi> through his <hi>Ribs,</hi> and reading his <hi>Meaning</hi> by his <hi>Jaws,</hi> that he ſcrupled the <hi>Deponent</hi> the Sacrament (their <hi>Sacraments</hi> and their <hi>Senſes</hi> are equal in number) of <hi>Confirmation</hi> (or laying his hand upon his head) meerly out of a conceit that his face was not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing enough. O the Sin and Folly of theſe Wretches, thus groſly to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe and impoſe upon their Bigotted <hi>Proſelites!</hi> For meer ſhame (<hi>Sirs</hi>) leave off to trouble the world with ſuch <hi>Trumpery,</hi> leſt the very <hi>Boys</hi> in the Streets, by the proper arguments of <hi>Turnip tops</hi> and <hi>addle Eggs,</hi> compel you to an acknowledgment of your <hi>Forgeries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, he produces a <hi>Reaſon</hi> that, at a <hi>bluſh,</hi> look'd as big as a <hi>Giant,</hi> as having four or five <hi>little</hi> Reaſons in the Belly of it; but upon the approach, I found it only a meagre <hi>Jack-a-lent,</hi> ſet up to raiſe wonderment in <hi>Children,</hi> and in <hi>Men</hi> Laughter; a <hi>ſhadow,</hi> and no more: as you your ſelves may ſee upon the uncaſing of it: Thus. He denies the <hi>Deponent</hi> to have been made a <hi>Doctor.</hi> 1. Becauſe he never was at <hi>Salamanca.</hi> 2. Becauſe he was not a <hi>Prieſt.</hi> And 3. Becauſe he was not <hi>Scholar</hi> good enough. His two firſt Reaſons he endeavours to corroborate with the <hi>Atteſtations</hi> (A and B, <hi>pag.</hi> 42.43.) of <hi>Lynch</hi> the Titular Archbiſhop of <hi>Tuam</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> (who ſtands accuſed as one of the Conſpirators) and <hi>Duelly</hi> another <hi>Tiege</hi>; the <hi>former</hi> of which (that part of it that relates to the point now in agitation) amounts to thus much; That <hi>Lynch</hi> proteſts and declares by his <hi>Conſecration, &amp; ex abandanti, per Sancta Dei Evangelia</hi> (do but behold how fluently the man ſpits <hi>Latin</hi>) that he never ſaw the <hi>Deponent,</hi> (I ſuppoſe his <hi>Reverence</hi> is blind, for otherwiſe it is more than he can ſafely ſay (much leſs ſwear) of any man living, even the <hi>Great Turk</hi> himſelf) and that he never was at <hi>Madrid,</hi> (gallantly undertaken!) both becauſe he had been told he came no further than <hi>Vallodolid,</hi> and alſo for that he vouchſafed not his Lordſhip a <hi>Viſit</hi> and <hi>Complement,</hi> for having refuſed him <hi>Holy Orders:</hi> and the <hi>Latter</hi> is only a <hi>Declaration</hi> (in manner and form aboveſaid) that the <hi>Deponent</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was at <hi>Madrid:</hi> 1. becauſe a <hi>Mule-man</hi> ſaid ſo to the <hi>Proteſter,</hi> and then, becauſe he was, by an Epiſtolary Correſpondence, acquainted with all his Grace of <hi>Tuam</hi>'s motions. Thoſe that ſtick not to ſwear and proteſt at this extravagant rate, how can it be expected that they will make Bones of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47905:4"/>
any Oath whatſoever? But now admitting the produced to be true Copies of theſe two <hi>obnoxious</hi> perſons (verbal) written <hi>Aſſurances.</hi> Yet ſince they run only upon the <hi>Negative,</hi> and of themſelves are Naked, Undue and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectural, they ought not to have any effect upon the Solemnity and Poſitivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of an <hi>affirmative Oath</hi> confirmed by ſeveral <hi>Collateral Evidences</hi>: a <hi>Tythe</hi> of which from one of their <hi>own</hi> hands, in their <hi>Inquiſitive Courts,</hi> would be eſteemed a ſufficient ground whereupon to condemn the worthieſt <hi>Heretick</hi> (ſo they are pleaſed to dignifie us) in <hi>England</hi> to the <hi>Faggot.</hi> But they inſiſt much upon the <hi>Deponents</hi> not being a <hi>Prieſt.</hi> Should we, for peace and quietneſs ſake ſuppoſe this, I believe the <hi>Obſervator</hi> would yet make ſome difficulty to reſolve me whether it be impoſſible for a man, in their Univerſities, to commence <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Doctor</hi> in one and the ſame week? I muſt alſo mind him that this <hi>Reaſon</hi> is wholly new to us; for the only <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection</hi> that we could hear of on this ſide the Sea, upon the firſt duſting of the <hi>Queſtion</hi> was, (and it came as piping-hot too from <hi>Oraculous S. Omers</hi>) that no man could be made a <hi>Doctor</hi> in any <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Country, under the charge of 400 <hi>l.</hi> a Sum, they ſaid, that the <hi>Deponent</hi> never had at command at one time. Both theſe <hi>Flams</hi> now (to give him his own words again, <hi>pag.</hi> 1.) <hi>are alike true per Antiphraſin.</hi> But how can they have the confidence to tax him with <hi>Illiterateneſs,</hi> when he hath ſo publickly approved himſelf to be a better <hi>Scholar</hi> than his <hi>Maſters?</hi> Yet the <hi>Compendious Calumniator</hi> pawns his honour, that the <hi>Deponent</hi> is not able to turn five Lines of <hi>Latine</hi> into true <hi>Engliſh.</hi> This was a handſom <hi>ſtretch</hi> indeed! and yet we find their own Authors every where telling ſcurvy Tales of, and inveighing againſt their <hi>ignorant Clergy,</hi> and what <hi>feeble parts,</hi> back'd with a <hi>ſtrong Purſe,</hi> are commonly found qualified for a <hi>Degree</hi> in any of their <hi>Colleges.</hi> Beſides, what is it to any one, if their <hi>Reverences</hi> were pleaſed to vouchſafe to the extraordinary <hi>merits</hi> of this their diligent Servant, the reward of an empty <hi>Title</hi> that only feeds the <hi>fancy</hi> of the <hi>Receiver,</hi> and ſubſtracts nothing from the <hi>Coffers</hi> of the <hi>Beſtower?</hi> But now I think on't a great deal of this might have been ſpar'd, for it is not the <hi>Oath,</hi> but the <hi>Veracity</hi> of the <hi>Deponent</hi> that lies <hi>here</hi> at ſtake; he never having (that I could hear of) given in this <hi>Punctillio</hi> as any part of his <hi>Evidence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt <hi>Paragraph,</hi> of <hi>pag.</hi> 2. furniſhes another <hi>Circumſtance</hi> not only to ſtrengthen the preceding <hi>Allegations,</hi> but even to call in queſtion the very <hi>being</hi> of the <hi>Plot</hi> too; and it is taken from the <hi>Order,</hi> kept in the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Houſes, they never employing their <hi>Scholars</hi> (ſuch as he told us before the <hi>Deponent</hi> was) <hi>in Negotiations</hi> (and Treaſons) <hi>of the higheſt Conſequence.</hi> And hence he <hi>wire-draws</hi> the <hi>Burthen</hi> of his Story, that the <hi>Deponents</hi> Doctor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Papiſts Treaſons were both hammered upon the ſame Anvil. Strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>concluded,</hi> I'll promiſe you, would but the ſcurvy <hi>Premiſes</hi> bear it out! This man will never take up with leſs than a <hi>Cardinals Cap</hi> ſure, he's ſuch an
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47905:5"/>
old dog at <hi>Syllogiſm</hi>! But if <hi>Clodius</hi> will impeach the <hi>Adulterers,</hi> who can help it? And ſince the Gentleman brings the <hi>beſt</hi> Arguments he has, (tho' never ſo ordinary) for the ſupport of his Tottering <hi>Cauſe,</hi> in <hi>Charity</hi> we ought to accept the <hi>will</hi> for the <hi>deed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He goes on to ſmatter moſt <hi>diſtinctly</hi> upon the name of <hi>D' Oliva</hi>; to twit the Deponent for impropriety of Speech, in terming thoſe Letters the <hi>Inſcription,</hi> which he is pleaſed to call the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of the <hi>Jeſuits Seal</hi>; and to threaten him <hi>correction</hi> for ſome other inſtances (to be produced in due time) of his <hi>ignorance in the</hi> (leſs material) <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> of the Jeſuits; he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready (it ſeems) perfectly well underſtanding their more <hi>important</hi> ones of plotting upon the Perſons and Dominions of Princes and Potentates.</p>
            <p>From this word of <hi>Reproof</hi> he comes (next) to attempt the laying open of the <hi>Deponents Contradictions,</hi> which he will needs have to be ſo very many, that it were an endleſs work to reckon them all. He cites (at the bottom of <hi>pag.</hi> 2.) the twenty ſeventh <hi>fol.</hi> of <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Tryal thrice, the 58 <hi>Item</hi> of the Narrat. the 28<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>Irelands</hi> Tryal, and twice the eleventh of <hi>Langhorns</hi>; relying all along upon the credit of the <hi>Prints</hi> of theſe kinds, notwithſtanding that he has been ſo often told, that of themſelves they are no <hi>Legal Evidence.</hi> Had he now been able to make out his <hi>Charge</hi> of Contradictions upon the <hi>Deponent,</hi> his work had been done: for I readily agree with him, that <hi>Truth has a real Ground, and is always the ſame; but falſhood is built only upon fancy, and changes accordingly</hi>; pag. 2. But let me aſſure the <hi>Obſervator,</hi> that there are ſome certain perſons in the world who have examined all the <hi>Tryals</hi> with much ſtrictneſs, and yet have not been able, even out of <hi>Them all,</hi> to pick any <hi>paſſages</hi> ſo directly contradictory as ingenuity and good will might not eaſily reconcile; or ſuch as were worthy the cognizance of a <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Juſtice:</hi> and as to thoſe places that he has inſtanced in; to me they appear ſo far from <hi>interfering</hi> one with another, that contrariwiſe thy ſufficiently explain themſelves, without being beholden to an <hi>Evaſion</hi> for a <hi>Salvo.</hi> And yet ſo reſolutely is he bent upon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> doing his beſt toward the blaſting of the <hi>Deponents</hi> Credit, (an <hi>atchievment</hi> that, no doubt of it, would be highly accounted of by <hi>Holy Church,</hi> could it be found <hi>practicable</hi> once) that nothing will ſerve his turn but concluding him (in deſpite of <hi>Logick</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi>) undeniably <hi>perjured,</hi> upon the ground of the fore-going ſickly <hi>Suggeſtions.</hi> Now though it be one of the <hi>Jeſuits Cuſtoms</hi> (ſo much applauded by our <hi>Obſervator!</hi>) from ſleight and weakly <hi>Premiſes</hi> to infer weighty <hi>Conſequences</hi>: yet this ſort of <hi>Argumentation</hi> is ſo forc'd, partial, and trifling, that to me it ſeems to be ſomething <hi>leſs</hi> even than downright <hi>Sophiſtry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>firſt Break</hi> of <hi>P.</hi> 3. has nothing in it worth the taking notice of, ſave only a ſhred or two of <hi>Latin,</hi> which are of much more natural applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the <hi>Obſervators</hi> Party, than to the perſon for whom (out of pure kindneſs) he intends them: and in the <hi>Second,</hi> he picks a quarrel with the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47905:5"/>
               <hi>manner</hi> of the <hi>Deponents</hi> Accuſation; calling it <hi>ſuch, as any Knave who dare tell a Lye, and confirm it by Oath, by it may bring any man or men, how innocent ſoever, into queſtion.</hi> This Suggeſtion, from ſuch a Pen, may fairly be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood as a very notable <hi>Complement.</hi> He then ſets forward, with giving his word, that none of the Letters mentioned in this <hi>Narrative</hi> were ever found, and that their <hi>Authors</hi> deny the writing of them. The <hi>confidenter</hi> man he, and the <hi>wiſer</hi> they. But ſtill the <hi>Windſor-Packet</hi> ſticks in his ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach; for having met with a <hi>ſleeveleſs Fable,</hi> upon the Subject of thoſe Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, in one of their own Printed Pamphlets, he preſently ſwallows it down for <hi>Goſpel,</hi> puzzles himſelf to find out a <hi>Providence,</hi> in the detection of what, upon the ſimple ground of a <hi>Libel,</hi> he ſtrongly conceits to have been an <hi>Impoſture:</hi> and thence takes occaſion, with great Gravity and Superciliouſneſs, to enjoyn the <hi>Deponent</hi> Penance; backing his admonition with a <hi>Text</hi>; and to make all ſure, ſubjoyning one of <hi>Whitebreads Learned Sayings.</hi> Let him but ſtay till there be occaſion for it, and then no doubt, his advice will be taken: And I muſt alſo mind him that <hi>F. Beddingfield</hi> knew very well what he did, in waiting (contrary to cuſtom) the coming in of that <hi>Mayle</hi>; for having before had notice of the Diſcovery of their Rogueries, and that the credit of the information depended in a great meaſure upon the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting of that <hi>Pacquet,</hi> he found himſelf concerned to be the firſt Receiver, and Divulger of it; and to do what he could toward the Repreſenting the whole matter as a <hi>Forgery.</hi> And blame him now who can. But if the <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervator</hi> be deſirous to know the true <hi>Contents</hi> and <hi>Meaning</hi> of thoſe Letters, <hi>Kirby</hi>'s and <hi>Tonge</hi>'s <hi>Narratives</hi> (which are of more credit ſure than a worthleſs, nameleſs <hi>Libel</hi>) will give him particular ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>Having thus diſpatch'd his preliminary <hi>Reaſonings</hi> in proof of the Nullity of the <hi>Plot,</hi> and the Knavery of the <hi>Deponent</hi>; the fourth page brings him to his <hi>Promiſes</hi> and <hi>Apologies</hi>; which I am already half of belief will prove of the very ſame complexion, and validity with the other. But yet he is ſo <hi>cock-a-hoop</hi> upon the buſineſs, that, tho' he tells us <hi>indubio favendum eſt Reo, potius quam Actori,</hi> yet he ſcorns to be beholden to the Peoples <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> in the caſe; as undertaking to prove irrefragably (he muſt be excuſed if he fall ſhort of his word) what he advances, with ſuch Evidence, and undoubtedly true Atteſtations, that unleſs his Adverſaries ſhut their eyes very hard, (I promiſe him to keep mine as open as I can; but the <hi>Thing</hi> is ſo wretched heavy, that it caſts me a <hi>Nod</hi> almoſt every <hi>Period</hi> of it) they ſhall ſee he's in the Right, <hi>pag.</hi> 4. He threatens <hi>Candor</hi> and <hi>Clearneſs</hi> too; (faults that a <hi>Jeſuite</hi> never yet was guilty of, and I'm miſtaken in the man if he prove a <hi>By-blow,</hi>) only he pretends ſcruple of Conſcience for not uttering <hi>publickly</hi> ſuch treaſonous expreſſions, as his Brethren whiſper in <hi>private</hi>: then at <hi>one Puff</hi> of his Breath he lays the <hi>Brat</hi> of the <hi>Plot</hi> at the <hi>Deponents</hi> Door, generouſly paſſing his word for the <hi>Honeſty</hi> of all the Prieſts and Jeſuites in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47905:6"/>
               <hi>Europe, Aſia, Affrica</hi> and <hi>America</hi>; but at the next, in a manner, recals it again.</p>
            <p>This leads on (<hi>Pag.</hi> 4. <hi>Par.</hi> 3.) to a <hi>Shuffle,</hi> and a new faſhioned ſort of an <hi>Hail Maſter,</hi> amounting to within a <hi>Nutſhel</hi> of a Profeſſion, <hi>ex abundanti,</hi> that he would not for a world be ſo unmannerly as to call the <hi>Deponent</hi> a Rogue, were it not purely out of an ardent zeal to contradict an <hi>Heretical</hi> Prince, Parliament and Court of Judicature. And thus after a ſuſpicious ſquint at <hi>Tonge,</hi> &amp;c. as the Contrivers of the Plot, he falls to handling the King himſelf a little familiarly, telling him of his Wickedneſs and Cruelty (a Loyal Subject the mean while) in <hi>Scripture Phraſe,</hi> and minding him that <hi>it is an abomination to Kings to commit wickedneſs:</hi> Prov. 16.12. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks it would better have ſuited with his pretences of <hi>Duty,</hi> to have admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed His Majeſty to <hi>love</hi> his <hi>Enemies,</hi> (the <hi>Obſervator</hi> and his <hi>Tribe</hi>) and <hi>bleſs them that curſe</hi> Him; rather than ſtill to have run on in charging <hi>Him</hi> with the effuſion of innocent Blood, becauſe the <hi>Law,</hi> upon due proof, has hanged a few of their <hi>Religious Conſpirators.</hi> Believe me, it is well for his Majeſty (it ſhould ſeem) that the <hi>Act de Haeretico comburendo</hi> is not in force; for the Fellow argues deviliſh <hi>ſuſpiciouſly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now for a ſolemn <hi>adieu</hi> to his <hi>Courteous Reader,</hi> he tells him in effect, (<hi>pag.</hi> 5.) that it is only a natural Concern for <hi>Reputation</hi> that prompted him to this Unworthy Undertaking; becauſe that tho' his Brethren be never ſo great Raſcals in ſecret, yet they are in common prudence obliged to carry their Diſh as even as they can, to the Eye of the World: Which in truth is no contemptible piece of <hi>Policy.</hi> And thus we have done with his <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="section">
            <head>SECT. III.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Obſervator</hi> introduces his Notes upon the <hi>Deponents Epiſtle Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory</hi> with a florid and Rhetorical <hi>Excurſion,</hi> which (<hi>pag.</hi> 6.) he winds up thus; that if the <hi>Narrative</hi> be <hi>True,</hi> (as it may be for any thing he has yet been able to prove to the contrary) no reward can be too great for the Author of it, if <hi>otherwiſe,</hi> there is no puniſhment but will ſeem too little for him: All this I ſhall not ſcruple to ſubſcribe to. But then in the ſame <hi>pag.</hi> 6. he falls heavily upon him for preſuming to ſay he was a <hi>Loyal Subject,</hi> when his <hi>Father</hi> was pretended to be otherwiſe. What is this but an endeavour to introduce that <hi>Maxime</hi> of their <hi>Inquiſition</hi> here among us, that, <hi>Cornelius A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grippa</hi> tells us, admits it to be a ſufficient ground to condemn any Man for a <hi>Witch,</hi> whoſe Father or Grandfather before him had there been ſentenced for dealing with the Devil. Yet ſtill he runs on to repreſent all the <hi>Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents</hi> words that tend that way, as criminal, and to torture them to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with his own evil meanings. He next labours to take off the edge
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47905:6"/>
of his <hi>Aſſertion, (Ep. Ded. to the Narrat. fol.</hi> 1.) that <hi>the Papiſts many paſt Treaſons and Encroachments upon ſeveral Princes for theſe thouſand years in the world, will prove their inclinations for the future</hi>: by oppoſing to it the like Practices of the <hi>Presbyterians:</hi> as if another mans ſtealing of a <hi>Horſe</hi> were an excuſe for my breaking open a <hi>Houſe!</hi> yet he will needs have it, that <hi>they</hi> did more miſchief in four years, than the Crimes charged upon the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> (only an unfortunate Attempt to murther the <hi>King,</hi> ſubvert the <hi>Government,</hi> and maſſacre the <hi>People</hi>) had they been put into act, would in all likelyhood have produced in four thouſand: (A moderate <hi>Stretch!</hi>) and that the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders that happened in <hi>Popiſh</hi> (I ſhould, for good manners ſake, have ſaid <hi>Catholick</hi>) Times, (as the ſeveral <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellions, for inſtance; the <hi>Pariſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> and <hi>Piedmont</hi> Maſſacres, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) were like an <hi>Ague</hi> in the Spring, painful, but not dangerous, and leaving the Body more healthy than before; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as thoſe of <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> (or <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſtill; for, <hi>mutato nomine de Te</hi>) are like putrid <hi>Feavers,</hi> or the <hi>Plague,</hi> which leaves ſcarce hopes of <hi>Life.</hi> It is no new thing for a <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Glaſs to repreſent <hi>other</hi> mens faults at <hi>Large</hi> to the Proſpect, but their <hi>own</hi> in <hi>Little.</hi> But they are <hi>both</hi> bad enough of all conſcience, to be better; which will never be (I fear) till they have changed <hi>their Principles</hi> for <hi>Ours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next; he is very pleaſant upon ſome ſneaking <hi>Monk</hi> or other (I ſuppoſe) for charging the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> with the firſt <hi>Murther</hi> in the world, and with tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Eve</hi> to eat the <hi>forbidden Fruit.</hi> This indeed is vaſtly diſproportionate from the <hi>Character</hi> they give of themſelves, (<hi>Myſtery of Jeſuitiſm, pag.</hi> 48. and 49.) <hi>viz. Men eminent for Learning and Prudence; a ſort of People that have the Pillar of Divine Wiſdom going before them, a ſurer Guide than any thing of Philoſophy; they are that ſociety of</hi> Men (Angels <hi>I ſhould have ſaid) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of</hi> Iſaiah <hi>hath propheſied in theſe words</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Go you ſwift and ready <hi>Angels.</hi> (Is not the Propheſie as plain as the back of your hand) <hi>They are Eagle-like Spirits, a flight of Phoenixes; there being an Author who hath not long ſince de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated, that there are more than</hi> one: <hi>They have changed the face of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> &amp;c. This is the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of their own words: and whether <hi>This</hi> or the <hi>Former</hi> Panegyrick more becomes them, and is wider from <hi>Truth,</hi> I leave it to the world to determine. But now he reaches the <hi>Deponent</hi> a blow for hinting that King <hi>James</hi> 'ſcap'd not <hi>their Poyſon.</hi> This I am very ſure of, that he ſcap'd not the <hi>Preſumption</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>In <hi>pag.</hi> 7. he falls moſt bitterly upon him again for inſinuating (<hi>Epiſt. Ded. to the Narrat. fol.</hi> 2.) what ſo many authentick <hi>Writers</hi> have averr'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>the Papiſts, by their known diabolical art of inflaming Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Paſſions againſt each other, were the firſt Authors and Contrivers of the late <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nnatural War.</hi> I cannot imagine what harm there ſhould be in this, ſave only that it contradicts (and juſtly too) the Obſervators fancyful and florid Blazonings of the <hi>Gigantick</hi> (not <hi>Romantick</hi>) Doings and Sufferings of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47905:7"/>
his Party, upon that occaſion. For it is as clear as the Sun, that the <hi>Scots</hi> began <hi>that</hi> Rebellion in 1637; and it is alike clear, even from their own Authors, that thoſe very <hi>Commotions</hi> were raiſed, and fomented chiefly by the Arts and Activity of <hi>Richelieu</hi> and his <hi>Agents.</hi> So that they <hi>firſt</hi> ſet us all in a flame, and <hi>then,</hi> under the notion of Porters, Dray-men, Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, and Fanaticks, (for they can indue all ſhapes; being as mallia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble us the <hi>materia prima</hi> it ſelf) rifled and diſpoiled us. Some of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed periſhed in the Scuffle; but then thoſe that ſcap'd had (or at leaſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped to have) the better bargain on't: and <hi>nothing venture, nothing win.</hi> 'Tis true (as <hi>Papiſts</hi>) they were never able to make a ſeparate Party in <hi>England</hi>; but then it is as undeniable, that they influenced in <hi>all</hi>; this (in all proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility) being their chief <hi>aim,</hi> to protract the <hi>Quarrel,</hi> till we had beaten one anothers Brains out, and waſted our ſtrength, ſo to make way for their ſhoals of hungry <hi>Pilgrims</hi> to croſs the Sea, poſſeſs, and re-people the <hi>Land.</hi> Yet God in his mercy diſappointed them. But now, I would fain know of theſe <hi>Loyoliſts</hi> who they were that began the <hi>Iriſh Rebellion,</hi> (at the ſame time with the <hi>other,</hi>) where ſo many thouſand <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of all Ages and Sexes were, without the leaſt diſtinction or remorſe, inhumanly butchered in a few months? I make no queſtion but they will ſtrive to ſhuffle even that <hi>too</hi> upon the wicked <hi>Fanaticks.</hi> Let me therefore tell them once for all, that theſe Traiterous <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> and thoſe Trayterous <hi>Papiſts</hi> make up one and the ſame Pack of <hi>Rebels,</hi> under different Appellations; they are <hi>Bone</hi> of the <hi>ſome Bone,</hi> and <hi>Fleſh</hi> of the <hi>ſame Fleſh</hi>; a ſwarm of malignant <hi>Inſects</hi> generated upon a commixtute and coition of the putrid Exhalations of the <hi>Rhoſne</hi> and <hi>Tyber</hi>; bearing in their <hi>Faces</hi> the very Picture of their <hi>Sire:</hi> and tho', like <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s <hi>Foxes,</hi> they looked divers ways, yet with <hi>Them</hi> too they are tyed together by the <hi>Tails,</hi> and drive at one and the ſame <hi>End,</hi> I mean the fattening themſelves upon the Subſtances of <hi>Others,</hi> and turning <hi>Order</hi> into <hi>Confuſion.</hi> This <hi>Obſervation</hi> is now ſo juſtly &amp; generally entertained and noted, that all theſe mens bitter and elaborate Invectives a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Rogueries of the <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> have no other effect upon the wiſe and ſober, than to be looked upon as a more groſs and proſtitute diſcovery of their <hi>own nakedneſſes:</hi> ſo that did they but well conſider it, they would hold themſelves concerned, in common prudence, to forbear the like for the <hi>future.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſince they are unwilling (and not without reaſon neither) to confeſs themſelves (otherwiſe than as <hi>Popiſh Fanatick<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>) guilty of the Diſorders that commenced in <hi>England</hi> in 1641; it may not be altogether impertinent, in this place, to inquire into their proceedings, under the name of <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks</hi> (a Title ſo immoderately affected by them) in the Civil Wars of <hi>Franc<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> in 1572, I ſhall therefore preſume (in imitation of our Learned <hi>Obſervators Method</hi>) to ask Who they were that maſſacred ſuch numbers of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47905:7"/>
               <hi>Hugonots</hi> in <hi>Paris</hi> and <hi>elſewhere,</hi> in cold Blood, and without any cauſe or provocation, other than that they were <hi>honeſter</hi> men and <hi>better</hi> Subjects than themſelves? <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Me</hi> muſt anſwer for them; <hi>theſe Catholicks</hi>! Who were they that, by force of Arms, drove their Lawful Prince (<hi>Henry</hi> the Third) out of the Capital <hi>City</hi> of his Kingdom; entered into a <hi>Treaſonous Combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or <hi>Holy League</hi>; (the <hi>Architype</hi> of our <hi>Solemn League and Covenant</hi>) raiſed a <hi>Religious</hi> Rebellion againſt him, under the <hi>Popes</hi> Banner; purſued him with Fire and Sword; and at length by the hand of one of their <hi>Prieſts</hi> ſtabbed him to the heart? The <hi>Catholicks</hi>! Who were they that proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſame Rebellion againſt his Rightful Succeſſor <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Fourth</hi>; called in a <hi>Foreign</hi> Power upon him; fought him in ſundry <hi>Pitched Fields</hi>; attempted upon his <hi>Perſon</hi> both by Sword and Poyſon; ſwore themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a freſh <hi>Engagement,</hi> never to admit him (or any other) to the Throne of <hi>France</hi>; but upon the terms of his being a <hi>Catholick,</hi> &amp;c. In a word, who were they that, when they had brought him over to hear <hi>Maſs</hi> (while he was in a <hi>good mind</hi>) ſpilt his Blood (by one of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi>) in the face of the Sun, and in the open Streets of <hi>Paris</hi>? why, the very ſame pretended <hi>Catholicks</hi> ſtill!</p>
            <p>Now our hand is in, and that we ſee what theſe <hi>Modern</hi> are; I hope it will not ſeem tedious if we take a ſhort view of the Behaviour, in the like caſes, of the <hi>Primitive Catholicks.</hi> Who were they then that would ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er renounce their <hi>Breath,</hi> than their <hi>Allegiance</hi>; or then be engaged in Arms againſt their Lawful Soveraign (whether <hi>Chriſtian, Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentile</hi>) or any duly <hi>Commiſſioned</hi> by him? The <hi>Primitive Catholicks</hi>! Who were they that held his <hi>perſon</hi> to be ſacred; that accounted the leaſt <hi>Violation</hi> of his Royal <hi>Prerogative,</hi> a <hi>Sacrilege</hi>; that would rather chuſe to die by <hi>Inches,</hi> than to lift up their hand againſt the <hi>Lords anointed</hi>; and that were ſtill in readineſs to ſacrifice their Lives, Fortunes, and all that was dear to them, in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of their <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Country</hi>? Theſe! theſe were (and, in <hi>modern Praiſe,</hi> are the <hi>Church of England Men,</hi> or) the <hi>true Catholicks.</hi> The Uſe and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of all <hi>this</hi> is ſo natural, and obvious, that any Deſcant or Remark upon it would be a ſuperfluity; the Goodneſs of the <hi>Tree</hi> being ever more known by the quality of its <hi>Fruit.</hi> So that I ſhall now return to tell the <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervator,</hi> that the ſecond <hi>Paragraph</hi> of this his ſeventh <hi>Page</hi> will readily be allowed him, upon the ſingle condition of its being underſtood in the <hi>ſenſe</hi> that himſelf really intended it (and that all other paſſionate <hi>Declamations</hi> of the like nature, by a private <hi>Key</hi> well known to themſelves, are uſually ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in;) that is to ſay as an <hi>Encomium</hi> upon <hi>Holy Church</hi> for certain pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Villanies,</hi> by the ſucceſsful courage &amp; conduct of her <hi>Votaries</hi> perpetrated againſt a Race of <hi>unregenerate Hereticks.</hi> And whereas, in the <hi>fourth,</hi> he ſays that <hi>Papiſts</hi> leave <hi>Monarchy</hi> the full Liberty of the <hi>Law:</hi> I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member him, that it is only becauſe they cannot do otherwiſe; and that a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:47905:8"/>
greater liberty than <hi>that</hi> will allow, muſt be had, before ſuch as he gain their ends upon us. But in his next <hi>Break</hi> he falls again to proclaiming the <hi>Merits</hi> of the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> and the <hi>Malice</hi> of the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> at ſuch a rate, as if <hi>Ireland</hi> had not ſtood in need of an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Indempnity</hi> as well as <hi>England.</hi> 'Tis a hard matter I find to make this <hi>Obſervator</hi> ſee on the <hi>Right</hi> Side.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Pag.</hi> 8. he will not allow the Jeſuites, <hi>Simond</hi> and <hi>Carleton,</hi> to have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered a thouſand pounds for the King's Diſcovery after his eſcape at <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> becauſe he knows there were others then to be found, as able and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling as they, to disburſe ſuch a Sum upon <hi>that</hi> account. To the <hi>Deponents</hi> affirming that <hi>Oliver</hi> kept a <hi>Convent</hi> (they call the ſame thing by another name) of <hi>Benedictines,</hi> he ſhapes an <hi>Anſwer</hi> as if he would have it thought that there are no ſuch people as the <hi>Benedictines</hi> in the world. Then he paſſes his <hi>Word</hi> (which is of little value, upon <hi>this Score</hi> eſpecially) for <hi>Mannings</hi> honeſty, whiles a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> only becauſe the <hi>Deponent</hi> avows the contrary. And thus having, in his own imagination, cleared the <hi>Coaſt,</hi> and got the <hi>wind</hi> of his <hi>Antagoniſt,</hi> he falls to inſulting over him, in this manner; <hi>By your honeſty</hi> (ſays he) <hi>in relating things done in the ſight of the Sun, and known to all men, we ſee what credit you deſerve in things done in corners, and known only to your ſelf.</hi> A mighty <hi>Cry</hi> truly; but I'm afraid we ſhall find but little <hi>Wool</hi> come after it!</p>
            <p>The <hi>Deponent</hi> then asks (<hi>Ep. Ded.</hi> of the <hi>Narrat. fol.</hi> 3.) <hi>What Arguments can perſwade them to be true to their Natural, who profeſs allegiance, out of conſcience, to a Foreign, contrary Soveraign?</hi> And the <hi>other</hi> anſwers to this purpoſe; that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> profeſs <hi>allegiance</hi> to a foreign <hi>Soveraign</hi> in <hi>temporal</hi> Concerns only in order to <hi>ſpirituals.</hi> An acute Reply! I promiſe you. He next pinches him for recommending it to the King to truſt to, and rely upon his <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>; chopping and changing his <hi>words</hi> moſt <hi>Jeſuitically,</hi> to make them ſpeak as he would have them. But I'll give both fair <hi>Play,</hi> by tranſcribing the <hi>paſſage</hi> it ſelf; and ſo leave it to be judged which has the better on't.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Next to Chriſt and the Truth (ſays the <hi>Deponent, Epiſt. Ded.</hi> to his <hi>Narrat. fol.</hi> 4 &amp; 5,) I ſhall with the utmoſt of my breath and power, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my Oath and Duty, in what place and ſtation ſoever I am, endeavour to be found ever Loyal and True to your Majeſty in all your Rights and Honours, as all good Subjects and Chriſtians ought, and as I find this Noble and Loyal Parliament are reſolv'd to be to an hair, or an expreſſion; and therefore cannot forbear to pray to God, out of my ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity and zeal for publick Peace and Concord between King and People, that, ſeeing your Majeſty muſt highly truſt ſome or other for your neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary eaſe and help, God would put it into your Majeſties Heart more to truſt and rely upon your two Houſes of <hi>Parliament</hi> (who will be moſt true to your Laws, and conſequently both to You and your People) than
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:47905:8"/>
to any <hi>ſingle Miniſter</hi> or <hi>Miniſters</hi> whatſoever, unaccountably, who may pretend to more Loyalty, or more comply with any humour, or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane frailty of your Majeſties, but are not true Friends either to your Majeſty or their Country, or themſelves, therein; but erect and prefer an Imperial <hi>Paramount</hi> Self-end, or Luſt, before all; which your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, by their art, muſt be brought unworthily to ſerve and promote, to publick diſturbance <hi>always,</hi> and the confuſion of themſelves and their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity <hi>moſt an end,</hi> by God's juſt vengeance. It is a falſe ſuggeſtion which ſuch <hi>tempters</hi> uſe, that a King that rules by <hi>will</hi> is more great, or glorious, or ſtrong, than a King that rules by <hi>Law.</hi> The quality of the Retinue beſt proves the State of the Lord; the one being but a King of Slaves, while the other, like God, is a King of Kings and Hearts. No Prince was ever more abſolute, to have what he wiſhed, than Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> who wiſhed for nothing more than the Subjects Right and Well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare—But nothing will make your Majeſty ſo amiable and acceptable in the Eyes of God and Man, and your Name and Memory bleſſed and glorious for ever, as the copying of the Laws of our <hi>Saviour</hi> in your Life, by a decent, paternal Example before the Sons and Daughters of your People, to encreaſe the fear of God, and its Conſequences amongſt us; it being the chief end and work of all ſupreme Powers to ſuppreſs Vice, and encourage Virtue amongſt their Charge, according to S. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 13. which is beſt done abroad, when it is firſt and effectually begun at home in your own Houſe and Family, (according to the ſame Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.) by baniſhing all vicious Livers from your Preſence and Converſe, and advancing the Virtuous in their ſtead: by the neglect of which princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal part of their Royal Truſt, and Office, Princes depoſe themſelves as uſeleſs before God and their own Conſciences, whatever may be their State and Glory in fact, and by humane Laws and Power, before Men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>After this; only with queſtioning the ſincerity of the <hi>Deponents</hi> Prayers for the King, he ſhuts up his <hi>Obſervations</hi> upon the <hi>Epiſtle Dedicatory,</hi> and undertakes for a Diſcovery of the <hi>Lyes</hi> in the <hi>Narrative</hi> it ſelf: as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="section">
            <head>SECT. IV.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> firſt thing we meet with in his <hi>ſecond Chapter,</hi> is this <hi>homely Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> to the <hi>Deponent. To tell Lyes,</hi> (ſays he, <hi>pag.</hi> 9.) <hi>ſeems as natural to you, as breathing; nothing comes from you without them.</hi> So he forthwith lays to his charge a great Lye (as he is pleaſed to call it) in ſaying in his <hi>Preface</hi> to the Reader, that his <hi>Narrative</hi> was preſented to his Majeſty the thirteenth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> when as it contains things which happened on the 3, 4, 6, 7, &amp; 8
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:47905:9"/>
of <hi>Sept.</hi> after. Now I muſt mind him, that this (if it be a <hi>Lye</hi>) is one of his own framing, by making it the <hi>whole,</hi> when the <hi>Deponent</hi> there plainly declares it was only <hi>part</hi> of it, that was delivered as is above ſpecified: <hi>Thomas</hi> Earl of <hi>Danby</hi>'s Caſe furniſhes an account of the manner of this Delivery: where ſatisfaction may be had as to this matter.</p>
            <p>Then he call it another great <hi>Lye,</hi> his ſaying that it was ſworn the ſixth of <hi>Sept.</hi> following, when both <hi>himſelf,</hi> and Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey,</hi> aſſure, that it was ſworn the twenty ſeventh of <hi>September</hi>: I cannot but take notice here how diſingenuous the <hi>Obſervator</hi> is: for when he is willing to <hi>paum</hi> a <hi>Contradiction</hi> upon the <hi>Deponent,</hi> he makes no Bones (I ſee) of ranſacking this and t'other <hi>Tryal,</hi> &amp;c. and turning every Stone, to add ſtrength to the <hi>Preſumption:</hi> but, when it is to do him even <hi>common Right,</hi> he will not ſo much as put his foot o'er the Threſhold. Now he muſt needs (ſure) have read ſomewhere, as well as my ſelf, that the <hi>Deponent</hi> firſt ſwore the <hi>Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Copy</hi> of the <hi>Narrative</hi> before <hi>Juſtice Godfrey</hi> on the ſixth of <hi>September,</hi> (probably) and after <hi>That,</hi> tranſcribed with his own hand, and ſwore di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <hi>others</hi> of them in the like manner, and according to the date that <hi>this</hi> Printed One bears. Thus much I conceive to be ſufficient for the reſolving of this <hi>doubt:</hi> but whether it be the <hi>true,</hi> or <hi>only</hi> Reaſon of the Differences of theſe <hi>Dates,</hi> I have neither <hi>means</hi> nor <hi>leiſure</hi> to be rightly informed. Thus we may ſee that the <hi>Obſervator</hi> is more unfortunate in his endeavours to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect</hi> theſe pretended <hi>Lyes,</hi> than he will needs have the <hi>Deponent</hi> to be in <hi>timing</hi> them. But now I muſt take the freedom to obſerve two <hi>trips</hi> upon the <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator</hi> himſelf. 1. <hi>Himſelf and Sir Edmundbury Godfrey aſſure,</hi> &amp;c. he ſays; when the <hi>Deponent</hi> affirms no ſuch thing; his <hi>Affidavit</hi> bearing date the twenty ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth of <hi>September,</hi> and his <hi>Atteſtation</hi> before the <hi>Council</hi> the twenty eighth. 2. Whereas he refers to <hi>fol.</hi> 62 of the <hi>Narrative</hi> for the <hi>aſſurance</hi> aforeſaid: if he had but put on his <hi>Spectacles</hi> again he would have found it (in <hi>my</hi> Book at leaſt) only the ſixtieth <hi>folio.</hi> The Gentleman, it ſeems, for all his big words, is no more <hi>infallible</hi> than his Neighbours: and conſequently no otherwiſe to be reſpected. But yet, all the world could not hinder him from grounding barely upon theſe <hi>Surmizes,</hi> a <hi>Salute</hi> to the <hi>Deponent</hi>: Thus. <hi>By this</hi> (ſays he) <hi>your Reader may gueſs what ſincerity he is to expect from you in the following</hi> Narrative, <hi>of which he meets ſo little in your</hi> Addreſs <hi>to him. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed</hi> (and indeed) <hi>your writings like the</hi> Cadmaean <hi>Brood</hi> (moſt Learnedly hinted) <hi>fight againſt, and ruine one another: They are like</hi> Chymaeras (moſt profoundly <hi>Pedantick</hi> ſtill!) <hi>which being compoſed of Contradictions</hi> (O how happy were he, could he but ſpy 'em once! <hi>one part deſtroys the other.</hi> The man's reſolv'd to throw <hi>dirt</hi> enough, (I ſee) thinking if ſome of it ſtick not, (none of it will) the devil's in't: as no doubt he is.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="section">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:47905:9"/>
            <head>SECT· V.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THIS third Chapter</hi> of his, promiſes a Diſcovery (like the <hi>former</hi> no doubt) of the <hi>Lies</hi> contained in the ſeven firſt <hi>Sections</hi> (or §) of the <hi>Narrative,</hi> which comprize the <hi>Deponents</hi> Informations from <hi>Spain.</hi> Againſt § 1. he raiſes two <hi>Objections (pag.</hi> 10.) the <hi>firſt,</hi> that <hi>Strange</hi> (in <hi>Atteſt. G. pag</hi> 50.) denies the writing of the Letters there mentioned. He does well; for why ſhould he himſelf adminiſter unneceſſary occaſion to be ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for a <hi>fool,</hi> when it is only his <hi>Knavery,</hi> that is here the ſubject of the Controverſie? And alſo for that <hi>Atteſt. C. (pag.</hi> 45.) proteſts it to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the <hi>Jeſuits Cuſtoms</hi> for <hi>many</hi> to ſign Letters together with their <hi>Provincial.</hi> Now becauſe he deſires that <hi>this may be taken notice of,</hi> for that <hi>the ſame miſtake</hi> (he ſays) <hi>freqaently occurrs</hi>; I will, in this place, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſo much upon it, as not to need troubling my ſelf any further with it, when it falls in my way hereafter. He ſpeaks as if the <hi>Jeſuites Cuſtoms</hi> were as <hi>unalterable</hi> as the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> and as if it were equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to a ſin againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> for any of their <hi>Religious</hi> in the leaſt to ſwerve from the <hi>Inſtitutions</hi> of their <hi>Founders.</hi> But this is not ſo: for even the <hi>Franciſcans</hi> themſelves, who pretend to a greater ſtrictneſs than the reſt in this particular, have yet made ſo bold with the <hi>Rule</hi> their Patron left them, as to expound the <hi>ſeverity</hi> of it into a conſiſtency with, and indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of their <hi>Eaſe</hi> and <hi>Convenience,</hi> upon ſundry accounts. I ſhall inſtance only in <hi>Two</hi> of the <hi>groſſer</hi> ſort. S. <hi>Francis</hi> injoyned all the <hi>Children</hi> of his <hi>Spirit</hi> to go <hi>Bare-foot:</hi> but they, finding themſelves hereby in danger of catching cold, or of taking harm by Thorns, Snakes, Sharp Stones, and the like, moderated the <hi>Rule</hi> (as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> tells us) to an allowance of their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>half-ſhod:</hi> ſaving however the dignity of the <hi>Preſcription</hi> by a <hi>Synechdoche,</hi> which takes that <hi>part</hi> of the foot which is ſeen <hi>naked</hi> through the Shooe, for the <hi>whole.</hi> Again. He alſo forbade them <hi>to receive any money either by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or by others.</hi> Now they ſoon experimenting the Inconvenience of <hi>This,</hi> took the liberty to change, <hi>not receive</hi> into, <hi>not touch.</hi> So that they take no money but with their <hi>Gloves</hi> on, or wrapt in a <hi>Clout,</hi> or by their <hi>Proctors,</hi> which (in <hi>that</hi> caſe only) they will not allow to be their <hi>own</hi> act and deed. But theſe <hi>thick-Scull'd Evaſions</hi> are not worthy of the <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nery</hi> of our <hi>Mercurial Jeſuites</hi>; whoſe ſmooth and ſubtle <hi>Gloſſes</hi> upon the <hi>Text</hi> of <hi>Loyola</hi> are ſo many and ſo notorious, that it would be ſuperfluous to recount them: ſo that I rather chuſe to enquire into their Treatment of the <hi>Holy Goſpel</hi> it ſelf. In the <hi>Indies,</hi> and in <hi>China,</hi> where the Belief of a <hi>Crucified God</hi> is accounted <hi>Extravagance,</hi> every body knows that it is their <hi>cuſtom</hi> there to ſmother the ſcandal of the <hi>Croſs,</hi> and preach only a <hi>Glorified,</hi> not a <hi>Crucifyed Jeſus Chriſt</hi>; and that they allow the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to commit <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:47905:10"/>
by warrant of a pretty invention of theirs, which is, to hide under their Cloaths an <hi>Image</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and ſo, by a <hi>mental Reſervation,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect to <hi>It</hi> thoſe publick Adorations which they render the Idol <hi>Cachim Choan,</hi> and their <hi>Keum Fucum.</hi> And for their <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Probabilities,</hi> which has render'd them ſo infamouſly famous all the world over; eight and forty of the modern <hi>Caſuiſts,</hi> viz. <hi>Villalobas, Conink<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Llamas, Achokier, Dealkozer, Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acruz, Vera Cruz, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>golin, Tambourim, Fernandez, Martinez, Suarez, Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riquez, Vaſquez, Lopez, Gomez, Sanchez, De Vecchis, De Graſſis, De Graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalis, De Pitigianis, De Graphatis, Squilanti, Bizozeri, Barcola, De Bobadilla, Simancha, Berez, De Lara, Aldreffa, Lorca, De Scarcia, Quaranta, Scophra, Jedrezza, Cabrezza, Biſhe, Dias, De Claviſio, Villagu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Adam à Manden, Iribarn, Binsfeld, Volfangi à Vorberg, Voſthery,</hi> and <hi>Streueſdorf,</hi> do lay down theſe as Fundamental Maxims, that, <hi>to deny abſolution to a penitent who walks according to a</hi> probable opinion <hi>is a ſin in its own nature mortal</hi>; and that <hi>no Judge or Civil Magiſtrate, in this caſe, ought to condemn any ſuch.</hi> And then unanimouſly declare, <hi>that</hi> it is lawful for one man to kill another, to prevent a Box o'th' ear, or a Blow with a Stick, or for giving him the Lye or any way <hi>Reviling</hi> him: For a <hi>Religious</hi> Man to kill him that leſſens his <hi>Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or only threatens ſo to do; as alſo any <hi>woman</hi> that he has abuſed, if ſhe go about to diſcover what paſſed between them; or any <hi>man</hi> that takes him in the act of making him a <hi>Cuckold: To</hi> ſay <hi>Maſs</hi> while he is under a <hi>mortal</hi> ſin, if he has taken money to that end, and, after he has received money of one man to ſay <hi>Maſs,</hi> to take of another as much as that part (a <hi>Third</hi>) of the Sacrifice which belongs to himſelf amounts to: <hi>For</hi> a man to defend his <hi>honour</hi> againſt one that would rob him of it, by charging ſuch a perſon with a <hi>Crime</hi> he is not guilty of, or by <hi>killing</hi> him; and not <hi>Him</hi> only, but even the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> produced by him, nay, and the very <hi>Judge</hi> himſelf, when he cannot be otherwiſe diverted from oppreſſing the innocent: <hi>To</hi> procure <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bortion</hi> before the Child be quick in the Womb, to ſave a Maids Life or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation: <hi>to</hi> fight Duels; or to kill him that takes our Goods from us, even tho' he run away to avoid it, it they be of value: <hi>For</hi> a <hi>Son</hi> to ſteal from his <hi>Father,</hi> or a <hi>Servant</hi> from his <hi>Maſter,</hi> if their Services be not recompenſed as they think they deſerve; <hi>for</hi> a <hi>Tradeſman</hi> to uſe <hi>falſe weights:</hi> a <hi>Judge</hi> to take <hi>Bribes</hi>; an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſerer, Extortion</hi>; a <hi>Prieſt</hi> to buy a Benefice, (without being guilty of <hi>Simony</hi>) tempt <hi>Women,</hi> and commit <hi>Adultery:</hi> And <hi>that</hi> the <hi>Clergy</hi> are not ſubjected to ſecular Princes, nor obliged to any obedience to the <hi>Laws,</hi> even tho' they are not any way contrary to the ſtate <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi>: that no Penal <hi>Laws</hi> are obligatory in point of <hi>Conſcience; that</hi> it is no ſin for Subjects to refuſe paying <hi>Taxes,</hi> or ſubmitting to a <hi>Law</hi> that has been duly proclaimed: <hi>that</hi> a man preſcribed by a <hi>Temporal</hi> Prince may not be killed out of his Territories; but one outlawed by the <hi>Pope</hi> may be killed in any part of the world; becauſe <hi>his</hi> Juriſdiction extends over <hi>all; that</hi> as well <hi>in</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:47905:10"/>
Judgment as <hi>out</hi> of Judgment a man may ſafely ſwear with a <hi>Mental Reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> without any regard had to the intention of him who obliges him to ſwear; <hi>that</hi> it is not <hi>Adultery</hi> to abuſe a <hi>married</hi> woman, if the <hi>Husband</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to it; <hi>that</hi> a man may be ſaved in any <hi>Sect</hi> or <hi>Hereſie; that</hi> an <hi>Infidel</hi> is not obliged to embrace the <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> tho' all his life-time, and even at the hour of death, he believe it to be the <hi>Right; that</hi> it is no ſin or irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence againſt God to addreſs himſelf to him in devotions, under an actual inclination <hi>mortally</hi> to offend him; and <hi>that</hi> there is no neceſſity that a man ready to die, ſhould, in order to the receiving the Remiſſion of his Sins of <hi>God,</hi> have a true deſire to reform his Life, if <hi>God</hi> ſhould ſpare it him a while; and that he may obtain it by the abſolution of a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> tho' he be in ſuch a diſpoſition, as to matter of <hi>Repentance,</hi> that if he were but confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent he ſhould live any longer, he would neither confeſs, nor quit his Sins at all, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> From this <hi>Taſte,</hi> of theſe peoples <hi>Morals,</hi> extracted out of their own <hi>Writings</hi> by one of their own <hi>Church,</hi> (the Author of the <hi>Myſt. of Jeſuit.</hi>) a Body may reaſonably and charitably infer, that not <hi>this</hi> now in queſtion, (if ſuch a one there really be) nor any other <hi>Preſcription</hi> (how ſacred ſoever) will be at all regarded by a <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> if it ſtand in oppoſition to his <hi>Intereſt.</hi> But alas! this <hi>cuſtom</hi> is ſo far from bearing a ſtamp of <hi>Loyola</hi>'s <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> (tho' in truth, it were all a caſe to <hi>them,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> too, if it did) that it ſeems it is only a <hi>By-Law,</hi> ſuperinduced to ſerve a particular occaſion, and (with diverſe others of the like value) is obſerved or neglected at the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincials</hi> pleaſure, who in all ſuch caſes is unaccountable in his Doings. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that it is haughty, irrational, and in twenty reſpects impracticable. Nay, and tho' it were not all <hi>this</hi>; yet would it be of no ſort of avail to them in any Court of <hi>Juſtice</hi>; it amounting to no more than if one of them ſhould <hi>there</hi> alledge his <hi>Vow</hi> of <hi>Continence</hi> to invalidate a poſitive <hi>Oath</hi> that he was taken in the very act of a <hi>Rape.</hi> As to the <hi>Atteſtation</hi> (C) (over and above that it is not of credit, as being made by none but <hi>Jeſuits</hi>) it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pretends to make it a <hi>cuſtom,</hi> and is not poſitive that it was ever put into <hi>practice</hi>—What the <hi>Deponent</hi> himſelf has to ſay to <hi>this</hi> ſuggeſtion, I am wholly ignorant; yet am prone to believe that he is able to give full ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction upon the point; till that be done, what is above delivered may perhaps be deemed ſufficient to raiſe a reaſonable ſuſpicion of its <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>ſecond Objection</hi> (or <hi>Lye,</hi> if you pleaſe) againſt this ſame Section has not one Syllable or Circumſtance to ſupport it ſelf upon, but only his own bare <hi>word</hi>; this I find he is very free of at every end and turn; but here eſpecially he ſquanders it about at ſuch a profuſe rate, that it looks as if it were done on ſet purpoſe to have it thought that he values it no more than the dirt under his ſhooes: paſſing it for (more than any body, in reaſon, is able to undertake) a man's <hi>motions</hi> and <hi>behaviour</hi> the <hi>whole year</hi> round. Did he
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:47905:11"/>
but mean either <hi>modeſtly,</hi> or <hi>well,</hi> he would certainly be more circumſpect, and not give underſtanding and indifferent men ſuch frequent occaſions of commiſerating his <hi>Levity</hi> and <hi>Weakneſs.</hi> Why ſhould he be ſo childiſh as to make himſelf reſponſible for this and t'other bodies integrity, hand over head, and at a venture: or to fancy that ſober Heads will give any ſort of heed to him, tho' he does? But we muſt (out of meet charity) allow of <hi>Garaſſus</hi>'s Apology for him. When <hi>great Wits (ſays he</hi> in his <hi>Summary of Truths, part</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 419.) are delivered of ſome excellent Work, they are juſtly recompenſed with <hi>publick</hi> Acclamations: but when an <hi>ordinary Ingenuity</hi> takes a great deal of pains to do ſomewhat that amounts to very little, or nothing at all, (like this pretended <hi>Vindication</hi>) and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently cannot lay claim to any <hi>publick</hi> applauſe; that his labour may not go without reward, God gives him a certain <hi>perſonal</hi> Complacency, which, without an injuſtice more than barbarous, cannot be envied him. Thus doth God, who is juſt, give the very <hi>Frogs</hi> a certain ſatisfaction in their <hi>Croaking,</hi> &amp;c. Now I am content, that he ſhould hug <hi>himſelf</hi> for this his elaborate production; provided he do but keep within compaſs. But if he will needs (and with ſo little reaſon too) advance at every turn to a lofty and magiſterial ſuperciliouſneſs; take up with nothing leſs than an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, at pleaſure, to ſhuffle upon the world his own <hi>Whims,</hi> and Sophiſtries, for Oraculous Inſpirations, he ought not to take it ill if he be flouted and contemned for his labour even to the degree of queſtioning an otherwiſe <hi>probable Relation,</hi> meerly becauſe no <hi>creditabler</hi> a man than he is found to be the <hi>avoucher</hi> of it. In ſhort; let his <hi>pretences</hi> be what they will, he muſt excuſe me for telling him, that I am not yet able to find any good cauſe to truſt him further than he may be ſeen. And yet nothing can ſtay him from <hi>reaſoning</hi> thus ſtrongly upon Sect. 2. <hi>If</hi> (ſays he, <hi>pag.</hi> 10.) <hi>there were no ſuch Letters,</hi> (as <hi>he</hi> will have it there were not, and the <hi>other</hi> ſwears there were) <hi>they could not be broke open at</hi> Burgos. This <hi>Booby's Play</hi> they would never endure in a <hi>Proteſtant</hi>; why ſhould we heed it then in a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt?</p>
            <p>He labours to make Sect. 3. ſpeak <hi>four</hi> Lyes, after this manner. 1. He alledges that the twelve <hi>Students</hi> there mentioned were actually ſent by the <hi>Rector</hi> or <hi>Vice Rector</hi> only; (but not a word againſt its being done by the joynt conſent and concurrence of the other perſons alſo, named by the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent.</hi>) not forgetting to ſay over again, that all their <hi>Patents</hi> had but <hi>one</hi> name a piece to them. 2. That the (ordinary) <hi>Oath of theſe Colleges</hi> does not preſs the renouncing of their <hi>Allegiance,</hi> but only obliges to peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able demeanour, become <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and return into <hi>England.</hi> By this <hi>Confeſſion</hi> you may ſee they do yet ſwear them to be <hi>Traitors, ipſo facto</hi>; for they are not to be told at this time a day, that for an <hi>Engliſh Man</hi> to take orders at <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp;c. and come over again after he has ſo done, is <hi>High-Treaſon</hi> by one
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:47905:11"/>
               <hi>Law.</hi> And I would fain know of him too, whether they might not add ſuch Clauſes to the <hi>Old,</hi> or ſo frame a <hi>new</hi> Oath, (to be taken as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of their admittance) as might beſt tend to the advancing and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing thoſe great and extraordinary <hi>Deſigns,</hi> that it appears they had then in agitation againſt us? But upon this point he is as Mute as a <hi>Fiſh.</hi> Let it be yet further noted; that in the latter part of this § (which (I ſuppoſe) the <hi>Obſervator</hi> thought too hot or too heavy to be meddled with) the <hi>Deponent</hi> ſeems to expound this <hi>renouncing of</hi> their <hi>Allegiance</hi> to be only a <hi>diſclaiming</hi> of the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> which <hi>Daniel Armſtrong</hi> called Heretical, Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and Deviliſh. It was alſo the work of two <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> ſome time ſince, (their Books are in <hi>Print</hi>) to endeavour to prove it ſuch: and a Letter of a much later date, (<hi>May</hi> 24, 78, or 9,) written by another <hi>Jeſuit</hi> (one <hi>Pracid</hi>) to Sir <hi>T. G.</hi> (to be found in his Tryal <hi>fol.</hi> 35.) has this remarkable paſſage in it, <hi>I have a Letter from our</hi> Superior <hi>at</hi> London, <hi>wherein he declares (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging</hi> authority) <hi>That</hi> the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance</hi> cannot be taken as it is word<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; adding, that three <hi>Breves</hi> have formerly been ſent from the <hi>Pope,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly prohibiting it: and in the <hi>Third</hi> it is declared <hi>damnable</hi> to take it. And yeſterday, we had a Letter communicated amongſt us, ſent by Mr. <hi>Middleton</hi> (now at <hi>Paris</hi>) to his Friends here, containing the <hi>Atteſtation</hi> of of all the <hi>Sorbon</hi> Doctors againſt it: adding, that whoſoever here in <hi>England</hi> give leave, they deceive the <hi>People,</hi> &amp; are <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>Whole Catholick Church.</hi> There was alſo a <hi>Meeting</hi> ſome years ago, of all the <hi>Superiors</hi> both <hi>Secular</hi> and <hi>Regular,</hi> wherein it is unanimouſly declared that it could <hi>not</hi> be taken, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now if this be ſo; what can be imagined more probable, than that they ſhould oblige their <hi>Novices,</hi> upon their Entrance, to diſavow an unto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Oath,</hi> of which they have ſo ill an opinion? 3. (and 4 too) He would have us believe that no body is bound to take any Oath at all till after a years abode there. But this is purely <hi>confident talk</hi>; and confutable by ſundry experiences: beſide that extraordinary times (ſuch as thoſe were) do ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily require extraordinary Methods and Impoſitions.</p>
            <p>In Sect. 4. the <hi>Obſervator</hi> pretends to the diſcovery only of two Lyes, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. he denies that the Letters brought by <hi>D. Armſtrong</hi> were ſubſcribed by more than the <hi>Rector.</hi> This <hi>Atteſt.</hi> C. would have believed: but it is only the old Story over again; and has been ſpoken to already. 2. That their <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents</hi> were treaſonous; labouring to make it out that they were not, by the <hi>Atteſt.</hi> D, K, O, Q: (<hi>pag.</hi> 45.52.54.55.) Now as to Atteſt. D, whoever is ambitious of ſeeing a <hi>Panegyrick</hi> upon the perfections of the Holy College of S. <hi>Omers</hi> in particular, drawn up by their own dear hands in ſo ambiguous a <hi>phraſe,</hi> that it looks more like a <hi>common place,</hi> or <hi>inſtructions</hi> for their young <hi>Miſſionaries</hi> to govern themſelves by, when they ſhould be called before the <hi>Bench</hi> here, than any Paper of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity</hi> and <hi>Credit,</hi> and as like that of <hi>Valderma</hi> (in his <hi>Canonization</hi> of <hi>Ignatius,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:47905:12"/>
pag.</hi> 10.) upon the <hi>Society</hi> of <hi>Jeſus</hi> in <hi>general</hi> as ever it can ſtare, <hi>viz. [The foundation of the Society of Jeſus</hi> (ſays he) <hi>bears date with the critical minute of the miraculous Conception of Jeſus Chriſt, when there became a perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion between our Humanity, and his eternal Divinity. This was the firſt Society that ever God inſtituted among men, and whereof the firſt College was the Womb of the Bleſſed Virgin—The Apoſtle S.</hi> Paul (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.9.) <hi>makes mention alſo of the Society of Jeſus,</hi> God is faithful, by whom we are called unto the fellowſhip <hi>or Society</hi> of his Son Jeſus Chriſt. And 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.3. That our Fellowſhip or Society may be with the Father and with his Son Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Hence it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears</hi> (ſays <hi>Arturus) that there was ſuch a thing as the</hi> Society <hi>of</hi> Jeſus <hi>extant even in the Apoſtles times; and therefore the erection of it is not of late, as</hi> Sadeel <hi>ſatyrically inſinuates.</hi>] I would recommend this ſame Atteſtation <hi>D</hi> to his peruſal: where he ſhall alſo find ſome of the preciouſeſt <hi>Plants</hi> of this <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Society,</hi> denying point blank the Treaſons charged upon them, by the <hi>Deponent</hi> and no more. Bleſs me! will theſe men never be ſayd: but ſtill run on amuſing the People with their <hi>Impoſtures</hi> and <hi>Impertinences?</hi> Why, even this very <hi>Trifle</hi> was offered to the <hi>Court</hi> at the Tryal of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and there rejected as an <hi>Evidence</hi> moſt ridiculouſly incompetent, and of ſuch a nature too, as it was not doubted but that twenty of the like might have been had upon eaſie terms. The <hi>Atteſt.</hi> K and O are of ſomewhat a worſer ſtrain (if poſſible) than the former; being only bare <hi>Negatives,</hi> and that too, neither upon <hi>Oath,</hi> nor before a <hi>Magiſtrate</hi>; no more than are <hi>Atteſt.</hi> G, S, T, &amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 50, 56. And Q is rather a <hi>Reference</hi> than an <hi>Atteſtation,</hi>; and runs all along in the <hi>Third Perſon</hi>; which would be enough to render ſuſpected the Truth of all the reſt, were it not that the <hi>Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> is ſo ready to become anſwerable for all his Brethren, even without a probability of conſulting them. Never ſure was there ſo much folly and confidence ſeen or heard of before! for ſhould ſimple <hi>Denials</hi> come once to be admitted for proofs of Innocence; farewel all Conviction of Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, and Courts of Juſtice; and mankind would be turn'd into one great Den of Thieves and Robbers, that might ſpoil, plunder, murther and raviſh without controul. And yet this, and not one jot more than this is all that comes of the <hi>Obſervator's</hi> promiſe (<hi>pag.</hi> 4.) <hi>to prove irrefragably what he advances, with ſuch evidence, that unleſs his Adverſaries ſhut their Eyes very hard, they ſhall ſee their innocence, and the wrong done them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. <hi>pag</hi> 11. he <hi>trifles</hi> at the ſame confident and extravagant rate, affirming that <hi>neither F. Suiman nor</hi> any other (mind <hi>that!) ever heard of any ſuch News.</hi> And <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. ſtands charged with two <hi>Lyes</hi> more, which he endeavours to make out juſt as idly as he has done the former; only he recommends <hi>Atteſtation</hi> L (<hi>pag.</hi> 52.) to conſideration: and the ſubſtance of it is <hi>this</hi>; (for it has not yet been taken notice of:) That a <hi>Publick Notary</hi> averrs that the <hi>Rector</hi> and <hi>Procurator</hi> of the College of S.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:47905:12"/>
               <hi>Alban</hi> ſwore to him, that the <hi>Deponent</hi> came thither on the eleventh of <hi>June,</hi> and went not thence till <hi>Oct.</hi> 29 following; becauſe they found it ſo ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in their <hi>Day-Book</hi> (which can ſpeak as they would have it beyond per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure!) Thus they would fain inſinuate that he never was at <hi>Madrid,</hi> as they had before done, when that pretenſe might be of uſe to them, that he was not in <hi>England.</hi> But how can it be expected that theſe People ſhould boggle at any <hi>Aſſeveration,</hi> who have had the confidence, not only in <hi>Print,</hi> but in open <hi>Court</hi> too, to avouch for the actions of a <hi>Criminal,</hi> a whole Twelve month together. But he is not yet aſham'd (I ſee) of his ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny childiſh and ſpiteful Inferences; for even here he's got to his old <hi>Haunt</hi> again, and tells the <hi>Deponent</hi> (believe it who liſt) that <hi>unleſs he were in two places at one time, he could not be at</hi> Madrid. His Notes upon the ſeventh Section are ſtill the ſame indigeſted Fopperies over and over; and therefore I ſhall paſs them by, all but his <hi>Atteſtation</hi> R (<hi>pag.</hi> 55.) which intimates that one <hi>B. L.</hi> (or <hi>Baſil Langworth</hi>) made Oath before the <hi>Bayly</hi> of <hi>Watten,</hi> that the <hi>Deponent</hi> had accuſed him of Treaſon (the Man's Conſcience was not at all skittiſh, it ſeems!) but he on the other ſide proteſted, that in ſo doing he lyed in every particular: only he recollected himſelf that he was at the Congregation in <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>April,</hi> 1678; tho' he forgets not to alledge, that others by him named were not: the <hi>Obſervator</hi> then ſteps in, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures that the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> of <hi>Watten</hi> put to this <hi>Proteſtation</hi> the Seal of their <hi>Lordſhip.</hi> This way of arguing is ſo groſs and brutiſh, that it were time loſt to inſiſt upon a formal Confutation of it: and yet tho' I do already in a manner deſpair of meeting with fairer play in the whole Libel, for once how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, and uſe it not, I will take the pains to trace him patiently, and ſtep by ſtep, thoroughout all his <hi>Fegaries.</hi> Section eight is found fault with: 1. For that the <hi>Deponent</hi> there ſtiles <hi>P. P. H. de Corduba Provincial</hi> of <hi>New Caſtile,</hi> tho' the <hi>Obſervator</hi> will have it that there is no ſuch <hi>Province</hi> in all the <hi>Society.</hi> Now he does not make him (that I can ſee) <hi>Provincial</hi> of <hi>New Caſtile,</hi> any otherwiſe than as it is an <hi>Appendix</hi> to the <hi>Old</hi>; the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in the <hi>Former</hi> being (he'll grant) under the Juriſdiction of the <hi>Latter.</hi> So that here again we meet with palpable <hi>Prevarications</hi>: but I can very well forgive him; for the <hi>Motives</hi> were great. 2. Becauſe he ſays he was ſent from <hi>Valla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolid, November</hi> 3. when as the Abſtract of an <hi>Atteſt.</hi> (M, <hi>pag.</hi> 53.) of one <hi>Juan de Sandobal,</hi> I know not what <hi>Jocky</hi> of a <hi>Muleman,</hi> that, (tho' a <hi>Spaniard</hi> yet) it appears, could ſpeak as good <hi>Engliſh</hi> as any <hi>Jeſuit</hi> of 'em all, pretends to inform the contrary. But how ſleevleſs ſoever this Pretext may be deemed by reaſonable men; yet he himſelf lays mighty ſtreſs upon it, and (according to cuſtom) ſarcaſtically bobbs him with being <hi>very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate in</hi> timing <hi>his Depoſitions.</hi> 3. (and <hi>Laſtly</hi>) And becauſe <hi>R. S.</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owned the writing of any ſuch Letter, as, in this <hi>Item,</hi> he is accuſed of; if <hi>Atteſt.</hi> G may be believ'd. But <hi>that</hi> we have remarked upon already. To
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:47905:13"/>
               <hi>theſe</hi> he tacks a few of his <hi>Reaſons,</hi> to evince the <hi>Improbability</hi> of <hi>All</hi>; but thoſe ſo ſhallow and untoward, that they fall foul upon one another; and have alſo been anſwered in other Books. And thus; after ſome ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial <hi>Smatterings</hi> about a wandring and uncertain <hi>Rumour</hi> concerning <hi>Don John</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> he puts a period to his weighty <hi>Quibbles</hi> upon the Third Chapter of his Diviſion of the <hi>Narrative.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="section">
            <head>SECT. VI.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>HIS Fourth</hi> Chapter, (which he intitles <hi>Lyes delivered from Sect.</hi> 9, <hi>to Sect.</hi> 27. <hi>Containing what he heard and read at S.</hi> Omers) ſtarts two Lyes in Sect. 9. 1. He denies that <hi>Strange</hi> penned ſuch Letters. 2. And if he did, that many <hi>Jeſuits</hi> ſubſcribed them. Here we meet with nothing new; ſaving that he ſets upon clearing the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> from writing about poyſoning, ſhooting, ſtabbing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> by delivering a <hi>Hear-ſay-ſtory,</hi> that <hi>all their Letters of ſeveral years had been found and peruſed by</hi> Authority, <hi>and not one word found, inſinuating any ſuch thing: pag.</hi> 12. An Aſſertion ſo notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly untrue in both reſpects; that only to ſay <hi>I hear the quite contrary,</hi> is, in my opinion, a ſufficient anſwer to it. As to his Obſervations upon Sect. 10, which endeavour to repreſent the <hi>Deponents</hi> Journey to <hi>Paris,</hi> as a <hi>Ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> they are no other than what have already been urged in a <hi>Court</hi> of Juſtice; &amp; <hi>there</hi> (and in divers <hi>Prints</hi> too) detected and ſlighted as adulterate, and invalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. Neither can any other reaſon be given for his inſerting ſome mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and groundleſs <hi>Reports</hi> concerning <hi>Don Juan</hi> and the <hi>Loure, (Hear-ſays</hi> being no Legal <hi>Evidence</hi>) but that it was done purely to lay the heavier Load of Scandal and Calumny (Favours that he is wonderfully laviſh of) upon the <hi>Deponent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It were unjuſt, even at this time a day, to leſſen this Gentlemans excellent knack of making and ferreting out Lies at pleaſure; but now he catches them by whole <hi>Couvies</hi> and <hi>Little Hundreds</hi>; ſmelling no leſs than half a dozen in Sect. 11. (<hi>pag.</hi> 13.) which he makes out thus. 1. <hi>You never returned from</hi> Paris (ſpeaking to the <hi>Deponent, having never been there.</hi> 2. <hi>Never was ſuch a</hi> Letter <hi>written.</hi> 3. <hi>No</hi> Engliſh Jeſuit <hi>ever dealt with</hi> Scotch Presbyterians. 4. <hi>Nor</hi> Iriſh Papiſts <hi>diſpoſed to rebel.</hi> 5. <hi>Nor any</hi> Black Bills <hi>prepared.</hi> 6. <hi>Nor way made for</hi> the French landing. Here's a Man of <hi>Mettle</hi> for you, now! Can any thing in nature be imagined more <hi>demonſtrative</hi> or <hi>infallible</hi> than ſuch a bold and menacing <hi>Poſitivity</hi>? High and Low, Great and Small, Mad and Sober, Wiſe and Weak, muſt needs ſtand corrected and converted by ſo ſubſtantial and undeniable an Evidence. But if any <hi>Logical Heretick</hi> of them all will needs be ſo preſumptuous as to <hi>whiffle</hi> againſt this New <hi>Jeſuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Way of <hi>Fending</hi> and <hi>Proving,</hi> that it falls not within <hi>Mood</hi> and <hi>Figure</hi>; let it be beaten into his Noddle with a Bullet that theſe Seraphical <hi>Sophiſts</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:47905:13"/>
are not to be limited to Pedantick Rules and Preſcriptions, how ſound and rational ſoever. But to proceed. Four <hi>Lyes</hi> more are detected in <hi>Sect.</hi> 12. The firſt is, about the time of <hi>Whitebread</hi>'s being made <hi>Provincial.</hi> This was objected to the <hi>Deponent</hi> at the Tryal of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> but would not hold water. The ſecond is grounded upon a ſuppoſition of the <hi>firſt's</hi> being <hi>true</hi>; and therefore muſt needs ſtand and fall with it. The third he makes to be a Lye, becauſe the perſon accuſed told him ſo it was. And to prove the fourth, he betakes himſelf again to the <hi>Jeſuits Cuſtoms</hi>; fortifying it (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a hard pinch) with ſomewhat that looks like a reflection upon the <hi>Fathers</hi> for keeping from <hi>Church,</hi> leſt they ſhould be defiled and profaned with the <hi>Scholars</hi> Devotions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Two</hi> of the <hi>three</hi> Lyes that (<hi>pag.</hi> 14.) he picks out of <hi>Sect.</hi> 13. are only the old pretenſes about many <hi>Jeſuits</hi> hands, and <hi>Whitebreads</hi> being <hi>Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial.</hi> The <hi>third</hi> (being a denyal of ſuch a Letter to have been written) he ſeeks to make good by his own <hi>Mother-wit,</hi> and by Atteſt. E, which ſpeaks thus much; that upon finding, that the <hi>Deponent</hi> had charged the Fathers at S. <hi>Omers</hi> with ſundry Treaſons, and heinous Miſdemeanours, they the ſaid Fathers had asked one another whether they were <hi>guilty</hi> or not; and all an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering, <hi>No,</hi> they reſolved joyntly and unanimouſly to ſwear that they are, and will be (every Mothers Son of them) <hi>innocent</hi> of what hath been, or ſhall be alledged againſt them by the ſaid Deponent: and conclude (pray note it, for it is the very <hi>Cream</hi> of the <hi>Jeſt</hi>) with hoping that <hi>he,</hi> having been ſo clearly prov'd perjured in ſo many points by this their Proteſtation, will find no credit (no, by no means) in the reſt. Theſe Gentlemen ought not to take it ill now, if I ſay that thoſe muſt have better eyes than mine are, who can diſcern (for all <hi>this</hi>) either the leaſt colour of a <hi>Proof</hi> on the <hi>one</hi> ſide, or of a <hi>Perjury</hi> on the <hi>other.</hi> As to his <hi>Collateral</hi> and <hi>corroborating Reaſons</hi>; in the <hi>upſhot</hi> they came only to an <hi>expoſtulation</hi> with the <hi>Deponent,</hi> for repreſenting the Fathers in <hi>England</hi> ſo good natur'd and complaiſant as to let their Treaſonable Letters to <hi>P. de la Chaize</hi> take in, and be read at S. <hi>Omers,</hi> before they reach'd his <hi>Reverences</hi> hand: this is a much more probable reaſon for their being directed to call in there, in their way to <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> then his ſuggeſtion that it could only be done out of a complemental re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the <hi>Deponent.</hi> Againſt <hi>Sect.</hi> 14. he oppoſes firſt that it is not uſual for the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> to make any <hi>Ordinaries</hi> (only an <hi>Equivocation</hi> upon the <hi>word,</hi> I believe) even in <hi>Catholick Countries.</hi> There, indeed, they ſtand migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily upon their <hi>Pantoffles</hi>; but in <hi>England</hi> they are content (we find) to govern themſelves by the very <hi>Letter</hi>; becoming <hi>all things to all men that by all means they may gain ſome.</hi> 2. That the <hi>Provincial</hi> gives no <hi>Offices</hi> by <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</hi> This by ſound experience may be proved to be a great Untruth; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he will ſalve it again, if put to it, with a <hi>Colluſion</hi> taken, either from the ambiguous ſignification of the word <hi>Patents,</hi> or from their giving to the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:47905:14"/>
               <hi>ſame thing</hi> a different <hi>Appellation: Little Arts</hi> that the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> are perfectly well verſed in! But for all this <hi>pother,</hi> at the very next breath he ſo far o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-ſhoots himſelf, as in a manner to <hi>confeſs</hi> all that juſt before he had ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly denyed; and puts forth an <hi>Apology</hi> in Rhetorical Garb, in juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Act</hi>; which being interpreted according to the <hi>Jeſuits Key,</hi> ſpeaks thus. If the <hi>Provincial,</hi> out of meer charity, did ſend one to bring ſuch Souls from <hi>Newgate</hi> into <hi>Purgatory,</hi> as by themſelves or Friends were able to contribute toward their being prayed out again; or, (according to the ſenſe of the <hi>Narrat. fol. ult.</hi>) to ſuborn <hi>Felons,</hi> through hopes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don or Tranſportation, to turn <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and then put ſuch as they found fit and deſperate, upon Firing Houſes, Plundering, and other wicked and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous Deſigns: no Body but ſuch an <hi>Atheiſt</hi> as the Deponent would blame him for it, he ſays; ſo conformable to right <hi>Reaſon,</hi> &amp;c. is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding.</p>
            <p>To the latter part of this <hi>Item</hi> he again objects (<hi>pag,</hi> 15.) that, tho' the Orders there ſpoken of were actually given (as he ſeems to grant) yet ſo many <hi>Jeſuits</hi> were not concerned in the giving of them; the <hi>Provincial</hi> being <hi>one and all</hi> in ſuch Caſes: the <hi>S. Omerian Atteſtation</hi> alſo declaring it unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for an <hi>Inferior</hi> to ſubſcribe with his <hi>Superior</hi>; who is ſtill endewed with a portion of his <hi>Fatuities</hi> Infallibility, ſufficient for the guidance of his <hi>Flock</hi> in the path he would have them walk in. O the ſpiritual <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Vanity</hi> of theſe deſpicable Creatures! How abject muſt needs be the condition of thoſe that lie under the laſh of ſuch tyrannical Taskmaſters? The <hi>Iriſh Monks</hi> of late that were obliged to lick up their Superiors <hi>Spittle,</hi> could not but be <hi>highly privileged Subjects,</hi> compared with them. What need we any longer wonder at their ſtickling ſo vehemently for <hi>Arbitrary Principles,</hi> when we find by their own Confeſſion, that every individual Neſt of theſe <hi>Hornets</hi> is a compound of the moſt exquiſite <hi>Tyranny</hi> and <hi>Thraldom</hi> imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? Or that <hi>Loyola</hi> ſhould chuſe <hi>Cavete vobis Principes</hi> for his <hi>Motto</hi>; when all his Raſcally Followers do thus ambitiouſly ſtrive to vye with, and ape <hi>Crowned Heads</hi> even in the moſt ſupreme Points of <hi>Regality?</hi> Had it not been their <hi>aim</hi> to endeavour at any rate (<hi>Dolus an Virtus</hi>?) to render the <hi>Narrative</hi> ſuſpected of <hi>Fiction,</hi> they would never ſure have diſcovered a <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret</hi> that (true or falſe) reflects ſo odious a ſavour upon their <hi>Society.</hi> True is the <hi>Saying</hi> too, <hi>Quos Deus vult perdere, dementat.</hi> 2. A <hi>Flam</hi> of his own contriving. For tho' beyond peradventure <hi>Whitebread</hi> was at leaſt <hi>Provincial elect</hi> at the time here in queſtion, yet the words [Thom. White, <hi>as</hi> Provincial, <hi>writ them.</hi>] (The Letters) are none of the <hi>Deponents,</hi> but only foiſted in by the Obſervator himſelf to ſtop a gap. No Reſpects or Obligations whatſoever can bind a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> (I ſee) when they come once to work againſt the <hi>Grain</hi>; for now he undervalues the dear and famous S. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> it ſelf, in point of <hi>Epiſtolary Conveniences,</hi> only to hook in by the Head
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:47905:14"/>
and Shoulders this venemous <hi>Scoff</hi> upon his <hi>Adverſary</hi> (pag. 15.) <hi>viz. As the Loadſtone draws Iron,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>ſo you drew all correſpondence to you.</hi> But he is a very thick-ſcull'd <hi>Jeſuite</hi> that cannot find means of <hi>correſponding</hi> for the embroiling of <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> be he where he will. As to <hi>Sect.</hi> 16.1. He produces <hi>Atteſt.</hi> E, K, and Q, to make out that there never were any ſuch Letters written, as are there mentioned. Theſe <hi>Pretences</hi> have already been examined, and found to be ſo far from <hi>True</hi> and <hi>Honeſt,</hi> that they are not ſo much as <hi>Legal</hi> Evidences. 2. He will have this and the preceding Section to <hi>interfere.</hi> But that muſt not be granted him; for the <hi>Deponent</hi> is poſitive rather in the <hi>ſpeaking</hi> of the <hi>words,</hi> than in the <hi>receipt</hi> of the <hi>Letters</hi> here in diſpute. But then he adds, that the <hi>Day-Book</hi> makes him to have been at <hi>Watten</hi> that day. All this is meer <hi>Childiſhneſs.</hi> But who can blame a drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man, if he catch at Twigs, Straws, or any thing that comes next to hand, and gives but the leaſt hope of keeping him above water.</p>
            <p>Next, he tells us in down right terms (<hi>pag.</hi> 16.) that there never were any ſuch Letters penned, as the ſeventeenth Section ſpeaks of; calling it a <hi>Tranſcendental Fiction to have many Jeſuits writing</hi> (the <hi>Deponents</hi> word is <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing) the ſame Letters. Section</hi> 18 he makes to be a Lye, becauſe the S. <hi>Omers Jeſuits</hi> called it ſo: Section 19 for the like reaſon. After the ſame faſhion (ſaving that he bobbs the <hi>Deponent</hi> upon his Father's account) he diſpatches the twentieth Section. And ſays that the twenty one, twenty two, twenty three and twenty fourth Sections are only <hi>cold Cabbage ſerv'd up again:</hi> labouring to Poſſeſs the People that there never were any ſuch Letters in being as are there particulariſed, becauſe they were not to be found after they had been burnt, or otherwiſe made away.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Remarks</hi> upon the twenty fifth Section are only 1. A <hi>back-ſide Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to the Popiſh <hi>Clergy.</hi> And 2. a <hi>Repetition</hi> of his thred bare pretence, that no bad Letters of theirs could ever yet be produced, that had <hi>many Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits</hi> hands to them. The twenty ſixth Section he would fain have to be thought a Fable; 1. By averring that no living mortal ever heard of the Contents of it, before the <hi>Narrative</hi> came out. 2. By quarrelling the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent</hi> for making <hi>Whitebread</hi> ſo <hi>ill-natured,</hi> as to impute <hi>Pickering</hi> and <hi>Groves</hi> failing of diſpatching the King. to negligence, rather than to what they alledged for themſelves, want of <hi>opportunity</hi>; and ſo <hi>partial</hi> too, as to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the ſimple, Bigotted <hi>Prieſt</hi> with <hi>Stripes</hi>; and the ſullen ſtomachful <hi>Ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fian</hi> only with <hi>Reproofs.</hi> This was a true <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> that could ſo exactly mete to each, according to their <hi>ſtrength,</hi> and yet keep them firm to their Party. Then he gives the Lye to all the particulars of Sect. 27 (that of the <hi>Conſult</hi> or <hi>Congregation</hi> only excepted) his own <hi>word,</hi> and a flat <hi>Negative</hi> being his only authority for ſo doing. Such ſtrong <hi>Proof</hi> cannot but produce won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſure.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="section">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:47905:15"/>
            <head>SECT. VII.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>HIS</hi> Prefatory Speculations upon the <hi>Conſult,</hi> (or <hi>Congregation</hi>) are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Recapitulation of what the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> alledged upon that Subject, at their Tryal: and he plainly confeſſes as much; leaving them to anſwer for, and make out the truth of it as well as they can; whilſt himſelf goes on with his <hi>Lyes</hi>; which in Section 28, he pretends to find as many of, as words; and proves them firſt by a Repetition of the Childiſh and extravagant Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the S. <hi>Omers</hi> Lads at <hi>Langhorn</hi>'s Tryal. 2. By <hi>Atteſt.</hi> F, (<hi>pag.</hi> 48.) which is only an oppoſing <hi>Teſtimony</hi> to <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> and <hi>that</hi> too in a moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident and inconſiderate manner. He next falls to his <hi>Criticiſms,</hi> and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to raiſe ſome fantaſtical Scruples; but finding that they anſwer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, he paſſes on to another Branch of this Section, out of which he would fain pick <hi>three Lyes</hi> more: he might with as much eaſe have made them <hi>three hundred</hi>; for he brings nothing but the breath of the <hi>Parties</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd to ſupport them. Then he forgets <hi>old</hi> and <hi>new Stile,</hi> in the queſtion of the <hi>Conſult</hi>; and denies the <hi>Deponent</hi> to have been there; formalizing ſo notably upon the probability of that Journey, that I cannot forget the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>A fool may ask more queſtions in one hour, than a wiſe man ſhall be able to reſolve in a whole Age.</hi> As to the laſt part of this ſame Section, he diſowns 1. their meeting at the <hi>White Horſe-Tavern</hi>; for this reaſon, that ſeveral of the <hi>Conſulters</hi> told this <hi>Obſervator,</hi> they knew no ſuch Tavern in the <hi>Strand.</hi> 2. Their dividing into <hi>Clubs</hi>; for that in that caſe their <hi>Reſolves</hi> would have been, <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> void. His <hi>Atteſt.</hi> F is more modeſt a great deal; as admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>Lawfulneſs</hi> of ſuch a Proceeding, and only denying any <hi>Propoſition</hi> of that nature to have been made. Then he finds fault with him for making them to buſie themſelves afreſh about the King's <hi>Death,</hi> when it had been reſolved upon the year before, and <hi>Agents</hi> hired accordingly. As if their many Diſappointments in that particular had not been a ſufficient <hi>incitement</hi> to their laying their heads together again, for a choice of more proper <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod</hi> and <hi>Inſtruments</hi> to effect it. But do but mind how clumzily he <hi>curvets</hi> upon this occaſion: <hi>When I conſider</hi> (ſays he, <hi>pag.</hi> 20.) <hi>our Nation capable to be impoſed upon by ſuch ridiculous Stories, I am half-aſhamed to own my ſelf of it.</hi> Indeed a <hi>Traytor</hi> and an <hi>Engliſhman</hi> are direct <hi>Contradictions.</hi> He concludes all with <hi>ſquabble</hi> about the <hi>Deponents</hi> return to S. <hi>Omers,</hi> grounded only upon his own <hi>ſuppoſititious Premiſes</hi>: and with this confident expreſſion, <hi>pag.</hi> 21. <hi>There is not one word related by me, which will not be depoſed upon Oath, when required.</hi> This is but the <hi>Proze</hi> of what his <hi>Fellow-Labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> in the <hi>Cauſe</hi> (the Poetical <hi>Ridiculer</hi> of the <hi>Plot</hi>) in <note n="*" rend="inter">
                  <hi>New Narrat. of the Plot, p.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Rhime Doggerel,</hi> (tho' upon another occaſion,) delivers thus;
<q>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:47905:15"/>
                  <l>The truth of my Story, if any man doubt,</l>
                  <l>We have witneſſes ready to ſwear it all out.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I find the <hi>Obſervator</hi> indued with ſo excellent a faculty of <hi>inventing</hi> Lyes, and <hi>proving</hi> them when he has done, that I ſhall as ſoon take his word in this caſe, as any man's living. This little <hi>Remark</hi> thus over; by joynt conſent, we have done with the buſineſs of the <hi>Congregation.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="section">
            <head>SECT. VIII.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> ſixth <hi>Chapter</hi> promiſes a Relation of what happened, from the <hi>Deponent</hi>'s return to S. <hi>Omers,</hi> till he left the place. The <hi>Contents</hi> of the Sections 29, and 30 are infallibly falſe he ſays, becauſe the perſons there charged would not own themſelves guilty. A like Anſwer he ſhapes to Sect. 31. Then he quarrels Sect. 32, becauſe the <hi>Deponent</hi> does not in one and the ſame time and place report all and every the occaſions of his leaving S. <hi>Omers</hi> in <hi>June</hi>; confeſſes (<hi>pag.</hi> 22. in his <hi>Rejoynders,</hi> to <hi>Sect.</hi> 32.) they gave him four pounds to bear the Charges of his Journey; chews over again his former abſurdities touching his not being in <hi>Spain</hi>; and ſtrives to invali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date his rational account of the manner of his diſmiſſion from S. <hi>Omers</hi>; by oppoſing to it an improbable, extravagant, but impudently malicious <hi>Flam</hi> of their own deviſing; which it ſeems, he was once of a mind might have ſerv'd well enough for a <hi>general Anſwer</hi>; but upon ſecond thoughts) and a fit of good nature, finds himſelf concern'd to be more <hi>particular,</hi> tho to never ſo little purpoſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="section">
            <head>SECT IX.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> thus comes on his ſeventh <hi>Chapter,</hi> comprizing what the <hi>Deponent</hi> relates ſince his return to <hi>London,</hi> concerning <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> from <hi>Sect.</hi> 33, to <hi>Sect.</hi> 53, incluſive. But upon <hi>Sections</hi> 33, and 34, we meet with nothing material; only the old miſerable pretenſes of the Jeſuits denying all, and an odd kind of Inference from their keeping him bare of money, that they never made him privy to the <hi>Treaſons</hi> which he hath now diſcovered. Of the very ſame ſtrain are his Anſwers to <hi>Sections</hi> 35, 36, and 37, (<hi>pag.</hi> 24.) and have already been diſcuſſed. Upon <hi>Section</hi> 38, he makes a queſtion whether, if any <hi>Jeſuites</hi> had been deſign'd for <hi>Holland,</hi> they would have acquainted the <hi>Deponent</hi> with the receit of thoſe Orders from <hi>Whitebread.</hi> He confutes <hi>Sections</hi> 39, 40, and 41, by oppoſing again a ſimple, verbal <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial</hi> to a poſitive and affirmative <hi>Oath.</hi> And excepts againſt <hi>Section</hi> 42, (<hi>pag.</hi> 25.) becauſe the Letters there mentioned are not producible; expoſtulates with him for the Commotions he has raiſed here, by diſcovering their
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:47905:16"/>
               <hi>Rogueries</hi>; and minds him of his danger. His Reply to <hi>Section</hi> 43, comes to thus much in effect, that no Jeſuits were ſent into <hi>Scotland,</hi> becauſe he (this <hi>Obſervator</hi>) knows them not, he ſeeks to evade the ſtroke of <hi>Sect.</hi> 44. by diſclaiming all correſpondence with <hi>De la Chaize</hi>; and cavils at <hi>Section</hi> 45, without ſo much as knowing, why, or wherefore.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Section</hi> 46, (<hi>pag.</hi> 26.) will not down with him. 1. Becauſe <hi>Wakeman</hi> was acquitted. 2. For that <hi>Pickering</hi> confeſs'd nothing at the Gallows. And 3. Becauſe the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> that the Letter there ſpecified is charged upon, find themſelves concern'd to diſown it. What think you now? Are not all theſe ſound and undenyable <hi>Evidences</hi>? But he goes on: and returns to <hi>Sect.</hi> 47, only a ſpiteful Reflection upon a converted <hi>Jeſuite</hi>; which will bear an <hi>Inference</hi> to this purpoſe, that the <hi>Deponent</hi> being neither a <hi>Fool,</hi> nor a <hi>Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> was ſcarce look'd upon as fit to wipe their <hi>Reverences</hi> Shooes, whereas the <hi>other</hi> being (upon the <hi>Obſervator</hi>'s Character of him) completely <hi>both,</hi> was readily adopted a Brother of the <hi>Society.</hi> He objects to <hi>Section</hi> 48, that there is no <hi>Heath</hi> of the Society; but preſently recollects himſelf that there is <hi>one Heath</hi> (the <hi>Deponent</hi> never ſaid there were <hi>two</hi>) that has (<hi>he ſays</hi>) been at <hi>Liege,</hi> ever ſince <hi>Jan.</hi> 1678. To <hi>Section</hi> 49, he oppoſes an improbable and uncharitable ſuppoſition, and the weakneſs of the <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted</hi>'s denyal to the Validity of the <hi>Deponents Proof.</hi> He diſpatches <hi>Section</hi> 50, by repeating the pretence of <hi>Ireland</hi>'s being at ſuch a time in <hi>Stafford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi>: the truth of which allegation was ever juſtly held ſuſpected, and at length ſolemnly impeached upon Oath. And thus, with denying their own <hi>Ciphers; (pag.</hi> 27.) ſtroaking <hi>Jenniſon</hi> the Jeſuite; ſcoffing at the <hi>Depoſition</hi> of an intended <hi>Maſſacre</hi>; and perverting the <hi>Deponents</hi> words to make them ſpeak <hi>Smith,</hi> a <hi>Jeſuite</hi>; (for want of better <hi>Arguments</hi>) he paſſes over <hi>Sections</hi> 51, 52, and 53, and concludes this his <hi>Seventh Section.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="section">
            <head>SECT. X.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE eighth Chapter</hi> undertakes to treat of <hi>What the</hi> Deponent <hi>relates concerning Jeſuites, and others; from Sect.</hi> 54, to <hi>Sect.</hi> 81. <hi>incluſive.</hi> And ſo he falls to telling us that <hi>Sect.</hi> 54 is a ridiculous Lye, for this weighty rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon among the reſt, that <hi>all of it is falſe.</hi> He thwarts § 55, and ſeeks to ſave their own <hi>Bacon,</hi> by ſetting his Teeth at his Brother <hi>Jack</hi>: and then takes upon him (under a ſhew of kindneſs) to adviſe the <hi>Government:</hi> but ſuch <hi>Hints</hi> are as unneceſſary, as inſincere; for <hi>that</hi> is not about to wink of either eye; as knowing full well that let them never ſo much affect <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Voice, their hands ſtill are (alike) the hands of <hi>Eſau.</hi> Againſt <hi>Sections</hi> 56, 57, 58, 59, 60, 61, 62, 63, and 64, he only produces (<hi>pag.</hi> 28, 29,) point blank denyals; Clamour and Calumny; malicious Surmizes; a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of the irreconcileable Fewds, and ambitious Jarrs betwixt his own
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:47905:16"/>
               <hi>Party,</hi> and the <hi>Dominicans</hi>; invidious <hi>Preſumptions</hi>; and ſcandalous and unmanly Taunts and Forgeries. Which (according to all <hi>judgments</hi>) are apparent Symptoms of his own diſhoneſty, and of the badneſs of the Cauſe that he has undertaken to defend.</p>
            <p>Next, he charges § 65 (<hi>pag.</hi> 30.) with as many Lyes as Periods; and ſo with full cry runs over again the old Tales of the <hi>Deponents</hi> never having been at <hi>Madrid,</hi> &amp;c. with all their appertenances; and calls upon him, at the price of his head and credit, to produce the Letter he there ſpeaks of. But, yet in the rear of this his Squadron of weak and wild <hi>Denyals,</hi> may be found a <hi>ſquinting Quaere,</hi> that, had he been well adviſed, he would never have inſerted; it amounting upon a reaſonable conſtruction, to little leſs than a tacit confeſſion of the whole Charge. For; <hi>If the Lord Arch-biſhop</hi> (otherwiſe <hi>Titular, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurping Prelate) of</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uam, <hi>or that Jeſuite</hi> (Suiman) <hi>being Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi>; (No; they have traiterouſly renounced <hi>that</hi> Subjection, by becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Feudataries</hi> to the <hi>Pope) of the King of</hi> England, <hi>waited on, and proffered their ſervice to his Majeſties Embaſſador, they did but their duty.</hi> (They'll find themſelves miſtaken.) <hi>And if his Lordſhip receiv'd them civilly</hi> (he has no reaſon to <hi>con</hi> them <hi>Thank,</hi> for <hi>crying Roaſt-meat,</hi> however) <hi>having no direct order</hi> (The man you ſee is as intimate with his <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> as if they were <hi>Cater-Cozens) to the contrary; I hope none are ſo</hi> barbarous (I know many that are ſo <hi>honeſt) as to blame him for it. But that there ever paſt any intimate correſpondence</hi> (O, have a care of <hi>that:</hi> for <hi>Hanging</hi> follows <hi>Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing) chiefly</hi> [The man's <hi>Conſcience</hi> flies in his face, and ſpoils all; for theſe <hi>Qualifications, Ifs</hi> and <hi>Ands,</hi> are a contradiction to <hi>Atteſtation</hi> A, (<hi>pag.</hi> 42.) where his <hi>Grace</hi> ſwears <hi>out-right</hi> that <hi>he never made unto, or heard from the moſt excellent Lord Sir</hi> William Godolphin <hi>any publick or private diſcourſe concerning any Religious</hi> (or laſcivious) <hi>matter whatſoever, nor concerning the Government, or State of Affairs in</hi> England, Ireland, <hi>or</hi> Scotland; —<hi>nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from any perſon any</hi> Letter <hi>or</hi> Paper <hi>whatſoever, directed unto, or intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the ſaid</hi> moſt excellent Lord, <hi>&amp;c.] relating to any publick concern, it is abſolutely falſe</hi>; forthe mighty reaſon aboveſaid. This paſſage ſpeaks plain enough, without the aſſiſtance of an Interpreter.</p>
            <p>He rather cavills at, then diſproves or oppoſes § 66, (<hi>pag.</hi> 31.) but yet pretends to ſee he knows not how many contradictions in it to what the Deponent has elſewhere delivered: and ſo makes his Triumph as upon a certain Victory; demanding, <hi>How came his Patrons</hi> (the <hi>King, Parliament,</hi> &amp;c.) <hi>to let them</hi> (the pretended <hi>Contradictions) paſs abroad uncorrected, but that in this God blinded them, that they might remain to Poſterity an everlaſting unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable Proof of the Injuſtice of their Judgments?</hi> This is a pretty round <hi>Complement.</hi> And I ſee too, that a Jeſuits <hi>Spectacles</hi> can magnifie or leſſen (even to <hi>annihilation</hi>) according to the reſpective aſpects of their Intereſts: for let the places which he here will have to ſtand ſo much at Daggers
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:47905:17"/>
drawing be duly compared and examined, and my word for his they may ſoon be made Friends. But a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> will ſtill be a <hi>Jeſuite</hi>; and <hi>None ſo blind as they that will not ſee.</hi> In <hi>Sect.</hi> 67 he only <hi>ſays</hi> there are ſix Lyes, and that's all; for he puts us to take his <hi>word</hi> for 'um; which truly is but a very ſlender evidence; to ſay no worſe on't. He endeavours to weaken the credit of <hi>Sect.</hi> 68, by inſerting a malicious and irrational <hi>Fable,</hi> which he pretends to have been <hi>Conyers</hi>'s account of what paſſed betwixt the <hi>Deponent</hi> and <hi>himſelf</hi> in <hi>Grays-Inn-Walks:</hi> preſſing it with as much confidence, as if he would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to <hi>Reaſon</hi> it ſelf, and tye the whole <hi>world</hi> to an implicit Belief in his <hi>Figments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He continues in the ſame jocular, and abuſive <hi>mood,</hi> throughout <hi>Section</hi> 69, making himſelf wonderful merry (<hi>pag.</hi> 33.) with the <hi>Deponents</hi> great days work on the two and twentieth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> here in controverſie; and diſcovering his own notable proficiency in the laudable and uſeful Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of <hi>Calumnyating, Falſifying,</hi> and <hi>Burleſquing.</hi> Now it is impolitique for a body to ſhew his Teeth, when he cannot bite; and by this time one may, without breach of <hi>Charity,</hi> conclude the <hi>Obſervators</hi> Tongue to be no ſlander. Beſide, I examined, as ſtrictly as I could for my life, the <hi>Items</hi> of the <hi>Narrative</hi> that he makes thus familiar with; and ſhall dare to ſay (all that this <hi>Frolicksome Gentleman</hi> has inſinuated to the contrary, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) that I have not been able to diſcern any thing in them, that may give the leaſt affront to <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Probability.</hi> He only <hi>trifles</hi> upon <hi>Sect.</hi> 70, and againſt <hi>Sect.</hi> 71, produces his old naked and unſatisfactory <hi>Fopperies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At <hi>Sect.</hi> 72, (<hi>pag.</hi> 34.) he makes a <hi>wonderment,</hi> and ſo paſſes it by. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Sect</hi> 73, he miſerably betrays his want of <hi>Honeſty, Prudence</hi> and <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> by witneſſing to <hi>Impoſſibilities.</hi> To <hi>Sect.</hi> 74. he contents himſelf with his bold <hi>Negatives</hi>; and pretends a Concern for the Nations <hi>wellfare,</hi> very much (in his opinion) diſturbed by the <hi>Fanaticks:</hi> and tho' contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for this Section to be a <hi>Lye,</hi> yet allowing it to be at leaſt a <hi>Profitable</hi> one, if made uſe of according to his <hi>own</hi> Direction.</p>
            <p>All that is remarkable in his <hi>Notes</hi> upon <hi>Sect.</hi> 75. is his informing the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent, (Pag.</hi> 35.) how he ſhould have <hi>worded</hi> it, to have made it <hi>acceptable</hi> to the pretended) <hi>Catholicks:</hi> Now though I ſuppoſe he is not over ambitious of ſuch a <hi>Favour,</hi> yet he will needs have it that he has committed a grievous <hi>Sin,</hi> in not caſting a <hi>Figure</hi> to hit upon't. In <hi>Sect.</hi> 76. he would fain be nib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling at a <hi>Contradiction</hi>; but finding he can make nothing on't, out of mere vexation he falls moſt bitterly upon <hi>Sect.</hi> 77, terming it <hi>Such incoherent Non-ſenſe as never came from any man in his Wits</hi>; and all this only for Repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Whitebread</hi> as a Perſon able (when his Zeal was in tune) to lift up his hand, and give the <hi>Deponent</hi> a <hi>Box o'th' Ear</hi> for having betrayed him, as he call'd it. Yet finding this <hi>Exception</hi> to want weight, he is once of the mind to let it paſs, but however catches at it again, before out of his reach,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:47905:17"/>
for ſlandering the <hi>honeſty</hi> and <hi>prudence</hi> of the <hi>Provincial,</hi> with a matter of <hi>Truth.</hi> But beſide that he was no great <hi>Conjurer,</hi> even at the very beſt (if a body may take meaſure of his <hi>Abilities,</hi> by the manner of his <hi>Defence</hi>) it is no wonder neither that <hi>that black malice</hi> (to apply the <hi>Obſervators</hi> own words) <hi>that appeared in him,</hi> (upon ſight of the Diſcoverer of his <hi>Treaſons) and common ſenſe, or the uſe of Right Reaſon, ſhould be inconſiſtent in the ſame mind: God darkening the underſtanding, when man leaves his will to the workings of malilce,</hi> &amp;c. He next proceeds (according to cuſtom) to ſet up his <hi>own</hi> adulterous <hi>Pratings</hi> againſt this ſober <hi>Account</hi> of the <hi>Deponents.</hi> But in the delivery of them makes ſuch unhappy <hi>ſlips</hi> as by dint of <hi>Argument</hi> could never have been extort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from him, and are far from advantaging his <hi>Cauſe.</hi> So true we ſee is the old Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>A Lyar had need have a good memory.</hi> But he winds up all with laying it home, that becauſe <hi>Whitebread</hi> was taken <hi>napping,</hi> by neglecting to endeavour his eſcape till it was too late, therefore <hi>Poſterity</hi> ought to conclude him <hi>innocent.</hi> Now I am afraid that, for all this weight of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> they will prove a little <hi>Refractory,</hi> and hardly be brought (by <hi>fair</hi> means, at leaſt,) to anſwer <hi>expectation</hi> in this <hi>particular.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 78. He thinks in his heart is an <hi>incredible Lye</hi>; but yet makes a ſhift to pick this ſorry <hi>comfort</hi> out of it, that <hi>others</hi> (the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> &amp;c.) have been as great <hi>Fools</hi> and <hi>Knaves</hi> as the <hi>Jeſuits</hi>: He quarrels at <hi>Sect.</hi> 79, becauſe he conceits the <hi>Deponent</hi> to have been leſs courageous and reſolute, upon his over-hearing a Pack of <hi>Jeſuites</hi> poſitively <hi>reſolve</hi> the ſending of him out of the Land, and <hi>torturing</hi> him to a <hi>confeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Accomplices</hi> in his <hi>Diſcovery</hi>; than he had approved himſelf two days before, when <hi>Whitebread</hi> only <hi>threatened</hi> to ſend him back to S. <hi>Omers,</hi> and, preſently eating his words again, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to reſtore him to his favour. From <hi>Sect.</hi> 80, he takes occaſion to twit the <hi>Deponent</hi> with his <hi>Gallantry</hi>; ſpitefully inſinuating as if he had been a <hi>Coney-catching,</hi> and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> when he ſhould have gone home to his Lodging. I am not willing to trace the <hi>Obſervator</hi> through all his immoral <hi>Deſcants</hi> upon the <hi>Frailties</hi> of <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi>; or to obviate this falſe and ſcandalous <hi>Innuendo</hi> of his, with a true Relation of the <hi>Amorous Adventures</hi> of the mettleſome <hi>Fathers, Keymaſh,</hi> &amp;c. But yet I cannot but upon this occaſion, call the bonny <hi>Jeſuite</hi> to mind, who, being not long ſince appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended ſomewhere about <hi>Clerken-well,</hi> had taken out of his Pocket (upon a ſearch) a <hi>Memorial,</hi> not only of the <hi>number</hi> of the Women (three in a day ſometimes) that he had <hi>accompanied</hi> with, but of the very <hi>hours</hi> alſo, nay, the critical <hi>Minutes,</hi> of his <hi>doing them reaſon.</hi> So ſcrupulouſly exact, it ſeems, he was in the buſineſs of <hi>Venerial Pleaſures</hi>— Then he falls to queſtioning him upon the matter; gives him a grain of <hi>charitable allowance,</hi> and pretends to ſtumble upon a <hi>contradiction,</hi> which no body can ſee but himſelf. Upon <hi>Sect.</hi> 81, he accoſts his <hi>Opponent</hi> thus: <hi>Your work</hi> (ſays he) (<hi>pag.</hi> 38.) <hi>is not yet done: ſome</hi> Jeſuites <hi>are yet alive, and the world begins to be weary of ſhedding their innocent blood, to ſatisfie your deſire of Revenge: which is an antidote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your poyſon.</hi> This is only intended as a modeſt <hi>Complement,</hi> thorow the <hi>Deponents</hi> ſides, to the <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Excellency</hi> of that Government, for which he has elſewhere pretended ſo much <hi>value</hi> and <hi>concern.</hi> But I have all along obſerved that this mighty man of <hi>Buffoonry</hi> has ever <hi>wit</hi> at <hi>will,</hi> when he has a mind to turn <hi>the Queſtion into a Night-Cart:</hi> nay, and he muſt alſo go ſome other way to work than has yet been thought of, to convince the world, that <hi>their Blood</hi> is ſo <hi>innocent,</hi> as he moſt audaciouſly ſpeaks it to be. Next, he ſtomachs it highly, that any man ſhould be ſo preſumptuous as to call <hi>Ignatius Loyola</hi> a <hi>Fool,</hi> when the precious <hi>Deza</hi> has given this <hi>glorious Euloge</hi> of him:
<q>God hath been pleaſed in theſe latter times, (<hi>ſays he, pag.</hi> 12. <hi>de Canoniz. Loyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lae</hi>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) To ſpeak unto us by his Son <hi>Ignatius,</hi> whom he hath made Heir of all things;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:47905:18"/>
to make whoſe Praiſes conſummate, there needs only the addition of this word, <hi>By whom he made the world,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
               <hi>P. Rebulloſa, thus,</hi>
               <q>
                  <hi>Ignatius</hi> is by God ſo placed in the <hi>Church (ſays he)</hi> as if he were the <hi>Corner Stone</hi> of that ſumptuous Edifice; whence we might juſtly ſay that there is no <hi>Stone,</hi> (that is, no <hi>perſon</hi>) which in reſpect of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, and greatneſs of merit, is any way comparable with our <hi>Ignatius,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
               <hi>And the dear</hi> Valderama <hi>this,</hi>
               <q>When the <hi>Pope</hi> (ſays he, <hi>pag.</hi> 48.) had looked very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly on the hands of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> he would find no other Inſcription or Impreſſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, than that of the name of <hi>Jeſus. (His Holineſs was well skilled in Palmiſtry, it ſeems)</hi> Whereupon he ſaid, <hi>The Finger of God is here; I find nothing in theſe hands, but the Finger of God.</hi>
               </q>
               <hi>And again,</hi>
               <q> It is not much to be wondered at <hi>(ſays the ſame</hi> Valder <hi>pag</hi> 51.) that <hi>Moſes</hi> did very great miracles; for he wrought them by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable Power of the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>God</hi> ingraven in his <hi>Staff:</hi> nor is it any more that the <hi>Apostles</hi> did ſo many wonders; when all was done in the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> But that <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> ſhould, <hi>with his own</hi> Name <hi>written in a peice of Paper,</hi> do more miracles than <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and all the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> put together, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That, that indeed ſhould raiſe in us an exceſs of admiration for him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
               <hi> Then he goes on, in the ſame place, inſtancing his Miracles, thus:</hi>
               <q>Father <hi>Ignatius</hi> hath a great tenderneſs and aſſiſtance for Women in <hi>Labour.</hi> [Becauſe a careful and vigilant <hi>Shepherd</hi> will not be far from the <hi>Ewes</hi> that bring forth; according to that of <hi>Iſaiah, He ſhall carry the young ones;</hi> (that is to ſay, <hi>Have a care of thoſe that bring forth) that he may receive the wool and make his advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the</hi> Lambs] And to effect <hi>this,</hi> there needs no more than the putting of <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi>'s <hi>Name,</hi> written, upon the woman in danger; for at the very <hi>ſight</hi> of that <hi>Name</hi> the blind recover their ſight; the handleſs their hands; the lame their feet; nay, it diſſolves the <hi>Stone</hi> in the <hi>Reins,</hi> and make women have an eaſie <hi>Delivery,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
No Body can deny ſure, that <hi>this</hi> is giving <hi>the devil his due to the full.</hi> And therefore if all of it be <hi>true,</hi> the world muſt needs grant that the Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter</hi> was to blame, if he ventured to call this <hi>Holy Founder</hi> of theirs a <hi>Fool,</hi> as <hi>Nevil</hi> ſaid he did; if profanely <hi>Romantick</hi> and <hi>Apocriphal</hi>; (but I forget my ſelf that it is accounted no leſs than a <hi>ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> the bare <hi>queſtioning</hi> of it) then [—<hi>Debitè moveat cornicula riſum, furtivis nudata coloribus</hi>] call him <hi>Fool, Knave,</hi> or what you will, and welcome, Sirs! But he ſhuts up all his <hi>Tiltings</hi> upon this <hi>Chapter,</hi> with making his <hi>Honours</hi> to the Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> and caſting <hi>a Sheeps eye out of a Calves Head</hi> at the <hi>Presbyterians.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="section">
            <head>SECT. XI.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>IN</hi> this <hi>Ninth Chapter</hi> of his, which threatens to ſpeak <hi>of the Commiſſions given to Noblemen,</hi> he looks up to <hi>Fol.</hi> 58, (otherwiſe 61,) of the <hi>Narrative;</hi> and there blames the <hi>Deponent</hi> for not filling his <hi>Liſt</hi> of <hi>Conſpirators</hi> with the names of more perſons (<hi>Lords, Gentlemen,</hi> &amp;c.) than he could call to mind at the time of the drawing it up. Then he is angry becauſe they are charged with <hi>receiving</hi> their <hi>Commiſſions;</hi> and vows he will not believe it; till the <hi>Deponent</hi> ſhall be able to produce one of them, or the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties concerned acknowledge themſelves <hi>guilty.</hi> Next, he queſtions the <hi>probability</hi> of the whole, purely out of a ſcruple to grant the perſons that gave out theſe <hi>Commiſſions</hi> for all Offices as well Civil as Military, in a <hi>Country</hi> that, by a <hi>Holy War,</hi> or more <hi>Holy Maſſacre,</hi> they had deſigned to make their <hi>own,</hi> by ſuch practices, to have been guilty of <hi>an attempt that is not to be parallel'd, but by that of</hi> Lucifer <hi>to be like</hi> God. He concludes this branch of his <hi>Argument</hi> with formalizing upon the <hi>Ordinary</hi> Power of a <hi>Superior</hi> of the <hi>Society</hi>; but ſpeaks not a word of thoſe their <hi>Extraordinary</hi> Motions and Emanations of <hi>Zeal,</hi> that refuſe to be bounded by any Laws or Obligations, divine or humane, when the good of the <hi>Cauſe</hi> requires matters to be carried on in ſo brisk, and elevated a <hi>ſtrain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:47905:18"/>But now, when he comes to talk of the <hi>Perſons receiving</hi> theſe <hi>Commiſſions (pag.</hi> 39.) he utterly loſes all Patience, and manfully undertakes for their <hi>Loyalty,</hi> even to the <hi>fourteenth Generation;</hi> he admires, reaſons, puts caſes, calumniates, beſpatters, reviles, prevaricates, calls him a <hi>Lyar</hi> from his Cradle, and tells of as wiſe a man as the <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator</hi> himſelf (tho' he would not name him for a world) who having read the <hi>Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> with the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> own <hi>Spectacles,</hi> pronounced thus judiciouſly upon it, that <hi>either what</hi> Homer <hi>and</hi> Ovid <hi>writ of their Gods, or</hi> Aeſop <hi>of Beaſts, were no</hi> Fables, <hi>or the</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Conſpiracy <hi>was</hi> a Fable. This notable <hi>Concluſion</hi> ſmells ſo ſtrong of the <hi>Scholar,</hi> that it is pretty <hi>tolerable,</hi> in being only <hi>three hundred thirty three Ells and half nail</hi> wide of the <hi>Mark.</hi> Then he very cleanlily bewrays his own Neſt, will needs have this <hi>Country</hi> to labour under a <hi>reprobated Senſe,</hi> for ſuppreſſing their <hi>Religious Cony-berries,</hi> gives it up to the <hi>Devil</hi> for believing the <hi>Plot,</hi> backs the <hi>Anathema</hi> with a <hi>Text, (Theſ.</hi> 2.10, 11.) to make it go down the better; and then after a <hi>Preſent</hi> of a matter only of half a ſcore <hi>Lyes</hi> at a clap, as a <hi>ſupplement</hi> to thoſe delivered in the Body of his <hi>Obſervations,</hi> (all which are left to be made good by time, and at his better convenience,) he forgets not, at <hi>Parting,</hi> to encourage the <hi>Criminals</hi> in their <hi>Obſtinacy,</hi> becauſe their telling the <hi>Truth</hi> would be the means of freeing them from their <hi>Impriſonment: [Veritas</hi> (ſays he) <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berabit vos,</hi> Joh 8.32.] And he thinks 'tis much better for them to be where they are, than get their liberty upon terms ſo diſadvantageous to <hi>Holy Church.</hi> They are much to blame, ſure, if they take not his Counſel.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="section">
            <head>SECT. XII.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Tenth Chapter</hi> he entitles, <hi>A word of Advice to the Deponent.</hi> And up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a right <hi>interpretation,</hi> it comes to thus much, in <hi>ſhort</hi>; (for having purpoſed <hi>Brevity,</hi> unneceſſary <hi>expanſion</hi> in <hi>contraction</hi> would be a <hi>Paradoxology</hi>) that after he has claw'd himſelf a little, for having ſo cleverly proved his Party <hi>innocent,</hi> as above; made ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable mention of the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Scroggs,</hi> [with whom (it ſeems) the world is well amended (in <hi>their</hi> opinion at leaſt) ſince the time of penning their <hi>Notes</hi> upon <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>'s Tryal; but his Lordſhip is too <hi>wiſe,</hi> and too <hi>honeſt,</hi> to regard either the <hi>Frowns</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or <hi>Flatteries</hi> of ſuch <hi>Miſcreants,</hi> as never will keep faith with any, longer than it ſtands with their <hi>convenience</hi> ſo to do:] ſpared no pains to repreſent him as <hi>black</hi> as <hi>Hell,</hi> by a <hi>courſe</hi> of <hi>Forgeries</hi> and <hi>Impoſtures</hi> of a prodigious nature, and by fathering upon him ſuch impious and atheiſtical <hi>Expreſſions</hi> as could never have been uttered, but by the moſt obdurate and accompliſh'd of <hi>Villains</hi>; he falls, at length, to laying both <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel</hi> to him; and then craving his mercy for <hi>ſlandering</hi> him, adviſes the New-moulding of the <hi>Narrative,</hi> according to the <hi>tenor</hi> of theſe his <hi>Notes,</hi> upon it, and beſeeches him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, promiſing him in <hi>that Caſe</hi> the eaſieſt Seat in all (<hi>Fools-Paradice,</hi> or) <hi>Purgatory.</hi> Then, after he has minded him to do what he does <hi>quickly,</hi> becauſe, the <hi>Parliament</hi> being upon the point of ſitting, he fears he ſhall not then have leiſure to admoniſh him thus friendly over again, and for that his <hi>Recantation</hi> will <hi>otherwiſe</hi> come too late; he ſhuts up all (<hi>pag.</hi> 42.) with this cordial Profeſſion, that if he has the good hap once more to bring him over to their <hi>Lure,</hi> he ſhall think his <hi>Labour</hi> in compiling this admirable <hi>Piece,</hi> very <hi>well ſpent,</hi> and have his <hi>hearts deſire.</hi> He never ſpake a greater <hi>Truth</hi> in his whole life; and there's an end on't.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="section">
            <head>THE CONCL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SION. SECT. XIII.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>TH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> am I now got through a <hi>Maze</hi> of as much Weakneſs, Calumny, Paſſion, and Malevolence, as I do remember my eyes ever yet to have beheld under ſo pompous and ſolemn a <hi>Pretence</hi>; ſo that if in the precedent ſhort <hi>Remarks</hi> there ſhall be found
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:47905:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
any thing excuſably <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Superficial;</hi> I may fairly plead, nevertheleſs, an <hi>unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> to combat with <hi>Shadows,</hi> and trouble my ſelf and others with an <hi>enlargement</hi> upon every <hi>Repetition,</hi> that occurr'd, of the ſelf ſame crude and indigeſted <hi>Fopperies;</hi> the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme Poverty and Barrenneſs of the <hi>Text</hi> it ſelf, that would neither bear nor deſerve a more ſerious and elaborate <hi>diſcuſſion;</hi> and a deliberate <hi>Preference</hi> of the <hi>Comical Stile,</hi> in point of <hi>Argument</hi> and <hi>Morality,</hi> to the <hi>Obſervators</hi> courſe, and ſlovenly <hi>Language</hi> of Rogue, Raſcal, Lyar, Villain, and the like. <hi>This</hi> or <hi>that,</hi> indeed, was all the <hi>Choice</hi> I had left me: and yet in my opinion this <hi>Looſe Garb</hi> is not altogether <hi>unagreeable</hi> neither, how <hi>neceſſary</hi> ſoever; in regard the <hi>Subject</hi> of the <hi>Conteſt</hi> is not of that vaſt <hi>importance,</hi> that <hi>Bloody Noſes</hi> may rationally be concluded the <hi>Conſequence</hi> of it: for I do not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the preſent <hi>queſtion</hi> to be the <hi>certain</hi> and abſolute <hi>Truth; [That</hi> having already been pronounced upon, and determined by the <hi>Supreme Authority</hi> of the <hi>Nation;</hi> which, tho it cannot be guilty of doing any thing <hi>hand over head,</hi> pretends not however to a poſitive <hi>Infallibility,</hi> but ever perſeveres to cultivate the laudible <hi>ingenuity</hi> of confeſſing and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting the <hi>unſoundneſs</hi> of any <hi>Judgment</hi> that <hi>time</hi> and better <hi>Light</hi> ſhall have convinced of <hi>Error.</hi>] But only whether or no, in the common way of <hi>Reaſoning</hi> and <hi>Thinking,</hi> there be not ground enough to avouch the <hi>Deponents Narrative,</hi> for undoubtedly <hi>probable</hi> and <hi>real,</hi> all that this <hi>Obſervator</hi> has been able to produce to the contrary notwithſtanding. Now how much I have done toward the putting <hi>this</hi> matter out of <hi>Diſpute,</hi> I muſt leave to the world to judge: only deſiring this to be taken along, that if the chief aim of that <hi>Party</hi> in diſperſing their numerous and venemous <hi>Libels</hi> were not, at any rate, to amuſe, and impoſe upon the People, but that they really believed that the <hi>Contents</hi> of all, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them were of an intrinſick value, weight and integrity, competent to abide the <hi>Teſt</hi> of a <hi>Legal Scrutiny,</hi> and to contribute the leaſt <hi>Mite</hi> toward their <hi>Compurgation;</hi> they could not fairly be preſumed ſo entirely <hi>ignorant,</hi> or <hi>regardleſs</hi> of their <hi>intereſt,</hi> as not to hold it their concern to keep what they have to ſay for themſelves as <hi>ſecret</hi> as poſſible; in as much as by divulging of it, they <hi>ipſo facto</hi> become <hi>Felones de ſe,</hi> and capacitate their <hi>Adverſaries</hi> to beat them at their own Weapons.</p>
            <p>True it is, that the <hi>Obſervator</hi> lays ſuch great ſtreſs upon his <hi>Atteſtations,</hi> (the <hi>Ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work</hi> of his <hi>Superſtructure,</hi> built with <hi>untempered Mortar</hi>;) as to think it worth his while to acquaint us, (<hi>pag.</hi> 59.) where (at S. <hi>Omers</hi>) the <hi>Originals,</hi> or <hi>authentical Copies</hi> of them, are depoſited, and to be ſeen. But why did he not rather tell what <hi>Language</hi> they are written in? and yet now I think on't, that's not a half penny matter neither; for no body but <hi>Fools</hi> or <hi>Mad-men</hi> would ever have made ſuch a <hi>quarter</hi> about a parcel of <hi>Baubles,</hi> that are of no more avail, <hi>in foro legis &amp; rationis,</hi> than the obſolete <hi>Relicks</hi> of <hi>Thomas a Beckets foul Socks, Handkerchers,</hi> and <hi>Anitergia.</hi> But not to have it ſuſpected that my buſineſs is only to find <hi>fault,</hi> and that nothing will pleaſe me; I propoſe thus: Let them but duly prove by the <hi>Oaths</hi> of ſuch ſober, creditable and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> nay, or <hi>Papiſts,</hi> as would be vouchſafed a hearing in any of their <hi>Courts</hi>; ſuch as ſtand not directly <hi>charged</hi> already (the Caſe of the <hi>Authors</hi> of their <hi>ſlievleſs Atteſtations</hi>) or. as the S. <hi>Omers Scullian, Tailor,</hi> or the <hi>Valladolid Muleman,</hi> &amp;c. are not <hi>Hangers on</hi> of their reſpective <hi>Colleges:</hi> Let them but prove in this manner (I ſay) that the <hi>Deponent</hi> never was at <hi>Madrid,</hi> at <hi>Paris</hi>; or that he was <hi>beyond Sea,</hi> when he ſwears he was in <hi>England</hi>; (for theſe are the three <hi>main points</hi>) and in the very moment of their doing it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I will believe they have been ſerv'd with very <hi>hard meaſure.</hi> Till <hi>then</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they muſt hold me excuſed, if I give no more heed to <hi>their</hi> inceſſant <hi>Yawling,</hi> than to <hi>that</hi> of a Ravenous <hi>Curr,</hi> when cudgelled for attempting to <hi>worry Sheep.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>ERRATA. <hi>Pag.</hi> 3. <hi>lin.</hi> 4 <hi>for</hi> Villains <hi>read</hi> Villanies. <hi>p.</hi> 5. <hi>l.</hi> 13. <hi>f.</hi> came <hi>r.</hi> come. <hi>p.</hi> 6. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>dele</hi> of. <hi>p.</hi> 8. <hi>l.</hi> 24. <hi>d.</hi> all. <hi>p.</hi> 9. <hi>l.</hi> 36. <hi>f.</hi> caſts <hi>r.</hi> coſts. <hi>p.</hi> 12. <hi>l.</hi> 23. <hi>f.</hi> ſome <hi>r. ſame. Ib. l.</hi> 26. <hi>f.</hi> looked <hi>r.</hi> look. <hi>p.</hi> 18. <hi>l.</hi> 40. <hi>f.</hi> preſcrib'd <hi>r.</hi> proſcrib'd. <hi>p.</hi> 21. <hi>l. ult. r.</hi> Valderama.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
