<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Account of the ceremonial at the coronation of Their Most Excellent Majesties, King James II and Queen Mary, at Westminster the 23 of April 1685, in the first year of His Majesties reign</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A24970</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A260</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4631</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11889878</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11889878</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50414</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A24970)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50414)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 47:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Account of the ceremonial at the coronation of Their Most Excellent Majesties, King James II and Queen Mary, at Westminster the 23 of April 1685, in the first year of His Majesties reign</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Newcomb in the Savoy,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published by order of the Duke of Norfolk, Earl Marshal of England"</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701 --  Coronation.</term>
               <term>Mary, --  of Modena, Queen, consort of James II, King of England, 1658-1718 --  Coronation.</term>
               <term>Coronations --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50414:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
            <head>An ACCOUNT of the Ceremonial at the CORONATION Of their Moſt Excellent MAJESTIES King JAMES II. and Queen MARY, At <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the 23 of <hi>April</hi> 1685, In the firſt year of His Majeſties Reign.</head>
            <p>THeir MAJESTIES being come from <hi>Whitehall</hi> to the Palace at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> (where the Nobility and others who were to go in the Proceeding, were aſſembled) came down in State from the HOUSE of LORDS into <hi>Weſtminſter-hall</hi> about eleven of the Clock in the Morning; and being ſeated on the THRONE there, the SWORD of STATE, the Sword CURTANA, and the two Pointed SWORDS, together with the GOLD SPURS, were preſented to His MAJESTY, and laid on a Table before HIM.</p>
            <p>Then the Dean and Prebends of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> (having before brought the CROWN and other REGALIA in Solemn Proceſſion from the Collegiate Church there,) came up the Hall, and preſented them ſeverally to His MAJESTY, which being likewiſe laid on the Table, were (together with the four SWORDS and SPURS) delivered to the Lords appointed to carry them in the Proceſſion, which began in this manner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Drums and Trumpets, then the ſix Clerks in <hi>Chancery,</hi> Chaplains having Dignities, Aldermen of <hi>London,</hi> and Maſters in <hi>Chancery,</hi> four a-breaſt, (in which Order all the reſt of the Proceeding went;) then Sergeants at Law, and others of the long Robe, Eſquires of the Body, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Privy Chamber, Judges and Chief Juſtices.</p>
            <p>Then Children of the Kings Chapel, Choir of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> Gentlemen of the Chapel, Prebends and Dean of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> Maſter of the Jewel-Houſe, and Privy Councellors not Peers.</p>
            <p>Next two Officers of Arms, then Baroneſſes, Barons, Biſhops. Two other Officers of Arms; Vicounteſſes, Vicounts. Two Heralds of Arms. Counteſſes, Earls. Two Heralds more; a Marchioneſs. Heralds of Arms; Ducheſſes, Dukes; Next the two Provincial Kings of Arms, Preceding the Great Officers and Arch-Biſhops. Then two Perſons in Robes of Eſtate repreſenting the Dukes of <hi>AQVITAIN</hi> and <hi>NORMANDY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then the Queens Vice-Chamberlain and Lord Chamberlain, and three Noblemen carrying Her Majeſties REGALIA; <hi>viz.</hi> The Earl of <hi>Dorſet</hi> The IVORY-ROD, the Earl of <hi>Rutland</hi> the SCEPTER, and the Duke of <hi>Beaufort</hi> the CROWN. Then the QUEENS MAJESTY, aſſiſted by the Biſhops of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> under a Rich Canopy ſupported by ſixteen BARONS of the CINQUE PORTS, Her Majeſties Train born by the Young Ducheſs of <hi>NORFOLK,</hi> aſſiſted by four Earls Daughters, followed by two Ladies of the Bedchamber, and two Women of the Bedchamber.</p>
            <p>Then the Noblemen who bore the Kings REGALIA, <hi>viz.</hi> The Earl of <hi>Ailsbury,</hi> St. <hi>EDWARDS</hi> STAFF, the Lord <hi>de Grey</hi> the SPURS, the Earl of <hi>Peterborow</hi> the SCEPTER with the CROSS; Next the Earl of <hi>Pembroke</hi> the Third SWORD, the Earl of <hi>Derby</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond SWORD, and between them the Earl of <hi>Shrewsbury</hi> bearing CURTANA or the POINTLESS SWORD. Then GARTER, between the Gentleman Uſher of the Black Rod, and the Lord Mayor of <hi>London.</hi> Then the Lord GREAT CHAMBERLAIN ſingle. Then the Earl of <hi>Oxford</hi> bearing the SWORD of STATE, between the Duke of <hi>Grafton</hi> LORD HIGH CONSTABLE, and the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> LORD EARL MARSHALL. Then the Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi> LORD HIGH STEWARD, bearing St. <hi>EDWARDS</hi> CROWN, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Duke of <hi>Somerſet</hi> bearing the ORB, and the Duke of <hi>Albemarle</hi> bearing the SCEPTER with the DOVE.</p>
            <p>Then the KINGS MAJESTY, aſſiſted by the Biſhops of <hi>DVRHAM</hi> and <hi>BATH,</hi> under a Rich Canopy born likewiſe by 16 Barons of the CINQUE PORTS, His MAJESTIES Train born by four Earls Eldeſt Sons, aſſiſted by the Maſter of the ROBES, followed by the Duke of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> CAPTAIN of the HORSE GUARDS, (in waiting) between the Earl of <hi>Huntington,</hi> CAP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAIN of the BAND of GENTLEMEN PENSIONERS, and the Vicount <hi>Grandiſon</hi> CAPTAIN of the YEOMEN of the GUARD; then the Lord <hi>Churchil</hi> Gentleman of the Bedchamber, followed by Two Grooms of the Bed-Chamber, the Yeomen of the Guard, cloſing the Proceeding. The Serjeants of Arms went in two Claſſes before their MAJESTIES, and the GENTLEMEN PENSIONERS on each ſide the Canopies. In this Manner, their MAJESTIES, Arrayed in their ROYAL ROBES Furred with Ermins, the <hi>KING</hi> with a VEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VET CAP, and the <hi>QVEEN</hi> a Rich Circle of Gold on her Head; All the Nobility in Robes of CRIMSON VELVET with their <hi>CAPS</hi> and <hi>CORONETS</hi> in their Hands, and the reſt who formed the Proceeding being Richly Habited or wearing their proper and peculiar Robes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded on foot upon blew Cloth, ſpread from the ſteps of the THRONE in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall</hi> to the Steps of the THEATRE in the Quire, from <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall</hi> to the Collegiate Church of St. <hi>PETER</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> (the whole paſſage being Railed in) and Guarded with His MAJESTIES Horſe and Foot Guards;) being entred the Church, and the Nobility and others all duly placed, their MAJESTIES aſcended the THEATRE and repaired to their Private Devotions on the Eaſt part thereof, and then ſeated themſelves in their Chairs of State. Then followed the <hi>Recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition;</hi> and after an <hi>Anthem,</hi> the KING and QUEEN came to the Altar and made their firſt <hi>OBLATION;</hi> and the Lords who carried the REGALIA preſented them at the Altar to be their depoſited.</p>
            <p>Then the <hi>Litany</hi> was Sung by two Biſhops, which ended, the Biſhop of <hi>Ely</hi> began the Sermon; After Sermon, the King took the accuſtomed Oath; and <hi>Veni Creator</hi> being Sung, and the KING Diſrobed of his Mantle and Surcoat, He was Anointed and Inveſted with all the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Habits in King <hi>EDWARDS</hi> Chair; and the Crown being put on juſt at Three of the Clock in the Afternoon, all the People ſhouted, the Drums and Trumpets ſounded, and the Guns in St. <hi>Jamer's Park,</hi> and great Guns at the <hi>Tower</hi> were diſcharged, and all the Peers put on their Coronets.</p>
            <p>The KING being Crowned, and having been fatther Inveſted with the Ring and Scepters, He made his ſecond Oblation, and being again ſeated in King <hi>EDWARDS</hi> Chair, He vouchſafed to Kiſs the <hi>Arch-Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops;</hi> and <hi>Te Deum</hi> being ſung, He aſcended the THRONE, and being Inthronized, the <hi>Arch-Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> did their Homage and Kiſſed the KINGS Cheek, and after them the <hi>Temporal Lords</hi> did alſo their Homage, and ſeverally kiſſed the KINGS Cheek and touched His CROWN; during which time the Treaſurer of the Houſhold threw about the <hi>Coronation Medals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then followed the CORONATION of the QUEEN, at which the Ladies put on their Coronets, as the Lords had done before at the Kings; and Her MAJESTY having received into Her Hands the SCEPTER and IVORY-ROD, was conducted to Her ROYAL SEAT upon Her THRONE.</p>
            <p>Thus their Majeſties being Inthronized, after an <hi>Anthem</hi> was ſung, the Arch-Biſhop ending with the <hi>Benediction,</hi> their Majeſties went in State into St. <hi>EDWARDS</hi> Chapel, where the King being diveſted of St. <hi>EDWARDS</hi> Robes, and Arrayed in His Royal Robes of Purple Velvet, the whole Company (except the Church of <hi>Weſtminſter)</hi> returned to <hi>Weſtmiſter-Hall</hi> in the ſame Order they came; their <hi>Majeſties</hi> and all the Nobility wearing their Coronets on their Heads; and being entred into the Hall were conducted to their ſeveral Tables to Dinner, which were all ready furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before their coming in. Only the firſt Courſe for their Majeſties Table was ſerved up with the uſual Ceremony, the Lord High Steward betwixt the Lord High Conſtable and the Earl Marſhal Riding in before it on Horſeback; And before the ſecond Courſe was ſerved up, Sir <hi>Charles Dymoke,</hi> the KINGS Champion, in Compleat Armour, accompanied with the Lord High Conſtable, and Earl Marſhal, all on Horſeback, performed the uſual Ceremony of the Challenge; After which the Officers of Arms Proclaimed his MAJESTIES Stile in <hi>Latin, French</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> after the accuſtomed manner.</p>
            <p>Dinner being ended, and all the Solemnity being performed to the great ſatisfaction of their Majeſties, with all imaginable ſplendor and Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Joy, their Majeſties retired to <hi>Whitehal,</hi> and all the Nobility and others departed.</p>
            <div type="license">
               <p>
                  <hi>Publiſhed by Order of the Duke of</hi> Norfolk <hi>Earl Marſhal of</hi> England.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Printed by</hi> Thomas Newcomb <hi>in the</hi> Savoy, 1685.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
