<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A character of the province of Mary-land ... also a small treatise on the wilde and naked Indians (or Susquehanokes) of Mary-land, their customs, manners, absurdities, &amp; religion : together with a collection of historical letters / by George Alsop.</title>
            <author>Alsop, George, b. 1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 127 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 74 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-10">2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25198</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A2901</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6606</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11602378</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11602378</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47901</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A25198)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47901)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 5:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A character of the province of Mary-land ... also a small treatise on the wilde and naked Indians (or Susquehanokes) of Mary-land, their customs, manners, absurdities, &amp; religion : together with a collection of historical letters / by George Alsop.</title>
                  <author>Alsop, George, b. 1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[25], 118, [3] p. : map, port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.J. for Peter Dring ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>(from t.p.) I. The scituation and plenty of the province -- II. The laws, customs and natural demeanor of the inhabitant -- III. The worst and best usage of a Mary-land servant opened in view -- IV. The traffique and vendable commodities of the countrey.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Susquehanna Indians.</term>
               <term>Maryland --  Description and travel.</term>
               <term>Maryland --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:47901:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of George Alsop</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <date>Anno Do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: 1666.</date> Aetatis Suae 28. </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>View here the Shadow whoſe Ingenious Hand</l>
                     <l>Hath drawne exact the Province Mary Land</l>
                     <l>Diſplay'd her Glory in ſuch Scaenes of Witt</l>
                     <l>That thoſe that read muſt fall in Love with it</l>
                     <l>For which his Labour hee deſerves the praiſe</l>
                     <l>As well as Poets doe the wreath of Bays</l>
                     <signed>H.W.</signed>
                  </lg>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:47901:1"/>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47901:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47901:2"/>
            <p>A CHARACTER Of the PROVINCE of MARY-LAND, Wherein is Deſcribed in four diſtinct Parts, (<hi>Viz.</hi>)
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>The Scituation, and plenty of the Province.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>The Laws, Cuſtoms, and natural Demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the Inhabitant.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>III.</hi> The worſt and beſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage of a <hi>Mary-Land</hi> Servant, opened in view.</item>
                  <item>IV. <hi>The Traffique, and vendable Commodities of the Countrey.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>ALSO A ſmall <hi>Treatiſe</hi> on the wilde and naked <hi>INDIANS</hi> (or <hi>Suſquehanokes</hi>) of <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> their Cuſtoms, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Abſurdities, &amp; Religion.</p>
            <p>Together with a Collection of Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical LETTERS.</p>
            <p>By <hi>GEORGE ALSOP.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. J.</hi> for <hi>Peter Dring,</hi> at the ſign of the Sun in the <hi>Poultrey</hi>: 1666.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:47901:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47901:3"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable <hi>Caecilius</hi> Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> Abſolute Lord and Proprietary of the Provinces of <hi>Mary-Land</hi> and <hi>Avalon</hi> in <hi>America.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have adventured on your Lordſhips accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance by gueſs; if pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption has led me into an Error that deſerves cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, I heartily beg In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempnity, and reſolve to repent ſoundly for it, and do ſo no more. VVhat I preſent I know to be true, <hi>Experientia docet</hi>; It being
<pb facs="tcp:47901:4"/>
an infallible Maxim, <hi>That there is no Globe like the occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and experimental view of a Countrey.</hi> And had not Fate by a neceſſary imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, confin'd me within the narrow walks of a four years Servitude, and by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees led me through the moſt intricate and dubious paths of this Countrey, by a commanding and unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable Enjoynment, I could not, nor ſhould I ever have undertaken to have written a line of this nature.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:47901:4"/>If I have wrote or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed any thing that's wilde and confuſed, it is becauſe I am ſo my ſelf, and the world, as far as I can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, is not much out of the ſame trim; therefore I reſolve, if I am brought to the Bar of <hi>Common Law</hi> for any thing I have done here, to plead <hi>Non compos men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> to ſave my Bacon.</p>
            <p>There is an old Saying in Engliſh, <hi>He muſt riſe betimes that would pleaſe every one.</hi> And I am afraid I have lain
<pb facs="tcp:47901:5"/>
ſo long a bed, that I think I ſhall pleaſe no body; if it muſt be ſo, I cannot help it. But as <hi>Felton</hi> in his <hi>Reſolves</hi> ſays, <hi>In things that muſt be, 'tis good to be reſolute</hi>; And therefore what Deſtiny has ordained, I am reſolved to wink, and ſtand to it. So leaving your Honour to more ſerious meditations, I ſubſcribe my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhip moſt Humble Servant, <hi>George Alſop.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:47901:5"/>
            <head>To all the Merchant Adventurers for <hi>MARY-LAND,</hi> together with thoſe Commanders of Ships that ſaile into that Province.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> are both Adventurers, the one of Eſtate, the other of Life: I could tell you I am an Adventurer too, if I durſt preſume to come into your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. I have ventured to come abroad in Print, and if I ſhould be laughed at for my good mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it would ſo break the credit of my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that I ſhould never dare to ſhew my face upon the Exchange of (conceited) Wits again.</p>
            <p>This diſh of Diſcourſe was intended for you at firſt, but it was manners to let my Lord have the firſt cut, the Pye being his own. I beſeech you accept of the matter as 'tis dreſt, only to ſtay your ſtomachs, and I'le promiſe you the next ſhall be better done. 'Tis all as I can ſerve you in at preſent, and it may be queſtionable whether I have ſerved you in this or no. Here I preſent you with <hi>A Character of Mary-Land,</hi> it may
<pb facs="tcp:47901:6"/>
be you will ſay 'tis weakly done, if you do I cannot help it, 'tis as well as I could do it, conſidering the ſeveral Obſtacles that like blocks were thrown in my way to hinder my proceeding: The major part thereof was written in the intermitting time of my ſickneſs, therefore I hope the afflicting weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my Microcoſm may plead a juſt excuſe for ſome imperfections of my pen. I proteſt what I have writ is from an experimental knowledge of the Country, and not from any imaginary ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. If I am blamed for what I have done too much, it is the firſt, and I will irrevocably pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe it ſhall be the laſt. There's a Maxim upon Tryals at Aſſizes, That if a Thief be taken upon the firſt fault, if it be not too hainous, they only burn him in the hand and let him go: So I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you to do by me, if you find any thing that bears a criminal abſurdity in it, only burn me for my firſt fact and let me go. But I am affraid I have kept you too long in the Entry, I ſhall deſire you therefore to come in and ſit down.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. Alſop.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:47901:6"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE Reaſon why I appear in this place is, leſt the general Reader ſhould conclude I have nothing to ſay for my ſelf; and truly he's in the right on't, for I have but little to ſay (for my ſelf) at this time: For I have had ſo large a Journey, and ſo heavy a Burden to bring <hi>Mary-Land</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> that I am almoſt out of breath: I'le promiſe you after I am come to my ſelf, you ſhall hear more of me. Good Reader, becauſe you ſee me make a brief Apologetical excuſe for my ſelf, don't judge me; for I am ſo ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited of my own merits, that I almoſt think I want none. <hi>De Lege non judicandum ex
<pb facs="tcp:47901:7"/>
ſolâ linea,</hi> ſaith the Civilian; We muſt not paſs judgement upon a Law by one line: And becauſe we ſee but a ſmall Buſh at a Tavern door, conclude there is no Canary. For as in our vulgar Reſolves 'tis ſaid, <hi>A good f<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce needs no Band, and an ill one deſerves none:</hi> So the French Proverb ſayes, <hi>Bon Vien il n'a faut point de Enſigne,</hi> Good Wine needs no Buſh. I ſuppoſe by this time ſome of my ſpeculative obſervers have judged me vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious; but if they did but rightly conſider me, they would not be ſo cenſorious. For I dwell ſo far from Neighbors, that if I do not praiſe my ſelf, no body elſe will: And ſince I am left alone, I am reſolved to ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon the <hi>Magna Charta</hi> of Fowles to the Bar for my excuſe, and by their irrevocable Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes plead my diſcharge, <hi>For its an ill Bird will befoule her own Neſt:</hi> Beſides, I have a thouſand <hi>Billings-gate</hi> Collegians that will give in their teſtimony, <hi>That they never knew a Fiſh-woman cry ſtinking Fiſh.</hi> Thus leaving the Noſtrils of the Citizens Wives to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate what they pleaſe as to that, and thee (Good Reader) to ſay what thou wilt, I bid thee Farewel.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Geo. Alſop.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_book">
            <pb facs="tcp:47901:7"/>
            <head>THE AUTHOR TO HIS BOOK.</head>
            <l>WHen firſt <hi>Apollo</hi> got my brain with Childe,</l>
            <l>He made large promiſe never to beguile,</l>
            <l>But like an honeſt Father, he would keep</l>
            <l>Whatever Iſſue from my Brain did creep:</l>
            <l>With that I gave conſent, and up he threw</l>
            <l>Me on a Bench, and ſtrangely he did do<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>Then every week he daily came to ſee</l>
            <l>How his new Phyſick ſtill did work with me,</l>
            <l>And when he did perceive he'd don the feat,</l>
            <l>Like an unworthy man he made retreat,</l>
            <l>Left me in deſolation, and where none</l>
            <l>Compaſſionated when they heard me groan.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:47901:8"/>What could he judge the Pariſh then would think,</l>
            <l>To ſee me fair, his Brat as black as Ink?</l>
            <l>If they had eyes, they'd ſwear I were no Nun,</l>
            <l>But got with Child by ſome black <hi>Africk</hi> Son,</l>
            <l>And ſo condemn me for my Fornication,</l>
            <l>To beat them Hemp to ſtifle half the Nation.</l>
            <l>Well, ſince 'tis ſo, I'le alter this baſe Fate,</l>
            <l>And lay his Baſtard at ſome Noble's Gate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>Withdraw my ſelf from Beadles, and from ſuch,</l>
            <l>Who would give twelve pence I were in their clutch:</l>
            <l>Then, who can tell? this Child which I do hide,</l>
            <l>May be in time a Small-beer Col'nel <hi>Pride.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>But while I talk, my buſineſs it is dumb,</l>
            <l>I muſt lay double-clothes unto thy Bum,</l>
            <l>Then lap thee warm, and to the World commit</l>
            <l>The Baſtard Off-ſpring of a New-born wit.</l>
            <l>Farewel, poor Brat, thou in a monſtrous World,</l>
            <l>In ſwadling bands, thus up and down art hurl'd;</l>
            <l>There to receive what Deſtiny doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive,</l>
            <l>Either to periſh, or be ſav'd alive.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:47901:8"/>Good Fate protect thee from a Criticks power,</l>
            <l>For if he comes, thou'rt gon in half an hour,</l>
            <l>Stifl'd and blaſted, 'tis their uſual way,</l>
            <l>To make that Night, which is as bright as Day.</l>
            <l>For if they once but wring, and skrew their mouth,</l>
            <l>Cock up their Hats, and ſet the point Du<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> South,</l>
            <l>Armes all a kimbo, and with belly ſtrut,</l>
            <l>As if they had <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> in their gut:</l>
            <l>Theſe are the Symtomes of the murthering fall</l>
            <l>Of my poor Infant, and his burial.</l>
            <l>Say he ſhould miſs thee, and ſome ign'rant Aſſe</l>
            <l>Should find thee out, as he along doth paſs,</l>
            <l>It were all one, he'd look into thy Tayle,</l>
            <l>To ſee if thou wert Feminine or Male;</l>
            <l>When he'd half ſtarv'd thee, for to ſatisfie</l>
            <l>His peeping Ign'rance, he'd then let thee lie;</l>
            <l>And vow by's wit he ne're could underſtand,</l>
            <l>The Heathen dreſſes of another Land:</l>
            <l>Well, 'tis no matter, wherever ſuch as he</l>
            <l>Knows one grain, more then his ſimplicity.</l>
            <l>Now, how the pulſes of my Senſes beat,</l>
            <l>To think the rigid Fortune thou wilt meet;</l>
            <l>Aſſes and captious Fools, not ſix in ten</l>
            <l>Of thy Spectators will be real men,</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:47901:9"/>To Umpire up the badneſs of the Cauſe,</l>
            <l>And ſcreen my weakneſs from the rav'nous Laws,</l>
            <l>Of thoſe that will undoubted ſit to ſee</l>
            <l>How they might blaſt this new born Infancy:</l>
            <l>If they ſhould burn him, they<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d conclude hereafter,</l>
            <l>'Twere too good death for him to dye a Martyr;</l>
            <l>And if they let him live, they think it will</l>
            <l>Be but a means for to encourage ill,</l>
            <l>And bring in time ſome ſtrange <hi>Antipod'ans,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>A thouſand Leagues beyond <hi>Philippians,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To ſtorm our Wits; therefore he muſt not reſt,</l>
            <l>But ſhall be hang'd, for all he has been preſt:</l>
            <l>Thus they conclude. — My Genius com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts give,</l>
            <l>In Reſurrection he will ſurely live.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="map_of_Maryland">
            <pb facs="tcp:47901:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47901:10"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
               <pb facs="tcp:47901:10"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>A Land-ſkip of the Province of MARY LAND Or the Lord Baltimors Plantation neer Virginia</head>
                  <byline>By Geo: Alſop Gent</byline>
                  <figDesc>map of Maryland</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:47901:11"/>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:47901:11"/>
            <head>To my Friend Mr. <hi>George Alſop,</hi> on his <hi>Character of MARY-LAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>WHo ſuch odd nookes of Earths great maſs deſcribe,</l>
            <l>Prove their deſcent from old <hi>Columbus</hi> tribe:</l>
            <l>Some Boding augur did his Name deviſe,</l>
            <l>Thy Genius too caſt in th' ſame mould and ſize;</l>
            <l>His Name predicted he would be a Rover,</l>
            <l>And hidden places of this Orb diſcover;</l>
            <l>He made relation of that World in groſs,</l>
            <l>Thou the particulars retail'ſt to us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>By this firſt Peny of thy fancy we</l>
            <l>Diſcover what thy greater Coines will be;</l>
            <l>This Embryo thus well poliſht doth preſage,</l>
            <l>The manly Atchievements of its future age,</l>
            <l>Auſpicious winds blow gently on this ſpark,</l>
            <l>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntill its flames diſcover what's yet dark;</l>
            <l>Mean while this ſhort Abridgement we embrace,</l>
            <l>Expecting that thy buſie Soul will trace</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:47901:12"/>Some Mines at laſt which may enrich the World.</l>
            <l>And all that poverty may be in oblivion hurl'd.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Zoilus</hi> is dumb, for thou the mark haſt hit,</l>
            <l>By interlacing Hiſtory with Wit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>Thou haſt deſcrib'd its ſuperficial Treaſure,</l>
            <l>Anatomiz'd its bowels at thy leaſure;</l>
            <l>That <hi>MARY-LAND</hi> to thee may duty owe,</l>
            <l>Who to the World doſt all her Glory ſhew:</l>
            <l>Then thou ſhalt make the Propheſie fall true,</l>
            <l>Who fill'ſt the World (like th' Sea) with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge new.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Bogherſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:47901:12"/>
            <head>To my Friend Mr. <hi>George Alſop,</hi> on his <hi>Character of MARY-LAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>THis plain, yet pithy and conciſe Deſcription</l>
            <l>Of <hi>Mary-Lands</hi> plentious and ſedate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>With other things herein by you ſet forth,</l>
            <l>To ſhew its Rareneſs, and declare its Worth;</l>
            <l>Compos'd in ſuch a time, when most men were</l>
            <l>Smitten with Sickneſs, or ſurpriz'd with Fear,</l>
            <l>Argues a Genius good, and Courage ſtout,</l>
            <l>In bringing this Deſign ſo well about:</l>
            <l>Such generous Freedom waited on thy brain,</l>
            <l>The Work was done in midſt of greateſt pain;</l>
            <l>And matters flow'd ſo ſwiftly from thy ſource,</l>
            <l>Nature deſign'd thee (ſure) for ſuch Diſcourſe</l>
            <l>Go on then with thy Work ſo well begun,</l>
            <l>Let it come forth, and boldly ſee the Sun;</l>
            <l>Then ſhall't be known to all, that from thy Youth</l>
            <l>Thou heldſt it Noble to maintain the Truth,</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:47901:13"/>'Gainſt all the Rabble-rout, that yelping ſtand,</l>
            <l>To caſt aſperſions on thy <hi>MARY-LAND</hi>:</l>
            <l>But this thy Work ſhall vindicate its Fame,</l>
            <l>And as a Trophy memorize thy Name;</l>
            <l>So if without a Tomb thou buried be,</l>
            <l>This Book's a laſting Monument for thee.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. W. Maſter of Arts.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Study,</hi>
                  <date>Jan. <hi>10, 1665.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:47901:13"/>
            <head>To my Friend Mr. <hi>George Alſop,</hi> on his <hi>Character of MARY-LAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>COlumbus</hi> with <hi>Apollo</hi> ſure did ſet,</l>
               <l>When he did Court to propigate thy Wit,</l>
               <l>Or elſe thy Genius with ſo ſmall a Clew,</l>
               <l>Could not have brought ſuch Intricates in view;</l>
               <l>Diſcover'd hidden Earth ſo plain, that we</l>
               <l>View more in this, then if we went to ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>MARY-LAND,</hi> I with ſome thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands more,</l>
               <l>Could not imagine where ſhe ſtood before;</l>
               <l>And hadſt thou ſtill been ſilent with thy Pen,</l>
               <l>We had continu'd ſtill the ſelf-ſame men,</l>
               <l>Ne're to have known the glory of that Soyle,</l>
               <l>Whoſe plentious dwellings is four thouſand mile.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:47901:14"/>
               <l>The portly <hi>Suſquehanock</hi> in his naked dreſs,</l>
               <l>Had certain ſtill been <hi>Pigmye,</hi> or much leſs;</l>
               <l>All had been dark (to us) and obſcure yet,</l>
               <l>Had not thy diligence diſcover'd it:</l>
               <l>For this we owe thee Praiſes to the Skie,</l>
               <l>But none but <hi>MARY-LAND</hi> can gratifie.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Will. Barber.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47901:14"/>
            <head>A CHARACTER Of the PROVINCE of MARY-LAND.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. Of the ſituation and plenty of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Mary-Land.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ARY-LAND</hi> is a Province ſituated upon the large ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending bowels of <hi>America,</hi> under the Government of the Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent Northwardly upon the Confines of <hi>New-England,</hi> and neighbouring
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:47901:15"/>
Southwardly upon <hi>Virginia,</hi> dwelling pleaſantly upon the Bay of <hi>Chaeſapike,</hi> between the Degrees of 36 and 38, in the Zone temperate, and by Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical computation is eleven hundred and odd Leagues in Longitude from <hi>England,</hi> being within her own im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces extraordinary pleaſant and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile. Pleaſant, in reſpect of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Navigable Rivers and Creeks that conveniently and moſt profitably lodge within the armes of her green, ſpreading, and delightful Woods; whoſe natural womb (by her plenty) maintains and preſerves the ſeveral di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities of Animals that rangingly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit her Woods; as ſhe doth other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe generouſly fructifie this piece of Earth with almoſt all ſorts of Vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, as well Flowers with their varieties of colours and ſmells, as Herbes and Roots with their ſeveral effects and operative vertues, that offer their bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits daily to ſupply the want of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitant, whene're their neceſſities ſhall
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:47901:15"/>
                  <hi>Sub-poena</hi> them to wait on their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. So that he, who out of curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity deſires to ſee the Landskip of the Creation drawn to the life, or to read Natures univerſal Herbal without book, may with the Opticks of a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet diſcerning, view <hi>Mary-Land</hi> dreſt in her green and fragrant Mantle of the Spring. Neither do I think there is any place under the Heavenly altitude, or that has footing or room upon the circular Globe of this world, that can parallel this fertile and pleaſant piece of ground in its multiplicity, or rather Natures extravagancy of a ſuper-abounding plenty. For ſo much doth this Country increaſe in a ſwelling Spring-tide of rich variety and diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of all things, not only common proviſions that ſupply the reaching ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach of man with a ſatisfactory plenty, but alſo extends with its liberality and free convenient benefits to each ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive faculty, according to their ſeveral deſiring Appetites. So that had Nature
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47901:16"/>
made it her buſineſs, on purpoſe to have found out a ſituation for the Soul of profitable Ingenuity, ſhe could not have fitted herſelf better in the traverſe of the whole Univerſe, nor in convenienter terms have told man, <hi>Dwell here, live plentifully and be rich.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Trees, Plants, Fruits, Flowers, and Roots that grow here in <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> are the only Emblems or Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyphicks of our Adamitical or Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſituation, as well for their variety as odoriferous ſmells, together with their vertues, according to their ſeveral effects, kinds and properties, which ſtill bear the Effigies of Innocency accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their original Grafts; which by their dumb vegetable Oratory, each hour ſpeaks to the Inhabitant in ſilent acts, That they need not look for any other Terreſtrial Paradice, to ſuſpend or tyre their curioſity upon, while ſhe is extant. For within her doth dwell ſo much of variety, ſo much of natural plenty, that there is not any thing that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47901:16"/>
is or may be rare, but it inhabits within this plentious ſoyle: So that thoſe parts of the Creation that have borne the Bell away (for many ages) for a vegetable plentiouſneſs, muſt now in ſilence ſtrike and vayle all, and whiſper ſoftly in the auditual parts of <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> that <hi>None but ſhe in this dwells ſingular</hi>; and that as well for that ſhe doth exceed in thoſe Fruits, Plants, Trees and Roots, that dwell and grow in their ſeveral Clymes or habitable parts of the Earth beſides, as the rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſuperexcellency of her own glory, which ſhe flouriſhly abounds in, by the abundancy of reſerved Rarities, ſuch as the remainder of the World (with all its ſpeculative art) never bore any occular teſtimony of as yet. I ſhall forbear to particularize thoſe ſeveral ſorts of Vegetables that flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhingly grows here, by reaſon of the vaſt tediouſneſs that will attend upon the deſcription, which therefore makes them much more fit for an
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47901:17"/>
Herbal, then a ſmall Manuſcript or Hiſtory.</p>
               <p>As for the wilde Animals of this Country, which looſely inhabits the Woods in multitudes, it is impoſſible to give you an exact deſcription of them all, eonſidering the multiplicity as well as the diverſity of ſo numerous an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of Creatures: But ſuch as has fallen within the compaſs or proſpect of my knowledge, thoſe you ſhall know of; <hi>videlicet,</hi> the Deer, becauſe they are oftner ſeen, and more participated of by the Inhabitants of the Land, whoſe acquaintance by a cuſtomary fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity becomes much more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon then the reſt of Beaſts that inhabit the Woods, by uſing themſelves in Herds about the Chriſtian Plantations. Their fleſh, which in ſome places of this Province is the common proviſion the Inhabitants feed on, and which through the extreme glut and plenty of it, being daily killed by the <hi>Indians,</hi> and brought in to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as well as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47901:17"/>
that which is killed by the Chriſtian Inhabitant, that doth it more for recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, then for the benefit they reap by it. I ſay, the fleſh of Veniſon becomes (as to food) rather denyed, then any way eſteemed or deſired. And this I ſpeak from an experimental know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; For when I was under a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and debarr'd of a four years ranging Liberty in the Province of <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> the Gentleman whom I ſerved my conditional and prefixed time withall, had at one time in his houſe fourſcore Veniſons, beſides plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of other proviſions to ſerve his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily nine months, they being but ſeven in number; ſo that before this Veniſon was brought to a period by eating, it ſo nauſeated our appetites and ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machs, that plain bread was rather courted and deſired then it.</p>
               <p>The Deer here neither in ſhape nor action differ from our Deer in <hi>England</hi>: The Park they traverſe their ranging and unmeaſured walks in, is bounded
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47901:18"/>
and impanell'd in with no other pales then the rough and billowed Ocean: They are alſo mighty numerous in the Woods, and are little or not at all affrighted at the face of a man, but (like the Docs of <hi>Whetſtons</hi> Park) though their hydes are not altogether ſo gaudy to extract an admiration from the beholder, yet they will ſtand (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt) till they be ſcratcht.</p>
               <p>As for the Wolves, Bears, and Panthers of this Country, they inhabit commonly in great multitudes up in the remoteſt parts of the Continent; yet at ſome certain time they come down near the Plantations, but do little hurt or injury worth noting, and that which they do is of ſo degenerate and low a nature, (as in reference to the fierceneſs and heroick vigour that dwell in the ſame kind of Beaſts in other Countries) that they are hardly worth mentioning: For the higheſt of their deſigns and circumventing reaches is but cowardly and baſe, only to ſteal a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47901:18"/>
poor Pigg, or kill a loſt and half ſtarved Calf. The Effigies of a man terrifies them dreadfully, for they no ſooner eſpy him but their hearts are at their mouths, and the ſpurs upon their heels, they (having no more manners then Beaſts) gallop away, and never bid them farewell that are behind them.</p>
               <p>The Elke, the Cat of the Mountain, the Rackoon, the Fox, the Beaver, the Otter, the Poſſum, the Hare, the Squirril, the Monack, the Musk-Rat, and ſeveral others (whom I'le omit for brevity ſake) inhabit here in <hi>Mary-Land</hi> in ſeveral droves and troops, rang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Woods at their pleaſure.</p>
               <p>The meat of moſt of theſe Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is good for eating, yet of no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue nor eſteem here, by reaſon of the great plenty of other proviſions, and are only kill'd by the <hi>Indians</hi> of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try for their Hydes and Furrs, which become very profitable to thoſe that have the right way of traffiquing for them, as well as it redounds to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47901:19"/>
                  <hi>Indians</hi> that take the pains to catch them, and to ſlay and dreſs their ſeveral Hydes, ſelling and diſpoſing them for ſuch Commodities as their Heatheniſh fancy delights in.</p>
               <p>As for thoſe Beaſts that were carried over at the firſt ſeating of the Country, to ſtock and increaſe the ſituation, as Cows, Horſes, Sheep and Hogs, they are generally tame, and uſe near home, eſpecially the Cows, Sheep and Horſes. The Hogs, whoſe increaſe is innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in the Woods, do disfrequent home more then the reſt of Creatures that are look'd upon as tame, yet with little trouble and pains they are ſlain and made proviſion of. Now they that will with a right Hiſtorical Survey, view the Woods of <hi>Mary-Land</hi> in this particular, as in reference to Swine, muſt upon neceſſity judge this Land lineally deſcended from the <hi>Gadarean</hi> Territories.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mary-Land</hi> (I muſt confeſs) cannot boaſt of her plenty of Sheep here, as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47901:19"/>
other Countries; not but that they will thrive and increaſe here, as well as in any place of the World beſides, but few deſire them, becauſe they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly draw down the Wolves among the Plantations, as well by the ſweetneſs of their fleſh, as by the humility of their nature, in not making a defenſive re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance againſt the rough dealing of a ravenous Enemy. They who for cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity will keep Sheep, may expect that after the Wolves have breathed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves all day in the Woods to ſharpen their ſtomachs, they will come without fail and ſup with them at night, though many times they ſurfeit themſelves with the ſawce that's diſh'd out of the muzzle of a Gun, and ſo in the midſt of their banquet (poor Animals) they often ſleep with their Anceſtors.</p>
               <p>Fowls of all ſorts and varieties dwell at their ſeveral times and ſeaſons here in <hi>Mary-Land</hi>: The Turkey, the Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock, the Pheaſant, the Partrich, the Pigeon, and others, eſpecially the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47901:20"/>
Turkey, whom I have ſeen in whole hundreds in flights in the Woods of <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> being an extraordinary fat Fowl, whoſe fleſh is very pleaſant and ſweet. Theſe Fowls that I have named are intayled from generation to genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Woods. The Swans, the Geeſe and Ducks (with other Water-Fowl) derogate in this point of ſetled reſidence; for they arrive in millionous multitudes in <hi>Mary-Land</hi> about the middle of <hi>September,</hi> and take their winged farewell about the midſt of <hi>March</hi>: But while they do remain, and beleagure the borders of the ſhoar with their winged Dragoons, ſeveral of them are ſummoned by a Writ of <hi>Fieri fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias,</hi> to anſwer their preſumptuous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon a Spit.</p>
               <p>As for Fiſh, which dwell in the watry tenements of the deep, and by a provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential greatneſs of power, is kept for the relief of ſeveral Countries in the world, (which would elſe ſink under the rigid enemy of want) here in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47901:20"/>
                  <hi>Mary-Land</hi> is a large ſufficiency, and plenty of almoſt all ſorts of Fiſhes, which live and inhabit within her ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rivers and Creeks, far beyond the apprehending or crediting of thoſe that never ſaw the ſame, which with very much eaſe is catched, to the great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment of the Inhabitants of that Province.</p>
               <p>All ſorts of Grain, as wheat, Rye, Barley, Oates, Peaſe, beſides ſeveral others that have their original and birth from the fertile womb of this Land, (and no where elſe) they all grow, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and thrive here in <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> without the chargable and laborious manuring of the Land with Dung; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing in ſuch a meaſure and plenty, by the natural richneſs of the Earth, with the common, beneficial and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient ſhowers of rain that uſually wait upon the ſeveral Fields of Grain, (by a natural inſtinct) ſo that Famine (the dreadful Ghoſt of penury and want) is never known with his pale
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:47901:21"/>
viſage to haunt the Dominions of <hi>Mary-Land.</hi>
               </p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>Could'ſt thou (O Earth) live thus ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, and now</l>
                     <l>Within an Age, ſhew forth thy plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous brow</l>
                     <l>Of rich variety, gilded with fruitful Fame,</l>
                     <l>That (Trumpet-like) doth Heraldize thy Name,</l>
                     <l>And tells the World there is a Land now found,</l>
                     <l>That all Earth's Globe can't parallel its Ground?</l>
                     <l>Dwell, and be proſperous, and with thy plenty feed</l>
                     <l>The craving Carkeſſes of thoſe Souls that need.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:47901:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. Of the Government and natural diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the People.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MARY-LAND,</hi> not from the remoteneſs of her ſituation, but from the regularity of her well-ordered Government, may (without ſin, I think) be called <hi>Singular</hi>: And though ſhe is not ſupported with ſuch large Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues as ſome of her Neighbours are, yet ſuch is her wiſdom in a reſerved ſilence, and not in pomp, to ſhew her well-conditioned Eſtate, in relieving at a diſtance the proud poverty of thoſe that wont be ſeen they want, as well as thoſe which by undeniable neceſſities are drove upon the Rocks of pinching wants: Yet ſuch a loathſome creature is a common and folding-handed Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, that upon the penalty of almoſt a perpetual<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> working in Impriſonment, they are not to appear, nor lurk near our vigilant and laborious dwellings.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:47901:22"/>
The Country hath received a general ſpleen and antipathy againſt the very name and nature of it; and though there were no Law provided (as there is) to ſuppreſs it, I am certainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, there is none within the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince that would lower themſelves ſo much below the dignity of men to beg, as long as limbs and life keep houſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; ſo much is a vigilant induſtrious care eſteem'd.</p>
               <p>He that deſires to ſee the real Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form of a quiet and ſober Government extant, Superiority with a meek and yet commanding power ſitting at the Helme, ſteering the actions of State quietly, through the multitude and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of Opinionous waves that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly meet, let him look on <hi>Mary-Land</hi> with eyes admiring, and he'le then judge her, <hi>The Miracle of this Age.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here the <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtant Epiſcopal,</hi> (whom the world would perſwade have proclaimed open Wars irrevocably againſt each other)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:47901:22"/>
contrarywiſe concur in an unanimous parallel of friendſhip, and inſeparable love intayled unto one another: All Inquiſitions, Martyrdom, and Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are not ſo much as named, but unexpreſſably abhorr'd by each other.</p>
               <p>The ſeveral Opinions and Sects that lodge within this Government, meet not together in mutinous contempts to diſquiet the power that bears Rule, but with a reverend quietneſs obeys the legal commands of Authority. Here's never ſeen Five Monarchies in a Zealous Rebellion, oppoſing the Rights and Liberties of a true ſetled Government, or Monarchical Authority: Nor did I ever ſee (here in <hi>Mary-Land</hi>) any of thoſe dancing Adamitical Siſters, that plead a primitive Innocency for their baſe obſcenity, and naked deportment; but I conceive if ſome of them were there at ſome certain time of the year, between the Months of <hi>January</hi> and <hi>February,</hi> when the winds blow from the North-Weſt quarter of the world,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:47901:23"/>
that it would both cool, and (I believe) convert the hotteſt of theſe Zealots from their burning and fierceſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence.</p>
               <p>The Government of this Province doth continually, by all lawful means, ſtrive to purge her Dominions from ſuch baſe corroding humors, that would predominate upon the leaſt ſmile of Liberty, did not the Laws check and bridle in thoſe unwarranted and tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Opinions. And truly, where a Kingdom, State or Government, keeps or cuts down the weeds of deſtructive Opinions, there muſt certainly be a bleſſed Harmony of quietneſs. And I really believe this Land or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Mary-Land</hi> may boaſt, that ſhe enjoys as much quietneſs from the diſturbance of Rebellious Opinions, as moſt States or Kingdoms do in the world: For here every man lives quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and follows his labour and imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment deſiredly; and by the protection of the Laws, they are ſupported from
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:47901:23"/>
thoſe moleſtious troubles that ever attend upon the Commons of other States and Kingdoms, as well as from the Aquafortial operation of great and eating Taxes. Here's nothing to be levyed out of the Granaries of Corn; but contrarywiſe, by a Law every Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick Governor of a Family is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to make or cauſe to be made ſo much Corn by a juſt limitation, as ſhall be ſufficient for him and his Family: So that by this wiſe and <hi>Janus</hi>-like providence, the thin jawed Skeliton with his ſtarv'd Carkeſs is never ſeen walking the Woods of <hi>Mary-Land</hi> to affrighten Children.</p>
               <p>Once every year within this Province is an Aſſembly called, and out of every reſpective County (by the conſent of the people) there is choſen a number of men, and to them is deliver'd up the Grievances of the Country; and they maturely debate the matters, and accord<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng to their Conſciences make Laws for the general good of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:47901:24"/>
and where any former Law that was made, ſeems and is prejudicial to the good or quietneſs of the Land, it is repeal'd. Theſe men that determine on theſe matters for the Republique, are called Burgeſſes, and they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly fit in Junto about ſix weeks, being for the moſt part good ordinary Houſholders of the ſeveral Counties, which do more by a plain and honeſt Conſcience, then by artificial Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſms dreſt up in gilded Orations.</p>
               <p>Here Suits and Tryals in Law ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome hold diſpute two Terms or Courts, but according as the Equity of the cauſe appears is brought to a period. The <hi>Temples</hi> and <hi>Grays-Inne</hi> are clear out of faſhion here: <hi>Marriot</hi> would ſooner get a paunch-devouring meal for nothing, then for his invading Counſil. Here if the Lawyer had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe to maintain him but his bawl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he might button up his Chops, and burn his Buckrom Bag, or elſe hang it upon a pin untill its Antiquity
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:47901:24"/>
had eaten it up with durt and duſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Then with a Spade, like his Grandſire <hi>Adam,</hi> turn up the face of the Creation, purchaſing his bread by the ſweat of his brows, that before was got by the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionated Water-works of his jaws. So contrary to the Genius of the people, if not to the quiet Government of the Province, that the turbulent Spirit of continued and vexatious Law, with all its querks and evaſions, is openly and moſt eagerly oppoſed, that might make matters either dubious, tedious, or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſom. All other matters that would be ranging in contrary and improper Spheres, (in ſhort) are here by the Power moderated, lower'd, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued. All villanous Outrages that are committed in other States, are not ſo much as known here: A man may walk in the open Woods as ſecure from being externally diſſected, as in his own houſe or dwelling. So hateful is a Robber, that if but once ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd to be ſo, he's kept at a diſtance,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:47901:25"/>
and ſhun'd as the Peſtilential noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſs.</p>
               <p>It is generally and very remarkably obſerved, That thoſe whoſe Lives and Converſations have had no other gloſs nor glory ſtampt on them in their own Country, but the ſtigmatization of baſeneſs, were here (by the common civilities and deportments of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of this Province) brought to deteſt and loath their former actions. Here the Conſtable hath no need of a train of Holberteers, that carry more Armour about them, then heart to guard him: Nor is he ever troubled to leave his Feathered Neſt to ſome friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſucceſſor, while he is placing of his Lanthern-horn Guard at the end of ſome ſuſpicious Street, to ca<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch ſome Night-walker, or Batchelor of Leache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that has taken his Degree three ſtory high in a Bawdy-houſe Here's no <hi>Newgates</hi> for pilfering Felons, nor <hi>Ludgates</hi> for Debtors, nor any <hi>Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>w<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ls</hi> to laſh the ſoul of Concupiſcence
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:47901:25"/>
into a chaſt Repentance. For as there is none of theſe Priſons in <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> ſo the merits of the Country deſerves none, but if any be foully vitious, he is ſo reſerv'd in it, that he ſeldom or never becomes popular. Common Ale-houſes, (whoſe dwellings are the only Receptacles of debauchery and baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and thoſe Schools that trains up Youth, as well as Age, to ruine) in this Province there are none; neither hath Youth his ſwing or range in ſuch a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe and unbridled liberty as in other Countries; for from an an<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ient Cuſtom at the primitive ſeating of the place, the Son works as well as the Servant, (an excellent cure for untam'd Youth) ſo that before they eat their bread, they are commonly taught how to earn it; which makes them by that time Age ſpeaks them capable of receiving that which their Parents indulgency is ready to give them, and which partly is by their own laborious induſtry purchaſed, they manage it with ſuch a ſerious, grave
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:47901:26"/>
and watching care, as if they had been Maſters of Families, trained up in that domeſtick and governing power from their Cradles. Theſe Chriſtian Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of the Land, eſpecially thoſe of the Maſculine Sex, are generally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently confident, reſervedly ſubtle, quick in apprehending, but ſlow in reſolving; and where they ſpy profit ſailing towards them with the wings of a proſperous gale, there they become much familiar. The Women differ ſomething in this point, though not much: They are extreme baſhful at the firſt view, but after a continuance of time hath brought them acquainted, there they become diſcreetly familiar, and are much more talkative then men. All Complemental Courtſhips, dreſt up in critical Rarities, are meer ſtrangers to them, plain wit comes neareſt their Genius; ſo that he that intends to Court a <hi>Mary-Land</hi> Girle, muſt have ſomething more then the Tautologies of a long-winded ſpeech to carry on his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:47901:26"/>
deſign, or elſe he may (for ought I know) fall under the contempt of her frown, and his own windy Oration.</p>
               <p>One great part of the Inhabitants of this Province are deſiredly Zealous, great pretenders to Holineſs; and where any thing appears that carries on the Frontiſpiece of its Effigies the ſtamp of Religion, though fundamentally ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo imperfect, they are ſuddenly taken with it, and out of an eager deſire to any thing that's new, not weighing the ſure matter in the Ballance of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, are very apt to be catcht. <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keriſm</hi> is the only Opinion that bears the Bell away: The <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> have little to ſay here, as well as in other places, ſince the Ghoſt of <hi>John of Leyden</hi> haunts their Conventicles The <hi>Adamite, Ranter,</hi> and <hi>Fift-Monarchy men, Mary-Land</hi> cannot, nay will not digeſt within her liberal ſtomach ſuch corroding morſels: So that this Province is an utter Enemy to blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and zealous Imprecations, drain'd
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:47901:27"/>
from the Lymbeck of helliſh and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Spirits, as well as profuſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſs, that iſſues from the prodigality of none but crackt-brain Sots.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>'Tis ſaid the Gods lower down that Chain above.</l>
                     <l>That tyes both Prince and Subject up in Love;</l>
                     <l>And if this Fiction of the Gods be true,</l>
                     <l>Few, <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> in this can boaſt but you:</l>
                     <l>Live ever bleſt, and let thoſe Clouds that do</l>
                     <l>Eclipſe moſt States, be alwayes Lights to you;</l>
                     <l>And dwelling ſo, you may for ever be</l>
                     <l>The only Emblem of Tranquility.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:47901:27"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. The neceſſarineſs of Servitude proved, with the common uſage of Servants in <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> together with their Priviledges.</head>
               <p>AS there can be no Monarchy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Supremacy of a King and Crown, nor no King without Subjects, nor any Parents without it be by the fruitful off-ſpring of Children; neither can there be any Maſters, unleſs it be by the inferior Servitude of thoſe that dwell under them, by a commanding enjoynment: And ſince it is ordained from the original and ſuperabounding wiſdom of all things, That there ſhould be Degrees and Diverſities amongſt the Sons of men, in acknowledging of a Superiority from Inferiors to Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors; the Servant with a reverent and befitting Obedience is as liable to this duty in a meaſurable performance to him whom he ſerves, as the loyaleſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:47901:28"/>
of Subjects to his Prince. Then ſince it is a common and ordained Fate, that there muſt be Servants as well as Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and that good Servitudes are thoſe Colledges of Sobriety that checks in the giddy and wild-headed youth from his profuſe and uneven courſe of life, by a limited conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as well as it otherwiſe agrees with the moderate and diſcreet Servant: Why ſhould there be ſuch an excluſive Obſtacle in the minds and unreaſonable diſpoſitions of many people, againſt the limited time of convenient and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Servitude, when it is a thing ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, that the beſt of Kingdoms would be unhing'd from their quiet and well ſetled Government without it? Which levelling doctrine we here of <hi>England</hi> in this latter age (whoſe womb was truſs'd out with nothing but confuſed Rebellion) have too much experienced, and was daily rung into the ears of the tumultuous Vulgar by the Bell-weather Sectaries of the Times:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:47901:28"/>
But (bleſſed be God) thoſe Clouds are blown over, and the Government of the Kingdom coucht under a more ſtable form.</p>
               <p>There is no truer Emblem of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion either in Monarchy or Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Governments, then when either the Subject, or the Servant, ſtrives for the upper hand of his Prince, or Maſter, and to be equal with him, from whom he receives his preſent ſubſiſtance: Why then, if Servitude be ſo neceſſary that no place can be governed in order, nor people live without it, this may ſerve to tell thoſe which prick up their ears and bray againſt it, That they are none but Aſſes, and deſerve the Bridle of a ſtrict commanding power to reine them in: For I'me certainly confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that there are ſeveral Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands in moſt Kingdoms of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that could not at all live and ſubſiſt, unleſs they had ſerved ſome prefixed time, to learn either ſome Trade, Art, or Science, and by either
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:47901:29"/>
of them to extract their preſent live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood.</p>
               <p>Then methinks this may ſtop the mouths of thoſe that will undiſcreetly compaſſionate them that dwell under neceſſary Servitudes; for let but Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of an indifferent capacity in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, when their Childrens age by computation ſpeak them ſeventeen or eighteen years old, turn them looſe to the wide world, without a ſeven years working Apprenticeſhip, (being juſt brought up to the bare formality of a little reading and writing) and you ſhall immediately ſee how weak and ſhiftleſs they'le be towards the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining and ſupporting of themſelves; and (without either ſtealing or beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging) their bodies like a Sentinel muſt continually wait to ſee when their Souls will be frighted away by the pale Ghoſt of a ſtarving want.</p>
               <p>Then let ſuch, where Providence hath ordained to live as Servants, either in <hi>England</hi> or beyond Sea, endure the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:47901:29"/>
prefixed yoak of their limited time with patience, and then in a ſmall computa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of years, by an induſtrious endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, they may become Maſters and Miſtreſſes of Families themſelves. And let this be ſpoke to the deſerved praiſe of <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> That the four years I ſerved there were not to me ſo ſlaviſh, as a two years Servitude of a Handi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft Apprenticeſhip was here in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don; Volenti enim nil difficile</hi>: Not that I write this to ſeduce or delude any, or to draw them from their native ſoyle, but out of a love to my Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, whom in the general I wiſh well to, and that the loweſt of them may live in ſuch a capacity of Eſtate, as that the bare intereſt of their Livelihoods might not altogether depend upon perſons of the greateſt extendments.</p>
               <p>Now thoſe whoſe abilities here in <hi>England</hi> are capable of maintaining themſelves in any reaſonable and hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom manner, they had beſt ſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, leſt the roughneſs of the Ocean,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:47901:30"/>
together with the ſtaring viſages of the wilde Animals, which they may ſee after their arrival into the Country, may alter the natural diſpoſitions of their bodies, that the ſtay'd and ſolid part that kept its motion by Doctor <hi>Trigs</hi> purgationary operation, may run beyond the byas of the wheel in a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and laxative confuſion.</p>
               <p>Now contrarywiſe, they who are low, and make bare ſhifts to buoy themſelves up above the ſhabby center of beggarly and incident caſualties, I heartily could wiſh the removal of ſome of them into <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> which would make much better for them that ſtay'd behind, as well as it would advantage thoſe that went.</p>
               <p>They whoſe abilities cannot extend to purchaſe their own tranſportation over into <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> (and ſurely he that cannot command ſo ſmall a ſum for ſo great a matter, his life muſt needs be mighty low and dejected) I ſay they may for the debarment of a four
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:47901:30"/>
years ſordid liberty, go over into this Province and there live plentiouſly well. And what's a four years Servitude to advantage a man all the remainder of his dayes, making his predeceſſors hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in his ſufficient abilities, which he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to partly by the reſtrainment of ſo ſmall a time?</p>
               <p>Now thoſe that commit themſelves unto the care of the Merchant to carry them over, they need not trouble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with any inquiſitive ſearch touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Voyage; for there is ſuch an honeſt care and proviſion made for them all the time they remain aboard the Ship, and are ſailing over, that they want for nothing that is neceſſary and convenient.</p>
               <p>The Merchant commonly before they go aboard the Ship, or ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in any forwardneſs for their Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, has Conditions of Agreements drawn between him and thoſe that by a voluntary conſent become his Servants, to ſerve him, his Heirs or Aſſigns, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:47901:31"/>
as they in their primitive ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance have made their bargain, ſome two, ſome three, ſome four years; and whatever the Maſter or Servant tyes himſelf up to here in <hi>England</hi> by Condition, the Laws of the Province will force a performance of when they come there: Yet here is this Priviledge in it when they arrive, If they dwell not with the Merchant they made their firſt agreement withall, they may chooſe whom they will ſerve their prefixed time with; and after their curioſity has pitcht on one whom they think fit for their turn, and that they may live well withall, the Merchant makes an Aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Indenture over to him whom they of their free will have cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to be their Maſter, in the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as we here in <hi>England</hi> (and no otherwiſe) turn over Covenant Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants or Apprentices from one Maſter to another. Then let thoſe whoſe chaps are alwayes breathing forth thoſe filthy dregs of abuſive exclamations,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:47901:31"/>
which are Lymbeckt from their ſottiſh and prepoſterous brains, againſt this Country of <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> ſaying, That thoſe which are tranſported over thither, are ſold in open Market for Slaves, and draw in Carts like Horſes; which is ſo damnable an untruth, that if they ſhould ſearch to the very Center of Hell, and enquire for a Lye of the moſt antient and damned ſtamp, I confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believe they could not find one to parallel this: For know, That the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants here in <hi>Mary-Land</hi> of all Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, diſtant or remote Plantations, have the leaſt cauſe to complain, either for ſtrictneſs of Servitude, want of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, or need of Apparel: Five dayes and a half in the Summer weeks is the alotted time that they work in; and for two months, when the Sun predominates in the higheſt pitch of his heat, they claim an antient and cuſtomary Priviledge, to repoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves three hours in the day with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the houſe, and this is undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:47901:32"/>
granted to them that work in the Fields.</p>
               <p>In the Winter time, which laſteth three months, (<hi>viz.) December, Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary,</hi> and <hi>February,</hi> they do little or no work or imployment, ſave cutting of wood to make good fires to ſit by, unleſs their Ingenuity will prompt them to hunt the Deer, or Bear, or recreate themſelves in Fowling, to ſlaughter the Swans, Geeſe, and Turkeys, (which this Country affords in a moſt plentiful manner:) For every Servant has a Gun, Powder and Shot allowed him, to ſport him withall on all Holidayes and leaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable times, if he be capable of uſing it, or be willing to learn.</p>
               <p>Now thoſe Servants which come over into this Province, being Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, they never (during their Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude) work in the Fields, or do any other imployment ſave that which their Handicraft and Mechanick endeavors are capable of putting them upon, and are eſteem'd as well by their Maſters,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:47901:32"/>
as thoſe that imploy them, above mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. He that's a Tradeſman here in <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> (though a Servant) lives as well as moſt common Handicrafts do in <hi>London,</hi> though they may want ſomething of that Liberty which Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men have, to go and come at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; yet if it were rightly underſtood and conſidered, what moſt of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the ſeveral poor Tradeſmen are taken up about, and what a care and trouble attends that thing they call Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, which according to the common tranſlation is but Idleneſs, and (if weighed in the Ballance of a juſt Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) will be found to be much heavier and cloggy then the four years reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a <hi>Mary-Land</hi> Servitude. He that lives in the nature of a Servant in this Province, muſt ſerve but four years by the Cuſtom of the Country; and when the expiration of his time ſpeaks him a Freeman, there's a Law in the Province, that enjoyns his Maſter whom he hath ſerved to give him Fifty Acres
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:47901:33"/>
of Land, Corn to ſerve him a whole year, three Sutes of Apparel, with things neceſſary to them, and Tools to work withall; ſo that they are no ſooner free, but they are ready to ſet up for themſelves, and when once entred, they live paſſingly well.</p>
               <p>The Women that go over into this Province as Servants, have the beſt luck here as in any place of the world beſides; for they are no ſooner on ſhoar, but they are courted into a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulative Matrimony, which ſome of them (for ought I know) had they not come to ſuch a Market with their Virginity, might have kept it by them untill it had been mouldy, unleſs they had let it out by a yearly rent to ſome of the Inhabitants of <hi>Lewknors-lane,</hi> or made a Deed of Gift of it to Mother <hi>Coney,</hi> having only a poor ſtipend out of it, untill the Gallows or Hoſpital cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them away. Men have not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo good luck as Women in this kind, or natural preferment, without
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:47901:33"/>
they be good Rhetoricians, and well vers'd in the Art of perſwaſion, then (probably) they may ryvet themſelves in the time of their Servitude into the private and reſerved favour of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, if Age ſpeak their Maſter defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, touching the Servants of this Province, they live well in the time of their Service, and by their reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in that time, they are made capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of living much better when they come to be free; which in ſeveral other parts of the world I have obſerved, That after ſome Servants have brought their indented and limited time to a juſt and legal period by Servitude, they have been much more incapable of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting themſelves from ſinking into the Gulf of a ſlaviſh, poor, fettered, and intangled life, then all the faſtneſs of their prefixed time did involve them in before.</p>
               <p>Now the main and principal Reaſon of thoſe incident caſualties, that wait
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:47901:34"/>
continually upon the reſidencies of moſt poor Artificers, is (I gather) from the multiplicity or innumerableneſs of thoſe ſeveral Companies of Tradeſmen, that dwell ſo cloſely and ſtiflingly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in one and the ſame place, that like the chafing Gum in Watered-Tabby, they eat into the folds of one anothers Eſtates. And this might eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be remedied, would but ſome of them remove and diſperſe diſtantly where want and neceſſity calls for them; their dwellings (I am confident) would be much larger, and their conditions much better, as well in reference to their Eſtates, as to the ſatisfactorineſs of their minds; having a continual im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, and from that imployment a continual benefit, without either beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, ſeducing, or flat<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ering for it, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croaching that one month from one of the ſame profeſſion, that they are hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out themſelves the next. For I have obſerved on the other ſide of <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> that the whole courſe of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:47901:34"/>
moſt Mechanical endeavors, is to catch, ſnatch, and undervalue one another, to get a little work, or a Cuſtomer; which when they have attained by their low-built and ſneaking circumventings, it ſtands upon ſo flaſhy, mutable, and tranſitory a foundation, that the beſt of his hopes is commonly extinguiſht before the poor undervalued Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is warm in the enjoyment of his Cuſtomer.</p>
               <p>Then did not a cloud of low and baſe Cowardize eclipſe the Spirits of theſe men, theſe things might eaſily be diverted; but they had as live take a Bear by the tooth, as think of leaving their own Country, though they live among their own National people, and are governed by the ſame Laws they have here, yet all this wont do with them; and all the Reaſon they can render to the contrary is, There's a great Sea betwixt them and <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> and in that Sea there are Fiſhes, and not only Fiſhes but great Fiſhes, and then
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:47901:35"/>
ſhould a Ship meet with ſuch an incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable encounter as a Whale, one blow with his tayle, and then <hi>Lord have Mercy upon us:</hi> Yet meet with theſe men in their common Exchange, which is one ſtory high in the bottom of a Cellar, diſputing over a Black-pot, it would be monſtrouſly dreadful here to inſert the particulars, one ſwearing that he was the firſt that ſcaled the Walls of <hi>Dundee,</hi> when the Bullets flew about their ears as thick as Hail-ſtones uſually fall from the Sky; which if it were but rightly examined, the moſt dangerous Engagement that ever he was in, was but at one of the flaſhy battels at <hi>Finsbury,</hi> where commonly there's more Cuſtard greedily devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, then men prejudiced by the rigour of the War. Others of this Company relating their ſeveral dreadful exploits, and when they are juſt entring into the particulars, let but one ſtep in and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt their diſcourſe, by telling them of a Sea Voyage, and the violency of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:47901:35"/>
ſtorms that attends it, and that there are no back-doors to run out at, which they call, <hi>a handſom Retreat and Charge again</hi>; the apprehenſive danger of this is ſo powerful and penetrating on them, that a damp ſweat immediately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volves their Microcoſm, ſo that <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery</hi> the old Matron of the Cellar, is fain to run for a half-peny-worth of <hi>Angelica</hi> to rub their noſtrils; and though the Port-hole of their bodies has been ſtopt from a convenient Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuation ſome ſeveral months, they'le need no other Suppoſitory to open the Orifice of their Eſculent faculties then this Relation, as their Drawers or Breeches can more at large demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to the inquiſitive ſearch of the curious.</p>
               <p>Now I know that ſome will be apt to judge, that I have written this laſt part out of deriſion to ſome of my poor Mechanick Country-men: Truly I muſt needs tell thoſe to their face that think ſo of me, that they prejudice me
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:47901:36"/>
extremely, by cenſuring me as guilty of any ſuch crime: What I have written is only to diſplay the ſordidneſs of their diſpoſitions, who rather then they will remove to another Country to live plentiouſly well, and give their Neighbors more Elbow-room and ſpace to breath in, they will croud and throng upon one another, with the preſſure of a beggarly and unneceſſary weight.</p>
               <p>That which I have to ſay more in this buſineſs, is a hearty and deſirous wiſh, that the ſeveral poor Tradeſmen here in <hi>London</hi> that I know, and have borne an occular teſtimony of their want, might live ſo free from care as I did when I dwelt in the bonds of a four years Servitude in <hi>Mary-Land.</hi>
               </p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>Be juſt (Domeſtick Monarchs) unto them</l>
                     <l>That dwell as Houſhold Subjects to each Realm;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="45" facs="tcp:47901:36"/>Let not your Power make you be too ſevere,</l>
                     <l>Where there's ſmall faults reign in your ſharp Career:</l>
                     <l>So that the Worlds baſe yelping Crew</l>
                     <l>May'nt bark what I have wrote is writ untrue,</l>
                     <l>So uſe your Servants, if there come no more,</l>
                     <l>They may ſerve Eight, inſtead of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Four.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. Upon Trafique, and what Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizing Commodities this Province affords, alſo how Tobacco is planted and made fit for Commerce.</head>
               <p>TRafique, Commerce, and Trade, are thoſe great wheeles that by their circular and continued motion, turn into moſt Kingdoms of the Earth
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:47901:37"/>
the plenty of abundant Riches that they are commonly fed withall: For Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique in his right deſcription, is the very Soul of a Kingdom; and ſhould but Fate ordain a removal of it for ſome years, from the richeſt and moſt popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Monarchy that dwells in the moſt fertile clyme of the whole Univerſe, he would ſoon find by a woful experiment, the miſs and loſs of ſo reviving a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter. And I am certainly confident, that <hi>England</hi> would as ſoon feel her feebleneſs by withdrawment of ſo great an upholder; as well in reference to the internal and healthful preſervative of her Inhabitants, for want of thoſe Medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Drugs that are landed upon her Coaſt every year, as the external pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, Glory and beneficial Graces that accrue by her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paracelſus</hi> might knock down his Forge, if Trafique and Commerce ſhould once ceaſe, and grynde the hilt of his Sword into Powder, and take ſome of the Infuſion to make him ſo
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:47901:37"/>
valorous, that he might cut his own Throat in the honor of <hi>Mercury: Galen</hi> might then burn his Herbal, and like <hi>Joſeph of Arimathea,</hi> build him a Tomb in his Garden, and ſo reſt from his labours: Our Phyſical Collegians of <hi>London</hi> would have no cauſe then to thunder Fire-balls at <hi>Nich. Culpeppers</hi> Diſpenſatory: All Herbs, Roots, and Medicines would bear their original chriſtening, that the ignorant might underſtand them: <hi>Album grecum</hi> would not be <hi>Album grecum</hi> then, but a Dogs turd would be a Dogs turd in plain terms, in ſpight of their teeth.</p>
               <p>If Trade ſhould once ceaſe, the Cuſtom-houſe would ſoon miſs her hundreds and thouſands Hogs-heads of Tobacco<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that uſe to be throng in her every year, as well as the Grocers would in their Ware-houſes and Boxes, the Gentry and Commonalty in their Pipes, the Phyſician in his Drugs and Medicinal Compoſitions: The
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:47901:38"/>
(leering) Waiters for want of imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, might (like ſo many <hi>Diogenes</hi>) intomb themſelves in their empty Casks, and rouling themſelves off the Key into the <hi>Thames,</hi> there wander up and down from tide to tide in contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> unreſolved cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, until the rottenneſs of their cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular habitation give them a <hi>Quietus eſt,</hi> and fairly ſurrender them up into the cuſtody of thoſe who both for profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, diſpoſition and nature, lay as near claim to them, as if they both tumbled in one belly, and for name they jump alike, being according to the original tranſlation both <hi>Sharkes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Silks and Cambricks, and Lawns to make ſleeves, would be as ſoon miſs'd at Court, as Gold and Silver would be in the Mint and Pockets: The Low-Country Soldier would be at a cold ſtand for Outlandiſh Furrs to make him Muffs, to keep his ten ſimilitudes warm in the Winter, as well as the Furrier for want of Skins to uphold his Trade.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:47901:38"/>Should Commerce once ceaſe, there is no Country in the habitable world but would undoubtedly miſs that flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing, ſplendid and rich gallantry of Equipage, that Trafique maintained and dreſt her up in, before ſhe received that fatal Eclipſe: <hi>England, France, Germany</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> together with all the Kingdoms —</p>
               <p>But ſtop (good Muſe) leſt I ſhould, like the Parſon of <hi>Pancras,</hi> run ſo far from my Text in half an hour, that a two hours trot back again would hardly fetch it up: I had beſt while I am alive in my Doctrine, to think again of <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> leſt the buſineſs of other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries take up ſo much room in my brain, that I forget and bury her in oblivion.</p>
               <p>The three main Commodities this Country affords for Trafique, are To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco, Furrs, and Fleſh. Furrs and Skins, as Beavers, Otters, Musk-Rats, Rackoons, Wild-Cats, and Elke or Buffeloe, with divers others, which
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:47901:39"/>
were firſt made vendible by the <hi>Indians</hi> of the Country, and ſold to the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant, and by them to the Merchant, and ſo tranſported into <hi>England</hi> and other places where it becomes moſt commodious.</p>
               <p>Tobacco is the only ſolid Staple Commodity of this Province: The uſe of it was firſt found out by the <hi>Indians</hi> many Ages agoe, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd into Chriſtendom by that great Diſcoverer of <hi>America Columbus</hi>: It's generally made by all the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of this Province, and between the months of <hi>March</hi> and <hi>April</hi> they ſow the ſeed, (which is much ſmaller then Muſtard-ſeed) in ſmall beds and pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches digg'd up and made ſo by art, and about <hi>May</hi> the Plants commonly appear green in thoſe beds: In <hi>June</hi> they are tranſplanted from their beds, and ſet in little hillocks in diſtant rowes, dug up for the ſame purpoſe; ſome twice or thrice they are weeded, and ſuccour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from their illegitimate Leaves that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:47901:39"/>
would be peeping out from the body of the Stalk. They top the ſeveral Plants as they find occaſion in their predominating rankneſs: About the middle of <hi>September</hi> they cut the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco down, and carry it into houſes, (made for that purpoſe) to bring it to its purity: And after it has attained by a convenient attendance upon time, to its perfection, it is then tyed up in bundles, and packt into Hogs-heads, and then laid by for the Trade.</p>
               <p>Between <hi>November</hi> and <hi>January</hi> there arrives in this Province Shipping to the number of twenty ſail and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, all Merchant-men loaden with Commodities to Trafique and diſpoſe of, trucking with the Planter for Silks, Hollands, Serges, and Broad-clothes, with other neceſſary Goods, priz'd at ſuch and ſuch rates as ſhall be judg'd on is fair and legal, for Tobacco at ſo much the pound, and advantage on both ſides conſidered; the Planter for his work, and the Merchant for adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:47901:40"/>
himſelf and his Commodity in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſo far a Country: Thus is the Trade on both ſides drove on with a fair and honeſt <hi>Decorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Inhabitants of this Province are ſeldom or never put to the affrightment of being robb'd of their money, nor to dirty their Fingers by telling of vaſt ſums: They have more bags to carry Corn, then Coyn; and though they want, but why ſhould I call that a want which is only a neceſſary miſs? the very effects of the dirt of this Province affords as great a profit to the general Inhabitant, as the Gold of <hi>Peru</hi> doth to the ſtraight-breecht Commonalty of the <hi>Spaniard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Shops and Exchanges of <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> are the Merchants Store-houſes, where with few words and proteſtations Goods are bought and delivered; not like thoſe Shop-keepers Boys in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> that continually cry, <hi>What do ye lack Sir? What d' ye buy?</hi> yelping with ſo wide a mouth, as if ſome Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:47901:40"/>
had hired their mouths to ſtand open to catch Gnats and Vagabond Flyes in.</p>
               <p>Tobacco is the currant Coyn of <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> and will ſooner purchaſe Commodities from the Merchant, then money. I muſt confeſs the <hi>New-England</hi> men that trade into this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, had rather have fat Pork for their Goods, then Tobacco or Furrs; which I conceive is, becauſe their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies being faſt bound up with the cords of reſtringent Zeal, they are fain to make uſe of the lineaments of this <hi>Non-Canaanite</hi> creature phyſically to looſen them; for a bit of a pound upon a two-peny Rye loaf, according to the original Receipt, will bring the coſtiv'ſt red-ear'd Zealot in ſome three hours time to a fine ſtool, if methodically ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Medera</hi>-Wines, Sugars, Salt, Wickar-Chairs, and Tin Candleſticks, is the moſt of the Commodities they bring in: They arrive in <hi>Mary-Land</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:47901:41"/>
about <hi>September,</hi> being moſt of them Ketches and Barkes, and ſuch ſmall Veſſels, and thoſe diſperſing themſelves into ſeveral ſmall Creeks of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, to ſell and diſpoſe of their Commodities, where they know the Market is moſt fit for their ſmall Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> together with the ſeveral adjacent Iſlands, has much Proviſion yearly from this Province: And though theſe Sun-burnt <hi>Phaetons</hi> think to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vye <hi>Mary-Land</hi> in their Silks and Puffs, daily ſpeaking againſt her whom their neceſſities makes them beholding to, and like ſo many <hi>Don Diego</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cackt <hi>Pauls,</hi> cock their Felts and look big upon't; yet if a m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n could go down into their infernals, and ſee how it fares with them there, I believe he would hardly find any other Spirit to buoy them up, then the ill-viſaged Ghoſt of want, that continually wanders from gut to gut to feed upon the undigeſted rynes of Potatoes.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:47901:41"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>Trafique is Earth's great <hi>Atlas,</hi> that ſupports</l>
                     <l>The pay of Armies, and the height of Courts,</l>
                     <l>And makes Mechanicks live, that elſe would die</l>
                     <l>Meer ſtarving Martyrs to their penury<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>None but the Merchant of this thing can boaſt,</l>
                     <l>He, like the Bee, comes loaden from each Coaſt,</l>
                     <l>And to all Kingdoms, as within a Hive,</l>
                     <l>Stows up thoſe Riches that doth make them thrive:</l>
                     <l>Be thrifty, <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> keep what thou haſt in ſtore,</l>
                     <l>And each years Trafique to thy ſelf get more.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:47901:42"/>
            <head>A Relation of the Cuſtoms, Manners, Abſurdities, and Religion of the <hi>Suſqueha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nock Indians</hi> in and near Mary-Land.</head>
            <p>AS the diverſities of Languages (ſince <hi>Babels</hi> confuſion) has made the diſtinction between people and people, in this Chriſtendom-part of the world; ſo are they diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed Nation from Nation, by the diverſities and confuſion of their Speech and Languages here in <hi>America</hi>: And as every Nation differs in their Laws, Manners and Cuſtoms, in <hi>Europe, Aſia</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:47901:42"/>
and <hi>Africa,</hi> ſo do they the very ſame here; That it would be a moſt intricate and laborious trouble, to run (with a deſcription) through the ſeveral Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Indians</hi> here in <hi>America,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the innumerableneſs and diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of them that dwell on this vaſt and unmeaſured Continent: But rather then I'le be altogether ſilent, I ſhall do like the Painter in the Comedy, who being to limne out the Pourtraiture of the Furies, as they ſeverally appeared, ſet himſelf behind a Pillar, and between fright and amazement, drew them by gueſs. Thoſe <hi>Indians</hi> that I have convers'd withall here in this Province of <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> and have had any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular experimental view of either of their Cuſtoms, Manners, Religions, and Abſurdities, are called by the name of <hi>Suſquehanocks,</hi> being a people lookt upon by the Chriſtian Inhabitants, as the moſt Noble and Heroick Nation of <hi>Indians</hi> that dwell upon the confines of <hi>America</hi>; alſo are ſo allowed and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:47901:43"/>
lookt upon by the reſt of the <hi>Indians,</hi> by a ſubmiſſive and tributary acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement; being a people caſt into the mould of a moſt large and War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like deportment, the men being for the moſt part ſeven foot high in latitude, and in magnitude and bulk ſuitable to ſo high a pitch; their voyce large and hollow, as aſcending out of a Cave; their gate and behavior ſtrait, ſtately and majeſtick, treading on the Earth with as much pride, contempt, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain to ſo ſordid a Center, as can be imagined from a creature derived from the ſame mould and Earth.</p>
            <p>Their bodies are cloth'd with no other Armour to defend them from the nipping froſts of a benumbing Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or the penetrating and ſcorching influence of the Sun in a hot Summer, then what Nature gave them when they parted with the dark receptacle of their Mothers womb. They go Men, Women and Children, all naked, only where ſhame leads them by a natural
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:47901:43"/>
inſtinct to be reſervedly modeſt, there they become cover'd. The formality of <hi>Jezabels</hi> artificial Glory is much courted and followed by theſe <hi>Indians,</hi> only in matter of colours (I conceive) they differ. The <hi>Indians</hi> paint upon their faces one ſtroke of red, another of green, another of white, and another of black, ſo that when they have accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed the Equipage of their Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in this trim, they are the only Hieroglyphicks and Repreſentatives of the Furies. Their skins are naturally white, but altered from their originals by the ſeveral dyings of Roots and Barks, that they prepare and make uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to metamorphize their hydes into a dark Cinamon brown. The hair of their head is black, long and harſh, but where Nature hath appointed the ſitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it any where elſe, they divert it (by an antient cuſtom) from its growth, by pulling it up hair by hair by the root in its primitive appearance. Several of them wear divers impreſſions
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:47901:44"/>
on their breaſts and armes, as the picture of the Devil, Bears, Tigers, and Panthers, which are imprinted on their ſeveral lineaments with much diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty and pain, with an irrevocable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of its abiding there: And this they count a badge of Heroick Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and the only Ornament due to their <hi>Heroes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Suſquehanock Indians</hi> are for the moſt part great Warriours, and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſleep one Summer in the quiet armes of a peaceable Reſt, but keep (by their preſent Power, as well as by their former Conqueſt) the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Nations of <hi>Indians</hi> round about them, in a forceable obedience and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection.</p>
            <p>Their Government is wrapt up in ſo various and intricate a Laborynth, that the ſpeculativ'ſt Artiſt in the whole World, with his artificial and natural Opticks, cannot ſee into the rule or ſway of theſe <hi>Indians,</hi> to diſtinguiſh what name of Government to call them by;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:47901:44"/>
though <hi>Purchas</hi> in his <hi>Peregrination</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Eſſex,</hi> (which he calls the whole World) will undertake (forſooth) to make a Monarchy of them, but if he had ſaid Anarchy, his word would have paſs'd with a better belief. All that ever I could obſerve in them as to this matter is, that he that is moſt cruelly Valorous, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the moſt Noble: Here is very ſeldom any creeping from a Country Farm, into a Courtly Gallantry, by a ſum of money; nor feeing the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralds to put Daggers and Piſtols in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Armes, to make the ignorant believe that they are lineally deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the houſe of the Wars and Conqueſts; he that fights beſt carries it here.</p>
            <p>When they determine to go upon ſome Deſign that will and doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a Conſideration, ſome ſix of them get into a corner, and fit in Juncto; and if thought fit, their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is made popular, and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:47901:45"/>
put into action; if not, they make a full ſtop to it, and are ſilently reſerv'd.</p>
            <p>The Warlike Equipage they put themſelves in when they prepare for <hi>Belona</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s March, is with their faces, armes, and breaſts confuſedly painted, their hair greazed with Bears oyl, and ſtuck thick with Swans Feathers, with a wreath or Diadem of black and white Beads upon their heads, a ſmall Hatchet, inſtead of a Cymetre, ſtuck in their girts behind them, and either with Guns, or Bows and Arrows. In this poſture and dreſs they march out from their Fort, or dwelling, to the number of Forty in a Troop, ſinging (or rather howling out) the Decades or Warlike exploits of their Anceſtors, ranging the wide Woods untill their fury has met with an Enemy worthy of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge. What Priſoners fall into their hands by the deſtiny of War, they treat them very civilly while they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main with them abroad, but when they
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:47901:45"/>
once return homewards, they then begin to dreſs them in the habit for death, putting on their heads and armes wreaths of Beads, greazing their hair with fat, ſome going before, and the reſt behind, at equal diſtance from their Priſoners, bellowing in a ſtrange and confuſed manner, which is a true preſage and fore-runner of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to their then conquered Enemy.</p>
            <p>In this manner of march they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue till they have brought them to their Barken City, where they deliver them up to thoſe that in cruelty will execute them, without either the legal Judgement of a Council of War, or the benefit of their Clergy at the Common Law. The common and uſual deaths they put their Priſoners to, is to bind them to ſtakes, making a fire ſome diſtance from them; then one or other of them, whoſe Genius delights in the art of Paganiſh diſſecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with a ſharp knife or flint cuts
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:47901:46"/>
the Cutis or outermoſt skin of the brow ſo deep, untill their nails, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Talons, can faſten themſelves firm and ſecure in, then (with a moſt rigid jerk) diſrobeth the head of skin and hair at one pull, leaving the skull almoſt as bare as thoſe Monumental Skelitons at Chyrurgions-Hall; but for fear they ſhould get cold by leaving ſo warm and cuſtomary a Cap off, they immediately apply to the skull a Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaſm of hot Embers to keep their Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricranium warm. While they are thus acting this cruelty on their heads, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral others are preparing pieces of Iron, and barrels of old Guns, which they make red hot, to ſear each part and lineament of their bodies, which they perform and act in a moſt cruel and barbarous manner: And while they are thus in the midſt of their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and execrable uſage, ſome tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their skin and hair of their head off by violence, others ſearing their bodies with hot irons, ſome are cutting their
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:47901:46"/>
fleſh off, and eating it before their eyes raw while they are alive; yet all this and much more never makes them lower the Top-gallant ſail of their Heroick courage, to beg with a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive Repentance any indulgent fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour from their perſecuting Enemies; but with an undaunted contempt to their cruelty, eye it with ſo ſlight and mean a reſpect, as if it were below them to value what they did, they couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly (while breath doth libertize them) ſing the ſummary of their Warlike Atchievements.</p>
            <p>Now after this cruelty has brought their tormented lives to a period, they immediately fall to butchering of them into parts, diſtributing the ſeveral pieces amongſt the Sons of War, to in-tomb the ruines of their deceaſed Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt in no other Sepulchre then their unſanctified maws; which they with more appetite and deſire do eat and digeſt, then if the beſt of foods ſhould court their ſtomachs to participate of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:47901:47"/>
the moſt reſtorative Banquet. Yet though they now and then feed upon the Carkeſſes of their Enemies, this is not a common dyet, but only a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular diſh for the better ſort; for there is not a Beaſt that runs in the Woods of <hi>America,</hi> but if they can by any means come at him, without any ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Conſcience they'le fall too (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſaying Grace) with a devouring greedineſs.</p>
            <p>As for their Religion, together with their Rites and Ceremonies, they are ſo abſurd and ridiculous, that its al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a ſin to name them They own no other Deity then the Devil, (ſolid or profound) but with a kind of a wilde imaginary conjecture, they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe from their groundleſs conceits, that the World had a Maker, but where he is that made it, or whether he be living to this day, they know not. The Devil, as I ſaid before, is all the God they own or worſhip; and that more out of a ſlaviſh fear, then
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:47901:47"/>
any real Reverence to his Infernal or Diabolical greatneſs, he forcing them to their Obedience by his rough and rigid dealing with them, often appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing viſibly among them to their ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, baſtinadoing them (with cruel menaces) even unto death, and burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Fields of Corn and hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that the relation thereof makes them tremble themſelves when they tell it.</p>
            <p>Once in four years they Sacrifice a Childe to him, in an acknowledgement of their firm obedience to all his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villiſh powers, and Helliſh commands. The Prieſts to whom they apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in matters of importance and greateſt diſtreſs, are like thoſe that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended upon the Oracle at <hi>Delphos,</hi> who by their Magick-ſpells could com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand a <hi>pro</hi> or <hi>con</hi> from the Devil when they pleas'd. Theſe <hi>Indians</hi> oft-times raiſe great Tempeſts when they have any weighty matter or deſign in hand, and by bluſtering ſtormes inquire of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:47901:48"/>
their Infernal God (the Devil) <hi>How matters ſhall go with them either in publick or private.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When any among them depart this life, they give him no other intomb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then to ſet him upright upon his breech in a hole dug in the Earth ſome five foot long, and three foot deep, covered over with the Bark of Trees Arch-wiſe, with his face Du-Weſt, only leaving a hole half a foot ſquare open. They dreſs him in the ſame Equipage and Gallantry that he uſed to be trim'd in when he was alive, and ſo bury him (if a Soldier) with his Bows, Arrows, and Target, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all the reſt of his implements and weapons of War, with a Kettle of Broth and Corn ſtanding before him, leſt he ſhould meet with bad quarters in his way. His Kinred and Relations follow him to the Grave, ſheath'd in Bears skins for cloſe mourning, with the tayl droyling on the ground, in imitation of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Solemners,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:47901:48"/>
that think there's nothing like a tayl a Degree in length, to follow the dead Corpſe to the Grave with. Here if that ſnuffling Prolocutor, that waits upon the dead Monuments of the Tombs at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> with his white Rod were there, he might walk from Tomb to Tomb with his, <hi>Here lies the Duke of</hi> Ferrara <hi>and his Dutcheſs,</hi> and never find any decaying vacation, unleſs it were in the moldering Conſumption of his own Lungs. They bury all within the wall or Palliſado'd impalement of their City, or <hi>Connadago</hi> as they call it. Their houſes are low and long, built with the Bark of Trees Arch-wiſe, ſtanding thick and confuſedly together. They are ſituated a hundred and odd miles diſtant from the Chriſtian Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> at the head of a River that runs into the Bay of <hi>Chaeſapike,</hi> called by their own name, <hi>The Suſquehanock River,</hi> where they remain and inhabit moſt part of the Summer time, and ſeldom remove far
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:47901:49"/>
from it, unleſs it be to ſubdue any For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Rebellion.</p>
            <p>About <hi>November</hi> the beſt Hunters draw off to ſeveral remote places of the Woods, where they know the Deer, Bear, and Elke uſeth; there they build them ſeveral Cottages, which they call their Winter-quarter, where they remain for the ſpace of three months, untill they have killed up a ſufficiency of Proviſions to ſupply their Families with in the Summer.</p>
            <p>The Women are the Butchers, Cooks, and Tillers of the ground, the Men think it below the honour of a Maſculine, to ſtoop to any thing but that which their Gun, or Bow and Arrows can command. The Men kill the ſeveral Beaſts which they meet withall in the Woods, and the Women are the Pack horſes to fetch it in upon their backs, fleying and dreſſing the hydes, (as well as the fleſh for provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) to make them fit for Trading, and which are brought down to the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:47901:49"/>
               <hi>Engliſh</hi> at ſeveral ſeaſons in the year, to truck and diſpoſe of them for courſe Blankets, Guns, Powder, and Lead, Beads, ſmall Looking-glaſſes, Knives, and Razors.</p>
            <p>I never obſerved all the while I was amongſt theſe naked <hi>Indians,</hi> that ever the Women wore the Breeches, or dared either in look or action predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate over the Men. They are very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant to their Wives; and let this be ſpoken to their Heatheniſh praiſe, that did they not alter their bodies by their dyings, paintings, and cutting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, marring thoſe Excellencies that Nature beſtowed upon them in their original conceptions and birth, there would be as amiable beauties amongſt them, as any <hi>Alexandria</hi> could afford, when <hi>Mark Anthony</hi> and <hi>Cleopatra</hi> dwelt there together. Their Marriages are ſhort and authentique; for after 'tis reſolv'd upon by both parties, the Woman ſends her intended Husband a Kettle of boyl'd Veniſon, or Bear; and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:47901:50"/>
he returns in lieu thereof Beaver or Otters Skins, and ſo their Nuptial Rites are concluded without other Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony.</p>
            <p>Before I bring my Heatheniſh Story to a period, I have one thing worthy your obſervation: For as our Grammer Rules have it, <hi>Non decet quenquam me ire currentem aut mandantem</hi>: It doth not become any man to piſs run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or eating. Theſe Pagan men na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally obſerve the ſame Rule; for they are ſo far from running, that like a Hare, they ſquat to the ground as low as they can, while the Women ſtand bolt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right with their armes a Kimbo, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the ſame action, in ſo confident and obſcene a poſture, as if they had taken their Degrees of Entrance at <hi>Venice,</hi> and commenced Bawds of Art at <hi>Legorne.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:47901:50"/>
            <head>A Collection of ſome Letters that were written by the ſame Author, moſt of them in the time of his Servitude.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To my much Honored Friend Mr. T.B.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have lived with ſorrow to ſee the Anointed of the Lord tore from his Throne by the hands of Paricides, and in contempt haled, in the view of God, Angels and Men, upon a publick
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:47901:51"/>
Theatre, and there murthered. I have ſeen the ſacred Temple of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in ſcorn by Schiſmaticks made the Receptacle of Theeves and Robbers; and thoſe Religious Prayers, that in devotion Evening and Morning were offered up as a Sacrifice to our God, rent by Sacrilegious hands, and made no other uſe of, then ſold to Brothel-houſes to light Tobacco with.</p>
               <p>Who then can ſtay, or will, to ſee things of ſo great weight ſteer'd by ſuch barbarous Hounds as theſe: Firſt, were there an <hi>Egypt</hi> to go down to, I would involve my Liberty to them, upon condition ne're more to ſee my Country. What? live in ſilence un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſway of ſuch baſe actions, is to give conſent; and though the lowneſs of my preſent Eſtate and Condition, with the hazard I put my future dayes upon, might plead a juſt excuſe for me to ſtay at home; but Heavens forbid: I'le rather ſerve in Chains, and draw
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:47901:51"/>
the Plough with Animals, till death ſhall ſtop and ſay, <hi>It is enough.</hi> Sir, if you ſtay behind, I wiſh you well: I am bound for <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> this day I have made ſome entrance into my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Voyage, and when I have done more, you ſhall know of it. I have here incloſed what you of me deſired, but truly trouble, diſcontent and buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, have ſo amazed my ſenſes, that what to write, or where to write, I conceive my ſelf almoſt as uncapable as he that never did write. What you'le find will be <hi>Ex tempore,</hi> without the uſe of premeditation; and though there may want ſomething of a flouriſhing ſtile to dreſs them forth, yet I'm cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain there wants nothing of truth, will, and deſire.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Heavens bright Lamp, ſhine forth ſome of thy Light,</l>
                  <l>But juſt ſo long to paint this diſmal Night;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:47901:52"/>Then draw thy beams, and hide thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious face,</l>
                  <l>From the dark ſable Actions of this place;</l>
                  <l>Leaving theſe luſtful <hi>Sodomites</hi> grop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill,</l>
                  <l>To ſatisfie each dark unſatiate will,</l>
                  <l>Untill at length the crimes that they commit,</l>
                  <l>May ſink them down to Hells Infernal pit.</l>
                  <l>Baſe and degenerate Earth, how doſt thou lye,</l>
                  <l>That all that paſs hiſs, at thy Treachery?</l>
                  <l>Thou which couldſt boaſt once of thy King and Crown,</l>
                  <l>By baſe Mechanicks now art tumbled down:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Brewers</hi> and <hi>Coblers,</hi> that have ſcarce an Eye,</l>
                  <l>Walk hand in hand in thy Supremacy;</l>
                  <l>And all thoſe Courts where Majeſty did Throne,</l>
                  <l>Are now the Seats for <hi>Oliver</hi> and <hi>Joan:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:47901:52"/>Perſons of Honour, which did before inherit</l>
                  <l>Their glorious Titles from deſerved merit,</l>
                  <l>Are all grown ſilent, and with wonder gaze,</l>
                  <l>To view ſuch Slaves dreſt in their Courtly rayes;</l>
                  <l>To ſee a <hi>Drayman</hi> that knows nought but Yeaſt,</l>
                  <l>Set in a Throne like <hi>Babylons</hi> red Beaſt,</l>
                  <l>While heaps of Paraſites do idolize</l>
                  <l>This red-nos'd <hi>Bell,</hi> with fawning Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice.</l>
                  <l>What can we ſay? our King they've murthered,</l>
                  <l>And thoſe well born, are baſely buried:</l>
                  <l>Nobles are ſlain, and Royaliſts in each ſtreet</l>
                  <l>Are ſcorn'd, and kick'd by moſt men that they meet:</l>
                  <l>Religion's baniſht, and Hereſie ſurvives,</l>
                  <l>And none but Conventicks in this Age thrives.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:47901:53"/>Oh could thoſe <hi>Romans</hi> from their Aſhes riſe,</l>
                  <l>That liv'd in <hi>Nero</hi>'s time: Oh how their cries</l>
                  <l>Would our perfidious Iſland ſhake, nay rend,</l>
                  <l>With clamorous ſcreaks unto the Heaven ſend:</l>
                  <l>Oh how they'd bluſh to ſee our Crimſon crimes,</l>
                  <l>And know the Subjects Authors of theſe times:</l>
                  <l>When as the Peaſant he ſhall take his King,</l>
                  <l>And without cauſe ſhall fall a murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him;</l>
                  <l>And when that's done, with Pride aſſume the Chair,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Nimrod</hi>-like, himſelf to Heaven rear;</l>
                  <l>Command the People, make the Land obey</l>
                  <l>His baſer will, and ſwear to what he'l ſay.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:47901:53"/>Sure, ſure our God has not theſe evils ſent</l>
                  <l>To pleaſe himſelf, but for mans puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</l>
                  <l>And when he ſhall from our dark ſable Skies</l>
                  <l>Withdraw theſe Clouds, and let our Sun ariſe,</l>
                  <l>Our dayes will ſurely then in Glory ſhine,</l>
                  <l>Both in our Temporal, and our State di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine:</l>
                  <l>May this come quickly, though I may never ſee</l>
                  <l>This glorious day, yet I would ſympathie,</l>
                  <l>And feel a joy run through each vain of blood,</l>
                  <l>Though Vaſſalled on t'other ſide the Floud.</l>
                  <l>Heavens protect his Sacred Majeſty,</l>
                  <l>From ſecret Plots, &amp; treacherous Villany.</l>
                  <l>And that thoſe Slaves that now predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate,</l>
                  <l>Hang'd and deſtroy'd may be their beſt of Fate;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:47901:54"/>And though Great <hi>Charles</hi> be diſtant from his own,</l>
                  <l>Heaven I hope will ſeat him in his Throne.</l>
               </q>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Vale.</salute> 
                  <signed>Yours in what I may, <hi>G. A.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>From the Chimney-corner upon a low Cricket, where I writ this in the noiſe of ſome ſix Women,
<date>
                        <hi>Aug.</hi> 19. <hi>Anno</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To my Honored Father, at his Houſe.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>BEfore I dare bid Adien to the old World, or ſhake hands with my native Soyl for ever, I have a Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence inwards tells me, that I muſt offer
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:47901:54"/>
up the Remains of that Obedience of mine, that lyes cloſe centered within the cave of my Soul, at the Altar of your paternal Love: And though this Sacrifice of mine may ſhew ſomething low and thread-bare, (at this time) yet know, That in the Zenith of all actions, Obedience is that great wheel that moves the leſſer in their circular motion.</p>
               <p>I am now entring for ſome time to dwell under the Government of <hi>Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,</hi> a Monarchy that I was never ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nured to live under, nor to converſe with in his dreadful Aſpect, neither do I know how I ſhall bear with his rough demands; but that God that has car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried me through thoſe many guſts a ſhoar, which I have met withall in the ſeveral voyages of my life, I hope will Pilot me ſafely to my deſired Port, through the worſt of Stormes I ſhall meet withall at Sea.</p>
               <p>We have ſtrange, and yet good
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:47901:55"/>
news aboard, that he whoſe vaſt mind could not be contented with ſpacious Territories to ſtretch his inſatiate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires on, is (by an Almighty power) baniſhed from his uſurped Throne to dwell among the dead. I no ſooner heard of it, but my melancholly Muſe forced me upon this enſuing Diſtich.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Poor vaunting Earth, gloſs'd with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain Pride,</l>
                  <l>That liv'd in Pomp, yet worſe then others dy'd:</l>
                  <l>Who ſhall blow forth a Trumpet to thy praiſe?</l>
                  <l>Or call thy ſable Actions ſhining Rayes?</l>
                  <l>Such Lights as thoſe blaze forth the vertues dead,</l>
                  <l>And make them live, though they are buried.</l>
                  <l>Thou'rt gone, and to thy memory let be ſaid,</l>
                  <l>There lies that <hi>Oliver</hi> which of old be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:47901:55"/>His King and Maſter, and after did aſſume,</l>
                  <l>With ſwelling Pride, to govern in his room.</l>
                  <l>Here I'le reſt ſatisfi'd, Scriptures ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pound to me,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tophet</hi> was made for ſuch Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The death of this great Rebel (I hope) will prove an <hi>Omen</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage deſtruction on the reſt. The World's in a heap of troubles and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and while they are in the midſt of their changes and amazes, the beſt way to give them the bag, is to go out of the World and leave them. I am now bound for <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> and I am told that's a New World, but if it prove no better then this, I ſhall not get much by my change; but before He revoke my Reſolution, I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to put it to adventure, for I think it can hardly be worſe then this is:
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:47901:56"/>
Thus committing you into the hands of that God that made you, I reſt</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Obedient Son, G. A.</signed>
                  <dateline>From aboard a Ship at <hi>Graveſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end,</hi>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Sept.</hi> 7th. <hi>Anno</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To my Brother.</head>
               <p>I Leave you very near in the ſame condition as I am in my ſelf, only here lies the difference, you were bound at Joyners Hall in <hi>London</hi> Apprentice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and I conditionally at Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors Hall, that now rides at an Anchor at <hi>Graveſend</hi>; I hope you will allow me to live in the largeſt Mayordom, by <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſon I am the eldeſt: None but the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:47901:56"/>
main Continent of <hi>America</hi> will ſerve me for a Corporation to inhabit in now, though I am affraid for all that, that the reins of my Liberty will be ſomething ſhorter then yours will be in <hi>London</hi>: But as to that, what Deſtiny has ordered I am reſolved with an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venterous Reſolution to ſubſcribe to, and with a contented imbracement enjoy it. I would fain have ſeen you once more in this Old World, before I go into the New. I know you have a chain about your Leg, as well as I have a clog about my Neck: If you can't come, ſend a line or two, if not, wiſh me well at leaſt: I have one thing to charge home upon you, and I hope you will take my counſel, That you have alwayes an obedient Reſpect and Reverence to your aged Parents, that while they live they may have comfort of you, and when that God ſhall ſound a retreat to their lives, that then they may with their
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:47901:57"/>
gray hairs in joy go down to their Graves.</p>
               <p>Thus concluding, wiſhing you a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Servitude, a proſperous Life, and the aſſurance of a happy departure in the immutable love of him that made you, <hi>Vale.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Brother, G. A.</signed>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Graveſend,</hi>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Sept.</hi> 7. <hi>Anno</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To my much Honored Friend <hi>Mr. T. B.</hi> at his Houſe.</head>
               <p>I Am got a ſhoar with much ado, and it is very well it is as it is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for if I had ſtayed a little longer, I had certainly been a Creature of the Water, for I had hardly fleſh enough to carry me
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:47901:57"/>
to Land, not that I wanted for any thing that the Ship could afford me in reaſon: But oh the great bowls of Peaſe-porridge that appeared in ſight every day about the hour twelve, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulfed the ſenſes of my Appetite ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with the reſtringent quality of the Sal<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Beef upon the internal Inhabitants of my belly, that a <hi>Galeniſt</hi> for ſome dayes after my arrival, with his Bag-pipes of Phyſical operations, could hardly make my Puddings dance in any methodical order.</p>
               <p>But to ſet by theſe things that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened unto me at Sea, I am now upon Land, and there I'le keep my ſelf if I can, and for four years I am pretty ſure of my reſtraint; and had I known my yoak would have been ſo eaſie, (as I conceive it will) I would have been here long before now, rather then to have dwelt under the preſſure of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious and Trayterous Government ſo long as I did. I dwell now by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:47901:58"/>
in the Province of <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> (under the quiet Government of the Lord <hi>Baltemore</hi>) which Country a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds in a moſt glorious proſperity and plenty of all things. And though the Infancy of her ſituation might plead an excuſe to thoſe ſeveral imperfections (if ſhe were guilty of any of them) which by ſcandalous and imaginary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures are falſly laid to her charge, and which ſhe values with ſo little no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice or perceivance of diſcontent, that ſhe hardly alters her viſage with a frown, to let them know ſhe is angry with ſuch a Raſcality of people, that loves nothing better then their own ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh and abuſive acclamations of baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: To be ſhort, the Country (ſo far forth as I have ſeen into it) is incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable.</p>
               <p>Here is a ſort of naked Inhabitants, or wilde people, that have for many ages I believe lived here in the Woods of <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> as well as in other parts
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:47901:58"/>
of the Continent, before e're it was by the Chriſtian Diſcoverers found out; being a people ſtrange to behold, as well in their looks, which by confuſed paintings makes them ſeem dreadful, as in their ſterne and heroick gate and deportments; the Men are mighty tall and big limbed, the Women not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſo large; they are moſt of them very well featured, did not their wilde and ridiculous dreſſes alter their origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal excellencies: The Men are great Warriours and Hunters, the Women ingenious and laborious Houſewives.</p>
               <p>As to matter of their Worſhip, they own no other Deity then the Devil, and him more out of a ſlaviſh fear, then any real devotion, or willing acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to his Hell<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh power. They live in little ſmall Bark Cottages, in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote parts of the Woods, killing and ſlaying the ſeveral Animals that they meet withall to make proviſion of, dreſſing their ſeveral Hydes and Skins
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:47901:59"/>
to Trafique withall, when a conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of Trade preſents. I would go on further, but like Doctor <hi>Caſe,</hi> when he had not a word more to ſpeak for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>I am affraid my beloved I have kept you too long.</hi> Now he that made you ſave you, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours to command, G. A.</signed>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Mary-Land,</hi>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Febr.</hi> 6. <hi>Anno</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>And not to forget <hi>Tom. Forge</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, tell him that my Love's the ſame towards him ſtill, and as firm as it was about the overgrown Tryal, when Judgements upon Judgements, had not I ſtept in, would have purſued him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the day of Judgement, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:47901:59"/>
               <head>To my Father at his Houſe,</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>AFter my Obedience (at ſo great and vaſt a diſtance) has humbly ſaluted you and my good Mother, with the cordialeſt of my prayers, wiſhes, and deſires to wait upon you, with the very beſt of their effectual devotion, wiſhing from the very Center of my Soul your flouriſhing and well-being here upon Earth, and your glorious and everlaſting happineſs in the World to come.</p>
               <p>Theſe lines (my dear Parents) come from that Son which by an irregular Fate was removed from his Native home, and after a five months dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous paſſage, was landed on the remote Continent of <hi>America,</hi> in the Province of <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> where now by provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:47901:60"/>
I reſide. To give you the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of the ſeveral accidents that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in our Voyage by Sea, it would ſwell a Journal of ſome ſheets, and therefore too large and tedious for a Letter: I think it therefore neceſſary to bind up the relation in Octavo, and give it you in ſhort.</p>
               <p>We had a blowing and dangerous paſſage of it, and for ſome dayes after I arrived, I was an abſolute <hi>Copernicus,</hi> it being one main point of my moral Creed, to believe the World had a pair of long legs, and walked with the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of the Creation upon her back. For to tell you the very truth of it, for ſome dayes upon Land, after ſo long and toſſing a paſſage, I was ſo giddy that I could hardly tread an even ſtep; ſo that all things both above and below (that was in view) appeared to me like the <hi>Kentiſh Britains</hi> to <hi>William the Conqueror,</hi> in a moving poſture.</p>
               <p>Thoſe few number of weeks ſince
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:47901:60"/>
my arrival, has given me but little ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience to write any thing large of the Country; only thus much I can ſay, and that not from any imaginary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures, but from an occular obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That this Country of <hi>Mary-Land</hi> abounds in a flouriſhing variety of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful Woods, pleaſant Groves, love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Springs, together with ſpacious Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigable Rivers and Creeks, it being a moſt healthful and pleaſant ſituation, ſo far as my knowledge has yet had any view in it.</p>
               <p>Herds of Deer are as numerous in this Province of <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> as Cuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kolds can be in <hi>London,</hi> only their horns are not ſo well dreſt and tipt with ſilver as theirs are</p>
               <p>Here if the Devil had ſuch a Vagary in his head as he had once among the <hi>Gadareans,</hi> he might drown a thouſand head of Hogs and they'd ne're be miſs'd, for the very Woods of this Province ſwarms with them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:47901:61"/>The Chriſtian Inhabitant of this Province, as to the general, lives wonderful well and contented: The Government of this Province is by the loyalneſs of the people, and loving de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanor of the Proprietor and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the ſame, kept in a continued peace and unity.</p>
               <p>The Servants of this Province, which are ſtigmatiz'd for Slaves by the clappermouth jaws of the vulgar in <hi>England,</hi> live more like Freemen then the moſt Mechanick Apprenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in <hi>London,</hi> wanting for nothing that is convenient and neceſſary, and according to their ſeveral capacities, are extraordinary well uſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected. So leaving things here as I found them, and leſt I ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Sacriledge upon your more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious meditations, with the Tauto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of a long-winded Letter, I'le ſubſcribe with a heavenly Ejaculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the God of Mercy to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:47901:61"/>
you now and for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Obedient Son, G. A.</signed>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Mary-Land,</hi>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Jan.</hi> 17. <hi>Anno</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To my much Honored Friend Mr. M. F.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOu writ to me when I was at <hi>Graveſend,</hi> (but I had no conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency to ſend you an anſwer till now) enjoyning me, if poſſible, to give you a juſt Information by my diligent obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, what thing were beſt and moſt profitable to ſend into this Country for a commodious Trafique.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir,</hi> The encloſed will demonſtrate unto you both particularly and at large,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:47901:62"/>
to the full ſatisfaction of your deſire, it being in Invoyee drawn as exact to the buſineſs you imployed me up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as my weak capacity could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir,</hi> If you ſend any Adventure to this Province, let me beg to give you this advice in it; That the Factor whom you imploy be a man of a Brain, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Planter will go near to make a Skimming-diſh of his Skull: I know your Genius can interpret my meaning. The people of this place (whether the ſaltneſs of the Ocean gave them any al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration when they went over firſt, or their continual dwelling under the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Clyme where they now inhabit, I know not) are a more acute people in general, in matters of Trade and Commerce, then in any other place of the World; and by their crafty and ſure bargaining, do often over-reach the raw and unexperienced Merchant. To be ſhort, he that undertakes Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:47901:62"/>
imployment for <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> muſt have more of Knave in him then Fool; he muſt not be a whindling piece of Formality, that will loſe his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployers Goods for Conſcience ſake; nor a flaſhy piece of Prodigality, that will give his Merchants fine Hollands, Laces and Silks, to purchaſe the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence of a Female: But he muſt be a man of a ſolid confidence, carrying al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in his looks the Effigies of an Execution upon Command, if he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes a baffle, or denyal of payment, where a debt for his Imployer is le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally due.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir,</hi> I had like almoſt to forget to tell you in what part of the World I am: I dwell by providence Servant to Mr. <hi>Thomas Stocket,</hi> in the County of <hi>Baltemore,</hi> within the Province of <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> under the Government of the Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> being a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try abounding with the variety and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of all that is or may be rare.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:47901:63"/>
But leſt I ſhould Tantalize you with a relation of that which is very unlikely of your enjoying, by reaſon of that ſtrong Antipathy you have ever had <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gainſt Travel, as to your own particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar: I'le only tell you, that <hi>Mary-Land</hi> is ſeated within the large extending armes of <hi>America,</hi> between the Degrees of 36 and 38, being in Longitude from <hi>England</hi> eleven hundred and odd Leagues.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Vale.</salute> 
                  <signed>G. A.</signed>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Mary-Land,</hi>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Jan.</hi> 17. <hi>Anno</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To my Honored Friend <hi>Mr. T. B.</hi> at his Houſe.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOurs I received, wherein I find my ſelf much obliged to you for
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:47901:63"/>
your good opinion of me, I return you millions of thanks.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir,</hi> You wiſh me well, and I pray God as well that thoſe wiſhes may light upon me, and then I queſtion not but all will do well. Thoſe Pictures you ſent ſewed up in a Paſtboard, with a Letter tacked on the outſide, you make no mention at all what ſhould be done with them: If they are Saints, unleſs I knew their names, I could make no uſe of them. Pray in your next let me know what they are, for my fingers itch to be doing with them one way or another. Our Government here hath had a ſmall fit of a Rebellious Quoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian, but five Grains of the powder of Subvertment has qualified it. Pray be larger in your next how things ſtand in <hi>England:</hi> I underſtand His Majeſty is return'd with Honour, and ſeated in the hereditary Throne of his Father; God bleſs him from Traytors, and the Church from Sacrilegious Schiſms,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:47901:64"/>
and you as a loyal Subject to the one, and a true Member to the other; while you ſo continue, the God of order, peace and tranquility, bleſs and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve you, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Vale.</salute> 
                  <signed>Your real Friend, G. A.</signed>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Mary-Land,</hi>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Febr.</hi> 20. <hi>Anno</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To my Honored Father, at his Houſe.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>WIth a twofold unmeaſurable joy I received your Letter: Firſt, in the conſideration of Gods great Mercy to you in particular, (though weak and aged) yet to give you dayes
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:47901:64"/>
among the living. Next, that his now moſt Excellent Majeſty <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, is by the omnipotent Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, ſeated in the Throne of his Father. I hope that God that has placed him there, will give him a heart to praiſe and magnifie his name for ever, and a hand of juſt Revenge, to puniſh the murthering and rebellious Outrages of thoſe Sons of ſhame and Apoſtacy, that Uſurped the Throne of his Sacred Honour. Near about the time I received your Letter, (or a little before) here ſprang up in this Province of <hi>Mary-Land</hi> a kind of pigmie Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion: A company of weak-witted men, which thought to have traced the ſteps of <hi>Oliver</hi> in Rebellion. They began to be mighty ſtiff and hidebound in their proceedings, clothing themſelves with the flaſhy pretences of future and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary honour, and (had they not been ſuddenly quell'd) they might have done ſo much miſchief (for ought I
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:47901:65"/>
know) that nothing but their utter ruine could have ranſomed their headlong follies.</p>
               <p>His Majeſty appearing in <hi>England,</hi> he quickly (by the ſplendor of his Rayes) thawed the ſtiffneſs of their frozen and ſlippery intentions. All things (bleſſed be God for it) are at peace and unity here now: And as <hi>Luther</hi> being asked once, What he thought of ſome ſmall Opinions that ſtarted up in his time? anſwered, <hi>That he thought them to be good honeſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, exempting their error:</hi> So I judge of theſe men, That their thoughts were not ſo bad at firſt, as their actions would have led them into in proceſs of time.</p>
               <p>I have here encloſed ſent you ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing written in haſte upon the Kings coming to the enjoyment of his Throne, with a reflection upon the former ſad and bad times; I have done them as well as I could, conſidering all things:
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:47901:65"/>
If they are not ſo well as they ſhould be, all I can do is to wiſh them better for your ſakes. My Obedience to you and my Mother alwayes devoted,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Son G. A.</signed>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Mary-Land,</hi>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Febr.</hi> 9. <hi>Anno</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To my Coſen <hi>Mris. Ellinor Evins.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>E</hi> 're I forget the Zenith of your Love,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>L</hi> et me be baniſht from the Thrones above;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>L</hi> ight let me never ſee, when I grow rude,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> ntomb your Love in baſe Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:47901:66"/>
                     <hi>N</hi> or may I proſper, but the ſtate</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O</hi> f gaping <hi>Tantalus</hi> be my Fate;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>R</hi> ather then I ſhould thus prepoſterous grow,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>E</hi> arth would condemn me to her vaults below.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>V</hi> ertuous and Noble, could my Genius raiſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> mmortal Anthems to your Veſtal praiſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>N</hi> one ſhould be more laborious then I,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>S</hi> aint-like to Canonize you to the Sky.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>The Antimonial Cup (dear Coſen) you ſent me, I had; and as ſoon as I received it, I went to work with the Infirmities and Diſeaſes of my body. At the firſt draught, it made ſuch ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vock among the ſeveral humors that had ſtoln into my body, that like a Conjurer in a room among a company of little Devils, they no ſooner hear him begin to ſpeak high words, but away
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:47901:66"/>
they pack, and happy is he that can get out firſt, ſome up the Chimney, and the reſt down ſtairs, till they are all diſperſt. So thoſe malignant humors of my body, feeling the operative power, and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinal vertue of this Cup, were ſo ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed at their ſudden ſurprizal, (being alwayes before battered only by the weak aſſaults of ſome few Emporicks) they ſtood not long to diſpute, but with joynt conſent made their retreat, ſome running through the ſink of the Skulle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the reſt climbing up my ribs, took my mouth for a Garret-window, and ſo leapt out.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Coſen,</hi> For this great kindneſs of yours, in ſending me this medicinal vertue, I return you many thanks<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It came in a very good time, when I was dangerouſly ſick, and by the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of God it hath perfectly reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered me.</p>
               <p>I have ſent you here a few Furrs, they were all I could get at preſent, I
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:47901:67"/>
humbly beg your acceptance of them, as a pledge of my love and thankfulneſs unto you; I ſubſcribe,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your loving Coſen, G. A.</signed>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Mary-Land,</hi>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Dec.</hi> 9. <hi>Anno</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To my Brother <hi>P. A.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Brother,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have made a ſhift to unlooſe my ſelf from my Collar now as well as you, but I ſee at preſent either ſmall pleaſure or profit in it: What the futu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of my dayes will bring forth, I know not; For while I was linckt with the Chain of a reſtraining Servitude, I had all things cared for, and now I have all things to care for my ſelf,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:47901:67"/>
which makes me almoſt to wiſh my ſelf in for the other four years.</p>
               <p>Liberty without money, is like a man oppreſt with the Gout, every ſtep he puts forward puts him to pain; when on the other ſide, he that has Coyn with his Liberty, is like the ſwift Poſt-Meſſenger of the Gods, that wears wings at his heels, his motion being ſwift or ſlow, as he pleaſeth.</p>
               <p>I received this year two Caps, the one white, of an honeſt plain counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, the other purple, which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to be ſome antient Monumental Relique; which of them you ſent I know not, and it was a wonder how I ſhould, for there was no mention in the Letter, more then, <hi>that my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had ſent me a Cap:</hi> They were delivered me in the company of ſome Gentlemen that ingaged me to write a few lines upon the purple one, and becauſe they were my Friends I could not deny them; and here I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:47901:68"/>
them to you as they were then written.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Haile from the dead, or from Eternity,</l>
                  <l>Thou Velvet Relique of Antiquity;</l>
                  <l>Thou which appear'ſt here in thy purple hew,</l>
                  <l>Tell's how the dead within their Tombs do doe;</l>
                  <l>How thoſe Ghoſts fare within each Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Cell,</l>
                  <l>Where amongſt them for Ages thou didſt dwell.</l>
                  <l>What Brain didſt cover there? tell us, that we</l>
                  <l>Upon our knees vayle Hats to honour thee:</l>
                  <l>And if no honour's due, tell us whoſe pate</l>
                  <l>Thou baſely coveredſt, and we'l joyntly hate:</l>
                  <l>Let's know his name, that we may ſhew neglect;</l>
                  <l>If otherwiſe, we'l kiſs thee with reſpect.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="109" facs="tcp:47901:68"/>Say, didſt thou cover <hi>Noll</hi>'s old brazen head,</l>
                  <l>Which on the top of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> high Lead</l>
                  <l>Stands on a Pole, erected to the sky,</l>
                  <l>As a grand Trophy to his memory.</l>
                  <l>From his perfidious skull didſt thou fall down,</l>
                  <l>In a diſdain to honour ſuch a crown</l>
                  <l>With three-pile Velvet? tell me, hadſt thou thy fall</l>
                  <l>From the high top of that Cathedral?</l>
                  <l>None of the <hi>Heroes</hi> of the <hi>Roman</hi> ſtem,</l>
                  <l>Were ever ſuch a faſhion'd Diadem.</l>
                  <l>Didſt thou ſpeak <hi>Turkiſh</hi> in thy unknown dreſs,</l>
                  <l>Thou'dſt cover <hi>Great Mogull,</hi> and no man leſs;</l>
                  <l>But in thy make methinks thou'rt too too ſcant,</l>
                  <l>To be ſo great a Monarch's Turberant.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Jews</hi> by <hi>Moſes</hi> ſwear, they never knew</l>
                  <l>E're ſuch a Cap dreſt up in <hi>Hebrew</hi>:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="110" facs="tcp:47901:69"/>Nor the ſtrict Order of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> See,</l>
                  <l>Wears any Cap that looks ſo baſe as thee;</l>
                  <l>His Holineſs hates thy Lowneſs, and inſtead,</l>
                  <l>Wears <hi>Peters</hi> ſpired Steeple on his head:</l>
                  <l>The Cardinals deſcent is much more flat,</l>
                  <l>For want of name, baptized is <hi>A Hat;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Through each ſtrict Order has my fancy ran,</l>
                  <l>Both <hi>Ambroſe, Auſtin,</hi> and the <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcan,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where I beheld rich Images of the dead,</l>
                  <l>Yet ſcarce had one a Cap upon his head:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> wears Caps, but not like thee,</l>
                  <l>Though ſeveral ſhap'd, with much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity:</l>
                  <l>'Twere beſt I think I preſently ſhould gang</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Edenburghs</hi> ſtrict <hi>Presbyterian;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But Caps they've none, their ears being made ſo large,</l>
                  <l>Serves them to turn it like a <hi>Garneſey</hi> Barge;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="111" facs="tcp:47901:69"/>Thoſe keep their skulls warm againſt North-weſt guſts,</l>
                  <l>When they in Pulpit do poor <hi>Calvin</hi> curſe.</l>
                  <l>Thou art not <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> for I daily ſee,</l>
                  <l>That which I wiſh is farthest off from me:</l>
                  <l>Thy low-built ſtate none ever did ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance,</l>
                  <l>To chriſten thee the <hi>Cap of Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then till I know from whence thou didſt derive,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt be call'd, the <hi>Cap of Fugitive.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>You writ to me this year to ſend you ſome Smoak; at that inſtant it made me wonder that a man of a rational Soul, having both his eyes (bleſſed be God) ſhould make ſo unreaſonable a demand, when he that has but one eye, nay he which has never a one, and is fain to make uſe of an Animal conductive for his optick guidance, cannot endure
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:47901:70"/>
the prejudice that Smoak brings with it: But ſince you are reſolv'd upon it, I'le diſpute it no further.</p>
               <p>I have ſent you that which will make Smoak, (namely Tobacco) though the Funk it ſelf is ſo ſlippery that I could not ſend it, yet I have ſent you the Subſtance from whence the Smoak derives: What uſe you imploy it to I know not, nor will I be too importunate to know; yet let me tell you this, That if you burn it in a room to affright the Devil from the houſe, you need not fear but it will work the ſame effect, as <hi>Tobyes</hi> galls did upon the leacherous Fiend. No more at preſent. <hi>Vale.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Brother, G. A.</signed>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Mary-Land,</hi>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Dec.</hi> 11. <hi>Anno</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:47901:70"/>
               <head>To my Honored Friend Mr. T. B.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THis is the entrance upon my fifth year, and I fear 'twill prove the worſt: I have been very much troubled with a throng of unruly Diſtempers, that have (contrary to my expectation) crouded into the Main-guard of my body, when the drowſie Sentinels of my brain were a ſleep. Where they got in I know not, but to my grief and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror I find them predominant: Yet as Doctor <hi>Dunne,</hi> ſometimes Dean of St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> ſaid, <hi>That the bodies diſeaſes do but mellow a man for Heaven, and ſo ferments him in this World, as he ſhall need no long concoction in the Grave, but haſten to the Reſurrection.</hi> And if this were weighed ſeriouſly in the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Religious Reaſon, the World
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:47901:71"/>
we dwell in would not ſeem ſo inticing and bewitching as it doth.</p>
               <p>We are only ſent by God of an Errand into this World, and the time that's allotted us for to ſtay, is only for an Anſwer. When God my great Maſter ſhall in good earneſt call me home, which theſe warnings tell me I have not long to ſtay, I hope then I ſhall be able to give him a good account of my Meſſage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir,</hi> My weakneſs gives a ſtop to my writing, my hand being ſo ſhakingly feeble, that I can hardly hold my pen any further then to tell you, I am yours while I live, which I believe will be but ſome few minutes.</p>
               <p>If this Letter come to you before I'me dead, pray for me, but if I am gone, pray howſoever, for they can do me no harm if they come after me. <hi>Vale.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your real Friend, G. A.</signed>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Mary-Land,</hi>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Dec.</hi> 13. <hi>Anno</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:47901:71"/>
               <head>To my Parents.</head>
               <p>FRom the Grave or Receptacle of Death am I raiſed, and by an om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent power made capable of offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once more my Obedience (that lies cloſe cabbined in the inward moſt apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my Soul) at the feet of your immutable Loves.</p>
               <p>My good Parents, God hath done marvellous things for me, far beyond my deſerts, which at beſt were prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterouſly ſinful, and unſuitable to the ſacred will of an Almighty: <hi>But he is merciful, and his mercy endures for ever.</hi> When ſinful man has by his Evils and Iniquities pull'd ſome pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trating Judgement upon his head, and finding himſelf immediately not able to ſtand under ſo great a burthen as Gods ſmalleſt ſtroke of Juſtice, lowers the Top-gallant ſayle of his Pride, and with
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:47901:72"/>
an humble ſubmiſſiveneſs proſtrates himſelf before the Throne of his ſacred Mercy, and like thoſe three Lepars that ſate at the Gate of <hi>Samaria,</hi> reſolved, <hi>If we go into the City we ſhall periſh, and if we ſtay here we ſhall periſh alſo: Therefore we will throw our ſelves into the hands of the</hi> Aſſyrians, <hi>and if we periſh, we periſh</hi> This was juſt my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition as to eternal ſtate; my Soul was at a ſtand in this black ſtorm of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: I view'd the World, and all that's pleaſure in her, and found her altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther flaſhy, aiery, and full of notional pretenſions, and not one firm place where a diſtreſſed Soul could hang his truſt on Next I viewed my ſelf, and there I found, inſtead of good Works, lively Faith, and Charity, a moſt horrid neaſt of condemned Evils, bearing a ſupreme Prerogative over my internal faculties. You'l ſay here was little hope of reſt in this extreme Eclipſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a deſperate amaze to ſee my eſtate
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:47901:72"/>
ſo deplorable: My better Angel urged me to deliver up my aggrievances to the Bench of Gods Mercy, the ſure ſupport of all diſtreſſed Souls: His Heavenly warning, and inward whiſpers of the good Spirit I was reſolv'd to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain, and not quench, and throw my ſelf into the armes of a loving God, <hi>If I periſh, I periſh.</hi> 'Tis beyond won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to think of the love of God exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſinful man, that in the deepeſt diſtreſſes or agonies of Affliction, when all other things prove rather hinderan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces then advantages, even at that time God is ready and ſteps forth to the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment of his drooping Spirit. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, about a fortnight before I wrote this Letter, two of our ableſt Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans rendered me up into the hands of God, the univerſal Doctor of the whole World, and ſubſcribed with a ſilent ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement, That all their Arts, ſcrew'd up to the very Zenith of Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtique perfection, were not capable
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:47901:73"/>
of keeping me from the Grave at that time: But God, the great preſerver of Soul and Body, ſaid contrary to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of humane reaſon, <hi>Ariſe take up thy bed and walk.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am now (through the help of my Maker) creeping up to my former ſtrength and vigour, and every day I live, I hope I ſhall, through the aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of divine Grace, climbe nearer and nearer to my eternal home.</p>
               <p>I have received this year three Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from you, one by Capt. <hi>Conway</hi> Commander of the <hi>Wheat-Sheaf,</hi> the others by a <hi>Briſtol</hi> Ship. Having no more at preſent to trouble you with, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting your promiſe, I remain as ever,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your dutiful Son G. A.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Mary-Land,</hi>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Apr</hi> 9. <hi>Anno</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>I deſire my hearty love may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred to my Brother, and the reſt of my Kinred.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:47901:73"/>
            <head>Theſe Books, with others, are Printed for <hi>Peter Dring,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, at the ſign of the <hi>Sun</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> next door to the <hi>Roſe Tavern.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>ELiana,</hi> A moſt Exquiſite New Romance, formed by an <hi>Engliſh</hi> hand. Fol.</p>
            <p>The Valley of Viſion: Or, a Clear Sight of ſundry Sacred Truths; deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in Twenty One Sermons, by that Learned and Reverend Divine <hi>Richard Holeſworth,</hi> Doctor in Divinity. 4.</p>
            <p>An Expoſition on the whole Book of <hi>Solomons</hi> Song, commonly called the <hi>Canticles</hi>; wherein the Text is Explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and uſeful Obſervations raiſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon; by <hi>John Robotham</hi> Preacher of the Goſpel. 4.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:47901:74"/>The Marrow of the Oracles of God: Or, divers Treatiſes, containing Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections about Six of the Weightieſt things can concern a Chriſtian in this Life; by <hi>N. Byfield,</hi> late Preacher of Gods Word at <hi>Iſleworth</hi> in <hi>Middleſex.</hi> The 13. Edition. 12. large</p>
            <p>The Principles, Or, The Pattern of Wholſome Words; containing a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of ſuch Truths as are of neceſſity to be believed unto Salvation, ſeparated out of the Body of Theology; by <hi>N. Byfield,</hi> Preacher of Gods Word at <hi>Iſleworth</hi> in <hi>Middleſex.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scrutinia Sacra</hi>; Or, the Souls nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſearch for Sin, in ſeven dayes So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Penitentials; by <hi>Thomas Phete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place,</hi> Doctor of Phyſick. 8.</p>
            <p>Tears in time of Peſtilence; by <hi>John Featly,</hi> Doctor in Divinity. 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Templum Muſicum</hi>; Or, the Muſical Synopſis of the Learned and Famous <hi>Johannes-Henricus Alſtedius,</hi> being a Compendium of the Rudiments both
<pb facs="tcp:47901:74"/>
of the Mathematical and Practical part of Muſick, of which ſubject not any Book is extant in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue; by <hi>John Birchenſha.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Ladies Directory, in choice Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments and Curioſities of Preſerving in Jellies, and Candying both Fruits and Flowers; by <hi>Hannah Wolley.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>The Cooks Guide: Or, Rare Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceipts for Cookery; by <hi>Hannah Wolley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Choice Banquet of Witty Jeſts, Rare Fancies, and Pleaſant Novels<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Fitted for all lovers of Wit, Mirth, and Eloquence 8.</p>
            <p>Troads Engliſhed: Whereunto is added ſeveral Excellent Poems and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negyricks upon divers Occaſions; by <hi>S. P.</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>A Comment upon the Two Tales of our Renowned Poet Sir <hi>Jeffray Chau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer,</hi> Knight. 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Courteous Reader,</hi> In the firſt Epiſtle Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, for <hi>Felton</hi> read <hi>Feltham.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
