<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The search after claret, or, A visitation of the vintners a poem in two canto's.</title>
            <author>Ames, Richard, d. 1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-12">2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25274</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A2989</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31891</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12272455</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12272455</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58314</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A25274)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58314)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1494:41)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The search after claret, or, A visitation of the vintners a poem in two canto's.</title>
                  <author>Ames, Richard, d. 1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 18, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for E. Hawkins,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-04</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-04</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58314:1"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:58314:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
THE Search after Claret; OR, A VISITATION OF THE VINTNERS. A POEM In two CANTO'S.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Doubtless the Pleasure is as great</l>
               <l>In being Cheated, as to Cheat.</l>
            </q>
            <bibl>Hudibras.</bibl>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>E. Hawkins,</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:58314:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58314:2"/>
            <head>THE Epistle Dedicatory.</head>
            <l>
               <hi>TO</hi> all Lovers, Admirers and Doters on <hi>Claret,</hi>
            </l>
            <l> (Who tho' at <hi>Deaths-Door,</hi> yet can hadly forbear it)</l>
            <l>Who can Miracles credit, and fancy <hi>Red-Port</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To be Sprightly <hi>Puntack,</hi> and the best of the sort.</l>
            <l>To all <hi>Mornings-draught Men,</hi> who drink bitter Wine,</l>
            <l>To Create a false Stomach against they'r to Dine.</l>
            <l>To all <hi>Tavern-kitchen</hi> Frequenters and Haunters,</l>
            <l>Who go thither to hear <hi>Mistress Cooks</hi> foolish Banters,</l>
            <l>To Partake of a <hi>Dumpling,</hi> or <hi>Sop</hi> in the Pan;</l>
            <l>A <hi>Large Rummer</hi> Drank up, troop as fast as they can.</l>
            <l>To all sober <hi>Half-Pint Men,</hi> and serious <hi>Sippers.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To all old <hi>Maudlin Drinkers,</hi> and <hi>12</hi> a Clock <hi>Bibbers,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To all Drinking <hi>Committees, Knots, Clubs, Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Who while others are snoaring, they'r settling the Nations</l>
            <l>To all the brisk <hi>Beau's</hi> who think Life but a Play,</l>
            <l>Who make Day like the Night, and turn Night into Day.</l>
            <l>To all Lovers of <hi>Red and White-Port, Syracuse,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Barcelona, Navarr,</hi> or <hi>Canary's</hi> sweet Juice.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:58314:3"/>To all Drinkers of <hi>Sherry, Old Hock,</hi> or <hi>Moselle,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Or of <hi>Tent,</hi> which soon teaches the Flesh to Rebel.</l>
            <l>To all <hi>Alicant-Tasters,</hi> and <hi>Malaga-Sots.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To all Friends to <hi>Straw-Bottles,</hi> and <hi>Nicking Quart-Pots.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To all <hi>Bacchus</hi> his Friends, who have Taverns frequented,</l>
            <l>This following <hi>Poem</hi> 
               <lb/> Is Humbly Presented.</l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58314:3"/>A SATYR ON THE VINTNERS.</head>
         <div n="1" type="canto">
            <head>CANTO. I.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>FRom keeping our <hi>Christmas,</hi> not far from <hi>Tom. Jolly's,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where innocent Mirth without Gambals and Follies,</l>
               <l>Where a plentiful Table, and strong humming Liquor,</l>
               <l>Serv'd to lengthen the Days, and make Night pass the quicker;</l>
               <l>Half tyr'd with that Friendship and Kindness was shown,</l>
               <l>My Friend and my Self then resolv'd for the <hi>Town,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To Drink, since our Stomachs both crav'd and could bear it,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Bottle</hi> of good Old Dry Orthodox <hi>Claret;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>We call'd not at <hi>Bow,</hi> least all things should not hap well,</l>
               <l>And stopt not to Drink till we came to <hi>White-Chappel.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="1">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:58314:4"/>
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>Where the first House we entred was honest <hi>Tom. C—xes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And planting our selves within one of his Boxes;</l>
               <l>We Order'd the Drawer to call for our <hi>Friend,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If a Glass of good <hi>Claret</hi> to us he'd commend;</l>
               <l>He smil'd at our Question, and shaking his Noddle,</l>
               <l>He told us <hi>by Yea</hi> and <hi>by Nay</hi> not a <hi>Bottle;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But if we would call for a Glass of <hi>Red-Port,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He'd afford us the best, or be paid nothing for't;</l>
               <l>But our thoughts with his <hi>Canting</hi> not able to wrastle,</l>
               <l>Declining his Motion we went to the <hi>Castle.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>Where it seems a too plentiful dose of <hi>Canary,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which some Butchers had Drank for to make themselves Merry,</l>
               <l>Had by Liberal <hi>Bumpers</hi> quite spoil'd the design,</l>
               <l>And made them all mad by their Drinking much <hi>Wine;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But seeing they all were Ingag'd <hi>Snicker-Snee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVe thought fit to march off, and keep our skins free.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>Crown,</hi> of good <hi>Claret</hi> we sure were to fail,</l>
               <l>VVhich like the <hi>Inn</hi> Drink was half Mild and half Stale.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>At <hi>P—points</hi> we call'd, but what e're was the matter,</l>
               <l>His <hi>Magpye</hi> had long since forgotten to chatter,</l>
               <l>And no wonder at all he had laid by his Note,</l>
               <l>VVhen of <hi>Claret—</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He had not a drop for to moisten his Throat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:58314:4"/>
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>Through <hi>Aldgate</hi> then passing, we stop at the <hi>Mitre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhere <hi>Young</hi> Married <hi>Couples</hi> to make their Hearts lighter,</l>
               <l>Take a jolly brisk Glass to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbolden 'em to say</l>
               <l>That very hard Chapter, <hi>for Ever and for Aye.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But the Drawers and <hi>S—th</hi> were so busie in Burning</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Red</hi> and <hi>White-Port,</hi> for the <hi>Bridegroom's</hi> returning,</l>
               <l>That they had no leisure (such mischief was in't)</l>
               <l>If they had any <hi>Claret,</hi> t'have drawn us a Pint.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>Crown</hi> we Expected to find a good Draught,</l>
               <l>But minding two Drawers who whisper'd and laught</l>
               <l>VVhen we askt for Old <hi>Claret,</hi> we soon chang'd our Notes,</l>
               <l>And spending no Pence, bid good Morn Mr. <hi>C—tes.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <l>VVe'd have call'd at the <hi>Rose,</hi> but we had a suspicion,</l>
               <l>(As wishing does sometimes exceed a fruition)</l>
               <l>That if we attempted to Taste of his VVine,</l>
               <l>'T would have a Complexion like that of the Sign.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>Griffin and Hoop</hi> we were farther to seek,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Claret</hi> to them was as barbrous as <hi>Greek;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of <hi>Red and White-Port</hi> in their Vaults was no lack,</l>
               <l>But by <hi>Bacchus</hi> they had not a drop of <hi>Puntack;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sure <hi>Popery</hi> will now be the <hi>A la-mode</hi> Fashion,</l>
               <l>VVhen the Vintners can swallow <hi>Transubstantiation,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And the Wine that was <hi>French</hi> about six Months ago,</l>
               <l>Has quite chang'd its nature, and's no longer so.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:58314:5"/>
               <head>IX.</head>
               <l>They whose Faith can a <hi>Vintners</hi> absurdities swallow,</l>
               <l>May take Scarlet for Blew, or Crimson for Yellow;</l>
               <l>For when for Old <hi>Claret</hi> we ask't Mr. <hi>St—bs,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Devil a drop could we find in his <hi>Tubs.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="10">
               <head>X.</head>
               <l>The <hi>King</hi>'s<hi>-Arms</hi> by its odd Situation and Bar,</l>
               <l>Did so like an <hi>Alsatian</hi> Tavern appear,</l>
               <l>That to tast of their <hi>Wines</hi> we were almost afraid,</l>
               <l>And so crossing the Kennel went to the <hi>Naggs-Head.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="11">
               <head>XI.</head>
               <l>Not <hi>Rome</hi> for its Building was ever more famous,</l>
               <l>Or the late Times for Juries, they call'd <hi>Ignoramus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Than was that for <hi>Claret;</hi> but ah! how we rue it,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jam jam Seges nunc est, u—bi Troja fuit.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="12">
               <head>XII.</head>
               <l>At our Friend <hi>Jacob Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>klins</hi> we thought to have found,</l>
               <l>Such <hi>Claret</hi> as would a dull <hi>Stoick</hi> confound;</l>
               <l>But our <hi>Friends</hi> in this Cause with the Wicked will joyn,</l>
               <l>He had no <hi>Claret (plainly)</hi> but he had <hi>Port-Wine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By which it appears like Noon-day to the Eye,</l>
               <l>Tho' <hi>Saints</hi> may not Swear, they'r permitted to Lye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="13">
               <head>XIII.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Mermaid</hi> who Swum in the Waves of brisk <hi>Claret,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Complains her Complexion no longer can bear it,</l>
               <l>Since which time in the Stream of <hi>Oporto</hi> she glides,</l>
               <l>Forgetting she ever knew <hi>Bourdeax</hi> swift Tides;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:58314:5"/>
Yet it looks something odd, and a kin to a Trance,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Cornhill</hi> scorns <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>France.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="14">
               <head>XIV.</head>
               <l>In some place of his Vaults that resemble a Church,</l>
               <l>One would think <hi>Peter W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llis</hi> his <hi>Claret</hi> did Lurch,</l>
               <l>But he Swears that his Tuns are as empty of any,</l>
               <l>As a bit Country Cully is empty of Mony;</l>
               <l>Besides he produces a Miracle for't,</l>
               <l>What in <hi>Cheapside</hi> was <hi>Claret</hi>'s, now turn'd to <hi>Red-Port.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="15">
               <head>XV.</head>
               <l>What resemblance the <hi>Ship</hi> and the <hi>Castle</hi> may bear,</l>
               <l>To Ships floating on Clouds, or to Castles in Air,</l>
               <l>We know not, but this we are sure of, 'tis plain,</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Clarets</hi> are serfectly Leigerdemain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="16">
               <head>XVI.</head>
               <l>By St. <hi>Gregory</hi>'s Slippers we thought not to miss</l>
               <l>Of a Glass of <hi>Puntack</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Fleece;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But he solemnly swore by the <hi>Saint</hi> of his Name,</l>
               <l>For this twelve-Months he had not a drop of that same.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="17">
               <head>XVII.</head>
               <l>Who ever was formerly Bit by the <hi>Bear,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Serv'd as use of Instruction to make us take care;</l>
               <l>For when ever the Soul of a <hi>Vintner</hi> is fled,</l>
               <l>In his Cellers a strange <hi>Interregnum</hi> succeed,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Reds</hi> quarrel with <hi>Whites,</hi> and <hi>Canary</hi> with both,</l>
               <l>If this be not so, give the <hi>Cooper</hi> his Oath;</l>
               <l>However for decency sake they are civil,</l>
               <l>Yet with <hi>Widows</hi> Wine-Cellers the Drawers play the Devil.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="18">
               <head>XVIII.</head>
               <l>He must surely have more than the Brains of a Man,</l>
               <l>VVho at <hi>Change-time</hi> can suffer the noise of the <hi>Swan,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:58314:6"/>
A <hi>Half-Flask</hi> of <hi>Red-Port,</hi> a <hi>Pint of Canary,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A <hi>Quart of Old Hock,</hi> and a <hi>Bottle of Sherry,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Are the noises the Drawers do make e'ery minute;</l>
               <l>If this be not pleasing the Devil is in it.</l>
               <l>Let me Drink with my Friend without noise or a throng,</l>
               <l>Here <hi>all in Confusion's</hi> plaid all the year long.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="19">
               <head>XIX.</head>
               <l>Looking at the <hi>King's-Head,</hi> and observing the Sign,</l>
               <l>We suspected to find but effeminate <hi>Wine;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For the Painter had Drawn him a <hi>Caesar</hi> in Dress,</l>
               <l>With an <hi>Amazons</hi> Hair, and a <hi>Womanish</hi> Face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="20">
               <head>XX.</head>
               <l>VVhat ever Devotion we pay to the Sign</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Popes Head,</hi> 'tis be sure for the sake of his <hi>Wine;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But his Tenant was lately Casheir'd for an ill-son,</l>
               <l>And he hopes that the <hi>Capt.</hi> proves better than <hi>Willson,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To which end all his <hi>Wines</hi> that from <hi>France</hi> lately came,</l>
               <l>Are to be Rebaptiz'd with a more <hi>Christian</hi> Name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="21">
               <head>XXI.</head>
               <l>At his Door with a Rummer we found <hi>Neddy Dr—ner,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And perceiv'd by his looks that he was a Complainer.</l>
               <l>VVe whisper'd in's Ear, and desir'd (could he spare it)</l>
               <l>To let's have a Bottle or two of old <hi>Claret;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He started as frighted to hear our Demands,</l>
               <l>And answer'd, why <hi>Gentlemen</hi> (holding up's hands)</l>
               <l>D'ye know what you mean? Let me dye like an Ass,</l>
               <l>If this twelvemonth I've seen, smelt, or tasted a Glass.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="22">
               <head>XXII.</head>
               <l>VVe shook our Heads at him, and crossing the way,</l>
               <l>At the <hi>Globe</hi> we attempted another Essay;</l>
               <l>VVhen we askt for old <hi>Claret,</hi> the Drawers were inchanted,</l>
               <l>And we for our parts thought the Mansion was Haunted,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:58314:6"/>
So leaving the Tavern, in study profound,</l>
               <l>We concluded indeed that the Globe was turn'd round.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="23">
               <head>XXIII.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>Mitre</hi> we call'd in, and walking the Entry,</l>
               <l>Spy'd a Soldier in Habit much unlike a Centry,</l>
               <l>Who spewing, did in his short intervals say,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pox take your Red-Port,</hi> and so Reel'd on his way,</l>
               <l>We soon took the hint from his Stomach's Alarms;</l>
               <l>They'r wise gain Experience by other Mens Harms.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="24">
               <head>XXIV.</head>
               <l>Half vext to be baulk't in our pious design,</l>
               <l>At the <hi>Birds with long Bills,</hi> vainly strove to get in;</l>
               <l>For a Croud at the Door 'bout a Man that was Prest,</l>
               <l>Deny'd our Admittance and yet spoil'd no Jest,</l>
               <l>For we fancied that Tavern was like all the rest.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="25">
               <head>XXV.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>Rose</hi> we no sooner had come to the Bar,</l>
               <l>But a sawcy Whelp askt if Arrested we were;</l>
               <l>We esteem'd this Affront, as provoking as any,</l>
               <l>Kickt his Arse, and went out without spending a Penny.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="26">
               <head>XXVI.</head>
               <l>We lookt in at the <hi>Ship</hi> and found the Boys idle;</l>
               <l>And it seem'd unto us but a kind of a Riddle,</l>
               <l>That a Vessel which only was fit to vend <hi>Brandy,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Should pretend to sell <hi>Wines,</hi> ay, and those good as can be;</l>
               <l>Besides, when we thought of a late Declaration,</l>
               <l>Which was there hatcht in order to settle the Nation;</l>
               <l>We declin'd going in, lest at once we should lose,</l>
               <l>Both our Health and our Credit by entring the House.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="27">
               <head>XXVII.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>Feathers</hi> we call'd to see honest <hi>Paul C—ry,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who was treating himself with a Glass of <hi>Canary;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:58314:7"/>
What, <hi>Paul,</hi> says my friend, dost thou Abdicate <hi>Claret?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of all mankind I thought you could never forbear it;</l>
               <l>He reply'd, once my Vaults had a plentiful Crop,</l>
               <l>But since my last Journey the Devil a <hi>Drop.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="28">
               <head>XXVIII.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>Bull-head</hi> Ariv'd, we'd have call'd to see <hi>V—rs,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But observing how Cullies and Cracks flockt by Pairs</l>
               <l>To the House, as the Unclean Beasts did into the Ark;</l>
               <l>We were certain we then had mistaken our mark.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="29">
               <head>XXIX.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>Shepherd</hi> when boldly for <hi>Claret</hi> we askt,</l>
               <l>He told us he'd very good <hi>Florence</hi> was Flaskt;</l>
               <l>VVe smil'd at the wit of the pleasant Drawcansir,</l>
               <l>And thought it was much such a pertinent answer,</l>
               <l>As if I should ask a Man where he does dwell?</l>
               <l>And he tells me his VVife and his Children are well.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="30">
               <head>XXX.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>Nags-head</hi> of good we were sure to despair,</l>
               <l>VVhen we spy'd a young Female a sleep at the <hi>Bar,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhen the Inches of Candles were twinkling in Sockets,</l>
               <l>And the Drawers stood yawning with hands in their Pockets.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="31">
               <head>XXXI.</head>
               <l>At <hi>Mat. Fowlers</hi> the fam'd <hi>Tory Tavern</hi> then calling,</l>
               <l>VVhere the Drawers were all of them Hoarse with their Bawling.</l>
               <l>VVhen of delicate <hi>Claret</hi> we askt for the best,</l>
               <l>VVe were told, with that Juice his Vaults once were opprest,</l>
               <l>But they had not a Drop since the <hi>Prentices</hi> Feast.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="32">
               <head>XXXII.</head>
               <l>Thus finding our wishes all come by mishap,</l>
               <l>VVent to House with the sign of <hi>Prelatical Cap,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And asking for <hi>Claret,</hi> the Master returning</l>
               <l>This answer, for want on't his Tuns were in Mourning;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:58314:7"/>
VVe presently knew he had found out the Knack,</l>
               <l>VVith <hi>Red-Port</hi> to supply all his wants of <hi>Puntack.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="33">
               <head>XXXIII.</head>
               <l>To <hi>Paul's Church-Yard</hi> hasting, 'mongst Drapers, Chair-Makers,</l>
               <l>VVhereof some are Christians, and others are Quakers.</l>
               <l>VVe call'd in at <hi>Pea—ks,</hi> and askt him the Question,</l>
               <l>But he told us his VVine, tho it had the Complexion,</l>
               <l>Was no more <hi>Bourdeaux Claret,</hi> than Brawn could be taken,</l>
               <l>Or by any one thought to be Gammon of Bacon.</l>
               <l>Besides, his Guests long since did's <hi>Claret</hi> Devour,</l>
               <l>By drinking of Healths to th' Bishops i'th' Tower.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="34">
               <head>XXXIV.</head>
               <l>Then Crossing the way we stept to <hi>Tom. A—llns,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But he swore by <hi>Stains-Bridg</hi> that he had but six <hi>Gallons</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of <hi>Claret;</hi> and they of his Trade were all <hi>Block heads,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If of that, of <hi>Red-Port</hi> they made not six <hi>Hogs-heads.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="35">
               <head>XXXV.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>Captains</hi> we though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> t'have found that which was good,</l>
               <l>But he told us in short, 'twas a <hi>Wonder</hi> we shou'd;</l>
               <l>For the <hi>French Wine</hi> he bought, and paid ready Cole for't,</l>
               <l>E're it came into <hi>Corn-hill</hi> 'twould all of't be <hi>Port.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="36">
               <head>XXXVI.</head>
               <l>Then passing through <hi>Lud-gate</hi> we stept to the <hi>Widows,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who a very kind Welcome obligingly bid us;</l>
               <l>But Old <hi>St—re</hi> assur'd us, of rich <hi>Claret</hi> Wine,</l>
               <l>Their Tuns were as empty as those of the <hi>Sign.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="37">
               <head>XXXVII.</head>
               <l>Just crossing, we came to the <hi>Vulture and George,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where just 'gainst the entrance, in Bar that was large,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Daniel Eu—r</hi> appear'd with a Presence as Noble,</l>
               <l>As if he were <hi>Visier</hi> at <hi>Constantinople.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:58314:8"/>
When we askt him for <hi>Claret,</hi> he had not a Drop,</l>
               <l>For the <hi>New River-Water Men</hi> drank it all up;</l>
               <l>Tho the Riddle it self we could hardly Divine,</l>
               <l>How the Dealers in VVater should Drink so much <hi>Wine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="38">
               <head>XXXVIII.</head>
               <l>Passing over <hi>Fleet-Bridg,</hi> still on that side the way,</l>
               <l>We resolv'd at the five <hi>Bells</hi> a visit to pay;</l>
               <l>When we askt him for <hi>Claret,</hi> he vow'd not a drop,</l>
               <l>For he had in <hi>Lavender</hi> laid it all up,</l>
               <l>Resolving for no man to draw off a Gill on't,</l>
               <l>Till by Law he could let all his Guests have their fill on't;</l>
               <l>His obstinate Humour we well could not weather,</l>
               <l>So stept cross the way for to call at the <hi>Feather.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="39">
               <head>XXXIX.</head>
               <l>But how much surpriz'd were we, both for to find,</l>
               <l>The Birds flown, who had yet left their <hi>Feathers</hi> behind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="40">
               <head>XL.</head>
               <l>To the <hi>Castle</hi> we went, and for <hi>Gl—ver</hi> inquir'd,</l>
               <l>And a Glass of Old <hi>Claret</hi> we humbly desir'd;</l>
               <l>But he vow'd he had none on't what ever we'd pay,</l>
               <l>For 'twas all on't Drunk up last <hi>Coecilias</hi> day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="41">
               <head>XLI.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>Greyhound</hi> we call'd, and did <hi>Claret</hi> demand,</l>
               <l>But the Drawers or did, or would not understand;</l>
               <l>Sir we 've <hi>Florence, Old Hock</hi> Sir, or very good <hi>Port;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Have you so (says my Friend) then to make you some sport,</l>
               <l>Mix your VVines all together, and when they are thick,</l>
               <l>Add some <hi>Gunpowder</hi> to 'em and give 'em <hi>Old-Nick.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="42">
               <head>XLII.</head>
               <l>To the <hi>Globe</hi> we then marching just over the way,</l>
               <l>VVe found Drawers ingag'd in Blood, Battle, and Fray;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:58314:8"/>
So thinking that <hi>Claret</hi> we there should find none,</l>
               <l>Turn'd our backs on the Bar, and advanc'd to the <hi>Sun.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="43">
               <head>XLIII.</head>
               <l>VVhere the <hi>Captain</hi> it seems, to his thoughts recommending,</l>
               <l>The threatning loud storm o're the <hi>Vintners</hi> impending;</l>
               <l>Discreetly resolves for to leave off betimes,</l>
               <l>And not be the Partner of other Mens Crimes,</l>
               <l>VVill Retire to the Country, and Live free from Strife,</l>
               <l>The wisest of Actions he did in his Life.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="44">
               <head>XLIV.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>Horn</hi> we were welcom'd with so much <hi>Address,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As if we were persons of highest Nobless;</l>
               <l>But when our demands had arriv'd at their Ears,</l>
               <l>By their Looks we soon read their suspicions and fears;</l>
               <l>For <hi>Informers</hi> they took us, but we well assur'd,</l>
               <l>That this was a Grievance not fit t' b' indur'd,</l>
               <l>Call'd 'em all Sons of Batchelors, Panders and VVhores,</l>
               <l>And so in a Passion went both out of Doors.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="45">
               <head>XLV.</head>
               <l>VVhen at the <hi>Green Dragon</hi> we askt for some <hi>Claret,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Us as if we were <hi>Camels</hi> the Drawers did stare at;</l>
               <l>They told of good <hi>Port</hi> we were sure not to fail,</l>
               <l>But we fearing the Sting it might have in the Tail,</l>
               <l>Declin'd it.—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="46">
               <head>XLVI.</head>
               <l>—And so to the <hi>Fleece</hi> next advancing,</l>
               <l>VVe heard such confusion of Singing and Dancing;</l>
               <l>And not willing to follow so loud an Example,</l>
               <l>Ne're stept in, but crost over the way to the <hi>Temple.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="47">
               <head>XLVII.</head>
               <l>VVhere <hi>Watt—</hi>like the Swiss of his Family stood,</l>
               <l>VVe whisp'ring in's Ear for a Bottle of <hi>Good;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:58314:9"/>
VVhy Gentlemen, says he, observe but my <hi>Sing,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And you'l ne're think I sell <hi>Anti-Christian Wine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="48">
               <head>XL VIII.</head>
               <l>VVe had call'd at the <hi>Hoop,</hi> but the Door was shut fast,</l>
               <l>And we heard the poor <hi>F—nch</hi> had just warbled his last;</l>
               <l>In some places we spend what in others we get,</l>
               <l>So the <hi>House</hi> and the <hi>Widow</hi> are both to be <hi>Let.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="49">
               <head>XLIX.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>Captains</hi> we hope't to have met with a Glass,</l>
               <l>(But sometimes we wish for what ne're comes to pass)</l>
               <l>He assur'd us of <hi>Claret</hi> he had not a Gill,</l>
               <l>But of Delicate <hi>Florence</hi> we might have our fill;</l>
               <l>And could he find <hi>Claret</hi> he'd give nothing for't;</l>
               <l>So we lest the <hi>Bull-head,</hi> cause his Horns were so short.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="50">
               <head>L.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>Head</hi> of Old Jolly Gruff great Codpeic'd <hi>Harry,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVe expected to find out a Glass to be Merry;</l>
               <l>But the name of <hi>Puntack</hi> was forgotten and Dead,</l>
               <l>And strange <hi>Barcelona</hi> now Reign'd in his stead;</l>
               <l>VVithal such a noise was still made at the Bar,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Florentine</hi> Flasks, and full Quarts of <hi>Navar;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let me Dye of the <hi>Pip,</hi> or my Mistress scorn,</l>
               <l>If I did not suppose that I was at <hi>Leghorn.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="51">
               <head>LI.</head>
               <l>VVe were crossing the way at the <hi>Star</hi> for to call in,</l>
               <l>But alas! we perceiv'd the <hi>Bright Meteor</hi> was fallen,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="52">
               <head>LII.</head>
               <l>At the the <hi>Queens-head</hi> the Porters were letting down <hi>Wines,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And at the Ropes, stumbling, my Freind hurt his Shins;</l>
               <l>This as an ill Omen supposing, refus'd,</l>
               <l>VVithin with bad VVine to be doubly abus'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="53">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:58314:9"/>
               <head>LIII.</head>
               <l>By the noise of <hi>Port, Port,</hi> which the Drawers all made,</l>
               <l>One would guess the <hi>Three-Tuns</hi> had a thundring great Trade;</l>
               <l>But <hi>Claret</hi> was <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> to their Ears,</l>
               <l>Tho' they know it as well as they do their Neck Verse.</l>
               <l>He does all th' occasions of doubting prevent,</l>
               <l>That's Cheated and Bubbled by's proper consent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="54">
               <head>LIV.</head>
               <l>At <hi>Fen—ks</hi> the Son of a Parson so civil,</l>
               <l>Who lives at the sign of the <hi>Junior Devil;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>We askt for a Bottle of you know what Juice,</l>
               <l>But he told he'd oblige us with rare <hi>Syracuse;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Syracuse</hi> quoth my Friend! what a Devil is that?</l>
               <l>For as sure as my Brains now lie under my Hat,</l>
               <l>It may be <hi>Aqua-Fortis,</hi> or else I may lye.</l>
               <l>Pox take your hard name Sir, and so Sir <hi>good Bu'y.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="55">
               <head>LV.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>Young-Devil</hi> failing, we went to his <hi>Dam,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But as soon as in sight of the Bar we were came,</l>
               <l>A Drawer Officiously shews us a Room;</l>
               <l>We told him immediately for what 'twas we come;</l>
               <l>He started as if a pale Ghost he had seen,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lord Gentlemen! pray you explain what you mean:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My Friend had explain'd it, I faith, on his Pate,</l>
               <l>If by my interposing I hindred not that;</l>
               <l>But because I desir'd him for once to be civil,</l>
               <l>He concluded with Heaven keep us from all evil;</l>
               <l>But send you all quickly, from whence we go, the Devil.</l>
               <l>Thus finding the Vintners, some Swearing, all Lying,</l>
               <l>And that no Man in's Wits would their words e're rely on;</l>
               <l>Dispairing to find out a Glass of good <hi>Claret,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Tho we thought 'twas no Virtue all times to forbear it;</l>
               <l>Finding all our Endeavours, our Hopes, Wishes fail,</l>
               <l>We concluded the Evening with <hi>Nottingham</hi> Ale,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:58314:10"/>
Resolving next morning as soon as Day-break,</l>
               <l>(Dispatching some business) to search for Puntack.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="canto">
            <head>CANTO II.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WIsht morning arriv'd, where Men Ply for their Fares,</l>
               <l>We took <hi>Oars,</hi> and were Landed at <hi>Parliament-Stairs;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Having finisht our Business in <hi>Westminster-Hall,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where the Lawyers do <hi>Billinsgate</hi> loudly out-baul.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>Bufflers-head</hi> first we propounded the question,</l>
               <l>But the Master o'th' House was such a mo—dest one;</l>
               <l>He believ'd that there was not a Drop in the Nation,</l>
               <l>For 'twas all on't drunk up at the <hi>Last Coronation.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>Fountain</hi> then looking, we lik't not the <hi>Sign,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For <hi>Hedg-Taverns</hi> have commonly none but <hi>Hedg-Wine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>We'd have call'd at the <hi>Bell,</hi> but were told by a Scout,</l>
               <l>That the <hi>Clapper</hi> for several Months has been out.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>As we entred the <hi>Sun</hi> with a grave <hi>Spanish</hi> pace,</l>
               <l>Met a Man in the Entry was Scorcht in the Face;</l>
               <l>But we willing to learn Wit by other Mens Harms,</l>
               <l>Left the House, and directly went to the <hi>King's-Arms.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>Who tho they pretended to sell <hi>Red</hi> good as can be,</l>
               <l>I'de rather at any time drink <hi>Cherry-Brandy.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:58314:10"/>
               <head>VI.</head>
               <l>Where ever the <hi>Swans</hi> may have done in the <hi>City,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Swan</hi> here in <hi>King-street</hi> had sung her last <hi>Ditty.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <l>Then passing along to the sign of St. <hi>Andrew,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And expecting to find Wine as good as e're Man Drew;</l>
               <l>But we found that our hopes were all as much mistaken,</l>
               <l>As his that took <hi>Sturgeon</hi> for <hi>Gammon</hi> of <hi>Bacon.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <l>Then passing <hi>White-hall,</hi> we first came to the <hi>Rummer,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which like a Town Jilt receives every new comer,</l>
               <l>But they were so busie in Dressing <hi>great Dinners,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That they then had no Rome for two thirsty poor Sinners.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9, 10, 11, 12, 13">
               <head>IX. X. XI. XII. XIII.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>Garter</hi> my Friend call'd, I at the <hi>King's-head,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And we both at the <hi>Crown,</hi> and three <hi>Tuns</hi> thought to speed,</l>
               <l>Nor omitted to call at the sign <hi>Sandy-Pry'd;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But alas! how some people in Lying will Glory,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Vintners</hi> like <hi>Gypsyes</hi> hang all in a Story.</l>
               <l>And when we demanded a Glass of <hi>Puntack,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Swore they had not a Drop if their Souls lay at stake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="14">
               <head>XIV.</head>
               <l>We had call'd at the <hi>Buffler,</hi> but that we both thought,</l>
               <l>Our <hi>Friends</hi> Wine and his Faith were both equally naught.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="15">
               <head>XV.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>Lyon</hi> the Master was thumping the Back</l>
               <l>Of a Drawer, who at Bar by mistake cry'd <hi>Puntack;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If naming the word is so Criminal thought,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Vintners</hi> their Hogs t'a fine Market have brought,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="16">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:58314:11"/>
               <head>XVI.</head>
               <l>Had we drank at the <hi>Chequer,</hi> no Physick could bar us</l>
               <l>From Death, for how little, alas! 'twould avail us,</l>
               <l>To drink Wine in a House that looks so like an <hi>Ale-house?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="17, 18, 19">
               <head>XVII. XVIII. XIX.</head>
               <l>So pale was the <hi>Rose,</hi> the <hi>Long-Dog</hi> out of Breath,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Duck-Wing</hi> had crow'd himself almost to Death;</l>
               <l>That had we at either of these askt for <hi>Claret,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVithout question our wishes had quickly miscarried.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="20">
               <head>XX.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>Sun</hi> we were loath for to moisten our Lips,</l>
               <l>For we plainly perceiv'd she was then in <hi>Eclipse.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="21">
               <head>XXI.</head>
               <l>At the sides of <hi>One Tun</hi> my Friend knockt for a Sign,</l>
               <l>But a hollow Voice answer'd, <hi>Puntack</hi>'s <hi>not within.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="22">
               <head>XXII.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>Bear</hi> when for <hi>Claret</hi> we askt the Drawcansir.</l>
               <l>Like the <hi>Sign</hi> he was Muzled, and gave us no Answer.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="23">
               <head>XXIII.</head>
               <l>VVhen at the <hi>Half moon</hi> we observ'd the gay Sign,</l>
               <l>VVe expected to find no good <hi>Claret</hi> within;</l>
               <l>If the <hi>Wine</hi> be but good, let the Sign be a Rush,</l>
               <l>For the Learned agree that good VVine needs no Bush.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="24">
               <head>XXIV.</head>
               <l>The Poets who with their Inventions so rack us,</l>
               <l>Yet assure us the Goat was accquainted with <hi>Bacchus;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet the <hi>Goat</hi> in <hi>Strand</hi> had not <hi>Claret</hi> a Drop,</l>
               <l>For last Summer the <hi>Bacchinals</hi> drank it all up.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="25">
               <head>XXV.</head>
               <l>At <hi>Po—<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> we thought some old <hi>Claret</hi> to try,</l>
               <l>But, alas! of that Liquor the <hi>Fountain</hi> was dry;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:58314:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
For since he so lately was fin'd fifty Pound,</l>
               <l>For fetching up Bottles from Cellar profound;</l>
               <l>VVhen oblig'd by the Law to Sell VVine in a Quart,</l>
               <l>VVe found him so fretful, so peevish and short;</l>
               <l>But 'twixt Humour and Purse is a Sympathy found,</l>
               <l>Our Humour's not well if our Purse is unsound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="26">
               <head>XXVI.</head>
               <l>How briskly the <hi>Feathers</hi> may look; yet we guest</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Claret</hi> (if any) was none of the best.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="27">
               <head>XXVII.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Vine</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> we observ'd was new Planted,</l>
               <l>And to find no good <hi>Claret</hi> there, took it for granted.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="28">
               <head>XXVIII.</head>
               <l>The Doors of the <hi>Swan,</hi> some by order had clos'd 'em,</l>
               <l>E're since <hi>Abraham H—lls</hi> went to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Bosom.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="29">
               <head>XXIX.</head>
               <l>When for <hi>Claret</hi> at <hi>Ca—ters,</hi> who lives at the Mitre,</l>
               <l>VVe askt, she admir'd we came there for to fright her,</l>
               <l>For she had not a Drop, or may Man ne're Delight her.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="30">
               <head>XXX.</head>
               <l>When at the <hi>Five Bells</hi> we would Ring a short Peal,</l>
               <l>We perceiv'd by some token all things were not well;</l>
               <l>'Twould grieve a Man thence to receive a sad Fate,</l>
               <l>For if I am Poyson'd it shall be in State.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="31">
               <head>XXXI.</head>
               <l>At <hi>La—fords</hi> the <hi>Grey-hound,</hi> to call we forbear it,</l>
               <l>He being better accquainted with <hi>Punch</hi> than with <hi>Claret.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="32">
               <head>XXXII.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>White-Horse,</hi> so fam'd for the Consults and Plots,</l>
               <l>By Jesuits held, as was sworn by <hi>T. Otes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:58314:12"/>
We call'd, but he told us he had not a Tast,</l>
               <l>For 'twas all on't drunk up at the <hi>Dorsetshire</hi> Feast.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="33">
               <head>XXXIII.</head>
               <l>VVhen we stept in at <hi>Rof—s</hi> we heard such distraction,</l>
               <l>Of Singing and Gaming, and things sold by Auction,</l>
               <l>That the <hi>Tavern</hi> resembled a Wake or a Fair,</l>
               <l>And hating all noises did soon disappear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="34">
               <head>XXXIV.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Ship</hi> who of late Sprung a Leak in the Main,</l>
               <l>Is new Corkt, Trim'd and Lancht in the Ocean agen;</l>
               <l>We hawld her and askt if she'd <hi>Claret</hi> Aboard,</l>
               <l>But the <hi>Captain</hi> and Ships Crew would not answer a word.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="35">
               <head>XXXV.</head>
               <l>The last Tavern we came to, was that of the <hi>Rose;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>At the Door of which stood such a parcel of <hi>Beau</hi>'s,</l>
               <l>VVho in Eating and Drinking great Criticks commence.</l>
               <l>And are Judges of every thing else but of Sense,</l>
               <l>VVhen we saw'em makes Faces, and heard one or two Swear,</l>
               <l>That the VVine was the Devil they lately drank there;</l>
               <l>VVe rely'd on their word, and ne're stept o're the Groundsil,</l>
               <l>But thought they spoke truth like General Council.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Two days in this Search were away vainly thrown,</l>
               <l>And we both of us thinking to find none in <hi>Town;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then agreed with <hi>a nemine contradicente,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That since Drinks of our <hi>English</hi> growth was so plenty;</l>
               <l>VVe all their Brew'd <hi>Wines</hi> would not value a Rush,</l>
               <l>Nor shorten our days by respect to a <hi>Bush.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:58314:12"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>IF any</hi> Vintner, VVine-Cooper, <hi>&amp;c. between</hi> VVhite-Chappel <hi>and</hi> VVestminster-Abby, <hi>have some Tuns or Hogs heads of Old, Rich Unadulterated</hi> Claret, <hi>and will sell it (as the Law directs) for six Pence a Quart: This is to give notice, he shall have more Customers than half his Profession; and his House be as full from Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Night as a</hi> Conventicle, <hi>or</hi> VVestminster Hall <hi>the first day of the</hi> Term.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:58314:13"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58314:13"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
