<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Account of the proceedings at Guild-Hall, London, at the Tolke-moot, or Common-Hall, held 24th of June 1676 relating to the cities petitioning His Majesty for a new Parliament.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-01">2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25699</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A355</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7747</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11634411</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11634411</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47947</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A25699)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47947)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 3:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Account of the proceedings at Guild-Hall, London, at the Tolke-moot, or Common-Hall, held 24th of June 1676 relating to the cities petitioning His Majesty for a new Parliament.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>City of London (England). --  Court of Common Council.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47947:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN ACCOUNT Of the Proceedings at GUILD-HALL, <hi>London,</hi> At the TOLKE-MOOT, or COMMON-HALL, Held <hi>24th.</hi> of June 1676.</head>
            <head type="sub">Relating to the Cities Petitioning His Majeſty for a new Parliament.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MR. COMMON SERGEANT,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT ſeems a vain thing for this Court, to be ſerious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the choice of Magiſtrates and Officers, for the well Government of this City, except they firſt take care to remedy thoſe many miſchiefs and grievances which the City now groans under, and which ſeems ſo to threaten the ruine and deſtruction of the whole, that if there be not ſome ſpeedy redreſs, there will be little need of Magiſtrates and Officers; for
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:47947:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
there will be no City or People left here to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> has once already been burned to aſhes, and firing is now become ſuch a Trade, that not only <hi>London,</hi> the Burrough of <hi>Southwark,</hi> and the Places adjoyning, but all the Cities, Burroughs, Towns Corporate, and Places of principal Trade throughout the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom are perpetually in danger; ſo that no rational and conſiderate Man amongſt us, can promiſe himſelf, his Wife, his Children, or Eſtate, one night ſecurity, but they may all be devoured in the conſuming flames, except ſome ſpeedy and effectual courſe be taken.</p>
            <p>But this is not all, for were our Houſes ſecure from Fire, yet ſuch is the general decay of Trade, as if not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medied, muſt inavoidably bring the whole City to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty and ruine; and it is conceived that this is very much occaſioned by the French, who have laid ſuch great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions upon our woollen Cloth, Stuffs, and other Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures, that we have almoſt loſt our Trade with <hi>France,</hi> and they have ſpoiled our Trade with <hi>Holland, Flanders,</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> by a deſtructive War. They have ruined our Trade at home, and beggared many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of our honeſt and induſtrious Weavers, and other Engliſh Manufactors and Traders, by the vaſt quantity of their Silks, and other unneceſſary Commodities im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported hither. So that upon an exact Ballance of the Trade, between Us and them taken, it has been demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated that this City and Kingdom doth loſe eleven hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand Pounds every year.</p>
            <p>By means whereof, they who in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s time might not be ſuffered to build Men of War, are
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:47947:2"/>
now grown ſo powerful at Sea as to be able to beat both Dutch and Spaniard, and have made themſelves in a manner ſole Maſters of the <hi>Mediteranian</hi> Sea. And they are grown ſo preſumptious, as daily to injure and affront our Engliſh Merchants, and ſometimes in His Majeſties own Ports. Their Privateers daily take our Merchant Ships, plunder others, ſtrip, impriſon, and torment our Sea-men, to the great diſcouragement of our Engliſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation, and almoſt ruine of the Merchant.</p>
            <p>I ſhall Inſtance but in one thing more, but that is worſe then all the reſt, that is the juſt apprehenſion that is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the minds of good Men, of danger to His Majeſties Perſon, and the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>I had not ſpoken this at this time and place, but hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the honour to ſerve this City in Common Councel, I have endeavoured at ſeveral times to bring theſe things before that Court, but could not. In the end of the laſt Common Councel I did deſire my Lord Major, that a Common Councel might ſpeedily be held, to hear and conſider of a Petition about Trade, ſubſcribed by a great number of Citizens of good quality; and his Lordſhip did then promiſe that a Common Councel ſhould ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be held: But it is a good time ſince, and there hath been many Fires and Loſſes, but no Common Councel. Whereof, me thinks, it doth become the wiſdom and gravity of this great Court, not <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o admit of any longer delay in a matter wherein their <hi>All</hi> i<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> concerned: And I do humbly move (and I conceive it is not only my ſenſe, but the ſenſe of the far greater part of this Court) that ſome Members of this Court may accompany the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs, and Mr. Common Sargeant, before we proceed to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47947:3"/>
any other matter, to wait upon my Lord Mayor and the Court of Aldermen, to deſire that a Common Councel might ſpeedily be held, humbly to Petition His Majeſty, that for the quieting and ſatisfying the minds of His liege People, and for the remedy of the many miſchiefs and grievances we now groan under, he would gratiouſly be pleaſed (according to the Statutes of the <hi>4th.</hi> and <hi>36th.</hi> of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3.) timely to call a <hi>New Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Scarcely were theſe words a <hi>New Parliament</hi> pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, but a very great number cryed out, Well moved, well moved; and though none ſpake up formally to the Sheriffs, yet ſeveral amongſt the multitude ſpake enough, to ſhew an high approbation of what had been ſaid, and no one word was ſpoken in contradiction: Which when the Common Sargeant ſaw, to prevent (as is conceived) others ſpeaking to the ſame matter, he ſpake to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>That what had been moved, ſeemed to be the general ſenſe of the whole Court, and ſince the Gentleman that made the motion was pleaſed to join him with the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs, and that he muſt offer his opinion in the matter: It was this, that it was not ſo proper to carry up that Meſſage before they did proceed to their Elections; as Firſt, To determine their Election, and then carry up an account of theſe and that together. But many in the Court did inſiſt upon the motion, and deſired a Meſſage might be ſent up immediately. Whereupon one of the Sheriffs ſpoke, and did acknowledge, that what had been ſaid by the Gentleman, t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpak<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rſt was true; but that he was an old Citizen, and had long known Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47947:3"/>
Halls, and he did believe that the proper work of the day was the Election of Officers, and therefore he did deſire that the Court would proceed to that, and not to carry up the Meſſage till after that was done. To which one replied, That according to his utmoſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that Court was one of the Ancienteſt, greateſt, and moſt powerful Courts in the City; and although the Cuſtomary buſineſs of this day was the choice of Officers, yet that Court had cognizance of any thing whatever that did relate to the good of the City, and therefore it was conceived that nothing was more proper at that time th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n this, which concerned the preſervation of the City from utter ruine.</p>
            <p>Upon which the other Sheriff directing his diſcourſe to the People ſaid, that what the Gentleman had moved there, was true and not unknown to moſt of the People there preſent; but that he was of his Brothers opinion, that it was fit firſt to go on to the work of the day, and not to carry up that Meſſage till after the Election. Many Perſons being ſtill diſſatisfied, and calling for a preſent Meſſage to be ſent up. Thereupon the Gentleman who firſt moved the buſineſs deſired, that ſince there ſeemed a difference touching the circumſtance of time, made it his Requeſt that they would proceed to Election, and carry up the Meſſage with the Perſons elected as the  She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs deſired, to which the Common-Hall u<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>animouſly agreed.</p>
            <p>Upon which, ſilence bei<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g made, the Common-Hall proceeded <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o Election of Sheriffs, and made their Election; And ſent up an acco<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt thero<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the Lord May<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d Aldermen, by the Sheriffs and Common Sergeant<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, as is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47947:4"/>
uſual in ſuch caſes. The Lord Mayor and Aldermen preſ<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntly came down, and took their Seats in the Court of Huſtings according to cuſtom; upon which the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Sargeant came forth to the front of the Court, and declared the names of the Perſons elected, and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately gave back. Thereupon the Common-Hall called out for an Anſwer to their Meſſage; upon which the Common Sargeant ſteping forward again, and in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord Mayor, Aldermen and Sheriffs, ſaid that he had acquainted his Lordſhip and the Aldermen with their Requeſt. And that his Lordſhip has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him, to declare unto them that he would be ready to join with them, in that or any other thing for the good of the City: And with that the Lord Mayor and Aldermen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> left the Court of Huſtings—And diſmiſſed the Aſſembly.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:47947:4"/>
            <head>To the Common-Hall of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Fellow Citizens,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>OUr deplorable caſe forceth theſe lines from me, as the danger of the Fathers life made the dumb Son ſpeak: Our City is in danger to be laid again into aſhes, and to become like <hi>Sodom;</hi> wicked Helliſh Inſtruments being hired (as ſome now in Goal have confeſſed) to fire our Houſes, no Man in City or Suburbs can promiſe himſelf ſafety for a night.</p>
            <p>But if vigilance ſhould preſerve our Houſes, our City is in no leſs danger to be depopulated and become deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, its Inhabitants (through decay of Trade and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of poverty) daily forſaking it, between three and four thouſand Houſes lying now deſolate. And its moſt wealthy Traders already refuſe to unite with the City, or to bear a part of, or be concerned in its Government, to ſupport the charge or burden neceſſary to preſerve ſo great a Body of Traders.</p>
            <p>The Credit of our Merchants (which is like the daily food or life-blood of Traders) is ſo miſerably broken and loſt, that Forreigners have with-drawn their Stocks, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted thereupon ſeveral Credits: And no Man knows where to lodge his Money in ſecurity; which muſt make a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of all Trade, proportionable to the diminution of Credit.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:47947:5"/>
Our Merchants Ship paſs in no ſafety, through the potency of the French, who are now Aſpirers to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of the Sea<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, they take our Ships in ſight of our Harbours, under vain pretences, and detain them to clear them in their Admiralties, until the Merchants principles are half ſpent; the crews of Engliſh Sea-men (either by want, or miſeries) forced, or baſely ſeduced to ſerve them; to purchaſe (with our Engliſh bloods) the French Domination by Sea as well as by Land.</p>
            <p>Our Sea-men on whom depends the <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reatneſs, ſafety, and being of our City, are by the former means and ſome other, not only loſt (in great numbers) to this City, and to <hi>England</hi> and our People decreaſed; but are (ignorantly as we will hope) the greateſt Enemies to our City and Kingdom, helping to put the King of <hi>France</hi> into poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Naval power, that our King can never hope to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy his ancient Rights of the Seas Dominion, unleſs by a vaſt expence of Engliſh blood and treaſure.</p>
            <p>Our Artizans, ſuch as Weavers, broad and narrow, Taylors, Hat-makers, Braziers, Shoo-makers, Stockin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, with the Trades attendant reſpectively upon theſe, are ſo miſerably impoveriſhed by the encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſeveral kinds made by the French and others upon us, that their pinching wants have already endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered tumults and ſeditions among ſome of them; (and others have waited in vain with great expence) at the door of His Majeſties Councel, and of His Parliament when ſitting; and how great our danger is, that the poor Artizans hunger may break through our Brick-walls, God alone knows.</p>
            <p>Our Native Manufactures and Commodities (the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47947:5"/>
tranſport whereof ſhould ſupport the City as well as the Kingdom, are ſome forbidden by the French King, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers loaden with inſupportable Impoſitions, ſo debaſed in price that our City and Kingdom, like conſuming Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digals, ſpend in <hi>France</hi> ten times our Engliſh revenue or growth; and if it ſo continue, we muſt become the King of <hi>France</hi> his Slaves for his Gaieties; as the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, more excuſably, yielded themſelves to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> for bread.</p>
            <p>But 'tis not only our Houſes, Trades, Liberties, and Lives, but our Proteſtant Religion; and therein the Souls of us and our Poſterity, are in eminent danger: The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts amongſt us lift up their heads, and ſay their day is near; and the Monaſteries and Convents of Engliſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, openly declare that they ſhall have their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Church-lands and Convents here again, by the French King's aid. And the People are ſo frighted, that ſcarce any Man dares buy Church-lands; And thoſe (that ſay) they will run the Reſque, openly declare two years purchaſe abatement of the price of other Lands, becauſe of the danger of Popery returning.</p>
            <p>And is there any more then the breath of Our King (which may paſs before morning) between that and us; If the preſumptive Heir of the Crown be a Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique, what ſecurity can be given that the King ſhall live eight or nine Moneths? And what ſafety is there provided for the Proteſtant Religion, if a Catholick ſhall poſſeſs the Crown? This being our ſad condition (judge I pray you) what can ſave this City, but Laws fitted by a Parliament to our caſe, in reſpect of every caſe and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance. And may not our caſe, and the Kingdoms too,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47947:6"/>
be deſperate, if we ſhall wait eight or nine Moneths for the Parliaments meeting.</p>
            <p>In the ſence of this, you were lately moved to deſire the Lord Mayor to call a Common Councel, to conſider of an humble Addreſs to His Majeſty, to call a New Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſpeedily, according to the Statutes of the <hi>4th.</hi> of <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>3d.</hi> and the <hi>36th.</hi> of <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>3d.</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a Parliament is to be holden at leaſt every year.</p>
            <p>And the Parliament (laſt held) being ſo Prorogued, that it cannot be convened within a year, as the Statutes require.</p>
            <p>I appeal to your conſciences, whether a more ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and neceſſary motion was ever made? How could a Citizen conſult his Fellows (about preſervation and the redreſs of ſuch grievances) in a more proper place or time then in their greateſt Aſſembly, and Court of greateſt Power?</p>
            <p>How could he move more modeſtly, then to deſire the debate of the matter might be had in their leſſer Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies?) their repreſentatives in Common Councel) how could he be more ſtudious of Peace, then to avoid the doing of any by that numerous Aſſembly, leaſt it might be tumultuous? what can be more innocent, then to pray that the Citizens authority ſhould ſhew their caſe to the King, and their thoughts of the means for their relief.</p>
            <p>Yet ſuch is our miſeries that ſuch a harmleſs need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full motion, is now taken by ſome of the King's Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel to be ſeditious and tumultuous, and your Fellow Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen, and one of your Common Councel, is made a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner for it; Oh how ſad is our Cities caſe! if His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47947:6"/>
do not rectifie ſpeedily a miſtake of dreadful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence.</p>
            <p>Our Common-Hall is the great authority and power in our City, the chief binding Acts in our Cities Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment have alwayes been made by the Common-Hall: And the Acts of the Lord Mayor, Aldermen, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, have been, and may be nulled by the Acts of the Common-Hall; You are inſtead of the whole Body of the Free-men of the City, to whom all our ancient Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Cuſtomes have been confirmed by the great Charter, and by thirty or forty Acts of Parliament.</p>
            <p>But if any of your number may be impriſoned, for men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning the Cities grievances to you, or for moving for an Addreſs to be made by your Common Councel to the King according to Law, you are not more an Aſſembly of any Authority or any uſe.</p>
            <p>Your ancient Liberty before the great Charter, and that alſo ſince, and all the Acts of Parliament are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come void to you, and all your Members, if when you are Aſſembled you muſt be dumb, leaſt the uſe of your Liberty and Faithfulneſs ſend you to a Goal.</p>
            <p>Was it ever heard of before, that a Member of a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Court or Aſſembly was impriſoned for making a lawful motion in it; for praying only that the King might be moved that the Statutes, concerning Parliaments might be put in Execution, when need ſo urgently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it?</p>
            <p>And if it be ſaid, that ſuch a motion was not the work of the day, being deſign'd to chuſe Officers, can any be deceived of their prime and greateſt liberty, to think that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47947:7"/>
leſſer Authority of the City can confine the greater and the higheſt, or to do nothing in their Aſſemblies but what the leſſer pleaſeth, that were to turn the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the City topſie turvie, and to make the power of the Common Hall inferior to t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e will of the Lord Mayor, yet in the preſent caſe leſs power was exerciſed then twelve of the Common Councel have frequently uſed, they having uſuall<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> demanded a Common Councel of the Lord Mayor, and this Common-Hall was only moved to pray it: And had the Aſſembly been only a Common meeting of Engliſh men, upon any occaſion whatever, might not any Man have lawfully diſcourſed, either the Cities or Countreys grievances and dangers among them? And ſhew his opinion, that nothing but a new Parliament ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily called was likely to relieve them, and that it was fit humbly to addreſs to the King for it.</p>
            <p>What can be more modeſt, innocent, and dutiful to His Majeſty? How can he know His Peoples grievances, or the need of a ſpeedy Parliament but by ſuch addreſſes? If ſuch motions are made criminal, the People are bar'd for ſeeking to His Majeſty, for relief from their great and in their moſt extream danger.</p>
            <p>Even that Law made in the <hi>13th.</hi> of this King, for preventing tumults and diſorders in petitioning, however were never reſtrained: Any Man, or number or Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Men from petitioning, or ſoliciting others to peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for any thing agreeable to the Laws eſtabliſhed. But allows the Lord Mayor or Court of Common Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of our City, to addreſs to His Majeſty againſt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eſtabliſhed by Law, in Church or State, thought by them ſo to be grievances; how is it then poſſible that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47947:7"/>
a motion ſhould be criminal, that a Common Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel ſhould addreſs for a Parliament, as the Law requires.</p>
            <p>Know then my Fellow Citizens, if you the Common-Hall of this our City ſhall by your ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence upon this occaſion, agree that your Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers may be lawfully impriſoned, for ſuch innocent, peaceable motions, you muſt bid A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diew not only to all your Rights and Liberties of your City, but to the common liberty of Engliſh men; you muſt and do ſeemingly bleſs thoſe breakers of the great Charter of Engliſh liberty, whom our Anceſtors ſo ſolemnly and dreadfully accurſed; you muſt bid fare-well to the happy ſecu<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity of our Lives, Liberties, and Eſtates, by the Laws, whereby every man ought to be ſafe in his Perſon and Eſtate, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he tranſgreſs the Law: And you muſt yield your ſelves ſubject to the wills of a few Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, and be buried in Goals, or otherwiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroved if you diſpleaſe them, though in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for that which might be demanded as your right.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:47947:8"/>
Good Citizens, let me freely ſay this one word, if there had been no need of a Parliament to be preſently called before this ſtrange invaſion of all your City Liberties, and all Engliſh free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, in the impriſoning one of your Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers without Bail, for doing his duty in ſo great an Aſſembly, this alone were ſufficient reaſon for you, to addreſs to His Majeſty for a ſpeedy Parliament.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:47947:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
