<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Account of the taking of the new-fort in Kinsale by the forces of the Earl of Malborough [sic]</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 3 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26050</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A402</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17817</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11741817</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11741817</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48496</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A26050)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48496)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 3:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Account of the taking of the new-fort in Kinsale by the forces of the Earl of Malborough [sic]</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Y.S.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licens'd, October 25th, 1690. J.F."</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marlborough, John Churchill, --  Duke of, 1650-1722.</term>
               <term>Kinsale (Ireland) --  Siege, 1690.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  War of 1689-1691 --  Campaigns.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="report">
            <pb facs="tcp:48496:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->
            <head>An Account of the Taking of the <hi>New-Fort in Kinſale,</hi> By the Forces of the EARL of MALBOROUGH,</head>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>LICENS'D,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>
                                 <hi>October</hi> 25th 1690.</date>
                           </dateline> 
                           <signed>J. F.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>ON the 10th of <hi>October</hi> our Cannon for Battery arrived in the Camp before <hi>Kinſale,</hi> they having been retarded ſome time by ſix days continued Rains, which very much incommoded the Beſiegers, whereby they were only contented to remain in their Trenches, without making any conſiderable Progreſs. On the 12th a Battery was raiſed and planted, of 12 Demy-cannon, which played all the ſucceeding Night, both upon the Counterſcarp and Fort, and the next Morning the Earl of <hi>Malborough</hi> commanded an Attaque to be made on two ſeveral Places of the Counterſcarp, and after an Hours Aſſault we entred the ſame, putting all we found to the Sword, which were about 40; our Men forthwith made a Lodgment thereon, notwithſtanding the Enemy ſallied out to impede us, but they were driven back with great Loſs. On the 13th and 14th we continued to enlarge the Breach in the <hi>New Fort</hi> and widen our Trenches, diſpoſing all things for a General Aſſault, and thoſe within made a Shew as if they would abide the Storm, the Governour Sir <hi>Edward Scot,</hi> late Deputy Governour of <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> returning Anſwer to the Earl of <hi>Malborough</hi>'s ſecond Summons, That he was reſolved to abide the laſt Extremy: But on <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the 15th, in the Afternoon, juſt as our Men were beginning the Storm, in the midſt of the ſhooting, a Drum beat a Parlee; which Colonel <hi>Fitz-Patrick,</hi> who commanded in chief the Attaque, obſerving, diſcontinued firing, and ſent to know the Demands: Who anſwered, That the Governour de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired that a Colonel and Lieutenant Colonel ſhould be ſent into the Fort, and he would ſend two of the like Quality into the Camp, by way of Hoſtage, in order to treat of ſomething relating to the Fort: which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accordingly done, it was that Evening capitulated and agreed to, and ſigned by the Earl of <hi>Malborough;</hi> Conſidering the Advance of the Seaſon, and the very wet Weather, That the Garriſon, being three bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Regiments, ſhould march out with Bag and Baggage, and the uſual Enſigns of Honours, to have ſeveral Dayes Proviſion, and to be conducted half way to <hi>Limerick;</hi> and that the Morrow, being <hi>Thurſday,</hi> two Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments of our Men ſhould take poſſeſſion of the Gates: And a particular Article was made in favour of the Governour, That he ſhould have the Liberty of three Months to go out of the Kingdom. On <hi>Thurſday,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, our Men took Poſſeſſion, when the aforeſaid Colonel <hi>Fitz-Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick</hi> was ſent Expreſs, by the Earl of <hi>Malborough,</hi> to give his Majeſty an account; and he arrived here the cloſe of the laſt Week, and ſays, That on <hi>Fryday</hi> the Iriſh were to march out, being not above 1000 Men: And that Colonel <hi>Churchil</hi> his Lordſhip's Brother is made Governour thereof.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Y. S.</hi> MDCXC.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
