<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Unity stated the only means to it assign'd and argu'd, together with the motives pressing it : in a sermon before the worshipful Company of Salters, Lond. in St. Swithin's Church, Sept. 1683 / by William Basset ...</title>
            <author>Basset, William, 1644-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26754</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1054</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14462</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12540787</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12540787</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62972</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A26754)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62972)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 304:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Unity stated the only means to it assign'd and argu'd, together with the motives pressing it : in a sermon before the worshipful Company of Salters, Lond. in St. Swithin's Church, Sept. 1683 / by William Basset ...</title>
                  <author>Basset, William, 1644-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 39 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Davis ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Concord --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62972:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62972:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Unity Stated.
The only Means to it
ASSIGN'D and ARGU'D.
TOGETHER
With the Motives preſſing it.
IN A
SERMON
BEFORE THE
Worſhipful Company of <hi>Salters, Lond.</hi>
In St. <hi>Swithin</hi>'s Church, <hi>Sept.</hi> 1683.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM BASSET,</hi> Rector of St. <hi>Swithin, Lond.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Earneſtly recommended to the peruſal of all
DISSENTERS.</p>
            <p>LONDON,
<hi>Printed for</hi> Walter Davis <hi>in</hi> Amen Corner. 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:62972:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62972:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSALM 133. 1.</bibl>
               <q>Behold, how good and joyful a thing it is:
Brethren, to dwell together in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THIS Text is a <hi>Theſis</hi> from whence the other
parts of the <hi>Pſalm</hi> are diſcours'd, but is not it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
deduc'd from any preceding matter. Therefore
without any farther introduction, I ſhall obſerve
in it,</p>
            <p>Firſt, The ſubject matter of it, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity;</hi> and</p>
            <p>Secondly, The duty we owe it, <hi>viz. to dwell toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
in it.</p>
            <p>—dwell together in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</p>
            <p>Which is preſſed upon us by no leſs than five Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;
whereof the</p>
            <p>Firſt, Is drawn from that common Relation we all
have one to another, in that word, <hi>Brethren;</hi> the</p>
            <p>Second, From the advantages of doing ſo, it is
<hi>good;</hi> the</p>
            <p>Third, From the comforts and ſatisfaction that ariſe
from ſuch a Life; it is <hi>joyful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, The whole is brought in with a <hi>Behold,</hi>
which points it out as a thing worthy our notice and
obſervation; <hi>Behold</hi> it is good—</p>
            <p>Fifthly, The manner of its propoſal farther ſpeaks
its excellency; in that particle <hi>How.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:62972:3"/>
Behold, how good and joyful a thing it is: Brethren,
to dwell together in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</p>
            <p>1. The ſubject is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> which falls under a three-fold
Conſideration, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>Judgments, Affections,</hi> and
<hi>Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. There is an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Judgment,</hi> which the great
Apoſtle both deſcribes, and pathetically preſſes on us,
1 <hi>Cor. 1. 10. I beſeech you, Brethren, by the Name of the
Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye all ſpeak the ſame things; that
there be no Diviſions amongſt you, but that ye be all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly
joyned together in the ſame mind, and the ſame judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
To which end, as the Sacred Scriptures have
given us a Form of Prayer, and a Summary of the
Commands; ſo it was the early care of the Church to
make a Collection of the main Articles of Belief, that
we may all <hi>come in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Faith, and knowledge
of the Son of God, to a perfect man.</hi> That there might
be no Jars and Diſcords, but a ſweet conſent of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
Worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the Chriſtian Church. That
our Aſſemblies might be like thoſe of the firſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
who met together <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with one mind, as
well as in one place.</p>
            <p>Though indeed difference of Conſtitution, Education,
and Converſe; difference of parts, both natural, and
acquired; the ambiguity of ſome Phraſes, and Texts
of Scripture; and the many impoſtors Men meet
withal; will no more ſuffer their minds to be all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionate
to the ſame rule, than their Bodies were to
<hi>Procruſtes</hi> his Bed. For we find difference between
even S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and S. <hi>Paul;</hi> and between particular
Churches themſelves. Difference about Moſaic Rites
occaſioned that famous Council, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. Difference
about the time, and manner of the Faſt of Lent, when
the thing was received by all the Churches, as an
Apoſtolical Tradition, had almoſt rent the Church in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62972:3"/>
pieces. Nor did they diſpute only ſome indifferent
things, and the Senſe of Scripture, but even the Canon
it ſelf; for the Epiſtles of S. <hi>James,</hi> the 2. of <hi>Peter;</hi>
the two laſt of <hi>John,</hi> and the <hi>Revelations,</hi> were not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
by all of a long time. No Canons, Councils,
Edicts, or any means imaginable, could ever yet make
all Men of the ſame mind.</p>
            <p>I know the impoſſibility of the thing is made an
Argument againſt all endeavours that way. But for
the ſame reaſon, we ſhould no more preſs Men to
<hi>live Soberly, Righteouſly, and Godly</hi> in this preſent
World, becauſe we find an equal impoſſibility of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging
all Men to theſe indiſpenſable Duties. The
difficulty of the thing rather ſpeaks it a Duty, while
the eaſineſs of the contrary is from its ſutableneſs to
the Looſeneſs, and Debaucheries of Humane Nature.
Nothing is ſo hard to do, as what we ought to do;
and the beſt things are uſually the moſt difficult.
Therefore we ſhould preſs toward this mark; and if we
fall ſhort through weakneſs, or want of better means,
allowances will be made; for God requires no more
than according to what a Man hath: And he uſually
ſecures ſuch that are not willfully wanting to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
from any miſtakes, dangerous to themſelves,
the Church, or Society they live in. But if any out
of idleneſs, humor, or an unreaſonable conceit of their
own light and reaſon, fall into falſe and miſchievous
Opinions, he leaves 'em to their own Inventions, to
make and believe a Lye; without any excuſe or miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,
either of Sin or Puniſhment. The caſe is like
that of <hi>Perfection,</hi> which is ſet as a mark for us all to aim
at; if we honeſtly endeavour, and cannot attain, the
Will is accepted for the Deed: But if we proudly, or
idly neglect the means appointed, what we fall ſhort
of will be imputed as a wilful Sin.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62972:4"/>
Therefore the Scripture is ſo preſſing in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular,
<hi>Eph. 4. 4, 5, 6. There is one Body, one Spirit, one
Hope, one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm, and one God,
and Father of all:</hi> For which reaſons, <hi>v.</hi> 3. We ſhould
keep the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace:</hi> Have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
but one Mind, one Religion, and one Church
amongſt us all. Diverſity of ways is unſuitable to all
theſe Unities. When in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 12. Men pleaded
<hi>I am of Paul, and I of Apollos,</hi> &amp;c. he immediately argues
<hi>v. 13. Is Chriſt divided?</hi> Is there difference and
oppoſition in him; that there is ſuch difference and
oppoſition among his Diſciples? Is the Doctrine he taught
diſſonant from it ſelf; are there any Diſcords in thoſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
Truths, that there is ſo much diverſity and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance
amongſt them that profeſs it? Is the head divided,
that there is ſo much diviſion in the Church, which is
his Body? Certainly difference of Opinion, falſly called
Religion, and oppoſition of Profeſſors, are a reproach to a
God of Unity and Order; and a Scandal to that Goſpel,
which teaches but <hi>one Faith,</hi> but <hi>one Baptiſm,</hi> and but <hi>one God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now becauſe Men muſt be ſuppoſed of themſelves
lyable to deluſions, and miſtakes; therefore the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
hath given us a rule, which (if we follow) will
ſecure us from all material Errors, that may be reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably
judg'd a breach of this Unity; and that is to follow
the Conduct and Cuſtoms of the Church. For when
the Spouſe inquires of our Saviour, where ſhe ſhould
find him; he anſwers, <hi>Cant. 1. 8. Follow the footſteps of
the Flock; and feed thy Kids by the Shepherds Tents.</hi>
And when there was a difference between the Jewiſh,
and Gentile Converts, about Moſaic Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,
which matters the people could no way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine,
nor be ſatisfied by their Teachers, even they
themſelves differing in the ſame points; a Council is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled
at <hi>Jeruſalem, Acts</hi> 15. who decree, that as to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62972:4"/>
the things in Controverſie, they abſtain <hi>from things
ſtrangled, and from blood,</hi> Ver. 20. which implies both
the power of the Church to determine, and the duty of
the People to receive, and abide by ſuch determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.
Our Saviour promiſed the Apoſtles, <hi>Matth. ult.
That he would be with them to the end of the World;</hi> that
is, with <hi>them, viz.</hi> in their own Perſons and Succeſſors;
becauſe they were no otherwiſe to continue to the end
of the World; and becauſe God is not Eſſentially only,
but even Graciouſly preſent with all good men;
therefore this promiſe made to the Apoſtles at the very
time of their receiving their Commiſſion of <hi>Baptizing,</hi>
and <hi>Diſcipling all Nations,</hi> muſt imply ſomething be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
the common grants made to the World; and that
is <hi>with them</hi> in a ſufficient way and manner for the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
Guiding, and Governing his Church: And when
the Canon of Scripture was compleated, the
many differences from age to age, which yet have
pleaded Scripture for their warrant, do abundantly
prove, that the Scripture of itſelf is no more able to
hinder and determine differences, than the Law to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
and decide Controverſies without a Judge; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
there being a promiſe of ſufficient Aids, and the
ſame neceſſity of Councils and Synods in after ages, as
there was then, the Church hath ever look'd upon her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
ſufficiently impowered to follow this pattern in the
<hi>Acts.</hi> Sometimes after this, when St. <hi>Paul, 1 Cor.</hi> 11.
had been preſſing matters of Decency in places and
times of Divine Worſhip, as for men to be Uncover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> he adds, Ver. 16. <hi>If any man ſeem Contentious,
i. e.</hi> not willing to abide by what hath been ſaid, but
is diſpoſed to Cavil, let him know, <hi>we have no ſuch Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom,
neither the Churches of God:</hi> Whence it was the
Apoſtolical practice, and a rule left to all Poſterity, to
correct the Errors and Cavils of particular perſons, by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62972:5"/>
the cuſtom and practice of the Church. Which was ſo
well obſerv'd of old, that as <hi>Euſebius</hi> relates, and <hi>Origen</hi>
ſomewhat to that purpoſe; it was then pleaded,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, theſe things are diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
from the Church; a ſufficient reaſon to reject 'em.
Nor was there leſs than an Anathema added to her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations;
a Curſe upon all them that ſhould refuſe
'em. We find the Church of <hi>Thyatira</hi> was commended,
<hi>Revel.</hi> 2. 19. for her <hi>works, and charity, and ſervice, and faith,
and patience</hi>—but yet, Ver. 20. <hi>I have a few things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
thee;</hi> and why? <hi>becauſe thou ſuffereſt that Woman
Jezebel, which calls herſelf a Propheteſs, to teach and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
my Servants</hi>—Whence that Church had a Power
(and it was her Sin ſhe did not uſe it) of obliging her
Members to ſuch a rule that might have been effectual
for the excluding theſe, and by parity of reaſon, all like
Errors. There was then no plea of Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
and judging every one for himſelf, allowed of;
things that were invented for the promoting Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical
Parties, and the ſerving every one his own hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor
and intereſt. And indeed it is ſo neceſſary to the
ends of Religion, and the very being of a Church, to
have this our rule, that it is therefore become the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
practice of the World. And thoſe who now joyn
in their common crys for Liberty, when time was, would
by no means allow it one to another.</p>
            <p>It is true indeed, if the Church determine and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
upon men, as terms of Communion with her,
things that are apparently repugnant to any proper
and expreſs Text of Scripture; then, and then only,
that queſtion comes honeſtly in, <hi>Whom ſhall we obey, God
or Man?</hi> Which is the only Argument Proteſtants have
to juſtifie their departure from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as
in thoſe inſtances of adoring the Creature, where the
Church commands, and the Scripture forbids. But if
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62972:5"/>
there be no ſuch apparent repugnancy, as there cannot
be in things of an Indifferent Nature, which are the
ground of our Controverſies, becauſe theſe are no
where forbid in Scripture; though a man cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
give a reaſon of all the Churches determinations,
or expoſe every Sophiſtical plea againſt them, yet there
being no ſuch apparent repugnancy, I ought to ſubmit
and follow her Judgment and Authority; in doing
which I follow even God himſelf, who hath made her
my Rule and my Guide. Therefore if a Queſtion
be moved about the Doctrine of the Church, contained
in the 39 Articles; or about her Rites and Ceremonies,
contained in the Canon and Rubrick; it is a grand mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake
in any to think, that if they meet a man, who
cannot prove and juſtifie all thoſe things, that they
may be rejected; for the Church may in all reaſon be
ſuppos'd to ſee more than Individuals may. I receive
'em from her, and it is enough to juſtifie my doing ſo,
that I have no plain Scripture againſt them: It lies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the adverſary, as a Member of this Church, to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie
his diſlike, or elſe to receive 'em too.</p>
            <p>For whatever the Church defines and impoſes, muſt be
either <hi>true, falſe,</hi> or <hi>doubtful:</hi> If <hi>true,</hi> we muſt obey, becauſe
the command falls upon a Lawful matter; elſe we make
the Command to alter the Nature of the thing, and
the Sin to lie in Obedience, which would quickly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb
all Societies, and overthrow every Government
in the World. If <hi>falſe,</hi> then prove it. Which muſt be
either,</p>
            <p>1. by ſome plain demonſtration that may even force
aſſent; or,</p>
            <p>2. By ſome plain and proper Texts of Scripture, which
either expreſly or by undeniable conſequence, forbids
or commands the contrary. For even Murther it ſelf
had not been unlawful, unleſs forbid by the Divine Law,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62972:6"/>
either natural or revealed. <hi>Ergo,</hi> if there be no ſuch
Law againſt the Definitions and Impoſitions of the
Church; there is nothing that can ſpeak them falſe
and unlawful. But if any think there is ſome ſuch
Law, let them produce their inſtances; which we are
certain none can do, becauſe all their attempts that way
have been hitherto baffled; whence ſome have denyed
reaſon in matters of Religion, becauſe they have none
for their own placits: And others fled from Scripture,
as not ſerving their wild Hypotheſes, to downright
<hi>Enthuſiaſm,</hi> and a <hi>Light within.</hi> Or,</p>
            <p>3. By ſhewing us ſuch a perfect rule, as to Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
Worſhip, and all particular things requiſite for
the gathering, governing, and maintaining a Sacred
Society, laid down in Scripture, that there can be no
room left for any Humane Conſtitutions. But becauſe
all parties differ ſo notoriouſly about theſe things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume
there is no ſuch perfect rule at all: And therefore
room left for any ſuch Humane appointments that are
not contrary to the reaſons of Mankind; or to any
part of Divine Revelation. But</p>
            <p>3. If <hi>doubtful,</hi> either in their own natures or circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances;
we ought in Prudence, as well as Duty to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
the Church, rather than our private Sentiments;
elſe we make our ſelves more wiſe and judicious than
the Church it ſelf, which is the very height of Pride;
and likewiſe a charging infinite wiſdom and goodneſs,
in appointing us ſo weak and treacherous a guide.</p>
            <p>Nor do we in this give any farther power to the
Church, than what the very <hi>being</hi> of Councils and Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods
doth ſuppoſe to belong to her. For their being
doth imply their power of determining in doubtful
and controverſial matters, and therefore of giving rules
in ſuch caſes; which rules and determinations the
people conſequently ſtand oblig'd to obſerve: For power
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62972:6"/>
of giving Laws in the Superior doth always infer a Duty
of receiving 'em in the inferior, and you will find that
not only ancient Councils, but the Synod of <hi>Dort</hi> about
the Doctrins of <hi>Arminius,</hi> and that undue Convocation,
which the <hi>Scotch</hi> taught us to call the <hi>Aſſembly of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines,</hi>
which laid aſide the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> and eſtabliſhed the
<hi>Directory,</hi> did very ſmartly evidence their belief, that
they had a power of obliging the people to their own
placits. For beſide the greatneſs of the undertaking,
they were as poſitive in their determinations; and as
ſevere in their injunctions as if they knew themſelves
ſeated in an infalliable Chair. Therefore their allowing
ſuch a power, when it miniſtred to their own paſſions,
and intereſt, doth evidence that they hold the thing not
abſolutely unlawful. From the faults that Diſſenters
now find with Eccleſiaſtical Eſtabliſhments, and that
monſtrous Bill for uniting the Kings Proteſtant Subjects
prepared by a late Houſe of Commons, which deſigned
the turning our Church upſide down, we muſt in all
reaſon conclude, they would make very great, and
peremptory Alterations, was it in their power. Whence
we muſt infer, that according to them themſelves, there is
ſuch a power lodg'd in the Church. Which if they deny,
they conſequentially deny the lawfulneſs of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,
both in its firſt ſettlement before, and in its
Reſtauration, after Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> they condemn the
haughty attempts of their late <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> and even them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
too, who put in their objections againſt ſome little
paſſages in our Liturgy, to the Convocation called ſoon
after his Majeſties return; and likewiſe take from the
Church all power of future Reformation from any
Errors ſhe may ſink into.</p>
            <p>And indeed it is reaſonable to ſuppoſe the Church
knows what is Lawful and Expedient, better than ſome
private Heads. For the Perſons called as Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62972:7"/>
of the whole Church, are uſually the moſt Grave,
Learned, and Judicious; many ſee more than one;
God hath more regards to the whole, whom theſe (due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
called) do repreſent; and in whoſe determinations
the whole are concern'd; than of a part, <hi>viz.</hi> a few ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered
Individuals, who are every one for his own Senſe.
He ſtands in thoſe relations to the whole, which he
doth not to particulars in ſeparation from her, as of an
<hi>Head,</hi> an <hi>Huſband,</hi> &amp;c. and hath promiſed to be <hi>with
them to the end of the World,</hi> as they are the guides and
paſtors of his Flock, and therefore in a more peculiar
manner, than with any private Perſons who are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned
not for all, but every one for his own ſelf. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
though the Church may err, yet it is not by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable
odds, ſo likely ſhe ſhould, as that a few
divided particulars may. Therefore it is my Prudence
as well as Duty, in all things doubtful, to ſubmit to
the Church; elſe I run into an apparent Schiſm, which
nothing can juſtify, but ſome apparent Evil, which I
cannot hold Communion with the Church, but I muſt
be polluted by. Therefore becauſe the Schiſm is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent,
but the Error not; I run into a certain Sin, only
for fear of what ſeems to me a probable Error.</p>
            <p>Now ſuppoſe that by this means I chance to err with
the Church yet I have uſed the means, and kept to my
guide; and conſequently have done the beſt I could to
ſecure my ſelf from Error; and for that reaſon my Sin is
only from weakneſs, in that I could not ſee the Error
of my guide; therefore I ſhall be excuſed <hi>à tanto,</hi> and
forgiven upon a general repentance. But he that errs
againſt the Church hath willfully, becauſe without ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent
reaſon left his guide, and means appointed; or
in caſe the reaſon of his diſſent ſeem'd to him apparent,
yet it had not ſeem'd ſo, had he honeſtly uſed the means
for his better Information; for God is never wanting
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62972:7"/>
to ſuch; but when Men have itching Ears, run after
Novelties, and have no love to the Truth, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 10.
then v. 11. <hi>For this cauſe God ſends 'em ſtrong Deluſions,
that they might believe a Lye.</hi> Therefore all their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent
Errors are the iſſue and Offspring of that cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,
and willful ſeparation; which kind of Sins are not
forgiven, but upon a ſpecial repentance.</p>
            <p>This is a rule ſo plain and ſafe; that certainly it
had never been oppos'd, had not ſome out of politick
ends, and others out of a weak and ſuperſtitious fear of
Popery run into all the extreams from it; unleſs where
intereſt and ſecular advantages may teach an Union:
For Knavery in ſome, and weakneſs in others, hath
gave being to all the parts of Phanaticiſm: The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts
ſhew Reverence in Churches, therefore theſe in
oppoſition will have all places alike: For fear of being
laviſh in their Devotions, they become prophane and
ſlovenly; and out of a dread of Idols, in ſome real, in
others pretended, run into Sacriledg; and in the caſe
before us, <hi>they</hi> are ſaid to believe as the Church believes,
without requiring any farther grounds and motives of
Credibility; therefore <hi>theſe</hi> will believe her in nothing,
but contradict and oppoſe her in all they can; and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
than they will be thought to follow the Church in
any thing, they give up themſelves with as real an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite
faith to ſome Illiterate and Mechanick guide, as
any are thought to do to the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> Which
neceſſarily runs 'em into more Errors, and greater Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions,
than they think by ſuch methods to avoid: For
from hence have ſprung our <hi>Quakers, Seekers, Ranters, Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites,
Famaliſts, Muggletonians, fifth Monarchiſts,</hi> withal
the heards of Sectaries, that have debauched Religion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
that of Heathen <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Turkey.</hi> Therefore to
avoid all damnable Hereſies and Schiſms; and the rove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
extravagancies of Enthyſiaſtick heads, we have no
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62972:8"/>
more certain and ready way, than to follow the
Church, where we have no plain Scripture to the
contrary.</p>
            <p>And indeed it is very obſervable, that all pretenders
to Chriſtianity do hold the neceſſity of ſome guide and
rule in matters of Religion, whereby they may come
to aright underſtanding of Scripture; and thence to a-conſent
and union in every Truth. Thoſe that are for
no Government, nor any Humane meaſures, but for
an abſolute Liberty, as they are Chriſtians, do boaſt of
an extraordinary <hi>Light,</hi> and <hi>Conduct</hi> of <hi>the Spirit;</hi> which
they make to be their guide, that leads 'em into all
Truth. But the monſtrous Errors, beaſtly Practices,
and direct Contradictions theſe people run into, do a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bundantly
convince all obſerving Men, that they have
not that Conduct, which by pretending to ſuch a guide,
they own neceſſary for Chriſtians. Then thoſe who
are for ſome Face of a Church and Government, do like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
grant the neceſſity of ſome helps this way. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<hi>Calvin</hi> will have every one go <hi>ad proprium paſtorem,</hi>
to his own Doctor, or Teacher: Now this Paſtor muſt
be taken either <hi>Independently,</hi> or <hi>Dependently;</hi> if the
former, then he attributes that to Individuals, which
we aſcribe to many: And would have Men give up
themſelves to the guidance of one, when we would
have him follow the Church of God; therefore he is a
thouſand times more likely to be led into Error that way,
than this. But take him dependently, as ſpeaking not
from his own private Light, but according to the
Doctrine, and Judgment of the Church, of which he
is a part, and this is no more than what we are plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
for; unleſs in name only, he meaning an <hi>Aſſembly
of Preſbyters,</hi> we a <hi>Synod of Divines.</hi> Therefore ſince
it is agreed on all hands, that there muſt be ſomething
to guide us to a right underſtanding of Divine things,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62972:8"/>
and keep us within the due bounds of reaſon, and Duty;
and ſecure us from thoſe ſly impoſtures, which debauch
the plaineſt Scriptures, and moſt reaſonable Duties;
let us not follow that, which ſad obſervation tells us,
hath ever proved the Mother of Confuſion; but that
which the Scripture directs us to, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>cuſtoms and
uſages of the Church:</hi> And then there is ſome hope
we may once come to be <hi>joyned together in the ſame mind,
and the ſame judgment,</hi> and as Brethren to <hi>dwell in
<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. There is an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Affections:</hi> When Men live
in mutual Love, and good will. This is an indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable
Duty, which is never ſuperſeded by any difference
of Judgment; for if we cannot agree in every point,
yet however this ſhould be no breach of our Love.
Unity of Affections ſhould always hold, though Unity
of Judgment may not.</p>
            <p>For we are commanded to love without conſideration
of Mens particular Opinions. Thoſe precepts make no
exception of Perſons, but reach to all Men, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
to thoſe that differ from us. S. <hi>John</hi> 1 Ep. 4. 7.
bids us to <hi>love one another,</hi> and that for this reaſon, <hi>viz.</hi>
that <hi>God is love; and every one that loves is born of God.</hi>
Nothing ſpeaks us ſo much his Children, as a Partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation
of Divine Qualifications; but then our love muſt
be like his, who makes the <hi>Sun to ſhine on the Evil, and
the Good:</hi> Elſe we can never be his Children, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.
44, 45. His Love and Mercy, which is over all his
Works, are the rule our Affections muſt walk by.</p>
            <p>It was the old Phariſaical Doctrine our Saviour con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns,
Thou ſhalt <hi>Love thy Neighbour, and hate thine
Enemy.</hi> To confine our Affections, and good Offices,
to our Friends, and them of our own party, is no more
than the Scribes and Phariſees have ever done; and Jews
and Turks at this day do. But Chriſtian charity is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62972:9"/>
more extenſive, and reaches even the poor Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritan.</p>
            <p>Now this was ever the Practice, as well as Duty of
the true Church; her very Cenſures are for <hi>Edification,</hi>
not for <hi>Deſtruction;</hi> all her Acts were lively inſtances
of her Affections. But all the contraries of Love have
conſtantly been the black Brand of falſe pretenders. For
when difference of Opinion draws Men off from the
Church, they ſoon loſe their Affections. When <hi>Donatus</hi>
divides, he confines the Church to <hi>Africa:</hi> And every
Heretick reſtrained her to the narrow bounds of his
own Fraternity. We have ſeen there are no ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural
heats, Unchriſtian Oppoſitions, and Unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
Cenſures, as of one party againſt another, and
of the whole againſt the Church.</p>
            <p>Nor is this an accidental, but a neceſſary conſequence
from the other, being ſo generally conſequent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon,
that you find no exceptions from this rule; if
of perſons, yet not of parties. For Envy, and Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,
is of the very nature of Diviſion: Gathered
Churches naturally teach Men to confine their Love to
their own parties; and live at a diſtance from all others,
as Perſons that are without. Every one is willing to
believe himſelf in the right, and to juſtify his own ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration;
which he cannot do without ſpeaking others
in the wrong. It is true, he is not always the Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick
that ſeparates, but he that gives the occaſion:
Therefore Separatiſts, to throw the odious Imputation
of Schiſm from themſelves, always indeavour to prove
the cauſe to be in the Church: To which end they
<hi>blacken,</hi> and beſpatter her all they can, as guilty of <hi>Will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip,
Superſtition, Idolatry, Lukewarmneſs,</hi> or any
other vile and filthy Imputation. Whence they diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh
themſelves from her by certain Novel names.
The <hi>Turks</hi> in their way delight in nothing ſo much as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62972:9"/>
to be called <hi>Muſulmans,</hi> right Believers, in oppoſition
to the <hi>Perſians,</hi> who agree with 'em in the ſame
impoſture; but differ about the Interpreters of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were an ancient Sect of Hereticks that called
themſelves the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> that is, knowing Men, as the
Etymology of the word imports; which implyed the
Church were a company of poor Fools, that were ſtill
in the Dark. After them others ſtiled themſelves the
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the pure, excluſive of all others: To which
the word <hi>Puritan</hi> afterwards ſucceded. And indeed this
is implyed in the very reaſon of Schiſm; for every
Sect thinks it ſelf purer than the Church it divides from,
otherwiſe it had never divided at all: And from the
ſame Root ſpring thoſe Phariſaical Appellations now in
uſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>good People,</hi> the <hi>ſober Party,</hi> the <hi>People of
the Lord,</hi> and the <hi>true Proteſtants,</hi> as if none were ſuch,
but their own ſelves. Whence S. <hi>Paul 1 Cor.</hi> 3. 3.
As a Polititian, as well as Divine, puts <hi>Envying, Strife,</hi>
and <hi>Diviſion</hi> all together; as Sins Dependent, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductive
one of another. And St. <hi>James ch.</hi> 3. 14. tells
the Jewiſh Converts, who differed from the Gentile
Chriſtians about Moſaic Rites, and Ceremonies; that
they had <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>bitter Zeal;</hi> or as our
Tranſlation renders it, <hi>bitter Envying, and Strife in their
Hearts.</hi> When the ten <hi>Tribes</hi> once ſet up their <hi>Calves</hi>
at <hi>Dan,</hi> and <hi>Bethel;</hi> they never after lived friendly
with <hi>Judah:</hi> Nor had the <hi>Samaritans</hi> any ſooner built
their Temple on mount <hi>Gerizim,</hi> but they quickly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed
all Commerce, and Society with the Jews; and
denyed entertainment to our Saviour, though for no
other reaſon, but becauſe he ſet <hi>his Face as though he
would go to Jeruſalem.</hi> Such are the black and ugly Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring
of difference of Judgment, when it runs Men
into parties: That we muſt indeavour to be of <hi>one Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:62972:10"/>
as the beſt expedient to a being <hi>like-minded</hi> one
towards another.</p>
            <p>3. There is an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Peace:</hi> When Men live ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
together, without being alarum'd by Ryots and Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults;
when they are not branded for <hi>Men worthy,</hi> nor
cloſely deſign'd to a common Slaughter. This flows
neceſſarily from the other, and is imply'd and wrapt up in
it, as the concluſion in its premiſes. For if we muſt
love, then we may not injure and deſtroy; difference
of Judgment ſhould not prove breaches of our Peace;
nor controverſies about Religion kindle the Flames of
an Irreligious War.</p>
            <p>This is a Truth founded in Nature, as well as Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation:
A Primitive State of War is as much a Monſter,
as the <hi>Leviathan</hi> that taught it. For all Men were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive
of this Truth: The Poet makes that a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate,
and Iron Age, ſuch as was not from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning,
wherein there was not
<q>—hoſpes ab hoſpite tutus.</q>
            </p>
            <p>One Friend and Neighbour ſafe by another.</p>
            <p>The Prophets foretold that the Goſpel Diſpenſation
ſhould bring <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Peace,</hi> and everlaſting <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi>
into the World: That then Weapons of Death ſhould
be turn'd to Implements of Husbandry; and Men <hi>ſhould
learn War no more:</hi> That <hi>the Lyon ſhould lie down with
the Lamb; and the Leopard eat Straw like the Ox:</hi> That
all evil Qualities ſhould be transformed into better tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers;
and that nothing ſhould hurt or <hi>deſtroy in all his
Holy Mountain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Jam redit &amp; Virgo, redeunt Saturnia regna:</p>
            <p>Now Juſtice, and the Golden Ages of the World,
return again.</p>
            <p>The Goſpel it ſelf was prefaced with, <hi>On Earth Peace,
good will towards Men.</hi> It deſigns not only the Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciling
us to God, but the Uniting us one to another.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62972:10"/>
It teaches Subjects to <hi>obey every Ordinance of Man;</hi> to
<hi>ſtudy to be quiet,</hi> and <hi>to do every one his own buſineſs.</hi>
It teaches not to revenge our ſelves, but to ſuffer in
ſmaller matters, rather than make a noiſe and diſturbance
in our juſt Vindications, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 39. 40, 41. It declares
that thoſe who live in <hi>Strife</hi> and <hi>Diviſion, are Carnal,
and walk as Men:</hi> 1 Ep. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 3. And therefore ſuch
that have made but little, if any advances in True Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.
In <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 13. we have <hi>Ryoting,</hi> and <hi>Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;
Chambering,</hi> and <hi>Wantonneſs; Strife,</hi> and <hi>Envying;</hi>
put all together as very fit Companions; whence the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation
is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, let <hi>us walk honeſtly
as in the day;</hi> implying that the practice of ſuch things
is a walking diſhoneſtly, and is ſuited to none, but
times of Darkneſs; Intemperance and Incontinence
are made the <hi>Luſts of the Fleſh,</hi> which make Men like
Beaſts; but Pride, Sedition, and Rebellion are the
<hi>filthineſs of the Spirit,</hi> which make 'em like Devils.</p>
            <p>Whence ſome have made it a queſtion and ſcruple
of conſcience, Whether Arms be at all Lawful for
Chriſtians? And it hath been by many determin'd that
none are but <hi>defenſive only:</hi> That is, not of Subjects
againſt Lawful Governours, but of one Society, or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
when invaded againſt another. Therefore thoſe
are new as well as falſe Lights, Monſtrous Saints, Club
Divines, and Bloody Caſuiſts, that ſtudy and adviſe
the perplexing all Humane affairs; and the making
a Society mad: The overturning Crowns and Miters;
and the imbroyling a Nation in Maſſacres and Blood.</p>
            <p>Having thus viewed our Subject, we paſs</p>
            <p>Secondly, To the Duty we owe it, and that is
<q>—to dwell together in it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Which Phraſe ſpeaks it the buſineſs, and conſtant
Companion of our Lives. For we muſt
<q>—dwell in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:62972:11"/>
To which end, the Text preſſes it with many apt
and cogent Arguments: As</p>
            <p>1. From our common Relation; we are <hi>Brethren,</hi> and
therefore ſhould live in Unity.</p>
            <q>—Brethren to dwell together in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</q>
            <p>We are deſcended from the ſame common Parents,
agree in the ſame common Nature; we are all parts of
the ſame Society, or Body Politick, and therefore <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
one of another.</hi> From which Topick the Scripture
often draws Arguments to this purpoſe, as <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 26.
<hi>Sirs, ye are Brethren, why do ye wrong one to another?</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying
that no reaſon can be given, why they ſhould
not agree that ſtand thus related.</p>
            <p>We have all but one Baptiſm, but one Faith, but one
Hope, and but one God: We are all parts of the ſame
Spiritual Building, and make up the Body of Chriſt,
which is the Church: We all live in hope and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation
of that common Inheritance; as we are <hi>Heirs
of God, and Joynt Heirs with Chriſt.</hi> Whence not only
the Scripture, but the firſt Chriſtians called one another
<hi>Brother</hi> and <hi>Siſter.</hi> Therefore our Relation, as well
as common Faith, ſhould oblige us to this Unity. Theſe
were the things that made the Primitive Profeſſors
hold together, as one intire Body, diſtinct from
the reſt of the World. Whence the Gentiles would of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
ſay, as <hi>Tertul.</hi> relates, <hi>See how theſe Chriſtians love
one another!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now our Religion is the ſame, its Rules and Precepts
are no way altered: Our Relation, Dependance, and all
other reaſons of Unity are the ſame too: Therefore the
Duty is as great, and the Obligations as ſtrong as ever.
And conſequently that we do not love and unite as much
as they; is from the ſole reaſon of Mens departure from
the <hi>Holy Commands delivered to 'em.</hi> Our breaches pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
from alterations, not in our Religion, but in the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62972:11"/>
minds of Men. Our rule is ſtill the ſame, but we do
not keep ſo well up to it. Men have not more Light
and Liberty now; but ſtronger Paſſions, and more
ſtubborn Luſts, that debauch 'em into parties, and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.
Where they have learn'd to reckon none Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren
but ſuch who like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> are <hi>Brethren
in Iniquity,</hi> who link'd in the ſame <hi>Aſſociation</hi> are <hi>in
their Anger for killing Men, and in their ſelfwill for digging
down our Wall, viz.</hi> of Strength and Government: While
others, poor Souls, are the wicked of the Earth, who have
forfeited all into the hands of the Saints, and are fit for
nothing but to be <hi>taken and deſtroyed:</hi> Or, as the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociation
words it, to be <hi>purſued to Deſtruction.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
ſeeing <hi>Hell</hi> hath taught Men, not only to enervate
this Argument of Heaven; but to turn it to the ends
of Deſtruction, inſtead of Edification, I ſhall inquire
what ſtrength there is in the next Argument, and that
is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, The advantages of doing ſo;</hi> it is good.—Behold
how good it is: Brethren to dwell together
in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</p>
            <p>For it is agreeable to our reaſons, and deſirable from
its own native worth, and Beauty: And therefore exacts
Praiſes from every Tongue, even from them, whoſe
private intereſts and humours lead 'em to deſtroy it.
Nor is it an unprofitable good, like ſome mere Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of the Univerſe, which ſerve only to pleaſe the
Eye, and delight the Mind; and give a pleaſant Theme
for the Orator, and Hiſtorian to play upon. Nor is
it like the pure Poſitives under the Law, which had no
intrinſick or relative good in 'em, but ſtood purely In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances
of obedience. For Unity brings Profit wherever
it comes, and derives a ſweet Proſperity to all publick
and private affairs of Men. It gives a free Commerce
and Communication of every good thing from one part
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62972:12"/>
of a Society to another. Like a due Circulation of
the Blood, it maintains every Member in health, and
Vigor; and inables 'em to perform their diſtinct and
proper Offices. Whence a very ſenſible increaſe muſt
neceſſarily ariſe to the whole: Which made the Ancients
to obſerve, that by <hi>Concord</hi> ſmall and inconſiderable
things ſoon wax great, and make a figure in the World.
For which cauſe the Founders of Cities and Nations
have endeavoured to contrive ſuch Laws that might
ſatisfy the minds, and give ſecurity to the Perſons, and
properties of Men; whence a laſting Unity might ariſe
as the ſureſt Foundation of outward greatneſs.</p>
            <p>Unity ſeldom wears the Willow Garland, but is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally
Crowned with Bleſſings and Succeſs; as our
own Hiſtories and Obſervation may evince: For Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
and Churches when waſted by War and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions
have ever found this, like the Vernal Sun, that
gives new Life and Vigor to the World; and makes
'em like the Hills of <hi>Sion,</hi> to laugh and ſing.</p>
            <p>Whereas Variance and Diviſions, like boding Owls
and Ravens, have ever proved unlucky both to Church
and State.</p>
            <p>For Controverſies about Religion have many times
almoſt deſtroyed Religion itſelf: When that zeal which
ſhould have been imploy'd in the duties owing to God
and Man, hath waſted itſelf in diſputes, and bitter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives.
Whence ſuch times have uſually heightned
mens Paſſions, but not their Graces; and made many
Combatants, but few Chriſtians. Till in fine, Religion
torn into numerous Fractions, hath, like the Eccho, pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
into little but a voice; and mens Chriſtianity been
concluded from their being on this, or the other ſide.
And whereas it is obſerved, that Divine Judgments have
uſually fallen upon the Church, when Diviſion hath
made her mad; we muſt conſider this not ſolely as an
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62972:12"/>
exertion of Divine Power and Juſtice, but alſo as the
Natural effect of this Sin: For God uſually puniſhes Sin
with thoſe Sufferings which are the Natural reſults and
neceſſary conſequences of 'em: He cloaths the Sluggard
in Rags, brings the Prodigal to a Morſel of Bread; and
fills thoſe with Confuſions, and every evil work, that
delight in breaking the Churches Order and Peace.
Therefore where we ſee a Divided, we muſt expect an
Afflicted people; not only becauſe God hath declared
his wrath from Heaven againſt ſuch things, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
by reaſon the ſame Diviſions have a Natural ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency
to divers kinds of miſchief.</p>
            <p>Nor hath Diviſion a leſs malignant influence on the
State; for it hath brought deſolation into almoſt eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
corner of the World, as may be proved by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction
of particulars from almoſt all parts of it an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently
known. It not only checks Trade in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,
but withdraws it from many particulars; and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
other ways oppreſſes and injures 'em; which muſt
be a conſiderable weakning to the whole: It ſometimes
neceſſitates Governours to act above and beyond Law,
for the preſervation of themſelves and Government;
and oftentimes hath given up the whole into Foreign
hands. Whence it was a Maxim, or concluſion from
reaſon, laid down by Antient Politicians, <hi>Divide and
Conquer.</hi> The <hi>Malmsbury</hi> Philoſophy, which preſumes
a ſtate of War to have been the Primitive condition of
Mankind, doth yet plead that mutual preſervation was
the Origin of all Societies; which is a plain conceſſion
that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> is the beſt means of mutual preſervation;
and conſequently Diviſion which runs men firſt into
Parties, and then into Oppoſition, is the ready way to
ruin. Our Saviour tells us, that <hi>an Houſe, a City, or</hi> a
<hi>Kingdom divided againſt itſelf, cannot ſtand, but is brought
to deſolation:</hi> Now he lays down this as a Medium to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62972:13"/>
prove ſomething farther, <hi>viz.</hi> that a Diviſion in the
Kingdom of Darkneſs will deſtroy that Kingdom; and
becauſe the thing that proves muſt be the <hi>notius,</hi> or bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
known than that which is proved; therefore that
ſuch Diviſion will deſtroy Kingdoms and Societies of
Men, muſt be very well known and eaſily granted
even in thoſe Ages of the World: Elſe we muſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
him to be proving <hi>ignotum per ignotum,</hi> which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
but weakneſs or fallacy can offer. It is therefore
the maddeſt thing in the World for Men to dream of
keeping off a ruine by the apteſt means and methods
to let it in. To ſecure their <hi>Perſons, Properties</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi>
by thoſe very courſes which all Hiſtories and
Obſervation tell us, have been Deſtructive to 'em all!
Which is no leſs mad than to break down our Banks,
to the end we may keep out the Sea: Or to take Poyſon
for recovery of our Health.</p>
            <p>And certainly our Circumſtances make the madneſs
and wonder greater than ever: Becauſe</p>
            <p>1. The parties divided from, and againſt the Church,
are ſo many, ſo irreconcilable, and ſo hot one againſt
another; that if we may ſuppoſe they had the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
again in their own hands; they could not live
comparably ſo happy as under preſent Eſtabliſhments.
For they muſt then either fall under ſome one party,
or live as they can in a Medly together: If the former,
they cannot but know they muſt expect ſeverer Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations
than from the preſent Government: If the
latter, they muſt live in continual Feuds, and conteſts,
every one for his own way; and becauſe nothing is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed,
and they know not what may; they muſt
conſequentially ſtand in continual uncertainties, both
as to Property and Religion; which muſt neceſſarily
make 'em as reſtleſs as under late Uſurpations; when
the Nation was vexed and harraſs'd; oppreſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62972:13"/>
beyond the example of all Ages. Which made
<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome who were the firſt beginners of our Calamities,
to wheel about for a Royal Intereſt, only as the leſſer
Evil. And becauſe</p>
            <p>2. Popery (as they daily tell us) is cloſely watching
an opportunity of obtaining amongſt us: Which in all
Humane reaſon it can never do, could we ſtand United
together. But by Diviſion they make a Gap and Lane
for its eaſy Advance. For thoſe that have ſeen, or
have otherwiſe any deep impreſſions from the Miſeries
of the late Rebellion, that nauſeate the damn'd Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies
Violence and Blood of thoſe days; finding <hi>Diviſions</hi>
ready to repeat the ſame Miſeries; that <hi>Hanibal</hi> was
ready again to enter our Gates; and that the <hi>Stirs,</hi> as the
<hi>L. R.</hi> in his laſt Papers diminutively calls 'em, were
juſt ready to devour us; they will ſet themſelves intirely
to the oppoſing this Evil; what little regards ſoever
they may have to the other. Nor can we in reaſon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
but that Men will the moſt oppoſe that, which is
the neareſt Evil, hath the moſt hands and means to
promote it; and which, like an <hi>Hurricane</hi> blown up
from Hell, hath deſtroyed not <hi>Job</hi>'s Houſe and Children
only; but born down even all before it. There is
therefore no ſuch Enemy, both to Religion and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
as Dividers are. A Truth ſo plain; that was
it not, that the Devil ows Men a ſhame; or that God
is pleas'd to puniſh 'em by their own inventions: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
their Choice to become their Ruine; we cannot
imagine any Man ſhould be ſo blind as not to ſee, at
leaſt in this their day,</p>
            <p>—<hi>How</hi> good <hi>it is for</hi> Brethren to dwell together
in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</p>
            <p>3. It is farther preſſed from the Comforts and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions
that ariſe from ſuch a Life: For it is
<hi>joyful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:62972:14"/>
—Behold how good and joyful a thing it is to dwell
in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Balaam Numb.</hi> 24. 2. ſaw <hi>Iſrael abiding in his
Tents, according to their tribes,</hi> ſo great a Body, and
yet in ſuch admirable Unity and Order, he breaks
forth into a kind of rapture, v. 5. <hi>How goodly are thy
Tents, O Jacob, and thy Tabernacles O</hi> Iſrael? Whence
he proceeds to the higheſt deſcription of their future
Greatneſs and Glory, v. 8, 9. <hi>He ſhall eat up the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi>
&amp;c. as if that ſight had moved him beyond his
former capacities. It is certain indeed that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
ſpoke <hi>as they were moved of God:</hi> Yet it was
uſually by the advantages of ſome external Object,
either real or viſionary: Thus we read of <hi>Daniel</hi>'s four
Beaſts, repreſenting the four chief Empires of the
World. <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s Roll, and his boiling Pot, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting
the matter they had to ſpeak. So when
<hi>Balaam</hi> ſaw <hi>Iſrael</hi> in his Tents, in Unity and Order,
which was it ſelf a rational Prediction, or promiſing
ſign of their future Greatneſs; it follows in the next
words, the <hi>Spirit of the Lord came upon him,</hi> and he
<hi>took up his parable and ſaid—he ſhall eat up the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi>
&amp;c.—But Ryots, Tumults, and unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
Hurries would have been an ill riſe for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
to have taken up his parable from. Had he ſeen
that vaſt Body crumbled into little parties, agreeing
in nothing but Oppoſitions; had he ſeen them with
Clubs and Staves aſſaulting the Tents of their Prince, and
the Prieſt. And ſcraming the Names of <hi>Corah, Dathan,
Abiram, Abſolom, Achitophel,</hi> &amp;c. our Seditious Bonfires;
a ſight ſo ugly, and the probable iſſues ſo fatal; we may
expect that either he would have ſung us another Song
or that the Aſs might once again have open'd his Mouth;
and have <hi>reproved</hi> the <hi>madneſs of the Prophet</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What more unmanly than that <hi>Aſian</hi> Ryot, <hi>Acts</hi> 23. 32.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62972:14"/>
Where the whole City was moved, but few could tell
what any would have? Or that in <hi>Acts</hi> 23. 10. where
S. <hi>Paul</hi> was like to have been torn in pieces by contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
parties? What more unſeemly, and nauſeous a ſight,
than the Mobile in <hi>Acts 22. 22, 23. caſting off their Coats, and
throwing duſt in the Air, and crying</hi> againſt S. <hi>Paul, away
with ſuch a Fellow from the earth, it is not fit that he ſhould
live?</hi> Such meetings are like herds of wild Beaſts, all
noiſe, but no order: Paſſion enough, but no reaſon, where
every one is ready to uſe his Paw as well as his Tongue.
Such Aſſemblies make Halls and Cities like <hi>Bedlam,</hi> where
all differ in noiſe and actions; and agree in nothing but
this, that they all are mad. Theſe ſights make ugly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions
on all ſober minds, and leave nothing but nauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs
and averſation behind them.</p>
            <p>While Unity hath beauty and comelineſs in it; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords
a delight, and complacency to every Eye. The
World hath not an Object more ſatisfactory and pleaſant
than a body of Men without noiſe and clamor, acting U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niformly
in their places, and driving up in a regular courſe
to their ſeveral ends. This is a ſpectacle ſo worthy of Men,
that S. <hi>Paul</hi> tells his <hi>Coloſſians</hi> ch. 2. 5. <hi>That he rejoyced,
beholding their Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is it more pleaſant in the Object, than joyful
in the effects, and conſequences: For while paſſionate
heats and giddy motions, run Men beyond Reaſon and
Law; make their Houſes too hot, and their Countries too
narrow for 'em; and perhaps bring 'em by weeping croſs
to their long homes: Unity and orderly Methods keep
'em Maſters of their Paſſions, ſecure 'em from Scaffolds
and Gibbets; and inable 'em to ſit under their Vines
and Fig-trees, where none can make 'em afraid. While
deſigning Heads fill'd with Cares and Fears; the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
Companions of unlawful Policies; vexed with
Delays and Diſapointments; hag'd by a Guilty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62972:15"/>
and night-mared with the Griping Jealouſies of
Bloody Fates and Vengeance; loſe the ſweetneſs of
all paſt, and preſent Comforts. Thoſe that live in Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
as they are Men and Chriſtians, fear no evil becauſe
they deſign and do none; and have leiſure not only to
guſt and reliſh every Mercy; but alſo to collect all the
ſcatter'd Bleſſings of their Lives into one Body, and at
every view repeat the pleaſure they perceiv'd from their
firſt Injoyment.</p>
            <p>Such void of fear, and ſecure from dangers, reflect
upon their Lives paſt, and joyfully ſee 'em ſullyed with no
Strife and Contention; no Schiſms and Seditions;
but ſo conform'd to their Lord and Maſter, that no
provocations, diſtracted times, and common deluſions
have been able to draw 'em to Factious Clubs and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious
Meetings; or at any time to have their Voice
heard in the Streets; in any <hi>common Rout deſigning
Shows or Bon-fires.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lives ſo ſuited to the Nature, and Intendments of
the Goſpel, as well as to that, the Saints do lead in
Heaven, that the Pleaſure and Satisfactions ariſing from
ſuch Contemplations, inable the Man to ſay of Unity,
as <hi>Solomon</hi> of <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> viz. that <hi>her ways are ways of
Pleaſantneſs, and all her paths are Peace: Length of days
are in her right Hand, and in her left Riches and Honours.</hi>
Whence it is no wonder that in the</p>
            <p>Fourth place we have a <hi>behold</hi> fixt upon it,
<q>—Behold it is good.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Which points out this Unity as a ſubject worthy our
Conſideration and Practice. For this word is ſeldom
uſed but in theſe two caſes, <hi>viz.</hi> where the matter is
either ſtrong, and ſomewhat ſurpriſing; or elſe of
more than ordinary importance, as it is in this place,
therefore its buſineſs is to turn our thoughts to ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
and worthy a Subject.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:62972:15"/>
            <q>—Behold it is good,</q>
            <p>Which Fifthly, Is farther recommended by the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
of its propoſal in that particle <hi>How;</hi>
               <q>—Behold how good and joyful a thing <hi>it is.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Such indefinite ways of expreſſion hint the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs
of the thing to be ſo incomparable, that we can
receive due and adequate thoughts of it from nothing
elſe but our own experience; therefore he doth not
ſay, but bids us taſte and ſee <hi>how good and joyful it is
to live in Unity?</hi> For who would expect any thing
farther, where the Author ſeems ſwallow'd up in the
Contemplation of ſo excellent a Life? And at a loſs
how to expreſs his large and ſublime Conceptions of it!
But at length he recovers himſelf, and tells v. 2. that
<hi>it is like the precious Ointment upon the Head, that ran
down upon the Beard: Even to Aarons Beard, and went
down to the Skirts of his Cloathing.</hi> A <hi>precious Ointment;</hi>
ſuch as was made by Divine appointment, ſuch as was
ſweet as Incenſe, and ſuch as was made Holy by God
himſelf, in that it was appropriate to ſuch a peculiar
uſe. Even ſuch is Unity, <hi>ſo</hi> Precious, <hi>ſo</hi> Sweet, <hi>ſo</hi>
Holy and therefore <hi>ſo</hi> acceptable in the ſight of God!
Then v. 3, 4. <hi>Like as the Dew of</hi> Hermon: <hi>Which fell
upon the Hill of</hi> Sion. <hi>For there the Lord promiſed his
Bleſſing: And Life for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now pleaſure and profit are the grand ends and
motives of all Humane Actions; without which all
labours and diligence would quickly ceaſe, and ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
attractives are theſe; that we can purſue the little
particles of either, through more than the common
hazards of Humane Life. Therefore it muſt needs
ſtand a reproach to them for ever; whom both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
and in ſuch excelling degrees too, cannot
oblige to this Unity, which as the Gentiles ſaid of Virtue,
is a reward to it ſelf. A Life which every wiſe and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62972:16"/>
conſiderate Man would chooſe, had it no other recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence,
but the preſent advantages and ſatisfactions that
ariſe from it.</p>
            <p>But becauſe many will commend Unity, and own
it a neceſſary Duty for all Chriſtians to agree together;
but plead the fault of Diviſion is not in them, but in the
Government, which requires their Union upon thoſe
terms they cannot cloſe with: I will therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</p>
            <p>1. What is the ſenſe of their chief Authors and
Leaders in this particular; and</p>
            <p>2. Whether we may in charity judge their Diviſion
from us to proceed really from any ſcruple of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
            <p>1. Mr. <hi>Vines</hi> who was an hot Man in the late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion,
and at the Treaty at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge againſt the King,</hi>
by which you muſt judge him no Church-man, in his
Sermons upon the Sacrament of the Lords Supper,
Printed after his Death, undertakes to prove that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
can juſtify a Separation from a True Church,
leſs than flat Idolatry: And gives a challenge to any
Man to give an inſtance in Scripture to the contrary:
For all Separation is either Local, or Moral; now a Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
Separation is required from Idolatrous Temples,
and Heathen Mixtures, as in 2 <hi>Cor. 6. 16. What Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
hath the Temple of God with Idols?</hi> For you Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
are his Temples both by Dedication in Baptiſm:
and alſo by the Gifts and Graces of the Spirit dwelling
in you: Therefore v. 17. <hi>Come out from amongſt 'em, and
be ye ſeparate:</hi> But we have neither Precept, nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
of any allowed ſeparation from a Chriſtian
Church, unleſs a <hi>Moral</hi> only. He argues from the
Church of <hi>Thyatira, Revel.</hi> 2. Which ſuffered the falſe
Prophets to ſeduce <hi>his People to commit Fornication, and
to eat things Sacrificed to Idols;</hi> which were great Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62972:16"/>
but yet v. 24, 25. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon you that are pure,
viz.</hi> from theſe things, <hi>I put no other burthen but this,
that which you have already, hold faſt till</hi> I <hi>come.</hi> Here
is not a word of ſeparation locally, <hi>viz.</hi> the leaving
their Aſſemblies, but morally only, <hi>viz.</hi> from her
Sins.</p>
            <p>If you conſult Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> on <hi>Jude</hi> v. 19. <hi>ſeparating
themſelves,</hi> where he tells you what a Church you may,
and what an one you may not ſeparate from; there is
nothing that can juſtify, but rather condemn his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
ſeparation. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> publiſhed a piece <hi>An. Dom.</hi>
1670. Intituled the <hi>Cure of Church-Diviſion, or Directions
for weak Chriſtians to keep them from being Dividers or
Troublers of the Church.</hi> Dr. <hi>Bryan</hi> in his Sermons
Printed <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 70. and pag. 328. preſſes all parties
to live free from <hi>any appearance of Contention, either in
Church or State:</hi> They that do ſo having the <hi>Brand of
Graceleſs Men ſet upon 'em by the Holy Ghoſt. Jud.</hi> 8, 11, 12.
In the next page every Man that dwells in God,
<hi>is of a Peaceable diſpoſition: Quiet in the Land. Pſal.</hi> 35. 20.
The Ancient <hi>Puritans</hi> were all for a Lay-Communion;
and ſmartly oppoſed the <hi>Browniſts,</hi> now Independents,
for the deſperate breaches they made in the Church:
And even <hi>Brightman</hi> himſelf, that extravagant Expoſitor,
on <hi>Revel. 3. 20. Behold, I ſtand at the Door and knock</hi>—ſaith
that thoſe who are aſham'd to ſit down in that
Church, where Chriſt is not aſham'd to knock by his
Word and Ordinances, do make themſelves <hi>purer than
Chriſt himſelf.</hi> We have a Cloud of Witneſſes to this
point in a late piece for <hi>Lay-Communion;</hi> therefore I ſhall
only give you part of an Epiſtle to a Book Intituled <hi>the
Saints Care of Church Communion.</hi> Printed <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1671.
By Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> a late Nonconformiſt.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> of old did account it their <hi>glory,</hi> that
they did not <hi>ſeparate,</hi> nor any way <hi>encourage</hi> or <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance,</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:62972:17"/>
but every way <hi>diſown</hi> and <hi>oppoſe</hi> the <hi>Separatiſt.</hi>
The Judicious <hi>Ball</hi> affirms, That as <hi>Hannibal ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
there was not one in the Enemies Camp called</hi> Giſco:
<hi>ſo there was not ſo much as one of the godly Miniſters which
ſuffered in</hi> England <hi>about the Diſcipline, that might be
deſervedly called</hi> Browniſt; <hi>not a Nonconformiſt could be
found a Separatiſt;</hi> I wiſh we could at this day ſay the
ſame thing, with the ſame truth and confidence. But
alas! How many whoſe Preaching and Writings have
been ſtrong and ſervent againſt <hi>Separation,</hi> do at this
day make the <hi>Independents</hi> inſult, <hi>Your Presbyters
leave the publick Aſſemblies, have gathered Churches, in
which they miniſter the whole ſolemn Worſhip of God;</hi> and
not contented with <hi>Domeſtick Liberty,</hi> have occaſioned
the <hi>Laws,</hi> and <hi>execution</hi> thereof, to confound them,
with the <hi>ſevereſt Separatiſts,</hi> and moſt vile Sects, that
ever troubled the <hi>Churches Order,</hi> or the <hi>Nations Peace?
Pudeat haec dici potuiſſe, &amp; non potuiſſe refelli.</hi> I did in
an Epiſtle publiſhed many years ſince, ſollicite the
<hi>ſerious Nonconformiſts,</hi> in this day of temptation, to
<hi>kick off that Baſtard-Brood of Separatiſts</hi> which <hi>hang on
them,</hi> and are by their Enemies <hi>laid at their door,</hi> as
their genuine <hi>off-ſpring.</hi> But I have not herein prevailed;
but, to the anguiſh of my Soul, ſeen Schiſm ſo acceptable
to good men, that ſcarce any called <hi>Nonconformiſt</hi> dare
once reprove it. In ſenſe whereof, and in conſcience
of duty, I could not keep ſilence, but by Pulpit and
Preſs ſtand up to teſtifie againſt this common growing
evil, eating out <hi>Love,</hi> the <hi>Heart</hi> of Piety, the <hi>Power</hi>
of Truth, and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of the Church.</p>
               <p>I expect the <hi>Committee of Diſcretion</hi> (at whoſe Barr
I have (on this very cauſe) ſtood more than twenty
years without conviction) to revive againſt Me, and
this Work, their old Charge; <hi>however the thing is good,
the Doctrine is truth, the diſcovery thereof be duty; yet
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62972:17"/>
it is done</hi> unſeaſonably, <hi>and out of time.</hi> I have been
often arraigned for <hi>miſſing the ſeaſon;</hi> yet no man hath
ſet me a <hi>Dial</hi> by which to determine the time of my
Miniſterial actings: In the year 1655, my <hi>Saints Zeal
againſt ſinful Altars,</hi> was out of ſeaſon: In 1661, my
<hi>Reformation not Separation,</hi> was out of ſeaſon. It is now
1670, and yet the <hi>ſeaſon</hi> of this duty is not ſeen.
When will this <hi>ſeaſon</hi> be, wherein I may appear againſt
Schiſm? When I am in the Grave (towards which I
haſten) where there is no mention of God, nor plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the cauſe of his Church? If I know any thing of
the Mind of the <hi>God of Time,</hi> and may compare Watches
with the faithful Watch-men of God's Houſe, the <hi>ſeaſon
of Miniſterial reproof,</hi> is the <hi>ſeaſon</hi> of <hi>ſin's prevalency:</hi>
When the Believers are in danger to be <hi>beguiled from
the ſimplicity of the Goſpel,</hi> was <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>ſeaſon</hi> to cry out,
<hi>Take heed of Angels of light,</hi> and <hi>falſe Apoſtles.</hi> When
<hi>Schiſms in the Church</hi> (not ſo dangerous and deadly as
Schiſms from the Church) <hi>diſtracted Corinth,</hi> was the
Apoſtles time to cry out, <hi>Ye are carnal, ye are not ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual.</hi>
When <hi>Peter</hi> turned <hi>Separatiſt,</hi> and drew <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi>
into the Schiſm, was <hi>Paul</hi>'s ſeaſon to <hi>withſtand
him to the face, becauſe he was to be blamed.</hi> What ſhall
I ſay of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> who timed their <hi>Propheſies</hi> by
the <hi>prevalency</hi> of Iſrael's defection: And our Saviour,
who choſe the <hi>ſeaſon</hi> to explain the Law, <hi>when</hi> the
Scribes and Phariſees had <hi>made the word of God of none
effect by their Traditions.</hi> Auſtin's <hi>ſeaſon</hi> to preach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<hi>Drunkenneſs,</hi> was when, and as long as the men
of <hi>Hippo</hi> lived <hi>Drunkards.</hi> And to appear againſt <hi>Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi>
when, and as long as the <hi>Donatiſt's Schiſm pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed</hi>
in the Chriſtian World. <hi>Luther</hi>'s <hi>ſeaſon</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs
his zeal againſt the <hi>German Anabaptiſts,</hi> and <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines,</hi>
was <hi>when</hi> they expoſed his Reformation to
<hi>reproach. Ball, Hilderſham, Hind, Nicols,</hi> and other
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62972:18"/>
Nonconformiſt's <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> to ſpeak and write againſt <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration,</hi>
was when the Browniſt's <hi>Non-communion</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
the reproach of their <hi>Non-conformity.</hi> If theſe
may not guide me, lend me your Watches; if they go
not falſe, I will ſet mine by them.</p>
               <p>In anſwer to this charge of miſſing the ſeaſon of
Truth and Duty, I have many years ſince appealed to
Presbyters, Whether men <hi>wiſely ſerving God's Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
and ſtudious to do God and his Church proper and
apt ſervice, muſt not judg the time of witneſſing corruptions</hi>
circa cultum publicum, <hi>will not warrant Non-communion
and Separation from a true Church,</hi> to be; <hi>then, when,
that</hi> is acted on <hi>this</hi> ground and reaſon? Till that be
argued and over-rul'd, I will plead no more to this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditement;
and that I expect not to be, till Chriſt do
come to Judgment.</p>
               <p>Secondly: But you will be ready to complain, That
I am <hi>too rigid, too ſevere</hi> and <hi>bitter againſt the</hi> Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
Congregationaliſt's, <hi>who undoubtedly are very good
men.</hi> To this I ſay:</p>
               <p>1. The Goodneſs of the men be to <hi>themſelves:</hi> But
remember, The <hi>Goodneſs of the men</hi> is the common
bait which hideth the Hook of <hi>Impoſture</hi> and <hi>Seduction,</hi>
by which the ſimple are beguiled. <hi>Angels of Light,
Men like the Apoſtles of Chriſt,</hi> Pious <hi>Pelagius,</hi> Devout
and Holy <hi>Novatius,</hi> have been the <hi>perverters of Truth,</hi>
and <hi>ſubverters of the Churches Peace and Order.</hi> And be
the men never ſo good, the ſevere <hi>reproof</hi> of their <hi>vile
Opinions,</hi> and <hi>ſinful Practices,</hi> muſt not be ſuperſeded
by that <hi>Goodneſs</hi> which is in them.</p>
               <p>2. Be the men as good as they will, if by their fruits
we may know them, we muſt be free to affirm, they
have been <hi>no good Plants in the Lord's Garden.</hi> To paſs
by the Narrative of their Practices beyond the Seas,
collected by the <hi>Anti-apologiſt,</hi> and improved by
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62972:18"/>
Mr. <hi>Robert Baylie,</hi> beyond the poſſibility of denial or
contradiction. Should we but declare their <hi>Paganizing
all England,</hi> the <hi>Confuſions</hi> in Church, and <hi>Commotions</hi>
in Commonwealth, which our Eyes have ſeen acted by,
and this preſent Age muſt atteſt to have been the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy
horrid <hi>Generation-work of theſe good men;</hi> you muſt
needs ſay, <hi>The ſevereſt rebuke of them</hi> muſt needs be
<hi>too gentle.</hi> But I will forbear to recite the Acts which
all of this Age muſt needs remember: Yet when I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
the <hi>ſinfulneſs</hi> of Schiſm, the <hi>ſpeciality</hi> of their
<hi>Schiſm,</hi> exceeding that of the <hi>rigid Browniſts;</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>churching
not only <hi>England,</hi> but all the <hi>Reformed
Churches,</hi> at one blow; meritoriouſly, by their <hi>Apoſtacy;</hi>
and legally, by the <hi>Law</hi> of their <hi>rejection:</hi> And remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
their <hi>precipitancy,</hi> if I muſt not ſay <hi>perfidy,</hi> in fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
into it when the <hi>pretended occaſions of ſtumbling</hi> were
out of their way, and they were <hi>ſolemnly engaged againſt
Schiſm,</hi> and this <hi>very Schiſm:</hi> I cannot but ſee much
reaſon to maintain a <hi>conſtant</hi> and <hi>ſevere zeal</hi> againſt
them; and the rather, for that (we have obſerved it,
we know the verity of it) the <hi>ſobriety, moderation,</hi>
and <hi>indulgent ſilence,</hi> of their ſoft and over-mild Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
hath been the <hi>nouriſhment, guard,</hi> and <hi>advantage</hi>
of their Schiſm: They, as (their Progenitors) the
<hi>Donatiſts,</hi> did at firſt ſtudy nothing more than by the
<hi>cry of Moderation, Moderation towards Brethren</hi> and
<hi>Good men,</hi> to charm the <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>Duty</hi> of thoſe who
ought to have diſcovered this <hi>Panther's Face,</hi> before
they had <hi>broken in,</hi> and <hi>made havock of the Church of
God,</hi> as at this day they do, neceſſitating more <hi>loud
cryes,</hi> and <hi>ſevere reproofs</hi> againſt them, than ever; for
that they have prevailed ſo far, as to <hi>ſeduce Multitudes,</hi>
and <hi>confound endeavours for Reformation,</hi> with their
<hi>groundleſs Separation;</hi> and, with the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> want
nothing but opportunity to make their <hi>Schiſm domineer</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:62972:19"/>
through the World, beyond the power of Magiſtratical
cohibition.</p>
               <p>The ſimple Godly have a long time been deluded
with a pretence, <hi>That there is no great difference between
them and their angry Brethren; it is but a matter of
Diſcipline, there is nothing in their Practice fundamentally
erroneous, or inconſiſtent with ſalvation.</hi> And ſcarce
any man is found ſo faithful, as to detect the falſehood
of this Plea: Let me tell you wherein the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie
only concerneth <hi>matters of Diſcipline:</hi> I have
often ſaid it, and now ſay it aloud; Though I know
the <hi>Diſcipline</hi> they pretend to, to be <hi>confuſed, diſorderly,</hi>
and <hi>miſchievous to the Church;</hi> neither found in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
nor right Reaſon or Polity; yet let them own
the <hi>being</hi> and <hi>truth</hi> of the Church, the <hi>ſalvability of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration</hi>
in it; and in <hi>union</hi> with the Church, in any
particular, orderly diſtributed Aſſembly, make their
<hi>Diſcipline practicable</hi> if they can; they ſhall not be by
me diſturbed, till they have experienced the evill there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
in its Effects. But be ye not deceived; there is
more cauſe of controverſie, than matters of Diſcipline
only. I have often under my hand aſſerted, what with
the leave of my more moderate Brethren I will perſiſt
in, and undertake to demonſtrate, to the conviction of
them who deny it, at leaſt to the undeceiving of the
<hi>weak,</hi> who are ſeduced by them: That if
<list>
                     <item>1. Groundleſs or cauſeleſs Separation from true Churches;</item>
                     <item>2. Self-conſtitution of new Churches;</item>
                     <item>3. Self-conſecration of a new Miniſtry;</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>be, as none can deny they be, <hi>fundamental errors,</hi> and
<hi>Practices inconſiſtent with a ſtate of ſalvation;</hi> then the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62972:19"/>
                  <hi>Way or Practice</hi> of the <hi>Independent-Congregationaliſts</hi>
among us, is <hi>fundamentally erroneous,</hi> and <hi>inconſiſtent
with Salvation:</hi> For, that they have groundleſly <hi>ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated</hi>
from <hi>true Churches,</hi> conſtituted <hi>new Churches,</hi> and
conſecrated a <hi>new Miniſtry;</hi> inſomuch that they who
were lawfully ordained, have renounced their Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,
and received their Miniſtry in their new Way;
let any who have ſeen their courſe, and conſidered their
Writings, deny if they can.</p>
               <p>Although I have charity to believe, many a <hi>ſincere
heart</hi> towards God, may <hi>ſimply communicate</hi> with Gods
Ordinances among them, and not be <hi>ſenſible of their
Schiſm,</hi> nor <hi>deſign</hi> ſo great an evil, no way obvious to
the weak; yet their Way being in it ſelf <hi>ſo evil,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth
all that will be found faithful (as <hi>Jerome</hi> and
<hi>Auſtin</hi> againſt the <hi>Donatiſts)</hi> to animate each other
to <hi>diſcover</hi> ſo great an evil, and withſtand ſo grievous
<hi>Schiſm,</hi> growing to ſo great an height, as to <hi>confound,</hi>
yea <hi>nullifie</hi> the Church of God among us.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Bravely offered: What to prove that our private
Meeters, who break off from the Church, and ſet up
Conventicles of their own, cannot be in a <hi>Salvable State!</hi>
That their Leaders for <hi>intereſt ſake,</hi> dare not reprove
the Schiſm! That theſe practices cauſed the late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion,
and Murthers, and have <hi>paganiz'd</hi> almoſt all
<hi>England!</hi> And dare none of theſe Men accept the
challenge? 'Tis a ſhrewd ſign they ſuſpect, the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
of their cauſe; elſe we ſhould certainly have had
a <hi>melius inquirendum.</hi> We may preſume thoſe Men are
in crooked paths, who will not bring 'em to the rule,
when required to do ſo. Hence we will inquire;</p>
            <p>Secondly, Into their Plea from <hi>Conſcience,</hi> whereby
they would juſtify themſelves every one in his own
way. Which <hi>Conſcience</hi> is made the greateſt cheat, and
the verieſt fool in the World.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:62972:20"/>
For Men eſpouſe ſuch, and ſuch Opinions, and ways
of Life:</p>
            <p>Whence they fly our Churches, Writings, and all
other means of better Information, till by Cuſtom, and
the juſt Judgment of God, who gives them up to <hi>ſtrong
Deluſions,</hi> that love not the Truth; they think there can
be nothing true and good but what is wrapt up in their
own Tenents and Practices. And becauſe they have no
mind to budg, therefore they cry <hi>Conſcience</hi> will not let
'em. Which Conſcience is mere <hi>Opinion, Deluſion, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice</hi>
and <hi>Self-will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Juſt ſuch a <hi>Conſcience</hi> as the greateſt Hereticks, and
their moſt deluded Followers had to plead for their
damnable Opinions: And ſeveral Nations for their own
Heathen Gods, and Sacreds. Such a Conſcience as
put the Jews upon Crucifying our Saviour, and ſtone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the Prophets; and ſpur'd on late Zealots to the
worſt Rebellion, Murther, Theft and Sacriledg. Such
a Conſcience as makes the <hi>Scotch</hi> Sectaries glory in their
ſufferings for their late Rebellion, and Inhumane But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery
of the late Arch-Biſhop of S. <hi>Andrews:</hi> And put
others amongſt our ſelves upon acting the amazing Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy
of 48 over again.</p>
            <p>The greateſt Villanies have ever been acted under
the Pleas of <hi>Conſcience:</hi> And never hath the World
ſeen worſe times, than where ſuch Conſciences have
been moſt in faſhion.</p>
            <p>Look into the many Sects amongſt us, and you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
find any two of 'em, but what hold ſome things
contradictory to each other: Yet every Man in all
parties pleads <hi>Conſcience</hi> for what he doth. Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
Conſcience cannot make contradictories to be
true; therefore it is not Conſcience that makes all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
differ from the Church, and every one from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
or if <hi>Conſcience</hi> muſt be in the caſe, it is but an <hi>Erroneous
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62972:20"/>
one,</hi> and that is to ſay, the <hi>Errors</hi> and <hi>Deluſions</hi> of Men
that make all this buſtle. It is but the Aſs under the
Lyons Skin, a Spirit of Deluſion under the Pretexts of
Conſcience, that hath made ſo many <hi>Opinions,</hi> falſly
called <hi>Religion</hi> amongſt us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſcience</hi> can never condemn a Man without ſome
warrant or rule, <hi>e. g.</hi> It can never condemn any
Man for Theft, had it not this or ſome ſuch rule,
viz. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteal,</hi> whereby to do it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
in all the little parts of Religion and Government,
which are not ordain'd in Scripture, and where there is
no contradiction to thoſe general rules of doing things
<hi>decently, in order,</hi> and <hi>to edification,</hi> falſe Notions and
Opinion may diſquiet the mind, but Conſcience cannot
oppoſe, becauſe ſhe hath no rule, whereby to do it;
nor any Foundation to ground an Accuſation on. And
conſequently it is a Man's <hi>Prejudice</hi> and <hi>Deluſion,</hi> not his
<hi>Conſcience,</hi> that draws back from <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> the
<hi>Sign of the Croſs,</hi> &amp;c. becauſe theſe things not being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid
in Scripture, Conſcience cannot oppoſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
'em.</p>
            <p>At the rate theſe Men talk, we muſt allow every <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor,
Prejudice, Opinion, Fancy,</hi> and <hi>trick of Knavery</hi> to
be <hi>Conſcience;</hi> the falſhood of which ſufficiently appears
from the contradictions, palpable Errors, beaſtly Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices,
and Confuſions of Religion and Government,
which ſuch Conſciences have already brought into the
World, and do farther expoſe us to.</p>
            <p>But if it be really <hi>Conſcience</hi> that makes all this ſtir,
Pray tell me how comes it to paſs, that Conſcience
ſhould ſcruple ſome things, which are no where for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid
in Scripture, and yet ſo readily cloſe with many
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62972:21"/>
that are expreſly forbid? How can it be, that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
ſhould boggle at a Surplice, and kneeling in
the Sacrament of the Supper; and yet make no Bones
of Schiſms and Seditions? How is it reconcilable to
my reaſon, that Conſcience ſhould fly mixt Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,
of which we have examples in Scripture, and
which themſelves can no way avoid; and alſo ſet Forms
of Prayer, for which the Scripture affords both ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,
and Precept too: And yet ſhould ſport and
ſolace it ſelf, in <hi>ſpeaking evil of the King; reſiſting the
Powers,</hi> &amp;c. Till I am ſatisfyed in theſe points, I
muſt conclude it is no Conſcience: But Deluſion in
ſome, and in others mere tricks and deſign.</p>
            <p>It is certainly now time for 'em to conſider, that if
the Evils which Diviſions naturally produce ſhould come
upon us, what an heavy aggravation it will be to their
ſufferings, to conſider that all this is the fruit of their
own doings; and the work of their own hands? That
their own <hi>Paſſions, Miſtakes</hi> and <hi>Self-will,</hi> have pull'd
all this upon their own heads? What excuſe can they
make to God and Man; what recompence to Poſterity
for the ruining a Church; the whole proteſtant cauſe
and intereſt by a Diviſion, which their beſt Writers
condemn, themſelves cannot juſtify, and are forced
falſly to plead <hi>Conſcience</hi> for, as their laſt and only
refuge?</p>
            <p>If any thing ſhall ever perſwade theſe Men to look
toward Unity; they muſt as a means thereto avoid all
the hindrances of it. Many are ſelf-conceited, and
think none underſtand truth ſo well as themſelves:
Others ſelf-willed, and reſolved to yield in nothing:
And yet for ſuch Men to wiſh for Unity, is really to
wiſh that the very Government would ſtoop, and all Men
yield to their own ſelves. Nor is it ſome few only, but
the Majority in every party that is of this mind: Which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62972:21"/>
renders a ſatisfaction utterly impoſſible; unleſs they
could make the Government like Manna to ſuit it ſelf
to every pallat. Therefore when S. <hi>Paul Eph.</hi> 4. 3. is
preſſing to <hi>keep the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit in the Bond of
Peace;</hi> he direct 'em to the fitteſt means to that end,
v. 2. walk with <hi>lowlineſs</hi> and <hi>meekneſs, with long ſuffering</hi>
and <hi>love: Endeavouring to keep the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit.</hi>—All
endeavours are like to prove unſucceſsful with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
theſe Methods and Qualifications. For it is a cenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,
haſty, proud and ungovernable Spirit, that leaves
its rule, and follows its own giddy motions; which makes
the greateſt breaches both in Church and State. Let
Men lay aſide all thoſe humors which in the Judgment
of any indifferent Man are inconſiſtent with any Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
as ſtanding ſtubbornly irreconcilable to any
but their own placits, and after all the complaints of
<hi>Grievances, Popery,</hi> &amp;c. they will certainly ſay of this
Church and Nation, <hi>Happy are the people that are in ſuch
a caſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed I did never yet know but that Men muſt
part with ſomething for the ends of Peace and Unity:
They muſt in ſomething deny themſelves, reſtrain their
paſſions, and yield to a rule; elſe they ſhall live their
own puniſhments, and at laſt be driven to what they
would never go.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
