<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A funeral-sermon for the reverend, holy and excellent divine, Mr. Richard Baxter who deceased Decemb. 8, 1691 : with an account of his life / by William Bates ...</title>
            <author>Bates, William, 1625-1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-03">2005-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26788</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1107</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21548</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12617886</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12617886</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64427</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A26788)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64427)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 343:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A funeral-sermon for the reverend, holy and excellent divine, Mr. Richard Baxter who deceased Decemb. 8, 1691 : with an account of his life / by William Bates ...</title>
                  <author>Bates, William, 1625-1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 132 [i.e. 124], [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Brab. Aylmer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisements: p. [1]-[4] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11</date>
            <label>Melanie Sanders</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11</date>
            <label>Melanie Sanders</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-01</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64427:1"/>
            <p>A Funeral-Sermon FOR THE Reverend, Holy and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent DIVINE, Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter,</hi> Who deceased <hi>Decemb.</hi> 8. 1691. WITH An Account of His LIFE.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM BATES,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Brab. Aylmer,</hi> at the <hi>Three Pigeons</hi> against the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:64427:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64427:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worshipfull, and his much Honoured Friend, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Henry Ashurst,</hi> Baronet.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOur Noble and Constant Kindness to Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> Living, and your Honourable Respect to him Dead, have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced me to inscribe the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Memorial of him to your Name. He was most worthy of your highest Esteem and Love, for the first Impressions of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven upon your Soul, were in Reading his unvalued Book of the <hi>Saints Everlasting Rest.</hi> This kindled a mutual Affection in your Breasts: his Love was
<pb facs="tcp:64427:3"/>
Directing, Counselling, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing you to secure your Future Happiness: your Love was Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servant, Gratefull, and Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent to him. The Sincerity and Generosity of your Friendship, was very evident, in your appearing and standing by him, when he was so roughly and unrighteously hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, by one, who was the disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of this Ages Law; whose Deportment in a high place of Judicature, was so contrary to Wisdom, Humanity, and Justice, that there need no foul words to make his Name odious. Of this and your other Favours Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> retain'd a dear and lasting Sense; and in his dying hours declared, that you had been the
<pb facs="tcp:64427:3"/>
best friend he ever had. He <hi>has finished his Course, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his Crown</hi>: His Name will shine longer than his Enemies shall bark.</p>
            <p>I cannot omit the mentioning, that Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> those incomparable Persons in their several Studies, and dear Friends, died within a short space of one another. Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> was enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the Contemplation of the Design and Architecture of the visible World, and made rare dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries in the system of Nature: not for Curiosity and barren Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, but to admire and adore the Perfections of the Deity in the Variety, Order, Beauty, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous Artifice of the Creatures
<pb facs="tcp:64427:4"/>
that compose this great Universe. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> was conversant in the invisible World: his Mind was constantly applied to understand the harmonious Agreement of the Divine Attributes in the Oeconomy of our Salvation, and to restore Men to the Favour and Image of God. They are now admitted into the inlightned and purified Society above: where the immense Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes of the Divine Wisdom are laid open, and by one glance of an eye, they discover more perfectly the Causes, Effects, and Concate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of all things in Heaven and Earth, than the most diligent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirers can do here, in a thousand years Study, though they had the Sagacity of <hi>Solomon.</hi> By the
<pb facs="tcp:64427:4"/>
Light of Glory, <hi>they see the face of God, and are satisfied with his likeness for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis a high honour to you, that Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> should by their Last Will nominate you amongst their Executors. It was the Saying of a Wise <hi>Roman, Malo divi Augusti judicium, quam beneficium.</hi> I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have the Esteem of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Augustus</hi> than his Gifts: for he was an understanding Prince, and his Esteem was very Honourable to a Person. That two who so excell'd in Wisdom and Goodness, should commit to your Trust the disposal of their Estates for the Uses of Piety and Charity, is a more noble Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
<pb facs="tcp:64427:5"/>
of their Esteem of your Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and inviolable Integrity, than if they had bequeathed to you rich Legacies.</p>
            <p>It is a satisfaction to me, that I have complied with Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s desire in Preaching his Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral-Sermon, and with yours in Publishing it. I shall unfeigned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recommend Your self, your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Lady, and vertuous Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to the Divine Mercies: and remain, with great Respect,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your humble and faithfull Servant,</hi> William Bates.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64427:5"/>
            <head>A SERMON On the DEATH of Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Luke 23.46.</bibl>
                  <p>And when Jesus had cried with a loud Voice, he said, Father, into thy Hands I commend my Spirit.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Words are the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of our Blessed Saviour in the Extremity of his Passion. His unrighteous and implacable Enemies had nail'd his Body to the Cross, but they
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64427:6"/>
had no power over his Spirit, that was ready to take its flight to the Sanctuary of Life and Immortality. This dying Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Christ is a Pattern for sincere Christians: He has in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vested them with the Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Children of God; and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorises them by his Example, to commend their departing Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to his powerful Love. The Observation I shall unfold and apply, is this:
<q>'Tis the Priviledg of dying Saints, to commend their Spirits into the Hands of their Heavenly Father.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In discoursing of this, I shall,
<list>
                  <item>I. Consider the Foundation of this Priviledg.</item>
                  <item>II. Shew what a blessed Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledg this is.</item>
                  <item>III. Apply it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64427:6"/>I. The Foundation of this Priviledg is to be consider'd: This is built upon two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Relation of God to the Saints.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His Perfections joined with that Relation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Relation of God to the Saints. The Title of <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> is upon several Accounts attributed to God.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) He is a Father by Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation: <hi>O Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 64.</note> 
               <hi>thou art our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: we are the Clay, thou art the Potter, we are the Work of thine Hands.</hi> He formed Man's Body into a Majestick Figure, becoming his original State, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lord of the lower World. But in a peculiar manner he is stiled <hi>the Father of Spirits:</hi> they have a near Alliance, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblance of the Father of Lights, in their intellectual
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64427:7"/>
Powers, and their immortal Nature. From hence it is, the Angels are called <hi>the Sons of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 2.</note> They are the eldest Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spring of his Power. <hi>Adam</hi> has the Title of the <hi>Son of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 3.</note> And since the Fall, Men are called <hi>God's Offspring.</hi> There is an indelible Character of Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity engraven in the reasonable Nature by the Hand of God. But since Man turn'd Rebel to his Creator and Father, this endearing obliging Relation aggravates his Rebellion, but gives him no Interest in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Love of God, of which he has made a deadly Forfeiture. 'Tis threatned against ignorant perverse Sinners, <hi>He that made them, will not save them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Upon the account of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Calling and Profession, there is an intercurrent Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Father and Sons between
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64427:7"/>
God and his People. Thus the Posterity of <hi>Seth</hi> are called <hi>the Sons of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 6.</note> and the entire Nation of the Jews are so sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; <hi>When</hi> Israel <hi>was young,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hosea 11.</note> 
               <hi>I called my Son out of</hi> Egypt. And all that have received Baptism, the Seal of the holy Covenant, and profess Christianity, in this general Sense may be called the Children of God. But 'tis not the outward Dedication that entitles Men to a saving Interest in God, unless they live accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that Dedication. There are baptized Infidels, as well as unbaptized. How many every day fall as deep as Hell, whose hopes were high, on the account of their external Christianity.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) God is our Father upon a more excellent Account, by Renovation and Adoption. The natural Man is what St. <hi>Paul</hi> saith of the voluptuous Widow,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64427:8"/>
               <hi>dead while he lives.</hi> There is not only a cessation of spiritual Acts, but an utter incapacity to perform them: he cannot obey nor enjoy God. Now the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of Man is called a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation: Our Saviour tells <hi>Nicodemus, Verily I say unto you, Vnless a Man be born again, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> The reason of the Expression is, because there is a new Nature, spiritual, holy and heavenly, communicated, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from the carnal, polluted and earthly Nature, derived from the first <hi>Adam.</hi> And as the Relation of a Father results from the communicating a vital active Principle to another, in that kind of Life like his own: so God by making us Partakers of <hi>a Divine Nature, of his Life and Image,</hi> is stiled our Father: <hi>Of his own Will beg at he us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>with the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64427:8"/>
Word of Truth.</hi> And we are said, <hi>to be born again,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 11.25.</note> 
               <hi>not of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible Seed, but incorruptible, by the Word of God, which liveth and abideth for ever.</hi> By the Divine Influence, the Word of God implants in them such Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and Dispositions whereby they resemble God, <hi>are holy, as he is holy, in all manner of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation.</hi> They are called <hi>god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> as they are like him in their Minds, Affections and Actions. And to such God has the Heart and Eye of a Father, to regard and relieve them in all their Exigencies.<note place="margin">Psal. 103.13.</note> 
               <hi>Like as a Father pities his Children, so the Lord pities them that serve him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are also the Children of God by Adoption. This hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Privilege is obtained for us by the meritorious Sufferings of Christ, and is founded in our Union with him. <hi>God sent his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64427:9"/>
Son,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 4.</note> 
               <hi>that he might redeem them that were under the Law, that they might receive the Adoption of Sons.</hi> For his sake we are not only pardoned, but preferr'd to this Heavenly Dignity. 'Tis wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of Observation, that the Degrees of our Redemption mentioned in Scripture, have annex'd to them parallel degrees of our Adoption. Thus when 'tis said, <hi>We are redeemed from the Curse of the Law,</hi> 'tis added, <hi>That we might receive the Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sons.</hi> When 'tis said, <hi>We are freed from the servile Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Law,</hi> it follows, <hi>We have received the Spirit of Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.15.</note> whereby we cry, Abba, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> And the Apostle tells us, That the redemption of our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies from <hi>the bondage of Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, into the glorious Liberty of the Sons of God, is our Adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> that is the manifestation
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64427:9"/>
of it before all the World.</p>
            <p>Our Adoption is founded in our Union with Christ. A Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Christ, and a Son of God are the same: 'Tis therefore said, <hi>As many as received him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>to them gave he Power,</hi> or Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, <hi>to become the Sons of God, even to them that believe on his Name.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 3.8.</note> And <hi>ye are all the Sons of God, by Faith in Jesus Christ.</hi> This is the vital Band of our Union with Christ, and invests us with his Relation to God. When he was to leave the World, he sends this comfortable Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage to his Disciples; <hi>Go,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 20.17</note> 
               <hi>tell my Brethren, I ascend to my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and your Father, to my God and your God.</hi> His Relation has the precedence in Order, Dignity and Causality. He is God's own Son,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.3.</note> in a sense infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely high and proper to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self:<note place="margin">Heb. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>To which of the Angels said
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64427:10"/>
he at any time, Thou art my Son, to day have I begotten thee?</hi> The sublimest Prophet breaks forth with Wonder,<note place="margin">Isa. 53.</note> 
               <hi>Who shall declare his Generation?</hi> 'Tis above our Capacity and Conception. It becomes us to acquiesce in what the Scripture reveals. He is the eternal Word and Wisdom of God,<note place="margin">Heb. 3.</note> 
               <hi>the Brightness of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Glory.</hi> This is the most fit Comparison: for as Light is productive of Light without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diminution; so the Eternal Father communicated his Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence to the Son. In short, God is Christ's Father by Nature, and God by Dispensation; he is our God as the Author of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and our Father by Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Before I proceed, it is fit to observe the Excellence of the Evangelical Adoption above the Civil Adoption among Men.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:64427:10"/>(1.) Adoption is a legal Act in imitation of Nature, for the Comfort of those who are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Children. But God had a Son, the Heir of his Love and Glory. His adopting Love is heightned by considering our Meanness and Vileness: we are but a little breathing Dust, worthless Rebels. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle cries out in a rapture of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration and Joy, <hi>Behold what manner of Love the Father hath bestowed upon us, that we should be called the Sons of God!</hi> If we consider the natural Distance between God and us, as he is the Creator, and we are the Works of his Hands, 'tis truly infinite; but the moral Distance between the holy righteous God and the guilty polluted Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is, if it were possible, more than infinite: Love inconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable! That releases us from
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64427:11"/>
Bondage, and adopts us into the Line of Heaven. If we admire any thing of this World in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison of it, 'tis a sign we have no share in this Privilege.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Civil Adoption conveys no Praise-worthy Qualities into the Person that is adopted. A King may adopt one to be his Son, and the Heir of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but cannot endow him with a Royalty of Spirit, with ruling Wisdom, with Justice and Equity, Clemency and Bounty, with Magnanimity and Fortitude, that may qualify him to manage the Scepter. The adopted Prince may be of a low sordid Disposition, a Slave to his vile Lusts, and designing to enslave others. But all the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted Sons of God are divine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly renewed; they are purified from defiling &amp; debasing Lusts, and are adorn'd with all the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64427:11"/>
Graces of the Spirit, that God <hi>is not ashamed to be called their God and Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb.</note>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 2.</note> 
               <hi>nor Christ asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to call them Brethren.</hi> Now from this special Relation and Interest of God in the Saints, there is a sure Foundation of their Trust in his saving Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. <hi>David</hi> addresses himself to God for his preservation from imminent Danger, <hi>I am thine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 119.</note> 
               <hi>save me:</hi> As if his miscarrying would be a Loss to God, who had so dear a Propriety in him.</p>
            <p>I come now to the second thing that encourages the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Faith of the Saints when they leave the World, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend their Souls to him, His Perfections joined with his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: His Love inclines, his Truth engages, and his Power enables him to bring them safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Heaven.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:64427:12"/>1. His Love. This is the brightest Ray of the Deity, the first and clearest Notion we have of God. St. <hi>John</hi> tells us, <hi>God is Love.</hi> His Love cannot be fully express'd by the dearest Relations and Affections in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The Relation of Parents, as 'tis most deeply implanted in Nature, so it implies the most cordial, strong and tender Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. But as God is infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly greater and better than earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Parents; so he equally excels them, as in his Abilities, so in his good Will to his Children. Our Saviour directs us, <hi>Call no Man Father upon Earth, for one is your Father, which is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven:</hi> The Title and Love of a Father is peculiar to him. Our Saviour argues, <hi>If you that are evil, know how to give good things to your Children, how much more shall your heavenly Father to those
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64427:12"/>
that ask him?</hi> The Inference is strong, not only from the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Authority of the Speaker, but from the native Perspicuity of the Things: for the Love of an earthly Father is but an Infusion into his Breast from the heavenly Father, and but a faint resemblance of his Love. The Love of a Mother is more ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and endearing than of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Even a fearful Hen will fly upon Death, to preserve its tender Brood from the Devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: Yet the Love of God to his Children far excels it. <hi>Can a Woman forget her sucking Child?</hi> What Heart, what Marble is in her Breast so incompassionate and unrelenting, as to neglect her helpless Infant? <hi>She may, but,</hi> saith God, <hi>I will never forget thee.</hi> The Seraphims, those bright and unperishing Flames, are but faint and cold, in comparison
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64427:13"/>
of God's Love to his Children.</p>
            <p>'Tis observable how the Love of God to them expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses it self in all the Notions of Propriety and Preciousness, to make it more sensible to us. They are stiled <hi>his Treasure,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 19.</note> 
               <hi>his Jewels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3.</note> the most precious part of his Treasure,<note place="margin">Zech. 9.16</note> the <hi>Jewels of his Crown,</hi> that are the richest Jewels. Now <hi>will he throw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way</hi> his Treasure, or suffer the cruel Enemy to rob him of his Jewels? Will he not take them into his safe Custody? 'Tis to be observed, that the Esteem and Affection of God principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly respects the Souls of his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: Their Souls have an ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Affinity with him in their Substance as Spirits: and being <hi>born again of the Spirit,</hi> they are Spirit in their Divine Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities &amp; Endowments, and more endear'd to him than by their
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64427:13"/>
first Alliance. His tender Care to preserve them, will be correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to his Valuation and Love.</p>
            <p>Moreover, the Condition of departing Souls affords ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Argument of reliance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Love; for they leave this visible World, with all their Supports and Comforts; they are stripp'd of all sensible Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities: And will he leave them fatherless in such a forlorn and desolate State? His Love is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press'd by Mercy, Compassion, Pity, melting Affections, that are most tenderly moved when the beloved Object is in Distress. Our Saviour propounds an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument for dependance upon the delivering Love of God, from the Exigence of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; <hi>Shall not God deliver his own Elect,</hi> the Designation of Love, <hi>who cry day and night to him? He will do it speedily.</hi> Love is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64427:14"/>
more ardent and active than in times of Distress. Therefore when his dying Children are deprived of all their Hopes and dependance upon Creatures, and fly to him for Protection and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, will he not hear their mournful Requests, and grant their fainting Desires? When their earthly Tabernacles are so ruinous, that they are forc'd to dislodg, will the Love of a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father suffer their naked Souls to wander in the vast Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of <hi>the other World, seeking Rest, and finding none?</hi> Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he will bring them into his reviving Presence. If Divine Love be so condescending, that <hi>the high and lofty One that inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits Eternity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 57.</note> 
               <hi>dwells with the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and contrite Spirit,</hi> to <hi>revive the Spirit of the Humble,</hi> when they are confin'd to our lowly Earth, we may be assur'd, when
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64427:14"/>
that Spirit shall be devested of Flesh, he will bring it to Heaven the Temple of his Glory, to be with him for ever. 'Tis great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Love for a King to lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side his State, and dwell in a mean Cottage with his Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, than to receive him into his Palace, and communicate to him of his rich Abundance. 'Tis another most comfortable Consideration, that the Love of God is unvariable towards his Children: His Love is the sole moving Cause of our filial Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to him:<note place="margin">James.</note> 
               <hi>Of his own Will he begat us by the Word of Truth.</hi> His Soveraign free Love was the Principle of his electing any to the Dignity of being his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: This Love is as unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as free; and Election that proceeds from it, is as unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as his Love. What can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce him to alter his Affection
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64427:15"/>
towards them? For such is the perfection of his Knowledg, that he can never be surprized by a sudden new Event, that may cause a change in his Mind and Will. He foresaw all the Sins of his People, with their provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Aggravations. Now if the foresight of them did not hinder his electing Love in its rise, can they frustrate its end, the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them to Glory?</p>
            <p>Besides, we may argue from what his Love has done for his Children, to what he will do: He has given his Son and Spirit to them, the surest Signs of his Love, if we consider the unva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable Excellence of the Gifts, and the Design of the Giver.</p>
            <p>The Son of God is the most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Gift of his Love, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deserved, as he was undesired: And from hence the Apostle ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, <hi>He that gave his Son for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64427:15"/>
us all, how much more will he with him give us all things?</hi> Blessed God! What richer Evidence, and more convincing Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration can there be of thy Love? <hi>Will he not with him give us all things?</hi> The Inference is direct and conclusive, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect to temporal and eternal Things. He will give to his Children in the present World, whatever his Wisdom, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with his Love, sees good for them. To illustrate this by a low and familiar In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance; If a Mother bestows upon her Daughter rich Jewels for her Marriage-Ornaments, will she deny her Pins to dress her? And we may as strongly argue, that with his Son he will give us eternal Blessings. Will he give us the Tree of Life, and not permit us to eat of the Fruit of it? What was the design of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64427:16"/>
his Counsel and Compassion, in giving his Son to be a Sacrifice for us, but to restore us to his Favour? The Apostle reasons strongly, <hi>If when we were Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, we were reconciled to God by the Death of his Son, much more being reconciled, we shall be saved by his Life.</hi> He has paid our Ransom, and revers'd the Sentence of Condemnation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst us; and it invincibly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, he can more easily accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plish our Happiness in Heaven. If Love justify a Sinner, it will glorify a Saint.</p>
            <p>And as the Gift of the Son, so the most precious Gift of the Spirit to God's Children, to make them holy and heavenly, is the most certain sign of his Love to them. The Apostle in the fullest expression speaks of it; <hi>God who is rich in Mercy, for his great Love wherewith he
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64427:16"/>
has loved us, even when we were dead in Sins, quickned us together with Christ: By Grace ye are sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi> Sanctification is the effect of <hi>rich Mercy, great Love,</hi> and <hi>saving Grace.</hi> The Children of God are seal'd by the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to the Day of Redemption: that Seal distinguishes them from the obstinate and polluted World, and ratifies the convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of eternal Life to them. The Spirit is stiled the <hi>Earnest of the Inheritance.</hi> His dwelling in the Saints by his sanctifying and comforting Operations, is an Earnest of their dwelling with God in his Sanctuary a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove. From hence the Apostle propounds a strong Argument to assure the Saints, upon their leaving this World, of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception into Heaven; <hi>Now he that hath wrought us for the self-same thing, is God;</hi> and the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64427:17"/>
Almighty always obtains his End: <hi>who hath also given us the earnest of his Spirit.</hi> Holiness is the Morning-Star of the great Day; Grace is the Preparative and Assurance of Glory: For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho the Saints are in themselves mutable, and while there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains Corruption within, and a tempting World without, are liable to falling away, yet the free and powerful Love of God that revived them when dead, will preserve them living; that which raised them from the Grave, will prevent their relap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing into it. <hi>The Gifts of God are without Repentance.</hi> How triumphantly does the Apostle express his Confidence,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Who shall separate us from the Love of God? Shall Tribulation, or Distress, or Persecution, or Famine, or Naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, or Peril, or Sword?</hi> These are the most powerful Terrors
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64427:17"/>
that the perverse World, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination with the Devil, can make use of to constrain us to desert the Service of God; but they are vain. <hi>Nay, in all these things we are more than Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, through him that loved us: For I am perswaded, that neither Death, nor Life, nor Angels, nor Principalities, nor Powers, nor Things present, nor Things to come, nor Height, nor Depth, nor any other Creature, shall be able to separate us from the Love of God, that is in Christ Jesus our Lord.</hi> This blessed Assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Apostle is not rais'd from his extraordinary Privile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, not from the apparition of Angels to him, nor his rapture to Paradise, nor special Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but from the Love of God in Christ Jesus our Lord, that everlastingly embraces all his Children. Briefly, in that God
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64427:18"/>
has given his Son to die for us, and his Spirit to live in us, his Son to purchase and prepare Heaven for us, his Spirit to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare us for Heaven, a dying Saint may with blessed Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity commend his Soul into God's Hands.</p>
            <p>I have more particularly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered the Fatherly Love of God, what a strong Security it affords to his Children, that he will never leave them, in that no Point requires and deserves more Confirmation, and weight of Argument to press it down into our distrustful Hearts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Divine Truth affords a strong Security to the Children of God, to commend their Souls to him at last. Truth is an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute as essential and dear to God as any of his Perfections. And in the Accomplishment of our Salvation, he ordered all
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64427:18"/>
things becoming to his Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that is for the illustration of all his principal Attributes, and accordingly design'd the Glory of his Truth equally with the Honour of his Mercy. Thus he declares to his chosen People, <hi>Know therefore that the Lord thy God, he is God, the faithful God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 7.9.</note> 
               <hi>which keepeth Covenant and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, with them that love him, and keep his Commandments.</hi> The Attribute that is set next to the Deity, as most sacred, is the <hi>Faithful God</hi>; and that further express'd, <hi>keeping Covenant and Mercy</hi>; for he delights in ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling his Promises, as in the freest Acts of Mercy. The Psalmist breaks forth with the affectionate Praises of these At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes,<note place="margin">Psal. 138.2</note> 
               <hi>I will worship towards thy holy Temple, and praise thy Name for thy loving Kindness and thy Truth: for thou hast mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64427:19"/>
thy Word above all thy Name.</hi> His Word here imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately signifies his Promise, that has its rise from his loving Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and its performance from his Truth. This he magnifies both with respect to the matter of his Promises that are exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great and precious, and the fulfilling them above all that we can ask or think. God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>repent or lie</hi>; his Counsels are unretractable, from the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutability of his Nature; his Promises are infallible, from his Fidelity: they are as unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as the Sun and Stars in their appointed Courses;<note place="margin">Jer. 31.35.</note> nay, more stable than the Centre: <hi>for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth shall pass away,</hi> but not a tittle of his Promises, and our Hopes be unfulfilled. If the Frame of Nature were dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved, it would be no loss to God, who is glorious and blessed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64427:19"/>
in his own Perfections: but if his Promises fail, the Honour of his Truth would be impair'd and blemish'd. The Psalmist saith, <hi>Those that know thy Name, will trust in thee:</hi> Those who know the Creature, its Levity, Mutability and Mortality, will be discourag'd from trusting in it; but those who know the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Constancy of God in his Nature and Promises, will se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely rely upon him.</p>
            <p>Now the Promises, the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of God's Love, without which we cannot have any solid and sustaining Hope in our Death, assure us of God's recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the separate Spirits of his Children. There was a constant clearness, tho not in that degree of Light as since the appearance of Christ, of the Happiness of the departed Saints. Dying <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> breaks forth with a lively
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64427:20"/>
Hope,<note place="margin">Gen. 49.18.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord, I have waited for thy Salvation. Job</hi> says, <hi>Tho he kill me, yet will I trust in him</hi>; that is, for his Almighty Mercy in the next State. The Psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mist expresses his Confidence, <hi>Thou wilt guide me by thy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 73.24</note> 
               <hi>and receive me into thy Glory.</hi> After the safe conducting him through a World of Troubles and Temptations, he would bring him to Heaven, a Place of equal Purity and Glory. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> when he was in pressing Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril,<note place="margin">Psal. 31.5.</note> addresses to God, <hi>Into thy Hands I commend my Spirit,</hi> to be preserved as a precious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positum; <hi>thou hast redeemed me, O Lord God of Truth.</hi> His As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance is built on God's Right and Title to him, <hi>Thou hast re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed me,</hi> and his everlasting Fidelity. The Apostle speaks with full assurance, <hi>We know that</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>if our earthly House of this
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64427:20"/>
Tabernacle be dissolved, we have a Building of God eternal in the Heavens.</hi> And, <hi>we are confident, I say, rather to be absent from the Body, and present with the Lord.</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> encourages Christians when surrounded with Death, <hi>to commit their Souls to him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>Wherefore let them that suffer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Will of God, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the keeping of their Souls to him in wel-doing, as unto a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Creator.</hi> He encourageth them to encounter Death in its most formidable Pomp, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering their Souls shall be safe for ever, upon the account of God's Right and Interest in them, and his Fidelity: he has an original Right in them by the first Creation, as they are intellectual immortal Spirits in their Nature, but a nearer and more especial Right by a new and nobler Creation, as they are
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64427:21"/>
renewed Spirits, made like to him in his Holiness, the most Divine Perfection. The Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Creator implies his om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent Love, and the Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute of Faithful, his eternal Love declar'd in his Promises. There can never be the least cause to charge him with Insin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity or Inconstancy. The <hi>Favour of God is round about the Righteous as a Shield:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 5.</note> 
               <hi>And his Faithfulness is round about him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 89.</note> that he is always ready to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form his Promise to them. They may safely trust the worth of their Souls, and the weight of Eternity with him, who has said, <hi>he will never leave them, nor forsake them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Besides, the Promise of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to the obedient Children of God, is secur'd not only by his Fidelity, but the declar'd Equity of his Proceedings in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:64427:21"/>
his final Judgment. 'Tis a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality invested in the Crown of Heaven to dispense Rewards: <hi>Whoever comes to God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note> 
               <hi>must be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that he is, and that he is a rewarder of them that diligently seek him.</hi> His Being and rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Bounty are the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Religion. 'Tis true, such is the Distance between God and the Creature, and the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Obligations of it to God, that it can challenge nothing from God, as due to its Merit. Justice unqualified with Bounty and Clemency, owes nothing to the most excellent Obedience of the Creature, tho innocent. But since the Fall, our best Works are defective and defiled, and want Pardon; and our heaviest Sufferings are but light in the Ballance, against the exceeding Weight of Glory. But the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle tells the Thessalonians, <hi>It is
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64427:22"/>
a righteous thing with God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compense Tribulation to them who trouble you: and to you who are troubled, rest with us.</hi> Consider them in the Comparison; 'Tis becoming his governing Justice to punish the unrighteous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutors, and reward his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Servants who suffer for his Glory. Now the present Life is the Day for our Work, as our Saviour saith, <hi>I must do the Work of him that sent me, while 'tis cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to Day:</hi> And at Death, the <hi>Spirit returns to God that gave it,</hi> in order to Judgment, either fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal or favourable, according to the tenor of Mens good Works, and the desert of their bad. The Promise is <hi>to them, who by pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent continuance in wel-doing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> 
               <hi>seek for Glory, and Honour, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, they shall obtain eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life.</hi> Our Saviour encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges his suffering Servants, <hi>Be
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:64427:22"/>
faithful to the Death, and I will give you the Crown of Life.</hi> The compleat Reward is reserved to the great Day of universal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compences, when the Sons of God by Regeneration, shall be the Sons of a glorious Resurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. But the righteous Judg will give a present Reward at the end of the Day,<note place="margin">Luke 20.35.</note> to all that with unfainting Perseverance have perform'd his Work. Our Saviour tells us,<note place="margin">Mat. 20.9.</note> that all who wrought in the Vineyard, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd their Rewards <hi>in the last Hour of the Day</hi>: The Parallel is instructive, that when the Night of Death comes, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward will be dispens'd. There is a Law recorded concerning the paying Wages to those who were hir'd, that it should be in the end of the Day; that it should not be detain'd <hi>all Night with thee until the Morning.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 24.15.</note> The
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:64427:23"/>
Allusion is very congruous, that God will fulfil his own Law to his Sons that serve him. The Reward shall not abide with him the long dark Interval, the Night, wherein their Bodies sleep in the Grave, till the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Resurrection. Our Saviour promised the dying Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, <hi>To day shalt thou be with me in Paradise. The End of our Faith</hi> is immediately attended <hi>with the Salvation of the Soul:</hi> The Labour of Faith being fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish'd, is productive of the beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick Vision in the State of Light and Glory. The Sum is, That the Children of God, who have by constant Conversation sincerely endeavoured to please and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify him, may with an entire Resignation commit their Souls to his Hands, as if an Angel were sent from Heaven to them in their dying Agonies, with
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:64427:23"/>
the comfortable Message, that they should presently be with God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Divine Power, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with Love and Truth, is the Foundation of our secure dependance upon God in our last Hours. This Consideration is absolutely necessary for our sure Trust: For Love without Power is ineffectual, and Power without Love of no comfortable Advantage to us. The Apostle gives this reason of his chearful and couragious Sufferings in the Service of God, <hi>For I know in whom I have believed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.</note> 
               <hi>and am perswaded he is able to keep what I have committed to him, till that Day.</hi> His Faith respected the Promises of God concerning his Salvation, which are infinitely sure, the Divine Power being alsufficient to fulfil them. The precious Depositum that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:64427:24"/>
to his dear Care, he can and will preserve inviolate. The Father of sincere Believers, is <hi>the Lord of Heaven and Earth,</hi> who by his Word, without the least strain of his Power, made the World, and preserves it from falling into Confusion. 'Tis the Essence of Faith, to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure us of God's Almighty Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to all that have the true Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of his Children, that are qualified for his Salvation. Our Redeemer joins the two Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>our Father and our God</hi>; the gracious and the glorious Relation are inseparable. Now the Love of our heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther engages the Power of our God, that we shall want no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to secure our Happiness, that is within the object of Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotence.</p>
            <p>I shall insist no further upon the Consideration of the Divine
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:64427:24"/>
Power, because it will return under some of the following Heads of Discourse.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Blessedness of this Privilege is to be unfolded. This will appear by considering,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> What is the Deposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, the Thing that is intrust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in God's Hands.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> What is implied in his receiving of it.</p>
            <p>In answer to the first; 'Tis the Soul, the more excellent and immortal Part of Man, that is commended to God's keeping.</p>
            <p n="1">1.'Tis our more excellent Part in its Nature and Capacity. Man is a compounded Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of a Body and a Soul: the Body in its Original and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution is Earth; the Soul is of a divine Descent, a spiritual Substance, and in the Nobility and Perfections of its Nature,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:64427:25"/>
but <hi>a little lower than the Angels:</hi> 'tis <hi>the vile Body, but the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In its Capacity it incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly excels the Body; for the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy lives &amp; moves in the low Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the Senses, that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with the Worms of the Earth; but the Soul in its Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding and Desires, is capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Communion with the blessed God, of Grace and Glory. From hence it is, that the whole World can't make one Man hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py; for the Ingredients of true and compleat Happiness are the Perfection and Satisfaction of the Soul. The Apostle tells us, <hi>The less is blessed of the greater.</hi> Can the World bring Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Man, that is so incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably short of his Imperfection? Our Saviour assures us, <hi>the Gain of the whole World cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compense the Loss of one Soul.</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:64427:25"/>
There is a vast Circuit in our Desires, and all the Lines ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate in the Centre of Blessed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. Can the World give sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Satisfaction to them? <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> who was as rich and high as the World could make him, has left an everlasting Testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Vanity of transient Things, from his experimental Observation, and the Direction of the Holy Spirit: So he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins and ends his Sermon,<note place="margin">Eccles. 1.1. &amp; 12.8.</note> 
               <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Vanities, all is Vanity</hi>; so vain and vexing, that we shall not only be weary of them, but of this Life,<note place="margin">Eccl. 1.17.</note> wherein we use them. Can the Creature make us happy, when their Empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and Anguish annex'd to it, makes our Lives miserable? The World cannot satisfy our narrow Senses: <hi>The Eye is not satisfied with seeing, nor the Ear with hearing,</hi> much less the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:64427:26"/>
Desires of our supreme Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties. Those who are now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanted with its Allurements, within a little while will see through its false Colours. As when one awakes, all the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant Scenes of Fancy in his Dream vanish; so when the Soul is awakened in the End of Life, <hi>the World and the Lusts thereof pass away,</hi> and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of them.</p>
            <p>I shall add further; What clearer Evidence can we have of the worth of the Soul, than from God's Esteem, the Creator of it? Now when God foresaw the Revolture of our first Parent, that brought him under a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Death in one Sentence, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and eternal, and that all Mankind was desperately lost in him, then his compassionate Counsels were concerning his Recovery: His Love and Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:64427:26"/>
accorded to contrive the Means to accomplish our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, by the Death of his incarnate Son:<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.</note> 
               <hi>We are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed with Silver and Gold, but with the precious Blood of Christ, as a Lamb without spot and ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish.</hi> Of what value is a Soul in God's account, that he bought with his own Son's Blood, the most sacred Treasure of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? We may say for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our Redeemer and our own,<note place="margin">O anima! erige te, tantivales. <hi>Aug.</hi> in Psal. 103.</note> that which the Angels cannot, we were so valued by God himself, that his Son be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Man, and died on the Cross for the Salvation of our Souls. I shall only mention a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Evidence and Effect of God's valuation of our Souls, that is, <hi>the eternal Weight of Glory,</hi> which exceeds all the Thoughts of our Minds, and Desires of our Hearts. What
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:64427:27"/>
are all the Kingdoms and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures of the World, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison of that Blessedness God has prepar'd <hi>for those who love him?</hi> Now the Soul that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>estimably precious, and should be most dear to us, is secured from Danger, when received by God's Hands.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Soul is our immortal Part. The Body is compounded of jarring Principles, frail and mortal: A Casualty or Sickness dissolves the vital Union, and it falls to the Dust. But the Soul is a Spirit by Nature, and immortal by its inherent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty. Its spiritual Operations perform'd without the ministry of the Senses, (the Eye of the Mind contemplates its Objects, when the Eyes of the Body are clos'd) demonstrate its spiritual Nature: for the Being is the Root of its working, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:64427:27"/>
that it exists indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently upon the Body: But of this we have the clearest assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the Scripture. This is another demonstration that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Things cannot make us happy, for they forsake us the first step we take into the next World, and then the Soul enters into Happiness or Misery equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eternal. The Immortality of the Soul, and the Immutabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of its State, are inseparable then; for the present Life is the time of our Work, the next is of Recompences according to our Works. <hi>If we die in the Lord,</hi> the Consequence is infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible, we shall live with him for ever: If we die in our Sins, we shall not be received by his merciful Hands, but fall into his bottomless Displeasure. And of what concernment is it to have our Souls with God in that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:64427:28"/>
infinite and incomprehensible Duration? All the Measures of Time, Days and Weeks, Months and Years, and Ages, are swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd up in that invisible Depth, as the Rivers that pour into the Sea, are swallowed up without any overflowing of its Waters. The Dove that <hi>Noah</hi> let out of the Ark, as a Spy to discover whether the Deluge was abated, found not a Place to rest on; but after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Circuits in the Air, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the Ark. If our Thoughts take wing, and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply Millions of Millions of Ages, we cannot rest in any Computation, for there remains after all an entire innumerable Eternity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I will consider more particularly what is contained in this blessed Privilege: The reception of the Soul into God's
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:64427:28"/>
Hands, implies three things.
<list>
                  <item>1. Entire Safety.</item>
                  <item>2. Heavenly Felicity.</item>
                  <item>3. 'Tis a certain Pledg of the reviving of the Body, and its reunion with the Soul in the State of Glory.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Entire Safety. After Death the separate Soul of a true Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver immediately passes through the airy and Ethereal Regions to the highest Heaven, the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, the native Seat and Element of blessed Spirits. The Air is possess'd by Satan with his Confederate Army, who are Rebels to God, and Enemies to the Souls of Men: he is stiled <hi>the Prince of the Power of the Air:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephes. 2.</note> He often raises Storms and Tempests, discharges Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Lightning, the woful Effects of which are felt in the lower World. The Numbers, the Strength, and the Malice of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:64427:29"/>
the evil Angels to the Souls of Men, render them very terrible: We may conjecture at their Number, from what is related in the Gospel,<note place="margin">Mark 5.</note> that <hi>a Legion possess'd one Man.</hi> They are superiour Spirits to Man, and tho stripp'd of their moral Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies, Holiness, Goodness and Truth, yet retain their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Power at least in great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees. Their Malice is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable. 'Tis said of the Devil, <hi>He goes about like a roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lion, seeking whom he may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</hi> All the Joy those ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Spirits are capable of, is the involving the Souls of Men in their desperate Calamity. And tho they know their oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing God will increase their Guilt and Torment, yet their Diligence is equal to their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, to seduce, pervert and ruin Souls for ever. Now when the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:64427:29"/>
Saints die, all the Powers of Darkness would, if possible, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ascension of their Souls to God. What <hi>David</hi> complains of his cruel Enemies, is appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable in this case, <hi>Their Souls are among Lions;</hi> and if desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of divine Preservation, the Danger would be the same; as if a little Flock of Lambs were to encounter with a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of fierce Lions, or fiery Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons. Anger sets an edg upon Power, and makes a Combatant but of equal Strength to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come. How dangerous then would the Condition be of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Souls, oppos'd by over-matching Enemies, armed with Rage against them? How easily would they hurry them to <hi>the Abyss,</hi> the Den of Dragons, the Prison where lost Souls are se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd to the Day of Judgment?</p>
            <p>But all the Potentates of Hell
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:64427:30"/>
are infinitely inferiour to God: they are restrain'd and tortur'd by the Chains of his powerful Justice: a Legion of them could not enter into the Swine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his permission, much less can they touch <hi>the Apple of his Eye.</hi> That black Prince with all his infernal Host cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercept one naked Soul from ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving at the Kingdom of Glory. Our Saviour assures us, <hi>None is able to pluck them out of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Hands.</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 10.</note> The Lord Christ our Head and Leader, having vanquish'd in his last Battel on the Cross, Principalities and Powers, made his triumphant Ascension to Glory: Thus his Members having overcome their spiritual Enemies, shall by the same Almighty Power be carried through the Dominions of Satan, <hi>in the sight of their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies,</hi> (tormented with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:64427:30"/>
of their lost Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and Envy that humane Souls should partake of it) to the Place of God's glorious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidence.</p>
            <p>I shall also observe, that as the Lord is a God of Power, so he is a God of Order, and uses subordinate Means for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishment of his Will. Our Saviour has reveal'd, that the Angels transport the separate Souls of the Righteous to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: Those glorious Spirits, who always behold the Face of God, such is their exact Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to him, and perfect Love to his Children, that they dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain not to protect his little ones in this open State.<note place="margin">Mat. 18.10</note> They <hi>rejoice at the Conversion of Sinners,</hi> at their first entrance into the Way of Life, and with tender watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness encompass them here, never withdrawing their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:64427:31"/>
Presence, till they bring them to their celestial Country, and resign their Charge to the Lord of Life. How safe are the departed Saints, when convey'd through Satan's Territories by the Royal Guard of Angels <hi>that excel in strength?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Heavenly Felicity. The receiving of holy Souls into God's Hands, is introductive into his Presence, which is both a Sanctuary to secure us from all Evil, and a Store-house to furnish us with all that is good. <hi>The Lord is a Sun and a Shield:</hi> he is to intellectual Beings, what the Sun is to sensitive, commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicates Light and Life, and Joy to them. <hi>In his Presence is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of Joy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 16.11</note> 
               <hi>at his right Hand are Rivers of Pleasure for ever.</hi> All that is evil and afflicting, is abolish'd: all that is desirable, is conferr'd upon his Children.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:64427:31"/>
A glimpse or reflected Ray of his reconciled and favourable Countenance, even in this low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er World, infuses into the Hearts of his Children a <hi>Joy unspeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and glorious:</hi> a taste of the Divine Goodness here, causes a disrelish of all the carnal Sweets, the dreggy Delights which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Men so greedily desire. And if the faint Dawn be so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving and comfortable, what is the Brightness of the full Day? None can understand the Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness that results from the full and eternal sight of God's Face, and the fruition of his Love, but those who enjoy the Presence of God in perfection. His Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness is truly infinite; the more the Saints above know it, and enjoy it, the more they esteem it, and delight in it. His com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat and communicative Love satisfies the immense Desires of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:64427:32"/>
that innumerable Company of blessed Spirits that are before his Throne: there is no Envy, no Avarice, no Ambition in that Kingdom, where <hi>God is all in all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Divine Presence is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-flowing Fountain of Felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The continual reflection upon this, makes Heaven to be Heaven to the Blessed: their Security is as valuable as their Felicity: they are above all danger of losing it. Methinks the belief of this should cause us, as it were with Wings of Fire, with most ardent Desires to fly to the Bosom of God, the alone Centre of our Souls, where we shall rest for ever.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The reception of the Soul into Heaven is a certain Pledg of the Resurrection of the Body, and its re-union with the Soul in the State of Glory. The Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of God was made with
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:64427:32"/>
the entire Persons of Believers: therefore under the Law the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Seal of it was in their Flesh. To be the God of Promise to them, implies his being a bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Rewarder to them. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour silences the Sadduces, who disbeliev'd the Resurrection, from the tenour of God's Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>I am the God of</hi> Abraham, <hi>and</hi> Isaac, <hi>and</hi> Jacob, which Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle he was pleased to retain af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their Death; <hi>Now God is not the God of the Dead, but of the Living.</hi> The immediate Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence from thence is, that their Souls did actually live in Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sedness, and that their Bodies, tho dead to Nature, were alive to God with respect to his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise and Power. If we consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that the Divine Law binds the outward Man as well as the inward, and that during the time of our Work and Trial
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:64427:33"/>
here, our Service and Sufferings for the Glory of God are from the concurrence of the Soul and Body, it will appear that the Promise of the Reward belongs to both, and that the receiving of the Soul into Heaven, is an earnest of our full Redemption, even that of the Body. 'Tis true, there is no visible Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the Bodies of the Saints and of the Wicked here; they are sick with the same Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases, and die in the same man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. As 'tis with Trees in deep Winter, when they are covered with Snow, we cannot distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish which are absolutely dead and destin'd to the Ax and Fire, and which retain their Sap, and will be fruitful and flourishing in the returning Year: so the dead Bodies of the Godly and Ungodly, to external appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, are alike: But what a vast
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:64427:33"/>
difference will be between them in the next World! The Bodies of the Ungodly, in conjunction with their Souls, shall be cast into the Lake of Fire; the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the Godly resumed by their Souls, shall enjoy a full and flourishing Happiness for ever.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>The Application.</head>
               <p n="1">1. This may inform us of the contrary States into which dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Persons immediately pass: The Children of God resign their Spirits to the Hands of their gracious Heavenly Father, but Rebels and Strangers to God, fall <hi>into the Hands of</hi> a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging Judg. Could we see the attending Spirits that sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>round sick Persons in their last Hours, what a wonderful Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression would it make upon us? A Guard of glorious Angels
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:64427:34"/>
convey the departed Saints to the Bosom of God's Love, and the Kingdom of his Glory. But when the Wicked die, a Legion of Furies sieze upon their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Prey, and hurry them to the infernal Prison, from whence there is no redemption.</p>
               <p>How many Rebels and open Enemies to God are in the Pale of the Christian Church? They will loudly repeat, <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the impudent and pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable Atheism of their Lives: they live as if they were inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent, and not accountable to him <hi>who will judg the World without respect of Persons.</hi> The more strict his Commands are, the Contempt of them is more visible. Our Saviour's Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is peremptory, <hi>I say unto you, Swear not at all:</hi> but how many make no more conscience
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:64427:34"/>
of Swearing than they do of Speaking, and pour forth Oaths of all fashions and sizes. We are severely forbid all degrees of Impurity, in the Look, in Words, or in Wish; yet how many without reflection or remorse, continue in the deepest Polluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons! We are commanded to <hi>live soberly in this present World</hi>; yet how many indulge their swinish Appetites, and debase themselves even below the Beasts that perish. And as the sensual Appetites are notoriously pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant in some, so the angry Appetite is tyrannous in others. Pride, Wrath, Revenge, possess the Breasts of many: How of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for a slight, or but reputed Injury, they are so fir'd with Passion, that their hot Blood cannot be satisfied without the cold Blood of their Enemies. In short, many live in such open
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:64427:35"/>
defiance of the Divine Law, as if there were no God to see and punish their Sins, or as if they would make a trial whether he will be true to his Threatning, and revenge their bold Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: They are partly worse than Brutes; for having an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding Faculty, a Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Reason, they submit it to Sense: and partly worse than Devils; for as the Devils, they rebel against God, and yet not, as they, tremble in their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. Now when Death is ready with its cold Hands to close their Eyes, and Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence awakes out of its Slumber, what Horrors seize upon them! They are stripp'd of their car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Securities, the Creature can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not help them, and the Creator will not. They have been Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to that Love that made them and preserv'd them, and,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:64427:35"/>
notwithstanding their violent Provocations, has spar'd them so long. They have rejected that infinitely condescending and compassionate Love, that so tenderly beseech'd them to be reconciled to God, as if it were his Interest to save them. Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will they fly from their Judg? What can rescue them from instant and irrecoverable Misery? Can they hope that Mercy will be their Advocate? Their Condemnation is so righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, that Mercy cannot dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pense with it. <hi>'Tis a fearful thing to fall into the Hands of the living God,</hi> who lives for ever, and can punish for ever. Who <hi>knows the Power of his Wrath?</hi> 'Tis boundless beyond all our Thoughts and Time. O take notice of this with Terror, <hi>all ye that forget God, lest he tear you in pieces,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 50.</note> 
                  <hi>and there be none to deliver!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:64427:36"/>Others are not so visibly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient as notorious Sinners, but are as really. You may see their Picture in the disobedient Son, mentioned by our Saviour in the Gospel,<note place="margin">Matth. 21.28, 30.</note> who <hi>when his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commanded him to go work in the Vineyard, answered, I go, Sir, and went not.</hi> 'Tis true, they perform the external part of some Duties, and abstain from the gross acts of some Sins, but 'tis with an exception and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve. A Duty that is contrary to their carnal Appetites and Interest, they will not perform; a Sin that bribes them with Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit or Pleasure, a temperamental Sin, they will not part with. Now any indulged habitual Lust <hi>is not the Spot of God's Children,</hi> but denominates the Sinner a Child of the Devil: for tho the Saints till they are devested of frail Flesh, have
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:64427:36"/>
their Allays, and cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from the relicks of Sin; yet the Divine Nature commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to them, is opposite to every Sin, and is an active Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple to subdue Sin.</p>
               <p>And from hence S. <hi>John</hi> tells us, <hi>He that is born of God, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not sin,</hi> that is, deliberately and habitually: Such Sinners, tho in the Hour of Death they may address with all the applying Titles, <hi>Our Father, and our God,</hi> shall ever be excluded from his sacred and saving Protection.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let us seriously consider whether we are of this spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Progeny, the Children of God, not only in Title, but in Reality. The Inquiry is of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite moment; for all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises and Priviledges of the Gospel are annex'd to this Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship: This secures us from <hi>the Wrath to come,</hi> and entitles us
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:64427:37"/>
to the eternal Inheritance; <hi>Fear not,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 12.</note> 
                  <hi>little Flock, 'tis your Father's good Pleasure to give you the Kingdom.</hi> This Inquiry is very useful to calm and quiet the troubled Saints, and to awaken unregenerate Persons out of their confident Dream of their good State. Many sincere Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians are infinitely concern'd whether they are the Children of God; of this their Tears and Fears give abundant evidence. The reasons of their Doubts are partly the Jealousy of their own Hearts, which are naturally <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful above all things,</hi> and most deceitful to a Man's self; and partly from the consequence of the Deceit: for knowing the inestimable value of this Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, <hi>to be the Sons of God,</hi> and that if they are deceived in it, they are undone for ever, they are anxiously thoughtful about
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:64427:37"/>
it. But carnal Persons who are not acquainted with the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crisy of their Hearts, nor duly understand the excellence of the Privilege, easily believe what they coldly desire. And the great deceiver of Souls is equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly subtile to varnish what is evil with the false colours of Good, and to conceal what is good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the appearance of Evil. From hence it is, that many tender-spirited Christians are timorous, and full of unquiet Agitations all their Lives: and many who have but a shew and fair pretence of Religion, are undisturb'd and hopeful, till at last they fall from their suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Heaven and high Hopes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Abyss of Misery.</p>
               <p>This Trial will be most clear and convincing, by representing from Scripture the inseparable Properties and Characters of the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:64427:38"/>
Children of God, that distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish them from all that are in the State of unrenewed Nature. The Apostle tells sincere Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, <hi>The Spirit it self witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses with our Spirits, that we are the Children of God.</hi> Here is a Consent and Agreement of those Witnesses, in whom are all that is requisite to give value to their Testimony. For the Spirit of God, such is his unerring Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, <hi>who searches the deep things of God,</hi> and such is the abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Sanctity of his Nature, that he can neither deceive nor be deceived, so that his Testimony is infinitely sure, and of more worth than the concurrent Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony of Heaven and Earth, of Angels and Men. The other Witness is the renewed Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that is acquainted with the Aims and Affections of the Heart, as the Apostle saith,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:64427:38"/>
                  <hi>Who knows the things of a Man, save the Spirit of a Man?</hi> This Faculty reflects upon our Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the Principles of them: to this Faculty is referr'd the decision of our spiritual State; <hi>If our Hearts condemn us not</hi> of any allowed Sin,<note place="margin">1 John. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc></desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>then have we Peace towards God.</hi> From the consent and agreement of these Witnesses, there is a blessed As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance of our Evangelical Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, that overcomes all our Fears. Now this Testimony is rational and argumentative, from the discovery of those Graces that constitute a Person the Child of God. I will make the Inquiry concerning the Grace of Faith and of Love, which are the vital Bands of our Union with Christ, the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Fruits of the sanctifying Spirit, and the Symptoms of Salvation.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:64427:39"/>(1.) The Grace of Faith is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press'd in Scripture by <hi>receiving of Christ:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 1.12.</note> this answers to God's offer of him to our acceptance in the Gospel. It receives him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely in his Person and Natures, as the incarnate Son of God; and in his Office, as <hi>a Prince and Saviour,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 5.31.</note> 
                  <hi>to give Repentance and remission of Sins.</hi> This re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Christ implies an Act of the Understanding and the Will; the Understanding as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents to the Truth of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelation, that Christ crucified is an alsufficient Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; and the Will closes with the Terms of it, <hi>that he will save to the uttermost all that obey him</hi>: From hence it follows, that reliance upon him, and a sincere resolution to obey him, are necessarily included in sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Faith. This Scripture-Account distinguishes between
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:64427:39"/>
that substantial Faith that is proper to the elect Children of God, and the Shadow of it in the Unregenerate; the one is the intimate and active Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Obedience, the other is a dead Assent without Efficacy, a mere Carcass and Counterfeit of Faith. A sincere Believer as fervently desires to be saved from the Dominion and Pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Sins, as from the Guilt and deadly Malignity: a carnal Man desires an Interest in Christ as a Saviour, that he may securely enjoy his Lusts.</p>
               <p>The crafty and cursed Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent deceives Men to their ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, by citing Scripture, and misapplying it. The Promise is sure, <hi>Whoever believes, shall be saved</hi>; and he easily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swades them they are Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. 'Tis strange to astonish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that Men who have Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:64427:40"/>
and Understanding, should presume in a high degree of the present Favour of God, and their future Happiness, as if they were his dear Children, when their Enmity against his holy Name and Will is evident in their Actions.</p>
               <p>We can never have too firm a dependance on God's Promise, when we are qualified for that Dependance. <hi>Come out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.17, 18.</note> 
                  <hi>and be ye separate, saith the Lord; and touch not the unclean thing, and I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you, and will be a Father to you, saith the Lord Almighty.</hi> Faith that purifies the Heart and Conversation, invests us with this blessed Privilege, and all the saving Mercies annex'd to it.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) From the spiritual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation between God and Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, there naturally and neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarily
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:64427:40"/>
results a sincere, dutiful, child-like Love to him, corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spondent to his beneficent and fatherly Love to them: This God indispensably requires, and specially delights in; <hi>Thou lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest Truth in the inward Parts.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 51.</note> Filial Obedience is inseparable from filial Love in its Reality: <hi>For this is the Love of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Joh. 5.3.</note> 
                  <hi>that we keep his Commandments.</hi> Our Saviour distinguishes between sincere Lovers of him, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, that <hi>they who love him, keep his Commandments</hi>;<note place="margin">John 14.23, 24.</note> 
                  <hi>but they who love him not, keep not his Commandments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Obedience that springs from Love to God, is uniform, respects all his Commands: for the two filial Affections, an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Desire to please God in all things, and an ingenuous Fear of displeasing him in any thing, are inseparably joined with
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:64427:41"/>
our Love to him.</p>
               <p>The Obedience that proceeds from Love, is free and volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, from Inclination as well as Duty. How passionately does the holy Psalmist express his Affection, <hi>O how I love thy Law!</hi> In the Covenant of Grace, God promises to <hi>write his Law in the Hearts of his Children:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 8.10.</note> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their Minds and Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, but to endear it to their Affections. There is much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between servile and constrain'd Obedience, and fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al chosen Obedience, as between the Motion of a living Man from the Soul, the inward Spring of Life, and the Motion of an Image or Statue from forcible Weights and Wheels.</p>
               <p>From filial Love proceeds godly Sorrow, if at any time by Carelesness and Surprize, or an over powering Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:64427:41"/>
on, his Children do what is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fensive and odious in his sight. When they consider their unkind and unthankful Returns for his Mercies, they look to their Heavenly Father with Grief and Shame, and down upon themselves with Abhorrence and Indignation: They are wounded with the sting of that Expostulation, <hi>Do ye thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 32.6</note> 
                  <hi>O foolish People and unwise? Is he not thy Father who bought thee?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From filial Love proceeds a Zeal for his Glory; <hi>If I be a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, where is my Honour?</hi> A Child of God is dearly concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that his Name be reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and magnified, his Laws be observed, his Worship main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, that his Interest be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced in the World. He has a burning Zeal against Sin and presumptuous Sinners.<note place="margin">Psal. 69.</note> The
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:64427:42"/>
Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi> says, <hi>I have been jealous for the Lord of Hosts: for the Children of</hi> Israel <hi>have forsaken thy Covenant, and thrown down thine Altars.</hi> Those who with an indifferent Eye see the Cause, the Truth, the Interest of God depress'd in the World, do renounce the Title of his Children.</p>
               <p>From the Relation to God as his Sons, proceeds a sincere fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Love to all the Saints. St. <hi>John</hi> infers,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 5.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Every one that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth him that begat, loves him that is begotten.</hi> Grace is not less powerful in producing cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial mutual Affections between the Children of the same Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father, than the subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Endearments of Nature. Notwithstanding the civil Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction between them, some high and rich, others mean and poor, yet there is a spiritual
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:64427:42"/>
Equality; the lowest Saints are Princes of the Blood-Royal of Heaven. <hi>To him that has washed us from our Sins in his Blood,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Revel. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>and made us Kings and Priests to God, be Glory for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The filial Relation to God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines and encourages all sincere Christians to resign themselves, even in their most afflicted Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, to the Wisdom and Will of God. Our Saviour meekly yielded up himself to his cruel Enemies, upon this Considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>The Cup which my Father has given me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 18.11</note> 
                  <hi>shall I not drink it?</hi> The Saints in imitation of Christ, and upon the same Ground, entirely resign them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to the Divine Disposal; for their Heavenly Father loves them better than they can love themselves.</p>
               <p>Finally, The filial Relation to God is productive as of live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:64427:43"/>
Hopes, so of ardent Desires to be with him. Love makes them to esteem Communion with him here in his holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, as the Joy of their Lives. The Psalmist when ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish'd from the Tabernacle, breaks forth in his impatient De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires,<note place="margin">Psal. 43.</note> 
                  <hi>When shall I come and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before God?</hi> that is, in the Place where he communicates his Grace to those that worship him. But our Father is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as his Throne, and most gloriously exhibits himself to his Saints there. The Earth is the Element and Residence of carnal Men, of their Souls as well as their Bodies: They de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire their <hi>Inheritance may be on this side</hi> Jordan, and are content to leave the Heavenly <hi>Canaan</hi> to those who like it. But those who <hi>are born from above,</hi> desire <hi>to be dissolved,</hi> that they may
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:64427:43"/>
be in their Father's House, and his reviving Presence for ever.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Let us be perswaded to prepare for the reception of our Souls in the next World. The present Life is a Passage to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, and 'tis so short and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, so uncertain and hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous, that 'tis our principal Wisdom without delay to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure our Souls in the future State. Our Saviour says, <hi>I must work the Work of him that sent me while it is Day:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 9.4.</note> 
                  <hi>the Night cometh when no Man can work. Now is the accepted Time, now is the Day of Salvation.</hi> 'Tis our indispensable Duty and main In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest now, <hi>to work out our own Salvation with fear and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling.</hi> In the state of Death there is an Incapacity to do any thing in order to Salvation: <hi>There is no Work nor Wisdom in the Grave:</hi> and all the Offers of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:64427:44"/>
Salvation cease for ever. The Sufferings of the Son of God are not a Ransom for Sinners in that State: <hi>He reconciled things in Earth and in Heaven,</hi> but not things in Hell. The Golden Scepter is extended to none there, the Holy Spirit strives with none, they are without the Reserves of Mercy. The Guilt of Sin remains in its full Obligation, the Pollution of Sin in its deepest Die, and the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment of Sin in its Extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for ever.</p>
               <p>O what Folly is it, or rather Frenzy, not to provide for our Souls in their greatest Exigence! Common Reason instructs us, knowing our own Weakness, to commit our Treasure to the custody of our Friends, which we cannot otherwise keep from our Enemies; especially to such a Friend as can and will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:64427:44"/>
it for our Use and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. The Soul is our Jewel above all Price, 'tis our Wisdom to secure it out of all danger: Let us therefore commit it to the safe and sure Hands of our Heavenly Father, otherwise we cannot preserve it from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal Spirits, the Robbers and Murderers of Souls.</p>
               <p>The wise Preacher denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces a fearful Evil, <hi>Wo be to him that is alone when he falleth</hi>;<note place="margin">Eccl. 4.10.</note> 
                  <hi>for he hath not another to help him up.</hi> In all the Senses of falling, Death is the greatest Fall: the High, the Honourable, the Rich, fall from all their State; and Men of all Degrees are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saken of all their carnal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts and Supports. If then the solitary Soul has not a God to receive, support and comfort it, how woful is its Condition! Methinks the apprehension of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:64427:45"/>
this should strike a Terror so deep into the Hearts of Men, that they should be restless till they have secur'd a Retreat for their departing Souls.</p>
               <p>For this end let us, according to the earnest Advice of St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>be diligent, that we may be found of him in Peace, without spot, and blameless.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord Jesus is the only Peace-maker of the righteous and holy God to Sinners. The Judg of this World is flaming with Wrath, and terrible in Vengeance to Sinners that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before his Tribunal out of Christ. We shall for ever be excluded from his blessed Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, without the Mediator restore us to his Favour. Our Reconciliation only is by <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption in his Blood.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 1.20.</note> 
                  <hi>The Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stisement of our Peace was upon him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Isa. 53.</note> He is <hi>the Lord our Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness,</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:64427:45"/>
by whom alone we can stand in Judgment. <hi>God was in Christ reconciling the World to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self.</hi> There is now an Act of Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion offer'd in the Gospel to all that come <hi>to God by him.</hi> We have sure Salvation in his Name: But we must with consenting Wills, close with him as our Lord and Life. The first Gospel preach'd by the Angel after his coming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World, declares, <hi>There was born in the City of</hi> David <hi>a Saviour, Christ the Lord.</hi> We must not separate between Christ the Saviour, and Christ the Lord; between his Salvation and his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion. God indispensably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires we should resign our selves to his Son as our King, and rely upon him as our Priest to atone his Displeasure. If we thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him, he will restore us to the Favour and Peace of God, establisht in an everlasting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:64427:46"/>How tenderly and compassio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately does the great God invite Sinners to re-enter into his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, <hi>to acquaint our selves with him, and to be at peace! His Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadours in his Name, and in Christ's stead beseech them to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God.</hi> But their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse Spirits would <hi>have God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to them,</hi> that they might be exempt from Punishment; but are <hi>unwilling to be reconciled to him,</hi> to part with their Lusts. In short, reconciliation with God ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily infers defiance with Sin. <hi>Ye that love the Lord hate Evil.</hi> If Men do not cease their Rebellion, there is no shadow of hope to obtain the Divine Favour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Do ye provoke the Lord to Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousie, are you stronger than he?</hi> Jealousie is the most sensible and severe Affection. As 'tis with a Town taken by storm, all that are found in Arms are without
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:64427:46"/>
Mercy cut off; so all that at Death are found with the <hi>weapons of unrighteousness,</hi> their unrepented unforsaken Sins about them, must expect <hi>Judgment without Mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lastly, Let the Children of God be encouraged with Peace and Joy to commend their Souls to him. Let rebellious Sinners tremble with deadly Fear upon the brink of Eternity; but let the Saints, with a lively Hope, enter into the Divine World.</p>
               <p>If Men possess their Treasure with Joy and Jealousie, and guard it with vigilant Care, will not God preserve his dearest Treasure, the Souls of his Children committed to his Trust?</p>
               <p>Can Love forsake, can Truth deceive, can Almighty Power fail? Will a Father, a heavenly Father, be without Bowels to his own Off-spring? No, he cannot deny
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:64427:47"/>
himself: he is readiest to relieve, when they are in distress.</p>
               <p>Old <hi>Simeon</hi> is a leading Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to Believers: after he had embraced Christ in his Armes, how earnestly did he desire his Dissolution? <hi>Lord, now lettest thou thy Servant depart in peace, for mine eyes have seen thy Salvation.</hi> St. <hi>Stephen</hi> in the midst of a showr of Stones, with a blessed Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity, makes his dying Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>Lord Jesus receive my Spirit.</hi> If the Fears of humble Souls arise in that hour, because they have not the Conspicuous marks of God's Children, the Graces of the Spirit in that degree of Eminency, as some Saints have had: Let them consider, there are different Ages among the Children of God: some are in a state of Infancy and Infirmity; others are more Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd: but the relation is the same in all, and gives an interest
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:64427:47"/>
in his promised Mercy. The weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of their Faith cannot frustrate God's faithfulness. 'Tis the Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, not the Strength of Grace, that is requisite to Salvation. If Faith be shaking <hi>as a bruised reed,</hi> and but kindling as <hi>the smoaking flax,</hi> it shall be victorious. O that these powerfull Comforts may encourage dying Christians to commend their Souls with Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency and Assurance to God, their Father, and Felicity.</p>
               <p>I have now finisht my Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course upon the Text, and shall apply my self to speak of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Subject, the Reverend Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter,</hi> that Excellent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument of Divine Grace, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover and restore so many revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Souls to God, out of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of his Enemy: or in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles Language, <hi>to translate them from the Kingdom of Darkness, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:64427:48"/>
the Kingdom of his dear Son.</hi> I am sensible, that in speaking of him I shall be under a double Disadvantage: For those who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly knew him, will be apt to think my Account of him to be short and defective, an imperfect Shadow of his resplendent Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues: others who were unacquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with his extraordinary Worth, will from Ignorance or Envy be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to think his just Praises to be undue and excessive. Indeed if Love could make me eloquent, I should use all the most lively and graceful Colours of Language to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc></desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn his Memory: but this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration relieves me in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciousness of my Disability, that a plain Narrative of what Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> was, and did, will bee a most noble Eulogy: and that his substantial Piety no more needs artificial Oratory to set it off, than refined Gold wants Paint
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:64427:48"/>
to add Lustre and Value to it.</p>
               <p>I shall not speak of his Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and his first Years: but I must not omit a Testimony I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd concerning his early Piety. His Father said with Tears of Joy to a Friend, my Son <hi>Richard</hi> I hope was sanctified from the Womb: for when he was a little Boy in Coats, if he heard other Children in play speak profane Words, he would reprove them to the Wonder of those that heard him.</p>
               <p>He had not the Advantage of Academical Education: but by the Divine Blessing upon his rare Dexterity and Diligence, his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Knowledge was in that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Eminence, as few in the University ever arrive to. Not long after his Entrance into the Ministry the Civil War began, and the Times rain'd Blood so
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:64427:49"/>
long, till the languishing State of the Kingdom, was almost despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and incurable. How far he was concern'd as a Chaplain in the Parliament's Army, he has publisht an Account, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of it.</p>
               <p>After the War, he was fixt at <hi>Kederminster.</hi> There his Ministry by the Divine Influence, was of admirable Efficacy. The Harvest answer'd the Seed that was sow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Before his coming, the Place was like a Piece of dry and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren Earth, onely Ignorance and Profaneness as Natives of the Soil were rise among them; but by the Blessing of Heaven upon his Labour and Cultivating, the Face of Paradise appear'd there in all the Fruits of Righteousness. Many were translated from the state of pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted Nature, to the state of Grace; and many were advanc'd to higher degrees of Holiness. The bad were
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:64427:49"/>
chang'd to good, and the good to better. Conversion is the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Work of Divine Grace: the Efficacy of the Means is from the Supreme Mover. But God usual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly makes those Ministers success<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in that Blessed Work, whose principal Design and Delight is to glorifie him in the saving of Souls. This was the reigning Affection in his Heart; and he was extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily qualified to obtain his End.</p>
               <p>His Prayers were an Effusion of the most lively melting Expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and his intimate ardent Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections to God; from the <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of his Heart his Lips spake.</hi> His Soul took Wing for Heaven, and rapt up the Souls of others with him. Never did I see or hear a holy Minister address himself to God with more Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and Humility, with respect to his glorious Greatness; never
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:64427:50"/>
with more Zeal and Fervency cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>respondent to the infinite Moment of his requests; nor with more Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial Affiance in the Divine Mercy.</p>
               <p>In his Sermons there was a rare Union of Arguments and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to convince the Mind and gain the Heart: All the Fountains of Reason and Perswasion were open to his discerning Eye. There was no resisting the Force of his Discourses without denying Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and Divine Revelation. He had a marvellous Felicity and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piousness in speaking. There was a noble Negligence in his Stile: for his great Mind could not stoop to the affected Eloquence of Words: he despis'd flashy Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory: but his Expressions were clear and powerful, so convincing the Understanding, so entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Soul, so engaging the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, that those were as deaf as Adders, who were not <hi>charm'd
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:64427:50"/>
by so wise a Charmer.</hi> He was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimated with the Holy Spirit, and breath'd Celestial Fire, to inspire Heat and Life into dead Sinners, and to melt the obdurate in their frozen Tombs. Methinks I still hear him speak those powerfull Words:<note place="margin">His Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the House of Commons 1660.</note> 
                  <hi>A Wretch that is condemn'd to dy to Morrow cannot forget it: And yet poor Sinners, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually are uncertain to live an Hour, and certain speedily to see the Majesty of the Lord to their unconceivable Joy or Terror, as sure as they now live on Earth, can forget these things for which they have their memory: and which one would think should drown the matters of this World, as the report of a Canon does a Whisper, or as the Sun obscures the poorest Glo-worm. O won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull stupidity of an unrenewed Soul! O wonderfull folly and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stractedness of the ungodly! That
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:64427:51"/>
ever Men can forget, I say again, that they can forget, Eternal joy, Eternal Woe, and the Eternal God, and the place of their Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal unchangeable Abodes, when they stand even at the door; and there is but the thin Vail of Flesh between them and that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazing sight, that Eternal gulph, and they are daily dying and step<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Besides, his wonderfull diligence in Catechizing the particular Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies under his Charge, was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding usefull to plant Religion in them. Personal instruction, and application of Divine Truths, has an excellent advantage and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy to insinuate and infuse Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion into the Minds and Hearts of Men, and by the Conversion of Parents and Masters to reform whole Families that are under their immediate direction and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. While he was at <hi>Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derminster</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:64427:51"/>
he wrote and publisht that accomplisht Model of an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical Minister, styled <hi>Gildas Salvianus,</hi> or the Reform'd Pastor: In that book, he clears beyond all cavil, That the Duty of Ministers is not confin'd to their Study and the Pulpit, but that they should make use of opportunities to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct Families within their Care, as 'tis said by the Apostle, that he had kept back nothing from his Hearers <hi>that was profitable, but had taught them publickly, and from house to house.</hi> The Idea of a faithfull Minister delineated in that book, was a Copy taken from the Life, from his own zealous Example. His unwearied industry to do good to his Flock, was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer'd by Correspondent Love and Thankfulness. He was an Angel in their Esteem. He would often speak with great Complacence of their dear Affections: and a little
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:64427:52"/>
before his Death, said, He believ'd they were more Expressive of kindness to him, than the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Converts were to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle <hi>Paul,</hi> by what appears in his Writings.</p>
               <p>While he remain'd at <hi>Keder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster,</hi> his Illustrious Worth was not shaded in a Corner, but dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers'd its Beams and Influence round the Countrey. By his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel and Excitation, the Ministers in <hi>Worcestershire,</hi> Episcopal, Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian and Congregational were united, that by their Studies, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and Advice, the Doctrine and Practise of Religion, the Truths and Holiness of the Gospel might be preserved in all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches committed to their Charge. This Association was of excellent use, the ends of Church-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were obtain'd by it: and it was a leading Example to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of other Counties. Mr.
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:64427:52"/>
                  <hi>Baxter</hi> was not above his Brethren Ministers, by a Superiour Title, or any secular advantage, but by his divine endowments and sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate excellencies, his extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wisdom, zeal, and fidelity: he was the Soul of that Happy So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety.</p>
               <p>He continued among his beloved people, till the year 1660. then he came to <hi>London.</hi> A while after the King's Restoration, there were many Endeavours us'd in order to an Agreement between the Episco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal and Presbyterian Ministers. For this end several of the Bishops elect, and of the Ministers, were call'd to attend the King at <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester</hi>-House: there was read to them a Declaration, drawn up with great wisdom and moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by the Lord Chancellor the Earl of <hi>Clarendon.</hi> I shall onely observe that in reading the several parts of the Declaration, Dr. <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:64427:53"/>
was the principal manager of the Conference among the Bishops, and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> among the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters: and one particular I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forget; it was desir'd by the Ministers, that the Bishops should exercise their Church Power with the counsel and consent of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters. This limiting of their Authority was so displeasing, that Dr. <hi>Cosins,</hi> then elect of <hi>Durham,</hi> said, If your Majesty grants this you will Unbishop your Bishops. Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> upon this produced the Book, entituled, <hi>The Portrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of his Sacred Majesty in his Solitude and Sufferings,</hi> and read the following Passage: <hi>Not that I am against the managing of this Presidency and Authority in One Man by the joint Counsel and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of many Presbyters: I have offer'd to restore that, as a fit means to avoid those Errors, Corruptions and Partialities, which are incident
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:64427:53"/>
to any One Man: also to avoid Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, which becomes no Christians, least of all Church-men. Besides, it will be a means to take away that burthen and odium of affairs, which may lie too heavy on one Man's shoulders, as indeed I think it did formerly on the Bishops here.</hi> The good Doctor thought, that the Judgment of the King's afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and inquiring Father would have been of great moment to incline him to that temperament: but the King presently replied, <hi>All that is in that Book is not Gospel.</hi> My Lord Chancellor prudently moderated in that matter, that the Bishops, in weighty Causes, should have the assistance of the Presbyters.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> considering the state of our affairs in that time, was well pleased with that Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: He was of <hi>Calvin</hi>'s mind, who judiciously observes, upon
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:64427:54"/>
our Saviour's words, That <hi>the Son of Man shall send forth his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and they shall gather out of his Kingdom all things that offend: Qui ad extirpandum quicquid dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicet praepostere festinant, ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertant Christi judicium, &amp; erep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Angelis officium sibi temere usurpant. They that make too much haste to redress at once all things that are amiss, anticipate the Judgment of Christ, and rashly usurp the Office of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</hi> Besides, that Declaration granted such a freedom to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scientious Ministers, that were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satisfied as to the Old Conformity, that if it had been observed, it had prevented the dolefull Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion succeeded afterward. But when there was a motion made in the House of Commons, that the Declaration might pass into an Act, it was oppos'd by one of the Secretarys of State, which
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:64427:54"/>
was a sufficient Indication of the King's averseness to it.</p>
               <p>After the Declaration there were many Conferences at the <hi>Savoy</hi> between the Bishops and some Doctors of their Party, with Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and some other Ministers, for an Agreement, wherein his Zeal for Peace was most conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous: but all was in vain. Of the Particulars that were debated, he has given an account in Print.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> after his coming to <hi>London,</hi> during the time of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, did not neglect that which was the principal Exercise of his Life, the preaching the Gospel, being always sensible of his duty of saving Souls. He Preacht at St. <hi>Dunstans</hi> on the Lord's-days in the Afternoon. I remember one instance of his firm Faith in the Divine Providence, and his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude when he was engaged in
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:64427:55"/>
his Ministry there. The Church was Old, and the People were apprehensive of some danger in meeting in it: and while Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> was Preaching, something in the Steeple fell down, and the noise struck such a terror into the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they presently, in a wild dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, run out of the Church: their eagerness to haste away, put all into a tumult: Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> without visible disturbance, sat down in the Pulpit: after the hurry was over, he resum'd his Discourse, and said, to compose their Minds; <hi>We are in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God to prepare our selves, that we may be fearless at the great noise of the dissolving World, when the Heavens shall pass away, and the Elements melt in fervent heat; the Earth also, and the Works therein shall be burnt up.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:64427:55"/>After the Church of St. <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stans</hi> was pull'd down in order to its re-building, he removed to <hi>Black-Fryars,</hi> and continued his preaching there to a vast Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of Hearers, till the fatal <hi>Bartholomew.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Year 1661, a Parliament was call'd, wherein was past the Act of Uniformity, that expell'd from their publick Places about two thousand Ministers. I will onely take notice concerning the Causes of that Proceeding, that the Old Clergy from Wrath and Revenge, and the young Gentry from their servile Compliance with the Court, and their Distaste of seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Religion, were very active to carry on and compleat that Act. That this is no rash Imputation upon the ruling Clergy then is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, not onely from their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:64427:56"/>
in passing that Law, for Actions have a Language as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing as that of Words, but from Dr. <hi>Sheldon</hi> then Bishop of <hi>London</hi> their great Leader; who when the Lord Chamberlain <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chester,</hi> told the King, while the Act of Uniformity was under de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, <hi>that he was afraid the Terms of it were so rigid, that many of the Ministers would not comply with it</hi>; he replyed, <hi>I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid they will.</hi> This Act was past after the King had engaged his Faith and Honour in his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration from <hi>Breda, to preserve the Liberty of Conscience inviolate,</hi> which promise open'd the way for his Restorat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc></desc>
                  </gap>on; and after the Royalists here, had given publick Assurance, that all former Animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities should be buried, <hi>as Rubbish under the Foundation of a Vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal Concord.</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volv'd with so many Ministers in
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:64427:56"/>
this Calamity, who was their brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Ornament, and the best De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of their righteous, though oppressed Cause: Two Observati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he made upon that Act and our Ejection.</p>
               <p>The one was, that the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters were turned and kept out from the publick Exercise of their Office, in that time of their Lives, that was most fit to be dedicated end employed for the Service and Glory of God, that is between thirty and sixty Years, when their intellectual and instrumental Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties were in their Vigour. The other was in a Letter to me after the Death of several Bishops who were concurrent in passing that Act, and exprest no Sorrow for it: his words were, <hi>for ought I see, the Bishops will own the turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of us out, at the Tribunal of Christ, and thither we appeal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:64427:57"/>After the Act of Uniformity had taken its effect, in the Ejection of so many Ministers, there was sometimes a Connivance at the private Exercise of their Ministry, sometime publick Indulgence gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and often a severe Prosecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them, as the Popish and Politick Interest of the Court va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried. When there was Liberty, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> applyed himself to his delightful Work, to the great Advantage of those who enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Ministry. But the Church-Party oppos'd vehemently the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty that was granted. Indeed such was their Fierceness, that if the Dissenting Ministers <hi>had been as wise as Serpents, and as innocent as Doves,</hi> they could not escape their deep Censures. The Pulpit represented them as seditiously disaffected to the State, as obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Schismaticks, and often the <hi>Name of God was not onely taken
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:64427:57"/>
in vain, but in violence,</hi> to autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rise their hard Speeches, and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Actions against them. Some drops of that Storm fell upon Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who calmly submit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their injurious dealings. I shall speak of that afterward.</p>
               <p>In the Interval, between his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privation and his Death, he wrote and publisht the most of his Books, of which I shall give some account.</p>
               <p>His Books, for their number and variety of Matter in them, make a Library. They contain a Treasure of Controversial, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suistical, Positive and Practical Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity. Of them I shall relate the Words of one, whose exact Judgment, joyn'd with his Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, will give a great value to his Testimony; they are of the very Reverend Dr. <hi>Wilkins,</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Bishop of <hi>Chester:</hi> he said that Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> had <hi>cultivated e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Subject he handled;</hi> and <hi>if he
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:64427:58"/>
had lived in the Primitive Times, he had been one of the Fathers of the Church.</hi> I shall add what he said with admiration of him ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time, <hi>That it was enough for one Age to produce such a Person as Mr.</hi> Baxter. Indeed, he had such an amplitude in his Thoughts, such vivacity of Imagination, and such solidity and depth of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as rarely meet together. His inquiring Mind was freed from the servile dejection and bondage of an implicit Faith. He adher'd to the Scriptures as the perfect Rule of Faith, and searcht whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Doctrines received and taught were Consonant to it. This is the duty of every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian according to his capacity, especially of Ministers, and the necessary means to open the Mind for Divine Knowledge, and for the advancement of the Truth. He publisht several Books against the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:64427:58"/>
Papists with that clearness and strength, as will Confound, if not Convince them. He said, <hi>he one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly desir'd Armies and Antiquity against the Papists: Armies,</hi> he cause of their bloody Religion so often exemplified in <hi>England, Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France</hi> and other Countries. However they may appear on the Stage, they are always the same persons in the Tyring-room: their Religion binds them to extirpate Hereticks, and often over-rules the milder inclinations of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: <hi>Antiquity,</hi> because they are inveigled with a fond pretence to it, as if it were favourable to their Cause: but it has been demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated by many learned Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, that the Argument of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity is directly against the principal Doctrines of Popery, as that of the Supremacy, of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>substantiation, of Image-worship, and others.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:64427:59"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>His Books of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonableness of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi>
                  </note>He has wrote several excellent Books against the impudent Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ism of this loose Age. In them he establishes the fundamental Principle, upon which the whole Fabrick of Christianity is built; that after this short uncertain life, there is a future state of happiness or misery equally Eternal, and that Death is the last irrevocable step into that unchangeable state. From hence it follows by infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Consequence, that the reason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Creature should prefer the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest of the Soul before that of the Body, and secure Eternal life. This being laid, he proves the Christian Religion to be the onely way of fallen Man's being restor'd to the favour of God, and obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a blessed Immortality. This great Argument he manages with that clearness and strength, that none can refuse assent unto it, without denying the infallible
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:64427:59"/>
Principles of Faith, and the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Principles of Nature.</p>
               <p>He also publisht some warm Discourses, to Apologize for the Preaching of Dissenting Ministers, and to excite them to do their Duty. He did not think that Act of Uniformity could disoblige them from the Exercise of their Office. 'Tis true, Magistrates are Titular-Gods by their Deputation and Vicegerency, but subordinate and accountable to God above. Their Laws have no binding force upon the Conscience, but from his Command; and if contrary to his Law, are to be disobeyed. The Ministers Consecrated to the Service of God are under a moral perpetual Obligation of Preaching the saving Truths of the Gospel, as they have opportunity. There needs no miraculous Testimony of their Commission from Heaven, to authorize the doing their ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Duty.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:64427:60"/>In some points of modern Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversie he judiciously chose the middle way, and advised young Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines to follow it. His reverence of the Divine Purity, made him very shy and jealous of any Doctrine that seem'd to reflect a blemish and stain upon it. He was a clear as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serter of the soveraign Freeness, and infallible Efficacy of Divine Grace in the Conversion of Souls. In a Sermon reciting the Words of the Covenant of Grace, <hi>I will put my fear into their hearts, and they shall not depart from me;</hi> he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served the Tenor of it was, <hi>I will, and you shall.</hi> Divine Grace makes the rebellious Will obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, but does not make the Will to be no Will. By the Illuminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Mind, the Will is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to Obedience, according to the Words of our Saviour, <hi>All that have heard and learn'd of the Father come to me.</hi> He preach'd that the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:64427:60"/>
Death of Christ was certainly ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual for all the Elect to make them partakers of Grace and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and that it was so far benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to all Men, that they are not left in the same desperate State with the fallen Angels, but are made capable of Salvation by the Grace of the Gospel: not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Efficience to convert them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, but as Subjects to receive saving Grace. He did so honour the sincerity of God, as entirely to believe his Will declared in his Word: he would not interpret the Promises of the Gospel in a less gracious sense than God intended them: Therefore if Men finally perish, 'tis not for want of Mercy in God, nor Merits in Christ, but for their wilfull refusing Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>His Books of Practical Divinity have been effectual for more nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Conversions of Sinners to
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:64427:61"/>
God, than any printed in our time: and while the Church re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains on Earth, will be of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Efficacy to recover lost Souls. There is a vigorous Pulse in them that keeps the Reader a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake and attentive. His Book of the <hi>Saints Everlasting Rest,</hi> was written by him when languishing in the suspence of Life and Death, but has the Signatures of his holy and vigorous Mind. To allure our Desires, he unvails the Sanctuary above, and discovers the Glory and Joys of the Blessed in the Divine Presence, by a Light so strong and lively, that all the glittering Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of this World vanish in that Comparison, and a sincere Believer will despise them, as one of mature Age does the Toys and Baubles of Children. To excite our fear he removes the Skreen, and makes the Everlasting Fire of Hell so visible, and represents the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:64427:61"/>
Passions of the Damned in those dreadfull Colours, that if duly considered, would check and controul the unbridled licentious Appetites of the most sensual Wretches.</p>
               <p>His <hi>Call to the Vnconverted;</hi> how small in bulk, but how pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull in vertue? Truth speaks in it with that authority and effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that it makes the Reader to lay his hand upon his heart, and find he has a Soul and a Conscience, though he lived before as if he had none. He told some friends, that six Brothers were Converted by reading that Call; and that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Week he received Letters of some Converted by his Books. This he spake with most humble thankfulness, that God was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to use him as an instrument for the Salvation of Souls.</p>
               <p>He that was so solicitous for the Salvation of others, was not neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:64427:62"/>
of his own; but as regular Love requires, his first Care was to prepare himself for Heaven. In him the Vertues of the Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plative and Active Life were emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently united. His time was spent in Communion with God, and in Charity to Men. He lived above the sensible World, and in solitude and silence convers'd with God. The frequent and serious Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Eternal things was the powerfull means to make his Heart holy and heavenly, and from thence his Conversation. His Life was a practical Sermon, a drawing Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. There was an Air of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and Sanctity in his morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Countenance; and his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment was becoming a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger upon Earth, and a Citizen of Heaven.</p>
               <p>Though all Divine Graces, the <hi>fruit of the Spirit,</hi> were visible in his Conversation, yet some were more eminent.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:64427:62"/>Humility is to other Graces, as the Morning-Star is to the Sun, that goes before it, and follows it in the Evening: Humility pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares us for the receiving of Grace, <hi>God gives Grace to the humble:</hi> and it follows the Exercise of Grace; <hi>Not I,</hi> says the Apostle, <hi>but the Grace of God in me.</hi> In Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> there was a rare Union of sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime Knowledge, and other spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Excellencies, with the lowest opinion of himself. He wrote to one that sent a Letter to him full of Expressions of Honour and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem, <hi>You do admire one you do not know; Knowledge will cure your Error. The more we know God, the more reason we see to admire him</hi>; but our knowledge of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture discovers its imperfections, and lessens our esteem. To the same person expressing his Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of him for his excellent Gifts and Graces, he replied with
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:64427:63"/>
heat, <hi>I have the remainders of pride in me, how dare you blow up the sparks of it?</hi> He desir'd some Ministers, his chosen friends, to meet at his House, and spend a day in Prayer for his direction in a matter of moment: before the Duty was begun, he said, <hi>I have desir'd your assistance at this time, because I believe God will sooner hear your Prayers than mine.</hi> He imitated St. <hi>Austin</hi> both in his Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitential Confessions, and Retracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. In conjunction with Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, he had great Candor for others. He could willingly bear with persons of differing Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: <hi>he would not prostitute his own judgment, nor ravish anothers.</hi> He did not over-esteem himself, nor under-value others. He would give liberal Encomiums of many Conforming Divines. He was se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere to himself, but candid in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusing the faults of others. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:64427:63"/>
the busie Inquirer and Censurer of the faults of others, is usually the easie Neglecter of his own.</p>
               <p>Self-denial and Contempt of the World were shining Graces in him. I never knew any person less indulgent to himself, and more indifferent to his Temporal interest. The offer of a Bisho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prick was no temptation to him: for his exalted Soul despised the Pleasures and Profits which others so earnestly desire; he valued not an empty Title upon his Tomb.</p>
               <p>His Patience was truly Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. God does often try his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by Afflictions, to exercise their Graces, to occasion their Victory, and to entitle them to a triumphant Felicity.</p>
               <p>This Saint was tried by many Afflictions. We are very tender of our Reputation: his Name was obscur'd under a Cloud of detrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Many slanderous Darts were
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:64427:64"/>
thrown at him. He was charg'd with Schism and Sedition. He was accus'd for his Paraphrase up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the New Testament, as guilty of disloyal Aspersions upon the Government, and Condemn'd, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, to a Prison, where he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc></desc>
                  </gap>d for some years. But he was so far from being moved at the unrighteous prosecution, that he joyfully said to a constant friend, <hi>What could I desire more of God, than after having serv'd him to my power, I should now be called to suffer for him.</hi> One who had been a fierce Dissenter, was afterward rankled with an opposite heat, and very contumeliously in his Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings reflected upon Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who calmly endur'd his Contempt: and when the same person publisht a learned Discourse in Defence of Christianity, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> said, <hi>I forgive him all for his Writing that Book.</hi> Indeed he was so much the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:64427:64"/>
more truly honourable, as he was thought worthy of the hatred of those persons.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, the Censures and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches of others whom he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steemed and loved, toucht him in the tender part. But he, with the great Apostle, <hi>counted it a small thing to be judg'd by Mens day.</hi> He was entire to his Conscience, and independent upon the opinion of others. But his Patience was more eminently tried by his continual pains and languishing. Martyrdom is a more easie way of dying, when the Combat and the Victory are finisht at once, than to dye by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees every day. His Complaints were frequent, but who ever heard an unsubmissive word drop from his lips? He was not put out of his Patience, nor out of the posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of himself. In his sharp Pains, he said, <hi>I have a rational Patience, and a believing Patience,</hi> though sense would recoil.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:64427:65"/>His pacifick Spirit was a clear Character of his being a Child of God. How ardently he endeavour'd to cement the breaches among us, which others widen and keep open, is publickly known. He said to a friend, <hi>I can as willingly be a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr for Love, as for any Article of the Creed.</hi> 'Tis strange to astonish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that those who agree in the substantial and great Points of the Reformed Religion, and are of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Sentiments onely in things not so clear, nor of that moment as those wherein they consent, should still be opposite Parties. Methinks the remembrance how our Divisions lately expos'd us to our watchfull Adversary, and were almost fatal to the interest of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, should conciliate our Affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Our common danger and common deliverance, should pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our Spirits for a sincere and firm Union. When our Sky was
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:64427:65"/>
so dark without a glimmering Horizon, then by a new dawning of God's wonderful Providence, a Deliverer appear'd, our gracious Soveraign, who has the Honour of establishing our Religion at home, and gives us hopes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storing it abroad, in places from whence it has been so unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously and cruelly expell'd. May the Union of his Protestant Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in religious things so desir'd by wise and good Men, be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plisht by his princely Counsel and Authority. Integrity with Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty would remove those things that have so long disunited us. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from this Digression.</p>
               <p>Love to the Souls of Men was the peculiar Character of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Spirit. In this he imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and honoured our Saviour, who prayed, dyed, and lives for the Salvation of Souls. All his natural and supernatural Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:64427:66"/>
were subservient to this blessed End. It was <hi>his Meat and Drink,</hi> the Life and Joy of his Life to doe good to Souls. His Industry was almost incredible in his Studies: he had a sensitive na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture desirous of ease as others have, and saint Faculties, yet such was the continual Application of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to his great Work, as if the Labour of one Day had supplyed strength for another, <hi>and the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingness of the Spirit had supported the Weakness of the Flesh.</hi> In his usual Conversation, his serious, frequent and delightfull Discourse was of Divine things, to inflame his Friends with the Love of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. He received with tender Compassion and condescending Kindness, the meanest that came to him for Councel and Consola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. He gave in one year a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Pounds to buy Bibles for the poor. He has in his Will dispos'd
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:64427:66"/>
of all that remains of his Estate after the Legacies to his Kindred, for the benefit of the Souls and Bodies of the Poor. He continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to preach so long notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his wasted languishing Body, that the last time, he almost died in the Pulpit. It would have been his joy to have been <hi>transfigured in the Mount.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not long after his last Sermon, he felt the Approaches of Death, and was confin'd to his sick Bed. Death reveals the Secrets of the Heart, then words are spoken with most feeling and least Affectation. This excellent Saint was the same in his Life and Death: his last Hours were spent in preparing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and himself to appear before God. He said to his Friends that visited him, <hi>You come hither to learn to dye, I am not the onely Person that must go this way, I can assure you, that your whole Life be
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:64427:67"/>
it never so long is little enough to prepare for Death. Have a care of this vain deceitful World, and the Lusts of the Flesh: be sure you choose God for your portion, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for your home, God's Glory for your end, His word for your rule, and then you need never fear but we shall meet with Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Never was a Sinner more hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and debasing himself, never was a sincere Believer more calm and comfortable. He acknowledged himself to be the vilest Dunghil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worm ('twas his usual Expression) that ever went to Heaven. He admir'd the Divine Condescension to us, often saying, <hi>Lord what is Man, what am I vile Worm to the great God?</hi> Many times he prayed, <hi>God be merciful to me a Sinner,</hi> and blessed God, that that was left upon record in the Gospel as an effectual Prayer. He said, <hi>God
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:64427:67"/>
may justly condemn me for the best Duty I ever did: and all my hopes are from the free Mercy of God in Christ,</hi> which he often prayed for.</p>
               <p>After a slumber he wak'd and said, <hi>I shall rest from my Labour:</hi> a Minister then present said, <hi>And your Works follow you:</hi> to whom he replyed, <hi>No Works, I will leave out Works, if God will grant me the other.</hi> When a Friend was comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him with the remembrance of the good many had received by his preaching and Writings, he said, <hi>I was but a Pen in God's hand, and what praise is due to a Pen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His resign'd Submission to the Will of God in his sharp Sickness, was eminent. When extremity of pain constrain'd him earnestly to pray to God for his release by Death, he would check himself; <hi>It is not fit for me to prescribe, and said, when thou wilt, what thou wilt, how thou wilt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:64427:68"/>Being in great Anguish, he said, <hi>O how unsearchable are his ways and his paths past finding out! the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of his Providence we cannot fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thom:</hi> and to his Friends, <hi>Do not think the worse of Religion for what you see me suffer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being often ask'd by his Friends, how it was with his inward Man, he replied, <hi>I bless God I have a well-grounded Assurance of my Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Happiness, and great Peace and Comfort within; but it was his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble he could not triumphantly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press it, by reason of his extreme pains.</hi> He said, <hi>Flesh must perish, and we must feel the perishing of it: and that though his Judgment sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, yet sense would still make him groan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being asked by a Person of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, whether he had not great Joy from his believing Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of the invisible State, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied: <hi>What else think you Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:64427:68"/>
serves for?</hi> He said, <hi>The Consideration of the Deity in his Glory and Greatness was too high for our Thoughts; but the Conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Son of God in our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and of the Saints in Heaven, whom he knew and loved, did much sweeten and familiarize Heaven to him.</hi> The description of Heaven in the 12. to the <hi>Heb.</hi> and the 22. was most comfortable to him: <hi>That he was going to the innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble company of Angels, and to the general Assembly and Church of the first-born, whose Names are written in Heaven; and to God the Judge of all, and to the spirits of just men made perfect; And to Jesus the Mediator of the new Covenant, and to the blood of sprinkling that speaks better things than the blood of Abel.</hi> That Scripture, he said, <hi>deserved a thousand thousand thoughts:</hi> He said, <hi>O how comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table is that promise, Eye has not
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:64427:69"/>
seen, nor Ear heard, neither hath it entred into the heart of Man to conceive the things God hath laid up for those who love him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At another time he said, <hi>That he found great comfort and sweetness in repeating the words of the Lord's Prayer, and was sorry that some good people were prejudiced against the use of it; for there were all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary Petitions for Soul and Body contain'd in it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At other times he gave excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Counsel to young Ministers that visited him, <hi>and earnestly prayed to God to bless their labours, and make them very successfull in Converting many Souls to Christ:</hi> And express'd great joy in the hopes that God would do a great deal of good by them; and that they were of moderate peacefull Spirits.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:64427:69"/>He did often pray that God <hi>would be mercifull to this misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble distracted World: and that he would preserve his Church and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest in it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He advis'd his Friends to <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of self-conceitedness, as a Sin that was likely to ruine this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> and said, <hi>I have written a Book against it, which I am afraid has done little good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being askd whether he had alter'd his mind in Controversial Points, he said, <hi>Those that please may know my mind in my Writings: and what he had done was not for his own Reputation, but the Glory of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I went to him with a very wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Friend, Mr. <hi>Mather</hi> of <hi>New-England,</hi> the day before he died, and speaking some comforting Words to him, he replyed, <hi>I have pain, there is no arguing against sense, but I have peace, I have peace.</hi>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:64427:70"/>
I told him you are now approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your long-desir'd home, he answer'd, <hi>I believe, I believe.</hi> He, said to Mr. <hi>Mather, I bless God that you have accomplisht your busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, the Lord prolong your Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He exprest a great willingness to dye, and during his Sickness, when the Question was ask'd, how he did, his reply was, <hi>almost well.</hi> His joy was most remarkable, when in his own apprehensions Death was nearest: and his Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Joy at length was consum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate in Eternal Joy.</p>
               <p>Thus lived and dyed that bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Saint. I have without any ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial Fiction of words, given a sincere short Account of him. All our Tears are below the just grief for such an unvaluable Loss. It is the Comfort of his Friends, that he enjoys a blessed Reward in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and has left a precious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance on the Earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:64427:70"/>Now blessed be the gracious God, that he was pleased to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the Life of his Servant, so useful and beneficial to the World to a full Age: that he has brought him slowly and safely to Heaven. I shall conclude this Account with my own deliberate Wish: May I live the short remainder of my Life, as entirely to the Glory of God, as he lived; and when I shall come to the Period of my Life, may I dye in the same blessed Peace wherein he died; may I be with him in the Kingdom of Light and Love for ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>I Shall annex two Passages decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory, the one of his Humility, the other of his Excellent Abilities. He had such an Abhorrence of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self for his Sins, that he said to a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister, <hi>I can more easily believe, that
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:64427:71"/>
God will forgive me, than I can for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give my self.</hi> The other was being in the Pulpit to preach, he found that he had forgot to put his Notes into his Bible: he pray'd to God for his Assistance, and took the first Text that occurr'd to his View in opening the Bible: and preach'd an Excellent Sermon for the Matter and Order of it upon the Priesthood of Christ. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he was come down, he enquir'd of a Minister present, whether he had not tir'd him, who replyed, <hi>No</hi>; but with several others declar'd they were exceedingly satisfied with his Discourse: he said, <hi>It was necessary to have a Body of Divinity in ones Head.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:64427:71"/>
            <head>BOOKS writ by <hi>William Bates,</hi> D. D. and sold by B. Aylmer.</head>
            <p>THE Harmony of the Divine Attributes, in the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance and Accomplishment of Man's Redemption by the Lord Jesus Christ: Or Discourses, wherein is shewed, how the Wisdom, Mercy, Justice, Holiness, Power, and Truth of God are glorified in that great and blessed Work, In <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Considerations of the Existence of God, and of the Immortality of the Soul, with the Recompence of the Future State. To which is added the Divinity of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Religion, proved by the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Reason, and Divine Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, for the Cure of Infidelity, the Hectick Evil of the Times. In <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:64427:72"/>The Soveraign and Final Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness of Man, with the effectual Means to obtain it. In <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Four Last Things, Death and Judgment, Heaven and Hell, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctically considered and applied, in several Discourses. In <hi>Octavo,</hi> and <hi>Duodecimo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Danger of Prosperity disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, in several Sermons, upon <hi>Prov. 1.17.</hi> In <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The great Duty of Resignation in Times of Affliction, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In <hi>Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Funeral Sermon preached up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Death of the Reverend and Excellent Divine, Dr. <hi>Thomas Manton,</hi> who deceased <hi>October 18, 1677.</hi> To which is added, the last publick Sermon Dr. <hi>Manton</hi> preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. In <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:64427:72"/>The Sure Trial of Vprightness, opened in several Sermons, upon <hi>Psal. 18.</hi> v. <hi>23.</hi> In <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Description of the Blessed Place and State of the Saints a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, in a Discourse on <hi>John 14.2.</hi> Preached at the Funeral of Mr. <hi>Clarkson.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Way to the highest Honour, on <hi>John 12.26.</hi> Preached at the Funeral of Dr. <hi>Jacomb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Speedy Coming of Christ to Judgment, on <hi>Rev. 22.12.</hi> Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the Funeral of Mr. <hi>Benj. Ashurst.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Funeral Sermon for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend, Holy and Excellent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter,</hi> who Deceased <hi>December</hi> the <hi>8</hi>th. <hi>1691.</hi> With an Account of his Life.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:64427:73"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>NEwly printed, The Holy Bible, containing the Old Testament and the New: With Annotations and Parallel Scriptures. To which is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex'd, The Harmony of the Gospels: As also, the Reduction of the Jewish Weights, Coins and Measures, to our English Standards. And a Table of the Promises in Scripture. By <hi>Samuel Clark,</hi> Minister of the Gospel. Printed in Folio of a very fair Letter; the like never before in one Volume. Printed for <hi>Brabazon Aylmer</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64427:73"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
