<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The triumphant chariot of antimony being a conscientious discovery of the many reall transcendent excellencies included in that minerall / written by Basil Valentine ... ; faithfully Englished and published for the common good by I.H. ...</title>
            <title>Triumph-Wagen Antimonii. English</title>
            <author>Basilius Valentinus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 211 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 93 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-10">2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26734</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1021</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37084</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16206227</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16206227</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105077</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A26734)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105077)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1087:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The triumphant chariot of antimony being a conscientious discovery of the many reall transcendent excellencies included in that minerall / written by Basil Valentine ... ; faithfully Englished and published for the common good by I.H. ...</title>
                  <title>Triumph-Wagen Antimonii. English</title>
                  <author>Basilius Valentinus.</author>
                  <author>J. H. (John Harding), b. 1600 or 1601.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 175 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>A. Lichfield], printed for Thomas Bruster, and are to be sold ... in London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Triumph wagen antimonii.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and publisher statement suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Antimony --  Therapeutic use.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105077:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TRIUMPHANT CHARIOT OF ANTIMONY; BEING A Conſcientious Diſcovery of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Reall Tranſcendent Excellencies in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in that Minerall, WRITTEN By <hi>BASIL VALENTINE</hi> A Benedictine MONKE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faithfully Engliſhed and publiſhed for the Common Good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> I. H. <hi>Oxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Thomas Bruſter,</hi> and are to be ſold at the three Bibles neere the Weſt end of <hi>Paules Church-Yard</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> 1660.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:105077:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105077:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:105077:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105077:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN this Booke are contained many excellent and precious Antimoniall Medcines both Phyſicall and Chyrurgicall: Some of them, even a meane Capacity may attaine unto, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome are more myſterious; and therefore tis very probable that the ſelfe-conceited man (who ſticks not to vilifie any thing that ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts his reach) will call them <hi>Figments,</hi> hopeing by his malitious ſubtilty to ſhun that deſerved Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach which his proud inſulting Demeanour expoſeth him unto: Wee have in theſe dayes many pretenders to great Myſteries, but by their Fruits you may know them; were there but any ſparke of modesty left in the hearts of ſuch Impudent Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant
<pb facs="tcp:105077:4"/>
perſons, they would not thus blemiſh ſo noble a Science, which forſooth they would be accompted Maſters of: For if it be an unſeemly thing for the authorized Traditiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts to pretend a Maſterſhip in this Faculty which concernes the Life of man, (and God knowes how much tis hazarded by the Wilfulneſſe and Rawneſſe of many of them;) how much more blame-worthy are thoſe Phantaſticall hare-brain'd <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pstarts, that (without either the feare of God, or any Reſpect to the good of their diſtreſſed Neighbour) Attempt, by the ſubtileſt wayes they can Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, to beguile the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwary, and to abuſe the neceſſities of their afflicted Patients, and yet highly pretend to I know not what ſublime Knowledge: I am perſwaded that ſuch as theſe have much injured many well diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, tender-Ingenuities, and have retarded the Endeavours of ſuch as pitty the deplorable Eſtate of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind: This peice therefore may ſerve
<pb facs="tcp:105077:4"/>
to quicken the Slow, and to ſettle the Wavering Mind. The Object of it is Antimony, Tis eaſie to be had at a mean price, the Medcines thence educeable are of great value; but yet ſuch of them as are ſo, have a ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble covering, the which remove by thy diligence and twill recompence thy paines. Labour therefore, and humbly implore the Searcher of all hearts to vouchſafe a Bleſſing upon thy handy worke; and whatſoever thou receivest through his mercy, be carefull to improve it to his Glory and thy Neighbours Comfort. For, <hi>Bleſſed are the mercifull for they ſhall obtain mercy: Farewell,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Freind, <hi>J. H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:105077:5"/>
            <head>The moſt material <hi>Errata's,</hi> are to be Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected as followeth.</head>
            <p>Page 52. l. 3. r. it Ceaſeth. p. 53. l. 2. r. Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. p. 58. l. 10. r. reſtraine. l. 11. r. leaſt. p. 80. l. 3. It firſt deſcribes. p. 158. l. 2. r. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="scientific_treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105077:5"/>
            <head>THE Triumphant Chariot of <hi>ANTIMONY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Fiery Stone of <hi>Antimony,</hi> its fixt tincture, and moſt red Oyl, ſhall in this work be briefly, but throughly taught, after an eaſy way and Method without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ridles or doubtfull ſhadowes. I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Baſil <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentine,</hi> a profeſſed <hi>Monk,</hi> and Brother of the order of St. <hi>Benedict,</hi> will fundamentally propound to the friendly Reader, a brief admonition concerning ſome <hi>Praecognita,</hi> which a Spagiriſt (care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully inquiring into the verity of Art) ought to be acquainted with: Very profoundly therefore, and heartily, let theſe directions be ruminated on, by him who hath a deſire after a certain enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105077:6"/>
of this Hermetical Science: For if any ſlightly value theſe my Propoſals, doubtleſs his labor ſhall be in vain, for theſe things following are very worthy of due conſideration. Now before I attempt the main work of this little Tract, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it requiſite to admoniſh the Spagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt, of thoſe things which are worth his knowledge; on what Baſis he ought to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect his Structure, and what Foundation truſting too, his Fabrick may reſiſt impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous ſtorms, without declining: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as a Monk, I hold it fitting, and as a thing expedient, that when my ſelf and thy ſelf, <hi>Titius</hi> and <hi>Sejus, Sempronius</hi> and <hi>Cajus,</hi> ſhall be tributaries to death, we may leave behinde us in the World, an honorable memory to the praiſe of God, that his Divine Majeſty may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored: By a due preparation we addreſs our ſelves unto the Journey: My ſtare and calling, forſooth, requires a different ſpirit from the vulgar.</p>
            <p>In this my conſideration, I have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted five Obſervations for the diligent ſearcher.</p>
            <p>1. An Invocation on the name of God, 2. A Contemplation on the Eſſentiality of things. 3. Their true and incorrupt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105077:6"/>
preparation. 4. Their uſe. 5. Their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit or proficuouſneſs. All which, a true Chymiſt muſt remember, and without which he cannot be, nor be called a true Chymiſt: Briefly therefore and ſeveral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe Heads ſhall be treated of, that a particular and the univerſal entire Work may thereby be brought to light, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear perfect.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt therefore, The Name of God ought to be called on religiouſly, with a pure heart, a ſound conſcience, without ambition, hypocriſie, and other abuſes, ſuch as are Diſdain, Pride, Arrogance, worldly Boaſting, oppreſſion of our Neighbors, and other Tyrannies and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ormities of that kinde; all which, ought to be totally eradicated out of the heart, that, when it would prevail at the Throne of Mercy for the health of its Body, it may be found a pure and well prepared Temple (the Chaff being ſeparated from the uncommix'd and undefiled Corn) For verily, verily, verily, God will not be mocked, as Sophiſters, and the Wiſelings of this Age imagine; nor will he be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto as a Creator, without a true fear, a due obedience, and moſt humble ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: For ſeeing man hath nothing,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105077:7"/>
but what his moſt bounteous Creator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows upon him, he having given him a Body, Life, an operating Spirit, and a moſt noble Soul, and freely vouchſafed his own holy Word for the ſupport and nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Soul to eternal Life; and having for Bodily neceſſaries provided him Food and Raiment, and ſuch other things as none can poſſibly want. It is juſt, that above all other things, his firſt Father (who hath created the Heaven and the Earth, things viſible and inviſible, the Firmament, the Elements, Vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things, and all Creatures) be with moſt inward humble Prayers ſought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to for the obtaining of them. Moſt certaine it is, that a wicked man ſhall never be acquainted with true medicine, and much leſſe taſte the truly immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and true celeſtiall bread of Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Primarily, and cheifly therefore, follow this Doctrine, placing all thy hope and confidence in God, humbly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore his bleſſing, that thy ſearch may begin in the fear of the Lord, and ſo ſhalt thou obtain deſired Wiſdom; <hi>for the fear of the Lord is the beginning of Wiſdom:</hi> Whoſoever then hath reſolved in himſelf to ſeek the top of Terreſtrials (that is,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105077:7"/>
the knowleege of the Good, lodging in all Creatures, (which the moſt high hath beſtowed upon man) lying dormant or covered in Stones, Herbs, Roots, Seeds, living Creatures, Plants, Minerals, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, and the like) let him caſt behinde him all worldly cares, and their appurte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and expect releaſe with his whole heart, by humble Prayers, and his hope ſhall not fail, but he ſhall become worthy of the laſt Redemption: Of this let none doubt or deſpair, for he alone re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemeth <hi>Iſrael</hi> from all their enemies, and will truly and faithfully perform the ſame to ſuch as truly and humbly call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his name: So that the firſt Admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on cannot be more rightly and better pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticed, then by Prayers, ſeeing it is an invoking of God; but beware you do it not from an Hypocritical and Deceitful heart, but cordially, after the rule of the <hi>Capernaites</hi>; with firmneſs of Faith and Hope, as the Woman of <hi>Canaan,</hi> thereby procuring her Daughters health; and with a Chriſtian Charity, as the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan</hi> poured in Wine and Oyl into the wounds of the poor man near <hi>Jericho,</hi> and, on his own coſt, took the care of him: Whoſoever uſeth this invocation, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105077:8"/>
with a Chriſtian charity the benefit of his Neighbor thereby, without doubt, ſhal obtain what he ſo earneſtly ſeeks for, <hi>viz.</hi> His wiſh'd for end, and propoſed hope of health and richneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Next to Prayer, follows a Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of all things (that is) before all other things, chiefly conſider their Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, Matter, Form, Original Virtues, Influence, Conjunction, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret force of the Stars, the Elementary compoſure, the Generation and Forming (out of the three Principles) the things that are; Then alſo that every thing is reducible, and may be brought back into its firſt Matter and firſt Eſſentiality, which, mention is made of in my wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; that of the firſt Matter, the laſt; and out of the laſt, the firſt may be made. This conſideration (next to ſeeking of God) is chief, Celeſtial, and Spiritually to be underſtood. The underſtanding of the Condition and Quality of every thing, is found out by the ſpiritual thoughts of man, from an out-flowing ſpeculation; and this ſpeculating is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, Poſſible, and Impoſſible.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Impoſſible conſiſts in ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Cogitations of things without or
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105077:8"/>
beyond Natures limits, wherein no form of Eſſentiality is manifeſt; as if a man attempted to ſearch out the Eternity of God, which cannot be done: But it is an abſolute, crazy, wicked ſin againſt the Holy Spirit, to ſet upon the inquiry of his immeaſureable, infinite, and eternal Deity, and to examine the unfathomable Myſteries of his Counſel and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Now the Poſſible Conſideration ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits the Theory of examining the nature of things viſibLe, manifeſt, and having a created Form or Eſſence, how by help of ſeparation each Body may be underſtood, that they may become profitable, the good may be ſegregated from the bad, and the Medicine from the lurking Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in an Anatomical manner, by ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and rectification, that the pure may be divided from the impure, without deceit; which ſeparation may be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed ſundry ways, (ſome whereof are known to the vulgar, others not ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon) as are Calcination, Sublimation, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verberation, Circulation, Putrefaction, Digeſtion, Cohobation, Deſtillation, Fixa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and other ways; all which degrees are in their order found out, learned, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticed,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105077:9"/>
and manifeſted by labor; and by which appears what is fix, what volatile, white, black, or red, and the like, help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Artificer to diſcern and walk rightly in his Art with mature conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for conſideration may truſt too, or lean on a falſe foundation, and erre, if the Kingly path be not attained too: But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily, Nature knows not how to erre, if rightly governed by a faithful ſteward, to whoſe care ſhe is committed: If thou (therefore) erre, becauſe thou haſt not looſned Nature, and freed her from the Body whereto ſhe's Captive; learn the Theory better, &amp; more accurately attend thy work, that thou may'ſt be acquainted with the true fundamental knowledge of ſeparating all things; and this is a chief, and the moſt principal thing. So then, the ſecond Baſis of Phyloſophy is the ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of all things and Eſſences, and is called the conſideration of nature, for its written <hi>Firſt ſeek the kingdome of God and his righteouſnes</hi> &amp;c. <hi>viz,</hi> by calling on his name, <hi>and the other things ſhall be added thereunto, viz.</hi> the underſtanding of things temporall, and enjoyment of neceſſaries for food and health.</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:105077:9"/>Having circumſpectly accompliſhed the conſideration of all things. (which in the precedent we called the Theory) followes in order a due preparation, which is compleated by manuall Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that ſome thing both profitable and active may be obtained, by meanes of which preparation is purchaſed the Knowledge of medicinall virtues: Now manuall operations muſt with diligence and paines be carefully proſecuted; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced Knowledge is praiſe worthy. But Anatomy doth judge and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the difference both of the good and the bad and their virtues. Handy Labour gives evidence that all things may be brought to the light, and bee made viſible: The theorical knowledge of the virtues of any ſubject is a good fore-runner of practiſe, and proves a truly ſolid foundation, whereby one may become a tru practioner, &amp; is nothing elſe than a confirmation of the good that is diſcovered by manual labour, whereby the ſecrets of Nature may be educed for profitable ends. For as in the reaſonable ſoul the way is to bee prepared by the Lord, ſo here an harmonious and legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate path is to be cut out, that a progreſs
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105077:10"/>
may be made for bodily health without doubtfulneſs and errour.</p>
            <p>And this is <hi>Preparation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Preparation</hi> or <hi>Separation</hi> of the hurtful &amp; profitable, being (by <hi>Reſolution</hi>) accompliſhed, We come to the <hi>Uſe</hi> or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration thereof: and here beware leſt thou either encreaſe or diminiſh the true Weight, which in the operation thou muſt obſerve [<hi>viz.</hi>] Whether or no thy reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy bee weak or ſtrong, which a Phyſitian ought afore hand to know, as whether it bee injurious and hurtful, or beneficial, leſt by the detriment and death of his neighbour, he expoſeth his own ſoul to hazard.</p>
            <p n="5">5. After that the Operation beginnes to bee dilated and diffuſed through the parts of the body, ſearching for the diſeaſe for which it was adminiſtred, The <hi>Profitableneſſe</hi> or <hi>Benefit</hi> comes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der conſideration, by which, as the main End, is diſcernable, what Good the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration hath induced; for it may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen that a Medicine may hurt, and not help the diſeaſed, which may be contrary to, or improper for the diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; and ſo is rather a Poyſon, than a Medicine for reſtoring health. Let every
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105077:10"/>
one on this accompt warily heed and aim at the publique good, that he may obſerve, and them ſo obſerved commit to writing; let them not periſh by oblivion, but be manifeſted for the uſe of others.</p>
            <p>Moreover in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> as alſo in the <hi>Benefit</hi> of Medicine, it is obſervable, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no a diſeaſe be a ſolution of conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity, or hath onely an internal ſeat; for the Exteriour differ from the Interiour, and ſo are their Remedies various. Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes therefore are to be diſtinguiſhed, whether or no they are curable by onely outward Remedies, or to be expelled by inward Medicines: On which account when the centre of a diſeaſe lodgeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, and is to be throughly found out, there ought to be admitted ſuch conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient remedies as may ſearch unto, ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly ſet upon, and divide it with the reſtauration of ſtrength: otherwiſe the Phyſitian labours in vain, if the centre be not reached unto.</p>
            <p>Every Phyſitian ought to know, that no Externall diſeaſe, having his originall and reſidence within, can be deſtroyed by outward medicines; but death and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction would enſue thereupon. For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, if a man ſhould endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105077:11"/>
the out-breaking flowers of a tree, back into their centre, he would not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thereby deſtroy the fruit of the flower, but the juice being forced back to the centre (againſt the Law of Nature) from whence it had its afflux to the tree, would not onely be unprofitable by this violent Reunition, but alſo totally ſuffocate it; becauſe the moiſt nutriment of the earth which it deſires, could not have admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Great therfore is the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween new wounds made with Iron, &amp; old Ulcers begotten from an inward diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. New Wounds are curable by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward remedies, old Ulcers are not ſo: But beſides the Application of Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Oyls, Balſoms, &amp; Cataplaſms, they require an inward cure, that the Fountain may be deſtroyed, and the thence-flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing River may be dryed up, by which (obſerving a right diet) the diſeaſe ſhall be eaſily helped. 'Tis no Art or Skill to cure a green wound, which even the Countryman with a peece of ſalted Hogs fat eaſily doth: 'Tis a peece of Art to remove the ſymptomes that happen to wounds, and to dry up the original of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes.</p>
            <p>All ye Phyſitians throughout the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105077:11"/>
all ye Doctors who practiſe Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, ye Maſters, and learned in Medicine of both ſorts, External and Internal, come hither, and examine your honourable Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and conſider in your conſciences, whether you received it from God or not, or proudly uſurp it in formality or not: Verily there is as vaſt a difference between an outward, and inward curing, as is betwixt the Heaven and the Earth.</p>
            <p>If you have received your Title from God, he will help, bleſſe, and proſper you. But if you faign it, or aſſume it to your ſelf, without ſuch a Call, ye, though Great, ſhall greatly fall; by which you prepare for your ſelves the unquenchable fire of hell. Truly our Saviour ſaid to his Diſciples, <hi>Ye call me Lord and Maſter, and ye doe well</hi>; ſo let every one that will take to himſelf this honourable Title, conſider that he doth what is right; that is, that he abuſeth not his Title, and boaſt not of more than he hath learned. He that will be a Doctor of both Medicines, ought wel to underſtand both Medicines, that he may diſcover inwardly the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the body by Anatomy, and in what member the diſeaſe hath his origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105077:12"/>
and by what means he may ſuccour it; he alſo ought to underſtand outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the circumſtances of Wounds and Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</p>
            <p>Good God! what would become of the Maſter of both Medicines, and his Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, where will it be found, if many of ſuch as uſe it were expoſed to an exact tryall. Heretofore the Phyſitians them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wrought with their own hands, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in outward diſeaſes, this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Phyſitians office; But now in our Age, they have brought up their Servants to exerciſe Chirurgery, and thus is this moſt noble Art become a baſe Trade, which even the moſt illiterate bluſh not to practiſe: Yea even ſuch alſo as know not how to drive an Aſſe out of the Corn, are Doctors of Chirurgery (yet even the Phyſical Doctors are their Diſciples) and frequently exerciſe it with more ſucceſſe, and a better conſcience (that I may ſpeak the truth) than thou, O Ambitious, titled onely, unlearned Phyſicall-Chyrurgeon, that boaſteſt of both names or titles, doeſt.</p>
            <p>But pray Maſter Doctor, and Maſter Phyſitian be not angry, I beſeech you, with my ſpeech and opinion; for thou
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105077:12"/>
wouldſt be forced to acknowledge, ſhould I examine thee of Cuts and Stabs, &amp;c. that thy judgement concerning ſuch things is as large, and as much knowledge lyes in thy pate, as in the head of a Hen painted on a Table. 'Tis my faithfull advice to all ſuch as are Learned (both of high and low eſtate) to conſider judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and conſcientiouſly thoſe things that are required in Doctors and Maſters, <hi>viz.</hi> the true manner of the Preparation, and the uſe of Medicine; then may you juſtly aſſume to your ſelves this honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Title, and you'l be able to ſuccour the diſtreſſed, and with a pure heart praiſe your Creatour.</p>
            <p>By what hath been ſpoken, let every one examine himſelf, and ſee whether (with right) he may aſſume this Title; for whoever will lay claim to any Title, 'tis behoovefull that he exactly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, and be able perfectly to give an accompt why he aſſumed it: For it is not ſufficient to ſay with the vulgar, Behold! a great deal of ſtinking ordure (with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to your eares) and to be ignorant of the cauſe of the ſtinch. Although a man often feeds on the moſt ſweet ſmelling food, yet preſently he caſts out moſt fetid
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105077:13"/>
dung; But you are to know the cauſe why fragrant fruit tranſmutes into ſtinch, the ground of which is naturall Putrefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And on the other hand (in Spices) the Odour is not ſolely to be reſpected, but a Genuine Philoſopher muſt ſearch into the Eſſence and Originall of that ſmell, and what good virtues lye therein. From ſtincking dung (with which the Earth is dung'd and nouriſhed, grows ſweet ſmelling fruit; for which are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaſons, and a large Book might bee written of the various Tranſmutations of Nature; but the chiefe cauſe of this change is Putrefaction and Digeſtion, and they are its chief Keyes; becauſe the Fire and the Air bring or cauſe Maturity, ſo that the Earth and Water are tranſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into each other; for 'tis a certain al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration, that, of Dung, a Balſome bee made, and contrariwiſe, of Balſome, Dung. But you will object and ſay, that I bring very Rurall and plain examples; I confeſſe they are homely, but the Wiſe man will by his own induſtry conſider my intention herein, how from the moſt low, the moſt high may be made, and from the high the moſt humble or low; how out of a Remedy a Poyſon, and out of a Poyſon
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105077:13"/>
a Remedy; out of a Sweet thing a Corroſive, and from thence a thing profitable may be produced. Good God! Nature will not be throughly ſearched by us all; for our Life is ſhort, and thou moſt juſt Judge haſt kept to thy ſelf many things, that Man may admire thy Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, of which thy ſelf wilt be the Judge; Give me grace, that I may firmly retain my Saviour in my heart, even to my ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate end, that beſides my bodily health and food which in abundance thou haſt beſtowed upon me, I may alſo obtain the riches and health of my ſoul, of which I make no ſcruple, ſince thou haſt ſhed on the wooden Croſſe, out of thy ardent Love and Mercy, the true Sulphur of the ſoul for me; which heavenly Sulphur of the ſoul proves a poyſon to the Devill; but to us, the greateſt Medicine. I cure my Brethren by Prayers, ſpiritually; by Appropriate remedies, bodily; and hope that they'l watch ſpiritually for me, that we may all become co-inhabitants in the Tabernacles of the moſt high God.</p>
            <p>But, to return to my Antimonial Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy.</p>
            <p>Be it therefore known unto the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105077:14"/>
that every thing hath in it ſelfe a quickning and operating Spirit which dwels in bodies, nouriſheth and preſerves them: In the Elements alſo are living Spirits, by Gods permiſſion be they good or evill. Men and other living creatures have a living operating ſpirit in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the which departing, a carkaſs only remains.</p>
            <p>Hearbs and Plants contain in them a healthy ſpirit, otherwiſe they would be unfit for medicinal preparation and uſe. So both Metals &amp; Minerals have in them their Impalpable ſpirit, wherein lyes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained all their force and efficacy; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſpirit the body is dead, nor can it diſcover any lively operation: Know then rhat in Antimony lyes a ſpirit, which effects all ſuch things as lye hid therein, and are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thence educible, but invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly, not unlike the inviſible virtue that lyes hid in the Loadſtone, whereof in my <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ract of the Magnet I ſhall ſpeake more largely. Now there is a twofold ſpirit; Intelligent, and not Intelligent. The Intelligent ſpirits are endowed with Reaſon (and can become when they liſt, impalpable, and without bodies) like us naturall men; of which kinde are the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105077:14"/>
inhabitants, <hi>viz.</hi> fiery, as wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and wandring lights, and other bright phantaſines: alſo inhabitants in the Ayre, and dwellers in, and governours over the Waters, &amp; laſtly, the Earthy inhabitants, of which Ranck are thoſe that frequently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in Metallick Mines, and are thence denominated Mine-Pit men: Now theſe are underſtanding Spirits, &amp; skill'd in Art, and are able to alter their ſhape, of whom I dare not determine any thing, but leave it to the all knowing God, whether it be expedient to deliver my judgment concerning them or not. The other ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the univerſe, and which doe not operate after the afore ſaid manner by their own innate power, are ſuch as ly hid in man, Animals, Brutes, Plants, &amp; Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, which notwithſtanding have in them an operative life, which they by their works diſcover, evidencing that there lyes an healing power in them, when they are ſeparated from their bodies by the benefit of Art. Thus alſo the Spirit of Antimony manifeſts its vertue, and communicates it to mankind, when by a freedom from the chains and bonds of its body (that its penetrative and opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting force may be awakened) it be uſed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105077:15"/>
to that intent for which by the Artiſt it is ordained. Truely tis expedient that the maſter or artiſt &amp; Vulcan entertaine fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity, for the fire ſeparates the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive force and virtue; But the artificer forms and faſhioneth the matter, as a black-ſmith by the help of one and the ſame fire, and of one and the ſame metal <hi>viz.</hi> Iron, forms (out of that one matter) ſundry and ſeveral utenſils, as ſpits, Iron ſhooes, forkes, plowſhares <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So alſo out of Antimony, many artificial things, and of diverſe uſes may be made: The artificer is the black-ſmith forming the matter, the fire is the unlocking key, the operation and utility confirms the prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and brings experience. O good God! Would but the fooliſh and unwiſe world ſee and hear rightly and diſcreetly, and truely underſtand, that a ſight and hearing onely of what I write, may not ſatisfy them, without the obtaining of a truly inward uſeful knowledge, It would not lick up the purulent dregs, but go un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe living fountains where it may drink of the water of life. And let all know that I ſhall indeed make fools of many learned Maſters; and on the contrary Doctors of many poor, deſpiſed, ſearching
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105077:15"/>
and inquiring ſchollars; all ſuch brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing and longing ſpirits I invite to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low my doctrine, to obſerve my writings and admonitions with a chearful heart, a faithful companion and good conſcience (to whom thus enjoying I promiſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things) and ſo ſhall they be effectors of their deſire, and ſpeak honourably of me, when I ſhall ly in my ſepulcher, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing my fame with a laſting memorial even to the worlds end.</p>
            <p>Now if any ſurviving me ſhall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute in my School againſt me, when dead, my writings will anſwer abundantly for me, and I certainly know that my diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples will not be unmindfull of the benefit they have reaped, but preſerve the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of truth, which hitherto we have alwayes obtained, to the confuſion of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity and lying, and alwayes ſhall obtaine it to the worlds end.</p>
            <p>
               <note rend="inter">The ſorts of Antimony.</note>Moreover the courteous &amp; favourable ſtudent of Art, ought to know the ſeveral ſorts and kinds of Antimony.</p>
            <p>One ſort is pure, faire, of a golden na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and abounds with Mercury. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther abounds with Sulphur, and largely differs from that of the golden property,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105077:16"/>
and temperature: For in the former ſort are faire, long, ſhining Radii, or Lines, whereby 'tis diſtinguiſhable from the latter; For the difference of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſorts of Antimony is as much as is betwixt the fleſh of four footed beaſts, &amp; of fiſhes, which have ſome agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and affinity, as to the name, and (if you will) eſſence, but in goodnes are dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent. The ingenuous ſtudent muſt alſo know that a great many men have written of the inward virtues of Antimony, but moſt few are they, who have learned the baſis of its vertue, or found how they might poſſeſſe it, and ſince they onely talke and ſpeak groundleſly, they looſe their honour in that, for which intent (of honour) they betook themſelves to wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
            <p>He that will write of Antimony, needs a great conſideration and moſt ample minde, and various rules of its prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and aſſured end; wherein it may with profit be uſed, that ſo he may give a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain undoubtful teſtimony of what is good or what is evil, what helpful and what poyſonous.</p>
            <p>Tis no ſmall thing truely to ſearch out Antimony, thereby to know its eſſence
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105077:16"/>
and at length by diligence and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to obtaine the knowledge of it, to take away its poiſon, (ſo much cryed out againſt by the clamours of the vulgar) and by a better omen to tranſmute it into wholſome medicine. Many inquirers or Anatomiſts have hunted ſome here, ſome there, and miſerably handled, tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and crucified Antimony, in ſo much that 'tis both unexpreſſible and incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. But (really) they have not found out, or accompliſhed any profitable operation, wandring from the true end, propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to themſelves things that are falſe, and thereby ſhadowing their ſight, from beeing able to diſcerne the mark.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antimony</hi> may deſervedly be compared (&amp; ſo alſo Mercury) to an infinite Circle, and painted with all ſorts of colours, and by how much the more it is ſought into, ſo much the more is found out and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, (ſo that your progreſſe therein be right and true;) In a word, one mans life is too too ſhort, perfectly to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with all its myſteries.</p>
            <p>It is the worſt of poyſons, the which being ſeparated therefrom, it becomes the ſupremeſt medicine, and is to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred for inward and outward diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105077:17"/>
Which to many moles will ſeem incredible, and will be adjudged vanity and folly, but yet may be pardonable in them, becauſe of their ignorance and want of judgment: but verily they are exceedingly to be blamed, who not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, have no deſire after knowledge nor any will to learn.</p>
            <p>Antimony hath four qualities, it is hot and cold, moiſt and dry, and imitates the four ſeaſons of the year: it is alſo fixt and volatile: the volatile part is not void of poyſon, but the fix'd part is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether free there from.</p>
            <p>Hence comes it to paſſe, that many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilful men write what they neither know, nor underſtand, which may (for that reaſon) be adjudged monſtrous, &amp; one of the ſeven wonders of the world: there being none that either hitherto hath bin found or is at preſent to be found, who hath fundamentally learned all its facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, virtues, and powerful operations, or hath ſo far tryed its force &amp; efficacy, that nothing more may be therein ſeen, then he by his own experience knows. If any ſuch can be met withall, he is well worthy to be drawn in the Triumphant Glorious Chariot of the ancient Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105077:17"/>
when they had gotten ſome notable victories: But in my opinion the chariot Smiths are likely of but light imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment about chariots of this kind: many artificers in this age being overwhelmed with their thoughts, have ſought after Riches only in Antimony, and have neglected the benefit that its wont to bring to ſuch as are diſeaſed, the which utility ought notwithſtanding firſt of all to be ſought after, that the wonders of the Lord may be manifeſted, and due thanks given to him. It cannot indeed be denyed, but that in Antimony Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches may be found, although neither thou nor I may beleeve it, ſince both of us are but Scholars and Diſciples in its ſearch; although haply I have ſeene more therein, and experimented more, then either thou or ſuch as thou art (that boaſt exceedingly much, and arrogate a large portion of Learning to themſelves) are able to learn to morrow or next day; yet let none greive at his fortune, nor deſpaire, for God doth wonderfully di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute his mercifull rewards; but yet the World abounds with ſuch as are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull, who contemn the bleſſings of God, eſteeming Wealth better then
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105077:18"/>
true riches, and therefore God hath ſet a Cloud before their eyes, that ſuch be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing blinded, may not know thoſe ſecrets that lie hid under a Metallick Form. All people, even in theſe days, cry out, Riches, riches, and imitate the ſaying of the Epicurean, <hi>If our Bodies would enjoy anything, our Souls muſt willingly ſearch after it</hi>; frequently repeating the fooliſh wiſh of <hi>Midas,</hi> ſo often ſpoken of by the Poets: Many therefore do here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with themſelves, how from Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony they may obtain their hoped for riches: But becauſe in their Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and devices they minde not their Creator, nor render a ſacrifice of praiſe, and neglect that charity due to their Neighbor, they in vain feel in the horſes mouth, whoſe age, force and ſtrength, they remain ignorant of: So in the Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> they indeed ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted and drank of the Wine, and knew it to be made of Water; but the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of its Tranſmutation they were not acquainted with, for our Saviour kept that Miracle to himſelf alone, for the confirmation of his Omnipotency. I do therefore affirm, that the Myſteries of all things, and thoſe ſecrecies that are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105077:18"/>
in the Creatures by the Creator, ought to be inquired into, and ſought af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from him: Although 'tis incredible and unlikely, that a man ſhould attain to a perfect knowledge, any more then they aforementioned could underſtand our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours Miracles; yet 'tis not forbidden us to ſeek, becauſe by ſtudy and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence we may come to learn, ſo much as to prevent the cauſes of complaining of the loſs of our health and riches; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo may finde cauſe enough to rejoyce in ſuch things, as by ſearch we finde out, for which, let God, who is well worthy, be for ever praiſed.</p>
            <p>Whoſoever therefore will be a true Antimonial Anatomiſt, let him firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the diviſion or opening of its body, that after a due manner, and in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and in its own ſeat, he make his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, without erroneous deviations.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Let the Regiment or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernance of the Fire be obſerved, that it be not too great nor too little, that it grows not too cold nor too hot (for in the fire lies the very Art) that its living Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits may be forced out, releaſed, and ſet at liberty, to perform their operating virtues.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:105077:19"/>Thirdly, let the uſe be obſerved, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the certain meaſure and quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, as before in my five neceſſary Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Heads or Obſervations I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noted, yet Ile repeat them paraboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally.</p>
            <p>By the Diviſion or Anatomical part, the chief thing receives its preparation; but in &amp; by the fire is it adduced to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and uſe: Even as a Butcher cuts an Ox, (which he hath killed) into ſeveral pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; but yet 'tis not fit for uſe being crude; but muſt be concocted by the fires heat, which takes away the rawneſs of the fleſh, and prepares it for uſeful nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment, (for if an houſholder ſhould eat crude fleſh, it would be rather a Poyſon then Food; becauſe the heat of mans ſtomack is too weak for concocting ſuch a crude groſs body.) Even ſo alſo, (my friend) maiſt thou conclude concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Antimony, which ſeeing 'tis a crude groſs Poyſon, and being Mineral, hath a more hard indigeſtible Body, then li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Creatures have; it cannot be dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in the ſtomack, without a precedent preparation and concoction, but death would ſoon follow ſo ſtrong a Medicine. Above all things (as to Antimony) let
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105077:19"/>
its poiſon be taken away, and let it be ſo handled and ordered that it may never be reducible into poiſon any more, even to eternity: even as Vinegar can never more be reduced into wine, out of which it was made by Putrefaction, not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence (<hi>viz.</hi> Vinegar) can a Spirit of Wine be extract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but it is Vinegar, and ſo it will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main.</p>
            <p>But contrarily if by diſtillation the ſpirit of Wine be ſeparated from its aquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, and be elevated into its own exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, twill never be changed into vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar in a whole age, but will alwaies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſpirit of Wine, as Spirit of Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar will ſtill continue to be Spirit of Vinegar: But the manner of the generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Wine-Vinegar is wonderfull; for of it, is made a thing different from what it was before in its vegetative Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; for in the deſtillation of Wine, the ſpirit of the Wine comes firſt, the watry part reſiding in the bottom; but in the diſtillation of Vinegar, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit riſeth laſt, as elſewhere hath been treated of. The Spirit of Wine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore makes things votatile, becauſe it ſelfe is volatile; but the fix'd Spirit of Vinegar fixeth them, <hi>viz.</hi> The Minerall
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105077:20"/>
and vegetable Medicines that they are enabled to operate upon fix't things, and heal fixed diſeaſes, which things ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve very diligently, for therein lies an an entrance of great concernment.</p>
            <p>Antimony ought therefore ſo to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared (which its owne proper Vinegar is able to do) that its poiſon may be taken away, and tranſmuted into Medicine, which never more for the future retaines any poiſon, but rather is ſufficient to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell all ſorts of poiſons. The preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Antimony conſiſts in the Keyes of Alchymy only, by which it is opened, divided and ſeparated; ſuch are Calci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, Reverberation, &amp; Sublimation: Alſo in the Extraction of its Eſſence, which is vivified into Mercury, which Mercury is to be precipitated into a fix'd Powder: moreover by art may an Oile be thence made, which is moſt exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profitable for the healing of the French diſeaſe: and ſo other preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are found out by the benefit of Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtry.</p>
            <p>For Example, A workman intending to make Ale out of Barly, Wheat, or other Fruits, tis needfull that he paſſeth through all theſe degrees before he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105077:20"/>
its Eſſence, and convert it into a noble drink. Firſt of all, he muſt mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate it in water, untill the fruit be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, (as I exactly obſerved, when being a young man I was in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>England</hi>) and this is nothing elſe but putrefaction; This being done let the water run there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from; and the corne thus macerated, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther up into an heap, and leave it ſo for ſome ſeaſon, that (of its own accord) it may grow warme, and this is called digeſtion, which being finiſhed, dry the corne thus prepared in the Aire, or at the heat of a fire, which is Reverbera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or coagulation; being dryed, let it be ground in a Mill like Meale, and this is its Vegetable calcination; all theſe things being performed, it is to be boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with water, that ſo the moſt noble ſpirit of the graine may be extracted by, and joyned unto the Water, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore its preparation could not have beene done: Thus then is the crude water changed into Ale, and this is diſtillation after a groſſe manner: The little leaves of the Hops that are at laſt mingled with it, are the Vegetable and preſervative ſalt, keeping the Ale from periſhing by a new putrefaction: The Italians and Spaniards
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105077:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:105077:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:105077:22"/>
have but a ſmall Knowledge of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe: in the upper <hi>Germany,</hi> alſo in the country of <hi>Rhine</hi> (being my country) few there are that are herewith acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: All the aforeſaid degrees being compleated, then by clarification is a new ſeparation made, and a little fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Yeſt added to the boyled Ale, which ſtirs it up to motion, that it lifts up it ſelf of its own accord, and by that Ebullition is the troubled ſeparated from the cleer, the impure from the pure, by convenient ſtanding and time, from whence the Ale attaines its due perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and can operatively penetrate and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh that for which intent tis given. As long as the operative ſpirit is hindred by impurity, it cannot performe its Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and Worke, which is apparent in Wine, which before its ſetling and ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, it cannot performe its operation; but only after the ſeparation of the pure from the impure; which is hereby diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable, becauſe that neither wine nor ale will inebriate, as long as they are new and unpurified, and are not capable of then emitting their operating ſpirits, but of this enough.</p>
            <p>Now after all this, a new ſeparation
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:105077:22"/>
may be inſtituted by a vegetable ſublima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereby the ſpirits of Wine or Ale may be reduced to another Drink, <hi>viz.</hi> (<hi>Aquavitae</hi>) which alſo is extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable out of either of their feces, which being done, and the operating ſpirituall virtue ſeparated from its body, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted by fire, there remaines nothing behind but only a warriſh and dead Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and by rectification, this Aquavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae may be ſo exalted, that by a frequent and artificiall abſtraction it may become moſt pure, without any phlegme or water accompanying it, and then one pound is more efficacious then twenty pounds or more were before, for it ſpeedily peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates and inebriates, being reduced to this high Degree of Volatile vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</p>
            <p>Thou therefore that art deſirous of art, if thou wouldſt obtaine Knowledge from my Writings, and Wealth, Riches, and true Medicine from Antimony, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider well what I have afore ſayd, for therein the leaſt Letter hath its ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and theres not a word writ in vain, verily in my writings all about, are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny words variouſly placed, which if the artificer did conſider and underſtand what
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105077:23"/>
the true intent is, and in what the Mark lyes, it would not greive him to read o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver every Leafe ſeverall times, and to engrave every word in a Table of Gold, and take notice, that although I have made uſe of Ruſticall and Groſſe Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, yet are they of great concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; I will not praiſe my own Bookes, it being too unbe-ſeeming; but let tryal be made, and they ſhall be found truly praiſe-worthy: I have the rather uſed ſuch groſſe examples, that (becauſe the virtue of Antimony lies moſt profoundly hid, and is to be drawn out of moſt ſecret places) by ſuch Examples, a way may be opened for thee, that thou mayſt ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner obtaine thy end, and begin in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient manner, and bring thy diligent ſearch to an happy iſſue. Antimony may be compared to a Bird flying in the ayre, which turnes herſelfe ſometime here, ſometimes there, even as the aire drives her: ſo here a man or artiſt is the Wind, who drives Antimony where it pleaſeth him, and brings it under a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellation in that place which he hath aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned it, for he can make it red, yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, white or black, even as it ſeemes him beſt, (having good reſpect to the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105077:23"/>
governance of his Fire) wherein he ſhall aſſuredly diſcerne that Antimony paſſeth all the colours which are wont to be found in Mercury, at which do not make ſuch great admiration, for Nature permits many things which neither I nor thou ſhall be able totally<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and throughly to learne to day, to morrow, or next day: When an illiterate man takes up any book he knowes not what the writing thereof containes, and is totally ignorant of the ſignification of the Letters therein, which he gazeth on as a Heifer on a new dore; but when that unskilfull man ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed as to the ſignification and uſe of thoſe Letters, he then ceaſeth to eſteem it any ſcience more, but counts it a thing common and very facile, the uſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent whereof he perfectly underſtands, ſo that nothing ſeemes to him ſecret or obſcure in that book, when both the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and true apprehenſion of its Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents are diſcovered and well conceived by him.</p>
            <p>In like manner Antimony is as it were a booke for unexperienced men to read, whom I faithfully admoniſh with all my heart, (if they would participate of the benefit of that booke) that they firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:105077:24"/>
its Letters, know and pronounce them, that to read, may be familiar unto them, (the which by practiſing) they may deſervedly be advanced unto a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Forme or Claſſis in the Schoole, in which Schoole, truly experience is the maſter, which by the Tryall diſcovers who ſhall obtaine the Garland, and be worthy its Enjoyment before ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Moreover, I will not that thou be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, how many men daily, but foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly, and very inconſiderately, cry out <hi>Crucifie, Crucifie,</hi> againſt all that adminiſter poyſons unto men, and prepare their accuſtomed Medicine thereof, whereby ſo many men are miſerably deſtroyed, of which Nature, are Mercury, Arſenick, and Antimony, and with theſe unſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned clamours do the unlearned Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians moſt of all cry out, themſelves being abſolutely ignorant what reall poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and what a true remedy is, how a ſeparation is to be begun and perfected, that ſo out of Poiſon the evill of its Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may be removed, and a better ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted: I do therefore my ſelf alſo ſpeak &amp; cry out againſt all ſuch as dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly adminiſter to man ſuch poiſonous
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:105077:24"/>
things, not verſed in their due prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, for Mercury, Arſenick, Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and the like, (in their ſubſtance with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out preparation) are plainly venemous and ſo remaine; But yet after a neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Preparation, Extraction, Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and Victory over their poyſon, they verily become a Medicine ſufficient to reſiſt all other internall poiſons, and fundamentally to Eradicate them. And certainly when that which is poiſonous ſhall by due preparation be ſo ordered, that it is no more noxious for the time to come, it then reſiſts all ſuch poiſons as it finds unprepared, and prepares them in ſuch manner, that they alſo lay aſide their venenoſity, and become conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto it, although both were hurtfull and poiſonous at firſt.</p>
            <p>Here I ſhal ſtir up amongſt the learned a great contention, as to the true meaning of this my writing, whether or no what I now mention be poſſible or not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which many a cenſure wil be paſt: Some ſuppoſe that from the aforeſayd things, their venemous qualities can not be altogether removed by any meanes,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105077:25"/>
no wonder indeed, that the knowledge of this thing is hid from their eyes, and that they do not at all think of Learning the wonders of this Univerſe. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, but a very few will readily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm my Doctrine of the Tranſmutation of evill into what is better. Conſider, that even Phyſitians will confeſſe, that the evill wherein a Diſeaſe doth lodge, may be converted into good, and if they allow ſo far, it may not be unlawful for me alſo to affirm, that the evill which lies hid in a phyſical or Medicinal ſubject, may be tranſmuted into better, that it may be adminiſtred with ſafety, rightly and wholſomely. But whereas Experience, and the manner of proceeding is knowne to, but a very few, there will be but a very ſmall number that will with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, adhere to the defence of my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed opinion, without yeilding up to the clamours of the Multitude, whoſe cryes are Poiſon, Poiſon, Poiſon, as thoſe impious Jewes throated it out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our ever bleſſed Saviour, <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie him,</hi> and avowing him the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt and worſt of poiſons, when as he was, and is indeed the <hi>Panacea</hi> of our Soules, redeeming of us from ſin, death,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:105077:25"/>
the Devill and Hell, although the proud inſulting Scribes and Phariſees denyed him, yet aſſuredly it both was and will remain a certain truth (let the Enemies of truth be broken to pieces) even to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity; nor ſhall be ever convicted of falſity, by either Death, Devils, or the Gates of Hell.</p>
            <p>So I know that many trifling wander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, lazy Doctors, Empericks, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Intruders into Phyſick, will cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor out againſt Antimony, crying, A Crucifige; but yet it will endure, when thoſe ignorant Medicaſters ſhall be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to pieces (I ſpeak not here of thoſe honeſt Phyſitians, who adjudge it no ſhame to receive inſtruction) it will, I ſay, remain, and by the vertue of it's due preparation, potently ſubdue and conquer its enemies, when as the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed haters and deriders of Antimony ſhal periſh, together with the blood-thirſty enemies of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I tend my ſpeech to you skilfull Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, who perſwade Kings and Princes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yea, and warn them to beware of this or that Medicine, as being hurtfull, poyſonous, and dangerous; how redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous you appear in my eye, I forbear
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:105077:26"/>
to mention, for I well perceive and finde, that though in their own eſteem they are moſt learned men, yet they ſpeak onely according to opinion, ignorantly, and without any true obſervation, on which account they cannot either judge or ſpeak otherwiſe; and if it ſhould happen that a man ſhould have drunk ſuch a Poyſon, and be even burſt aſſunder, even there, by the help of God, would I adminiſter ſuch an Antidote of my own preparation (which, out of meer charity, I always am careful of having ready by me) which ſhould timely expel all the Poyſon, and caſt it out: Although thou, Mr. Doctor, who neither obſerveſt or underſtandeſt, wilt ſay 'tis falſe and a lie; it matters not, I know how to defend my own, and by approved experience to confirm it; I have tryed it, prepared it, and (if ſo liked me) could produce teſtimony of its operation from the hands of many. And if I were to diſpute in a methodical le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimate order with that Doctor, as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares not any of his Medicines, nor knows how to do it, but commits the charge and care thereof to another: I am confident that I ſhould outſtrip him in his function of adminiſtring ſuitable remedies, &amp; tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:105077:26"/>
him down to a place more low, with ſhame enough, he being ignorant of what he adminiſters to his Patients, and unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Qualities of his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, whether white, black, red, caeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leous, yellow, hot, cold, moiſt, or dry, or what they be: He reads of them one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Books, and by length of time ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains a poſſeſſion of them, (or, as it were, a poſſeſſion) nor endeavors he after any more acquaintance with them: Moſt righteous God! what will theſe do? what care do theſe men take of their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences? how will they ſuccor the ſick? Woe, woe, In the laſt day they'l finde the end thereof, and deſervedly finde whom it is that they have pierced. Their thoughts are altogether after money, when as if they rightly minded their Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, they would night and day think how to obtain farther for the augmenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their renown: But labour being burdenſome unto them, they let that paſs, and run on, and defend their Cure with prating, but yet with a checking Conſcience, and without any foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And let thus much ſuffice them.</p>
            <p>Coles, to ſuch men, are out of uſe, nor do they want them, but keep their
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:105077:27"/>
money to beſtow it on better uſes: <hi>Vulcan</hi> has but ſmall familiarity with them, their Furnaces for deſtillation are onely in the Apothecaries Shop, and thither alſo they rarely come: A little peice of Paper, ſtufft with a Recipe, compleats all things; the which, a ſervant with his Peſtle and Mortar, compoſeth: Moſt bounteous God! change the time, put a period to their pride, lop off the Trees leaſt they grow up to Heaven; cruſh the Gyants, leaſt they heap up mountain upon moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and be aſſiſtant to thoſe that truſt upon thee, that they may ſtand before their hateful enemies.</p>
            <p>I do therefore admoniſh all my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, who live with me in this Cloyſter, that they conſtantly help me in their Prayers for more plenty of true Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, and that God would enlighten its hateful deriders, and reclaim them from their errors, whereby they may come to acknowledge the power of the Creator placed in his Creatures, and may hear it apparently and perſpicuouſly, and may underſtand the very inward ſecrets (by their endeavors and Anatomy) which lie moſt deeply hid under the outward form; &amp; I hope that the Almighty Creator wil
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:105077:27"/>
hear our Prayers, which if he pleaſe not, during mine and my Brethrens lives, yet haply after our deceaſe ſome may repent them, to whom ſo much Grace may be given, that their darkſome, blinde, and dimmed eyes, may receive ſight, and by a true enlightning, finde the loſt Groat, the which God grant. Amen.</p>
            <p>Now therefore, having decreed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver a perfect, and my abſolute opinion of Antimony, I think convenient to ſpeak a few words touching its name: Obſerve therefore, It was formerly called by the <hi>Arabians, Aſinat</hi>; by the <hi>Chaldeans, Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium</hi>; by the <hi>Latines</hi> 'tis to this day cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Antimonium</hi>; but the <hi>Germans,</hi> (ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious in their own proper Language) call it <hi>Spiſglâſſe, i. e.</hi> ſpeared or radiated Glaſs, becauſe its ſubſtance is in ſuch a form, and out of it may be made Glaſs (either apart, or by addition) of divers colours, lying hid therein, and educible therefrom. Let every one on that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count conſider, that the Obſervations of the <hi>Chaldeans, Arabians, Latines, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> and other People, about Antimony, were not in vain, but that both its vertue and uſe might equally and deſervedly be taken notice of, and 'tis very likely and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:105077:28"/>
credible, that by ſucceeding Hereſie its praiſe and virtue died, for truth may be oppreſt by the enemies violence, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil being by God permitted to act many things, becauſe of our Tranſgreſſions and blindneſs.</p>
            <p>Satan, you know, is mans enemy, and now that the verity of ſincere Medicine may be impeded and totally drowned, he makes uſe of all his Art and endeavors, that the power of God may be eclipſed, and no thanks aſcribed to him for his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted Bleſſings, and that natural reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and redreſſes may be removed from man.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing 'tis not ſo much requiſite to diſpute and diſcourſe much of the name of Antimony, becauſe its Title neither helps nor hinders, and becauſe all the praiſe conſiſts in its preparation, and in that power which by nature is given to it, and by the Creator beſtowed on it: I ſhall omit to mention more of its name, and come to deſcribe its efficacy and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, by which its vertues may be laid open, and immortal praiſe may be obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Yet before I come to rehearſe the virtues of Antimony, ſeeing (by my own acknowledgement) that it is a meer Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon:
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:105077:28"/>
I will propound an Example, how one Poyſon attracts another like to it ſelf, more effectually then any other thing whatſoever. For (friendly Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er) obſerve that the true and inadulterate Unicorns horn, caſts from it ſelf all ſorts of Poyſon, which is thus evidenced: Draw a circle with the ſaid Horn about a Spider, and he will never get out, becauſe he flies from what is contrary to him; but if another Poyſon be put thereto, he would not fly or run from it, but paſſing through it, would go out of the Circle.</p>
            <p>Moreover, if a little piece of Silver, hollowed, be made ſwim in a veſſel full of water (<hi>wherein put ſome poyſon</hi>) place the ſaid Horn thereunto, and let there not be any bodily or corporal touch, and yet you ſhal ſee it to repel the ſaid peice far from it, which will fly upon the Water, even as a Duck foreſeeing the Fowler: But if it be placed, <hi>viz.</hi> the Horn nigh to a piece of pure unadulterated Bread, ſwimming upon the Water, it will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently attract the Bread unto it ſelf, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any corporeal touch, and the Bread will follow the Horn round about, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as you move it, which is moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:105077:29"/>
wonderful in nature, that each thing ſhould attract its like, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily hate and abandon what is oppoſite unto it: From whence, the Phyſitians have taken occaſion to conſider how to attract Poyſon by Poyſon, and things not Venomous, by things void of Poyſon, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Magnetical manner. And thus Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons is expelled two ſeverall wayes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, By its contrary, which oppoſeth and reſiſts the Venome, as I have ſpoken of the Unicorns <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orns.</p>
            <p>Secondly, By its like, that one Poyſon may extract the other Magnetically; yet ſo, that the attractive Poyſon be firſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, that its venenoſity may be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muted into Medicine, ſufficiently able to deſtroy the Poyſon by its attractive power: So Soap waſheth Greaſe out of cloath, though it ſelfe was at firſt a fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but when it is prepared of Lime, Oyl, and other things, by boyling and ſeparation (chiefly by the help of ſalt) it ceaſeth to defile of to ſpot, but rather takes them away; ſo (by the help of God) in like manner Poyſon by precedent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, may ceaſe to be poyſonous, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting it, diſſipating it, and reſtore to former health: But that I may give
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:105077:29"/>
thee, and the Students of Art, oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of being acquainted with the gifts of Nature, and what Poyſon is, or how to be adjudged, whether good or bad, or what it is, I ſhall make uſe of ſome Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples for confirmation of the truth, and the diſcovery of falſity and error; which proudly arrogant Medicaſters or Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, by reaſon of their ſluggiſh and droan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh lazineſſe are unacquainted with.</p>
            <p>Take an Egge frozen with cold in the Winter ſeaſon, put it into exceeding cold Water for a little while, and then the frigidity of the Water will extract the coldneſs of the Egge, and reduce it to its priſtine eſtate; So, whoſoever ſhall have any member benummed with cold, let him ſpeedily apply cold Snow water thereunto, and ſo one cold will extract another, and the Member ſhall be heat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: So to any member poſſeſſed with a fervent burning heat, let be applyed ſome warm, hot matter (to wit, Spirit of Wine rectified, or the Quinteſſence of Sulphur, both which are fiery in the ſupreameſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree) and you ſhall ſee that the one heat attracts the other, by the force of mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netiſm from the member whereto it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, and adminiſters not onely reſt, but
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:105077:30"/>
perfect health. I could confirm my ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with many undenyable Examples; Take the Sperm of Frogs, appearing in the Spring, put them upon a Tile, dry them at the Sun and powder them; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperge of this Powder on the venomous bitings of Snakes and water-Serpents, and 'twill induce a good baſis for their healing, inſomuch that other Medicines will compleat the cure <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a linnen cloath oftentimes moiſtned with the ſaid Frog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpawn, dryed, cut in p<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ces, and applyed, will perform the ſame.</p>
            <p>I <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill alſo lead thee to the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals of truth, by another enſample<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> Take a living Toad, dry him firſt at the Sun, then in a covered Pot well luted, bring him to aſhes, pound him, and lay the powder on venomous bitings, or ſuch accidents, and you ſhall ſee one Venome attracting the other; and the reaſon is, becauſe by burning or calcination, the vertue of the Toad is opened, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred effectually powerful to attract its like Poyſon.</p>
            <p>Let this certain, indubious, and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory example, of Poyſon attracting its like, ſerve thee inſtead of the reſt: If therefore any one be infected with the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:105077:30"/>
Plague, and ſhall cautiouſly and diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerve this thing, he ſhall finde that I have written moſt true; now the beſt preſervatives in the Plague are, the Star of the Sun, and the Spirit of Mercury ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred together, now the Spirit of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury operates, by attracting to it ſelf Poyſons of a like nature, as a true cure of all venomous accidents: But becauſe the Star of the Sun (by whom (as an ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating vivifying Sun) all things are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated) doth after a manner conquer uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally every thing, I have placed the ſupreameſt active power in the vertue of the Sun; that is, in its Star, from whence all Metals and Minerals do principally obtain the original of their Generation and Increaſe, of which I ſhall treat more at large, when I ſhall come to make ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt the Star of the Sun unto thee, thine own conſcience bearing me witneſs.</p>
            <p>Under the which Solar nature, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is contained, and deſerves obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for it produceth the ſelf ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects as Gold doth, and acts as much as corporeal Gold can do; but it hath not attained the vertue of the Star of the Sun, but fears and trembles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him; and although Antimony may
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:105077:31"/>
well boaſt of his vaſt ſurpaſſing of the moſt fundamental medicines, yet falls he ſhort of univerſally accompliſhing that, which the Star of the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>un hath (by teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of a Celeſtial virtue) in it ſelf, and is able to perform.</p>
            <p>I omit to ſpeak of the Star of <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> although it ſprings from the ſame matter as the aforementioned do, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the penetrative force of the Star of the Sun, it yeilds to it as its ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
            <p>All my Books do harmoniouſly follow experience, even as links in a chain, or as Braſs ſtamps Braſs: Let the virtues of what is therein mentioned, be exactly conſidered, and judiciouſly experiment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Fire; for thus theſe writings of mine, my buſineſs, my propoſals and medicines are to be brought to a certain end and concluſion, and ought (if onely a right Judge be preſent) to obtain the true Hereditary ſeat, and by means of that attempted way, bear away the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and Renown: Now <hi>Vulcan,</hi> a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Artificer, as to the Fire (his own E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement) is the onely Judge; concerning which, hear an Example of a certain and indubitable Experiment: When a Flint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:105077:31"/>
is ſmitten againſt a Steel, a Fire is ſtirr'd up by their mutual colliſion and violent motion; the hidden Sulphur or occult Fire is diſcovered by that ſtriking, and is by the Air enkindled, ſo that it burns actually and ſenſibly; the Salt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in the Aſhes, and the <hi>Mercury</hi> flies away like combuſtible Sulphur. From hence you may underſtand a certain man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how to proceed with Antimony, <hi>viz. That his Mercury be ſeparated from his Sulphur and Salt,</hi> by <hi>Medium</hi>'s, granted us by nature. As the Fire (whil'ſt lying in its matter) operates nothing, either pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable or permanent, unleſs it be made manifeſt; ſo all remedies, except they are ſeparated from their more groſs parts, and are rectified, looſned, clarified, and artificially prepared (by which all men may acknowledge that there's a ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made of the pure from the impure) and except the Metallick: arth be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the rich, pure Metal, there's no ground of any certain and infallible hope; all which tranſites cannot be done without the true manner of opening and looſening the Body by the Regiment of Fire.</p>
            <p>In a word, I thus unfold the Nature of Antimony.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:105077:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>All ſecret things (whilſt hidden) are eſteemed arts, the ſecret being revealed ceaſeth to be an art, and becoms a Trade, as I have elſewhere taught.</p>
            <p>The Bee ſucks Honey from the Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers by an art which God hath given him, wherein the Virtue, Juice, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting faculty of Medicines is contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and out of which is openly or every where a Medicine made; and contrarily, from the ſweeteſt Honey may a Corroſive be made, and the worſt of poiſon, which experienced men only know, and (after Obſervation) beleive: Yet Hony is not to be rejected or deſpiſed, which, (notwithſtanding its moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſweetneſſe) becomes deſtructive to its own medicinall faculties, if a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſive be prepared therefrom, but, that the unvers'd and unexperienced Phyſitian knowes not its preparation: here there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will I fix a Croſſe even to the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment day, for ignorant and unlearned Phyſitians.</p>
            <p>Now Hony is thus prepared, Out of the Excrements of bruit beaſts, the Meadowes and dunged fields produce ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Flowers, Herbs, and Plants, (the Earths young ones) from theſe Plants,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:105077:32"/>
Herbs, and Flowers, the Bees extract a Juice or Quinteſſence, of which an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration is made, or a Generation of one thing from another, <hi>viz.</hi> a meat or Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney differing from the firſt ſavour and form; out of honey is prepared for man a moſt commodious, ſweet, and moſt profitable food for many things: Out of the ſame Honey may be prepared an intoxicating Eſſence, moſt deſtructive to man and beaſt.</p>
            <p>Conſider therefore O Phyſitian, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou art, young or old, learned or unlearned, rich or poor, a Workman or Artificer, or whatever thou art, follow me and Nature, I will fundamentally teach thee the truth without any lye; In what thing profit, and that which is good and right is, and in what injury is, and how thou ſhalt be able to ſeparate the good from the evill, the loweſt from the higheſt. Verily out of Antimony may be prepared a Medicine, (but all its ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenoſity muſt be firſt changed into Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine) which may be able to blot out and conſume all Diſeaſes, and to pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate, in the manner of fire. Know therefore that Antimony ought to be prepared into a true Stone like to fire, as
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:105077:33"/>
to its virtue, as I have ſaid; on which account the Quinteſſence of Antimony is by me called the Stone of Fire; for if it ſhall have been firſt brought to its own coagulation; and if our ſtone of fire ſhal be truly prepared (of which, at the end of this Tract I ſhall write more largely) its Operation is not unlike thoſe things, which conſume maligne Humours, and purifie the bloud even to the utmoſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, performing all ſuch things as are found in potable gold. Be therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated my Doctor, (and yet no Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, when as to this day thou haſt learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no due preparation, and much leſſe, Cognizance of the uſe of my Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines) that thou judge me not by thy opinion only, having no other Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes then the unexperienced imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thine own braines. But rather ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe thy ſelf to labour, learn the way of preparing Antimony, how it is to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded withall, how its poiſon is to be rejected and ſeparated, and a ſalubrious wholſome Remedy introduced in its roome; which if thou haſt done, thou mayſt truly judge of thoſe things which formerly were, and at preſent are to thee unknown.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:105077:33"/>O miſerable worldly Sophiſters, who are loaden, and with child as it were, of falſe Wiſdome, ye lean on a deceitfull Foundation, ye fly in the ayry imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of your owne fancies, and are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ignorant of the place of your reſt: I do therfore admoniſh you, as you will give an account at the dreadfull day of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Son of God, that you ſeek and learn what things you muſt uſe, that you may perform your duty, leaving the remainder unto God, who will bleſſe you, and afford his help unto you.</p>
            <p>O ſlow aſſes and drones, who care not to make any progreſſe in Learning, and fear to black your hands with coales, be not haſty to judge, neither give any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſion of pulling that Sentence upon your ſelves, which your childrens children may write againſt you in a booke incorruptible,</p>
            <p>Above all things let every Phyſitian be cautious, that he preſcribe nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe to Nature or to his cure, leaſt his hope of reſtoring Health deceive him. As if ſpirit of Wine ſhould be poured in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the water of ſeparation, a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict and burning would ſuddenly follow, becauſe one nature cannot brook the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:105077:34"/>
But he that knowes how to unite and conjoyne them Philoſophically in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillation, will be able by the help there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to make things momentary. So the Oyle or Liquor of Tartar, and Vinegar cannot be united by reaſon of their mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall hatred (although they both ſprang from the ſame Fountaine) differing from each other, as much as fire and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; ſo then the Phyſitian in his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking a cure, ought heedfully to inquire into all circumſtances that reſpect his patient, and having ſo examined, let him conſider and uſe ſuch right Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums as may remove the evill, leſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction ariſeth from that which ſhould have remedied the Diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>As when a red hot iron is quenched in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quafortis,</hi> &amp; oyl of Tartar forthwith pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thereunto, thou ſhalt ſcarce preſerve thy glaſſe from breaking, but thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Natures, will caſt out fire from themſelves in the manner of Gunpowder, concerning which, our Doctor with his Gowne being ignorant, is forc'd to hold his peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ah</hi> wretched men, unlearned Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, unexperienced Phyſitians, who write tedious Receipts in a long paper:
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:105077:34"/>
O ye Apothecaries that ſet over the fire great cauldrons ſufficient to boil the meat of noble mens houſes, and to hold enough for an hundred perſons, how long will ye be blind, anoint your eyes with a Collyrium and Balſom, that the ſcales may be taken off, and your Eyes may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a true ſight, which the Lord vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe unto you, that you may acknowledge his wonders, and conſider his works, let Love and Charity to your Neighbour take root within you, that you may be ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers after true Medicine, which the King and Heavenly Prince of all, hath formed by his own omnipotent arme, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Wiſdome, and freely given for the benefit of the moſt noble creature, Man, <hi>viz.</hi> For his help and health in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt neceſſity.</p>
            <p>O deplorable, putrid, and ſtinking bag of Wormes,, ah poor little Worm and vileſt of creatures, what thinkeſt thou that thus feeleſt after the Husks, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt the kernells, nor ever thankeſt thy Creatour for them, after whoſe image thou wert created, nor ever giveſt praiſe unto him for all his wondrous works?</p>
            <p>Return, Return unto thy ſelf delineate or paint thy ſelf out, and make a Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:105077:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of thy Effigies, that it may ſhame thee of all thy ingratitude, becauſe tho<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haſt not hitherto ſought that which Go<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hath hidden in thoſe good things he hat<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> granted unto us, and infuſed into hi<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> creatures, that a Sacrifice of Praiſe ma<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be returned unto him. But I ſhall hold my peace, and from bewailing this miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, blindneſſe, and errour, (wherein the world is drowned) I ſhall reſtain<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my ſelf, left by the trickling down of tears my writings ſhould receive defilement, from which I can hardly abſtaine. <hi>I</hi> am an Eccleſiaſticall man, implanted into: Church-order, whereto <hi>I</hi> ſhall ſubject my ſelf with my heart and mouth as long as my Soule lives in this miſerable body: <hi>I</hi> am on that account compelled to refrain, nor dare <hi>I</hi> write any thing of my ſelfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> unleſſe it be ſuitable to my Order, elſe <hi>I</hi> would lift up my voice like a Trumpet, and were <hi>I</hi> but a Temporall Judge, <hi>I</hi> would have audience at the hands of thoſe contumacious men, who as yet not knowing the truth (but are ignorant) do ſlanderouſly perſecute it, calumniate, reproach, and oppreſſe it with all their ſtrength. Moſt good God, moſt high Lord of hoſts, that ſitteſt in thy Glorious
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:105077:35"/>
Throne, governeſt the Heavens and the earth which thou haſt created, conſerveſt the ſtars, diſpoſeſt the elements, &amp; the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament, that they may run their courſe, before whom all the World trembles, the internall Spirits fear; Look down for once upon the vanity of this unthankfull World: Teach the Sons of men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly to acknowledge what thou haſt outwardly ſet before their Eyes, that thou maiſt be glorified in thy Throne, truly known in thy power, and worthily praiſed in thy infinite government &amp; rule.</p>
            <p>Truly I (wretched and worthleſſe man do give all thanks to thy moſt glorious mjeſty for thoſe great miracles and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, of health and riches which thou haſt vouchſafed me, I cannot give thee any more in this World, which is but tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary and corruptible.</p>
            <p>But now in my writing of Antimony, I ſhall diſcover its beginning truly, of what originall, and how it obtaines ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority and government; how it may be elevated into its perfect operation: I will propound its root and its generation in the bowels of the Earth, to what pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominating ſtar it is ſubject, what Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they are which have concocted it.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:105077:36"/>
Let therefore the ſtudious artiſt know that Antimony is nothing elſe but a fum<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or minerall vapour, produced above by the ſtars, and then digeſted by the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments into a coagulated forme. Let all know, that Antimony receives its Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, Virtue, Faculty, Operation, and all qualities, as to its <hi>initium,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> birth, and root, as the Mercury of the Vulgar doth; but with an harder coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. Seeing that it is reduced to a more hard confirmation or <hi>coagulum,</hi> then common running mercury, which wants this induration, and the reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it participates of a more thick ſalt, (out of the three principles) although with reſpect to its three principies, the ſalt obtains in it the ſmalleſt roome, yet it hath more thereof then common mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury hath; from which meanes it ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains its coagulation; becauſe tis ſalt that gives hardneſſe in all things, which hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe common Mercury wants, becauſe of its ſmall portion of ſalt: In which mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury, a combuſtible ſulphur is inviſibly implanted, alwaies keeping it in flux, prohibiting its coagulation, nor can it be coagulated without the addition of other metallick Spirits, which in the matrix of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:105077:36"/>
Saturne are moſt potently effuſed, and to be there had beyond all the other metals, and otherwiſe it cannot be accompliſhed without the ſtone of the Wiſe men, by which its three principles are made har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious, and threby it obtaines a fuſil malleable, ſoluble, and conjugable bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy like to the other metalls, otherwiſe mercury is running mercury ſtill, and ſo remains untill this quality be taken from it. And on that account all animall and vegetable things are too too weake to bring mercury unto a fix, permanent and malleable hardneſſe (though ſome imagine the contrary) becauſe they are not of a metallick kind: for mercury is a meere fire, whence tis, that he can not be burnt by any fire, theres no fire touches him, at leaſt ſo, as totally to deſtroy, for he either ſuddenly flies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and is ſpiritually reſolved into an Oyle incombuſtible, or elſe after fixation he abides conſtant that none can abſtract from him any thing more; and by this it appears alſo, becauſe of him may be made whatſoever can by art be made of gold, for after a due coagulation hee is in all things like to gold, becauſe he enjoyes the ſame root, ſtock, and originall, as gold
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:105077:37"/>
doth: But ſeeing it is not my purpoſed aime to ſpeake more prolixly of mercury here, and by ſpeaking to introduce diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations, but ſimply and candidly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the true fundamentall Originall of Antimony, farewell mercury, that the diſcourſe of Antimony may be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but yet that which I have ſpoken of mercury; parabollically, for your farther meditation, is not mentioned in vaine, but that Antimony may thereby be the more rightly underſtood, it alſo being endowed with a Mercuriall Orig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</p>
            <p>Obſerve, mark and underſtand this, commit it to thy memory, <hi>viz.</hi> That all mineralls, as alſo all metalls are born of one <hi>Principium</hi> or beginning, to wit, of a vapour, which the ſuperiour ſtars do as it were extract from the Element of the Earth, by a certain diſtillation of the Macrocoſme or greater world, the influx of which upper aſtrall heat, operates upon things below, by an aereall fiery p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, infu<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing it in, ſpiritually and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſibly. Which vapour is reſolved in the Earth, and flowes, as it were, into water; from which minerall water, all mettalls are ſeaſonably brought to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:105077:37"/>
their maturity and perfection, and of it is made this or that metall or minerall, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the predominating power of one of the three principles, or that which it abounds withall, be it one, or two, or all, equally tempered together, from whence tis that ſome metalls are fixt, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſome not fixt, as are Gold, Silver, Copper, Iron, Tin, and Lead; more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over beſides thoſe known metalls, out of the ſame three principles (according to the various commixion of them) are ſundry and divers mineralls generated and produced, ſuch are Vitrioll, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, Marcaſits, and other like Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrams, and Mineralls, all which to rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon up, would be ſuperfluous; Now whe<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Gold in its own Aſteriſme and Generation becomes ſuddenly impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated with, and receives a portion of a more pure and perfect Sulphur and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury then the other mineralls and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls have, therefore its operative pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and virtue is more large and effectuall in acting then the <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tars of the other me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls, and mineralls are, and on that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, in the ſtar of the Sun all things ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear more perfectly (if at leaſt it ſhall be, by the benefit of the fire, reduced to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:105077:38"/>
its maturity) then are to be found in the reſt of the metalls and mineralls. And yet notwithſtanding is there one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly minerall, (frequently mentioned by me) wherein the Sulphur of the Sun is found to be as ſtrong (yea and ſtronger) then in the Sun it ſelf, even as alſo there are two ſorts of metalls found, wherein thoſe dominations do abundantly triumph of which this is no place to treate: but I ſhall go on to finiſh the deſcription of the Nature of Antimony. Antimony therefore is a minerall having its minerall vapour turned into water, which ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Emanation of the ſtars, is the true ſtar of Antimony; which water in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement of the Earth, by the ſtrength of the ſtars, and alſo of the Fire dwelling in the aire, being dryed, became by coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation a palpable thing; out of which, Antimony is generated and brought forth in a forme, wherein ſulphur beares the ſway. Mercury hath the next portion, and ſalt the leaſt; although it hath received ſalt enough to become an hard unmalle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able forme. As to its quality it is dry and cold, its cold and moiſture are not much, even as common Mercury and corporeal gold it ſelf, hath more of heat then cold:
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:105077:38"/>
Let theſe things ſuffice concerning the matter and the 3 Principles of Antimony, and how by the Archeus in the Element of the Earth, It became perfect. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch a narrow, Philoſophical ſearch is not of ſo much concernment to the Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of Art, and moſt men value not in what centre the ſtar of Antimony Reſides, and from whence tis ſprung, but would rather learne what good lyes in it, and would underſtand its preparation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction to a due ſtate, that the virtues and operations thereof; ſo much every where, by all, ſpoken of, may not be to them unknown: I ſhall therefore omit to delay them with long doubtings, but will briefly and ſincerely write thoſe things which in my private labour I have obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be in Antimony: Although, for the ſhortneſſe of life none can perfectly learn all, becauſe in its preparations, miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous accidents doe follow each other, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree following degree, colour following colour. One virtue, faculty, and operation ſucceds another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antimony</hi> therefore is no light or trivial poyſon, but a chief one, and moſt high, being deadly both to man and beaſt; from whence the common Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:105077:39"/>
and ignorant plebeians (having no true knowledge of Medicine) reject the uſe of Antimony as Poiſonous; &amp; Phyſitians forbid it to noble men, as dangerous; and the Academical Profeſſours doe barke out and howle (even to madneſſe) to their diſciples, a Caveto: O beware of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony for its a merely abſolute poyſon: Now the inhabitants of Towns, or Cities on theſe clamours forbid the uſe of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and with thoſe out cryes have moſt men bin ſtird up, that even to my Age or time, they'l not hear of Antimony, nor give any truſt unto his medicines, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though immenſe and unſpeakable things are found therein: Well, bee it ſo, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily I ſpeak the truth and my writings are void of falſity: I call God my Creatour to witneſſe, that there is not a more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble medicine under the heavens, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a capital rich-pillar may be placed, then is in Antimony, and deſervedly on that accompt ought there to be fixed and erected.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Son; mark my ſayings</hi>; Reader, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve my writings, wiſe men, Conſider the Antimonial experiments which I doe mention; My theory is founded upon na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and my practick on experience,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:105077:39"/>
moſt frequently demonſtrated &amp; produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing its effect to the admiration of many incredulous people; I doe confeſſe as formorly I have done, that Antimony at firſt before its preparation is a meere poyſon. But good <hi>M.</hi> Doctour, or Batche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, or Phyſitian, (but yet without any true degree,) ſince thou art buried as to Art, and Onely beateſt the buſh, what doſt thou talke for, let me alſo ſpeak too, remember what thou ſayeſt and conſider that doctrine which I propound unto thee; Antimony (ſay'ſt thou) is poyſon. <hi>Ergo,</hi> none ought to uſe it; a miſerable concluſion good <hi>M.</hi> Doctour and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelour or <hi>M.</hi> Phyſitian with your red cap: The beſt Triacle is made of poyſon or of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from whence it hath its denomination. And therefore none may take it into their bodies, becauſe a poyſon is therein: what? doth this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine pleaſe you? is this voice acceptable to your ears? Antimony after preparation ceaſeth to be a poyſon, and the whole of it being by Spagyrick Art tranſmuted, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes medicinal, even as Triacle is made of the venemous viper; But before its preparation thou ſhalt not receive any profit or benefit from Antimony, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:105077:40"/>
diſcommodity and danger.</p>
            <p>Now if thou intendeſt to become an Antimonial diſciple (having firſt pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) frequent the School of Vulcan beyond all other things, who is the maſter and teacher of all ſecrets, (which the meanly learned men doe deride, and by their ſloathful lazineſſe never come to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with any ſecret from him, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off the manifeſtation of any Arcanum by their own ſluggiſhneſſe,) nor is there any remedy in the world to be prepared without fire, let them cry out as they liſt, though never ſo madly.</p>
            <p>But what ſhall we ſpeak of theſe haters of Antimony, let us not value them, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they can bring to the light ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing better and more excellent then An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony is; ſeeing that eſpecially out of Antimony, may like remedies be had as ly hid in Gold and the Mercury of the vulgar, (the ſtar of the ſun onely excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) from both which may an <hi>Aurum Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabile</hi> bee made to heal the Leproſie, and the ſpirit of Mercury is the chief Top remedy of the french diſeaſe and many others. Although thoſe contemning fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows neither know nor are able to ſearch it out. An ignorant man can no more
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:105077:40"/>
judge, then the Aſſe (being ignorant of ſymphony) can inſtruct the ſhepherd how to handle his pipe. He therefore that would truely judge, ought afore to learn all ſuch things as he intends to deliver his judgement about, and to know as well from experience as from books that which is true and that which is falſe, that ſo he may judge aright.</p>
            <p>But before I addreſſe my ſelf to the manner of proceding, I may perchance meet with ſome who will inquire whence minerals and other venemous ſubjects at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract their poyſon, what the eſſentiality of poyſon is, &amp; from whence generated in all things; how (the poyſon being removed) that thing may be converted unto medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine &amp; ſafely adminiſtred without danger. I ſhall therefore informe you, concerning the influence of poyſon, the which may be conſidered, naturally &amp; ſupernaturally.</p>
            <p>Therefore the firſt reaſon why God (the ſupream guide, and governour of the ſtars, the Creatour of Heaven and Earth,) hath thought good to ſet before us ſenſible poyſons, eſpecially in mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, is that by their firſt conſtitution, mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous and powerful operation there plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God, a man might ſee that his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:105077:41"/>
of thus expoſing them to view, was, that there might be a diſtinction between good and evil, even as in his law, he hath preſcribed us the knowledge of things to be done and to be left undone, <hi>viz.</hi> of good to be embraced and of evil to be avoided; After the ſame manner as the tree in Paradiſe was placed before our firſt parents, the uſe whereof tended to good, but the abuſe to evil, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God being violated miſery and deſtruction ſtep't in.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another cauſe is that the good and the evil being known, the evil might be avoided and reduced unto a better ſtate; for its not the will &amp; pleaſure of God that men drowned in deſtruction ſhould total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly periſh, but that returning from evil, they proceed to what is better, and avoid the loſſe of their ſouls; On that account hath he by ſimilitudes placed before us good and evil, which in like manner is to be found in the command of his mouth verbally, and in the work of creation, that we may chooſe things tending to health, and avoid things tending to deſtruction.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, poyſon is alſo produced by the ſtars, wherein are malevolent and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rary conjunctions and oppoſitions of the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:105077:41"/>
Planets, whence it falls out that the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets become infected and then cauſe in this inferiour world and microcoſme pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues and other venemous diſeaſes; The like may you conceive of the comets.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, Poyſon is alſo Produced by the fighting of two contraries, as for example, if a man exceedingly angry, or ſad, or boyling with rage ſhould drink, a deadly poyſon would thereby be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindled.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Fifthly; For illuſtrations ſake, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons may be ranked under the forme of poyſons, if by them, any one receive a mortal wound, (in which the abuſe of weapons conſiſts;) But if they be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed for defence and preſervation of life, therein, their uſe is lawful and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted unto medicine.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Sixtly and laſtly, The cauſe of poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon becomes apparent from conſidering nature. Whatſoever fights againſt her is a poyſon to her, as in ſome men, they beeing not able to bear ſome meats, thoſe meats being contrary to nature, become a poyſon, but to ſuch as love them, a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine; But principally, venenoſity is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted from an earth of a Mercurial ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance (I ſpeak of mineral poyſons) which
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:105077:42"/>
being immature, indigeſted, of a form contrary to nature, and of hard concoction (which hinders maturity and perfection,) the whole body becomes thereby as it were a <hi>Crude mineral</hi>; As if a man ſhould devour crude or raw wheat, his ſtomack would hardly concoct it, but weakneſſe and inconveniences would ſeize upon the whole body, becauſe of the deficiency and weakneſſe of natural heat to digeſt it.</p>
            <p>But the wheat beeing maturated by the fire of the Macrocoſme, ought to be againe boyled or concocted by a leſſer fire that it may be digeſted by the Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme, as I have aforeſaid concerning the eating of fleſh; hence tis evident that ſeeing Antimony is crude, volatile and not maturated in the Earth, or enough decocted, it cannot be born by the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach without terrible torment of the body, and deſtruction, becauſe of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of natural heat, too inſufficient throughly to digeſt it; experience tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth thus much, that all purging me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines (be they mineral, animal, or vegetable) are of a poyſonous ſubſtance, becauſe of the predominating, Mercurial, volatile eſſence that is in them, which volatile ſpirit is the cauſe of caſting out
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:105077:42"/>
thoſe things that are found in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet they do not ſet upon the root of that diſeaſe which is fixt, becauſe fix't remedies onely doe throughly ſearch out and radically expel fix't diſeaſes, which to unfixt purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions is not granted, they, beeing like a violent torrent, ſweep away what lyes in their compaſſe, but doe not work upon the fixed earth. Now fixed and prepared Purgatives doe not operate by ſtoole, but ſhow themſelves onely by ſweat and and other means, and hunt out the very kernel and not the huske or ſhell and chaffe of the diſeaſe, as volatile, unfixt and unprepared purges doe, they onely expel the cruſt as it were, and cover of what is excrementitious, but as to the centre of the diſeaſe, that they reach not unto.</p>
            <p>Be it on that account known to every one, of what ſtate, age, or title ſoever, that the venomous Eſſence muſt be total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly removed out of <hi>Antimony,</hi> before it can be tranſmitted into Medicine, and be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled with the name of a Remedy. Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken therefore to the ſeparation of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, of the good from the bad, of the fix'd from the volatile, of diſtinguiſhing what is helpful from what is poyſonous, if at leaſt we would obtain profit with
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:105077:43"/>
honour, and verity, which cannot be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed without the ſeparation of Vulcan or fire, who is the artificer, as to all ſuch things. For whatſoever Vulcan leaves imperfect in the Macrocoſme, that the Microcoſme repairs and amends by a new Vulcan, which maturates what is crude, and perfectly concocts it, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſeparation of the pure from the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure; And let it not ſeem ſtrange that the pure and the wholſome can be ſegre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated from the impure and unwholſome, and that a remedy can (by the benefit of fire) be made out of that which is hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; Becauſe tis evidenced by daily expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience in the probation and inſpection of colours diſcovered by the fire: for ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and fire makeing a fixation, take away the venome and in its roome ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute a Salubrious remedy. Tis the fire then, that ſeparates the poiſon from the medicine, the good from the evil, which thing none of the Phyſitians either can or dare ſet their ſeales unto, unleſſe they have contracted a moſt intimate familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity with Vulcan, <hi>and obtained that infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Bath of Amity, wherein the bride being waſhed from all her uncleaneſſe</hi> may enter with her bridegrome into a legitimate
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:105077:43"/>
bed; O worldly ſubtilty that deſpiſeſt or doſt not underſtand my writings, did'ſt thou but know what I have now ſaid unto thee, what may be called fixt, and what volatile, what the ſeparation of the Pure from the impure meanes, thou wouldſt turn off many things to Lethes Lake, and contemne thoſe trifles wherein thou tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteſt and follow me. For in me <hi>(theſe are the words of Antimony</hi>) ſhalt thou find a Mercury, Sulphur, and ſalt, moſt uſeful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies for the health of man; the Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial part lyes hid in the Regulus, the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur in the redneſſe, and the Salt in the Black Earth which remains in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome. Theſe three rightly ſeparated and againe co-united by a due artificial man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that a fixation without any poyſon may be accompliſhed, give juſt cauſe of bo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſting to the Artiſt, that he hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the ſtone of fire, which may be made of Antimony both for mans health, his food and rayment. For in Antimony maiſt thou find all the colours of the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, as white, black, red, green, blew, aſhcolour, yellow, and colours innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, diverſly preparable by incredible mixtures, diverſly to be known and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral wayes to be adminiſtred in ſundry
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:105077:44"/>
caſes, every ſort to be orderly diſpoſed according to an appointed method; I will therefore in ſeveral particles make mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt how medicine is to be prepared, how poyſon is to be ejected, fixation to be inſtituted, things that are to be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted how to be begun withal, that the evil may be conquered and the good may overcome. <hi>Tis well</hi> known to ſtudious Artiſts, that Antimony doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the virtue of one onely Gemme in it ſelfe, as the other metals which (in their kind) are attributed but to one; But univerſally containes the virtues of all ſtones, which appears by the various co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, which by the regiment of fire it doth yeeld forth; of this colour ſome, otherſome of another ſort <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Its pellucid ſhining redneſſe is attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to a Carbuncle, Rubine, and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals; Its whiteneſſe to the Diamond and Chryſtal: Its blew and sky colour to the Saphyr; Its green to a Smaragdine; Its yellow to a Hyacinth; Its black to a Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, which naturally carryes in it an Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult hidden blackneſſe; But in relation to metals; Its black is aſcribed to Saturn, Its redneſſe to Mars, yellow to the Sun, Green to Venus, sky colour to the Moon,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:105077:44"/>
white to Mercury, its various mixt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour to Jupiter; But as all the colours expreſſed in ſtones and metals are found in Antimony, ſo therein alſo all the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and faculties of remedies are to be found according to the Reaſon of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, which though they are all found in Antimony, tis notwithſtanding impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that one man alone ſhould be throughly acquainted with them all, for the ſhortneſſe of life <hi>prohibits</hi> one man alone to learn all thoſe Arcanums which nature Carryes with it; <hi>Some-times</hi> in its preparation, a moſt acid vinegar is extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by deſtillation; After another way and manner is prepared from it a perfect and tranſparent Redneſſe, ſweet and pleaſant as Hony or the pureſt Sugar; Then again of a ſudded tis prepared into the bitterneſſe of Wormewood; Another while it imitates the Acrimony of the Oile of ſalt, and ſo one nature ſucceeds another: <hi>Some-times</hi> again tis elevated by ſublimation into the Olympian Mountains in the manner of a flying Eagle, red, yellow and white, being forced down <hi>per deſcenſum</hi> it yeelds va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious particular colours and preparations, as alſo by reverberation, Tis alſo conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:105077:45"/>
into a metal like to lead and into pellucid glaſſe, white, red, yellow, or black or of any other colour, but all the ſorts of this glaſſe are not with ſafety to be uſed in medicine, unleſſe tryed by a previous examen.</p>
            <p>Antimony may alſo be reſolved into various and ſeveral wonderful oiles, either alone by it ſelf, or elſe with the addition and commixtion of other things, of which oiles ſome are onely to be outwardly uſed, and anointed on wounds or ulcers, otherſome may be taken inwardly and drunken; It yeelds alſo marvelous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions which diſcover themſelves ſo various in colour, that the oracle of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo can hardly divine and reckon up the wonderous mutations of its nature manifeſted and opened by the help of fire; There's alſo made thereof Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver, and Sulphur Combuſtible, like to the common Sulphur, whereof Gunpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may be made; as alſo a true and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Salt and many other things. I'le therefore now begin to treat of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of Antimony, to wit of Its eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, magiſtery, Arcanum and Elixir, and its particular Tincture, which ſtudiouſly obſerve: where (towards the latter end)
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:105077:45"/>
I ſhall rehearſe ſomewhat of the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſtone of fire, I'le alſo recite many other ſecrets, but litle known, or elſe neglected in the world, becauſe the <hi>Egyptians, Arabians</hi> and <hi>Chaldeans</hi> are long ſince dead, who exerciſed this Art, which may abundantly ſerve as the head and fountain of true and inadulterate me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine.</p>
            <p>Obſerve therefore diligently and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly all my preparations, as I ſhall lay them open unto thee, of which not one is without fruit and profit, Its due ſtate beeing obſerved; for the fixd medicines of Antimony heal fixt diſeaſes, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixd, heal diſeaſes not fixed: ſo crude An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony (not its prepared glaſſe) doth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>load and purge the ventricle onely, but ſuffers the cauſe of the diſeaſe to remaine. I now therefore begin at the ſeveral ſorts of the ordering of Antimony and make evidence of all the keyes of its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, which by fire onely is manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, as a new birth, in that vocation or calling preſcribed by God: The ſolution or preparation of the mineral of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is done by ſundry ſorts of fire and regiments of Art, by which its medicinal force and operation is extracted by heat,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:105077:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and ſeeing that Antimony is of a mixt colour, of a dull reddiſh black with a litle ſhining whiteneſſe. I'll firſt deſcribe its firſt deſtruction, or calcination, which is thus brought to paſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Take</hi> Hungarian Antimony, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, (the beſt) grind it upon a marble into moſt ſubtile powder, lay this powder thin and ſparingly in a plain Earthen veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, round or ſquare, which let be made with rims about the heigth of two fingers breadth; Place this veſſel on a calcining furnace, adminiſter at firſt a Gentle fire of coals, and when the ſtibium begins to fume, ſtir it with a litle iron rod to and againe, without ceaſing, until it ceaſeth to emit any Vapour; but if in the calcina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Antimony chanceth to melt and run into balls, Take off the veſſel from the fire and let the ſtibium cool, and grind it again, and doe as afore, which muſt be ſo often don, until it neither fumes nor runs together any more, but remains in the form of white Aſhes, for then is your Calcination perfect.</p>
            <p>Take now this ſtibium thus calcined put it into a goldſmiths Crucible, Place it at a violent fire, that the Antimony may flow like pure clear Water, and that you
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:105077:46"/>
may know when the glaſſe of ſtibium hath attained a perfect and pellucid colour, put into the crucible a long cold iron, and the glaſſe will ſtick thereunto, which ſtrike of with an hammer, and ſo ſeparate it, and hold it up againſt the light, which if it be tranſparent tis good and perfect glaſſe.</p>
            <p>But the Reader and Tyro in this Art, (for I write not to experienced Artiſts, who have a long time endured the heat of the fire, and ſo its a ſlight and eaſy thing to them to make Glaſſe of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, but to young followers of Pyro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techny) ought to know that all glaſſe be it made of what it will, either of a mineral, or a metal, or other things, ought to have its due perfection, that it may ſhine througly, may operate and be moreover further prepared for medicine.</p>
            <p>The Antimony thus melted in the Crucible, Take a plain and broad diſh or platter of Laton, which (firſt) well warm, leſt it break; poure in the ſtibium by litle and litle, and very thinly, and thou ſhalt have a yellow tranſparent fayr glaſſe. And this way of preparing the glaſſe of Antimony without any adition is the beſt, which in its operation diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:105077:47"/>
a greater virtue, and this is that which I call pure Glaſſe, the other ſorts being made by the addition of Borax, and other ſuch things, for example.</p>
            <p>Take Antimony one part, Venice Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rax two parts, grind them together, put them in a crucible, and place them at a moſt violent fire, untill they melt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, poure them out into a Diſh of Latton warmed, by little and little, and let it run thin, and thou ſhalt have (if thou haſt rightly proceeded) a red tranſparent Glaſſe like to a Rubine, the redneſſe or which glaſſe may be extracted with ſpirit of Wine by a long circulation in the fire, and adminiſtred with very great ſucceſſe, for a moſt noble Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine.</p>
            <p>There may be alſo made of Antimony a white Glaſſe after this manner, Take Antimony one part, Venice Borax four parts, grind them together, and flux or melt them in a crucible as aforeſaid, firſt twill become yellow, but by a longer continuance in the fire, it wil become moſt white, which you may try by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thereinto a cold Iron, and examine if the colour be perfect or not, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed as above.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:105077:47"/>There may be prepared alſo out of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony, glaſſe of ſeverall other colours, but I have only ſet before you ſuch as I have learned by experience, &amp; know their Tendency to health, nor do I judge it neceſſary to fill up paper with too much talking, and by unprofitable verball cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuits to prove irkſome to the Reader, and the rather, for that there hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared unto thee (as to the glaſſe made of Antimony) the cheifeſt colour, <hi>viz.</hi> A tranſparant Redneſs: The blackneſſe which at firſt was its aſſociate fled away with the fume after a ſpirituall manner, becauſe according to that ſpirituall kinde, by the violence of fire the poiſon is blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out, and taken away by calcination, although the Glaſſe be not abſolutely deſtitute of poyſon, but holds (as yel) a great portion thereof in it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>I will go on therefore to acquaint thee, how the poyſon may be altogether taken away from the glaſſe, the pure from the impure, and a new ſeparation of that which is hurfull, from what is helpfull may be inſtituted; that the Tongue of the Eloquent may be looſned, and cauſe given him of propagating my praiſe to the Worlds end, which without all que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:105077:48"/>
my Diſciples wil cheerefully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, when they come to ſee and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive with their eyes, and feel with their hands, that I have written the naked truth for their profit and renoun, and have left behind me as it were a memorable Teſtament.</p>
            <p>Now the firſt ſeparation of the Sulphur from its own body and extraction of the Tincture from the Salt is thus brought to paſſe.</p>
            <p>Take pure glaſſe of Antimony made without any addition, as I have taught thee, grind it to the conſiſtency of meal or ſlower, put it into a glaſſe bolt head having a broad bottom, whereto poure ſtrong, rectified, diſtilled Vinegar, ſet it at a gentle heat, or in the ſummer time in the Sun, ſtirring or ſhaking it twcie every day; until the Vinegar re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the colour of molten gold, which ſeparate from the Glaſſe, and reaffuſe new diſtilled Vinegar, do as afore, and as ſoon as that is coloured, take it out, <hi>viz.</hi> the tinged Liquor, which change ſo often and extract untill the Vinegar will not be coloured any more; conjoyne all theſe extractions, filtre them, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract the Vinegar by an Alembeck in B.
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:105077:48"/>
M. and a dark-red or yellowiſh powder will remain at the bottome; to which powder, poure pure diſtilled Rain Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and take it again off, pouring more new thereupon, and do ſo ſeverall times; by which meanes the ſharpneſſe will be taken away, and the powder will remain ſweet and pleaſant. Grind this powder upon a Marble or Glaſſe firſt heated, and place it in a new Alimbeck, whereon poure Spirit of Wine rectified to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſupreameſt perfection, three fingers high, and ſo a Tincture of Antimony moſt pleaſantly red, is extracted, ſome feces reſiding at the bottome; This extraction is ſweet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and profitable, and ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy as (without experience) is ſcarcely to be beleeved.</p>
            <p>The Feces left behind hold the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and the Extraction receives the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine only, which Medicine may ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſefully be adminiſtred to men and beaſts, both inwardly and outwardly.</p>
            <p>For if four grains of this extraction be adminiſtred, and ſeverall times repeated, it expels the <hi>Leproſie</hi> &amp; the <hi>Lues <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea,</hi> purifies the corrupt bloud, reſiſts melancholly: oppoſeth poyſons, heales the Aſthmatick, and moſt other diſeaſes,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:105077:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
if it be rightly and orderly uſed.</p>
            <p>But if the afore mentioned yellow powder, before its Extraction with the Spirit of Wine, be ground on a warmed ſtone, and if Eggs be boyled to an hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and divided long wayes, and the Yelke taken out, and the Cavity filled with this yellowiſh powder, and placed in a cold moiſt place or Wine cellar for ſome dayes, it will be reſolved into a yellow Liquor, which Liquor heales all new wounds and ſolutions of continuity, if preſently at the beginning it be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred and anointed upon the Wounds, with a fine feather, ſtrengthning and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending the Wound by ſuperpoſition of a Wound plaiſter, it hinders corruption and Putrefaction, heales new Wounds with ſuppuration and tumour, ſo that Praiſe and Thanks ought deſervedly to be aſcribed to the only Creatour, for theſe mercifull Gifts, In old Ulcers and Gangrenes, uſe this Extraction or Balſom of Antimony, it will not leave thee or forſake thee in thy neceſſity, but thou wilt ſing of its Praiſe, and the Virtues which its endowed with, as I have done, and of its ſucceſſefull uſe in Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Greifs: The Gangrene, Cancer,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:105077:49"/>
Polypus, Woolfe, Ulcers of the Legs, and all ſuch like eating and creeping diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, fly before this remedy, and leave the houſe at Liberty for former health to re-enter. if well fixt Medicines be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly taken inwardly, and other conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient Remedies applyed outwardly. I am wont to reduce the Glaſſe of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony into at Oyle by an Alembick two wayes, thus. Take the Glaſſe made out of the Mineral of Antimony, grind it moſt exceeding ſmall, extract it with diſtilled Vinegar, which Extraction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made, abſtract the Vinegar by B.M. and to the remaining matter, pour on ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Wine, and again extract it, put this Extraction, thus, twice dulcorated by the Spirit of VVine into a veſſell Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and exceedingly wel ſhut, circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late or pelicane it for a whole Moneth, then by a ſingular artifice let it be diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by it ſelfe without any addition, and ſo ſhalt thou have a ſweet, pleaſant, and wonderfull Medicine in the forme of a clear red Oyle, out of which is the ſtone of fire made. This Oyle is the ſupream Quinteſſence which can poſſibly be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of Antimony, as may be ſeen in my admonition, where I have breifly ſpoken
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:105077:50"/>
thereof, where I ſaid that four inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were requiſite as to its preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and a fifth which Vulcan dwels in, that is, four preparations are to precede its perfection, and the fifth is the benefit, and right application of the work in mans body. For example,</p>
            <p>The firſt Labour is calcination or mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting into Glaſſe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is digeſtion, by which the Extraction attaines perfection.</p>
            <p>The third is coagulation.</p>
            <p>The fourth is diſtillation into an Oyl, by which diſtillation the thin is ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the thick, after which ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſucceeds fixation, by the ultimate and laſt coagulation by which the matter is reduced into a tranſparent ſtone of fire, which after all theſe Operations, may be fermented in Metalls, becauſe it hath a very penetrative faculty, but much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to the virtues of the ancient and true ſtone of the Philoſophers, becauſe it tingeth not univerſally but only parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly as I ſhall in the end demonſtrate, when I come to treat particularly of the ſtone of fire.</p>
            <p>The afore deſcribed Oyl doth (before its coagulation) operate whatſoever
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:105077:50"/>
is beneficially uſefull for a Phyſitian to know, in curing diſtempers, eight grains (before coagulation) being taken in pure Wine, makes a man young, frees him from the Aſthma, and cauſeth that whatſoever Excreſcenſcies grow on man, as Nailes hair, &amp;c. fall away, and new to be gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated in their room; ſo renovating as if a m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n were but newly born, as the Phenix (which fabulous ſtory I mention for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples ſake) is renewed by the fire, and this Medicine is much leſſe combu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtible then the wings of the unknown Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamander.</p>
            <p>Moreover it conſumes all the Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes of mans body in the manner of a conſuming fire, whereunto it may be compared; it expels and caſts out all that evil which <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> is able to do; but the ſtar of the Sun only, overcomes all the medicines in the World, if being rightly prepared, it be brought to a due fixation; for the Star of the Sun, and the ſtar of Mercury (which even of it ſelf is very potent) are generated and ſpring from the bloud of their own mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and from the living overflowing channell of health.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:105077:51"/>Nor let it trouble thee that this extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with diſtilled Vinegar, and Spirit of wine hath thus been reduced to a moſt ſubtil purity, and exalted to the very height by <hi>Vulcan,</hi> for it neither purges by ſtool, nor yet by vomit; but by Sweate, Urine, and ſpittle. it caſts out the cauſe of every Diſeaſe, and reſtores whatſoever became co<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rupted, by meanes of acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Symptomes.</p>
            <p>The common glaſſe of Antimony moſt ſmally ground or beaten, and ſix grains or thereabouts, (according to the ſtrength of the ſick) being adminiſtsed, having beene firſt infuſed in a little VVine in a warm place over night, and purely ſtrei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the morning, and the infuſion drunk provokes to ſtool, and oftentimes ſtirs up Vomit, becauſe of the crude mercuriall quality which remaines in the Glaſſe, on which account let every wiſe and prudent Phyſitian, conſider with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and look well how he uſeth the glaſs as to Purgations, and let him rightly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine, and in due manner adminiſter it, Now I, being hindred by the ſhortneſſe of time, it cannot be expected that I ſhould throughly ſearch every thing, and the rather, for that many more men there
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:105077:51"/>
are in the VVorld, who have abilities to ſearch, which if rhou wilt do, thou ſhalt receive the largeſt portion of praiſe next my ſelfe, and I will alſo in theſe Writings of mine, commend thee even when I am buried in my aſſigned Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre, for thy diligence in finding more Experiments. Although I never ſaw thy face, and ſhould have haply a little controverted with thee, wert thou at preſent borne or brought forth into the world.</p>
            <p>The common glaſſe of Antimony may be alſo converted into an Oyle, praiſe worthy, by the addition of ſomething, which may without danger be given to the Epileptick, and is thus prepared.</p>
            <p>Take the glaſſe of Antimony, grind or beat it exceeding well, pour upon it the juice of unripe Grapes. Digeſt them in a Glaſſe bolt head with a plain bottome, excellently well Luted, then abſtract the juyce, and dry the powder, and grind it with twice its weight of clarified Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, moiſten it with diſtilled Vinegar, diſtill it in the name of God through a Retort, and at the end augment the fire, and ſo thou ſhalt extract a Red Oyle, which clarifie with the Spirit of Wine eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:105077:52"/>
to tranſparency; a Doſe of which admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred in a little Quantity, is found to be very profitable. To this Oyl may be added ſome Spirit of Salt, and both pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected on the Subtil Calx of Gold prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by its own water, extracted by an Alembeck, which I have elſe where taught in my Writings, and 'twil extract the Tincture of Gold only, without ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing upon its body, this Fermentation being made, enough paper would not be procured to deſcribe all the miſteries which appear therein, far beyond the thoughts of man: But I adviſe the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian that he liſten unto, and mark my philoſophicall propoſals, that he labour and bring the preparation unto uſe, ſo ſhal he daily obtain honour, and be throughly acqu<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inted with more Operations then any Phyſitian is able to preſcribe unto him.</p>
            <p>When thou haſt proceeded with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony thus far, and rightly obtained this proceſſe (wherein 'twil be expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, that thou behave thy ſelf very diſcreetly, and learn the things with dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent cogitations, and try it by Labour and working) thou maiſt boaſt of that magiſtery thus by thee obtained, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:105077:52"/>
the vaſt ignorance wherein moſt men lye enthralled.</p>
            <p>This Magiſtry mixt with a ſolution or Tincture of corals, and given in drink with ſome comforting water, operates e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to admiration in dyſenterian diſeaſes and ſtops all infirmities proceeding of impure bloud, makes glad the heart, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cites chaſtity and honeſty, and in a word makes a man quick and ready in all his undertakings. For all which benefits let us aſcribe moſt humble thanks to the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator and conſervator of all things, who hath bounteouſly vouchſafed unto us mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable in body, and ſick in Soul, reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies for both diſeaſes; ſupplying us with refreſhment and help or ſuccour, in all our neceſſities, I wil alſo in few words de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver an arcanum of Antimony.</p>
            <p>Take Antimony and ſalt Armoniack ſubtilly ground or beaten, of each equal parts, mingle them and diſtil them by a Retort, dulcorate that which comes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with diſtilled Raine Water heated, and put upon it, which being abſtracted, and together with it, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Water, all the acrimony and taſt of the Salt, the Glaſſe of Antimony will remaine in the bottome like white ſhining ſmall,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:105077:53"/>
feathers, which ſubtilly dry in a very gentle heat; this done, put them into a Pelican, or circulatory glaſſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to pour the beſt rectified Spirit of white Vitriol, both which let be circulated untill they ſhall be well united, diſtill them, and being diſtilled, poure Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Wine upon them, which circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late as before, and ſo will there be a ſeparation, and ſome Feces will ſtay in the bottome, but the Arcanum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines united to the Spirits of Wine, and Vitriol. Which Arcanum if it be yet once more rectified, one drop thereof drunk with a ltitle Roſe-water, operates more potently then a whole kettlefull of their boyled pottage; It quickens the Appetite, corrects the Stomack, drives out Melancholly, generates good Moud, helps Concoction, and is the beſt Treaſure for allaying the Riſings of the Matrix, and for the Collick that can be. Which moſt Laudable Arcanum can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be bought for, and valued by any ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
            <p>Having ſpoken of the Arcanum of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony, I ſhall now ſpeak of its Elixir which is thus made.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:105077:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>Take (with the Help of God) of Antimony ground, or beaten, two parts, of Salt Armoniack one part, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime them, that which it ſublimed drive over by a Retort into a Recipient three times, every time ſeparating the Faeces, then by dulcoration evaporate the Sal Armoniack, which matter of Antimony being well ſhut in a veſſell, reverberate at a gentle Fire, by little and little, untill it becomes like to the Minerall of Cinaber, then poure upon it diſtilled Vinegar, and extract its redneſſe, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate the Vinegar, and poure upon the powder, the Spirit of Wine, which extract in B. M. and this Extraction will be moſt pure, ſome Feces being left in the bottome; put now this Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Wine, or this Extraction into a bolt head, poure thereon a little Quinteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Rhubarb and Coralls, three or foure drops, whereof being given to a man, do gently provoke to Stoole, and purgeth without any Gripings, if thou haſt rightly prepared it, it lightens the Bloud, and is a moſt profitable and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Remedy for thoſe who deſire gentle purges; But perhaps ſome Phyſitian or other will wonder how tis poſſible that
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:105077:54"/>
this Medicine can purge ſo mildly, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Antimony is of it ſelfe, moſt exceedingly penetrative, and is here commixt with Rhubarb, which of it ſelf is likewiſe a purgative Medicine; But deſiſt from wondring, for Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is by this meanes deſtroyed, that his poiſonous and purging Quality, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not operate upon any thing, as long as tis mixt with another ſimple, purging Medicine; for this ſimple hath only a Naturall opening power. But prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Antimony by this meanes, fleed from it's Labour of the Expulſion of any thing from the Vent<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le, can leaſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly finde out ſome other way, whereby to operate and performe that Office for which it was appointed.</p>
            <p>Beleeve me (for <hi>I</hi> have no Reaſon to falſifie or to lye) this Elixir thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, can in the ſame manner-purge and penetrate the body, as Antimony purgeth Gold, and if <hi>I</hi> were to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and number up all its Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, <hi>I</hi> ſuppoſe it neceſſary to entreat at the hands of God, a longer life, that ſo I might more plentifully under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and try the wonders of his divine Majeſty, and having experienced them
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:105077:54"/>
communicate them to others that they, together with me, acknowledging and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving thoſe wondrous things may give all prayſe and thanks to God their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour.</p>
            <p>But that I may goe through with my purpoſed intention, which is ſo far to deſcribe the virtues of Antimony, as I have experimentally Learned, I ſhall be ſilent as to things hidden from and not compoſed by me; nor would it be hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome for me, to judge of other mens actions and things unknown unto my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, but leave them to another judge, who hath by his own induſtry made tryal: it being impoſſible for one man fundamentally to learn all, becauſe of the ſhortneſſe of life, and the new ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents that daily happen in operations about the ſaid Antimony.</p>
            <p>Moreover be it known to all, that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony doth not onely purge Gold and ſeparate all extraneous additions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, but performs the ſame operation in the bodyes of men, and other living creatures, which I ſhall prove by an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely example. If a houſeholder intends to fatten a beaſt, but eſpecially an hog, let him give him in his meat (three dayes
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:105077:55"/>
before he ſhuts him up) halfe a dragme of crude Antimony, by which means his appetite to his meat will be, whetted, and ſtird up within him, and heel ſoone grow fat; and if he hath any hurtful quality or diſeaſe in his liver, or be leaprous, he ſhall be healed: This example will ſeem ſomewhat groſſe to the ears of delicate men; but I intended it for illiterate men, or country people, in whoſe brains the more ſubtile Philoſophy is a meer ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, that they may diſcerne that experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally, which for examples ſake I have made uſe of, that ſo they may the ſooner credit my other writings, wherein I ſpeak more abſtruſely: But becauſe theres a great difference between the bodies of men and beaſts, I have no intent (by this example here induced) that crude Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony ſhould be given to men alſo; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that the beaſts are able to bear and concoct much crude meats; which is not permitted to the tender nature and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion of man to doe.</p>
            <p>He therefore that will ſuccesfully and with profit make uſe of Antimony ought above all things to be experienc'd, and exactly to know the preparation thereof, and furthermore to conſider the nature
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:105077:55"/>
of his patient, whether he be old or yong, ſtrong or weak, leſt through the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians errour, the patient be deſtroyed in ſteed of being cured: I now ſpeak as to the weight of the doſe wherein the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame magiſtry is contained; But if I ſhould make uſe of circumſtances and tedious enſamples for the further illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of every thing, I ſhould be to long: I will therefore omit to ſpeak any more thereto, and addreſſe my ſelf to another preparation or fixation of Antimony: for as the ſpirit of wine ſeparated from its body heats and warms a man, if it be drunk; but if outwardly applyed, it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts all the cauſes of inflamed members: on the contrary vineger, cooles and refri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerates both inwardly and outwardly, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be of the ſame original and kind, and meerly for this reaſon, becauſe vineger is made by digeſtion alone, whence followes the putrefaction of the wine with a vegetable fixation; But the ſpirit of wine is made by the ſeparation of deſtillation, or by a vegetable ſublima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by which the ſpirit of wine is made volatile. Even ſo Antimony (according to this or that manner of preparation) doth wonderfully diſplay his gifts, and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:105077:56"/>
that, even beyond mans apprehenſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is thus fixt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take of Antimony moſt ſubtily pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, as much as you pleaſe, put it into a bolt head, poure upon it as much Aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortis as will cover it 6 inches, or halfe a foot high, place it at a moſt gentle fire to extract for ten days, filtre the extraction that it may be free from the feces; Then draw off the Aquafortis by aſhes or ſand, even to a dryneſſe, &amp; there will remaine a yellow powder at the botrome, whereto pour deſtilled raine water, place it at a continual heat, and you ſhall have a red extraction, filtre it, abſtract the water <hi>per B.</hi> Even to a dryneſſe, and a red powder will reſide behind: Hereto poure deſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vineger, which, in the heat, will by litle and litle grow red, and leave ſome whitiſh feces, deſtil this vineger by aſhes, and reverberate that red powder which ſtayes behind three dayes in a conſtant open fire, &amp; then extract its tincture with ſpirit of wine, &amp; ſeparat the remaining feces. All which things being accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed abſtract the ſpirit of wine <hi>per B.</hi> and there will remain a red powder, fix'd, and conſtant, which doth wonderfully perform its office: for if halfe a dragme be taken
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:105077:56"/>
three times in a day (morning, noon and evening) or oftner (which you may doe without any injury) it drives forth coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated bloud out of the body, and in time opens dangerous apoſtems, radically cures the Lues venerea, produceth new hayr, and notably renews a man.</p>
            <p>Now having ſufficiently ſpoken of the fixt powder and extraction of Antimony, I ſhall forbear to ſpeak more about it, and come now to treat of its flores, which may be made ſundry wayes: And here moſt men can neither tell what to ſpeak, or what to anſwer, as being altogether ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of this artifice and ſuch like, there will be ſome (but an exceeding ſmall number) of my diſciples, who are earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſirous of the Spagyrick Art, that will give heed unto my ſayings, and will cenſure otherwiſe then the moſt will doe; To you therefore (my diſciples) I have to ſay, <hi>if ye will follow me take up my croſſe</hi>; ſuffer even as I have ſuffered, learn to undergo perſecutions as I have done, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver not as to your intended labour, pray unceſſantly, work without Jrkſomeneſſe; and thus doing, God who heard my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, will not forſake you in yours, whoſe goodneſſe I thankfully acknowledge with
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:105077:57"/>
hearty ſighes, and ocular tears. Now as to my admonition touching the flores of Antimony. I doe declare that they admit of ſundry and various preparations, as is known to all Spagyriſts; Some by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixtion of ſalt Armoniack drive them downward <hi>per deſcenſum,</hi> out of a retort, and dulcorate them by extracting the ſalt Armoniack, and theſe flores being of a moſt white colour, doe much: Others make uſe of ſome particular appropriated inſtruments, having litle pipes or necks, that the Antimony enjoying the liberty of the ayre may aſcend.</p>
            <p>Others performe their ſublimation in a ſtrong fire, over which they place three convenient pots, and extract white, yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and red flores together, which I have alſo attempted without any errour; But when I would rightly uſe the flores in medicine, I am wont to mingle Colco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha of Vitriol with the red flores, and to ſublime them together three ſeveral times, for thereby the eſſence of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol Co-aſcends, and the flores become the ſtronger; which having done, I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract the flores with ſpirit of wine, and ſeparate the remaining feces and deſtil off the ſpirit of wine <hi>per B. M.</hi> Until a dry powder is left.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:105077:57"/>And theſe are my prepared flores, which I adminiſter to my brethren, and other ſick perſons addreſſing themſelves unto mee, whoſe ſouls I adminiſter ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual comfort unto by virtue of my office; and whoſe bodyes I ſuccour by virtue of faith and confidence. Theſe flores purge gently, without exceſſe of ſtooles, and have taken away many Tertians and Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes, and conſumed other diſeaſes; But I have decreed by the help of God and the bleſſed Virgin Mary, to compoſe a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable Teſtament and leave behind me, in my old age, a catalogue of all ſuch cures as I have happily perfected, that I may openly aſcribe thanks due to God; and my ſucceſſours may know my hearty good will, and together with me, admire and acknowledge thoſe wonders of God, which he hath hid in nature, and which by my labour I have extracted: Tis worth the readers knowledge, to underſtand, concerning the ſublimation of Antimony and its flores, that as to its condition, it is not unlike to that water which flowes down from the moſt high Towring Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains; Thus therefore may a man judge of the difference of water; ſome break forth even in the loftieſt mountains, and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:105077:58"/>
were there far higher mountains, yet would the water climb up thither, (for in truth there are plentiful fountaines in the tops of the ſtatelieſt hils) otherſome ly hidden in the bowels of the earth, and by tedious and hard digging are found out. Now as to their difference I ſay, that the Matrix of the terreſtrial water is, in many places, more potently furniſhed with the rich treaſures of water, then in others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all the Elements have a proper and own Matrix of begetting eaſily, or more difficultly, by the force and virtue of the ſtars, from which the elements them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are generated and procreated. Now if that Matrix be ſtrong in the Earth, it potently caſts forth its ſeed by a ſtrong expulſion, even unto the higheſt of the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropean Alpes, or the top of the Babilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian Tower: They that are not very wiſe, hearing me ſo to ſpeak will lay madneſſe to my charge, or cry out that I am drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with new wine, even as the Jewes dealt with the Apoſtles in the feaſt of Pentecoſt. As is the elevation of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſo is the ſublimation of flores, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (<hi>viz.</hi> of the waters,) thoſe that appear in the higheſt mountains are more whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and cool then the well waters and
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:105077:58"/>
ſuch as are obtained by digging; ſo, if the matter be lifted up, by the force and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of fire, into the mountain of the ancient wiſe men, long ſince deceaſed, the earth will ſtay behind in the bottome, out of which <hi>a ſalt may be extracted for its proper uſe.</hi> And by ſublimation is made a ſeparation of the good from the bad, of the pure from the impure, of the thin from the thick, and medicine becomes thereby diſtinguiſhable from poyſon.</p>
            <p>Wee poor, wretched, miſerable men, being after death (which for our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties we have deſerved) buried in the earth, are ſeaſoned with ſalt until we pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trify, and at length are raiſed up by the heavenly fires heat, are clarified and liſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted up to a celeſtial ſublimation and exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, where being purged from all the impure dregs, and feces of ſin, we become the ſons of God and heyres of eternal life, which our merciful God grant unto us. But I hope that none will reprove me, becauſe of my comparing things corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real, with things ſpiritual, and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſublimation with the earthly in this my example. For I have not done it (cauſeleſly, underſtanding by mine own experience what is white, or what is black,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:105077:59"/>
whether it be a cloudy or clear heaven; Ile therefore paſſe to another preparation of Antimony.</p>
            <p>Tis expedient that my Art-deſiring diſciple doe underſtand, and remember by my Philoſophicall teaching, that the extractions of Antimony and of all other things doe differ exceedingly among themſelves in their operations, which dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is not either in the matter, nor known from the matter, out of which it is extracted, but depends upon the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, and addition, whereby the whole virtue is extracted, experience being witneſſe. And this I ſhall illuſtrate and confirme by an example, thus; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is extracted either from Antimony or from other things by the ſpirit of wine, obtains an operation far different from that which is extracted with ſtrong vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. The chief cauſe whereof I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready mentioned, for all extractions with ſpirit of wine doe provoke to ſtoole moſt powerfully, whether they be made of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony or other purging things, as hearbs, roots, ſeeds, and the like. (I ſpeak as to the firſt extraction) Contrarywiſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is extracted with vineger doth not provoke to ſiege, as doth the other, but
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:105077:59"/>
rather conſtipates and binds by a ſingular medium. Whereby the volatile is made fixed.</p>
            <p>This ſecret or Arcanum ought very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to be lookt unto, but a very few doe conſider it; for many things ly hid and profoundly ſhut up in this myſtery, which many maſters, and ſervants, yea and many knowledge-pretending Sophiſters have not ſeen unto this day:</p>
            <p>The extraction of Antimony is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed two ſeveral wayes, to wit, with vineger and ſpirit of wine, the vineger doth condenſe, but the ſpirit of wine doth of it ſelf provoke urine and ſiege, as I have frequently mentioned, and eſpecially in my twelve keyes, that the extraction of the glaſſe of Antimony is a gentle Purge, but the extraction of Antimony with vineger, doth not purge at all, which is moſt certainely true, which experiment is a cauſe of more mature conſideration and further-reaching thoughts, by which conſiderations nature gives &amp; produceth a true Philoſopher. And it is altogether miraculous, that thoſe things which at firſt have bin extracted with ſpirit of wine ſhould retain a purging quality, when as, on the contrary, if the glaſſe of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:105077:60"/>
be at firſt extracted with vineger, and the vineger beeing ſeparated it be againe extracted with ſpirit of wine, there's no ſuch poyſonous and purging faculty then left, but tis totally taken away, and not a footſtep thereof, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining, ſo as to cauſe ſiege, yet it can operate by ſweat, and other wayes; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by ſpitle and vomit, it can performe its office, and ſeeks about, if it can find out any thing unfitting, It purgeth the bloud, heales the <hi>Peripneumonia,</hi> is profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for the Aſthmatick, and conduceth to other diſeaſes; It allayes any violent cough of what ſort ſoever, and it is a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine remedy:</p>
            <p>And this extraction is perfected by common vineger. There is alſo another extraction <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take powdered Antimony: Poure thereupon deſtil'd vineger, not common vineger, but that which is extracted from its own mineral, cloſe it up well, and place it at the heat of the Sun, and ſo in time the vineger will become as red as blood, ſeparate this extraction, and filtre it, deſtil it in ſand by an Alembick, and in its drawing over it will repreſent wonderful colours moſt delectable to the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:105077:60"/>
fight, This oyle at length comes to be bloud-like, and leaves many Feces, and may be profitably uſed in moſt Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
            <p>For in the Leproſie its Glory appeares, and its, virtue becomes manifeſt, the French Pox lately brought into our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey is conſumed and dryed up thereby, and it operates ſeverall other miraculous things, if that the Phyſitian hath regard to its right uſe, and obſerves a true Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration; let him diligently conſult with Experience, and remember without forgetfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>Antimony is alſo prepared after this enſuing manner.</p>
            <p>Take of Antimony and red Tartar of each equall parts, grind them exceeding well together, and burn them in a pot well luted, (leaſt the Spirits exhale) untill the Tartar be burnt, which you muſt do in a wind Furnace, beat or grind the matter thus combuſt very ſmall, whereto poure common warme water, ſtraine it as you would a Lixivium; by which meanes a Liver will be made, (for that Title our ancient predeceſſors put upon it) dry this Liver, put it into a Cucurbit, and pour Spirit of Wine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:105077:61"/>
filter it through a thick paper, and abſtract it in B.M. to a third part; this extraction may be uſed, but very ſparing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and with very great diſcretion, wherein is to be obſerved a notable mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Spirit of Wine once abſtracted will not be united to the Red extraction any more from whence it was ſeparated, but ſwims on the top there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as Oyle ſwims on the ſurface of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But if this Spirit of VVine be again poured upon new Liver, it extracts as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; but this ſecond Extraction poured on the former, will not at any rate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mix, which really is greatly to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at, but who can declare all the great wonders of God, or obſerve thoſe gifts which the Creatour hath implanted in his Creatures, moſt profoundly to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
            <p>I have a little before mentioned an Extraction of Antimony with Vinegar and Spirit of VVine; now if the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar be ſeparated from that Extraction by B.M. and the powder remaining be put in a moiſt place, it will reſolve into a wound-Liquor or yellow Oyle, which in new wounds acts wonders ineffable, and in like manner in old, it hinders,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:105077:61"/>
and abſolutely prevents any Symptomes from taking root, and reſiſts putrefaction.</p>
            <p>The other or ſecond extraction out of this powder before its ſolution with Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Wine, doth alſo ſhew its effect, and in inward diſeaſes gives place to no other remedy.</p>
            <p>I have in my precedent writings moſt frequently propounded the way of its preparation, and in this Antimoniall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, abundantly repeated it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I know how much utility and how great ſecrets ly hid therein, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hope that thoſe Repetitions in my Writings will not be tedious or trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to the Learner; for what I write, is not cauſeleſly written; But my ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings are ſhort, and containe a large ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent within them; and albeit they are manifold and frequently rementioned, yet are they moſt obſcure to ſuch as are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>experienced and unprofitable to children and Infants, and moſt beneficiall to the Diſciple of Art only.</p>
            <p>There's alſo gotten another Extracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by a Cauſtick water, and tis thus: Grind equall parts of Vitrioll and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Salt together, and diſtill from them a water <hi>Per Latus,</hi> or retortwiſe: Increaſe
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:105077:62"/>
and urge the fire, and ſo ſhall you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract a Liquor like unto melted Butter or Oyle, which keep for its proper uſe.</p>
            <p>Powder the <hi>Caput mortuum,</hi> and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve it in a Cellar into water which ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther apatt, and filter through Paper: Then take Hungarian Antimony moſt finely ground or powdered, put it into a broad bottomed Glaſſe, and pour upon it that water, ſet it at a gentle warmth, where if you let it abide its ſeaſon, it will at the beginning reſemble the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olet colour of the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>methyſt; which when tis brought to this Paſſe, aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the fire, and thou ſhalt have the colour of a Tranſparent Saphyr, and from this Saphyrick colour will precipitate a white powder by the help of common water poured thereon, which inwardly taken, operates by ſtoole and Vomit like as the Extraction of Crude Vitrioll doth.</p>
            <p>The ſolution in the Cellar which was extracted from the <hi>Caput mortuum,</hi> doth truly tranſmute the thin leaves of <hi>Mars,</hi> if boyled therein, into Copper, Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence being witneſſe: now hearken to me, and conſider ſomewhat further.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:105077:62"/>Pour the Oyle, or the aforeſaid water ſpoken of in the proceſſe, upon Crocus Martis, being firſt reverberated with Sulphur to a Redneſſe, place it in ſome heat, and extract the bloud red Tincture of <hi>Mars,</hi> then take of this Extraction one part, of the red Extraction of Antimony burnt with Salt Petre, and prepared with ſpirit of wine three parts, of the water of Mercury made apart by injection into an hollow pipe, one part; of the <hi>Calx</hi> of the Sun diſſolved in this Cauſtick water, halfe a part, mix them, and by effuſion, out of one Veſſel into another, purge them, then forthwith abſtract them by aſhes in a fire meanly ſtrong, but the whole will not come over, for there will reſide in the bottom a fair, red, fixt ſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on very profitable for old Ulcers. The remaining <hi>Caput Mortuum</hi> begets by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution in a dark place ſo ſharp a Liquor that ſcarce any <hi>Aqua fortis</hi> can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with it in acrimony or ſharpneſs, but of this enough.</p>
            <p>Out of Antimony may alſo be prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a white powder thus.</p>
            <p>Take of Hungarian Antimony and Salt Petre thrice depurated and ground to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, equall parts, burn them in a new
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:105077:63"/>
pot wherein hath been no greaſe, in a fire of circulation, you muſt not caſt in all at once, but by little and little, and apart, which the ancient Spagyriſts call by the name of puffing (for tis neceſſary that the Students in Art be acquainted with their ſtrange Termes, which as to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Language is unknown) that puffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or injection being accompliſhed, powder that hard remaining matter in the pot, put it into a veſſell of Glaſſe, and pour thereunto common water war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and when the matter ſhall have ſetled, ſeparate it, and pour on more, which do ſometimes, that the Salt Petre may be extracted; dry and powder the matter, and mix it again with an equall part of Salt petre, proceed as before, and do thus three times, then grind the matter which remaines, and pour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto the beſt ſpirit of Wine, and circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late it for a month in Cucurbit or Circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latory well ſhut, then burn on it new ſpirit of Wine, nine or ten times, which labour being done; dry the powder lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurely, and in a melting Crucible, let it be well heated red hot, for an whole day at the fire.</p>
            <p>Out of this powder, being reſolved in
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:105077:63"/>
a moiſt place, either upon a Table of Glaſs, or Stone, or in the Whites of Eggs, is made a Liquor, which by the heat may be again dryed into a powder; Verily this powder operates many very gallant things, ſcarce credible without Experience. It workes not of a ſudden, but by little and little, and time muſt be granted for the production and diſcovery of its force and virtue.</p>
            <p>Let any one who is afflicted with an inward Apoſteme, take conſtantly of this powder, five or ſix times every day, in ſpirit of Wine, or meere Wine, fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen graines at a time, and he ſhall be healed, and the bloud ſhall by little and little be ejected, and the Patient be come perfectly well.</p>
            <p>He that is afflicted with the French Diſeaſe within his body, let him uſe this powder, and he ſhall be radically cured. It produceth new Haire, purgeth the bloud, and doth many other good things which we omit for brevities ſake. For I cannot expound every thing with that plainneſſe, and ſo perſpicuouſly, as that every one ſhould become a great Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, by the bare reading of my Writings, without any paines or labour, no, let
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:105077:64"/>
them endure the burden, (as is reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) and let him know that the country man that threſheth and worketh on the Corne will eat the beſt bread.</p>
            <p>But now I proceed too much into the open Field, in which the ancient Fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers catch their Larks, whom the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger will ſpeedily follow with their Nets, for my ſtile (as all my Writings wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) hath a peculiar method, even as other Philoſophers have likewiſe done before me; But now that my Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy is changed by the proceſſe therein immixed, let not any Reader wonder at it; for my Philoſophical ſpeech having deſcription of the proceſſes therein, is different from another bare ſpeech that hath no manifeſtation; Mark this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, neither accuſe me of being changeable in my intention, in my philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophical ſtile, preparation and proceſs: for in my philoſophical ſpeech, thou ſhalt learn &amp; obſerve the Theory, but the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs together with admonition ſufficient, doth teach the practiſe, and on that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, are perſpicuous and ſufficient words to be made uſe of thereabouts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Balſom may alſo be prepared out of Antimony (not crude, but out of its Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulus) profitable for very many diſeaſes,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:105077:64"/>
from which the Mercury of Antimony may be vivified, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take of Hungarian Antimony, and crude Tartar, of each equall parts, Salt Petre halfe a part; grinde them and flux them in a wind Furnace, poure them forth into a Cone, and let them coole; Let the Regulus thus made be in like ſort purified in the fire by Tartar, and Salt Petre, three or four times, and ſo it will become white like to ſilver (that hath paſſed the fulmination) and the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amen of Lead. Grind this Regulus, pour unto it (in a Glaſſe) the Oyl of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niper or Spirit of Turpentine, (which aſcends firſt in diſtillation, and is clear like to Water) ſhut your Glaſſe well, place it in B.M. at a moderate heat, and that Spirit or Oyl will grow red in the manner of Bloud, pour it off, and recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it with Spirit of Wine. It hath the ſame Virtues as the Balſom of Sulphur hath, as I ſhall adviſe thee when I come to ſpeak of Sulphur; for the preparation of both is in a manner alike: Three drops of this Balſome taken in warme Wine only thrice in a week, heales the Diſeaſes of the Lungs, the Aſtmah, Ptyſick, Pleuritick, and ſuch as are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with an old Cough.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:105077:65"/>There are alſo made of Antimony ſeverall Oyles, ſome by themſelves, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by addition, and have not the ſame Virtues, but diverſe from each other, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the manner of the preparation; I wil ſpeak a parable unto thee, many li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Creatures live only in the Earth, as Wormes, Serpents, and other kinds, and ſometimes new ſorts are generated by corruption, formerly unknown. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers live in the water, as Fiſhes; O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the Ayre, as Birds; others in the fire, as the Salamander, and there are found in the hot Iſlands and burning Countryes, other wonderfull Creatures, of which we are ignorant, who conſerve their Life by the ſolary heat, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently dye at being brought into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ayre.</p>
            <p>So Antimony prepared with a watry addition, operates otherwiſe then if pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with a fiery one; and although e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very preparation thereof be done with fire, without which its virtue is not detected, or opened; yet note and conſider that an Earthy addition workes divers from a watry one; and ſo ſuitably, if Antimony be by the fire elevated <hi>Per ſe</hi> into the aire, and further prepared, it
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:105077:65"/>
obtains a ſeverall virtue, according to its ſeverall preparations.</p>
            <p>The cheifeſt Oyl and Sulphur of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony is thus made, without any additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ought elſe.</p>
            <p>Take Ungarian Antimony, beate it groſly, put it into a glaſſe cucurbit, with a plain bottome, pour thereto the true Vinegar of the Philoſophers, <hi>viz.</hi> The Vinegar with its own Salt, Lute up the Glaſſe, Putrefie it in Horſe Dung, or in B. M. for forty dayes, and the body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes again opened, and is made more black then Ink, which is a ſigne of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſolution.</p>
            <p>Put this black matter into an Alem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beck, and abſtract the vinegar with a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Fire, and an unſhapen matter will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in the bottome, which grind, and waſh with diſtilled Raine water, even to a ſweetneſſe, dry it, place it in a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culatory <figure/> with a long neck, (which muſt have three bellies, as if three Spheres were diſtinctly counited, after that manner as ſublimatories are with their Alludels or heads, and having along neck like a Violl or bolt head) leave it in a moderate Heate for two months, with Spirit of Wine, rectified to the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:105077:66"/>
higheſt degree ſo that it may ſwim o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over it three fingers breadth; and let it be well luted; The Spirit will be tinged with a pellucid redneſſe in the manner of a Rubie, pour it off, filtre it, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate the black earth, as unprofitable for this thing, diſtill the Spirit of Wine in a Glaſſe Alembick well luted by ſand, with a gentle fire, and twill bring over with it the Tincture of Antimony, the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments will ſeparate themſelves, and thou ſhalt ſee thy Alembick to be ſo won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull, as if it were made of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Gold, and at the bottome a very few Feces will reſide, and the golden colour of the Glaſſe will vaniſh. Pour the diſtilled matter into a circulatory, and leave it ſo for ten dayes, and the Oyl of Antimony wil grow weighty, and ſeperate from the Spirit of VVine, and deſcend unto the bottome, and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Wine will return to its firſt clarity and brightneſſe, and ſwim on the top of the Oyle: ſeparate it with a ſeparating Glaſſe. This is a moſt ſweet Oyle, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any corroſiveneſſe, whoſe virtues cannot be credited by any one, and therefore I call the Sulphur of Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, the Balſome of life; for it hath much
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:105077:66"/>
profited by the help of God, even there where all hope hath failed, and certain Death ſuppoſed to be at hand, as my Brethren can ſufficiently teſtifie. It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novates a man, purgeth the Bloud, mixt with the Tincture of Corals, cures the Leproſie, heales ſcabs proceeding from impure bloud, expels Melanchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſadneſſe, Corroborates the hea<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t and members, eſpecially if it be taken with Magiſtry of Margarits; In the Lipothymia it is the top-Remedy, for being mixt with the Oyle of Cinamome, each equall weight, and ſix drops thereof put upon the Tongue (the Noſtrills and Arteries, being anointed with the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Saffron) preſently brings a man to himſelf.</p>
            <p>But good God, why do I ſpeake or write, I ſuppoſe that I ſhall meet with moſt few that will credit this Teſtament which I leave unto my diſciples: yet ſome few will be found, who acknowledging theſe wonders, and acquainted by Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with them, will more circumſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider them, and give me honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable thanks when I lye rotting in my Tomb, becauſe I have by the gift of God, ſet free from priſon that Virtue which is
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:105077:67"/>
united to the Creature, and made it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perative.</p>
            <p>Another way of bringing Antimony o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Helme, without any addition, is this: Make Regulus of Antimony, Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and Salt nitre, as I have afore ſpoken, powder that Regulus, put it into a great round glaſſe, in a gentle fire in Sand, and the Antimony will ſublime; but every day bruſh down with a feather, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is ſublimed, into the bottome of the glaſſe, and thus do until it will ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime no more, but a fixt precipitate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulus remaines in the bottome: but know that this work will require time ere the work appear; grind this precipitate, and leave it in a Cellar upon a poliſht ſtone, for halfe a yeare, and then twill be reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into a red Liquor, and ſome Feces will remain, for the Salt of Antimony will only melt, filtre this Liquor, and abſtract the Phlegme in an Alembeck, till a thick Liquor be left, which lay aſide in the Cellar, and twill be congealed into Chryſtalls of a reddiſh white, and if they be again purged, they will be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether white: this is the true Salt of Antimony, which I have frequently made; dry it: mix one part of this Salt,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:105077:67"/>
with three parts of Venetian Earth, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill it with a ſtrong fire, and there will come, firſt white Spirits, then red, the which do alſo reſolve into white, recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie this ſpirit Gently in a dry Bath, and thou ſhalt have another Oyle of Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but much inferiour to the former, and tis rather a Spirit then an Oyle, becauſe this Salt is ſpiritually forced out. It hath frequently deſerved praiſe in quartane Feavers and others; it breakes the Stone of the Bladder, provokes U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, cleanſeth filthy Serpentine or cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Ulcers, (which have their Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from <hi>Mars</hi>) being outwardly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed. It purgeth the bloud like to the Salt of Gold, and may be uſed in many other Diſeaſes, but it is not ſo perfect as the red Oyl of Antimony is, whoſe Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur hath been ſeparated, purged, and brought to the higheſt degree.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Sulphur and the Salt of Antimony</hi> having beene deſcribed, together with their preparation and medicinall uſe, I will paſſe to the deſcription of its <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury,</hi> and its medicinall virtue.</p>
            <p>Take therefore the Regulus of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony eight parts, the Salt of mans urin, clarified, and ſublimed; ſalt armoniack,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:105077:68"/>
and ſalt of Tartar, of each one part, mix the Salts, and thereto poure ſtrong vinegar, Lute it with the Lute of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and digeſt the ſalts for a month in a continuall heat, then diſtill off the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar by Aſhes untill the Salts remaine dry, which being done, mix with them three parts of Venetian Earth, urge them by a Retort with a ſtrong fire, and thou ſhalt have a wonderfull ſpirit, poure this Spirit upon the powdred Regulus, and putrifie them together two moneths, then abſtract the Vinegar, and to the Remainder add four times as much file<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of <hi>Mars,</hi> and diſtill it by the force of fire in a Retort, the ſpirits of the Salts will bring the Mercury over with them in the manner of a fume, but thou muſt place inſtead of the Recipient, a large glaſſe full of Water, thar the ſpirits of the ſalt may mix therewith; but the Mercury will come together, and be converted into true quick Mercury in the bottome of the veſſell. Thus may the Artificer extract living and running Mercury out of Antimony, which hath beene by many a one every where ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſought after, now therefore will I come to make known its uſe in medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:105077:68"/>Take (with the help of God) one part of this Mercury, preſſe it through a skin of Leather, poure thereunto four parts of the red Oyle of Vitriol, rectifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ſupreameſt height, abſtract the Oyle, and the ſpirits of the Oyle will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main with the Mercury, urge the fire, and ſomewhat will ſublime, throw back the ſublimate upon the Earth remaining in the bottome, and pour again thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as much new Oyle, ſublime it as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, and iterate it three times: The fourth time caſt back your ſublimate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain upon its own Earth, grind it toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and it will be pure like Chryſtall, put it in a Circulatory, and pour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as much Oyle of Vitriol, and thrice the quantity of the ſpirit of Wine, circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late it even to ſeparation, and ſo the Mercury reſolved into Oyle will ſwim at the top in the manner of Oyle Olive; ſeparate this Oyle, and put it into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Circulatory Glaſſe, and pour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ſharp diſtilled Vinegar, and by this meanes the Oyle will recover its weight within twenty dayes, or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, and will ſettle to the bottome, and whatſoever is poyſonous remaines in the vinegar, the which will be cloudy
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:105077:69"/>
and blackiſh, and this is a miracle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Nature, that an Oyle at firſt ſwimming, ſhould in the end ſettle to the bottome: But note, that even the Oyl of Vitriol is heavy, and therefore beares up the Mercury, which in its ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not as yet altogether pure; but when that light impurity is received by the Vinegar, then doth the Oyle recover its own weight, and being made compact goes to the bottome, and this is the oyle of the Mercury of Antimony, <hi>And is the fourth Pillar of all Remedies.</hi> Now where ever thou art who beeſt Leprous, I will procure for thee a meanes of health; This Oyle heales the Apoplexy, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts the Brain and Reaſon, excites the vitall ſpirits of the Braine; and whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall uſe this oyle daily, for ſome time, and is afflicted with any Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, he ſhall looſe both his Nailes and Haire, and become young again: the Bloud is thereby purged, and every E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill expelled: the French Diſeaſe is but a ſpot to this Medicine, which in a very little white radically ejects it; the praiſe of this Remedy cannot be deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed with either Tongue or Pen: Ah miſerable clod of earth, and bag of worms
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:105077:69"/>
why doſt thou delay to offer a ſacrifice of Praiſe to thy Creator, for thoſe Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies which he hath granted unto thee? O ye bragging boaſters of both medicines! come unto me, a Monk, and ſervant of God, I will lay open to your Eyes, what you never ſaw before, and will ſhew you the way of health, which as yet you have not obſerved; Now if any one knowes better preparations, let him not be ſilent, but ſpeak: I am deſirous to learn, nor is it a ſhame unto me to make further en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, and to ſearch out that light which as yet I have not ſeen; for I have oft ſaid, no one is able becauſe of the brevity of Life, to perceive all the ſecrecies of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>But whatſoever Artificer hath leſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience then I have, and doth not throughly underſtand my Writings, I ſhal adviſe him to be ſilent, and nor pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to correct or diſgrace them with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly prating, and many unprofitable words; becauſe he hath not heard them in the Schoole, nor rightly underſtands the proceſſes; my Termes are different from thoſe which are in uſe with my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, who are aſhamed of Labour,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:105077:70"/>
the which is neceſſary as to the planting of good Trees, and ingraffing of whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome fruits; whence it happens that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying on a wild Tree they never come to any ſweet bough of a gentle Garden Tree Unskilfull man! do not at the very firſt word judge the things thou doſt not know, nor condemn that which neither by know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or ſtudy, thou haſt attained un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</p>
            <p>Many Country people indeed, ſay that the Fiſhes dy in the water by reaſon of cold, but whoever affirm it, ſpeak igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly and indiſcreetly, and what cannot be proved, for if in the Winter Seaſon, when the Superficies of the Water is mightily congealed and frozen, there be little holes made by breaking the Ice, not a Fiſh will periſh by reaſon of the cold, but if the Ice of Ponds or other waters be not broken, the Fiſh will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly dye, not becauſe of the Frigidity, but the want of the aire which cannot pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate through all the Ice; For tis clearly evident, that no living Creature can live without the uſe of Ayre; whence tis, that the Fiſhes are choaked under the Ice, and are not kill'd with cold; I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply this Example thus.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:105077:70"/>It is neceſſary in Antimony, that (becauſe of its manifold uſe) holes be made by the miner in the mountain, that it may enjoy the Ayre, and then tis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovefull that it be prepared with Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Ayre, and Fire, leaſt its fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe be choaked in the Earth, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of its being manifeſted by the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous preparation of the Phyſitian, for the hoped-for correcting and qualifying of diſtempers, which was the ground of its ſearching after.</p>
            <p>Moſt miſerable man that art an hater, and deſpiſer of Antimony, and cryeſt out that tis a meere poiſon, where is thy E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence and Rhetorick to defend thy ſelf withall?</p>
            <p>And ſeeing thou doſt not underſtand, neither white, black, nor any other Colour in this buſineſſe, as to the prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Antimony, and art a ſtranger to its virtue and benefits, thou mayeſt juſtly hold thy peace, and ſuffer theſe ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and writings to paſſe by thy Eares, (becauſe of thy unskilfullneſſe) like an impetuous Torrent, agitated by the wind; But beware leſt the wind &amp; the waves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing, thy broken little Ship be total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drowned. Now to avoid this danger,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:105077:71"/>
do as the Apoſtles did; ſeaſonably im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring help by thy prayers unto thy ſleeping maſter, not hypocritically, but with a pure and ſincere heart, and ſo thou ſhalt be ſaved, and really find, that the ſea and the winds wil be tractable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, and thou ſhalt bring all things to the deſired end.</p>
            <p>Good God! were but this the mind of man, in following after ſomewhat with ſtudy and labour, without doubt the Muſes and Fortune would be propitious unto him; and that Diſciple of Art would find, that health and proſperity would at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend him in his Cloſet of Art, and habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Grace, ſo as that he ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a ſure Foundation, a full unſpotted and conſtant Corner ſtone, whereon he may with ſafety reſt, and found his owne Conſcience, and ſo the unprofitable tat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Diſputers, with the ſick would be omitted, and caſt out of the Schooles, and the ſilent man would take his Turne alſo, and publickly aſſert and prove that a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle built of ſtone is not ſo eaſily combu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtible as a pigeon-houſe, or a thatch't roof, or an old wooden neaſt of a ſtork, that is dryed every year in the ſun.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:105077:71"/>My Diſciples attend rightly with the utmoſt of your underſtanding to my ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple plain admonition, ſtudiouſly and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently ſeek the Centre which is ſcarce or never known by the outward face; ſearch throughly its virtue with a carefull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, even as an Hunter doth after a wild Beaſt, Mark the print of the footſteps in the ſnow, that you take not a Stag înſtead of a Doe, or an Hare for a Fox, through their footſteps ill-underſtood, and worſe judged of: caſt forth your Net, but right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and then you ſhall have it well ſtored with the beſt Fiſhes, ſpread open your Nets diſcreetly &amp; carefully, bind on your ſnares and intrapments, and ſo ſhall the Fowler effectually and ſuccesfully ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his own deſire. In a word, that I may give my ultimate Admonition unto the curious Seeker, I do adviſe thus; Dear Fowler, expoſe thy Nets and thy voluble feathers deliberately unto the Wind, and thou Mariner attend wel on thy Compaſſe when thou ſayleſt in the deep Sea, night and day, and art fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently toſſed with tempeſtuous ſtormes, now here, now there; For thus obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, thou ſhalt not faile in thy hopefull Expectations, but in the end ſhalt take
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:105077:72"/>
ſomething with profit; and arrive with my <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hip to its Port, from the remoteſt Countryes, with augmentation of thy wares and adventures.</p>
            <p>But why do I ſpend time in ſpeaking or comparing; I do but tread and threſh the empty ſtalks and ſtrawes, in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Tatling <hi>Sophiſters,</hi> for my Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings are ſo born, that but few Letters in them will paſſe by, without ſome fruit, and be extinguiſhed without the ſparkes of ſome benefit; But verily, they do contain in them a certain Doctrine and Inſtruction, that the Labour of writing is to me a kinde of Recreation and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light.</p>
            <p>Well! I will retire or go back, one paſſe in the manner of a Fencer, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce into the Laboratory a new ſchoole or Learning, <hi>viz.</hi> of externall things, that I may declare and manifeſt the Reaſon or Cauſe, and Preparation of Antimony, that it may be approved as moſt profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for outward Diſtempers (as indeed it is) Ile therefore give you the proceſſe in a very few words.</p>
            <p>My Diſciple and Lover of Art, who deſireſt throughly to ſearch into Natures ſecrets, and to find out the moſt hidden
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:105077:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
myſteries, that thou mayſt diſtinguiſh betwixt day and night, light and darkneſs I ſay unto thee.</p>
            <p>Take one part of the beſt Ungarian Antimony, and halfe a part of common, or of foſile ſalt, of potters Earths not baked ſix parts, grind and mix them well together; diſtill them with a ſtrong fire, and a red Oyle will forthwith flow or diſtill forth, from which abſtract the Phlegme by diſtillation, that a red pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may remain dry in the bottome, grind it, and let it be reſolved upon a Marble ſtone, and thence wil iſſue a red Pellucid Balſome, far more noble then other vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerary Balſomes, moſt profitable in old Wounds, which the common Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans with their Plaiſters, Unguents, Oyles, &amp; Ligaments, do eſteem as dangerous &amp; to be ſuſpected, and are with deriſion com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to take off the bridle &amp; Trappings from the Horſe, and lay them aſide, and lead him back again into the ſtable from whence they brought him. My Cuſtome of ſpeaking now containes no other thing; for a Monk cannot write all things ſo cleerly, as the reaſon and neceſſity of the work requires, becauſe he is not verſed in the circumſtances of ſuch buſineſſe; he
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:105077:73"/>
is (I ſay) ignorant of their Termes, that he cannot illuſtrate them formally or orderly enough; and he entreats pardon for any Tranſgeſſion of that kind commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him, and in like manner will he ſhow his forward readineſſe to ſerve all Chriſtians night and day in his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Office, and he will reward the kindneſſe of the Reader with his dayly Prayers. This Oyle is found to be moſt wholſome in old Ulcers and Wounds, of the greateſt moment, nor are there many remedies above it or equall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, except an Oyle of Antimony pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with common Mercury ſublimate, which in healing of Cancers, Gangreens, Wolfes, <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> is more po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and noble; But in Fiſtulaes and creeping Ulcers, the afore preſcribed Oyle, doth experimentally ſhew its force in many incredible accidents, even to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, which I forbear to rehearſe, leſt I ſhould be thought to be ambitious and greedy after Honour, which vice I <hi>have</hi> alwaies fled from, <hi>doe</hi> flye from, and <hi>will</hi> fly from, by the help of God, and the Bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tis thus prepared.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:105077:73"/>Take of common Mercury well mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified and moſt purely ſublimed, and of Antimony, of each equall parts, grind them, mix them, and diſtill them by a Retort (which can hold the Spirits) three times, rectifie this Oyle with ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of VVine, and tis prepared, being of a bloud-like colour; at the beginning it was white and reſembled Ice, or molten Butter: This Oyle performes many wonders, which without it, 'twould be impoſſible in Nature to beleeve, could be amended, but yet notwithſtanding its virtue, faculty, and operation, herein ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares in making good out of evill.</p>
            <p>Another moſt profitable for externall wounds, may alſo be prepared, with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
            <p>Take of Antimony and Sulphur, of each one part, Salarmoniack and Salt of Urine clarified, of each halfe a part, <hi>Calx vive</hi> or Quick-Lime two parts. Grind, mix, and diſtill them, if any thing ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limes, ſcrape it off, and grind it againe with the <hi>Caput mortuum,</hi> pour thereunto the Oyle which thou abſtractedſt, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill it as afore, and thus do three times, and tis prepared: old maligne and contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macious Ulcers, refuſing every remedy,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:105077:74"/>
do not deſpiſe this Oyle, it is moſt ſtrong, moſt penetrative, and layes a foundation of moſt certain healing, even as the Oyle of Vitriol doth.</p>
            <p>There's alſo prepared a wonderfull Vulnerary Balſome compoſed of many things, whereof Antimony is one.</p>
            <p>Receive of ſulphur four Ounces, melt it in the fire very gently, mix thereto halfe a pound of Quick ſilver, ſtir it with a ſtick untill it comes into a Maſſe, which grind or beate, becauſe it is prepared, as Cinaber is wont to be prepared; grind with it of Antimony four Ounces, Red Arſenick four ounces, <hi>Crocus martis</hi> two ounces, powdred Bricks eight ounces, let them be ſublimed together according to art, in a glaſſe veſſell, and thou ſhalt have Rubies not unlike the Oriental ones, (as to the colour) (for they are vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, and have nothing fix in them.) Let theſe Rubies be moſt neately ſeparated from the Cinaber, which in the ſubliming did co-aſcend with them, grind them, and extract them with Vinegar, which done, abſtract the Vinegar in B. M. by little and little, and the remaining powder grind moſt finely ſmall, and extract it with ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of VVine in another veſſell, ſeparate
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:105077:74"/>
the remaining feces, and digeſt this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction with ſpirit of wine, in a veſſel well luted, in B. M. for a moneth, Then abſtract the ſpirit of wine (as you did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly the vineger,) put the remaining powder into a Cucurbit with a round bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, and put it into a veſſel full of water in a pit, that it may therein ſwim like a boat, and ſo in a few dayes it will reſolve into a fair tranſparent liquour, moſt profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for old ulcers and wounds, if they be anointed with a feather dipt therein, and a common vulnerary plaiſter laid thereupon; It will not leave thee deſtitute of help, eſpecially in thoſe outward wounds which are old and uncapable of any other remedy.</p>
            <p>But thoſe ſolutions of continuity which depend upon ſome inward cauſe, are not to be underſtood or meant in this place; but for the healing of ſuch, ſomewhat more is requried; which verily cannot be recovered without inward Remedies, which dry up and radically put out the Symptomes and centre of the diſeaſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there are but few maſters in the world at this day, who circumſpectly and exactly think of, and conſider the thing which at preſent I doe write. Would man
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:105077:75"/>
but conſider the miſerable ſtate and poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of our life, whereinto we are ſlipt by the fall of our firſt parents; (which lapſe or fall, original ſin and all kinds of cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities have followed, yea many and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous diſeaſes frequently too, wherewith we are oppreſſed,) he would ſpend his time more rightly and profitably, that ſo he mought (out of Chriſtian charity) find out a means for his neighbours health, which is laid upon him as a duty, by the prince of heaven; But becauſe moſt men doe trifle away and looſe their time about toyes and trifles, and refuſe labour as being troubleſome, they remaine in their old opinion, and are good ſtewards of their fleſh, fearing the wearing out their hands with the waſhing them, and the anointing of them with oyl, fearing alſo that by buying much ſoap to purge &amp; waſh themſelves, they ſhould encreaſe the merchants price; Poor miſerable men, what have we in this world whereof we may boaſt, ſtrangers we are in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, having our dwelling with God, who hath given us all things for our uſe whileſt we live here, without pledge; we ought on that acount bodily and ſpiritually ſo to behave our ſelves unto him, as faithful
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:105077:75"/>
ſtewards towards their maſters, that we may with a good conſcience ſtand in that day, when all theſe beſtowed goods ſhall return unto him, and that heavenly houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder ſhall require an accompt from all his ſervants; left through means of our ſins and unthankfulneſſe, we be caſt out into the utter priſon of torment, where ſhall be gnaſhing of teeth. Did but a man alwayes think thereupon, it would not be ſtrange for his heart, never to think of committing any evil, but would moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently perform his office, that he might ſerve his neighbour; But the world very litle or nothing at all gives reſpect here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, but graſps up mony right or wrong; the Potentates care not, the commons help them forward; they defend force by the name of equity, that themſelves may alſo enjoy a portion of ill gotten goods, and may as 'twere rightly devoure like Lords and Maſters, the goods of their ſervants. Beware, I ſay, leſt the bones ſtick in your throat, and the fiſh bones pierce and adhere to your heart.</p>
            <p>But theſe Admonitions are but in vaine; ridiculous and contemptible unto the world, for when a while ſince I went on Pilgrimage to S. James of Compoſtella
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:105077:76"/>
according to a vow, it being a difficult journy, and returned back unto my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent (for which I bleſſe God even to this day) I did believe that many would both rejoyce and praiſe God together with me, for thoſe holy reliques which for the help and comfort of our convent, and all the poore I brought with me; But few amend their lives, and but few teſtify their thankfulneſſe to God for ſo large a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit; but have rather encreaſed their deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, their contumelies, and their blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies: But the juſt judge well knows how to puniſh them at the laſt day: But of this enough. I return to Antimony, Out of which is another remedy prepared moſt profitable for all feavers, and alſo in time of the plague.</p>
            <p>Take of Antimony excellently well ground or beaten, without any addition, deſtil it with a ſtrong fire in a Retort, whereto let be united a large glaſſe reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pient. Iterate it three or fower times, for ſo at length will be produced a red pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which extract with deſtilled vineger, Circulate the extraction in a gentle fire for ten dayes, then forthwith deſtil it to the Abſtraction of the vineger; urge the remainder by a peculiar Artifice that it
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:105077:76"/>
may paſſe into an oile, which yet circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and pellicane it, until the Phlegme be gon, and it be again reduced into a powder: the vineger muſt at firſt be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated in the deſtillation, and the oyl (comeing laſt) muſt be gathered in a new receiver. This oyl cures Quotidians, Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, and Quartain feavers, four grains being given with the deſtill'd water of carduus benedictus, and the ſick covered ſo that he may ſweat.</p>
            <p>The ſame doſe with Spirit of wine or deſtill'd vineger (according as the plague at firſt ſeized on the patient, either with burning or cold) doth moſt potently expel the plague, as three of my brethren can teſtify, who were, taken with the plague and having made their wils and given up themſelves to death, were delivered by this Arcanum, and from that time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward did more highly eſteem my medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine then before, and did aſſiſt me, both with their Prayers, and manual labour, (after performing the worſhip and ſervice of God) ſo carefully, that at length, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with me, they attained to many ſecrecyes and experiments, whence, by the induſtry of them, and other my brethren, more ſecrets of nature were detected and
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:105077:77"/>
opened in one yeare, then in a long time before, for which I gave them thanks (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to my laſt age) and moreover will be heartily thankfull, becauſe they well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it both of me, and other honeſt Chriſtians. But becauſe they dyed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, I do ſupplicate the Heavenly Cheiftain for their Reward, who without doubt hath paid unto my btethren a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Premium in Heaven, that they may be joyfully ſupplyed with a Celeſtial re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence, in the ſtead of that which is taken from them in this Life, and which could not have beene paid them by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilful and ungratefull men.</p>
            <p>There's alſo another Vulnerary Oyle made of Antimony, by an Addition, Thus.</p>
            <p>Receive of Antimony, ſulphur, and ſalt Petre, of each equal parts, ſhut them under a Campane, according as is cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary; but you wil do better if you uſe an Alembick with a Recipient, and you ſhall gather more Oyl then <hi>Per Campa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam,</hi> as to its colour it reſembles common oyle of ſulphur, but it is much ſtronger, becauſe of the addition, and operates more potently then the common vulne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary oyle of ſulphur doth, it is inwardly
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:105077:77"/>
adminiſtred for diſeaſed Lungs, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly adminiſtred to putrid filthy Vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, the Doſe inwardly is three drops with ſpirit of Wine, outwardly tis uſed only with a wound plaiſter layd thereon, thou ſhalt finde it an excellent Remedy in all evils.</p>
            <p>Another profitable oyle for Gangre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Diſeaſes and old Ulcers is thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared.</p>
            <p>Receive of Antimony ground or pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, one pound, of common ſalt, halfe a pound, of Potters Earth unba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked five pounds, mix them, grind them, and diſtill them in a Retort, and a yellow Oyle will come forth, all the ſpirits being come forth, put the matter into another Glaſſe, abſtract the Phlegme, put the remaining powder in a Cave upon a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and twill reſolve into a liquid Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, moſt profitable for ſerpentine cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and Gangrenous evills, eſpecially in the face of a man, or breaſts of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: I could write more things of this Balſome, but that I fear, that the unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and tatling ſophiſter, will ſay that (in his opinion) I write too much, and teach many things in Paper, which I never found by uſe, but only conceived in my imagination.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:105077:78"/>Another Oyle, may alſo be thus made.</p>
            <p>Receive of Antimony foure parts, ſalt Armoniack one part, grind them together and ſublime them with a gentle fire, &amp; ſo the ſalt will lift up with it ſelf the blood-like ſulphur of Antimony, grind this ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate well, &amp; for every pound of the crude Antimony that you ſublime, add five oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces mo<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of Antimony to the ſublimate, &amp; ſu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>li<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> it as afore. This ſublimate will be excellently wel diſſolved in a moiſt place, or elſe ſeparate the ſalt therefrom, and dry it by little and little, and thou ſhalt have a ſulphur combuſtible, like the common ſulphur ſold every where. Extract this ſulphur (in time) with diſtilled Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and ſeparate the Vinegar in B. M. by a gentle heate, extract or draw out its Tincture, and the remaining Powder draw over or diſtil into a Recipient by a ſubtill Artifice; if the ſtudious Artiſt doth rightly proceed in this way, he ſhall find a ſweet excelling oyle, without any Corroſion or danger; It heales the <hi>Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pneumonia,</hi> expels the dolour of the ſides and let the Aſthmatick take thereof in the morning, and at evening going to bed two graines, with the Elixir or ſpirit of
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:105077:78"/>
Wine; it heales pectorall Diſeaſes and caſts forth all impurities from the breaſt, and it hath been uſeful to me, and help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to many a one, even beyond hope. But ſeeing that in other preparations I have ſufficiently deſcribed the virtues of Antimony, I ſuppoſe it needleſſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat them again in this place, leaſt I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come tedious to the ſtudious, and excite in them I know not what ſuſpitions. The Liquor, made of this ſulphur (as I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſaid) is moſt profitably uſed in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Remedies, it takes away all the filth of the skin, and if a little Oyle be thereto admixt, it takes away the Pimples and ſpots of the hands, if anointed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall. It makes the skin bright, and heales the <hi>Alopecia</hi> or head ſcab.</p>
            <p>The ſulphur of Antimony is alſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared yet another way.</p>
            <p>Boile Antimony beaten or ground, two houres or more in a ſtrong Lixivium made of Aſhes, filtre the Antimony and pour thereunto moſt ſtrong Vinegar, and a red ſulphur will ſettle to the bottome, pour away the Phlegme and dry the pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; extract the Tincture with diſtilled Vinegar, as in the former ſulphur, bring it into an oyl by diſtillation, which is not
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:105077:79"/>
unprofitable, but yet weaker then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther precedent, where by the benefit of ſublimation with ſalt Armoniack, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Antimony is opened and realeaſed.</p>
            <p>Now followes three preparations of Antimony cheifly neceſſary for a Spagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt, <hi>viz.</hi> The preparation of a vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar out of its proper Minerall: The ſigned ſtar of the Philoſophers, and Philoſophical Lead, much eſteemed of by many, who have beleeved that out of it might be made the true Mercury of the Philoſophers, but it is impoſſible, neither is there ſo much granted by God thereunto, that in, or from Antimony, the Mercury of the Philoſophers ſhould be found; or the firſt <hi>Ers, Argent vive,</hi> and firſt water of perfect metalls, out of which is made the great ſtone of the Ancient Philoſophers. But this <hi>Primum Ens</hi> is found in another Mineral, in which (having Relation to metals) the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is higher then that of <hi>Stibium,</hi> although that this hath its particular profit. Note well, That the Pillar as twere of internal and externall Medicine is to be had in every ſhop or place of vendible things, were it but rightly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared; which I have oftentimes ſaid,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:105077:79"/>
and there wanteth nothing but that the Artificer learn to diſcerne the Nature of Mineralls and metals, and with exactneſs obſerve the preparation and uſe of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, whereupon a right Judgement will follow, and not before. I wil therefore accompliſh my promiſe, and ſatisfie the wiſhes of my Diſciples, and perfectly teach the Knowledge of the ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate and true ſeparation of the good from the bad, beginning at the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Philoſophicall Vinacre of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Aes</hi> or <hi>Minerall</hi> out of which Antimony is melted and purged, beat or grind exceedingly ſmall, put it into a glaſſe Phyal with a moſt long Neck, pour thereunto deſtilled raine water, that the glaſſe may be halfe full, Lute it and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefie it in Horſe Dung until the <hi>Aes</hi> or Minerall begin to boil, and to froth, or ſpume, and aſcend or worke up, then take it out, becauſe this is a ſigne that the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is opened; put this digeſted matter into a Cucurbit well Luted, and abſtract the water which will be a little Acid, which being drawn off, increaſe the ſire and ſomewhat wil ſublime, this ſublimate being commixt with the Faeces, let it be
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:105077:80"/>
again moiſtned with the water which was extracted from it, and diſtill it as before, and iterate this Labour ſo often untill it hath purchaſed the Acrimony of the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt diſtilled vinegar, but the ſublimate doth decreaſe in every diſtillation. pour this vinegar thus prepared upon new <hi>Aes</hi> or Antimony-minerall in a pellican, that it may ſwim three ſingers over it, let it ſtand in a gentle heat twelve dayes, ſo the vinegar will become red and be more acid, ſeparate this moſt purely, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtil it <hi>per</hi> B. abſtracting the Vinegar, and a redneſſe wil remaine at the bottome, which extract with ſpirit of Wine, and twill be a ſupreame medicine, rectifie the Vinegar again in B. that the Phlegme may be ſeparated, and then diſſolve there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in its own proper ſalt, <hi>viz.</hi> one ounce of ſalt to four ounces of vinegar, diſtill it ſtrongly in Aſhes, and ſo the vinegar will be more fortified, it refrigerates in a wonderfull manner beyond the force of common Vinegar, it allayes the gangrene that is enkindled by gunpowder, and ſuch other burning accidents, if it be ground with the ſoule of Saturne into an Ointment, and applyed like a Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaſme: Being mixt with the water of
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:105077:80"/>
Endive, and with the fixt part of ſalt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, burnt and prepared with ſulphur, it divides and cures the ſquinancy, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſheth heat.</p>
            <p>In the Plague a full Spooneful drunk at a time, and outwardly alſo applyed upon the Bubo, with a third part of the diſtilled water of the combuſt ſperme of Frogs, extracts the poyſon and refrigerates</p>
            <p>The ſigned ſtone of Antimony is by many a one much eſteemed of, and moſt men have earneſtly attempted its prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; ſome have enjoyed their wiſhes, the intent and purpoſe of others hath come to nothing, many have beleeved that this ſtar is the true matter of the phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers ſtone; imagining it ſo over-ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtily, becauſe Nature hath freely formed this ſtar of its own accord, but I deny it: (Theſe men leave the Kings high way; and do journey through unfrequented rocky places where the wild goats do live and the birds of prey do build their neſts) Tis not given to this ſtar to be the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſo noble a ſtone though the cheifeſt of Medicines lye therein. It is thus made.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Take of Ungarian Antimony</hi> two parts, fileings of Sttele one part, burnt Tartar four parts, melt them together and pour
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:105077:81"/>
them out into a Goldſmiths Crucible, wherein they are wont to purge Gold Let it coole, ſeparate the Regulus from the <hi>Scoria</hi> and <hi>Faeces,</hi> grind it or beat it, and again add of burnt Tartar three times its weight, and melt it as afore, ſeparate, grind it, and again add thrice its weight of burnt Tartar, melt it, and ſo the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulus ſhal be purged; If thou haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded aright (which is here the maine thing) thou ſhalt have a white ſtar ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning like to pure ſilver, and divided, as if the moſt accurate Painter had deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed it with its Radij or Beames. This Star ſublimed with ſalt Armoniack; grows red, for the Tincture of <hi>Mars</hi> aſcends, this ſublimate may be reſolved (in a Cellar) into an Oyl profitable for wounds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Regulus or Star</hi> may be often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled by the fire, with the ſtony Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, ſo that in the end being totally conſumed, he aſſociates himſelfe to the ſerpent; the which being finiſhed, the Artiſt wil have a moſt burning matter, and altogether fiery, wherein many arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall things lye hidden, and this matter is alſo reſolved into an Oyle, which ought to be brought over by deſtillation, and then rectified untill it be pure and cleer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Its uſe in the body, and to be adminiſtred
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:105077:81"/>
inwardly, is thus. Mix no more then three drops only with ſome convenient Liquor, as two Ounces of Wine or ſome diſtilled water, according to the Nature of the diſeaſe, and ſo give it, and but twice only in a weeke: Tis expedient therefore that the Phyſitian reſpects the cauſes of Diſeaſes, and the complexion of the ſick, that he may with ſafety uſe his Remedyes. But this Oyle is of a moſt great Acrimony, wherein lye many things, not fit to be revealed unto the common people, but to be reſerved as certain ſecrets for Philoſophers, who have daily ſuſtained moſt bitter Labours: Well then, whoever thou art that follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt my ſteps, be not dejected in ſo doing, thou ſhalt find as I have found by my hard pains, which I wiſh unto thee withal my heart.</p>
            <p>I have preſcribed unto thee things e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough even from the beginning, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thou mayſt finde the end, but many dye, who (as yet) have not attained the beginning, and periſh before the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of the magiſtry, I will on that account leave behind a book of Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or Principles, that my Diſciples being acquainted with the firſt experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:105077:82"/>
may the ſooner arrive to the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed end, and give God and me thankes. In this oyle is this wonderful thing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable, that it operates upon Chryſtals calcined for three dayes, and extracts their ſalt, which done, the oyle is yet once more to be diſtilled by a Retort, and ſo haſt thou a Remedy ſo potent, that it breaks and expels the ſtone of the blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and perfects many other things.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now concerning the Philoſophers Lead.</head>
               <p>Let the ſearcher into Art, know, that Antimony is of kin to common Lead: For even as ſome trees expell and drives out from themſelves their too much Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin (which is their Sulphur) (as is ſeen in the Cherry tree, and other trees) ejecting and caſting out their Gumme; but otherſome (abounding with over much Mercury) produce out of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, other heterogeneous plants, as appeares in the Oake and Apple, which bring forth Baſtards and Monſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Even ſo the Earth hath its abortives that are rejected from the pure metals in the ſeparation. Now ſeeing Antimony be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of affinity to <hi>Saturne,</hi> is thrown out from him, by reaſon of his too much Sulphur, neither (in his Nativity)
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:105077:82"/>
cold arrive to the perfection of a fuſil body, he remained a Minerall, for his over abounding quantity of hot ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur hath overcome, and hindred the Mercury (through the want and defect of cold) from coagulation into a fuſible body.</p>
               <p>But the Lead of Antimony is no other thing then its Regulus, which is not as yet malleable, &amp; as I have ſaid, is produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the copulating and fuſeing of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulus and ſteel in the fire, whereby the ſtar is made, out of which many have erroneouſly ſought for, the ſtone of the ancient Philoſophers, but in vain: But as for the remedies, thence educible by preparation, I have already demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and will not repeat them.</p>
               <p>But on this account doth the Regulus admit of the name of Lead, becauſe that that which <hi>Stibium</hi> gives of it ſelfe from its own glaſſe, if it be melted for three houres, (being firſt cemented) in a wind Furnace, in a well ſhut Crucible with the ſalt of <hi>Saturne,</hi> and then taken out it becomes malleable, and more weighty then before, becauſe it hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived malleability and increaſe from the ſalt, that it is become a compact and
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:105077:83"/>
ponderous body. Nor is there much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt the ſigned ſtar, and Lead of Antimony, although many Artificers propoſe a difference, for both are made of Regulus, and may be prepared into the ſame Medicine as I have ſaid, and <hi>Here I'le ceaſe,</hi> and next to the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Appendix, manifeſt the ſtone of fire.</p>
               <p>Let God be favourable, and open the Eares and Hearts of ſuch as are ſtubborn, and bleſſe them, that knowing the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Nature they may praiſe his om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotence and be aſſiſtant to their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>The Appendix</head>
            <p>FINALLY note, That there are other uſes of <hi>Stibium,</hi> as in Typogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicall Characters: alſo Sigills and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, (of wonderfull virtue) are made with metals mixt, under certaine conſtellations and planetary Conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and by a certaine commixion are made looking glaſſes, or ſpeculums of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers faces or ſhapes and proprieties, alſo
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:105077:83"/>
litle tingling Bells and ſtatues, which for that they appertain not unto medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, nor belong unto my calling, I wil here deſiſt, and leave their handling to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Artificers.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic_poem">
            <head>ACROSTICHON.</head>
            <l>
               <hi>A</hi>T the Beginning when the Earth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived me,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>N</hi>o Parent had I but the Heaven alone,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>T</hi>hen a faithfull helper (that ſo I might he borne)</l>
            <l>
               <hi>J</hi>aſon the duplicate was choſen for to be,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>M</hi>y Virtue is the gift of ſolar heat,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>O</hi>f Fire debarr'd, I ſweat not any bloud;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>N</hi>ow don't neglect <hi>Pluto</hi> thy mate to make</l>
            <l>
               <hi>I</hi>n fighting let him alſo be the heater,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>
                  <hi>V</hi>ulcan</hi> doth ſhew the way to honour true</l>
            <l>
               <hi>
                  <hi>M</hi>ethuſalem,</hi> unto thee giveth thanks.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:105077:84"/>
            <pb n="157" facs="tcp:105077:84"/>
            <head>OF THE Triumphant Chariot OF <hi>ANTIMONY,</hi> AND WHAT THE STONE Of Fire is.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N a time by ſerious Prayers powred out before God, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abſolved &amp; quitted from ſuperfluous thoughts, and wordly affairs I decreed to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate on ſuch ſpiritual caſes, as might be uſeful for a more thorough ſearch into the condition of Nature, I therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved with my ſelf to get me ſome wings
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:105077:85" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that ſo I might flye unto the ſuperiour ſtars, and make inſpection thereunto, as (by the Teſtimony of the Poets) <hi>Icarus</hi> and <hi>Dedalus</hi> have done. But when I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached overneer to the Sun, my wings were burnt by his heat, and down I tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble headlong into the deepeſt ſea; But becauſe I called upon God in my neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; he ſent me aid and help from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, whereby I was reedeemed from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and danger. For an Angell from Heaven came unto my ſuccour who Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the water to ſtand ſtill, and there was opened a great Abyſſe, like a moſt high mountain, where walking up and down, I would needs ſearch whether or no it were poſſible (as the ſons of men ſpeake) that there ſhould be a familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty between things moſt high, and things moſt low, and whethet or no, the ſupream ſtars have received from the Creatour, force and virtue, ſufficient for the produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of things in the earth like unto themſelves, and having ſearched through all, I found it certainly true, which our ancient Teachers have long ſince left behind them for our Inſtruction, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation (if we are deſirous Diſciples
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:105077:85"/>
after truth and verity) and have ſet down as fundamental, for which I gave moſt cordial thanks to the omnipotent God, and author of all wonderful things.</p>
            <p>Briefly, I find that all minerals flow from the Celeſtial Stars, and have their original out of an Aqueous Vapour, which haveing bin a long time nouriſhed by the ſtars, is reduced by the Elements into a palpable forme; whence, that va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour is dryed, and the wateriſhneſſe loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth its dominion, and the fire (after or next to the water) by the benefit of Aire bears the ſway, that out of the water the fire may be made, and out of the fire and the Aire, the earth may be made, which notwithſtanding are found inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in all the corporeal things of the world before their reſolution. The firſt matter therefore of all bodies is water, which by the dryneſs of the fire and the aire is changed into earth.</p>
            <p>But becauſe I have determined to teach, how the ſtone of fire is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared out of Antimony, and becauſe it doth not onely cure men, but particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cures even Metals alſo. It is convenient to adviſe what the ſtone of fire is; what its mineral is; whether or no a ſtone can be
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:105077:86"/>
made without matter, and alſo of the ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate difference, kinds and uſe of ſtones.</p>
            <p>Let the Holy Spirit be aſſiſting in this my determination, that I may truely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain this art as far as is lawful, from whence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I hope for an eternal abſolution from my chief Confeſſour, who eternally ſits in the throne of grace, and that from eternity, and will bear witneſſe of all things, when the laſt ſentence and decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Judgement ſhall paſſe upon all men, without proteſtation or Appellation.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, and above all other things know that the true Tincture of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony, which is a medicine both for men and metals, is not to be made of crude melted Antimony, ſuch as the drugſters and the merchants ſell, But out of its mineral or Aes, as tis dig'd out of the Mountains, and that too, made into glaſs: But how to performe that extraction is all the art, and workmanſhip; and whoſoever finds it ſhall be thereby inriched with health and wealth. Know alſo (friendly Reader) that the prepared, fixt, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent Tincture of Antimony (which I call the ſtone of fire) is a penetrating, ſpiritual, fiery eſſence reduced into a coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated matter, and may be compared to
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:105077:86"/>
the <hi>Salamander</hi> which cannot be burnt, but is purged and conſerved in the fire. But our ſtone of fire doth not ting univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally as the ſtone of the Philoſophers doth, which is made of the eſſence of Gold, nor hath it ſo much virtue granted it: But it tinctureth particularly <hi>viz.</hi> Luna, Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and Saturne into Gold; It toucheth not <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> but onely as to what may by this ſeparation be in part produced from them. Alſo one part of this Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture can tranſmute but five parts, ſo as to remain conſtant in the trial, colour, and weight, In <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Antimony</hi> it ſelf; when as contrarywiſe the true, antient, and great ſtone of the Philoſophers doth perfect innumerably. But yet this can be yet exalted it its own augmentation. And its Gold is pure, and conſtant.</p>
            <p>The Mineral of the ſtone of fire or of the Tincture is the Mineral or <hi>Aes</hi> of <hi>Stibium</hi> out of which (as I have afore men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned) it is made, but how it is done, and what virtues and operations are therein I will preſently declare.</p>
            <p>Moreover the Reader may obſerve that many ſtones tinge particularly, (for all fixt tinging powders are by me called ſtones) but yet one tingeth deeper then
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:105077:87" rendition="simple:additions"/>
another; as firſt; The ſtone of the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers which far tranſcends all others. Next which are the Tinctures of the Sun, and of the Moon <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As to the white. Then the Tincture of <hi>Vitriol</hi> or <hi>Venus,</hi> and the Tincture of <hi>Mars,</hi> both which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein in them the Tincture of the <hi>Sun,</hi> if they have bin formerly brought unto fixa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; next to theſe follow the Tincture of <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Saturne</hi> for the Coagulation of <hi>Mercury</hi> and then finally the Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of <hi>Mercury</hi> itſelf, this is the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and multiplicity of Stones and Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, which notwithſtanding are all ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated out of one ſeed and one principal Matrix, from whence alſo flowes the true Univerſal one, and without theſe no me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallick Tincture can be given.</p>
            <p>And verily tis not in other things of what name ſoever; I value not ſtones and Gems as to my preſent purpoſe, for I will ſpeak not of ſuch now, ſince that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine in them a medicinal virtue onely; I will alſo omit animal and vegetable ſtones, as appartaining to medicine ſolely, being unprofitable in metallick operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; As the virtues of which Mineral ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getable and animal ſtones, are conteined in the Philoſophers ſtone together, and at
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:105077:87"/>
once. <hi>Salts cannot ting, but are onely a Key to the preparation of stones, otherwiſe, they are impotent of themſelves; (At least, as to what belongs to metallick and mineral Salts) and now I ſpeak to the purpoſe if thou rightly underſtandst me, as to what dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference I ſuppoſe to be between mineral Salts) they ought not to be rejected, (neither can they) in Tinctures, in whoſe compoſition none can be wtthout them; for in them is found an excellent treaſure by which every fixation and conſtancy hath its original and foundation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some body will now haply enquire (who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I do not upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this account reprehend) whether or no without matter ſuch a ſtone can be made; I ſay, No. For every thing neceſſarily hath its own matter, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly. The animals, theirs; The mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, theirs, and vegetables their matter: Yet conſider exactly, that no body with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>fermentation</hi>; (of which in the end of the work of the preparation of the great ſtone where I conſider the tranſmutation of other metals with profit;) which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be wanting, is profitable or fit for any ſtone. Although at the beginning a bodily form &amp; corporeal eſſence, viſible &amp; palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:105077:88"/>
be taken, yet out of ſuch a bodily eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence the heavenly and ſpiritual viſion (for I cannot otherwaies call it) ought to be extracted, which was at firſt infuſed into that body by the ſtars, and alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten and concocted by the Elements, which ſpiritual eſſence ought in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner palpably and formally to be again changed with a little fire by the regiment and diſpoſing of the Microcoſme into a Palpable, fixt and conſtant matter. I ſpeak without any imagination into an open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field, if I were wiſe I ſhould not ſo much as whiſper, and would refrain my hands from writing. Therefore all Tinctures of metals ought ſo to be prepared, that they may ſingularly love the metals, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly and ſolely deſire to be united to them, and to perfect them, juſt like two lovers who burning with love cannot reſt until they are united and accompliſh their deſires; then at laſt, they reſt and are multiplyed by the will of God; man lyes ſubject to many and wonderful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, which in ſome, doe debilitate and take away the ſtrength of nature; Thoſe diſeaſes may be dealt withall by anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes; and that man may be reſtored to his former health.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:105077:88"/>But love it is, that overcomes all other diſeaſes, for which is no redreſs, or help but by a reciprocal love, and becauſe that the deſire of both ſex is mutual, tis onely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed by ſatisfaction of the inflamed and hungry longing; many things may be teſtified of the power of love, which doth not onely ſeize upon the younger ſort, but the elder alſo, who in their extreame age, doe not onely doat, but even grow mad by the fury of love. There are other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes which imitate or follow the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral complexions of men, and ſo aſſualt one more then another; But love ſets upon all without diſtinction, rich and poor, old and young, nor fears it any net that may be laid to trap it; In other natural diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the grief poſſeſſeth onely ſome certain members, the others being peaceable and quiet; But love captivates the whole body, all its eſſence, forme, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, not the leaſt part eſcaping; for the heart is ſo filled with heat, that it is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed through out all the veins and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news. And (as I may ſo ſpeak) love reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in its power, ſeizeth upon the ſenſe, reaſon, and thoughts, and withdraws a man from his mind, that he forgets, omits and diſ-eſtems every thing; he contemnes
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:105077:89"/>
God; Gods word, promiſes, wrath, threats and puniſhment (I ſpeak of inordinate &amp; forbidden love) nor can any thing recal him from that love, he is unmindful of his office, of his condition and vocation; he tramples upon admonitions, deſpiſeth the adhortations of his well wiſhing neighbour, yea he ſhuts his eyes from moſt things, that he ſees not his own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; ſtopping his eares to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful adviſe of ſuch as do admoniſh him. It deprives many a one of ſleep, takes away the appetite to food, procures a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect of labour and arts, that ſo love may be followed and wayted on. Many fall into a melancholy ſadneſs, becauſe of love, eſpecially if things do not preſently ſucceed according to deſire, and they conſume away like a candle, yea ſome looſe both life and ſoul, as is apparent by examples. But ſuch a one cares not, he contemnes the dangers both of ſoul and body, which indeed is a dreadful thing, let this ſuffice, for tis unſeemely for me who am an Eccleſiaſtical man, to give place to ſuch things in my heart, even as (be not offended with the word) hitherto all my life time I have forborne it, and moreover will ſupplicate my God and
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:105077:89"/>
Lord that I may conſerve my ſelf for my bride (the Chriſtian Church) to which by a faithful vow I have devoted my ſelf. But this I induce for examples ſake onely, that ſo I might diſcover and evidence, that al Tinctures ought to have a love to the metals, (elſe they cannot enter into true friendſhip) and by a true penetrative love attaine to Melioration or a better condition.</p>
            <p>Let us now come to the preparation of the ſtone reſerving its uſe to the latter end; And ſince this ſtone is of a moſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrative and meer fiery property, let it be boiled with fire and ripened as other things of the world; but yet differently according to the different natures of things, even as there are divers fires.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt fire is celeſtial, inſtituted by God, whereby charity is kindled and faith towards the moſt high God, moſt holy Trinity, and our moſt merciful Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Jeſus Chriſt, which faith will never deceive us, nor forſake us in any neceſſity, but will deliver our ſouls from eternal deſtruction.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond fire is the Sun, or Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary fire produced from the Sun, which brings all things in the Macro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:105077:90"/>
to maturity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third is corporeal, whereby all meats and medicines are boiled and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, which men cannot want either for health or nouriſhment.</p>
            <p>We alſo find in the Holy Scripture, that before the laſt judgment, God will conſume this viſible world with fire, but what fire this will be, let us refer it to the judgement of the moſt high.</p>
            <p>There's alſo mention made in the word of God of another, or an eternal fire, which is reſerved in hell for the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal puniſhment of the damned; (being infinite and without ceaſing, God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting it; and not onely for them, but for the devils alſo, from which fire I pray the almighty God to preſerve us; whence I do faithfully admoniſh all, that they pray unceſſantly that the call and life of every one, may have an harmony betwixt them, for thereby ſhall he conſerve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and be delivered by God from that infinite puniſhment.</p>
            <p>Now let all know, that our ſtone of fire ought to be boiled and maturated with the corporeal fire of the Microcoſme, even as other meats and medicines are; for at the farewel of the operative fire
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:105077:90"/>
of the Macrocoſme, doth the fire of the Microcoſme begin the production of a new generation, and therefore let no man wonder at this coction.</p>
            <p>Wheat grew and ripened by the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary fire of the Macrocoſme, and a new coction and maturation is again pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by the corporeal fire of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crocoſme, that ſo man may further uſe that bleſſing for his own conſervation, and that he may enjoy even the utmoſt, and the leaſt thing, which (by the firſt and great world, was under operation and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king on.</p>
            <p>The true Oyle of Antimony out of which the ſtone of fire is prepared, is of a moſt ſweetly pleaſant property, and is thus purged and ſeparated from its own Earth, place a glaſſe filled therewithal in the Sun, and it emits from it ſelfe ſundry and admirable beames like to the reddy Rubine, ſhining with a fiery brightneſſe, reſembling other wonderfull Colours and ſhapes, like to manifold Speculums expoſed unto the ſolar bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>But hear me, thou ſtudious Lover of art and truth, if thou deſireſt to make a farther progreſſe in experience, Take in
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:105077:91"/>
the name of the moſt high, the <hi>Aes</hi> or mineral of Antimony born after the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Sun, one part, of the pureſt and beſt mundified ſalt petre, as much, grind them, and mix them exceedingly well, place them in a gentle fire, burne or fire them together according to art, (this is the work, and this is the Labour) then ſhalt thou finde a dark, dusky, colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red matter remaining behind, of which make glaſſe, out of which being powde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, extract a moſt red Tincture with a moſt ſtrong vinegar, diſtilled and made out of its own proper Minerall, abſtract the vinegar in B. M. and there will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine a powder which yet again ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract with ſpirit of Wine rectified unto the height, and ſome feces wil remaine, and thou ſhalt have a moſt red extraction, profitable in medicine.</p>
            <p>This is a moſt pure ſulphur of Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeparated to the utmoſt, which if thou haſt two pounds of, add foure ounces of the ſalt of Antimony (made as I have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore taught thee) thereto, mix them, and circulate them in a veſſel well ſhut for a month at leaſt, ſo wil the ſalt be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited to the extraction, if any feces re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main let them be ſeparated, then firſt of
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:105077:91"/>
all deſtil off the ſpirit of Wine in B. M. and that being abſtracted, augment the fire, and there wil come forth the moſt ſweet, pellucid red oyle, with many mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous colours, rectifie this oyle in B. that a fourth part may remaine, and tis good. Which being done, take of the quick mercury of Antimony already ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, and pour thereto a red oyle of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol made out of Iron, and ſupreamly rectified, diſtil the phlegme in ſand, from the mercury, and thou ſhalt have a precipitate, a fairer then which cannot be ſeen, nor a more profitable in old wounds and ulcers, for it dryes up accidentall hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, from whence martial diſeaſes have their Riſe, where (alſo) the united ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the oyl aſſiſts him.</p>
            <p>Take of this precipitate, and of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid dulcorated oyle of Antimony e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual parts, mix them, put them into a glaſſe wel ſhut, in a gentle continuall heat, &amp; the precipitate wil be diſſolved in the oyle and be fixt, conſume all the phlegme in the fire, and then ſhal you have a fix, dry, red, fuſible powder, emit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting no fume; <hi>My diſciple,</hi> I wil now ſpeake in the manner of the Prophets, foretelling things to come: When thy
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:105077:92"/>
ſtudies have guided thee thus far in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, and thou haſt perfected the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of Antimony, which I have preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed thee, thou haſt a medicine both for men and metals, it is ſweet and ſafe, it penetrates, it moves not the belly, it corrects and expels what is evil; If thy progreſſe hath been right, this medicine wil reward thee in thy health and food, that nothing in the world ſhal be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting unto thee, for which thou oweſt unto God a ſacrifice of praiſe.</p>
            <p>My God! I now ſpeake with a ſadned mind, being an Eccleſiaſtical man, for I do not know whether I have done right or otherwiſe, whether too much or too litle: I leave it to every ones judgment: ye that are my diſciples make tryal as I have done, if you attaine to your end, give praiſe to God, and thank me who am your maſter, if ye erre from the way, blame your ſelves, for I am not the cauſe of your errours.</p>
            <p>I have ſpoken enough, I have written enough, yea ſo clearly that none can teach more cleare, unleſſe a man would purpoſely run into Hell, and there drown himſelf, uttering things prohibited by the Creatour, and eating of the tree placed
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:105077:92"/>
in the middle of Paradiſe: but what I have done, ſhal ſuffice me, until I can more largely judge of what is lawful as to this thing, and now Ile ſpeak a few words of its uſe.</p>
            <p>The uſe conſiſts in the view of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and obſervation of his complexion, as to humane health, ſee thou giveſt nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too much nor too little, that thou neither burden nature nor deny her what is ſufficient. Albeit it hurts not, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though too much be given, for it helps loſt health and reſiſteth poiſons.</p>
            <p>Yet know that three or four graines at a doſe, is ſufficient for the expulſion of all diſeaſes, being given with ſpirit of wine; This ſtone or Tincture penetrates all the joynts of the body, and far tranſcends other Arcanums, it doth moſt readily take away the Pthiſis, and all diſeaſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing from the Lungs, the Aſthma, the Cough, Lepry, and <hi>Lues venerea</hi>; the Plague, Jaundiſe, dropſie, and all Feavers, it expels any poiſonous drink, tis profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for ſuch as are infected by a phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre or love potion; it comforts the head, the brain, and what is of affinity to them, the ſtomack, the Liver; it heales the diſeaſes of the Reines, it purgeth cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:105077:93"/>
bloud, expels maligne humours, leſſens the ſtone of the bladdet, and drives it forth, heales the windy <hi>Dyſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, &amp;c.</hi> It brings back the vitall ſpirits, compreſſeth the ſuffocatian of the Matrix, provokes the Menſtrues, and allayes their overflowings, it begets fruitfulneſs, and ſound ſeed in both ſexes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Outwardly.</hi> This ſtone of fire (but yet it muſt be be alſo taken into the body and a ſuitable wound plaiſter externally applyed) heales the Gangrene, and all other corroding diſeaſes, the ſcab, and infirmities ariſing from the corruption of the bloud, and the <hi>Noli me tangere</hi>: In a word, this ſtone (as a particular Tincture) is a remedy, for almoſt all the diſeaſes whereto man is ſubject, which experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſhowes, together with the way, if only thou beeſt a true Phyſitian ſent and called by God.</p>
            <p>I will write no more of Antimony, I have acted my part, let another alſo act his, that the myſteries of God may be layd open (before the worlds end) to the glory of him, and for the health of men; Ile hold my peace, and returne to my monaſtick order, until I ſhal have made larger progreſſe in my Philoſophy,
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:105077:93"/>
that I may alſo write thoſe things which I have a long time decreed, <hi>viz.</hi> of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol, common ſulphur, and the Magnet, their beginnings and virtues, may it pleaſe the Prince of Heaven to beſtow upon us health of body, and eternall welfare of our ſoules in the unſearchable joyes of his celeſtial delight, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I conclude this Tract of Antimony, thoſe things, which I have written of the red oyle of Antimony made of its purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſulphur, and of its ſpirit which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared of its ſalt, obſerve, and therewith compare this laſt Doctrine of the ſtone of ſire, wherein if thou whetteſt thy wit and mind, from this comparing wilt thou finde their conjunction, for the Baſis and Foundation is one and the ſame, and the Amiry and Freindſhip is the ſame, by which health is attained unto, and the lamenting Stag caught by a pleaſant cheer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full hunting.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Water, Fire, Aire, Earth, yea all things ſhall be reduced into powder and Aſhes, whatſoever is borne of them, doth alſo in time periſh: The mercy of God only endures to all Eternity, which alone Man enjoyes, for which let us be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
