<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A dialogue between a modern courtier and an honest English gentleman to which is added the author's dedication to both Houses of Parliament, to whom he appeals for justice / by Samuel Baston.</title>
            <author>Baston, Samuel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26755</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1056</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37087</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16206513</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16206513</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105080</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A26755)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105080)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1087:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A dialogue between a modern courtier and an honest English gentleman to which is added the author's dedication to both Houses of Parliament, to whom he appeals for justice / by Samuel Baston.</title>
                  <author>Baston, Samuel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed:</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCVII [1697]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Admiralty. --  Commission for Sick and Wounded.</term>
               <term>Misconduct in office --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>Robyn Anspach</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>Robyn Anspach</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105080:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DIALOGUE BETWEEN A <hi>Modern Courtier,</hi> AND AN Honeſt Engliſh Gentleman.</p>
            <p>To which is added The AUTHOR's Dedication TO Both Houſes of Parliament, To whom he Appeals for Juſtice.</p>
            <p>By <hi>SAM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EL BASTON, </hi>Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year MDCXCVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:105080:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105080:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Lords Spiritual <hi>and</hi> Temporal, <hi>and</hi> Commons <hi>in Parliament Aſſembled:</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AGainſt the Opening the preſent Seſſion of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, I thought it my Duty, (conſidering the Nation's great Diſtreſs) to point out to your Honours, who were the principal Cauſers and Continuers of its Miſeries; which I did in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Dialogue; Containing, 1<hi>ſt.</hi> Bare Matter of Fact already prov'd againſt the <hi>Lords of the Admiral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Commiſſioners of the Navy, Commiſſioners of the Post-Office,</hi> and <hi>Commiſſioners of the Sick and Wounded Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> &amp;c. with the foul Practices of the <hi>Commiſſioners of the Publick Accounts,</hi> for Concealing and Juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſaid Crimes. 2<hi>dly,</hi> Natural Conſequences and Arguments drawn from the ſaid Matter of Fact, in Reference to Religion, Law, Policy and the true
<pb facs="tcp:105080:3"/>
Intereſt and Safety of the King and Kingdom.</p>
            <p>The Book being out, it was ſeiz'd by Meſſengers, divers reporting it was <hi>High Treaſon,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Cros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feild,</hi> and a Poor Woman, were Committed to the <hi>Poultrey Compter</hi> about it, by a Juſtice of Peace, at the bare Inſtance of a Meſſenger: The ſaid Juſtice of Peace often profeſſing he was ſorry the matter came before him, for that by his own Loſſes he could ſpeak deeply to the Truth and Honeſty of the Book, but was afraid of being chid by ſome of the Court, if he neglected to do what the Meſſenger bid him, with Divers other Expreſſions of like Nature; which ſhews the great Force of Truth, that it will be Confeſs'd, tho from the mouths of its ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Oppoſers.</p>
            <p>I was alſo inform'd, that the aforeſaid Meſſenger had given direction to the ſaid Juſtice of Peace to Commit me the firſt time he ſaw me; for that there was a Warrant out againſt me for <hi>High Treaſon</hi> (which Trouble they need not have given the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of Peace, for they knew where to have found me themſelves). But I being very infirm and weak of body, by reaſon of long ſickneſs (occaſion'd by my ill uſage) was unwilling to be committed to
<pb facs="tcp:105080:3"/>
               <hi>Newgate,</hi> in this ſmugling manner, to deſtroy my Health (which I knew was the Deſign againſt me); and the ſaid Juſtice of Peace, thro' Ignorance and Timerouſneſs, wou'd certainly have done it, (had he ſeen me) tho the book I had printed had been <hi>David</hi>'s <hi>Pſalms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Report was on <hi>Saturday,</hi> and the <hi>Monday</hi> following I went to the Secretaries Office to ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my ſelf to this Warrant of <hi>High Treaſon:</hi> but, upon Enquiry, found there was no Warrant againſt me for <hi>High Treaſon;</hi> Sir <hi>William Trumball</hi>'s Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary making a Jeſt of it, told me, 'twas only the Meſſenger's miſtake (but I could not get him to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the Meſſenger about it); and that what was againſt me in that Office, was only upon Suſpicion of being the Author of this Dialogue (ſo the <hi>High Treaſon</hi> was fallen only to Suſpicion of a Miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour), and that I muſt ſubmit to be confin'd in a Meſſenger's Cuſtody, which was accordingly done. After ſome days I got a ſight of the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for my Commitment, which was not upon Suſpicion of my being the Author of this <hi>Dialogue</hi> (as <hi>I</hi> was told at the Office), but for <hi>Publiſhing and Diſperſing a Seditious and Scandalous Libel against His</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:105080:4"/>
               <hi>Majeſty and Government;</hi> without Naming what Libel, or mentioning its Title in the Warrant. The Warrant alſo ſhews, that 'twas drawn after <hi>I</hi> ſurrender'd my ſelf; for it begins thus, <hi>Theſe are in His Majeſties Name to require you to keep in ſafe Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> &amp;c. Whereas another Warrant directed to a <hi>Meſſenger,</hi> to apprehend any Perſon, commands him to go and take a Conſtable to his aſſiſtance, and ſeize or attach the Body of ſuch a one, and bring him and his Papers before the Secretary to be Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, &amp;c. By which it appears what Drudgery was deſign'd for this Timerous Juſtice of Peace to commit me to <hi>Newgate</hi> for High Treaſon, to Ruin my Health without Warrant, Law, or Sence.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>I</hi> continued a Priſoner in a <hi>Meſſenger</hi>'s Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody from the 26<hi>th October</hi> 1696. to the 29<hi>th Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi> following, being 3 months and 3 days, to the great endangering of my Life by bad Diet, and was then diſcharg'd, giving a Recognizance of 500 l. to appear the firſt day of the next <hi>Term.</hi> So <hi>I,</hi> that have ſerv'd the King, and diſcover'd, and detected many of the Utter Enemies of his <hi>Majeſty</hi> and his <hi>People,</hi> am now Cited to anſwer as a Criminal, for pointing out the Deſtroyers of the Nation to the Parliament.
<pb facs="tcp:105080:4"/>
And thoſe Notorious Criminals <hi>I</hi> write of in this <hi>Dialogue,</hi> are brought to no <hi>Tryal,</hi> but protected, as if there was no Law to take Cognizance of them.</p>
            <p>And further, the matters of Fact related in this <hi>Dialogue</hi> (the <hi>Poſt-Office</hi> excepted) are no more than what are contain'd in a Petition and Articles Exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited by <hi>Mr. Crosfeild</hi> and others, in the Houſe of Peers, about two years ſince, where it is now depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: The late <hi>Commiſſioners of Accounts,</hi> to whom it was Referr'd to Examine into it, and make their Report, having hitherto by Evaſions, and Falſe Allegations, in behalf of the Criminals, delay'd and ſtopt the laying open theſe Grievances, and have to this day diſappointed your Honours of a true Knowledge of them; whereby the ſaid Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances have been ſupported and increaſed; for which the Nation has ſeverely ſuffer'd; But has reaſon now to give thanks to God, that the ſaid Commiſſion is ſo happily Diſſolv'd, <hi>which was ſo great a Bulwork of Iniquity;</hi> And I hope it is a good O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, or Preſage of a General Overthrow of Fraud and Wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:105080:5"/>
So now becauſe the Facts contain'd in this Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, are not yet Examin'd in Parliament, (by means of the aforeſaid Commiſſioners of Accounts) the Printing them again, to re-mind the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the preſent miſeries, that God may be honour'd by the Puniſhment and Suppreſſion of Wickedneſs, the King and Kingdoms Enemies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd, and the Laws put in Execution for the publick ſafety, for the future, is (it ſeems) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>A Seditious and Scandalous Libel, againſt his Majeſty and Government.</hi> I<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>m ſure, this Dialogue chiefly depends but upon three things. Firſt, Truth in the matter of Fact related. Secondly, The Goſpel in reference to Gods Judgments, for Imo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallity and Tollerated Wickedneſs. And Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, The Laws of the Land in reference to their being Invaded, and Perverted, and not put in Execution: And if this Dialogue will endure a Tryal by theſe three Touch-Stones, and yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ſtill to be a <hi>Seditious and Scandalous Libel,</hi> &amp;c. Why, then, Truth muſt be Scandalous, and the Scripture and Statutes of <hi>England</hi> Seditious Libels, and he that Writes for the ſafety and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the King and Kingdom, is an Enemy to his Majeſty and Government. This ſhews how
<pb facs="tcp:105080:5"/>
Exceedingly Wickedneſs abounds, and what a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal of Men there are in Power, ready to turn the King's Authority againſt himſelf, and to ſubvert <hi>Gospel, Law, Loyalty, Juſtice,</hi> and all things tending to the honour of God, and benefit of the King and State.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Dialogue</hi> is call'd <hi>a ſeditious Libel:</hi> Whereas it ſpeaks for the <hi>Execution of the Law</hi> with as much Force as words can expreſs. Now where the Law is put in Execution, there can be no <hi>Sedition;</hi> but where the <hi>Laws and Conſtitutions of a Kingdom</hi> are <hi>invaded and perverted,</hi> by the <hi>Arbitrary Power of Evil Miniſters,</hi> it is that which introduces <hi>Sedition;</hi> and as <hi>Sedition</hi> is a dangerous Diſtemper in a Nation, ſo the Impartial Execution of the Law is a Sovereign and Certain Cure. And whereas it is call'd <hi>a ſcandalous Libel,</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that if 'tis true, 'tis <hi>not ſcandalous,</hi> and every Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of <hi>England</hi> has an undoubted Priviledg to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of, and diſcover <hi>Injuries done to the King,</hi> and alſo lay open <hi>the Grievances of his People:</hi> And if all the Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> tho in never ſo high a Station, are ſubject to the Law, and anſwerable for their <hi>Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> (which I hope is not in the leaſt queſtion'd), then this <hi>Dialogue</hi> will not deſerve theſe <hi>Characters,</hi> nor the <hi>Author</hi> deſerve to be Arraign'd as a <hi>Criminal</hi> for wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it (while <hi>the real Criminals</hi> he writes of are prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted): For certainly <hi>the pure and undefiled Law of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:105080:6"/>
does not provide any <hi>puniſhment</hi> for its <hi>Advocates.</hi> 'Twas a Noble ſaying of that Glorious Prince <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. of Famous Memory (when he hang'd his Chief Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice <hi>[Thorp]</hi> of the <hi>Kings Bench,</hi> for taking a Bribe of 100<hi>l.) That he being intruſted as the King's Deputy, to adminiſter Juſtice in that Court, had, as much as in him lay, broken that ſolemn Oath that his Majeſty made to his People at his Coronation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If ſuch ſtrict Scrutinies ſhou'd be made in theſe Days, (which no doubt God Requires) what a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudewould there be found Guilty of this <hi>Chief Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice's Crime,</hi> who continue to practice it without any regard to their Maſter's <hi>Safety, Honour</hi> or <hi>Coronation-Oath,</hi> or Safety of their Country? nay, ſo far are they from thinking it a <hi>Crime,</hi> that a Learned Lawyer not long ſince (as I was inform'd) brought it as a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Objection to the Bill againſt buying and ſelling Offices, <hi>That the Perquiſites of his Employment came to about</hi> 3000<hi>l. per an.</hi> and pray'd a Clauſe in the Bill to ſecure it to him, which ſhews how ſtrong a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire he had ſtill to be able to Expoſe the Rights and Liberties of the People to Sale to the higheſt Bidder: So Religious a Regard had that Gentleman to his Maſter's <hi>Coronation-Oath.</hi> Nevertheleſs, ſuch Corrupt Men as theſe, who ſo openly oppoſe Juſtice, do gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally pretend to have a great Love for their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign,
<pb facs="tcp:105080:6"/>
and how they'll ſtand by him with their Lives and Fortunes, and what not, when alas, their Love has no more reallity than the pretended Love of a Common Harlot: For Certainly, a Corrupt and Unfaithful Servant, can no more Love his Maſter, than an Adulterous Wife can Love her Husband:</p>
            <p>It is not Improbable, but this Dialogue may by a Tryal in the Kings <hi>Bench</hi> be made (as 'tis call'd) <hi>A Seditious and Scandalous Libel againſt his Majeſty and Government;</hi> And ſo the Tables ſhall be turn'd, and I ſhall be try'd as a Criminal, for laying open the Nations Grievances to the Parliament, and the Criminals acquited of the Crimes they are accus'd of, without any Tryal at all; It cannot be ſuppos'd, that I ſhall have free Liberty in the Kings <hi>Bench Court,</hi> to bring ſuch Numbers of Witneſſes, as are neceſſary to prove the Matters of Fact contain'd in this Dialogue; For the Court is ty'd to one ſingle Iſhue, and therefore cannot Enquire into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of Grievances in the State: Beſides, it is rarely ſeen that any Man eſcapes the Cenſure of the Courts of <hi>Westminſter,</hi> who runs Counter to the Predominant Party at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> let his Cauſe be ever ſo juſt; Inſtances enough may be given of it in the late Reigns, when the Courts of Juſtice have (under pretence of Law) been made perfect Slaughter-Houſes to Puniſh, Impriſon, Fine, and take away the Lives of Divers Noble Patriots of their Countrey, for doing that which we now call their Duty, whoſe memories we Commemorate, and the Judgments againſt them have been Revers'd in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But Certainly, it had been much more Honourable (if it cou'd have been done) to have ſav'd their Lives, by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a ſtop to their Illegal Tryals, than now to ſay, we are ſorry for their Deaths.</p>
            <p>Therefore, I moſt humbly appeal to this moſt <hi>Auguſt</hi> Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, who in theſe Caſes are ty'd to no ſingle Iſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue, but
<pb facs="tcp:105080:7"/>
may throughly enquire and ſearch into the Nations Grievances, (which my Deſigns has been only Loyally and Faithfully to lay open) humbly Conceiving, that if I produce Witneſſes to prove the Matters of Fact, Contain'd in this Dialogue; That then it will not deſerve the Title, given it in the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for my Commitment, <hi>Viz. A Seditious and Scandalous Libel, againſt His Majeſty and Government.</hi> Neither, ſhall I deſerve to be Arraign'd at the Kings <hi>Bench Bar</hi> as a Criminal, the next Term, where I am bound to appear by Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of 500 <hi>l.</hi> after above three Months Impriſonment, to the hazard of my Life.</p>
            <p>And being thus ready and able to produce Witneſſes, to prove the ſaid Matters of Fact, Contain'd in this Dialogue (to the great Advantage of the King and Government) when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever your Honours ſhall pleaſe to Command; I humbly Caſt my ſelf upon your Honours Juſtice and Protection, that no ſuch Proſecution may be made againſt me, as is intended, till I be firſt heard, and have liberty to prove, that what I have Written in this Dialogue is Truth, and for the King and Kingdoms true Intereſt, Peace, and Safety, and then I ſhall be willing to ſtand a Tryal at the Kings <hi>Bench Bar;</hi> And ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to what Law my Adverſaries can find, to puniſh me, for Writing this Dialogue. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>With all Dutiful Reſpect, Your Lordſhips, and Honours, Moſt Obedient Servant,</hi>
SAM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EL BASTON.</signed>
               <dateline>London, <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 16<hi>th of</hi> March, 169<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105080:7"/>
            <head>A DIALOGUE BETWEEN A Modern <hi>Courtier,</hi> and an Honeſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentleman.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Courtier.</speaker>
               <p>DEAR Sir, Your Humble Servant, you are Welcome to Town; Pray how long have you been arrived.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gentleman.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I came but laſt Night, and thought my ſelf oblig'd to pay my Reſpects to you in the firſt place: I hope all your Noble Family is well.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I thank you Sir, they are very well; But pray how does your good Lady? And how do Matters go in the <hi>Country?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G.</speaker>
               <p>Why we are all reaſonable well in Health, but out of Order every way elſe; For the Taxes are ſo high, Money ſo ſcarce, Trade ſo dead, &amp;c. That I Proteſt my Eſtate is ſo Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated, 'twill hardly maintain my Family.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Come, Sir, you are my Worthy Friend, and therefore I would not have you find Fault with any thing; for, if you are willing, I doubt not, but you may ſoon have ſuch an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, that you will not feel the weight of the Taxes;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105080:8"/>
nay, you may be a Great Gainer by the War; and I would fain have you in the Government. What ſay you, Will you Advance a ſmall Summ.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I give you many Thanks for your kind Offers which at this time-a-day I can by no means accept; and I am deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be plain with you in my Reaſons for Refuſal: but you being a Privy-Councellor, and Member of Parliament, &amp;c. I know not whether 'twill be Convenient to uſe Freedom of Speech; for, you may Interpret ſome things I may ſay, as Reflections on your Self.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I aſſure you, what I Offer is deſign'd for your Intereſt; but, if you don't approve on't, you may uſe what Freedom of Speech you pleaſe; for, though I am Honour'd with thoſe Offices you mention, yet that ſhall not, in the leaſt, be any barr to the freedom of our Diſcourſe, neither ſhall I take any thing Ill, for I perceive you have a deſire to Talk about Publick Affairs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I heartily Thank you for the Liberty you have given me; And now I muſt tell you, that I am of Opinion, there is ſuch a <hi>Caball</hi> of Corrupt Men in the Government, that 'tis impoſſible for an Honeſt Man to live and act amongſt them, unleſs he will renounce his Duty to God and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; For (as one well obſerves) <hi>Good and Bad Men Joyn'd in a Government, are like the Iron and Clay in the Toes of</hi> Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezar's <hi>Image, they may Cleave, but they will never Incorporate.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Why truly, what you Alledge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is a good Reaſon for not taking an Employment, provided there be any Juſt Grounds for your Opinion about the Corruption in the Government.—I Confeſs there is, and has been a Great Noiſe and Clamour about Corruption and Miſmanagement and I have always endeavoured, as narrowly as I could to ſearch out the Truth of Matters, but cou<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d never yet find any thing ſo Material, as to be worthy the Cogninance of either King or Parliament.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105080:8"/>
However, Great Clamours have been made by ſome Private-Men, who (I ſuppoſe) were Male<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Contents, they have Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd Vaſt Diſcoveries of Treachery and Fraud, but when it has come to Examination, I never found that the Accuſers could make out their Allegations, but Mountains dwindled away into Mole-hills, and, as I ſaid before, nothing appear'd that was thought worthy of <hi>Cognizance.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G.</speaker>
               <p>I find, by your Diſcourſe, you endeavour not only to Evade, but Cover thoſe Groſs and Monſtrous Evils that have been the Cauſes of the Length of the War, and of our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Diſtreſs: Sir, I know not what kind of <hi>Miſcarriages</hi> you think are worthy of <hi>Cogniſance,</hi> but, I fear, upon Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, 'twill be found, that the Crimes already prov'd in the Faces of our Rulers, will Amount to the Degree of <hi>ROBBE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RY</hi> and <hi>M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RDER;</hi> and, which makes them more Hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, they have not been done in a <hi>Hoſtile Manner,</hi> in Open Defiance of the Law, as the High-way-man takes away your <hi>Money</hi> on the Road, But with the Audacious Face of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, under the Sacrilegious <hi>Mask</hi> of Law, Juſtice and State-Pollicy: The Authors and Upholders of theſe <hi>Miſchiefs</hi> in the mean time blowing the Trumpet of Fame in each others Praiſe, as Long-headed Councellors, &amp;c So that I do not wonder theſe matters ſhould be Rejected, and not thought worthy of Cognizance, when I conſider that Infallible <hi>Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im, That the Inferiours cannot be Knaves, and be Protected by the Superintendants, unleſs thoſe Superintendants be as bad.</hi> And thus it appears almoſt Impoſſible any Fault could be Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but that all Criminals muſt be Protected, and their Crimes hid from the King, when <hi>Corrupt Men</hi> ſat Judges of each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Actions—Therefore 'twas not likely they wou'd hurt one another; For the very <hi>Scripture</hi> tells you, <hi>That Satan can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not caſt out Satan,</hi> if he ſhould his Kingdom would fall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you have Charg'd the Court with a <gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> yet 'tis
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105080:9"/>
but a General and bare Aſſertion; and let me tell you (being ſomething Concern'd) there's a great difference between Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting and Proving, and therefore I'd fain have you (if you can) branch out your General Charge into ſome particular Inſtances, as for what may ſeem to Reflect upon me, as I told you before, pleaſe to uſe your Freedome, for I ſhall not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent any thing that ſhall happen in Diſcourſe at this time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G.</speaker>
               <p>Why then, Sir, for your Satisfaction, I ſhall give you ſome Inſtances, that have accidentally fallen under my Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, which I fear, in Reference to the Mighty <hi>Maſs</hi> of <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption</hi> in the Government, will be found only as a ſmall Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern or Sample of a vaſt quantity of Goods, that the Whole Parcel is of the ſame Sort, otherwiſe there cou'd never be ſuch an agreeable ſweet harmony among all the Offices, in Cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the Parts, and hiding the Crimes of each other from King and People: But having more than one Office to ſpeak of, I think I ſhall begin firſt with that of the Navy.</p>
               <p>The Commiſſioners of that Office have been accus'd of making moſt horrible Waſt of the Publick Treaſure, by a long Practice of Fraudulent Contracts for Naval-Stores, and dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Trades in Embezelling all ſorts of Stores, as well as Foul and Shameful Extravagance in Building and Repairing the King's Ships: Theſe things have been Fully Prov'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them before the Lords of the Admiralty, and before the Lords of the Council, and afterwards openly ſet forth in Print to both Houſes of Parliament, and yet the Delinquents are ſtill Continu'd in their Employments. So that by this Open Villany, the Neceſſary Charge of the Navy is more than doubled, and the King Shamefully Betray'd and Cheated, and His Subjects made Beggars by Heavy Taxes. But there is one thing more that is a moſt Dangerous and Curſed Evil, and that is the Uſage of the Poor Saylors, whoſe Number is about Forty Thouſand Employed in the Service of their King and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105080:9"/>
Countrey: Their <hi>DEPLORABLE CASE</hi> has been often at Large ſet forth in Print, and made known to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Council, Admiralty, &amp;c. And to Relate all their Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, and the Curſed Arts us'd to Ruin and Deſtroy them and their Families would be Endleſs: Therefore to avoid being Tedious, I ſhall only give you a ſhort Account of their <hi>MISERIES,</hi> as I find it Inſerted in a BOOK, Entituled, <hi>Juſtice Perverted,</hi> &amp;c. Printed and Publiſhed laſt Year by Mr. <hi>Crosfeild,</hi> and <hi>Dedicated</hi> to <hi>Both Houſes of Parliament.</hi> The BOOK contains beſides this a Great <hi>Maſs</hi> of Flat Down-right Knavery; and the Commiſſioners of the Navy, and others, are Named therein to the particular Facts: But I find, it has all been paſs'd over and Stifled. However, I ſhall Relate it as follows, in his Own Words, having, by Good Luck, the BOOK in my Pocket to Aſſiſt me.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>The poor Saylors (Says he) that Venture their Lives and Limbs to Serve their King and Country, and who are one of the greateſt Bulworks of the Kingdom, have been all along moſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanely and Barbarouſly Treated; and they and their Families reduc'd to a Miſerable and Deplorable State, particularly by the wicked practices of putting Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERY's and R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NS upon their Pay, For amongſt thoſe great Numbers that are Set on Shoar Sick; thoſe that Dye and others that Continue Sick above Thirty Days, and thoſe ſent to the <hi>London</hi> Hoſpitals who are thereby diſabled to return to their Ships, are for the moſt part made Run. Others whoſe Ships are Sayl'd before recovery having gone aboard other Ships, are prick'd Run in that Ship from which they were Sent: And if a Seaman is Turned over from Ship to Ship, and by that means has Serv'd on board four or five Ships in the Navy, Yet if he happens to be prick'd Run in the laſt Ship he ſerved in, he ſhall of Conſequence be prick'd Run in all the preceding Ships. By this Means a Query or Run takes away a Mans pay worſe than an Execution, and by the preſent practice <gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Seaman<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or <gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oor
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105080:10"/>
Family is at any Certainty of having the benefit of the Kings pay, For it is in the power of the <hi>Captain, Captain's Clerk, Purſer, Clerk</hi> of the <hi>Checque, Muſter-Maſter,</hi> or <hi>Clerks</hi> in the <hi>Navy-Office,</hi> wherever they pleaſe to put a Run or Query upon any Seamans pay without Inſerting the Reaſon for ſo doing, or the Name of the perſon that put it, ſo that for theſe Black pieces of Robbery, No one is lyable to be Call'd to Account, but the poor Saylor is kept wholly in the Dark, and he or his Wife may wait at the Navy-Office Month after Month with Petitions to no purpoſe, till he has Spent all his Subſtance, and if he begins to talk of his being thus Cheated and Robb'd, he is Threatned to be Try'd for his Life as a Mutineer: So that the Barbarity the poor Saylors do and have Suffer'd this War is unexpreſſible, For the Blood of Thouſands of Familys are pour'd out as Sacrifices to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs of thoſe whoſe Duty and place it is to be their Guardians and Protectors. By all which it's plain, That whatever Good-Laws may be made for the Increaſe and Incouragement of Seamen, will prove Ineffectual, ſo long as theſe Practices Continue.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Grievances have been at large ſet forth in Print by one Mr. <hi>Hodges,</hi> and a Scheme of their true Cauſe laid bare-fac'd before the Admiralty by Mr. <hi>Trevor</hi> in a Letter, and a remedy for them propoſed in Writing, to the Admiralty by Mr. <hi>Gibſon,</hi> by order of a Committee of Council; and why there's nothing done but this Fraud and Robbery ſtill practic'd and ſupported, is, what no reaſon can be given for, ſince neither Mr. <hi>Hodges</hi>'s, Mr. <hi>Trevors,</hi> nor Mr. <hi>Gibſons</hi> Papers beforemention'd; have ever been exploded.</p>
                  <p>The Lords of the Treaſury were ſo fully Convinc'd of theſe Cheats, that their Lordſhips did by Warrant under their hands in <hi>December</hi> laſt, appoint Mr. <hi>Gibſon</hi> to receive all Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of abuſes in Payment of Seamens Tickets; which doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, would have put a ſtop to theſe wicked Practices, Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing which, the ſaid Mr. <hi>Gibſon</hi> has never been ſuffer'd to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105080:10"/>
Act, and ſo their Lordſhips good Intentions have been wholly defeated: But why their Lordſhips have not been able to put their own orders in Execution, is another ſtrange thing to me.</p>
               </q>
               <p>This is the Account he gives; and 'tis certainly very amaz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to conſider that the Government ſhould be ſo wretchedly Corrupt, as to paſs over Crimes of ſuch fatal Conſequence.</p>
               <p>But you may ſee that by this Cheating and Robbing there are vaſt Summs of Mony gotten for ſome body, and certainly the Actors in it cannot have the whole profit to themſelves, but it muſt be diſtributed elſewhere, to perſons of higher Rank; Becauſe their Intereſt is ſo great, that even after Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, they have power enough to Chain up Law and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice from doing their proper Offices. And now Sir, what think you, are theſe Crimes worthy of Cognizance or not? but I have many more to add</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Why then, Pray Sir proceed, for this is ſomething more than I knew before; I confeſs, one of <hi>Crosfeilds</hi> Books was given me at the Houſe of Commons, it lies ſomewhere about the Houſe, but I had never time to read it over.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G.</speaker>
               <p>Indeed I thought as much, for it appears all things of that kind have hitherto been ſhamefully thrown aſide as waſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, as if the perſons to whom they were Dedicated did not deſire to be Informed: But I ſhall go on and give you ſome Account of the Commiſſioners of the Admiralty.</p>
               <p>Their Lordſhips have been accus'd of Concealing and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocating the Crimes of the <hi>Navy-Board,</hi> and Diſcouraging and Ruining ſuch of the Kings faithful Officers and Subjects, that laid them open<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this has been prov'd againſt them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Council, but all things lie dormant and unregarded: So that here is three degrees of ſuch fatal Corruption, from the <hi>Navy</hi> to the <hi>Adm<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>raity</hi> and from them to the <hi>Council,</hi> that alone is ſufficient to ſhake the very Foundation of the Government.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:105080:11"/>
It were endleſs, to tell you the reſt of the <hi>Admiralties</hi> Crimes, who thro' Corruption and Ignorance, have not been able with about two hundred Sail of Ships to Guard our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation; whereby Trade has been deſtroy'd, and our Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants undergone Infinite Loſſes, which our Enemies have had the Benefit of; and then further, the Admiralty have all along plac'd Commanders in the <hi>Fleet</hi> without any regard to Merit. So that this War we have loſt above a hundred Ships, the greateſt part of which have been fool'd away, by the Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of the Commanders; and ſome by Cowardice with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fighting, beſides the horrid Miſcarriages in Expeditions againſt the Enemy, as the ſhameful Expedition to <hi>Breſt,</hi> &amp;c. Which ſerves only to diſpirit the People, and Increaſe their Taxes. Certainly a Man would think, that theſe Gentlemen have a deſign Totally to deſtroy the Navigation of <hi>England,</hi> for tho the Crimes of the <hi>Sea</hi> Commanders are ſo Hanious and Numerous; yet has not one of their Sea Journals been Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in'd all this War, to ſee how they have perform'd their Duty, tho there is no other way to Judge of their Fidelity and Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in their Stations but by Traceing their Journals; and thus Ignorance and Negligence, as well as horrible Profaneneſs and Debauchery has generally over-ſpread the <hi>Sea,</hi> as well as the Land. But what ſhould I ſpeak any more of this Admiral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for every one knows their Wickedneſs and Ignorance, yet I have often wonder'd there has not been more Complaints againſt them, from the <hi>Eaſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>India</hi> and <hi>Guinea</hi> Company and others, who are almoſt Ruin'd with Loſſes: Certainly our Merchants are like the Fools ſpoken of by <hi>Aeſop,</hi> that none would meddle to remove the Stone from the Mouth of the <hi>Bath,</hi> tho every Man ſtumbled, and broke his ſhins over it at going in, till at laſt a Wiſe Man came and Roll d it away; God grant we may have ſome VViſe Men by the next Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, that will ſtand up for the publick good, or elſe in ſhort we muſt prepare for foul VVeather.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:105080:11"/>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>But Sir, what needs all this Complaint, why moſt of theſe ſores are heal'd, for here's a Council of Trade now ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, by which the Merchants Grievances, and ſeveral other things will be rectify'd</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G.</speaker>
               <p>I confeſs, the Council of Trade was excellently propos'd at firſt to the Parliament; But the Intereſt of the Court quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>beat out it's Brains,</hi> and from this Eſtabliſhment I doubt little good will ariſe, my reaſons for it are theſe. <hi>Firſt,</hi> They do not underſtand Trade, 'tis Forreign to them, and out of their ſphere. <hi>Secondly,</hi> I cannot but obſerve, that the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part of theſe perſons are the ſame that ſit in Council; and from time to time have heard the Crimes of the Admiralty and Navy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and wanted no Power to redreſs thoſe Grievances there: So that the Regulation is no more than removing theſe Gentlemen from one Room to another, as the Barons of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> paſs from the Law to the <hi>Chancery ſide,</hi> now cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly if I am a Corrupt or Ignorant Man in the Parlour, I am the ſame in the Dineing Room.</p>
               <p>Put Sir, there you flatly Arraign the very Wiſdom of the Government.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, certainly and their honeſty too (if by the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment you mean the Court or elſe what d' think I have been talking of all this while or how is it poſſible I could ſpeak at all of any publick Grievances, unleſs I Arraign'd both, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out you would have me ſay we are all Ruin'd; and at the ſame time affirm, that no body did it: But I muſt beg your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience a little further, becauſe you did as it were, Challenge me to give you ſome Inſtances of Corruption.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, Then you may proceed if you pleaſe; I am ſorry to hear ſo much, tho I think none of it do's Actually relate to me, for I'm ſure, I always did what I cou'd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G.</speaker>
               <p>Why, then in the next place, I ſhall give you ſome Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105080:12"/>
of the Commiſſioners, for taking Care of Sick and Wounded Seamen, and Exchanging Priſoners of War, and theſe you will alſo find to be a wretched Pack: For one of their Clerks who laid down his Employment, has prov'd No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Crimes againſt them.; as holding a Pernitious and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Correſpondence with the <hi>French</hi> all this War, So that there has been an open and quick paſſage to give Intelligence to the Enemy of all our Affairs and Deſigns, and to betray the Kings Councils from time to time, alſo he has prov'd that they have Cheated the King in their Accounts; and Cheated the poor Sick and Wounded Seamen in <hi>Plymouth</hi> Hoſpital out of their Proviſions, and that they have all along Cheated the Poor <hi>French</hi> Priſoners under their Care, out of part of their Allowance, and treated them in a very Barbarous manner. For it ſeems their whole Allowance was but four pence each Man a day, and they deducted three farthings out of that four pence: It was alſo prov'd that the <hi>French</hi> Intendant General <hi>Marine,</hi> writ diverſe doleful Letters of Complaint to theſe Commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, telling them how Barbarouſly and inhumanely the poor French Priſoners were us'd, whereby many of them Periſhed; And that he had Orders from the <hi>French</hi> King to uſe our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Priſoners in like manner if it was not rectify'd; But no Regulation being made, but the Evil rather Increaſing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was the true Cauſe that the <hi>French</hi> have all along us'd our poor <hi>Engliſh</hi> Captives in ſuch a dreadful and Barbarous Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: For by reaſon of their Miſerable ſhort allowance and lying diverſe Months in Filthy and Loathſome Priſons, and others by being driven like Gally Slaves ſeveral hundred Miles Naked through the Country, I ſay from theſe Cauſes many hundreds of them have Periſhed, and many Familys have thereby been brought to utter Ruin: Nay theſe Men have Committed Murther on both ſides of the Water; For, beſides the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> they have baſely and Cruelly deſtroy'd many of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105080:12"/>
the poor <hi>French</hi> priſoners, which doubtleſs is no leſs Murther in the Sight of God notwithſtanding the War.</p>
               <p>Theſe and Diverſe other Crimes were Examin'd and prov'd before the Admiralty by the Kings Special Order above two years ſince, and a Report thereof was made to his Majeſty and Carry'd by the Admiralty to the <hi>Cabinet-Council,</hi> but the Matter was ſo manag'd, that the Report was Stifled and not Read to the King: ſo that the Commiſſioners, upon their Petition, were granted a Re-hearing before the Council in Publick, where theſe Matters were Fully Prov'd over again; but the buſineſs was delay'd from time to time, till the King was gone for <hi>Flanders,</hi> ſo that the Report of the Council was alſo kept from his Majeſty, and how that Report was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards curry'd in his Majeſtys abſence I know not, but this I know, the Commiſſions are ſtill in their places with power to purſue their Villainy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo that what I told you juſt now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears again to be true. <hi>That Satan cannot Caſt out Satan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There may many things more be ſaid of theſe Mens horrid Wickedneſs, as their deſtroying the poor Sick and Wounded Seamen with bad Medicines for the <hi>Lucre</hi> of gain, which with many other Crimes were fully prov'd againſt them before the Comiſſioners for Stateing the publick Accounts, where ſome Witneſſes they brought appear'd moſt <hi>Willfully and Notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly perjur'd,</hi> and Eſcap'd puniſhment. But for a more plain and particular Information herein, I ſhall refer you to a Book Printed and Publiſh'd laſt year, by the Perſon that brought the Complaint againſt theſe Men, and Dedicated to the houſe of Peers, It is Entituled <hi>Baſtons Caſe</hi>  (for ſo was the Clerks Name) <hi>or a Brief Account of the Evil Practices of the preſent Commiſſioners for Sick and Wounded, as they were prov d.</hi> 1<hi>ſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Before the Lords of the Admiralty.</hi> 2<hi>ly. Before the Lords of the Council, and</hi> 3<hi>ly. Before the Commiſſioners for Stateing the publick <gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>counts.</hi> For there is Contain d the Admiraltys and Councills Report,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105080:13"/>
and there the Crimes of theſe Commiſſioners for Sick and Wounded lye barefac'd to the World.</p>
               <p>And now Certainly it would Stir up a Mans Zeal for the publick good, if he did but Conſider in what Jeopardy and peril the poor Saylor Serves his King and Country; For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the hazard of his Life in open Fight) if he continues in the Kings Service without being Sick or Wounded or Taken by the Enemy, why then he's lyable to be <hi>Query'd,</hi> or <hi>Run'd</hi> out of his pay, or oblig'd for Neceſſity to ſell his Ticket for half loſs (or more) to ſome of thoſe Curſed Monſters, call'd <hi>Ticket-buyers,</hi> who (as it has appear'd too plain) are but <hi>Deputy's or Journy-men to the Navy-Board.</hi> If he is ſet on Shoar Sick and Freſh dyet and Broath will not Cure him, why then he runs a great hazard of being Poyſon'd with his Phyſick, but if he recovers 'tis ten to one but he's prick'd <hi>Run;</hi> And if he's taken by the Enemy 'tis a great Chance if ever he returns to his Native Country.</p>
               <p>Certainly it muſt ere long be Counted hard Meaſure, that for ſuch petty Retail Robbery and Murther, as taking away a ſmall Matter upon the Road, or for killing another in a Duel for an Injury receiv'd that a Man ſhou'd be hang'd like a Dog; When ſuch wholeſale Murtherers and Robbers as theſe are protected and Flouriſh in their Villainy, though their Actions tend to the utter Subverſion and overthrow of a State: But this is an Age full of Wonders; <hi>For from the Court proceeds Abundance of Praying and Preaching and Faſting, but hardly a Grain of Integrity, Honeſty, Juſtice or Humanity, as if theſe were Accounted Needleſs Ingredients in Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I am unwilling to try your patience any further with theſe unpleaſing Relations, otherwiſe I could add ſeveral other things and particularly of the Commiſſioners of the <hi>Poſt Office,</hi> how they have been lately prov'd Horribly Corrupt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful before the Lords Juſtices; likewiſe more might be ſaid
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105080:13"/>
of other Offices, and alſo of the great Corruption in the Army and abuſe of the poor Soldiers, by the Agents and others, which was alſo plainly prov'd; But I think this is Enough at preſent to ſhew you what a Condition the Nation is in: For any one may Judge by theſe what the other Offices are, They being all Streams that proceed from the ſame Fountain (I mean the Court) and muſt conſequently afford the ſame Bitter Water. And now I hope you are throughly convinc'd that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of Grievances have not been meer Clamour, as you were pleaſed to ſay in the beginning of our diſcourſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I Confeſs Sir theſe things do look with an Ill face: Yet 'tis the greateſt Riddle in the World to me, how ſuch Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carryages as theſe cou'd be carry`d on, when we have had for ſome years paſt <hi>a Commiſſion Eſtabliſh`d by Act of Parliament to Take, State and Examine the publick Accounts of the Kingdom,</hi> and they have Power by the Act to Adminiſter Oaths and to Call all Perſons to an Account that have the Receipts or Iſſues of the Publick Revenue and that <hi>Commiſſion</hi> conſiſts only of Members of the houſe of Commons, who are utterly unqualifyd for any Employments at Court<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and conſequently unbyas`d Men; And therefore I wonder how theſe things can be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G.</speaker>
               <p>Why I Confeſs, this is a <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity</hi> that has darken'd the underſtandings of ſome, however 'tis a matter eaſily unriddled, for 'twill be found that theſe are alſo a pack of Gentlemen, nothing Inferiour to the worſt of thoſe already ſpoken of; for as the Court have hid the Grievances of the People from the King, ſo theſe have kept them from the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and have us'd ſuch Arbitrary Arts, Tricks, and Devices to acquit and Juſtifie the worſt of Villains that have come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, and to blacken the Reputations of Honeſt Men, that certainly the like has not been known, for an Inſtance of which I refer you to the Printed Book I ſpoke of juſt now<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> about the Crimes of the Commiſſioners for Sick and Wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105080:14"/>
Entituled <hi>Baſtons Caſe,</hi> &amp;c. There you will ſee in what an Arbitrary manner they heard that buſineſs, and Endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all the ſhameful ways Imaginable, to acquit thoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of Crimes they had been prov'd Guilty of twice before, <hi>Viz.</hi> At the <hi>Admiratly</hi> and <hi>Council.</hi> They allow'd Criminals to ſwear in their own behalf contrary to Law, and when <hi>Baſton</hi> made them appear Notoriouſly perjur'd, they Barbarouſly Encourag'd one of them to ſwear on, (whoſe Name was <hi>Nicholas Sharrack)</hi> which he did, and was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd again, and again, as plain as the Sun, and as black as Hell; and then they diſcharg'd him any further Attendance, with as much Commendation and Applauſe as if he had Sworn right, but I refer you to the Book for that and much more, for by this <hi>Illegal and Ungodly Method</hi> of Swearing Criminals in their own behalf; with diverſe other new Invented Arbitrary ways in hearing the Peoples Grievances, theſe Gentlemen can at pleaſure make the Devil white. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, it ſeems this buſineſs of the Commiſſioners for Sick and Wounded was ſo plain being twice before both prov'd and Reported) that they were not able to wipe off their Guilt and Infamy: But this they were able to do for them, to bury it in their Office and keep it from the knowledge of the Houſe of Commons, which they have accordingly done: And when it was afterwards brought into the Houſe of Lords to be heard, they prevented it there alſo by a Trick, and got it out of the Houſe, for they Acquainted their Lordſhips that the matter was then depending before their Board; and pray'd it might be Recommitted to them to finiſh the ſame, and make their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, which the Houſe accordingly did; but the Report is not made to this day, neither will be I ſuppoſe till the day of Judgment: And as to what they told the Houſe of Lords, that the matter was then depending before them, 'twas a great falſity, and deſign'd only as an Excuſe to diſappoint the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105080:14"/>
of the matter in Parliament. Much more might be ſaid of theſe Men concerning the <hi>Navy</hi> and <hi>Army,</hi> how they have brow-beat and diſcourag'd Witneſſes, and Incourag'd Knaves and Villains, ſtifled, Complaints, &amp;c. So that theſe Men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of being a <hi>Checque</hi> to Corruption; have been the <hi>Props and Pillars to ſupport it,</hi> as true Servants and Vaſſals to the Court.</p>
               <p>Certainly ſuch a Commiſſion might have been of exceeding uſe to the publick, had it conſiſted of true <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> and been Wiſely and Honeſtly manag'd; for 'twou'd have been a place to Puniſh and reform Knavery and Villany, and Rogues and Cheats, with Tears in their Eyes, might have call'd it the terrible Office of <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> but now, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, they may Rejoyce, and truly ſay, 'tis an Office of <hi>Abſolution;</hi> For they have Examin'd no Accounts, nor ſav`d the Nation a penny of Mony this War, but Knaves, Kna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very and Taxes have conſtantly Increas`d; all that they do, as I know of, is, they receive the Accounts of the Receipts and Iſſues of the Kings Revenue from all Offices and Perſons, and them they take the pains to Tranſcribe in Books and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of their own, ſo as to be able to Anſwer any Queſtion of the Houſe of Commons, relating to the Receipts of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue or Charge of the War, but to detect Frauds, is ſo ſmall a part of their work that they hardly Regard it. Sure, in this mighty Maſs of Corruption the parties concern`d, could not have ſubſiſted without the help of this Office; for it is a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle for all their Knaviſh Accounts, where being New-Moulded (without Alteration) they receive a <hi>Vizard</hi> of Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſty; In ſhort, this Office, as tis manag`d, has been a great <hi>Blind to the Nation,</hi> and may (for its Abominable foulneſs) be fitly compar`d to a Capital Common-ſhoar, into which abundance of other Common-ſhoars and little petty Sinks do Empty themſelves.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>But Sir, I tell you again, They are Men utterly unquali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy`d
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105080:15"/>
for any Employments at Court, to what end therefore can this Corruptien be among them? really 'tis ſtill a Riddle to me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G.</speaker>
               <p>Why Sir, to the ſame End that all other Corruption is, Namely <hi>to get Mony</hi> and I muſt tell you they are in a moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent way for <gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> because they have it in their power to Cruſh or Protect ſuch a great Number of Knaves of all ſorts and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes: And I hope Sir, you don't queſtion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but that they have <hi>Pockets</hi> and <hi>Coffers</hi> enough to put their Mony in, as well as the Courtiers. Therefore pray where the Riddle on't, for my part, I ſee none at all; For it plainly appears, theſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen have been ſo far from obſtructing, that they have af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded great help, and performed their part towards the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of their Country, as well as the reſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Well, admit all you ſay is true, and that there is ſuch a General Corruption as you ſpeak of; How can you help it at preſent, pray would<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you have the King at this juncture Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately go to Turning out<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Puniſhing ſuch a great Number of Men? Certainly, <gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> make ſuch Diſorder and Confuſion, as would ſoon <gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> up the very Foundation of the Government, and than would be a Remedy with a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G.</speaker>
               <p>Why then, I find you have Changed your Opinion, and own at laſt that the Nation is Sick, But now to ſave the <hi>Court,</hi> you would have the Diſtemper ſo far gone, that there is not ſtrength left to undergo a Courſe of Phyſick, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Imminent hazard of Life: I confeſs the Court of all ſorts of Phyſick, ever hated Purges. They will take Gold Cordials, and they are great Admirers of Quieting Pills, but Purging they mortally hate, and will have it to be a Vile and Dangerous way of Practice But, to ſpeak in your own words—Admit what you ſay is true, that the Government is brought to this degree of Feebleneſs, Pray how highly
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105080:15"/>
then is the King and Nation Oblig'd to theſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Long-headed <hi>STATES-MEN</hi> and <hi>CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCELLORS</hi> (whoſe Parts and Honeſty, for ſome Years paſt, it has been almoſt Treaſon to Queſtion) Or what Satisfaction can they render to His Majeſty, and the People of <hi>England,</hi> for bringing upon them this Incurable Diſeaſe?</p>
               <p>But now, Sir, pardon me, if I differ a little from you in O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion: I do not believe the Government is ſo weak, but that a Fit Remedy might be apply'd for all theſe Evils, and that is, to Turn Out in the firſt place ſome of thoſe that have been moſt Obnexious to the People, and put in their Rooms Men of Publick Spirits, Fearing God, and Hating Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and they will have Courage ſufficient to Ballance the reſt of the Wicked Party, till the Law is let looſe to do its Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Office upon them that are Turn'd Out, whoſe Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will ſtrike others with Great Terror, and make them fearful how they Offend: But if they eſcape, 'twill be a moſt Pernicious Example to Encourage and Excite all Men to become as Corrupt <gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they; 'twill alſo be highly Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to God, and 'twill greatly Incenſe the People; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed none has any Rightful Power to Pardon them, becauſe their Crimes have been Univerſal, and committed not only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King, but againſt the Whole Body of the People of <hi>England.</hi> In this manner the Court may be ſoon Gradually Purg'd, and then the Inferiours will of conſequence be purg'd alſo. The Scripture ſays, <hi>Reſiſt the Devil, and he will flee from you:</hi> and no doubt the ſame Rule holds for thoſe that have Acted like his Children; Therefore why ſhou'd we fear to Execute <hi>JUSTICE</hi> upon them? Alas, they are but poor Feeble Creatures, not worth mentioning, in Compariſon of the Force of the Law: 'tis true, they have Power to do great <hi>Miſchief</hi> in their Stations, as we have found to our Coſt, but when the Law lays hold on them, their Power ceaſes like the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105080:16"/>
Power of a <hi>Witch,</hi> when She<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Seiz'd by a <hi>Conſtable:</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he that knows their Actions, and Contributes to Save them from the Juſt Cenſure and Sentence of the Law, makes himſelf an Approver, before God, of all the Ruin and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction they have brought upon this Nation, and of all the Innocent Families they have Deſtroy'd and Blood they have Spilt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Therefore, unleſs the Law is put in Execution, there can be but a Half fac'd Regulation, or a Palliative Cure, that will ſoon Relapſe, and become Incurable. For, let none Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdly and Fooliſhly Dream, that God will-ſuffer us to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper in the midſt of thoſe Oppreſſions, Frauds, and moſt Hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Immorallities, that we are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Bound in Duty, and Able by Authority to Puniſh and Hinder. 'Tis a Falſe and Villanous Saying, to Whiſper in the Ears of <hi>Princes,</hi> That VVhole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Laws have any Antipathy to True <hi>Policy:</hi> The Law, when 'tis Upheld, is the <hi>Princes</hi> beſt Friend, it cannot Diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but always faithfully ſtands by Him, ready to Oppoſe His Enemies: It gives Him His RIGHT, and His Subjects theirs, and ſo makes a powerfull prince, and a Vertuous VVealthy and peaceable Government. But 'tis Natural for Corrupt Men to Hate Good Laws, and that makes it and the Nation have ſo many Enemies at Court. And now, after all, when theſe <hi>Long-headed Men</hi> have brought the Nation to this <hi>Pitch</hi> of <hi>Ruin,</hi> for them Cunningly to Inſinuate, That 'twill be Dangerous to Call them to an Actount for their <hi>CRIMES,</hi> and Adminiſter Help to our ſelves, purſuant to the Laws of <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Nation;</hi> is an Unparallel'd Audacious Abſurdity: But I confeſs, we can expect no better Advice from that Party, becauſe the King, and Kingdoms Safety, ſeems Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to Theirs; For hitherto they have Pernitiouſly and Pittifully made Themſelves the Center of all Their Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:105080:16"/>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I believe things are bad enough; but, methinks you'r too Furious for a Regulation; really 'twill put things into Great Diſorder: therefore I am of Opinion 'tis better to ſee the Succeſs of One Year more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G.</speaker>
               <p>As for Staying a Year longer 'twill be highly dangerous; <hi>Why ſhould God be Provok'd, and the Nation Oppreſs'd a Year Longer?</hi> perhaps a Year hence we ſhall not have ability to help our ſelves. 'Tis ſaid in the Law of <hi>Moſes, Thou ſhalt not delay Juſtice,</hi> as if the Legiſlator had ſaid, Thou ſhalt not put it off to a further time. The poor Mans Cauſe ſhall not be delay'd an hour. God knows by willful and Needleſs delays Multitudes of private perſons are Barbarouſly Robb'd of their Right and utterly Ruin'd by the horrid, delaytory, Expenſive unrighteous practice in our Courts of Law and Equity; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let that Suffice, and let not the, whole Body of the People have a General Ruin, by a Delay in the State; Certainly 'twill be very Dangerous to delay the Cauſe of this drooping Nation any longer. A Learned States-man Speaking of fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runers of Troubles, ſays, <hi>That when any of the four Pillars of Government are Shaken or Weaken'd (which are Religion, Juſtice, Council, and Treaſure) Men had need pray for fair Weather:</hi> Now certainly with us not only ſome, but all theſe Pillars are Shak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Ready to fall; As for Religion we have none, though we have much <hi>Preaching, Praying,</hi> &amp;c. for had we any Real <hi>Religion,</hi> we ſhould have <hi>Juſtice and Morallity.</hi> Juſtice it plainly appears has almoſt quite left us. And as for <hi>Council or Pollicy,</hi> I Confeſs we have abundance of that, but it is of a VVretched Stamp, being ſuch as is oppoſite to Divine and Humane Law. And for our <hi>Money on Treaſure,</hi> we may Reckon that gone alſo; For though there may ſtill be a great Stock in the Nation, yet the people may Starve, becauſe by a long devouring Corruption it's almoſt all gather'd into the hands of a few <hi>Court-huxters,</hi> that neither do nor will uſe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:105080:17"/>
'Tis no hard Conjecture to ſay that a <hi>General Poverty, Oppreſſion, Breaking of Laws, and Advancement of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthy Perſons to Great Offices,</hi> are Common Motives to, and Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners of Seditions and Troubles; and the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> certain way to prevent theſe Evils, is to take away the Cauſe and Matter of them, which the Adminiſtration of Juſtice, and Suppreſſing of Vice and Wickedneſs will Effectually do; For God will ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give Succeſs to all ſuch Remedies, if they be Sincerely and Faithfully apply'd, and all contrary Policy, in this Caſe, muſt certainly prove very Fooliſh, if not Fatal.</p>
               <p>How Ridiculous is it to Delay this Matter, and to think that theſe Perſons now upon the Stage, can ever make this a Flouriſhing Nation, when they have neither <hi>Parts</hi> nor <hi>Moral Vertues</hi> equal to other Men<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 'Tis true, they are Gifted with a little Cunning, which a Learned Stateſman (truly) ſays, <hi>Is only a Crooked ſort of Wiſdom.</hi> Beſides, it does appear by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Seven Years Experience, that the very Talent of theſe Gentlemen lies not to Enrich or Increaſe, but to Impoveriſh, and bring a Flouriſhing State to Ruin and Decay, <hi>and to Trample upon Law and Juſtice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and all Good Men, and</hi> (as one excellently obſerves) <hi>to make Magiſtracy, which was Intended for the Benefit of Mankind, prove a Plague and Deſtruction to it.</hi> But the Honour of God, and the Good of their Prince and Country is the leaſt of their Care. They Level their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils and Polliticks to their own Advantage, and Slyly Study <hi>rather be throughly acquainted with their Maſter</hi>'s <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, than to be Skilful in His Buſineſs.</hi> I Pray God that all the Enemies of our King and Nations Happineſs may be Plentifully Stock'd with Stateſmen of ſuch Parts and Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and be ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>effectually blinded as not to perceive them.</p>
               <p>Certainly at this time a Day, when Poverty, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently Diſcontentment is ſo Univerſal, 'tis Highly Dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to make any Delay in Juſtice; For, of this you may reſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105080:17"/>
Aſſur'd, <hi>That as many as are Ruin'd, or Impoveriſh'd in their Subſtance, by Injuſtice, or Male-Adminiſtration, ſo many VOTES there is for TRO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLES.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Why really I know not well what to ſay to't; I wiſh all things were done for the Beſt: But yet methinks 'tis ſtrange to Obſerve, That all theſe Complaints have been brought upon the Stage, by a few Inconſiderable Men, ſuch as had generally Bad Characters, and were Reported to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey Ill Men in themſelves, and that they did theſe things with Ill Deſigns, and I believe that was one Reaſon why they were no more taken Notice of, as likewiſe becauſe none of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Great Figure appear'd with them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G.</speaker>
               <p>Why that's no Wonder at all: For it may be obſerv'd, that the Generality of the World is ſo Fooliſh, that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard more the Outward Manner of things, than the Inward Matter of them. It is ſo in Religion it ſelf (to our Eternal Shame be it ſpoken) as appears by the Vaſt Troops of Pious Hypocrites, <hi>Overſeers, Paſtors, and Members of all Churches,</hi> who take Great Pains by abundance of <hi>Praying</hi> and <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and <hi>Faſting,</hi> to make an Outward Gaudy Shew of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, but uſe no Hearty, nor Sincere Endeavours really to Suppreſs Vice and Wickedneſs: <hi>As if Religion was a Noun Substantive, that cou'd ſtand by it ſelf, without requiring Moral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to be joyn'd with it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Ill Characters</hi> theſe Perſons generally have, that's no wonder neither; For, 'tis one great Maſter-piece of this Corrupt Party's Policy, <hi>in their Fencing with Law and Juſtice,</hi> to ſerve all thoſe that Complain of Grievances, as the Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting <hi>Pagans</hi> did the Primitive <hi>Chriſtians, who put them into Lyons and Bears Skins, that the Dogs might ſeize on them, and Bait them to Death;</hi> So theſe Monſters, after they have Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, Delay'd, Deny'd, or otherways Baffled Juſtice, give an Honeſt Man a Curſed Character, and in that <hi>Maſquerade</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:105080:18"/>
turn him looſe to the Mercy of <hi>a Miſtaken Multitnde:</hi> But certainly 'tis a high degree of Preſumption, as well as Deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Wronging the Publick, thus falſely to Brand thoſe (that ſtand up for the Intereſt of their <hi>Country,</hi> to preſerve their Laws and Liberties) with ſuch Baſe <hi>Characters,</hi> as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Diſaffected to the King and Government, as tho' by ſuch Complaints they only deſign'd to ſtir up the Minds of the People to <hi>Sedition</hi> and <hi>Rebellion;</hi> when, in Truth, 'tis them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that only <hi>Bid Fair for REBELLION,</hi> by their Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and VVicked practices: For he that Endeavours to Inform King and People of ſuch Dangerous Diſtempers in the STATE, certainly does nothing but his Duty, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot deſerve ſuch an Odious <hi>Character,</hi> for endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Preſerve, Support and Defend <hi>the King, Government and Laws he lives under.</hi> But he, that by his horrible Male-Adminiſtration, and Oppreſſion, endeavours to overthrow all, let him be in ever ſo great a Place to paſs his <hi>Crafty Cenſures</hi> on others, does certainly himſelf deſerve the Name and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a <hi>Rebel</hi> and <hi>Traytor.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>But, pray Sir, Anſwer me one thing, How can the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment be ſo corrupt, as you ſay, and ſo regardleſs of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, when there has been divers Great Men turn'd out this Reign for <hi>Miſmanagement?</hi> Theſe muſt be Acts of Juſtice, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you'l ſay, they were all Turn'd out only for their Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G.</speaker>
               <p>Not I indeed Sir, If I ſhould ſay ſo, I ſhould wrong my Conſcience, But I believe I can unfold the Miſtery, which generally I take to be only this; all Men know the Court is divided into Factions, which ſometimes have a difference, either about their <hi>Profit</hi> or <hi>Preferment</hi> or ſomething of like Nature, when the Quarrel is broach'd one muſt overcome and perhaps the others fall into diſgarce; But they are not turn'd out for any of their Crimes, or through any principle of Juſtice
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105080:18"/>
in their Adverſarys, but only through a private peake and Quarrel, <hi>wherein Vertue, Honeſty, and the Publick Good has no Concern;</hi> For you may obſerve in the Courſe of this War that though there has been great Crimes alleag'd againſt ſome of thoſe that were turn'd out: Yet after they were diſmiſs'd their Adverſarys made no proſecution againſt them, Not for want of <hi>Malice</hi> or <hi>Proof,</hi> but as if both partys were alike Concern'd and ſo Equally afraid of the Law. Juſt as two <hi>Harlots</hi> (Pardon the Compariſon) that live together, and falling out about their Profit, the Strongeſt turns the Weakeſt out of doors; Why this is no Argument that ſhe's Vertuous that Remains in the Houſe: For both of them were <hi>Harlots</hi> before they met, <hi>Harlots</hi> while they liv'd together, and <hi>Harlots</hi> after they part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; Neither does the <hi>Prevailing Harlot</hi> follow the other with Warrants to ſend her to the houſe of Correction, becauſe 'twill alſo bring her ſelf into Jeopardy: <hi>For the ſame Law will Whip them both.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I could wiſh with all my Heart that things were better, yet ſure they cannot be ſo very bad as you ſay, becauſe there are in Office perſons of different Opinions, part <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> and part <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> and no doubt it has been Wiſdome ſo to do: For they wou'd be forward, and glad of an Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to tell each others Faults, to Weaken the Contrary party, and Strengthen their own; So that there's Cauſe to believe they have hitherto been a perfect Checque upon each others Actions, and therefore it do's not ſtand to reaſon there can be ſuch a United Cabal as you ſpeak off.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G.</speaker>
               <p>Why Sir, this is only another <hi>Court Riddle</hi> much like the former, which has alſo Confounded the Judgments of the people; yet if a Man will but Conſult Reaſon 'tis Eaſily un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded. I believe there is at Court the <hi>Church-party</hi> and the <hi>Diſſenting-party</hi> (as they call themſelves) and I Confeſs the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105080:19"/>
Argument that you bring from it ſeems ſomething plauſible, though I can by no means allow it to be true.</p>
               <p>The Philoſophers ſay, <hi>That one Experiment will knock a hundred Arguments in the head:</hi> Then Certainly your Argument cannot ſtand, For we have ſeen by long and Woful Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience that theſe partys have had no differences in the State for promoting the Honour of God, the good of their Prince and Country, and Suppreſſing Vice and Wickedneſs; <hi>For theſe indeed wou'd have been glorious Quarrels,</hi> But all their differences have been Independant of this only to promote <hi>Private Intereſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What though they ſeem to be at Variance one with another, It has hitherto been found, If any Man offers to do his Duty, and Stand up for the Publick Good, he finds no difference in them, but they are all his Mortal Enemys: <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters</hi> all alike, all ſtand firm for the <hi>Profitable Cauſe of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,</hi> to Betray their King, and Ruin their Country; This I ſay we have found by Experience, and therefore all the Arguments in the VVorld will never Refute it.</p>
               <p>VVhat though they pretend to diverſe Opinions in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, VVhat then? Do not <hi>Harlots</hi> do the ſame? Yes Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, there are <hi>Church of England Harlots, Diſſenting Harlots, Roman Catholick Harlots,</hi> &amp;c. Though theſe pretend to differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Religions, yet they are all of one <hi>Trade,</hi> and no doubt wou'd Unanimouſly agree in the Main that all <hi>Juſtices of Peace, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables, Houſes of Correction,</hi> &amp;c. ſhould be Suppreſs'd, becauſe by them their <hi>Trade is Obſtructed:</hi> So in like manner theſe Men notwithſtanding any petty Differences, Stand together in a body againſt <hi>Law and Juſtice,</hi> becauſe it tends to Mortify their Ambition and Luſts, and to hinder their Profit.</p>
               <p>But Sir, I am afraid after all that you and I are Miſtaken, and that the Court do's not Conſiſt ſo much of a Real <hi>Church of England</hi> and <hi>Diſſenting-party</hi> as of a <hi>Predominant Atheiſtical</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:105080:19"/>
                  <hi>Party,</hi> for ſo indeed they appear to be by their Actions, and it alſo agrees with our Saviours Rule, <hi>That the Tree is known by its Fruit;</hi> For 'tis Certainly very fooliſh, and Contradictory to ſay, <hi>That a Corrupt and Wicked Man has any real Religion,</hi> let him pretend to what he will; ſo that theſe that Divide themſelves into two diviſions, under the Maſquerade of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> do plainly appear to be but one and the ſame party, whoſe <hi>Moralls</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> is ſuch that they can truly be of no <hi>Religion or Church,</hi> unleſs they be of the <hi>Synagogue of Satan.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Why Sir, I know not what to ſay to it, you have ſuch an odd way of Arguing; yet methinks 'tis Strange the Nations Grievances ſhou'd arrive to ſo great a pitch (as you ſay they are at) with ſo little Oppoſition; Why 'tis in Effect Charging the whole Body of the People to be a Company of <hi>Sleepy, Senceleſs, Sotts and Fools,</hi> that have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Priviledges,</hi> they did not make more <hi>Power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> and <hi>Formidable Complaints</hi> to the <hi>Parliament:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I muſt ſtill tell you 'tis very unintelligible to me to believe that Matters can be ſo bad as you ſay, and the People ſo quiet, <hi>Who ſo bravely like Engliſhmen Stood up for their Laws and Priviledges in the late Reign.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G.</speaker>
               <p>Certainly Sir, the Peoples Patience ought not to be us'd as an Argument to Continue their Grievances, I'm ſure that is an odd way of Arguing: However I Wave it, and for your Satisfaction ſhall give you ſome Reaſons why they have hitherto been ſo quiet under their Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Revolution</hi> (you know) was wrought by the General Conſent of the People who for many Years paſt have had great and Juſt Apprehenſions, and fears, of <hi>Popery and Slavery:</hi> The War was alſo Engag'd in by our general Approbation, ſo that having a King after our
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105080:20"/>
own Heart, ſo generally Belov'd, a known Proteſtant, and Engag'd in a War that we ſo long wiſh'd for, every Man then ſlept Secure, thinking all things were ſafe, <hi>becauſe the Head was Sound;</hi> and the <hi>Court</hi> likewiſe, and all the <hi>vaſt Troops of their Dependants</hi> Cry'd up the ſame thing (as indeed they had good Reaſon) <hi>for Matter's went well wish them;</hi> So that the generallity of the People being Voyd of Miſtruſt never Troubled themſelves about <hi>State Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> but minded their Private Affairs, and with great Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs paid the <hi>Taxes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereas in the late Reign, the King being a known <hi>Papiſt,</hi> all the People in general were poſſeſt with Jealouſy, and even the very Cobler in his Stall wou'd Eagerly En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after News, and thought himſelf Concern'd to know the Affairs of the <hi>Court:</hi> So that the Actions of the <hi>State,</hi> and the Peoples Knowledge of it, went hand in hand, For we ſee they were forewarn'd to make ſuch proviſion as they did to diſappoint their deſigns; For then <hi>the King Acted openly with his Court,</hi> but now <hi>the Court Acts private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without the King,</hi> by hiding each others Crimes, and the Peoples Grievances from him, <hi>having had the great advantage of His Majeſty's Abſence about Six Months in every Year during the Courſe of this War.</hi> And this I take to be a Principal reaſon why the generallity of the People have been ſo quiet from making any <hi>Publick complaints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But then it may be further obſerv'd there's a great Difference between the Grievances of the la<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>e, and thoſe of this Regin; The one was the Endeavouring to take away our <hi>Laws,</hi> to bring in <hi>Papery,</hi> which all the Nation were Enemies to: Rich and Poor, Good and Bad, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and Vitious, Saint and Sinner, all were <gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Enemys to <hi>Popery:</hi> Beſides it would take away abundance of <hi>Eſtates of Abbey-lands</hi> which was ſo great and general an
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105080:20"/>
Allarm to the whole Nation, but Eſpecially to the <hi>Clergy,</hi> That <hi>thoſe Celebrated, Simple, Threadbare Doctrines of Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive-Obedience, Non-Reſiſtance, &amp;c. were Inſtantly frighted out of the Kingdom, and never heard of ſince:</hi> Nay, I dare Affirm, the very <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves (tho 'twas to Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce their own Religion) wou'd ha been very unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to part with any of theſe Eſtates.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But what are our Grievances now! VVhy not about</hi> Popery; <hi>They only conſiſt of</hi> Pure Downright Cheating the Publick; <hi>And, Sir,</hi> to our Eternal Shame and Infamy, <hi>I muſt tell you,</hi> That multitudes of Poperies Zealous and Mortal Enemies, are Dear and Intimate Friends to this. <hi>Nay, to ſpeak in General, there are few Men but what will much rather chuſe to take Part in it, than make Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint againſt it;</hi> for indeed the Nation is miſerably De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch'd by the horrid Naſty Fogs and Fumes of the Courts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſavoury Noyſome Luſts.</p>
               <p>But now, after all this Mighty <hi>Hate to Popery,</hi> and <hi>Love to Cheating,</hi> the Conſequence of both is much alike; For if our Preſent Grievances, viz. <hi>Cheating the Puhlick,</hi> be well follow'd, <hi>the People will ſoon be made Beggars and Bankrupts,</hi> and then <hi>Poverty and Slavery</hi> will be found as True and Proper a Saying, as <hi>Popery and Slavery:</hi> And therefore, (to Speak in your own Stile) I think there's many that do well deſerve the Character of <hi>Sleepy, Sence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Sots</hi> and <hi>Fools;</hi> But eſpecially thoſe Great Ones that have got Vaſt Eſtates by Fraud, Treachery, &amp;c. Sure they are Beſotted with a WITNESS, Fondly to Fancy, that they ſhall hold their Ill-got-Goods by Vertue of thoſe Wholeſome Laws that they have Conſtantly broke to Get them, <hi>This, I ſay, is a ſtrange Paradox.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:105080:21"/>
And now, pray, Who wou'd you have to omplain of Grievances, and eſpecially of theſe ſort of Grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that are ſo generally Belov'd by thoſe that ſhou'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs them: You ſee a very conſiderable part of the Nation are Silent, for Reaſons I ſpoke of juſt now; and as for the Popularity, or Middle ſort, <hi>viz.</hi> Traders, Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen, &amp;c. who are the Main Body of the People, they know their Grievances in General, but can tell no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in Particular, where to fix the Fault; and ſo cannot Complain, but only <hi>Grumble, Mutter</hi> and <hi>Murmur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now, if a <hi>Self-intereſted Man</hi> won't Complain, and if an <hi>Ignorant Man</hi> can't Complain, and if a <hi>Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Man</hi> (that knows the Strength and Power of the Corrupt Party) dare not Complain; Pray, Who wou'd you have to Complain at all? Certainly, 'tis ſo far from being ſtrange (as you ſay) that ſo few have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd, That 'tis a great wonder to me, how any have had ſo much <hi>GRACE</hi> or <hi>CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RAGE</hi> to open their Mouths againſt <hi>Corruption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For who d'think ſhou'd Complain of a <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal and Gainful Grievance?</hi> You ſee the <hi>Deſtruction of our Coyn</hi> went forward all this Reign, and had even juſt <hi>destroy'd the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> before our <hi>Long-Headed-Stateſmen</hi> did take the Pains to put <hi>King or Parliament</hi> in Mind to Redreſs it; This cou'd not poſſibly be through Ignorance: no, there was too much Money got by the Evil: and when the Trade cou'd be carried on no longer, <hi>Then they all Cry'd out, like Patriots of their Countrey, to have it Redreſs'd.</hi> So that for this <hi>Branch of the Nations Ruin,</hi> we may alſo Thank the <hi>Court,</hi> and Pray God we get well over it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:105080:21"/>
Theſe are all Miſerable and Deſtructive Evils, that this Poor Nation at preſent Staggers under, only for want of the Early, Conſtant and Impartial <hi>Execution of Juſtice</hi> to Encourage Virtue, and Suppreſs Vice. <hi>But it ſeems this has been contrary to the deep Maxims of our Pollicy, and ſo has hitherto been omitted:</hi> And thus I think I have ſhew'd you, why ſo few have Publickly Complain'd, tho' the Nation is ſo Loaded with Grievances. But I had almoſt forgot one Party<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that is the <hi>Jacobites;</hi> and, I hope, you wou<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d not have them Complain againſt theſe Grievances: no, they had much rather forward them. For, 'tis upon theſe <hi>Shameful Corruptions</hi> they build their Hopes, and for which they Contemn and Scoff at the Government in all Publick Places, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe their Party by many Proſelytes: For no Honeſt Man is capable to Contradict them, being able to ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is Good of the Court: Whereas, had Juſtice been duly Adminiſtred, and Vice and Wickedneſs Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and Suppreſs'd (which we had, and have Power e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to do) there cou'd not have been at this day a <hi>Proteſtant Jacobite</hi> left in the Nation; For, the Juſtice and Equity of the Government muſt needs long before this, have Brought them all over from <hi>Stubborn Folly,</hi> and made them <hi>Proſelytes to their own Intereſt, and to Common Sence,</hi> as well as Loving and Loyal Subjects to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty.</p>
               <p>And now, Sir, ſince you have Ask'd me ſeveral Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I ſhall beg leave Calmly to Ask you one, and, that is, Pray to what end were your Honours and Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Conſerr'd upon you? <hi>Were they, d'think only to get a Great Eſtate to leave to your Posterity?</hi> Certainly the Duty's Incumbent on ſuch Offices cannot have ſo
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105080:22"/>
poor a Center, but muſt aim at much Higher and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler Objects, if a Man wou'd rightly conſider them; But I ſhall not detain you at preſent with an Account how Great and Extenſive they are, not doubting your Knowledge therein; however, in point of Friendſhip, I cannot but put you in Mind<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>That (as a Privy-Councellor) you have Power to <hi>Adminiſter Juſtice,</hi> but no Power to <hi>Obſtruct</hi> it.</p>
               <p>You have Power to put the <hi>Law in Execution,</hi> but you have no Power to <hi>Pervert it, or render it uſeleſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You have power to puniſh any <hi>Capital Publick Offender,</hi> but you have no Power to <hi>Conceal his Crimes, Protect him, and let him Eſcaps Puniſhment:</hi> For, in doing it, you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray the <hi>King,</hi> and take from Him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> His <hi>Regal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Power,</hi> and Rob the People of their <hi>Laws and Liberties.</hi> For you are to conſider, that in hearing the Crimes of a <hi>Publick Offender,</hi> your Power only extends to Hear and Examine that Cauſe in Truſt for your <hi>King and Country,</hi> that <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> may take place; <hi>and a Lord Chief Juſtice may as lawfully preſume to Pardon</hi> MURDER, <hi>or Forgive one of my Debtors, or a Juſtice of Peace to Compound that Fellony whereby I am Robb'd, as you to Protect, or Acquit any Publick Offender.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In ſhort, In all your publick Stations, you'r only a <hi>Truſtee for your Prince and Country,</hi> to promote the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of both; and you are Anſwerable to both, in this World, as well as to God in the next, how you Diſcharge theſe Truſts; <hi>and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I fear many</hi> MEN <hi>have moſt Dreadful Reckonings to make on this Account.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:105080:22"/>
Therefore Sir, I do Earneſtly Adviſe you to take a Reſolution to Save your Self from the Terrible Burden of this Guilt, and <hi>Rouſe a Noble Engliſh Genius, and ſtand up for the Honour of God, and the Good of your Prince and Country</hi> (whoſe true Intereſts are Inſeparable) <hi>that Juſtice may be Adminiſtred, Vertue Incourag'd, and Vice and Wickedneſs Puniſh`d and Suppreſs`d:</hi> For if you Sincerely Study True Pollicy; God will ſurely Inſtruct, and put you in the Right Way; Otherwiſe, you may ſtill Continue to Wander, as you have Hitherto done: But after all, do not Entertain any fond opinion, that a Private Company of Men <hi>can poſſibly hold their Riches in the midſt of a Ruin'd Nation;</hi> No, Certainly they muſt be Ruin'd alſo: For if there's any Law, that will do their buſineſs; if not, They'l only have the pleaſure of being Plunder'd laſt, by an Inrag'd and Furious Popularity: For (as 'tis ſaid in Job,) <hi>Fire ſhall Conſume the Tabernacles of Bribery.</hi> If God has ſaid it, We may affirm it; and Pawn our Lives and Souls, 'twill be done if Attonement be not made.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed in the Year 1696.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
