<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Select arguments and reasons against popery by R. Baxter.</title>
            <author>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-12">2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27036</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1406</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36645</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15747333</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15747333</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104624</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A27036)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104624)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1164:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Select arguments and reasons against popery by R. Baxter.</title>
                  <author>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: t.p. torn with loss of imprint date.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104624:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104624:1"/>
            <p>Select
Arguments
AND
REASONS
AGAINST
POPERY.</p>
            <p>By R. Baxter.</p>
            <p>LONDON<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
Printed in the Year. <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:104624:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104624:2"/>
            <head>Select
Arguments,
AND
REASONS, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>POpery,</hi> is a certain heap or mixture of many grievous Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours
in the Doctrine of Faith, Government, and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
expreſſed in the Authorized Writings of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts,
eſpecially in their Decretals and Counſels<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting
the Chriſtian Religion which they profeſs, The whole
being denominated from that one Falſhood, The Pope of <hi>Rome</hi>
is the Univerſal Biſhop, and viſible Head of the Univerſal Church
and Chriſts Vicar General on Earth, and that, that only is the
Catholick Church, and thoſe only Catholicks that ſo believe;
For the Papiſts profeſſing to be Chriſtians do firſt own the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
of Chriſtian Doctrine, and then corrupt it, and contradict
it by ſuper-adding this Fardle of their own Inventions; Now to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104624:3"/>
ſhew how dangerous ſuch their opinion is, be pleaſed to conſider
theſe Arguments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argument.</hi> 1. Thoſe Doctrines which are ſounded upon a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious
falſhood and reſolved into it, are not a ſafe way to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
but ſuch are the Doctrines which we call <hi>Popery,</hi> Therefore
<hi>Popery</hi> is no ſafe way to Salvation;</p>
            <p>As for the minor the Papiſts confeſs, they are founded on and
reſolved into the Doctrine of the Popes infallibility, or at leaſt
his Counſels, but that this is a notorious falſhood is evident from
their Hiſtories of both Popes and counſels that have erred, and
their own confeſſion, I mean, whilſt one part of them do confeſs
that the Pope may err (as the <hi>French</hi>) and the other (that is the
<hi>Italians</hi> and <hi>Spaniards</hi>) that a counſel may err<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nay Pope <hi>Adrian</hi>
the 6<hi>th.</hi> (whoſe word fure may be taken in this caſe of himſelf)
wrote his Judgement of it, acknowledging that a Pope may err.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> are not agreed amongſt themſelves either
Clergy or Layity about the very fundaments of their Faith, o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
matters which they make neceſſary to Salvation, for they main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
that we muſt receive our Faith and the Scriptures upon the
Authority of the infallible church, and yet are not agreed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
themſelves nor ever like to be what the infallible Church
is, whether in the Pope, or in a counſel or in both together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 3, <hi>Popery</hi> is a new deviſed way to Heaven, ſuch as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles
never knew, nor the Church after them for many a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
year (in the main parts of it) And therefore can be n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> s<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e
way to Salvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 4. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> are the greateſt Schiſmaticks on Earth,
moſt deſperately rending the Church, and ſeparating themſelves
from the main body thereof, and lay the grounds of a continual
Schiſm in making a new Head, and center of the unity of the
Church; The Catholick Church for many hundred years after
Chriſt was that body of Chriſtians who were united only in
Chriſt the Head, and held communion in the Fundament<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ls of
Faith and Worſhip and had no moral Head or Center but the
Worldly greatneſs of the City of <hi>Rome</hi> occaſioning the uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104624:3"/>
of her Biſhop he would needs make himſelf the Center of
union and Univerſal Head, and is not this the vileſt Schiſm that
Men can be guilty of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. The Doctrine of <hi>Popery</hi> derogateth from the written
word of God, and ſetleth the decrees of Men above it, enabling
them to contradict it's moſt expreſs Inſtitutions, and therefore is
no way to ſalvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 6. <hi>Popery</hi> is Idolatry teaching Men to worſhip the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
with divine Worſhip, as the conſecrated Hoſt or Bread in
their Maſs, 'Tis true they tell us, That it is no longer Bread but
the Body of Chriſt, but this is a Fiction, conſider theſe Reaſons,
If the Bread were Chriſts real Body, then Chriſt had two real
bodies, a ſenſe and an inſenſible body both at once, and then the
Apoſtles did tear Chriſts true fleſh, and draw out his blood as
well as the <hi>Jews,</hi> and thence it will follow that Chriſts glorified
body is corruptible, and may be digeſted by a Mans Stomach and
become ſinful as being a natural part of a ſinner, for the Bread
and Wine do nouriſh us, and turn into our ſubſtance, and that
a Creature (the Baker or Prieſt) may make God, and that the
Scriptures are not true, which witneſs that the Heavens muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
him till the reſtitution of all things, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 21. with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
other abominable abſurdities.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 7. The Doctrine of Popery teacheth Men to turn the
moſt of Gods Worſhip into meer unreaſonable ceremonies and
vain formalities of Mans deviſing, and who can think that the
holy and bleſſed God will be delighted in their vain bablings and
childiſh cantings, and affected repetitions of words, and ſaying and
hearing we know not what.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 8. Popery is maintained moſt commonly by moſt wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
and abominable means, the very buſineſs they ſo much contend
for, Is Pomp, Greatneſs, Dominion, yea Tyranny in the World,
ſo that 'tis evidently pride, vain glory, and covetouſneſs ſets them
on, for the ſupport of which, they care not what wickedneſs
they venture: As diſpenſing with the vileſt ſins, forging miracles,
raiſing egregious lyes, and butchering where they have power,
thoſe that oppoſe them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:104624:4"/>
               <hi>Argument</hi> the 9<hi>th.</hi> If all that part of the Chriſtian World
that was out of reach of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire did never ſubmit to
the Soveraignty of the Pope, Then hath he not been ſucceſſively
or at any time the actual Head of the Univerſal Church, But 'tis
certain vaſt numbers of Chriſtians amongſt the <hi>Indians, Abiſſines,
Poles, Muſcovites</hi> and other parts did never ſo ſubmit, Therefore
the Pope was never actual Head of the Univerſal Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argument</hi> the 10<hi>th.</hi> The Rule or Teſt of the Faith of <hi>Papiſts</hi>
never had a real being, or no ſucceſſion from the Apoſtles, and
therefore their Faith and Church hath either no real being, or
no ſuch ſucceſſion, for either general Counſels, or Popes, or the
Church eſſential (as they call it, that is the whole Body) is the rule
of their Faith, if it be general Counſels. 1. They had no being
from the Apoſtles till the counſel of <hi>Nice,</hi> therefore the Rule of
the <hi>Papists</hi> Faith was then unborn. 2. Yea the truth is, they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
had a being in the World, for that of <hi>Nice</hi> was ſo far from
being Univerſal, that it had but one or two Biſhops preſent, but
thoſe of the Empire, nor was there any thing like a free general
counſel ſince the days of the Apoſtles to this day; If it be the
Pope that is the rule of their Faith, then their Faith hath been
interrupted, yea and turned to Hereſie and Infidelity when the
Pope hath ſo turned. But laſtly, If it be the major part of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal
Church, 'tis known that two to one are againſt them, or
at leaſt the greateſt part, if we reckon (as we muſt) the Greek
Church; and all others profeſſing chriſtianity in the World, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
by that Rule their belief in the Papal Soveraignty is falſe, and
yet beſides it would be hard if a man muſt be of no belief till he
have brought the World to pole for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 11. If ſence be either fallible or infallible, the Pope is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible,
but ſence is either fallible or infallible, <hi>Ergo,</hi> The conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
is proved thus, If ſence be fallible, the Pope is infallible,
and all his Church, for their ſenſes and the Apoſtles and their
Followers too muſt be fallible, but if ſenſe be infallible, ſtill the
Pope and his counſel are, becauſe the common ſenſes of all ſound
men take that for Bread and Wine which they expreſly ſay (as <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
fide</hi> to be believed) Is not Either Bread or Wine.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:104624:4"/>
Reaſons to reſolve any conſiderate Man againſt Popery.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. The Faith or Religion of <hi>Papiſts</hi> as deſcribed by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
is ſo far from infallibility, that it is utterly uncertain unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible
and meer contradiction and confuſion, a changeable
thing that no Man knoweth whether he have it or not, nor when
he hath it all, but whoever hath it, hath certainly a hodge podge
of Truth and Falſhoood.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. Their Papacy which eſſentiateth their Church is a hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid
uſurpation of Chriſts own Prerogative, and of an office to do
that which is incomparably above the power or capacity of any
mortal Man to take care of all the Souls on Earth, and rule the
Antipodes, and in thoſe parts of the World which he hath no
knowledge of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3. The ſaid Papacy is an arrogant uſurpation of the
power of all Chriſtian Princes and Paſtors, or of a power over
them never given by Chriſt, It ſetteth up a Kingdom in a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
and taketh from Paſtors the power which Chriſt gave them
over their particular flocks.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 4. Their Church is oft eſſentially unholy, Heretical and
wicked, becauſe the Pope is often ſo, who is an eſſential part of
it, and therefore it is not the Holy Catholick Church, for whole
Counſels have upon examination judged their Popes to be Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,
Schiſmaticks, Adulterers, Blaſphemers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that
Church cannot be holy, whoſe eſſential part is ſo unholy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 5. Their Doctrine is not only contrary to many expreſs
Texts of holy Scripture, but alſo contrary to it's ſelf, one Pope
and one counſel having decreed one thing, and another the clean
con<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 6. Their Religion tendeth greatly to mortifie Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
and turn it into a dead Image by deſtroying much of its
life and power; by befriending Ignorance, locking up the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
blind devotion and external formalities.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 7. They plead for a Church that never had a being in
the World, that is all Chriſtians Headed by one Pope, when all
the Chriſtian World did never take him for their Head, nor were
governed by him to this day.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:104624:5"/>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 8. They dreadfully injure the holy Scriptures; as if Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
Chriſt, and the Prophets and Apoſtles in thoſe ſacred Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords
had not skill or will to ſpeak intelligibly, and plainly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver
to us the Doctrines neceſſary to Salvation, but they make
their voluminous counſels more intelligible and ſufficient as if they
had done it better, And whereas Men muſt only diſcern God<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
Laws, and judge cauſes by the Law, they make themſelves Judge<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
of the Law it ſelf; by which they muſt one day be judged.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 9 Every honeſt Godly <hi>Proteſtant</hi> may be as ſure tha<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Popery</hi> is falſe, as he is, that he is himſelf ſincere, and loveth God<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
and is truly willing to obey him; and no Man can turn <hi>Papiſt</hi> with<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
ou<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſelf contradiction, who is a true Chriſtian, and an honeſt man
for b<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> turning <hi>Papiſt</hi> he confeſſeth himſelf to be before a fall
heart<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Hypo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rite, for it is a part of <hi>Popery</hi> to believe that non<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
in a ſtate of Salvation but the Subjects of the Pope, or Mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers
of the Papal Church, and conſequently that no others hav<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
true Faith, Repentance, or Love to God, all therefore that kno<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
their own hearts to be truly devoted to God are ſafe from Pope<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
And ſince it is agreed on both ſides that none ought or can tu<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
Papiſts, but ungodly Hypocrites, no wonder if ſuch are delud<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
by the moſt palpable deceits and forſaking of God when they h<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
before forſaken him.</p>
               <p>To conclude this Paper, there is yet one Argument behind <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quisite
againſt Popery, for it's profeſſors plead not as other p<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
only by the Tongue, but by exciting Princes and States <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt
us, and diſputing with the Faggot, or Ha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>chet in th<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
hands, and therefore if we have not Arguments that will con<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
a Navy, an Army, or a Powder-plot, we may ſtill happen to <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
worſted by them. Which I beſeech the Lord for the ſake of
Church, and the honour of the Goſpel to prevent.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
