<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A postscript to a book published last year entituled Considerations on Dr. Burnet's Theory of the earth</title>
            <author>Beaumont, John, d. 1731.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-01">2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27209</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1622</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29033</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10797719</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10797719</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45950</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A27209)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45950)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1415:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A postscript to a book published last year entituled Considerations on Dr. Burnet's Theory of the earth</title>
                  <author>Beaumont, John, d. 1731.</author>
                  <author>Burnet, Thomas, 1635?-1715. Telluris theoria sacra.</author>
                  <author>Beaumont, John, d. 1731. Considerations on Dr. Burnet's Theory of the earth.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Randal Taylor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Page 7 signed: John Beaumont, Jun.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Creation.</term>
               <term>Earth --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45950:1"/>
            <head>A POSTSCRIPT TO A BOOK Published the Last Year, ENTITULED CONSIDERATIONS ON Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s Theory of the Earth.</head>
            <p>MANY Persons, since the publishing my <hi>Conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations on Dr.</hi> Burnet's <hi>Theory of the Earth,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving used Cavillations against some parts of them, <hi>viz.</hi> where I seem to leave some things in Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which they will needs have to proceed from Enthusiasm: Some having done this in my Presence, and Others where I have not been present, as I have been Inform'd by many Friends: I have thought fit, by printing this Paper, to bring the Matter above Board, and to see what may be said in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45950:2"/>
the Case; and try whether we cannot sound the Depths of these Mens Thoughts as they take upon them to judge others.</p>
            <p>To disswade a Man from leaving any thing he writes, or discourses on, in Mystery, I remembred to have read an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Writer of <hi>Politick Essays,</hi> who says, <hi>That a man renders himself as lyable to Censure, by offering to maintain a Mysterious Truth, as an open Falsehood;</hi> and therefore he dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swades Men, by all means, from meddling in Mysteries. I remembred also that <hi>Ecclesiastical Maxim</hi> of <hi>Melancthon; So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent homines aut odisse aut superlè contemnere quae non intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt.</hi> I called to mind the old Tricks, both of <hi>Aesop's Fox,</hi> which cried out, that the Grapes were sour, which were out of his Reach; and of his ill natur'd Curr in the Manger, which would not permit the Horse to ear Oats, when he cared not to eat them himself. I remembred likewise those wretches mentioned in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> who damm'd up <hi>Isaac's Wells,</hi> and would not permit him to draw Waters for his Use, though themselves made no use of them. <hi>Moses</hi> does not say, if the <hi>Paschal Lamb</hi> cannot be eaten by your self, it must presently be burnt; but first call in your Neighbour, and if he cannot eat it, then let it be committed to the Fire. And as for some things which may seem obscurely intimated in my Work, I well know there are many Men in the World who will fully apprehend what they import; but if all do not, I cannot help it. Are there not <hi>Tacenda</hi> on many Accounts, in the common Practice of Life? And why may there not be in some parts of Learning? It's known that the greatest Writers among Mankind have left a great Part of what they have writ, wrapt up in Enigma's; or however they have otherwise exprest themselves, it's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible only to a few. Are <hi>Roger Bacon, Picus Miran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dula, Joannes Trithemius, Cornelius Agrippa, Joannes Reuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> our Dr. <hi>Dee,</hi> any of the whole Tribe of <hi>Hermetick</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:45950:2"/>
               <hi>Philosophers,</hi> or any Masters of a Contemplative Life a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Jews, Gentiles,</hi> or <hi>Christians,</hi> I say, are any of these open in all things they write, so that every Man acquainted in Common School Learning, or any Man, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted in no more, understands them? Or have the Writers of the Scriptures, or <hi>Christ</hi> himself thought fit, still to be open to every Man's Capacity? Because in the first Chapter of my <hi>Considerations,</hi> I mention a <hi>Promethean Arcanum Astrologicum,</hi> and a <hi>Seven Reed Pipe</hi> of <hi>Pan.</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a farther Explanation, some will needs have This to be Enthusiasm: Now as for the <hi>Promethean Arcanum Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicum, Prometheus</hi> is known to have been Famous for some notable Skill he had in <hi>Astrology,</hi> as a School-Boy may read in any <hi>Mythologist:</hi> And the <hi>Assyrians</hi> are known to have been the most Famous of any Men in the World, for <hi>Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy,</hi> and their most <hi>Ancient Astronomical Observations,</hi> which Sciences they are said to have first learnt of <hi>Prometheus.</hi> And there are many Men living in the World, who know themselves to have been touch'd by the <hi>Rod of Prometheus,</hi> or of some Priest of <hi>Apollo</hi> touch before at the Chariot of the Sun; whereby They are become animated with a lively and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrating Aetherial Spirit; whereas before they were as Lumps of Clay, conversant only with the outside Barks of things: And in Réference to <hi>this,</hi> Men may remember the <hi>Epitaph</hi> of the Antient Poet <hi>Colophonius Phoenix</hi> on <hi>Ninus,</hi> where reflecting on him for his giving himself wholly over to the Vanities and Pleasures of this Life; among other things he says thus of him;
<q>
                  <l>Astra nunquam vidit, nec forsitan id optavit</l>
                  <l>Ignem apud Magos sacrum non excitavit;</l>
                  <l>Deum nec virgis attigit, &amp;c.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:45950:3"/>
It's of this Fire of the <hi>Magi</hi> that <hi>Zoroaster</hi> speaks in the <hi>Oracles. Quando videris Ignem Sacrum, forma sine Collucen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, totius per profundum Mundi, Audi Ignis Vocem.</hi> And I know Men in our Nation, who have seen this Fire, and hearkned with Dread to the Voice of it.</p>
            <p>And even in the <hi>Temple</hi> of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> as in the <hi>Holy Place,</hi> on the North side stood, on a Table, the Twelve Loaves of <hi>Shewbread,</hi> denoting, as <hi>Josephus</hi> tells us, the <hi>Twelve Signs</hi> of the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> and having a Crown of Gold about them, said by the <hi>Jews,</hi> to denote the Crown of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. So on the South side of it, there stood the <hi>Candlestick</hi> with <hi>Seven Lamps,</hi> denoting the <hi>Seven Planets,</hi> six of which were turned bending towards the <hi>Lamp</hi> in the <hi>middle,</hi> and that towards the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> where the Mystery lay. And how far this may relate to some Astrological <hi>Arcanum,</hi> I shall leave it to Men acquainted in an apt dispensation of <hi>Types,</hi> and to those Masters of a contemplative Life, who have pass'd Proficients in the most sublime Science of <hi>Mystical Divinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Seven Reed Pipe</hi> of <hi>Pan,</hi> a Man that knows any thing of <hi>Hieroglyphical Philosophy,</hi> knows that <hi>Pan</hi> is always drawn with a <hi>Pipe</hi> of <hi>Seven Reeds,</hi> and that those <hi>Seven Reeds</hi> denote the <hi>Seven Planets.</hi> And certainly <hi>Virgil</hi> had heard this <hi>Pipe,</hi> and could play upon it himself; when, in the Person of <hi>Corydon,</hi> he said to <hi>Alexis,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Est mihi disparibus septem compacta Cicutis</l>
                  <l>Fistula,—</l>
                  <l>Having said before to him,</l>
                  <l>Mecum unà in Sylvis imitabere Pana canendo.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And why must it be expected that I should be more expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natory concerning this <hi>Pipe</hi> than <hi>Virgil?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:45950:3"/>
Indeed, I make no doubt, but there have been, and are still many Men in the World, who through an affected Sublimity in Writing, or a Vanity of seeming Knowing in what others are not, have often been sinking themselves in Mystery, where, in truth, there is no Bottom. And again, on the other hand, I am as well satisfied, that there have been, and are still many Men in the World, who being deeply sick of a <hi>Philautian Arrogancy,</hi> to keep up their Repute for Learning among the Vulgar, have gone about to perswade them, that there is nothing valuable in Learning, forsooth, but what is known to their Learned Selves, though, in truth, there are Parts of Learning of far greater Excellency than any they ever came acquainted withal. If a meer <hi>Grammarian,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his Boys about him, should hear one <hi>Logician</hi> say to another, that a <hi>Syllogism</hi> contains a <hi>majus extremum,</hi> a <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus extremum,</hi> and a <hi>medium;</hi> to make himself seem some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body among his Boys, he may say, that this is but <hi>Cant, Ostentation,</hi> and <hi>Enthusiasm.</hi> For there are Men, who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing of some Sciences, and thinking it Shame to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess their Ignorance of any thing, or seeking a Subterfuge, or solacing themselves in their Want of knowledge, make their Boast, that those things they know not, are but Trifles, of little or no Use. But, as <hi>Terence</hi> says, <hi>It's no wonder if a Whore acts <unclear>impudently</unclear>.</hi> And are there not many Realities in Nature, which cannot be brought under every Man's Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension? A Man may talk long enough to a Person, born blind, of Light, Colours, and a Sun; but he shall never make him frame a Conception of them. You will say, we are not Blind, we have more Learning than your self, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you must not obtrude this on us. Be it so, you are more learned many Ways; yet if a Child tells a blind Man that there is a Sun, Light, and Colours, and the blind Man will not believe him, the Child cannot but smile at him for it, though the blind Man may have a sound Sense other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45950:4"/>
and the Child is but a Child. And I say, there are many Truths in Nature, which cannot be known but by Experience (as all Masters of a Contemplative Life testifie) and that the greatest Man of Parts in the World cannot ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend them, without having had a peculiar and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Initiation for taking Knowledge of them; according to what <hi>Zoroaster</hi> says in the <hi>Oracles, Est quoddam intelligibile, quod oportet te intelligere mentis flore,</hi> (by an esflorescent Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess of Mind.) The Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> tells us, that the <hi>Magia Naturalis</hi> is <hi>a Setting of Forms a Work.</hi> Now I would fain have any Man, who has not seen an Operation in that kind, to tell me (if he can) the Meaning of That; but I know it impossible.</p>
            <p>We read of <hi>Socrates,</hi> that having perused the Works of <hi>Heraclitus,</hi> he said, what he understood of them was Excellent, and therefore he believed that what he did not understand of them was so too. And though I pretend not to any Excellency of Writing, I hope, what I have openly offered in my Considerations, may be thought tolerably Plausible by indifferent Judges; and if I leave a few Things Veil'd, I think there may be no great Reason for Censure. Some may object that if we give Way to Obscure Writing, all Enthusiasm breaks in upon us, and we know not how to distinguish betwixt the one and the other. To this I can only say, that if, when a Man reasons Openly, he reasons Soundly, and Writes in a Free and Unaffected Manner, I think it may be a rational Inducement for us to believe, that though sometimes, for Reasons known to himself, he leaves some few Things in Mystery, there may be some worthy Learning contained under them, which he conceives not fit to be Openly explained. So let any Man of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment read the <hi>Tract</hi> of <hi>Joannes Reuchlin, De Verbo mirifico,</hi> or his other Works; and though in many Places he finds him involv'd in Mystery, that he is not understood by him;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45950:4"/>
yet I believe, by what he has Writ openly, and his Way of Delivery, the Reader will be convinc'd, that he is no Muddy-brain'd Enthusiast, using an affected Obscurity, to beget Admiration in his Readers, for his Seeming deep Reach into Mysteries to others unknown. And so I may say of a multitude of others, of the like kind; Men whom a great Insight in the low <unclear>Circumstances</unclear> of human Life, had made truly humble, so that they could be no ways guilty of so poor a Vanity.</p>
            <p>Having been thus far Explanatory in this Matter, I shall little value any Man's Censure in such Cases: Nay, I shall be so far from dealing precariously with him for his favourable Opinion, that I shall freely come wi<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h him to this Unexcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable Accommodation, <hi>viz.</hi> That we laugh at each other by Consent, and let him pass for the Idiot, who laughs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Just Cause. And I shall conclude with <hi>Bede,</hi> who was Clamour'd, and supercili<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>usly <note place="margin">De Elem. Philos. 1. <hi>2.</hi> in proaem.</note> Censured by some Men of his Time, for his searching into and writing on some Parts of Learning vulgarly not understood. <hi>Nihil de Multitudine, sed de Paucorum prolitate gloriantes, Soli Veritati insudamus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>JOHN BEAUMONT Jun.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>I recommend the following Particulars to be inserted in their proper places, in my <hi>Considerations on the Theory of the Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>BOOK</hi> 1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>Pag.</hi> 10. <hi>Lin.</hi> 20. after <hi>times</hi> read, And hence, as the preceding Age was called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>obscure,</hi> so this Age was called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>fabulous. Ib. p.</hi> 11. in the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45950:5"/>
last Line, after <hi>Mind</hi> read, And from hence sprung their Multiplicity of Gods, according to the diversified Powers of Nature. At the end of the said Chapter add the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Paragraph.</p>
               <p>I shall conclude this Point concerning the Learning of the Antients, with the <unclear>Testimony</unclear> of <hi>Averrhoes;</hi> who (as the Learned <hi>Fabricius</hi> tells <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <hi>Zoroaster</hi>) says in some part of his Works, That Philosophy was in as great Perfection among the <hi>Antient Chaldeans,</hi> as it was in the times of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stotle.</hi> Now the Testinony of this Man is the more to be valued, because he was indisputably the soundest Reasoner, and the most Learned among all the <hi>Arabians,</hi> and a great Favourer as well as Folower of <hi>Aristotle,</hi> he having writ Commentaries on his Works; so that had he not been thoroughly convinc'd of <unclear>the</unclear> height of Philosophy among the <hi>Antient Chaldeans,</hi> he would not have brought it in Competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with that in the Times of <hi>Aristotle.</hi> So again the Learned <hi>Pierius,</hi> concerning the Learning of the Antient <hi>Egyptians; Constantissimâ famâ celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">In Ep. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rog. prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missâ.</note> 
                  <hi>est, Sacerdotes</hi> Aegyptios <hi>omnem Naturae ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scuritatem adeo manifestè sibi cognitam professos, ut <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> traditam disciplinam hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditariam possiderent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 15. <hi>l.</hi> 7. after <hi>conceiving,</hi> add. And as for any other meaning in it, they would say with <hi>Trismegistus,</hi> in his <hi>Minerva Mundi; Minime posteris credenda Fabula putetur esse Chaos.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have thought on many other Additions and Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but I want Room to insert them here.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed, and are to be sold by <hi>Randal Taylor</hi> near Stationers Hall. 1694</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:45950:5"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
