<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A iustification of The city remonstrance and its vindication, or, An answer to a book written by Mr. J.P. entituled, The city remonstrance remonstrated wherein the frequent falsifyings of the said Mr. J.P. are discovered, the many charges by him laid upon the remonstrance and its vindicator, disproved, and the parity and agreement of the remonstrance ... with the propositions, declarations, remonstrances, and votes, of both or either House of Parliament manifested / by John Bellamie.</title>
            <author>Bellamie, John, d. 1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 126 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-05">2003-05 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27361</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1814</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4476</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12020759</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12020759</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52607</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A27361)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52607)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 83:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A iustification of The city remonstrance and its vindication, or, An answer to a book written by Mr. J.P. entituled, The city remonstrance remonstrated wherein the frequent falsifyings of the said Mr. J.P. are discovered, the many charges by him laid upon the remonstrance and its vindicator, disproved, and the parity and agreement of the remonstrance ... with the propositions, declarations, remonstrances, and votes, of both or either House of Parliament manifested / by John Bellamie.</title>
                  <author>Bellamie, John, d. 1654.</author>
                  <author>Price, John, Citizen of London. City remonstrance remonstrated.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Cotes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In defense of: To the Right Honourable the Lords assembled in high court of Parliament, the humble remonstrance and petition of the Lord major, aldermen, and commons of the city of London (1646), and Bellamie's A vindication of The humble remonstrance (1646); supports the Presbyterian attempt to suppress the Independents.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 48.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-01</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52607:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52607:1"/>
            <p>A
IVSTIFICATION
OF THE
City Remonstrance
AND ITS
VINDICATION.
<hi>OR,</hi>
An Answer to a Book written by M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>I. P.</hi>
Entituled,
<hi>The City Remonstrance Remonstrated.</hi> Wherein the frequent Falsifyings of the said
M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>I. P.</hi> are discovered, the many Charges by him
laid upon the Remonstrance and its Vindicator, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved,
and the parity and agreement of the Remonstrance
(especially in those particulars so much condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
by him) with the Propositions, Declarations,
Remonstrances, and Votes, of both or either
House of Parliament manifested.</p>
            <p>By JOHN BELLAMIE.</p>
            <p>LONDON,
Printed by <hi>Richard Cotes,</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:52607:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52607:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable Thomas Adams
Lord Major, and to the Right Worshipfull
the Aldermen, and the rest of the Common-Councell
of the City, LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,
Right Worshipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon the 14 of <hi>April</hi> last, you being in Court of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-councell</hi>
assembled, made choice of a Committee
of <hi>Aldermen</hi> and <hi>Commoners</hi> to prepare a draught
of <hi>A Remonstrance and Petition to both Houses of
Parliament,</hi> and to present it in Court, to be there either approved
or altered, as upon debate should be judged meet.</p>
            <p>In obedience thereunto, the said Committee upon the 20 of <hi>May</hi>
following, presented it in <hi>Common-councell,</hi> where every
branch thereof was taken apart and by it self into serious Conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
and after three dayes debating in open Court, it was by
consent and approbation of the Court finished, and upon the 26 of
<hi>May,</hi> in the name of the <hi>Lord Major, Aldermen, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-councell</hi>
presented to both Houses of <hi>Parliament.</hi> Since
which time two <hi>Libells</hi> have been Printed against the said <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrance,</hi>
the one call'd, <hi>A moderate Reply to the City
Remonstrance,</hi> the other entituled, <hi>The Interest of</hi> England
<hi>maintained;</hi> In one of which it is charged <hi>to carry a full com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance
with His Majesties wonted Declarations against the
Parliament;</hi> and in the other, <hi>That a great part of the main
Sticklers in it, are such as were alwayes backward to the
Parliament, and forced to pay their Fifth and twentieth part;</hi>
with many other foolish, foule, and false aspersions in them both:
Whereupon, (though the unmeetest, because the unablest of many
others) I adventured the <hi>Vindication</hi> of it; In answer whereof,
a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in further opposition to the said <hi>Remonstrance,</hi> one <hi>Mr. J. P.</hi>
hath since published a Book named, <hi>The City Remonstrance
Remonstrated,</hi> calling it a <hi>hard-hearted Remonstrance,</hi> and
<hi>a Remonstrance invective against the Parliament, &amp;c.</hi> And
<pb facs="tcp:52607:3"/>
in <hi>Page 29.</hi> charges mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for saying s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mething (but instances in
nothing,) <hi>concerning the King, the Lords, and the power
of the Commons, and what my carriages have been not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
long since in Common-councell, &amp;c.</hi> and doth thereby, as
it were, in a tacite way, call the Court to testifie against me. All
wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch, hath occasioned me this second time to put pen t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Paper, in a
further <hi>Justification of your Remonstrance,</hi> and also of its
<hi>Vindication,</hi> and to a clearing of my self from those many charges
of mutation and change, which (to beget a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sesteem of what I have
written in <hi>Vindication of the Remonstrance)</hi> hee hath laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
me.</p>
            <p>My intention in this my addresse unto your <hi>Lordship,</hi> to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<hi>Aldermen,</hi> and to all the rest of the <hi>Common-councell,</hi> is,
neither to exasperate you against the person of my opposite, nor yet to
seeke protection from you for my self or Books; for if what I have
written be not co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cordable to Truth and true Reason, let both mee
and them fall before my Antagonist.</p>
            <p>But being thus publ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kely charged that I should (not very long
since) speak something (but what it is, hee saith not) in <hi>Common-councell,
&amp;c.</hi> as if it were crosse or contrary to some passages in the
<hi>Remonstrance,</hi> or to what I have written in the <hi>Vindication</hi>
thereof, for saith he, <hi>It makes them that heard it, and observe
what your Carriages are now, stand with admiration and
amazement at your wheeling thus about.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oe therefore humbly crave leave to present this my <hi>Justifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of your Remonstrance, and its Vindication</hi> to your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,</hi>
and to the whole Court of <hi>Common-councell,</hi> and doe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal
to all of you in generall, and to every one of you in particular,
t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>estifie against me, if at any time since I had that undeserved
honour and happinesse to be a member of this Court, there ever fell
any one word from me, so much as savouring of such things, as by
this <hi>Mr. J. P.</hi> I am charged to speak in your presence, and I shall
ever remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordships, and this Cities servant
<hi>IOHN BELLAMIE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:52607:3"/>
            <head>To my truly Loved and Honoured
FRIEND
M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> IOHN PRICE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have perused your Book, entituled, <hi>The City
Remonstrance Remonstrated,</hi> or an answer to
my <hi>Vindication</hi> of the said <hi>Remonstrance,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
I perceive you have been very ready to receive
whatever Reports, either true or false have been broug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t unto
you conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rning my carriage in matters of Religion, even from
the day of my birth to the publishing of your Book, and
taking them upon trust, (for you have not the least knowledge
of any one of the particular<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and many of them relate, I think,
to the time before you were born,) without ever speaking one
word to me about them, (though wee are professed, and have
been long acquainted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntimate Friends, and to the best of my
knowledge and remembrance, not any time the least offensive
word ever passed between us, and now are so neare neighbors
that whenever you p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eased, in lesse then one quarter of an hour
you might freely have communicated to me whatever you h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d
a desire to bee satisfied in) you have, as I con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eive, to weaken
my esteem, and to render what I have written to bee the more
invalid, divulged them to the world.</p>
            <p>Two th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngs I desire i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> love to represent unto you in this,
First, if all that you have written of mee were true, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
wherof I shall easily prove when I come to the particulars;
<pb facs="tcp:52607:4"/>
yet I beseech you consider how irregular this your proceeding
against me is, and contrary to the rule given by our <hi>Saviour
Christ,</hi> for you and mee and all Gods people to walke by, in
Mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h. 18. 15, 16, 17. <hi>If thy brother trespasse against thee,
goe and tell him his fault between thee and him alone,
if he shall heare thee, thou hast gained thy brother,</hi> &amp;c.
and mind that of <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 15. 18. <hi>A man that bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
false witnesse against his neighbour, is a maul, a
sword, and a sharpe arrow.</hi> Secondly, I pray al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
remember how exceedingly your selfe, and all your
friends the <hi>Antipresbyters,</hi> have distasted, and by word of
mouth often with much dislike, blamed Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> for
medling with personall matters, notwithstanding his way of
writing in this kind, is much different from this of yours, as
being of practises and matters within these few years, since they
went into that <hi>way of Independency,</hi> and as hee conceives,
flowing from their principles (and not as you in this, of things
raked up through the whole course of their lives) being also
professedly to discover the errors of the times <hi>(viz Here<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies,
Blasphemies, &amp;c.)</hi> and thereby to preserve the people from
the evill of them.</p>
            <p>Now I pray you put this question seriously to your own soul,
whether the same act done in the same kind by Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi>
against the <hi>Independents, &amp;c.</hi> be a vice and blame worthy,
and y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t being done by Mr. <hi>J. P.</hi> against a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> or a
<hi>Remonstrant,</hi> be a vertue, and worthy commendation; think
seriously of it, and then receive such an answer as your owne
heart shall dictate to you.</p>
            <p>You know Mr. <hi>J. P.</hi> how carefull I was of your good name,
when about four mone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hs since a report was brought unto mee
c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ncerning some opinions of yours in matters of Religion
(whether true or false I now argue not) that presently by a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
intimate friend of yours and mine, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>James Russell,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:52607:4"/>
I did privately, without the least divulging them abroad, make
you acquainted with it: And that very morning after your
Book came forth against me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the like report was again pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely
brought unto mee in the presence of sundry witnesses;
but in s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ead of taking revenge of you (which God ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
me, Rom. 12. 19. saying, <hi>Avenge not your selves,
but rather give place unto wrath, for it is written,
Vengeance is mine, I will rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y saith the Lord)</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
by spreading them by reports, or printing them
to your d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sparagement, I did p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>esently, in the presence of
Mr. <hi>James Story,</hi> who also heard them reported, tell them
to you, remembring that of <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 1. 9. <hi>He that
repeateth a matter separateth very Friends;</hi> and desiring
to follow our Saviours counsell, <hi>Matth. 7. 12. Whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
you would that men should do to you, doe yee even
so to them;</hi> and I hope I shall ever make it a rule for me to
walk by, <hi>viz. to doe as I would be done unto, and not as
I am dealt with.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore in the examination and answering of your
Book, I will (though much provoked by you, yet) by Gods grace
indevour to be as free from pasiion or retaliation as possibly I
can, well remembring that <hi>David,</hi> when <hi>Shimei</hi> cursed and
railed upon him, observed much good from God in <hi>Shimei</hi> his
great evill, and said, <hi>So let him curse, because the Lord
hath said unto him, curse</hi> David; <hi>who shall then say,
wherefore hast thou done so? 2 Sam. 16. 10.</hi> So I heartily
desire, without the least reluctancy of Spirit against you, as
the instrument seriously to observe, and truly to bee sensible of,
whatever is from God in all that you have said, and to lay my
selfe in the dust in giving God the glory, both in the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging
of any error justly charged upon mee, and of his
mercy in my recovery. And I trust that through the goodness
of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God I shall yet get much good out of that which perhaps you
<pb facs="tcp:52607:5"/>
int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nded, and therefore divulged for mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> evill, setting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
me as a pattern in this to walke by the practice of our
<hi>Lord Christ,</hi> recorded for our example in <hi>1 Pet. 2. 21, 23.
Who when hee was reviled, reviled not againe, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
himselfe to him that judgeth righteously;</hi> and
with freedome of spirit I do heartily both praise the Lord, and
thanke you for your plaine deali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g with mee in any thing
wherein as you professe, you really and singly intended my spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
good, and pray the Lord to give you repentance, and to
pardon you in every thing wherein in this transaction you
have done otherwise.</p>
            <p>Thus with the reall dem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nstration of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y true love and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
to you, I crave your leave to goe on to the answearing of
your Book, earnestly desiring that if yet after all wee cannot
agree in judgement and opinion, we may still close together in
heart and affection, which (whatever the event shall prove)
shall alwayes bee the desire, prayer, and endeavour of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your cordially loving and
faithfull Friend
<hi>Iohn Bellamie.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52607:5"/>
            <head>A
IVSTIFICATION
OF THE
City Remonstrance,
AND ITS
VINDICATION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE first thing you quarrell withall, is the
Title of the Book, <hi>A Vindic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion, &amp;c.</hi> and
this you continue to the latter end of your
sixth Page, and (as in the Moderate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,
so here in this) you endeavour in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
termes to lay low the Remonstrance
and its Vindication in the eyes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;
As in your first page by comparing
them to <hi>a bad Cause and its Advocates,</hi> then to the <hi>Kings Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>monstrances, and their Abettors, to</hi> Absaloms <hi>reb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llion again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
his Father</hi> David, <hi>and</hi> Achitophels <hi>cunning counsell to draw the pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ple
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fter hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, to</hi> Demetrius <hi>his plea for</hi> Diana's <hi>greatnesse, and to</hi> Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> against St.</hi> Paul.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e passe by the parallel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which here you make with the
Vindicator of the City Remonstrance, and leave it wholly to the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ensure of the judicious Reader, whether there be
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52607:6"/>
any the least par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty in the things and cases by you compared, for
I had much rather abide their test and tryall, then in this to bee
a pleader of my own cause, and so I come to your application of
it in these words: <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As it was in the beginning, so it is now; witnesse the present case, A
moderate Reply to the City Remonstrance, in just<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fication of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
innocencie from the prejudice raised against them by the said Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrance,
as <hi>(say you)</hi> shall bee fully evidenced before we have d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> Two things I observe in this: first, that you say, (and
therein you lay a charge upon the City) that the City Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strance
hath raiseda prejudice against the Parliaments innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy:
And secondly, you further say, that this shall bee fully evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced
before you have done; the first is exprest, as usually you
use to doe, onely in generals, which amount to nothing: But I
pray consider with your selfe, is not Mr. <hi>I. P.</hi> a Freeman and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen
of <hi>London,</hi> one who lives, under God, in and by the Trad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
of the City, and yet so farre to forget himselfe and his duty, as
thus to asperse the City and its actions with generall, and yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just
defamations, and all this under a specious shew of a justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication
of the <hi>Parliaments innocency,</hi> when as there are clouds
of witnesses, and many of them under the Parliaments own
attestation, at all times ready to bee produced if required, of
<hi>Londons</hi> fidelity, of <hi>Londons</hi> loyalty, of <hi>Londons</hi> unparal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel'd
embowelling, and in a great measure emptying themselves,
not onely of treasure, but of blood also, and all this unwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riedly
from time to time, since the Parliament first fate, to this
very day, yea alwayes, with alacrity and freedome both of heart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
and hands, for the honour, the defence, the just and necessary oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions
of Parliament; and hath not the <hi>Honourable Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se of Lords,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> accepted and fully approved most of the particulars in the
said Remonstrance, yea, those in speciall, and by name, which
you so much oppose, <hi>viz. the suppressing of all Heresies and S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ismes,
&amp;c.</hi> and promised <hi>to take the other particulars into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir serious and
speedy consid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ration,</hi> as by their answer to that Remonstrance pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented
to them it doth appeare? and hath not the <hi>Honourable House
of Commons</hi> also received the said Remonstrance, and promised to
give an answer thereunto in due time, and not at any time since
its receiving into their Honourable House, by any p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e act ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifested
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52607:6"/>
to the world the least dislike thereof? and yet must <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s
Remonstrance</hi> by one of its own members be charged with rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
a prejudice against the <hi>Parliaments innoceney?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pray consider whether by this you doe not first charge the
<hi>House of Lords</hi> for their being well satisfied with that, which yet
you say, <hi>doth raise a prejudice against the Parliaments innocencie.</hi>
And secondly, whether you doe not prejudge the judgement of
<hi>the House of Commons,</hi> and therein breake the Priviledge of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament,
in passing such a sentence, and laying such a charge upon
that, which yet lyeth under their consideration: I onely offer
these two Quaeries to your after, or second consideration.</p>
            <p>But for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this, you say that this shall bee fully evidenced be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
you have done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> I pray remember what it is that in this you promise, and
be sure that in the particulars of it you make your Charge good,
otherwise you must not bee offended, nor take it ill, if according
to the common Proverbe, you be judged to be one of them, which
will undertake more in an houre, then you can performe in an
age. I appeal to the Reader, whether as yet, either the Moderate
reply, or this your Remonstrance Remonstrated, hath in any one
instance, which either of you have given, or in all that both of
you have done, done any thing which proves that <hi>the City Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strance</hi>
hath raised a prejudice against <hi>the Parliaments innocency;</hi> and
t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly you must needs beare with me in this, that I cannot judge
your bare word to be of that Authority, as to beleeve it because
you affirme it, especially considering <hi>the honorable House of Commons</hi>
hath not as yet passed any the least displeasing sentence against it;
and <hi>the honorable House of Lords</hi> hath declared, that they are wel sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied
with the particulars contained in it. And both House<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of
Parliament, since their receiving of this Remonstrance, have in the
Propositions sent to his Majesty for a safe &amp; w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l grounded Peace<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
even in <hi>terminis,</hi> proposed more to his Maje<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty for his R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oyall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
assent, as unto Reformation of Religion, then the Remonst<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
have desired in their second, third, and fourth Petitidus, so much
condemned by you; for the drift of all that they desire, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall
conformity of all the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> to the publike dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ipline
and doctrine set forth, or to bee set forth by Authority of
Parliament, as by reference to those three Petitions will clearely
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52607:7"/>
shew, but both Houses of Parliament in their great wisdome,
faithfulnesse, and care for the publike safety and peace of the
Kingdome, have in the fifth and sixth Articles of the Propositions
in these words thus proposed; <hi>viz.</hi> Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ic. 5. <hi>That Reformation
of Religion accordin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> by Act of Parliame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,
in such manner as both Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ses have agreed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> agree upon, after
consultation had with the Assembly of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> And Article 6 it thus
followeth; <hi>For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> much as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Kingdome<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> oblig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d by the
same Covm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to indeavo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>arest <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onjunction and unif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmity in
matters of Religion, that such unity and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in Religi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the Covenant as after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Divines of b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
Kingdomes now assembled, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> shall bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> agreed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
of Parliament of</hi> England, <hi>and by the Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rch and Kingdome of</hi>
Scotland, <hi>be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by Acts of Parliament of both Kingdomes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectively.</hi>
And therefore were I thought worthy to bee of your
Councell, I sho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld advise you to bee so inge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ous, as in this to
confesse your error, and not to imagine that you see more in the
<hi>City Remonstran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> then either one or both <hi>Houses of Parliament</hi> can
yet discerne; and for after times, I wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d perswade you to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare
the thus unjust besm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing and falsly acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sing that City
wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reof you are a member, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> amongst whom under God you
enjoy your livelihood.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e on and say,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Reply <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with adversary
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon adversary representi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hor of the said <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ooke, a lyer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> tells <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> a friend to the
Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Truly, these are fine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> if they were true, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Remonstrance, and to ingratiate the
opposer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the eyes of the people. But I pray what doe you
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, I must needs say you tread in the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Replyer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and it's very
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the book and the page
if you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and tell us the truth
you have told, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> you are called a Lyer, and where you
are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> you are a friend to the
Parliame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> be taking with chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:52607:7"/>
The next thing you fall upon, is in your fourth page, and that
is the word Humble Remonstrance, and upon this you descant in
some similitudes, as of Court complements, and Cavaliers carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age,
and then in plaine termes you call it, <hi>a Remonstrance invective
against the Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> You are full of charges, though never so false, and libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
in your expressions, though you make nothing good; I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
you thinke your selfe safe and secure, and perhaps you are so
from ever giving an accompt of these your actions to any earthly
authority: but yet methink<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the words of the ninth <hi>Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
should be of some authority to you, and beare some sway
with you, <hi>viz. Thou shalt not beare false witnesse against thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</hi>
If not against a particular person, then sure not against a
Corporation, a City whereof your self are a member.</p>
            <p>Then you are offended at these expressions, <hi>viz. Two late Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells,
published by two Anonymusses;</hi> and you aske why I call them
Libells before I prove them so.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> They were so in themselves before I named them so;
neither called I them Libells, for any of those reasons which you
would have the world beleeve I did. As first, because they are
written by an Antipresbyter; nor yet because they containe in
them lies, falsities, untruths, though all these in severall instances
are in the vindication made good against them, nor because they
are little Bookes, nor yet singly, because they are written against
the City, or because they are without the Authors Names, but for
these two last reasons joyntly and together: A Libell I call that
which is an untrue, and therefore an unjust Charge upon or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
a Person, a Corporation, a Court, without any name an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed
to make good what is there charged; and in this respect I
appeale to the Reader, whether I did not truly and justly call  them
Libells.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lastly, before you come to the body of the Booke, you have yet
another fling against the Title,</hi> A Vindication of the City Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrance,
that is, <hi>(say you)</hi> a Vindication of that which is invindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable:
<hi>And therefore (say you)</hi> better it would bee that both the City
Remonstrance, and the vindication thereof were written in ashes with
the finger of vanitie, then in marble with the pen of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> For ought I yet see, it is but one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> opinion, and 
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52607:8"/>
he none of the gravest neither, that the City Remonstrance is
invindicable, and what you have said to prove it to be so, I desire
the Reader to judge, for truly I cannot dis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ern it. But of this I
am confident, that it is app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oved by the <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rch of Scotland,</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
the Letter now in Print for all the Kingdome to see, which
was sent from the Generall Assembly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Church of Scotland,</hi> to
the <hi>Lord Major, Alderme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>London,</hi> June
18. 1646. manifesting thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> approbation of it, and thankfulness
for it. And sure I may say<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it is app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ved by the generality of
the ablest, grave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> witnesse their Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition
subscribed by eight Thous<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Hundred, thirty and four
of their Hands presented the twenty third of <hi>Iune,</hi> 1646. to the
<hi>Court of Common-Councell,</hi> giving them Thankes for it; testifying
their approbation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, and des<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing them to wait upon the
<hi>House of Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns</hi> fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir gracio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s answer to it, which Petition
is by Order of Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t since Printed. And me think<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you should
not forget that the same Remonstrance for the substance of it, was
not onely well accepted, but also graciously answered by the
<hi>House of Lords.</hi> And therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urely in the judgment of all these,
the City Remonstrance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>: But perhaps
you ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 6. 16. who was
<hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> reason.</hi> And
I make as little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, yet it is
and will be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all the Reformed Churches in <hi>Europe,</hi>
not one excep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arrells
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> is you have to
say against the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:52607:8"/>
whether in all probability the Reply, and not the Remonstrance
h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th raised those disturbances, for the Subject of the Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strance
is an earnest desire of the settlement of government, by
one Uniforme Law, for all the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> to submit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually
and alike unto, which I am sure must needs tend to peace
and quietnesse, but the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ift of the Reply is quite contrary, and
therefore without all peradventure it's this, and its abettors, and
not that and its promoters, which hath desired and occasioned
these Divisions both in Church and State.</p>
            <p>In pag. 9 you go about to shew that the <hi>Common-Councell</hi> by their
Remonstrance, <hi>did act in a direct, evident, and obvious manner against
the expresse Will and Word of God;</hi> and for proofe of this in page
11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you give us some Scriptures, and some passages in the Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rance,
which you say, or at least would have the world beleeve,
is in a direct, evident, and obvious manner against the expresse
Will and Word of God; but you never tell the reader how, or
wherein they are so, but thus you deliver them.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>LET US TRY THEN:</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>WORD OF GOD.</cell>
                     <cell>CITY REMONSTRANCE.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Rom. 14. 5.</hi> Let
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>very man bee fully
perswaded in his owne
minde.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>That as we are Subjects of one Kingdom,
so all may bee equally required</hi> (and here to
delude the Reader, you insert, without making
the least change of the character, these following
words, as if they also were in the Remonstrance;
<hi>viz.</hi> Be they perswaded in their own minds, or
not perswaded) <hi>to yeeld obedience to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
set forth, or to be set forth by the
Parliament.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Now I shall wholly all along in these your Parallels, leave it
to the judgment of the Reader to consider, whether there be such
an antipathy between these Scriptures, and those Petitions of the
Remonstrance, as in the Remonstrance, without your insertion,
they are exprest; and crave your leave in the same way of paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel,
to set the same Scriptures with some branches of the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:52607:9"/>
sent by both Houses of Parliament to the King, and other
pass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ges of Parliament and then desire your judgement, whether
they also <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a direct, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ident and obvious manner against the
expresse Will and Word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>WORD OF GOD.</cell>
                     <cell>Propositions of both Houses of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament,
<hi>Article</hi> the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Rom. 14. 5.</hi> Let
every man bee fully
perswaded in his owne
minde.</cell>
                     <cell>That r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>formation of Religion according to the
Coven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nt, bee setled by Act of Parliament, in
su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h manner as both Houses have agreed, or shall
agree upon, after consultation had with the
assembly of Divines.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>CITI REMONSTRANCE.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Rom. 14. 13.</hi> That
no man put a stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling
block or an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion
to fall, in his
b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> others way.</cell>
                     <cell>That all such Sectaries as conform not to
the publike Discipline established, or to bee
established (by Parliament, <hi>saith the Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strance,
but this you leave out,)</hi> may be fully
declared against, and some effectual course
setled for proceeding against such persons:
<hi>Here,</hi> say you, <hi>is a stumbling block<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> viz. <hi>a
menace in a brothers way.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> But why doe you leave out the beginning of that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
in the Petit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on which you cite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t tels you the meaning of the
Remonstrants, by the words all such Sectaries, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iz.</hi> Those immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately
before mentioned, as Anab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ptists, Brownists, Heretiques,
Schismaticks, Blasphemers; doe you not by omitting the menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning
of these, indeavour to del<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de the Reader?</p>
            <p>I pray put down that Petition wholly together, and let the
Reader be fairly dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t with all, and have it, as in the Remonstrance
it is exprest, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then see how it is opposite to the Scripture by
you set against it.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:52607:9"/>
I desire here also in a parallel way, to set downe the Scriptu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
by you brought, and a passage or two of the Parliaments, and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> desire your judgement, whether they also be in a direct,
evident and obvious manner, against the expresse Will and Word
of God.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>WORD OF GOD.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>Parliaments Declaration upon his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties
Declaration after the Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile
at <hi>Edgebill,</hi> Pag. 659.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="3">
                        <hi>Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 14. 13.</hi> That
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> put a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
blo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>k, or an occasion
to fall, in his brothers
way.</cell>
                     <cell>Had not his Majesty (seduced thereunto by that
Popish and Prelaticall faction) denyed his conse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t
to the Bil for the Assembly, so often by both Houses
presented to him, wee had long since manifested
to the world by a well setled reformation, our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
dislike of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>* Brownisme and Anab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ptisme.Remonstrance of the State of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
page 19.We do declare, that it is far from our purpose or
d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>sire, to let loose the golden reynes of † discipline
and government in the Church, to leave private
persons, or particular Congregations to take up
what for me of Divine Service they please, for
wee hold it requisite that there should be through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
the whole realme, a conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rmity to that Order
which the Laws enjoyne, according to the Word of
God.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t. 7 12.</hi> As you would that men
should doe unto you, so doe unt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
them, for this is the Law and the
Propheis.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Page 3.</hi> Wee will not receive im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression
of any forced construction of
the Covenant: compare this with
Page 7.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Will you never leave fals<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fying? where doe you finde any such
expression in the Remonstrance, either in Page 3, or 7. as this is,
<hi>viz.</hi> we will not receive impression of any forced construction
of the Covenant? The House of Commons in their late De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration
of the 17 of <hi>Aprill,</hi> 1646. doe say, <hi>Wee expect that the
people of</hi> England <hi>should not receive impressions of any forced constru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
of that Covenant;</hi> and in obedience thereunto, the Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strants,
doe say in page 2 and 3 of the Remonstrance, that in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suance
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52607:10"/>
of that Noble resolution of this Honourable House, for
the due observation of the Covenant, and their expectation of
conformity of the people of <hi>England</hi> thereunto, expressed in the
late Declaration, we doe resolve by the grace of God not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
impression of any forced construction thereof; and is it now
become an acting in a direct, evident and obvious manne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> against
the expresse Will and Word of God, for the Common-Councell
to professe their resolutions to yeeld obedience to the desires and
expectations of the House of Commons, in their not receiving
impressions of any forced constructions of the Covenant?</p>
            <p>I desire your leave here also in a parallel way to set downe the
Scripture by you here brought, and another branch of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions
sent by both House of Parliament to the King; and
to desire your judgement, whether that also be in a direct, evident
and obvious manne against the expresse Will and Word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>WORD OF GOD.</cell>
                     <cell>Propositions of both Houses of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<hi>Article</hi> the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Mat. 7. 12</hi> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
you would that m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n
should do unto you, so do
unto them, for this is
the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hets.</cell>
                     <cell>For as much as both Kingdomes are mutually
obliged by the same Covenant, to endeavour the
nearest conjunction and uniformity in matters
of Religion: That such unity and uniformity in
Religion according to the Covenant, as after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sultation
had with the Divines of both kingdoms
now assembled, is, or shall bee jointly agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
by both Houses of Parliament of <hi>England,</hi>
and by the Church and Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> be
confirmed by Acts of Parliament of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
respectively.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>CITY REMONSTRANCE.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Mat. 7. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> As
you would, that
men should doe
unto you, so doe
unto them, for
this is the Law
&amp; the Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hets.</cell>
                     <cell>The 4 Petition, That no person disaffected to
Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>byterian government <hi>(saith the Remonstrance,</hi>
s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t forth, or to be set forth by the Parliament, <hi>but
according to your usuall course, this to blind the reader
you sti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> leav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>)</hi> may be employed in any place of
publike trust; <hi>and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> you add, which is not at all in
that Petition, those words:</hi> viz. <hi>But some effectual course
setled to proceed against such persons, as in the 3 Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
where there is not the shadow of a word ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to any such purpose.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:52607:10"/>
I confesse the words you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cite are in the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Petition, but not at all
in the least manner applyed to persons onely disaffected to Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian
government, for there is no such word in that Petition,
nor any thing looking that way; neither doth the <hi>Common-Councell,</hi>
in any part of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir Petitions so much as desire that
persons onely disaffected to Presbyterian government, should by
some effectuall course<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> setled, be proceeded against; and therefore
methinks you should have been a little more considerate, before
you should thus falsly and unjustly have charged the <hi>Common-Councell
to act in a direct, evident, and obvious manner against the
expresse Will and Word of God.</hi> This I will grant you, that in the
second Petition the <hi>Common-Councell</hi> doth desire, that all Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists,
Brownists, He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etiques, Schismaticks, Blasphemers, and all
<hi>such Sect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ries</hi> as conforme not to the publike Discipline establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed,
or to be established by Parliament, may be fully declared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst,
and some effectuall course setled for proceeding against
<hi>such Persons,</hi> but is there no difference between Anabaptists, Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists,
Heretiques, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>chismaticks, Sectaries, and persons but disaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
to Presbyterian government? I pray tell mee your minde
plainly, would you have Heretiques and Blasphemers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. such
as deny the Scriptures to bee the Word of God, such as professe
the Scriptures are writings onely probable to be beleeved as the
Story of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> such as deny the Trinity of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
in the Unity of Essence, such as call the Trinity a three hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<hi>Cerberus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch as deny the Divinity of Christ, such as deny
the immortality of the Soule, and such as deny that there is a
God, or say, if there bee a God, the Devill is a God, such as say
God is the author of sin, such who hold that all men shall bee
saved, yea, and the Devills too, such as say that Christs humane
Nature is defiled with Originall sin as well as ours, such as hold
that all R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ligions, Worships, Consciences, whether Paganish,
Jewish, Antichristian, &amp;c. should bee tolerated: would you
have these tolerated, or would you not have some effectuall
course setled for proceeding against such Persons? or doe you
thinke these to be no more dangerous, if permitted to broach these
Here<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies and Blasphemies in the Kingdom, then to permit persons
otherwise every way peaceable, godly, and orthodox, because
meerly disaffected to Presbyterian government?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:52607:11"/>
I desire here also in a parallel way to set downe the Scripture
by you here brought, and a Vote of the <hi>House of Commons</hi> of the
30 <hi>Iuly,</hi> 1641. and to desire your judgement, whether that also
be in a direct, evident, and obvious manner against the expresse
Will and Word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>WORD OF GOD.</cell>
                     <cell>Vote of the House of Commons, <hi>die V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris
30 Iubii,</hi> 1641.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 12 As you
would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> men should
doe unto you, so doe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
them; for this is the
Law and the Prophets.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Resolved upon the Question.</hi> That this House doth conceive that the Protesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
made by them, is sit to be taken by every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
that is well-affected in Religion, and to the
good of the Common-wealth: And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>herefore doth
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eclar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, That what person soever shall not take the
Protestation, is unfit to bear Office in the Church
o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Common-wealth.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Thus having given you these Articles of the Propositions of
both Houses of Parliament sent to the King for a safe and well
grounded Peace, and the other passages of both or either House
of Parliament, which I have placed after your example, in a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel
way, against the Scriptures by you brought, and desired your
judgement whether these also do act (as you would have the
world beleeve the Petitio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in the Remonstrance doth) in a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ect,
evident, and obvious manner against the expresse Will and
Word of God. I pray you now also seriously to consider of
those Petitions in the Remonstrance, and compare them together,
with thes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Propositions for Peace, and the other passages of both
or either House of Parliament, and then tell mee what the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrants
in those three (so much by you condemned) Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
for the substance of them, did more desire of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
then both Houses of Parliament have now proposed to the
King, or hath been formerly by them in these passages of both
or either House of Parliament declared to the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you say,</hi> Presbyteriall government is not in the Covenant, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re
a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and this <hi>(say you)</hi> you inforce upon others,
though you will receive no forc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ruction of the same your selves.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:52607:11"/>
Answ. <hi>Where did the Remonstrants say that Presbyteriall
government was in the Covenant? and if they never said it, as
they never did, why doe you here bring it in as if they had said
it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I hope that at last you will learne to forbeare falsifying. It
is true, that in page 2 of the Remonstrance, they speake of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
for Presbyteriall government; and I thinke you will not
deny but there are such, if you doe, I will produce them; but
though Presbyteriall government be not nominally, and</hi> in
v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>bis <hi>in the Covenant, yet I hope without offence, it may be said
that it is concord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble to the Covenant, as being nearest to that
government which the best reformed Churches doe practise, and
that by our Covenant we are bound to endeavour the settlement
of. And that progresse which both Houses of Parliament have
already made, in, and towards the settlement of Presbyteriall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
they have done it in pursuance of the said Covenant, as
by their owne words in the Ordinance of the 14 of</hi> March, 1645.
<hi>it doth appear,</hi> Viz. The Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament
being very sensible of the gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t duty which lyeth upon them to settle mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eligion and the worship of Almighty God; and having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually
before their eyes the Covenant, which they have so solem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly taken:
for the performance thereof, and the manifold motives and incouragements
thereunto, which are given them from God himselfe by a speciall hand of
Providence, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wring forth daily mercies upon them; In discharge of their
duty, and in purs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance of the said Covenant, and in thankefulnesse to
God for all his Mercies, have diligently applyed themselves to that work
of his Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>se, by his grace and assistance they have made some progresse
therein, notwithstanding the exigency of other affaires, accompanied of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es
with great and imminen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dangers. And notwithstanding the
great difficulty of the worke it selfe in divers respects, and particularly
in the right jointing of what was to be setled with the Laws and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nt
of the Kingdome, the want whereof hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aused much trouble i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
this and other States; yet by the mercifull assistance of God, having re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
the booke of Common-prayer, with all its unnecessary and burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some
Ceremonies, and established the Directory in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ome thereof, and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aving abolish<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d the Prelaticall Hierarchy, by Archbishops, Bishops, and
their dependants, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in stead thereof, laid the foundation of a Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteriall
Government in every Congregation, with sub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rdin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion to Cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,
Provinci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll, and Nationall Assemblies, and of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:52607:12"/>
Why doe you also wrong the Remonstrants, in saying, <hi>They
force Presbyteriall government upon others?</hi> doe they any other thing
then Petition the Parliament to settle that government which in
the words of this Ordinance both the <hi>Lords and Commons</hi> do say,
<hi>that in discharge of their duty, and in p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ance of the said Covenant,
they have laid the foundation</hi> already, <hi>viz.</hi> of a Presbyteriall govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>You have yet one parallel more:</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>WORD OF GOD.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ITY REMONSTRANCE.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ut. 19. 15.</hi> At the
mouth of two or three
witnesses shall every
thing be established.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>That Quarterman may be brought to
some exemplary punishment for the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front
done by him, &amp;c. And then you say,</hi>
Though no such thing was ever proved by one
witnesse or testimony, that what hee did was any
aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> done to the Priviledges and Government
of the City<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Hang him, hang him, what hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e
done?</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> You deny not the act of <hi>Quarterman</hi> presume it is not
that which you say was never proved by one witnesse or testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
for the act was done at high Exchange time, within the sight
and hearing of many hund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eds; but I conceive your meaning
(for you doe not expresse it, and therefore I can but guesse at it)
is, that the act in entring the City, and making proclamation
therein with sound of Trumpet; without acquainting the Lord
Major therewith, was not proved by one witnesse or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>estimony
to be any affront done to the Priviledges or Government of the
City, there never was any the least exception taken against the
Order to proclaime, nor against the matter proclaimed, nor the
time when, nor the place where the Proclamation was made; if
according to the constant and uninterrupted course of trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting
things of that nature, the <hi>Lord Major,</hi> who is the chiefe
Magistrate of the City had but been acquainted with it. Now I
appeale to the Reader, whether such an act done in such a manner
in the sight and hearing of many hundreds, without acquainting
the <hi>Lord Major</hi> therewith, be not an affront done to the priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
and government of the City.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In page 14. you tell the Reader, that</hi> I except against the replyer,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52607:12"/>
for saying, The Parliament hath promised in severall Declarations a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
respect to tender Consciences.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> In page 9 of my Vindication, I cited out of the Replyer,
page 2, these following words, <hi>viz. That it is notoriously known that
the Parliament did promise in severall declarations, a gracious respect to
tender Consciences.</hi> I did not except against him for so saying, but
I told him then, and I tell you now, that I will not say that
this is false, left I should fall into that sin, which I am forced so
frequently to reprove you for; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> bee any such promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
in former Declarations which I yet remember not, as I then
said to him, so I now say to you, you should have done well to
have expressed the date of those Declarations, and the words of
the promises, that so the Reader might see, that at least in some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
you, I say you, as well as the Replyer, desire to deale fairly
with them, for the Remonstrants they still laid a fair Copy before
you in the Remonstrance, so to have writ after them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And now without shewing any one Declaration more then the
Replyer did, you goe on and say,</hi> It seems you are willing to hide your
eyes from such observations in the Parliaments Declarations, as though
this were an abòminatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to you, that they should <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e any respect to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er
consciences.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> I never knew before, that a desire to know the dates of
the Parliaments severall Declarations, and to see the words
of the promises which they therein make, of a gracious respect
to tender consciences, which the Replyer saith, is so notoriously
knowne, (and which I must confesse as then, so now, I remember
not,) had been a manifestation of a mans willingnesse to hide
his eyes from such observations in the Parliaments Declarations.
And it is so farre from being an abomination to me, that the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
should have any respect to tender Consciences, that I shall
much rejoice both in the beholding of any true tendernesse of
conscience in any man, and at all due respect which the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
shall shew unto them.</p>
            <p>Yet can I not conceive that Heretiques that deny there is a
God, or that the Scriptures are the Word of God, and that they
are no more to bee beleeved then the Stories of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>', &amp;c.
or Blasphemers, which call the Trinity of Persons in the Unity
of Essence, a three headed <hi>Cerberus, &amp;c.</hi> that these, and such as
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52607:13"/>
these, can properly be brought in under the notion of tender con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences.</p>
            <p>But th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n you aske me if <hi>I have forgotten th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st Declaration of the
17 of</hi> Aprill, 1646, <hi>Answ.</hi> You know tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neither the Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strants,
no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yet my self have forgotten that Declaration, for it
is by the Remonstrants in their second page, cited as a Noble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution
of this Honourable House for the due observation of the
Covenant: and their expectation of the conformity of the people
of <hi>England</hi> thereunto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in that Declaration, and it is
by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the tenth page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> my Vindication quoted as a justifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the Remonstrants (who to answer the expectation of
the House of Commons manifested in that Declaration in these
words, <hi>viz. Wee do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> expect that the people of</hi> England, <hi>should not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
impressi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s of any forced co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>struction of that Cov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nant)</hi> doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse
that they doe resolve by the grace of God not to receive
impressions of any forced construction thereof. But what is this
one Declaration to that the Replyer saith, <hi>that it is notoriously
known that the Parliament did promise a gracious respect to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
Conscience<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in many severall De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>larations,</hi> or what i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it to that
which you doe say, <hi>viz. Wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I as well furnished with Books as
your selfe, doubtlesse I cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d shew you s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>verall other D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>clarations, where
they promise a Christian respect to tender C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then you goe on and say,</hi> I am so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry <hi>Mr. Bellamie,</hi> you sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uld
bee so apt now adayes to cast out of your memorie the praise<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orthy Acts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f
the Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> Ile say no more in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Replyer or your
selfe, but that I would desire you not to take it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, because
I remember not that which yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> so notoriously known,
and that which you say, were I well furnished with bookes,
doubtlesse I could shew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> is whil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neither
hee, nor you, can, or at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance
of any other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reat
you at present to fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>beare your sorrow, and for aftertimes
not to be so censori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us as to charge me to be so apt now a dayes
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Parliament;
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> I shall be as
ready to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> without any ground
charges mee to be so apt now a dayes to cast them out of my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:52607:13"/>
               <hi>In your 16 page you thus goe on, speaking to me,</hi> viz. In th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
next place you begin with an interrogation, as if you had gotten a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ission
to ins<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'t; thus; <hi>What?</hi> is Londons care to keep the Covenant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
now become Lond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns ruine, &amp;c. Doubtlesse these are Doctrines of a new
date, and neare a kin to those new Lights, which so many now ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yes d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e
so much bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st of. <hi>And th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n you say,</hi> Whither now Mr. <hi>Bellamy?</hi> I
professe my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eart akes, and my hand trembles, shall I write, or shall I
forbeare? I passed by your sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffing at new Lights once b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fore at <hi>pag. 10.</hi>
and tooke no notice of it; but I meet with it againe, yea, with an addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall
scoffe, Doctrines of a new d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te, and new Lights, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> When I resolved to indevour the Vindication of the
City Remonstrance, I resolved with my selfe, that I should mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
with oppositions, and therefore desired so to carry on the worke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
as not willingly to let a phrase fall from me, that might justly give
any cause of offence, and to that end, my care was to weigh
words as well as matter, well knowing that sweet and pleasing
langu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge, with solid reason and st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ong a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>guments, best conduce to
the carrying on of a controversie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I confesse, that as in</hi> p. 10. <hi>so here, I use the word new Lights,
and Doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ines of a new date, but whether in the least appearance
as a scoffe or a jeere, I freely leave to the Reader both to examine
and censure; for as scoffing and jeering are farre from my dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position,
so I can safely say, they were as farre in this from my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.
I desire the Reader to take a survey of the passages im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately
preceding these expressions, as they are transcribed out
of the Moderate Reply, and judge whether I had not just cause to
speake what ever is there spoken; the expressions are these,</hi> viz.
That the Remonstrants doe discourage the Parliament, and that they presse
them in all haste, unto a sudden enfeebling of their strength, by crushing
a considerable party of as cordiall friends as ever they had since the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs
began. <hi>And that,</hi> because they will not sweare a submission unto that
Church-government, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>(say you)</hi> neither they, nor your selves ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
understand, and to make so ill a requitall of their Winters w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rke. <hi>And
then againe,</hi> Shall the whole Kingdome, that was almost re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all
its Quarters to congratulate with <hi>London</hi> for all its love, now throw by
these thoughts, and with sad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earts, and pale faces, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll their wives and
children, friends, and neighbours, W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and alasse <hi>London</hi> will ruine
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>London</hi> begins to decline the Parliament, <hi>London</hi> begins to clos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:52607:14"/>
with the King, <hi>London</hi> is fill'd with Malignant language, <hi>London</hi>
remonstrates to the Parliaments prejudice, <hi>Londons</hi> City is <hi>Englands</hi>
woe.</p>
            <p>Now I pray consider whether these so many, so foule, and yet
withall so false charges shall bee laid against <hi>London,</hi> and that for
their performance of what by Covenant they are sworne unto,
doth not justly occasion these interrogations; and let the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
judge whether my using of them gave you any cause to say,
that I begin with them, as if I had a Commission to insult, and
whether from these, and my calling them Doctrines of a new date,
w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whether they be so or no, the Reader will easily discerne. And
my saying that they are neare akin to those new Lights which so
many now adayes doe so much boast of; which I therefore did,
because they which doe now adayes so much boast of their new
Lights, are the persons which doe thus calumniate <hi>London</hi> for this
their Remonstrance, and are the prime men which vilifie the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
as in sundry particular instances in my Vindication I
made it good. I say, pray consider, and let the Reader judge
whether all or any of these things gave you any just occasion
thus to rake up, as you have done, reports against mee, whether
true or false, and to publish them to the whole World, as in your
1617, 18, 19, 20, &amp; 21 pages of your Book, and so almost al along
to the end you have thus done, leaving the argument in difference
between us, and falling upon some personall things, which you
say have been reported to you concerning my carriage in matters
of Religion: Ile come to the particulars; first, you tell the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the place of my birth, and that <hi>I was borne a Son of the Church
of</hi> England <hi>under Episcopacy:</hi> Truly, if this bee a fault or e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rour, I
conceive Mr. <hi>I. P.</hi> will not deny himselfe to bee guilty of the
same crime. Then you come to the manner of my breeding, the
time of my comming to <hi>London,</hi> and my being bound an Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
to Mr. <hi>Nicholas Bourne, Citizen and Stationer of London:</hi> and
you tell the Reader how my carriage was for the time of my Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentiship,
which you are pleased thus to expresse, <hi>Exercising such
strictnesse and exactnesse in keeping and preserving that rich jewell of a
quiet and tender conscience, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> What is this either to the City Remonstrance, or to
my Vindication thereof? these are the things now in debate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52607:14"/>
you and mee; but your thus elevating mee up in praises i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
this, and some such other passages in your Book, is only to cast me
downe with the greater violence, so farr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as you can, to my defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
and destruction; but I pray consider (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t your owne
heart bee y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur owne Iudge, for I will not accuse you) whether
your dealing with me in this, be not just like the Devils with our
Saviour Christ, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4 5, 6. who tooke him up to the Pinnacle
of the Temple, that so, if it were possible, hee might breake his
neck by throwing him down to the ground.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But say you, my tendernesse of conscience appeared,</hi> In that I
would not personally sell such Bookes (as Prayer books) which were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily
sold by other Stationers, and in my Masters Shop.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> Mr. <hi>I. P.</hi> you and the Reader shall both see by this first par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular,
what credit either you are to give to the reports you have
heard of me, for there is not any one thing that you deliver upon
your knowledge, but all upon heare-say; and you know the old
Proverb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Fam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>est mendax,</hi> or what little regard is to bee had to
what you all along in this, and in other particulars have written
of mee; For as you have delivered them, I solemnly professe, that
to the best of my knowledge and remembrance there is not one of
them true. I confesse that neither my selfe, nor any of my fellow
Servants did sell any Play-books, or other books in that nature;
and our not selling these, was by my Masters owne order and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,
and that upon such good grounds, as I know you neither
will, nor can question. But for the particular which you instance
in, <hi>viz. Prayer-books,</hi> there is but one man living that I know of,
that can testifie any thing upon knowledge concerning my pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise
in this particular, and that is my Master <hi>Mr. Nicholas Bourne,</hi>
who was concerned in it, and therefore his testimony is the more
considerable: Ile give it you in, as an answer to what in this you
have Printed upon the Credit of your reporters, and that in his
own words written to mee in a Letter upon the sight of this pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage
in your Book; it thus follows:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>This 24. of Iuly, 1646.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Mr. Bellamie,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>This day there came to my hands, a Booke called the City Remonstrance
Remonstrated, where in <hi>pag. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> I find you are accused, that when you
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52607:15"/>
were my S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rvant you would not sell Prayer-books: To which I answer, to
prove the contrary, that I know you nev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r refused to sell any Prayer-books;
and that I printed a Prayer-book, called <hi>The Supplications of Saints,</hi>
of which I doe beleeve you sold some hundreds: And this I test<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fie under
my Hand the day and year<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> above written.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r me Nicholas Bourne.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>The next thing you fall upon, thinking thereby to defame me,
is,</hi> That after I set up Shop for my selfe, the businesse of Infants B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme
grew into deb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te; and <hi>(say you)</hi> I then fell into the Opinion of
the An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>baptists, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> Mr. <hi>I. P.</hi> I am sorry you should so easily entertain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports
without ground, and so freely publish them to the World,
knowing nothing of them; hee that told you this, if hee knew
what it was hee said unto you, knows, that as unto the point of
time hee told you an untruth. I confesse, that many years before
this, even when I was not above 17 yeares of age, I did upon some
s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruples put into me by an Anabaptist, entertaine their opinion,
but I blesse God, it was not above a moneths time before the Lord
discovered my error to mee. It is now above 30 yeares since, and
must this be raked up afresh by you, and throwne in my face to
blemish what you can that which I have written in defence of the
Remonstrance? Is this a carriage becomming a sober Christian?
one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olid argument, or good reason, if you had them to give, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
the Remonstrance or its Vindication, would with wise
men bee more regarded, then twenty such uselesse or vaine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports.</p>
            <p>Then you tell the Reader <hi>of my applying my self to a separate Cox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,</hi>
and of my continuance with them, and the manner of
departing from them; and all this you affirme, it seems, as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
your owne knowledge, for you doe not in all this say as in
others things, it is reported so, but positively affirme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars
to be so.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> I am sure you know nothing more, nor lesse, of all
that in this you have written, for the time you relate to, was
neare twenty yeares before you and I ever saw the faces one of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother,
but to shew you your mistake, and to let it appeare how
you are abused in receiving, and have abused mee in divulging of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52607:15"/>
of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>se things, Ile give you and the world, (being as it wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
thus by you called thereunto) a true account of them, It's true,
I did above thirty yeares since apply my self to that Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
whereof Mr. <hi>Iacob</hi> was then Pastor, with whom I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
in Communion all the time he continued in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
and some yeares after: but that this was then as you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme
<hi>a Separate Congregation,</hi> I deny, and son proof of what I
say, I appeale to the confession of the faith of the said Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
published in print, in <hi>Anno</hi> 1616. Which was a little after the
time applying my self, as you call it unto them, in which it doth
appeare that Separation was then witnessed against by that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,
and the judgement of that Congregation then was
that the pub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ique Congregations in this Kingdom, was the true
Churches of Christ, the Ministery thereof as received by the
people, a true Ministery, the Ordinances there administred,
both of Baptisme, the Lords Supper, &amp;c. the true Ordinances
of Jesus Christ, and that wee not onely might, but in some re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect
ought to joyn in Communion with the said publique Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations
in the said Ordinances, and that not so to doe was our
sinne. Ile give it you for your present satisfaction in the very
words of the printed confession of the Faith of that Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
Article the eleventh, the latter end of it, thus it is. <hi>It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
no evill, nor any appearance of evill, justly in us to joyne to the Parish-Congregation
and Ministery in such respect, and so far fort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is
aforesaid, wee ought, (as wee bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eve) sometime on w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> occasion
so to joyne, and wee sinne if wee doe not.</hi> This printed confession of
Faith I have by mee, and am very ready for the cleare and full
confirmation of what in all this I write, to shew to you, or to
any one that desires satisfaction in the truth of what I affirm.</p>
            <p>And as it was then the judgement of that Congregation, so
was it also then the practice of the members thereof. And for the
proofe of this, I appeale first to so many of the then members in
generall of that Congregation, who are now living, and knew
the Churches practice in this particular, and in speciall to Mr. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine
Staresmore,</hi> who, (I conceive, and that upon good grounds)
hath been one maine instrument by mis-reports to have thus mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
you, and therein abused mee: but if it bee so, God give him
grace to see his sin, and forgive it him, or whoever it was; I
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52607:16"/>
trust, my heart shall never with consent, entertaine so much as
the shadow of a thought to make the like requitall; but I will
study and indeavour, and lay hold upon every opportunity
which the Lord shall hold forth unto mee, to doe all the good I
can to him, to them, to you, for this your evill done to mee, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring
what our Saviour Christ hath taught mee, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.
44. <hi>Love your enemies, blesse them that curse you, doe good to them that
hate you, and pray for them which despitefully use you, and persecute you.</hi>
But I beseech you all seriously to consider, that if this bee not
persecution with the tongue, then tell mee what is. And I pray
you considerately to ponder and weigh well that of the Prophet
<hi>Ieremy</hi> 20. 10. and make such use of it to your owne soules, as
God shall direct you to doe; the words are these, <hi>I heard the defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
of many, feare on every sid, report, say they, and wee will report
it, all my familiars watched for my halting, saying, Peradventure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
will bee enti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d, and we shall prevaile against him, and we shall take
our revenge on him.</hi> But my comfort and stay in this I trust s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all
be the same with the Prophet, in that, manifested in the next verse,
<hi>But the Lord is with me as a mighty terrible one, therefore my persecutors
shall stumble, and they shall not prevaile, they shall bee greatly ashamed,
for they sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll not prosper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther appeale for proofe of what I affirme, unto Mr. <hi>Henry
Roborough,</hi> now one of the Scribes of the Assembly of Divines,
and Pastor of <hi>Leonards E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st cheape London,</hi> whether hee hath not
at that time observed that Mr. <hi>Jacob, and other knowne members of
that Congregation, did usually communicate in the Ordin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nces of Christ
in the publike Congregations:</hi> And whether hee hath not with his
owne hands, administred <hi>the Lords Supper to Mr.</hi> Jacob, <hi>and other
then knowne members of his Church.</hi> And that the members of this
Congregation, did then not onely communicate in the publique
Assemblies in the <hi>Sacrament of the Lords Supper,</hi> but also in the
<hi>Sacrament of Baptisme,</hi> yea, that they did <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ptize their owne chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
in the publique Assemblies;</hi> I appeale for the truth of this, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the testimony of so many of them as bee now living, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
the Churches practice in this particular at that time, and
if there bee none now living that can remember, and will testifie
this, then in particular I appeale to the Register Book of <hi>Andrew
Hubbard London,</hi> whether upon the 7 of December, 1623. there
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52607:16"/>
was not then and there baptized, <hi>Susan the daughter of</hi> Robert
Lynell, <hi>and of</hi> Susan <hi>his Wife,</hi> both which was then Parishioners
of that Parish and <hi>members of this C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngregation,</hi> and <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bert Lynell
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Deacon of the Church.</hi> I fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther appeal unto the Regi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er-book of
<hi>Saviours Southwarke,</hi> whether upon the third of <hi>February,</hi> 1624.
there was not then and there baptized, <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rshua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> the daughter of
<hi>Daniel Ray,</hi> who then was a Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ishioner of that Parish, and a
member of this Congregation. I could produce many others in
the like kind, but these may suffice to confirme the truth of what
I affirme, neither would I have printed this, but for the witnesse
of this truth, <hi>viz. That that Congre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation did then ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d it not onely
lawfull, but of nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ssity, upon pain of sin, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rding to the Printed Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession
of Faith, to c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmunicate in the publike Ministery and Ordin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
and that b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th of Baptisme and the Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither do I write this in the least measure, to reflect upon the
present now members of that Congregation, if in their judgments
and practice they now walk otherwise; provided, that by the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
of the word of <hi>God</hi> they can clearly justifie their present wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king;
but I must crave your favor for my self stil to continue in the
same judgment and practice I then was, and which is concordable
to the then Confession of the Faith of the Church, as unto com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
in the Parish Congregations, both in the Ministery and
Ordinances of Baptisme and the Lords Supper, though you false<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
charge me of mutation and change in so doing. And thus I
hope I have shewed you your mistake in that you affirm, I apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
my self to a separate Congregation. I shall also endevour to
give you as ample an account of the just reason (as I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive)
of my leaving them.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ob</hi> leaving <hi>England,</hi> and going to <hi>Virginia,</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation
was then for a time, to the best of my remembrance, left
without a Pastor: and then many of the members of the said
Congregation varying in their judgements from what was in the
<hi>Confession of the Faith of the Church</hi> formerly printed; and being
now both in judgement and practice against <hi>Communion in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances
of Christ in the publike Congregations, which by the Confession
of the Faith of the Church, we were bound upon pain of sin to maintain,
both in judgement and practice;</hi> this occasioned many disputes, and
some differences, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> last the point of <hi>Ordination of Ministers</hi> came
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52607:17"/>
under debate, which was the first, yea, the onely occasion that
Put a thought into my breast about my departing from that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation:
And at that time Mr. <hi>Iohn Lothrop,</hi> a learned, holy,
humble, and painfull Preacher was the Pastor, then the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation
ordered three of their members to conferre with mee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
that difference, I then did, now doe, and ever will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
their great love, and tender respect to mee in it, but after
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>undry Conferences, and wee not agreeing, I thought it my
duty, to signifie my mind in writing under my hand to the whole
Congregation, which I then did in these words:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>To his dearly beloved Christian Friends Mr. John Lothrop, and all
the rest of the Congregation with him assembled, this publikely present.</head>
                  <p>Christian Friends, and dearly beloved in the Lord Jesus Christ,
having by the Congregations appointment had Conference with
three of the Brethren, about a point in controversie, which wee
cannot agree, I thought it my duty to signifie my minde in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
to the whole Congregation, which is, That after many
thoughts spent, and some paines taken in Conference, and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination
of Scriptures, and searching the judgements of
Divines, both ancient and moderne, about the matter in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versie,
<hi>viz. Ordination,</hi> or the compleat investing of persons cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen
by the free consent of the Congregation into those Offices
(for Ministeriall imployments) unto which they are elected, I
conceive for the Reasons following, this to be the truth, <hi>viz.</hi> That
it ought to bee performed actually by precedent Church-Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</p>
                  <p>1. Because that the Apostles in <hi>Acts</hi> 6. finding the Church to
be in want of Officers, gave them direction for the performance
of what was their duties, tending to the obtaining of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said
wants, which was to elect persons qualified according to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,
which they, <hi>viz.</hi> the Congregation did, &amp; reserving the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of compleat stating them into their Offices, unto themselves,
which they, <hi>viz.</hi> the Apostles effected: the texts for confirmation,
which with a single eye I desire to be considered of, are, <hi>Acts 6. v.</hi>
3. for the precept injoyning the duty, and <hi>v.</hi> 5, and 6. for the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
in obedience to the precept performed, the words are, <hi>Chuse you
out whom we may appoint,</hi> not chuse you and appoint.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:52607:17"/>
2. That which the Apostles reserved in this place to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
in their precept to the Congregation, and accordingly
after practised, as in the first appeareth, so also in other Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations
or Churches they did the like, as <hi>Acts 14. 23, When they
had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> them Eld<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rs in every Church,</hi> they, that is, <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas,</hi>
as appeareth <hi>v.</hi> 12, 14.</p>
                  <p>If it bee objected, that this was done by Officers extraordinary,
which had their Calling and Commission immediately from God,
and therefore is not fitly brought so, as to require the like to bee
done by ordinary Officers: I desire for answer to it, this third
reason may be con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>idered.</p>
                  <p>3. That which in this kind was done by the Apostles, which I
grant were extraordina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ily called by God, and gifted according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
the same was after done by them which had their ordinatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
by ordinary Officers in Churches, as <hi>Timothy Titus,</hi> as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth,
1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 14. where <hi>Timothy</hi> was ordained by the hands of
the Company of the Eldership, and he in particular, and not the
Congregation in generall, is <hi>charged before God and the Lord Iesus
Christ, and the elect Angels, to lay hands suddenly on no m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n, 1 Tim.</hi> 5.
21, 22. which Scripture, with submission to better judgments, I
conceive teacheth these two duties.</p>
                  <p>1. That <hi>Timothy</hi> an ordained Officer ought to lay on hands in
Ordination, and not any other but Officers ordained.</p>
                  <p>2. That they that doe Ordaine, ought to doe it with advise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
and great deliberation, <hi>not preferring one before another par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And as <hi>Timothy,</hi> so <hi>Titus,</hi> as testifieth the Apostle, 1 <hi>Titus v.</hi> 5.
<hi>was left at</hi> Creta <hi>to ordaine Elders in every City:</hi> And for my part, I
am ignorant of any one example in all the new Testament, where
Ordination was performed by any but Church Officers; and for
the clear and distinct understanding of the quality and difference
of Church Officers extraordinary and ordinary, that we may
know which is, which, I desire that this Scripture may bee
considered, <hi>Gal. 1. 1. Paul an Apostle, not of men, neither by man,
but by Iesus Christ;</hi> where the Apostle to prove his Apostolicall,
or extraordinary Calling, affirm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th that hee was not an Apostle
of men, neither by man, for then hee had been but an ordinary
Minister, but by Jesus Christ; and so as his calling was extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52607:18"/>
his O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ice is the like; from whence followeth this infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
that such as is the calling, such is the Office, they that had
their calling immediately, was extraordinary Officers, such was
t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Apostles; &amp; such as have their calling mediately, or by means
are ordinary, such was <hi>Timothy,</hi> as in the fore-quoted Scripture
may appear, and so are all such as have their Ordination by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt
Church Offi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ers. This interpretation I so give, as upon a
better manifested, I shall desire to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tract this.</p>
                  <p>4. If it had been in the power of the Congregations as to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect,
so lawfully and without sinne to Ordaine, the Apostle might
have written from place to place, Letters of direction according
to which, Congregations might have proceeded, and so of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
effected it, and then the Apostles by that might have had
the more time for the publishing of the Gospel of Christ in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
places, where yet they had not been, and not have travailed
so many miles back againe from place to place to Ordaine El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
which if lawfully it might have been omitted, it would
have spared them much paines, and much advanced the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing
of the Gospel, for wee see that when the Church omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
another Ordinance, <hi>viz. Excommunication,</hi> the Apostle went
not to them, but sent to them to doe it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>5. That which the holy Ghost maketh two distinct Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
in Churches, and commands them to bee performed by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
of a twofold or distinct consideration in Churches, that
none ought to confound, or make them one Ordinance, neither
ought they to be performed by Churches otherwise th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n by the
persons in the said twofold or distinct considerations.</p>
                  <p>But the holy Ghost maketh <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Ordination</hi> two distinct
Ordinances in Churches, &amp; commands them to be performed by
persons of a twofold or distinct considerations in Churches, <hi>viz.
Election</hi> by the members, <hi>Ordination</hi> by the Officers, <hi>Act.</hi> 6. 3.</p>
                  <p>Therefore none ought to confound, or make them one O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance,
neither ought they to bee performed by Churches o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise
then by the Persons in the said twofold or distinct con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderations.</p>
                  <p>These things thus considered, prove this Conclusion, That
that Church or Churches which hold and enjoy their Church
Officers any otherwayes, then by the Ordination of former
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52607:18"/>
Church officers hold and enjoy them not according to the mind
of C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rist, and all the administrations of such Church Officers,
their manner of entrance into their Office, not being grounded
on Scripture, are unlawfull, and not to bee c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mmunicated with;
and this is the ground of my withdrawing my selfe from that
Congregation with whom I formerly walked.</p>
                  <p>If it bee objected, I formerly made question of this same par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular,
and yet after that walked with the Congregation again.
I answer, that it is true, and that I did upon this ground, as to
some it's evidently known.</p>
                  <p>After some question with the Congregation about it, one of
the members, who formerly also had doubt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d of the same thing,
at last said, hee was stayed for the present upon this considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
That if the Ordination of the Church without Officers,
were not of force to give a compleat being by Ordination to a
Pastor, yet our Pastor having formerly been Ordained by a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent
Ministery, in that respect his Ministery was t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ue, and his
Administrations lawfull; unto which, as willing to embrace
any truth manifested, I assented, and upon that ground, and
no other, I received his Ministery, and partooke in, and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated
with his Administrations, and this not secretly, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessedly.</p>
                  <p>But after that, I being in trouble, and in probability to be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stioned
about my practise in this particular, I was, as some know,
in mind much troubled, for having withdrawne my selfe from
the Publike Assemblies, and yet enjoying in my own judgement,
and by my owne confession, neither Ministery nor Administra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
but what derivatively I had from them; and also pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing
both the Publike Congregations, and Ministery, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances,
to be the true Churches Ministery, and Ordinances of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hrist, and so farre pure, as for mee to refuse communion with
them, even by the publike Confession of that Congregation
with whom I walked, was a sinne: I could not then, neither can
I now tell which way, without a great deale of scandall, to take
upon mee, before authority in these respects to cleare my practice,
or to reconcile this at least seeming Paradox, the rather conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,
that in this particular I was not onely left alone by the most
and best of Orthodox Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ines, Foraine and Nationall, but even
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52607:19"/>
by that Congregation also with whom I walked, who though it
hold a necessity of communicating in the Assemblies in some ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,
and that as before the Churches Ministery and Ordinances
be true, yet hold not their Ministery in their owne, by vertu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
of Ordination from a precedent Ministery, but by the Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the Congregation, unto which, neither could I then,
nor can I now, for the Reasons fore-specified give my assent, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
must remaine contrary minded till the force of the Reasons and
Argument, be taken away, or a beter ground bee manifested to
mee, which at all times, I shall desire to embrace. Thus desiring
what truth herein is contained may be received, and what error,
if any, may be shewed, that all of us by leaving the evill, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the good, may obey our God in whom I rest; desiring ever
to be a true Friend and Brother to you all, and to all others that
love the Lord Christ.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Iohn Bellamie.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>After the sending of this Letter, I received an answer from the
Congregation, and returned them a Reply, a Copy of which
Reply I have now by me, but upon desire, I delivered back the
Answer to one of the members, and would now have obtained it
againe, and printed it with my Reply to it, but it would not bee
granted me. I would not have printed these passages, but that I
conceived it requisite to satisfie you and the reader the grounds of
my leaving that Congregation. And after this, (what further
passed in that Congregation concerning my selfe) I know not.
Now, if that Congregation with whom I then walked, was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards
in their judgements and practice changed or altered,
from what the Confession of the Faith of the Church then was
when I joyned to them, and the practice of the members thereof
then was, while I walked with them, as unto communion in the
Ministery and Ordinances both of Baptisme and the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
&amp;c. in the Publike Parish Congregations (for that is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression
in the Confession,) and that not thus to communicate,
in such respect, and so farre forth onely as aforesaid, was our sin,
even by our own confession; then I pray you tell me (for I will not
judge) whether is most blame worthy, they or I, and in whom is
most mutation to be found.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:52607:19"/>
But if I may without offence speake it, methinkes you exceed
the bounds of Christian love and charity (yet will I not call it,
a piece of your Independent justice which we must expect, as in
another case you call it, <hi>a piece of Presbyteriall justice, which</hi> (say
you) <hi>wee are like to finde from you when power is in your hands,</hi> Pag 4.)
in presuming that revenge against this Congregation and its
members, hath put me thus on worke in the <hi>City Remonstrance</hi>
and <hi>its Vindic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion,</hi> for the Lord that searcheth the hearts of all
men, knoweth my heart, and unto him I doe appeale, that from
that time to this hour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, which I thinke is now near twenty years,
I never had the least thought of revenge in me, either against the
whole, or any particular member of that Congregation, but
have according to my poore ability, been alwayes ready and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
to performe all offices of Christian love and respect unto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
of them; and I hope, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccasion is offered, ever shall be; and
though I cannot agree with them in opinion and practice, yet I
hope I shall ever love them as my own soul.</p>
            <p>In page 18. you speak of my meeting with a select company of
Christians in a cursory way; where you are pleased to say
more then ever I deserved, or had cause to thinke of, concerning
my carriage amongst them to their comfort and content.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w.</hi> Truly, I blesse God, I have often met with sundry s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect
Companies of godly Christians in holy duties, and been wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
according to the best of my abilities, to doe or receive any
good to, or from them, but sure I dare not think you judge this to
be criminall; but yet you say, <hi>that with much griefe of soul they assert
these things.</hi> What your meaning in this is, as you expresse it not,
so indeed I know it not; I hope, as I ever have done, so I ever
shall endeavour to do or to receive any spirituall goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from any
company of Christians with whom either purposely or occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally
I shall converse; and for this you have my minde and
judgement, which according to that talent God hath given mee
is, and ever shall be concordable to my practice; you may read it
in my Vindication, page 21. it is in an answer to a Querie of the
Replyer, <hi>viz.</hi> what the Remonstrants meane by private and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate
Congregations; it's answered negatively in these words,
<hi>That the Remonstrants doe not mean by private and separate Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
the private meetings of Christian people for Prayer, Exhortation,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:52607:20"/>
Repetition of Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmons, or any other laudable and Christian familie, or
neighbourly duties amongst the Saints; as to these I am assured all the
Remonstrants will joyne with you in your desire, that abh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r'd h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th by God
and all good men, may all requests be that shall bee made for the suppres-pressing
of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, you goe about summarily to reckon up such things, as
either lying fame hath told you, or your own fancy dictates to
you, and for fear of failing, you repeat them in several places; and
therefore where you are pleased to lay them downe, I must un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe
the paines to take them up, they are in p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge 19, and page
30. where you say, I have been for Bishops, and against Bishops;
for Separates, and against S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>parates; a Sectary, and an A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-sectary;
a Schismatick, and an Anti-schismatick; and so you
goe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urther on in many other the like expressions according to
your pleasure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> If all these were true which here you specifie, and all
the former particulars before recited, yet what are all, or any
of these to the City Remonstrance or its Vindication? Truly, I
must needs say, that it is a shrewd signe of a bad Cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e; and I
thinke the Reader will bee of the same minde with mee, when
in stead of Arguments or Reasons to confute what is affirmed,
you must fall so foule upon the Person, and the suppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages
of him whom you oppose; it seems you had little hope
that your selfe by strengtst of Argument should doe any good,
and therefore you call in for helpe, such as it is, in this way of
combating to cast mee downe, just like the Heathens against the
Christians in the Primitive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>imes, and the Papists against the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants
in these latter times; but I pray <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emember what you say of
the Reply, in the 5 page of your Booke, the latter end, That
<hi>there may possibly be mistakes more then enough</hi> in it, <hi>for the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
onely excepted, where is thirt writing without mistakes?</hi> May not
the like bee said, as of Books, so of men, where is the man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
his errors, without his miscariages? as I will not accuse, so
I beleeve you will not excuse Mr. <hi>I. P.</hi> himselfe from these. And
truly, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y self, I dare not to these plead my defence; for I know
more by my selfe, then you, or all your Reporters can accuse
me of, and earnestly &amp; humbly I desire that God may be glorified
both in my acknowledgement of them to him, and his pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52607:20"/>
of them to mee; but upon what ground you should thus
boldly breake in upon mee, knowing nothing of any thing that
of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e you affirme, I can but wonder: I pray be pleased to
make a second inquiry amongst all your Reporters, and see if they
can make it out for truth unto you, that ever at any time, in any
place, either by word or writing, any thing fell from mee, either
for Bishops, for Separates, for Schismaticks, or for Sectaries, and
if not, as confident I am nor you, nor they can, then why doe
you wrong your selfe and your Cause, in thus going about to
wrong me, by reporting and divulging these untruths of me?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But I have tyred out my selfe, and perhaps wearied the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
too, in following you so long upon these personall things,
yet must I needs crave favour to particularize one passage more,</hi>
viz. <hi>in your 29 pag. in these words,</hi> viz. Mr. <hi>John Bellamie,</hi>
what kinde of man are you? They that observe your sayings what they
have been formerly concerning the King, concerning the Lords, concerning
the power of the Commons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (whispering your thoughts in the eares of many
that now speake of it) what your carriages have been not very long since
in Common-Councell, or among your brethren the Stationer's, the
Committee appointed for the keeping up and maintaining the Expository
Lectures, and what your carriages are now, stand with admiration and
amusement at your wheeling thus about.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> I desire the Reader to observe the many Charges which
in this you lay against mee, at the least six, yet you particularize
not any one; might I not more justly then you, take your owne
words used in reference to <hi>Quarterman,</hi> in your 12 page, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
them to that which in this you spake against mee, <hi>viz. Hang
him, hang him, what hath he done?</hi> And what I pray you may such as
know mee not, be ready to judge of mee? when they heare so
many, and so great Charges in the generall laid against mee, and
seemingly confirmed by so many Witnesses, as the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Councell,
the Company of Stationers, the Committee for
Expository Lectures? was there ever the like passages printed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
any man by the worst of enemies that ever he had to charge
him with something against the King, as if that were Treason,
something against the Lords &amp; Commons, as if that were either
Treason, or at least <hi>Scandalum Magnatum,</hi> and this to be whis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered
by mee in the eares of many, that now speake of it againe,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:52607:21"/>
and yet to instance in nothing at all; and then furth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r to say,
what your carriages have been not very long since in Common-Councell,
or among your Brethren the Stationers, the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee
appointed for the keeping <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> maintaining the Expository
Lectures. Now I appeale to your own soule, whether this your
dealing can have any defence m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de for it. And I do appeale also
to the worst of Enemies that I have alive (as it seemes I have a
great many; for I thanke you heartily for it, you told mee pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately
by word of mouth upon Saturday the 8 of this August,
that there is a Booke of the History of my life, already drawn up,
and fitted for the Presse, wherein are many heavie Charges laid
against me in the matters of my conversation:) to make any thing
good against mee in any of these generalls which here you sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ak
of, and in particular I appeal to the Court of Common-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell,
to the Company of Stationers, and to the Committee a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
for the keeping up and maintaining the Expository Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures,
(for all these you seeme to bring as witnesses against me,)
whether ever I did or spake any thing at any time in any of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e
Assemblies, which in any thing was any way crosse or contrary
either to the City Remonstrance, or to any thing in my Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
thereof; for you say, that they observing your now carriages,
stand with admiration and amasement at your wheeling thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout.</p>
            <p>Mr <hi>I. P.</hi> I pray remember that Scripture, which in your 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
page you set in a parallel against a passage in the Remonstrance,
to prove that the <hi>Common-Councell doth act in a direct, evident, and
obvious manner against the expresse Will and Word of God,</hi> and bring
it hither, and set it likewise in parallel against this your dealing
with me, and then tell mee <hi>who doth act in a direct, evident, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious
manner, against the expresse Will and Word of God;</hi> the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
you cite, is <hi>Matth. 7. 12. As you would that men should doe unto
you, so doe unto them, for this is the Law and the Prophets.</hi> Mr. <hi>I. P.</hi>
I beseech you aske your owne soule, whether you would that I,
or any other man should deale thus by you, as you have dealt by
me, gathering up whatever you cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d heare against mee, whether
true or false, in my carriages about matters of Religion, and that
for above 30 yeares together; and though you know nothing
of any one of them more or lesse, and there being not one of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52607:21"/>
them true as you relate them, yet without ever speaking one
word to me about them, with such boldnesse and confidence of
truth to publish them to the world: And now tell me, <hi>Whether you
doe as you would bee done unto, and whether in this, your owne Conscience
being your judge, you doe not act in a direct evident, and obvious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
against the expresse will and word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I must break off, yet with this resolution, that your indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
thus to blaz on my Name, and blast my Repute, shall by Gods
grace quicken mee up to a more Christian watchfulnesse over all
my wayes, that I may walke more inoffensively towards men, and
more pleasingly before <hi>God;</hi> and I blesse my <hi>God,</hi> that my Name is
neither in the power of your tongue, nor pen, nor yet of your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters
neither, but onely in the hand &amp; power of my good God
who is able to keep that which I have committed to him; and I
blesse his Name, I am not in any thing terrified by that which
you or they have in this already done, in thus seeking to defame
mee, nor yet, I hope, ever shall bee at that History of my Life,
which you say is ready for the Presse to be Printed against mee.</p>
            <p>Next, you come in your 22 page to that question wherein re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides
the Supreme power of the Kingdome, and upon this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
you continue neare to the end of your Book; and in page
23 you begin your Que<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies, and first, you aske what I meane by
three Estates, and yet in the same, and the foregoing pages you
transcribe my very words, where I told you, that by the three E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states
I meant (as all the Laws and Records of the Kingdome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse
it, and as all men unquestionably have hitherto concluded
it, and as the truth in it selfe is) <hi>the King, the Lords,</hi> and <hi>the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</hi>
Your second Querie is, <hi>What I meane by Fundamentall;</hi> and
then you tell the Reader, that <hi>I say the King, the Lords, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
are the three Estates of which the Fundamentall constitution of the
Kingdome is made up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's true, I did, and doe say so still, and you say little to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict
it, onely you aske another question (which, how wise a
one it is, I desire the Reader to observe, for I must not judge) <hi>viz.
are there three Fundamentalls?</hi> and you propose it, as if I had said
or imply'd so much; and then you tell the Reader, you ever
thought there had been but one; and in this I agree with you, but
herein is our difference which you and I must leave to the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:52607:22"/>
               <hi>of the reader to determine, I say this one Fundamental con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution
of the Kingd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, is the three Estates of the</hi> King, Lords,
<hi>and</hi> Commons, <hi>and this I still abide by; but you say,</hi> this one Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall
is the Commons, <hi>and that for two Reasons; 1.</hi> Bec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>use the
Commons made the King, and the King made the Lords, and so the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
are the prime <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion. 2. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cause both the King and the
Lords were adv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nced for the benefit, quiet, and welfare of the Commons,
and not the Commons made for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m: <hi>And you say,</hi> if you are deceived,
the common Maxime of <hi>Salus populi suprema Lex,</hi> deceived you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> First, the frame of the Government of this Kingdome,
by the admired wisdom of the Architects and Contrivers thereof,
is so composed of these three Estates, as may best preserve the
whole, and keep either of those Estates from any such exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy
as might destroy the other; for as they are the three Estates
in Parliament, I humbly conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ive there is no subordination of
the one to the other, but a co-ordination of them all three toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
by which the Princes Soveraignty, and the peoples free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
and liberty are together preserved and maintained, and
herein is that common Maxime of <hi>Salus populi suprema Lex,</hi> chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
made good.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the legislative Power of this Kingdom is not in any
one Estate distinct, but in al the three Estates conjunct, yea, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
root and essence of this Legislative Power is compounded, and
as it were, mixed together in the three Estates of <hi>King, Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> and these three concurrent Estates producing one su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme
Act as con-Cause,
ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>not have a subordination among
themselves, it not being imaginable how a power can cause the
supreme effect, and yet be subordinate: thus the very being of our
Common and Statute Lawes prove this truth, for they are not
composed nor enacted by any one of the three Estates <hi>divisim,</hi>
but they are established by the sole authority of the three Estates
<hi>conjunctin,</hi> every act <hi>being enacted by the Kings most excellent Majesty,
and by the authority of the Lords and C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmons assembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, I must needs dissent from you, in that you say, that
both <hi>the King and the Lords were advanced for the bene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t, quiet, and
welfare of the Commons,</hi> if your meaning bee, as indeed by your
words it seems to be, <hi>exclusive,</hi> excluding therein the benefit, quiet
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:52607:22"/>
and welfare of <hi>the King</hi> and <hi>the Lords,</hi> for I conceive the benefi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
quiet and welfare of the whole, <hi>viz. King, Lords,</hi> and <hi>Comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns</hi>
was equally and alike intended in <hi>the Fundamentall constitution of
the Kingdom,</hi> and so the <hi>Commons</hi> were as well made for the <hi>King,</hi>
as the <hi>King</hi> for the <hi>Commons,</hi> yea the <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>the Lords,</hi> and <hi>the
Commons</hi> were all alike made for the benefit, quiet, and welfare
each of others, and so of the whole together; and this is that,
which in my minde maketh the Constitution of this Kingdome
in this state of a limited and mixed Monarchy farre to surpasse
the Constitution of any other Kingdome that I know; and I
think, that in a good sense it may truly bee said of the severall
members of this thus constituted <hi>Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itique body of this Kingdome,</hi>
as the Apostle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 21. speakes of the members of <hi>the naturall
body, the eye c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nnot s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y to the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd, I have no need of thee, nor again the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ead to the feet, I have no need of you;</hi> for as every member in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall
body is by God there set and placed, not alone for its owne
good, but for the welfare of the whole, and accordingly it acts,
and is serviceable therein for the good of the whole, yea, such a
naturall necessity there is in the body, of every member, that not
any one member can be wanting, but the body is thereby defective,
and so <hi>the eye cannot say to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and, I have no need of thee, nor againe,
the head to the feet, I h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no need of you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So in the <hi>body Politique of this Common-wealth,</hi> by the ancient and
excellent Constitution thereof, the three Estates, <hi>viz. King, Lords</hi>
and <hi>Commons</hi> are so set and placed, that in their severall stations
they should not act alone for their owne particular, but for the
Common and Publike good and welfare of the whole; yea, I
humbly conceive, that to the upholding &amp; continuance of this so
excellent a Constitution, there is such a <hi>Politique necessity</hi> of every
one of the three Estates in this Commonwealth, for the preserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the whole, that <hi>the King cannot say to the Commons, I have no
need of you, nor againe the Commons to the King, I have no need of thee,</hi>
nor yet the King <hi>and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Commons to the Lords, we have no need of you:</hi>
For if any one Estate in <hi>this b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dy Politique</hi> be cut off, the whole
constitution is presently destroyed; and when I seriously consider
how by the Fundamentall Constitution of this Kingdom, there
is such care taken for the preservation of the Soveraignty of the
<hi>King,</hi> and yet withall such provision made for the just Liberties
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52607:23"/>
and freedome of the people, and how the one may be justly allay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
and yet consist without impeachment of the other, I cannot
but conceive it to be unparalleld for true policy in the whole
world: and thus much in answer to your two first Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Your third Querie is,</hi> whether the King, and suppose the major part
of the Lord, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke up two Estates, do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> agree tog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther, suppose it be to
set up absolute prerogative, and the Commons will not assent hereunto,
whether the majo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> part of the Estates must not conclude the minor, the two
conclude the third, and so as for the Common, will they, nill they, sl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es
they must be, and slaves they shall be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> To the making of a Law, there must bee the concurrent
consent of all the three Estates, <hi>viz. King, Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons;</hi>
the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Lords,</hi> without the consent of the <hi>Commons</hi> can
make no Law valid, and in that case the <hi>major</hi> part of the Estate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
doe not conclude the <hi>minor,</hi> and so the <hi>Commons</hi> are thereby pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>served
from slavery; but in another case the <hi>major</hi> part of the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>states
doe conclude the <hi>minor, viz.</hi> when the <hi>Lords</hi> and Common<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
doe agree upon a Law for the good and safety of <hi>the Kingdome,</hi>
then <hi>the King</hi> is concluded in that their agreement, and ought t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
set his <hi>flat</hi> thereunto: <hi>For the Kings of England</hi> are bound by
their Oaths to grant such Laws which shall bee for the good and
safety of <hi>the Kingdome,</hi> with the accord of their people <hi>in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> presented to them, as in the preamble of the Statute made in
the 25 yeare of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dward</hi> the Third, entituled, <hi>The Statute of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s
of Benefices, made at W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stminster,</hi> in these words it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare:</p>
            <p>Whereupon the said Commons ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e prayed our Soveraigne Lord the
King, that sith the Right of the Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> and the Law of
the said Realme is such, that upon the mischiefs and damm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ges which
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>appen to this Realme, Hee ought, and is bound by His Oath, with the
accord of His People in His Parliament thereof, to make remedy and law.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>King</hi> acknowledgeth this for a truth, and accordingly
Acted, as in these following words in the same Statute, it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth:</p>
            <p>Our Soveraigne Lord the King, seeing the mischiefes and dammages
before mentione<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and having r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gard to the Statute made in the time of his
Grandf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther, and by so much as Hee is bounden by Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th to cause the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> a Law of His Realme, &amp;c. by the assent of all the great
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:52607:23"/>
Men and Comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nalty of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is said Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lme, to the honor of God, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
of the said Church of <hi>England,</hi> and of all His Realm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
and es<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ablished, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus farre the words of that Preamble and Statute, upon
which <hi>the Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> in this present <hi>Parliament</hi> assembled
say thus: <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here the Lords and Commons claime it directly as the right of the
Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> and of the Law of the Land, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the King is
bound by his O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th, with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of his people in Parliament, to make
remedie and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the mischiefs and damm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s which happen to this
Realme, and the King doth not deny it, <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llect of Declarations, p. 229.
L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t this suffice as answer to your third Querie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Your fourth Que<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie is this,</hi> Wheth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee <hi>(viz. the King)</hi> be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
as a distinct Estate, if so, if one distinct Estate may bee present in
power <hi>quatenus,</hi> an Estate, and absent in person, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y not a second Estat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
be so present, though absent in body; yea, a third Estate s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> present, and
yet absent in body; and so we shall have the Estates in Parliament, and
not a man amongst them; this is a Riddle ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed Mr. <hi>Bellamie,</hi> I pray
you unfold this also.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> At your request <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e undertake the taske; your owne
words grant, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s well in Parliament, as in all his inferiour
Courts of Justice, <hi>the King is present in his power;</hi> these are your
words, <hi>viz. I know Sir, hee is present in power in all his inferiour
Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts of Iustice, as well as in the Parliament,</hi> 24. Now in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
there is no power but the power of the three Estates, <hi>viz.
King, Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons;</hi> and therefore all the Acts that are
en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted by the power of <hi>Parliament</hi> are enacted by the power of
the three Estates <hi>conjunction;</hi> It is possible that the <hi>King</hi> may
withdraw his person from the <hi>Parliament,</hi> as now hee hath done,
but hee can never withdraw his power, no, not his power as a
distinct Estate, for in the making of every Act of <hi>Parliam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt,</hi> there
is present in <hi>Parliament</hi> the power of all the three Estates, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
all which <hi>conjunctim,</hi> no act can bee made. But there is an
Act made this Parliament by the free consent of all the three
Estates in Parliament, that this Parliament shall not be dissolved,
prorogued, or adjourned without the consent of both Houses of
Parliament first had and obtained, <hi>viz. Anno 17 Caroli Regis,</hi> enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled,
<hi>An Act to prevent inconveniences which may happen by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:52607:24"/>
adjourning, proroguing &amp; dissolving of this present Parliament.</hi> In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
Act are these words, viz. Be it declared and enacted by the King our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne
Lord, with the assent of the Lords and Commons in this present
Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, That this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
Parliament now assembled, shall not bee dissolved, unlesse it be by Act
of Parliament to bee passed for that purpose, nor shall b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e at any time or
times during the Continuance thereof, prorogued or adjourned, unl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sse it
be by Act of Parliament to be likewise passed for that purpose.</p>
            <p>Now then thus I argue, if at the passing of this Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
there was present the power of all the three Estates in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
<hi>viz. King, Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> and by vertue of this Act
of Parliament, the Parliament cannot be dissolved, prorogued,
or adjourned, unlesse it be by act of Parliament to bee passed for
that purpose, then the power of all the three Estates, <hi>viz. King,
Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> must needs continue in Parliament, till by Act
of Parliament to be passed for that purpose this Parliament bee
dissolved, prorogued, or adjourned.</p>
            <p>But at the passing of this Act of Parliament, there was present
the power of all the three Estates in Parliament, <hi>viz. King, Lords</hi>
and <hi>Commons, (vide the Act <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> supra)</hi> and by vertue of this Act of
Parliament, the Parliament cannot be dissolved, prorogued, or
adjourned, unlesse it be by Act of Parliament to be passed for that
purpose, <hi>vide</hi> also the Act <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> supra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore the Power of all the three Estates in Parliament,
<hi>viz. King, Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> must needs continue in Parliament
till by Act of Parliament to bee passed for that purpose, this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
be dissolved, prorogued, or adjourned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And thus the particular by me affirmed, is clearly proved,</hi> viz.
That though the person of the King bee absent from the Parliament, yet
the power of the King, <hi>viz.</hi> as one of the three Estates in Parliament, is
present with the Parliament.</p>
            <p>I now come briefly to the second part of your Querie, and
will endeavour herein, (as you call it) to unfold your Riddle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
the other two Estates in Parliament, <hi>viz. Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi>
cannot be absent from the Parliament, neither in power, nor ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
in person: thus farre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e grant you, that many of the members
of either House may bee absent from either of their respective
Houses, and yet the two Estates of Parliament continue entire
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52607:24"/>
in Parliament, for there must be at least three Lords present in the
House of Lords to make it a House, and so an Estate in Parliament;
and forty Commons with the Speaker, in the House of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
to make it an House, and so an Estate in Parliament; and
therefore there cannot bee, as you affirme, three Estates in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
and not a man amongst them; and this I give as an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer
to your fourth Querie, and if you please, you may also let it
passe for the unfolding of your Riddle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ifth place, in page 24. you have these words,</hi> viz. The
Replyer observing the Remonstran s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ascribing onely a share of the supreme
Power to the House of Commons proposeth this Question to them; Will
not you allow so much power to the Kingdome representative, in r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
to the Kingdome, as to the representative City, in reference to Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don?
<hi>And then you come to your fifth Querie in these follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
words,</hi> viz. And so doe I Querie, will not the Commons of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
yeeld or ascribe unto the Commons of England, as the Commons of
London to themselves will ascribe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> I pray ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k the termes of your Querie, for methinks it
is a little defective; you say the Commons of <hi>London,</hi> not the
Common-Councell, but as you propose your Querie, I answer
affirmatively, that the Commons of <hi>London</hi> will yeeld and ascribe
unto the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> as the Commons of <hi>London</hi> to
themselves will ascribe; but I say again, observe your termes, you
say the Commons of <hi>London,</hi> not the Common-Councell; I
shall pres<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntly shew you the difference, the Commons of <hi>London</hi>
are not the City representative, but the Common-councell,
(which doth consist of the Lord Major, Aldermen, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons)
is the City representative.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then you goe on in these words,</hi> viz. Therefore Mr. <hi>Bellamie</hi>
to make your absurdities the better appeare, in your parallel between the
Kingdome representative, and the City representative, I come upon you
thus;</p>
            <p>First, you grant that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Common-Councell is the City representative,
<hi>page 2 of your Vindication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> I grant it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, you grant that the House of Commons in Parliament assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled,
is the Kingdom representative, <hi>in the same page.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> I grant the House of Commons in Parliament assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:52607:25"/>
to be the Kingdome representative in that sense in which in
page 2 of my Vindication, I said it was, <hi>viz.</hi> as it is made up of
and chosen by the Kingdome collective, <hi>viz.</hi> the Commons of
the Kingdome, whom in Parliament it onely represents, and
therefore onely can be the representative body of them, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly
in all their addresses to the House of Lords, they goe
in their owne names, and in the names of all the Commons of
<hi>England;</hi> and desiring the concurrence of the House of Lords in
any Act, they desire it in their owne names, and in the names of
all the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> of whom they onely are a repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentation,
or whom they doe represent, and in that sense I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed
it in page 4, where I called the Kingdome collective, the
body of the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> not the body of the Kingdom
of <hi>England;</hi> And as this representative body, <hi>viz.</hi> the House of
Commons, is one of the three Estates in Parliament, so also in
that page I called it the House of Commons in Parliament assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled,
but I called it not the Parliament; so the Lords are called
the House of Lords in Parliament assembled, but no man cals tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
House the Parliament. Likewise the Lords and Commons joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
together in any one Act, as, in the last Propositions sent to
His Majesty, it is said to be agreed by both Houses of Parliament,
as in Article 1, 5, 6, 12, &amp;c. it appeareth, but it is not said to be
agreed by Parliament, for it had been so agreed, why then is
the Kings assent to these Propositions prayed for by both Hous<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s
of Parliament, as in the Proem to the said Propositions in these
words it doth appeare? <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>May it please your Majesty,</p>
               <p>Wee the Lords and Commons assembled in the Parliament of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi>
in the name, and on the behalfe of the Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi>
and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Commissioners of the Parliament of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
in the name, and on the behalfe of the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> Doe
humbly present unto your Majesty, the humble desires and Propositions for
a safe and wel-grounded Peace, agreed upon by the Parliaments of both
Kingdomes respectively, unto which we do pray your Majesties assent, and
that they, and all such as shall bee tendred to your Majesty in pursuance
of them, or any of them, may bee established and enacted for Statutes and
Acts of Parliament by your Majesties Royall assent in the Parliaments
of both Kingdoms respectively.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:52607:25"/>
You might also have observed in the same page, that when I
come to speake of making Laws, which is the worke of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
and not of any particular Estate alone in Parliament; I
there say in expresse termes, the Kingdome representative, which
is the Parliament.</p>
            <p>And sure no man could possibly imagine that my expression
should be taken in any other consideration; for I did all along in
the 14, 15, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 17, 18 pages of my Vindication also hold out this
truth, that there was three distinct Estates in Parliament, <hi>viz. the
King, the Lords,</hi> and <hi>the Commons,</hi> and doe you thinke that it was
probable or possible that I should meane, that one of the thee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states
in Parliament, should be a representation of all the three?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, you say, the City representative hath a power to make a Law
for those whom it represents.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> I grant this too.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then you thus goe on,</hi> viz. Fourthly, I desire to know whether
you allow the Kingdom representative the same power to make a Law for
those whom it represents.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> I crave your favour and patience before you goe any
further to present you in this place with these two following
considerations:</p>
            <p>First, that the House of Commons, all the members thereof
be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing chosen by the collective body of the Kingdome, <hi>viz.</hi> the
Commons, are in that respect, and in that sense truly the repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentative
body of the Kingdome, <hi>viz.</hi> of the Commons of the
Kingdome, and so have in them in this consideration, the full
Legislative power of the Commons of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, I pray also consider, that though the House of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
have in them the full Legislative power of the Commons
of <hi>England,</hi> yet the whole Legislative power of the Kingdome
of <hi>England,</hi> is not concentred in the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> but
is, (as hath before been fully proved) in the three Estates of <hi>the
King, the Lords,</hi> and <hi>the Commons of England conjunctim,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
no one Estate alone, and by its selfe can make a Law; but to
the making of every Law in the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> there must
be the concurrent consent of all these three Estates <hi>conjunctim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this as I humbly conceive, makes a cleare way to give an
answer to your Querie, <hi>viz. Whether you allow the Kingdom repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentative
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:52607:26"/>
(viz.</hi> the House of Commons) <hi>the same power to make a
Law for those whom i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> represents,</hi> and the answer will bee this; It
hath in it the full <hi>legislative</hi> power of <hi>the Commons of England,</hi>
whom <hi>in Parliament</hi> it doth represent, but it hath not in it the full
<hi>legislative power of the kingdome of England,</hi> it hath in it all the
power of <hi>the Commons of England</hi> towards the making of a Law,
but it must have the concurrent consent of the other two Estates, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>the King,</hi> and of <hi>the Lords</hi> to the full consummating of a
Law, and making it obligatory to <hi>the Kingdome of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And besides, that it is thus setled by the fundamentall Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution
of the Kingdome, I humbly also conceive that there is just
reason for it too, and that not onely from the relation which
these three Estates have one to another, but also because of that
interest which one Estate hath in another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> King being no otherwise King of England, but with relation
to <hi>the subjects of England,</hi> and so he hath an interest in them, and
they are his <hi>liege,</hi> that is, his lawfull Subjects, or, his Subjects ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the Law. And likewise <hi>the Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi>
are no otherwise <hi>Subjects of England,</hi> but with relation to
<hi>the King,</hi> as hee is <hi>the King of England,</hi> in whom also they have the
like reciprocall interest, and so he is their <hi>liege, our lawfull Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne,
or their King according to the Law,</hi> and thus runs the formes
of our Laws, <hi>viz. Bee it enacted by the King our Soveraigne Lord,
with the assent of the Lords and Commons in this present Parliament
Assembled.</hi> But the City of <hi>London</hi> by the Charter of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. in
the 15 yeare of his Reigne, hath a power granted <hi>to the Major,
and Aldermen, and their successors, with the assent of the Commonalty,
to make lawes for the common profit of the Citizens of the same City;</hi> by
vertue of which grant, <hi>the Lord, Major, Aldermen, and Commons
in Court of Common-Councell assembled,</hi> being therin as one entire
Court, <hi>the representative Body of the City,</hi> doe to this day make
Laws, which are alwayes binding to the Citizens of the same
City. And there is no other consent required to the consummation
of these Laws, but the sole and onely authority of this Court, and
therefore all our Acts of <hi>Common-councell</hi> are made in the joint
names of the <hi>Lord Major, Aldermen, and Commons in the Court of
Common-councell assembled,</hi> and by the authority thereof; and in the
addition of any branch in an act of <hi>Common councell</hi> it is still thus
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:52607:26"/>
exprest, <hi>It is by this Court further Ordered, &amp;c. Or this Court doth
further Order, &amp;c.</hi> which doth fully prove that all the power of
making or altering, or adding to the City lawes, rests wholly
and alone in the body of that one <hi>Court of Common-councell,</hi> or
the greater number of them, which doth alwayes consist of <hi>the
Lord Major, Aldermen, and Commons,</hi> but all the power of making
or repealing, or adding to the <hi>lawes of the kingdome,</hi> doth not rest
wholly and alone in <hi>the House of Commons,</hi> but the concurrent
consent of the other two Estates, <hi>viz. the King,</hi> and <hi>the Lords,</hi>
is necessarily required to this of <hi>the Commons,</hi> for making or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing
of <hi>the Laws of the Kingdome.</hi> And thus I hope I have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered
your first head of Queries arising from that question, <hi>viz.
wherein resides the Supreme power of the Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I shall now likewise endeavour to give a solution to your Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
and all the satisfaction I can to the second head of your
Queries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For a foundation to build your Arguments upon, you produce
an Argument of mine out of my Book, entit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>led,</hi> A Plea for the
Commonalty of London, thus it is, That Court which hath a power to
make a law, and by that law to conferre a power upon the Lord Major
and Aldermen, which as Lord Major and Aldermen they had not before,
must needs bee <hi>quoad hoe,</hi> as unto the making of a law, above the Lord
Major and Aldermen.</p>
            <p>But this Court of Common-councell hath, &amp;c. <hi>Ergo,</hi> this Court of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-councell so farre as to the making of a Law must needs bee above
the Lord Major and Aldermen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> I owne the Argument, and for confirmation of what I
t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re affirmed concerning the power of <hi>the Court of Common-coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell,</hi>
I made it good, and proved it <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> facto,</hi> by an act of <hi>Common-councel</hi>
made in the sixth yeare of <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. upon the 15 of <hi>Aprill,</hi>
concerning the <hi>choice of the Chamberlaine of</hi> London, <hi>and the Bridge-masters
of the City,</hi> as by reference to the said Book appeareth,
and I would willingly see what you have to say against it.</p>
            <p>But upon this in your 25 page you thus argue:</p>
            <p>That Court which hath the power to make a law, and by that law,
to conferre a power upon the King, and Lords, which as King and Lords
they had not before, must needs be <hi>quoad hoc</hi> unto the making of a law,
above the King and Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:52607:27"/>
But the House of C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mmon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, which say you <hi>(speaking of mee)</hi> is
the kingdome representative, even as the Common-councell is the City repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentative
upon your suppos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion, hath a power, &amp;c. <hi>Ergo,</hi> the House of
Commons, so far as unto the making of a law, must needs bee above the
King and Lords.</p>
            <p>But I pray you tell me, is there no difference between the Court
of Common-councell, and the Commons in Common-councel?
I told you even now in page 42 that the Lord Major, Aldermen,
and Commons in Common-councell assembled being therein
one entire Court, are the representative body of the City, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
said the Commons in that Court were so; and if you had
been pleased to have perused that Booke of mine you cite to this
purpose, and out of which you take my argument, <hi>viz. The Ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
for the Commonalty of London,</hi> in page 10. where I instance in four
severall acts of that Court, <hi>viz.</hi> the removing of Deputy <hi>Ald<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi>
from the Court, Mr. <hi>Iohn Wilde</hi> from being Town Clerk, Mr. <hi>Tho.
Wiseman</hi> from being the City Remembrancer, and divers Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens
Deputies from their places of Deputyship, you might there
have found that I thus conclude it, <hi>viz. And all this by the joint
and concurrent power of the Lord Major, Aldermen, and Commons
in this Common-councell assembled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what though the <hi>Court of Common-councell,</hi> which alwayes
consisteth of <hi>the Lord Major, Aldermen, and Commons,</hi> have a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
to conferre upon the <hi>Lord Major and Aldermen</hi> that power,
which as <hi>Lord Major and Aldermen</hi> they had not before (as I fully
proved, and therefore without the least mutation am still of the
same mind) and in that respect, as unto the making of a Law are
above the <hi>Lord M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>jor</hi> and <hi>Aldermen,</hi> as the whole is above a part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
But will it hence follow that <hi>the Commons in Common-councell</hi> alone
and by themselves, have either this power to conferre a power
upon <hi>the Lord Major and Aldermen,</hi> which as <hi>Lord Major and
Aldermen</hi> they had not before, or that they are above them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
If you will argue from my assertion, bee sure you keep my terms,
and then see how it will advantage you for the confirmation of
your argument.</p>
            <p>I grounded this power of making City Laws from the Charter
of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. in the 15 yeare of his Reigne. And in the same Book
of mine, out of which you took my argument, you might also
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:52607:27"/>
have had my authority for it, it is in page 7 in these words, <hi>Wee
have granted further for us and our heires, and by this our present Charter
confirmed to the Major and Aldermen of the City aforesaid, that if any
customes in the said City hitherto obtained and used, be in any part diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult
or defective, or any thing in the same newly happening, where before
there was no remedy ordained, and have need of amending, the same
Major and Ald<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmen and their successors, with the assent of the Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty
of the same City, may adde and ordaine a remedy meet, faithfull,
and consonant to reason, for the common profit of the Citizens of the same
City, as oft, and at such time as to them shall be thought expedient,</hi> which
Charter was confi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>med by act of Parliament 43 yeares after, in
the 7 of <hi>Rich.</hi> 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Now if you can produce the like authority
granted alone to <hi>the House of Commons</hi> by <hi>the Parliament,</hi> that they
of themselves, without the consent of <hi>the King</hi> and <hi>the Lords,</hi> have
power to make lawes for the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> as by this Charter the
Lord Major, Aldermen, and their successors, with the assent of the
Commons of <hi>London,</hi> haue for the City, then you hit the bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ines
a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight indeed, but otherwise I thinke your argument is not true:
And therefore for after times, let me advise you, that if you will
imitate an argument in the words of it, be sure you imitate it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
in the proofes of it, and let them be as full and cleare for the
confirmation of what you affirme; for it is not words, though
never so smooth, that proves any thing in matters of fact, as this
is: And truly, should I have laid down that argument to prove
the power of <hi>the Court of Common-councell,</hi> as unto the making of
<hi>City laws</hi> to bee above the <hi>Lord Major,</hi> and <hi>Aldermen,</hi> and not
have proved it <hi>de facto,</hi> by the acts of the <hi>Court of Common-coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell,</hi>
I should have thought it at least to have been a <hi>scandalum
Magnatum,</hi> against the Lord Major and Aldermen, and very
blame-worthy in my selfe to have done it. But perhaps you think
the condition of <hi>the King,</hi> and <hi>the Lords</hi> to bee such, as that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
you speak or publish concerning them, tending to the anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilating
<hi>of their legislative power and authority in Parliament,</hi> can
neither be an offence to them, nor a fault in you, or if it bee, it
seemes you regard it not; but I hope you will not take it amisse,
if, as I did in that so I desire you in this, either to produce a proof
<hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> facto,</hi> to make good that the <hi>House of Commons</hi> hath by an Act
of that House alone conferred a power upon the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:52607:28"/>
as <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords</hi> they had not before, which are the very word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
of your argument, or else in plaine English to tell the Reader<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
that though you can transcribe the words of my argument,
which a childe of ten yeares old can doe as well as you, yet now
upon second thoughts you must needs confesse you come very
short in a parallel proofe of it, there neither now being, nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
was any act of the House of <hi>Commons</hi> that doth prove that, that
House alone and by it selfe did ever make a law which did confer
a power upon the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords,</hi> which as <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords</hi> they
had not before, and without this proofe, I perswade my selfe no
man will beleeve, that as unto the making of a law the House of
<hi>Commons</hi> is above the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords,</hi> though Mr. <hi>I. P.</hi> affirmes
it to bee so. And this I give not onely as a solution to this your
argument, but also to the other arguments which follow, <hi>viz.</hi>
concerning the power of the House of <hi>Commons</hi> alone without
the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords</hi> to repeale what lawes they think meet, and to
make laws and rules for all the Courts and people in <hi>England</hi> to
bee steered and acted by, and whereunto (say you) the <hi>King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
is bound by his Oath, and therefore ought in duty to cons<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut;</hi> and
likewise to that which you say will follow from my logick, <hi>viz.
that the Kingdome representative is inferiour in its power, in
reference to the government of the Kingdome, then the City re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentative
is in reference to the government of the City,</hi> and
to the other Queries which you ground upon them, for they all
alike hang upon this string, and if in the opinion of the Reader,
to whose judgement I referre it, this be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut asunder, I am sure they
must all then needs fall to the ground, and therefore I shall not
need to trouble my self any more with them.</p>
            <p>And now Mr. <hi>I. P.</hi> I have endeavoured with all the candor
and tendernesse I could to examine your Book, and have not I
hope, let one word fall from mee, that in the least measure doth
reflect upon your person, for it is the matter of your Book, and
not any of your personall infirmities (for, alasse the Lord
know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, I have work more then enough to meddle with, and to
master my own) or other your supposed errors in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
that I encounter with. And if we cannot yet agree in this
present difference and debate, my earnest desire is, and I trust <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y
endeavour shall for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver be answerable thereunto, that wee may
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:52607:28"/>
manage the matter with that sweet moderation and temper of
Spirit as becommeth Christians, for of this I am confident, that
though through weaknesse or error in judgement, perhaps mine,
not yours, we cannot agree together to live in one Church fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship
or communion here upon earth, yet we shall for ever mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
enjoy communion and fellowship with God the Father, with
Christ, with the blessed Spirit, three Persons in one Essence, and
with the holy Angels, and the glorified Saints for ever in heaven.
And therefore I beseech you while we yet live here in this vale
of teares, let us remember and obey that counsell the Apostle
gives us, <hi>Philip. 3. 15, 16. Let us therefore, as many as bee perfect bée
thus minded, and if in any thing you bee otherwise minded, God shall
reveale even this unto you; neverthelesse, whereunto we have already at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
let us walke by the same rule, let us mind the same thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I shall gladly imbrace and entertaine any truth of God, which
shall by you bee held forth unto mee with the warrant of his
Word, and as willingly leave and forsake whatever either in opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
or practice I now hold or doe that shall bee made apparent
to be dissonant thereto; for I solemnly professe unto you, that I
labour not for Masteries, neither desire I to give the last blow, I
esteem it no shame to be conquered, when Christ proves the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor,
nor no losse to bee vanquished when the Truth prevailes,
for it's verity, not victory that shall be my comfort.</p>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>A POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>I Have at this time no more to say, either to your selfe, or to
your Book, but in one word to let the Reader know, that my
desire and endevour to afford you all the faire quarter that possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
I could in this our Conflict about this Subject, was such, That
I did upon Saturday the 8 of this instant <hi>August,</hi> in the presence
of Mr. <hi>Samuel Clarke</hi> Pastor of <hi>Bennet Fynck, London,</hi> and of
Mr. <hi>Iames Story,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Henry Overton,</hi> two of yours, and of my
owne acquaintance, shew you in Writing this my Justification
of the City Remonstrance and its Vindication, before ever I ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
it either to be Licensed, or Printed, and desired you to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>use
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:52607:29"/>
it, and if there was any thing in it either for matter of Fact,
or otherwise, that you could justly except against, I would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punge
it, and it should never see the light; And when you
would not accept of that offer, I then read some passages in the
Epistle to you which I told you, that in my apprehension, they
were the things which most nearly concerned your Person; this
I did to manifest my unwillingnesse to let any thing passe from
mee, that might bee either prejudiciall to the Truth, or justly
distastefull to your Person, and if it be possible, to overcome evill
with good.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>In the absence of the Author these following Errata's escaped in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
of the Vindication, which I pray thus Correct.</head>
            <p>Page 2. line 23. for you will charge, read, <hi>you will not charge;</hi> p. 6. l. 30. for
and Sectaries, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>of Sectaries;</hi> p. 7. l. 1. for till, r. <hi>the;</hi> p. 8. l. last, for stated, r.
<hi>sacred;</hi> p. 14. l 22 for finde in, r. <hi>finde it in;</hi> l. 24. for these their words, r. <hi>these
are their words,</hi> p. 23 l. 27. for elected, r, <hi>erected;</hi> p. 26. l. 26. for ones Poesie,
r <hi>Ovids Poesie.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:52607:29"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
