<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The souldiers march to salvation wherein is shewn the lawfulness of voluntary serving upon the assured knowledge of a just cause, how it is lawful and necessary for prest souldiers to obey authority in case of doubting ...</title>
            <author>Bland, Francis.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-01">2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28353</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3156</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13075</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12096339</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12096339</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53992</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A28353)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53992)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 809:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The souldiers march to salvation wherein is shewn the lawfulness of voluntary serving upon the assured knowledge of a just cause, how it is lawful and necessary for prest souldiers to obey authority in case of doubting ...</title>
                  <author>Bland, Francis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 41 (i.e., 49) p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Yorke :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Soldiers --  Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>War --  Moral and ethical aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53992:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Souldiers MARCH TO SALVATION: Wherein is ſhewn the lawfulneſſe of Souldiery in a neceſſitated Warre, the lawfulneſſe of voluntary Serving upon the aſſured knowledge of a juſt Cauſe. How far it is lawfull and neceſſary for preſt Souldiers to obey Authority in caſe of doubting. What innocency ought to be in Souldiers, wherein is contained a plea againſt Plundering; in what caſes and with what Cautions it is lawfull to Kill, impriſon, or ſpoil an enemy; With what courteſie enemies ſubmitting are to bee received, and with what fidelity to be protected, with other things profitable to all men as well as Souldiers.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Francis Bland,</hi> Miniſter.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>Yorke, Anno Dom.</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:53992:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53992:2"/>
            <head>The ſouldiers March to ſalvation</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Luke. 13. 14.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>And he ſayed unto them, Doe violence to no man, neither accuſe any falſely, and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with your wages.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words containe <hi>Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tis</hi> anſwer to the ſouldiers ſearch for ſalvation, or que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, what they might doe to be ſaved; From whence may be collected ſome things ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerallyobſerveable for all men, ſome things more pecular to military men: for the generalls we may firſt note the fidelity of <hi>Iohn</hi> in<note n="a" place="margin">Mores taxat &amp; jubet aſſueta emendare vitia. <hi>Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. ſtella.</hi>
               </note> taxing the faults of theſe ſouldiers, and enjoyning them to amend and reforme their lives, if they would eſchew the vengeance of God; as
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53992:3"/>
               <note place="margin">Obſervation.</note> he did alſo the extortion of the <hi>Publicanes,</hi> and the inceſt of <hi>Herod:</hi> whence we learne, what fidelity and boldneſſe ought to be in Paſtors and<note place="margin">Iſa. 58. 1.</note> Preachers in reprehending ſinnes, and calling for<note place="margin">Matth. 5. 13.</note> reformation. The Prophet muſt cry aloud, and and lift up his voice like a trumpet; the Apoſtles muſt be ſalt becauſe of<note n="b" place="margin">Haec doctrina exigit mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem carnis. <hi>Mar.</hi> Eccleſ. 12. 11.</note> their doctrine, which requires mortification of the fleſh, faith and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, which are not pleaſant to a Carnall man. And the wordes of the wiſe are as goades<note n="c" place="margin">Junius &amp; gloſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Inter lin. in loc.</note> which ſharply prickes the ſlow, and awakes the ſleepy, that thereby the wicked may be called from their wayes, and the godly rouſed from their naturall ſluggiſhneſſe to follow their duty with greater diligence. The neceſſity of this<note place="margin">Ezek. 33. 7.</note> fidelity in all paſtors and preachers may be learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the duty of watchmen, as the Prophet Ezekiel is taught by God himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Application. 2 Tim. 4. 2.</note> This firſt teaches us our duty as S. <hi>Paul</hi> did <hi>Timothy,</hi> that we muſt reprove, rebuke, and exhort; Our Sermons muſt be rather <hi>ad planetum</hi> then <hi>ad placitum,</hi> to call men to bewaile their ſinnes then to pleaſe them in their ſinnes, according to the ſaying of an ancient father (teaching one the right way of preaching)<note n="d" place="margin">Docente te in Eccleſia non cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor populi, ſed gemitus ſuſcitet.</note> 
               <hi>when thou teacheſt in the Church let not the ſhouts, but the ſighes of the people be ſtirred up: let the teares of the hearers be thy commendations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence alſo ariſe a juſt reprehenſion of ſuch as ſeeme by ſilence to approve and by flatteries to encourage wicked men in their evill wayes,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53992:3"/>
calling evill good, and caſting vailes over mens faces, and ſowing pillowes under their elbowes, and heale the wound deceitfully, crying peace peace when there is no peace; and this is either through avarice and hope of gaine, or cowardice for feare of harme, if they ſhould ſpeake what they think, then which as S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſayd to the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Nihil in ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote tam pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riculoſum apud Deum, tam turpe apud homines, quod ſentiat non libere denunciare <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 5. 29.</note> There is nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God more dangerous, and before man more baſe.</p>
            <p>Againe, it ſerves to teach you that are hearers humility in hearing the word of exhortation and reprehenſion, count not our plain-dealing malice, nor our ſelves your enemies becauſe we tell you the truth; call us not the troublers of Iſrael for reprehending the vices of the times, ſciſe us not our Sermons what we ſhould preach as thoſe that ſayed to the Seers, ſee not, and to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets prophecie not us right things, ſpeake unto us ſmooth things, propheſie deceits; deſire us not to ſay unto you in your bad wayes as <hi>Ahabs</hi> Chaplaines, <hi>Go up, and proſper,</hi> leaſt your ends be like his; for the<note n="f" place="margin">Adulantium linguae alligant animas in pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis. <hi>Proſper. tit. Epigram.</hi> 86. Acts 10. 33. 1 Sam. 3. 17.</note> tongues of flatterers binde mens ſoules in their ſinnes which prepares them to chaines of utter darkeneſſe; you ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſay as <hi>Cornelius</hi> to <hi>Peter, we are all here in the preſence of God to heare all things which are Commanded thee of God:</hi> or as <hi>Eli</hi> did <hi>Samuel,</hi> charge them to conceale nothing of all that the Lord hath ſayed unto them. We may further from this ſpeech of <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> to theſe ſouldiers,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53992:4"/>
bidding leave their former practiſe and amend their wayes, by doing violence to no man, &amp;c. obſerve, That in repentance to ſalvation there muſt be a forſaking of ſin, and amendment of your lives; to this the Prophers and Apoſtles beare witneſſe, <hi>Waſh you, make you clean, put away the evil of your doings, ceaſe to do evill, learn to do well,</hi> (thus<note place="margin">Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Iſaiah)</hi> and then he promiſeth forgiveneſſe, that though our ſinnes were red like Scarlet or Crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yet theyſhould be as white as Wooll ar Snow:<note place="margin">Iſa. 55. 7.</note> and againe, <hi>let the wicked forſake his way and the unrighteous man his thoughts, and return unto the Lord. Repent and turn you from all your tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 18. 36. Acts 4.</note> faith <hi>Ezekiel.</hi> And the Apoſtles doctrine <hi>is, repent and be converted;</hi> and to the ſame<note n="f" place="margin">Ubi emenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio nulla, poenit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia neceſſariò eſt vana, quia caret fructu cui Deus eam ſevit. <hi>Ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ull.</hi> Vera poenitentia ſic plangit com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſla ut non committit plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genda. <hi>Bern. medi<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Application.</note> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe are the ſuffrages of the fathers, Where there is no amendment, there repentance is ſurely vaine, becauſe it wants the fruit whereunto God hath appointed it: thus one: and another ſayth, that true repentance doth ſo lament the faults committed, that it doth not committ the faults which are to be lamented; he is but a mocker, and not a true penitent that ſtill doth the things which he lamenterh.</p>
            <p>Let every one of us that deſires repentance un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to life, apply this unto his ſoul, with a ſaying of S. Bernard:<note n="g" place="margin">Si vis verus poenitens eſſe ceſſa à peccato, &amp; noli amplius pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi ſupr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> John 5. 14. &amp; 8. 11</note> 
               <hi>If thou wilt be a true penitent, ceaſe from ſin, and ſin no more:</hi> and let every one of us think that ſaying of our Saviour firſt ſpoken to him that was diſeaſed thirty and eight years, and after to the woman taken in adultery, to be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53992:4"/>
ſpoken to himſelfe, <hi>Sin no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, let us beware of flattering our ſelves  in our knowne ſinnes, thinking with ſimple <hi>miſerees,</hi> ſaying, God be mercifull to me, without ſincere endeavours of reformation, to eſcape the damnation of hell; and let none of us ſpeake to himſelfe in the language of the drunkard, I ſhall<note place="margin">Deut. 19. 19.</note> have peace though I goe on to add ſin to wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and wickedneſſe to ſin; as drunken<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe to thirſt, and thirſt to drunkeneſſe; for the anger of the Lord and his jealouſie ſhall ſmoake againſt ſuch an one: let us therefore bewaile and tremble at the word of the Lord, by the Prophet, Shall I<note place="margin">Micah 6. 11.</note> count them righteous with wicked ballances and the bag of deceitfull weights? which is as much as if it ſhould be ſaid, Shall I juſtifie him that ſtills keeps his ſin?<note n="h" place="margin">Non, ſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnabo cum, ſim juſticiae regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la. <hi>Gloſſ. int. in loc.</hi>
               </note> no, but I will condemne him, ſeeing I am the rule of juſtice: and no leſſe dangerous then this is recidivation, falling back to the mire and vomitt of our former filthineſſe, or finnes once forſaken, againſt which let us note well the ſaying of the ſon of Syrack; He that waſheth himſelf after the touching of a dead body, what availeth his waſhing if he touch it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine?<note place="margin">Ecclus. 34. 26.</note> ſo it is with a man that faſteth for his ſinnes, and goeth againe, and doth the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">There is a lawfull uſe of warre. <hi>Non jubet arma abjicere, Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento ſuo renun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciare.</hi> Calv. apud Marlorat.</note> From theſe generall obſervations, let us de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to ſome particulars, more nearly concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the queſtioners, and men of the ſame order of life. And firſt, whereas <hi>Iohn Baptiſt doth not bid them lay downe their Armes, nor renounce their</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:53992:5"/>
               <hi>troth which they plighted;</hi> nor (as wee ſay) flye away from their colours. Hence is rightly col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chemnit. Harmon. Brent. P. M. utyr. Auſtin. apud Grat. cauſ.</hi> 23. <hi>Aquin.</hi> 22. 9.40. <hi>Art.</hi> 1. Si Chriſtiana diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplina omnia bella culparet, hoc potiùs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilium Baptiſta dediſſet; ut arma abjicerint, ſeque militiae omnia ſubtraherent. Matth 8. Act. 10.</note> by learned Authors in their expoſitions upon the place, and tractates upon this ſubject of warre, an Approbation of ſouldiery or warfare, and that there is a lawfull uſe of Armes, and warre, and that even unto Chriſtians; for, <hi>If Chriſtians diſcipline did diſallow all warres, the Baptiſt would rather have given them this Advice, that they ſhould throw away their Armes, and withdraw themſelves from all manner of warfare;</hi> which he did not: nor yet did our Saviour for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid the Centurion, in whom was found greater faith then in Iſrael, to continue in his Office; Nor the Apoſtle S. <hi>Peter</hi> teach any ſuch leſſon unto the devoute Captaine <hi>Cornelius</hi> his family and friends, that were gathered together to heare all things that were commanded him of God;<note place="margin">Ecclus. 2. 8.</note> And <hi>Solomon</hi> tels us, that there is a time of warre, as well as a time of peace. Beſides all theſe, we have the examples of worthy and godly men, ſerving God in military Affaires; Some of which are ſpoken of by the Apoſtle, <hi>as of Gideon, of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 3. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Barak, of Jephthah, of Sampſon, of David, and others who through faith ſubdued Kingdomes, eſcaped the edge of the ſword, out of weakneſſe were made ſtrong, waxed valiant in Battell, and turn'd to flight the Armies of Aliens;</hi> And we finde what good ſervice <hi>Claudius Lyſias</hi> who commanded in chiefe the Garriſons and forces in <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> did unto the Church of God, by ſending <hi>Paul</hi> away from
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53992:5"/>
               <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> to <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> with a guard of two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Souldiers, threeſcore and ten Horſemen, and ſpear men two hundred; by which he ſafe eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped the conſpitacy of the Jews, that had bound<note place="margin">Acts 2. 23.</note> themſelves with an oath to kill him; And of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, it is recorded what helpe he<note place="margin">Euſeb. de vit. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan.</note> did make to the Chriſtian's, by armes againſt the tyrannie of <hi>Lycinius,</hi> and other perſecutors.</p>
            <p>Againe, as we have the conceſſion of the Spirit of God for the lawfulneſſe of warre, in not forbiding it, and the examples of worthy men ſerving God in it, ſo have we the wiſdome of the Spirit, in giving rules and lawes for mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary<note place="margin">Deut. 20.</note> orders to be obſerved in the purſuit of warre; which is another ſtrong Argument for<note place="margin">Alioqui de hâc re non ferret Leges Spititus Sanctus. <hi>Gualier.</hi>
               </note> the lawfull uſe of Armes in needfull caſes: <hi>other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Spirit of God would not have given rules on this matter;</hi> And withall adviſing not to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any thing in this kinde, but with mature<note place="margin">Prover. 20. 18. &amp; 24. 6.</note> deliberation; Thus <hi>Solomon</hi> teaches, <hi>With good Advice make warre, for that is the way to ſafety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Warre neceſſary in ſome caſes.</note> Further, that the uſe of the ſword is not only lawfull, but in ſome caſes neceſſary, may be truely collected from the ſaying of the Apoſtle, that the<note place="margin">Rom. 13. 4.</note> Magiſtrate or higher power beareth not the ſword in vaine; there being two <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>endes of the Magiſtracy, the one the good and defence of thoſe that doe good, the other the puniſhment of thoſe that doe evil: unto which ends the uſe of the ſword is very neceſſary, for hereby the Magiſtrate is enabled to defend himſelfe and his Subjects;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53992:6"/>
himſelfe, in his juſt power, and his ſubjects in their rightfull proprieties, whereunto (without the uſe of the ſword) he ſhould ſometime be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, by an over-powring ſtrength of a forreigne enemie, and others: ſometimes by the conſpiring and conbining together of inteſtine foes, and ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions perſons, raiſing routs and rebellions to the oppreſſion of the people, ſubverſion of States, ruines and alterations of Kingdoms and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and other like miſchiefes incident to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man<note place="margin">Omninò enim cùm tanta <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum turba, ut ſunt neceſſariae lege<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ica &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratus: atque etiam qui his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt milites. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer. in locum apud Marlorat.</hi> 2 Sam. 18. &amp; 20.</note> Affaires; for the prevention of which, lawes, Magiſtrates and Armes are equally ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary; <hi>Vndoubdtedly therefore ſeeing that there are ſuch a multitude of wicked men, as lawes are neceſſary, ſo alſo Magiſtrates, and likewiſe ſouldiers which are under them;</hi> And wee find this prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed by <hi>David,</hi> not only againſt the ſorraigne foes of himſelf, and his people, the Philiſtines and Ammonites: but alſo againſt the uſurpation of <hi>Iſhboſheth,</hi> as likewiſe againſt the rebellion of <hi>Abſolom,</hi> and <hi>Shebah,</hi> and their adherents.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Application.</note> From hence we may inferre conſolations and encouragments to thoſe Princes and Magiſtrates, whom open hoſtility of forreigne enemies (as <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> aſſaulted by the <hi>Moabites,</hi> and <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monites.)</hi> or the inteſtine diſobedience of unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Traitours and Rebells (as <hi>David</hi> by the<note place="margin">2 Chr. 20.</note> rebellions of <hi>Abſolom,</hi> or <hi>Shebah)</hi> or the exigencie and diſtreſſe of friends, (as <hi>Lots</hi> captivity did <hi>Abraham)</hi> or allies and confedrates (as the <hi>Gibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onites</hi> being in feare of the five Kings did <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhuah)</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:53992:6"/>
doe neceſſitate and compell to draw the ſword, and make warre (for we do alwayes think that, <hi>warre ought to be of neceſsity)</hi> and do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound<note place="margin">Bellum debeat eſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> neceſſitatis.</note> unto themſelves juſt ends, as defence of themſelves and ſubjects, their friends and confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, in their juſt powers, rights, proprieties and priviledges from wrongs; Reparation of injuries, for which no reparation can be had by peace, reſtraint of violence or confuſion, ariſing by tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous and factious men, reſtitution of peace and publique Tranquiltie where it is violated or broken, and conſervation of it where it is aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; <hi>for warre is waged, that peace may be obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellum geritur ut pax quoeratur.</note> Theſe ends I ſay, and not ſiniſter and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Aimes propounded, as enſlaving free Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, oppreſſion of weaker ſtates, invaſions and conqueſts of others dominions, enlarging private territories and treaſures, and ſuch like; which ends doe render a warre lawfull. And together with theſe ends, doe not proſecute their warres with a purpoſe to hurt, cruelly thirſting after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge with implacable malice, brutiſh rebellion, and deſire of dominearinge; with ſuch other like Affections, of which it is ſaid, that in warres<note place="margin">Nocendi cupidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, iraſcendi crudelitas, feritas rebellandi, libido dominandi; &amp; ſi qua ſunt ſimilia, haec ſunt quae in bellis jute cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pantur.</note> they are juſtly condemnable, but being on the other ſide peaceably affected, only ſeeking and demanding reparation of injuries, offering con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of peace and agreement, and having a mind prepared to embrace peace, when it ſhall be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered; and purpoſeth nothing more then to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce thoſe whom they ſhall ſubdue unto peace
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53992:7"/>
               <note place="margin">Eſto ergò bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lando pacificus, ut quas expugnas, ad pacis unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem perduc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. <hi>Gratian. cauſ.</hi> 23.</note> and unity, according to this direction; <hi>be a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker by warring, that thoſe whom thou conquereſt, thou maiſt reduce unto the unity of peace;</hi> Theſe I ſay herein may bee comforted and encouraged, their ſervice herein is no leſſe acceptable to God, though it be done by the ſword, then that which they performe in the Adminiſtration of juſtice by the Scepter in times of peace and greateſt Tranquility.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Conſolation to Souldiers.</hi> Vir juſtus, ſi fortè etiam ſub Rege homine ſacrilego militet, rectè po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt illo jubente bellare, ſi vice pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, ordinem ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vans, quod ſibi ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur, vel non eſſe contra praecep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Dei certum eſt, vel utrùm ſit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> certum non eſt; ita ut fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>taſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um reddat regem iniquitas impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randi, inocentem autem militem oſtendat ordo ſerviendi. <hi>Auguſt. apud Gratian. ubi ſupra.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Secondly, this conſolation and encouragement extends unto all ſouldiers, that are called to armes by juſt Authoritie, and doe ſerve under their Princes in the Lords Battels; The workes of a juſt warre duely managed, are no more by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to true happineſſe, then the workes of their ordinary vocations in times of peace; yea, ſo it may bee, that juſt and godly ſouldiers may ſerve under a wicked King or Prince, and yet may be free from ſinne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> A juſt man if happily he ſerve under a King that is a ſacrilegious man, may rightly warre vnder his Command, if inſtead of peace, keeping the order of warre, he be aſſured that the thing which is commanded him be not contrary to the commandement of God, or bee vncertaine whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be ſo or not: and thus the unjuſt command may make the King an offendex, but the order of ſerving may ſhew the ſouldier to be innocent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Unto the queſtion which is ſometime made,</hi> See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Princes do ſometimes raiſe warres from bad Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and for wicked ends and purpoſes, hom ſhould the conſciences of the Subjects be ſatified?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:53992:7"/>
               <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> It is anſwered thus, or to this purpoſe; The Subjects either know the cauſe wherein the King commands their ſervice to bee juſt or wicked, or elſe they are ignorant or doubtfull whether it be ſo or not; in caſe of ſure knowledge, there is no difficulty in anſwering, but they ought to obey, the cauſe being juſt, and to refuſe obedience, the cauſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> being apparantly unjuſt; and any thing commanded repugnant to juſtice, godlineſſe and Religion, and are rather to ſuffer his diſpleaſure, then fullfill his will contrary to a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, remembring God is to be obeyed before man; but if they be doubtfull, or ignorant, then the Subject ought to be perſwaded that the cauſe and intended ends of ſuch warre are juſt, and that it is not undertaken contary to the word of God; and becauſe ſubjects cannot alwayes underſtand the councels of their Princes, here in the caſe<note place="margin">Tene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ertu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que incertum. <hi>Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ha. Magiſt. quaſt.</hi> 50</note> of doubting, the Rule muſt be followed, <hi>hold that which is certaine, and leave the vncertainty;</hi> but the certaine is that Princes and Powers are to be obeyed, which command nothing contrary to the word; and in ſo doing, as a Sanctuary or Refuge was appointed by the Lawe to him that killed his Neighbour not wilfully, or of ſet purpoſe, ſo the ſubjects are worthily excuſed, whileſt in a doubtfull cauſe they obey their Prince.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Conſolation to Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunteers.</note> Thirdly, this conſolation and encouragement extends not only to Princes and ſouldiers preſt and compelled to Armes by their Authority, but even unto voluntiers, ſuch as upon the knowledge
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53992:8"/>
and perſwaſion of a juſt cauſe, for love to uplhold the honour of God, and the King his vicegerent, and for the ſafety of their country, Church, Laws, liberties, and Religion, or for the defence and vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of their friends, Allies and confederates, do of their owne free will and meer motion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take themſelves to Armes; ſo as not being moved with mercenary ends, reſpecting pay and hire, which are the Attractives of mercenary ſouldiers, A ſort of men condemned not only of divine but<note place="margin">Cauponantes Bellum. <hi>Tull. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ic. lib.</hi> 1. 18.</note> even humane Authors. As of the noble <hi>Pyrr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> it is ſaid, that he would not have <hi>Huckſters of warre;</hi> That would ſell their ſtrength and kill for mony. And a Poet Satyrically thus declames againſt<note place="margin">Nulla ſides pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſque viris qui caſtra ſequuntur, Venaleſque ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus: ibi fas ubi maxima merces; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt parvo <hi>Luca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. lib.</hi> 10. 406.</note> them.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Faith and devotion are of one account,</l>
               <l>To men that Campe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and mexcenary warre</l>
               <l>Frequent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there's right where greateſt pay doth mount,</l>
               <l>For little hire they ſerve, that's all they care.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But not being drawne by this conſideration of pay, or intent together wealth by pillage and booty, reſpecting neither the cauſe for which they fight, nor perſon, whether Turke, Tyrant or Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour under<note place="margin">Non enim mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare dil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctum oſt, ſed propter prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam militav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum eſt <hi>De verb. Dom. Serm.</hi> 19.</note> whom they ſerve, which doth render the warre unlawfnll<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> according to the ſaying of S. <hi>Auſten; to warre it is not a ſin, but to make warre or ſerve in warre for the prey or booty, is a ſin.</hi> but thoſe (I ſay) whoſe candid ſpirits are free from ſuch ſiniſter and baſe intendements, their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53992:8"/>
voluntary and valourous endeavours, and adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing their lives, and what is precious unto them, (like thoſe noble Voluntiers the governours of<note place="margin">Judg. 4. 9.</note> Iſrael that offered themſelves willingly among the people) as their Act is worthy of unfading honor, ſo may they receive infallible comfort and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, and know themſelves as well as<note place="margin">Non eſſe Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidas, ſed mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtros legis, nec ultores injuria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſuarum, ſed ſalutis publicae defenſores <hi>Aquin. Caetenâ a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reâ in locum.</hi>
               </note> others, <hi>Not to be murderers, but miniſters of the Law; not Revengers of their owne priviate wrongs, but defenders of the publike ſafety;</hi> As tis noted that <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> did account theſe ſouldiers in our Text. I will ſtretch this line no further, leaſt I ſeem to flatter, only I crave leave to adde this pithy exhortation, which I have borrowed from an Author, not unlearned; and here inſerted it, being very profitable for all ſouldiers to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve;<note place="margin">A profitable exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to all ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</note> Let the Chriſtian ſouldier therefore be ever doing ſomething, let him be couragious,<note place="margin">Semper itaque agat miles Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianus a liquid, ſit ſtrenuus, fidelis, laborioſus; cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turionibus obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quens, &amp;c. <hi>Bullin. de Cad.</hi> 2. <hi>Ser.</hi> 9.</note> faithfull, laborious, and obedient to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders; Let him not ſlip any occaſion, but be excerciſed in military diſcipline, let him not be cowardly, but valiant; not cruell and bloudy, but yet ſevere and withall gentle, and courteous, as times ſhall require; Let him ſpoile nothing that he can preſerve, and before all things, let him not neglect his dayly and conſtant prayers unto God, as well in ſafety, as in midſt of danger: let him begin all things with God, and, without God, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt nought at all; if hee taſte Adverſity, let him not caſt downe his heart, and if he enjoy proſperity let him not be proud, but ever thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53992:9"/>
and alwayes uſe the victory with clemencie and mercy; let him totally depend upon God, and deſire nothing more then the defence of the Common-wealth, lawes, Religion, Juſtice and the innocent; and thus fighting the good fight, he ſhall at laſt obtaine the crowne of righteouſneſſe; and if the Lord of hoſts (which is the Generall of all Armies, and other Generalls but his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers) at his comming ſhall finde him thus doing, he ſhall be no leſſe happy, then if he were found imployed in the workes of his ordinary vocation;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fuit ejus vitae ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia virtus, gloria mortis comes.</hi> Epitaph. Freder, D. Bavariae cogno. vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victorioſ. apud Ph. Camerar. oper. ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſivarum, Tr. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> or at his prayers and exerciſe of his moſt pious and ſacred devotions, and upon his Monument may worthily be inſcribed this Epitaph, <hi>Valour was the Aſſociate of his life and the Comerade of his death was glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having ſeen the lawfulneſſe of ſouldiery, let us now come to ſee what is unlawfull in ſouldiers, taught us by theſe words of John Baptiſt, <hi>Do violence to no man, neither accuſe any ſalſely, and be content with your wages;</hi> wherein are obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, theſe things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that they muſt hurt no mans perſon, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the poore which cannot defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, wounding their Bodies, unduly affrighting them, or other wayes injuring them under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of their office; for it uſually happens, that thoſe Armes which the Prince commands to be taken up for the defence of the publike orders, and honeſty, are turned to the dammage and ruine of the inhabitants of city and country
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53992:9"/>
For oftentimes the ſouldiers do plunder and burne houſes, drive away the inhabitants, raviſh the women, breake open the doores, and commic ſuch like outrages; all which they think lawfull for them being ſouldiers.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they muſt not accuſe any man falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or lay ſome capitall crime to his charge, as ſome did, accuſing the innocent, and making in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation againſt them to the Generall, or other chiefe Commanders, that they might thereby lick money out of the rich men, which they could not otherwayes extort out of them, and at the laſt ſome part of the goods that were confiſcated, might accrew to the Informer, for their labour, and for the hire of ſuch information.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they muſt be content with their wages, ſuch pay as was allowed unto them by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror for their labor &amp; pains taken in war for the defence of the commonwealth, or with ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of victualls as was appointed them, for in times paſt ſouldiers had not their pay in mony, but in victualls<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and with this <hi>Iohn</hi> teacheth them to be content, and not to extort mens goods from them, or to grate giftes out of them, or to borrow any thing, or buy it of them, and pay them either ſlowly, little, or nought at all; Thus<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et. Chemnit. Gorram Stell. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the words are expounded by divers Authors of great learning and famous in the Church; from all which we learne, how innocent ſouldiers ought<note place="margin">Obſervation.</note> to be, and to offend or wrong no man in body, name or goods, Not in body, <hi>They muſt do vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:53992:10"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vivel fraude fiat injuria.</hi> Tull. Off. l. <hi>1.</hi> ubi agr. de bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licis Officiis.</note> 
               <hi>to no man,</hi> not in name, <hi>They muſt not accuſe any falſely,</hi> nor in goods <hi>by force or fraud;</hi> for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries may be done either by open force or cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſubtility: but they muſt be content with their wages.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12. 11.</note> That I may drive this nayle (as <hi>Solomon</hi> cals the words of the <hi>wiſe)</hi> to the head, give me leave to beate it home with ſome reaſons or Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;<note place="margin">I. <hi>Chriſtianitie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it.</hi> Matth. 10. 16.</note> And firſt, becauſe I ſpeak unto Chriſtians, this may be learned from Chriſt, who commands us to be innocent or harmleſſe as Doves. This we are taught to be the foundation of our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall building up in a Chriſtian practice and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right<note place="margin">Aedificanti itaque tibi ſpiritualem domum, non ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per levitatem are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae, ſed ſuper ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liditatem petrae, innocentiae inpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ponatur, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per quod poſſis ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duum juſtitiae culmen erigere, maximam enim partem juſtitiae imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>evi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Hieron. Epiſt. ad Celan.</hi> Noviſſimun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quod dabitur tali viro, eſt pax. <hi>Munſter.</hi>
               </note> living, by an Ancient Father thus ſpeaking; <hi>Whilſt thou art building thy ſpirituall houſe, let the foundation be firſt layd not upon light ſand, but upon the ſolid Rock, upon which thou maleſt more eaſely reare up the high top of Righteouſneſſe; for he ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filleth the greateſt part of righteouſneſſe, that hurts no body;</hi> and he which ſhall lay the foundation of innocencie, and proceed on the high topp of Righteouſneſſe, howſoever he ſhall be toſſed in tumultuous warres and troubles for a ſhort while in this life, yet ſhall hee be ſure to find reſt and peace at the laſt; if not in his life, yet at leaſt in his death; as we learne from <hi>Davids</hi> words; <hi>Keep innocency and take heed unto the thing that is right, for that ſhall bring a man peace at the laſt;</hi> or as the other Tranſlation reades it, <hi>Marke the perfect man and behold the upright, for the end of that man is peace;</hi> or as another reade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the laſt thing that</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:53992:10"/>
               <hi>ſhall be given to ſuch a man is peace.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>II.</hi> The nature and property of a godly war requires it.</note> A ſecond Argument to induce ſouldiers to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie, ſhall be the ſame that <hi>Abigail</hi> uſed to reſtraine <hi>David</hi> from plundring and deſtroying <hi>Nabal,</hi> as he had reſolved, in revenge of a diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, in <hi>Nabals</hi> refuſing to ſend him ſome ſmall proviſion, which he requeſted of him in his great neceſſity; <hi>My Lord</hi> (ſaid ſhee) <hi>fighteth the Lords</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25. 28. Si bella Jehovae Dominus meus gerat, &amp; malum non inveniatur in te. <hi>Junius.</hi> Cùm praelia Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini Domin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> praeliari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, malitia ergò non invenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. <hi>Vulgar.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>battels, and evill hath not been found in thee all thy dayes;</hi> it is thus read by a learned Tranſlatour; <hi>If my Lord fight the Lords battels, and evil ſhould not be ſound in thee;</hi> And another thus, <hi>Seeing thou my Lord wageſt the Lords warres, therefore let not iniquity bee found in thee:</hi> Teaching us, that thoſe that fight the Lords battels, (as all thoſe doe who fight under a juſt Authority in a good and juſt cauſe) ſhould be carefull to be free from violence and iniquity. It is a diſgrace to an honeſt man to have wicked perſons lodge in his houſe, and to a School-maſter to have Rakehells under his tuition, and to a Generall to harbour vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains under his command; but moſt of all it is a diſhonour to the Majeſty of the Lord of hoſts, that wickedneſſe and villany ſhould march under his colours, and take up quarters in his leaguers and garriſons.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>III.</hi> Innocency preſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es from grief of heart, and torture of conſcience.</note> A third reaſon may be collected alſo from other words of <hi>Abigail</hi> in the purſuit of her buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe unto <hi>David, This ſhall be no griefe unto thee, nor offence of heart to my Lord (ſaith ſhee) either that thou haſt ſhed blood cauſeleſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or that my</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:53992:11"/>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 31.</note> 
               <hi>Lord hath avenged himſelfe;</hi> if her former argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will not move, her latter ſurely will prove effectuall; though a man reſpect not the glory of God, yet ſurely he will (even of ſelfe-love) have reſpect to his owne comfort, and freedom from a tormenting conſcience, which by innocencie is conſerved; and know all men aſſuredly, that thoſe who now lay ſiege to Townes and Caſtles, ſhall one day either in warre or peace, in bed or battel be beſieged with the memory of their ſinnes;<note place="margin">Hic murus ahe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus erit, Nil conſcire ſibi, nullâ pallelcere culpâ. <hi>Horat. Ep.</hi> 1.</note> and then,
<q>
                  <l>This unto him ſhall be a Brazen Wall,</l>
                  <l>His Conſcience to fear no ſinn at all.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>A ſtrong Fort (I ſay) it ſhall be, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable to all the Helliſh Furies, to have a Conſcience void of offence before God and man, when innocent and cauſleſſe blood, plundered<note place="margin">Exugentes ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinem Elephan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum eos occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt, &amp; ipſi vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſim incbriati opprimuntur &amp; commoriuntur. <hi>Plin. Hiſt. nat. l.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>Violence in Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers makes the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition unſuccesfull.</hi>
               </note> Goods, and unjuſt Booty, ſhall be unto the Actors thereof, as the Elephants blood unto the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons, that <hi>ſucking the blood of the Elephants, do kill them, and they themſelves, being drunk &amp; therewith, oppreſſed, not able to digeſt it, die alſo:</hi> So thoſe that by violence, rapine and injuſtice have kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and undone others, ſhall by ſuch deeds be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly and eternally undone themſelves.</p>
            <p>A fourth reaſon recalling ſouldiers from vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, may be taken from the malignant effect or conſequence hereof, that it makes the expedition unſucceſſefull, and prepares diſcomſiture to the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53992:11"/>
whole Army, and that by theſe particulars. <note place="margin">Exercitus quem injuria &amp; audacia antecedit plerum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que cladem &amp; interitum omi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturi. Iſa. 1. 51.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>I.</hi> Their priyers are hindred.</note> Firſt, hereby the acceſſe of their prayers unto God, &amp; his acceptance of them is hindered, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the menace of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, VVhen you ſpread out your hands I will hide mine eyes, yea when you make many prayers I will not hear; your hands are full of blood.</hi> The neceſſity of innocent hands to be preſented to God in prayer, rhoſe that had onely naturall Theologie well percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and therefore the Perſians arriving at <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos</hi> with a Navy of a thouſand Ships, did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent<note place="margin">Religioſas potiùs quàm rapaces manus. <hi>Val. Max. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1, 2 Chron. 20.</note> in <hi>Apolloes</hi> Temple <hi>rather religious then ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picious hands.</hi> And for the practice and efficacy of prayers in Armies, we have the examples of <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> aſſaulted by the <hi>Moabites</hi> and <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monites,</hi> and of the Chriſtian Emperours <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> who appointed prayers unto his ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and taught them to aſcribe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Victories unto God, and to crave his bleſſing and aſſiſtance for the time to come; and <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> who count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed<note place="margin">Euſeb. de vit. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> his prayers his beſt and accuſtomed Forces: Beſides, our own Chronicles relate the effect of prayer in the Army of King <hi>William</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour, who the night and morning before the<note place="margin">Ruffin. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. 1. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> Battell with <hi>Harold,</hi> did give themſelves to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge<note place="margin">Stow.</note> their ſins, prayer, and communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Lords Body; whileſt <hi>Harold</hi> and his Forces ſpent the whole night in drinking, ſinging and dancing.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>II.</hi> Memory of former violence makes men Cowards.</note> 2. The conſcience, wherin remains the memory of former violence &amp; injuſtice, makes men Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53992:12"/>
and afraid to grapple with death, which they muſt encounter together with their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies<note place="margin">Merces malae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcienciae eſt time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re eos, quibus ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i eſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uit. In praelio cervi, in pace Leones. <hi>Beza in Annotat. Mar.</hi> 11. 32. <hi>apud Jun. in Bibl. Majo.</hi>
               </note> in the field; and ſo afraid of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as Deaths meſſengers: <hi>The reward of an evill Conſcience is to fear thoſe unto whom a man might be a terrour;</hi> and this makes them to be <hi>as ſwift as Harts in time of warre,</hi> that are <hi>as ſtout as Lyons in time of peace;</hi> whereas a candid and clear conſcience that is not terrified with the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of by-paſt ſins, makes them that expedite a good cauſe as bold as Lyons. It was a noble ſaying of one <hi>Dercyllidas</hi> a Senatour of <hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Siquidem Deus eſt qui minatur, non timeamus, nihil enim injuſtè agimus; ſin homo, norit quod viris minetur. <hi>Stob. de fortitud. cap.</hi> 7. Occidere poſſunt, laedere non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt.</note> hearing that <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> lead a great Army a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and threatned ſore, <hi>If he be a God that threatens us, let us not fear, for we do nothing amiſſe; but if he be a man, let him know that he threatens men.</hi> This (I ſay) is the fruit of a guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe conſcience, which may encourage the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſor to ſay of his enemies, <hi>Kill me they may, hurt me they cannot.</hi> But the evill conſcience, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing death, not onely as the diſſolution of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but as Gods Provoſt-Marſhall, to arreſt him, binde him hand and foot, neck and heels, and ſo caſt him into utter darkneſſe and eternall tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; no wonder it is if it beget a cowardize the heart of Souldiers, and ſo they become either<note place="margin">
                  <hi>IV.</hi> Violence and inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice cauſeth God to withdraw his help from the whole army Propter impios &amp; ſceleratos ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines, caeteri Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinâ ope deſtituti ab hoſtibus cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duntur. Joſhua 7. Non ex infirmita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te corporis, ſed ex peccato vince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur. <hi>Chryſoſt. Hom.</hi> 14. <hi>ad popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Tom.</hi> 4. Poſtquàm in pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum cecidêrunt omnibus facti ſunt expugnabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, &amp; quos arma &amp; equi, &amp; mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp; tot machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namenta capere non potuerunt, hos peccati na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura vinctos ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtibus tradidit. Sed quales oro fructus metimus hodiè ex hujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi ſemente? vincimur à Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, ludibrium ſumus omnibus gentibus, pareu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; Mahometiſmo ſubduntu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> regna; &amp; inexplicabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus indiem malis involvimur. <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin. Decad.</hi> 2. <hi>ſer.</hi> 9.</note> Runawayes from their Colours, or in hot ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to hang back, which giveth advantage to the enemie, diſcourageth their fellows, diſorders the Army, and hazzards all.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, violence, rapine and injuſtice in ſome
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53992:12"/>
Souldiers cauſeth God to withdraw himſelf from the whole Army, and ſo <hi>for wicked and impious men the reſt are deſtitute of the help of God, and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of their enemies;</hi> yea, although they other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe proſecute a good Cauſe, as is apparent in the caſe of <hi>Achan,</hi> whereunto I referr you; and of the Jewes affairs in their warrs, it is obſerved by <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> that <hi>they were conquered not of the weakneſſe of Body, but of their wickedneſſe</hi> and further notes, how the Midianites under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that the Iſraelites could not be vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by the ſword, cunningly ſought to bring them into ſin, by ſending their daughters to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit whoredome with them, and then <hi>after they fell into ſin they became eaſie to be ſubdued of all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and thoſe whom Arms, and Horſes, and Souldiers and ſo many enemies could not take, the nature of ſin betrayed them bound unto their enemies.</hi> And not unlike to this obſervation of this Ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the obſervation and ſad complaint of the impiety and wickedneſſe of ſome ſouldiers by a learned Author of latter times, <hi>what fruit I pray you reap we from ſuch ſeed? we are conquered of the Turks, we are a ſcorn to all Nations; Kingdoms periſh and are ſubdued to Mahometiſme, and wee are daily involved in inexplicable miſeries.</hi> Thus by violence, rapine and other ſinns in ſouldiers, whileſt their prayers are rejected, their courage abated, and Gods favour and help alienated, are whole Armies routed and diſcomfited, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Kingdoms overthrown and ruinated.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:53992:13"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>IV.</hi> Violence and inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice are unfruitfull in the end.</note> A fourth reaſon, and that a very forcible one to diſſwade ſouldiers, and indeed all manner of men from violence, rapine and injuſtice, may be taken from the unfruitfulneſſe of ſuch Acts, and conſideration of what benefit is gotten by ſuch deeds; ſuppoſe a man could get into his hands all the wealth of the world, and bring the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms under his dominion, when he ſhall thinke to ſing a Requiem to his ſoule and to take his eaſe, having goods laid up for many years, at laſt hee muſt heare or feele what is ſpoken to the<note place="margin">Luke 12.20.</note> Richman, <hi>Thou fool th is night ſhall they fetch away thy ſoule from thee, then whoſe ſhall thoſe things be that thou haſt gotten?</hi> Thoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms which thou haſt ſubdued, thoſe Lands and Houſes which thou now poſſeſſeſt, having expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the old inhabitants, thoſe clothes and jewells wherewith thou now arrayeſt and adorneſt thy ſelfe, whileſt the ancient owners goe fortorne and diſtitute, whoſe ſhall they be? thine they ſhall not be, for thy ſoule ſhall be fetched away from thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and for thy body, naked cameſt thou out of thy mothers wombe, and naked ſhalt thou returne thither; All thy high Trophies and rich prizes and booties left behind thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd thou, if thy deſires were as boundleſſe as<note place="margin">U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s Pellaeo ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veni non ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>icit Orbis. <hi>Juvenal. Satyr.</hi> 10. Sarcophago con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentus oris.</note> 
               <hi>Alexanders</hi> of whom it was ſaid, that,
<q>
                  <l>One world doth not the Pellaean youth ſuffice.</l>
               </q>
Yet,
<q>
                  <l>Then with a Cophine thou muſt be content.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:53992:13"/>
But if thy Aſhes after thy death ſhall have the honour of a Statue, or a rich Monument, yet time will conſume it, or malice breake it downe. As <hi>Scipio Africanus</hi> his Statue was broken downe, and removed from the place where it was firſt ſet, and the brazen urne wherein his aſhes were put, with an Epitaph inſcribed, of which theſe verſes were a part,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Whom neither Europe could reſiſt,<note place="margin">Cui non Europa, non obſtitit Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca quondam, Reſpice res ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum quàm brevis urna tenet <hi>Epitom. Plutarch. per Darium Tiber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi>
                  </note> nor Afrique in times paſt,</l>
               <l>See mens Affayres, how him doth hold a little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rn at laſt.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But might they ſo part with on even hands their acts of violence, plundering and injuſtice, happy were they; but then comes their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> S. Auſten ſayth, <hi>This is the unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ipſa eſt infelici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas hominum proprer quod pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant morientes hic dimittunt, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> peccata ipſa ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum portant.</note> 
               <hi>of men, that the thing for which they ſin when they die, they leave here behind them, But their ſinnes themſelves they cary along with them;</hi> and an heavy burthen will ſuch a carriage be unto their ſoules. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hans</hi> heape of ſtones, which were caſt upon him, were heavier ſure then the Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniſh<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hom.</hi> 2.</note> garments, and all the Gold and Silver that he had plundered at <hi>Hiericho:</hi> But if thoſe<note place="margin">Joſhua 7. 26.</note> ſtones were poyſed, they would be found lighter by much then the guilt of thoſe ſinnes, which by violence, plundering, rapine, and other Acts of injuſtice, men doe contract unto their ſoules, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o heavy is it, as they are not able to beare it, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53992:14"/>
yet ſo adhering that they were not able to ſhake it of. Oh who is able to expreſſe with what unwillingneſſe the ſoul at death doth undertake its neceſſitated departure, being loath to leave the things that were precious to it, and appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God with a conſcience blotted with inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood, and other acts of cruelty and injuſtice, which if it might, it would now caſt away with as much diſdaine and anguiſh of ſpirit, as <hi>Iudas</hi> did the thirty peeces of ſilver gotten for betraying Chriſt; and through the terrour of an accuſing conſcience, deſpairing, cry out, I have ſinned in ſhedding the blood, cheating, extorting, and plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the goods, and in ſlandering and defaming the credits and cauſes of juſt and innocent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. There is an excellent paſſage in S. <hi>Bernard,</hi> which we will borrow, being very profitable to the purſuance of this Argument; When the ſoul<note place="margin">Cùm magno me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u, magis dolori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus anima ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur à corpore, &amp;c. <hi>Meditat. Devot. cap.</hi> 2.</note> with great feare and mighty griefes is ſeparated from the body, then do the Angels command, arreſt it, and bring it before the Throne of the dreadfull Judge, and then the ſilly ſoule remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring all the evil, yea the worſt deeds, which day or night it wrought, ſhal tremble &amp; crave ſparing, or (as wee ſay) cry quarter, ſaying, give me leave &amp; ſpaning, if it be but for an hours ſpace; but then his ſinnes (as it were) ſpeaking, ſhall ſay unto him, Thou haſt wrought us, we are thy deeds, wee will not leave thee, but we will be alwayes with thee, and goe with thee to judgement; Then his vices ſhall accuſe his ſoule with many and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53992:14"/>
ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dry crimes, and ſhall find many falſe witneſſes againſt it, though the true ones are enough to its condemnation; The divels alſo with a terrible countenance and horrible aſpect, ſhall affright it, and with a great fury perſecute it, and catch at it, deſiring to keep and poſſeſſe it, except there be ſome to deliver it: then the ſoule findes the eyes and mouth and other ſenſes ſhut up, by which it was wont to goe out and ſolace it ſelfe in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, ſhall turne back into it ſelfe, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelfe all alone and naked, ſhall (thorow deſpaire) faile in it ſelfe, and fall under its owne ſelfe; And becauſe for the love of the world and pleaſure of the fleſh it hath forſaken th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> love of God, it ſhall be forſaken of God in the houre of ſo great neceſſity, and be delivered to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels in Hell to be tormented. Thus farre S. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> whoſe Meditation, (were it well thought upon and ſeriouſly beleeved) would worke un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly a great reſtraint in men from many acts of violence and injuſtice, which now without ſcruple of conſcience they commit.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſing all that hath been ſaid to be ſpoken <note place="margin">Que<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</note> of friends, what may be done to enemies? ſure it is lawfull to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe all violence againſt them;</p>
            <p>Hereunto I anſwer; Firſt we are to conſider <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> enemies as men opponent to peace and juſtice, and to theſe they are by warrs to be reduced; And no other ends in the purſuite of enemies by ſword and hoſtile Acts are to be ſought for; Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſaying of <hi>Tully,</hi> For this end are
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53992:15"/>
               <note place="margin">Ut in pace cum Juſtitiâ vivatur. <hi>Offic. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Gratian. ubi ſupra.</hi> Pax quaeſita. <hi>Auſt.</hi>
               </note> wars undertaken: <hi>that men may live in peace with juſtice.</hi> And S. <hi>Auſten</hi> calls a juſt warre, <hi>peace ſought,</hi> or <hi>a ſeeking of peace:</hi> Theſe Authors from Nature and Divinity, teaching us, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is done in warre ought to aime at theſe ends of peace and juſtice: As firſt, to offer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of peace, as was commanded by God unto<note place="margin">Deut. 20. 10.</note> the people of Iſrael, and if they ſhould be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then their enemies were to be preſerved in ſafety; upon the performance of tribute or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions agreed on.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if ſuch conditions of peace ſhould be<note place="margin">Ibid. 12. 13</note> refuſed, then were the enemies to be proſecuted in hoſtile manner, as killing the men and ſpoyling their goods; But here the Lord, though he gave the Iſraelites liberty againſt their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, yet he gave them two rules of reſtrainte;</p>
            <p>Firſt, the ſword ſhould nor touch the innocent, as women and children.</p>
            <p>Secondly, regard was to be had of ſuch things as were neceſſary to the preſervation of life, as fruit-trees, of which reſpect was to be had, that they were not to be cut downe for any ſervice in<note place="margin">Deut 20. 19.</note> warre or in a ſiege of a City; becauſe <hi>the Tree of the field is mans life:</hi> The like we may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand of corne-fields and Meadowes, Gardens, and Orchards; by the fruit and ſtrength whereof mans life is preſerved; and ſurely the conſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe, both in Leaguers and Marches, ought very heedfully to be provided, whether they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to friends or foes; If they belong friends,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53992:15"/>
it is inhumane to ſpoyl or waſte them; if they belong to enemies, it is great pollicy to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them, that the Army may be ſupplied with neceſſaries; and here if I could doe it without ſeeming to digreſſe, I would gladly plead for the ſafety and immunity of the fruits of the ground from ſpoyle and devaſtation in warrs, and make ſuite for a protection for the husbandman and his labours, together with things belonging unto husbandry, that they might be ſafe from violence, the neceſſity of Agriculture or husbandry being of ſuch conſequence, that by it onely both in warres and peace the life of Kings and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms is conſerved; for this cauſe there was an<note place="margin">Camerar. Meditat, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt. Tom. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi> Tom. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> Imperiall Lawe, that husbandmen and ſuch as were occupied in country buſineſſes, whilſt they were reſident in villages and country-Townes, ſhould be ſecure in any part of the Empire, ſo as none ſhould be found that dare preſume to invade, take or violently carry away their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Oxen, inſtruments of Husbandry, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever belonged unto the country-work; and if<note place="margin">Concil. Lateranenſ.</note> any man ſhould dare through raſh boldneſſe to violate and breake this Statute, he ſhould reſtore what he had taken fourefold, ſhould incurre in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famie by the Law, and be further puniſhed at the Generals or Emperours diſcretion: And as the the commonwealth, ſo the Church according to its power did provide for the priviledge and ſafety of husbandmen among others, that, <hi>Thoſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">In agriculturâ ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tes &amp; animalia quibus arant, &amp; Semina portant ad agrum, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruâ ſecuritate laetentur.</note> 
               <hi>who were employed in Husbandry, and their cattell</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:53992:16"/>
               <hi>wherewith they tilled the ground, and carried ſeed to the field, ſhould enjoy convenient ſecurity:</hi> And of <hi>Cyrus</hi> the great it is regiſtred, that when he went to warrs, he cauſed proclamation to be made, that husbandmen ſhould be ſpared, and that the conqueſt ſhould be ſo ordered, that they might ſtill remaine in their poſſeſſions; and of <hi>Xerxes</hi> King of Perſia in his expedition againſt the Graecians, that he gave charge for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity<note place="margin">Armatis viris non paſtoribus bellum inferamus</note> of Country men, ſaying unto one <hi>Artabanus, Let us fight with armed men, and ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dirs, and not with ſhepherds;</hi> And of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Indians</hi> it was counted a wrong in warres, either to take the husbandmen, or to ſpoyle their fields; and ſuch was their care for husbandry, that at one and the ſame time and place ſome did meet and joyn battle with their enemies; when others did plow and digge, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any danger. This courſe was taken by <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, in his warres with <hi>Francis</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> in <hi>Piedmount;</hi> ſo as they kept either of them a numerous Army, for certaine years, otherwiſe proviſion would quickly have been wanting to their Forces.</p>
            <p>But to return from whence we digreſſed; women, and children being ſpared, the ftuits of the earth conſerved, and husbandmen kept indemnified, thoſe, who by force and Armes oppoſe peace and juſtice, to ſuch armed powers as ſeeke to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh them, to kill and ſlay, none will deny to be Acts of Juſtice: or to take them alive, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53992:16"/>
or enſlave them, and to appropriate their Goods, Riches, and Poſſeſſions as a lawfull prize unto the conquerors; And yet herein much caution is to be had, whereunto it ſhall not be unprofit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able<note place="margin">
                  <hi>I.</hi> How to kill an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in warre.</note> to obſerve theſe Rules.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in killing, ſlaying and taking away the life of the enemy, is much regard to be had with what mind, intentions, and affections it is done. S. <hi>Bernard</hi> hath a diſtinction very profitable to this<note place="margin">Si praevales, &amp; vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntate ſuperandi vel vindicandi, fortè occidis hominem vivis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> homicida. <hi>Bern. ad milit. Templ.</hi>
               </note> purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>If thou prevaileſt, and perhaps killeſt a man out of deſire of conqueſt and revenge, then thou liveſt a Murtherer;</hi> which name who is he that would not be loath to carry among men, or that his ſoule ſhould appeare in the preſence of God with ſo grievous a ſin upon the conſcience, as the murther of a man: that creature whereon God hath ſet the glorious character of his own Image.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>There is nevertheleſſe ſome which</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſt tamen qui non ulciſcendi zelo, nec vincen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di typho, ſed tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tùm evadendi re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medio interficit hominem.</note> 
               <hi>neither out of zeal, to revenge, nor deſire of vistory, kils a man, but only for remedies ſake,</hi> of avoyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or eſchewing ſome ill; as to ſuppreſſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, to reſiſt invaſions, oppeſſions and the like; In which caſes to kill an enemie is undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly lawfull. And yet herein it ſhall much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hove the killer, (though neceſſity compell him to deſtroy the body of his enemie) to wiſh well unto him that falleth under his hand, and toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the wounds of death which hee giveth him, to pray unto God to ſave his ſoule, and to grant him repentance, faith, and every grace that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53992:17"/>
is needfull to everlaſting life.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>II.</hi> Clemency to be ſhewn to ſubdued and conquered enemies.</note> Againe, not only in taking away the life of the enemy, but alſo in impriſoning or enſlaving his perſon, and taking his goods, appropriating them to the Conquerours themſelves, is much moderation and gentle clemency to be uſed. And that for theſe Reaſons;</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Humanity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it.</note> Firſt humanitie requires it, the conquerours and conquered being both of one Nature, and deriving their originals both from one Roote, and that theſe warres as other oppoſitions, are the conſequents of mans fall, wherein the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and conquered had equall ſhare, being in the loyns of <hi>Adam,</hi> which ſhould move the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours to pity thoſe who by hoſtile Acts, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther force or feats of warre, are ſubdued; And<note place="margin">1 King. 20. 32.</note> to ſay of them as <hi>Ahab</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſaid of <hi>Benhadab</hi> King of <hi>Syria,</hi> ſubdued by his Forces, and making ſuit for quarter, <hi>Hee is my Brother;</hi> and the conquerours ſhould behold neither the mortall wounds, nor the living miſeries of their ſubdued enemies, but with compaſſion. Thus of <hi>Aneas</hi> it is ſaid, when he ſaw the blood and fall of<note place="margin">Ingenuit miſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, <hi>Virgil Aeucid Lib.</hi> 10. Pictatis imago.</note> 
               <hi>Lauſus</hi> his enemie, ſlaine by his owne hand, <hi>He la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented him pitifully;</hi> and therefore is called, <hi>The image of piety</hi> (I may ſay, <hi>of pitie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>)</hi> And of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ollas,</hi> which having conquered <hi>Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilie,</hi> which had ſtood out very obſtinately againſt him, and ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding upon a high place that he might behold the condition of that Citie, which of late was moſt rich and flouriſhing, but now moſt miſerable, hee
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53992:17"/>
could not abſtaine from weeping, ſo as if ſome<note place="margin">Quia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> inco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumi ſtare fas non erat, leviter ſub tam manſucto victore occidiſti. Humanitatis dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedo etiam ineffo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rata barbarorum ingenia penetrat; orboſque &amp; truces mollit hoſtium oculos, ac victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae inſolentiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos ſpiritus fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctit, vincit iram; proſternit odium, hoſtilemque ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinem hoſtilibus lachrymis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcer. <hi>Val. Max. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> Cùm bella quae inter Chriſtianos geruntur, cùm ſint ejuſdem reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionis, etiamſi juſta fuerint, pluſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quàm civilia ſint; noſtri magiſtratus (niſi obſteterint juſtae rationes) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> animos debent habere propenſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ad miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam victis impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tranda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Pet. Mart. in qu. occid. an ſerv. captiv. loc.</hi> 17. <hi>cla.</hi> 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> man had ſeen him, and not known how the caſe had been, he would have thought the victory to have been anothers; which made one ſay to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſed <hi>Sicilie, This may be ſome gratulation or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigation of thy grieſe, Becauſe ſeeing thou mighteſt not ſtand in ſafety, thou falleſt ſo eaſily under ſo gentle a Conquerour,</hi> Omitting other examples, theſe ſhew us, that <hi>The ſweetneſſe of humanity pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the brutiſh diſpoſitions of Barbarians, molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the hard and cruell eyes of enemies, and bendeth thoſe ſpirits that are moſt proud and inſolent of their victory, it conquereth Anger, ſcals hatred, and mixeth the blood of an enemie with his enemies teares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, as humanity, ſo Chriſtianity teacheth us to be propenſe and ready to clemency and mercy unto conquered enemies; <hi>Seeing thoſe warrs which are waged amongſt Chriſtians, when they are of one Religion, are more then civill warrs, yea though they be juſt, our Magiſtrates (except their be juſt reaſons that withſtand it) ought to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry minds ſo much more ready to ſhew mercy unto thoſe that are conquered;</hi> And not only Magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates and Commanders, but all ſouldiers and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary men, even for Chriſtianities ſake, (if ſo be they be Chriſtians) ought to be ready to ſhew mercy and gentleneſſe to thoſe that are ſubdued, or brought under their power: Excellent and imitable is the example of the valiant and vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious firſt Chriſtian Emperour <hi>Conſtantine,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:53992:18"/>
who in his warres, during the battell, gave charge,<note place="margin">Nè multorum fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret caedes, unde non magis, ſuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, quàm hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſaluti pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpexie. <hi>Euſeb. de vitâ Conſtant. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 13. Ut captivorum miſereantur, &amp; cùm homines eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, humanae na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae nequaquàm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os caperet oblivio</note> 
               <hi>That there ſhould not be a ſlaughter of many, whereby he tooke no more care for the ſafety of his owne, then of his enemies;</hi> and when victory was gotten, his charge was, <hi>That they ſhould have mercy on the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, and ſeeing they more men, the oblivion or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulneſſe of humane nature ſhould never overtake them;</hi> And if at any time he ſaw the minds of his Souldiers to be very fierce, he would refraine them with gifts; and further gave order, that if any could take an enemy alive, he ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded; by which means the wiſdome of the Emperour found out an alluring way for the conſervation of men, ſo as infinite numbers, even of very Barbarians, eſcaped ſafe; Of<note place="margin">O clementiam noſtrâ aetate inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentem. <hi>Grynae Annot. in loc. Euſeb.</hi>
               </note> this rare goodneſſe and mercy of the Emperour, one (as it were ſighing) thus ſpeaks, <hi>Alas for this clemency and gentleneſſe that it is out of faſhion in this our Age!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>III.</hi> A motive to cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency will be to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall to the Conqueror</note> Further it would much induce the victors or conquerours to ſhew clemency and be kind to the conquered and ſubdued, if they ſhould reflect upon themſelves, and ſeriouſly bethink what clemencie or kindneſſe they would deſire if they were in the ſame caſe, and therewith remember<note place="margin">Math. 7. 12.</note> the ſpeech of our Saviour, <hi>whatſoever yee would that men ſhould do unto you, doe yee even ſo unto</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 6. 38.</note> 
               <hi>them;</hi> and that <hi>with the the ſame meaſure that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee meete to others, it ſhall be meaſured to you againe,</hi> And ſurely ſuch conſiderations may well at ſome time take hold of them, as <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> hearing
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:53992:18"/>
this ſentence, <hi>it may befall to every one, that befall to any one;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cuivis continge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re poteſt, quod cuiquam contigire Pompeï caſum deploro, &amp; meam fortunam metuo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>to any one;</hi> he fell a weeping and being demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the cauſe of ſuch teares, he anſwered, <hi>I lament the fall of</hi> Pompey, <hi>and am affraid of mine ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fortune:</hi> And it is a very frequent, that the ſame quarter men give to others, they receive backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine from others, as in the caſe of <hi>Adonibezek</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judges 17. 1 Sam. 15. 33. 1 King. 2. 33.</note> and <hi>Agag,</hi> Generall <hi>Ioa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and others, may be ſeen. To be ſhort, a warning peece unto all men may be that ſevere threat of the Lord by the prophet <hi>Iſaiah, we unto theo that ſpoyleſt</hi> (or as we ſay plundereſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) <hi>and thou waſt not ſpoyled, and dealeſt treacherouſly, and they dealt not treacherouſly</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.</note> 
               <hi>with thee: for when thou ſhalt ceaſe to ſpoile, thou ſhall be ſpoiled.</hi> In which wordes the prophet ſeemes to threaten the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> or the land, or <hi>Ninivelh,</hi> the chiefe city of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> which did oppreſſe, ſpoile and plunder the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions about them, that they ſhould be ſpoiled af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward; As if it ſhould be ſaid, Woe unto thee that ſpoileſt and plundereſt the Nations about<note place="margin">Nunc tibi graſſari licet, nullae vir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> reliſtunt, ſed erunt aliquando qui vos viciſſim praeden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Calv. in loc.</hi> Sic mortalium negotia Divina (fortuna) Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videntia ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſat. <hi>Val. Maxim. cap.</hi> i. <hi>de Pomp.</hi>
               </note> thee; <hi>Now thou maiſt ſpoile and plunder at thy pleaſure, there is no ſtrength to reſiſt thee; but there will be ſome, one time or other, that will plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thee againe;</hi> which came to paſſe when the <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aldeans</hi> did come and deſtroyed <hi>Niniveh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ſo the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> did plunder the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the <hi>Chaldees</hi> did plunder the <hi>Aſſyrians;</hi> wee will conclude with a ſentence of an Heathen Author, a little refined, <hi>Thus doth the providence of God change the affaires and buſineſſe of men.</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:53992:19"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>IIII.</hi> Courteous uſage <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the conquered, draws others to voluntary ſubmiſſion.</note> Unto theſe Arguments we may add this one, that gentle and courteous uſage of thoſe that are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, helpeth to drew others unto a voluntary ſubmiſſion, to lay down Armes, and embrace peace and juſtice; as <hi>Benbadab</hi> King of <hi>Syria</hi> his ſervants moved their Maſter, that with ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth upon their loyns, and Roaps<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> about their neckes they might grave pardon for him, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine<note place="margin">2 King. 20. 31.</note> a pacification at the King of <hi>Iſraels</hi> hands (whom he had unjuſtly by warre provoked) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had heard that the Kings of the houſe of Iſrael were mercifull Kings; And of <hi>Tygrane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> King of <hi>Armenin</hi> his willing ſubmiſſion (as an<note place="margin">Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tarch.</note> Authour reportes) to <hi>Pompey,</hi> is aſcribed to his aſſurance of <hi>Pompeys</hi> clemency; whereas on the other part, if there be not a certain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> expectation of gentle and kind uſage upon ſubmiſſion it makes enemies that they will fight it out to the laſt man, and rather chuſe to die in battell, then to ſubmit, yea perchance being death upon thems<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Maccab. 14. 41.</note> ſelves, as <hi>Rhaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> of whom in the hiſtory of the <hi>Maccabe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> it is reported, That he firſt fell upon his own ſword, then leaped downe from, awall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his enemies, and at laſt pulled out his owne gutts, and threw them among them; chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing rather ſuch a death, then to fall into the hands of the wicked, and be abuſed otherwiſe then beſeemed him: or if captives be diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly uſed, it will drive them to worke ſome feate to bring deſtruction upon their Victors or Conquerours, yea though it be purchaſed with
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:53992:19"/>
their owne ruine alſo; As <hi>Sampſon</hi> pulling the<note place="margin">Judg. 16.</note> houſe upon himſelfe, and the Philiſtines, triumph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over him, ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he became revenged for the great indignitie which he ſuffered and at his death he flew more then he had done in his life. The ſum of all theſe arguments is, that Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, Chriſtianitie, conſideration of like future condition, and the motive to induce others op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponents and enemies to voluntary ſubmiſſion, and pacification, may plead for, and obtaine clemency and courteous dealing with enemies ſubdued and conquered.</p>
            <p>Something would yet be ſpoken of dealing<note place="margin">
                  <hi>V.</hi> Humanitie and kindeneſſe to be ſhewn to enemies after their death. <hi>2 Sam. 2. 4.</hi>
               </note> humanely and courteouſly with a enemie, and that even after his death<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which in a word is to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend his body to due burials; There was a law among the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> that they ſhould not ſuffer the dead bodies of their enemies to lie unburied; and we find how <hi>David</hi> did take in good part the action of the men of <hi>Jabeſh-Gilead</hi> that bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Saul,</hi> who had been his enemie, and ſlaine by anothers hand; And of the worthy <hi>Judas Maccubaeus,</hi> that he uſed to burie the bodies of<note place="margin">2 Mac. 12. 39.</note> his ſlaine enemies; yea, we have the heroique Heathens, performing thus much, as <hi>Caeſar</hi> to his enemie <hi>Pompey,</hi> whoſe head being cut off and lying long unburied, <hi>(forgetting that he had been an enemie)</hi> he cauſed to have an honourable<note place="margin">Oblitns hoſtis.</note> funerall fire perfumed with many precious and ſweet ſpices; And <hi>Marcus. Antonius</hi> gave the body of <hi>Marcus Brutus</hi> his late enemie, unto one
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:53992:20"/>
that had been <hi>Brutus</hi> his ſervant, that it might be buried; and to the end it might have the more honourable rites, he gave him his owne<note place="margin">Jacentem non hoſtem, ſed civem depoſito exiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans odio.</note> Roabes to cover his Corps in the funerall: <hi>His hatred being laid aſide, counting him, being dead, not as an enemie, but a Citizen;</hi> And <hi>Hannibat</hi> would not ſuffer the bodies of his enemies <hi>Aemylius Paulus, Tiberius Gracchus,</hi> and <hi>Marcus, Marcellus</hi> to lie unburied, but cauſed them to be<note place="margin">Aliquantò ei plùs gloriae Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Gracchus, &amp; Marcellus ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulti, quàm op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſi attulerunt.</note> interred, ſaying, <hi>that Taulus Gracchus and Marcellus brought him ſomewhat greater honour being buried, then being ſubdued by him.</hi> Theſe examples from holy and humane Stories, are enough to convince the inhumanitie of thoſe who rifle and ſtrippe the bodies of their ſlaine enemies, and ſo leave them naked to be a prey to ravenous Birdes and Beaſts: I wiſh it might not be ſometime ſaid of ſuch, <hi>The dead Bodies of thy ſervants have they</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalmes.</note> 
               <hi>given to be meat unto the fowls of the Ayre, and the fleſh of thy Saints unto the beaſts of the land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>VI.</hi> How to deal with enemies ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and accepting peace offered unto them.</note> There are yet another ſort of Enemies, which upon the offer of conditions of peace, (which, as we have ſhewed aſore out of <hi>Deut.</hi> 20. 10, 11. were to be made at the beginning of Warre) ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of ſuch conditions, and ſubmit, or ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be received into protection, upon conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be agreed upon; theſe upon the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of ſuch conditions, may challenge a greater meaſure of kindneſſe and gentle dealing, then any of which it is yet ſpoken, they are not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be ſuffered, but to be ſaved and kept harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:53992:20"/>
Thus <hi>Joſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ah</hi> did not onely ſpare the Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beonites,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that they ſhould not ſuffer by any under his command, but did alſo protect them againſt the Kings of the Amorites which came againſt them: And when <hi>Saul</hi> out of his zeal to the<note place="margin">2 Sam. 27. 28.</note> Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> would have broken the League, and deſtroyed the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> God puniſhed his attempt with three yeers Famine, and at laſt by hanging up ſeven of <hi>Sauls</hi> Sons. And <hi>David</hi> was much offended, and curſed the act of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oab</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> who was Generall of his Forces againſt <hi>Iſhbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth)</hi> treacherouſly murthering <hi>Abner,</hi> who had been in open &amp; actuall Rebellion againſt him, and Generall of <hi>Iſhboſheth</hi> his Forces, after he had granted him pardon. And of the noble and victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> it is recorded, that<note place="margin">Euſeb. de vit. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. lib. cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> if thoſe that were of the contrary part, finding themſelves to weak to reſiſt his power, would come and lay down Armes, and falling down at his feet, crave quarter and pardon, he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive<note place="margin">U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pote ex homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus conſervan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis capie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptatem. <hi>Plutarch. Valer. Max.</hi>
               </note> them all, and keep them ſafe; <hi>As taking delight in ſaving of men.</hi> It would be too long to relate all examples of this ſort, as of <hi>Pompey,</hi> who having conquered <hi>Tygranes</hi> King of <hi>Armenia,</hi> would not ſuffer him to bee long craving his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, but with good words comforted him, and reſtored him his Crown, which he had caſt down at <hi>Pompey</hi> his feet, and reſtored him to his former eſtate; <hi>Judging it alike honourable to create Kings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aequè <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> eſſe judicans, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vincere Reges &amp; facere.</note> 
               <hi>as to conquer them.</hi> And the famous act of <hi>Lucius Paulus,</hi> who hearing that <hi>Perſes,</hi> (who of a King
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:53992:21"/>
in a ſhort time was made a captive) was brought to him, he went out to meete him, in his Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Roabes, and when the captivated King would have fallen on his knees before <hi>Lucius Paulus,</hi> he would not ſuffer him, but lifted him up, bad him be of good comfort, brought him into his Tent, made him ſit beſide him in his counſell, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed him the honour of his Table, with other courteous Reſpects; In which Spectacle of <hi>Perſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſubjected, and <hi>Lucius Paulus</hi> ſo humanely and kindely dealing with him, it may appeare, that if it bee a famous Act to ſubdue an enemie, it<note place="margin">Non minùs lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dabile infelices ſeire miſereri.</note> is <hi>No leſſe praiſe worth to know how to take pitie upon the affllicted and him that is in miſery.</hi> Thus from ſacred and humane Authoritie may be lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, with what gentle and courteous Reſpect to entertaine, and fidelitie to protect enemies upon conditious of peace, and ſubmiſſion.</p>
            <p>The Application of this which hath been<note place="margin">Applycation. I. <hi>To ſouldiers.</hi>
               </note> ſpoken will be of ſingular uſe to all ſouldiers, and all men whoſoever are employed in militarie<note place="margin">Cum graviter peccant, hâe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>atis ſuis primâ vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſe excuſare, quòd militant. <hi>In verb, Dom. ſer. 19. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> de coro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Militis.</hi>
               </note> Affaires, to prevent that excuſe which S. <hi>Auſten</hi> notes to have been common among ſouldiers, and other officers of publicke buſineſſes; <hi>when: they greatly offend they excuſe themſelves at firſt with this ſaying, that they are ſouldiers;</hi> as if then it were lawfull for them to doe any thing. <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> ſpeaking of ſouldiers, that are Chriſtians, requires two things of them: the one; That they commit nothing againſt God., the other, That they be ready to ſuffer for God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>For warre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:53992:21"/>
                  <hi>neither impunity, nor freedom from puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nec enim deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum impuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem, &amp; Marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riorum immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem militia promittit.</note> 
                  <hi>of ſin, nor immunitie or priviledge from Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome:</hi> But ſome will ſay, becauſe they are ſouldiers, they muſt needs do ſo; but our Author will tell us, <hi>There is no neceſſity to ſin layed upon them, uponw hom lyeth the only neceſſity not to ſin at</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nulla eſt neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas delinquendi, quibus eſt una neceſſitas non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquendi.</note> 
                  <hi>all;</hi> In that which hath been ſaid, we have ſeen the neceſſity of not ſinning, by violence and falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations againſt any man, and how ſouldiers ſhould carry themſelves to friends and enemies, rather to be helpfull to both, then by injuſtice hurtfull to either; To hurt a friend is villai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, to help an enemie (ſo it redound not to our owne wrong) or to abſtaine from harming him, is a token of a minde truly noble and valourous: ſuch I wiſh were billeted in all ſouldiers breaſts, and that there could not be found any (among Chriſtians eſpecially) which neither reſpect friend nor foe, ſo as their owne pleaſure or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit<note place="margin">Ut praedarentur quicquid poſſint, five eſſent bona amicorum, five inimicorum, ut enim res peſſimè caderet, cogeren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ad reſtituen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum; ſed interim aliquam praedae portionem reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere apud rapto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em. <hi>Eraſin. in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notat. ſuper locum.</hi>
                  </note> may be promoted; ſuch a one <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſaith he once met with, and heard him (being a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine) thus advice his ſouldiers: <hi>They ſhould plunder what they could, whether the goods of their friends or foes; for howſoever the matter ſhould fall, at the worſt they could but be compelled to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution: and at the leaſt ſome part of the pillage would remaine with the plunderer;</hi> But leaving ſuch to the Judgement of the Lord of Hoſts; it ſhal bring more honour to Souldiers in their life, and more comfort and hope at their death, if they ſhall obſerve this counſell which <hi>Aurelianus</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:53992:22"/>
                  <note place="margin">Si vis Tribunus eſſe, imò ſi vis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, manus mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum contine, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo pullum alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num rapiat, ovem nemo contingat, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vam nullus au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferat, ſegetem non deterat, oleum, ſal, lignum nemo exigat, Annonâ ſuâ quiſque con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentus ſit, de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dâ hoſtis, non de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>achrymis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincialium habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. <hi>Citatur à Buca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no loc. de Magiſtra. quaſt.</hi> 50. <hi>Philip Camerar. Meditat. Hiſtor. Tom. 1. cap.</hi> 5.</note> the Emperour gave to his Tribune, or Sergeant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>major; <hi>If thou wilſt be a Tribune, yea if thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeſt to live, reſtraine the hands of the ſouldiers, let no man ſteal another mans chicken, let no man touch another mans ſheep, let no man pluck another mans grape, let none thraſh out another mans corne, let every one be content with his owne victualls, and let him have what hee gets out of the ſpoyle of his enemies, and not out of the teares of ſuch as are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our charge, whom wee ſhould protect:</hi> And the Admirable diſcipline of the Turkes is worth learning (and I wiſh it riſe not up in Judgement againſt Chriſtians) of which it is ſaid. That no ſouldier dare take any thing injuſtly, if he doe, he is puniſhed without pitie: and that there are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Officers to looke to thoſe things which are in way that the ſouldiers march, ſo as bread, eggs, Fruites, Oates, and ſuch like things are carried by Boyes of eight or tenn years old, and nothing touched; and Orchards full of fruit by the way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, yet none dare pluck an Apple without the owners conſent; if he doe, his head is loſt for it. Let Chriſtian-ſouldiers thinke it a ſhame that Heathens and Turkes ſhould outgoe them in juſt and innocent Actions and demeanours; And let them ſtudy ſo to carry themſelvs, both in marches and quarters, that they may ſay as <hi>Samuel, whoſe Ox have</hi> I <hi>taken, or whoſe Aſſe have I taken?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 12. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>who have</hi> I <hi>defrauded? whom have I oppreſſed? or of whoſe hand have</hi> I <hi>received any bribes?</hi> And when they enter into Armes, take unto them the brave
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:53992:22"/>
reſolution which <hi>Abraham</hi> carried in his noble breaſt, when he came to the aſſiſtance of the King of <hi>Sodome,</hi> againſt <hi>Chedorlaomer,</hi> and to relieve his friend <hi>Lot,</hi> who was taken priſoner, that he would not take from a threed even to a ſhoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latchet: Let them walk in the ſteps of their father <hi>Abraham,</hi> and they ſhall march unto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and reſt in <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome; And as their Fame ſhall be honourable, ſo ſhall their harmleſſe ſpirits, holding a true faith in Jeſus Chriſt, the Captaine of our ſalvation, when they ſhall ſigh them out upon their bedds, or dropp them out at their wounds, with their blood up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the field, ſo encourage them, that they may ſay,<note place="margin">Nec pudet viv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c piget moſt. II.</note> I <hi>neither ſhame to live, nor do</hi> I ſhrinke or am affraid to die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, if ſuch innocency be required in<note place="margin">What innocency is required of men in times and places of place.</note> ſouldiers, what is required of men imployed in places and vocations of peace, and tranquility in the Commonwealth, how innocent ought they to bee, to Life and Perſon, Name and Credite, Goods and Eſtates of their Neighbours, not to wrong them, but according to their abilitie, to labour and endeavour to preſerve them, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect<note place="margin">Duobus modis pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>catur in homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, uno modo ſi laedatur; alio mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do fi cùm poteſt, non ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur. <hi>A. ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n de meribus e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cleſie.</hi>
               </note> no meanes that may doe them good; For by theſe two wayes it is offended againſt our Neighbour, either by commiſſion of injuries, or omiſſion of kindneſſes, according to the ſaying of S. <hi>Auſten, By two wayes wee offend againſt a man, one way if he bo hurt of us; the other is, if when it is in our power, he be not holpen of us;</hi> And another
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:53992:23"/>
               <note place="margin">Non ſuflicit ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re à malo, niſi fiat quod bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num eſt, &amp; parum eſt nemini noce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, niſi ſtudias multis prodeſſe, <hi>Proſper. titul. Epigr.</hi> 77.</note> teacheth us, that <hi>It is not ſufficient to abſtaine from doing ill, except that be done which is good; and it ſmall avails to hurt no man, except thou ſtudieſt to help and profit many.</hi> And it is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> that of theſe precepts, which <hi>Iohn</hi> gave to his hearers, ſome were peculiar to particular men, but the precept of mercy is a common precept, <hi>Mercy is neceſſary to all offices;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Omnibus Officiis, omibus aetatibus, neceſſaria, &amp; ab omnibus defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renda miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia; non Publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, non miles excipitur, non agricola, vel ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banus, dives &amp; pauper, &amp;c. <hi>Ambroſ. in locum.</hi> Luke 16.</note> 
               <hi>and is of all men to be ſhewn or performed, there is neither Publican nor ſouldier excepted, nor country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, nor citizen, nor rich, nor poore, none is exempted: all men in generall are admoniſhed that they helpe him, that hath not of his owne to helpe himſelfe;</hi> The omiſſion of this was the condemnation of the Richman that gave no foode nor Raiment to hungrie and naked <hi>Lazarus,</hi> wee finde no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any that he had oppreſſed, and yet is he found to bee in Hell in torments; and if it thus beſell the neglect of mercy, what ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall to acts of crueltie? If the fruitleſſe figtree be accurſed, what ſhall become of thornes and briars, ſuch as murderers, fighters, quarellers, ſlanderers baſe informers, and ſuch others, and all, who (nor content with that portion that God hath given them) do by cheating, oppreſſion and extortion, or any injuſt way advance and enrich themſelves with the damage, defamation and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing of others? If at the laſt doome for the omiſſion of mercy, it ſhall be ſaid, <hi>Goe ye curſed into everlaſting fire, prepared for the Divell and his Angels; For I was an hungry, and yee gave me no</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:53992:23"/>
               <hi>meate, I was thirſty, and ye gave me no drink, I was a ſtranger, and ye took mee not in, naked, and yee cloathed me not, ſick, and in priſon, and yee viſited mee not;</hi> With what confuſion ſhall it be heard, if Chriſt ſhall ſay:</p>
            <p>Goe yee curſed Tyrants, oppreſſours, and perſecutours into everlaſting fire; for the meane food which God had given mee, yee tooke it from mee; from the poore and homely habitation which I enjoyed, yee expelled and baniſhed mee; of the Rayment and Cloathes, wherewith my nakedneſſe was covered from the eyes of men, and my weakneſſe ſhielded from the violence of the weather, yee have ſtripped mee; of my health, wherein I cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully walked with God, and ſerved my Neighbour in love and charitie, yee have bereaved mee, of my libortie, yee have reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed mee, and in cloſe priſons and dungeons ſhut mee up; and all this though yee have not done to mee in the members of my naturall body, yet have yee done it to theſe little ones, the members of my miſticall Bodie; who
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:53992:24"/>
are as precious to mee as mine owne life; For their ſakes I tooke upon mee the forme of a Servant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I gave my ſpotleſſe blood, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured the bitter paines of death and Hell for their Redemption.</p>
            <p>Surely to hear this will much amaze and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found, for if he were ſpeechleſſe (upon the check) who wanted the Wedding garment, needs muſt he be dumb and without excuſe whoſe garments are rolled in blood, and as red as Scarlet and Crimſon, Dyed in the blood and ſufferings of the Innocent.</p>
            <p>One ſhort Obſervation more would I deſirouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commend to your Chriſtian piety, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with take leave, it being conſolatory that I may be free, as in mine own intentions, ſo in others eſtimation, from ſuſpition of having ſpoken or written any thing which hath not proceeded from unſaigned Charity, the proper fountain of all Chriſtian Action<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Whereas theſe Souldiers who had been addicted to violence, rapine and other vices, and were men accounted the worſt alive (as afore from ſundry Authors is obſerved) now comming to <hi>Iohn,</hi> confeſſing and ſorrow full for their fins, and deſiring directions which they might ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erve in ſeeking ſalva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion, are not reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of <hi>John</hi> as men without hope, but are rather
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:53992:24"/>
received and inſtructed what to do, and how to demean themſelves for the future, with an inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of ſafety upon the performance of that which is preſcribed; We collect, <hi>That great ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervation,</hi> Great ſenners repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting may obt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in ſalvation.</note> 
               <hi>repenting and reforming themſelves, may obtain ſalvation;</hi> If there had not been time of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and hope of ſalvation upon repentance and amendment, he would not have exhorted theſe ſouldiers to amendment. S. <hi>Hierome</hi> hath a col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection<note place="margin">Hierom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. in Epiſt. adverſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Revel. 2. 3.</hi>
               </note> not unlike hereunto upon the Epiſtles of Jeſus Chriſt to ſome of the Churches:</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> had left her firſt love; the Church of <hi>Pergamus</hi> alſo was not free from all offence, for ſhe had in her ſome which did hold the doctrine of <hi>Balaam,</hi> which taught to eat things offered to Idols, and to commit For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication; and ſuch as held the doctrine of the the <hi>Nicolaitans;</hi> and the Church of <hi>Thyatira</hi> did ſuffer the falſe Propheteſſe <hi>Jezabel,</hi> which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced<note place="margin">Ettamen hos omn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus hortatur ad poenitenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, ſub commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione quoque futurae poenae, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi convertantur; non autem coge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret poenitere, fi non e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſet poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentibus veniam conceſſurus.</note> men to commit Fornication, and to eate things offered to Idols; <hi>Yet all theſe the Lord exhorts to repentance, and that under a threat of a puniſhment to come upon them, except they did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; but he would not have preſſed to repentance except he would grant pardon to them that repented.</hi> And another ancient Author obſerves as much of other Churches mentioned in thoſe Sacred E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles; In the Church of <hi>Sardis</hi> the imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of workes; in the <hi>Laodiceans</hi> confidence in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:53992:25"/>
               <note place="margin">Et tamen ad poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentiam com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monet, ſub com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minationibus quidem; non comminaretur autem non poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenti, ſi non ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſceret poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenti. <hi>Tertul de poenitent.</hi> Exod. 34. 6, 7. Ezek. 18. 32.</note> riches is reprehended; <hi>And yet theſe he admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to repent, and that under threatnings, except they repented; But he would not threaten him that repents not, except he would pardon him that doth repent.</hi> This ariſeth from the goodneſſe of the nature of God, as may be ſeen in the Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, which paſt before his manifeſtation to <hi>Moſes, The Lord mercifull and gracious, long-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering and abundant in goodneſſe and truth, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mercy for thouſands, forgiving iniquity and ſinne.</hi> And the Prophet will tell us from GOD, that he hath no pleaſure in the death of him that dieth.</p>
            <p>For this end Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God came into the world, that he might ſeek and ſave that which was loſt, and that hee might call the ſinners to Repentance, yea, even ſuch ſinners as in the eye of man none could exceede, even them that put him to death, for whom hee prayed,<note place="margin">Luke 23. 34.</note> 
               <hi>Father forgive them, for they know not what they doe;</hi> Of whom we finde ſome afterward (hearing their ſin in crucifying and murdering the Lord of life, taxed by <hi>Peter)</hi> pricked in conſcience, and crying out (like the ſouldiers in the Text) <hi>What</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 2. 37.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall wee doe?</hi> &amp;c. and by <hi>Peter</hi> directed to this medicine of Repentance and Baptiſme, with a promiſe of forgiveneſſe of ſins, and receiving the<note place="margin">Auſt. Tract. 38. in in Ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng. ſecundum Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>em.</note> Holy Ghoſt. Of theſe we may ſay, and inferre with S. <hi>Auſten;</hi> This people it was of whom
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:53992:25"/>
Chriſt was crucified, of whom he was hanged on a Tree, of whom, hanging there, he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rided, of whom he was thurſt thorow with a Speare, of whom was given unto him Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger mingled with Gall to drink: yet for theſe he prayes, Father forgive them, for they knowe<note place="margin">Quid autem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſo non ignoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur, ſi fuſus Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inguis ignoſcitur. Application. I.</note> not what they doe, <hi>And what is there that is not to be forgiven to him that is converted, when the blood of Chriſt being ſhed, was thus forgiven?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The application hereof ſhall be compriſed in two words;</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſeeing great ſinners repenting and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming<note place="margin">It cals ſinners to repentanoe. <hi>Ezekiel 18.</hi>
               </note> themſelves, may be forgiven, it calls us to repentance, as the prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding and promiſing pardon, upon repentance and amendment, calls them to reformation, and caſting away their tranſgreſſions; and this he doth as it were by an expoſtulation, or reaſoning the matter, <hi>For why will ye die O houſe of Iſrael?</hi> As if hee ſhould ſay, If yee will not repent and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and are guiltie of your own deſtruction, and that not only by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> committed, but alſo by the remedie of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance neglected; And this alſo is confirmed of God by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n oath, <hi>As I live ſaith the Lord God, I have no pleaſure, in the death of a ſinner; but</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>that the wicked ſhould turne from his way, and live; Turne yee, turne yee from your evill wayes, for why will ye die O houſe of Iſrael!</hi> Hereon is thus
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:53992:26"/>
               <note place="margin">Ergò poenitentia vita eſt, cùm prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponitur morti; cam tu peccator ita invade, ita amplectere, ut naufragus alicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us tabu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> fidem; haec te p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fluctibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> merſum proleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, &amp; in portum Divinae clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlae protelabit. <hi>Ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ul. depoenit.</hi> 2.</note> much noted; <hi>Repentance therefore is life, when it is perſerred before death: Thou therefore O ſinner, ſo ſeaze upon it, and ſo imbrace it, as a ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrackt man doth ſome truſty piece of a plank broken out of the ſhipp, this ſhall lift thee up being ſunk under the waves of thy ſins; and draw thee into the haven of Gods mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it comforts thoſe that are truely pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent for their ſinnes, wherein they have long lived; or are of great guilt and offence in the eyes of God, as Murder, Whordome, oppreſſion, and ſuch like, upon their repentance and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they are pardonable, if they will waſh and make themſelves cleane, then though their ſinnes<note place="margin">Conſolation to true penitents.</note> were as Scarlet, they ſhall be white as Snow, if they be redde like Crimſon, they ſhall bee as<note place="margin">Eſai. 1. 18.</note> Wooll: Can any blood or ſin whatſoever die a deeper colour then the ſacred blood of the Sonn of God? and yet wee ſee that forgiven to the <hi>Jewes</hi> repenting and embracing the faith; For<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cati ſui remiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedeſperet, quando illi veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am meruerunt, qui occidêrunt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Auſt. in Tract.</hi> 31. <hi>in Evang<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſecund. Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m.</hi>
               </note> when they (wounded in conſcience) they are directed to this remedie with hope of cure and ſafety, Which may teach us, <hi>That<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>no man ſhould diſpaire of the forgiveneſſe of his ſinne, when they obtained pardon that killed Chriſt,</hi> as ſaith Saint <hi>Auſten;</hi> wee will end with a ſaying of the ſame Father, which may ſerve unto us, both as a Cordiall againſt deſpaire, and a caveat againſt preſumption; <hi>No man therefore</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:53992:26"/>
               <hi>(although hee bee load<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n with an huge burden of ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>)</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nemo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gitur (quamvis ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti pondere p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum prematur) de boni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae pie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aris de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperare debeat. <hi>Ibidem S r n de temp</hi> 53. Ideò non propt er ſpem v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>niae per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeve an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er pec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re debemus. Utroque periculo evitato, &amp; à malo d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>clinemus, &amp; de pietate De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ſperemus.</note> 
               <hi>ought to deſpaire of the goodneſſe of Gods mercy, but out of hope of that aſſured mercy, with dayly teares to begge their pardons; which they may rightly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, if they ſhall ceaſe from acting their evill workes.</hi> And on the otherſide avoyd preſumption<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Wee ought not therefore to ſinne, or conſtantly perſevere in ſinne, becauſe of the hope of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe, but keeping our ſelves in the golden mean and ſwimming in the clear ſtreame of the living Waters, that ſhall flow out of the belly of him that beleeveth on Chriſt; Both dangers being avoyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, let us flye and decline that which is evill, and hope for pardon from the mercy of God. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
