<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anniversary to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty, Charles the II. on his birth-&amp;-restauration-day, May 29, having resolv'd to marry with the Infanta of Portugall, May the 8th, 1661</title>
            <author>Bold, Henry, 1627-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-08">2004-08 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28576</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3469</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19876</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11766670</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11766670</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48759</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A28576)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48759)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 15:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anniversary to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty, Charles the II. on his birth-&amp;-restauration-day, May 29, having resolv'd to marry with the Infanta of Portugall, May the 8th, 1661</title>
                  <author>Bold, Henry, 1627-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signed (p. 4): Hen. Bold.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48759:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head type="illustration">
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:yhwh">יהוה</g>
                  </head>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>ANNIVERSARY TO THE Kings Most Excellent Majesty CHARLES the II. ON HIS Birth-&amp;-Restauration-Day, May 29. Having Resolv'd to Marry with the Infanta of Portugall, May the 8th. 1661.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Connubio jungam stabili, Propriamque dicabo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <bibl>Virg.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <l>LEt us fall down! and Worship <hi>Charles His Ray!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A <hi>Sun!</hi> that <hi>Summer's</hi> all our <hi>Year</hi> to <hi>May!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Had <hi>Phoebus</hi> ever shone so <hi>fair</hi> as <hi>This,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Daphne</hi> had scap'd her <hi>Metamorphosis.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Priests</hi> oth' <hi>East,</hi> by th' influence of <hi>your Worth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Mistaking <hi>Shrines,</hi> shall <hi>now Adore</hi> the <hi>North.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:48759:2"/>
The <hi>Guiding-Starr,</hi> oth' <hi>Man-Childe God,</hi> did gaine</l>
               <l>Lesse <hi>Seekers there,</hi> than does our <hi>Charles His Waine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sol</hi> in <hi>Aspect</hi> with <hi>Luna!</hi> Loe! a <hi>Queen</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Comming from farr! fam'd <hi>Beauties Magazin!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Wealth</hi> oth' <hi>World!</hi> the <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>Earth!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fair</hi> as the <hi>Starr</hi> that blaz'd at <hi>Charles His Birth!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>Beauty, Love,</hi> and <hi>Innocence!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sweet as the <hi>Smoak</hi> perfum'd with <hi>Frankincence!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A <hi>Feature</hi> made up of such <hi>Harmony,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As <hi>Nature</hi> had her nicest <hi>Symmetry</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Reserv'd till <hi>now.</hi> Her more than <hi>Glorious Eye,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shines like a <hi>Diamond</hi> set in <hi>Ebonye.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whereat, the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Love,</hi> does Light his <hi>Darts</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When <hi>He</hi> resolves the spoyle of sullen Hearts.</l>
               <l>Her World-like <hi>Head,</hi> tress'd with such lovely <hi>Brown,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That Every single <hi>Hayre</hi> deserves a <hi>Crown.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whose <hi>All,</hi> and <hi>Every part,</hi> doe so excell,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> Could <hi>ne're</hi> have found <hi>Her Paralell.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For sure as <hi>Heavens</hi> have design'd <hi>Her Queen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Twas onely <hi>Charles</hi> could <hi>Match</hi> with <hi>Katherine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus like the <hi>Southern Queen Shee</hi>'s drawing on</l>
               <l>To Commune with our Wiser <hi>Solomon.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVee'l 'bate the <hi>Spice</hi> and <hi>Camells (Gifts</hi> too small)</l>
               <l>Bringing <hi>Her</hi> single <hi>Self, She gives</hi> Us <hi>All.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:48759:3"/>
VVhen <hi>two such Planets</hi> in <hi>Conjunction</hi> are</l>
               <l>At <hi>Every Birth,</hi> how <hi>Great</hi> will be the <hi>Starr!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Twice did Our <hi>Edward</hi> winn the <hi>Peoples Love</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By <hi>Meen,</hi> and <hi>Person.—</hi>Oh how <hi>Charles</hi> would move!</l>
               <l>'Twixt <hi>their</hi> two <hi>Fates</hi> the onely difference is</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That</hi> gain'd <hi>it</hi> for a <hi>Time,</hi> for <hi>ever, This.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As erst to <hi>Caesar, Nations now</hi> agree</l>
               <l>To yield to <hi>One</hi> that's more <hi>August</hi> than <hi>Hee.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How timely did the <hi>Graecian</hi> fall asleep!</l>
               <l>Had <hi>Hee now</hi> Liv'd, there were no Cause to <hi>Weep.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hee</hi> little thought the <hi>Sea</hi> had ever hid</l>
               <l>A <hi>World,</hi> where <hi>You</hi> should <hi>out-doe</hi> what <hi>Hee did.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How tamely did the <hi>Swedish Charles</hi> retreat!</l>
               <l>And quit the <hi>Earth</hi> in dread of <hi>Charles the Great!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Tis one Excuse for <hi>Atheists,</hi> that they view</l>
               <l>A <hi>Deity,</hi> and think there's <hi>None,</hi> but <hi>You.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhen <hi>two such Planets</hi> in <hi>Conjunction</hi> are,</l>
               <l>At <hi>Every Birth,</hi> how <hi>Great</hi> will be the <hi>Starr!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Blest be <hi>this Moneth</hi> for ever! <hi>Nature's Pride!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVorth all the <hi>Seasons</hi> of the <hi>Year</hi> beside!</l>
               <l>A <hi>Moneth</hi> that such a <hi>Flower</hi> has brought forth,</l>
               <l>As decks the <hi>South,</hi> and perfumes all the <hi>North!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhat <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaster</hi> could ne're have done,</l>
               <l>Till they were well Contracted into <hi>One.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:48759:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>This Moneth</hi> scarce ownes <hi>a Day</hi> that hath not shown</l>
               <l>More <hi>Triumph</hi> in it, then in <hi>Annalls</hi> known.</l>
               <l>For un-beholden to his <hi>Ushers</hi> Shower,</l>
               <l>Hee (of himself) affords <hi>Another Flower,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So rare, that, amongst <hi>Natures Glories,</hi> seen</l>
               <l>'Twill be un-question'd, Which is <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>May from this precious <hi>Plant</hi> an <hi>Off-spring</hi> rise</l>
               <l>To make all <hi>Christendom</hi> a <hi>Paradise!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That <hi>Every Son</hi> may be <hi>AUGUST,</hi> we pray,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Every Daughter Lady</hi> of the <hi>May!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>—Tecum Sociales <hi>impleat annos</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quae nisi</hi> Te, <hi>nullo</hi> Conjuge, <hi>Digna fuit!</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <bibl>Ovid.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Hen. Bold</hi> olim e <hi>N. C. Oxon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed for</hi> Henry Brome <hi>at the Gun in</hi> Ivy-lane. 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
