<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Abstract of the accusation of Robert Bolron and Lawrence Maybury, servants, against their late master, Sir Thomas Gascoigne, Kt. and Bart. of Barnbow in York-shire, for high-treason with his tryal and acquittal, 11 February 1679/80.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-10">2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28605</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3499</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35766</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15558937</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15558937</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103730</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A28605)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103730)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1585:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Abstract of the accusation of Robert Bolron and Lawrence Maybury, servants, against their late master, Sir Thomas Gascoigne, Kt. and Bart. of Barnbow in York-shire, for high-treason with his tryal and acquittal, 11 February 1679/80.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 11, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for C.R.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXX [1680]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: creased and stained with print show-through and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gascoigne, Thomas, --  Sir, 1593?-1686.</term>
               <term>Bolron, Robert, fl. 1674-1680.</term>
               <term>Maybury, Lawrence.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
               <term>Trials (Treason) --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103730:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ABSTRACT OF THE ACCUSATION OF <hi>Robert Bolron</hi> and <hi>Lawrence Maybury,</hi> Servants againſt their late Maſter Sir <hi>THOMAS GASCOIGNE,</hi> K<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> and Bar<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> of <hi>Barnbow</hi> in <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> FOR HIGH-TREASON: With his Tryal and Acquittal 11. <hi>February</hi> 1679/80.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fit error Noviſſimus pejor Priore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>C. R.</hi> M DC LXXX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:103730:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103730:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THou art here preſented with the firſt Eſſay in the Diſcovery of the ſecond Popiſh Plot brought from the North, and mentioned in the Front hereof. Some Matters may at firſt ſeem alien and novel, but they relate to the Subject or Perſons treated of; for who deſires not to have a true account of the Witneſſes? which you will yet further underſtand by the Trials that are ſhortly to be at <hi>York,</hi> ſince they proſecute all the <hi>Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coigne</hi> Family, as Maſters, Mistreſſes, Kindred, Servants, Male and Female, nay every neighbouring Acquaintance or Friend, beſides 500 more in reſerve; for they ſwear they ſaw a Liſt with ſo many Names in it. You will find the Topicks of their Predeceſſors (I mean the firſt Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verers of the preſent Popiſh Plot) handled very fully, and the Strain not ill followed, conſidering their ſervile Capacities; viz. <hi>Conſults, Eaſie Admittance thereto, Hearings, Over-hearings, Letters, Treaties, Liſts, Commiſſions, Oaths of Secrecy, Firing of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Collections, Money return'd to</hi> London, <hi>Arms, Privy-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors to be made, Canonizing of Saints, Regicides to be meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, Deſtruction of Hereticks made lawful, A few naked Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts (being ſcarce one to three thouſand) ready to ſubdue all the Armed Proteſtants of the Nation.</hi> Nothing offenſive is deſigned by this ſhort Diſcourſe; but purely to give ſatisfaction to thoſe that deſire to know the Reaſons of Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoigne</hi>'s Acquittal, who has had this happineſs, that his Witneſses were, except one or two, known Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and have alſo made Oath of what they atteſted in his behalf before a Lawful Magiſtrate; ſo that their Teſtimony is not now barely Verbal.</p>
            <closer>Farewell.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="abstract">
            <pb facs="tcp:103730:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103730:3"/>
            <head>An Abſtract of the Accuſation of <hi>Robert Bolron</hi> and <hi>Laurence Maybury,</hi> Servants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>RObert Bolron</hi> of <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> upon <hi>Tyne</hi> was bound Apprentice to Mr. <hi>Deale,</hi> a Jeweller in <hi>Pye-Corner London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He abandoned his Maſter in a Twelve-month, and liſted himſelf a Foot-Soldier in <hi>Tinmouth-Caſtle.</hi>—He was with others thence put on Board the <hi>Rainbow</hi> Frigat, in the ſecond War againſt the <hi>Dutch.</hi>—He got aſhoar, and came in his Yellow Coat to Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoignes</hi> Houſe, having acquaintance with <hi>Richard Pepper,</hi> one of his Servants, and thence he went to <hi>NewCaſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſometime after much importuned the ſaid <hi>Pepper</hi> to recommend him to Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his Service, upon pretence of his having been uſed to look after ColeMines near <hi>New-Caſtle;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1674.</note> and by his means he was admitted to over-look a ſmall Colliery of Sir <hi>Thomas</hi>'s.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lawrence Maybury,</hi> (being the Son of a Day-labouring Forge-Smith about <hi>Leeds)</hi> and now of late a Bum-Bailiff) through the means of <hi>Francis Johnſon</hi> (one of Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi>'s Tenants and Neighbours) was preferr'd to be Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his Foot-boy.</p>
            <p>The ſame <hi>Maybury</hi> being lay'd in a Chamber, where was a ſecret Place, in which the Lady <hi>Tempeſt</hi> (Sir <hi>Thomas</hi>'s own Daughter, upon her going to <hi>London</hi> about <hi>Midſummer</hi> 1675.) put a ſmall little Trunk, and in it ſome twenty Pieces of Gold, her Wedding <note place="margin">1675.</note> Ring, and ſeveral little Stone Rings, Medals, and other things, to the value of about ſixty Pounds, and he who was known to all the Servants not to be worth a Groat, and having but a ſmall Salary, being afterwards diſcovered to have Gold, Silver, a large Wedding-Ring, and other Rings; and the Lady <hi>Tempeſt</hi> returning about <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and the Trunk being <note place="margin">1676.</note> gone, and theſe Particulars talk'd of he became vehemently ſuſpected to be the Thief. Howbeit her Ladiſhip, not having certain Proofs, did not proſecute him; but upon the <hi>14th</hi> of <hi>January</hi> following Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> turn'd him away, both for ſuſpition of the ſaid Theft, and for ſome inſolent attempts upon his Maids.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maybury</hi> being diſcharged in <hi>January,</hi> cloaths himſelf finely, and ſets up for a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, goes to the Dancing-School at <hi>York,</hi> intrudes into the company of ſome of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, appears fluſh of Money, and at the <hi>Sunday</hi> after <hi>Eaſter</hi> he called at Sir <hi>Thomas</hi>'s, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to be admitted to Prayers into the Houſe, but was poſitively denyed; others of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily (having within ſome weeks after the ſaid <hi>Maybury</hi>'s being gone) miſs'd 100 <hi>l.</hi> in a Bag, beſides other Moneys, <note n="*" place="margin">As lately hath been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, and <hi>Affidavit</hi> made thereof.</note> out of the Place where they kept their Money. Finding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf much eyed and taken notice of by thoſe who knew him, about <hi>May</hi> the Spark comes <note place="margin">1677.</note> to <hi>London;</hi> and not contented with the Name of <note n="*" place="margin">Whereof ſome Letters are extant.</note> 
               <hi>Maybury,</hi> as he uſed to write himſelf before, he now aſſumes the more Honourable Title of <hi>Mowbray,</hi> takes Lodgings in <hi>Holborn,</hi> where he ſpent moſt part of that Summer. He gives himſelf out alſo to be a great Heir, borrows a Gentlemans Coach, Courts a Gentlewoman of Quality, having 1500 <hi>l.</hi> to her Portion; being refuſed, he writes Verſes (ſuch as they were) againſt her. About which time, being in company with ſome Gentlemen, into whom he had inſinuated himſelf, he fairly borrowed of them a Sum of Money, (about 70 <hi>l.)</hi> giving them a Bill of Exchange on his pretended Merchant in <hi>London</hi> for Security; but the Merchant being ſoon enquir'd of, had no advice, nor knew neither <hi>Maybury,</hi> nor any elſe concerned in the Bill; which therefore being diſcovered to be a Forgery, he leaves his reſidence above ſaid, pretending to go in all haſt to <hi>Warwick-ſhire</hi> to take poſſeſſion of 400 <hi>l. per Annum</hi> juſt fal'n to him; but in very few days after his old Land-lord found him in an obſcure Houſe near <hi>Smith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> abſconding for fear of thoſe he had wrong'd: On the <hi>24th</hi> of <hi>December</hi> he removes again, pretending to <hi>Biſhopſgate-ſtreet;</hi> and in the beginning of <hi>February</hi> next enſuing, (having debauch'd and play'd away his Money) as eaſily as he got it, he made ſuch ſhift as to return to <hi>Leeds,</hi> but with a lighter Purſe, and far heavier Heart than he parted from thence; and having formerly, by the Charity of Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> improved his Hand-writing, he now ſets up a School for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bolron</hi> likewiſe being after ſome time more than ſuſpected to be an ill Man, his Accounts of the Colliary were inſpected, and upon the peruſal of them in <hi>February</hi> 1677/8. he was <note place="margin">1677/8.</note> found to have received about 300 <hi>l.</hi> for Coles, and accounted for to Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> but 60 <hi>l.</hi> whereof much more was due.—That he had defrauded Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> very much in other pretended disburſements about the Colliery;—and that he had taken out of Sir <hi>Thomas</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:103730:4"/>
his Chamber a Book of Accounts, whereby it appeared how he had wrong'd his Maſter more particularly of other Moneys and Dues, and that he return'd many Perſons indebted for Coles, who in truth had paid him: Hereupon Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> reſolved not only to part with him, but to puniſh him according to Law; but upon his earneſt beſeeching Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> to ſhew him mercy, he in compaſſion accepted of 12 <hi>l.</hi> and two Bonds for payment of 48 <hi>l.</hi> Principal more, and ſo about <hi>April</hi> 78. let him go quietly and peaceably away; Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1678.</note> (like a good Chriſtian) being deſirous he might amend, and do better in another Service.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Thomas Gaſcoigne,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his eldeſt Son, having reſolved, by reaſon of the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles to thoſe of his Church, or in general to Catholicks, to go beyond Seas, as many others did; took leave of Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> in order thereunto at the end of <hi>March;</hi> and having obtain'd <note place="margin">1679.</note> his Majeſties Paſs-Port on the <hi>4th</hi> of <hi>April</hi> following, he went from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Dover</hi> the <hi>7th</hi> of that Month, and Letters were received from him in his way to <hi>Paris,</hi> (and as by a publick Teſtimonial ſince ſent) he ſetled himſelf there the firſt of <hi>May</hi> following New Stile, or 20 <hi>April</hi> Old Stile, and was not yet departed thence, as many Witneſſes now in <hi>England</hi> can teſtifie. About a year after his the ſaid <hi>Bolrons</hi> departure from Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> he being ſtill indebted to Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> and alſo to others of the Family, <hi>viz.</hi> to Mr. <hi>Thomas Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coigne,</hi> and his Siſter the Lady <hi>Tempeſt;</hi> and being now become inſolent by his own ill government, he declares himſelf a Proteſtant, and accordingly takes the Oaths at <hi>Ponte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fract</hi> Seſſions; being alſo call'd upon for the aforeſaid Payments, he earneſtly preſs'd one of Mr. <hi>Thomas</hi> his Servants, with whom he thought he was intimate, to aſſiſt him to ſteal a Hundred Pound from his Maſter, or otherwiſe to acquaint him where his Maſters Money lay, that he might do it himſelf; but not prevailing therein, he importun'd him at leaſt to ſteal from Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> the Bonds, for which he promiſed to reward him.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> obſerving <hi>Bolrons</hi> declining condition, ſent a Servant for him, whereat <hi>Bolron</hi> ſeemed much concerned, and amongſt other things told the Meſſenger, that he had been reading the Printed Tryals, and that he had learn'd <hi>T. O.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">The Reader may ſee in further peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal hereof, that <hi>Bolron</hi> is not come much ſhort of his pretended <hi>Pater.</hi>
               </note> his way of witneſſing ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly, <hi>that he did not doubt to hang any Man whom he pleaſed;</hi> but upon the <hi>29th</hi> of <hi>May</hi> he came to Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> to tender a Mortgage of a poor Houſe his Father left him at <hi>New-Caſtle;</hi> which Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> then ſlighted, having ſeveral others bound with him for the Debt, the next day being <hi>the remarkable</hi> 30th <hi>of</hi> May <hi>laſt,</hi> (and on which day <hi>Bolron</hi> had laid the ground of his Principal Accuſation;) Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> ſtir'd not from about home, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſix of the Clock that evening one of Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his Servants went to the Houſe of <hi>Nicholas Shippen,</hi> not a quarter of a Mile from <hi>Bolrons</hi> Houſe, and there found <hi>Bolron,</hi> who ſaid he had lain private there moſt part of that day for fear of the Bailiffs; and moreover, that he would now keep himſelf conceal'd, and get into the Cole-pit at <hi>Caſtleforth</hi> not far off, where he was ſure the Bailiffs ſhould not find him.—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bolron</hi> having by his Wife (who was formerly a Servant in the Family) gotten into one of Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his Farms, and being in arrear of Rent alſo, a Declaration of <hi>Ejectment</hi> was ordered by Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> to be delivered him, and on the <hi>4th</hi> of <hi>June</hi> (following the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boveſaid <hi>30th</hi> of <hi>May) Bolron</hi> had notice thereof, about which time <hi>Bolron</hi> went to Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his Houſe, and ſlipt up to Mr. <hi>Ruſhtons</hi> Chamber; but at his coming down ſeem'd much in paſſion, and told one of Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his Servants, that he had been with Mr. <hi>Ruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> to borrow 5 <hi>l.</hi> but was refuſed it, and with a great Oath vow'd to be reveng'd on him, going away without ſpeaking to Sir <hi>Thomas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bolron</hi> having now reſolved revenge, told his Wife he would now pay Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> all, by Mortgaging <note n="*" place="margin">Above three years before <hi>Bolron</hi> had mortgaged it fully to one <hi>Carr</hi> of <hi>New-Caſtle,</hi> an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman.</note> his Houſe at <hi>New-Caſtle,</hi> wherein ſhe had her Joynture, if ſhe would give conſent to it; ſhe conſenting at length, he brought her a Writing to Sign, purporting her conſent, as he pretended, to her. He likewiſe pretended to Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his Attorney, that he had gain'd his Wives conſent to Mortgage or ſell the ſaid Houſe, and pray'd him to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare a Deed of Mortgage thereof to Sir <hi>Thomas;</hi> and he did ſo, having perſwaded Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> to accept it; but it proved ineffectual.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bolron</hi> being become more and more enraged, and having ſtudied the ſeveral Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which had come forth ſince <hi>T. O.</hi> ſuppoſed diſcovery of the Plot, goes to <hi>Broderton Tyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal</hi> Eſq; Juſtice of the Peace, and informs him ſeveral things againſt <hi>Ruſhton;</hi> and that Mrs. <hi>Mary Preſſeck,</hi> Wife to Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his Servant, had ſpoken ſeveral ſtrange words concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Majeſty. Afterwards he gave his Information to <hi>William Lowther</hi> Eſq; another Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the Peace.—After that he attended Mr. <hi>Lowther,</hi> Mr. <hi>Tindal,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Francis White</hi> Eſq; a third Neighbouring Juſtice of the Peace, and there likewiſe confirm'd to them what he had ſaid the two former days, and then deſired four or five days to give them a further account.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bolron</hi> attending them accordingly, requeſted that the former Information he had given them might be return'd to him; but 'twas told him, that the Informations he had given them were ſent up to <hi>London;</hi> and thereupon he reſolved to follow them, and prayed them
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:103730:4"/>
to lend him a little Money for his Journey, (for he was grown very low) and he ſaid they gave him 8 <hi>s. 6 d.</hi> towards it, and Mr. <hi>Tyndal</hi> gave him a Letter of Directions and Aſſiſtance to his Brother in <hi>London;</hi> but another of them (a Neighbour of Sir <hi>Thomas</hi>'s) gave him ſomething more to make quicker expedition; but he perceiving that moſt of the Juſtices would give little faith to his Informations, they being made up of hear-ſays, contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and improbabilities, and Mr. <hi>Thomas Gaſcoigne,</hi> whom he involved, being gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Sea near two Months before the time hinted of the <hi>30th</hi> of <hi>May;</hi> and that therefore they would iſſue out no Warrants againſt any whom he had accuſed, but a Servant, which otherwiſe (as the whole Country knows) they would moſt readily have done, he reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to mend his Error when he came to <hi>London;</hi> and ſo by becoming <hi>a Kings Witneſs</hi> to be above all wants, and alſo be reveng'd on Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> and ſecur'd from him, and all other his Creditors; and in order to thoſe good ends, (he gave out in the Country, he would go to <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> and ſell his Houſe) but in ſtead thereof he haſted to <hi>London</hi> immediately.—</p>
            <p>At <hi>Ware</hi> upon the Road he loſt Juſtice <hi>Tyndal</hi>'s Letter; but getting to the <hi>Green-Dragon</hi> in <hi>Biſhopſ-gate-ſtreet</hi> upon the third of <hi>July</hi> following, he immediately acquainted the Land-lord with his errand, and by his directions goes in all haſt to Sir <hi>Robert Clayton,</hi> and the next day, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>4th</hi> of <hi>July,</hi> he attended the Right Honourable the Lord Preſident <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> and the Lords of His Majeſties Privy Council, and poſitively upon Oath accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> and others of Conſultations in relation to the Kings death; for he ſwore, that <hi>upon the</hi> 30th <hi>day of</hi> May, he being at Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his Houſe, Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> bade him go into the Gallery, where <hi>Ruſhton,</hi> (though he were ſo angry with him the ſaid <hi>Bolron</hi> (as <hi>Bolron</hi> ſwore) for taking the Oath of Allegiance, that he was ready to have ſtrucken him; nevertheleſs tempted him in expreſs terms to kill the King; and that upon his refuſing to do it, <hi>Ruſhton</hi> pray'd him however to keep it ſecret. That waiting by Sir <hi>Thomas</hi>'s ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment till his return, Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> about ſix of the Clock that evening took him into his Chamber, and having ask'd him what <hi>Ruſhton</hi> ſaid to him, <note n="*" place="margin">Which was a ſufficient Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement for any Man in his Senſes, if it were true.</note> Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> told him, <hi>That if he would undertake a deſign to help to kill the King, he would ſend him to his Son Mr.</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Gaſcoigne, <hi>who ſhould inſtruct him how to do it, and he ſhould have a thouſand Pounds re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward;</hi> but refuſing again to have any hand in blood, Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> deſired him of all love to keep it ſecret. Now as to the Account the ſaid <hi>Bolron</hi> then gave of Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, he declared, that <hi>Maybury</hi> went away about ſuſpition of a Trunk the Lady <hi>Tempeſt</hi> had loſt, with Moneys and Jewels in it; for then he had not pitch'd on the ſaid <hi>Maybury</hi> for his ſecond Witneſs, as afterwards in a Month, or thereabouts, he did.</p>
            <p>Their Lordſhips preſently ſent away <hi>Bolron</hi> and a Meſſenger into <hi>York-ſhire</hi> for Sir <hi>Thomas;</hi> and in the mean time examin'd thoſe Perſons in <hi>London,</hi> to whom <hi>Bolron</hi> had directed them where to find or hear of Mr. <hi>Thomas Gaſcoigne,</hi> Son to Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> mentioned in the aboveſaid Accuſation, and when they ſaw him laſt. But their Lordſhips ſoon found upon Enquiry, that Mr. <hi>Gaſcoigne</hi> was then and long before gone beyond Sea, having ſet forward for <hi>Dover, viz.</hi> on the <hi>7th</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> and was ſo far from being ſeen ſince in Town by them, that ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Letters had been received from him from beyond Sea by the Poſt, with the Poſt-mark on them, which cauſed ſtrange reflections on this new Evidence given by <hi>Bolron:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe Perſons being ſeperately examin'd by the Lord Preſident, were admoniſh'd to take great care what they anſwered, for that it was ſworn (by <hi>Bolron</hi> and another) that Mr. <hi>Gaſcoigne</hi> was ſeen at <hi>London</hi> both the beginning and latter end of <hi>May</hi> by ſeveral; whereto it was reply'd by one of them under examination, That <hi>on that</hi> 30th <hi>of</hi> May he aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in a Cauſe or Law-ſuit of Sir <hi>Thomas</hi>'s againſt one Mr. <hi>Nelthorp</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> and that his Sons preſence, if he were in <hi>London,</hi> had been neceſſary, and that if Mr. <hi>Thomas</hi> had been any where near, he would have appeared at it to have ſupplyed his Fathers place at the ſaid Tryal in <hi>Chancery:</hi> Nay <hi>Bolron</hi> himſelf has ſince depos'd, that one principal cauſe of Mr. <hi>Gaſcoigne</hi>'s coming to Town when he left the Country, was <hi>this very Law buſineſs with Mr.</hi> Nelthrop, how truly the effect hath ſhewn, as well as of the reſt of thoſe Allegations.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">For he Mr. <hi>Tho.</hi> went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Sea near two months before the Tryal with the ſaid <hi>Nelthrop.</hi>
               </note> The <hi>7th</hi> of <hi>July</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> was taken into cuſtody, late at night, out of his Houſe at <hi>Barnbow,</hi> fourteen Miles from <hi>York,</hi> and <hi>Bolron</hi> cauſed a Warrant to be ſerved on his own Wife and Grand-mother, to teſtifie before Mr. <hi>Lowther</hi> and Mr. <hi>Tyndal</hi> what they knew of the things they had charged Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> with; but they were very unwilling to go, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted before God, that they never knew nor heard of any ill by the ſaid Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> or any thing in the leaſt ways concerning any wicked deſign againſt the Kings Perſon, the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Religion of the Nation. Whereupon the ſaid <hi>Bolron</hi> being much enraged, ſwore and threatned, and then ſaid, if they would go and teſtify what he had ſworn againſt Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> he ſhould get 500 <hi>l.</hi> by it; but if they refuſed to do ſo, he ſhould be utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done; after this <hi>Bolron</hi> was very melancholly, and being ask'd if his Conſcience did not trouble him for what he had ſworn againſt Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> he declared, That if ſome Perſons would paſs it by, he would not proſecute him any further. One of Sir <hi>Thomas</hi>'s Servants
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103730:5"/>
went to <hi>Bolrons</hi> Houſe that night about nine a Clock, and found <hi>Bolrons</hi> Wife in bed cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing extreamly, complaining that her Husband had lately made her ſet her Hand to a Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, pretending to her that it only concern'd her conſent to part with her right to the Houſe at <hi>New-Caſtle,</hi> which ſhe willingly agreed to; but ſhe now found it was a Writing wherein her Husband had accuſed Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> and ſeveral others, but had not found pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to produce it as yet.</p>
            <p>The <hi>18th</hi> of that Month Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> was examin'd at the Council-Board, and the day following he was committed to the Tower; now <hi>Bolron</hi> (who was alſo return'd) conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that he had often named Mr. <hi>Corker,</hi> (a Priſoner in <hi>Newgate)</hi> as a Man he intimate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knew, though in truth he had never ſeen him in his life; and thinking alſo that it was neceſſary he ſhould be able to diſtinguiſh him at leaſt from other Men, (againſt the time he ſhould be brought to charge him about the Plot, and about the Moneys return'd to him) he came on the <hi>22d</hi> of <hi>July</hi> laſt to the Preſs-yard at <hi>Newgate,</hi> in another Man's Name, deſiring the Turn-key to bring Mr. <hi>Corker</hi> to him; Mr. <hi>Corker</hi> being inform'd that a Stranger would ſpeak with him, very prudently deſired a Gentleman then preſent to ſtep down, and ſee who it was; the Gentleman coming into the Box, and asking before ſome Proteſtants that were by, who would ſpeak with Mr. <hi>Corker? Bolron</hi> ſuppoſing him to be the Man, call'd him Mr. <hi>Corker,</hi> and ask'd him how he did, pretending a particular know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him, and ſeveral years acquaintance with him; whereat the Gentleman following the humour, ſate down by him, and drank with him; ſo that the familiarity encreaſing, <hi>Bolron</hi> (among other things) told him he had ſeveral times heard him ſay Maſs; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Mr. <hi>Corker</hi> being made acquainted with this pleaſant Paſſage, came down to the Box likewiſe, and ſate by <hi>Bolron,</hi> who knew him not in the leaſt, but wholly applied himſelf to the other; all which the Proteſtants, and others preſent, have atteſted under their Hands.</p>
            <p>—The like accident happened to <hi>Bolron</hi> the laſt Summer Aſſizes at <hi>York;</hi> for there he demanded of Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> the Goaler a ſight of his Priſoners, (a Method learn'd of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraternity at <hi>London</hi> (to whom all Priſons were open at their call) and having there throughly view'd and ſurvey'd one <hi>Lambert,</hi> he at length ſaluted him by the Name of one <hi>Osbaldeſtone;</hi> who anſwering that he was not the Man, <hi>Bolron</hi> told him that he was, and that he would ſwear that he heard him ſay Maſs: Whereon Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> replyed, That he was a raſh Man, for that <hi>Lambert</hi> was a Tradeſ-man, as ſeveral could teſtifie, and beſides, <hi>Osbaldeſtone</hi> was twenty five years elder.</p>
            <p>At this time <hi>Bolron</hi> becoming more known in <hi>London,</hi> and familiar, was advertiſed by ſome of his new Collegues, <note n="*" place="margin">Who had peruſal of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Papers, and all Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for their better infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation through moſt Offices.</note> and Well-wiſhers, in plain Language, that he had made a mighty falſe ſtep in ſwearing on the <hi>4th</hi> of <hi>July, That Sir</hi> Thomas <hi>had ſaid to him on the</hi> 30th <hi>of</hi> May <hi>laſt, that if he would aſſiſt to kill the King, he would ſend him to his Son</hi> Thomas, <hi>who would inſtruct him how do it, and that he ſhould have</hi> 1000 l. <hi>reward;</hi> whereas in truth it was found that Mr. <hi>Thomas Gaſcoigne</hi> was gone to <hi>Paris</hi> about eight weeks before that <hi>30th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> with His Majeſties Licence or Paſs-Port, and had continued there ever ſince in much company. <hi>Bolron</hi> was extreamly ſurprized in having ſo unluckily named Mr. <hi>Tho. Gaſcoigne</hi> to be his aſſiſtant to kill the King, at a time when he was not upon the Land, nor of ſo many weeks before had been, and which his former Depoſition implyed, and as he had aſſured the Lords on Oath, and they had found it different, <hi>Bolron</hi> was at a loſs, but his Brethren had bethought them of a Salvo; he confided the Point to others alſo, ſhews them Copies of all, and it was reſolved the Redreſs ſhould be by a ſecond additio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Information (given in about the end of the ſaid <hi>July)</hi> to reconcile the former, and to cover the Artifice of it by a latter Superfoetation of ſuch old and new things as might be proper, and ſeem natural; but it's plain, the drift of the ſaid Addition was to make Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> have ſpoken to him in theſe different words from his former, <hi>viz. If thou wilt undertake to aſſiſt to kill the King, I will ſend thee to my Son,</hi> (if in Town) <hi>who,</hi> with the reſt that are concern'd, <hi>ſhall inſtruct thee how thou ſhalt aſſiſt in it, and thou ſhalt have</hi> 1000 l. <hi>reward.</hi> Having ſworn thus in his ſecond Depoſition, and compoſed the Matter as he thought, the Conſult adviſed him to apply now to the greateſt difficulty, which was to get a ſecond Witneſs, who might confirm what he had already ſworn.</p>
            <p>Therefore about the beginning of <hi>Auguſt</hi> he ſets out for <hi>York-ſhire;</hi> and pretending he had many Prieſts and others concerned in his Plot, he obtained Moneys and Commiſſions to ſeize and ſecure all ſuch Papiſts as he found obnoxious; and under this pretence going to <hi>Leeds,</hi> he wonderfully careſſed his old Fellow-ſervant <hi>Maybury,</hi> informs him of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Proclamations, Narratives, and other Tranſactions at <hi>London,</hi> ſhews him how much the World was mended with him, tells him how eaſie it is, not only to get a Pardon for any former Felony, Forgeries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but to make ones Fortunes for ever, and alſo to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd on all Enemies. And that certainly the Lady <hi>Tempeſt</hi> (Daughter to Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coigne)</hi> could not be deem'd his Friend, who had ſo defam'd him, and blaſted his Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103730:5"/>
in her noiſe about her Trunk, and the Moneys taken from the Family, which in time might have a worſe effect, and he ſuffer for't, when too late to repent the loſs of this Golden opportunity to deſtroy her and ſecure himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maybury</hi> thus won in few days, declares himſelf a Witneſs, notwithſtanding he had few days before proteſted to ſeveral, (who were amaz'd at Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his Charge) that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd him to be moſt unjuſtly accuſed; nay <hi>Bolron</hi> was ſo pleaſed with his new Conqueſt, that he tells a young Woman, (whom <hi>Maybury</hi> courted) that ſhe might marry him now with ſatisfaction, for that he had ingaged him (the ſaid <hi>Maybury)</hi> in a Buſineſs againſt Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> and that he ſhould be well rewarded out of his Eſtate, and come to great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment. Methods and Circumſtances being now fully ſetled and agreed upon by them, <hi>Maybury</hi> goes to Mr. <hi>Tyndal</hi> and <hi>Lowther,</hi> Juſtices of the Peace, and acquaints them in ſhort of his buſineſs; whereupon the <hi>16th</hi> of <hi>Auguſt</hi> the ſaid <hi>Maybury</hi> informs th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m upon Oath, (and as it appears in his Narrative more at large) That Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoigne</hi> and Sir <hi>Miles Stapleton</hi> had made Deeds of Truſt of their Eſtates, and that about <hi>Michaelmas</hi> 76. <note n="a" place="margin">At firſt <hi>May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> had ſworn this treaſonable diſcourſe to have been o're heard by him in <hi>Spring</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent, when ſome of the Accuſed were not in <hi>York-ſhire,</hi>—Now (like <hi>Bolron)</hi> advertiſed by the Brethren of his miſtake, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof that would enſue, he turns the Spring into <hi>Michaelmas.</hi>
               </note> Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> his Son Mr. <hi>Thomas,</hi> the Lady <hi>Tempeſt,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Ruſhton,</hi> being in <hi>Barmbow</hi> Dining-room, he heard them holding ſeveral diſcourſes concerning killing the King, and firing of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>York,</hi> &amp;c.—That there was in the Houſe one Doctor <hi>Stapleton,</hi> who coming from another Room, and finding him at the Door, went in, and in <hi>a low Voice</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">He could o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-hear low as well as high, and though at a greater di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance than before.</note> deſired them to forbear their diſcourſe, for there was one at the door.—And thereupon her Ladiſhip call'd him in, and ſent him down to entertain ſome Strangers; and that he heard ſeveral diſcourſes from Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Ruſhton</hi> about a Nunnery to be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd at <hi>Dolebanke,</hi> and of Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his ſelling 90 <hi>l. per Annum</hi> for maintaining it.</p>
            <p>Whilſt <hi>Maybury</hi> was hugging himſelf with <hi>Bolron,</hi> that this Information would ſuddenly be at the Council-Board, he found more than a fortnight paſſed, and no manner of notice taken of him, his impatience prompts him the laſt of that Month to write <note n="c" place="margin">He becomes officious and importune.</note> to Sir <hi>John Nicholas,</hi> that there were divers material Circumſtances relating to his Diſcovery, which were not inſerted in his firſt Information before the Juſtices, which ſhould be declared when the Council ſhould command a full account from him. Upon this he had a Summons by a Meſſenger ſent him on purpoſe, and a Letter ſuperſcrib'd <hi>To Mr. Lawrence Mowbray,</hi> at his Houſe in <hi>York-ſhire;</hi> and ſo repairing to <hi>London</hi> on the ſecond of <hi>October</hi> following, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd Juſtice <hi>Warcup</hi> by Order of Council upon Oath, that he had not diſcovered <hi>all he knew</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">As his Oath in the Country implied then, whereon a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark was made, and ſomething more to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile it.</note> of the horrid Plot, for fear of <hi>York-ſhire</hi> Papiſts, whom he was to detect; but now would do it, conceiving himſelf under the Protection of the Council, and hoping that they would intercede for his Pardon: <note n="e" place="margin">Which was ſoon after granted him and his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legue.</note> Then he ſaid, That in the Year 1674. he came to Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> and was with him in his Service till <hi>January 1676, &amp;c.</hi>—That waiting on <hi>Ruſhton</hi> at the Altar, he was permitted to be in his private Chamber, when other Prieſts were conſulting with him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as appears more at large in his Narrative and Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>That he took the Sacrament of Secrecy from <hi>Ruſhton,</hi> and well remembers, that about <hi>Michaelmas</hi> 1676. there was an Aſſembly of many Prieſts and others at <hi>Ruſhtons</hi> Chamber, when they all agreed and declar'd that the King ſhould be kill'd, and then Fire and Sword were to be imploy'd againſt the Oppoſers of the Catholick Religion, and all or moſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks were engaged therein.—That <hi>Ruſhton</hi> then produced to the Prieſts a Liſt <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>T. O.</hi> his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod to have a grand reſerve or ſtock for ſure Accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, if his firſt ſucceeded.</note> of 4 <hi>or 500 Names</hi> engaged in the Deſign, and he had read many of them, and remembers very well that Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoigne,</hi> Sir <hi>Miles Stapleton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Thomas Gaſcoigne,</hi> the Lady <hi>Tempeſt, Thomas Preſſick,</hi> and many others were in the Liſt: That Moneys <hi>and Arms</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">But never produced.</note> were collect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and that on <hi>the firſt of</hi> January 1677. he wrote a Letter (for ſo he ſwore and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms in his Narrative) to the Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> which he ſent that day by the Poſt from <hi>Leeds</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> declaring therein, (not in hopes of Reward, (God forbid) but as a true and Loyal Subject to the King) that ſome Papiſt-Conſpirators had a wicked and deſperate Deſign againſt the King; and by an immediate Inſurrection to proceed with Fire and Sword, till they had altered the Government, or ſetled the Crown upon the Head of ſome other Perſon. <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>T. O.</hi> by him degraded from the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt knowledge of the Plot.—And at Sir <hi>Thomas</hi>'s Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al <hi>Oats</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Father, and <hi>Bolrons</hi> good Mother, had a conteſt in the Hall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy due to one of their Sons.</note> So that by conſequence the Death of the King was conſpired and ſought for.—That this Conſpiracy was to his knowledge contriv'd almoſt three years ago, and now was at the height of a deſperate reſolution.—That his Heart was Loyal and true to the King; but confeſs'd, that through <hi>Ruſhtons</hi> perſwaſions, he himſelf had ſubſcribed to this wieked Deſign, and now was forced by his Loyalty to his King, and to clear his ſtain'd Conſcience, to reveal it: That he would endeavour to procure <hi>a Liſt of the Conſpirators</hi> which he had ſeen and ſubſcribed to. That he was certain Mr. <hi>Ingoldsby,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coigne, Thomas Gaſcoigne</hi> Eſq;, Sir <hi>Miles Stapleton,</hi> with many others, had ſubſcribed it, and were great promoters of this Act, and are ſtill providing Force and Arms to carry on this Deſign.—That he begg'd his Lordſhips pardon for this boldneſs, and intreated him to communicate this to whom he thought fit.—That at preſent he durſt not ſubſcribe his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103730:6"/>
Name, being within the <note n="a" place="margin">Whereas by his Narrative ſince printed, and Proofs of his conſtant habitation, it appears he was in <hi>London</hi> from Spring to the end of the ſaid year.</note> Claws of the Papiſts, but upon protection from them he would acknowledge the Hand and Mark ſubſcribed. <note n="b" place="margin">☞ As in his Narrative, <hi>fol.</hi> 15. ſays <hi>York;</hi> but <hi>ibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem P.</hi> 21. ſays it from <hi>Leeds.</hi>
               </note> ☞—<hi>York 1. January</hi> 1677/8. yet ſent from <hi>Leeds</hi> as a few Lines before he had depoſed.—This is the effect of the pretended Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which forſooth never came to the Dukes Hands; and yet I etters we find do as ſeldom miſcarry here, as in any place of the World; but the whole deſign is (Reader) ſo vain, that one would wonder how a Man could fancy ſuch a childiſh Fable would take and ſalve his not diſcovery of the Plot before; for he not only lay dormant three whole quarters of a year, I mean the whole time between the date of his wifes Letter, and <hi>T. O.</hi> his appearing in the World, but almoſt a year after the full diſcovery of the Plot, notwithſtanding the encouragements the Witneſſes had by the Kings Royal Proclamations, and the miſery of the Catholicks in <hi>England</hi> were in: But to be ſhort, it appears by what is already ſaid and ſhew'd, that this <hi>Maybury</hi> was ſo far from writing any ſuch Letter at that time from <hi>York</hi> or <hi>Leeds,</hi> (and he ſwears both) that he was then actually at <hi>London,</hi> (as ſeveral Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants here are ready to teſtifie.) So that his deſign and ambition was not only to equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize, but alſo to exceed and out-go thoſe of the Kings Evidence that had got the ſtart of him in the ſuppoſed Diſcoveries.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoigne</hi> being committed to the Tower, as has been mentioned, an Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was preferr'd at <hi>Leeds</hi> before eſpecial Commiſſioners of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer,</hi> on the <hi>7th</hi> of <hi>November,</hi> againſt him and Sir <hi>Miles Stapleton,</hi> for that they, with ſeveral others, on the aforeſaid <hi>30th</hi> of <hi>May</hi> 1679. at <hi>Barmbow</hi> contriv'd to kill the <hi>King,</hi> &amp;c. and that Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> then ſolicited <hi>Bolron</hi> to't, and promiſed him a thouſand Pounds for't; upon the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of <hi>Bolron</hi> and <hi>Maybury</hi> it was found; and <hi>Bolron</hi> being then ask'd, if <hi>Maybury</hi> had not been ſuſpected of ſtealing Money and Jewels, he ſaid, <hi>No;</hi> (and that the things ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be ſtoln, were his the ſaid <hi>Bolrons)</hi> ſo that the denial is a new eſcape, and directly contrary to what he found by his Copies he had ſworn before the Council, of the ſaid <hi>Maybury</hi> parting from Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> on ſuſpition of Theft.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Priſoner</hi> was under infinite diſadvantages, he being about 85 years of age; he had of late years almoſt totally loſt his Hearing; his Memory was mightily decay'd; his Sight bad; his Hands ſhaking; his Body crazy; his Mind ſo little intent to publick buſineſs, that he was not in <hi>London</hi> but once in thirty years, and that was in paſſing to <hi>France</hi> and back, which happened about 14 years ago. This poor Gentleman now finding that theſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons had ſworn poſitive Treaſon againſt him, and underſtanding by ſome who were inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate with them, and had had a ſight of their Papers, that they had poſitively contradict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves in their ſeveral Informations, he thought fit to petition for Copies of the ſaid Informations, but was denied them; ſo that all his dependance, under God, was his Innocency, and in the aſſiſtance of Mr. <hi>Charles Ingoldsby</hi> a Lawyer, and his near Kinſ-man, and therefore to him he committed all the management of his Affairs.</p>
            <p>On the <hi>24th</hi> of <hi>January</hi> he was arraigned at the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> Bar, where, firſt croſſing himſelf with his Hand, he anſwered. <hi>In the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt, Amen. Not Guilty.</hi> Now he prayed the Court, (ſome of his material Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes being at <hi>Paris)</hi> that his Tryal might not be till they could conveniently be ſent for, for he feared the day appointed for them was of the ſooneſt, and ſo it prov'd, for they came not till a day or two after. <hi>Bolron</hi> finding that Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> rely'd wholly on Mr. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goldsby,</hi> (as has been ſaid) what does he, but informs againſt him as a Conſpirator, and ſo got him ſeiz'd by a Meſſenger, which fell out whilſt he was actually penning Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his Breviate, which amaz'd not a little every body; for Mr. <hi>Ingoldsby</hi> had not only openly frequented <hi>London</hi> and the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> Bar every Term ſince the Plot was firſt talk'd of, but was at home in <hi>York-ſhire</hi> when Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> was accus'd and taken with the reſt; nay he was publickly at <hi>York</hi> Aſſizes, (as Mr. Juſtice <hi>Dolbin</hi> acknowledged) when <hi>Bolron</hi> came thither with Commiſſions to apprehend whom he pleaſed: Nay yet more, was in a Room where <hi>Bolron</hi> came to ſearch, and yet took no notice of him there neither.</p>
            <p>The <hi>11th</hi> of <hi>February</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> was brought to his Tryal, Serjeant <hi>Maynard</hi> and Mr. Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, Mr. Solicitor and Mr. Recorder being of Counſel againſt him; and there <hi>Bolron</hi> ſwore, that he came to his Service in the year 1674.—That a Deed of <note n="c" place="margin">All Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks do the like, when they fear any freſh perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing the Poenal Laws.</note> Truſt was executed to Sir <hi>William Ingoldsby</hi> by Mr. <hi>Charles Ingoldsby</hi>'s advice about <hi>April.</hi> 1675. and that Sir <hi>Miles S.</hi> ſaid it was well done.—That in 1676. Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> ſaid that he would ſend 3000 <hi>l.</hi> to the Jeſuits at <hi>London</hi> for carrying on the Deſign; but if ſent or not he knows not.—That in 1677. Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> Mr. <hi>Thomas Gaſcoigne,</hi> Mr. <hi>Ingoldsby,</hi> Lady <hi>Tempeſt,</hi> and others, met at Sir <hi>Thomas</hi>'s, and agreed to eſtabliſh a Nunnery.—That Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> was to give 90 <hi>l. per An'</hi> towards it, and be Canonized, his Son <hi>Thomas</hi> to be made a Privy-Councellor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—That they were ſix hours in conſultation to carry on the Deſign.—That in <hi>March</hi> laſt Mr. <hi>Thomas</hi> told his Father he had gotten a Licence to go to <hi>London.—That he would fly into</hi> France, <hi>and commit the Deſign</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bolron</hi> his variation from his firſt Depoſition, and uniting with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond to ſalve the former.</note> 
               <hi>to thoſe would not fail to do it:</hi> And Sir <hi>Tho.</hi> approv'd it.—That
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103730:6"/>
on the <hi>30th</hi> of <hi>May</hi> he went into Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his Gallery, and <hi>Ruſhton</hi> chid him for taking the Oaths of Allegiance, and told him it was meritorious to kill the King, and he would aſſiſt in't; but, he, <hi>Bolron</hi> would have no hand in it.—That having ſtaid by S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r <hi>Thomas</hi> his order till he returned, Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> took him into his Chamber about ſix a Clock that night; and having ask'd him the diſcourſe between him and <hi>Ruſhton,</hi> which was ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the preſent purpoſe, yet ſaid, if thou wilt undertake to aſſiſt to kill the King, I will give thee a thouſand Pounds, and ſend thee to my Son <hi>Tom, if in</hi> London, <hi>or elſe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers concerned therein.</hi> But he refuſing to have his Hands in Blood, Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> pray'd him <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bolron</hi> renews his <hi>Salvo</hi> for his firſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</note> to keep it ſecret, and he promis'd it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bolron</hi> being ask'd by the Lord Chief Juſtice, when he firſt diſcovered this to any body? he ſaid, that about a week or a fortnight after he went to Mr. <hi>Tyndal,</hi> and upon Oath in writing inform'd him that Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> offer'd him a thouſand Pounds to kill the King; and that Mr. <hi>Tyndall</hi> ſaid he would give the Council an account thereof, and iſſued out his War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant againſt <hi>Preſſick,</hi> but not againſt Sir <hi>Thomas:</hi> Whereat his Lordſhip ſeem'd to wonder yet more, as well he might. <note n="a" place="margin">To ſee ſo little credit given to his Information, as not to ſeize Sir <hi>Tho.</hi> in ſo important a Caſe.</note>—That in the latter end of <hi>June</hi> (he ſhould have ſaid the beginning of <hi>July)</hi> he came to <hi>London,</hi> and was examin'd by Sir <hi>Robert Clayton,</hi> and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> the fourth <hi>ditto,</hi>—and there he might have told how that he then made a full Information upon Oath; and that upon the <hi>29th</hi> he made the amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, both which he hath now united into one, as he had done in his Narrative, leſt he ſhould offend the Criticks with his humane frailty, and want of memory in ſo freſh a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; but he thought better on't, and that it would be a diſcovery of his chiefeſt Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maybury</hi> being next ſworn, depoſed, That he came to Sir <hi>Thomas</hi>'s Service in 1674. and liv'd with him till <hi>January</hi> 1676. that divers Prieſts came to Sir <hi>Thomas</hi>'s, and he ſerving at the Altar, was permitted to be with them.—That 1676. he heard them diſcourſing of bringing in Popery by Fire and Sword, if it could not be done by fair means.—That <hi>York</hi> and <hi>London</hi> ſhould be fired, and the King kill'd for a Heretick.—That <hi>Ruſhton</hi> ſaid ſo, (Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> not being preſent) but Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> and his Son <hi>Thomas,</hi> and the Lady <hi>Tempeſt,</hi> and <hi>Stephen Tempeſt,</hi> received firſt <hi>the Sacrament of Secrecy,</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">It is but rare in Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors, and the greateſt Princes have taken the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, on occaſion even of ratifying Articles of peace, leagues, and marriages of State. But amongſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks in private the very word Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Secrecy is not underſtood; or ſeen pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, as Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions can te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie.</note> and then were made acquainted with it, who all agreed to kill the King, and he the ſaid <hi>Maybury</hi> received the Oath of Secrecy alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That about</hi> Michaelmas 1676. <hi>he ſaw a Liſt with 500 Names; that the Title of it was, The Names of them engaged in killing the King, and ſetting up the Popiſh Religion; that Sir</hi> Thomas Gaſcoigns <hi>Name was to it with his own Hand, as alſo the Lady</hi> Tempeſt, <hi>Mr.</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Gaſcoign, <hi>Mr.</hi> Stephen Tempeſts, <hi>Sir</hi> Walter V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Sir</hi> Francis Hungates, <hi>the</hi> Townleys, <hi>and ſeveral others.</hi>—That they diſcourſed of Commiſſions, Indulgences, and Pardons from the Pope for it.—That about <hi>Michaelmas</hi> 1676. Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> his Son <hi>Thomas,</hi> the Lady <hi>Tempeſt,</hi> Sir <hi>Miles Stapleton,</hi> and <hi>Ruſhton,</hi> in the Dining-room at <hi>Barmbow,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared they would do their utmoſt to kill the King, and would venture their Lives and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates therein.—That <hi>Doctor Stapleton</hi> coming from ſome other part of the Houſe, went in, and told them, that, he, the Deponent, was at the door; that thereupon the Lady <hi>Tempeſt</hi> bade him go down and entertain Sir <hi>Miles</hi> his Servants.—Being ask'd why he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd it not long before? he anſwered, That about <hi>Michaelmas</hi> 1679. he diſcover'd it to Mr. <hi>Tyndal,</hi> but durſt not do it of three years before, <hi>for fear that Papiſts ſhould kill him.</hi> He further added, That he turn'd Proteſtant about the time that the Plot firſt came out; which occaſioned the greater wonder in the Auditory, conſidering him a twelve-month ſilent, when <hi>Oates</hi> and the reſt had broken the Ice with ſuch ſucceſs and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and a whole Nation with their Repreſentative <note n="c" place="margin">Beſides His Majeſties Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations and Aſſurances of Reward to the further diſcoveries, and his having liv'd in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> about a year. His Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation known ſince to many.</note> ſtanding at his back.</p>
            <p>Several of Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his Almanacks, which were taken from him, were produced alſo againſt him, and there it appear'd, (by his own writing) that from the <hi>21ſt</hi> of <hi>July</hi> 1678. Mr. <hi>Corker</hi> had received from him 900 <hi>l.</hi> and directions were there alſo how to ſend Letters to Mr. <hi>Harcourt,</hi> and about buying <hi>Heworth,</hi> and likewiſe about buying the Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Heworth</hi> for his Niece <hi>Thwing;</hi> as alſo a <hi>Memorandum</hi> to acquaint <hi>Thomas Thwing with his deſign,</hi> and other Notes; as alſo a Paper of the <hi>9th</hi> of <hi>June</hi> 78. which had been taken out of Sir <hi>Thomas</hi>'s Chamber, was produced againſt him likewiſe, being a Letter from <hi>John Praſſet,</hi> and a Paper to Mr. <hi>Benefeild,</hi> with a <hi>Proviſo,</hi> that if <hi>England</hi> ſhould be converted, then the whole 90 <hi>l. per Annum</hi> ſhould be applied to purchaſe <hi>Heworth,</hi> and the Writing to be made without any alteration. Moreover the word <hi>Yes,</hi> on the ſide of the ſaid Paper, was written by Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> himſelf.</p>
            <p>There was alſo a Letter of the <hi>24th</hi> of <hi>May</hi> laſt from Mr. <hi>Praſſet</hi> produced, wherein he he declared the taking of the Oath, as now worded, damnable; but ſome Letters that were for Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his advantage, and would plainly have made appear ſome of <hi>Bolrons</hi> Informations to be moſt inſulſe and inconſiſtent, were ſuppreſſed and kept from the Priſoner, and from the view of any.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:103730:7"/>
After this <hi>Richard Fiſhwick</hi> was ſworn, who declar'd, that he had ſerv'd Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſix years, and a Writing was ſhewn, which gave an account of his returning in ſix years 6000 <hi>l.</hi> to <hi>London.</hi> This the ſaid <hi>Fiſhwick</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Formerly Servant to Sir <hi>Thomas.</hi>
               </note> own'd, and that part thereof was Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his own Money, part of it was Mr. <hi>Thomas Gaſcoignes,</hi> and the Lady <hi>Tempeſts,</hi> and that Mr. <hi>Thomas Gaſcoigne</hi> had 4 or 500 <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> and the Lady <hi>Tempeſt</hi> 3 or 400 <hi>l. per Annum.</hi>—Mr. Attorney General produc'd an Account out of Mr. <hi>Mawſon</hi>'s Book, That from <hi>March</hi> 1674. to <hi>December</hi> 1677. there was return'd from him to Sir <hi>Thomas 2500 l.</hi> and that ſeveral Sums thereof were paid to Mr. <hi>Corker,</hi> which Sum was taken as part of the 6000 <hi>l.</hi> return'd from <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> as before mentioned: And here Mr. Attorney ended, ſaying, that he would give no further evidence at preſent, till he heard what the Priſoner would offer in his defence.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> who all this while underſtood not one ſyllable from the Witneſſes themſelves of what they had ſworn againſt him; but having by his Solicitors, hollowing in his Ear, an imperfect apprehenſion of ſome Particulars, prayed the Court, (after he had a little conſidered his Breviate) that the Witneſſes following might be examin'd; who being call'd, teſtified to this purpoſe.—</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>James Babington</hi> teſtified, and offered to depoſe,—That he was, and for ſeveral <note place="margin">Proteſtant.</note> years had been Attorney at Law to Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoigne;</hi> and by his direction ſued <hi>Bolron</hi> in <hi>May</hi> laſt upon his two Bonds of 20 <hi>l.</hi> and 28 <hi>l.</hi> and that <hi>Bolron</hi> deſired him to forbear ſuing him for a fortnights time, and promiſed to pay the Money due upon the ſaid Bonds, or to ſecure the ſame. That <hi>Bolron</hi> alſo offer'd afterwards to make a Mortgage of his Houſe at <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> for Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his ſecurity; but that his Wife refuſed to joyn therein, unleſs the Bonds were cancell'd.—That on or about the <hi>13th</hi> of <hi>June</hi> laſt, he, by Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his direction, delivered <hi>Bolron</hi> a Declaration in <hi>Ejectment</hi> for the Farm he liv'd in, and told him that he had Orders from Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> to proceed againſt him; and <hi>Bolron</hi> ſaid,—By God then will I do that which I did not intend.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obediah Moore</hi> teſtified, That he being bound with <hi>Bolron</hi> in the ſaid Bonds, preſs'd him <note place="margin">Proteſtant.</note> for Counter-Security; but <hi>Bolron</hi> told him, that he need not fear; for if Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> offer'd to ſue him, he would be reveng'd on him, and inform againſt him.—That after this, he the ſaid <hi>Moore</hi> ſued <hi>Bolron,</hi> and that upon the <hi>29th</hi> of <hi>May</hi> laſt ſeveral Bailiffs by his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment attended to arreſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stephen Thompſon</hi> teſtified, That he was likewiſe perſwaded by the ſaid <hi>Bolron</hi> to be ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his Securities for payment of the ſaid 48 <hi>l.</hi> Capital Money to Sir <hi>Thomas;</hi> and that <note place="margin">Proteſtant.</note> he pray'd the ſaid <hi>Bolron</hi> to keep him harmleſs from the fame; and <hi>Bolron</hi> thereupon told him, <hi>if Sir</hi> Thomas Gaſcoigne <hi>ſues me, I will do his work for him.</hi> Whereupon he ask'd <hi>Bolron</hi> how he would do it, and if Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> was in the Plot? <hi>Bolron</hi> ſaid no, he is as clear of the Plot as the Child unborn, but he would inform againſt him <hi>for harbouring of Prieſts.</hi>—That after Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> was impriſon'd, the ſaid <hi>Bolron</hi> declar'd, that what he had ſaid of Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his not being in the Plot was falſe, and was ſpoken by him when he was a Papiſt, and could ſay any thing. That now he was offer'd Money for diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Plot, but would not take it till he knew what <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Bedlow</hi> had done.—That before he gave his Evidence he would have as much Money as they had; and further, that he would thereby diſcharge the ſaid Debt; and then the ſaid <hi>Bolron</hi> deſir'd him not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what he had ſpoken.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Backhouſe</hi> teſtified, that upon the <hi>7th</hi> of <hi>July</hi> laſt he was charged by Warrant to <note place="margin">Proteſtant.</note> carry <hi>Bolrons</hi> Wife before Mr. <hi>Lowther,</hi> but that ſhe was ſick in bed, and cry'd, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd to go, ſaying, <hi>That ſhe knew nothing ill againſt Sir</hi> Thomas: That thereupon <hi>Bolron</hi> threatned her, telling her ſhe muſt go and ſwear againſt him, or elſe he would draw her thither at the Carts tail,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cuthbert Hemſworth</hi> teſtified to the ſame effect. Then—<note place="margin">Proteſtant.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nicholas Shippen</hi> teſtified, That upon <hi>the</hi> 29th <hi>of</hi> May laſt he was at <hi>Garforth</hi> Horſe-race, and that night he ſaw <hi>Bolron,</hi> who ask'd him if he had ſeen any Bailiffs abroad; that he told him he had ſeen <hi>Obedia Moore,</hi> and two Bailiffs, going towards <hi>Bolrons</hi> Houſe that Evening; whereupon <hi>Bolron</hi> wiſh'd that he might eſcape them. That the day following (being the very <hi>30th of May,</hi> or day on which <hi>Bolron</hi> ſwore, he had thoſe treaſonable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes with <hi>Ruſhton</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas; Bolron</hi> came to his the ſaid <hi>Shippens</hi> Houſe about two a Clock in the Afternoon, and ſtay'd there till two hours after Sun-ſet; and that <hi>Bolron</hi> was never out of his ſight all that time, having told him that he came thither to ſend a Letter to <hi>Newcaſtle, for that he</hi> durſt not carry it himſelf to the Poſt-houſe for fear the Bailiffs ſhould take him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Roger Grigſon</hi> teſtified, That in <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt <hi>Bolron</hi> ſaid that Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> would come off well <note place="margin">Proteſtant.</note> enough, only it would coſt him Moneys; and in caſe <hi>Addiſon</hi> that Rogue had not examin'd, and taken his Accounts, he would never have done what he did againſt Sir <hi>Thomas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:103730:7"/>
               <hi>William Bateby</hi> teſtified, That about the beginning of <hi>Auguſt</hi> (he and <hi>George Dixon</hi> being <note place="margin">Proteſant.</note> together, and <hi>Bolron</hi> and <hi>Maybury</hi> in another Room) he heard <hi>Bolron</hi> ſay to <hi>Maybury,</hi> that Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> and the Lady <hi>Tempeſt</hi> had been ſevere againſt them, and now they had an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to be reveng'd on them.—That <hi>Maybury</hi> ſaid Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> was an honeſt Man, and that he knew no ill by him, nor had ever done him harm; but that if he knew any thing againſt the Lady <hi>Tempeſt</hi> he would hang her.—That <hi>Bolron</hi> reply'd to <hi>Maybury,</hi> that if he would be rul'd by him, he would adviſe him how to accompliſh his deſires; and added, that he was ſued by Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> and that if he made not out ſomething againſt him, he ſhould be ruin'd. That if they both joyn'd and ſtruck at them, it might be effected, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing being to be done againſt them, but by the Teſtimony of two Witneſſes.—That in caſe <hi>Maybury</hi> would come to his Houſe, he would inſtruct him therein, and that he would engage he ſhould have a good reward out of Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his Eſtate; and thereupon he heard <hi>Maybury</hi> agree thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>George Dixon</hi> confirm'd this Teſtimony; whereupon—<hi>Bolron</hi> anſwered, <hi>That upon</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Proteſtant.</note> 
               <hi>the Oath he had taken he had never ſeen the Witneſs.</hi> And <hi>Maybury</hi> ſaid to the ſame purpoſe; which ſeem'd not only ridiculous, had their Aſſertion been true, (for a Stranger may over-hear as well as an Acquaintance) but caus'd the Witneſs in indignation at their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence to declare, that they were well known to each other; and this ſeveral can teſtifie.</p>
            <p>One of the Judges urged againſt the Priſoners Witneſs, why this Combination of <hi>Bolron</hi> and <hi>Maybury</hi> was not ſooner made known to ſome body; and it was immediately replyed to his Lordſhip, That it was very early communicated to their Acquaintance, and named ſome regardable, being Proteſtants alſo.</p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>Deborah Jefferſon</hi> teſtified, That about the beginning of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt <hi>Maybury</hi> ſaid to <note place="margin">Proteſtant.</note> her, That Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> was a very honeſt Gentleman, and that he believ'd he was unjuſtly accuſed.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Matthew Hickeringal</hi> teſtified, That <hi>Maybury</hi> was generally ſuſpected to have ſtol'n <note place="margin">Proteſtant.</note> ſeveral conſiderable things from Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoigne,</hi> and the Lady <hi>Tempeſt;</hi> and that in <hi>September</hi> laſt <hi>Maybury</hi> told him that Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> and the Lady <hi>Tempeſt</hi> had endeavoured what they could to take away his Reputation and Life: That they deſerv'd as much from him, and he would now requite them.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Peebles</hi> teſtified,—That <hi>Bolron</hi> had done ſeveral ill Actions, and that he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd <note place="margin">Proteſtant.</note> of the <hi>Judges</hi> the laſt Affizes at <hi>York,</hi> as not regarding him, nor admitting him to ſpeak with them. That both <hi>Bolron</hi> and <hi>Maybury</hi> had no good Name among their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and that he could ſay more againſt them, but that he was unwilling to't, in regard they were the Kings Evidence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Clough</hi> teſtified,—That upon the <hi>24th</hi> of <hi>May</hi> laſt he arreſted <hi>Bolron</hi> by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections <note place="margin">Proteſtant.</note> of Mr. <hi>Hickeringal,</hi> (Steward to Sir <hi>Thomas)</hi> and that he then declar'd, that he would be reveng'd of Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> if he got free from that Arreſt, for that he ſaid it was through Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his means that he was arreſted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Francis Johnſon</hi> teſtified, That <hi>Bolron</hi> had much wrong'd Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> in his Accounts, whilſt he was in his Service, and look'd after his Cole-pits, and mentioned ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alice Carpmel</hi> teſtified—<hi>Bolrons</hi> malice, and <hi>Maybury</hi> being ſuſpected of ſtealing of Money; and would have proceeded, but was interrupted on directions of the Kings Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of being a Plotter.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Edward Hobart</hi> teſtified, That Mr. <hi>Thomas Appleby</hi> married one of Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his Daughters, and by her had Iſſue <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Helena,</hi> and that towards raiſing of Portions for them, after ſome years previous proviſion, their Father had granted out of his Eſtate a Rent charge of 200 <hi>l. per Annum</hi> to Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> for 21 years, and he produced the Deed in Court, and ſaid, that 4 or 500 <hi>l.</hi> thereof being in arrear, Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> commenc'd a Suit in <hi>Chancery,</hi> and the Arrears were thereupon paid him, and the 900 <hi>l.</hi> aforeſaid, which were ſent to Mr. <hi>Corker,</hi> were part of the ſaid <hi>Mary</hi>'s Portion, who is now in a religious Convent beyond Seas, and were return'd by him to her, for no other purpoſe whatſoever; he the Deponent having drawn the Acquittances for the ſame; that he was privy thereto, and conſtantly entred the ſame in his Account-Books.—That the other Siſter <hi>Helena</hi> was diſpoſed in Marriage, and 2000 <hi>l.</hi> of her Portion was likewiſe paid not long after. That he was likewiſe privy to Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> returning 1988 <hi>l.</hi> to Mr. <hi>Mawſon,</hi> and that the ſame was paid to Mr. <hi>Trumbull</hi> and Mr. <hi>Mauleverer</hi> for the Purchaſe Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> made of an Eſtate at <hi>Manſtone</hi> in <hi>York-ſhire;</hi> that he was at Mr. <hi>Trumbulls</hi> executing the Conveyance thereof, and drew the Acquittance for the ſaid Money.—That 200 <hi>l.</hi> more of the ſaid Purchaſe-money was paid to <hi>William Errington,</hi> and 80 <hi>l.</hi> more thereof to Widow <hi>Coſton,</hi> in purſuance of directions from Sir <hi>Thomas.</hi> That he the Deponent had ſeveral Letters by him, directing Payments to ſeveral of Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his Brothers, Siſters, Children, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103730:8"/>
Grand-children abroad, which Payments to his knowledge were made accordingly, and that the ſame amounted to no leſs than the 6000 <hi>l.</hi> which Mr. <hi>Fiſhwick</hi> depoſed he had return'd in ſo many years, and that the ſaid Moneys were paid to no other uſe, than as he had before declared.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> had many more Proteſtant Witneſſes in and about the Court; but by his not hearing from the Mouths of the Parties themſelves what had paſſed either for or againſt him, and eſpecially the interlocutory diſcourſes, (which in a falſe accuſation ever afford main advantages) and by his being dim-ſighted, ſo that he could not readily nor methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally follow his Breviate; as alſo tyr'd with long ſtanding, and ſtun'd too with the often hollowing in his Ears, he became ſo amaz'd and confounded, that he was wholly unable to help himſelf. Nor was any body ſuffer'd to call his Witneſſes, till he had named them; and therefore ſeveral never appeared. Nay the hurry was at length ſo great in Court, that ſome of them were diſmiſs'd before they had half done; ſome being call'd too quick after the others, that the latter got in firſt, and the former call'd loſt admiſſion; which the Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner not perceiving, and his Friends not permitted to re-mind him, was a great diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in many material occurrences; amongſt other things, thoſe Witneſſes which happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be omitted ſtood ready to teſtifie and make out the Thefts of <note n="*" place="margin">Which though before ſuſpected, were only diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered fully the night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Tryal of Sir <hi>Thomas.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Maybury:</hi> Others his Cheats, and manner of living at <hi>London:</hi> Others the Gold and Medals ſold and changed by him: Others the ill opinion Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> and his whole Family had of him, and <hi>Bolron</hi> alſo eſpecially after their departure much encreaſed: Others how the ſaid <hi>Bolron</hi> threatned his Wife, if ſhe would not joyn to accuſe Sir <hi>Thomas:</hi> Others how much he fear'd to be ſued and arreſted hy his Bonds-men: And others of Mr. <hi>Thomas Gaſcoignes</hi> being conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at <hi>Paris,</hi> or on his Journey thither from the <hi>7th</hi> of <hi>April</hi> (which was almoſt two Months before the aforeſaid <hi>30th</hi> of <hi>May)</hi> till that day of the Tryal; which was wholly inconſiſtant with a moral poſſibility of Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his directing <hi>Bolron to his Son</hi> Thomas, <hi>then to aſſiſt him in the pretended Propoſition of killing the King,</hi> as <hi>Bolrons</hi> firſt Information ſworn to did run.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that were called by Mr. Attorney in behalf of the Kings Evidence, were—firſt <hi>Bolrons</hi> Wife; who ſaid,—That her Husband never threatned or endeavoured to force her to ſwear any thing againſt Sir <hi>Thomas.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Bolrons</hi> Grand-mother, who wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed, that he was a very honeſt good Man. And laſtly, <hi>Fiſhwick,</hi> who declared, That whilſt he the ſaid <hi>Fiſhwick</hi> liv'd with Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> he knew no diſhoneſty by <hi>Bolron.</hi> Now it ſeems <hi>Fiſhwick</hi> had left Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his Service long before the Examinations of <hi>Bolrons</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, and the other matters afterward laid to his Charge, were made.</p>
            <p>Mr. Juſtice <hi>James</hi> (by reaſon the Lord Chief Juſtice was gone to try Cauſes in <hi>London)</hi> ſumm'd up the Evidence; and having done it with the uſual Tope of ſhewing not only the Principles and Practiſes of the Papiſts, generally ſuppoſed to be believed, but the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiveneſs of the two Witneſſes Oaths for the King; and then diſcending to ſome Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars in behalf of the Priſoner, he left the whole matter to the Jury. After Mr. Juſtice <hi>Dolbin</hi> had remembred him of a thing forgotten in the re-capitulation, very conſiderable,—<hi>viz.</hi> That Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> (as had been prov'd by Proteſtant Witneſſes) did ſue <hi>Bolron</hi> not only before the <hi>30th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> but juſt after alſo; and yet he had then (as <hi>Bolron</hi> ſwore) propos'd the killing of the King to him. But in Counterpoiſe to Juſtice <hi>Dolbins</hi> Remark, Mr. Juſtice <hi>Pemberton</hi> offer'd the great tye of Sacramental Secrecy, <note n="*" place="margin">A thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Catholicks, as hundreds of them recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil'd to the Church of <hi>England</hi> can teſtifie.</note> which he ſaid as if neither Life nor Death, Heaven nor Hell, nor any other provocation could move Catholicks to break, or to that effect.</p>
            <p>This done, the Jury withdrew, being, as the Law intends, Gentlemen of the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood; and therefore knowing not only Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> but his Accuſers alſo, they conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that the ſaid Accuſers were decayed and neceſſitous Perſons, who had left their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter (as the whole Country knew) upon very ill accounts:—That they tim'd the Fact in a very unlikely ſeaſon, ſeeing the Proteſtants of <hi>England</hi> were not only long alarm'd, and upon their guard againſt ſo ſmall, naked, and diſtracted a Party, but that moſt of the conſiderable <note n="*" place="margin">If one Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſant to 500 Proteſtants can be ſaid conſiderable.</note> Papiſts were retir'd beyond Seas, and the reſt (which were but a handful) diſarm'd or in Priſon, or in as low and dejected condition as could be well imagin'd. That a Pardon of all paſt Crimes, and an aſſurance of future Rewards, were great temptations to Men of an ill repute. That no body of thoſe ſince accus'd by <hi>Bolron</hi> and <hi>Maybury</hi> had ever fled or abſconded, unleſs <hi>(Ruſhton</hi> the Prieſt) who had refus'd to lend <hi>Bolron</hi> five Pounds in his neceſſities, and was obnoxious to the Law, purely on account of his being in Orders; and in common ſenſe ought not to appear.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Bolron</hi> was indebted to Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> and others of his Family, as alſo ſued by him both before and after the <hi>30th of</hi> May: That he was at the Afternoon till ten at night on the ſaid <hi>30th of</hi> May at <hi>Shippens</hi> Houſe for fear of Bailiffs; and yet pretends that at ſix that afternoon he had the treaſonable propoſition made him by <hi>Ruſhton</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas.</hi> That both <hi>Bolron</hi> and <hi>Maybury</hi> had declared an ill will to their Maſter, and that they would
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103730:8"/>
be reveng'd on him and his Daughter <hi>Tempeſt.</hi> That their very confederacy procuring to make them guilty of the Plot, was over-heard by two Proteſtant Witneſſes.—That they had not only accuſed all Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his Family and near <note n="*" place="margin">Sir <hi>Tho. Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coigne,</hi> Mr. <hi>Gaſcoine</hi> his Son, Lady <hi>Tempeſt</hi> his Daughter, Sir <hi>Miles Staple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Charles Ingoldsby</hi> Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, <hi>Nich. Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coigne, Francis Gaſcoigne, Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen Tempeſt</hi> his Nephew, <hi>Ellen Thwing</hi> Niece, <hi>Tho. Thwing</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew, <hi>Tho. Preſſick</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, <hi>James Verley</hi> Servant, <hi>Alice Carpmal</hi> Servant, <hi>Mary Root</hi> Servant, and others, as in their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and at the Tryals affirm'd.</note> Relations, Friends and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, to render him deſtitute of all help, comfort, Witneſſes, and defence; but had now juſt before the Tryal moſt unreaſonably and impudently ſeiz'd upon his Couſin and Counſel Mr. <hi>Charles Ingoldsby,</hi> who was publick even at <hi>York</hi> Aſſizes in Court, and never was touch'd, though <hi>Bolron</hi> came then with Authority to apprehend whom he pleaſed, and was often in Court alſo, where, as well as in other places, <hi>Bolron</hi> might have ſecur'd him.</p>
            <p>That as for <hi>Maybury,</hi> he had been ſuſpected in the Country of the aforeſaid Thefts; that he had long been forbidden Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his Houſe, which could not be imagin'd, had he been a Conſpirator.—That the Liſt of the 500 Perſons, and the improbable Title to it, <hi>viz.—(A Liſt of thoſe that are ingaged to kill the King,)</hi> was ſo extravagant and fooliſh, that 'twas ſufficient of it ſelf to invalidate all his Teſtimony.—That his lying ſtill ſo long after the Proclamations and known Encouragements to all Witneſſes in relation to the Plot, ſhew'd his idle <note n="†" place="margin">The Letter in his Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive being then printed and publiſhed.</note> Letter, and all he had now ſaid to be an invention, and of a late date alſo.—That Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> had above a dozen Proteſtant-witneſſes, who proved moſt important matters in his defence, and had evidently made out the Uſes for which he had return'd the 6000 <hi>l.</hi> to <hi>London;</hi> and that as for <hi>Dolbank,</hi> it might have been bought with the Money and Portions of ſome Nuns, for they are known ſometimes when they have it, to lay out their Money in this manner, that ſo they and their Community may be maintained abroad with an Annual Income, and conſequently have always ſome Relation or other for their Truſtee, who acts as they direct,—Beſides, they conſidered that a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Oath by blaſted Men, without any material Circumſtances proved effectually, or produced, is of little force.—That the very neighbouring Juſtices did not iſſue War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants againſt Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> though <hi>Bolron</hi> had accuſed him of Treaſon.—That <hi>Bolron</hi> had mended and altered his firſt Depoſition moſt corruptly. And laſtly, That to ſwallow this Evidence might be of a moſt pernicious conſequence, and would ſettle ſuch a ſtock of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and Belief on theſe vile Perſons, as might after the deſtruction of the <hi>Gaſcoigne</hi> Family extirpate Root and Branch many others in their Liſt of 1500 in reſerve, whoſe Loyalty to their Prince hath been eminent in the memory of the Living, and was not at all doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of hitherto.</p>
            <p>The Jury declared Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> not Guilty, and accordingly he was acquitted.</p>
            <p>There wanted not ſeveral of different Conceptions, who (on occaſion of the imperfect and defective management of this Tryal, by reaſon of the Priſoners being decay'd, as well in Mind as Body) did ſpeak and vote variouſly of the Succeſs, ſo that ſome of the Jury mov'd at it, did give out Minutes of the Tryal, and the Reaſons which led them to their Verdict, to many of their Acquaintance, and in reality who converſed the Priſoner more intimately did perceive he was become very uncapable and unfit for ſuch a performance, being doſed with Years, his Sence decayed, and his Mind diſuſed and abſtracted of late from Converſation. The Pamphlets of the Age have made him ſince his Tryal a Fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive beyond Seas; but his unſatiable Proſecutors have him in freſh purſuit here on new pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, and have wearied the Attorney General with ſearch and expoſition of the Laws, to bind and faſten him on ſome new Tenter; yet the old Gentleman prays for them and the Nation; his Life is at the Kings Service, and his Soul travelling to his Creator, who hath alſo witneſſed for him, giving him length of days on the Land, a Bleſſing promis'd of old to thoſe who honour and obey their Superiors, as he profeſſes to have done, and hopes it will appear better when ſome of thoſe Perſons come upon their laſt Pillow, where God grant them his Grace and true Repentance.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Magna eſt veritas &amp; praevalebit.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="attestation">
            <pb facs="tcp:103730:9"/>
            <head>An Atteſtation of a certain Intercourſe had between <hi>Robert Bolron,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Thomas Langhorne,</hi> (miſtaken by <hi>Bolron</hi> for Mr. <hi>Ja. Corker)</hi> wherein is manifeſted the Falſhood and Perjury of the ſaid <hi>Bolron.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ON the <hi>22d</hi> of <hi>July</hi> 1679. there came to the Preſs-yard adjacent to <hi>Newgate</hi> two Perſons, the one called himſelf by the Name of <hi>Baker,</hi> and the other called himſelf by the Name of <hi>James. Baker</hi> declared he was the Man who had accuſed Mrs. <hi>Preſwike,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Thwing,</hi> and is now known to be <hi>Bolron.</hi> Theſe Perſons told the Turn-key they came to ſpeak with Mr. <hi>Corker:</hi> Hereupon they were lead into a Drinking-Room, and Mr. <hi>Corker</hi> was called; but he having experienc'd the falſified Oaths of others who had never ſeen him, and happily reflecting theſe might be ſuch, deſired Mr. <hi>Thomas Langhorne</hi> (who was by chance there) to go down and ſee who they were; the which Mr. <hi>Tho. Langhorn</hi> did; and coming into the company of <hi>Bolron,</hi> this diſcourſe followed. Mr. <hi>Langhorn</hi> ſaid, Would you ſpeak with me? <hi>Bolron</hi> anſwered, Your Servant Mr. <hi>Corker.</hi> Mr. <hi>Langhorn</hi> ſaid, Do you know me? <hi>Bolron</hi> anſwered, Yes, I know you well, you will not deny your ſelf to be Mr. <hi>Corker?</hi> Mr. <hi>Langhorn</hi> ſaid, Deny my ſelf? what are you? what is your Name? <hi>Bolron</hi> anſwered, You know my Wife well, and I know you well, and I have known you ſeveral years, and ſeen you in ſuch and ſuch Places, (which Places he named.)</p>
            <p>After ſome time ſpent in diſcourſe to this and the like effect, Mr. <hi>Corker</hi> himſelf, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with an under Clerk of the Preſs-yard, came into their Company; but <hi>Bolron</hi> neither owning nor knowing Mr. <hi>Corker,</hi> the diſcourſe continued, amongſt other things, <hi>(Bolron<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ſtill addreſſing himſelf to Mr. <hi>Langhorn)</hi> affirmed ſeveral times, That he knew him to be Mr. <hi>Corker,</hi> and confirmed it by often calling him Mr. <hi>Corker,</hi> and ſaying to him, I have ſeen, you ſometimes in the company of Mr. <hi>Hubbert,</hi> and ſometimes in the company of Mr. <hi>Pepper,</hi> in the company of Mr. <hi>Haskit,</hi> and ſeveral others; I have ſeen you in <hi>London,</hi> and in the Country in <hi>York-ſhire.</hi> Uſing further expreſſions of a long indeared familiarity with him. At length Mr. <hi>Corker,</hi> wearied with his impertinences, going out of the Room, <hi>Bolron</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired who that Gentleman was? Soon after the Turn-key coming by chance in, with Wine and Tabacco, <hi>Bolron</hi> in the preſence of the ſaid Turn-key, Mr. <hi>Thomas, Langhorne,</hi> and the ſaid under Clerk<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> called Mr. <hi>Langhorne</hi> by the Name of Mr. <hi>Corker,</hi> and ſaid he knew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of him he again posſitive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> he knew him; and added in the preſence of the aforeſaid Witneſſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou to be a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>The under Clerk admiring the impudence of <hi>Bolron,</hi> herein jeſtingly told <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> he pretended ſo much friendſhip and acquaintance with Mr. <hi>Corker,</hi> he would do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> do him a kindneſs in not revealing what he knew; and if you do him a Peny-wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> kindneſs, ſaid the ſaid Clerk, Mr. <hi>Corker</hi> will give you a Pound for it. <hi>Bolron</hi> anſwered, Aye, then ſomething may be done. Mr. <hi>Langhorne,</hi> who all this while was ſuppoſed by the ſaid <hi>Bolron</hi> to be Mr. <hi>Corker,</hi> replyed, I will give nothing by way of Bribe. <hi>Bolron<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> anſwered No, I will take nothing by that Name. This is the ſubſtance of this intercourſe, and will be atteſted to be true, as it is here reſpectively ſet down.</p>
            <p>Now notwithſtanding this ſo often repeated-confident aſſeveration of <hi>Bolrons</hi> intimate acquaintance and familiarity with Mr. <hi>Corker,</hi> ſeconded here by ſo many pretended circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Inſtances of known friendſhip with him; yet it is moſt certain, that he never knew ſaw Mr. <hi>Corker,</hi> till this before mentioned intercourſe at <hi>Newgate:</hi> As is palbably mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> both in that he took Mr. <hi>Langhorne</hi> for M <hi>Corker,</hi> and converſed with him as ſuch in the very preſence of Mr. <hi>Corker.</hi> And alſo in that Mr. <hi>Corker</hi> being brought to <hi>Bolrons</hi> face before the Lords of His Majeſties Privy Council on the <hi>13th</hi> of this preſent <hi>October,</hi> he denied Mr. <hi>Corker</hi> to be the Man who was ſhewn to him at <hi>Newgate.</hi> And after a long and full view had of Mr. <hi>Corker,</hi> he durſt not poſitively affirm, that the Perſon there preſent was he againſt whom he had any thing to ſay; but expreſſing himſelf doubtfully, deſired time of deliberation in it.</p>
            <p>Theſe notorious undeniable Contradictions, will, it is hoped, convince judicious Men, that no credit ought to be given, in a Matter of no leſs than High-Treaſon, to an indigent Wretch, of a loſt Conſcience, and condemned of falſhood by the Teſtimony of his own Mouth.</p>
            <closer>We under-written do reſpectively teſtifie, That what is here ſaid of the Intercourſe had between Mr. <hi>Bolron,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Thomas Langhorne,</hi> is true in the Whole, and every Part thereof: <dateline>Witneſs our Hands <date>the <hi>12th</hi> day of <hi>January</hi> 1679.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Witneſſed in the Preſence of
<list>
                     <item>E. Smith.</item>
                     <item>Jonathan Grove.</item>
                     <item>Francis Leea.</item>
                     <item>Thomas Matchet.</item>
                     <item>Booke Bookey.</item>
                     <item>Tho. Langhorne.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
