<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Experiments and considerations about the porosity of bodies in two essays / by the honourable Robert Boyle ...</title>
            <author>Boyle, Robert, 1627-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 150 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28974</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3966</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17645</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12547275</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12547275</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63097</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A28974)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63097)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 955:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Experiments and considerations about the porosity of bodies in two essays / by the honourable Robert Boyle ...</title>
                  <author>Boyle, Robert, 1627-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 145 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Sam. Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Chemistry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Porosity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anatomy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Physiology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>Jason Colman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>Jason Colman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63097:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63097:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>EXPERIMENTS AND Conſiderations ABOUT THE Poroſity of Bodies, IN TWO ESSAYS.</p>
            <p>By the Honourable ROBERT BOYLE, Fellow of the Royal Society.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Sam. Smith</hi> at the <hi>Prince's Arms</hi> in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard. 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:63097:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63097:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THe Reader is to be adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis'd, not to expect in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Eſſay a Regular, or ſo much as a Coherent, Diſcourſe. For it was intended only as a collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of looſe Experiments and Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons about the Poroſity of the parts of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies belonging as Chymiſts ſpeak) to the Animal Kingdom, and laid (not to ſay thrown (together, in order to what I had thoughts of offering, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards an Intelligible account of Occult Qualities. I am not ignorant, that even one of the moſt ancient and famous of Phyſicians hath ſaid, that a mans body is
<pb facs="tcp:63097:3"/>
(almoſt) every where perſpirable. But I judg'd that a Doctrine of ſuch mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and which diverſe things in the Theory and Practice of after Phyſicians may make one think they either disbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved or diſregarded, did not deſerve to be ſlightly deliver'd, and in general terms, but to be more narrowly conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and likewiſe made out by Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Inſtances, whoſe applyableneſs and uſefulneſs to explain divers obſcure <hi>Phaenomena,</hi> may hereafter appear much greater, then perchance at the firſt ſight they will be thought.</p>
            <p>And the foregoing advertiſement, with a light change, which 'tis preſum'd the Reader may eaſily make of <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, is to be extended to the Eſſay tacked to this <hi>about the Pores of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Bodies,</hi> and ſo may excuſe the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of a diſtinct Preface to it.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63097:3"/>
            <head>An Eſſay of the POROUSNESS OF ANIMAL BODIES.</head>
            <p>AS the moſt numerous part of the Pores of Bodies is too minute to be ſeen, ſo the Contemplation of them has been thought too inconſiderable to be regarded. But when I conſider, how much moſt of the Qualities of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and conſequently their operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons depend upon the ſtructure of their minute, and ſingly inviſible, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, and that to this latent contex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bigneſs the figure and the collocation of the Intervals and Pores
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63097:4"/>
do neceſſarily concur with the Size, Shape and Diſpoſition or contrivance of the ſubſtantial parts I cannot but think the Doctrine of the ſmall Pores of Bodies, of no ſmall importance to Natural Philoſophy. And I ſcarce doubt, but if ſuch little things had not eſcaped the ſight of our Illuſtrious <hi>Verulam,</hi> he would have afforded a good Porology (if I may ſo call it) a place, (and perhaps not the loweſt nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,) among his <hi>Deſiderata.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, <hi>though</hi> other imployments and avocations hinder me from at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting to treat of this ſubject as am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and particularly as it deſerveth, or even as I had deſign'd in a Scheme drawn diverſe years ſince, and ſeen by ſome <hi>Virtuoſi; Yet,</hi> not to leave apart of Phyſicks, that ſeems to me ſo curious and important, altogether as unculti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated as I found it; I ſhall preſent you as many of the Notes I had drawn together about this ſubject, as I can conveniently (for I do not pretend to do it methodically) reduced to three heads: Whereof the firſt, which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63097:4"/>
will challenge to it ſelf this preſent eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, is the <hi>poroſity of Animal Bodies,</hi> about which I ſhall not be ſolicitous to marſhal my obſervations, ſince they all conſpire to ſhew but this one thing; That the parts of Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals, eſpecially whileſt theſe are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, are furniſhed with numerous Pores.</p>
            <p>Thoſe parts of the Bodies of Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals, wherein their poroſity may be beſt ſhewn ſeem to be their Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes or Skins, the Bones, the Fleſh, and Coagmentations of Membranes, Fleſh and Juices. And therefore it would be proper enough to treat of theſe Heads diſtinctly, and give In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of each of them in particular. But yet I think it will be more conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, to ſet down in order the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Fountains, whence the Porouſneſs of the ſubſtances belonging to the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Kingdom (as the Chymiſts ſpeak) may be derived, and to annex to each of theſe the Experiments and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, upon which I argue from it, and which it will be eaſy to refer, if
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63097:5"/>
that be thought fit, to this or that of the parts above mentioned (namely the Membranes, Bones, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) whereto they ſhall (reſpectively) appear the moſt properly to belong.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>THe firſt thing from which I will deduce the Poroſity we have been ſpeaking of, is, the Frame or Conſtitution of the ſtable Parts of the Bodies of Animals. For the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of an Animal being not a rude and indigeſted lump of matter, but a curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous engine, admirably framed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived for the exerciſe of ſeveral Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions as Nutrition, Generation, Senſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and many differing local Motions, it was neceſſary that it ſhould be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with variety of Diſſimilar and Organical parts not only very Skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, but very differingly, contrived congruous to the ſeveral uſes for which they were deſigned, or if you pleaſe, to the ſeveral Functions they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63097:5"/>
were to perform. And, becauſe 'twill be eaſily granted, that the Corpuſcles, that are skilfully brought together for ſuch purpoſes, muſt be ſo contexed as not to touch one another exactly every where, it will readily follow that they muſt leave little Intervals or Pores between them, and that, conſidering the multitude of particles that muſt go to the making up the Body of the Animal, and the great difference and variety in point of bigneſs and figure of the Corpuſcles that are requiſite to contex ſuch differing parts, as Membranes, Fibres Bones, Grizles, Ligaments, Veins, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terys, Nerves, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Both the number and the variety of the Pores cannot but be very great. This argument will be much confirmed, by what there will be occaſion to ſay further to the ſame purpoſe, in the Eſſay touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Poroſity of even Solid Bodies. Wherefore I ſhall now proceed to the Second thing, whence we may derive that of Animal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:63097:6"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>THis is afforded us by conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Nutrition of Animals. For there being continually a great waſte made of their ſubſtance, partly by the excluſion of viſible excrements, and partly by the avolation of inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles ſteam, this great loſs muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily from time to time be repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired by the ſupplies afforded by Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition of which the beſt, if not the only Intelligible, way of giving an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, is, to conceive that the alimental Juice, prepared chiefly in the Stomach is impelled or attracted (for to our preſent purpoſe it matters not which) to the parts of the Body that are to be nouriſhed by it, and the Corpuſcles of the juice inſinuate themſelves at thoſe Pores they find commenſurate to their Bigneſs, and Shape; and thoſe that are muſt congruous, being aſſimilated, add to the ſubſtance of the part wherein
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63097:6"/>
they ſettle, and ſo make amends for the Conſumption of thoſe that were loſt by that part before. This may be illuſtrated by what happens in Plants, and eſpecially Trees, in which, of the various Corpuſcles that are to be found in the liquors, that moiſten the Earth, and are agitated by the heat of the Sun and the Air, thoſe that happen to be commenſurate to the Pores of the Root, are by their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervention impelled into it, or imbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by it, and thence conveyed to the other parts of the Tree in the form of Sap which paſſing through new ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, (whereby its Corpuſcles are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated, and prepared or fitted to be detained in ſeveral parts) receives the alterations requiſite to the being turned into Wood, Bark, Leaves, Bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms, Fruit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But to return to Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals, our argument from their Nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will be much confirmed, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, that in Children and in other young Animals, that have not yet at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained their due Stature and Bulk, the Nutrition is ſo copious as to amount
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63097:7"/>
to a continu'd Augmentation. For, as 'tis evident that Animals grow in all their parts, and each part according to all its Dimenſions, in ſo much that even the cavities of Bones increaſe; ſo we cannot well conceive how this can be done, unleſs the Nutritive liquor be diſtributed through the whole Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the part that is to be nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed and augmented. And to this diſtribution 'tis requiſite that the Body abound with Pores into which the congruous particles of the Juice may be intimatly admitted, &amp; penetrating even into the innermoſt receſſes, may place or lodge themſelves in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that is moſt convenient for the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Increaſe of the part. But the more particular Declaration of this Proceſs I leave to Anatomiſts and Phyſicians.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>HAving premis'd once for all, that in this Eſſay, I often uſe the word Skin in the lax and popular ſenſe of it,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63097:7"/>
without nicely diſtinguiſhing the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermis</hi> or <hi>Cuticula,</hi> called in Engliſh the <hi>Scarf-skin,</hi> from the <hi>Cutis</hi> it inveſts and ſticks cloſely to; I ſhall proceed to another Topic, whence the Porouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Animals may be argued, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the great plenty of matter that is daily carried off by Sweat, and inſenſible Tranſpiration. For, 'tis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that Sweat is diſcharged at the Pores of the skin; and ſince there is no penetration of Dimenſions, we may ſafely conclude, that the matter that is not waſted by Sweat, or by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſenſible way of evacuation, muſt have ſmall Pores or out-lets in the Skin, at which it may iſſue in the form of ſteams; though nothing hinders but that inviſible <hi>Effluvia</hi> alſo may evapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate at the ſame Pores with the Sweat, though for want of plenty or groſſneſs, or a fit diſpoſition in the ambient, thoſe Effluvia be not at the Orifices of thoſe Pores brought into little Drops, ſuch as thoſe of ſweat.</p>
               <p>That therefore the Skins of a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Animals, though they ſeem
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63097:8"/>
cloſe to the eye, may be porous, may (as we have been ſaying) be argued in many of them from their ſweating. But becauſe all of them have not been obſerved to ſweat, as is wont to be particularly affirmed of Dogs, we ſhall add ſome other Inſtances to make it probable.</p>
               <p>We may ſometimes, in the ſmooth skin of a living man, diſcern Pores with good Microſcopes, and, with one that is none of the beſt, we may eaſily on the inſide of gloves, which are made but of skins dreſt, diſcern good ſtore of theſe little out-lets: Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times orderly enough ranged to make the ſight not unpleaſant. And though ſome of them may, I think, be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected to have been made by the Hairs that grew on the skin before 'twas dreſt, yet that greater numbers of them, than can be ſuppoſed to come from thence, are perforations that paſs quite through the Leather, may, not improbably, be ſhewn by the uſual Practice of Chymiſts, to purify Quick-ſilver by tying it up ſtrictly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63097:8"/>
in a piece of kids or ſheeps Leather, and then wringing it hard to force it out; by which means the lower ſurface of the Leather will be covered with a Mercurial Dew or Sweat which will fall down and fly out, as the Pores happen to open this or that way, in a thick ſhower of globules, leaving the droſs behind in the Leather. And tho when a mans skin is tanned it is of a greater thickneſs then one would expect, and that which I employed ſeem'd almoſt as thick as a Buck-skin Glove yet having had the curioſity to try the ſame Experiment with the skin of a mans Arm, I found the Quick-Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver would be ſqueez'd out at the Pores of that alſo. 'Tis not neceſſary that I ſhould here inquire, whether the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle holes, unperceiv'd by the naked Eye, at which the Sweat is diſcharged, and perhaps the matter that the Body looſes by inſenſible tranſpiration gets out, be not, at leaſt moſt of them, the Orifices of ſmall excretory veſſels, belonging to thoſe very numerous glandules which the excellent Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63097:9"/>
                  <hi>Steno and Malpighi</hi> are ſaid to have diſcovered beneath the <hi>Cuticula,</hi> and which for their ſmalneſs and ſhape have been called <hi>Glandulae miliares.</hi> I need not, I ſay, engage in this inquiry, ſince according to this ingenious opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion alſo, the Skin muſt be allow'd a multitude of ſmall Perforations or Pores, and that is ſufficient for my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, from whenceſoever this Poroſity proceeds in a mans Skin. For the next obſervation will ſhew that ſome mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes of Animals may give paſſage to tranſpir'd matter without being perfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by the excretou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Veſſels of Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dules.</p>
               <p>The Membranes or Skins under the ſhells of Hens Eggs, though they be very thin, are of a Contexture very fine and cloſe as may be confirmed by their reſiſting the ſharp Corpuſcles of Vinegar; and yet, that not only theſe Skins, but the ſhells that cover them, are porous, may be inferred from the Experiments I made, of keeping them ſuſpended for a good while, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully counterpoiſed in good ſcales;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63097:9"/>
for by theſe it appeared, that the Eggs did from time to time manifeſtly loſe in weight; which could not reaſonably be imputed but to an inviſible Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, the rather, becauſe uſually in eggs that have been kept long, there will be at one end a cavity which is wont to increaſe with their age, and is made by the ſhrinking of the Membrane from the Shell, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate it ſelf to the diminiſhed quantity of matter, that remains to be involved by it.</p>
               <p>When I conſider the plenty of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that is wont to be diſcharged dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by inſenſible Perſpiration, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Healthful men that exerciſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves moderately, I cannot but think it probable, that the minute Pores, that ſuffice for the carrying off ſo much matter, are very numerous, and are much more ſo than even by the multitude of drops of ſweat, that ſerve to wet the skin, men are wont to imagine. For <hi>Sanctorius</hi> in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent little Tract <hi>de Medicina ſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> affirms, that what is barely car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63097:10"/>
off by inſenſible tranſpiration does ordinarily amount to more, that is, diminiſhes more the weight of a mans Body, than all the viſible ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements (whether groſs or liquid) put together. <hi>Aph. vi.</hi> He adds, If the meat and Drink, taken in one day, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to the weight of eight pound, the inſenſible Tranſpiration ordinarily amounts to five pounds or thereabouts. And elſewhere ſays, that ſometimes in the ſpace of 24 hours, in the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter time, a healthy Body may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hale fifty ounces or more. And ſome Tryals, that I have carefully made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my ſelf, added to ſome others of a very curious as well as great Prince, that made uſe of a like inſtrument, &amp; did me the honour to acquaint me with the events, gave me no cauſe to reject <hi>Sanctorius</hi> obſervations, conſidering the difference in point of heat, between the climate of <hi>Italy,</hi> where he writ, and that of <hi>England,</hi> where ours were made; only I fear, there has been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted an overſight by thoſe many that aſcribe all the decrement of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63097:10"/>
weight, that is not referrable to the groſſer Excrements, to what tranſpires at the Pores of the viſible parts of the skin, without taking notice of that great plenty of ſteams that is in expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations diſcharged through the Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pipe by the Lungs, and appear manifeſt to the Eye it ſelf in froſty weather; though they may be preſumed to be then leſs copious than thoſe Inviſible ones that are emitted in Summer, when the ambient Air is much war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. But <hi>though</hi> I look upon the Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pipe as the great Chimney of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in compariſon of thoſe little Chimneys (if I may ſo call them) in the Skin, at which the matter that is waſted by perſpiration is emitted, <hi>yet</hi> the number of theſe little vents is ſo very great, that the fuliginous Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halations that ſteal out at them, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be very conſiderable. Beſides that, thoſe that are diſcharged at the <hi>Aſpera Arteria,</hi> do probably, at leaſt for the moſt part, iſſue out at the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Pores of the Membranes that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt the Lungs; which membranes
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63097:11"/>
may be lookt upon as external parts of the Body, in reference to the air, tho not in reference to our ſight. But, to return to our Eggs, we may ſafely al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a very great evacuation to be made at the Pores of the skin in man, who is a ſanguineous and hot Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal, ſince we ſee that even Eggs, that are ſtill actually cold, tranſpire. And I elſewhere mention the copious tranſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration even of Frogs, that are always cold to the touch; and the Decrement in weight of ſome Animals, ſoon after they are ſtrangled or ſuffocated, when, their vital Heat being extinct, no more fumes are emitted by expirations at the wind-Pipe: To which ſigns may be added the trivial experiment of holding in warm weather the palp of ones Finger, as near as one can without contact, to ſome cold &amp; ſolid ſmooth body, as to a piece of poliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Steel or Silver; for you will often times ſee this Body preſently ſullyed or overcaſt, with the inviſible ſteams that iſſue out of the Pores of the Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and are by the cold and ſmooth
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63097:11"/>
ſurface of the Body condenſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to viſible ſteams, that do as 'twere cloud that ſurface, but upon the Removal of the Finger, quickly fly off, and leave it bright again.</p>
               <p>The Perviouſneſs of the skin out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards may not improbably be argued from the quickneſs wherewith ſome Medicines take away ſome black and blew Diſcolorations of the skin, that happen upon ſome lighter ſtroke, or other contuſions. For, ſince theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternatural and unſightly colours are wont by Phyſicians to be imputed to ſome ſmall portions of blood, that upon the contuſion is forced out of the capillary veſſels that lye beneath the ſurface of it, &amp; being extravaſated are obliged to ſtagnate there; it ſeems very likely, that if a powerful Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine do quickly remove the diſcolora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that work is performed by attenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating, and diſſolving, and agitating the matter, and diſpoſing it to tranſpire through the cutaneous Pores, though perhaps, when 'tis thus changed, ſome part of it may be imbibed again by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63097:12"/>
the Capillary Veſſels, and ſo by the circulation carryed into the maſs of Blood. Now, that there are Medicines that will ſpeedily work upon ſuch black and blew marks, the Books and Practice of Phyſicians and Chirurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will oblige us to admit. <hi>Helmont</hi> talks much of the great vertue of white Briony root in ſuch caſes. And a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Experiment made a while ago by a Learned acquaintance of mine in an odd caſe, did not give <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont</hi> the Lye. And I know an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Perſon, who having ſome while ſince received a ſtroke, by a kick of an Horſe, on his Leg, a very threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning contuſion, which made the part look black and frightful, he was in a few hours cured of the pain of the hurt, and freed from the black part of the Diſcoloration by the bare ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the chopt leaves of Hiſſop mixt with freſh Butter into the form of a Pulteſs.</p>
               <p>Nor is it only the Skin that covers the viſible parts of the Body that we judg to be thus porous, but in the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63097:12"/>
that inveſt the internal parts, we may reaſonably ſuppoſe both nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous and very various Pores, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the exigency of their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar and different Functions or Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. For, the two firſt cauſes of Poro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity mention'd in this Eſſay, are as well applicable to the Membranes that cover the internal parts, as the Liver, the Spleen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as to the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Skin, or Membrane that covers the Limbs; and in ſome reſpects the tranſpiration through ſuch Pores ſeems more advantaged, than that through the Pores of the ſurface of the Body; ſince the parts that environ the Spleen, Liver, Kidneys, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in man, are hot in compariſon of the ambient Air, and being alſo wet, which the Air is not, the laxity of the Pores of the internal parts is doubly befriended. And perhaps it may be allowable to conceive, both the Skin that covers the Limbs, and the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes that inveſt the internal parts of the Body, to be like worſted ſtock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Waſt-Coats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which in their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63097:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:63097:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:63097:14"/>
ordinary ſtate have a kind of continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity, but upon occaſion can have their Pores every way enlarged and ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in this or that manner, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents that work on them determine them to be. This may be confirmed, by what we manifeſtly ſee in the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſort of leather, as that of Kid or Lamb, and by the latent Pores that may be opened in Sheeps-Leather, and mans Leather, by the preſſure of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded Quick-Silver.</p>
               <p>This Poroſity of a living mans Skin and other Membranes, though inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ones, will the more eaſily be aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to if it appear that ſuch thick and groſs Membranes, as the urinary blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of dead Animals, are Porous and Penetrable even by Water. This we tryed, by putting ſome ſalt of Tartar in a clean well dryed bladder (which ought to be afterwards tyed up cloſe in the neck, leſt the effect ſhould be aſcribed to the moiſt Air) and leaving the lower part of the blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as far as the Salt, reached immer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in common Water, whoſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63097:14"/>
by degrees inſinuated themſelves into the Pores of the bladder, in plenty enough to reſolve the Salt of Tartar into a liquor. And, that it may not be ſaid that the Acrimony of the Salt, by fretting the bladder, made way for the Corpuſcles of the Water, I ſhall add that the Experiment ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, but much more ſlowly, when we tryed it with Sugar inſtead of Salt of Tartar. And there are ſome, who pretend that certain Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rups made this ſlovenly way, which they would have paſs for a ſecret, are very much preferable to thoſe made of common Water.</p>
               <p>That the films that line the ſhells of Eggs are of a very cloſe Contexture ſeems probable, as by other things, ſo by their reſiſting ſome liquors, ſharp enough to corrode the ſhell, and yet that ſuch Membranes are pervious to Liquors that are none of the moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile of all, we found by the enſuing Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment. This was made by taking an ordinary Hens Egg, and keeping it for two or three days in diſtill'd Vinegar,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63097:15"/>
or in ſtrong crude Vinegar. For then taking it out of the Liquor and wiping it well, it was viſibly, and not incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderably, ſwell'd, which I concluded to be from the ingreſs of ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the liquors, at the Pores of the Skins that inveſt the White of the Egg. For we found nothing broken, though we made the Tryal more than once. And to be ſatisfied that the manifeſt expanſion proceeded from ſome other cauſe, than the meer dilata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the White, or Yolk, or both, we compared the weight of the Egg, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it was taken out and well wiped, with that which had been taken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'twas put into the <hi>Menſtruum,</hi> and found the Egg, notwithſtanding the loſs of the Shell, to be conſiderably heavier than 'twas before its immer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>I ſhall add on this occaſion that by a more unlikely way than that newly recited, both the Egg, Shell and Lining of an Egg, may be penetrated. For, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the fine and cloſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texture of the Membranes that inveſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63097:15"/>
the Eggs, the <hi>Chineſes</hi> have a way of Salting them in the ſhell, as I have been aſſured both by Engliſh and Dutch Merchants trading to the Eaſt <hi>Indies.</hi> And in one of the Dutch Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals ſent by the Council of <hi>Batavia</hi> to their Principals in <hi>Holland,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercepted by an Engliſh man of War, I met with divers accounts of great numbers of ſalted Eggs, that were ſuch or ſuch a day of ſuch a Month brought in by Sea to <hi>Batavia</hi> or other Ports. Long after which time, meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with an ingenious Phyſician, that liv'd in <hi>Batavia,</hi> I learned by enquiry from him, that 'tis very true that ſuch Eggs are frequently met with in thoſe parts; he having divers times eaten of them there: ſome that he judged to have been either boyled or roaſted, before they were ſalted; and others that were raw, when they came to be dreſſed for him, but yet retained a Briny taſt. And, though the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants I enquired of could not tell me what way the <hi>Chineſes</hi> employed to Salt their Eggs, without making them
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63097:16"/>
unfit for common uſe, yet by a tryal made with clay and Brine, in which I kept the Eggs for a competent time, I was perſwaded that 'twas poſſible the <hi>Chineſes</hi> ſhould have the Art aſcribed to them. For upon the breaking of an Egg coated with clay, after it had lain for a competent time in Brine, I found its Taſt conſiderably Salt, but was, by I know not what accident, hindered from proſecuting the Experiment, and endeavouring to make it more practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable and uſeful.</p>
               <p>I knew a Phyſitian of more lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning than vertue, who, being tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a violent and obſtinate Colic of a peculiar kind, was wont to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve himſelf by Cliſters of Sack; thô he uſually found that not long after he had taken any of them, they would make him giddy, and fuddle him, as he himſelf confeſſed to me. But upon this Inſtance I lay not much weight, and leſs upon what was anſwered me by a great Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, who having practiſed his Art in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> and being asked
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63097:16"/>
by me whether he had not dreſſed Wounds and Ulcers with the recent juice of Tobacco (a plant I uſe to keep growing in my Garden for its excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent vertues in cuts, burns, and tumors;) and whether, if he employed it, he did not find it emetick, he told me among other things, that having Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times dreſſed with this Juice a ſmall Ulcer in a Womans leg, the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient ſoon after the application would grow ſick, and have her ſtomack tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or actually vomit. But, as I was ſaying, on this inſtance I lay no ſtreſs, becauſe the Corpuſcles of the Tobacco might probably enough get in at the ſmall Orifices of ſome corroded Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and ſo be conveyed inwards, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the help of the Circulation of the blood, than on the account of the Porouſneſs of the Parts. And therefore I ſhall rather mention what has been related to me, by an eminent Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician of the famous Colledge of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> namely, that he had divers times given himſelf a vomit, by a certain application of decocted Tobacco to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63097:17"/>
his wriſts, and ſome other external parts; which brings into my mind, what is affirmed to have been obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in ſome Children that have ſcabb'd Heads, who have been made Drunk, by the application of Clothes or ſpun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges wetted in Infuſion of Tobacco, or of ſtrong Liquors, and applied to the part affected. Though in this caſe the inebriating Particles may be ſuſpected to have got in, not at the meer Pores, but rather at the Orifices of the Capil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary Veſſels, that were made acceſſible by ſuch little ſolutions of Continui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as are ſeldom wanting in ſcabbed Heads.</p>
               <p>That Children may be purged by outward applications is aſſerted by ſome Phyſicians; and an experienced Perſon of that number has affirmed to me, that he can almoſt conſtantly do it by a Plaiſter. But 'tis more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable what was related to me by an eminent <hi>Virtuoſo,</hi> who being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſed to believe ſuch things a while before he told me the ſtory, was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired by a curious Perſon to ſhew him
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63097:17"/>
his Hand which the Relator having done the other took it in his hand, which was moiſtened (as was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards confeſſed) with a kind of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Chymical Oil, but ſo ſlightly, that the Relator ſcarce minded it, till ſome time after when he found himſelf preſt with a motion, like that which a purge would have given him; for the other thereupon ſmiling, my acquaintance began to ſuſpect what the matter might be, and was in a ſhort time purged four times, without griping, or other pain or diſcompoſure. But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the Porouſneſs of Membranes, it may ſerve to make way for your admitting it, to obſerve, that <hi>though</hi> Lute-ſtrings be but Ropes of Fibres (which are at leaſt the chief parts that Membranes conſiſt of) dead, cold and ſtiff, <hi>yet</hi> when the lute is in tune they will ſometimes in wet weather ſwell ſo forcibly as with noiſe and violence to break, which proceeds from the copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ingreſs of moiſt vapors into their Pores, whereby they are not only ſhortened, but as I have tryed in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63097:18"/>
nice ſcales, made manifeſtly heavier.</p>
               <p>The Poroſity of the internal parts of Animals by both the foremention'd ways (<hi>viz.</hi> of emiſſion and reception of Corpuſcles,) may be confirmed by the things that happen in ſome of the <hi>Metaſtaſes</hi> or Tranſlations (as the Phyſitians call them) of the morbifick matter in diſeaſed Bodies. 'Tis known to them that are any thing converſant with Hoſpitals, or the obſervations of Phyſicians, that there do not ſeldom occur in Diſeaſes ſudden Removes of the matter that cauſed them, from one part to another according to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and functions of which, there may emerge a new Diſeaſe, more or leſs dangerous than the former, as the invaded part is more or leſs noble. Thus oftentimes the matter, which in the ſanguiferous Veſſels produced a Feaver, being diſcharged upon ſome internal parts of the Head, produces a <hi>Delirium</hi> or <hi>Phrenitis</hi>; in the latter of which I have ſomewhat wondered, to ſee the Patients Water ſo like that of a Perſon without a Feaver; the ſame
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:63097:18"/>
Febrile matter either by a deviation of Nature, or medicines improper or unskillfully given, is diſcharged ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times upon the <hi>Pleura,</hi> or Membrane that lines the ſides of the Cheſt; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times upon the throat; ſometimes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Guts; and cauſes in the firſt caſe a Pleuriſie, in the 2d a Squinancy, and in the third a Flux, for the moſt part dyſenterical. But, becauſe I ſuppoſe, that many, if not moſt, of theſe tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of peccant humors, are made by the help of the circulation of the Blood, I forbore at the beginning of this Section to ſpeak in <hi>general terms,</hi> when I mentioned them in reference to the Porouſneſs of the internal parts of the Body, and contented my ſelf to intimate, that <hi>ſome</hi> of them may ſerve to confirm that Poroſity.</p>
               <p>This will not perhaps ſeem impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, if we conſider that 'tis in effect already proved, by the ſame argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by which we have ſhewn, that both the Skin and the internal Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes are furniſhed with Pores, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meable by Particles whoſe Shape and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:63097:19"/>
Size are correſpondent to them. For we may thence probably deduce, that when a morbifick matter, whether in the form of Liquor, or of exha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, chances to have Corpuſcles ſuited to the Pores of this or that part of the Body, it may, by a concourſe of Circumſtances, be determined to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade it, and ſo diſlodge from its for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer receptacle, and excite Diſorders in the part it removes to.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>ANother thing whence the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity of Animals may be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is, their taking in of <hi>Effluvia</hi> from without. For theſe cannot get into the internal parts of the Body, to perform their operations there, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out penetrating the Skin, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently entring the Pores of it.</p>
               <p>Now, That things, outwardly apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Body, may without wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Skin, be convey'd to the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal parts, there are many things that argue.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:63097:19"/>And firſt, it has been obſerved in ſome Perſons, (for all are not equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpoſed to admit the action of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Poyſons) that <hi>Cantharides,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing externally apply'd by Chyrurgions or Phyſicians, may ſoon, and before they break the Skin, produce great diſorders in the Urinary Paſſages, and ſometimes cauſe bloody Water. And I remember, that having once had a bliſtering Plaiſter, applyed by a skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Chyrurgion between my ſhoulders, though I knew not that there were any <hi>Cantharides</hi> at all mixt with the other Ingredients, yet it gave me about the neck of my Bladder one of the ſenſibleſt pains I had ever felt, and forced me to ſend for help at a very unſeaſonable time of night.</p>
               <p>The Porouſneſs of the Skin may be alſo argued from divers of the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects even of Milder Plaiſters. For, though ſome Plaiſters may operate as they cloſely ſtick to the Skin, and hinder Perſpiration from within, and fence the part from the external cold; yet, twill ſcarce be denied, that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:63097:20"/>
many of them have notable effects up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on other accounts, whereof none is ſo likely and conſiderable as the copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ingreſs of the Corpuſcles of the Plaiſter, that enter at the Pores of the Skin, and being once got in, act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their reſpective Natures &amp; Vertues. The like may be ſaid of Ointments, whoſe operations, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally on Children (whoſe Skin is ordinarily more ſoft and lax) are ſometimes very notable. And I have known conſiderable things performed by them, in an internal Diſeaſe of grown men, where I ſhould ſcarce have expected a Vegetable Ointment ſhould perform ſo much: I ſay, a Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getable Ointment, for 'tis vulgarly known that by Mercurial Ointments Salivation may be excited; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, againſt the Phyſitians will, the Corpuſcles of the Quick Silver get ſo far into the Body, that he is not able to get them out again.</p>
               <p>What we lately ſaid of Plaiſters, may be applyed to thoſe that Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians call <hi>Pericarpia,</hi> or Wriſt-bands:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63097:20"/>
The better ſort of which, though ſometimes ineffectual, are oftentimes ſucceſsful in ſtopping Fits of Agues, as I have frequently found in a mixture, elſewhere mention'd, of Currans, Hops, Bayſalt well beaten together, by which, by Gods bleſſing, many, and I among others, have been freed from ſimple Tertians, and either double Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians or Quotidians.</p>
               <p>The Argument of the Poroſity of Animals, drawn from thoſe things that get in through their skins, without breaking or wounding them, may be much ſtrengthned, if it can be made appear, that thoſe Phyſitians do not deceive us, who aſcribe ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Operations and Vertues, to things externally applyed, in ſo looſe a way, that they do not ſo much as ſtick to the Skin, or perhaps immediately touch it; ſuch as ſome call <hi>Periapta</hi> and <hi>Appenſa</hi>; divers of which are beſt known among us, by the name of Amulets; ſuch as are the Quills con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Quick-ſilver or Arſenick, that ſome hang about their necks, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:63097:21"/>
wear under their Shirts, againſt the Plague and other Contagious Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes; and the Bloodſtones that others wear againſt Haemorrhages; and the ſtone which the Women uſe in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> for a quite contrary effect, in <hi>Obſtructione Menſium.</hi> That many of theſe external Medicines, anſwer not the promiſes of thoſe that extol them, having ſome of them no ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible operation at all, and others no conſiderable one, experience has aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured judicious obſervers; but that ſome of them, eſpecially on ſome Patients, may have conſiderable, not to ſay admirable, operations, I confeſs my ſelf by other motives, as well as Authority, to be perſwaded. Hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing been one ſummer frequently ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to bleed at the Noſe, and reduced to imploy ſeveral remedies to check that diſtemper; that which I found the moſt effectual to ſtanch the blood, was ſome moſs of a dead mans Scull (ſent for a preſent out of <hi>Ireland</hi> where 'tis far leſs rare than in moſt other Countrys) though it did but
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:63097:21"/>
touch my skin till the herb was a little warm'd by it. And though I remember not that I have known any great matter done to ſtop Haemorrha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies by the bare outward application of other Blood-ſtones; yet of one that look'd almoſt like an Agate, I admired the effects, eſpecially upon a young and extraordinarily Sanguin perſon. To which I ſhall add a memorable thing,<note rend="inter">If one would ſee this paſſage at large he may find it at the end of the Eſſay.</note> communicated to the experienced <hi>Zwelfer</hi> by the chief Phyſitian of the States of <hi>Moravia.</hi> For this learned man whom he extols for a great Phyſician and Philoſopher; aſſures him, that having prepared ſome Trochiſchs of Toads according to <hi>Helmonts</hi> way, (which I remember I alſo was ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous to prepare, but had not occaſion to make tryal of their vertue,) he not only found, that being worn as Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets they preſerved him and all his Domeſticks, and Friends, from the Plague (though he daily viſited the infected) but that having cauſed theſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63097:22"/>
Trochiſchs to be put upon the Plague ſores of ſeveral perſons, none of them died, but the venom of the peſtilential Carbuncles was thereby ſo weakened that the ulcers were afterward eaſily cured by vulgar remedies.</p>
               <p>And now, as to the difficulty, which I acknowledge not to be ſmall, to conceive how Bodies actually cold can emit <hi>Effluvia,</hi> capable of pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trating (without moiſtening it) a Membrane of ſo cloſe a Contexture as a mans Skin; I ſuppoſe it will be much leſſened in the objectors opinion, by what he will meet with hereafter about the Pores of Bodies, and the Figures of Corpuſcles. For ſuppoſing theſe to be congruous, it will not ſeem incredible, that the <hi>Effluvia</hi> of Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets ſhould in tract of time get paſſage through the Pores of the Skin of a Living Body. And to make this the more probable, I will give an Inſtance in the Skin of a dead <hi>Animal.</hi> And, becauſe this requires a Liquor I much employ in theſe trials about Porology, though I have many years ſince in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:63097:22"/>
another Tract taught how to make it for another purpoſe; yet I ſhall here repeat, that 'tis made by exactly ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Flower of Brimſtone, powdered <hi>Sal Armoniac</hi> and good Quicklime in equal quantities, ſave that, if the Quicklime be not very dry and good, a fourth or fifth part muſt be ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>added, for theſe being nimbly mixed, and diſtilled by degrees of Fire in a Retort, till the Sand be at length brought to be almoſt red hot, there will come over a ſmoaking Spirit, which muſt be kept very carefully ſtopt, and which for diſtinctions ſake, I alſo uſe to call, The <hi>Permeating Menſtruum or Liquor,</hi> and its expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations the Penetrant, or Permeating Fumes.</p>
               <p>And now you will eaſily under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the experiment I was about to mention, which was this; We took a very clean piece of poliſh'd Copper, in want of which one of ſilver will ſerve the turn, and having lapt it up in a piece of either Lambs or ſheeps Leather, ſo that it was every way
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:63097:23"/>
incloſed, we then held it over the Orifice of the Vial that contained the Spirit, at a pretty diſtance from the Liquor, whoſe fumes nevertheleſs did quickly, (perhaps in a minute of an hour or leſs) pervade the Pores of the Leather, and operate upon the inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded metal as appeared by the deep and laſting tincture it had given to the lower ſurface of it, though the interpoſed Leather it ſelf was not deprived of its whiteneſs, nor at all ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly diſcoloured; however it ſmelt of the Sulplureous ſteams that had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded it. And, if I miſremember not, the ſame Experiment ſucceeded, though ſomewhat more ſlowly, when a double Leather was interpoſed between the fumes and a new piece of Copper coin. This will be thought the leſs ſtrange, when I ſhall come to ſome other Inſtances of the Penetrancy of theſe Spirits. In the mean while I leave it to be conſidered, whether this may not ſuggeſt ſome conjecture at that ſtrange <hi>Phoenomenon,</hi> which is recorded by Authors of good repute,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:63097:23"/>
That ſometimes in great Thunders the Lightening, among other opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, has been found to have mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly diſcoloured mens money, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out burning the Purſes or Pockets wherein it lay. For in our experiment, the ſteams that in a trice pervaded the Leather, the moſt uſual matter where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Purſes are made, were ſulphureous, as the ſmell argues, that thoſe which accompany the <hi>Fulmen</hi> are wont to be; and whereas theſe, when they invade Bodies, are uſually very hot, ours operated when the Liquor that emitted them was actually cold. And if it be ſaid, that ſometimes their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney has been found diſcolored in their Pockets, who were not ſtruck, by the <hi>Fulmen,</hi> but had it only paſs near them, it may be objected, that tho the intire Body, whether fluid or ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid, if there be any of this latter kind that is in Latine called <hi>Fulmen</hi> (for our Engliſh word, <hi>Thunderbolt</hi> ſeems not ſo applicable to a fluid) did not touch them, yet it might ſcatter ſteams enough round about it, to cauſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:63097:24"/>
the <hi>Phoenomenon.</hi> For confirmation of which I ſhall take notice, that a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Perſon of my acquaintance, having had the Curioſity to aſcend a burning mountain in <hi>America,</hi> till the ſulphureous ſteams grew too offenſive to him, he told me that, among other operations he obſerved them to have upon him, one was, that he found the money he had about him turned of a black and dirty colour, ſuch as I have obſerved our ſulphureous ſteams of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten give both to Copper, and to Silver Coins. But whether or no our Spirits will juſtify the conjecture, they invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me to mention, at leaſt their ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily pervading the Skin of a dead Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal may make it probable, that the Skin of a Living man may be eaſily pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrated by external ſteams whoſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the Eye does not perceive, and whoſe operations, though not inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, may therefore be unſuſpected. I leave to Phyſitians to conſider, what uſe may be made of this obſervation, in reference to the propagation of contagious Diſeaſes, by the contact of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:63097:24"/>
infected Air, diſtinct from the Reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of it, and by the penetration of the ſteams, that iſſuing from divers Bodies invade the Skin, and may perhaps be capable of operations, either hurtful or friendly, that are not uſually ſuſpected to proceed from ſuch cauſes, and are therefore miſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to others. And on this occaſion it will not be impertinent to add, that by hanging up ſheeps Leather or Lambs Leather in the free Air, the vapors of it would ſo inſinuate themſelves into the Pores in wet weather, that a moderate degree of moiſture in the Air would add to it a not inconſiderable weight, of which dry weather, whether hot or cold, would deprive it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>I Muſt not in this place omit ſome Inſtances, very proper to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the Penetrableneſs of Membranes to Fumes themſelves, if they be ſubtile
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:63097:25"/>
enough for their Pores, or correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent enough to them.</p>
               <p>Among the obſervations publiſhed by Phyſicians I have met with ſome by which it appears that <hi>Cantharides</hi> may have great Effects upon the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Parts of the Body, though they do not ſo much as touch the Skin, but are placed at ſome diſtance from it,<note rend="inter">Schenkii Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervationum Lib. <hi>7.</hi> Obſ. <hi>37.</hi>
                  </note> ſo that their <hi>Effluvia</hi> muſt be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmitted through other Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies before they can pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate that. The learned <hi>Michael Paſchalius</hi> menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons a Chyrurgion, who was twice brought to void much Blood with his Urine, by ſome Spaniſh Flies that he carryed about in a Purſe or Bag. And another Doctor of note relates of another perſon that came to complain to him, that he piſſed Blood, having carryed about with him <hi>Cantharides,</hi> though in his Pocket, and adds, that a like Caſe was recounted to him by <hi>Helidaeus,</hi> whom he calls an eminent <hi>Bolognian</hi> Phyſician.</p>
               <p>We ſee, that in Linnen Cloth, the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:63097:25"/>
finer and more ſlender the threads are the cloſer and leſs Porous, <hi>coeteris paribus,</hi> the Linnen is: By analogy to which one may eſteem the thin film that lines the ſhell of an Egg, to be of an exceeding cloſe Contexture; and yet that even this film is not imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to ſome Fumes, I have found by the following Tryal.</p>
               <p>To make this, we ſlowly and warily pick'd off a ſufficient part of the Shell of a Hens Egg, from the Skin that lay juſt beneath it, and is wont to ſtick ſo cloſe to it, that their ſeparation, without injuring the Membrane, is not eaſy. In this Skin, being wip'd, we wrapt up a flat piece of Copper, whoſe ſurface was made bright, that the change of Colour might be the better ſeen; and having kept this covered bit of Plate, over the Fumes of our ſmoaking Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor lately mentioned for a minute or two by our gheſs we unfolded the Skin, and found, as we expected, that the lower ſurface of the Copper which was it that had been held over the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:63097:26"/>
Fumes, was turned of a very dark co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, which manifeſted that even ſo fine and cloſely contexed a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane was not only, as we have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſhewn, penetrable by Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors, but readily pervious to our ſulphureous exhalations, tho theſe were probably but faintly emitted, ſince the Liquor they came from was then actually cold. But in making the Tryal it is fit to hold (as we did in that newly recited) the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane againſt the light, to ſee if it be intire, and have eſcaped all thoſe little lacerations that are hardly avoidable in ſevering it from the Shell it ſticks ſo cloſe to. If this caution be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, 'tis eaſy to be impoſed on, by overlooking ſome little holes, that are not eaſily diſcerned when one looks down upon the Skin, and yet may be ſufficient to make the Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment deceitful. But, thô when 'tis well made, it is a notable confirmation of the Doctrine endeavoured to be eſtabliſhed in this Paper, yet I ſhall now ſubjoyn a more conſiderable
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:63097:26"/>
Inſtance to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
               <p>The Porouſneſs of the Internal Membranes of the Body, will be more eaſily granted, if it be conſidered that either the Liquors, or the moiſt Exhalations, whoſe Action is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted by the Natural Heat of the Parts, keeps them conſtantly wet or moiſt, and thereby renders them more lax, and more penetrable by ſubtle Spirits or other Corpuſcles. In favour of this Reflection I made the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Experiment. We took a piece of a dryed Urinary Bladder, which was judged to have been a Calfs; and having lapt it about a new piece of Silver Coin, ſo that the Bladder was ſingle where it covered the lower ſide of the Piece, we kept it for divers Minutes, by gueſs, over the Spirituous Fumes of our often mentioned Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meating Liquor, but could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that the Coin was thereby at all affected or terniſhed. Whence we concluded that the Pores of the dry Bladder were too cloſe and narrow<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to give paſſage to the Expirations of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:63097:27"/>
the <hi>Menſtruum.</hi> But preſuming that moiſture would ſome what relax them with another piece of the ſame Bladder, made limber by being a little wetted in common Water, we lapt up another like peace of new Coin, as we had done the former, and kept it at the ſame diſtance as before, from the Liquor, but not for ſo long a time. For after about two Minutes, by gueſs, we remov'd and took out the Piece, and, as we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, found much of its lower ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face (that regarded the Liquor) deeply diſcoloured. Which Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will not only juſtify what I lately ſaid, of the greater Laxity of moiſt than of dry Membranes, but will be thought no mean confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of what is in this Eſſay delivered about the Poroſity of Membranes, ſince the Urinary Bladder does, as Anatomiſts well know, conſiſt of more than one Membrane, though they ſtick ſo cloſe together, as to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear but one to the Eye. And this Bladder was ſpeedily penetrated by
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:63097:27"/>
the Fumes that our Liquor emitted in exceeding Cold and Froſty weather, though the Bladder it ſelf was not in the warm Body of the live Animal, but had been ſo long kept dryed and cold, that probably the Moiſture it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced in ſcarce one minute of an Hour, could not reſtore it to the Laxity it had, whilſt it was a part of the living Calf.</p>
               <p>One of the notableſt Inſtances I ever met with, of the Poroſity of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Membranes of the Humane Body, was afforded me by that <hi>Britiſh</hi> Nobleman, of whom our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Harvey</hi> tells a memorable, not to ſay matchleſs, ſtory. This Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, having in his youth, by an accident which that Doctor relates, had a great and laſting Perforation made in his <hi>Thorax,</hi> at which the motion of his Heart could be directly perceiv'd did not only out live the accident, but grew a ſtrong, and ſomewhat corpulent man; and ſo robuſt, as well as Gallant, that he afterwards was a Souldier, and had
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:63097:28"/>
the honour to command a Body of an Army for the King. This Earl of <hi>Mount-Alexander</hi> (for that was his laſt Title having mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed one of my neareſt kinſwomen, and having been told that I was very deſirous to ſee, what I had heard ſuch ſtrange things of, very obliging<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly came, at a fit time, to give me that ſatisfaction. In order to which he removed that which covered the wide Orifice of his Hurt, and gave me the opportunity of looking into his <hi>Thorax,</hi> and of diſcerning there the motions of the Cone, as they call it, or <hi>Mucro</hi> of the Heart. But theſe things I mention but upon the by, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the ſtrangeneſs of the fact; the thing I principally intended relates to my preſent argument. Having then made ſeveral inquiries fit for my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, his Lordſhip told me, that when he did, as he was wont to do from time to time, (though not every day) inject with a Syringe ſome actually warm medicated Liquor into his <hi>Thorax,</hi> to cleanſe and cheriſh the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:63097:28"/>
Parts, he ſhould quickly and plainly find in his Mouth the taſt and ſmell of the Drugs, wherewith the Liquor had been impregnated. And I further learned, that, whereas he conſtantly wore upon the uncloſed part of his Cheſt, a Silken Quilt, ſtuffed with Aromatick and odorife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Powders, to defend the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Parts and keep them warm; when he came, as he uſed to do after ſome weeks, to imploy a new Quilt, the fragrant <hi>Effluvia</hi> of it would min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle with his breath in exſpiration, and very ſenſibly perfume it, not, as I declared I ſuſpected, upon the ſcore of the pleaſing Exhalations that might get up between his Clothes and his Body, but that got into the Organs of Reſpiration, and came out with his Breath at his Mouth, as was confirmed to me by a grave &amp; judicious Stateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that happened to be then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and knew this General very well. Other circumſtances I might add, but that I dare not truſt my memory for them, and unhappily loſt the Paper,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:63097:29"/>
wherein the oddneſs of the things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited me to ſet them down, for fear of forgetting them.</p>
               <p>That part of this Narrative which relates to Injections may be much confirm'd by what is delivered by <hi>Galen</hi> himſelf, who ſays that <hi>Mulſum</hi> or <hi>Honeyed Water,</hi> being injected at the Orifice of Wounds penetrating into the cavity of the <hi>Thorax,</hi> has been obſerved to be in part received into the Lungs, and diſcharged out of the <hi>Aſpera Arteria</hi> by coughing. And this he mentions as a known thing, imploying it as a <hi>Medium</hi> whereby to prove another.</p>
               <p>The mention that has been made of the Poroſity of Membranes, brings into my mind what I once obſerved at the Diſſection, made by ſome Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, and Anatomiſts, of a luſty Souldier, that was hanged for I know not what crime. This man, though otherwiſe young and ſound, was obſerved to have been long moleſted with what they call a <hi>ſhort, dry Cough,</hi> which made us expect to find ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:63097:29"/>
much amiſs in his Lungs. But meeting with nothing there, we were at a loſs for the cauſe of this Cough, till coming to conſider the internal part of the Cheſt, we perceived ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing on one of the ſides, by tracing of which we diſcovered, that between the <hi>Pleura</hi> and the ſubſtance of the intercoſtal muſcles, there was lodged a certain matter, of the breadth of a Silver Crown piece, or thereabouts, of a roundiſh figure, and of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence and almoſt colour of new, ſoft Cheeſe, which odd ſtuff was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded to have been the remains of ſome ill cured Pleuriſy, and to have tranſmitted through the Pores of the <hi>Pleura,</hi> though that be a very cloſe Membrane, ſome noxious <hi>Effluvia,</hi> which ever and anon irrita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Lungs into an irregular and troubleſom motion, and ſo produced the Cough the Malefactor had been moleſted with.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:63097:30"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>I Am well aware that 'tis far leſs difficult, to prove the permeable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſingle Membranes, than that of ſuch a Part of the Body, as ſeems to be an aggregate of ſeveral parts, which in regard of their cloſe adheſion, are looked upon but as one part, to which, on that account, men common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give a diſtinct name. But yet there are ſome <hi>Phaenomena</hi> that ſeem to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, that even ſuch compounded or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting parts if I may ſo call them, are not deſtitute of Pores, which whether they be not ſome of them the Orifices of exceeding ſlender and therefore unobſerved Capillary Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, I muſt not now ſtay to enquire.</p>
               <p>When the cavity of the <hi>Abdomen</hi> in thoſe Hydropical Perſons that are troubled with an <hi>Aſcites,</hi> is filled with Water, or rather with a Liquor that I have found to be much more viſcous, it juſtly appears ſtrange, that by an
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:63097:30"/>
Hydragogue, or ſome appropriated purging medicine, great quantities of this groſs Liquor ſhould in a ſhort time be carryed off by Siege, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps alſo by Urine, though to get into the cavity of the Guts, or that of either of the Kidneys, it ſeems neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that it Permeate the Tunicles, and other component parts, of the <hi>Viſcera</hi> it gets into.</p>
               <p>I know not whether I may on this occaſion take notice of what Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans obſerve to occur now and then in <hi>Empyema's</hi> that follow ill condition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Pleuriſies.</hi> For it has ſeveral times been obſerved, that upon the burſting of ſuch impoſthumes into the cavity of the Cheſt, the Purulent matter hath been voided by Siege and Urine. I he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitate, as I was ſaying, whether I ſhould alledge this <hi>Phaenomenon,</hi> as a proof of what I now contend for, till it be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined whether this <hi>Metaſtaſis</hi> be made by <hi>tranſudation</hi> properly ſo called, or by the ingreſs of the <hi>Pus</hi> into the imperfectly cloſed Orifices of the Veſſels of the Lungs;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:63097:31"/>
where being once admitted and min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with the Blood they may with this circulating Liquor arrive at the Kidneys, or any other Parts fitted to make a ſecretion of this Heterogeneous matter.</p>
               <p>But whatever be the Reaſon or manner of it, we find that the Lungs do ſometimes odly convey things to diſtant parts of the Body. And if I may here mention a thing, <hi>cui honos praefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis eſt,</hi> I ſhall add that I have ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times obſerv'd in my ſelf, that when I had been an actor or an aſſiſtant in the Diſſection of a living Dog, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if his Blood or Body were rankly Scented, I ſhould divers hours after plainly find that odour in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements I voided by Siege.</p>
               <p>A famous Chirurgeon and Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt relates, that one who was very ill of a dropſy, judged to ariſe from a <hi>Scirrhus</hi> of the Spleen, coming to ask his counſel and aſſiſtance, though he judged the patients caſe deſperate, yet to content him, he ordered him to dip a very large Sponge in good Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime-Water,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:63097:31"/>
and having ſqueezed out the ſuperfluous Liquor, to bind it upon the region of the Spleen, only ſhifting it from time to time. He adds, that after ſome months he was much ſurprized to receive a viſit from this Patient, with ſolemn thanks for his recovery; the outward Medicine having, it ſeems, reſolved the <hi>Scirrhus</hi> and concurred with nature to evacuate the hydropical humour. For the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of which hard tumour it ſeems neceſſary, that the ſanative Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſcles of the external remedy ſhould at length penetrate, not only the <hi>Epidermis,</hi> and the true <hi>Cutis,</hi> but the Muſcles themſelves of the <hi>Abdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and ſome other interpoſed parts.</p>
               <p>Theſe inſtances may be ſtrengthen'd by an eminent obſervation of <hi>Galen,</hi> who takes notice that Bones being ſometimes broken, without piercing the Skin that covers the part they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to, when the <hi>Callus</hi> is making, and the broken parts of the Bone begin to be conglutinated together, a Portion
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:63097:32"/>
of that Blood which had flowed to the part affected is carryed to the Skin and permeats that, ſo as to wet and foul the Dreſſings or Bandages that are kept upon the limb affected by the Fracture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BOnes, Horns,</hi> and parts of the like Subſtance, being thoſe that are granted to be the moſt ſolid of the Bodies of Animals, I come in the laſt place to ſhew by particular Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that theſe alſo have their <hi>Pores.</hi> I ſay, by particular Experiments, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in a general way, their <hi>Poroſity</hi> has been already proved, by the ſame Arguments, from their original Tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Nutrition, Augmentation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That have been employed to manifeſt the <hi>Porouſneſs of Animal ſubſtances in general.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the Nails of men, as well as their <hi>Skins,</hi> are Porous, may be gathered from their being eaſily and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:63097:32"/>
permanently tinged with divers me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talline ſolutions, and particularly with thoſe of ſilver in <hi>Aquafortis,</hi> and Gold in <hi>Aqua Regia</hi>; the former of which ſolutions though cold, will but too eaſily tinge the Skin and Nails it chances to touch, and makes ſome little ſtay upon, with a dark and blackiſh colour; which I found not that I could waſh out with water, or, even with a far more penetrating and abſterſive liquor. The like durableneſs I found in the Purple ſpots, that I ſometimes purpoſely made on my Nails, by letting ſome little drops of the ſolution of Gold in <hi>Aqua Regia</hi> dry upon them, which I now and then did, to obſerve the way of the Nails growth. For if the ſtain were made near the root of the nail, it would be ſtill, though very ſlowly, thruſt on by the new matter, till after ſome weeks it arrived to the further end of the Nail, and was fit to be pared off with it. But this only upon the by. 'Tis more to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to take notice, that, though the <hi>Menſtruums</hi> imployed in the recited
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:63097:33"/>
Experiments be of themſelves very acid and corroſive, yet they are ſo changed by the metals they have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, that they are Acid no more, the ſolution of Silver being rather ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly bitter, and that of Gold of a kind of <hi>Stiptic</hi> taſt, almoſt like that which ſloes, growing in the hedges, are wont to be of.</p>
               <p>Ivory is a thing too well known to need to be deſcribed. And, ſince 'tis generally lookt upon (for I have had no opportunity to compare it with the Bones) as the ſolideſt part of the vaſteſt of Tereſtrial Animals, Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments proving its poroſity, will be ſtrong preſumptions for that of the hardeſt parts of other Animals. And the Porouſneſs of Ivory may be argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the ſeveral ways of dying it with permanent colours. For in theſe colorations the Tinctures that make them, muſt penetrate into, and be lodged in the Subſtance of the Ivory, eſpecially when the Subſtance remains ſmooth and glaſſy, as I have divers times made it do, when I employed
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:63097:33"/>
fit <hi>Menſtruums</hi> and Metalline Pigments. The ſolution I formerly mentioned of Silver in <hi>Aqua fortis,</hi> being laid upon Ivory, will ſoon give it a dark and blackiſh ſtain, which is not, that I have found, to be waſhed off. I remember alſo that I many years ſince taught ſome ingenious artificers, to adorn Ivory with a fine purple colour, by moiſtening it with, and ſuffering lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurely to dry on it, a ſolution of Gold made in <hi>Aqua Regia.</hi> And if occaſion required, allayed with water, nor needs either of theſe ſolutions be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed hot, any more than the Ivory needs to be heated. Both which cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances favour the Porouſneſs of the ſolid Body.</p>
               <p>Copper diſſolved in <hi>Aqua fortis</hi> ſtains Ivory with a blewiſh colour, as I have ſometimes ſeen in the hafts of knifes, about whoſe coloration never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs another way is alſo employed. But I remember that without making uſe of any Acid or Corroſive <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruum,</hi> I have even in the cold ſtained Ivory, with a fine and permanent
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:63097:34"/>
blew, like a Turquois, by ſuffering to dry upon it as deep a ſolution as I could make of Crude Copper, in an urinous Spirit, as that of <hi>Sal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniack.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now to return to Bones, their growth in all their dimenſions, does, as I lately noted, argue their Poroſity and the marrow that is found in the great hollow Bones, whether it nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh them or no, muſt it ſelf be ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſome alimental juice, that ſoaks or otherways penetrates, into the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities that contain it.</p>
               <p>Nor does it ſeem at all improbable, that Blood it ſelf may through ſmall Veſſels be conveyed into the very ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Bone, ſo as that the Veſſels reach at leaſt a little way in it, though perhaps the Liquor they carry may afterwards by Imbibition be brought to the more internal parts of the Bone. For not to urge that we manifeſtly ſee, that on each ſide of the lower Jaw, Nature has been careful to perforate the Bones and make a Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel in the ſubſtance of it; which Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:63097:34"/>
receives not only a larger Nerve but a Vein, &amp; Artery to bring in &amp; carry back Blood for the nouriſhment of the Teeth, by diſtinct Sprigs ſent from the great branch to the particular Teeth. Not to urge this, I ſay, (which I mention but to ſhew that the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion lately propoſed is agreeable to a known practice of Nature) I have been aſſured by eminent Anatomiſts, whom I purpoſely conſulted, that they have obſerved Blood-veſſels to enter a great way into the ſubſtance of the larger Bones. And one of them affirmed, that he had traced a Veſſel even to the great Cavity of the Bone. Which I the leſs ſcrupled to admit, becauſe it has been obſerved, that in younger Animals the Cavity is in great part furniſhed with Blood<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as well as Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and in thoſe larger Pores, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of many are found in the more Spongy Subſtance of divers Bones, Blood has been obſerved to have been lodged, as alſo in the ſpongy part of the Skull, that lies between the two Tables, as I have been aſſured by Skilful Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:63097:35"/>The blackneſs alſo, that Bones ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire when put into a competent heat, and a peculiar kind of fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which they may by heat be made to afford, ſhew that they harbour, even in their internal parts, ſtore of Unctuous Particles, ſeparable from the ſolid ſubſtance, (which ſtill retains its ſhape and continues ſolid) in whoſe Pores they may thereby be argued to have been lodged. The Lightneſs of Bones, even when their Cavity is acceſſible to (Air and) Water, is alſo a great ſign of their Poroſity. And ſo is their being cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roded by tinging liquors, if they be penetrative and well applyed. I know not whether I ſhould add on this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, that having taken calcined and pulverized Bones, ſuch as we uſe to make our Cupels of, and, after having given them a good heat, kept them for ſome time in the Air, but in a well covered place; I found the imbibed moiſture of the Air to have manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly increaſed their weight; and that I alſo obſerved in a curious <hi>Skeleton,</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:63097:35"/>
where the Bones were kept together by wires, inſtead of other Ligaments, that though I kept it in a well cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed place, not far from a Kitchin Fire, yet in very moiſt weather the Bones ſeemed to ſwell, ſince thoſe joynts that were eaſy to be bent, in dry weather, and that after ſeveral man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, would grow ſtiff and refractory, and indiſpoſed to be put into ſuch motions, when the weather was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderably wet. Theſe particulars (as I was ſaying) I am ſomewhat doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful whether I ſhould here inſert, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe one may ſuſpect the <hi>Phaeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena</hi> may proceed rather from ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what elſe, than the imbibed moiſture of the Air; and yet I would not omitt to mention theſe obſervations, becauſe I do not yet ſee any cauſe to which they may more probably (or indeed ſo probably) be aſſigned.</p>
               <p>And on this occaſion I ſhall ſubjoyn ſome obſervations made on large and ſolid Ox Bones, which in one of my Note Books I find thus regiſtred. <hi>Nov.</hi> 15. We weighed two [entire or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broken]
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:63097:36"/>
Marrow Bones, and found the one to weigh ℥xxix + <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ſs, and the other ℥xxiv + <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>iv + 30 gr. <hi>Nov.</hi> 24. The former weighed ℥xxix + <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>vi, and the latter ℥xxv + <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>i + 30 gr. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 28. the former weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ℥xxix + <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>iij. 55 gr. and the latter ℥xxiv + <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>vii. + 39 gr. <hi>June</hi> 7th of the following year, the former weigh'd ℥xxix + <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ii. And the latter ℥xxiv + <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>vii. By which obſervations purpoſely made at differing times of the year, and in very good ſcales, it ſeems that Bones do plentifully enough imbibe the Exhalations of the Air, and emit them again, together with ſome of their own, according as the ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent happens to be diſpoſed. And theſe alterations argue the Bones to abound with Pores, ſince the external ſteams muſt have Pores to receive them, and the <hi>Effluvia</hi> muſt upon their receſs leave Pores behind them.</p>
               <p>I confeſs that to think (as with ſome Anatomiſts I lately ſeemed to do) that Bones themſelves admit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their ſubſtance, Veſſels capable of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:63097:36"/>
conveying a nutritive Liquor, we muſt ſuppoſe thoſe Veſſels extreamly ſlender. But that 'tis not only poſſible but ſomewhat credible, there may be ſuch, I am induced to think, by what is known to happen in that diſeaſe, which from the Country it moſt infeſts is called the <hi>Plica Polonica.</hi> For, tho one would think that the hairs of men are much too ſlender, to have cavities in them capable of viſible Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors; and though I have found it very difficult, even with a good Microſcope, to perceive any cavities in the hair of a man tranſverſly cut; yet not only ſome other writers of good note, but the Judicious <hi>Sennertus</hi> himſelf deliver, that in this diſeaſe (of which he par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly treats) it has been obſerved, that if the Patients cauſe their intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled hair to be cut, as they ſometimes do, by reaſon of its naſtineſs or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſightlineſs, they are not only thereby endangered, but ſometimes the ſingle hairs will actually bleed, where the ends have been cut off; ſo that ſo thick a Liquor as Blood may be conveyed
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:63097:37"/>
through Veſſels, that can at moſt be but in a proper ſenſe <hi>Capillary</hi> and muſt be far leſs than hairs, if their Perfora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be like thoſe by which many Plants have their nouriſhment con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to them, or ſuch as are obvious in divers Canes, which being cut quite through transverſly, diſcover a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of diſtinct Pores, that by ſome Experiments one may be induced to gueſs, reach all along, and make the Cane like a Cylindrical Bundle of Minute Pipes; or rather a multitude of ſmall cavities, that perforate from end to end the <hi>Parenchyma,</hi> or Subſtance analogous to it, that gives them ſtabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. And for the preſent this ſort of Veſſels ſeem to me, the more likely to be thoſe that convey the Blood to the extream Parts of the Hair, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe even in Horſe hairs, which yet are nouriſhed and grow, I am not yet ſure, that I have diſcovered with my Microſcopes any cavity, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuſpect there may be divers im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perceptible ones, for the Hair is nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed and grows, which it is not like
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:63097:37"/>
it ſhould do if the Body were ſolid; and if there were but a ſingle cavity in it, as in the lower part of a Quill, 'tis like the Microſcope I uſed would have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered it, ſince with one much infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour I could eaſily ſee, that ſeveral little ſhort Hairs, that grow upon the Animal that yields Musk, had each of them a cavity in it like that of the lower part of a Quill.</p>
               <p>To the things that have already been ſaid about the Poroſity of Bones, I ſhall now add an obſervation of a very learned Phyſician, that is very remarkable to our preſent purpoſe, becauſe it argues, that even Bodies not ſaline, nor actually moiſt, may from without get into the Pores and Cavities of Humane Bones. Divers Phyſicians have complain'd of the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs done to the Bones by Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, employ'd to ſalivate in Venereal Diſeaſes. Whereof I remember I have read a very notable Inſtance, in a learned Book (which I have not now by me) of an eminent Roman Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of Phyſick, who had the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:63097:38"/>
of making ſeveral curious ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations in the famous Hoſpital of the <hi>Incurabili</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi>; and is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the more to be credited; where he relates, that in the Cavity of at leaſt one Pocky-mans Bones, there was found real Quick-Silver that had pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrated thither. And this brings into my mind a memorable obſervation of an ancient and experienced Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, who being famous for the cure of Venereal Diſeaſes, was asked by me, what Inſtances he had found of the Penetration of Quick-Silver, either outwardly or inwardly adminiſtred, into the Bones of men? To this he anſwered, that he could not ſay he had himſelf taken notice of any Quick-Silver, in the Cavities of greater Bones, but that ſome other Practition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers had told him, that they had met with ſuch Inſtances, as I enquired after. But for himſelf, he only remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred that a Patient, who had been ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly fluxed with mercurial Inunctions, coming afterwards to have one of the Grinders of his lower Jaw pulled out,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:63097:38"/>
becauſe of the raging pain it had long put him to; my Relater had the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity to view narrowly this great Tooth, and found, to his wonder, a little drop of true Mercury in that ſlender Cavity of the Root, that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits the ſmall Veſſels which convey nouriſhment and ſenſe to the Tooth, in more than one of whoſe three Roots he affirmed to me that he found true, though but exceeding little, Quick-Silver. But a full Teſtimony to my preſent purpoſe is afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me by the experienced Phyſician <hi>Euſtachius Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius,</hi> who relates,<note rend="inter">Euſtach. Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius (apud Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nertum) lib. <hi>5.</hi> de morbis acu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis cap. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> that he ſaw himſelf, and that others alſo obſerved, ſome Bodies diſſected, of thoſe that had been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed for the Venereal Pox, in the Cavities of whoſe Bones no ſmall quantity of Quick Silver was got to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, (which yet (to add that upon the by) he ſays, did not hinder ſome of them from living many years, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving thoſe Inunctions.)</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:63097:39"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>I Am not ignorant that, among the Particulars laid together in the foregoing Eſſay, there are ſome that are not abſolutely neceſſary, to prove the Porouſneſs of the Bodies of Animals. But I thought it not impertinent to mention them, becauſe I hoped that they, in conjunction with the reſt, may be of ſome uſe to Naturaliſts, in giving an account of ſeveral things that paſs in a Humane Body, whether ſound or ſick, eſpecially if it be of a Topical diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and may remove, or much leſſen that great Prejudice, that makes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (and ſome of them otherwiſe learned) Phyſicians deſpiſe the uſe of all <hi>Amulets, Pericarpia,</hi> and other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Medicines in Diſtempers of the Inward parts, upon a confident, but not well grounded ſuppoſition, that theſe Remedies immediately touching but the outſide of the Skin, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not exerciſe any conſiderable opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:63097:39"/>
upon the internal parts of the Body.</p>
               <p>But though I have thus acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged ſome Paſſages of the foregoing Eſſay to be ſupernumerary, yet I muſt not diſmiſs it without intimating that I might from one Topick more have fetched a probable, though not a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrative argument, in favour of the Porouſneſs of Animals. For this may be very probably argued from hence, that even Inanimate, Solid and Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous Bodies, that in all likelyhood muſt be of a far cloſer Texture than the living Bodies of Animals (whoſe various Functions require a greater number and diverſity of Pores in their differing Organs) are not devoid of Pores, and have ſome of them very numerous ones, as will be ſufficiently made out in the following Eſſay, to which I ſhall therefore haſten.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:63097:40"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>N. B.</hi> The following Paper is that which is refer'd to in the 35th Page of this Eſſay.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note rend="inter">Pharma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copoeiae Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giae claſſis xiii. <hi>pa.</hi> 614.615.</note>Hujus rei veritatem comprobat Doctiſſimus ac celeberrimus Medicus &amp; Philoſophus D. <hi>Johannes Chryſoſtomus</hi> Irmbler, Statuum Moraviae Marchionatûs Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomedicus, his verbis ad me ſcribens: Et revera paravi ego, Anno M. <hi>DCLV,</hi> quo tempore inter Infectos verſabar quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidie, Trochiſcos Bufonios, eóſque ut caetera Helmontii, indefeſſi veritatis indagandae, &amp; ex puteo Opinionum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terum noſtram credulitatem excaecanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um eruendae, nati Philoſophi, experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta ſuas laudes ſuſtinere comperi: Inter, viginti autem Bufones vix unum quidem, jucundo ſane ſpectaculo, vidi ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miculos, per nares &amp; oculos egreſſuros, manu repellere quamdiu poterat, doxec elanguerit Bufo: ſed Trochiſcos ex vermiculis unà cum pulvere emo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui bufonis, &amp; materiâ per anum (non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:63097:40"/>
vidi per vomitum;) ſcilicet alis, pedibus, capitibus, ventribus Scara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baeorum viridibus, auratiſve &amp; ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gris, quos bufo cum terra in eſcam vena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ejectâ, cerea patinâ exceptis, cum Tragacantho roſato formatos, pluribus perſonis ſuper anthraces opponi feci, at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> nullum eorum mortuum eſſe dicere poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, ſed &amp; meorum domeſticorum, ut &amp; aliorum, quibus dedi, amicorum nullus, quod ſcio, infectus eſt. Sic comperi non tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tùm hiſce Trochiſcis enervari virus peſtilens in Carbunculo jam admiſſum, ut dein vulgaribus chirurgicis remediis ulcus facili negotio fuerit curatum, ſed etiam ad ſiniſtram mammam liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos, mihi meísque accurſui &amp; occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſui infectorum expoſitis, animoſitatem quandam indicibilem conferre, atque ita miaſmata &amp; effluvia peſtilentialia abarcere. Hucusque Excel. Medicus Moraviae.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb facs="tcp:63097:41"/>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:63097:41"/>
            <head>An Eſſay of the POROUSNESS OF SOLID BODIES.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I</head>
               <p>AS 'twill with far leſs difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be allowed, that Animals and Vegetables, and ſuch Bodies, as have belonged to either, abound with Pores, than that Inanimate, Solid, and even Ponderous Bodies are not deſtitute of them: So 'tis far leſs difficult to make out the former than the latter of theſe Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:63097:42"/>
And therefore, <hi>Pyrophilus,</hi> I hope you will not expect that I ſhould give you as many proofs of the one, as I have of the other; however I deſpair not, that thoſe I ſhall preſent you, will appear ſufficient for my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, though they be not numerous enough to make me careful to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal them in any exact order.</p>
               <p>Of the reaſons that induce me to think that even Solid Bodies are not deſtitute of Pores, there are <hi>ſome</hi> that have a greater Affinity with thoſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments that the Schools are wont to call <hi>à priori,</hi> becauſe they require more unobvious Ratiocinations upon Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical Principles, and <hi>others</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble, and indeed are, ſuch proofs as are uſually named <hi>à poſteriori,</hi> being ſuggeſted by the <hi>Phaenome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> afforded us by experience, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of any difficult Ratioci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations.</p>
               <p>Of the Firſt ſort of Reaſons I ſhall propoſe to you three; and begin with that, which may be drawn from the Origine and Formation of divers hard
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:63097:42"/>
Bodies.<note rend="inter">See the Tract of the Origine and Vertues of Gems, and the Notes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical production of Hardneſs.</note> For I have elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where endeavour<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and I hope not unſu<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſsfully, to ſhew, both that divers ſtones, and even Gems themſelves, and that ſeveral Metalline and other Mineral Bodies, were once either vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Liquors or at leaſt very ſoft ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. And I have elſewhere proved, that both theſe kinds of Bodies do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of, (which is the caſe of Liquors) or abound in (which is the caſe of ſoft and moiſt Bodies) minute particles of determinate Sizes and Shapes; from whence I think one may very proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conclude, that ſuch Gems and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mineral Bodies, notwithſtanding any hardneſs they afterwards come to acquire, are not deſtitute of Pores, ſince 'tis no way likely, that Corpuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of various and very irregular Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, ſuch as thoſe of moſt Liquors of the terreſtrial Globe are wont to be, can be ſo brought together, eſpecially by chance, cold, or any other ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, as not to intercept little Intervals or Pores between them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:63097:43"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>ANother thing which makes me think the Poroſity of the moſt part even of Solid Bodies to be great, is the conſideration of the great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parity, that may be found in the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifick Gravities of ſuch Bodies, as the Eye does not perceive to be Porous. For, <hi>though</hi> Water be a Body of that kind, and though its parts be ſo cloſe packt together, that the attempts of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious men, to make a manifeſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of that Liquor by outward violence, have not hitherto proved ſucceſsful, <hi>yet</hi> we find, that ſtones, Clays, metals, and even ſome Woods and a multitude of other kinds of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lids, will readily ſink in Water, and by conſequence are ſpecifically heavyer than it; which greater gravity ſeems not any way explicable, without ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, or at leaſt ſo well as by ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, that the Corpuſcles whereof
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:63097:43"/>
ſuch ſinking Bodies conſiſt, do either lye cloſer together, or are ſeparately more ſolid, than thoſe of Water; which Liquor muſt conſequently be Porous, though neither the Eye, nor the great force that has been ſeveral ways em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to compreſs it, can diſcover any Pores in it. Upon the ſame ground I further conclude, that ſolid Stones themſelves, as Marble, Flints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Are not free from Poroſity. For whereas, as far as ſeveral Tryals purpoſely made can inform me, I have found, that ſuch of theſe as have nothing metalline in them do ſeldom or never reach to treble the weight of an equal bulk of Water, they will, upon the former grounds, appear to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derably Porous; ſince the lighteſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, which are Tin and Iron, are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove twice heavier <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> that is, the bulks being equal, than Marble, Flints, Chryſtal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And by the ſame reaſon I alſo infer the great Poroſity, even of the Solid Body of Iron, which is as well heavier, as very much harder, than Tinn. For though
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:63097:44"/>
Copper be a good deal more ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous than Iron, or Steel, yet I have divers times found fine Gold, to be more than twice as heavy <hi>in ſpecie</hi> as Copper, ſince, whereas this Metal, whether it be <hi>European,</hi> or brought from <hi>Japan</hi> (for of that alſo I made Tryal) is about nine times as heavy as ſo much Water; I found refined Gold to be about nineteen times as heavy as Water equal to it in bulk. By which it ſeems highly probable, that ſo ſolid and heavy a Body, as Iron or Steel it ſelf, may be ſo porous, that Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talline matter equal to it in weight may naturally be contained in much leſs than half the Dimenſions that Metal poſſeſſes. And that Gold it ſelf, which is the moſt comPact and ſolid Body we know of, is not deſtitute of Pores, may appear by the Diſſolution of it in Quick-Silver, of which I ſhall ſpeak a little below. And if any ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, that hardneſs may be a greater argument of the Compactneſs of a Body, and its immunity from Pores, than its ſpecifick weight can be; I
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:63097:44"/>
ſhall add, that though I have found that <hi>Emery,</hi> which is the Body em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to cut ſteel and Load-ſtones and Cryſtal, and the moſt of Gems, being indeed much harder than Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or Flints, be far heavier than thrice its bulk of Water; <hi>yet</hi> that ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſneſs proceeds, as I elſe where inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, from the mixture of a metal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line Subſtance, which I have ſeparat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from it. And Diamonds, though much harder Bodies than <hi>Emery,</hi> and indeed the hardeſt we know of in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are ſo far from being, as ſome of late have written, the moſt ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of Bodies, that having examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them hydroſtatically, by a way elſewhere mentioned, I found them not much heavier than either Cryſtal, or fine Glaſs, and not half ſo heavy as the lighteſt Metals.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:63097:45"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>THe next thing, from which the Porouſneſs of Solid Bodies, and even thoſe that belong to the Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Kingdom (as the Chymiſts ſpeak) may be deduced, is the ſame with the firſt of thoſe from which we former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly argued the Poroſity of Subſtances belonging to the Animal Kingdom, namely, the very frame &amp; conſtitution of ſuch Bodies. For the ſolideſt Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies themſelves, reſulting from the Convention or Coalition of a great number of Particles of ſeveral big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and ſhapes, we cannot reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably ſuppoſe, (eſpecially in thoſe concretes wherein they are not ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by a ſeminal Principle) that they ſhould be contexed ſo, as to touch one another exactly every where and therefore they muſt of neceſſity leave ſome little Intervals and Pores be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:63097:45"/>This reaſon will, I hope, appear clear enough of it ſelf, to him that ſhall attentively conſider it, eſpecially if he know, that it has been Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trically demonſtrated, that there are but very few figures that will, (as they ſpeak) <hi>implere ſpatium,</hi> that is, which being adjuſted to one another will ſo exactly touch, that there is not the leaſt unfilled ſpace within the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference or circuit, if the figures be plain, or within the ambient <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies,</hi> if they be ſolid; ſo that, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the vaſt variety of other Figures, which made <hi>Epicurus</hi> and other <hi>Ato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> pronounce it <hi>incomprehenſible,</hi> 'tis very obvious to conceive, that Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſcles of ſuch differing ſhapes being put together, will leave multitudes of little Pores intercepted, between thoſe parts that do not every where touch one another. And even the Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Figures lately ſpoken of, may be ſaid to fill ſpace rather in a <hi>Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trical</hi> than a <hi>Phyſical</hi> ſenſe. For, if ſuch Portions of matter as are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to conſtitute, for inſtance, a Cube,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:63097:46"/>
were actually put together, they would not exactly fill the ſpace com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended within the ambient ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of the Body they compoſe, becauſe the component Bodies, being Phyſical, conſiſt of Corpuſcles of their own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſhapes, which we never find Mathematically exquiſite. As if, for example, the Cube were of Marble, no Art could poliſh the ſides of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent Body ſo, as that they ſhould be perfectly ſmoothed ſince (as, if I miſtake not, the learned <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> well obſerves) Emery, Pumice-ſtone, and even Puttee, or other Powders that are employed to poliſh them, do them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves conſiſt of little hard angular Corpuſcles, that leave ſmall ſcratches, like ſo many little furrows, on their ſurfaces, which muſt needs hinder the perfect contact of the whole ſurfaces of two contiguous Bodies, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently leave here and there Intervals or Pores, between thoſe ſurfaces; to which I ſhall add that Marble it ſelf as 'tis Marble, abounds with internal Pores, as will ere long appear by
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:63097:46"/>
Experience, and as may be rationally conjectured from the Specifick Levity of it, in compariſon of Gold and Lead.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>HAving diſpatched the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>à priori,</hi> that may be imployed to ſhew the Porouſneſs of Solid Bodies, 'twill be now ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to propoſe ſome Experiments and obſervations, that may (as 'twere) <hi>à poſteriori</hi> either evince or confirm the ſame Doctrine.</p>
               <p>Of theſe Inſtances ſome relate to Solid Bodies that are of leſs ſpecifick gravity ſome to Foſſiles preſumed to be devoid of Metalline parts, ſome to Minerals that are thought to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate of a Metalline nature, ſome to Metals themſelves, and ſome to Glaſs.</p>
               <p>To begin with the firſt ſort of theſe Inſtances; That Wood is Porous, there are many things that argue; ſome of which are elſewhere mentioned. But few would ſuſpect, that Quick-Silver which is ſo unapt to enter the Pores
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:63097:47"/>
of Bodies much leſs compact, ſhould permeate peices of Wood of a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable thickneſs; and yet, that we have made it do by the following Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. We took a wooden Trunk, ſuch as is employed to ſhoot pellets at Birds, with ſtrength enough to kill them, and having cloſely ſtopt one end of it, we poured in Quick Silver at the other, till it reached to a good height in the cylindrical Cavity of the Inſtrument, and then the lower parts of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talline Liquor, being aſſiſted by the weight of the Incumbent ones, (not to mention that of the Air) to preſs into the Pores of the Wood, they iſſued out at them on all ſides, in great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of minute drops, much after the manner of Quick-Silver ſtrained through Leather, out of amalgams; which was a <hi>Phaenomenon</hi> not unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to behold. But till I have oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to repeat this Experiment with differing circumſtances, I ſhall not think it fit to lay much ſtreſs upon it, for want of knowing, what intereſt the great weight of the Quick Silver may have had in the event.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:63097:47"/>And this caution may perchance be applicable to the following Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment, namely, that having, by the help of my Pneumatical Engine, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn the Air from one ſide of a round peice of board, the Air on the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite ſide, not having its preſſure any longer reſiſted by that which it uſed to meet with from the withdrawn Air, preſſed ſo ſtrongly againſt the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of the Wood expoſed to it, as to make it ſelf way through the Pores of it, and get copiouſly enough into the Cavity whence the other Air had been pumpt out; (the weight of the incumbent Atmoſphere doing on this occaſion, what the weight of the Quick-Silver did on that laſt recited:) Which was a ſurprizing ſpectacle to the by-ſtanders becauſe the board that was thus permeated, was of ſtrong Wood, and of conſiderable thickneſs.</p>
               <p>I ſhould here ſubjoin ſeveral other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of the Porouſneſs of Wood, if I could diſplay them without more words, than I am willing to allow them;
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:63097:48"/>
and I preſume it may here ſuffice, if I let you ſee by ſome ſurprizing Effects that when Wood is reduced to that thinneſs, that its cloſeneſs or Poroſity may conveniently be examined, it will eaſily enough give paſſage, even unto viſible, odorable, and tinging Corpuſcles though they invade it not in the form of a Liquor, but of dry Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halations, ſo they be not incommenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate to its Pores. This I ſuppoſe, you will not ſcruple to infer from the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Tryals, as they were long ſince ſet down in one of my Note-Books.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Fumes of our ſmoaking Liquor [deſcribed in the foregoing Eſſay] tinged a Copper half penny, through a broad thin ſhaving of Dale, that did not, when held againſt the window, diſcover any perforation; tinged it, I ſay, very deeply in about a quarter of a minute and ſomewhat leſs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſame Fumes tinged mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly, but not ſo notably, the ſame half penny firſt cleanſed through two ſuch ſhavings of Dale, laid one upon
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:63097:48"/>
another in ſomwhat leſs than one minute.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And in about one minute the ſame Fumes tinged the cleanſed half penny, through three ſuch ſhavings of Dale very viſibly, but not ſo conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly, as through the two foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. Theſe Tryals were made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of heat to promote the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of the Fumes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>FRom the conſideration of Woods let us now proceed to give ſome Inſtances of the Porouſneſs of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies made of cloſe and compact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and perhaps well baked Clays or other Earths.</p>
               <p>That Earthen Veſſels, thô ſtrong and well bak'd, are many of them porous enough may be argued not only from what has been lately reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but from hence, that ſome of them will ſuffer themſelves to be
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:63097:49"/>
ſoakt through by Oyl. Others by ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of Nitre, and ſome other Salts. And there are very few of them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excepting <hi>Haſſian</hi> Crucibles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that will long keep Salt of Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and ſuch like fixt Alcalies, in fuſion without being penetrated by them. I have heard Diſtillers complain, that when they have diſtilled corroſive ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials, as Vitriol and Salt-Petre, with ſtrong fires, in thoſe Earthen Veſſels that are commonly made uſe of in <hi>London</hi> (eſpecially by refiners) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Retorts though their necks be ſtrait and long (upon which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count they are called long-necks) a conſiderable quantity of the fineſt Spirits make their eſcape quite tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the Veſſel; ſo that in the Retort and Receiver many ounces are found want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, of the firſt weight of the matter to be diſtilled. And this ſometimes, when the Vitriol has been previouſly calcin'd, and a reaſonable allowance has been made, for what may have eſcaped thorow the Lute, that joined together the long Neck and Receiver.
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:63097:49"/>
And <hi>though</hi> I have obſerved of our Bottles, made of the ſame Earth with Juggs, that they are hard enough to ſtrike Fire with a good Steel, <hi>yet</hi> a good Experimenter upon ſuch Veſſels of whom I made enquiry, has aſſured me that theſe, as compact as they are, may, even without external heat, have their Pores pervaded by the finer parts of Spirituous Liquors.</p>
               <p>To this purpoſe I remember that meeting once with a <hi>Virtuoſo,</hi> that was curious about the ways of making Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as brisk and ſpirituous a Liquor as he could; I enquired of him, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he was able to keep in the ſubtil Spirit of this Skilfully fermented Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, in thoſe earthen Bottles, that, by reaſon of the ſolidity they acquire by the vehement coction of the Fire, are commonly called <hi>ſtone Bottles</hi>; to which he replyed. that he often found to his trouble, that the Liquor would permeate the compact Subſtance of the Bottles: And when I objected that the Spirits might either eſcape out at the Cork, which I have made ſeveral Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:63097:50"/>
of divers kinds that would readily permeate; he replyed, that what he had ſaid appeared by the outſide of the Bottles: To which when I further ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, that the ſight of dew on the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of the Bottles, would not convince me, without taſting whether it were vinous, becauſe I had divers times obſerved, that brisk Liquors would produce a dew, on the outſide of the Veſſels that contained them, not by any tranſudation (for I have made Tryal of it in Glaſſes) but by conden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the aqueous vapors, diſperſed through the neighbouring part of the Ambient Air: He replyed that, beſides what his taſt had informed him of the quality of this dew, he found that the included Liquor, though exactly ſtopt, waſted in not very many Months ſo conſiderably, as ſometimes to loſe a ſixth, or even a fifth part; &amp; this eſcape or percolation of the Liquor through the Subſtance of the Veſſels, he affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf to have obſerved, not only in one or two Bottles, but in very many and the like obſervation for the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:63097:50"/>
main was confirmed to me, upon his own experience, by an eminent Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, who, being a great Lover of brisk Sider, uſed to bottle it up early and carefully.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Though</hi> good <hi>Haſſian</hi> Crucibles be very cloſely compacted, as well as throughly baked Bodies, and upon that account are able to keep Silver and divers other Metals long in fuſion, without letting them at all run out; <hi>yet</hi> having diſſolved Silver in <hi>Aqua fortis,</hi> I obſerved that, <hi>though</hi> the Salts were by this operation ſo chang'd that this horn-like Silver did diſſolve nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the <hi>Aqua fortis,</hi> nor in the <hi>Aqua Regia</hi> that I put it into; <hi>yet</hi> when I kept it a while in fuſion, (which 'tis eaſily brought to be) among quick Coals, it would without cracking or perforating the Crucible, ſoak into it, and permeate the Pores of it, in I know not how many places, as I convinced ſome curious perſons, by ſhewing them on the outſide of the Veſſel, a multitude of minute globules of pure Silver, like ſo many little drops, that
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:63097:51"/>
were got thither, as it were, by tranſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>FRom baked Earths, that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned in point of hardneſs to emulate ſtones, we will proceed to give ſome inſtances of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſneſs of Natural Stones them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>There goes a tradition, that in ſome part of the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> they have a Stone, of which they make large Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, wherein they put Water to perco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, as it were, through a ſtrainer. Of theſe Veſſels I had one ſent me for a preſent, whereof being hereafter to give ſome account in a more op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune place, I ſhall now only take notice that I found that Water would (thô ſlowly) ſoak through the Veſſel, thô it were conſiderably thick.</p>
               <p>If, as many of the Ancients, and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:63097:51"/>
moſt of the modern Corpuſcular Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers have conceived, the Tranſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency and Opacity of Bodies proceeds from a Rectitude or Crookedneſs of Pores, which makes them fit or unfit to transmit the Light, that tends to pervade them in Phyſically ſtraight Lines: If this <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> I ſay, be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, we may draw a very proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble argument, that Stones may be Porous, from the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> of that odd Gem, that is beſt known by the name of <hi>Oculus Mundi.</hi> For this ſmall ſtone (at leaſt that which I made my Obſervations of) when 'tis dry, and is kept in the Air, is opacous, almoſt like a poliſhed piece of white Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and ſo it continues, as long as 'tis kept dry. But if you put it into fair water, it will in no long time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by degrees quite Tranſparent, and that which I made Tryal of look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed then not unlike a piece of clear yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Amber which by degrees does in the free Air loſe its Tranſparency and turn to be opacous as before. Now according to the above mentioned
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:63097:52"/>
Corpuſcular <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> the Pellucidneſs which the Stone acquires in Water, may be accounted for, by ſaying, that the Liquor getting in at the crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Pores of the Stone, does for the time rectify them, and make them per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to the ſtraight Beams of Light; as we ſee that White Paper, being wetted with Water, or, which does far better, being made ſo imbide Oyl, has its Pores ſo changed and rectified, that the Water much leſſens its Opacity, and makes it almoſt Semidiaphanous and the Oyl, if it be fine and well ſoaked up, makes it Tranſparent. But upon the receſs or evaporation of the imbibed Particles of Water, the Pores of the little Stone becoming crooked again reflect the Rays of light they ſhould tranſmit. Which explication will be the better allowed of, if my memory do not miſinform me, when it tells me, that a learned Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Royal Society found the <hi>Oculus Mundi</hi> to weigh more in a nice ballance, when it was taken out of the Water and well wiped, than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:63097:52"/>
it was put in. This Stone, which very few of the writers about Gems take notice of, is ſo rare and difficult to be got, that I had not opportunity to make upon it all the Tryals I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired; and therefore, though the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject be curious, I may, I hope, be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, if I haſten from it to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>There is ſo much difference in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Qualities betwixt Stones and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, that 'tis very probable, that when the Corpuſcles of both come to be brought together into one Maſs, they will not touch one another ſo cloſe, as not to leave ſtore of little Intervals or Pores between them. And upon this ground I have been apt to think that divers very hard Stones, Diapha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and Opacous, are not devoid of Poroſity. For I have elſewhere deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered a way by which I have obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed good ſtore of Metalline parts, both from American <hi>Granats,</hi> and from <hi>Emery</hi>; though this laſt be ſo exceeding hard a Stone, that 'tis uſually im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by artificers to work upon
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:63097:53"/>
Iron and Steel, and to cut not only <hi>Rock Cryſtal,</hi> but divers Gems that are harder than either that or Steel.</p>
               <p>Upon the ſame ground one may probably infer the Poroſity of many Artificial Gems made by Fuſion; for to give theſe the colour of Sapphirs, To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pazes, Amethyſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we are wont to add to the vitrifiable matter, either ſome prepared metal, as calcined Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, <hi>calx</hi> of Gold, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or elſe ſome Mineral as <hi>Zaffora</hi> and <hi>Manganeze</hi> (as the Glaſs-men call <hi>Magneſia</hi>) that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds in Metalline parts. Nay I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, I have ſometimes given the colour to the vitrified ſubſtance, by imploying natural Gems, as Granats; though to ſhew that the coloration which the maſs received from theſe, proceeded from the Metalline Corpuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, that lay hid in the tinging matter, the Colour produced was not that which was conſpicuous in the Gem it ſelf, but one very different from it, and ſuch as the metal, which upon other accounts I ſuppoſed the Gem to partake of, ought, according to the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:63097:53"/>
Grounds I proceeded upon, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in the vitrifiable matter. And this very Experiment makes it alſo highly probable, that even natural tranſparent Gems, (divers of which are much harder than Marble, Iron &amp; even Steel) are themſelves Porous; ſince, notwithſtanding their Tranſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency and ſeeming Homogeneity. They are made up of Ingredients of ſuch differing natures as are Stony and Metalline Corpuſcles.</p>
               <p>From the ſame Ground we may likewiſe deduce the Poroſity of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſites; many of which I have obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be, not only hard enough, plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully to ſtrike fire by colliſion with Steel, but more ponderous than even divers Oars, that were rich enough in Metal, to be wrought with good profit. And yet theſe hard and heavy (Mineral) Stones are very far from being homogeneous; ſince I have met with few Inanimate Bodies, produced by Nature her ſelf, ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded as ſeveral Marcaſites that I have ſeen. For theſe are wont to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:63097:54"/>
more or leſs Copper, and Iron too: and they abound in Combuſtible Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur, a Corroſive Salt, and a certain Fixt Subſtance, which I found to differ from true Earth, but of whoſe Nature the Tryals I have hitherto made on it, have but little ſatisfied me.</p>
               <p>I might here deduce the Poroſity of the Load-ſtone, as hard and ſolid a Body as it is, partly from the <hi>Effluvia</hi> it emits and admits, and partly from the Heterogeneity I have by Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Tryals found to be in it. But theſe things belong more properly to a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per about Magnetical Bodies, for which I the more willingly reſerve them, becauſe other Experiments will keep them from being needful to be here inſiſted on.</p>
               <p>The Poroſity of Marble, and divers other Stones of like Contexture, may with probability be deduc'd from this, that they are liable to be diſſolved by divers of the corroſive <hi>Menſtruums</hi> of the Chymiſts, ſuch as <hi>Aqua fortis</hi> ſp. of Salt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſome of them even by Vegetable Liquors, of Natures own
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:63097:54"/>
preparing, as the juice of Limons, and that of Barberries. But a more noble and ſatisfactory inſtance may be afforded, by the invention of ſtaining or colouring white Marble, without imploying any fretting Liquor, or ſpoiling the Texture of it. This way being caſually lighted on by an ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Stone-cutter in <hi>Oxford,</hi> who gained by it both credit and money, he long ſince thought fit to acquaint me with it, upon condition of ſecreſy (which I have to this day inviolably kept) and of my aſſiſting him to improve his Invention by making it practicable with other Colours than Red. Theſe circumſtances I mention, to ſignify that I write not by gueſs, of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, having both ſeen the Experiment tried, and made it my ſelf. But though I found it far leſs improvable to other uſes, then one would expect, yet, as to our preſent purpoſe, it is very ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite. For by this way an excellent red Colour, may be made to ſoak into a piece of White Marble, almoſt as Oyl will do into Leather, without
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:63097:55"/>
impairing, that I obſerved, the ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of the ſtone, which, after being dyed, will be capable of a fine gloſs as before. Some other Colours (yet but few fair ones) would by this way be brought to ſoak into Marble, on which one may with them ſo define, and limit the Colorations, that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Artificer, when I brought him to kiſs the Kings hand, preſented His Majeſty with an <hi>Andromeda,</hi> whoſe Colours were ſo vivid, that this skilful Judge of curious things, was pleaſed to honour it with a place among his Rarities. And, to ſatisfy his Majeſty that the fine Red was not, as ſome ſuſpected, a mere varniſh, I purpoſely broke a plate of Marble, in whoſe fragments he ſaw, that the Pigment had ſunk to a conſiderable depth, into the very Subſtance of the Stone. And I doubt not but it might have been made eaſily enough to ſink much deeper, if it had been thought neceſſary. A fine Plate of ſuch White Marble, with the penetrating Pictures of Coloured Flowers drawn upon it I
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:63097:55"/>
yet keep by me to ſatisfy the curious. And ſome Utenſils, as Hafts of Knives, Salt-Sellers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I have known to have laſted ſeveral years.</p>
               <p>There is an Experiment that ſeems much ſtronger for the Porouſneſs of Solid Bodies, than that it ſelf (which was lately recited) of ſtaining Marble. For in <hi>Italy</hi> ſome Goldſmiths have a way of imbuing Fragments of Rock-Cryſtal, which is a Body much harder than Marble, with divers Colours; which do ſometimes ſo imbelliſh them, that having ground off thoſe parts that would not receive the ſame Tincture, they ſet ſome of them in Gold Rings, and ſell them with profit. When I was inform'd of this, I thought of a Compoſition, that I hop'd might perform the ſame thing, and perhaps better than that which was employ'd by them, who either knew not, or for ought I could perceive, us'd not, ſome Minerals that I thought fit for the purpoſe. Upon this Preſumption we carefully cemented ſome clear Fragments of Native Cryſtal with a
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:63097:56"/>
Compoſition of ſome Volatile Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, together with a Salt or two, and having ſuffered the Crucibles to cool leiſurely, we had divers of the Fragments ſtain'd here and there, ſome with one Colour and ſome with another, as differing Fumes happen'd to invade them. And of theſe Colours ſome were dark or dull, and ſome vivid enough. But having conſider'd the ſtain'd pieces, and the progreſs of the Operation, more attentively, I began to doubt, whether theſe Adventitious Colours were really pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by the bare penetrating of the Mineral Fumes into the Pores of the Cryſtal it ſelf. For I thought it poſſible, and not very unprobable, that the great Heat of the Fire, and the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bient Mixture, might cleave or flaw in many places ſome of the Cryſtalline Fragments; and that the finer parts of the Minerals being vehemently agitated, might inſinuate themſelves into theſe thin Flaws, which upon the ſlow refrigeration of the Stones, ſhutting themſelves cloſe again, might
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:63097:56"/>
lock up the tinging Particles, without appearing diſcontinued, eſpecially to the Eyes of Perſons that were not made uſe of with a more than ordinary at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, excited by diſtruſt. This ſuſpicion was not removed by the apparent entireneſs of each little piece of Cryſtal. For having taken more than once a Lump of that ſtone, and ſlowly brought it to be red hot in the Fire, I found that if I warily quenched it in Water, though it would thereby acquire a multitude of little cracks or Flaws, which deſtroyed its former tranſparency, and made it look whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh, yet it continued ſtill an entire Body, notwithſtanding the diſadvanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous haſte, wherewith the operation had been performed. And having after this ſuſpicion, inquired of an ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lapidary, that belonged to a great Prince whether in poliſhing of Gems upon the Wheel, he had taken notice that the Heat would flaw them, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered me, that now and then he had obſerved that ſome Stones, eſpecially<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if I miſremember not, Rubies, when
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:63097:57"/>
they were very much heated by the ſwift motion of the Engine he employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to poliſh them, did cleave as it ſeemed to him, and gape, ſo as at firſt to make him fear the Stones were ſpoiled; and yet afterwards they cloſed ſo perfectly, that no Flaw at all could be perceived in them. I have mentioned the foregoing Experiment of tinging Cryſtal, to comply with the dictates of Philoſophical candor, which forbids me to lay much ſtreſs upon a Proof, whoſe validity I my ſelf diſtruſt. But perhaps my ſuſpicion may by further Tryal, which I have not now conveniency to make, appear not to have been well grounded, and in that caſe the tinging of Cryſtal, as well inwardly as outwardly, by Fumes will be a noble Argument for the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity of Solid Bodies, Rock-Cryſtal being harder, and probably cloſer, not only than Marble, but even than Glaſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:63097:57"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>THat Metals, though the heavieſt of Bodies, are not deſtitute of Pores, may be with probability proved in a general way by this; That they are all diſſoluble in their appropriate <hi>Menſtruums,</hi> as Gold in <hi>Aqua Regia,</hi> and all the reſt in <hi>Aqua Fortis,</hi> except Tin, which yet it ſelf will be corroded by that <hi>Menſtruum,</hi> though not well kept up in a fluid form, as it may be by another <hi>Menſtruum,</hi> which I elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where teach; and ſometimes the ſame Metal may be diſſolved by very diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Menſtruums,</hi> as Lead by <hi>Aqua for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> and Spirit of Vinegar; and Copper by <hi>Aqua fortis, Aqua Regia,</hi> Spirit of Vinegar, Spirit of Salt, and ſome other Solvents, that upon Trial I have found ſufficient for that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>But 'twill, I preſume, be thought more conſiderable to my preſent ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, if it be ſhewn, that Bodies that appear Groſs, and which in their Natural ſtate are not fluid, and are
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:63097:58"/>
confeſſed to be of a compounded na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, will penetrate Metals quite through, even without melting them.</p>
               <p>This we have divers times effected by a Cementation of Copper Plates, With common 🜍 (much a kin to a way preſcribed by ſome Alchymiſts to make <hi>Vitriolum Veneris</hi>) which we warily performed much after this manner. We took good Copper lami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated to the thickneſs of a Shilling or thereabouts, and having cut it into ſmall pieces, that they might the more eaſily be put into a Crucible or Cemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Pot, we ſtrewed at the bottom of the Veſſel ſome beaten 🜍, and then co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered it pretty well with ſome of theſe Plates, which were laid on flat-wiſe. Upon theſe we ſtrewed another Bed of powdered Brimſtone, and cover'd that alſo with Plates, upon which we put more Sulphur, &amp; ſo continu'd ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king one lair of Brimſtone, &amp; another of Metal, till we had employed all our Plates, or filled the Crucible, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing careful that the uppermoſt Bed, as well as the loweſt, ſhould be of Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:63097:58"/>
This done, we luted on an earthen Cover to the Veſſel, to keep the 🜍 from taking Fire, and afterwards having placed the Pot amongſt Coals kindled at a good diſtance from it, that it might be heated by degrees, we kept it for ſome few hours (perhaps Two or Three) in ſuch a degree of Fire as was ſufficient to keep the Sulphur melted (which is eaſily enough done) without bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Metal to fuſion; the Pot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cold, we took off the cover, and found the Plates quite altered in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and Texture, ſome of them hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a dark and dirty Colour, whilſt others looked of a fine Violet or Blew; they were generally ſo brittle, that 'twas very eaſy to break them with ones finger, and reduce them to Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. And (now to add ſuch Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances as a Chymiſt would not take notice of) many of the Plates, when they were broken, appeared to have been (by the contiguous Beds of Sulphur above and below) horizon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally divided each of them into two
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:63097:59"/>
Plates, divers of which in ſome places had a manifeſt diſtance or Cavity between them. And 'twas obſervable, that when I conſidered one or other of theſe Plates attentively in the parts that had been contiguous before I broke it, I could plainly diſcern a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude as 'twere of Fibres, reaching from one of the flat ſides of the Plate to the other, &amp; running many of them, as to ſenſe, parallel to one another. Theſe Circumſtances may ſufficiently argue, that the Plates were pierced quite through by the Brimſtone; but for confirmation of this, and to ſhew too that the Sulphur does as it were ſoak into the Body of the Metal, and in a Groſs manner lodge it ſelf there; I ſhall add, that not only to the Eye the Plates appeared much ſwelled, or thicker then when they were put in, but having weighed them before the operation was begun, and after it was quite ended, the Copper, though it needed not to be freed from externally adhering Sulphur, was found to have a conſiderable increaſe of weight by
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:63097:59"/>
the acceſſion of the Sulphur, which (to add that circumſtance) though it appeared not to the Eye, yet if a Plate were laid upon quick Coles, and blown, would often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times diſcover it ſelf by a Blew flame.</p>
               <p>By making the like Experiment for the main, we found that refined Silver, though a more heavy and compact Body, than Copper, and not diſſoluble by moſt of the <hi>Menſtruums,</hi> that work on this Metal, is penetrable by the Body of Sulphur, which will alſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine Tin and Lead and (eſpecially) Iron.</p>
               <p>Nor is Sulphur the only conſiſtent Body that has this ingreſs into Metals; for we have found them penetrable by prepared Arſenick. But becauſe theſe operations are not ſo eaſy, and the Subject is not eaſily handled without danger, I forbear the mention of them in this place, where, after what has been recited, it is not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</p>
               <p>Another Experiment there is,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:63097:60"/>
which does more advantageouſly than that made with Brimſtone, diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Poroſity of Copper. For there is a way by which, without the help of Salts, Sulphur or Arſenick, one may make a ſolid and heavy Body ſoak in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Pores of that Metal, and give it a durable Colour. I ſhall not mention the way, becauſe of the bad uſe that may be made of it. But having had the curioſity more than once to try it upon a new Copper Farthing, the event was, that one part of it, which I purpoſely forbore to tinge, remained common Copper ſtill, but the other part acquired a yellow, that differed very little, if at all, from a Golden Colour, the former ſtamp that was impreſſed upon the coin continuing viſible. And to convince the ſcrupulous, that the Pigment did really ſink, and as it were ſoak into the Body of the Metal, and did not meerly colour the <hi>Superficies,</hi> I made them take notice, that the Farthing was not melted, and yet by filing off a wide gap from the Edge of the Coin, inwards, it plainly
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:63097:60"/>
appeared, that the Yellow or Golden Colour had penetrated a pretty way beneath the ſurface of the Farthing; ſo that it looked there as if two thin Plates, the one Yellow, and the other Reddiſh, did, without any Interval be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, lye upon one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>If Bodies be not to be pervaded, or deeply pierced into, by Corpuſcles, but only to have their more ſuperficial Pores, if I may ſo call them, penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thereby, 'tis poſſible that Bodies, which are either much harder, or much cloſer, than Marble, Alabaſter or the like Bodies, may have their Pores poſſeſſed even by odorous Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſcles; I ſay, <hi>even by ſuch,</hi> becauſe they are moſt of them groſs enough to be kept from exhaling, by Bodies much leſs compact then Earthen Bottles; and are far from being of the fineſt particles that Nature affords. But that ſuch odorous Corpuſcles may lodge themſelves in the exterior Pores of very cloſe Bodies, I have been inclined to think, <hi>not only,</hi> by the obſtinately
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:63097:61"/>
adhering Odour, which I found by Tryal, that ſome ſuttle and Spirituous parts, ſuch as the Chymiſts would perhaps call in their Aggregates, the Eſſence of Musk, Amber, Amber-greece, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> notwithſtanding the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Glaſſes, that had long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſuch Liquors; but by what has been aſſured me by a Phyſician of great Experience, who travelled and lived much in the Eaſt. For having told him, that I had been informed, that in ſome places leſs famous then <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> for curioſity in making fine Sword blades, there was a way found and practiſed of making them richly ſcented, without injury to their Gloſs; I deſired to know of him, if at <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> or elſewhere, he had ſeen any of them; to which he replied, that he did not remember he had, but yet made no doubt the Information might be true. For he himſelf had in <hi>Europe,</hi> and kept for divers years, a Watch, whoſe Metalline Caſe, was richly perfumed; and when I askt him, whether there were not ſome
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:63097:61"/>
thin varniſh, or ſome outward Caſe of perfumed Leather, or Chagran, or ſomewhat elſe, from whence the odour proceeded, he aſſured me, that his obſervations had prevented and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved that and divers other Scruples, and that the caſe being clean and Gloſſy, he could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that the Odour proceeded from any thing elſe, than ſome odori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferous thing, or other that was inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly lodged in the Pores, or Porous Subſtance of the metal it ſelf. And indeed, ſince both Arſenick, and even common Sulphur, may by Art be as it were incorporated with ſome Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls, and even with Silver, I ſee not why it ſhould be impoſſible, that ſome pleaſingly ſcented Subſtances ſhould be admitted into the Pores of Metalline Bodies, and be volatile enough to have their ſubtiler parts fly off in odorous Exhalations, eſpecially if they be a little excited, as the Watch Caſe lately mentioned was, by a gentle heat, ſuch as was that of the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:63097:62"/>
wearers pocket. And on this occaſion I remember to have made a certain Metalline compoſition, which looked like Gold, and of which I cauſed a Ring to be caſt, and yet this Metal retained ſo many unperceived Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Corpuſcles in it, that an Ingenious Perſon to whom I diſcovered the compoſition of it, found after Tryal, as he aſſured me, that being worn as a Ring, it had in ſome diſtempers, particularly of the Eyes, manifeſt ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, that evidently enough ſeemed to flow, at leaſt in great part, from its participation of the Mercury we employed in preparing the Factitious Metal.</p>
               <p>Since the writing of the former part of this Eſſay, having met with an inquiſitive Nobleman, who had lived in ſeveral parts of <hi>Africk,</hi> and was Governour of the beſt Town the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropeans</hi> have on that Continent, I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed with him, among other things, about the Skill that ſome aſcribe to the <hi>African Moors,</hi> of making excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent weapons, whereof I knew his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:63097:62"/>
was very curious. Upon which occaſion he told me, that ſome of the Off-Spring of the <hi>Granadine Moors</hi> were indeed the beſt at making Arms that ever he met with; and that he had ſeen ſome weapons of their forging and tempering, that he preferred even to thoſe of <hi>Damaſco.</hi> And when I asked him whether any of them had the art of perfuming their Weapons, he anſwered me, that ſome of them did it admirably well, and inſtanced in a Blade which he kept for ſome years, &amp; found it ſtill to retain the perfumed ſcent, which he ſuppoſed to be as it were incorporated with the Steel whereof the Blade was made. When I told him, I ſuſpected that the ſcab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard might have been well perfumed, and communicate its odour to the contained Blade, he allowed the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to be plauſible, but replyed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that it was not concluding, ſince miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liking the Scabbard, as not handſom &amp; faſhionable enough, he cauſed a new one to be made, wherein he afterwards kept it. And the ſame Lord further
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:63097:63"/>
told me, that he had alſo a Fowling Piece, whoſe Barrel was perfumed. And when I objected that perhaps the odoriferous ſcent proceeded from the ſtock, and not from the Metal, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered that the Gun not being, when it came into his poſſeſſion, skilfully and handſomely mounted, he cauſed the Barrel to be fitted with a new ſtock, notwithſtanding which, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to ſmell fragrantly. And when I further asked, whether he ever cauſed the Gun to be waſhed or ſcoured after it was grown foul by having been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſhot in, he anſwered me, that he had, and, as far as I can remember, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, that after it was made clean it did (notwithſtanding the ill ſcent that the ſoot of the Powder had given it) retain a pleaſing ſmell, but fainter than before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:63097:63"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>SInce the Subject of this Eſſay is the <hi>Porouſneſs of Solid Bodies,</hi> and ſince there is no Body that is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally reputed ſo cloſe and compact as Glaſs, it will be pertinent to this diſcourſe, and probably will be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, that I ſhould here ſay ſomething about the Queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Glaſs be, or be not, devoid of Pores.</p>
               <p>But before I acquaint you with my Tryals, or my thoughts, about this Problem, I think it requiſite to clear the ſenſe, in which I mean to handle it, that I may not, as ſome others have done, for want of diſtinctly ſtating the Queſtion, ſpeak confuſedly and erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neouſly of it.</p>
               <p>I ſhall then here obſerve, to prevent miſtakes, that the Poroſity of Glaſs may admit of two Acceptions. For it may be ſaid to be quite pervious to
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:63097:64"/>
Fluids, as a Boot is to Water, or only to be capable of having its ſuperficial parts further and further diſſolved or corroded thereby, as a Silver Cup is Porous in reference to <hi>Aqua fortis,</hi> which cannot ſweat through it, as Water does through a Boot, but eat its way through it, by diſſolving the Texture of the Veſſel.</p>
               <p>Another thing requiſite to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, to prevent Ambiguity, is, that Glaſs it ſelf is not all of one ſort, as men unacquainted with Chymiſtry are wont to preſume, for Glaſs of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony, for inſtance, and that of Lead, both of them made <hi>per ſe,</hi> do mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly differ, uſually in colour, and conſtantly in weight, and alſo in their operations upon Humane Bodies; and both theſe ſorts of Glaſs do in ſeveral points differ from <hi>common Glaſs,</hi> under which name, for brevities ſake, I comprehend both White or Cryſtalline Glaſs, as 'tis called in the Shops, and that courſer ſort, which they uſually call Green Glaſs; both which ſorts I here conſider under one Notion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:63097:64"/>
both are made of fixt Alcalies, and other fit Ingredients, as Sand, Earth, Aſhes, Pebbles, or Flints, Colliquated by a ſtrong &amp; laſting ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Fire: and 'tis of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Glaſs, in the ſenſe now declared, that I ſhall conſider the Poroſity in the remaining part of this Eſſay. In which to proceed with ſome Method, I ſhall digeſt what I have to ſay into the enſuing Propoſitions, and the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations annext to them.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Prop 1.</hi> 'Tis very probable, that Glaſs may be pierced into to ſome diſtance, even by viſible and tangible Bodies.</q>
               <p>I know that this will ſeem a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox to many, and repugnant to common Experience, which ſhews that Glaſs Veſſels will contain very ſubtile and even highly corroſive Liquors, as the Spirit of Hartſhorn, of Urine, and that of Nitre; as alſo thoſe potent <hi>Menſtruums,</hi> as <hi>Aqua fortis, Aqua Regis,</hi> and Oil of Vitriol,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:63097:65"/>
which not only are not obſerved to pierce into it, but are unable to make any ſenſible alteration, ſo much as on the ſuperficial parts, even in thoſe Vials wherein they have been long kept.</p>
               <p>But, notwithſtanding all this, I preſume you will not condemn the lately propoſed Paradox, when you have conſidered what may be ſaid to juſtifie it. For, beſides that it may be made probable <hi>à Priori,</hi> by the Arguments whence we have formerly proved the Porouſneſs of Solid Bodies in general; there are two ſorts of Experiments, from whence one may argue, that Glaſs in particular is not devoid of Pores in the ſenſe wherein we are now ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them.</p>
               <p>And firſt, I remember, that, having kept for a good while in a vial, a quantity of a certain Spirit of Salt, that I had reſerved in a cool place; I found, when I came to uſe it, that the Glaſs was crackt, and moſt of the Liquor was run out; but, before this
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:63097:65"/>
happened, it had ſo far corroded the inſide of the Glaſs, that in ſome places it was eaten almoſt as thin as a piece of Paper; and this part which yet continued Glaſs, was lin'd with a much thicker white ſubſtance, that ſtuck to the ſides of it, and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and taſted like a kind of odd Salt; ſo that it invited me to conjecture, that it proceeded from the ſubſtance of the Glaſs, which you know conſiſts of an <hi>Alcali</hi> as well as of <hi>Sand</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roded by the Saline Spirits of the <hi>Menſtruum,</hi> and coagulated with them into this odd kind of Concrete; and 'twas remarkable in our veſſel, that the upper part of the vial, to which the <hi>Menſtruum</hi> did not reach, was not corroded, nor alter'd, tho the operation of the Liquor reached as high as the Liquor it ſelf. And I remember, that when I related all this to ſome experienced Chymiſts, one of them that was a more heedful obſerver, aſſured me, the like had once or twice, happened to him, as ſince that time it hath likewiſe done to me.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:63097:66"/>I had alſo, if I miſremember not, another Vial, corroded by a diſtilled Liquor of Vitriol, that had in it more of the Phlegm than of the Oil; which you will ſomewhat the leſs wonder at, if you conſider, that ſome Corroſive <hi>Menſtruums</hi> will ſcarce work on ſome Bodys, if they be too well dephlegmed, or at leaſt will not corrode them ſo readily and powerfully, if they are very ſtrong, as when they are diluted with a convenient quantity of Water. And, as to Oil of Vitriol it ſelf, which is the <hi>Menſtruum</hi> I am ſpeaking of, when we employ it to make <hi>Vitriolum Martis,</hi> we are wont to weaken it with Water, that it may the better diſſolve that Metal. And perhaps you will ſuſpect, that Vitriol has ſome pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar faculty of penetrating and fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Glaſs, when to the Experiment newly recited I ſhall add that which follows, as I find it regiſtred among my Notes.</p>
               <p>[A pound of <hi>Dantzick</hi> Vitriol and a pound of Sea Salt, after the former had been very lightly calcined, and the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:63097:66"/>
latter decrepitated, that they might not boil in, or crack the Veſſel; we cauſed to be diſtilled in a well coated Retort by degrees of Fire, giving at length a very ſtrong one, then taking off the Veſſel, we were not much ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized to find, that the heat had here and there melted it, and that the fluxed <hi>Caput Mortuum</hi> had corroded the Glaſs, fetching off as 'twere films from it, and thoſe parts which did not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to the Eye thus manifeſtly waſted, ſeemed yet by their great brittleneſs, to have been penetrated, ſo that their Texture was ſpoiled by the ſaline and vitriolate Corpuſcles.]</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Prop II.</hi> Common Glaſs is not ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily permeable by Chymical Liquors, though ſtrong and ſubtile, nor by the directly viſible or odorable Expira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Bodies tho abſolutely ſpeaking it be pervious to ſome Corporeal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</q>
               <p>This Propoſition conſiſting of two parts, we ſhall allow each of them its diſtinct Proofs.</p>
               <p>And as for the firſt part, 'tis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:63097:67"/>
agreeable to the Common Experience of Chymiſts; who dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find, that in well ſtopt Vials, or at leaſt in Hermetically ſeal'd Glaſſes, they can preſerve their ſubtileſt and moſt piercing <hi>Menſtruums,</hi> as Spirit of <hi>Nitre, Aqua Fortis,</hi> Spirit of Salt, Spirit of Vinegar, and Oil of Vitriol. And this they find to be true, not only as to Acid and Corroſive Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors, like thoſe I have newly nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but alſo in thoſe Spirits that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound with Fugitive Salts, as the Spirit of Urine, of Blood, and of <hi>Sal-Armoniack</hi>; and in the moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile &amp; highly rectified Spirit of Wine; as alſo in the Ethereal Oil, or, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny call it, Spirit, of Turpentine: as likewiſe in the Liquors of Salt of Tartar, and other fixt Alcalies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved by <hi>Deliquium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Reſult of theſe Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may be much confirmed by conſidering, how often it happens in the Deſtillation of more Wild and Fugitive Spirits, as of Nitre, Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and Sugar; that, though they
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:63097:67"/>
are much agitated, and perhaps ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilized, by Heat, yet, if the Lute, that joins the Receiver to the Retort be very firm &amp; cloſe, the Receivers, though large, are often broken in pieces; which probably would not happen, if the Spirits could inſinuate &amp; croud themſelves, through the pores of Glaſs.</p>
               <p>But, whereas it may be pretended, that ſuch Veſſels are ſtrong and thick, I ſhall add, that I have had the Curioſity to cauſe very fine bubbles to be blown at the flame of a Lamp, purpoſly that they may be made extreamly thin, and of but a ſmall part of the thickneſs we meet with in the Veſſels made at the Glaſs houſe; and ſome of theſe I caus'd to be exactly ſtopt, and others to be Hermetically ſeal'd; but could not find, that either dry Salt of Tartar would relent in one, that was kept a good while under water, or that ſtrong Spirit of <hi>Sal Armoniack,</hi> which is one of the ſubtileſt Spirits that we know, would penetrate one of theſe thin films of Glaſs, which we kept
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:63097:68"/>
a great while immerſed in it, though to diſcover whether it would at all penetrate the thinneſt Glaſſes, we employed ſome which were of that fine ſort that is called <hi>Eſſence Vials.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe and ſome other Tryals have, I confeſs, made me very diffident of the Experiments, that have been delivered by ſome men of Note, and built upon by others, of the Permeableneſs of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Glaſs Veſſels to Chymical Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors, as, that Mercury and <hi>Aqua fortis</hi> being digeſted together in a Bolt-head may, by rubbing the outſide of the Glaſs, be made viſibly and palpably to tranſudate. Which Experiment (if my Memory do not much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive me,) I purpoſely tryed with care, but without ſucceſs.</p>
               <p>But after all this I muſt deſire, that it may be remembred, that in wording the Propoſition of the Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viouſneſs of Glaſs, I intimated that I would have it underſtood of what <hi>Ordinarily</hi> happens. For in ſome <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary</hi> caſes, which I take to be exceeding rare, I do not abſolutely
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:63097:68"/>
deny, but that the General rule may admit of Exceptions. And, if it be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to conjecture, theſe exceptions are likelieſt to take place, when the peculiar Texture of this or that Glaſs, is more ſlight or lax than ordinary; or when the Bodies that are to pervade it, are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently agitated by heat; or when, beſides a great ſubtlety, and perhaps degree of heat too, their particles chance to have a ſpecial congruity, to the relaxed Pores of that particular Glaſs they are to paſs through. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member I have ſeen, not without ſome wonder, a ſort of Glaſs of ſo ſoft and reſoluble a Texture, that Veſſels of it of a competent thickneſs, would be manifeſtly prejudiced and wrought upon by Liquors, that were not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derably Sharp or Corroſive, if they were put in very hot. I have alſo heard of another ſort of Glaſſes, made in a certain Forreſt, complained of by a Deſtiller, as ſubject to be ſometimes injured by Corroſive Liquors. I once knew a Doctor of Phyſick, that by divers credulous Alchymiſts was ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:63097:69"/>
to have, what they call the <hi>Philoſophers Stone,</hi> becauſe of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Book, Ingenious enough, that he was ſuppoſed to have written on that ſubject. But when after ſome acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance I happened to debate his Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples freely with him, he confeſſed to me, that he had been miſtaken, and to invite me to give him my thoughts upon ſuch like works, he frankly made me an ingenuous relation of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, wherein the main thing that dazled him, and kept him from ſeeing his Error, was, that he had reduced the matter he wrought on, which was real Gold, to that degree of Fuſible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſubtlety, that when he gave too ſtrong a Fire, as miſtake or curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity made him ſeveral times do, the finer part of the Metal would ſweat through his Glaſſes, and ſtick ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to the outſide of them, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to the Neighbouring Bodies. And, when I objected, that he might be miſtaken in this, and that what he thought had come forth by tranſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, rather iſſued out at ſome
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:63097:69"/>
ſmall unheeded crack, he replyed that he had made the obſervation ſo often, and with ſuch care, that he was fully ſatisfied it was a real penetration of the Glaſs, by the attenuated Metal, which he was to have convinced me of by Tryal. But, before he could come to make it, by an Errour of his own he unhappily died.</p>
               <p>But, whatever be judged of this penetrating Gold, I elſewhere relate, that I having upon a time deſtilled Spirit of Harts-horn with a very ſtrong Fire, into a Receiver that was large and thick enough, but of a courſe kind of Glaſs, it did appear, upon my beſt examination, that the Glaſs itſelf was penetrated by ſome vehemently agitated Fumes, or ſome ſubtile Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, that ſetled in ſtrongly ſcented drops on the outſide of the Receiver. But ſuch Inſtances being very rare, and happening but in ſome caſes or conjunctures of circumſtances, that are not like to be at all frequent, they cannot hinder the firſt part of our Propoſition to be true, in
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:63097:70"/>
the ſenſe wherein 'tis laid down.</p>
               <p>And, as to the ſecond part of the Propoſition, which <hi>aſſerts Glaſs to be pervious to ſome Corporeal ſubſtances,</hi> it may be proved <hi>ad hominem</hi> againſt any Epicurean that ſhould deny it, and the Carteſians muſt not) by the free ingreſs and egreſs, which our ſeal'd Thermoſcopes ſhew, that the Atoms or Corpuſcles of Cold and Heat are allowed, through the Pores of the Glaſs, that contains the riſing or fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lng Tincture, or other Liquor. And without proceeding upon the peculiar Principles of the Epicureans, we may give more certain proofs of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meableneſs of Glaſs by certain Bodies. For I have elſewhere manifeſtly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced that the <hi>Effluvia</hi> of a Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone will attract and invigorate Steel, though incloſed in Hermetically ſeal'd Glaſſes; nay, I have alſo ſhewn by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment, that the <hi>Effluvia</hi> of ſo groſs and dull a Body as the Earth, are readily tranſmitted through Glaſs, and will operate on Iron, in Veſſels hermeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally ſealed. If Light be, as probably
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:63097:70"/>
'tis, either a ſubtile and rapidly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Body, or at leaſt require ſuch an one for its Vehicle, it muſt not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, that 'tis poſſible for a Body without difficulty to paſs through the Pores of Glaſs; ſince 'tis by its help that we can clearly ſee the Dimenſions, Shapes, and Colours of Bodies inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Glaſſes. To this I ſhall add, that far leſs ſubtile Bodies than thoſe that conſtitute or convey Light, may be made to permeate Glaſs, if their Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures being congruous enough to the Pores of it, their penetration be aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by an impetuous motion, or a brisk impulſe; as I have found by the increaſe of weight in ſome Metals, expoſed for divers hours in Hermeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally ſeal'd Glaſſes, to the action of a Flame. On which occaſion I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that having ſome years ago tryed the ſame Experiment with ſome Filings of Copper, they had indeed their colour much alter'd, being beautified with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding vivid Dyes, which they yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, but did not evidently appear to be increaſed in weight, as if, becauſe
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:63097:71"/>
they were not of a Texture looſe enough to be melted, the Igneous particles could not pierce them enough to ſtick faſt in them, at leaſt in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers great enough, to amount to a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible weight.</p>
               <p>But without the help of Fire, or any ſenſible Heat, I think it not impoſſible that Glaſs ſhould be freely penetrated by ſome kind of Corpuſcles, (though I do not yet know of what ſort they are) that ſometimes happen to roave about in the Air. This you will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably be ſurprized to read; but perhaps not more than I was at the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> that induce me to write it. But becauſe theſe are very unuſual, and can ſcarce be diſcourſed of without ſome odd reflections hinted by them, I thought fit to ſet down a Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial account of them in another Paper, to which it more directly belongs than to this Eſſay; and therefore ſhall now only tell you, what may be ſufficient for my preſent purpoſe, namely, that having in two or three Vials cloſely ſtopt, kept a certain limpid and colour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:63097:71"/>
Liquor, it would by fits acquire and loſe a high Colour, though I could not reaſonably impute the Changes to any manifeſt ones in the Air, nor to any other cauſe ſo proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as the Ingreſs and Receſs of ſome very ſubtle and uncommon particles, which at that time happened to ſwim to and fro in the Air, and now and then to invade, and ſometimes to deſert, the Liquor.</p>
               <p>There is another ſort of Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments relating to the Poroſity of Glaſs, to ſhew that it may be pierced into by Bodies that are not corroſive in taſt, and are not Liquors, but only have a forced and temporary Fluidity, if they have ſo much as that.</p>
               <p>Theſe Experiments may be drawn from <hi>ſome of the ways</hi> of colouring Panes of Glaſs, for the Windows of Churches and other buildings; I ſay, <hi>ſome of the ways,</hi> becauſe, to deal can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly with you, I think, and ſo I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume will you ere long, that in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of thoſe Glaſſes, the Colour doth not pierce at all deep into the Glaſs,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:63097:72"/>
but is produced by the cloſe adheſion of a deep Red, but thin and tranſparent, Pigment, to the ſurface of a Glaſſy Plate, through both which the Beams of Light paſſing to the Eye, receive in their Paſſage the colour of the Pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>But, as by ſome operations the Glaſs is rather Painted, or externally enamelled, than tinged, ſo in ſome others the Pigment or dying ſtuff ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to pierce a little beneath the very <hi>ſuperficies</hi> of the Glaſs, and the Yellow Colour will not only go fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or deeper, but ſometimes ſeems (for I do not yet poſitively affirm it) to penetrate the whole Glaſs from ſide to ſide.</p>
               <p>The Methods of Painting and ſtaining Glaſs, having been hitherto the Practices of a particular Trade that is gainful enough, and known but to few, the Artificers are wont to be ſhy of communicating their ſecrets, thô we know in general that Glaſs is ſtained, by having the Plates covered with Mineral Pigments, laid on Beds of
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:63097:72"/>
beaten Lime, or ſome other conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Powder, and kept for divers Hours in a ſtrong fire, but yet not ſtrong enough to make the Plates melt down, by which means the Pores of the Glaſs being much opened by the Heat, and the Pigments being likewiſe agitated, and ſome of them as it were vitrified with it, they are made either to pierce into the Plate, or at leaſt to ſtick very cloſely and firmly to it. But becauſe the Practices of Glaſs Painters require, beſides skill and experience, a particular Furnace, and divers Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements, I ſhall add, that to try, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Glaſs may not, without ſo much ado, be ſo ſtained, as to ſhew it to be Porous, we took prepared Silver, (that Metal having, of all the Minerals I have tryed, the beſt Ingreſs into Glaſs) and having laid it upon a piece of Glaſs, not thick, nor yet ſo thin as to Melt very eaſily, we laid this Glaſs (with the Pigment uppermoſt) wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily upon a few Quick-coals, and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuffered it to neal a while we gave it about ſuch a degree of heat, as might
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:63097:73"/>
make and keep it red hot, without bringing it to compleat fuſion, and then, ſuffering it to cool by degrees, we found, as we expected, that the Glaſs had acquired a Yellow, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Golden, Colour, which was not to be waſhed off, or to be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, without ſuch ſcraping as would injure or ſpoil the Glaſs it ſelf. The way of preparing Silver for this ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, is not always the ſame, the Glaſs Painters commonly add to the calcined Silver ſome Mineral Bodies, as Antimony, Yellow Oker, or the like. But I, who take the penetration of the colour to proceed from the Silver it ſelf, do ſometimes imploy only ſome thin piece of Silver, ſuch as an old Groat, upon which a little Sulphur being put, and kindled in the open Air, the Metal is preſently calcined, and the Powder made uſe of. And this it ſelf I do not ſo much out of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, as becauſe the Calcination re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces the Metal into ſmall parts, and gives it a form, that makes it more eaſy be laid on, as one thinks fit. For
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:63097:73"/>
otherwiſe, going upon this my ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the Silver was the true Pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Glaſs, I have more than once made Glaſs Yellow by Leaf-Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver laid flat on the ſurface of it, and a little moiſtened, to keep ſo light a Body from being blown off. And (to note that upon the by) 'tis pretty, that if the Fire be made too ſtrong, which 'tis hard to avoid doing, when we will make it ſtrong enough, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of a Furnace, it has ſeveral times happened to me that the dyed Glaſs, though when held againſt the Light it appeared of a Golden or Yellow Colour, yet when held from the Light it appeared Blew, ſo that here we have in a Mineral, ſomewhat that is very like that we admire in the tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of <hi>Lignum Nephriticum,</hi> which ſhews almoſt the like difference of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, as 'tis held againſt or from the Light, which may ſerve for a confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of what I have elſewhere ſaid to ſhew that colours may be derived from Mechanical Principles: But that only upon the by. Whether the Gold
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:63097:74"/>
colour produced by Silver, do favour the hopes of thoſe Alchymiſts that work on that Metal, upon preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that 'tis but unripe Gold, 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper here to examine. But ſince Yellow is not the Colour of Silver, it ſeems the Yellowneſs, acquired by our Glaſs Plates, argues, that there has been ſome ingreſs of the ſubſtance of the particles of the Silver into the Glaſs, there appearing no way ſo ready, to give an account of the change of Colours, as by ſuppoſing the Particles of the Silver to be wrought on by the fixt Salts, and other fine parts, of the Glaſs; ſince we know, that Metals may afford differing colours, according to the Saline and other Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies that work upon them, as Copper with Spirit of Urine, which abounds in Volatile Salt, gives a deep Blew; with Spirit of Salt, a fair Green; and with <hi>Aqua fortis,</hi> a Colour that participates of both. And in the making of Glaſs of Lead with <hi>Minium</hi> and White-Sand, or Cryſtal, the Glaſs, it ſelf if well made, is uſually of an Amethyſtine Colour. But
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:63097:74"/>
if you put a due Proportion, (which is a very ſmall one,) of calcined Copper to it, this Metal will not communicate to the Glaſs its own reddiſhneſs, but be ſo changed by it, as to give it a good green, and ſometimes ſo good an one, that pieces of this Glaſs, ſuch as we have cauſed to be cut and ſet in Rings, might, among thoſe that Judge of Stones but by the Eye, paſs for no bad <hi>Emeraulds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On this occaſion, 'tis likely 'twill be asked, whether there be any way of tinging Glaſſes quite through, with a true and beautiful red, and whether the Art of dying Plates of Glaſs, which the windows of many old Churches ſhew to have formerly been practiſed, be now (as 'tis commonly ſuppoſed) altogether loſt?</p>
               <p>This Queſtion, conſiſting of 2 Parts, I ſhall quickly diſpatch; the former, by anſwering it without heſitancy in the affirmative. Yet adding withal, that the red tincture being communicated to Glaſs, not properly by mere penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Pigment, but by the incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:63097:75"/>
of it with Glaſs or its Materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, by the help of fuſion, I think the Experiment of no ſuch great uſe in our preſent Inquiry, as to hinder me from reſerving what I have obſerved about it to a more opportune place. And as to the ſecond Part of the inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, it being rather a Hiſtorical than a Philoſophical queſtion, I ſhall not here meddle with it; only I ſhall wiſh the queſtion may be cautiouſly ſtated. For, upon the burning the famous Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> many pieces of the red Glaſs that adorned the windows, were found broken and ſcattered about, ſome of which I procur'd from a Chymiſt, that had carefully preſerved them, deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to retrieve the loſt Invention of making the like. But when I came to examine them narrowly, I was confirmed in the ſuſpicion I had, that the redneſs did not penetrate the whole Glaſs, but proceeded from a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aphanous Pigment very artificially laid on, for though in other Poſtures no ſuch thing could be diſcerned, yet
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:63097:75"/>
when I ſo held it, according to my Cuſtom in examining painted Glaſſes, that the ſurfaces of the Plate lay in the ſame level with my Eye, between it and the window, ſo that a broken edge was next my Eye, I could plainly ſee, and made the Chymiſt himſelf ſee, the lower part of the Plate to be of ordinary uncoloured Glaſs, upon which there lay a very thin Plate or Bed of a Diaphanous red Pigment, which, though it were not eaſily, was not impoſſible to be here and there ſcraped off.</p>
               <p>But, to return to thoſe colorations that ſeem to pierce into the Pores of Glaſs, I remember that I had once oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to deſtil in a ſmall Retort ſome Gold, amalgamed with ſuch a fine and ſubtile Mercury, that being (without the addition of any Salt) put to the Gold in the cold, they preſently grew hot together. And in the deſtillation of this uncommon mixture, I found the matter had, before it flew a way, permanently died or ſtained, about an Inch in Diameter of the bottom of the
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:63097:76"/>
Glaſs, with a colour that, looked on from the Light, was like that of the better ſort of Turquoiſes; but beheld when 'twas interpoſed between the Window and the Eye, appeared of a ſomewhat Golden colour. And this Glaſs, with ſome others oddly colored, I have yet by me to ſatisfy the Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, though I cannot but give Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement, that the colorations of Glaſs may be much better performed with ſuch Plates, and in ſuch Furnaces, as the Glaſs Painters uſe, than without them.</p>
               <p>Since the Writing of the foregoing Paragraph, I was viſited by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious perſon, much addicted to ſome Chymical Operations, who had formerly adviſed with me about a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, of which I had had ſome Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that he conceived might be uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to him. I then acquainted him with ſome of my thoughts about it, and he having afterwards united Gold with Quick-Silver, (which by its Effects will be eaſily concluded not to have been common,) he kept them in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:63097:76"/>
for ſome Months, &amp; afterwards coming to me with a Melancholy look, told me that the Fire having been once immoderately increaſed in his abſence, the ſealed-Glaſs burſt with an affrighting noiſe, and the included Amalgam was ſo ſtrangely diſſipated, that ſcarce the leſt fragment of it could be retrieved. But the Decoction hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing continued ſo long a time, it ſeems the matter was ſubtiliated enough to have a notable operation upon the Glaſs. For, though the upper part of the Bolt-glaſs were blown of, and ſhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into many pieces, yet the lower part ſcaped well enough, and when he brought it me, to obſerve what change had been made in it, I took notice with much delight, that the Glaſs ſeemed to be tinged throughout, with ſo fine and glorious a Red colour, that I have ſeen ſeveral Rubies themſelves, in that point, inferiour to it.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
