<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of the cause of attraction by suction a paradox / by the Honourable Robert Boyle ...</title>
            <author>Boyle, Robert, 1627-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-01">2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29012</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4008</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36504</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15713749</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15713749</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104481</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A29012)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104481)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1179:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of the cause of attraction by suction a paradox / by the Honourable Robert Boyle ...</title>
                  <author>Boyle, Robert, 1627-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 67 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Godbid, and are to be sold by Moses Pitt ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Vacuum --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-05</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104481:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104481:1"/>
            <p>OF THE
CAUSE
OF
<hi>ATTRACTION</hi>
BY
Suction,
A
PARADOX.</p>
            <p>By the Honourable
<hi>ROBERT BOYLE,</hi>
Fellow of the <hi>Royal Society.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed by <hi>William Godbid,</hi> and are to
be Sold by <hi>Moſes Pitt,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> over
againſt the little North Door of
St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church. 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:104481:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104481:2"/>
            <head>PREFACE.</head>
            <p>HAving about twelve years ago
ſummarily expreſt and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd
my Opinion of the Cauſe
of <hi>Suction,</hi> and a while be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
or after brought to the <hi>Royal Society</hi>
the Glaſs Inſtrument I employ'd to make it
out; I deſiſted for ſome time to add any thing
about a Problem, that I had but occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionally
handled: Only, becauſe the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
I mention'd in my <hi>Examen</hi> of
Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi>'s Opinion, and afterwards
us'd at <hi>Greſham-College,</hi> was difficult
enough to be well made, and not to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd
ready made, I did for the ſake of
ſome <hi>Virtuoſi,</hi> that were curious of ſuch
things, deviſe a ſlight and eaſily made
Inſtrument, deſcrib'd in the following
Tract, Chap. <hi>4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>,</hi> in which the chief <hi>Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomena,</hi>
I ſhew'd before the <hi>Society,</hi>
were eaſily producible. But afterwards
the miſtakes and erroneous Opinions,
<pb facs="tcp:104481:3"/>
that, in Print as well as in Diſcourſe, I
met with, even among Learned Men,
about <hi>Suction,</hi> and the Curioſity of an
Ingenious Perſon, engaged me to reſume
that Subject and treat of it, as if I had
never before meddled with it, for the
reaſon intimated in the beginning of the
inſuing Paper. And finding upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view
of my later <hi>Animadverſions</hi> on
Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi>'s <hi>Problemata de Vacuo,</hi>
that ſome paſſages of this Tract are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd
to there; I ſaw my ſelf thereby
little leſs than engaged to annex that
Diſcourſe to thoſe Animadverſions. And
this I the rather conſented to, becauſe it
contains ſome Experiments, that I have
not elſewhere met with, which, together
with ſome other parts of that <hi>Eſſay,</hi> may,
I hope, prove of ſome uſe to illuſtrate and
confirm our Doctrine about the Weight
and Spring of the Air, and ſupply the
leſs experienced than ingenious Friends
to our Hypotheſis with more grounds of
anſwering the later Objections of ſome
Learned Men, againſt whoſe endeavours
I perceive it will be uſeful to employ va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety
of Experiments and other Proofs to
<pb facs="tcp:104481:3"/>
evince the ſame Truth; that <hi>ſome or
other</hi> of theſe may meet with thoſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments
or evaſions with which they ſtrive
to elude the force of <hi>the reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Title of the following Eſſay may
ſufficiently keep the Reader from expecting
to find any other kind of <hi>Attraction</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours'd
of, than that which is made by
<hi>Suction.</hi> But yet thus much I ſhall here
intimate in general, that I have found by
Trials purpoſely made, that the Examples
of <hi>Suction</hi> are not the only noted ones of
<hi>Attraction,</hi> that may be reduced to
<hi>Pulſion.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="tcp:104481:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104481:4"/>OF THE
CAUSE
OF
Attraction by SUCTION,
A
PARADOX.</head>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. I.</head>
            <p>I Might, <hi>Sir,</hi> ſave my ſelf ſome
trouble in giving you that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
you deſire of me about
<hi>Suction,</hi> by referring you to a
paſſage in the <hi>Examen,</hi> I long ſince
writ, of Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi>'s <hi>Dialogus Phyſicus
de Natura Aeris,</hi> if I knew, you had
thoſe two Books lying by you. But
becauſe I ſuſpect, that my <hi>Examen</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:104481:5"/>
may not be in your hands, ſince 'tis
almoſt out of Print, and has not for
ſome years been in my own; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
I do not ſo well remember, after
ſo long a time, the particulars that
I writ there, about Suction, as I do
in general, that the <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed,
was very incidentally and
briefly diſcours'd of, upon an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
miniſtred by a wrong Explication
given of Suction by Mr. <hi>Hobbes,</hi> I
ſhall here decline referring you to
what I there writ; and propoſing to
you thoſe thoughts about Suction,
that I remember I there pointed at,
I ſhall annex ſome things to illuſtrate
and confirm them, that would not
have been ſo proper for me to have
inſiſted on in a ſhort and but occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſional
Excurſion.</p>
            <p>And I ſhould immediately proceed
to what you expect from me, but
that <hi>Suction</hi> being generally look'd
upon as a kind of <hi>Attraction,</hi> it will
be requiſite for me to premiſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
about <hi>Attraction</hi> it ſelf. For,
beſides that the Cauſe of it, which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104481:5"/>
I here diſpute not of, is obſcure, the
very Nature and Notion of it is wont
by Naturaliſts to be either left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touch'd,
or but very darkly deliver'd,
and therefore will not be unfit to be
here ſomewhat explain'd.</p>
            <p>How general and ancient ſoever
the common Opinion may be, that
<hi>Attraction</hi> is a kind of Motion quite
differing from <hi>Pulſion,</hi> if not alſo op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite
to it; yet I confeſs, I concur
in opinion, though not altogether
upon the ſame grounds, with ſome
modern Naturaliſts, that think At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction
a <hi>Species</hi> of Pulſion. And at
leaſt among inanimate Bodies I have
not yet obſerved any thing, that
convinces me, that Attraction cannot
be reduced to Pulſion; for, theſe two
ſeem to me to be but extrinſical deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations
of the ſame Local Motion,
in which, if a moved Body <hi>precede</hi>
the Movent, or tend to acquire a
greater diſtance from it, we call it
<hi>Pulſion;</hi> and if, upon the ſcore of the
Motion, the ſame Body <hi>follow</hi> the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
or approach to it, we call it
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104481:6"/>
               <hi>Attraction.</hi> But this difference may
conſiſt but in an <hi>accidental</hi> reſpect,
which does not <hi>Phyſically</hi> alter the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
of the Motion, but is founded
upon the reſpect, which the Line,
wherein the Motion is made, happens
to have to the ſituation of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent.
And that which ſeems to me
to have been the chief cauſe of mens
miſtaking Attraction for a motion op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite
to Pulſion, is, that they have
look'd upon both the moving and
moved Bodies, in too popular and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficial
a manner; and conſider'd
in the <hi>Movent</hi> rather the ſituation
of the conſpicuous and more bulky
part of the Animal or other Agent,
than the ſituation of that part of the
Animal, or Inſtrument, that does
immediately impreſs that motion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the <hi>Mobile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For thoſe that attentively heed this,
may eaſily take notice, that ſome part
of that Body, or of the Inſtrument,
which by reaſon of their conjunction
in this operation is to be look'd on
but as making one with it, is really
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104481:6"/>
placed behind ſome part of the Body
to be drawn, and therefore cannot
move outwards it ſelf without thru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting
that Body forward. This will
be eaſily underſtood, if we conſider,
what happens when a Man draws a
Chain after him; for, though his
Body do <hi>precede</hi> the Chain, yet his
finger or ſome other part of the hand,
wherewith he draws it, has ſome
part or other that reaches <hi>behind</hi> the
fore part of the firſt Link, and the
hinder part of this Link comes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind
the anteriour part of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
Link; and ſo each Link has one
of its parts placed behind ſome part
of the Link next after it, 'till you
come to the laſt Link of all. And ſo,
as the finger, that is in the firſt Link,
cannot move forwards but it muſt
thruſt on that Link, by this <hi>Series</hi> of
Truſions the whole Chain is moved
forwards; and if any other Body be
drawn by that Chain, you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,
that ſome part of the laſt Link
comes behind ſome part of that Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
or of ſome intervening Body,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104481:7"/>
which, by its coheſion with it, ought
in our preſent caſe to be conſider'd as
part of it. And thus <hi>Attraction</hi> ſeems
to be but a <hi>Species</hi> of <hi>Pulſion,</hi> and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually
belongs to that kind of it,
which, for diſtinctions ſake, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<hi>Truſion,</hi> by which we underſtand
that kind of Pulſion, wherein the
Movent goes along with the moved
Body without quitting it whilſt the
progreſs laſts; as it happens, when
a Gardiner drives his Wheel-barrow
before him without letting go his
hold of it.</p>
            <p>But I muſt not here diſſemble a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty,
that I foreſee may be ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
urged againſt this account of
Attraction. For it may be ſaid, that
there are Attractions, where it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
be pretended, that any part of
the <hi>Attrahent</hi> comes behind the <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted</hi>
Body; as in <hi>Magnetical</hi> and
<hi>Electrical</hi> Attractions, and in that
which is made of Water, when 'tis
drawn up into Springs and Pumps.</p>
            <p>I need not tell you, that you know
ſo well, as that partly the <hi>Carteſians,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:104481:7"/>
and partly other Modern Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,
have recourſe on this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
either to <hi>ſcrewed</hi> Particles and
other Magnetical Emiſſions, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate
<hi>Phaenomena</hi> of this kind. And,
according to ſuch <hi>Hypotheſes,</hi> one may
ſay, that many of theſe Magnetical
and Electrical <hi>Effluvia</hi> come behind
ſome parts of the attracted Bodies,
or at leaſt of the little ſolid Particles,
that are as it were the Walls of their
Pores, or procure ſome diſcuſſion of
the Air, that may make it thruſt the
Moveable towards the Loadſtone or
Amber, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But if there were none
of theſe, nor any other ſubtil Agents
that cauſe this Motion by a real,
though unperceived, Pulſion; I ſhould
make a diſtinction betwixt other At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions
and theſe, which I ſhould
then ſtile <hi>Attraction by Inviſibles.</hi>
But, whether there be really any
ſuch in Nature, and why I ſcruple
to admit things ſo hard to be concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
may be elſewhere conſider'd.
And you will, I preſume, the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier
allow me this liberty, if, (ſince
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104481:8"/>
in this place 'tis proper to do it,) I
ſhew you, that in the laſt of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances
I formerly objected (that of
the drawing up of Water into the
Barrel of a Syringe,) there is no true
Attraction of the Liquor made by the
external Air. I ſay then, that by
the aſcending Rammer, as a part of
which I here conſider the obtuſe end,
Plug, or Sucker, there is no Attra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
made of the contiguous and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent
Water, but only there is room
made for it, to riſe into, without
being expos'd to the preſſure of the
ſupeiour Air. For, if we ſuppoſe
the whole Rammer to be by Divine
Omnipotence annihilated, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently
uncapable of exerciſing any
Attraction; yet, provided the ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour
Air were kept off from the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
by any other way as well as 'twas
by the Rammer, the Liquor would
as well aſcend into the Cavity of
the Barrel; ſince, (as I have elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where
abundantly proved,) the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face
of the Terraqueous Globe being
continually preſs'd on by the incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104481:8"/>
Air or Atmoſphere, the Water
muſt be by that preſſure impell'd into
any cavity here below, where there
is no Air to reſiſt it; as by our Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
there is not in the Barrel of
our Syringe, when the Rammer, or
whatever elſe was in it, had been
annihilated. Which Reaſoning may
be ſufficiently confirm'd by an Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment,
whereby I have more than
once ſhewn ſome curious perſons,
that, if the external Air, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
its preſſure, be withdrawn
from about the Syringe, one may
pull up the Sucker as much as he
pleaſes, without drawing up after it
the ſubjacent Water. In ſhort, let
us ſuppoſe, that a Man ſtanding in
an inner room does by his utmoſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance
keep ſhut a Door, that is
neither lock'd nor latch'd, againſt
another, who with equal force en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours
to thruſt it open: In this
caſe, <hi>as</hi> if one ſhould forcibly pull
away the firſt Man, it could not be
ſaid, that this Man, by his receſs
from the Door he endeavoured to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104481:9"/>
preſs outwards, did truely and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly
draw in his Antagoniſt, though
upon that receſs the coming in of his
Antagoniſt would preſently enſue;
<hi>ſo</hi> it cannot properly be ſaid, that by
the aſcent of the Rammer, which
diſplaces the ſuperiour Air, either the
Rammer it ſelf, or the expelled Air,
does properly <hi>attract</hi> the ſubjacent
Water, though the ingreſs of that
Liquor into the Barrel does there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
neceſſarily enſue. And that, as
the Compariſon ſuppoſes, there is a
preſſure of the ſuperiour Air againſt
the upper part of the Sucker, you
may eaſily perceive, if having well
ſtopt the lower orifice of the Syringe
with your finger, you forcibly draw
up the Sucker to the top of the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel.
For if then you let go the Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,
you will find it impell'd down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
by the incumbent Air with a
notable force.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:104481:9"/>
            <head>CHAP. II.</head>
            <p>HAving thus premis'd ſomething
in general about the Nature of
<hi>Attraction,</hi> as far as 'tis neceſſary
for my preſent deſign; it will be now
ſeaſonable to proceed to the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
of that kind of Attraction,
that is employed to raiſe Liquors,
and is by a diſtinct Name called
<hi>Suction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About the Cauſe of this there is
great contention between the New
Philoſophers; as they are ſtiled, and
the Peripateticks. For the Followers
of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and many Learned Men
that in other things diſſent from him,
aſcribe the aſcenſion of Liquors upon
<hi>Suction</hi> to Natures abhorrence of a
<hi>Vacuum.</hi> For, ſay they, when a Man
dips one end of a Straw or Reed into
ſtagnant Water, and ſucks at the
other end, the Air contain'd in the
cavity of the Reed paſſes into that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104481:10"/>
of his Lungs, and conſequently the
Reed would be left empty, if no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Body ſucceeded in the place it
deſerts; but there are only (that they
take notice of,) two Bodies that can
ſucceed, the Air and the (groſſer Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor)
the Water; and the Air can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
do it, becauſe of the interpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the Water, that denies it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs
to the immers'd orifice of the
Reed, and therefore it muſt be the
Water it ſelf, which accordingly does
aſcend to prevent a <hi>Vacuum</hi> deteſted
by Nature.</p>
            <p>But many of the Modern Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,
and generally all the <hi>Corpuſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larians,</hi>
look upon this <hi>Fuga Vacui</hi> as
but an imaginary Cauſe of <hi>Suction,</hi>
though they do it upon very differing
grounds. For, the <hi>Atomiſts,</hi> that
willingly admit of Vacuities, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly
ſo called, both within and
without our World, cannot think
that Nature hates or fears a <hi>Vacuum,</hi>
and declines her uſual courſe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
it: And the <hi>Carteſians,</hi> though
they do, as well as the <hi>Peripateticks,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:104481:10"/>
deny that there is a <hi>Vacuum,</hi> yet
ſince they affirm not only, that there
<hi>is</hi> none <hi>in rerum Natura,</hi> but that
there <hi>can be</hi> none, becauſe what O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
call an empty Space having
three Dimenſions, hath all that they
think belonging to the Eſſence of a
<hi>Body,</hi> they will not grant Nature to
be ſo indiſcreet, as to ſtrain her ſelf
to prevent the making of a thing that
is impoſſible to be made.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Peripatetic</hi> Opinion about the
Cauſe of Suction, though commonly
defended by the Schools, as well Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern
as Ancient, ſuppoſes in Nature
ſuch an abhorrence of a <hi>Vacuum,</hi> as
neither has been well proved, nor
does well agree with the lately diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd
Phaenomenon of <hi>Suction.</hi> For,
according to their <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> Water
and other Liquors ſhould aſcend upon
Suction to any hight to prevent a <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuum,</hi>
which yet is not agreeable to
experience. For I have carefully
tryed, that by pumping with a Pump
far more ſtanch than thoſe that are
uſually made, and indeed as well
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104481:11"/>
clos'd as we could poſſibly bring it to
be, we could not by all our endeavours
raiſe Water by Suction to
above<note n="*" place="margin">See Cont. of Phyſ. Mech. Exp. the 15th Exp.</note> 36½ foot. The <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricellian</hi>
Exp<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhews, that
the weight of the Air is able to ſuſtain,
and ſome of our Experim<hi rend="sup">ts</hi> ſhew, 'tis
able to raiſe a Mercurial Cylinder e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual
in weight to as high a Cylinder
of Water as we were able to raiſe by
pumping. For Mercury being near 14
times as heavy as Water of the ſame
bulk, if the weight of the Air be
equivalent to that of a Mercurial
Cylinder of 29 or 30 Inches, it muſt
be able to counterpoiſe a Cylinder of
Water near fourteen times as long,
that is, from thirty four to near thirty
ſix foot. And very diſagreeable to
the common <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> but conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
to ours, is the Experiment that
I have more than once tryed, and I
think elſewhere deliver'd, namely,
That, if you take a Glaſs Pipe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
three foot long, and, dipping
one end of it in Water, ſuck at the
other, the Water will be ſuddenly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104481:11"/>
made to flow briskly into your
mouth: But, if inſtead of Water
you dip the lower end into Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver,
though you ſuck as ſtrongly
as ever you can, provided that in
this caſe, as in the former, you hold
the Pipe upright, you will never be
able to ſuck up the Quickſilver near
ſo high as your mouth; ſo that if the
Water aſcended upon Suction to the
top of the ſame Pipe, becauſe elſe
there would have been a <hi>Vacuum</hi> left
in the cavity of it, why ſhould not
we conclude, that, when we have
ſuckt up the Quickſilver as ſtrongly
as we can, as much of the upper part
of the Tube as is deſerted by the Air,
and yet not fill'd by the Mercury, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits,
in part at leaſt, a <hi>Vacuum,</hi> (as
to Air) of which conſequently Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
cannot reaſonably be ſuppos'd to
have ſo great and unlimited an abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency,
as the <hi>Peripateticks</hi> and their
Adherents preſume. Yet I will not
determine, whether there be any
more than many little Vacuities, or
Spaces devoid of Air, in the Cavity,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104481:12"/>
ſo called, of the Pipe unfill'd by the
Mercury; (ſo that the whole Cavity is
not one entire empty Space;) it being
ſufficient for my purpoſe, that my
Experiment affords a good Argument
<hi>ad hominem</hi> againſt the <hi>Peripateticks,</hi>
and warrants us to ſeek for ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Cauſe than the <hi>fuga Vacui,</hi> why
a much ſtronger Suction than that,
which made Water aſcend with eaſe
into the Suckers mouth, will not alſo
raiſe Quickſilver to the ſame height
or near it.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Modern Philoſophers that
admit not the <hi>fuga Vocui</hi> to be the
Cauſe of the raiſing of Liquors in
Suction, do generally enough agree
in referring it to the action of the
Suckers <hi>thorax.</hi> For, when a Man en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours
to ſuck up a Liquor, he does
by means of the Muſcles enlarge the
cavity of his Cheſt, which he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
do but at the ſame time he muſt
thruſt away thoſe parts of the ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
Air that were contiguous to his
Cheſt, and the diſplac'd Air does,
according to ſome Learned Men,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104481:12"/>
(therein, if I miſtake not, Followers
of <hi>Gaſſendus,</hi>) compreſs the contiguous
Air, and that the next to it, and ſo
outwards, 'till the preſſure, ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively
paſſing from one part of the
Air to the other, arrive at the ſurface
of the Liquor; and all other places
being as to ſenſe full, the impell'd Air
cannot find place but by thruſting the
Water into the room made for it in
the Pipe by the receſs of the Air that
paſs'd into the Suckers lungs. And
they differ'd not much from this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication,
that, without taking in
the compreſſion of the ambient Air
made by the <hi>thorax,</hi> refer the Phaeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menon
to the propagated motion or
impulſe, that is impreſt on the Air diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plac'd
by the <hi>thorax</hi> in its dilatation,
and yet unable to move in a World
perfectly fill'd, as they ſuppoſe ours
to be, unleſs the Liquor be impell'd
into as much of the cavity of the
Pipe, as faſt as 'tis deſerted by the
Air that is ſaid to be ſuck'd up. But
though I readily confeſs this Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
to be ingenious, and ſuch as I
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104481:13"/>
wonder not they ſhould acquieſs in,
who are acquainted but with the
long known and obvious <hi>Phaenomena</hi>
of Suction; and though I am not
ſure, but that in the moſt familiar
caſes the Cauſes aſſign'd by them may
contribute to the Effect; yet, preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
for <hi>Carteſius</hi> and <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> the
reſpect I willingly pay ſuch great Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers,
I muſt take the liberty to
tell you, that I cannot acquieſs in
their Theory. For I think, that the
Cauſe of <hi>Suction,</hi> they aſſign, is in
many caſes not neceſſary, in others,
not ſufficient. And <hi>firſt,</hi> as to the
Condenſation of the Air by the dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
of the Suckers Cheſt; when I
conſider the extent of the ambient
Air, and how ſmall a compreſſion
no greater an expanſion than that of
the <hi>Thorax</hi> is like to make, I can
ſcarce think, ſo ſlight a condenſation
of the free Air can have ſo conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
an operation on the ſurface of
the Liquor to be rais'd, as the <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis</hi>
I examin requires: And that
this impulſe of the Air by a Suckers
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104481:13"/>
dilated <hi>Thorax,</hi> though it be wont to
accompany the aſcenſion of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
procured by Suction, yet is not of
abſolute neceſſity to it, will, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume,
be eaſily granted, if it can be
made out, that even a propagated
<hi>Pulſion,</hi> abſtracted from any Conden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation
of Air, is not ſo neceſſarily the
Cauſe of it, but that the Effect may
be produc'd without it. For ſuppoſe,
that by Divine Omnipotence ſo much
Air as is diſplac'd by the <hi>Thorax</hi> were
annihilated; yet I ſee not, why the
Aſcenſion of the Liquor ſhould not
enſue. For, when a Man begins to
ſuck, there is an <hi>Aequilibrium,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Aequipollency <hi>between</hi> the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
which the Air, contained in the
Pipe, (which is ſhut up with the
preſſure of the Atmoſphere upon it,)
has, by virtue of its <hi>Spring,</hi> upon
that part of the ſurface of the water
that is environ'd by the ſides of the
Pipe, <hi>and</hi> the preſſure which the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſpherical
Air has, by virtue of its
<hi>weight,</hi> upon all the reſt of the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face
of the ſtagnant water; ſo that,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:104481:14"/>
when by the dilatation of the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers
<hi>Thorax,</hi> the Air within the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity
of the Pipe comes to be rarified,
and conſequently looſe of its <hi>Spring,</hi>
the <hi>weight</hi> of the external Air conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing
in the mean time the ſame, it
muſt neceſſarily happen, that the
Spring of the internal Air will be
too weak to compreſs any longer the
gravitation of the external, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently,
that part of the ſurface of
the ſtagnant water, that is included
in the Pipe, being leſs preſs'd upon,
than all the other parts of the ſame
ſurfaces muſt neceſſarily give way,
where it can leaſt reſiſt, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
be impell'd up into the Pipe,
where the Air, having had its Spring
weakened by expanſion, is no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
able to reſiſt, as it did before.
This may be illuſtrated by ſomewhat
varying an Inſtance already given,
and conceiving, that within a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
three Men thruſt all together with
their utmoſt force againſt a Door,
(which we ſuppoſe to have neither
Bolt nor Latch) to keep it ſhut, at
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104481:14"/>
the ſame time the three other Men
have juſt equal ſtrength, and imploy
their force to thruſt it open. For
though, whilſt their oppoſite endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
are equal, the Door will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
to be kept ſhut, yet if one of
the three Men within the Room
ſhould go away, there will need no
new force, nor other acceſſion of
ſtrength to the three Men, to make
them prevail and thruſt open the
Door againſt the reſiſtance of thoſe
that endeavour'd to keep it ſhut,
who are now but two.</p>
            <p>And here (upon the by) you may
take notice, that, to raiſe water in
Suction, there is no neceſſity of any
rarified and forcibly ſtretch'd Rope, as
'twere, of the Air, to draw up the
ſubjacent water into the Pipe, ſince
the bare debilitation of the Spring of
the included Air may very well ſerve
the turn. And though, if we ſhould
ſuppoſe the Air within the Pipe to be
quite annihilated, it could not be
pretended (ſince it would not have
ſo much as Exiſtence) that it exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104481:15"/>
an attractive Power; yet in this
caſe the water would aſcend into the
Pipe, without the aſſiſtance of Natures
imaginary Abhorrence of a <hi>Vacuum,</hi>
but by a Mechanical Neceſſity, plainly
ariſing from this, that there would
be a preſſure of the incumbent At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſphere
upon the reſt of the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face
of the ſtagnant water, and no
preſſure at all upon that part of the
ſurface that is within the Pipe, where
conſequently there could be no reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
made to the aſcenſion of the
water, every where elſe ſtrongly
urg'd by the weight of the incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent
Air.</p>
            <p>I ſhall add on this occaſion, that,
to ſhew ſome inquiſitive Men, that
the weak reſiſtance within a Veſſel,
that had but one orifice expos'd to the
water, may much more contribute
to the aſcenſion of that Liquor into
the Veſſel, than either the compreſſion
or the continued or reflected impulſe
of the external Air; I thought fit to
produce a Phaenomenon, which by
the Beholders was without ſcruple
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:104481:15"/>
judg'd an Effect of Suction, and yet
could not be aſcrib'd to the Cauſe of
Suction, aſſign'd by either of the Sects
of Philoſophers I diſſent from. The
Experiment was this: By a way,
elſewhere deliver'd, the long neck of
a Glaſs-bubble was ſeal'd up, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
all the Air had been by Heat
driven out of the whole cavity of
the Bubble or Vial, and then the
Glaſs was laid aſide for ſome hours,
or as long as we pleas'd; afterwards
the ſeal'd <hi>apex</hi> of the neck was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
off under water: I demand now
of a <hi>Peripatetic,</hi> whether the Liquor
ought to be ſuck'd or drawn into the
cavity of the Glaſs, and why? if he
ſays, as queſtionleſs he will, that
the water would be attracted to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
a <hi>Vacuum,</hi> he would thereby ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge,
that, 'till the Glaſs was
unſtopt under water, there was ſome
empty ſpace in it; for, 'till the ſealed
end was broken off, the water could
not get in, and therefore, if the <hi>fuga
vacui</hi> had any thing to do in the aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
the Liquor muſt riſe, not to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:104481:16"/>
prevent an empty ſpace, but to fill
one that was made before. Nor does
our Experiment much more favour
the other Philoſophers, I diſſent from:
For in it there is no dilatation made
of the ſides of the Glaſs, as in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
Suction there is made of the
<hi>Thorax,</hi> but only there is ſo much
Air driven out of the cavity of the
Bubble, into whoſe room ſince nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
common Air nor Water is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
to ſucceed, it appears not, how
the propagated and returning impulſe,
or the Circle of Motion, as to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
Air and Water, does here take
place. And then I demand, what
becomes of the Air, that has been by
heat driven out, and is by the Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metical
Seal kept out of the cavity of
the Bubble? If it be ſaid, that it dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſes
it ſelf into the ambient Air,
and mingles with it, that will be
granted which I contended for, that
ſo little Air as is uſually diſplac'd in
Suction cannot make any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
compreſſion of the free ambient
Air; for, what can one Cubic Inch
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104481:16"/>
of Air, which is ſometimes more
than one of our Glaſſes contains, do,
to the condenſation ſo much as of
all the Air in the Chamber, when the
expell'd Corpuſcles are evenly diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted
among thoſe of the ambient.
And how comes this inconſiderable
condenſation to have ſo great an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
in every part of the room, as to
be able there to impel into the Glaſs
as much water in extent as the whole
Air that was driven out of the cavity
of it? But if it be ſaid, that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd
Air condens'd only the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guous
or very neighbouring Air, 'tis
eaſie to anſwer, that 'tis no way
probable, that the expell'd Particles
of the Air ſhould not by the differing
motions of the ambient Air be quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
made to mingle with it, but ſhould
rather wait (which if it did we ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
made it do for many hours) 'till
the Veſſels whence 'twas driven out
were unſtopp'd again. But, though
this could probably be pretended, it
cannot truly be aſſerted. For if you
carry the ſeal'd Glaſs quite out of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104481:17"/>
room or houſe, and unſtop it at ſome
other place, though two or three
miles diſtant; the aſcenſion of the
water will, (as I found by tryal) ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs
inſue; in which caſe I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume,
it will not be ſaid, that the Air,
that was expell'd out of the Glaſs,
and condens'd the contiguous or near
contiguous Air, attended the Bubble
in all its motions, and was ready at
hand to impel-in the water, as ſoon
as the ſeal'd <hi>apex</hi> of the Vial was
broken off. But I doubt not, but
moſt of the Embracers of the Opinion
I oppoſe, being Learned and Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous
Perſons, if they had been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted
with theſe and the like
<hi>Phaenomena,</hi> would rather have chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
their Opinion about <hi>Suction,</hi> than
have gone about to defend it by ſuch
Evaſions, which I ſhould not have
thought worth propoſing, if I had
not met with Objections of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
publickly maintain'd by a Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
Writer, on occaſion of the Air's
ruſhing into the exhauſted <hi>Magden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgic</hi>
Engine. But as in our Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104481:17"/>
theſe Objections have no place,
ſo in our <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> the Explication is
very eaſie, as will anon be intimated.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. III.</head>
            <p>HAving thus ſhewn, that the
Aſcenſion of Water upon Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
may be caus'd otherwiſe than
by the Condenſation or the propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
Pulſion of Air contiguous to the
Suckers <hi>Thorax,</hi> and thruſt out of
place by it; it remains that I ſhew,
(which was one of the two things I
chiefly intended,) that there may be
Caſes wherein the Cauſe, aſſign'd in
the <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> I am examining, will
not have place. But this will be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
underſtood, if, before I proceed
to the proof of it, I propoſe to you
the thoughts, I had many years ſince,
and do ſtill retain, about the Cauſe
of the Aſcenſion of Liquors in Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>To clear the way to the right un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:104481:18"/>
of the enſuing Diſcourſe,
it will not be amiſs here to premiſe
a ſummary intimation of ſome things
that are ſuppos'd in our <hi>Hypotheſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſuppoſe then <hi>firſt,</hi> without
diſputing either the Exiſtence or the
nature of Elementary Air, that the
Common Air we breath in, and
which I often call Atmoſpherical Air,
abounds with Corpuſcles not devoid
of Weight, and indowed with E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſticity
or Springineſs, whereby
the lower parts, compreſt by the
weight of the upper, inceſſantly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
to expand themſelves, by
which expanſion, and in proportion
to it, the Spring of the Air is wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken'd,
(as other Springs are wont to
be) the more they are permitted to
ſtretch themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Next,</hi> we ſuppoſe, that the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raqueous
Globe, being inviron'd with
this gravitating and ſpringy Air, has
its ſurface and the Bodies plac'd on it
preſt by as much of the Atmoſphere
as either perpendicularly leans on
them, or can otherwiſe come to bear
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:104481:18"/>
upon them. And this preſſure is by
the <hi>Turricellian</hi> and other Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
found to be equivalent to a
perpendicularly erected Cylinder of
about twenty nine or thirty Inches of
Quickſilver, (for the height is diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,
as the gravity of the Atmoſphere
happens to be various.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> we ſuppoſe, that, Air be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
contain'd in a Pipe or other hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
Body that has but one orifice
open to the free Air, if this orifice be
Hermetically ſeal'd, or otherwiſe (as
with the mouth of one that ſucks)
clos'd, the now included Air, whilſt
it continues without any farther ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panſion,
will have an elaſticity equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent
to the weight of as much of
the outward Air as did before preſs
againſt it. For, if the weight of
the Atmoſphere, to which it was
then expos'd, had been able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs
it further, it would have done
ſo, and then the cloſing of the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,
at which the internal and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal
Air communicated, as it fenc'd
the included Air from the preſſure
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:104481:19"/>
of the incumbent, ſo it hindred the
ſame included Air from expanding it
ſelf; ſo that, <hi>as</hi> it was ſhut up with
the preſſure of the Atmoſphere upon
it, that is in a ſtate of as great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion
as the weight of the Atmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphere
could bring it to, <hi>ſo,</hi> being
ſhut up and thereby kept from wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kening
that preſſure by expanſion,
it muſt retain a Springineſs equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollent
to the preſſure 'twas expos'd
to before, which (as I juſt now no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted)
was as great as the weight of
the incumbent Pillar of the Atmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphere
could make it. But if, as
was ſaid in the firſt Suppoſition, the
included Air ſhould come to be dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
or expanded, the Spring being
then unbent, its Spring, like that of
other elaſtical Bodies, would be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitated
anſwerably to that expan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>To me then it ſeems, that, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
in general, Liquors are upon
Suction raiſed into the cavities of
Pipes and other hollow Bodies, when,
and ſo far as, there is a leſs preſſure
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:104481:19"/>
on the ſurface of the Liquor in the
cavity, than on the ſurface of the
external Liquor that ſurrounds the
Pipe, <hi>whether</hi> that preſſure on thoſe
parts of the external Liquor, that
are from time to time impell'd up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the orifice of the Pipe, proceed
from the weight of the Atmoſphere,
<hi>or</hi> the propagated compreſſion or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe
of ſome parts of the Air, <hi>or</hi>
the Spring of the Air, <hi>or</hi> ſome other
Cauſe, as the preſſure of ſome other
Body quite diſtinct from Air.</p>
            <p>Upon the general view of this <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis,</hi>
it ſeems very conſonant to
the Mechanical Principles. For, if
there be on the differing parts of the
ſurface of a fluid Body unequal preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,
'tis plain, as well by the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
of the thing, as by what has
been demonſtrated by <hi>Archimedes,</hi> and
his Commentators, that the greater
force will prevail againſt the leſſer,
and that that part of the waters ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face
muſt give way, where it is leaſt
preſt. So that that, wherein the <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis</hi>
I venture to propoſe to you,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:104481:20"/>
differs from that which I diſſent
from, is not, that mine is leſs Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanical;
but <hi>partly</hi> in this, that,
whereas the <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> I queſtion,
ſuppoſes a neceſſity of the protruſion
or impulſe of the Air, mine does not
require that ſuppoſition, but, being
more general, reaches to other ways
of procuring the Aſcenſion of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors,
without raiſing them by the
impulſe of the Air; and <hi>partly,</hi> and
indeed chiefly, in that the <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi>
I decline, makes the Cauſe of the
Aſcenſion of Liquors to be only the
increaſed preſſure of the Air exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
to the pipe; and I chiefly make
it to depend upon the diminiſhed preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
of the Air within the pipe, on
the ſcore of the expanſion 'tis brought
to by Suction.</p>
            <p>To proceed now to ſome Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
that I made in favour of this
<hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> I ſhall begin with that
which follows:</p>
            <p>We took a Glaſs-pipe bended like a
Syphon, but ſo that the ſhorter legg
was as parallel to the longer as we
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:104481:20"/>
could get it made, and was Herme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically
ſeal'd at the end: Into this Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon
we made a ſhift (for 'tis not
very eaſie) to convey water, ſo that
the crooked part being held down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,
the liquor reach'd to the ſame
height in both the leggs, and yet
there was about an Inch and half of
uncompreſt Air ſhut up in the ſhorter
legg. This little Inſtrument (for 'twas
but about fifteen Inches long) being
thus prepar'd, 'tis plain, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to the <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> I diſſent from,
there is no reaſon, why the water
ſhould aſcend upon Suction. For,
though we ſhould admit, that the
external Air were conſiderably com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt,
or received a notable impulſe,
when the Suckers cheſt is enlarged;
yet in our caſe that compreſſion or
protruſion will not reach the ſurface
of the water in the ſhorter legg, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
it is there fenc'd from the action
of the external Air by the ſides of
the Glaſs, and the Hermetical Seal
at the top. And yet, if one ſuck'd
ſtrongly at the open orifice in the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:104481:21"/>
longer legg, the water in the ſhorter
would be depreſt; and that in the
longer aſcended at one ſuck about an
Inch and half: Of which the reaſon
is clear in our <hi>Hypotheſis.</hi> For, the
Spring of the included Air, together
with the weight of the water in the
ſhorter legg, and the preſſure of the
Atmoſpherical Air, aſſiſted by the
weight of the liquor in the longer
legg, counter-ballanced one another
before the Suction began: But, when
afterwards upon Suction the Air in
the longer legg came to be dilated
and thereby weaken'd, 'twas ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd
unable to reſiſt the undimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd
preſſure of the Air included
in the ſhorter legg, which conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
expanding it ſelf by vertue of its
Elaſticity, depreſt the contiguous
water, and made it proportionably
riſe in the oppoſite legg, 'till by the
expanſion its Spring being more and
more weaken'd, it arrived at an equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollency
with the gravitation or preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
of the Atmoſphere. Which laſt
clauſe contains the Reaſon, why, when
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:104481:21"/>
the perſon that ſuckt had rais'd the
water in the longer legg <hi>leſs than</hi> three
Inches higher by repeated endeavours
to ſuck, and that without once ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
the water to fall back again, he
was not able to elevate the water in
the longer, <hi>ſo much as</hi> three Inches
above its firſt ſtation. And if in the
ſhorter legg there was but an Inch
and a quarter of ſpace left for the
Air unfill'd by the water, by divers
skilfully reiterated acts of Suction he
could not raiſe the liquor in the
longer legg above two Inches; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
by that time the Air included in
the ſhorter legg had, by expanding
it ſelf further and further, proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably
weaken'd its Spring, 'till at
length it became as rarified; as was
the Air in the cavity of the longer
legg, and conſequently was able to
thruſt away the water with no more
force than the Air in the long legg
was able to reſiſt. And by the reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
tryal it appear'd, that the rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
uſually made of Air by Suction
is not near ſo great, as one would
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:104481:22"/>
expect, problably becauſe by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latation
of the Lungs the Air, being
ſtill ſhut up, is but moderately rarified,
and the Air in the longer legg can by
them be brought to no greater de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree
of rarity, than that of the Air
within the Cheſt. For, whereas the
included Air in our Inſtrument was
not expanded, by my eſtimate, at
one ſuck to above the double of its
former dimenſions, and by divers ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive
ſucks was expanded but from
one Inch and an half to leſs than four
Inches and an half, if the Suction
could have been conveniently made
with a great and ſtanch Syringe, the
rarefaction of the Air would proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
have been far greater; ſince in
our Pneumatick Engin Air may,
without heat, and by a kind of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
be brought to poſſeſs many
hundreds of times the ſpace it took
up before. From this rarefaction of
the Air in both the leggs of our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument
proceeds another <hi>Phaenome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non,</hi>
readily explicable by our <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis.</hi>
For if, when the water was
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:104481:22"/>
impell'd up as high as the Suction
could raiſe it, the Inſtrument were
taken from the Suckers mouth, the
elevated water would with violence
return to its wonted ſtation. For,
the Air, in both the leggs of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument,
having by the Suction loſt
much of the Spring, and ſo of its
power of preſſing; when once the
orifice of the longer legg was left
open, the Atmoſpherical Air came
again to gravitate upon the water in
that legg, and the Air, included in
the other legg, having its Spring de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitated
by the precedent expanſion,
was not able to hinder the external
Air from violently repelling the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated
water, 'till the included Air
was thruſt into the ſpace it poſſeſs'd
before the Suction; in which ſpace it
had Denſity and Elaſticity enough to
reſiſt the preſſure, that the external
Air exercis'd againſt it through the
interpos'd water.</p>
            <p>But our <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> about the Cauſe
of Suction would not need to be ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citouſly
prov'd to you by other ways,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:104481:23"/>
if you had ſeen what I have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
been able to do in our Pneu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick
Engin. For, there we found
by tryals purpoſely devis'd, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
made, that a good Syringe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
ſo conveyed into our Receiver,
that the open orifice of the Pipe or
lower part was kept under water, if
the Engin were exhauſted, though
the handle of the Syringe were drawn
up, the water would not follow it,
which yet it would do if the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
Air were let in again. The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
of which is plain in our <hi>Hypotheſis.</hi>
For, the Air, that ſhould have preſt
upon the ſurface of the ſtagnant wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
having been pumpt out, there
was nothing to impell up the water
into the deſerted cavity of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe,
as there was when the Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
was fill'd with Air.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:104481:23"/>
            <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
            <p>BUt becauſe ſuch a conveniency as
our Engin, and the <hi>apparatus</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
for ſuch Tryals are not eaſily
procurable, I ſhall endeavour to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm
our <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> about Suction by
ſubjoining ſome Experiments, that
may be tryed without the help of that
Engin, for the making out theſe three
things:
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>I.</hi> That a Liquor may be rais'd by
Suction, when the preſſure of the Air,
neither as it has Weight nor Elaſticity, is
the Cauſe of the Elevation.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>II.</hi> That the weight of the Atmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpherical
Air is ſufficient to raiſe up Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors
in Suction.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>III.</hi> That in ſome caſes Suction will
not be made, as, according to the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis
I diſſent from, it ſhould, although
there be a dilatation of the Suckers <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rax,</hi>
and no danger of a <hi>Vacuum</hi>
though the Liquor ſhould aſcend.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:104481:24"/>
And <hi>firſt,</hi> to ſhew, how much
the riſing of Liquors in Suction de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends
upon the weight or preſſure of
the impellent Body, and how little
neceſſity there is, where that preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
is not wanting, that, in the
place deferted by the Liquor that is
ſuck'd, there ſhould ſucceed Air or
ſome other viſible Body, as the <hi>Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patetic</hi>
Schools would have it; to
ſhew this, <hi>I ſay,</hi> I thought on the
following Experiments. We took a
Glaſs-pipe fit to have the <hi>Torricellian</hi>
Experiment made with it, but a good
deal longer than was neceſſary for
that uſe: This Pipe being Hermeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally
ſeal'd at one end, the other end
was ſo bent as to be reflected upwards,
and make as it were the ſhorter legg
of the Syphon as parallel as we could
to the longer, ſo that the Tube now
was ſhap'd like an inverted Syphon
with leggs of a very unequal length.
This Tube, notwithſtanding its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient
figure, we made a ſhift,
(for 'tis not eaſily done) to fill with
Mercury, when 'twas in an inclin'd
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:104481:24"/>
poſture, and then erecting it, the
Mercury ſubſided in the longer legg,
as in the <hi>Torricellian</hi> Experiment, and
attain'd to between two foot and a
quarter and two foot and an half a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
the ſurface of the Mercury in
the ſhorter legg, which in this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument
anſwers to the ſtagnant
Mercury in an ordinary <hi>Barometer,</hi>
from which to diſtinguiſh it I have
elſwhere call'd this Syphon, furniſh'd
with Mercury, a <hi>Travelling Baroſcope,</hi>
becauſe it may be ſafely carried from
place to place. Out of the ſhorter
legg of this Tube we warily took as
much Mercury as was thought con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient
for what we had further to
do, and this we did by ſuch a way
as to hinder any Air from getting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the deſerted cavity of the longer
legg, by which means the Mercurial
Cylinder, (eſtimated as I lately men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd)
retain'd the ſame height above
the ſtagnant Mercury in the ſhorter:
The upper and clos'd part of this
Travelling Baroſcope you will eaſily
grant to have been free from Common
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:104481:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:104481:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:104481:26"/>
Air, not only for other Reaſons that
have been given elſewhere, but par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
for this, that, if you gently
incline the Inſtrument, the Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver
will aſcend to the top of the
Tube; which you know it could not
do, if the place, formerly deſerted
by it, were poſſeſt by the Air, which
by its Spring would hinder the aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
of the Mercury, (as is eaſie to be
tryed.) The Inſtrument having been
thus fitted, I caus'd one of the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanders
to ſuck at the ſhorter legg,
whereupon (as I expected) there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
enſued an Aſcenſion of four or
five Inches of Mercury in that legg,
and a proportionable Subſidence of
the Mercury in the longer, and yet
in this caſe the raiſing of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury
cannot be pretended to proceed
from the preſſure of the Air. For,
the weight of the Atmoſphere is fenc'd
off by that, which cloſes the upper
end of the longer Tube, and the
Spring of the Air has here nothing
to do, ſince, as we have lately ſhewn,
the ſpace deſerted by the Mercury is
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:104481:26"/>
not poſſeſt by the included Air, and
the pulſion or condenſation of the Air,
ſuppos'd by divers modern Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers
to be made by the dilatation of
the Suckers Cheſt, and to preſs upon
the ſurface of the Liquors that are to
be ſuck'd up, this, <hi>I ſay,</hi> cannot
here be pretended in regard the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face
of the Liquor in the longer legg
is every way fenc'd from the preſſure
of the ambient Air. So that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains,
that the Cauſe, which rais'd
the Quickſilver in the ſhorter legg
upon the newly recited Suction, was
the weight of the collaterally ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour
Quickſilver in the longer legg,
which, being (at the beginning of
the Suction) equivalent to the weight
of the Atmoſphere, there is a plain
reaſon, why the ſtagnant Mercury in
the ſhorter legg ſhould be rais'd ſome
Inches by Suction; as Mercury ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
in an open Veſſel will be rais'd
by the weight of the Atmoſphere,
when the Suction is made in the open
Air. For, in both caſes there is a
Pipe, that reaches to the ſtagnant
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:104481:27"/>
Mercury, and a competent weight to
impel it into that Pipe; when the
Air in the cavity of the Pipe has its
Spring weaken'd by the dilatation
that accompanied Suction.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Second</hi> point formerly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd,
which is, <hi>That the weight of
the Air is ſufficient to raiſe Liquors in
Suction;</hi> may not be ill prov'd by
Arguments legitimately drawn from
the <hi>Torricellian</hi> Experiment it ſelf, and
much more clearly by the firſt and
fifteenth of our <hi>Continued Phyſico-Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanical
Experiments.</hi> And therefore I
ſhall only here take notice of a Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomenon,
that may be exhibited by
the <hi>Travelling Baroſcope,</hi> which, though
it be much inferiour to the Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
newly referr'd to, may be of
ſome uſe on the preſent occaſion.</p>
            <p>Having then provided an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
like the <hi>Travelling Baroſcope,</hi>
mention'd under the former Head,
but whoſe leggs were not ſo unequally
long, and having in it made the <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricellian</hi>
Experiment after the manner
lately deſcrib'd; we order'd the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:104481:27"/>
ſo, that there remain'd in the
ſhorter legg the length of divers In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
unfill'd with ſtagnant Mercury.
Then I caus'd one, vers'd in what
he was to do, ſo to raiſe the Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver
by Suction to the open orifice
of the ſhorter legg, that, the orifice
being ſeaſonably and dexterouſly clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
the Mercury continued to fill
that legg, as long as we thought fit;
and then having put a mark to the
ſurface of the Mercury in the longer
legg, we unſtopp'd the orifice of the
ſhorter; whereupon the Mercury,
that before fill'd it, was <hi>depreſs'd,</hi> 'till
the ſame Liquor in the longer legg
was rais'd five Inches or more above
the mark, and continu'd at that height.
I ſaid, that the Mercury that had
been raiſed by Suction, was <hi>depreſs'd,</hi>
rather than that it <hi>ſubſided,</hi> becauſe its
own weight could not here make it
fall, ſince a Mercurial Cylinder of five
Inches was far from being able to raiſe
ſo tall a Cylinder of Mercury as made
a counterpoiſe in the longer legg;
and therefore the depreſſion we ſpeak
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:104481:28"/>
of, is to be referr'd to the gravitation
of the Atmoſpherical Air upon the
ſurface of the Mercury in the ſhorter
legg: And I ſee no cauſe to doubt but
that, if we could have procured an
Inſtrument, into whoſe ſhorter legg
a Mercurial Cylinder of many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
higher could have been ſuck'd
up, it would by this contrivance
have appear'd, that the preſſure of
the Atmoſphere would eaſily impel
up a far taller Cylinder of Mercury
than it did in our recited Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>That this is no groundleſs conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture
may appear probable by the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment
you will preſently meet
with. For if the gravity of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent
Pillar of the Atmoſphere
be able to compreſs a parcel of inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
Air as much as a Mercurial Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linder,
equivalent in weight to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
thirty and five and thirty foot
of water, is able to condenſe it, it
cannot well be denied that the ſame
Atmoſpherical Cylinder may be able
by its weight to raiſe and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballance
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:104481:28"/>
eight or nine and twenty
Inches of Quickſilver, or an equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
pillar of water in Tubes, where
the reſiſtance of theſe two Liquors to
be rais'd and ſuſtain'd by the Air,
depends only upon their own unaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted
gravity.</p>
            <p>To confirm our Doctrine of the
Gravitation of the Atmoſphere upon
the ſurface of the Liquors expos'd to
it, I will ſubjoin an Experiment, that
I devis'd to ſhew, that the incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent
Air, in its natural or uſual ſtate,
would compreſs other Air not rarified,
but in the like natural ſtate, as much
as a Cylinder of eight or nine and
twenty Inches of Mercury would
condenſe or compreſs it.</p>
            <p>In order to the making of this, I
muſt put you in mind of what I have
ſhewn elſewhere at
large,<note place="margin">See the Authors Defence of the Doctrine touching the Spring and Weight of the Air, againſt <hi>Fr. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> chap 5.</note> and ſhall fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
confirm by one
of the Experiments
that follows the
next; namely, that about twenty
nine or thirty Inches of Quickſilver
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:104481:29"/>
will compreſs Air, that being in its
natural or uſual ſtate (as to rarity and
denſity) has been ſhut up in the ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
legg of our Travelling or Syphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
Baroſcope, into half the room
that included Air poſſeſs'd before.
This premis'd, I paſs on to my Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment,
which was this:</p>
            <p>We provided a <hi>Travelling Baroſcope,</hi>
wherein the Mercury in the longer
legg was kept ſuſpended by the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoiſe
of the Air that gravitated on
the ſurface of the Mercury in the
ſhorter legg, which we had ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd,
that it reached not by about
two Inches to the top of the ſhorter
legg. Then making a mark at the
place where the ſtagnant Mercury
reſted, 'twas manifeſt according to
our <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> that the Air in the
upper part of the ſhorter legg was in
its natural ſtate, or of the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree
of denſity with the outward
Air, with which it freely commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated
at the open orifice of the ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
legg; ſo that this ſtagnant Air
was equally preſt upon by the weight
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:104481:29"/>
of the collaterally ſuperiour Cylinder
of Mercury in the longer legg, and the
equivalent weight of a directly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent
pillar of the Atmoſphere.
Things being in this poſture, the
upper part of the ſhorter legg, which
had been before purpoſely drawn out
to an almoſt capillary ſmallneſs, was
Hermetically ſeal'd, which, though
the Inſtrument was kept erected, was
ſo nimbly done by reaſon of the ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs
of the Pipe, that the inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
Air did not appear to be ſenſibly
heated, though for greater caution
we ſtaid a while from proceeding,
that, if any rarefaction had been
produc'd in the Air, it might have
time to loſe it again. This done,
we open'd the lower end of the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
legg, (which had been ſo order'd
before, that we could eaſily do it, and
without concuſſion of the Veſſel,)
by which means the Atmoſpherical
Air, gaining acceſs to the Mercury
included in the longer legg, did,
as I expected, by its gravitation upon
it ſo compreſs the Air included in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:104481:30"/>
the ſhorter legg, that, according to
the eſtimate we made with the help
of a Ruler, (for by reaſon of the
conical figure of the upper part of
the glaſs we could not take preciſe
meaſures,) it was thruſt into near
half the room it took up before, and
conſequently, according to what I
put you lately in mind of, endur'd a
compreſſion like that, which a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curial
Cylinder of about twenty nine
Inches would have given it.</p>
            <p>This Experiment, as to the main
of it, was for greater caution made
the ſecond time with much the like
ſucceſs; and though it had been more
eaſie to meaſure the Condenſation of
the Air, if, inſtead of drawing out
and ſealing up the ſhorter legg of the
Inſtrument, we had contented our
ſelves to cloſe it ſome other way;
yet we rather choſe to imploy <hi>Hermes</hi>'s
Seal, leſt, if any other courſe had
been taken, it might be pretended,
that ſome of the included Air, when
it began to be compreſt, might eſcape
out at the not perfectly and ſtrongly
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:104481:30"/>
clos'd orifice of the legg wherein 'twas
impriſon'd.</p>
            <p>To make it yet further appear, how
much the Aſcenſion of Liquors by
Suction depends upon Preſſure, rather
than upon Natures imaginary Abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
of a <hi>Vacuum,</hi> or the propagated
Pulſion of the Air; I will ſubjoin
an <hi>Inſtance,</hi> wherein that preſum'd
Abhorrence cannot be pretended.
The Experiment was thus made:</p>
            <p>A Glaſs-Syphon, like thoſe lately
deſcrib'd, with one legg far longer
than the other, was Hermetically
ſeal'd at the ſhorter legg, and then by
degrees there was put in, at the orifice
of the longer legg, as much Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver
as by its weight ſuffic'd to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs
the Air in the ſhorter legg into
about half the room it poſſeſs'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore;
ſo that, according to the <hi>Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patetick</hi>
Doctrine, the Air muſt be in
a ſtate of preternatural Condenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
and that to a far greater degree,
than (as I have tryed) 'tis uſually
brought to by Cold, intenſe enough
to freeze water. Then meaſuring
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:104481:31"/>
the heighth of the Quickſilver in the
longer Tube above the ſuperficies of
that in the ſhorter, we found it not
exceed thirty Inches. Now, if Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors
did riſe in Suction <hi>ob fugam
vacui,</hi> there is no reaſon, why this
Quickſilver in the longer part of the
Syphon ſhould not eaſily aſcend upon
Suction, at leaſt 'till the Air in the
ſhorter legg had regain'd its former
Dimenſions, ſince it cannot in this
place be pretended, that, if the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury
ſhould aſcend, there would be
any danger of a <hi>Vacuum</hi> in the ſhorter
legg of the Tube, in regard that the
contiguous included Air is ready at
hand to ſucceed as faſt as the Mercury
ſubſides in the ſhorter legg of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon.
Nor can it be pretended, that,
to fill the place deſerted by the Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver,
the included Air muſt ſuffer
a preternatural rarefaction or diſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion;
ſince 'tis plain in our caſe, that
on the contrary, as long as the Air
continues in the ſtate whereto the
weight of the Quickſilver has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd
it, it is kept in a violent ſtate
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:104481:31"/>
of compreſſion; ſince in the ſhorter
legg it was in its natural ſtate, when
the Mercury, poured into the longer
legg, did by its weight thruſt it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
about half the room it took up
before. And yet, having caus'd ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
perſons, one of them vers'd in
ſucking, to ſuck divers times as
ſtrongly as they could, they were
neither of them able, not ſo much as
for a minute of an hour, to raiſe
the Mercury in the longer legg, and
make it ſubſide in the ſhorter for more
than about an Inch at moſt. And
yet to ſhew you, that the Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
was not favourably tryed for
me, the height of the Mercurial Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linder
in the longer legg above the
ſurface of that in the ſhorter legg
was, when the Suction was tryed,
an Inch or two ſhorter than thirty
Inches, and the compreſt Air in the
ſhorter legg was ſo far from having
been by the exſuction expanded be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
its natural and firſt dimenſions,
that it did not, when the contiguous
Mercury ſtood as low as we could
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:104481:32"/>
make it ſubſide, regain ſo much as
one half of the ſpace it had loſt by
the precedent Compreſſion, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently
was in a preternatural ſtate
of condenſation, when it had been
freed from that ſtate as far as Suction
would do it. Whence it ſeems evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,
that 'twas not <hi>ob fugam vacui,</hi>
that the Quickſilver did upon Suction
aſcend one Inch; for, upon the ſame
ſcore it ought to have aſcended two,
or perhaps more Inches, ſince there
was no danger, that by ſuch an aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
any <hi>Vacuum</hi> ſhould be produc'd
or left in the ſhorter legg of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon;
whereas, according to our
<hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> a clear cauſe of the Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomenon
is aſſignable. For, before
the Suction was begun, there was
an <hi>Aequilibrium</hi> or equipollency be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
the weight of the ſuperiour
Quickſilver in the longer legg, and
a Spring of the compreſt Air inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
in the ſhorter legg: But when
the Experimentor began to ſuck, his
Cheſt being widen'd, part of the
Air included in the upper part of the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:104481:32"/>
longer legg paſs'd into it, and that
which remain'd had by that expan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
its preſſure ſo weaken'd, that
the Air in the ſhorter legg, finding
no longer the former reſiſtance, was
able by its own Spring to expand it
ſelf, and conſequently to depreſs the
contiguous Mercury in the ſame ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
legg, and raiſe it as much in the
longer.</p>
            <p>But here a <hi>Hydroſtatician,</hi> that heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
marks this Experiment, may
diſcern a difficulty, that may perhaps
ſomewhat perplex him, and ſeems
to overthrow our Explication of the
Phaenomenon. For he may object,
that if the compreſt Air in the ſhorter
legg had a Spring equipollent to the
weight of the Mercury in the longer
legg, it appears not, why the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury
ſhould not be ſuckt up in this
Inſtrument, as well as in the free
Air; ſince, according to me, the
preſſure of the included Air upon the
ſubjacent Mercury muſt be equivalent
to the weight of the Atmoſphere,
and yet experience ſhews, that the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:104481:33"/>
weight of the Atmoſphere will, upon
Suction, raiſe Quickſilver to the height
of ſeveral Inches.</p>
            <p>To clear this difficulty, and ſhew,
that, though it be conſiderable, 'tis
not at all inſuperable, be pleaſed to
conſider with me, that I make indeed
the <hi>Spring</hi> of the compreſt Air to be
equipollent to the <hi>Weight</hi> of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing
Mercury, and I have a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt
reaſon to do it; becauſe, if the
Spring of the Air were not equipol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
to that Weight, the Mercury
muſt neceſſarily compreſs the Air
farther, which 'tis granted <hi>de facto</hi>
not to do. But then I conſider, that
in our caſe there ought to be a great
deal of difference between the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
of the <hi>Spring</hi> of the <hi>included
Air</hi> and the <hi>Weight</hi> of the <hi>Atmoſphere,</hi>
after Suction has been once begun.
For, the Weight of the Atmoſphere,
that impels up Mercury and other Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors,
when the Suction is made in
the open Air, continues ſtill the ſame,
but the force or preſſure of the inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
Air is equal to the counterpreſſure
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:104481:33"/>
of the Mercury no longer than the
firſt moment of the Suction; after
which, the force of the impriſon'd
Air ſtill decreaſes more and more,
ſince this compreſt Air, being fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
and further expanded, muſt needs
have its Spring proportionably wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken'd;
ſo that it need be no wonder,
that the Mercury was not ſuckt up
any more than we have related; for
there was nothing to make it aſcend
to a greater height, than that, at
which the debilitated Spring of the
(included but) expanded Air was
brought to an equipollency with the
undiminiſh'd and indeed ſomewhat
increas'd weight of the Mercurial
Cylinder in the longer legg, and the
preſſure of the Aerial Cylinder in the
ſame legg, leſſen'd by the action of
him that ſuck'd. For whereas, when
the orifice of this legg ſtood open,
the Mercury was preſt on by a Cylin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
of the Atmoſpherical Air, equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
to about thirty Inches of Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver;
by the mouth and action of
him that ſuck'd the Tube was
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:104481:34"/>
freed from the external Air, and by
the dilatation of his <hi>Thorax,</hi> the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring
Air, that had a free paſſage
through his wind-pipe to it, was
proportionably expanded, and had
its Spring and preſſure weaken'd:
By which means, the compreſt Air in
the ſhorter legg of the Syphon was
inabled to impel up the Mercury, 'till
the lately mention'd <hi>Equilibrium</hi> or
equipollency was attain'd. And I
muſt here take notice, that, as the
Quickſilver was rais'd by Suction
but a little way, ſo the Cylinder
that was rais'd was a very long one;
whereas, when Mercury is ſuck'd up
in the free Air, it is ſeldom rais'd to
half that length; though, as I noted
before, the impellent cauſe, which
is the weight of the Atmoſphere,
continued ſtill the ſame, whereas in
our Syphon, when the Mercury was
ſuck'd up but an Inch, the compreſt
Air, poſſeſſing double the ſpace it
did before, had by this expanſion al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
loſt a very conſiderable part of
its former Spring and Preſſure.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:104481:34"/>
I ſhould here conclude this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,
but that I remember a <hi>Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomenon</hi>
of our Pneumatic Engin,
which to divers Learned Men, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<hi>Ariſtotelians,</hi> ſeem'd ſo much
to argue, that Suction is made either
by a <hi>Fuga Vacui,</hi> or ſome internal
Principle, that divers years ago I
thought fit to ſet down another ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
of it, and lately meeting with
that account among other papers, I
ſhall ſubjoin it juſt as I found it, by
way of <hi>Appendix</hi> to the foregoing
Tract.</p>
            <p>Among the more familiar <hi>Phaeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena</hi>
of the <hi>Machina Boyliana,</hi> (as
they now call it,) none leaves ſo much
ſcruple in the Minds of ſome ſorts of
Men, as this, That, when ones fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
is laid cloſe upon the orifice of
the little Pipe, by which the Air is
wont to paſs from the Receiver into
the exhauſted Cylinder, the pulp of
the finger is made to enter a good
way into the cavity of the Pipe,
which doth not happen without a
conſiderable ſenſe of pain in the lower
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:104481:35"/>
part of the finger. For moſt of thoſe
that are ſtrangers to <hi>Hydroſtaticks,</hi>
eſpecially if they be prepoſſeſs'd with
the Opinions generally receiv'd both
in the <hi>Peripatetick</hi> and other Schools,
perſwade themſelves, that they feel
the newly mention'd and painful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuberance
of the pulp of the finger,
to be effected not by preſſure, as we
would have it, but diſtinctly by At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction.</p>
            <p>To this we are wont to anſwer,
That common Air being a Body not
devoid of weight, the Phenomenon
is clearly explicable by the preſſure
of it: For, when the finger is firſt
laid upon the orifice of the Pipe, no
pain nor ſwelling is produc'd, becauſe
the Air which is in the Pipe preſſes
as well againſt that part of the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
which covereth the orifice, as the
ambient Air doth againſt the other
parts of the ſame finger. But when
by pumping, the Air in the Pipe, or
the moſt part of it, is made to paſs
out of the Pipe into the exhauſted
Cylinder, then there is nothing left
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:104481:35"/>
in the Pipe, whoſe preſſure can any
thing near countervail the undimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd
preſſure of the external Air on
the other parts of the finger; and
conſequently, that Air thruſts the
moſt yielding and fleſhy part of the
finger, which is the pulp, into that
place where its preſſure is unreſiſted,
that is, into the cavity of the Pipe,
where this forcible intruſion cauſeth
a pain in thoſe tender parts of the
finger.</p>
            <p>To give ſome viſible Illuſtration of
what we have been ſaying, as well
as for other purpoſes, I thought on
the following Experiment.</p>
            <p>We took a Glaſs-pipe of a conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient
length, and open at both ends,
whoſe cavity was near about an Inch
in <hi>Diameter,</hi> (ſuch a determinate
breadth being convenient, though not
neceſſary:) To one of the ends of
this Pipe we cauſed to be firmly tyed
on a piece of very fine Bladder, that
had been ruffled and oyl'd, to make
it both very limber and unapt to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
water; and care was taken, that
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:104481:36"/>
the piece of Bladder tyed on ſhould
be large enough, not only to cover
the orifice, but to hang looſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
beneath it.</p>
            <p>This done, we put the cover'd end
of the Pipe into a Glaſs-body (or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curbit)
purpoſely made more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily
tall, and the Pipe being held
in ſuch manner, as that the end of
it reach'd almoſt, but not quite, to
the bottom of the Glaſs-body, we
cauſed water to be poured both into
this Veſſel and into the Pipe (at its
upper orifice, which was left open)
that the water might aſcend equally
enough, both without and within
the Pipe. And when the Glaſs-body
was full of water, and the ſame li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor
was level to it., or a little higher
within the Pipe, the Bladder at the
lower orifice was kept plump, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
the water within the Pipe did
by its weight preſs as forcibly down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,
as the external water in the
large Glaſs endeavour'd to preſs it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
and upwards.</p>
            <p>All this being done, we caus'd
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:104481:36"/>
part of the water in the Pipe to be
taken out of it, (which may be done
either by putting in and drawing out
a piece of Spunge or of Linnen, or
more expeditiouſly by ſucking up part
of the water with a ſmaller Pipe to
be immediately after laid aſide;) up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
which removal of part of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal
water, that which remained
in the Pipe being no longer able, by
reaſon of its want of weight, to preſs
againſt the inſide of the Bladder near
as forcibly as it did before, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal
water, whoſe weight was
not leſſen'd, preſs'd the ſides and
bottom of the Bladder, whereto
it was contiguous, into the cavity
of the Pipe, and thruſted it up there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
ſo ſtrongly, that the diſtended
Bladder made a kind of either Thim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
or Hemiſphere within the Pipe.
So that here we have a protube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
like that above-mentioned of
the finger, effected by Pulſion, not
Attraction; and in a caſe where there
can be no juſt pretence of having
recourſe to Natures Abhorrence of a
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:104481:37"/>
               <hi>Vacuum,</hi> ſince, the upper orifice of the
Pipe being left wide open, the Air
may paſs in and out without reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
            <p>The like ſwelling of the Bladder
in the Pipe we could procure without
taking out any of the internal li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor,
by thruſting the Pipe deeper
into the water; for then the external
liquor, having by reaſon of its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe
of depth a greater preſſure on
the outſide of the Bladder, than the
internal liquor had on the inſide of
it, the Bladder muſt yield to the
ſtronger preſſure, and conſequently
be impell'd up.</p>
            <p>If the Bladder lying looſe at the
lower end of the Pipe, the upper end
were carefully clos'd with ones
thumb, that the upper Air might
not get out until the Experimentor
thought fit, and if the thus clos'd
Pipe were thruſt almoſt to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom
of the water, the Bladder would
not be protuberant inwards, as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly;
becauſe the included Air by
virtue of its Spring, reſiſted from
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:104481:37"/>
within the preſſure of the external
water againſt the outſide of the Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der:
But if the thumb, that ſtopp'd
the Pipes upper orifice, were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd,
the formerly compreſs'd Air
having liberty to expand it ſelf, and
its elaſticity being weaken'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,
the external water would with
ſuddenneſs and noiſe enough, not to
be unpleaſant to the Spectators, drive
up the Bladder into the cavity of the
Pipe, and keep it there very protu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berant.</p>
            <p>To obviate an Objection, that I
foreſaw might be brought in by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
not well vers'd in <hi>Hydroſtaticks,</hi>
I caus'd the Pipe fore-mention'd, or
ſuch another, to be ſo bent near the
lower end, as that the orifice of it
ſtood quite on one ſide, and the
parts of the Pipe made an angle as
near to a right one as he that blew
it could bring it to. This lower o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifice
being fitted with a Bladder, and
the Pipe with its contained liquor
being thruſt under water after the
former manner, the lateral preſſure
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:104481:38"/>
of the water forc'd the Bladder into
the ſhort and horizontal legg, and
made it protuberate there, as it had
done when the Pipe was ſtraight.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, that the Experiment might
appear not to be confin'd to one li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor;
inſtead of <hi>Water</hi> we put into
the unbent Pipe as much red <hi>Wine</hi>
(whoſe colour would make it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous)
as was requiſit to keep the
Bladder ſomewhat ſwelling outwards,
when it was ſomewhat near the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom
of the water; and then 'twas
manifeſt, that, according as we had
foreſeen, the ſuperficies of the red
liquor in the Pipe was a good deal
higher than that of the external wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
and if the depth of both liquors
were proportionably leſſen'd, the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
of height betwixt the two
ſurfaces would indeed, as it ought
to happen, decreaſe, but ſtill the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face
of the wine would be the higher
of the two, becauſe being lighter in
<hi>ſpecie</hi> than the common water, the
<hi>Aequilibrium</hi> between the preſſures of
the two liquors upon the Bladder
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:104481:38"/>
would not be maintain'd, unleſs a
greater height of <hi>wine</hi> compenſated
its defect of ſpecifick gravity. And
if the Pipe was thruſt deeper into
the water, then the Bladder would
be made protuberant inwards, as
when the Pipe had water in it. By
which it appears, that theſe <hi>Phaeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena,</hi>
without recourſe to <hi>attraction,</hi>
may be explicated barely by the Laws
of the <hi>Aequilibrium</hi> of Liquors.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
