<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Brief and true remonstrance of the illegal proceedings of Roger Osburn (an Irish man born) governour of Mount Serrat, one of the Caribba islands, with his Irish complices against Samuel Waad the younger, of Topsham in the county of Devon, gent. and of his barbarous and inhuman murthering of the said Waad in the said island upon the first day of May, 1654.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29425</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4537</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37466</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16959681</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16959681</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105476</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A29425)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105476)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1610:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Brief and true remonstrance of the illegal proceedings of Roger Osburn (an Irish man born) governour of Mount Serrat, one of the Caribba islands, with his Irish complices against Samuel Waad the younger, of Topsham in the county of Devon, gent. and of his barbarous and inhuman murthering of the said Waad in the said island upon the first day of May, 1654.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 broadside.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Murder --  Montserrat.</term>
               <term>Montserrat --  History.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Colonies --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:105476:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
            <head>A brief and true Remonſtrance of the Illegal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of <hi>Roger Osburn</hi> (an <hi>Iriſh</hi> man born) Governour of MOUNT SERRAT, one of the <hi>Caribba</hi> Iſlands, with his <hi>Iriſh</hi> Complices againſt <hi>Samuel Waad</hi> the younger, of <hi>Topſham</hi> in the County of <hi>Devon, Gent.</hi> And of his barbarous and inhuman murthering of the ſaid <hi>Waad</hi> in the ſaid Iſland upon <date>the firſt day of <hi>May</hi> 1654.</date>
            </head>
            <p>THat the ſaid <hi>Samuel Waad</hi> took to wife <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the Relict of one <hi>Anthony Brisket</hi> in the year 1650, who had been ſome time Governour of the Iſland, the which <hi>Waad</hi> ſhortly upon his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage went with his ſaid wife unto the Iſland aforeſaid to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the eſtate that his Predeceſſour formerly enjoyed, and at his arrival there the eſtate was valued by the then Governour <hi>Roger Osburn</hi> and others of the Iſland; ſince which time the ſaid <hi>Waad</hi> hath paid of the debts of the ſaid <hi>Anthony Brisket</hi> more then the then value thereof, ſo about the end of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember</hi> 1653. the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his wife dyed, who was ſiſter to the then Governour <hi>Roger Osburn,</hi> the which <hi>Osburn</hi> maligning the ſaid <hi>Waad,</hi> who lived in better ſtate than himſelf, reported in the preſence of one <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth Collings</hi> wife to the then Secretary, that if his Siſter (meaning the wife of the ſaid <hi>Waad</hi>) were dead, that he would order him the ſaid <hi>Waad</hi> well enough, and ever after the ſaid Governour and his <hi>Iriſh</hi> Complices, uſed what means they could to entrap the ſaid <hi>Waad</hi> by affronts, ſuggeſting ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rums upon the Iſland, but his devices prevailed not. And about the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>April</hi> following the ſaid Governour took an occaſion to ſend for one Mr. <hi>Thomas Hurſt</hi> by his Marſhall from out of the ſaid <hi>Waads</hi> houſe, and committed him to priſon for ſtiking a Taylor with his Cane that affronted him, which occaſioned the Writing of a Letter by the ſaid <hi>Waad</hi> unto the ſaid Governour, bearing date <hi>April</hi> 2. 1654, the Copy whereof (written by the ſaid <hi>Waads</hi> own hand) is as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>A true Copy ſubſcribed, To the Honourable Col. <hi>Reger Os<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn</hi> Governour of <hi>Mount Serrat.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſpending the Circumſtances you were pleaſed yeſterday by virtue of an <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll favoured <hi>Capias ad Reſpondendum</hi> to fetch an Engliſh Gentleman out of my houſe, and without Baylor Mainprize to commit him cloſe Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, had you dealt ſo with the Iriſh Murderer or late acquitted fellon im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately imployed in your ſervice, it had been just. I cannot think of theſe paſſages without Reluctancy, it will be one day accounted for, with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended alarum. Is this the way to preſerve the Peace of an Iſland, by you wholly neglected and left as a Prey to the next Invader? have we not ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies enough abroad to ruin us, but that you must command and keep the Barbarous <hi>Iriſh</hi> and their Abetters in arms, I will not ſay to the terror but to the admiration of our Nation, ſhould we be ſo precipitate as to meet your ſpleen in its full career upon the Defenſive poſture, you might have just cauſe to repent it. Surely the plot is ſpoiled, we are reſolved to bear with patience the yoke till God in Mercie remove it. Sir had I been of yoar Council, I ſhould have put you in minde of the word Moderation, and not have ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated a Crew of idle Fellows to proſecute the deſerved conſequences of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts. Give me leave to tell you, it is beneath a Gentleman; and if you think to catch me by ſo mean a ſtratagem't will not hold twice. I know you too well already, and onely now deſire you either to enlarge the Priſoner upon my Recognizance of <hi>1000.</hi> l. ſterling, to his Highneſs the Lord Protector of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. for his Appearance at the next Seſſions, according to Law; or give me leave to ſupply his neceſſity during reſtraint; for I may not in point of Honour ſuffer a Gentleman to periſh for want of ſuſtenance. We are to be regulated by Law, not your exorbitant will, nor the ſatisfaction of a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies fancy. I ſhould be loath to hazard my Eſtate upon a Frolick; yet ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than comply with palpable injuſtice, let me die a Beggar. All theſe forced Depoſitions will come to nothing but your ſhame at laſt. For your own ſake I beſeech you, Remember there is a God which can never fail.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>April <hi>2. 1654.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute> 
                     <signed>Your very humble Servant.
<hi>SAM: WAAD.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Then the 26. of the ſame <hi>April</hi> the ſaid <hi>Waad</hi> having occaſion in their Court then held, did voluntarily repair thither, being one of the eminenteſt men of the Iſland, amongſt other buſineſs, he the ſaid <hi>Waad</hi> with one Cap. <hi>Mathew Floyer</hi> diſliking the exorbitant Government of the Iſland did ſollicite the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour in open Court that they might be regulated by due courſe of Law, as other of the Iſlands were, which was to be by a Common Council and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, and with all told him that he would juſtifie the contents of the ſaid Letter and much more before the Lord Protector of England, upon which the ſaid Governor committed the ſaid <hi>Waad</hi> and <hi>Floyer</hi> to ſeveral priſons, kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping <hi>Floyer</hi> in Irons for certain days, and upon ſubmiſſion releaſed him, ſo <hi>Apr.</hi> 25. he commanded a ſtrong guard of <hi>Iriſh</hi> to be in arms, and the 29. (being Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day in the afternoon) the ſaid Governour conſtituted Officers, that is to ſay, <hi>Nathanael Read</hi> who married an <hi>Iriſh</hi> woman, <hi>William Bentley</hi> a Papiſt, one <hi>Dabram</hi> an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſt, Lieutenant, and <hi>Nathaniel Stephens</hi> a Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgian, who together with himſelf, on <hi>Munday</hi> following, being the firſt of <hi>May,</hi> condemned the ſaid <hi>Waad</hi> to be ſhot to death, his hands manakled with Iron by five <hi>Iriſh</hi> and one <hi>Engliſh</hi> man, which about two of the clock the ſame day was accordingly done, never ſuffering all the time of the ſaid <hi>Waads</hi> impriſonment, nor hour of death, any one Friend or Servant of his to ſpeak with him, but as is reported, the ſaid <hi>Waad</hi> wrote much the time of his impriſonment; but the ſaid Governour (the ſaid <hi>Waad</hi> being dead) ſeaz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all his eſtate real and perſonal, entering into his houſe, taking poſſeſſion of all his books and writings, which amounted to a very great value, and to our beſt knowledge we here declare.</p>
            <p>A plantation called <hi>Newark,</hi> whereon is one of the ſtatelieſt Sugar works in all the <hi>Caribba</hi> Iſlands, ſet up by the ſaid <hi>Waad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A plantation at the Wind-ward of the Iſland, whereon is a fair houſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Tobacco Plantation.</p>
            <p>A plantation whereon the ſaid <hi>Waad</hi> lived, called States Caſtle, whereon is a Stately built Stone-houſe richly furniſhed, with all ſorts of furniture, to a great value, being eſteemed the faireſt of any houſe in the <hi>Caribba</hi> Iſlands; In the which houſe was great ſtore of merchandice, to what value we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expreſs. Belonging to theſe plantations were</p>
            <p>Seventy head of Cows, Bulls, and Oxen.</p>
            <p>Five hundred Sheep, Two Horſes and two Colts.</p>
            <p>Hoggs a great number.</p>
            <p>Thirty Chriſtian Servants. Fifty Slaves young and old.</p>
            <p>Many debts, amongſt which the ſaid <hi>Osburn</hi> owed him about twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand weight of Sugar and Tobacco.</p>
            <p>Twenty thouſand weight of ſugar and a great quantity of Tobacco at the time of his death in his Magazine, all which as aforeſaid the ſaid Governor took poſſeſſion of, and preſently ſhipped aboard the Ship called <hi>The Industry of Plymouth, Henry Wiſeman</hi> Maſter, three hundred and fifty Rolls of the ſaid <hi>Waads</hi> Tobacco, being about four and twenty thouſand weight, and conſigned it unto his Brother <hi>Robert Osburn,</hi> a Miniſter in the County of <hi>Cornwall,</hi> which ſaid goods came to the hands of the ſaid <hi>Robert Osburn,</hi> and by him ſold to one Mr. <hi>Richard Lobb</hi> of the Pariſh of <hi>Myler</hi> in the County of <hi>Cornwall,</hi> about the end of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, at the price of ſixteen pounds the thouſand pound, clear of all coſt and charges.</p>
            <p>This we are ready to teſtify upon our Oaths, when ever we ſhall be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto called, who were all then reſident upon the ſaid Iſland.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Henry Waad.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Waad.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Henry Wheeler.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Medford.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Wyke.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
