<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An historical account of Mr. Rogers's three years travels over England and Wales giving a true and exact description of all the chiefest cities, towns and corporations in England, Dominion of Wales, and town of Berwick upon Twede : together with the antiquities, and places of admiration, cathedrals, churches of note in any city, town or place in each county, the gentleman above-mentioned having made it his whole business (during the aforesaid time) to compleat the same in his travelling, : to which is annexed a new map of England and Wales, with the adjacent parts, containing all the cities and market towns bound in just before the title.</title>
            <author>Brome, James, d. 1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 212 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29627</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4857</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39940</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18570128</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18570128</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108032</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A29627)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108032)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1647:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An historical account of Mr. Rogers's three years travels over England and Wales giving a true and exact description of all the chiefest cities, towns and corporations in England, Dominion of Wales, and town of Berwick upon Twede : together with the antiquities, and places of admiration, cathedrals, churches of note in any city, town or place in each county, the gentleman above-mentioned having made it his whole business (during the aforesaid time) to compleat the same in his travelling, : to which is annexed a new map of England and Wales, with the adjacent parts, containing all the cities and market towns bound in just before the title.</title>
                  <author>Brome, James, d. 1719.</author>
                  <author>D. J.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 128 (i.e. 144) p., [1] folded leaf of plates : map.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by J. Moxon and B. Beardwell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Editor's preface signed: D.J.</note>
                  <note>Pages 97-112 repeated in numbering only.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Description and travel.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Robyn Anspach</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Robyn Anspach</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108032:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108032:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN
HISTORICAL ACCOUNT
OF
M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Rogers</hi>'s
Three Years TRAVELS
OVER
<hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>GIVING
A True and Exact Deſcription of all
the chiefeſt Cities, Towns and Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
in <hi>England,</hi> Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> and
Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Twede.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>TOGETHER
With the Antiquities, and Places of Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
Cathedrals, Churches of Note in any City,
Town or Place in each County. The Gentleman a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove-mentioned
having made it his whole Buſineſs
(during the aforeſaid time) to Compleat the ſame
in his Travelling.</p>
            <p>To which is Annexed a New Map of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi>
with the Adjacent parts, containing all the Cities
and Market-Towns, bound in juſt before the Title.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed and Sold by <hi>J. Moxon</hi> and <hi>B. Beardwell</hi> at the
<hi>Sign</hi> of <hi>Atlas</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane,</hi> and in <hi>Weſtminſter-hall</hi>
right againſt the <hi>Parliament-Stairs,</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:108032:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108032:2"/>
            <head>TO THE
READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT were a needleſs Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking
to offer any
Apology for the enſuing
Treatiſe, its own intrinſick
Value being ſufficient to raiſe
it both above the reach of
all aſperſing Cavillers, and at
the ſame time to recommend
it to every judicious <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſer;</hi>
but yet it will not be
impertinent to give ſome few
<hi>Hints,</hi> wherein both its
<pb facs="tcp:108032:3"/>
               <hi>Uſefulneſs</hi> and <hi>Excellency</hi>
doth conſiſt.</p>
            <p>Its Bulk is but ſmall, yet
the Matter contain'd large
and extenſive, as compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending
conciſely, but yet ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
conſpicuouſly, an Account
of the moſt <hi>Remarkable Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi>
in this our <hi>Native</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
intermixt with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
very uſeful and divert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<hi>Occurrences:</hi> There are
indeed voluminous Treatiſes
of this Nature already ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant,
which claim a juſt
Praiſe in their kind, and
ſome of a ſmaller Size, that
<pb facs="tcp:108032:3"/>
have their <hi>Uſefulneſs</hi> alſo;
but none, in my Judgment,
ſo well handled, ſo compleat,
and truly recommendable as
this; for what they in lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
Volumes have done, you
have here contracted into a
ſmall compaſs, but yet ſo, as
that there is nothing Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial,
or worthy to be known,
omitted, and what the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer
Tracts have paſſed over,
is here fully inſerted. Our
<hi>Author</hi> hath ſpared no pains
to oblige thee, <hi>(kind Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der)</hi>
having ſpent <hi>Three
whole Years</hi> of his Life in
this his <hi>Peregrination,</hi> now
<pb facs="tcp:108032:4"/>
expoſed to thy view: To ſay
nothing of his <hi>Perſon</hi> and
<hi>Character,</hi> his <hi>Language</hi> is
Elegant and Pithy, his <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions</hi>
lively and airy,
his <hi>Hiſtorical Relations</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent
and ſeaſonable, and
ſuch a pleaſing <hi>Variety,</hi> and
engaging <hi>Divertiſement</hi>
throughout the whole Series
of the <hi>Story,</hi> as can do no leſs
than excite in thee a kind
of a <hi>Longing-wiſh</hi> that
thou hadſt been preſent with
him, and actually pertici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated
of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:108032:4"/>
But what ſignifies what
we have now premiſed, if
<hi>Truth</hi> be not the Standard
of all, and in this regard we
muſt not pretermit in <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi>
what ſo eminently di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhes
our Ingenious <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi>
from moſt, if not all, that
have gone before him upon
this <hi>Subject,</hi> in that he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents
you here with nothing
but his own <hi>Ocular Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations,</hi>
whereas others, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining
themſelves to their
Studies, have obtruded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the World what they
have taken upon the bare
<hi>Credit</hi> of thoſe, who were,
<pb facs="tcp:108032:5"/>
perhaps, more ſlothful than
themſelves.</p>
            <p>In fine, <hi>Gentle Reader,</hi>
Peruſe, and Judge mature<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
and when thou haſt ſo
done, I make no doubt of thy
Approbation, and plenary
Satisfaction, which will not
be a little grateful to</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thy Compatriot</hi>
D. J.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="map">
            <pb facs="tcp:108032:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108032:6"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>A
NEW MAPP OF<hi>ENGLAND </hi>&amp;<hi> WALES</hi>
With the Adjacent parts. Containing all the Citties
And Marcket Towns
As alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Roads Acording to <hi>J. Oglebey</hi> Eſq. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>LONDON
Printed and ſold by <hi>J. Moxon</hi>
At the <hi>Atlas</hi> in Warwick Lane. and
at his Shop in Weſtminſter Hall
Right againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Parliament
Staires</p>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:108032:7"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>lower half of map</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:108032:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:108032:8"/>
            <head>An ACCOUNT
OF
M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>R. Rogers</hi>'s
Three Years Travels
OVER
<hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="account">
               <p>FROM <hi>London,</hi> the Epitome of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
it ſelf, we took our Journy
thro' <hi>Middleſex,</hi> a County famous
for its goodly Edifices, as well
wiſely Compacted together upon
the Banks of <hi>Thames;</hi> as likewiſe for divers
ſtately Palaces diſperſed in ſeveral Parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.
The firſt Town of Note we came to was
<hi>Colebrook,</hi> which takes its Name from the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<hi>Cole;</hi> a Town of great Antiquity, and of
a conſiderable length, and well ſtored with
Inns: We ſtayed here a ſmall time, and ſo ſet
forward to <hi>Maidenhead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:108032:9"/>
                  <hi>MAIDENHEAD</hi> is Eight Miles diſtance
from <hi>Colebrook,</hi> and ſo we came into the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines
of <hi>Barkſhire.</hi> It is a County of near e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual
Length and Breadth; it was thus De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominated
from the Superſtitious Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
that was given to the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Maid,
being one of the Eleven Thouſand, which
by the Conduct of St. <hi>Urſla,</hi> returning home
from <hi>Rome</hi> were all Martyr'd at <hi>Cologne</hi> in
<hi>Germany</hi> by the Tyrant <hi>Attila,</hi> that moſt cruel
Scourge to the <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> 'Tis of no long
Date or ſtanding; and it is certain, as I was
credibly informed, That <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> making
an Inrode into this County did paſs over the
River not far from this Place, and by the
voluntary Submiſſion of theſe People here,
did ſoon compleat his Conqueſt amongſt
them.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Windſor.</head>
                  <p>In this County is <hi>Windſor.</hi> This Place
was given away by <hi>Edward the Confeſſor</hi> from
the Crown to the Church of <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi>
but <hi>William the Conqueror</hi> taking a very great
Affection to it by reaſon of its pleaſant Situ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,
made an Exchange with the Abbot
of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> for ſome other Lands in the
room of this, and ſo it returned to the
Crown again. The Palace in which the
King reſides when he comes down hither,
is inferior to none for Sight and Pleaſure
throughout all His Majeſty's Dominions. In
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:108032:9"/>
the front of it lies a pleaſant Valley, chec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered
with the various colors of Green and
Red Verdant Meadows, and fertile Tillage,
melodious Woods, and the murmuring of
the Noble River <hi>Thames.</hi> Behind it is a
pleaſant Proſpect of a delightful Forreſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned
on purpoſe by Nature for Sport and
Recreation, whilſt ſhe ſo liberally ſtocks it
with numerous Herds of Deer, lurking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
the ſhady. Thickets; and our Kings
and Nobles did very uſually reſort hither from
the City of <hi>London,</hi> it being ſo fine a Place of
pleaſure and delight. K. <hi>Edward</hi> the Third
being born at this Town, did much aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
and ſtrengthen the Caſtle there upon
the Hill, which <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt had before
erected, fortifying the ſame with ſtrong
Walls and Trenches, which are now to be
ſeen. After K. <hi>Edward</hi> the Third had ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued
both the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Scots,</hi> and took
their Kings Captive, he Committed <hi>John,</hi>
King of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> King of the <hi>Scots,</hi>
for ſome time Priſoners to this Caſtle, which
is divided into two Partitions; in the firſt,
which looks towards the Eaſt, is the King's
Palace, ſplendid and glorious; in the other,
which is the outward Partition, ſtands a ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Church, Dedicated by <hi>Edward</hi> the Third
to the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> and St. <hi>George,</hi> but beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified
and illuſtrated with moſt rare and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
Work; K. <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth lies en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:108032:10"/>
therein: But that which makes it ſtill
more Holy and Venerable is, the Body of
our Sacred Martyr K. <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
Royal Saint of ever Bleſſed Memory. From
hence we w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt to <hi>Reading.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>READING</hi> in this County is a Town of
very good Note, and not inferior to any in
all that County. It is ſituated, as it were,
on the ſide of a little Hill, with a ſmall aſcent
towards the Market-place. It is very well
watered by a good River which runs along
the one ſide of it, and hath the Noble River
of <hi>Thames,</hi> which comes within a little di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
on the other ſide. It hath a Mayor
for its chief Magiſtrate, and it is famous
for a very great Market once a Week for all
Sorts of Grain. We ſtayed here but one
Night, having a deſign to take a farther view
of this County by <hi>Wallingford,</hi> and ſo to</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ABBINGTON,</hi> This is a fair Town in
this County; the River <hi>Iſis</hi> after it hath win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
it ſelf a long way about in a crooked
Channel, makes its approach to this Town.
It is a large and populous Place, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives
its Denomination from a famous Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
which was here erected, although this
Monaſtery did, for ſome Years, flouriſh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly,
yet it was afterwards Subverted
by the fury of the <hi>Danes;</hi> but through the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:108032:10"/>
Bounties and Munificence of King <hi>Edgar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
was reſtored again to its Primitive Splendor
and Greatneſs, and by the Induſtry and Care
of the <hi>Norman</hi> Abbots, it grew to that pitch
of Grandeur, and ſo exceeding Rich and
Wealthy, that it began to have an Eſteem
of it ſelf beyond all Compariſon, and indeed
the Ruins too be-ſpeak it to have been a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
glorious Structure: As for the Town,
though it had its chief Dependance from
this Abby, yet from the Year 1430, that one
<hi>John,</hi> Surnamed St. <hi>Helena,</hi> built a ſtrong
Bridge of Stone over its River, and ſo made
a Through-fair and High Road through the
Town, it began to be populous, and much
frequented, and ever ſince hath been moſt
deſervedly reputed the eminent, principle
Town in this County. The Inhabitants are
great Maulſters, and Barly is the great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity
of the Market. The Magiſtrates, by
their Vigilancy and Care, do keep up this
Corporation in great Honour and Requeſt,
and the Mayor and Aldermen are very Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect
in the diſcharge of their Offices;
and for the more great and weighty Matters
which are above their Sphere, the Judges,
when they come their Circuit, and keep
the Aſſizes here for the County, do eaſe
them of that trouble, by giving a final De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination
of all.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:108032:11"/>
                     <hi>FARRINGDON</hi> was the next Town of
Note we went to in this County, which
though it be ſituated upon a ſtony Soil, yet
'tis now as famous for its great Market, as
it was once Renowned for its Impregnable
Fortreſs, which <hi>Robert,</hi> Earl of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> built
here againſt King <hi>Stephen,</hi> which the King
though with the loſs of a great number of
Soldiers, at laſt by his continual Aſſaults and
Batteries took and utterly demoliſhed.</p>
                  <p>But one thing is to be obſerved in this
County; That it is very pleaſant and fertile,
watered with the River <hi>Iſis,</hi> adorned with
woody Hills and thick Groves, and in its
Eaſtern parts thereof with fertile Valleys,
and in the Weſtern part, being called <hi>The
Vale of White Horſe,</hi> is extreamly delightful,
and Nature compenſates the Barrenneſs of
the Soil in one place, by her manifold
Gifts ſhe beſtows upon it in another.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>NEWBURY</hi> was the next place we went to.
'Tis a Town of very good Note, and of a
conſiderable largeneſs, governed by a Mayor
and Aldermen, and hath a very commodious
Market-houſe, which is not much inferior
to any in the County. The Town is ſitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
in a pleaſant Valley, and watered by a
very good River, called <hi>Newbury River,</hi> which
runs through one part of the Town near the
Market-houſe; and in the other part of it is a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:108032:11"/>
very find Rivelet, which runs from one end of
the Town to the other, and is mighty ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
for all the Inhabitants. We made no
long ſtay here, but went to <hi>Marlborough</hi> in
<hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> of which hereafter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Wiltſhire.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MARLBOROUGH</hi> is a Town of an
indifferent largeneſs, and is Ruled by a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yor
and Aldermen. The Buildings of this
Town, and the Market-place, are not much
inferior to any Town in <hi>England;</hi> but that
which is moſt remarkable, and to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
at is, a Mount belonging to the Duke
of <hi>Summerſet,</hi> the like is not in <hi>England.</hi> The
Mount it ſelf is made round, with a Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet
Hedge which is all entire, and goes ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
times round about, the Mount riſing with
a very ſmall Aſcent till it comes up to the
top; within this Hedge is a very plain Path,
or Walk, and the ground ſeems to be ſo
even, that you cannot well perceive the riſe
of it till you are at the top, which is of a
very great height, and of a large circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
but yet as you go down you may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily
perceive the ground fall much. The
Gardner there told us, That it is a Mile from
the bottom up to the top, and go the Path-way
which leads up to it. On the top of the
Mount, is a very fine level piece of Ground,
planted with ſeveral ſorts of Fruit-Trees;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:108032:12"/>
there ſtands likewiſe on the top, a very large
leaden Ceſtern, of about 12 foot ſquare, and
4 foot deep, and is repleniſhed with Water
by a leaden Pipe, which comes from a Spring
along the Path that leads up to the top. On
the one ſide of this Mount is a very commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious
Wilderneſs, and on the other a fine
Garden; in a word, this Mount is the moſt
to be admired, and muſt have the Reſpect
of all Travellers, to be the greateſt piece of
Artificial Workmanſhip in our own Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
We ſtayed here but one Night, and
went to take a farther View of this County,
in which there are many things very obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.
About two Miles out of this Town is
a great Down, called <hi>Marlborough Downs,</hi>
where there is an exceeding Curioſity of
Nature's workmanſhip, it is a huge number
of Maſſy Stones, they are called by the Name
of <hi>The Grey Wethers,</hi> and ſhew to your ſight,
at a diſtance, like a great number of Sheep,
and ſome of them higher; but for the great
number of them, and containing ſuch a vaſt
diſtance of Land, to be all in one and the
like poſture. It is a large Plain, or Valley,
between two Hills where they ſtand, and is
in breadth almoſt a Mile, and about ſix Miles
in length, as we were informed, undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
it hath as much need to be mentioned, as
any thing in the Kingdom. Having made
ſome Obſervations here, we went to take
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:108032:12"/>
ſome account of <hi>Stonehenge</hi> in this County,
of which I ſhall give you a ſhort Relation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>STONEHENGE.</hi> This place contains
in it, within the circumference of three Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
foot, a rude and indigeſted Maſs of vaſt
large Stones, rough, and of a grey colour,
25 Foot in length, 10 in breadth, and 8 in
thickneſs; they look as if they were hewen
ſquare, and are joined two and two toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
and every couple hath a third Stone
lying a-croſs, which is faſtened by Tennants
that enter into Morteſſes, not cloſed with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Morter. It appears as if they had been ſet
in three Ranks going round, as Circles, one
within another, whereof the uttermoſt and
largeſt is in compaſs about 300 Foot, but the
other Ranks are decayed, and ſome of them
being faln down to the ground, 'tis very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult
to reckon how many there are; like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
it ſeems very ſtrange, how ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe
Bulks ſhould happen here, where there
is no Stones of any ſmall demenſion within
the Neighbourhood: Whereupon ſome are
of an Opinion, That they are not purely na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural,
or had their growth in this place.
'Tis now generally credited and believed,
that they were a Monument ſet up by <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relius
Ambroſe,</hi> in Remembrance of the <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains</hi>
that were Slain and Buried there, in the
Reign of <hi>Vortiger,</hi> at a Banquet and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication
of <hi>Hengiſt,</hi> which the <hi>Saxons</hi> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:108032:13"/>
                     <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Chronicles teſtifie, <hi>That whereas the</hi>
Saxons <hi>about the Year of our Lord</hi> 450. <hi>had ſlain
Four hundred and eighty of the</hi> Brittiſh <hi>Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
by Treachery, under a Colour of a Parley and
Treaty; this</hi> Aurelius Ambroſe <hi>being then King
of the</hi> Brittains, <hi>deſirous to continue their Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
as well as the Infamy of his baſe and treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
Enemies, cauſed theſe Stones to be ſet up in
the very place of their Death and Burial, the
which Stones had been firſt brought out of</hi> Africk
<hi>into</hi> Ireland, <hi>and there placed on Mount</hi> Killare,
<hi>and from thence, by the Art and Magick of</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lina,
<hi>a renowned Magician in that Age, were at
length conveyed to this place upon this very Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi>
Others think, that the <hi>Brittains</hi> did E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
this, as a Monument for <hi>Ambroſius</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
to perpetuate his glorious Name to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity,
who died afterwards upon this place
by the Sword, in the Anſwer of their Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel,
and Vindication of their Liberties; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
certain it is, that there are thereabouts
certain little Hills, or Banks, under which
there are ſometimes found Bones of tall, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantick
Men, and pieces of Armour; and
not far from hence, remains ſtill ſome of the
Ruins of an old kind of Fortreſs, which the
<hi>Romans,</hi> as it is probable, did raiſe for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
during their Poſſeſſion of theſe our
Territories, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From hence we went to <hi>Wilton-Houſe,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing
to the Earl of <hi>Pembrook.</hi> It is ſitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:108032:13"/>
in a pleaſant Valley, and hath the Town
of <hi>Wilton</hi> on the one ſide of it, and a ſpacious
Park on the other ſide, with delightful Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens
and Meadows on the other ſides, and
a fine River running through the Gardens.
In this Houſe are excellent Rooms, and great
variety of Pictures, and in the Gardens are
undoubtedly the moſt curious Water-works
that are in all <hi>England.</hi> We did not tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
long here, but went away to <hi>Salisbury,</hi>
of which I ſhall inform you as briefly as I
can.</p>
                  <p>Leaving <hi>Wilton-Houſe</hi> we rode to <hi>Salisbury,</hi>
and in our way beheld the place where for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
old <hi>Wilton,</hi> the Metropolis of this
County, ſtood, called <hi>Willey.</hi> 'Tis ſituated,
ſaith <hi>Cambden,</hi> where the two Rivers <hi>Willey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brook</hi>
and <hi>Alderbourne</hi> meet; and here it was
that <hi>Egbert,</hi> King of the <hi>Weſt Saxons,</hi> in the
Year of our Lord 821, fought the ſecond
Battle againſt the <hi>Mercians,</hi> ſo bloody on both
ſides, that the River <hi>Avon</hi> was all over dyed red
with the Blood of the ſlain; and in the Year
871, <hi>Alfred</hi> having maintained a long Fight
againſt the <hi>Danes,</hi> and upon the firſt Onſet
had ſucceſs, but was at laſt quite routed, his
Forces defeated, and himſelf forced to flee
away to preſerve his life. In the <hi>Saxons</hi> reign
it flouriſhed mightily, and <hi>Edgar</hi> built there
a Nunnery, and made his Daughter <hi>Editha</hi>
Lady Governeſs thereof; afterwards being
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:108032:14"/>
long expoſed to the fury of the <hi>Danes,</hi> who
were its Mortal Enemies, and deſerted the
Biſhops of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> who were at firſt its Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters,
it went to decay, and almoſt return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
again on a ſudden into its firſt Principle
of Nothing; and ſo old <hi>Salisbury</hi> then, and
ſince new <hi>Salisbury</hi> which hath ſprang from
that, have quite extinguiſhed its Primitive
Luſtre and Glory. Old <hi>Salisbury</hi> was ſituated
upon a Hill, expoſed much to Winds and
Storms, very dry, barren and uncomfortable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
by reaſon of the great Defect of Water
throughout the whole City; it was well for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified,
as appears by ſome ancient pieces o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
Walls which are there ſtill to be ſeen. The
<hi>Saxons,</hi> in the Year 553, firſt Sacked it, and
took it, and in the Reign of <hi>Edward</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond,
<hi>Oſmund,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Sherbourne,</hi> Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
the See hither, and built a Cathedral
Church, though the <hi>Danes</hi> not long after, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
took and burnt the City, that likewiſe
underwent the ſame fatal Calamity, and was
levelled with the ground, till both of them
were raiſed again in <hi>William the Conqueror</hi>'s
time; for after that he had made his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs
throughout all his Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi>
he at laſt Summoned all the Three Orders of
the Nation to come hither, and here to take
their Oaths of Allegiance to him: But after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
in the Reign of <hi>Richard</hi> the Firſt, the
Citizens being oppreſſed by the Inſolence of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:108032:14"/>
the Soldiers, which then kept Garriſon, and
was in great want for Water, reſolved to free
themſelves from theſe Burdens, by Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planting
themſelves into another Soil, which
they unanimouſly agreed upon, and ſeated
themſelves about a Mile from this place in a
more pleaſant Valley, where the flowry
Meads, and Chryſtial-ſtream'd Rivers, gave
them a more hearty Welcome, and far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
Entertainment than before they were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted
withal. After a new Colony was
Tranſplanted hither, <hi>Richard Pore,</hi> firſt Biſhop
of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> then of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> afterwards of
<hi>Durham,</hi> did likewiſe Tranſplant the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral
from the barren, dry place in which it
was erected near to the old Caſtle of the
Earls of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and built it in a more
plentiful Soil; this moſt pious Prelate, for he
did not only Tranſplant it, but (by the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
and Contrivance of the moſt excellent
and ingenious Artificers, not only Natives,
but Foreigners, whom he drew hither by his
large Rewards) he raiſed it to that Splender
and Magnificence, that now it matches with the
ſtalieſt of Structures, for the rare Workmanſhip
thereof throughout the Nation. The Steeple
is built in the form of a Pyramid very high,
and as the Pole Star directs the Pilot at Sea,
ſo doth this Spire direct the wandring Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller
over the Plain, diſcovering its lofty
head at the diſtance of 20 Miles, as we were
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:108032:15"/>
credibly inform'd; but the admirableneſs of
the Structure conſiſts in this, That it hath as
many Pillars as there are Hours in the Year,
and theſe not cloſe but you may ſee the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertices
betwixt them, and ſhake thoſe that
are of the leſſer ſize, and there is as many
Windows as there are Days in the Year, and
theſe very artificially Adorned, and curiouſly
Painted to admiration; and there is likewiſe
as many Doors as there is Weeks in the Year,
and as many Chappels as Months. Thus did
this great Prelate, which by augmenting it,
augment his own Fame, and even Cannoniz
himſelf: And as the Church was then re-e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dified,
ſo was the City much enlarged too
by the Citizens, and for the more ſweetneſs,
as well as cleanlineſs of their Habitations,
they made ſeveral Channels and Rivolets in
the midſt of their Streets very commodious
and beneficial to them. Thus, by degrees,
Old <hi>Salisbury</hi> is vaniſhed away, and very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
to be ſeen in it, but the Ruins and old
Walls of the Earl's Caſtle, and one ſmall
Dwelling-houſe, and New <hi>Salisbury</hi> is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
glorious and aimable, reſorted to, and
frequented and admired by Perſons of all
Qualities and Degrees; for its Houſes are
ſtately, its Churches magnificent, its Streets
clean, its Rivers pleaſant and well ſtored with
Fiſh, its Gardens delightful and very fragrant,
and nothing wanting in it to pleaſe either
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:108032:15"/>
the Eye or the Pallate; it is governed by a
Mayor and Aldermen. Thus have I given
you a brief Account of <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> I could have
wrote much more, for there are many other
things very obſervable in this County, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
for Travellers to take notice of, which
is too tedious here to relate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Summerſetſhire.</head>
                  <p>The firſt Place of Note we came to in this
County was <hi>Wells,</hi> the chief City of the
Shire, and receives its Denomination from the
variety of freſh and wholſome Springs which
bubble up about it in great abundance. The
Houſes therein are well contrived, and built of
Stone, the Government ſafe and regular, but
the chief Ornament hereof is the Cathedral,
built by King <hi>Ina</hi> in honour to St. <hi>Andrew;</hi>
the Church hath been enriched with large
Revenues by religious Benefactors; it was
made a Biſhop's See in the Reign of King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi>
the Second, and <hi>Eadulphus</hi> was Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted
the firſt Biſhop here in the Reign of
<hi>William Rufus,</hi> and in the Year 1092, <hi>John,</hi> a
<hi>Turon</hi> born, being elected Biſhop, united that
of <hi>Bath</hi> with this; and hence it comes to
paſs, that he that is Biſhop of this See, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells.</hi> This Church
underwent the ſame Calamities that other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious
Places did in this Kingdom, and took
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:108032:16"/>
away the Revenues annexed to it; 'tis a
magnificent Structure, and the Quire of it
yeilds to none for ſtatelineſs; if we conſider
the artificial Boſſes very delicately gilded
which adorn it above, or the curious Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumns
which uphold it below, or the Biſhop's
Seat of Marble, ſet out with moſt glorious
Embelliſhments, ſupported with rich Pillars,
and with its towring Piramids, being the
Head and Ornament in a more eſpecial man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
of the Quire, as he is of the Church; to
this I may add the variety of carved Images,
which almoſt environ the Church on the
out ſide, containing the Hiſtory of the Old
Teſtament, and the curious Architecture of
the Chapter-houſe, ſupported only by one
large Column which ſtands in the middle of
it. Near unto the Church is the Biſhop's Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace
of great Grandeur, which becomes a
Reverend Father of the Church to be ſeated ed
in. But the remarkableſt, and which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
but have the reſpect of all Travellers to
be the moſt admirable piece of Nature's
Workmanſhip in our Kingdom, is a Place
called <hi>Ochy-hole,</hi> two Miles from this City:
'Tis a Cave under a very high Rock, ſitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
amongſt the <hi>Mendippe-hills,</hi> of which I
ſhall endeavour to give a Deſcription as
briefly as I can.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:108032:16"/>
                     <hi>OCHY-HOLE.</hi> After that we had, with
ſome difficulty, climbed up to the top of a
Rock, we went along the Brow of a Hill till
we came to the Mouth of the Cave, where
opening a Door that gave entrance, and ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
24 Candles of 6 in the Pound, which we
provided for that purpoſe, we ventured in;
being got within it, we found the Cave very
hollow, and ſo dark, that the Candles there
ſcarce burning ſo bright, though there were
24, as two doth ordinary in the Night in
one of our largeſt Rooms; we thought cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
we had been come into the Confines
of the Infernal Regions, or ſome ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal
Place, and began to be affraid to viſit it,
<hi>viz. That although we entered in frolickſome
and merry, yet we might return out of it Sad
and Penſive, and never more be ſeen to Laugh
whilſt we lived in the World;</hi> ſuch dreadful
Apprehenſions ſeized upon ſome of us; and
indeed we had cauſe to fear ſome ſuch O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations
might have proceeded from this,
as well as the other, ſince both were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually
uncomfortable, by reaſon of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privation
from the leaſt glimmerings of light,
and conſequently had the ſame Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
to beget both Horror and Amazement:
however we plucked up our Spirits, and crept
in one after another as faſt as we could conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently:
The Cave as we went a long was
parted into ſeveral kinds of Rooms, the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:108032:17"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:108032:17"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:108032:18"/>
Names whereof our Guides informed us:
The firſt was the Kitchin, and at the Door
ſticks out a large Maſs of the Rock, which,
they tell us, was the Porter's head, formerly
the Keeper of this Cave; it bears the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance
of a Head, and by that lies a Stone
which they call <hi>The Tombſtone,</hi> under which,
the Report is, That his Body lies Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
and his Dogherd by him in the ſame
ſubſtance; yet their Transformations are not
ſo ſtrange and wonderful, being ſomething
too fabulous to be given Credit to, as the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety
which the Rock affords into which they
are incorporated, part of it gliſtering like
Silver, and part like Diamonds, and both ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
very pleaſant to the Eye: A little fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
on the right hand is another piece of the
Rock that bears the reſemblance of a Bell, and
on the left hand a Veſſel, which they term
a But, in which the Beer of an old Sorcereſs,
(Couſin to the famous <hi>Circe,</hi> Lady Governeſs
of this diſmal Cave,) uſed to be work'd in;
'tis a hollow Ceſtern of a conſiderable depth
always filled with Water, and now and then
flowing over, to which the drops of Water
which continually trickle down from the
top of the Rock add every moment freſh
ſupplies; hard by this ſtands another Veſſel
of hers, in which, they ſay, ſhe made her
Mault, they call it the <hi>Eaſt Hurdle,</hi> 'tis like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
hollow, and of a pretty depth. Now
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:108032:18"/>
appears unto your view the old Witch her
ſelf, heating of her Furnace which ſeems
black and ſooty; it ſeems to be Alablaſter,
by reaſon of its whiteneſs, though 'tis moſt
probable to be the product of Nature, and
not of Art, becauſe the place is very unfit
and very unſuitable for any Artiſt to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
his Skill in, it being very oft ſo low,
that it is impoſſible here and there for any
one to ſtand upright in it; and therefore it
was that we were forced frequently to ſtoop,
and buckle almoſt double for fear of hiting
our Heads againſt the Rock, until we came
to ſome Steps which we were to deſcend,
and the Defect thereto was very tedious and
affrightful, for on the right hand the Rock
hung down over us extream low and ſloping,
and on the left hand a great Rivolet which
runs along through the Cave, being pretty
deep, and making a loud noiſe in its gliding,
yet at length we came ſweating into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Room which is called <hi>The Hall,</hi> and
here, at firſt ſight, we were entertained with
as great a Rarity as <hi>Nature</hi> hath in all her
Store-houſes, 'tis a Ceſtern almoſt ſquare,
about ſix Foot each way, and of a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
depth, always brimful of Water, ſupplied
by the Drops which falls from above; but
that which is to be admired in it is this, tho'
the Water be conſtantly droping, and is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually
brimful, yet it never runs over, as
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:108032:19"/>
our Guides told us. Round about this Hall
hangs four Stones reſembling four Fletches
of Bacon, for the outſide is blackiſh and the
inſide white; in this place the Daughter of
the old Sorcereſs had took up her Reſidence,
and appears to your eye like the Statue of a
Woman that is great with Child; ſhe is of a
different colour from her Mother, being
much more dusky than ſhe is: But nothing
more pretty to behold here than thoſe
which they call <hi>The Organ Pipes</hi> placed upon
one ſide of the Rock, and are very like to
thoſe we have in our Churches, ſome being
of bigger and ſome of leſſer Dimenſions, in
the middle of a good reaſonable thickneſs
though at the ends ſharp and ſlender. After
ſome more Difficulties in our Paſſage, and no
leſs dangerous than before, we came into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
part of the Cave more ſtrange than
any we had yet ſeen. 'Tis a place they call
the <hi>Dancing Room,</hi> ſo well Contriv'd, and ſo
curiouſly ſet forth, that <hi>Nature</hi> hath wrought
here what Art could never do or compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend,
both above and below; if you look up,
the variety of Colours which are there to be
ſeen by the light of the Candles, and the
checquered Configurations of the Rock,
which is now very high above your head;
will both feaſt your Eyes and refreſh your
Body, which by that time is ſufficiently wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
by the tediouſneſs, as well as the trouble
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:108032:19"/>
of the Paſſage; for there is ſo great a gliſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
ſuch a Luſtre as it were of Silver and
precious Stones round about you, that you
would be ready to miſtake your ſelf, and
think that you were in the Palace of ſome
great Monarch of the Earth, and not in ſuch
a diſmal Cave; and if you look down, there
you will find no ſtony, hard, ruggy Tract to
perplex you, but a fine, even, ſandy Flower,
and indeed beyond expectation, that we who
had beheld ſuch craggy Stones and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
Paſſages ſhould at laſt arrive in ſo ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
and delightful a place; they told us,
That it was very uſual for Gentlemen and
Ladies, that lived thereabouts, to bring Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick
and Dance here, the Muſick making a
more ſweeter Melody than ordinary; we
pauſed and breathed a little here, delighting
our ſelves as well with it, as alſo with the
reſemblance of a Chimney, which we took
really to be one, it being of that faſhion, and
having in it a kind of black moiſt Matter,
which, if you touch it, will ſtick to your fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,
and black them like Soot, and yet no
fire was ever known to be there: But we
were not as yet ſatisfied, though we were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
300 Yards under the Ground, and in a
moſt horrid Dungeon, but went ſtill farther
to a place termed <hi>The Seller,</hi> that is curiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
vaulted, and 'tis very uſual to carry Bottles
of Wine and drink there upon a ſtone Table
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:108032:20"/>
which is form'd in it of natural Stone; in
this place lies alſo a great Stone which they
call <hi>The Great Gun,</hi> the nature of it is this,
take it but up in your hands, and let it fall
down to the ground, and a great Gun can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
give a louder Report. We tried the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment
thrice, but we thought the very
Rock we were under would have rent in
pieces about our Ears, yet they that were
half way the Cave, or at the Mouth of it,
heard nothing of any noiſe at all; this we
found experimentally true, for one of the
Perſons that accompanied us in our Journey,
ſtaying a little diſtance in the Cave, being
unwilling to venter any farther, aſſured us
when we came back, that he had not
heard any noiſe at all; we ventured a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
farther, and at the end of the Celler,
when we had gone down ſome few Steps,
we found a great Rivolet ſeveral Yards deep,
but as clear as Chryſtial, and pleaſant to the
Taſte, but very cold; it gave a Period to our
Journey. It runs under ground, though its
Head from whence it firſt ſprings is like that
of the River <hi>Nilus</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> which is not yet,
or at leaſt very difficult to be diſcovered,
conveying it ſelf out of this Cave, it ſets
30 Mills on work after it comes into the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent
County, as we were informed. When
we had got thus far, and almoſt a Mile un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
ground, as our Guides told us, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:108032:20"/>
to think how we ſhould return and get
out ſafe, being afraid to find the ſame diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty
and trouble we had encountered with
in our Entrance; for tho' the Place was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
reſembling an Infernal Abbyſs, and
our Paſſage into it proved ſo troubleſome
and irkſome, yet we came back without any
toil, or rather with great facility and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
notwithſtanding 'tis impoſſible to find
out the way without a Guide, there being
ſo many Turnings and Windings; nor could
the Guides themſelves, without a light,
find the way out of this forlorn place, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
they ſteer their Courſe: However, at
laſt, we made a ſhift to creep up again to the
top of the Rock, juſt as merry <hi>Lucian</hi> tells us
old <hi>Menippus</hi> did out of a hole in <hi>Lebadia,</hi>
after he returned from Hell, and had ended
the Diſcourſes with the Ghoſts below. Thus
have I given you a ſmall Relation of this
wonderful Rarerity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>GLASTENBURY</hi> lies four Miles from
<hi>Wells,</hi> a Place of great Antiquity, as any
whatſoever in the Kingdom; for the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
thereof is deducted from <hi>Joſeph of Arima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thea,</hi>
who, together with <hi>Mary Magdalen, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi>
and <hi>Martha,</hi> was ſent hither by St. <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi>
the Apoſtle of the <hi>Gauls,</hi> to preach the
Goſpel about 63 Years after Chriſt, and
were buried here themſelves, upon which
account it was, in proceſs of time, very
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:108032:21"/>
much enlarged by pious Princes, King <hi>Ina</hi>
who was the firſt here, that cauſed his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
to pay <hi>Peter-Pence</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> rebuilt
the Abby which was then gone much to
decay; to which he added a very fine and
ſtately Church, dedicated to Chriſt, S. <hi>Peter,</hi>
and S. <hi>Paul;</hi> and that which is very remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable
here, is the Kitchin of the Abbots, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
20 foot high, built in the form of a Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramid
of pure Stone, and divided into four
Angles or Corners; to each of which were
allotted a Window and a Chimney: But all
of them went to rack, and were razed to the
ground, and there is nothing left now but
the Ruins to proclaim its former Glory and
Magnificence; and to reckon up all the Kings
of the Weſt-Saxons that were buried here
would be too tedious.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Walnut-Tree</hi> and <hi>Holy Hawthorn.</hi> But
to come nearer to our own days, here was
ſomething not many years ſince very notable
and ſtrange: The <hi>Walnut-Tree</hi> in the holy
Churchyard, that did never put out any
Leaves before S. <hi>Barnabas</hi> day, and upon that
very day grew rank and full of Leaves; and
the <hi>Hawthorn</hi> in <hi>Wiral</hi> Park, that always on
<hi>Chriſtmas-day</hi> ſprouted forth as if in <hi>May,</hi> both
deſerve Credit, as well as Admiration: For
the truth of both theſe we were credibly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd
of divers Perſons Inhabitants of this
Place; and that theſe Trees, through the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:108032:21"/>
Malice and Fury of ſome Perſon in the late
Warrs, were cut down and deſtroy'd: But
many things here are very obſervable, which
I have not room to inſert.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BATH.</hi> It lying low and all ſides ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded
with Hills, the Town is well water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
with Springs, though ſome of them are
ſulphureous and bad to the Taſt; environ'd
with a Wall, very commodious for its Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-place,
and handſomly adorn'd with three
Churches; one whereof is very large and
ſpatious, built in the form of a Cathedral;
the Steeple is four-ſquare, and hath a Ring
of very tunable Bells, and a Quire with very
ſweet Organs; and in it are erected ſeveral
antient and ſtately Monuments of Perſons of
Quality, and Biſhops of this See, who have
been noble Benefactors to it; 'tis governed
by a Mayor and Aldermen, and the Aſſizes
are generally kept there in the Summer
time: But that which is moſt remarkable
here, and cauſeth a Concourſe in the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
not only of the Nobility and Gentry,
but of the Commonalty too, from all parts
of the Nation hither, are the <hi>Baths,</hi> which are
not inferiour to any that ever <hi>Italy</hi> or <hi>France</hi>
could glory in; they have without queſtion
cured many weak and feeble Limbs, and do
cure divers Diſeaſes which are incident and
deſtructive to Humane Nature; by cauſing
Men to ſweat either more or leſs, propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:108032:22"/>
to their Diſtempers. Who they
were that firſt found them out is very uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,
whether <hi>Bleyden</hi> alias <hi>Bladud</hi> the Son of
<hi>Rudhudibras</hi> the Magician, or <hi>Julius Coeſar,</hi>
I ſhall not undertake to determine the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie:
However they are of very great
Antiquity, and 'tis many hundred years ſince
their powerful Vertues were firſt diſcovered,
though they are all different in their Nature,
as well as their Operation; as the learned
Dr. <hi>Stubbs</hi> by divers Experiments aſſures us.
The Baths are in number ſix; the King and
Queens Baths, the <hi>Croſs Bath,</hi> the <hi>Hot Bath,</hi>
the <hi>Leper's Bath,</hi> and the <hi>Horſe:</hi> That which
is the Chief is the <hi>Croſs Bath,</hi> the Water
whereof being more mild than the other,
the Orders are very ſtrict and regular. And
Perſons of the greateſt Quality of the Nation
chuſe to bath themſelves here, and to drink
the Water thereof; hard by this ſtands the
<hi>Hot Bath,</hi> not much frequented ſave by thoſe
who having quite loſt the Uſe of their Limbs,
come hither to ſeek remedy: Not far from
this is that they call the <hi>Leper's Bath,</hi> which
is believed to be very efficacious againſt that
ſpreading Diſeaſe: And an Hoſpital, or Spit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,
built by <hi>Reginald</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Bath,</hi> for the
Uſe and Benefit of poor, aged, decrepid Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.
About the middle of the Town, near
to the great Church are the King and Queens
Baths, the Water of the one flowing into
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:108032:22"/>
the other; and the difference is, that the
King's Bath is large, and the Queens leſſer
in circumference; and I was credibly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
that there hath been found here an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient
Statue of <hi>Hercules,</hi> amongſt other great
Monuments of Antiquity, holding a Serpent
in his hand; which was found in the Ruins
of a famous Temple, that once ſtood here,
near this place: And it might be thought
very convenient, as well as reaſonable, that
<hi>Hercules,</hi> who expoſed himſelf to ſuch diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties
and manifold dangers, and underwent
ſuch hard and unſupportable Labours, ſhould
now and then eaſe and refreſh his weary
Limbs by ſuch Purgations as the Baths could
afford him. In this, and other Baths, hang
divers Crutches of lame and decrepit Perſons,
which they left behind them as Trophies of
their Recovery, being perfectly cured of their
Lameneſs and Infirmity, and reſtored again
to their former Health and Strength. Laſt
of all, that which is called the <hi>Horſe Bath,</hi>
is very effectual for the Cure of lame and
foundred Horſes, and the removal of ſome
other Diſtempers. Thus have I given a
ſhort account of the Bath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Many things
there are more in this County very obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
for all Travellers to take notice of,
which I think too tedious to relate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:108032:23"/>
                  <head>Briſtol.</head>
                  <p>The next Place we went to in theſe Parts
was <hi>Briſtol,</hi> which is undoubtedly the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
City of <hi>England,</hi> which if we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the Statelineſs of the Buildings; or its
Natural, or Artificial Fortifications; the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modiouſneſs
of its Harbours, and its moſt
pleaſant Situation betwixt the two Rivers of
<hi>Avon</hi> and <hi>Frome;</hi> its lofty Churches, and
its ſtately Palaces; the great Concourſe of
Foreigners, as well as the great Number of
Natives, Citizens: Upon which account, no
Wonder if both the Counties of <hi>Somerſet</hi> and
<hi>Glouceſter</hi> do contend which of them may be
moſt glorious and happy, in its Superiority
over them; and yet neither of them can at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
to that Honour, it being both City and
County of itſelf, and having particular Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges,
Immunities, and Laws of its own:
'Tis governed by a Mayor and two Sheriffs,
twelve Aldermen, with other Miniſters and
Officers befitting its dignity; 'tis environ'd
with a double Wall, and adorn'd with two
navigable Rivers, <hi>Avon</hi> at Spring-Tides is
11 or 12 Fathom deep, and <hi>Frome;</hi> over
which ſtands a Bridge beautified with curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Edifices, conſiſting of four large Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches:
It is very convenient for the Ships
and great Veſſels to anchor in, and hath a
Key in it very commodious for the export<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:108032:23"/>
and importing of Goods, out or into the
Merchants Houſes: This returns back into
the River <hi>Avon;</hi> and ſo both by their mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
Union enrich this City, and augment
its Happineſs At what time it was firſt built
is very hard to determine, but it ſeems to
have been of latter years, becauſe we find it
no where ſpoken of by Hiſtorians in the times
of the <hi>Danes,</hi> when they made their Invade
into this Nation: And it is ſuppoſed to take
its riſe in the Declination of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,
at the time when <hi>Harold</hi> is ſaid to have
ſailed from <hi>Briſtol,</hi> with a great Navy, into
<hi>Wales;</hi> which was about 213 years before
our Saviour's Incarnation. <hi>Robert,</hi> Biſhop of
<hi>Conſtance,</hi> made choice of this place firſt to
begin his War in, which he deſigned againſt
<hi>William Rufus;</hi> and did encompaſs it with
the inner Wall, as ſome conjecture, part of
which in ſome places is ſtill to be ſeen; and
from that time it hath received great En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largment,
and by degrees is riſen to that
we now behold it in: As its Houſes are fair,
and its Streets clear; ſo are its Gates ſtrong
and its Churches glorious, conſiſting of
nineteen Pariſh-Churches, whereof that
which is the Cathedral, and Mother-Church,
dedicated to S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
by King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th. with Revenues
for a Biſhop's See; yet notwithſtanding this,
the Church of <hi>Ratcliff</hi> in the Suburbs of this
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:108032:24"/>
City is a more noble Structure, being curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
Arched, and made a ſtately Fabrick all
of pure Stone, without any Addition of
Beams, or Rafters of Timber, no not one
Stick to be found throughout the whole
Building; the Steeple is four ſquare, and of
a great height, but moſt artificially carved
with divers Sculptures, all at the coſt and
charges of one Mr. <hi>Cannius</hi> a Merchant of
this City about 108 years ſince, who in the
erecting this famous piece of Architecture,
employ'd at his own Expence 800 Labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
and Artificers, beſides Maſons and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penters
to the number 300, in all 1100, for
2 years together; until the Work was total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
compleated; and in it his Monument doth
ſtand in Marble: May his Memory be more
laſting, than that Marble which is ſet to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
it; and his Name more durable than
any Monument, and remain to ſucceeding
Generations.</p>
                  <p>S. <hi>Vincent</hi>'s <hi>Rocks.</hi> On the Northern ſide
of this City are ſeveral high and craggy
Rocks, by which the River <hi>Avon</hi> gently glides
along, till it returns back again into the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern;</hi>
one of the chief whereof is called
S. <hi>Vincent</hi>'s <hi>Rock,</hi> which hath great plenty of
pellucid Stones, commonly called <hi>Briſtol-ſtones;</hi>
the learned Mr. <hi>Cambden</hi> hath obſerved, that
their Pellucidneſs is beyond that of the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond
we receive from the <hi>Indies;</hi> only the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:108032:24"/>
Hardneſs of the latter gives them the pre-emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence;
and yet certainly Nature never made
greater demonſtrations of her Art, having
made ſome of theſe Stones as ſmooth as the
moſt expert Jeweller could have done, as
round and ſharp, as broad above and ſmall
beneath, as the greateſt Artiſt could have ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected;
ſhaping ſome of them with four, ſome
of them with ſix Angles apiece, like the Stones
which we uſually ſet in Rings. To make us
ſtill the more admire her Perfections, ſhe hath
not given them all one colour, but ſome of
them are like Chryſtal, clear; and ſome of
a more ruddy colour, and ſanguine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion,
according to the nature of the Soil;
ſhe cauſeth her Productions not to be unlike
their great Parent.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Hot Well.</hi> There is one thing ſtill
here very remarkable, and that is the <hi>Hot
Well,</hi> which is juſt at the bottom of this Rock,
and at the very brink of the River <hi>Avon;</hi> yet
it ſtill retains its natural Head, and by its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
Ebullitions purgeth away all the Scum
and ſaltiſh froth it might have contracted by
the Sea; the Water is exceeding wholeſome,
and very good to purge away ill Humors, and
purifie the Blood; and I was there credibly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
that it hath wrought great Cures, and
is much frequented and reſorted to by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
ſorts of People.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:108032:25"/>
                  <head>Devonſhire.</head>
                  <p>The next County we went to in theſe
Parts, was <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> where we made but
little Stay: The Air is ſharp and wholeſome,
the Soil hilly and woody; and they uſe here,
as they do likewiſe in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> Sea-Sand to
mend and inrich their Land. The chief Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities
of this County are, Wooll, Kerſeys,
Sea-Fiſh, and Sea-Fowl; and the Weſt of it is
well ſtored with Tin Mines, and Loadſtones
have been found upon <hi>Dartmore</hi> Rocks of
good value and vertue, ſo at other places in
this County are found Mines of Lead, and
ſome Veins of Silver.</p>
                  <p>Upon <hi>Exmore</hi> Foreſt are ſuch huge Stones,
and placed confuſedly as they are upon <hi>Saliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi>
Plain, and one of them hath <hi>Daniſh</hi> Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
upon it directing Paſſengers that way. At
<hi>Hubbleſtow</hi> in this County was a Battle fought
by the <hi>Danes,</hi> where their Banner called <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fan,</hi>
in which they repoſed all their confidence,
of Victory and Succeſs, was notwithſtanding
taken, and <hi>Hubba</hi> their General ſlain.</p>
                  <p>The People of this County are ſtrong; and
well made, and as they have a peculiar ſort of
quaking Pudding, which they call Whitepots,
ſo the Women have a peculiar kind of Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
which they wear upon their Shoulders,
called Whittles; they are of divers Colours
made like Mantles, with Fringes about the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:108032:25"/>
Edges, without which the common ſort of
People never ride to Market, nor appear in
publick.</p>
                  <p>In divers places of this County the ways are
ſo rocky and narrow, that it is not poſſible
for Waggons to paſs, ſo that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
People are forced in Harveſt time to
carry home their Corn upon Horſes in certain
Crooks made for that purpoſe, which creates
no ſmall Toil and Labour to them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>EXETER</hi> is the principal City in this
Province, ſituated upon the Eaſtward by the
Banks of the River <hi>Ex,</hi> or <hi>Iſe,</hi> upon a little
Hill, gently ariſing with an eaſie Aſcent to
a pretty height, the Pendant whereof lies Eaſt
and Weſt, environed about with Ditches
and very ſtrong Walls, having many Turrets
orderly interpoſed, and ſix Gates which
gives entrance into the City, and contains
about a Mile and half in circumference; the
Suburbs branch forth a great way on each
ſide; the Streets are broad, kept clean and
well paved; the Houſes are as gay within as
trim without; there are Seventeen Pariſh-Churches,
and in the very higheſt part of the
City near the <hi>Eaſt Gate</hi> is a Caſtle, formerly
the Seat of the <hi>Weſt Saxon</hi> Kings, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
the Earls of <hi>Cornwal,</hi> which <hi>Baldwin
de Redures</hi> the Governor holding out againſt
King <hi>Stephen,</hi> was by ſcarcity of Proviſions
forced to Surrender, and after the ſurrendry,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:108032:26"/>
he, with his whole Family was baniſhed that
Kingdom. Juſt without the <hi>Eaſt Gate</hi> are
two pleaſant Walks call <hi>Southney</hi> and <hi>North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi>
beſet on both ſides with Rowes of high
Trees, which being mounted up aloft afford
a curious Proſpect to <hi>Topeſham,</hi> the place
where all the Ships and Veſſels of the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens
lie at Anchor, from whence (ſince the
River was ſtopt up by certain Dams or Wears
that <hi>Edward Courtney,</hi> Earl of <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> for
ſome Diſtaſte that he had took from the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
cauſed here to be made) all their Goods
and Commodities are brought home by
Land. In the ſame quarter of the City ſtands
the Cathedral founded by King <hi>Athelſtan</hi> in
honour to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Edward the Confeſſor</hi>
made it the Biſhop's See of <hi>Cornwall</hi> and <hi>Kir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi>
and Conſtituted the firſt Biſhop thereof,
who Succeſſors augmented it greatly both in
Edifices and Revenues, and <hi>William,</hi> the Ninth
Biſhop after him, when the Monks were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted
brought in a Dean and Four and
Twenty Prebendaries, to which has been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
in our times, four Arch-Deacons. In the
Church are Six private Chappels, and a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary
very handſomly built and finiſhed by a
Phyſician of this City; the Quire is curiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
beautified and adorned, eſpecially with
Organs, whoſe Pipes, though they are of a
larger ſize than any which ever we beheld in
any Cathedral beſides, yet the Muſick is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:108032:26"/>
pleaſing and melodious to the Ear.
All which Additions hath been erected ſince
the Return of K. <hi>Charles</hi> II.</p>
                  <p>On the Weſt ſide of this City runs the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,
over which is built a ſtrong Stone-bridge
with four Arches, and about the middle of
the City is the Town-Hall, where the Aſſizes
and Seſſions are held for the City, it being
both City and County of it ſelf. 'Tis gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
by a Mayor, two Sheriffs, four and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
Aldermen, a Recorder and Town-Clerk,
with other Officers befitting the Grandeur of
ſo honourable a Place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Plimouth.</head>
                  <p>So called from the River <hi>Plime</hi> which runs
along by it, where is one of the largeſt and
moſt ſecureſt Haven in <hi>England,</hi> for before
the very Mouth of it lies St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> Iſland,
ſtrongly fortified both by Art and Nature,
and in the Haven are Fortifications laid on
both ſides for the ſafe Riding of Ships, and
the annoyance to Enemies. One the one ſide
is Mount <hi>Batton,</hi> in which is a ſtrong Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
having twelve Guns mounted upon its
Platforms, and on the other ſide the Cittadel
which may, for Strength, compare with moſt
Places in the Nation, commanding both the
Sea and Town at Pleaſure; without the Walls
of the Cittadel runs a Trench, out of which
was digged a certain kind of Marble with
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:108032:27"/>
which they were built, being Eleven Foot
thick at the bottom, and Seven at the top,
and three quarters of a Mile in compaſs; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the Walls are placed divers Watch-Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
and each of them are adorned with a
round Ball upon the top, ſo curiouſly gilded
and painted with the King's Arms, that they
make a very great gliſtering ſhew at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance;
and round about are placed between
two and three hundred Pieces of Ordnance.
There are two Gates, and as many Draw-Bridges
which gives entrance into the Caſtle,
and upon the Front are admirably carved
the Arms of his Majeſty, by which is placed
his Royal Statue, with the Arms of the Earl
of <hi>Bath</hi> who is Governor hereof; within the
Walls is the Governor's houſe, and divers Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partments
for Soldiers, a Magazine for Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition,
and a Store-houſe for Proviſions:
For the Strength and Conveniencies of this
Fortreſs, which is almoſt impregnable, the
Town is much obliged to the excellent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity
of Monſieur <hi>Bernard de Gum,</hi> his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's
Engineer.</p>
                  <p>The Commodiouſneſs of the Harbour of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes
cauſeth a Fleet of Ships to ride
here; 'tis now ſo repleniſhed with Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
frequented by Merchants, enriched by
Traffick, that it ſeems to outvey ſome great
Cities of this Kingdom. It is Governed by
a Mayor, Aldermen and Common-Councel,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:108032:27"/>
who have a ſtately <hi>Guild-hall</hi> for their more
ſolemn Conventions, and is adorned with two
handſome Churches.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Cornwall.</head>
                  <p>This place is hilly; one cauſe of a very tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate
heat of the Summer, and the lateneſs
of Harveſt, as its Situation is the cauſe of the
gentleneſs of the Winter. Its Hills are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
with ſhort and narrow Valleys, the Earth
is but ſhallow, underneath is Rocks and
Shelves, ſo that it is hard to be Tilled, and
apt to be parched by a dry Summer. The
middle of the Shire lies open, the Earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of a blackiſh colour, and bears Heath
and Spirry-graſs; there is but little Meadow-ground,
but ſtore of Paſture for Cattle and
Sheep, and plenty of Corn-ground.</p>
                  <p>They have a Stone called here a <hi>Moor-ſtone,</hi>
found upon Moores and waſte Ground, which
ſerves them inſtead of Free-ſtone for Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows,
Doors and Chimnies, it is white with
certain glimmering Sparkles; they have like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
a <hi>Stone</hi> digged out of the Sea-cliffs of
the colour of a grey Marble, and another
as black as Jet, and out of the Inland Queries
they dig Free-ſtone; nor muſt we omit
what is here obſerved of ſome Stones, That
the Sea works the Pebbles upon the ſhoar,
by the frequent rolling of the Waves, into a
kind of roundneſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:108032:28"/>
They have a Slate of three ſorts, Blew,
Sage-leaf coloured and Grey, which laſt is
the worſt, and all theſe Slates are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
found under another kind of Slate that
they Wall with when the depth hath brought
the Workmen to the Water. They alſo make
Lime of a kind of Marble-ſtone by burning
it. There are Copper Mines in ſundry pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
of this County, and the Ore is ſometimes
ſhipped off to be refined in <hi>Wales:</hi> and tho'
<hi>Cicero</hi> will have none in <hi>Brittain,</hi> yet Silver
hath been found in this County in the time
of <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt and Third, who reaped
good profit by it: Nay Tinners do find little
quantities of Gold, and ſometimes Silver a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
the Tin Ore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as I was informed; but
for the generality the Mettal that the Earth
abounds with in this County is Tin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Richard,</hi> Earl of <hi>Cornwall,</hi> Brother to King
<hi>Henry</hi> the Third, was the firſt that began to
make Ordinances for theſe Tin works, and
afterwards <hi>Edmund</hi> his Son granted a Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
and certain Liberties, and preſcribed
withal certain Laws concerning the ſame,
which he ratified or ſtrengthened under his
Seal, and impoſed a Rent, or Tribute upon
Tin to be paid unto the Earls; theſe Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
Privileges and Laws King <hi>Edward</hi> the
Third afterwards confirm'd and augmented.</p>
                  <p>In ſome places on the Sea Coaſts there are
Pearls found that breed in big Oiſters and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:108032:28"/>
Muſles, yet though they are great they are
not good; here are alſo Aget and white Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,
as they ſay, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the Weſt Parts of
<hi>Cornwall</hi> there are Bents growing on Sandy
Fields, which are knit from over the head
in narrow breadths, after a ſtrange faſhion,
of which they make Mats: Many other
things here are very obſervable in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
but I ſhall forbear mentioning any more,
becauſe it will ſeem tedious.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Dorſetſhire.</head>
                  <p>'Tis a County of very fertil Soil, well
ſhaded with Woods, enriched with Paſture,
and covered with great Flocks of Sheep.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PORTLAND,</hi> although ſome would
have deriv'd its Name for its lying over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the Port of <hi>Weymouth,</hi> yet it ſeems rather
to have receiv'd it from one <hi>Port,</hi> a Noble
<hi>Saxon,</hi> who about the Year 703, grievouſly
infeſted and annoyed theſe Coaſts. This ſame
<hi>Portland</hi> was very much expoſed to the <hi>Daniſh</hi>
outrage, but after their Wars were over, it
fell into the Poſſeſſion of the Church of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi>
when <hi>Emma,</hi> Mother to <hi>Edward the
Confeſſor,</hi> being Accuſed by her Son with too
great familiarity with <hi>Aldwin,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi>
and having cleared herſelf of that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt
Imputation, by ſuffering (which in thoſe
Days was a uſual Trial of Chaſtity) in wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:108032:29"/>
bear-foot upon Nine <hi>Culters</hi> of red hot
Iron, which ſhe did to a Miracle, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
harm or prejudice to her ſelf; ſhe for a
Memorial hereof, beſtowed Nine Lordſhips
upon the See of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> to which her Son
added this Iſland, with many other Revenues,
to expiate the Crime of this defamitory Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion,
and unjuſt Accuſation of his Mother's
Honeſty. The Iſland is about ſeven Miles in
compaſs, riſing up about the ſides with high
Rocks, but lying low and flat in the midſt,
inhabited ſcatteringly here and there, plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
enough of Corn, and very good to feed
Sheep, but great ſcarcity of Wood. The
ancienteſt of their Inhabitants do find a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
the Weeds of the Sea a thing grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
without Leaves like Coral, which when
it is cut waxeth hard and black, but 'tis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
brittle, and if it fall it ſoon breaketh; it
grows amongſt that Sea-Weed called <hi>Alga;</hi>
here is likewiſe divers Querries of excellent
Stone, which is conveyed into divers Parts
of this Nation, and eſpecially to <hi>London</hi> for
the rebuilding of Churches; on the Eaſt ſide
there is only one Church, and ſome few
Houſes ſtanding cloſe thereto; and on the
North ſide is a Caſtle built by King <hi>Henry</hi> the
Eighth, which being well Fortified, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
the Entrance into the Haven of <hi>Wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth.</hi>
From hence we went to <hi>Dorcheſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:108032:29"/>
                     <hi>DORCHESTER</hi> is about 7 Miles from
the Sea, and is the Head Town of the whole
Shire, watered by a ſmall River, but neither
very large nor beautiful, being much decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
and long ſince diſpoiled of its Walls by
the <hi>Danes,</hi> who raiſed, as it thought, certain
Trenches, whereof one is called <hi>Maumbury</hi>
being an Acre inditched, another <hi>Poundbury</hi>
ſomewhat greater, and the third a Mile off
as a Camp with fine Trenches containing near
ten Acres called <hi>Maiden-Caſtle,</hi> which, in all
probability, was a <hi>Roman</hi> Station; but that
which argues its Antiquity is the Coin of
the <hi>Romans</hi> both Copper and Silver found
there, and eſpecially at <hi>Fordington,</hi> hard by
which the common People call King <hi>Dorne</hi>'s
Pence, whom by ſome Alluſion to the Name
they think him to be the Founder of the
Town. It had anciently a Caſtle in that
place, where the <hi>Grey-Friars</hi> built their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
out of the Ruins thereof. It has three
Pariſh Churches, and ſeveral Alms-houſes
for the ſupport and maintenance of poor
impotent People, and it was formerly a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
Place for the Manufacture of Cloth, and
is now for Sheep, of which there are huge
Numbers to the great benefit and enriching
of the County. The next Shire we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd
to purſue our Progreſs in was <hi>Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi>
of which it follows.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:108032:30"/>
                  <head>Hampſhire.</head>
                  <p>We went out of <hi>Dorſetſhire</hi> through ſome
part of <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> which I have already men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned,
and ſo came into the Confines of
<hi>Hampſhire,</hi> and paſt through part of <hi>New
Forreſt,</hi> where along the Eaſt is the Banks of
the River <hi>Avon. William the Conqueror</hi> demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed
all the Towns, Villages, both Houſes
and Churches far and near, and likewiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected
the Inhabitants; after having done
ſo, he made all the ground within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs
of 20 Miles into a Forreſt, or Harbour
for Wild Beaſts, and ſo it was called <hi>New
Forreſt;</hi> and this he did, either that the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi>
might arrive more ſecurely in this
place <hi>(Normandy</hi> lying juſt over againſt it)
in caſe new Broils ſhould ariſe after his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts,
or for the Pleaſure he took in Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
or elſe to encreaſe his Treaſure; for
being better affected, and more favourable
to Beaſts than Men, he impoſed very heavy
Fines and Penalties, yea, and moſt grievous
Puniſhments upon all ſuch Perſons as did
meddle with the Game; but it ſeems the
Children ſuffered for the Cruelty of their
Father, for <hi>Richard,</hi> his ſecond Son, and <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam
Rufus,</hi> who Succeeded him, both periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in this Forreſt, the one with a Blaſt of
peſtilent Air, the other with an Arrow ſhot
by chance by Sir <hi>Walter Tirrel: Henry</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:108032:30"/>
his Grandchild by his eldeſt Son <hi>Robert,</hi>
whilſt he was here in the hot purſute after
his Game, was caught up by a Bough, where
in a very ſhort time he underwent the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
Fate of poor <hi>Abſolom.</hi> The firſt Town
of Note we came to in this County was
<hi>Southampton,</hi> which is ſituated betwixt two
Rivers, the one running forth at the Weſt
ſide called <hi>Teſt,</hi> and the other on the Eaſt.
The Town is fair and hath ſtately Buildings,
with two commodious Keys which do high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
adorn it, and the great concourſe of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants
which Trade to Foreign Parts do
mightily enrich it. There are five Pariſh-Churches,
with one for the <hi>French,</hi> likewiſe
it hath a ſtrong Wall and ſeven Gates, with
a Caſtle upon a Mount caſt up to a great
height built by <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, and it
was made a Corporation by <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth,
who Conſtituted it both Town and County,
which doth abundantly dignifie it. It hath
three Markets a week, and that for Fiſh is five
Days in a Week; 'tis likewiſe of great Note
for building of Merchant's Ships. After ſome
ſmall ſtay here we went to <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> of
which take this following Account.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Wincheſter.</head>
                  <p>I find it to have been a Place of great An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity,
and that it was in great Requeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
the <hi>Romans.</hi> In this City was <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:108032:31"/>
who, was become a Monk, ſaluted
<hi>Caeſar</hi> by the Order of his Father <hi>Conſtantine,</hi>
though afterwards he paid dearly for his
Honour by the loſs of his Life. This was
the chief Seat in which the <hi>Saxons</hi> placed
themſelves, and made it famous by their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting
Magnificent Temples; in the Time
of the <hi>Normans</hi> too it flouriſhed exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
until it was almoſt once or twice quite
deſtroyed by the Sword, but now again 'tis
very fair and populous, large and ſtately, and
is computed to be within the Walls above a
Mile in length; it hath ſix Gates which
give entrance into the City, though all of
them have been very much defaced in our
<hi>Civil Wars,</hi> as likewiſe the Caſtle which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
hath been very formidable for its
Strength and Impregnableneſs. This is that
Caſtle that <hi>Maud</hi> the Empreſs having took,
held it out ſome conſiderable time againſt
King <hi>Stephen,</hi> and being at laſt ſtrictly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged
by the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> then in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
who was Brother to the King, fearing
to be took Priſoner and delivered up into
her Enemies hands, ſhe ſecured her ſelf by
this cunning Way; ſhe commanded it ſhould
be given out for a moſt certain truth that
ſhe was Dead, and was carried out upon a
<hi>Beir</hi> as if ſhe had been ſo indeed, and by
this means ſhe deceived her Enemies, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured
her own Perſon. Upon the Wall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:108032:31"/>
hangs the <hi>Round Table</hi> ſo much talked of,
and called by the Name of King <hi>Arthur's
Round Table,</hi> whether this can gain to it ſelf
ſo great Antiquity as is attributed to it, I
ſhall not undertake to determine, yet certain
it is, that thoſe kind of Tables are of a very
long ſtanding; for formerly when there hath
been great Entertainments amongſt the vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant
Champions of this Nation, it was uſual
for all ſuch to ſit round them, leſt any Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
ſhould ariſe amongſt the Noblemen
about Superiority of Place. About the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle
of the City ſtands the Cathedral, built
by <hi>Kenelwalchius,</hi> King of the Weſt <hi>Saxons,</hi>
who Conſtituted <hi>Ina</hi> the firſt Biſhop there,
and it was always had in great Veneration
by the <hi>Saxons,</hi> becauſe divers of their Kings
was Enterred in it, and was called by them
<hi>The Old Monaſtery;</hi> there is a Dean and 12
Prenbendaries belonging to it; the Church
is curiouſly adorned with Monuments of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
Hero's and Biſhops of that See, <hi>William
Wainfleet</hi> Founder of <hi>Magdelen</hi> College in
<hi>Oxford</hi> lies here Entombed with his Hart in
his Hand, and Cardinal <hi>Beaufort,</hi> and Biſhop
<hi>Gardner,</hi> that bloody Scourge to the poor
Proteſtants in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s days, who did
ſo inſatiably thirſt for the Blood of Queen
<hi>Elizabeth,</hi> but was always croſſed in his moſt
wicked Inclinations; there lies alſo the Lord
<hi>Weſton,</hi> Earl of <hi>Portland,</hi> whoſe Monument is
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:108032:32"/>
of Braſs, and by him his Father who lies in
Marble; here is likewiſe preſerved the Chair
of State in which Queen <hi>Mary</hi> was Married
to King <hi>Philip;</hi> the Counteſs of <hi>Exeter</hi> is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
Enterr'd here; alſo the Chappel of Biſhop
<hi>Fox</hi> is worth ones obſervation which he built
for his own uſe, together with his Study and
Preſs for his Books all in one place. In the
Quire under a plain flat Marble Stone lies the
Body of <hi>William Rufus,</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> who
received his Mortal Wound as he was Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
in the <hi>New Forreſt</hi> by Sir <hi>Walter Tyrrel;</hi>
Sir <hi>Walter</hi> ſhooting at a Deer unawares hit him
on the Breſt on which he died immediately,
and was brought to <hi>Wincheſter</hi> and buried
in this place, though afterwards his Bones
were Tranſlated into a Coffer. At the Weſt
end of the Quire ſtands in Braſs two Statues
very curiouſly wrought, the one of King
<hi>James</hi> the Firſt, and the other of King <hi>Charles</hi>
the Firſt of ever bleſſed Memory; there is
another thing alſo very remarkable in the
Cathedral, and that is the rich and famous
Monument of <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Wickham,</hi> who was
Conſtituted Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> in the Reign
of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third: But to return again
into our Diſcourſe relating to the City. We
find it not only to have attained a great E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minency
for its Religious Houſes, for its
pleaſant Gardens, for its Silver-ſtream'd
Brooks and flowry Meadows, for its publick
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:108032:32"/>
and private Edifices, for its great Hall where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
the Aſſizes are uſually held for the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of <hi>Southampton,</hi> not to be parallel'd for
Length and Breadth by any throughout this
Nation, except <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> for the Antiquity
of its Corporation, with the true and exact
Rules of Equity and Juſtice preſcribed by its
Governors and Magiſtrates; 'tis likewiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported
to have been very famous and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned
by its Sufferings and Ruins of its
Palaces, and in the time of <hi>Adelſtane,</hi> King
of the <hi>Weſt Saxons,</hi> that invinceable Hero,
<hi>Guy</hi> Earl of <hi>Warwick,</hi> in a ſingle Combat
ſlew <hi>Colbrand</hi> the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Giant in <hi>Hide-Mead</hi>
near to this City. After ſome time ſpent
here, we travelled to <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> of which I
come next to diſcourſe of.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PORTSMOUTH</hi> is about 16 Miles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
from <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and ſituated in a little
Iſland called <hi>Portſey.</hi> 'Tis a place of great
Strength, and of no leſs importance by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
of the Dock, where many of the King's
greateſt Men of War are built, thoſe impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
Wooden-Walls of our <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Iſland.
'Tis fortified with a Wall made of Timber,
and the ſame well covered over with thick
Banks of Earth; 'tis likewiſe environed with
a double Trench, over which are placed two
Drawbridges, from which about a Mile di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
is another, and at all of them ſtands
Centuries of Soldiers who are kept in Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:108032:33"/>
with a little Fortreſs adjoining to it
which leads up the Continent; to the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
is a Caſtle and Block-houſes, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
firſt begun by King <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth,
King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, as it is reported, did
afterwards compleat; which Fortifications
have of late Years received exceeding great
Augmentations by the ſucceeding Monarchs,
eſpecially in the late King <hi>Jame</hi>'s Reign.
Here is only one Church, and an Hoſpital
called <hi>God's Houſe,</hi> built by <hi>Peter Roch,</hi> Biſhop
of <hi>Wincheſter;</hi> hereabouts are divers Saltpan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes,
which make exceeding white Salt.
Much more might have been wrote concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
this County, but this may ſuffice for
theſe two Reaſons; the firſt is, The ſmallneſs
of the Volume will not allow it, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
is, That what has been related is the
notableſt, and moſt requiſite to be mention'd.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Suſſex.</head>
                  <p>The next place of Note we went to was
<hi>Chicheſter</hi> in <hi>Suſſex.</hi> 'Tis a good large City
well Wall'd, re-built by the ſecond <hi>Saxon</hi>
King of this Province; it was before the
Conqueſt of a ſmall Repute, Biſhop <hi>Raulf</hi>
built a Cathedral here, which before he had
fully finiſhed was conſumed by Fire, yet by
his Endeavours, and the bounteous Liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt, it was raiſed up
again, and is now a Biſhop's See. The Church
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:108032:33"/>
is not very large, but was formerly a curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
beautiful Fabrick, having a Spire-ſteeple
of Stone of a very great height, and an high
Tower ſtanding near the Weſt Door, which
was built by King <hi>Rinon,</hi> as they ſay. In
the South Croſs-Iſle of the Church was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
on the one ſide artificially pourtrayed
and painted the Hiſtory of the Churches
Foundation, with the Images of the Kings
of <hi>England</hi> on the other; there was likewiſe
the Images of the Biſhops, at the charge of
Biſhop <hi>Sherborne,</hi> who greatly Adorned and
Illuſtrated this ſacred Structure. The City
is walled about in a circular round Form,
the <hi>Lavant,</hi> a pretty River, running hard by
it on the South and Weſt ſides. It hath four
Gates opening to the four Quarters of the
World, from whence the Streets leads direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
and croſs themſelves in the midſt where
the Market is kept, and where Biſhop <hi>Read</hi>
Erected a fair ſtone Market-houſe, ſupported
with Pillars round about.</p>
                  <p>We went from hence to <hi>Amberly</hi> Caſtle,
which is about 12 Miles from <hi>Chicheſter</hi> high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
into the County; it was built by <hi>William
Read,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> in the Reign of
<hi>Edward</hi> the Third for the uſe of his Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors,
and Leaſed out now to the worthy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily
of the <hi>Butlers,</hi> who are the preſent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants.
We ſtayed here the ſpace of a
Week, where we were generouſly Entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:108032:34"/>
with great courteſie and civility. We
went from hence to <hi>Arundel,</hi> and from thence
to <hi>Lewes,</hi> of which take this brief Account.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ARUNDEL</hi> is about four Miles from
<hi>Amberly,</hi> ſituated upon the Brow of an Hill,
but finding nothing to detain us here but
the Ruins of an old Caſtle, which for many
Generations hath ſucceſſively appertained to
the Earls of <hi>Arundel,</hi> we travell'd on to</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LEWES,</hi> which was the next Town we
came to. 'Tis ſituated upon a Riſing almoſt
on every ſide, and hath been Wall'd, but now
there is no great ſign of the Walls; there is
ſeveral Streets near it as Suburbs, and in the
times of the <hi>Saxons</hi> when King <hi>Athelſton</hi>
made a Law for the coining of Money, he
appointed two Coiners in this place. There
are five Churches belonging to it, and this
place was very memorable for that Mortal
and bloody Battel between King <hi>Henry</hi> the
Third and the Barons, in which proſperous
beginning of the Fight on the King's ſide,
proved the overthrow of his whole Army,
for whilſt Prince <hi>Edward</hi> his Son, breaking
by force through certain of the Baron's
Troops, careleſly purſued the Enemy over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>far,
as making ſure account of the Victory;
the Barons having reinforced themſelves, and
giving a freſh Charge, ſo diſcomforted and
put to flight the King's Forces, that they
conſtrained the King to accept of unequal
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:108032:34"/>
Conditions of Peace, and to deliver his Son
and others into their hands. From hence
we went to <hi>Pevenſey,</hi> or <hi>Pemſey,</hi> of which it
follows.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PEVENSEY,</hi> or <hi>PEMSEY.</hi> There is a
very low Level which, ſome are of Opinion,
hath been over-flowed by the Sea, and the
Town of <hi>Pevenſey</hi> is the noted place for the
firſt Landing of <hi>William the Conqueror,</hi> and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
there was a Haven and Caſtle. <hi>Haſtings</hi>
is not far from hence, where was fought
that bloody Battel betwixt King <hi>Harold</hi> and
the <hi>Norman</hi> Duke, which proved ſo fatal to
the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and ſucceſsful to the <hi>Normans,</hi>
which Ground where the Fight was hath
been thought ever ſince to have worn the
Conqueror's Livery, becauſe always after
Rain it looks of a reddiſh colour. I could
haved cited other Remarks in this County,
but what is related is moſt material.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Kent.</head>
                  <p>'Tis a County divided into three ſeveral
Portions, the firſt of which is called <hi>Health
without Wealth,</hi> the ſecond is <hi>Health and Wealth,</hi>
and the third <hi>Wealth without Health,</hi> to all
which Nature notwithſtanding hath liberally
apportioned ſo many Bleſſings, that ſhe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſates
the Defects of one thing by the
Collation of another, not ſuffering any pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar
Place to monopolize all her Favours at
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:108032:35"/>
once; but thus, if the <hi>Weald</hi> be very emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
for <hi>Wooll,</hi> the ſame of <hi>Eaſt Kent</hi> ſhall be
as great for <hi>Corn,</hi> and <hi>Tenham, Goddington</hi> and
<hi>Otham</hi> ſhall be no leſs cried up for <hi>Orchards,</hi>
and <hi>Sheppey</hi> for the beſt <hi>Wheat,</hi> and <hi>Thanet</hi>
ſhall bring forth as good Crops of <hi>Barley;</hi>
but if <hi>Dover</hi> and <hi>Cranbrooke</hi> hath the Name
for <hi>Beer, Tunbridge</hi> ſhall for <hi>Water,</hi> and if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
the fertility of the Soil, or ſafe Roads or
ſure Harbours for Ships, or the broad Streams
of great Navigable Rivers, or the vicinity
of a vaſt and large City can be any ways to
advance it Proſperity, it muſt needs be one,
if not the moſt flouriſhing County in the
Kingdom of <hi>England:</hi> As touching the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes
and Privileges of <hi>Kent,</hi> they have been
already ſo fully diſcourſed of by Mr. <hi>Lambert</hi>
in his <hi>Kentiſh Perambulation,</hi> and what was
by him omitted, have been ſupplied by the
ingenious Pen of Mr. <hi>Philipot,</hi> ſo that I ſhall
wave them, and only give a very ſmall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
of it, although I have been in moſt
Towns and Pariſhes in this County. <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi>
becauſe the Antiquity of this City, with
all its Liberties and Privileges, the Beauty
and number of all its Churches and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Houſes before their Diſſolution, the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence
of its Cathedral, with all its renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
Tombs and Monuments are very exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitely
Surveyed and Diſcribed by other Pens,
I ſhall not go about to pourtray that in any
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:108032:35"/>
contracted Landskip, which hath been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
repreſented in ſo large a Scheme, but
referr all ſuch as deſire a particular Account
of this City, to thoſe Writters who have
pencelled out every Part and Limb thereof
with great Exactneſs and Accuracy.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Rocheſter.</head>
                  <p>A City which, in ancient Times, was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent
for its Strength and Granduer, and
had not thoſe violent Impreſſions which the
rough hands of War formerly defaced and
deminiſh'd its Bulk, and bereaved it of its
Beauty, it might have been regiſtered at this
day in the Inventory of the principal Cities
of this Nation. In the Year 1225, by the
indulgent Bounty of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third,
it was inveſted with a Wall, and that this
Fortification might be of more concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
it was ſecured or fenced with a Ditch.
It was governed by a <hi>Port Reeve,</hi> until King
<hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth in the Second Year of his
Reign raiſed it to a higher Dignit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed,
by his Royal Grant, that it ſhould
henceforth be under the Juriſdiction of a
Mayor and Twelve Aldermen, and to this
Monarch doth the City owe much of its
preſent Felicity; indeed formerly many and
diſmal Calamities did attend it, and that ſo
frequently, that the fury of the Elements
ſeemed to enter into a Corrivalſhip, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:108032:36"/>
with the fury of the Enemies for its
ruin, and the Fire and Sword ſeem'd to be
join'd Confederates to deſtroy it. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs
it maugres all theſe Caſualties by the
Favour of the Princes, and their Royal Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence,
it ſtill recruits its Loſſes, and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vives
in Splender. The goodly Skeleton of
the Caſtle, which yet courts the eyes of the
Beholders to an admiration of its former
Strength, and built many hundred Years
ſince. The Cathedral, with the Biſhoprick
of <hi>Rocheſter</hi> united to it, were formerly E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed
by that pious Monarch <hi>Ethelbert,</hi>
King of <hi>Kent,</hi> and the firſt Biſhop to whom
was entruſted the Paſtoral Staff or Croſier,
was Biſhop <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> the Apoſtle to the <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
Here is likewiſe a very fine ſtone Bridge
built by Sir <hi>Robert Knowles</hi> over the River
<hi>Medway,</hi> which is fixed and built upon one
and twenty Arches, and coped about with
Iron-ſpikes by Archbiſhop <hi>Warham,</hi> and leads
into <hi>Stroud.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And becauſe (according to the Orator)
every one is obliged to be ſerviceable to his
Country proportionable to his Abilities, and
every one hath an inrate Propenſity to love
the Native Soil which firſt gave him a Being,
I cannot but in Duty pay ſome Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of the Benefits I have received herein,
both for my Nativity, and firſt Education,
and indeed I may juſtly ſay without any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:108032:36"/>
That it is a Province not much infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior
to any in <hi>England,</hi> being divided into
three ſeveral Parts, of which I have made
ſome mention before. It is in all parts ſo
ſufficiently fruitful of all things neceſſary for
the uſe of Man, and if we will take the pains
to courſe over the Vallies, we ſhall find the
Earth groaning under the burdens of boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful
<hi>Ceres,</hi> and the Fields and Meadows in
conteſt which ſhould ſhine moſt gay and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious;
if we range the Woods and Hills, we
ſhall hear ſuch charming Melodies by the
mutual reciprecation of Birds and Trees, that
we ſhould fancy all had got the knack of
Speaking and Pratling, Groves being now
become viſible to us; if we be ſo curious
as to dig into the Entrails of the Earth, and
take a view of the recondite Treaſures, we
ſhall find plenty of Iron-Ore in the South
parts of this County, and great Queries of
Stone in ſeveral places; alſo towards the
North ſide they dig out of the Earth plenty
of excellent fat Chalk, which they uſe to
lay upon their Land for the enriching of it,
and cauſeth it to bring forth great Crops of
Corn: If we be taken with the harmonious
Murmurs of Brooks and gentle Rivers there
are ſeveral, the Banks of the Noble River of
<hi>Thames</hi> on the North ſide, and the River <hi>Med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way</hi>
which comes out of <hi>Surrey</hi> glides along
for many Miles together on the South ſide
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:108032:37"/>
of this County, and takes its courſe through
almoſt the middle of the County, and doth
not run ſwift in many places, but glides ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
admiring, as it were, the pleaſantneſs of
its Soil; there is alſo at <hi>Newel</hi> in the
Pariſh of <hi>Orpington</hi> the fineſt Spings undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly
in the Kingdom, both for the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
of its Water, and the riſing up of it in
ſuch abundance, that within two Furlongs
of the Head it drives a Mill, and afterwards
is called by the Name of <hi>Cray River.</hi> Moſt
of the Rivers in this County do afford ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
ſorts of Fiſh to gratifie the Pallate, and all
the Towns and Villages are well inhabited,
having a great many very fine Seats of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen
and Gentlemen, in which reſpect 'tis
honourable; the Churches fair and uniform,
and ſo 'tis glorious; the Air in many parts
is clear, which renders it wholſome.</p>
                  <p>One word or two I muſt I ſay in relation
to <hi>Maidſtone.</hi> 'Tis the principal Town in the
County; as in reſpect of its having the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſizes
and Seſſions kept in it, and its being ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated
near the middle of the County upon
the River <hi>Medway,</hi> which renders it ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant
and delightful, that even that alone
might be ſufficient to ſet forth all the other
Parts of it. Leaving this place, we ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
arrived in <hi>London,</hi> where we only tarried
a reaſonable ſpace of time to give our Selves
and Horſes ſome Reſt and Refreſhment, as
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:108032:37"/>
likewiſe to viſit our Friends and Acquaintan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
and then proceeded on, deſigning to finiſh
our intended purpoſes, and ſo (with God's
Aſſiſtance) took Horſe and went to</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Eſſex.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>RUMFORD</hi> is about 10 Miles from
<hi>London,</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſſex.</hi> It is well ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
with Inns, and hath a great Market for
Cattel; the whole County is populous, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
in it divers fine Seats of Perſons of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.
We tarried here not long but Travell'd
on to <hi>Burntwood,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Ingerſtone,</hi> both
which Places have no great Remarks worth
our tarrying, we rid on to <hi>Chelmsford,</hi> which
place is ſituated in the heart of the County
between two Rivers which meet here. It
hath a great Market for Corn, and the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſizes
are generally held here for the County;
here are likewiſe ſeveral Perſons of Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty's
Seats in and about the adjacent Places,
which do mightily enrich it. We ſtayed
here but one Night, and the next Place of
Note we came to in this County was <hi>Colche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi>
of which it follows.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>COLCHESTER</hi> is pleaſantly ſeated up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the brow of an Hill, and doth extend it
ſelf in length Eaſt and Weſt, and is very nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous
for Inhabitants whereby its Buildings
are enlarged, and its Churches encreaſed to
the number of fifteen; but in the late unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:108032:38"/>
                     <hi>Civil Wars</hi> it had its ſhare of Calamities,
for being cloſe Beſieged by their Enemies,
the <hi>Royaliſts</hi> who were within behaved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
ſo bravely, that they could neither
take it by Violence, nor enforce it to a Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendry,
until at laſt having blocked up all
places whereby the leaſt Proviſions might be
conveyed to them, ſo that they were redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
to that Want and Exigency, Hunger ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing
its Tyranny within the Walls with
no leſs Vigour than the Enemy did without,
that they were compelled by one Enemy to
ſurrender to the other, by truſting to the
a mercileſs Sword, rather than to die thro'
griping Hunger: So that the Rebels having
got poſſeſſion of the Town, they did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
uſe their utmoſt Cruelty upon the weaker
Sort, who could make no reſiſtance, but even
in cold-Blood did they barbarouſly murther
thoſe very Perſons, who, had they been at
the Head of an Army would have made the
ſtouteſt Champion of their Party to give way
to them. Sir <hi>Charles Lucas</hi> and Sir <hi>George Liſle,</hi>
Perſons of as great Integrity and undaunted
Courage as any whatſoever, were cowardly
and cruelly Shot to death by the Sanguinary
of the inſolent Soldiers in the <hi>Caſtle Yard,</hi> on
which very Spot of ground where they fell
down dead hath never ſince ſprouted up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Graſs, as there were wont, the Ground
it ſelf from that time being clad in mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:108032:38"/>
Weeds and Graſs dreading ſuch execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Murthers, retires and hides its head with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
the Bowels of the Earth, and this Plat of
ground is a Monument to ſucceeding Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,
yet doth a Vault that belonged to the
Family of Sir <hi>Charles Lucus</hi> ſecure both his
own and his Fellow-ſufferer's Bodies from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
farther Attempts of the Sons of Violence,
and being wrapped in Lead they were laid
in that Church which was next to his own
Houſe, which formerly was a fair and ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
Structure, but ruinated by his Enemies
who hated the Houſe for the Maſter's ſake.
The Caſtle which did ſtand about the midſt
of the Town, is likewiſe now demoliſhed and
gone to decay; and though the Inhabitants
ſhewed us a Brazen-gate which gives en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance
into a Vault fifteen Miles under the
ground, as ſome of the Inhabitants tell Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
of it, yet I think there is no credit to be
given to it. Here are other large Towns,
and a conſiderable many of ſtately Buildings,
but I have not room here to inſert them.
From hence we went to</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Suffolk.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IPSWITCH</hi> is a Town very commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
for its Haven, Enriched by foreign Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce,
repleniſhed with Inhabitants, ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
with ſeveral magnificent Churches, and
being united into a Corporation is governed
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:108032:39"/>
by two Bailiffs, who have all other Miniſters
befitting their Granduer to attend them, tho'
formerly it hath ſuſtained great Loſſes by the
<hi>Danes;</hi> the Streets are very clean and well
paved, and in the midſt of the Market-place,
which is ſurrounded with rich Shops and
goodly Houſes, ſtands a very curious ſquare
Croſs which hath the Effiges of <hi>Impartiality,</hi>
bearing a pair of Scales in one hand and a
Sword in the other, a ſit Emblem to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minde
the Magiſtrates of the exact Meaſure
that they muſt uſe in the diſtribution of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.
The Store-houſes which are kept for
the King's Ships do much promote the Trade
of the Town. Before the ſubverſion of the
Monaſteries, it could glory in four Religious
Houſes, beſides a magnificent College ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
by Cardinal <hi>Woolſey,</hi> who received his
firſt Breath in this place, being only a But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher's
Son of this Town.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>St. EDMUNDS-BURY,</hi> or <hi>BURY,</hi> a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned
Town; a Place for ſituation and
wholſomneſs of Air ſo excellent, that <hi>Camb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi>
ſaith, <hi>Sol non vidit urbem ſitu elegantiorem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
Many of the Gentry live here. There are two
Churches in one Churchyard, where there
are Lectures ſeveral days in the Week. Here
was born <hi>Richardus de Bury,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi>
the Governour of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third
when young, and famous eſpecially for a
Work which he Entituled <hi>Philobiblos,</hi> in the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:108032:39"/>
Preface of which he confeſſeth, <hi>Ecſtatico quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam
librorum amore potenter ſe abreptum.</hi> He
was well acquainted with <hi>Petrark</hi> the <hi>Italian,</hi>
and other learned Men of that Age. <hi>Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardine</hi>
Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and <hi>Richard
Fitzralph, Armachanus, Walter Burleigh, Robert
Halcot,</hi> and other moſt famous Men of that
Age were his Chaplains.</p>
                  <p>We have been at moſt of the Towns in
this County, and there is five hundred ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty
and five Pariſhes in it, and the whole
County is very fruitful. We went from
hence to <hi>Scole</hi> Inn in the County of <hi>Norfolk,</hi>
of which hereafter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Norfolk.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SCOLE</hi> is a little Village very famous for
an Inn and Sign-Poſt built by Mr. <hi>Peck,</hi> a
Gentleman, which thing coſt him ſeveral
Hundred Pounds. The Houſe is of Brick ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
neat and uniform, and hath great variety
of Objects for diverſion: In the Porch, at
the four corners, ſtands two Men playing on
Wind-Muſick, a Tapſter filling of Drink, and
a Mountebank ſhewing of Tricks; on the
two ſide-Poſts <hi>Hercules</hi> with his Club, and
<hi>Sampſon</hi> with his Jaw-bone; on the Front is
the Figure of the Whale vomiting up <hi>Jonah</hi>
out of his Mouth, and on the Eaſt ſide of the
Houſe the Statue of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Hope</hi> with an
Anchor and an Olive branch; but that which
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:108032:40"/>
is moſt admirable, is the contrivance of the
Sign-poſt which ſeems to contain great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties;
on the top of all is an Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
looking thro' a Quadrant, riding upon
an Anchor with the four Cardinal-Vertues
on each ſide of him, <hi>Fortitude</hi> with her bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
Pillar, <hi>Temperance</hi> with her Cup pouring
out Wine, <hi>Prudence</hi> with a Snake in her right
hand, and a Horn of Plenty in her left, and
<hi>Juſtice</hi> with a pair of Scales and a Sword;
along the Sign-poſt ſtands ſeveral Images ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
curiouſly carved and painted, the firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents
a Huntſman equipped and accou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
with his Horn and his green Jacket, juſt
as if he were then very hot upon the Chaſe,
and next to him <hi>Acteon</hi> transformed into a
Stag, with his Pack of Hounds worrying and
devouring him, the next is <hi>Diana</hi> with an
Half-Moon upon her head, and the Planets
under her feet, her Quiver in her hand, and
her Horn by her ſide, and before her is a
Greyhound, as it were, in a cloſe purſuit af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
the Hare; next to this ſtands old <hi>Time</hi>
with an Hour-glaſs on his head, a Sythe in his
left hand, and a prodigal Youth in his right,
and <hi>Death</hi> under his Feet with this Inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<hi>Tempus edax rerum;</hi> in the middle hangs
the ſign of the <hi>White Heart,</hi> ingeniouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived
into an Oval figure, with two Angels
and two Lions on each corner, under one of
which are placed four naked Boys treading
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:108032:40"/>
of Grapes, and under the other a Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bank
ſhewing of Feats of Activity; on both
ſides are the Arms of the chief Families both
in <hi>Suffolk</hi> and <hi>Norfolk,</hi> and alſo a Shepherd
playing merrily upon his Pipes, and laſt of
all on each ſide of the Poſt which ſupports
the whole Fabrick, ſtands three-headed <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berus
the Great</hi> of the Infernal Court, and old
griſle-bearded <hi>Charon</hi> with his Boat and Oars
wafling a Wench over the <hi>Stigion</hi> Lake; the
ſplendedneſs of this curious and coſtly piece
of Workmanſhip, is worthy of any Traveller's
obſervation. The next Town of Note we
came to in this County was</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>YARMOUTH,</hi> which entertained us
with a pleaſant Proſpect, the Haven being as
commodious as the Town is beautiful, and
is fortified both by Art and Nature, for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
it be environed almoſt round with
Water on the Weſt ſide by the River <hi>Yare,</hi>
from whence it borrows its Name, which
hath a Drawbridge over it, and from other
parts with the Ocean, unleſs it be North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
where there is firm Land, yet it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
encloſed with a very ſtrong Wall, upon
which, beſides Towers, is caſt up a Mount
towards the Eaſt, and there are likewiſe plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
ſeveral pieces of Ordnance to defend the
Town and command the Seas; there is but
one Church, but that is fair and lofty, ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
with a high Spire-ſteeple, built at firſt by
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:108032:41"/>
                     <hi>Herbert,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Norwich;</hi> there are alſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
clean and ſpacious Streets, on each ſide
of which are ſeveral Rows of very uniform
Buildings, inhabited by wealthy and gentle
Perſons. This Town is of no long date or
ſtanding, as appears by Antiquaries, for it
received its beginning from the Ruins of old
<hi>Garianum</hi> which was near this place, after
which, in a ſhort time, as we were informed,
built this new Town which grew potent
and populous, and they ſtrengthened it with
a Wall, and grew very numerous in Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants,
and there happened a fearful and
ſudden Peſtilence, which in the ſpace of a
Year brought above ſeven Thouſand Men
and Women to their Graves, all which was
faithfully recorded in an ancient Table, which
formerly uſed to hang up in their Church,
but ſince reſtored to its primitive Luſtre, and
their Wealth hath increaſed, and 'tis now a
place of great Merchandize and Traffick, but
eſpecially renowned for its Fiſhery of <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings</hi>
of which, at the Seaſon, here is very
great plenty, and by their care and induſtry
are ſalted and dried in particular Houſes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned
and appointed for that very purpoſe,
and do ſupply our own and foreign Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
too. The next place of Note we went
to was</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:108032:41"/>
                     <hi>NORWICH</hi> is one of the moſt renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
Cities in our <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Iſland, for whether
we conſider the Wealth of the Citizens, the
Number of Inhabitants, the great Conference
of Foreigners, the ſtately Structures, and
beautiful Churches, the obliging Carriage of
the Gentry, and the Induſtry of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,
do all concur to illuſtrate and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
it. 'Tis ſituated on the brow of a Hill,
and environed with a Wall in which are pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
divers Turrets, and twelve Gates to give
entrance into the City, unleſs it be on the
Eaſt ſide, where the River <hi>Yare</hi> after it hath,
with many windings, watered the moſt part
of the City, having four Draw-bridges for
People to paſs over, and is a farther defence
by reaſon of its deep Channel, and high
Banks; 'tis reported to be a Mile and a half
in length, and half as much in breadth. It
hath had great Misfortunes, and ſuffered ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
much by the <hi>Danes</hi> when they took their
range in theſe parts, and after <hi>William the
Conqueror</hi> had ſettled the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Crown up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
his head, it ſuffered much more, which
is too tedious to relate, but in ſucceeding
Ages it began to recruit its Strength, and
hath flouriſhed exceedingly. King <hi>Henry</hi> the
Firſt permitted the Citizens to Wall their Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
and King <hi>Richard</hi> the Second gave them
a Grant for the Tranſportation of Worſted,
and to advance their Trade which was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:108032:42"/>
eclipſed. King <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed
their Charter, and conferred on them
the Honour to chuſe every Year a Mayor
for their Magiſtrate, whereas by a former
Order from King <hi>Stephen</hi> they were only go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned
by Coroners and Baliffs. It contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
thirty two Pariſhes, forty two Chappels
and Churches, of which the Cathedral is the
faireſt and chiefeſt, the firſt Stone of which
was laid by Biſhop <hi>Herbert,</hi> in the Reign of
King <hi>William Rufus,</hi> who Tranſlated the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal
See from <hi>Thetford</hi> to this place, and
procured a Grant to have it confirmed the
Mother-Church of <hi>Norfolk</hi> and <hi>Suffolk,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowing
it with great Revenues, and it is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
ſtately and magnificent Structure, but moſt
famous for its Roof which runs aloft over
the very body of it, on which is drawn to
the life the whole Hiſtory of the Bible in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
little Images, curiouſly carved and ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
from the Creation of the World, to the
Aſcention of our bleſſed Saviour, or the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent
of the Holy Ghoſt, with the perfect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance
of our Lord's Crucifiction and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection,
and divers other things. The
Market, Croſs and Cloiſter of the Cathedral
are the faireſt in <hi>England.</hi> There is a great
Houſe that was the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi>'s, now
the Earl of <hi>Arundel</hi>'s, where there are very
fine Granaries, and the beſt Bowling-Alley in
the Kingdom. There is alſo an Hoſpital,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:108032:42"/>
where an hundred Men and Women are
maintained. The Arms of the City are the
<hi>Caſtle</hi> and <hi>Lion.</hi> After ſome time of abode
in this City, we Travelled to a little Village
called</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>TETTLESHALL,</hi> in the Pariſh-Church
whereof is erected a ſtately Monument of
Marble, in honour to Sir <hi>Edward Cooke,</hi> that
moſt famous Lawyer of his time, on the top
are placed his Coat of Arms, with the four
<hi>Cardinal Vertues</hi> to ſupport them at each cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
his Effigies is of Marble laid out at full
length, above which this Motto is engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven'd,
<hi>Prudens qui Patiens,</hi> and underneath in
golden Characters this following Inſcription,
<hi>The Monument of Sir</hi> Edward Cooke, <hi>Knight,
born at</hi> Mileham <hi>in</hi> Norfolk, <hi>Recorder of</hi> Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich
<hi>and</hi> London, <hi>Solliciter to Queen</hi> Elizabeth,
<hi>and Speaker to the Parliament, afterwards At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney
General to her and King</hi> James, <hi>Chief Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
of both Benches, a Privy Councillor, as alſo of
Council to Queen</hi> Anne, <hi>and Chief Juſtice in Eire
of all her Forreſts, Chaſes and Parks, Recorder of</hi>
Coventry, <hi>and High Steward of</hi> Cambridge,
<hi>of which he was a Member in</hi> Trinity College.
<hi>He died in the Eighty third Year of his Age, his
laſt Words being theſe,</hi> Thy Kingdom come,
thy Will be done. The next place of Note
we came to in this County was <hi>Lynne Regis,</hi>
of which it follows.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:108032:43"/>
                     <hi>LYNNE,</hi> this Town, though its ſtanding be
but of latter Years, as receiving its Original
from old <hi>Lynne,</hi> which is ſeated in the <hi>Marſh-Land,</hi>
and is oppoſite againſt it, yet it is grown
of far greater requeſt, for the commodiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
of its Haven, and ſafe Harbour cauſeth
a great reſort of Mariners to frequent it, and
the Veſſels which come loaded with Coals
from <hi>New-Caſtle,</hi> do here, for the moſt part,
lighten their Burdens, and is conveyed into
the adjacent parts in the Counties. The
Town is environed with a ſtrong Wall, the
Streets are well paved and kept very clean;
it is, for the moſt part thereof, divided by two
ſmall Rivers that have fifteen Bridges, or
thereabout, over them; it is called <hi>Old Linne,</hi>
and <hi>Linnum Regis,</hi> that is, <hi>King's Linne;</hi>
there are five Churches to adorn it, the chief
of which is a curious Fabrick dedicated to
St. <hi>Margaret,</hi> upon the top of which ſtands a
large and ſtately Lanthorn very admirable
for its rare Workmanſhip. The Town is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned
by a Mayor and Aldermen, which
have received great Kindneſſes from their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereigns,
and eſpecially from K. <hi>John,</hi> who,
for the good Service they had done him in
defence of his Quarrel, not only preſented
them with his own Sword from his ſide,
(which is continually carried before the
Mayor, when ever he pleaſeth to appear in
publick) but likewiſe gave them a great Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:108032:43"/>
Cup gilt for the uſe of the Town, which
becauſe they ſhew it moſt to Strangers and
Foreigners who are of any Note or Repute,
they generally have it filled with Wine to
drink his Majeſty's and Mr. Mayor's healths,
for which there is a particular Allowance
proportioned by the Town: Moſt of their
little Churches over the County are Thatch'd.
Here are many other things very obſervable
which I have not room to ſet down. We
went from hence to <hi>Cambridge,</hi> of which it
follows.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Cambridgeſhire</head>
                  <p>Is an extream, pleaſant, open County, and
a place of ſuch Variety and Plenty through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,
that fruitful <hi>Ceres</hi> with a ſmiling coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance
invites the induſtrious Peaſant to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,
with joy, the Fruits of his Labour,
whilſt ſhe crowns his Induſtry with a plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
Harveſt, and this County doth in divers
places make ſome annual Additions of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Crop, by adorning its Fields with large
Productions of Saffron, thro' which great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits
continually ariſe unto them; here it is that
the green Banks of murmuring Rivers and
ſunny Hills bedeckt with diverſity of Plants
and Simples, call forth the Students from
their muſing Cells, and teach them <hi>Theory,</hi>
by diving into their Natures, contemplating
their Signatures, and conſidering their Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:108032:44"/>
and various Effects: In a word, here is
nothing wanting for Pleaſure, Profit, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light;
and though the Northern parts of
the County towards the Iſle of <hi>Ely</hi> lying
ſomewhat low is moiſt and fenny, yet the
gentle Gales which are frequently ſtirring,
drive away all Miſts and Fogs which may
ſeem to annoy it, and by their means makes
it a fit Seat for the Muſes to inhabit, and we
have no reaſon to complain of the Soil,
ſince our wiſe Anceſtors thought good and
convenient to plant a Colony here, and place
one of the Eyes of our Nation in this Spot
of ground, the famous and moſt glorious U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſity
of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> which we could not,
in honour, paſs by without a Viſit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CAMBRIDGE</hi> was formerly called
<hi>Grantbridge,</hi> from a fair large Bridge made o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
the River <hi>Grant,</hi> which is now called <hi>Cam,</hi>
from whence the Town it ſelf receives its
Name. It is increaſed much by the Ruins
of <hi>Granceſter</hi> ſometime a famous City, ſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate
a little above a Mile from this place,
and the Caſtle that is beyond the River, the
Ruins of which are ſtill to be ſeen, was built,
as ancient Records teſtifie, in the firſt Year
of <hi>William the Conqueror,</hi> or in the firſt Year
of <hi>William Rufus</hi> in the Year of our Lord
1092, A Nobleman of the <hi>Norman</hi> Blood
named <hi>Picot,</hi> a <hi>Vice Comes,</hi> or Sheriff, at the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:108032:44"/>
Requeſt of his Wife founded a Church to
the honour of God, and Dedicated it to
St. <hi>Giles,</hi> near unto this Caſtle, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
in 1102, the Canons were remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
from hence, and there is only one Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege
beyond the Bridge ſacred to St. <hi>Mary
Magdalen;</hi> on this ſide of it are very ſpacious
Streets, adorned with fifteen ſeveral magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent
Colleges and Halls, each of which are
liberally endowed with large Revenues, more
or leſs, in the practice of Religion, and the
dilligent purſuit of all kind of Learning;
here are fifteen Churches, beſides private
Chappels in every College, the chief of
which is called St. <hi>Mary's</hi> Church, ſet a part
particularly for the uſe of the Univerſity,
and the Commencement is kept yearly the
firſt Sunday in <hi>July,</hi> that the Name and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
Memory of our moſt pious Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors
may ſtill flouriſh and be renowned, for
their great Munificence and moſt memoral
Acts. The Town is a Corporation, and is
governed by a Mayor and Aldermen, and
the Aſſizes, for the moſt part, are kept here
for the County, which is very profitable to
the Town, and 'tis obſervable that one High
Sheriff ſerves for both the Counties of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi>
and <hi>Huntingdon,</hi> which borders upon
it; but one thing more is very noteable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
it, and that is the great Fair annually
kept within a Mile of it in <hi>September,</hi> called
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:108032:45"/>
by the Name of <hi>Sturbridge</hi>-Fair; from whence
it received its Denomination is uncertain,
but this is moſt ſure, that of all Fairs in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
'tis the greateſt and beſt ſtored with all
kind of Wares and Commodities which the
<hi>Londoners</hi> take ſpecial care to import hither;
when you are within the limits, you would
rather be ready to imagine your ſelf in ſome
great Town, by the variety of Shops and
multiplicity of Booths, than in a wide open
Feild, thoſe Booths are always built for the
time in which it laſts, which is well nigh a
Fortnight; neither are you preſented only
with Booths upon the Land, but Booths on
the Water too, there being particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances
in the Boats for Rooms and ſecret
retirements all covered above, for the conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency
of Strangers which reſort thither,
and indeed here is always a great Reſorting
of People from moſt Parts of this Nation.</p>
                  <p>Near unto <hi>Cambridge</hi> on the South Eaſt
ſide, there appears aloft certain high Hills
called <hi>Gogmagog.</hi> On top of them is a very
large Fort, entrenched, ſtrengthened with a
three-fold Rampire.</p>
                  <p>There are contained in the Shire, eight
Market-Towns, and one hundred and ſixty
three Pariſhes.</p>
                  <p>Having paid our Devotions, and taken a
Review of that which affords ſo great varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
we, at laſt took our farewel, and biding
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:108032:45"/>
it a-dieu we betook our ſelves into its neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring
County of</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Huntingdonſhire</head>
                  <p>Is joined to <hi>Bedfordſhire</hi> on the South, <hi>Nort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hamptonſhire</hi>
on the North and Weſt, and <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgeſhire</hi>
on the Eaſt. 'Tis a very fruitful
County both for Corn and Graſs, and is wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered
by two pleaſant Rivers <hi>Avon</hi> and <hi>Ouſe.</hi>
The firſt Village we arrived at in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
was <hi>Fenny-Stanton,</hi> but found nothing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable,
we went from hence to</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>GODMANCHESTER,</hi> a very great
Country-Town, and of as great a Name for
Tillage; ſituate in an open Ground, of a
light Mould, and bending for the Sun. There
is not a Town in all <hi>England</hi> that hath more
ſtout and luſty Husbandmen, or more Plows
a going: For they make their boaſt, That
they have in former time received the Kings
of <hi>England,</hi> as they paſſed in their Progreſs
this way, with Nine-ſcore Plows, brought
forth in a ruſtical kind of pomp for a gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant
ſhew.</p>
                  <p>Soon after King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<hi>England,</hi> here the Bailiffs of the Town
preſented him with ſeventy Teem of Horſes,
all traced to fair new Plows, in ſhew of their
Husbandry, of which when his Majeſty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
the Reaſon, he was anſwered, <hi>That
it was their ancient Cuſtom, whenſoever any King
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:108032:46"/>
of</hi> England <hi>paſſed through their Town, ſo to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
him.</hi> Beſides they added, <hi>That they held
their Lands by that Tenure, being the King's Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants.</hi>
His Majeſty took it well, and <hi>Bad
them uſe well their Plows, being glad he was
Landlord of ſo many good Husbandmen in one
Town.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is mention'd in Hiſtory to have been a
flouriſhing City, and the old <hi>Roman</hi> Coins
which have been digged up there do atteſt
its Antiquity, and that a Biſhop did former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
reſide in this place, when it was in that
condition.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HUNTINGDON</hi> is about half a Mile
diſtant from this place, and is the chief Town
of the County, ſituated upon the River <hi>Ouſe,</hi>
over which ſtands a Bridge made of Stone
which gives entrance into it; the Houſes are
fair, and the Streets large; 'tis adorned with
four Churches. and had formely an ancient
Monaſtery belonging to it, ſome of the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ins
are ſtill to be ſeen. Near the River, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
a high Hill, ſtands the remains of a Caſtle
which was built about the Year of Chriſt 917,
afterwards <hi>David,</hi> King of <hi>Scots,</hi> waging War
againſt King <hi>Stephen</hi> upon the account of
<hi>Maud</hi> the Empreſs, who was his Niece, this
then was given upon ſome certain Terms to
the <hi>Scotch</hi> King, who did exceedingly beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie
and ſtrengthen it, by making ſtrong Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers
and Fortifications round about it, but
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:108032:46"/>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> the Second finding it, in proceſs of
time, a Cage for Rebels and Ring-leaders to
Sedition, at laſt quite demoliſhed it; from
the top of the Hill is a very pleaſant Proſpect
for ſome Miles. The Town is governed by
a Mayor and Aldermen, and the Aſſizes are
held here twice a Year for the Shire, and
wants no kind of Proviſion to entertain Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers
who reſort hether out of the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern
parts, the great Road to the City of
<hi>London</hi> lying through this Town.</p>
                  <p>In this Town, in the Year 1599, was that
Uſurper and Religious Cheat <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi>
Born and Educated, whom though we have
reaſon to curſe his very Name, and deteſt
his Memory as odious and execrable, yet
ſince proſperous Succeſſes of the moſt cruel
Tirants, makes others inquiſitive after thoſe
Perſons which they did ſo fortunately attend.
It will not be amiſs to tell the World that
this place gave him his firſt Being, who, <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi>
like, deſtroyed his Father and his Mother
too; the Father of his Country, and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
too, being a Murderer of the one, and a
Plague to the other, who was of ſo unparal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel'd
and baſe a Temper of Mind from his
Cradle to his Grave, that nothing could ſtay
with him, or be pleaſing to him long, but
what carried even the World before it Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion
and Ruin. In this little Shire are num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred
ſeventy eight Pariſhes, four Hundreds,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:108032:47"/>
and ſix Market-Towns. We ſtayed here one
Night, and the next day we went into</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Northamptonſhire.</head>
                  <p>This County is ſituate in the very middle
and heart (as it were) of <hi>England.</hi> On the
Eaſt lie <hi>Bedford</hi> and <hi>Hunting donſhires.</hi> On the
South <hi>Buckingham</hi> and <hi>Oxfordſhires:</hi> Weſtward
<hi>Warwickſhire:</hi> Northward <hi>Rutlandſhire,</hi> and
<hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> ſeparated from it by <hi>Avon</hi> the
leſs and <hi>Welland,</hi> two Rivers.</p>
                  <p>It is a champion County, exceeding po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous,
and paſſing well furniſhed with
Noblemens and Gentlemens Houſes, replen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhed
alſo with Towns and Churches; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much
as in ſome places there are twenty,
and in others thirty Steeples with Spires or
ſquare Towers within view at once.</p>
                  <p>The ſoil very fertile both for Tillage and
Paſture, yet nothing ſo well ſtored with
Woods unleſs it be in the further and hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
ſides. But in every place, as elſwhere
alſo in <hi>England,</hi> it is over-ſpread, and (as it
were) beſet with Sheep.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THARPSTONE</hi> is twelve Miles diſtant
from <hi>Huntingdon,</hi> has a great Market for all
ſorts of Grain, and well ſtored with Inns;
from hence we went to another Town cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<hi>KETTERING,</hi> which is of much
more Note than it Neighbours, by reaſon of
a handſome Croſs beautified with divers I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:108032:47"/>
curiouſly carved; the next place was
<hi>HIGHAM-FERRERS.</hi> The excellent
Ornament of this place was <hi>Henry Chichley,</hi>
Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who built <hi>All-Souls</hi>
College in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and another here, where
he placed ſecular Clerks and Prebendaries,
and withal an Hoſpital for the Poor.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FOTHERING-HAY</hi>-Caſtle, environed
on every ſide with moſt pleaſant Medows.</p>
                  <p>Here <hi>Mary,</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> was beheaded.</p>
                  <p>There belongs unto this Shire three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
twenty ſix Pariſhes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Leiceſterſhire.</head>
                  <p>The next place of Note we went to was
<hi>Leiceſter,</hi> the Metropolis of <hi>Leiceſterſhire.</hi> 'Tis
more venerable for its Antiquity than its
comelineſs, or preſent beauty. I find that
about the Year 680, it was a Biſhop's Seat,
though in few Years after the Sea was Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated,
and the Dignity being taken away
from the Town, it began to go much to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay,
but in the time of the <hi>Normans</hi> it flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed
exceedingly, and encreaſed mightily
in Inhabitants, yet afterwards in the Reign
of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Second it was again invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
in great Calamities and Diſaſters. Here
is to be ſeen an ancient Hoſpital, in the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel
whereof <hi>Henry,</hi> Earl of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> and <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi>
his Son, the firſt Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> lie In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred,
for that Duke being very Aged, and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:108032:48"/>
being willing to give ſome viſible Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
of his Charity, built this Hoſpital for the
Uſe and Maintenance of divers poor, aged,
decreped Perſons of both Sexes; and on the
other ſide, amongſt thoſe flowry Meadows
which the River <hi>Sore</hi> enricheth with its bub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
Stream, <hi>Robert,</hi> the crook-backt Earl of
<hi>Leiceſter,</hi> built a Monaſtery very ſpacious and
magnificent, and Dedicated it to the Virgin
<hi>Mary,</hi> and endowed it with large Revenues.
In the Chappel of this Monaſtery lay interr'd
the great and puiſſant Cardinal <hi>Woolſey,</hi> who
being at firſt a poor Man's Son of <hi>Ipſwich</hi> in
<hi>Suffolk,</hi> was raiſed by King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth,
for his great Parts and Learning, to the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
Degree of Honour in this Nation, being
advanced to be Lord Chancellor, of <hi>England,</hi>
and preſented with a Cardinal's Cap from
the Pope, and the unknown Incomes and
Revenues, and by his great Treaſures and
Mints of Money, atchieved more magnificent
Acts than ever any Prelate did before him,
for he erected the Royal Palace of <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi>
beſides two famous Colleges, the one
at this Native Town, and the other a moſt
glorious Structure called <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege
in <hi>Oxford;</hi> and for the height of his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
and Attendance, it is very elegantly ſet
forth by the writer of his Life: But notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
he was the Favourite of his Prince,
and the Darling of Fortune, and ſued to by
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:108032:48"/>
Foreigners, and his own Country-men too,
as to be the only Perſon to apply to in all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts,
yet true it is, that Fortune very oft
ſets great Perſons upon the Hill of Honour,
thereby to precipitate them with the greater
Violence; we find this lofty Cardinal could
no way ſecure himſelf from the reach of fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
Envy, and learn'd by the mutability of
his own Condition, for being retired into the
Country, after he ſeeing his Fortunes began
to ebb at Court, having the Great Seal took
from him by the King's Order, and was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards
ſent for by the Lieutenant of the
<hi>Tower</hi> to appear before his Majeſty; and as
returning out of the North to the City of
<hi>London,</hi> in his Journy he fell ſick of a Flux
at the Earl of <hi>Shrewsbury</hi>'s houſe in <hi>Sheffeild</hi>-Park,
which being accompanied with a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
did ſo weaken his Body, that when he
came to <hi>Leiceſter</hi> Abby, which way he took,
he told the Abbot, after the Solemnities of
receiving him were paſt, <hi>That, indeed, he was
come to lay his Bones amongſt them,</hi> which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly
came to paſs, for their he died,
and after his death, his Corps being inveſted
by the Monks with all ſuch Ornaments as he
was Profeſſed in, when he was made Biſhop
and Archbiſhop, as Mitre, Croſs-King and
Pall, with all other things due to his Order
and Dignity, and having lain ſome few days
in State, to be viſited by thoſe who had a
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:108032:49"/>
mind to pay their laſt Reſpects to his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;
he was buried in their Chappel dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> with great Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
though all periſhed in the ruin of the
Monaſtery, Subverted not long after when
Popery was baniſhed from the Confines of
<hi>England.</hi> This Town had its ſhare of Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities
in the unhappy <hi>Civil Wars:</hi> It is well
furniſhed with all kind of Grain; it is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned
by a Mayor, Alderman and Recorder,
with other inferiour Officers to attend them.
The Town is ſtrengthened with ſeveral
Gates, in one whereof is kept the Magazine;
it is alſo adorned with divers eminent Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricks
both Sacred and Civil; the Croſs in
high Street is a very excellent Structure; there
are likewiſe five Churches, by that which is
called St. <hi>Martins</hi> ſtands the new Hoſpital,
being a ſtately Edifice, built and endowed
by ſeveral Benefactors for the uſe of divers
aged Men and Women, with a Chappel, and
a Chaplain to read Divine Service, and to be
aſſiſtful to thoſe poor People therein, and to
this joins their publick Library, which was
given for the uſe of Miniſters and Schollars
who inhabit here; hard by St. <hi>Mary</hi>'s Church
ſtands the Caſtle, where the Aſſizes are kept
for the County, and by St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> there is
a Wall, which, by the Ruins of it, ſeems to
be of very great Antiquity, having ſeveral
hollow places in it of an oval form, of which
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:108032:49"/>
the Inhabitants have ſtrange Conjectures
concerning them, as if there had been ſome
place in which the Pagans did offer up their
Children to their blood-thirſty Idols, or that
they made them here paſs through the fire,
as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did to <hi>Moloch,</hi> but of this there
is no probability at all, and theſe only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
conjectural Gueſſes, I ſhall leave them,
and obſerve one thing more concerning this
Town. After the fatal Battel betwixt King
<hi>Richard</hi> the Third, and <hi>Henry,</hi> Earl of <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi>
afterwards <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh King of
<hi>England</hi> in <hi>Boſworth</hi>-field, about the Year of
our Lord 1485, in which King <hi>Richard,</hi> with
four Thouſand Men more were ſlain, and not
above ten Perſons on the other ſide. The
Corps of the deceaſed King was brought to
be buried there in great diſgrace, as the day
before he went out in pomp; for his Body
being rifled by the Souldiers, was carried
naked behind a <hi>Purſivant at Arms,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
all over daub'd with Mire and Blood,
was conveyed to the <hi>Grey Friar's</hi> Church,
that then was within the Town, and there
buried very obſcurely and meanly, whilſt
<hi>Richmond,</hi> with joyful Acclamations, was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed
King in the very midſt of ſlaughte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
Bodies round about.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CARLETON,</hi> all that are born there,
whether it be by a peculiar Property of the
Soil, or of the Water; or elſe by ſome other
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:108032:50"/>
ſecret Operation of Nature, have an ill favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
untunable and harſh manner of Speech,
fetching their Words, with very much ado,
deep from out of the Throat, with a certain
kind of wharling, the Letter <hi>R</hi> being very
irkſome to them to pronounce.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Rutlandſhire.</head>
                  <p>It is the leaſt County of all <hi>England.</hi> Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
in form almoſt round like a circle, it is
in compaſs ſo far about, as a Light-horſman
will ride in one day.</p>
                  <p>It was called <hi>Rutland,</hi> as one would ſay
<hi>Red-land,</hi> the Earth in this Shire is every where
red, and ſo red, that even the Sheeps fleeces
are thereby coloured red: The <hi>Engliſh-Saxons</hi>
called <hi>Red</hi> in their Tongue <hi>Roet</hi> and <hi>Rud.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>UPPINGHAM,</hi> a place upon an high
aſcent, whence that name was impoſed, a
well frequented Market Town.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Vale of Catmoſe,</hi> a field full of Woods.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Okeham</hi> is in the middle of it, ſo called from
Oaks.</p>
                  <p>This ſmall Shire hath Pariſh Churches four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
eight.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Lincolnſhire.</head>
                  <p>A very large County reaching almoſt three
Score Miles in length, and carrying in ſome
places above thirty Miles in breadth; paſſing
good for yielding of Corn, and feeding of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:108032:50"/>
Cattel, well furniſhed and ſet out with great
number of Towns, and watered with many
Rivers, having great ſtore of Fiſh and Fowl.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BOSTON</hi> is a famous Town, ſtanding
on both ſides the River <hi>Witham,</hi> which hath
over it a wooden Bridge of great height, well
frequented by means of a commodious Haven
unto it: The Market-place is fair and large,
and the Buildings are very beautiful; alſo a
moſt ſtately Church, with a very high Tower-ſteeple,
and hath as many ſteps in its ſteeple
from the bottome to the top, as there are Days
in the Year; which Steeple ſalutes Paſſengers
and Travellers a great way off, and giveth
Direction alſo to Sailers. In the Coat of
<hi>Boſton</hi> for the Corporation, there are three
Crowns relating to the three Kingdoms, the
Creſt a Ram lying upon a Wool-ſack, the
Ram ſignifying the great Sheep-walks in the
Fens round about, and the Wool-ſack, that
it was a Staple-Town; the Supporters of the
Coat are two Maremaids, ſignifying that it
was a Port-Town.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LINCOLN.</hi> The chief City of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
and is large, well inhabited and frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
it is ſituated upon the ſide of an Hill,
and thence hath its Name from its Situation,
or becauſe it hath been a Colony. Certain
it is a Place of great Antiquity, and of a very
long ſtanding; there are fourteen Churches,
whereof the Cathedral is very glorious, being
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:108032:51"/>
not much in feriour to any, and in one of
the Steples there is a very great Bell rung by
ſixteen Men, called <hi>Great Tom of Lincoln.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>'Tis governed by a Mayor and Aldermen.
The Dioceſs here is the largeſt in <hi>England,</hi>
for after three Biſhopricks were taken out of
it, it contained four whole Counties, and
parts of two; the whole Shire is divided into
three Part, whereof one is called <hi>Holland,</hi> a
ſecond <hi>Keſtuen,</hi> and the third <hi>Lindſey.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>GRANTHAM,</hi> a Town of good reſort, ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
with a School built by <hi>Richard Fox,</hi> Biſhop
of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and with a fair Church, having
a Spire-ſteeple of a mighty height. There are
in this Shire ſix hundred and thirty Pariſhes,
thirty and one Hundreds, and thirty Market
Towns. We went from hence into</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Nottinghamſhire.</head>
                  <p>It is limited Northward with <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi>
Weſtward with <hi>Darbyſhire,</hi> and in ſome other
parts with <hi>Yorkſhire.</hi> The South and Eaſt parts
thereof are made fruitful by the River <hi>Trent,</hi>
with other Riverets reſorting unto it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>NOTTINGHAM</hi> is built upon a Rock,
and is environed by Rocks on one ſide which
are waſhed by a crooked winding of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious
River, and hath a very fair Park of
the Duke of <hi>New Caſtle</hi>'s adjoining to it, with
the Foreſt of <hi>Shirewood</hi> bordering upon it.
The Streets are large and well paved, the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:108032:51"/>
Market-place very handſome and conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,
the Churches ſpatious and well contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
and the Houſes high and ſtately, they
are for the moſt part built with Brick, but
ſome of them are rare pieces as well for Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture
as Deſign; and, in ſhort, the whole
front of their Fabrick is beautified with Sculp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
and gliſtering Balconies, the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants
be very deſirous of the new Modes and
Draughts of Architecture. The Caſtle which
is on the Weſt ſide of the Town is ſituated
upon an exceeding high Rock, and is ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
to be a place of very great Antiquity,
This Caſtle held out a Siege by the <hi>Danes</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<hi>Alfred,</hi> and it was then called <hi>Snotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi>
and now <hi>Nottingham.</hi> King <hi>Edward</hi> the
Second ſtrenghened the Town by an addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of Walls, and a new Caſtle was built by
<hi>William the Conqueror</hi> to keep the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in
awe and ſubjection, and by Art and Nature
together it became even impregnable. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi>
the Fourth illuſtrated it with ſeveral
Dwelling-houſes for Commanders and Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers,
and indeed in the Rock upon which
the Caſtle ſtands, are ſeveral ſmall Cottages
hewen out of it, in which, at preſent, dwells
divers poor people; and it is reported, that
it never was taken until it was ſurprized by
<hi>Robert,</hi> Earl of <hi>Derby,</hi> in the <hi>Baron</hi>'s Wars,
who having once got this entered the Town,
and then uſed the Townſmen according to
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:108032:52"/>
his pleaſure; though I find too in the Life
of King <hi>Stephen,</hi> that <hi>Robert,</hi> Earl of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi>
invaded this Town with a great Power, and
when moſt of the Townſmen were ſlain and
burnt in the Churches whither they fled for
refuge; there is a Story of one of them who
was richer than the reſt, and being forced
to return to his own houſe by the Soldiers
that had taken him, to ſhew them where all
his Treaſures lay, he bringing them into a
Celler, and whilſt they were buſy in break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
open Locks and Coffers, conveyed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
away, making the Door faſt after him,
and ſet the Houſe on fire, ſo that the Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
being thirty in number, periſhed all in
the Flames, which ketching hold of other
Buildings joining to it, almoſt burnt up the
whole Town: But that which makes this
Caſtle moſt ſignally remarkeable, was the
Diſcovery of <hi>Roger Mortimore,</hi> Earl of <hi>March,</hi>
and the Impriſonment too of <hi>David le Braſe,</hi>
King of the <hi>Scots,</hi> who was here confined;
the relation of which I ſhall ſet down as brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
as I can.</p>
                  <p>After King <hi>Edward</hi> the Second had been
Depoſed and Murdered by the Plots of his
own Wife, Queen <hi>Iſabella,</hi> and King <hi>Edward</hi>
the Third, her Son, had Reigned about four
Years, a Parliament was called at <hi>Nottingham,</hi>
where this <hi>Roger Mortimore,</hi> who was then
the Queen's moſt eſpecial Favourite, was in
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:108032:52"/>
ſuch Glory and Renown, that it was beyond
all compariſon: None ſo much Lord Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount,
as the Earl of <hi>March:</hi> None appears
in ſo great an Equippage, and attended with
ſo honourable a Retinue, as the Earl of <hi>March;</hi>
ſo that the King's Train was inferiour to his,
and his Majeſty's Glory eclipſed, by the
Pomp and Grandeur of one of his Nobles,
for he very oft would preſume to go fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt,
and his own Officers, and was ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
proud and haughty, as to make all
Perſons cringe, and do as great Homage to
him, as to Majeſty it ſelf; nay, he undertook
to Order and Diſpoſe of all Perſons and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs
to his own Will and Pleaſure; and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
one day he very ſharply rebuked the
Earl of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> the King's Couſin, for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming
to appoint Lodgings for certain No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen
near the Court, without his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
Licenſe and Aſſignation, and having diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodged
the Earl, with ſome other Perſons of
very great Quality, and removed them a Mile
out of Town, he did by this means ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe
the Nobility againſt him, that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
to pry more narrowly into his Actions,
and being enraged to ſee his Pride and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation
of his great Prerogatives, they u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimouſly
held againſt him, and gave it out
amongſt the People, <hi>That this</hi> Mortimore <hi>was
the Queen's Gallant, and the King's Maſter, and
ſought by all means he poſſibly could to deſtroy the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:108032:53"/>
Royal Blood, and to Uſurp the Crown;</hi> which
Report did ſo work upon ſome of the King's
moſt truſty Friends, that they got <hi>Robert Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
who had a long time been Governor
of the Caſtle, and knew well all the ſecret
Corners therein, to ſwear Secrecy to them,
and Fidelity to the King, and accordingly to
aſſiſt them in thoſe Deſigns they had in hand:
Whereupon one night King <hi>Edward</hi> lying
without the Caſtle, both he, and his Friends,
were brought by Torch-light through a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
place under ground, beginning a far off
from the ſaid Caſtle, ('tis the Vault which is
ſtill called <hi>Mortimore's Hole)</hi> till they came e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
to the Queen's Chamber, which, by
chance, they found open; being armed with
naked Swords, in they ruſhed, leaving the
King in the ſame poſture at the Door; being
entered into the Privy-chamber, they found
the Earl of <hi>March</hi> undreſſed, ready to go to
bed to the Queen, but they croſſed his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign,
and cool'd his Courage, halling him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
by force, upon which the Queen cried
out, <hi>Good Son, take pitty upon gentle</hi> Mortimore,
ſuſpecting her Son to be there in the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny:
The Keys of the Caſtle were preſently
called for, and every place, withal the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture
committed into the King's Hands, and
<hi>Mortimore</hi> was forthwith ſent to the Tower,
who, being Tried by his Peers, Arraign'd
and found Guilty, was hanged upon the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:108032:53"/>
common Gallows two Days and two Nights.
The Articles that were brought againſt him
were divers, though his Familiarity with the
Queen, his Treachery to his King, and his
great Service to <hi>David,</hi> King of the <hi>Scots,</hi> was
the chief, whilſt he alſo burnt the Charters
by which the <hi>Scotch</hi> King ſtood obliged to
do Homage to the King of <hi>England,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
enſued a great War betwixt them; for
King <hi>David</hi> being ſpurred on by the <hi>French</hi>
King Invaded <hi>England,</hi> and having made a
great Road into the Northern Counties, and
ſpoiling and burning every where as they
went along, at length, at <hi>Durham</hi> his Army
was routed, and himſelf taken Priſoner, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
firſt ſent to the Tower, afterward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
to this Caſtle, where, during his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinement,
he engraved upon the Walls of his
Deportment, the Hiſtory of our Saviour's
Death and Paſſion, the Relicts of which are
ſtill to be ſeen. After eleven Years Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment,
he was reſtored againſt to his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
by paying a good Ranſom for his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty;
but before he returned, he was one
of the four Kings that was nobly Treated by
<hi>Henry Picard,</hi> a Vintner, then Lord Mayor of
<hi>London:</hi> Theſe were the four Kings, <hi>Edward</hi>
the Third, King of <hi>England; John,</hi> King of
<hi>France; David,</hi> King of the <hi>Scots;</hi> and the
King of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> together with <hi>Edward, The
Black Prince,</hi> all bearing him company at the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:108032:54"/>
ſame Table; this was about the Year 1358.
But before I leave this Town, I cannot but
take notice of one thing more memorable in
our Age, this being the firſt place where
King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt ſet up his Royal Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard
againſt the Rebels in the late unhappy
Wars, and when the King's Forces were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced,
to leave it, the Caſtle was quite demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.
We went from hence to view the
Chair of <hi>Robin-Hood,</hi> of which it follows.</p>
                  <p>Having pleaſured our ſelves with the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquities
of this Town, we took Horſe and
went to viſit the Well and ancient Chair of
<hi>Robin-Hood,</hi> which is about a Mile within the
Foreſt of <hi>Shirwood:</hi> Being placed in that
Chair, we had a Cap, which, they ſay, was
his, very formally put upon our Heads, and
having performed the uſual Ceremonies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitting
ſo great a Solemnity, we received the
Freedom of the Chair, and were incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
into the Society of that renowned Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood;
but that we may not receive ſuch
Privileges without an honourable mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of the Perſons that left them to Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;
know, we muſt, that the Patent was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed
to the inferior Rangers of this Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt,
by <hi>Robin Hood</hi> and <hi>Little John,</hi> honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
Perſonages indeed, being the chief Lords
of ſome moſt renowned Robbers in the Reign
of King <hi>Richard</hi> the Firſt: This ſame <hi>Robin
Hood</hi> entertained one Hundred tall Men, all
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:108032:54"/>
good Archers, with the Spoil he daily made
himſelf Maſter of, whom four Hundred, tho'
every way well Accoutred to give Battel,
durſt ſcarce make an Onſet. He ſuffered no
Woman to be violated, oppreſs'd, oa any
ways moleſted; poor Men's Goods he ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
and did relieve them very liberally with
what he got from the rich <hi>Carles:</hi> He kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
none, and by this means he did, for a
long time, keep up the Order of <hi>Knight Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants.</hi>
Having, for ſome time, pleaſed our
ſelves with our new Brothers that very curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
entertained us, we went from hence into</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Yorkſhire.</head>
                  <p>The County of <hi>York</hi> is the greateſt Shire
by far of all <hi>England,</hi> and is thought to be in
a temperate meaſure fruitful. If in one place
there be ſtony and ſandy barren ground, in
another place there are for it Corn-fields, as
rich and fruitful; if it be void and deſtitute
of Woods here, you ſhall find it ſhadowed in
another place with moſt thick Foreſts. The
Length extendeth from <hi>Hart-hill</hi> in the South,
to the Mouth of <hi>Tees</hi> in the North, which is
near ſeventy Miles; the breadth from <hi>Flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough-head</hi>
to <hi>Horn-Caſtle</hi> upon the River <hi>Lun</hi>
is Eighty; the whole circumference three
hundred and eight Miles.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HELMSLEY,</hi> a Mannor in <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> hath
two Parks and a Chaſe in it, ſaid to be about
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:108032:55"/>
146 Miles in compaſs, and had 40000 Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-Trees,
and 200 Acres of Wood. There
are many Free-holders there.</p>
                  <p>The whole Shire is divided into 3 parts,
which, according to the 3 Quarters of the
World, are called <hi>The Weſt-Riding, The Eaſt-Riding,
The North-Riding. Weſt-Riding,</hi> for a
good while is compaſſed in with the River
<hi>Ouſe,</hi> with the bound of <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> and with
the South limits of the Shire, and beareth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
the Weſt and South: <hi>Eaſt-Riding</hi> look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
to the Sun-riſing, and the Ocean, which,
together with the River <hi>Derwent,</hi> encloſeth it.
<hi>North-Riding</hi> reacheth Northward, hemmed
in (as it were) with the River <hi>Tees,</hi> with <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>went,</hi>
and a long race of the River <hi>Ouſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>YORK</hi> is the fairſt City in all this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
and deſervedly reputed the Second of
<hi>England;</hi> for its Greatneſs and Munificence,
the pleaſantneſs of its Situation, the Buildings
are ſtately and beautiful. The whole City is
rich, glorious and honourable, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
of its being governed by a Lord Mayor,
who moderates in all Caſes of Temporal Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs,
as alſo by an Archbiſhop who is Judge
in all Spiritual Matters. The River <hi>Ouſe</hi> flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
with a gentle Stream from the North
part cutteth it in twain, and divided (as it
were) into two Cities, which are conjoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
with a ſtone Bridge, having one mighty
Arch. There is a Cathedral Church dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:108032:55"/>
to Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> an excellent fair and ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Fabrick, near unto which there is the
Prince's Houſe, commonly called, <hi>The Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>York</hi> was a Colony of the <hi>Romans, Ptolomey</hi>
and <hi>Antonine;</hi> and alſo by a piece of Money
coined by the Emperour <hi>Severus,</hi> in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe
whereof we read,
<q>COL. EBORACUMLEG. VI.
VICTRIX.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Severus</hi> had his Palace in this City, and here
at the hour of death gave up his laſt breath,
with theſe words: <hi>I entered upon a State every
way troubleſome, and I leave it peaceable even to
the</hi> Britains.</p>
                  <p>There are many fine Seats of Perſons of
Quality, by reaſon of the Pleaſantneſs of its
Soil, which abounds in Plenty of all things,
and for Pleaſure and Recreation it affords the
moſt of any County in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the <hi>North-Riding</hi> of this County is <hi>Ouns<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery-Hill,</hi>
or <hi>Roſebery-Topping,</hi> which mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>up
a mighty height, and maketh a goodly
ſhew a farre off, ſo often as the Head thereof
hath his cloudy Cap on, lightly there follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
rain whence they have a proverbial Rhime,</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>When <hi>Roſebery-Topping</hi> wears a Cap,</l>
                     <l>Let <hi>Cliveland</hi> then beware a clap.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>I could have particuliz'd ſeveral other
Towns and Villages in this Shire, but what
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:108032:56"/>
has been related is moſt material, and again
the Volume is but ſmall, and would not bear
it. In this County there are 459 Pariſhes,
under which are very many Chappels, for
number of Inhabitants equal unto great Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes.
We went from hence into the Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick
of <hi>Durham,</hi> of which it follows.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Durham.</head>
                  <p>The chief Town; in Latin, <hi>Dunelmum,</hi> a
County Palatine, and a Biſhop's See; 'tis ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated
upon a Hill, and encompaſſed almoſt
round by the River <hi>Were,</hi> is alſo ſhaped in
form of an Egg, and ſtrongly fortified both
by Art and Nature. There is a ſtately Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral
which makes a fine and lofty ſhew,
with an high Tower in the midſt, and two
Spires at the Weſt end. The County in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
is very pleaſant, and rich in its Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains
with Iron and Coals, and its Vallies with
Corn and Graſs: But before I leave this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
I cannot omit the mentioning of a certain
place near <hi>Derlington,</hi> which is 3 Pits full of
Water of a wonderful depth, called by the
common People <hi>Hell Kettles,</hi> concerning which
Sir <hi>Richard Baker</hi> in his <hi>Engliſh Chronicles</hi> gives
this Account, That in the 24th Year of King
<hi>Henry</hi> the Second the Earth in this place lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
up it ſelf in the manner of an high Tower,
and ſo remained from Morning till Evening
unmoveable, and preſently after that time
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:108032:56"/>
fell with ſo horrible a noiſe, that it affrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
all the Inhabitants thereabouts, and the
Earth ſwallowing it up made thoſe 3 deep
Pits, which are ſtill to be ſeen. The next
place we took notice of was</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Northumberland.</head>
                  <p>The Ground appears to be very barren and
rough, and is Mountainous and Rocky in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
parts of it. Towards the Sea and <hi>Tine,</hi> by
diligence and good Husbandry, it becometh
fruitful, but elſwhere 'tis hard and rugged.
By reaſon of the ſharpneſs of the Air, and
courſneſs of the Soil, the Inhabitants are lookt
upon, and eſteem'd to be a War-like People,
and excellent Light-horſemen. The Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
and Gentry of the North are of great An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity,
and can produce more ancient Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies
than any other Part of <hi>England,</hi> many of
their Gentry taking date before the Conqueſt,
the reſt came in with <hi>William the Conqueror.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>NEW-CASTLE upon TINE,</hi> (ſo called
becauſe <hi>Robert de Curtois,</hi> Son of <hi>William the
Conqueror,</hi> built there a New Caſtle out of the
ground againſt the neighbouring <hi>Scots)</hi> the
very Eye of all the Towns in theſe Parts, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled
by a notable Haven, which <hi>Time</hi> mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,
being of that depth, that it beareth very
tall Ships, and ſo defendeth them, that they
can neither be eaſily toſſed with Tempeſts,
nor driven upon Shallows and Shelves. The
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:108032:57"/>
Town is ſituated on the riſing of an Hill, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned
with four Churches, and fortified with
ſtrong Walls which have 7 Gates in them,
with many Towers. It is wealthy, partly by
entercourſe of Traffick with the <hi>Germans,</hi> and
partly by carrying out Sea-coals, wherewith
this Place aboundeth, both into foreign Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,
and alſo into other parts of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BERWICK</hi> is the utmoſt Town in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
and the ſtrongeſt hold in all <hi>Britain.</hi> It
is well near compaſſed about with the Sea,
and <hi>Twede</hi> together. Upon the Weſt of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland</hi>
the <hi>Picct's</hi> Wall is to be ſeen of
great height, and almoſt whole. There are
about 46 Pariſhes in <hi>Northumberland.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Cumberland.</head>
                  <p>This County is like the reſt of the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern
Counties, and hath a ſharp piercing
Air; the Soil is fertile, for the moſt part, both
with Corn and Cattel, and in ſome parts
hereof with Fiſh and Fowl. Here are
likewiſe ſeveral Minerals which have of late
been diſcovered, not only Mines of Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per;
but Veins of Gold and Silver too
have been found here, as I was credibly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd;
and of all the Shires we have, it is
accounted the beſt furniſhed with the <hi>Roman</hi>
Antiquities. Nor it is no leſs renowned for
its high Mountains than for its Mines, of
which there are three, <hi>Skiddow, Lanvellin</hi> and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:108032:57"/>
                     <hi>Caſticand,</hi> and theſe Words goes much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
the height of them,</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Skiddow, Lanvellin </hi>and<hi> Caſticand</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Are the higheſt Hills in all <hi>England.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CARLISLE,</hi> is commodiouſly Situated,
and is fortified with a ſtrong Wall, Caſtle
and Cittadel; the Cathedral Church there
being formerly a very ſtately and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence
Structure, adorned with rare Ornaments.
Not far from this City, is a Trophy of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory,
as is ſuppoſed, called by the Country
People <hi>Long-Megg and her Daughters,</hi> being
Seventy and ſeven Stones, each of them Ten
Foot high above-ground, and one of them is
fifteen foot. There are in <hi>Cumberland</hi> 9 Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-Towns,
and 58 Pariſhes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Weſtmorland.</head>
                  <p>It is ſo called becauſe it lieth amongſt
<hi>Moors</hi> and high Hills, and was, for the moſt
part, unmanured; ſuch barren places the
Northern <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> call <hi>Moors;</hi> and <hi>Weſtmore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
is a Weſtern Mooriſh-county. The Air
is ſharp and cold.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>KENDALE-KIRKE</hi> by <hi>Kendale,</hi> a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
great Town of Trade and Reſort, with
two broad and long Streets croſſing the one
over the other; a place excellent for Cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
and for Induſtry ſo ſurpaſſing, that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
thereof it carrieth a great Name. For,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:108032:58"/>
the Inhabitants have great Traffick, and vent
of their Woollen-cloaths throughout all parts
of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>APELBY,</hi> memorable for its Antiquity
and Situation only. It ſtandeth in a pleaſant
Site, encompaſſed for the moſt part with the
River <hi>Eden;</hi> for its Antiquity it deſerves to
be counted the chief Town of the Shire. The
Caſtle is the common Goal for Malefactors,
and the Seſſions and Aſſizes are there kept.</p>
                  <p>In this Shire are contained 26 Pariſhes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Lancaſhire.</head>
                  <p>It is a large, populous and well wooded
County. The County Palatine of <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi>
(famous for the four <hi>Henries,</hi> the Fourth,
Fifth, Sixth and Seventh Kings of <hi>England,</hi>
derived from <hi>John Gaunt,</hi> Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,)</hi>
is upon the South-confined and parted by the
River <hi>Merſey,</hi> from the County Palatine of
<hi>Cheſter,</hi> the County of <hi>Darbyſhire</hi> bordering
upon the Eaſt; the large County of <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi>
together with <hi>Weſtmorland</hi> and <hi>Cumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
being her kind Neighbours upon the
<hi>North,</hi> and the Sea called <hi>Mare Hibernicum</hi>
imbracing her upon the <hi>Weſt.</hi> Their Kine
and Oxen have goodly Heads and fair ſpread
Horns, and are in body well proportionate
withal; but the Ground, for the generality,
is Hilly and Mountainous.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:108032:58"/>
                     <hi>MANCHESTER,</hi> a Town of great an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity,
from <hi>Main,</hi> a <hi>Britiſh</hi> Word, which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth
a <hi>Stone:</hi> It is ſeated upon a ſtony Hill,
and beneath the Town, there are moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
Quarries of Stone. It far excelleth the
Towns lying round about it, for the Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
ſhew it carrieth, for reſort unto it, and
for Cloathing: In regard alſo of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
place, the fair Church and Colledge.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LANCASTER,</hi> or <hi>Loncaſter</hi> from the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<hi>Lone,</hi> the chief Town of this Region. I
ſhall now give a ſhort Account of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
Wonders, which are as follows,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Firſt Wonder</head>
                  <p>Is at the <hi>Divel</hi>'s <hi>Arſe,</hi> near a Village called
<hi>Caſtleton,</hi> ſufficiently Noted for that wide
Subterraneons Cavarn, known by the Name
of the <hi>Devil's Arſe,</hi> which runs under the
Hill upon which the Caſtle ſtands; and at
its Entrance, it is Large and Capatious, tho'
the further you go in, the more narrower
it is Contracted; within the Mouth of it
are ſeveral poor Cottages Erected, the top
of this Cave is an exceeding great Height,
and appears to the Eye as if it were Arched
above and Chequer'd with diverſity of cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured
Stones. At the Entrance the poor Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
are very ready to attend with Candles,
and Lanthorns, to conduct Strangers in,
tho' it belonged to <hi>Satan</hi>'s Territories, and it
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:108032:59"/>
is very Dark and Slippery by reaſon of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
Currants of Water which runs along
the Cave, which puts a ſtop to your Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney;
there is a Story of a Shepherd that paſt
over all theſe Currents, and at laſt came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
a very fair and delightful Meadow, which
ſavours too much of a Romance to be cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited;
however, 'tis ſuppoſed could all theſe
Waters once be gone over, there might be
made ſome new Diſcoveries, but it is a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal
place both for its Name and Nature,
and hath ſo near a Relation to the Diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
Regions.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Second Wonder</head>
                  <p>Is <hi>Mamtar;</hi> 'tis a high ſteep Cliff, and from
the top of which Cliff or Rock the Sand tho'
the Air be never ſo Calm, doth continually
trickle to the bottom Night and Day, and
now and then great Stones fall down with a
very great Noiſe, and do much affright the
poor Neighbouring Inhabitants. On the top
of it, bubbles up a Fountain which in ſome
places ſtreams down the Cliff.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Third Wonder</head>
                  <p>Is a Fountain which Ebbs and Flows like
the Sea, receiving an influence from the
Moon, and obſerving the ſame regular Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
by which the Ocean it ſelf continually
is regulated.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:108032:59"/>
                  <head>The Fourth Wonder</head>
                  <p>Is called the <hi>Marble Stones</hi> by their order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Diſpoſitions, into ſeveral rows, one row
higher than another; it ſeems rather to be
the contrivance of Art than of Nature, but
that we ought not to Derogate from that
great Parent, whoſe production are conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually
Rare and Unimitable.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Fifth Wonder</head>
                  <p>Is <hi>Elden Hole,</hi> near unto the Fourth Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;
'tis reputed a bottomleſs Abyſs, and
could never as yet by any Art be Fathom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:
The Mouth of it is wide and craggy,
but the inward receſſes contracted and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trecate.
There is a Story that they let a
Man down by Ropes, and Candles to light
him, to give an Account of this infernal
Pit, but paid dearly for his Preſumption with
the loſs of his life for his Boldneſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Sixth Wonder</head>
                  <p>Is <hi>Buxtons-Well,</hi> about two Miles from
the fifth Wonder; it glories in a hot Well;
'tis incloſed in a very fair Stone Building,
erected formerly by the Earl of <hi>Shrewsbury;</hi>
the Operation is very near to that of the
Croſs Bath, having two Springs of Water,
the one within a hand breadth of the other,
and one is Hot, the other cold as Ice.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:108032:60"/>
                  <head>The Seventh and laſt Wonder</head>
                  <p>Is <hi>Pool Hole;</hi> 'tis a Hollow Cave under a
very high Rock, bearing ſome reſemblance
with that by the City of <hi>Wells,</hi> called <hi>Ochy
Hole,</hi> but not containing in it ſelf half ſo
great Varieties. From hence we went into</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Cheſhire.</head>
                  <p>It is a County Palatine, and of great
Note for plenty of ſeveral Commodities; as
alſo for moſt excellent Cheeſe, and the Men
and Women are generally Acounted very
Handſome here. There is in this County
great ſtore of Salt-Springs, Mettals and
Mines, and in the River <hi>Dee</hi> is plenty of
<hi>Salmons;</hi> on the <hi>South</hi> part of <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> Trees
are very frequently found by Diging under
the Ground, which is believed have been
here ever ſince <hi>Noah</hi>'s Flood.</p>
                  <p>The chief Town of this County is <hi>Weſt
Cheſter,</hi> a City famous for its Antiquity and
Situation, and no leſs for its Renown; 'tis
Built in the form of a Quadrant, with very
ſpacious Houſes, neat and uniform, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vironed
with a very ſtrong Wall, and hath
a Caſtle ſtands upon a high Hill near the
River <hi>Dee</hi> ſtrongly Fortified. Here are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
Churches which are very Antient and
goodly Fabricks, but eſpecially for the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrals.
The Houſes are very fairly Built,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:108032:60"/>
and along the chief Streets are Galleries or
Walking-places; they call them Rows, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Shops on both ſides, through which a
Man may walk dry from one end to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>NANTWICH,</hi> which the River <hi>Wever</hi>
firſt viſiteth, is reputed the greateſt and fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
built Town of all this Shire after <hi>Cheſter.</hi>
It is called the <hi>White-wich</hi> or <hi>Salt-pich,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
the whiteſt Salt is there boiled. This
Shire containeth 13 Market Towns, and 68
Pariſhes. We went next into</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Shropſhire.</head>
                  <p>Or the County of <hi>Salop,</hi> is for the moſt
part Rich in Corn and Cattle, and glories in
in its moſt famous City of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> which
is compaſſed almoſt round by the River <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern,</hi>
having two fair Bridges upon it, and
is Fortified both by Art and Nature. It is
like a Horſe-ſhew in the opening place, and
doubtleſs deſerves the Obſervation of all
Travellers, more than any Town or City in
this Nation, and is built upon the Riſeing
of a Hill; the Churches are very fair and
Spacious, it is inhabited with both <hi>Welſh</hi> and
<hi>Engliſh,</hi> ſpeaking both Languages. One of
their Rarities there is their Cakes, ſuch as
cannot be made ſo well in any other place
of <hi>England,</hi> and many things here is very
obſervable, which I ſhall not mention, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:108032:61"/>
they have been allready ſo well ſet
fourth by other Pens. From hence we went
into</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LUDLOW,</hi> is one of the chiefeſt Towns
in this County, and is of greater Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity
than Beauty; 'tis Situated by a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant
River, and is famous for its Caſtle built
by <hi>Roger,</hi> Earl of <hi>Mountgomery,</hi> who enviro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
it with a Wall a Mile in compaſs; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards
when <hi>Robert,</hi> Earl of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi>
and Eldeſt Son to <hi>Mountgomery,</hi> was taken in
his Rebellion againſt <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt, and
was baniſhed out of the Land; the King
took this Caſtle into his own Hands; after
this it was given away from the Crown,
by King <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, and came into
the Family of the <hi>Lacys</hi> and <hi>Mortimors,</hi> at
laſt to be the inheritance of the Princes of
<hi>Wales.</hi> And by this means beginning to be
in great requeſt, the Inhabitants erected
a very large Church to make it more Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous;
and in a little time, it excelled all its
Neighbourhood, and out-ſhin'd them in Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre
and Dignity; for King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth
inſtituted here the Counſel of the Marches of
<hi>Wales,</hi> in which he Ordered there ſhould be
a Preſident, Secretary, Attorney and Solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,
four Juſtices of ſome of the Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Counties of <hi>Wales,</hi> and as many other
Privy Counſellours, as the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi>
ſhould Elect to be Aſſiſtant to himſelf in this
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:108032:61"/>
Court, being erected for his own particular
Uſe and Service. We ſtaid in this Town
but two Nights, and went from hence into</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Staffordſhire.</head>
                  <p>Is very Rich in Paſture and Cattle, and
enriched by the River <hi>Trent, Trigenta</hi> as ſome
will have it; becauſe there are Thirty ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
Streams or Rivolets which run into it, or
Thirty ſeveral ſorts of Fiſh which Swims
within its Streams: However, 'tis very Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous
to the whole County; the firſt
Town of Note we came to in this County
was</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>STAFFORD</hi> is ſituated on a pleaſant Soil,
ſweet Air, Environed with a Wall, and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified
with Gates, and adorned with two
Churches, and a Spacious Free-School, and
a large Market-place, and the Houſes very
Handſome and Beautiful; it is Governed
by a Mayor and Aldermen; not far from
the Town are to be ſeen the Ruins of an old
Caſtle, Situated upon a Hill, heretofore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing
to the Barons of <hi>Stafford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LICHFIELD.</hi> This City is low Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
of good Largeneſs, and Fair withall,
divided into two parts with a ſhallow pool
of clear Water; which Parts notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
join in one by the means of two Bridges,
or Cauſeys, made over, that have their
Sluces made, to let out the Water.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:108032:62"/>
It was beautified with a very goodly Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral
Church, which being round about
compaſſed with a fair Wall-Caſtle-like, and
garniſhed beſides with fair Houſes of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendaries,
and with the Biſhop's Palace alſo,
mounting up on high with three Pyramids or
Spires of Stone, making a lovely ſhew,
and for elegant and proportional Building it
did yield to few Cathedral Churches, but
is now demoliſhed. There are accounted
an Hundred and Thirty Pariſhes in this Shire.
We went next into</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Warwickſhire.</head>
                  <p>It is bounded on the <hi>Eaſt-ſide</hi> with <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thamptonſhire,
Leiceſterſhire,</hi> and the <hi>Watling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet</hi>-way;
on the <hi>South</hi> with <hi>Oxfordſhire</hi> and
<hi>Gloceſterſhire;</hi> on the <hi>Weſt</hi> for the greateſt
part with <hi>Worceſtorſhire;</hi> and on the <hi>Northſide</hi>
with <hi>Staffordſhire.</hi> It is divided into a plain
Champion, and a woody Country; which
parts the River <hi>Avon,</hi> running crookedly
from <hi>North-Eaſt</hi> to <hi>South-Weſt,</hi> doth after a
ſort ſever one from the other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WARWICK</hi> is the principal Town of
the whole Shire. It ſtandeth over the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<hi>Avon</hi> upon a ſteep and high Rock, and
all the Paſſages into it are wrought out of
the very Stone. It ſtands in a dry and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile
Soil, having the benefit of rich and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant
Medows on the <hi>South</hi> part, with the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:108032:62"/>
lofty Groves and ſpacious Thickets of the
Woodland on the <hi>North.</hi> It hath a very
ſtrong Caſtle, the ſeat in times paſt of the
Earls of <hi>Warwick,</hi> the Town it ſelf is adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
with fair Houſes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>COVENTRY.</hi> It is a City very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modiouſly
Seated, large, ſweet and neat, was
fortified with a ſtrong Wall, and is ſet out
with right goodly Houſes; among which
there riſe up on high two Churches of rare
Workmanſhip, ſtanding one hard by the
other, and matched (as it were) as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currents;
the one conſecrated to the <hi>Holy
Trinity,</hi> the other to Saint <hi>Michael.</hi> One
and the ſelf ſame Biſhop carried the name
both of <hi>Coventry</hi> and <hi>Lichfield.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Leofrick,</hi> the firſt Lord of this City, being
much offended and angry with the Citizens,
oppreſſed them with moſt heavy Tributes,
which he would remit upon no other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,
at the earneſt ſuit of his Wife <hi>Godina,</hi>
unleſs ſhe would her ſelf ride on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back
Naked through the Greateſt and moſt
inhabited Street of this City; which ſhe did
indeed, and was covered with her fair
long Hair, and alſo a Proclamation was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd,
commanding all People to keep cloſe
within their Houſes, as alſo their Doors and
Windows ſhut, no Perſon on pain of Death
to appear in that Street, nor ſo much as to
look into it, whether out of a Window or
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:108032:63"/>
otherwiſe; upon which, as ſhe was riding
along Naked, one Man curious than
Ordinary, ventures to peep out of a Garret
Window, and being immediately diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
was Apprehended and Hang'd, as by
the Effigies of a Man, that is continually
kept up as a <hi>Memorandum,</hi> in a full proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
looking out of a Garret Window, and
called by the Inhabitants, <hi>Peeping Jack:</hi> And
thus ſhe did ſet free her Citizens of <hi>Coventry</hi>
from many Payments for ever.</p>
                  <p>At <hi>Gosford</hi>-Gate there hangeth to be ſeen
a mighty great Shield-bone of a wild Bore,
(or rather of an Elephant, being not ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
as a yard in length) which <hi>Guy</hi> of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi>
ſlew in Hunting, when he had turned
up with his Snout a great Pit or Pond, which
is now called <hi>Swanſewell,</hi> but <hi>Swineſwell</hi> in
times paſt. In this County there are an
Hundred and Fifty Eight Pariſh Churches.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Worceſterſhire.</head>
                  <p>At the firſt entring on the Confines of this
Shire, we found it a very Healthfull and
plentiful County: One part is of Note for
its excellent Cheeſe, but moſtly for its great
number of Pear-trees growing all along the
very Hedges, of which the Inhabitants make
a very pleaſant Drink, called <hi>Perry;</hi> 'tis
likewiſe very full of Salt Pits, and hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
been admir'd for the abundance of
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:108032:63"/>
Salt-Springs, which have very oft been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered
in this County; but that which
makes it moſt renowned, is the River <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern,</hi>
which ſtreams along the County. This,
as alſo the River <hi>Avon,</hi> which comes out
of <hi>Warwickſhire,</hi> are well repleniſhed with
all ſorts of <hi>Fiſh,</hi> but more particularly ſeem
to have been deſigned on purpoſe, as Stews
and Ponds for the preſervation of <hi>Lampreys;</hi>
a Fiſh of great Eſteem in that Country, and
ſent far and near as a very great preſent
throughout divers parts of <hi>England.</hi> They
are called <hi>Lampreys,</hi> from the Latin word
<hi>Lampretra,</hi> as if they had their Denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
from licking of Rocks; they are like
Eels, ſlippery and blackiſh, however on their
Bellies they are of a blewiſh Collour; in the
Spring they are moſt wholeſome and ſweet,
for in the Summer the part which is to them
inſtead of a Back-bone, waxeth very hard:
Naturaliſt obſerve that theſe Fiſh receive and
let in Water at ſeven Holes, for that they
have no Gills viſible at all; the <hi>Romans</hi> all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
thought this a very Noble Diſh, and
when any Perſon of Quality deſired a Sump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
Feaſt, he would be ſure to be provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
with theſe; and the <hi>Italians</hi> at this day
are very much delighted with them, and
upon that Account are very exquiſite in their
Dreſſing of them, and conſequently by their
Cookery, make them exceeding delicate to
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:108032:64"/>
the taſte. The firſt Town of Note we came
to in this County, was the City of</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WORCESTER,</hi> It is the chief City of
this County, and gives its Name to it; the
River <hi>Severn,</hi> which in other parts of the
County runs along in a ſwift Currant here,
glides more ſoftly with a more gentle Stream,
admiring as it were this City as it paſſeth
by. It is famous both for its Antiquity and
Beauty, 'tis ſuppoſed that the <hi>Romans</hi> built
it, at that time when they firſt planted Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
on the <hi>Eaſtern</hi>-ſide of the <hi>Severn,</hi> to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the Incurſion of the <hi>Britains,</hi> who were
on the other ſide, even as they did on the
<hi>South</hi>-ſide of the <hi>Rhine</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> to repreſs
the <hi>Germans,</hi> and keep them within their own
Boundaries. 'Tis ſituated partly upon the
brow of a Hill, riſing with a gentle Aſcent,
and hath a very fair Bridge over the River,
and is of great Repute by Reaſon that the
Citizens are generally great Clothiers. The
Houſes are Neat and well Built, the Streets
clean and well Paved, the Churches in Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
many, in Order and Beauty excellent,
but eſpecially, the Cathedral built many
Hundred Years ſince; in this Church are
divers ſmall Pillars, all of pure Marble,
which ſtand in Rows, and do uphold that
vaſt Bulk and Fabrick, ſomewhat ſtrange to
ſee the Body larger then the Supporters,
that ſo ſmall props ſhould be able to bear
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:108032:64"/>
up ſo great a Weight. This City hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
great Calamities by Fire, having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
been quite Burnt up by the <hi>Danes</hi> three
times, and in the Year 1113. by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known
Caſualty, and once again in the
Reign of King <hi>Stephen:</hi> And, ſure I am, 'tis
not long ſince it fell into the Hands of ſome
Barbarous and mercileſs Rebells, who were
as raging as the Flames, and whoſe Fury
was as unquenchable as the Fire. Witneſs
the grevious Preſſures it groaned under for
its Loyalty, Love and Obedience to the
King in the Year 1651. For here it was,
That after His Majeſties long Exile, he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived
with an Army of <hi>Scots</hi> and ſome <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi>
the 22<hi>d.</hi> of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and by the Aſſiſtance
of the Citizens beat out the Soldiers, who
kept it for the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> and being
Proclaim'd by the Mayor that then was,
and one of the Sheriffs, King of <hi>England,
Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> nevertheleſs
was attended with the ſame ill Fortune and
Succeſs which had been too long his Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance.
And having but a ſmall Army in
compariſon of the numberleſs Number of
Rebells that were poured in upon him, was
totally Defeated; in this City ſeveral of his
Nobles ſlain and took Priſoners, the reſt
forced to fly for their Lives, and himſelf
conſtrained to make his Eſcape as privately
as he could, and to betake himſelf into a
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:108032:65"/>
Wood in <hi>Staffordſhire,</hi> where he hiding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
in the Shady Bows of a well ſpread Oak,
he found more pitty and ſecurity from the
Trees and Woods, than from his own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural
and Bloody Subjects; who for the
fear of God by whom Kings Reign, as well
as their Allegiance which they have ſworn
to him, ought to have been his continual
Protection and Safe-good: However, 'tis
reſtor'd again to its Luſtre, and like the <hi>Phe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix</hi>
is raiſed again out of the Aſhes to its
native Splender and Magnificence, being ſtill
Governed by a Mayor, two Sheriffs, and a
Court of Aldermen, with other Officers fit
to preſerve it in that Bravery, to which it
hath now attained. From hence we went
next into.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Herefordſhire.</head>
                  <p>Having ſufficiently ſatisfied our ſelves with
the Varieties of that City, we came into
the Confines of the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> part of <hi>Hereford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi>
which is very Rocky and Mountain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
at the firſt; but having paſſed thoſe
Rocky parts, we began to find the County
more pleaſant to the Eye. We diſcovered it
to be a fertile Soil, the Vallies thick with
Corn, and the Meadows abounding with
Graſs, and well watered with Rivers, the
Hills covered with Sheep, and the Hedges
full of Apple-trees, which bear a ſort of
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:108032:65"/>
Fruit, called <hi>Red Streaks,</hi> of which they
make the beſt Cyder in <hi>England;</hi> in a word,
we found it according to the uſual report
which is made of it, to yield to no Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
in this Nation for three <hi>W. W. W.</hi> Wheat,
Wool and Waters, to which formerly might
have been added Wood, but the Iron Works
have deſtroyed it very much, and made it
now become leſs plentiful. The firſt Town
of Note we came to in this County was</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LEOMSTER,</hi> Is a Town of great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt
in this County, and is of great Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity:
Some are of an Opinion, that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
its Denomination from <hi>Linen, Hemp</hi> or
<hi>Flax;</hi> becauſe, that grows thereabouts in
plenty, but it may be ſo called from <hi>Lana,</hi>
becauſe it is reported to have the beſt Wool
known by the Name of <hi>Leomſter Ore,</hi> and is
ſaid to make the fineſt Cloth in <hi>England,</hi>
and as its Wool makes the fineſt Cloth, ſo
doth its Wheat the pureſt Bread; and they
ſay hereabouts, that for <hi>Leomſter</hi> Bread, and
<hi>Weobly</hi> Beer, none can Compare. Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the Town it is Situated in a pleaſant
Valley, and is Governed by a Bayliff and
Aldermen, and is Adorned with a very
handſome Hall, for the diſpatching of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
Affairs. We went from hence to</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HEREFORD,</hi> The chief City hereof,
is Situated almoſt in the Middle of the
County, and Watered by two pleaſant Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:108032:66"/>
                     <hi>Wye</hi> and <hi>Lugg,</hi> which by their happy
Union not far from this City, advance her
Felicity and enrich her Soil: Antiquaries
are of an Opinion, that this City had its
Riſe from <hi>Ariconium,</hi> which at this Day hath
no form at all of a Town, as having been
over-turned by an Earthquake, as ſome do
imagine it to have been in this Place, which
they now call <hi>Lencheſter,</hi> ſome three Miles
diſtant from this City, which they conceive
to be ſo from the Ruines of old Walls that
are here to be ſeen, as likewiſe from four
ſquare Pareing Stones and thick Bricks, as
well as ſeveral Roman Coins digged up in
the Earth, though now all grown over with
Trees, Buſhes and Brambles: We obſerved
when we went to Viſit this place, we ſaw
ſeveral peices of an old Wall, which do Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue
the place to continue in it very great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains
of Antiquity; however, her Siſter <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reford,</hi>
which now is Beautiful by the pains
of others, claims rightly the Pre-eminence
before all other places in this County, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
nothing for Pleaſure and Profit to make
her Renowned. She is thought firſt to have
ſhewn her Head in the time of the <hi>Saxon,</hi>
and it is ſuppoſed to have received great
Helps and Increaſe by Religion, and the
Martyrdom of <hi>Ethelbert,</hi> King of the <hi>Eaſt
Angels,</hi> who when he courted the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
of <hi>Offa,</hi> King of the <hi>Mercians,</hi> was trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſly
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:108032:66"/>
put to death by <hi>Quendred, Offa</hi>'s
Wife; hereupon, being Regiſtered for a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr,
he had a Church built and dedicated to
him by <hi>Milſred,</hi> a petty King of this County,
which after the Eſtabliſhment of a Biſhop's
See, it grew to great Wealth and Honour,
and is thought never to have ſuffered any
Misfortune until <hi>Edward the Confeſſer</hi>'s time,
when <hi>Griffith,</hi> Prince of <hi>South Wales,</hi> and
<hi>Algarus</hi> had raiſed a Rebellion againſt King
<hi>Edward,</hi> and led away Captive the Biſhop,
Sacked the City, and burnt the Cathedral;
afterwards the <hi>Normans,</hi> at the Eaſt end of
the Church by the River <hi>Wye,</hi> built a ſtrong
Caſtle, and fortified the City with a Wall,
and by the Trench near the Caſtle, is a very
fine Spring called St. <hi>Ethelbert</hi>'s <hi>Well.</hi> Within
this City are four Pariſh-Churches, and Biſhop
<hi>Reinelin,</hi> in the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the
Firſt, founded the Cathedral which now is,
being a beautiful and magnificent Structure,
adorned with divers ancient Monuments of
Biſhops and Abbors. The City is governed
by a Mayor, (who is annually Sworn upon
<hi>Michaelmas-Day,</hi> 12 Aldermen, a Recorder,
and divers Common-Councel-Men, and by
their Charter have Privileges for particular
Companies and Societies amongſt themſelves,
who have ſeveral diſtinct Halls and Petty-laws
Enacted, for Regulating and Ordering their
Affairs in Trade. It hath three Markets a-Week,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:108032:67"/>
in which there are plenty of Corn,
and all ſorts of Proviſions.</p>
                  <p>About two Miles from this County ſtands
<hi>Rotheram,</hi> as formerly belonging to the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
of <hi>Boddenham,</hi> now in the Poſſeſſion of
the Family of <hi>Van Arker,</hi> and is one of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfulleſt
and ſweeteſt Seats in all the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
having a ſpacious Park before it, the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<hi>Nye</hi> behind it, pleaſant Meadows on the
one ſide, and fruitful Tillage on the other;
and having had ſuch great plenty of Apple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees
belonging to it, as I have been credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
informed by thoſe that then knew it,
That take but one Apple from each Tree, it
would make a Hogſhead of Cyder.</p>
                  <p>Concerning ſome remarkable Things in
this County, <hi>&amp;c. BONE-well</hi> near <hi>Richard</hi>'s
Caſtle, we went to viſit, to take ſome notice
of Nature, who is never more curious than in
her Water-works, preſented us with another
new Rarity; a Well called <hi>Bone-well,</hi> in the
Water whereof are always bubling up ſeveral
little Bones, like Bones of Fiſhes, and altho'
they which be upon the Surface are, with as
great care as can be, taken off, yet others will
immediately ſucceed in their room.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HOPTON's-well</hi> is not far from this, the
Water whereof is found very effectual for
the Curing of ſeveral Maladies which have
ſeized upon Poor, Languiſhing, Decriped
Mortals; it hath likewiſe been obſerved to
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:108032:67"/>
by very good for the reſtoring of Eye-ſight
to the Blind, and is alſo of great uſe in ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening
the Limbs of weak Perſons.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SUTTON WALLS.</hi> Amongſt the
other Varieties we were entertanied with in
this County, there were ſome Remains of
Antiquity, called <hi>Sutton walls:</hi> Near to the
Village of <hi>Marden,</hi> are the Ruins of ſome
antient great Buildings, in all probability,
ſuppoſed to be the Manſion-houſe of <hi>Offa,</hi>
when <hi>Rencheſter</hi> flouriſhed, or, at leaſt, when
<hi>Hereford</hi> was but in its Infancy: This <hi>Offa</hi>
being King of the <hi>Mercians,</hi> having invited
<hi>Ethelhert,</hi> King of the <hi>Eaſt-Angles</hi> into his
Palace under colour and pretence of beſtowing
his Daughter upon him in Marriage; by the
Councel of his ambitious Wife (in hopes to
ſucceed him in his Kingdom,) baſely and
treacherouſly cauſed his Head to be ſtricken
off, by one <hi>Grimbert,</hi> his Servant, and his
Body being buried on the Banks of the
River <hi>Lugg,</hi> was afterwards removed to
<hi>Hereford,</hi> and over it was built a Cathedral
by King <hi>Milfred,</hi> which was ſince dedicated
to St. <hi>Ethelbert.</hi> Having ſufficiently recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
our ſelves with all the pleaſure, paſtimes
and rarities in this County, we began to think
to return towards <hi>London,</hi> and went from
this City to a place called <hi>Roſs,</hi> in this County,
a Town noted for its famous Houſes of
Slates and Stones, as alſo for a great number
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:108032:68"/>
of Blackſmiths, hammering out their living
upon their Anvells, and when we were
paſt that Town we ſoon came into the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines
of <hi>Glouceſterſhire,</hi> of which hereafter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Glouceſterſhire.</head>
                  <p>Being within the Confines of this County,
we found it moſt fertile, watered by the
River <hi>Severn,</hi> and be-ſet with Woods and
thick Groves; 'tis happy in the enjoyment
of all things which are neceſſary for the
Uſe and Service of Man; the very Hedges
and Land are well ſtored with Apples and
Pear-trees, and their fragrant bluſhing Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
invites the wandering Travellers to
refreſh himſelf with their moſt Wholeſome
Juices: And as Concerning this County in
General, the Towns ſtands thick together
in moſt parts of this County, and ſo 'tis
populous; the Houſes numerous, and well
built, the Churches fair and handſome
and ſo 'tis honourable; but that which is
one of the greateſt Bleſſings of all is, the River
<hi>Severn;</hi> there is not any River in all our
Nation for its Channel broader, for a Stream
Swifter, and for Variety of Fiſh better ſtock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
though ſometimes it overflows the
Banks, and when it hath roved a great way
it retires back again, as it were, triumphing
over the Conqueſt of the Land. This River
<hi>Severn,</hi> or <hi>Sabrina,</hi> was ſo called from
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:108032:68"/>
                     <hi>Sabenia,</hi> a fair Lady, concerning whom
there goes this Story; <hi>Loarnie,</hi> the eldeſt
Son of <hi>Brutus,</hi> who came firſt into <hi>Britain,</hi>
took to Wife the Daughter of the Duke of
<hi>Cornwall,</hi> but notwithſtanding this he kept
a very beautiful Miſtriſs, and by her he had
a Daughter, whom he named <hi>Sabenia;</hi>
whereupon he grew ſo enamoured of her,
that after the Death of his Father-in-law, the
Duke of <hi>Cornwall,</hi> he put a way his Lawful-Wife,
and Wedded his Miſtriſs; his Wife was
ſo extreamly netled at this, that ſhe imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately
repaired into <hi>Cornwall,</hi> and made
her Complaint there amongſt her Friends
and Relations, and having gathered a great
Power to revenge her Injury, ſhe fought
with her Husband <hi>Loarine,</hi> and Slew him,
and buried him at <hi>Trynobant,</hi> or <hi>London,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards
executed her Revenge ſtill in the
higheſt Degree: She took the Lady, with
her fair Daughter <hi>Sabenia</hi> too, and drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
them both in this River. The firſt place
of Note we came to in this County was the
City of</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>GLOCESTER.</hi> This City is well ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
and as well inhabited, and of a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
Trade by reaſon of the <hi>Severn,</hi> which
being Navigable, Boats of great Burden
come up to their Key ſide loaded with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
Commodities. 'Tis governed by a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yor
and Aldermen, and is adorned with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:108032:69"/>
fair Churches, amongſt which the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral
is the chief and moſt glorious, Ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
by <hi>Alfred,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>York</hi> and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop
of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> it hath been, by the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
of good Benefactors, much enlarged.
King <hi>Edward</hi> the Second lies here Interred
under a Monument of Alablaſter, and in the
Quire under a wooden painted Tomb lies
<hi>Robert,</hi> the Eldeſt Son of <hi>William the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi>
who was deprived both of his Life and
Kingdom by his younger Brother. Here is
likewiſe to be ſeen the Monument of <hi>Lucius,</hi>
the firſt <hi>Chriſtian King</hi> that ever was in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
about the Year 179. The Pillars of this
Church are of an extraordinary thickneſs,
ſcarce to be parallel'd in any Church in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi>
but that which makes it more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable,
is a place at the Eaſt end of the
Quire called <hi>The Whiſpering-place,</hi> 'tis a Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagone-Arch
in the from of a Semicircle 30
Yards in circuit, and ſo rare a piece of Art,
That if any Perſon ſtands at one end of it,
and whiſpers never ſo ſoftly, he that lays
his Ear to the other end will diſcover diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
the Words he ſpeaks. Then next Town
of Note we went to was</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>TEWKSBURY,</hi> a Market-Town of
good Note, and of a great Trade for Cloth
and Stockins. 'Tis ſituated amongſt the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant
Rivers, <hi>Severn</hi> on the one ſide enricheth
it, on the other ſide <hi>Avon,</hi> and another ſmall
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:108032:69"/>
River which comes from the Eaſt, over each
whereof ſtands Bridges which give entrance
into it. It hath been counted famous for the
great Battel fought here between the Houſe
of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter</hi> utterly Subverted; In
the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, there is
a ſtory of a <hi>Jew</hi> that lived in this Town Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded,
That falling into a Jakes, or Privy,
on the Sabbath, or <hi>Saterday,</hi> by no means,
for Reverence of that Day, ſuffer any Help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-hands
to come and pluck him out of
that unpleaſant Hole, whereupon the then
Earl of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> having ſome Intilligence of
his refractory Sullenneſs, gave a ſtrick Charge
that no one ſhould dare to take him out on
the <hi>Sunday,</hi> for the Reverence of that Day,
and ſo the poor Circumſized-Wrecth periſhed
in that moſt Loathſom Dugeon through his
own folly. This was about the year 1259.
The next place of note we went to was</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CICITER,</hi> which the River <hi>Ornus,</hi> or
<hi>Churne,</hi> Riſing amongſt the Woods near <hi>Corbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi>
is very commodious for Mills. This Place
doth appear to have been of great Antiquity
and Renown, The <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Chronicles ſhew
that this Town was burnt, being ſet on fire
by a Company of Sparrows through an Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
deviſed by on <hi>Gurmund;</hi> certain it is,
that the Inhabitans ſhew a Mount below the
Town which they report this <hi>Gurmund</hi> did
caſt up, they corruptly call it <hi>Gurmund</hi>'s
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:108032:70"/>
Tower. Hear is likewiſe to be ſeen ſome
ruinated Wall of an old Abby; 'tis now beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified
with a very handſome Church having
a high ſpired Steeple, and a Market once a
week. Many other things are very obſerve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,
which will be too tedious to relate. We
went from hence to</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FAIREFORD,</hi> a place well known
for its curious Church-Windows, in which
are moſt rarely pourtrayed in Painted-glaſs,
the whole hiſtory of the Bible. From hence
we went into</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Oxfordſhire.</head>
                  <p>Which being once entered into, we could
not ſufficiently enough admire the pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
of the Soil: There it is that <hi>Cerces</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowes
her Gifts moſt Liberally upon the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours
of Husband-men: There it is that the
Meadowes are garniſhed with variety of
Plants, allure and intice the induſtrious and
ſtudious Herbaliſts into a more ſtrict Inquiry
of Names, Natures and Properties there; 'tis
where the Hills are adorned with ſhady
Woods, and afford moſt delightful Bows to
the waried Students, whilſt the Silver-ſtream'd-Rivers
with their Murmures nimbly courſing
along, do whet their fancies, and ſcrew up
their Intellectuals to the higheſt pitch. The
firſt Town of Note we came to in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
was.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:108032:70"/>
                  <head>Burford.</head>
                  <p>Is a Town of good Note, ſituated, as it
were, on the ſide of a Hill very pleaſantly,
and if we will give Credit to ancient Records,
'tis ſtoried, That <hi>Cuthred,</hi> King of the <hi>Weſt
Saxons,</hi> when he was no longer able to bear
the ſevere Tributes and Exactions of <hi>Ethelbeld,</hi>
King of the <hi>Mercians,</hi> who did moſt cruelly
oppreſs him, and began to ſuck the very
Blood and Marrow of his Subjects, came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the Field againſt him, and in a pitcht
Battle routed him totally, taking from him
his Banners on which was painted a golden
Dragon, and ſo raiſed his Subjects from their
Tributary-Vaſſalage. The next place we
came to was.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>OXFORD,</hi> a Ford for Oxen to paſs over,
as is called by the <hi>Germans, Oxhenfurt.</hi> It
hath a moſt healthy Air, and commodious
ſituation, and is well adorned with private
Structures, as alſo with goodly and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent
Colleges and Halls, and is thought,
by Antiquaries, to have been a place of
publick Study before the learned <hi>Saxon</hi> King
<hi>Alfred</hi>'s time, who very much angmented it
out of his Princely Favour and Love to
Learning and Religion. It boaſts in <hi>Unive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity-College,</hi>
founded, at firſt, by King <hi>Alfred,</hi>
afterwards re-edified by <hi>William,</hi> Arch-Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con
of <hi>Durham,</hi> or, as others write, by <hi>William,</hi>
                     <pb n="108" facs="tcp:108032:71"/>
Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> in the Twelfth Year of
<hi>William the Conqueror,</hi> and of <hi>New-College,</hi>
built by <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Wickham,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi>
and the Magnificence <hi>Chriſt Church,</hi>
erected by Cardinal <hi>Woolſey</hi> in the Reign of
<hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth. This City is adorned
with 22 Colleges, beſides the curious Fab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick
of the Schools, and the admirable
Sructure of the Theatre, built at the ſole
Coſt and Charges of the moſt Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
in God, <hi>Gilbert,</hi> late Lord-Archbiſhop
of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> the famous Library, not much
inferiour to the <hi>Vatican</hi> at <hi>Rome;</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful
Phyſick-Garden, repleniſhed with
divers both of Foreign and Domeſtick Plants,
ſurrounded with a ſtrong ſtone Wall at the
ſole Expence of the Right Honourable <hi>Henry,</hi>
Earl of <hi>Danby,</hi> together with all the Cuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oms,
Privileges, Offices and Dignities, which
are already elegantly ſet forth by the inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious
Author of the <hi>Preſent State of</hi> England:
And as concerning the South ſide of this
County, What can be more pleaſant than
<hi>Thamiſs?</hi> branching it ſelf forth into ſeveral
Veins, gives refreſhment to ſeveral parts of
this County; at laſt, by ſeveral Turnings
and Windings, lodgeth it ſelf again in its
natural Couſe. We went from hence to.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>DORCHESTER.</hi> It ſeems to be a
Town of great Antiquity, and is credibly
reported that this was formerly a Biſhop's ſee,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:108032:71"/>
which was Tranſplanted from this place to
<hi>Lincoln</hi> by <hi>William the Conqueror</hi>'s diſlike, that
the Biſhop's Seat ſtood in ſo ſmall a City,
from which time it began to decline into a
low and mean Condition, and is now only
famous for its venerable Relicts and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ins,
and for the mutable Union of the two
noted Rivers <hi>Tama</hi> aud <hi>Iſis,</hi> which here una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly
embrace each other. From hence
we went to <hi>Hendly,</hi> in this County, of which
it follows.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HENDLY,</hi> which the <hi>Thames,</hi> after it
hath fetch'd a handſome compaſs, enricheth
with its ſilver ſtreams, the Inhabitants here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
being moſt of them Bargemen, and get
good Livelihoods by carrying of Corn and
Wood out of the neighbouring Counties to
<hi>London;</hi> there is now a very large and ſtrong
Timber-bridge over the River, which, they
ſay, was formerly arched, and of Stone,
but whether this be the Bridge that the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi>
went over, when <hi>Caſar</hi> purſued the
<hi>Britains</hi> who fled into theſe Parts, is hard
to determine; however it is very probable
that this was the place. We went from
hence into.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Buckinghamſhire, <hi>or</hi> Bucks.</head>
                  <p>Which might poſſibly be ſo called from
Beech-trees, there being ſuch great plenty
in that County; or likely from a Country in
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:108032:72"/>
                     <hi>Germany</hi> called <hi>Buchonia,</hi> from its great plenty
of thoſe kind of Trees. The County gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erally
is of a plentiful Soil, and paſſing full
of Inhabitants, who chiefly employ them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
in grazing of Cattle. There is ſtore of
Mutton and Beef.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WICKHAM,</hi> or <hi>Weicombe,</hi> ſituated above
a pleaſent Valley, by which runs a-long the
Currant of a ſmall Rivolet, and poſſibly from
this ſituation it might take its Name, for
<hi>Combe,</hi> in the <hi>Saxon</hi> Language, ſignifies a
<hi>Valley,</hi> and <hi>Wick,</hi> any Turning or Winding
of a River or Sea. 'Tis a Town for Large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
and Buildings not much inferiour to any
throughout the Shire, and hath a Mayor and
Aldermen. It is a place well known for the
abundance of Bone-lace that is made here,
which brings good Advantage and Profit to
the Inhabitants. The next Town we arrived
at was.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BEACONSFIELD,</hi> a Town better
known for that it was formerly the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants
by Succeſſion to the Lord <hi>Scudamore,</hi> than
for any thing it contains in it ſelf. We tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
not long here, but went to.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>UXBRIDGE,</hi> formerly called <hi>WOX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BRIDGE,</hi>
a Town built of latter times, and
well ſtored with Inns. We paſt from hence
to ſee ſome part of <hi>Harfordſhire</hi> and <hi>Bedford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi>
which Counties we found very rich in
Corn and Cattle; but in relation to theſe
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:108032:72"/>
Counties, and their renowned Towns of
<hi>Bedford, Dunſtable,</hi> and St. <hi>Albans,</hi> and divers
other Towns, they having been ſo well ſet
forth by others, I ſhall forbear mentioning
them. We went to.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WARE</hi> in <hi>Hartfordſhire,</hi> where we tarried
two Nights. This Town, according to
Writers, was built by <hi>Edward</hi> the Second,
King of the <hi>Weſt Saxons,</hi> in the Year 914.
'Tis wartered by the River <hi>Ley,</hi> and hath a
great Market for all ſorts of Grain; it is po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous,
and well Inhabited by Perſons of
very good Quality, and lying in the great
Road to <hi>London,</hi> is frequented conſtantly by
Perſons of all Degrees; and altho' <hi>Hartford</hi>
be the Eye of the County, 'tis now infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour
to this place; but the moſt remarkable
thing in <hi>Ware</hi> is the <hi>New-River,</hi> or Aqueduct,
conveyed above 20 Miles together in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
Channel from this Place to <hi>Iſlington,</hi>
from whence the Water thereof is diſperſed
in Pipes laid a-lond in the ground for that
purpoſe, into abundance of Streets, Lanes,
Courts and Alleys of this City and Suburbs
of <hi>London;</hi> the great Contrivance whereof
all the Citizens have daily Experience, and
ought to immortalize the Name of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventor
Sir <hi>Hugh Middleton,</hi> who beſtowed
this moſt excellent Gift upon them, and
Conſummated this good Work ſo uſeful and
beneficial to the City at his own proper Coſt
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:108032:73"/>
and Charges. I have not mention'd the
County of Surrey diſtinctly as yet, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
had almoſt forgot it, but I will give
ſome brief relation of it, tho' not in its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Surrey.</head>
                  <p>From the Weſt it boundeth partly upon
<hi>Barkſhire</hi> and <hi>Hantſhire;</hi> from the South upon
<hi>Suſſex;</hi> and from the Eaſt on <hi>Kent;</hi> towards
the North it is watered with the River <hi>Thames,</hi>
and by it divided from <hi>Middleſex.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is a County not very large, yet wealthy
enough, where it beareth upon <hi>Thames,</hi> and
lieth as a plain and champion Country.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FERNHAM,</hi> ſo named of much Fern
growing in that place.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>GUILFORD,</hi> a Market Town well fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented,
and full of fair Innes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>KINGSTONE,</hi> a very good Market
Town for the bigneſs, and well frequented.
It had begining from a little Town more
ancient than it of the ſame name, in which,
when <hi>England</hi> was almoſt ruinated by the
<hi>Daniſh</hi> Wars, <hi>Aethelſtan, Edwin</hi> and <hi>Ethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred</hi>
were crowned Kings upon an open ſtage
in the Market place, whence it was called
<hi>Kingſtone.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SHENE,</hi> ſo called of its ſhining bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
now <hi>Richmond,</hi> wherein the moſt migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
Prince, King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, when
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:108032:73"/>
he had lived ſufficiently both to glory and
nature, died.</p>
                  <p>King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh built it, and gave
it that name of <hi>Richmond,</hi> of the Title he bore,
being Earl of <hi>Richmond,</hi> before he obtain'd the
Crown of <hi>England.</hi> He had ſcarce finiſhed
this new work, when in this place he yeild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
unto Nature, and ended his Life. Here
Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> alſo died.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CROIDON,</hi> there was the Archbiſhop's
Houſe of <hi>Canterbury:</hi> There are Charcoles.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LAMBETH, Canutus,</hi> the Hardy King
of <hi>England,</hi> there amidſt his Cups yeilded up
his vital Breath. It is the Palace of the
Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This County hath in it an hundred and
forty Pariſh Churches.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <argument>
                  <p>I have been both in <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South Wales,</hi>
of which other Pens have already ſet forth, ſo
that I do not intend to deliver any thing to the
Publick that hath been already ſet forth by others,
but only give a ſhort Account of ſeveral things ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
obſervable, not yet ſet forth by any.</p>
               </argument>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:108032:74"/>
               <head>WALES.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Flintſhire.</head>
                  <p>THe Air is healthful, without any Fogs or
Fenny-Vapours, and the People gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
are very Aged and hearty. The Snow
lies here very long upon the Hills; the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
affords great plenty of Cattel, but they
are ſmall; Millſtones are alſo digged up in
theſe Parts, as well as in <hi>Angleſey.</hi> Towards
the River <hi>Dee</hi> the Fields bears, in ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
Barley, in others Wheat, but generally
throughout Rye, with very great encreaſe,
and eſpecially the firſt Year of their break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
up their Land, and afterward two or
three Crops together of Oats.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Holy-Well, <hi>or St.</hi> Winifrid's-Well.</head>
                  <p>This County is moſt remarkable for a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
Village called <hi>Holy-Well,</hi> where is the
Well of St. <hi>Winifrid,</hi> ſo famous for the ſtrange
Cures which have been wrought by the
Vertue of it, as it is ſuppoſed; the Water
hereof is extream cold, and hath likewiſe
a very great Stream that flows from it, which
is preſently able to drive a Mill; the Stones
which are at bottom being of a ſanguine co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour,
are believed to receive that colour
from the Drops of Blood which trickled
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:108032:74"/>
down from her Body, when ſhe was here
beheaded, by the bloody Tyrant that would
have raviſhed her, and the Moſs which grows
upon the ſides, and bears a very fragrant
Smell, is averred to have been the product
of her Hair, though I find, by ſome we
brought away with us, that in proceſs of
time it loſeth all its ſweetneſs. Over the
Well ſtands a Chappel dedicated to her built
of Stone, after a curious manner, to which,
formerly, was much reſorting by Pilgrims,
who came hither out of blind Devotion, and
the generality of the Commonalty herea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts
do believe, That this Martyred-Virgin,
and the great Miracle that was wrought by
St. <hi>Benno,</hi> who reſtored her to life again, as
they ſay, by claping on her head immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately,
after it was cut off, upon her Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
which Relation thoſe Inhabitants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts
do verily believe to be true. So
having made ſome ſmall ſtay here, in which
time we converſed with the <hi>Welſhmen,</hi> and
gathered up a true Account of this County,
which was as follows.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Radnorſhire.</head>
                  <p>In the Eaſt and South parts thereof 'tis
more fruitful than the reſt, but is uneven
and rough with Mountains, yet it is well
ſtored with Woods, watered with running
Rivers, and, in ſome places, with ſtanding
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:108032:75"/>
Pools; the Air is very cold and ſharp, becauſe
the Snow lying long unmelted under the
ſhady Hills and hanging Rocks, whereof there
are many, and upon the Borders of it which
lies next to <hi>Herefordſhire,</hi> runs a-long a famous
Ditch, which <hi>Offa,</hi> King of the <hi>Mercians,</hi> with
great toil and labour cauſed to be caſt up from
<hi>Dee</hi> mouth to <hi>Wye</hi> mouth, for the ſpace of
90 Miles, to ſeparate the <hi>Britains</hi> from the
<hi>Engliſh:</hi> Several other things there are very
obſervable, which are too tedious to relate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Brecknockſhire.</head>
                  <p>Lies beneath <hi>Radnorſhire.</hi> It is thick with
Hills, and fruitful in the Valleys.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MOUNTH-DENNY,</hi> three Miles from
<hi>Brecknock,</hi> is a Hill ſo called, that hath its top
above the Clouds, and if a Cloak, or Hat, or
the like, be thrown from the top of it, it will
never fall, but be blown up again, nor will
any thing deſcend but Stones or Mettals, or
things as heavy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LYNSARATHAN-MERE,</hi> two Miles
Eaſt from the ſame place is a Mere called
<hi>Lynſarathan,</hi> which (as the People dwelling
there ſay) was once a City, but the whole
City was ſwallowed up by an Earthquake,
and this Water, or Lake, ſucceeded in the
place; they ſay likewiſe, That at the end of
Winter, when aftr a long Froſt, and the Ice
of this Lake breaks, it makes a fearful noiſe
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:108032:75"/>
like Thunder, poſſibly becauſe the Lake is
encompaſſed with high ſteep Hills which pen
in the ſound, and multiply it; or elſe the
ground may be hollow underneath, or near
the Lake.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LIVENNY-River.</hi> Through this Lake
runs a River called <hi>Livenny,</hi> without mixture
of its Waters, as may be perceived both by
the Colour of the Water, and alſo by the
Quantity of it, becauſe it is no greater after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,
than when it entered the Lake.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CADIER-ARTHUR,</hi> or <hi>Arthur's Chair,</hi>
a Hill ſo called on the South ſide of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;
from the Tops reſembling the form of
a Chair, proportionate to the Demenſions of
that great and mighty Perſon; upon the top
whereof riſeth a Spring as deep as a Well,
four ſquare, having no Streams iſſuing from
it, and yet there are plenty of Trouts to be
found therein.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Glamorganſhire.</head>
                  <p>Hath a temperate Air, and is generally
the moſt pleaſant part of all <hi>South Wales.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MINYD-MORGAN Hill.</hi> On the top
of a certain Hill ſo called, is a Monument
with a ſtrange Character, which the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants
thereabouts ſay, if any Man read the
ſame, he ſhall die ſhortly after.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="118" facs="tcp:108032:76"/>
                     <label>The Springs by <hi>Newton.</hi>
                     </label>
Upon the River <hi>Ogmore,</hi> and near to <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi>
in a ſandy Plain, is a Well, the Water
whereof is not very clear, in which, at full
Sea in Summer-time, can hardly any Water
be took up, but at the Ebb it bubbleth up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main;
in Summer-time, I ſay, for in the
Winter the Ebbing and Flowing is nothing
near ſo evident, becauſe of the Veins of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
coming in by Showers, or otherwiſe;
beſides it is obſerved, this Spring never riſeth
up to the top brink, or over-floweth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ABERBARRY Cave.</hi> There is in this
Shire a Cave ſo called, under the bottom of
a Hill, and on the top of it a gaping Chinck,
where, many times, is heard as it were a
Muſical-noiſe, and ſometimes other very
ſtrange Noiſes, which is very obſervable for
all Travellers to take notice of.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LANDAFF,</hi> a ſmall Town, but of good
Repute in that it is a Biſhop's See, and ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
with a Catheral-Church.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Carmardenſhire.</head>
                  <p>A moſt hilly Country, yet it hath a whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
Air, and though the Soil be not very
fruitful in Corn, 'tis well ſtored with Cattel,
and in ſome places yeilds very good Pit-coal
for Fuel: On the South ſide, the Ocean hath
with ſo great violence encroached upon the
Land, that the Country ſeems to have ſhrunk
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:108032:76"/>
back in a fright, and withdrawn it ſelf more
inwardly for ſecurity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>The Cave and Well near <hi>Carreg-Caſtle.</hi>
                     </label>
Near <hi>Carreg-Caſtle</hi> are many Undermines,
or Caves of very great wideneſs within the
ground, now covered all over with Green-ſword
and Turf, wherein, it is probable, the
Multitude unable to bear Arms, when the
<hi>Normans</hi> made their firſt Incurſion into theſe
Parts, hid themſelves during the heat of the
War: There is alſo a Well that, like the Sea,
Ebbs and Flows twice in 24 hours.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Pembrokeſhire.</head>
                  <p>Hath a good temperate Air, conſidering
it lies ſo near to <hi>Ireland;</hi> the Inhabitants are
many of them <hi>Dutchmen,</hi> but by their Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
and Language they are much like the
<hi>Engliſh,</hi> that upon this Account this County
is called <hi>Little</hi> England <hi>beyond</hi> Wales.</p>
                  <p>In the Rocks of this Shire there breeds a
rare kind of Falcon which is thus deſcribed,
The Head is flat and low, the Feathers laid
in rows, the Legs pale and wan, the Claws
ſlender and wide ſpread, hooked round.</p>
                  <p>About 300 Years a-go, it was reported,
That for five Generations, the Father of the
Family in the Earldom of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> their
Name was <hi>Haſtings,</hi> never ſaw his Son.</p>
                  <p>At the time when <hi>Henry</hi> the Second made
his Abode in <hi>Ireland,</hi> there were extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:108032:77"/>
violent and laſting Storms of Wind and
Weather, ſo that the Sandy-ſhoar on the
Coaſts of this Shire were laid bare to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
hard ground, which had lain hid for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Ages, and by farther ſearch the People
found great Truncks of Trees, which when
they were digged up were apparently lop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped,
ſo that they might ſee the Stroaks of
the Ax upon them, as if they had been gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
not long before; the Earth looked very
black, and the Wood of theſe Truncks alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
like Ebony, as the Inhabitants infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
us. At the firſt diſcovery made of theſe
Storms, the Trees, we ſpake of, lay ſo thick,
that the whole Shoar ſeemed nothing but a
lopped Grove; from whence may be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
That the Sea hath over-flowed much
Land on this Coaſt, as it had upon the Shoar
of many Countries bordering upon the Sea.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>The <hi>Salmon's-Leap</hi> at <hi>Kilgarran.</hi>
                     </label>
About <hi>Kilgarran</hi> are abundance of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
taken, and there is a place called <hi>The
Salmon's-Leap,</hi> as there is alſo in other Rivers,
for this reaſon, The Salmon coveteth to get
into freſh-water Rivers to Spawn, and when
he comes from places where the Water falls
down-right almoſt perpendicular, as ſome ſuch
like Places there be, he uſeth this Policy, He
bends himſelf backwards, and takes his Tail
in his Mouth, and with all his force unloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
his Circle, on a ſudden with a ſmart
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:108032:77"/>
Let-go, he mounteth up before the Fall of
the Stream; and therefore theſe down-right
Falls are called <hi>The Salmon's Leaps.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>St. DAVIDS</hi> is in this County, formerly
an Arch-Biſhop's See: There is a Cathedral,
erected in the Time of King <hi>John,</hi> and
near unto it ſtands the Biſhop's Palace, and
ſeveral other Houſes belonging the Biſhop's
See, all encloſed round with a Wall, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
they call it <hi>The Cloſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Cardiganſhire.</head>
                  <p>Being a hilly Mountainous County like the
reſt of <hi>Wales,</hi> was not formerly planted or
garniſhed with Towns, but little Cottages, as
may be gathered by that Speech of their
Prince, who being taken Priſoner and carried
to <hi>Rome,</hi> after he had throughly viewed the
Magnificence of that City, <hi>What mean you,</hi>
ſaid he, <hi>when you have ſuch ſtately Buildings of
your own, to covet our poor ſmall Cottages?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Many other things here might be mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
in relation to this County, but I muſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
them by reaſon I have not room enough.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Montgomeryſhire.</head>
                  <p>In this Shire there is nothing more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable
than its excellent Breed of Horſes,
which (as I have been informed) are of moſt
excellent Shapes and ſtrong Limbs, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable
for Stoutneſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:108032:78"/>
                     <label>The Hill <hi>Plim-limmon.</hi>
                     </label>
It raiſeth it ſelf up to a wonderful height,
and on that part where it boundeth on part
of this Shire it poureth forth the <hi>Severn,</hi> the
greateſt River in <hi>Britain</hi> next the <hi>Thames,</hi> as
likewiſe in the other parts of it riſeth the
River <hi>Wye,</hi> and the River <hi>Rideal.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>The Hill <hi>Cerdon.</hi>
                     </label>
Upon <hi>Cerdon</hi> Hill are placed certain Stones,
in a round Circle like a Coronet, in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability,
to commemorate ſome notable Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory:
In this County are ſeveral old Caſtles,
and other things very obſervable.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Merionethſhire.</head>
                  <p>The Air may be wholſome, but the Soil
is very barren, for 'tis exceeding full of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
Hills, being the moſt mountainous place
in <hi>Wales</hi> (except <hi>Caernarvonſhire)</hi> upon which
account it is ſubject to many and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
great Winds.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>The Pool near <hi>Bala.</hi>
                     </label>
Near <hi>Bala</hi> is a great Pool of Water that
drowns, at leaſt, 200 Acres of ground, whoſe
Nature is ſuch, as they ſay, That the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
Floods cannot make this Pool ſwell big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
though never ſo great; but if the Air
be troubled with violent Tempeſts of Wind,
it riſeth above the Banks: The River <hi>Dee</hi> runs
into with a ſwift Stream, and glides through
it without mixture of Water, for in this Pool
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:108032:78"/>
is bred a ſort of Fiſh which are never ſeen in
<hi>Dee,</hi> and in <hi>Dee</hi> River, Salmons are taken
which are never found in this Pool. Upon
the Sea-Coaſts of this County, great ſtore of
Herrings are taken at time of Year, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the Weſt ſide of it the Sea beats ſo ſore
and hard, that it is thought it has carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
part of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Caernarvonſhire.</head>
                  <p>In this County the Air is ſharp and pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing,
and in it are the higheſt Hills in <hi>Wales,</hi>
on ſome of which the Snow lies long, and
on others all the Year long, hard cruſhed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.
'Tis affirmed likewiſe, That on the
high Hills of this Shire are two Meres, one
of which produceth Fiſh that have but one
Eye, and the other a floating Iſland: I do
not verifie the truth of this, becauſe I think
it meer Fables.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SNOWDEN-HILLS,</hi> altho' they have
always Snow lying upon them, yet they are
exceeding rank with Graſs, inſomuch that
they are become a Proverb amongſt the
<hi>Welſhmen,</hi> That thoſe Mountains will yeild
ſufficient Paſture for all the Cattle in <hi>Wales,</hi>
if they were put upon them together; and 'tis
certain that there are Pools and ſtanding Waters
upon the top of theſe Mountains, and they
are ſo coated with a ſnowy Cruſt that lies
on them, That if a Man does but lightly ſet
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:108032:79"/>
his foot any where upon the top of them,
he ſhall perceive the Earth to ſtir for ſeveral
Foot from him, which probably might occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
the Story of the floating Iſland before
mentioned.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PEN-NEANMOUR, The great ſtony
Head,</hi> a Hill ſo called in this County. It is
an exceeding high and ſteep Rock, which
hanging over the Sea when it is Flood, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordeth
a very narrow Way for Paſſengers,
having on the one ſide huge Stones over
your heads, as if they were ready to fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
you, and on the other ſide the raging
Ocean lying off a wonderful ſteep depth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
it; but after a Man hath paſſed over this,
together with <hi>Pen-mean-Lythan, The leſs ſtory
Head,</hi> he ſhall come to an open broad Plain
that reacheth as far as the <hi>Conway,</hi> in which
are bred a ſort of Shell-fiſh, which being
Conceived of an Heavenly-dew, as is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectured,
bring forth Pearl.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BANGOR-PENCHOR,</hi> ſo called, is
alſo in is this County, a Biſhop's See; the
Church was Conſecrated to <hi>Daniel,</hi> Biſhop
hereof, but that which is now ſtanding is but
a mean Structure; for <hi>Owen Glender,</hi> that
notorious Rebel, who deſigned to deſtroy
all the Cities in <hi>Wales,</hi> ſet it on fire, becauſe
the Inhabitants of this Place choſe rather to
ſide with the King of <hi>England</hi> than with him:
Hereupon the ancient Church being defaced,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:108032:79"/>
                     <hi>Henry Denry,</hi> Biſhop hereof, did afterwards,
repair it, about the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth,
as we were credibly inform'd by
the Inhabitants,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Angleſey.</head>
                  <p>In this Iſland (which is computed to be
in compaſs 85 Miles, or thereabout) are
frequently found and digged up in the lower
Grounds, Bodies of huge Trees with their
Roots, and Firr-tres of a wonderful bigneſs
and length, which Trees, ſome believe,
were cut down by the <hi>Romans,</hi> as the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants
do ſay, That when the <hi>Romans</hi> had
Conquered this Iſland, they cauſed all the
Woods to be cut down and deſtroyed. This
Iſland was in time paſt, full of Woods and
Timber but inſtead thereof now it yeildeth
plenty of Corn, Sheep and Cattle. The Air
is indifferently healthful in moſt parts of it;
here are likewiſe great ſtore of Mill-ſtones
and Grind-ſtones, and in ſome places a ſort
of Earth of which they make Allum and
Copperas; alſo it yeilds ſuch plenty of
Wheat, that it ſeems to be deſerving of the
Title of, <hi>The Mother of</hi> Wales.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:108032:80"/>
                  <head>Denbighſhire.</head>
                  <p>The Air is cold, but very wholſome; the
Snow lies long on the Hills, being a hilly
Country, the high Hills reſembling the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlements
of Walls.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MOILENLLY-hill</hi> is the higheſt Hill in
this Shire, having a Spring of very clear Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
upon the top of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WREXHAM</hi> in this County is about 16
Miles from <hi>Holy-well,</hi> and is much admired
for its Church-ſteeple, being a very curious
Fabrick, contrived according to the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act
Draught and Models of Architecture,
no where to be parallel'd in thoſe parts for
Workmanſhip, of which taking ſome ſmall
view, we paſſed into <hi>Shropſhire,</hi> of which I
have already made mention.</p>
                  <p>I having already given a Relation of moſt
of the Shires in <hi>Wales,</hi> and omitted <hi>Monmouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi>
of which I could not in honour to the
County paſs by without a Viſit, ſo ſtaying
at <hi>Hereford</hi> ſome days, we ſet a-part ſome
time to go ſee <hi>Monmouth,</hi> of which it follows.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Monmouth.</head>
                  <p>We found the Ways near <hi>Monmouth</hi> hard
and rugged, and that Town to be enviro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
with Hills on all Sides, the Ruins of its
Walls and Caſtle argue its Antiquity. It
hath a fair Church and Market-place, with
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:108032:80"/>
a Hall for the Aſſizes and Seſſions. 'Tis go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned
by a Mayor, Recorder and Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
and the Inhabitants do generally ſpeak
both the <hi>Welſh</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue: They
told us there, of great Immunities and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges
granted to them by the Houſe of
<hi>Lancaſter,</hi> but for no other thing is it ſo
much renowned, as that it was firſt the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
place, and gave Breath to <hi>Henry</hi> the
Fifth, that Scourge of the <hi>French,</hi> and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Pillar of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, who Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered
<hi>Charles</hi> the Sixth King of <hi>France,</hi> and
all his Army, and made him ſurrender up
his Crown unto him, and Acknowledge
him the triumphant Conqueror: Here we
were entertained with no other Objects but
what the ſtony Rocks, the dangerous Clifts,
the towring Mountains, and craggy Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pices
did afford us, being now and then co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered
with Flocks of Sheep, and Herds of
Goats; the Inhabitants told us, That upon
the <hi>Black Mountain</hi> there, as they call it, or
thereabouts, are ſome Hills ſo high, whoſe
Tops are ſo ſharp, that two Perſons may
ſtand upon two different Points thereof and
diſcourſe with one another, and underſtand
each other very well, although they muſt
be forced to go ſome Miles before they can
embrace each other, but the truth of this I
will not averr; certain I am<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
of them of ſo unconceivable a height,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:108032:81"/>
and ſo ſteep an Aſcent, that they ſeem, as it
were, Nature's Stair-caſes, by which we may
climb up to ſome higher Region, and have
Entercourſe with the Inhabitants of the
Moon.</p>
                  <p>Thus have I given a true and faithful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
of my Travels over <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi>
but cannot much commend the latter for
their Cookery, yet for their Linen it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different
ſweet and clean: I could have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
ſeveral other things, but what has
been ſpoke of is moſt material.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:108032:81"/>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
