<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ill effects of animosities among Protestants in England detected and the necessity of love unto, and confidence in one another, in order to withstand the designs of their common enemies, laid open and enforced.</title>
            <author>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-03">2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30357</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5802</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11786</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11998183</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11998183</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52139</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A30357)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52139)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 558:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ill effects of animosities among Protestants in England detected and the necessity of love unto, and confidence in one another, in order to withstand the designs of their common enemies, laid open and enforced.</title>
                  <author>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
               <term>Dissenters --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-10</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-11</date>
            <label>Rina Kor</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-11</date>
            <label>Rina Kor</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-12</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52139:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52139:1"/>
            <p>THE ILL
Effects of Animosities
AMONG
PROTESTANTS
IN
ENGLAND
DETECTED:
AND
The necessity of Love unto, and Confidence in one
another, in order to withstand the Designs of their
Common Enemies, laid open and enforced.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Every Kingdom divided against it self, is brought to desolation; and every
city or house divided against it self, shall not stand.</q> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. xii.</hi> 25.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Dum pugnant singuli, universi vincuntur.</q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Tacit.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:52139:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:52139:2"/>
            <p>IT is long since the Court of <hi>England,</hi> under the Authority of the late King and his
Brother, was embarked in a design of subverting the Protestant Religion, and of
introducing and establishing <hi>Popery.</hi> For the two Royal Brothers being in the time
of their Exile seduced by the Caresles and importunities of their Mother, allured by the
promises and favours of Popish Princes, and being wheedled by the Crafts and Arts of
Priests and Jesuits, who are cunning to deceive, and knew how to prevail upon persons,
that were but weakly established in the Doctrine, and wholly strangers to the practice
and power of the Religion they were tempted from; they not only abjured the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
Religion, and became reconciled to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but by their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
and the influence which they had over those that depended upon them both for
present subsistence and future hopes, they drew many that accompanied them in their
Banishment, to renounce the Doctrine, Worship, and Communion of the Church of
<hi>England,</hi> though in the War between <hi>Charles</hi> I. and the Parliament, they had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
to fight for them in equal conjunction with the Prerogatives of the Crown.
So that upon the Restoration in the year 1660. they were not only moulded and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
themselves for promoting the desires of the Pope and his Emissaries, but they
were furnished with a stock of Gentlemen out of whom they might have a supply of
Instruments both in Parliament and elsewhere, to cooperate with, and under them, in
the methods that should be judged most proper and subservient to the extirpation of
Protestancy, and the bringing the Nation again into a servitude to the Triple Crown.
And besides the Obligations, that the Principles of the Religion to which they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted,
laid them under for eradicating the Established Doctrine and Worship, they
had bound themselves unto it, by all the promises and Oaths, which persons are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
of having proscribed unto and exacted of them.</p>
            <p>Nor can any Now disbelieve his late Majesties having lived and died a Papist, who
hath either heard what he both said and did, when under the prospect of approaching
death, and past hope of Acting a Part any longer on the present Stage, or who have
seen and read the two Papers left in his Closet, which have been since published to the
World, and attested for Authentick by the present King. And had we been so just to
our selves, as to have examined the whole course of his Reign, both in his Alliances
abroad, and his most important Counsels and Actions at home, or had we hearkned
to the reports of those who knew him at <hi>Collen</hi> and in <hi>Flanders,</hi> we had been long
ago convinced of what Religion he was. Nor were his many repeated protestations of
his Zeal for Protestancy, but in order to delude the Nation, till insensibly as to us,
and with safety to himself, he had overturned the Religion which he pretended to own,
and had introduced that which he inveighed against. And while with the highest as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>severations
he disclaimed the being what he really was, and with most sacred and tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendous
Oaths professed the being what he was not, his Religion might in the mean
time have been traced through all the signal occurrences of his Government, and have
been discerned written in Capital Letters, through all the material affairs wherein he
was engaged from the day he ascended the Throne, till the hour he left the World.
His entring into two Wars against the <hi>Dutch,</hi> without any provocation on their part,
or ground on his, save their being a Protestant State; his being not only conscious un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,
but enterposing his commands, as well as encouragements, for the burning of
<hi>London;</hi> his concurrence in all the parts of the Popish Plot, except that which the
Jesuits, with a few others, were involved in against himself; his stifling that Conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy,
and delivering the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks from the dangers into which it had cast
them; his being the Author of so many forged Plots, which he caused to be charged
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52139:3"/>
upon Protestants; his constant Confederacies with <hi>France,</hi> to the dissobliging his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
the betraying of <hi>Europe,</hi> the neglect of the Reformed in that Kingdom, and
the encouraging the design carried on against them for their extirpation; his entail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the Duke of <hi>York</hi> upon the Nation, contrary to the desires and endeavours of
three several Parliaments, and that not out of love to his Person, but affection to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,
which he knew that Gentleman would introduce and establish: all these, besides
many other things which might be named, were sufficient evidences of the late Kings
Religion, and of the design he was ingaged in for the Subversion of ours. So that it
would fill a sober person with amazement, to think that after all this there should be
so many sincere Protestants and true <hi>Englishmen,</hi> who not only believed the late King
to be of the Reformed Religion, but with an insatiableness thirsted after the blood of
those that durst otherwise represent him. And had it not been for his receiving Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution
and Extreme Unction from a Popish Priest at his death, and for what he left
in Writing in the two Papers found in his <hi>Strong Box,</hi> he would have still passed for a
Prince who had lived and died a Cordial and Zealous Protestant, and whosoever had
muttered any thing to the contrary, would have been branded for a Villian and an
execrable person. But with what a scent and odour must it recommend his memory to
them, to consider his having not only lived and died in the Communion of the Church
of <hi>Rome,</hi> in contradiction to all his publick Speeches, solemn Declarations and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est
Asserverations to his people in Parliament, but his participating from time to time
of the Sacrament, as Administred in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> while in the interim he
had Abjured our Religion, stood reconciled to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and had obliged
himself by most sacred Vows and was endeavouring by all the Frauds and Arts imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
to subvert the Established Doctrine and Worship, and set up Heresie and Idolatry
in their room. And it must needs give them an abhorrent Idea and Character of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,
and a loathsom representation of those trusted with the Conduct and Guidance
of the Consciences of Men in the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, that they should not only
Dispence with, and indulge such Crimes and Villanies, but proclaim them sanctified
and meritorious from the end which they are calculated for, and levelled at.</p>
            <p>And for his dear Brother, and renowned Successor, who now possesseth the Throne,
I suppose his most partial Admirers, who took him for a Prince, not only merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
in his Temper, and imbued with all gracious inclinations to our Laws, and the
Rights of the Subject, but for one Orthodox in his Religion, and who would prove
a Zealous Defender of the Doctrine, Worship, and Discipline of the Church as Esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished
by Law; are by this time both undeceived, and filled with resentments for
his having abused their credulity, deceived their exspectations, and reproached all
their gloryings and boastings of him. For as it would be now the greatest affront
they could put upon the King, to question his being of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion,
or to detract from his Zeal for the introduction of Popery, notwithstanding his own
antecedent protestations, as well as the many Statutes in force for the preservation
of the Reformed Religion; so I must take the liberty to tell them, that his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postacy
is not of so late a Date, as the World is made commonly to believe.
For though it was many years concealed, and the contrary pretended and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled;
yet it is most certain that he Abjured the Protestant Religion, soon
after the Exilement of the Royal Family, and was reconciled to the <hi>Romish</hi> Church
at St. <hi>Germains</hi> in <hi>France.</hi> Nor were several of the then suffering Bishops and
Clergy ignorant of this, though they had neither the Integrity nor Courage to give
the Nation and Church warning of it. And within these five years there was in
the custody of a very worthy and honest Gentleman, a Letter written to the late
Bishop of D<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>by a Dr. of Divinity, then attending upon the Royal Brothers, wherein
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52139:3"/>
the Apostacy of the then<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Duke of <hi>York</hi> to the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> is particularly related,
and an account given how much the Duchess of <hi>Tremoville</hi> (who without being
her self observed) had heard the Queen Mother glorying of it, bewailed it as a
dishonor to the Royal Family, and as that which might prove of pernicious conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
to the Protestant Interest. But tho the old Queen privately rejoiced and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed
in it, yet she knew too well what disadvantage it might be both to her Son,
and to the Papal Cause in <hi>Great Britain,</hi> to have it at that season communicated and
divulged. Thereupon it remained a Secret for many years, and by vertue of a Dispensa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
he sometimes joyned in all Ordinances with those of the Protestant Communion.
But for allthe art, hypocrisie and sacrilege, by which it was endeavoured to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed,
it might have been easily discerned, as manifesting it self in the whole course
of his Actions. And at last his own zeal, the importunity of the Priests, and the
cunning of the late King, prevailing over Reasons of State, he withdrew from all
Acts of Fellowship with the Church of <hi>England.</hi> But neither that, nor his refusing
the <hi>Test</hi> enjoyned by <hi>Law</hi> for distinguishing Papists from Protestants, tho thereupon
he was forced both to resign his Office of Lord High Admiral, and to stand exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
from the House of Lords; nor his declining the Oath which the Laws of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
for the securing a Protestant Governor, enjoyn to be taken by the High Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioner;
nor yet so many Parliaments having endeavoured to get him excluded
from Succession to the Crown, upon the account of having revolted to the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi>
and thereby become dangerous to the established Religion, could make impression
upon a willfully deluded and obstinate sort of Protestants, but in defiance of all
means of Conviction, they would persuade themselves, that he was still a zealot for
our Religion, and a grand Patriot of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Nor could any thing
undeceive them, till upon his Brothers death he had openly declared himself a <hi>Roman</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick,
and afterwards in the fumes and raptures of his victory over the late Duke of
<hi>Monmouth,</hi> had discovered and proclaimed his intentions of overthrowing both our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
and our Laws. Yea, so closely had some sealed up their Eyes against all Beams of
Light, and hardened themselves against all evidences from Reason and Fact, that had
it pleased the Almighty God to have prospered the Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s Arms in the
Summer 85. the present King would have gone off the State, with the reputation
among them of a Prince tender of the Laws of the Kingdom, and who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing
his own being a Papist, would have preserved the Reformed Religion, and
have maintained the Church of <hi>England</hi> in all her Grandeur and Rights. And tho
his whole life had been but one continued Conspiracy against our Civil Liberties and
Privileges, he had left the Throne with the Character and under the Esteem of a
Gentleman, that in the whole course of his Government would have regulated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
by the Rules of the Constitution, and the Statutes of the Realm.</p>
            <p>Now among all the Methods fallen upon by the Royal Brothers, for the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining
and subverting our Religion and Laws, there is none that they have pursued
with more ardor, and wherein they have been more succesful to the compassing of
their designs, than in their dividing Protestants, and alienating their Affections,
and imbittering their Minds from and against one another. And had not this lain
under their prospect, and the means of effecting it appeared easie, they might have
been Papists themselves, while in the mean time they had been dispensed with to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test
and swear their being of the Reformed Religion, and they might have envied
our Liberties, and bewailed their Restriction from Arbitrary and Despotical
Power; but they never durst have entertained a thought of subverting the established
Religion, or of altering the Civil Government, nor would they ever have had the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
to have attempted the introducing and erecting Popery and Tyranny in their room.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52139:4"/>
And whosoever should have put them upon reducing the Nation to the Church of
<hi>Rome,</hi> or upon rendring the Monarchy unlimited and iudependent on the Law, would
have been thought to have laid a snare for exposing the Papists to greater severities,
than they were obnoxious unto before, and to have projected the robbing the Crown
of the Prerogatives which belong unto it by the Rules of the Constitution, and to
which it was so lately restored. And the despair of succeeding, would have rendred
the Royal Brothers deaf to all importunities from <hi>Romish</hi> Emissaries, and Court Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
Neither the promises and Oaths which they had made and taken beyond Sea
to introduce Popery, nor their ambition to advance themselves beyond the restraint of
Laws, and the Controll of Parliaments, would have prevailed upon them to have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred
the hazards and difficulties, which in case of the Union of <hi>English</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants,
must have attended and ensued upon attempts and endeavours of the one kind
and of the other. Or should their beloved Popery, and their own be biggottedness in the
<hi>Romish</hi> Superstition, have so far transported them beyond the bounds of wisdom and
discretion, as to have appeared possessed with an intention of Subverting the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant
Religion, and of enslaving the Nation to the Superstition and Idolatry of <hi>Rome,</hi>
they would have been made soon to understand. That the Laws which make it Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
to own the jurisdiction of the Pope, or to seduce the meanest subject to the
Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> were not enacted in vain, and that those as well as many more made
for the security of the Protestant Religion, and to prevent the growth and introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of Popery, were not to be dallied and plaid withal. Or should they have been so
far infatuated and abandoned of all understanding, as out of a foolish and haughty
affectation of being Absolute, to have attempted the alteration of the Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
they would have been immediately and unanimously told, that the people have
the same Right to their Liberties, that the King hath to the Prerogatives of the Crown.
And if they would not have been contented with what belongs unto the Prince by
the Common and Statute Laws of the Realm, but had invaded the Priviledges re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served
unto the Subject: they would have been made to know, that they might not
only be withstood in what they strove to Usurp contrary to <hi>Magna Charta, Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of Right,</hi> and other Laws of the Kingdom, but that thereby they forfeited, and
might be disseized of what either appertained unto the Crown by fundamental A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greements,
or hath been since settled upon the Monarch by Statute Laws. Nor could
any thing have emboldned his late Majesty and the present King, to enterprises of the
one kind or the other, but the prospect of begetting a misunderstanding, jealousie,
and rancour among Protestants, and thereby both of making them instrumental to
the ruin of one another, and contributary to the loss of <hi>English</hi> Liberty and the
Reformed Religion, which they equally value and esteem, and to the setting up
Popery and Tyranny, which the one detesteth and abhorreth no less than the
other.</p>
            <p>Though all <hi>English</hi> Protestants have ever been at an accord in all the Essentials
and Vitals of Religion, yet from the very beginning of the Reformation, there have
been differences among them concerning Ecclesiastical Government and Discipline,
and about Forms, Rites, and Ceremonies of Worship. And had they consulted ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
their Duty to God, or the common interest of Religion, they might have
found ways either for removing the occasions of them, or they ought to have lived
together as Brethren, notwithstanding the differences which were among them in
those things. But how much wiser are the Children of this World, than those of the
Kingdom of God and of Jesus Christ. For though the differences amon the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists
do far exceed ours, both in their number and in the importancy of those things
wherein they disagree, yet they do mutually tolerate and bear with one another. The
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52139:4"/>
matters wherein they differ, are neither made the Terms of their Church Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
nor the grounds of mutual Excommunications and Persecutions.</p>
            <p>But alas! one party among us hath been always endeavouring to cut or stretch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
to their own size, and have made those things which themselves stile indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,
both the Qualifications for admission to the Pastoral Office, and the conditions
of Fellowship in the Ordinances of the Gospel. Nor is it to be expressed, what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages
were hereby administred all along to the Common Enemy, and what Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
Peaceable and Orthodox Christians were exposed unto from their peevish and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry
Brethren. And tho these things, with the heats begotten among all, and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities
undergone by one side, were not the cause of that funestous War betwixt
<hi>Charles</hi> the First, and the Parliament, yet they were an occasion of diverting thousands
from the side which the persecuting Church Men espoused, and of engaging them in
the behalf of the two Houses, in the Quarrel which they begun and carried on against
that Prince, for Defence of the Civil Liberties, Privileges, and Rights of the
People. But some of the Mitred Clergy were so far from being made wise by their
own and the Nations Sufferings, as upon their Restoration to hearken to moderate
Counsels, and to decline their former Rigors and Severities, that they became the
Tools and Instruments of the Court, not only far reviving, but for heightning and
enflaming all the Differences, which had formerly been among English Protestants.
For the Royal Brothers finding nothing more adapted and subservient than this, to
their design of altering the Government, and subverting Religion, they animated
those waspish and impolitick Ecclesiasticks, not only to pursue the Restoration of
all those things which had given rise and occasion to former Dissentions and Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
but to lay new snares for alienating many persons of unspotted lives and tender
consciences from the Church, and of rendring them obnoxious to suffer in their
Names, Persons, and Estates. And what a satisfaction was it to the late King and his
Brother, to find the old Episcopal Clergy prepared through principles of revenge, as
well as from love of domination, ambition, and covetousness to fall in with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign
not only of increasing Divisions among Protestants, both by making the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions
of entring upon the Pastoral Function narrower and for screwing conformity
with the Church in her Forms and Ceremonies of Worship, into Tests for admis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
to Magistracy and Civil Trusts, but of obtaining severer Laws against Dissenters,
whereby the penalties to which they foresaw that people would become liable, were
rendered greater than they had been before, and their Sufferings made more merciless,
inhuman and barbarous.</p>
            <p>For tho his late Majesty had by a Declaration dated at <hi>Breda,</hi> promised Indulgence
to all Protestants that would live peaceably under the Civil Government; yet it was
never in his thoughts to perform it, and the previous obligations which he was under
to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> had a vertue to supercede and cancel his Engagements to
English Hereticks. And all he intended by that Declaration was only to wheedle and
Iull those into a tameness of admitting his Return into his Dominions, whom a
jealousie of being afterwards persecuted for their Consciences, might have awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened
to withstand and dispute it. And to give him his due, he never judged
himself longer bound to the observation of Promises and Oaths made to his People,
than until without hazard to his Person and Government he could violate and break
them. Accordingly he was no sooner seated in the Throne of his Ancestors, and
those whom he had been apprehensive of resistance and disturbance from, put out of
capacity and condition of attempting any thing against him, but he thought
himself discharged from every thing, that the Royal Word and Faith of a Prince
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52139:5"/>
had been pledged and laid to stake for in that Declaration, and from that day for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
acted in direct opposition to all the parts and branches of it. For having soon
after his return obtained a Parliament moulded and adapted both to his Arbitrary and
Papish Ends, he immediately set all his Instruments at work for the procuring such
Laws to be enacted, as might divide and weaken Protestants, and thereby make us
not only the more easie a Prey to the Papists, but afford them an advantage through
our Scuffles, of undermining our Religion with the less notice and observation. How
such persons came to be chosen and to constitute the majority of the House of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,
who by their actings have made themselves infamous and execrable to all ages,
were a matter too large to penetrate at present into the reasons of: but that which my
Theme conducts me to observe, is, that as they sacrificed the Treasure of the Nation
to the profuseness and prodigality of the Prince, and our Rights and Liberties to his
Ambition and arbitrary Will, so they both reintroduced and established those things
which have been a means of dividing us, and by many severe and repeated Laws,
they subjected a great number of industrious English Men and true Protestants, to
Excommunications, Imprisonments, rigorous and multiplied Fines, and all this for
matters only relating to their Consciences, and for their Obedience to God in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances
of his Worship and House. And notwithstanding the late Kings often pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
compassions to the Fanaticks, it will be hard to discern them, unless in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects
which proceed from very different and opposite principles. The distance which
hekept them from his Person and favor; the influencing these members of both
Houses that depended upon him, to be the Authors and Promoters of Severities
against them; the enjoyning so often the Judges and Justices of Peace to execute the
Laws upon them in their utmost Rigor; the instigating the Bishops and Ecclesiastical
Courts, if at any time they relented in their prosecutions, to pursue them with fresh
Citations and Censures; the arraigning them not only upon the Statutes made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentionally
against Dissenters, but upon those that were originally and solely enacted
against the Papists; these and other procedures of that nature are the only proofs
and evidences which we can find, of the late Kings Bowels, Pity, and Tenderness to the
Fanaticks. And whereas the weak Church-Men were imposed upon to believe,
that all the Severity against the Nonconformists, was the Fruit of his Zeal for
the Protestant Religion, and for the Security of the Worship and Discipline
established by Law; they might have easily discovered, if passion, prejudice, wealth
and honor, had not blinded them, that all this was calculated for ends perfectly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structive
to the Church, and inconsistent with the safety and happiness of all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants.
For as his seeking oftner than once to have wriggled himself into a
power of superceding and dispensing with those Laws, and suspending their
Execution, plainly shews that he never intended the support and preservation of
the Church by them; so his non-execution of the Laws against Papists, his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niving
at their encrease; his persuading those nearest unto him to reconcile them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
to the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> as he did among others the late Duke of <hi>Monmouth;</hi> his
countenancing the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks in their open and intolerable Insolencies, and
his advancing them to the most gainful and important Places and Trusts, sufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
that he never had any love to Protestants, or care of the Reformed Religion; but
that all his designs were of a contrary tendency, and his fairest pretences for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection
and grandeur of the Church of <hi>England</hi> adapted to other ends. Thus the Royal
Brothers having obtained such Laws to be enacted whereby one party of Protestants
was armed with means of oppressing and persecuting all others, neither the necessity of
their affairs at any time since, nor the application and interposure of several Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
for removing the grounds of our Differences and Animosities by an indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52139:5"/>
to be past into a Law, could prevail either upon his late Majesty or the present
King to forego the advantage they had gotten of keeping us in mutual enmity &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
of ministring to their projection of supplanting our religion, &amp; of reestablishing the
Faith, &amp; Worship of the Church of Rome. Hereupon the last King not only refused to
consent to such Bills as diverse late Parliaments had prepared for indulging Dissenters,
&amp; of bringing them into an union of Counsels, &amp; conjunction of interest, with those of
the Church of England, for resisting the conspiracies of the Papists against our legal
Government &amp; established Religion; but he rejected an address for suspending the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution
of the penal Laws against Fanaticks, which was offered &amp; presented unto him
by that very Parliament which had framed &amp; enacted those cruel &amp; villanous Laws.</p>
            <p>And as the Royal Brothers have made it their constant business to Cherish a divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
&amp; rancour among Protestants, and to provoke one party to persecute &amp; ruine an
other, so nothing could more naturally fall in with the design of Arbitrariness, or
be more subservient to the betraying the Nation to Papal Idolatry &amp; Jurisdiction. For
severe penal Laws against a considerable Body of the people, do either expose them
against whom they are enacted, to be destroyed by the Prince with whom the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
power of the Law is trusted and deposited, or they prove a temptation to such as
are obnoxious, of resigning themselves in such a manner to the will and pleasure of the
Monarch, for the obtaining his connivency at their violation of the Laws, as is unsafe
and dangerous for the common liberty, and good of the Kingdom. For in case the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream
Magistrate pursue an interest distinct from and destructive to that of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
they who the Law hath made liable to be oppressed, are brought under induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of becoming so many Partisans for abetting him in his designes, in hopes of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
thereupon protected from the penal Statutes, the execution whereof is committed
to him. And as it is not agreeable to the wisdom &amp; prudence which ought to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
men, nor to the mercy &amp; compassion which should be among Christians, for
one party to surrender an other into the hands &amp; power of the Soveraign to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poverished
&amp; ruined by him at his pleasure, especially when those whom they give
up to be thus treated &amp; entertained, are at agreement with them in all the Essentials
of Religion, equally zealous as themselves for the Liberties of their Country, &amp; who
for sobriety in their lives, industry in their callings, &amp; usefulness in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,
are inferior to none of their Fellow Subjects: so it is obvious to any who
give themselves leave to think, that the King would long ere this have been stated
in the absoluteness that is aspired after, &amp; both Church and State reduced to ly at the
discretion of the Monarch, provided the Nonconformists, for procuring his favour in
non-execution of the Laws, had suffered themselves to be prevailed upon, and drawn
over to stand by and assist him in his Popish and Despotical Designs.</p>
            <p>But those people, tho hated and maligned by their Brethren, rather than be found
aiding the King in his usurpations over the Kingdom, have chosen to undergoe the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most
calamities they could be made subject unto, either through the execution of
those Laws which had been made against them, or through our Princes &amp; their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters
wrecking their malice upon them in arbitrary and illegal methods. But what
the Royal Brothers could not work the afflicted and persecuted side unto, they found
the art to engage the other side in, tho not only excepted from all obnoxiousness to
those Laws, but strenthened &amp; supported by them. For as soon as the Court begun to
despaire of prevailing upon the Fanaticks, to become their Tools &amp; Instruments of
enslaving the Nation, and of exalting the Monarchy to despotical absoluteness,
they applyed to Some of the Church of England, whom by gratifying with a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52139:6"/>
execution of the Laws upon Dissenters, they brought to abett, applaud, and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stify
them, in all those counsels and ways which have reduced us into that miserable
condition wherein we now are. The Clergy being advanced to grandure and opulency,
things which many of them are fonder of, and loather to forego, than Religion and the
Rights of the Nation, the Court made it their business to possess them with a belief, that
unless the Fanaticks were suppressed and ruined, they could not enjoy with security
their dignities and wealth. Whereupon not only the lesser Levites, but the superior
Clergy having their lesson and cue given them from Whitehall and St James, fell upon
pursuing the Nonconformists with Ecclesiastical punishments, and upon exciting and
animating the Civil Officers against them. And under pretence of preserving and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending
the Church, they gave themselves over to an implicit serving of the Court, and
became not only Advocates but Instruments for the robbing of Corporations of their
Charters, for imposing Sheriffs upon the City of London who had not been legally
elected, and of fining and punishing men Arbitrarily for no crime, save the having
asserted their own and the Nations Rights in modest and lawful ways. Posterity will
hardly believe that so many of the prelatical Clergy, and so great a number of members
of the Church of England, should from an enmity unto, and pretended jealousie of
the Panaticks, have become Tools under the late King for justifying the Dissolution of
so many Parliaments, the invasion made upon their priviledges, the ridiculing and
stifling of the Popish plot, the shamming of forged Conspiracies upon Protestants,
the condemning several to death for high Treason who could be rendred guilty by the
Transgression of no known Law, and finally for advancing a Gentleman to the Throne,
who had been engaged in a conjuration against Religion and the legal Government, and
whom three several Parliaments would have therefore excluded from the Right of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession.
And being seduced into an espousal of the Interests of the Court against Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
Parliaments, and the Nation, it is doleful to consider what Doctrines both from
pulpit and press, were thereupon belched forth and divulged. Such as Monarchy's being
a Government by divine Right; that it is in the Princes power to Rule as he pleaseth;
that it is a grace and condescention in the King to give an account of what he does; that
for Parliaments to direct or regulate the Succession borders upon Treason, and is an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
against the Law of Nature; and that the only thing left to subjects in case the King
will Tyrannise over their Consciences, Persons &amp; Estates, is tamely to suffer, and as they
absurdly express it, to exercise passive obedience. So that by corrupting the minds &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences
of men with those pestilent and slavish Notions, they betrayed the Nation both
to the mischiefs which have already overtaken us, &amp; to what further we are yet threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
with. Nor did these Doctrines tend meerly to the fettering &amp; enfeebling the Spirits
of men, but they were a temptation to the Royal Brothers to put in execution what
they had been so long contriving and travelling with, and were a kind of reprimanding
them for being ignorant of their own Right and power, and for not exerting it with
that vigour and expedition which they might. I do acknowledge that there were many
both of the sacred order, and of the laick Communion of the Church of England, who
were far from being infected with those brutish sentiments and opinions, and who
were as zealous as any for having the Monarchy kept within its ancient limits; Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
maintained in their wonted Reverence and Authority; the subjects preserved in
the enjoyment of their immemorial priviledges; and who were far from sacrificing
our Religion and Laws to Popery &amp; Arbitrariness, and from lulling us into a tameness
and lethargy, in case the Court should attempt the abolishing the established Doctrin
and Worship, and the subverting and changing the Civil Government. But alas! be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52139:6"/>
their being immediately branded with the name of conformable Fanaticks, and
registred in the Kalender with those that stood precluded the Kings favour &amp; merited
his animadversion; their modesty was soon drownd and silenced in the loud noise of
their clamorous Brethren, and their retiredness from conversation, while the others,
frequented all places of society and publick concourse, deprived the Nation of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit
of their example, and the happiness of their instructions. Not have I mentioned
the extravagancies of any of the Ecclesiasticks and members of the Church of England,
with a design either of reproaching and upbraiding them, or of provoking and exas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perating
the Fanaticks to resentments, but only to shew how fatal our divisions have
been unto us, what excesses they have occasioned our being hurried and transported
into, and what mischievous improvement our enemies have made of them to the sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planting
and almost subverting of all that is valuable unto us as we are Englishmen,
Christians, and Protestants.</p>
            <p>And as our animosities through our Divisions gave the Court an advantage of sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orning
that party, which they pretended to befriend and uphold, into a ministration
to all their Counsels and projections against our Religion and Laws; so by reason of
the unnatural heats wherewith Protestants have been enflamed and enraged against
Protestants, many weak, ungrounded, and unstable Souls, have been tempted to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion
the truth of our Religion, and to apostatise to the Church of Rome, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
have become united in inclination, power, and endeavours with the Court and
our old Enemies the Papists, for the exstirpation of protestancy and the alteration of
the Government. As it hath been matter of offence and scandal to all Men, so it hath
been ground of stumbling and falling unto many, to see those who are professedly of
the same Religion, to be mutually embittered against one another, and so far tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sported
with malice and rage, as to seek and pursue each others destruction. For such
a carriage and behaviour are so contrary to the spirit an principles of Christianity,
and to the genius and temper of true Religion, that it is no mervaile, if persons igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
of the holy Scriptures, and strangers to the converting and comforting vertue of
the Doctrine of the Gospel asserted in our Confessions, and insisted upon by our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines;
should suspect the Orthodoxy of that Religion which is accompanied with so
bitter fruits, even in the Dispensers of the word as well as in others, and betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
to the Communion of that Church, where how many and important soever
their differences be one with an other, yet they do not break forth into those flames
of excommunicating and persecuting each other; that ours have done. How have some
among us through having their spirits fretted and exasperated by the craft and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
of our Enemies, not only loaded and stigmatised their Bretheren and Fellow Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants
with crimes and Names, which were they true and deserved, would justly
render us a loathing and an abomination to mankind, but have libelled and branded
those whom God had honored to be instruments of the Reformation, with appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
and characters fit to beget a detestation of their Doctrine, as well as their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.
The worst that the Papists have forged and vomited out against Luther Zwin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glius,
Calvin &amp;c. hath been raked up and repeated to the disparagment of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,
and to the scandalising the minds of weak men against it. And as the Jesuites
and Priests have improved those slanders and calumnies to the seduction of diverse
from the Church of England, and to a working them over to a Reconciliation with
the Church of Rome; so the Court hath there by had an increase of their Faction
and party against our Religion aud Liberties, and have been inabled to muster Troops
of Janisaries for their Despotical and unlimited claim.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:52139:7"/>
Nor have our Divisions with the heats, animosities, revilings, &amp; persecutions that
have ensued thereupon, proved only an occasion of the seduction of several from our
Religion, and of their Apostacy to Popery, but they have been a main spring &amp; force
of the debauchery, irreligion and Atheisme, which have overspread the Nation, &amp;
have brought so many both to an indifferency and unconcernedness for the Gospel and
all that is vertuous and noble, and have disposed them to fall in with those that could
countenance and protect them in their impiety and prophaneness, &amp; feed their luxury
and pride with honor and gain. What a woful scheme of Religion have we afforded
the world, and how shamefully have we painted forth and represented the holy Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin
of the blessed Jesus, while we have not only lived in a direct opposition to all the
commands of meekness, love and mutual forbearance, which our Religion lays us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the Authority off, but have neglected to practice good manners, to observe the rules
of Civility, to treat one another with common humanity &amp; to do as we would be
done unto. While we have been more offended at what seemed to supplant our Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations
&amp; Grandures than at what dishonor'd God &amp; reproached the Gospel; while
we weighd not so much whether they whom we took into our sacred Communion as
well as into our personal friendship, were conformable in their lives to the Scripture, as
whether they comply'd with the Canons of the Church; while we reprobated all that
were not of our way, tho never so vertuous &amp; devout, and sainted all that were, tho ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
so wicked &amp; prophane; while we branded such for Fanaticks, whom we could just<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
charge with nothing, save the not admiting that into Religion which came not from
the divine Author of it, &amp; hugged those for good and orthodox believers, that would
sooner consult the Statute Book for their practice in the Worship of God, than the
Bible; while we haled those to prison &amp; spoiled them of their Estates, to whom no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
could be objected except their being too precise and conscientious in avoiding
that through fear &amp; apprehension of sinning, which others had a liberty &amp; latitude to
do as judging it lawful, and in the mean time esteemed those worthy of the chiefest
Trusts in the Church &amp; commonwealth, whose folly &amp; villanies made them unfit for
civil Societies; while they who lived most agreeably to the Laws of God, &amp; the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
of Christ, were persecuted as Enemies to Religion and the pests of the Kingdom,
and in the interim too many of the very Clergy were not only countenancers of the
most profligate persons as their best friends, but joined and assisted in scandalous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baucheries,
under pretence of sustaining the honor of their Tribe, &amp; doing service to
the Church. I say while these were unhappy but too obvious fruits of our Divisions
&amp; of the bitter heats that accompanied them, how was the reverence for the sacred
Order lessened &amp; diminished, the veneration for Religion weakned and lost, the shame
&amp; dread of appearing profane &amp; wicked removed and banished, &amp; such who took the
measures of Chistianity from the practices of those that were stiled Christians, rather
than from the immaculate and holy Scriptures, tempted to think all Religion a juggle,
&amp; priesthood but an artifice &amp; craft to compass honor &amp; wealth. And tho nothing but
a shortness of understanding, and an immoderate love to their lusts, could occasion
the drawing such a conclusion from foregoing premisses, yet I must needs grant that
there was too just ground administr'd to them of saying that many did not believe that
themselves, the Faith whereof they recommended to others. But that which I would
more particularly observe, is, that it is from among those who by the foregoing occasion
have been tempted to debauchery &amp; irreligion, that the Romish Emissaries have made
the harvest of proselytes &amp; converts to the Church of Rome. For as they who fear
not God, will be easily brought to imitate Caesar, &amp; such who are of no Religion, will
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52139:7"/>
in subserviency to secular ends assume the mask and profession of any; so Popery is
extreamly adapted to the wishes and desires of wicked and profane men, in that it
provides for their living as enormously as they please here, &amp; flatters them with hopes
&amp; assurances of blessedness hereafter. They who can be ascertained of going to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
upon the confessing their sins to a Priest, and their receiving Absolution, the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charist
and Extreme Unction, need not look after Repentance toward God, Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
to holiness, nor a life, of Faith, Love, Mortification, and Obedience, which
the Protestant Religion, upon the Authority of the Gospel obligeth them unto, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
to the obtaining of eternal happiness. And as the late Apostates to Popery in
England, are chiefly such who were Notorious for loosness, prophaness and immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality,
and were the scandal of our Religion while they professed it, and while in our
Church were not properly of it, so it from among men of this stamp &amp; character that
his late Majesty and the present King have found persons assisting and subservient to
their Despotical and Arbitrary designs. For whosoever takes a survey of the Court Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
&amp; considereth who have been the Advocates for encroachments upon our Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
and abetters of usurpation over our Right, they will find them to have been prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally
the profligate and debauched among the Nobility and Gentry, the Mercenary,
ignorant &amp; scandalous among the Clergy, the offscouring and such as are an ignominy
to humane Nature among the yeomanry and pesants. And it was in order to this vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanous
End, that the Royal Brothers have endeavoured so industriously to debauch
the Nation, &amp; have made sensuality &amp; profaneness the qualifications for preferment, &amp;
the badges of Loyalty. And if among those that appear for the preservation of the
Liberties of their Country, there be any that deserve to be stiled Enemies to Religion
and vertue, as I dare affirm that they owe their immoralities to Court Education,
Converse &amp; Example, so I hope that though they have not hitherto been all of them
so happy as to have left their vices where they learned them, yet that they will not
continue to disparage the good cause which they have espoused with an unsuitable
life, nor give their Adversaries reason to say, that while they pretend to seek the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
of the State, they are both the deriders of sobriety &amp; virtue, without which
no Constitution can long subsist, &amp; guilty of such horrid Oaths, Cursing, imprecations,
blasphemies and uncleanesses, which naturally as well as morally and meritously dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose
Nations to subversion and Extirpation.</p>
            <p>Finally being through the bitter effects which have ensued upon our Divisions, made
apprehensive &amp; jealous one of another, it hath from there come to pass, that while
the care of the Conformists hath been to watch against the grouth of the Dissenters, &amp;
the solicitude of the Nonconformists hath been how to prevert the rage of the Bigotted
Church men, the Papists in the mean time without being headed or observ'd have both
incredibly multiplied, &amp; made considerable advances in their designs of ruining us.
For whensoever the Court was to take a signal step towards Popery &amp; Arbitrary pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
there was a clamor raised of some menacing boldness of the Fanaticks. And if the
Nation grew at any time alarm'd, by reason of the favor shewn to Roman Catholicks,
&amp; of some visible progress made towards the Kings becoming Despotical, all was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly
husht with a shout and cry of the Government and Churches being in emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
hazard from the Dissenters. Yea whensoever the Papists &amp; their Royal Patrens
stood detected of having been conspiring against our Religion &amp; Civil Liberties, all
was diverted &amp; stiffled by putting the Kingdom upon a false scent, and by hounding
out their Beagles upon the Nonconformists. So that the eyes &amp; minds of Protestants
being employed in reference to what was to be apprehended &amp; feared from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52139:8"/>
the workings of our Popish Enemies either escaped our observation, or were
heeded by most only with a superficial and unaffective glance. And while our Church
men stood prepossessed by the Court with a dread and jealousie of the Fanaticks, all
that was said and written of a Conspiracy carried on by the Papists against our Laws
and Religion, was entertained and represented by the prejudiced Clergy, as an Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
only of the Dissenters for compassing an Indulgence from the Parliament, which in
case such a plot had obtained the belief that a matter of so great danger and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
required, would have been easily granted, being the only rational expedient for
the preservation of the established Religion and the legal Government. Nor did our
Enemies question but that having enflamed our Divisions and raised our Animosities
to so great a height, rather than the one party would lay aside their severities, and the
other let fall their resentments, we would even be contented to lye at their mercy, and
submit our selves to the pleasure and discretion of the Court and Papists. And there
have not wanted some peevish, foolish, and ill men of both parties, who rather than
sacrifice their spleen and passion, and abandon their particular Quarrels for the interest
and safety of the whole, would be inclined to expose the Protestant Religion and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish
Liberties, to the hazards wherewith they are apparently threatned, and to suffer
all extremities, meerly to have the satisfaction of seeing those whom they respectively
hate, involved with them under the same miseries. But as this is such a degree of
madness and infatuation, as can proceed from nothing but brutish rage, and argues
no less than a Divine <hi>Nemesis;</hi> so I hope they are but few that stand infected with
these passionate sentiments and inclinations, and remain thus hardned in their mutual
prejudices. And to those I have nothing to say, nor the least advice to administer, but
shall leave them to their own follies, as persons to whose conviction no Discourse
tho never so rational can be adapted, and whom only stripes can work upon.</p>
            <p>'Tis to such therefore as are capable of hearkning to Reason, &amp; who are ready to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace
any Counsel that shall be found adjusted to the Common Interest, that I am to
address what remains to be represented and said in the following leaves. For all parties
of Protestants having seen, how far our Enemies have improved our divisions and ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours
to the compassing their wicked and ambitious designs, and the robbing us of all,
that good &amp; generous men account valuable, they are at last convinced of the necessity
we are reduced unto, of altering the measures of our acting towards one another, and
both of laying aside our persecutions, and of exchanging our wranglings among our
selves, into a joint contending for the Faith of the Gospel, &amp; the Rights of the Nation.
For what the Gentleman now in the Throne intends and aims at, is not any longer mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
of meer suspicion &amp; jealousie, but of demonstrable evidence &amp; unquestionable cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty.
His mask &amp; vizor of zeal for the preservation of the Church of England, and
of tender regard for the Laws of the Land are laid by &amp; put off, and his resolutions of
Governing arbitiarily, &amp; of introducing Popery, are become obvious to all men whom
Reason and sense have not forseken &amp; left. The Papists whom it was thought much a
while ago to see connived at in the exercise of their Worship in private Houses, are
allowed now to practice their Idolatry openly in our chief Towns, and in the Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan
City of the neighboring Kingdom to usurp the publick Churches &amp; Cathedarals.
Those Catholick Gentlemen whom heretofore it was matter of surprise, to see coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced
with the private favor of the Prince, are now advanced to the supream Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
in the Army, &amp; the principal Trust in Civil affairs. The Recusant Lords whose
enlargement out of the Tower, we could not but look upon as an unpresidented viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
both of Laws of the Land &amp; of the Rights &amp; jurisdiction of Parliament, being
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52139:8"/>
committed thither by the Authority of the House of Lords upon a charge &amp; Impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of high Treason by the Commons of England in Parliament assembled, are now
honored to be members of the privy Council, and exalted to be chief Ministers of
State. They whom the Statutes of the Realm make subject to the severest penalties for
Apostacy to Rome, are not only protected from the edge of the Law, but maintained
in Parochial Incumbencies &amp; Headships of Colledges. Our Orthodox Clergy are not
only inhibited to preach against Popery, but are illegally reprimanded, silenced, &amp;
suspended, for discharching that duty, which their Consciences, Offices, Oaths, and the
Laws of the Kingdom oblige them unto. And such whom neither the Ecclesiastical nor
Westminster Courts, can arraign &amp; proceed against, we have a new Court of <hi>Inquisition</hi>
erected for the adjudging &amp; punishing of them. So that it is not the Fanaticks who
are the only persons to be stuck at and ruined, but the Conformists are to be treated
after the same manner, and to share in the common lot whereunto all honest &amp; sincere
Protestants are destined &amp; designed. Even they who were the darlings of <hi>Whitehall</hi>
&amp; St. <hi>Iames</hi>'s, &amp; recompenced with Honors and Titles for betraying the Rights and
Priviledges of Corporations, persecuting Dissenters, &amp; heading Addresses, wherein Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments
were reproached, the Course of Justice against Popish Offenders was slander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
the illegal &amp; arbitrary procedures of the Court applauded and justified, &amp; all that
were zealous for our Laws and Liberties stigmatised with the names of Villains and
Traitors, are now themselves, for but discouraging Popish Assemblies &amp; attempting
to put the Laws in execution against Priests who had publickly celebrated Mass, not
only checkt and rebuked, but punished with seisure and imprisonment. Nor are our
Religion and Civil Liberties meerly supplanted and undermined by illegal Tricks glos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
over with the varnish of judicial Forms, but they are assaulted &amp; battered in the
face of the Sun, without so much as a palliation to give their procedures a plausible fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure.
And the King being brought to a despair of managing the Parliament to his bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced
purposes of Popery &amp; Arbitrariness, &amp; of prevailing with them to establish
Tyranny &amp; Idolatry by Law, notwithstanding their having been as industriously packt
&amp; chosen to answer such a design<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as art, bribery &amp; Authority could reach, &amp; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing
their having been obsequious in their first Session to an excess that hath prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
unsafe to themselves &amp; the Nation, he seems resolvd not to allow them to meet any
more, but to set up <hi>a la mode de France,</hi> and to have his personal Commands, seconded
with the assent of his <hi>durante beueplacito</hi> judges to be acknowledged and obeyed for
Laws. So that they who were formerly seduced into a good opinion of him, are not
only undeceived, but provoked to warm resentments for having had their credulity &amp;
easmess of belief so grosly abused. And as the converting so vast a number of well
meaning but wofully deluded people, who had suffered themselves to be hoodwinked
and fatally hurried to betray their Religion, Country, &amp; Posterity, to the Ambition
&amp; Popish Bigottry of the Court, was a design becoming the Compassion, Mercy and
Wisdom of God; so the methods &amp; means whereby they are come to be enlightned &amp;
proselyted, are a signal vindication of the Sapience &amp; Righteousness of God in all these
tremendous steps of his providence, by which our Enemies have been emboldned to
detect &amp; discover themselves. For tho their continuing so long to have a good opinion
of the present King, and their abetting him so far in the undermining our Religion and
invading our Liberties, may seem to have proceeded not so much from their ignorance
is from their obstinacy &amp; malice; yet God who penetrates into the hearts of men, may
have discovered some degrees of sincerity in their pretensions &amp; carriages tho accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied
with a great deal of folly &amp; unmanliness. Nor are the Lords ways like to outs,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52139:9"/>
to give persons over us unteachable and irreclaimable, upon their withstanding every
measure of light, and the resisting even those means which were sufficient and proper
for their conviction; but he will try them by new and extraordinary methods, &amp; see
whether feeling &amp; doleful experience may not convert those, upon whom arguments
and moral evidence could make no impressions. And their being among those for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
missed and deluded Protestants, many who retained a love for their Country, a
care for their posterity, and a zeal for the Gospel and Reformed Religion, even when
their actions imported the contrary, &amp; seem'd to betray them; the singling and weed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
out such from among the Court Faction &amp; party, is a compensation both for the
defeatment of all endeavours for the prevention of the evils that have overtaken us, &amp;
for the distresses &amp; calamities under which we do at present lye &amp; groan. And if there
be joy in Heaven upon the conversion of a Sinner, with that thankfulness to God, &amp;
joy in themselves, should they who have so many years wrestled against the encreach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of Popery &amp; Arbitrariness, &amp; who have deeply suffered in their Names, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
and Estates upon that account, welcome &amp; embrace their once erring &amp; misled
but now enlightned, reclaimed and converted Brethren. And instead of remembring
or upbraiding them with the opposition and rancour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which they expressed against our
persons, principles, &amp; ways, let there be no language heard from us, but what may
declare the joy we have in our selves for their conversion, and the entire trust &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence
which we put in them. For tho as to many things which might have been hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred,
had they not been lulled into deep delusions, they may seem born out of due
time, yet there is season enough left both for giving obstruction to what we are farther
threatned with, &amp; for recovering out of the jaws of the Enemy what he thinks he hath
irretrievably swallowed and devoured.</p>
            <p>The first duty incumbent therefore upon Dissenters towards those of the Church of
England, is to believe that notwithstanding there having been many of them so long
Advocates &amp; Partizans for the Court through ignorance of what was aimed at &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended,
they are nevertheless as really concerned as any others, and as truly zealous
for the preservation of the Protestant Religion, &amp; for maintaining the legal Rights &amp;
Liberties of the Subject, &amp; when occasion shall offer will approve themselves accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly.
'Tis a ridiculous as well as a mischievous fancie, for one party to confine all
Religion only to themselves, or to circumscribe all the ancient English ardor for the
common Rights of the Nation to such as are of their particular Fellowship &amp; persuasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
there being sincere Christians, &amp; true Englishmen among those of all judgments,
&amp; societies of Protestants, &amp; among none more than those of the Communion of the
Church of England. It were the height of wickedness as well as the most prodigious
folly, to imagine that the Conformists have abandoned all fidelity to God. &amp; cast off
all care of themselves and their Country, upon a mistaken iudgment of being Loyal
&amp; obedient to the King. They know as well as any, that the giving to <hi>Cesar</hi> the things
that are <hi>Cesars,</hi> lays them under no obligation of surrendring unto him the things that
are Gods, nor of sacrificing unto the will of the Soveraign the priviledges reserved unto
the people by the Fundamental Rules of the Constitution, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d by the Statutes of the
Realm. And they understand as well as others, that the Laws of the Land are the
only measures of the Princes Authority and of the Subjects Fealty, and where they
give him no Right to command, they lay them under no tye to obey. And tho here
&amp; there a Dissenter have written against Popery with good success, yet they have
been mostly conformable Divines who have triumphed over it in elaborate Discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,
and who have beaten the Romish Scriblers off the Stage. Nor can it be thought
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52139:9"/>
that they who have so accurately related and vindicated the History, and asserted an
desended the Doctrine of the Reformation, should either tamely relinquish, or be
wanting in all due and legal ways to uphold and maintain it. And tho one or two
Fanaticks have with sufficient strength and applause brandished their pens against
Arbitrariness and in detecting the Designs of the Royal Brothers, yet they who have
generally and with greatest honor appeared for our Laws and Legal Government a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
the Invasions and Usurpations of the Court, have been Theologues and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Nor in case of further attempts for altering the
Constitution and enslaving the Nation, will they shew themselves unworthy the
having descended from Ancestors, whose Motto in the high places of the Field was
<hi>Nolumus leges Angliae mutari.</hi> They who have so often justified the Arms of the <hi>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited
Netherlands</hi> against their Rightful Princes the Kings of <hi>Spain,</hi> and so unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerably
vindicated their casting off Obedience to those Monarchs, when they had
invaded their Priviledges, and attempted to establish the <hi>Inquisition</hi> over them,
cannot be ignorant what their own Right and Duty is in behalf of the Protestant
Religion and English Libertles; for the security whereof, we have not only so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Laws, but the Coronation Oaths and Stipulations of our Kings. And those
Gentlemen of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who appeared so vigorously in three Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
for excluding the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> from the Succession to the Crown, by reason
of a jealousie of what, through being a Papist, he would attempt against our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
and Priviledges, in case he were suffered to ascend the Throne; cannot be
now to seek what becomes them towards him, tho actually Regnant, having seen
and felt what before they only apprehended and feared. For if the Law that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talleth
the Succession upon the next of Kin, and obligeth the Subjects to admit and
receive him, not only may but ought to be dispensed with, in case the Heir, through
having imbib'd Principles which threaten the safety, and are inconsistent with the
happiness of the People, hath made himself incapable to inherit; we know by a
short Ratiocination how far we stand bound to a Prince on the Throne, who by
transgressing against the Laws of the Constitution, hath abdicated himself from the
Government, and stands virtually deposed. For whosoever shall offer to Rule arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily,
does immediately cease to be King <hi>de jure,</hi> seeing by the Fundamental,
Common and Stature Laws of the Realm, we know none for Supream Magistrate
and Governor, but a limited Prince, and one who stands circumscribed and
bounded in his Power and Prerogative. And should the Dissenters entertain a belief
that the Conformists are less concerned and zealous than themselves for the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant
Religion and Laws of the Kingdom, they would not only sin and offend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
the Rules of Charity, but against the measures of Justice, and daily Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences
from matters of Fact. For neither they not we owe our Conversion to God,
and our practical holiness to the Opinions about Discipline, Forms of Worship,
and Ceremonies, wherein we differ, but to the Doctrines of Faith and Christian
Obedience, wherein we agree. 'Tis not their being for a Liturgy, a Surprize, or
a Bishop, that hath heretofore Influenced them to subserve the Court in Designs
tending to Absoluteness, but they were seduced unto it upon Motives whereof they
are now ashamed, and the ridiculousness and folly of which they have at last dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered.
Nor is the multitude of profligate and scandalous persons with which
the Church of <hi>England</hi> is crowded, any just impeachment of the purity of her Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
in the Vitals and Essentials of Religion, or of the Virtue and Piety of many
of her Members. For as it is her being the only Society established by Law that
attracts those Vermin to her Bosom, so it is her being restrained by Law from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barring
them, that keeps them there to her reproach, and to the grief of many
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52139:10"/>
of many of her Ecclesiasticls. Neither is it the fault of the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
that the Agents and Factors for Popery and Arbitrary Power, have chosen to pass
under the name of her Sons; but it proceeds partly from their Malice, as hoping
by that means to disgrace her with all true Englishmen, as well as with Dissenters,
and partly from their Craft, in order thereby the better to conceal their Design,
and to shrowd themselves from the Censure and Punishment, which had it not
been for that Mask<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they would have been exposed unto, and have undergone.
And I dare affirm, that besides the Obligations from Religion, which the Conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ists
are equa<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly under with Dissenters, for hindering the introduction of Popery,
there are several inducements from Interest, which sway them to prevent its establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
wherein the Fanaticks are but little concerned. For tho Popery would be
alike afflictive to the Consciences of Protestants of all Perswasions, yet they are
Gentlemen and Ministers of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whose Livings, Revenues, and
Estates are threatened in e<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>se it come to be established. Nor wou'd the most Loyal
and Obsequious Levites, provided they resolve to continue Protestants, be willing
that their Parsonages and Incumbencies, to which they have no less Right by Law,
than the King hath to the Excise and Customs, should be taken from them and
bestowed upon Romish Priests, by an Act of Dispotical Power, and of unlimited
Prerogative. And for the Gentlemen, as I think sew of them would hold them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
obliged to part with their Purses to High-way Padders, t<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ough such should
have a Patent from the King to rob whomsoever they encountred upon the
Read; so there will not be many inclined to suffer their Mannors and Abbey-Lands,
to which they have so good a Title, to be ravished from them either by
Monks or Janizaries, tho authorized thereunto by the Prince's Commission. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
they who had formerly suffered themselves to be seduced to prove in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
Betrayers of the Rights and Religion of their Country, will now (being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceived!
not only in conjunction with others withstand the Court in its prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution
of Popish and Arbitrary Designs, but through a generous exasperation
for having been deluded and abused, will judg themselves obliged in vindication
of their actings before, to appear for the Protestant Religion and the Laws of
<hi>England,</hi> with a Zeal equal to that wherewith they contributed to the undermin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
and supplanting of them. For they are not only become more sensible than
they were of the Mischiefs of Absolute Government so as for the future to prize
and assert the Priviledges reserved unto the People by the Rules of the Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
and chalkt out for them in the Laws of the Land; but they have such a
fresh view of Popery both in its Heresies, Blasphemies, Superstitions and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,
and in the Treachery, Sanguinariness, Violence and Cruelty, which the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal
Principles mould, influence, and oblige men unto, that they not only enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
the greatest Abhorrency and Detestation imaginable for it, but seem resolved
not to cherish in their Bosom, a thing so abominable to God, execrable to good
Men, and destructive to Humane as well as to Christian Societies.</p>
            <p>Nor are the Dissenters merely to believe that the Conformists are equally zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
as themselves for the Reformed Religion and English Rights, but they are to
consider them as thy only great and united Body of Protestants in the Kingdom,
with whom all other Parties compared bear no considerable proportion. For tho
the Nonconformists considered abstractedly make a vast number of honest and useful
People, yet being laid in the Scale with those of the Episcopal Communion, they
are but few and lie in a little room. And whosoever will take the pains to ballance
the one against the other, even where the Fanaticks make the greatest Figure, and
may justly boast of their multitude, they will soon be convinced that the number
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52139:10"/>
of the other doth far transcend and exceed them. And it be so in Cities and
Corporations, where the greatest Bulk of Dissenters are, it is much more so in
Country Parishes, where the latter bear not the proportion of one to a hundred.
Nor doth the Church of <hi>England</hi> more exceed the other Parties in her number,
than she doth in the Quality of her Members. For whereas they who make up and
constitute the separate Societies, are chiefly persons of the middle Rank and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,
the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth in a manner vouch, and claim all the Persons
of Honor, of the Learned Professions, and such as have valuable Estates, for her
Communicants. And though the other sort are as necessary in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,
and contribute as much to its Strength, Prosperity, and Happiness, yet
they make not that Figure in the Government, nor stand in that capacity of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
influence upon publick Affairs: for not only the Gentlemen of both the Gowns,
who by reason of their Calling and Learning are best able to defend our Religion
and vindicate our Laws and Privileges with their Tongues and Pens, but they whose
Estates, Reputation, and Interest, recommendeth them to be elected Members of
the great Senate of the Nation, as well as they who by reason of their Honors and
Baronages are hereditary Legislators, are generally, if not all, of the Communion
of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> so that they who conform to the established Worship
and Discipline, are to be look'd upon and acknowledged as the great Bulwark
of the Protestant Religion in <hi>England,</hi> and the Hedge and Fence of our Civil Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
and Rights. And though it be true that this great breach, made upon our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
and Laws, is fallen out under their hand, while the poor Dissenters had neither
accession to, nor were in a condition to prevent it; yet seeing their own Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
do sufficiently load and charge them for it with Shame and Ignominy, it
were neither candid, nor at this juncture seasonable, to upbraid it to them, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove
it to their dishonor and reproach. For as they have tamely look'd on and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nived
till our Religion and Liberties are so far undermined and supplanted, so it is
they alone who are in a condition of stemming the Inundation of Idolatry and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny
with which we are threatned, and of repairing our Breaches, and reducing
the Prerogative to its old Channel, and making Popery sneak and retreat into its
Holes and Corners again. And should the Church of <hi>England</hi> he overthrown and
devoured, what an easie Prey would the Fanaticks be to the <hi>Romish</hi> Cormorants.
And could the King, under the Conduct of the <hi>Iesuits,</hi> and with the assistance of
his Myrmidons, dissolve the established Worship and Discipline, they of the Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
would be in no capacity to support the Reformed Religion, nor able to escape
the common Ruine and Persecution. 'Tis therefore the interest as well as the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of the Dissenters, to help maintain and defend those Walls, within the skreen
and shelter whereof, their own Hutts and Cottages are built and stand; and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
seeing the Conformists are at last, tho to their own Religion's and the Nations
expence, become so far enlightned, as to see a necessry of growing more amica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
towards them, and if not to enlarge the Terms of their Communion, yet to grant
an Indulgence to all Protestants that differ from them. And as we ought to admire
the Wisdom of God in those Providences, by which Protestants are taught to
lay aside their Animosities, and to let fall their Persecutions of one another; so
it would be a contradiction both to the Principles and repeated Protestations of Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senters,
to aim at more than such a Liberty as is consistent with a National Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siastick
Establishment. Yet it were to proclaim themselves both Villains and
Hypocrites, not to allow their Fellow Protestants the exercise of their Judgments,
with what farther Profits and Emoluments the Law will grant them, provided
themselves may be discharged from all obnoxiousness to Penalties and Censures up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the account of their Consciences, and be admitted a free and publick practice of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52139:11"/>
their own respective Modes of Discipline, and be suffered to Worship God in those
ways which they think he hath required of and enjoyned them. And were <hi>England</hi>
immediately to be rendered so happy as to have a Protestant Prince ascend the
Throne, and to enjoy a Parliament duesy chosen, and acting with freedom, no one
Party of the Reformed Religion among us, must ever expect to be established and
supported to the denyal of Liberty to others, much less to be by Law empowered to
ruin and destroy them. Should it please Almighty God, through denying Male
Issue to the King, to bring the Princess of <hi>Orange</hi> to the Crown, tho the Church of
<hi>England</hi> may in that case justly expect the being preserved and upheld as the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional
Establishment, yet all other Protestants may very rationally promise them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
an Indulgence, and that not only from the mildness and compassionate
sweetness of her Temper, but from the influence which the Prince her Husband will
have upon her, who as he is descended from Ancestors, whose glory it was to be
the Redeemers of their Country from Papal Persecution and Spanish Tyranny, so
his Education, Generosity, Wisdom, and many Heroick V<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rtues, dispose him to
embrace all Protestants with an equal tenderness, and to erect his Interest upon the
being the Head and Patron of all that profess the Reformed Religion. Had the late
Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> been victorious against the Forces of the present King, and ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
to have wrested the Scepter our of his hand; tho all Protestants might there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
have expected, and would certainly have enjoyed an equal Freedom, without
the lyableness of any Party to Penal Laws for matters of Religion, yet he would
have been careful, and I have reason to believe that it was his purpose, to have
had the Church of <hi>England</hi> preserved and maintained, and that she should have
suffered no alteration but what would have been to her strength and glory, through
an enlargement of the Terms of her Communion, and what would have been to
the praise of her Moderation and Charity, through her being perswaded to bear
with such as differed from her in little things, and could not prevail with
themselves to partake with her in all Ordinances. Upon the whole, it is both the
prudence and safety of Dissenters, as they would escape Extirpation themselves,
and have Religion conveyed down to Posterity, to unite their strength and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
to those of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for the upholding her against the Assaults
of Popish Enemies, who pursue her Subversion. As matters are now circumstanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
and stated in <hi>England,</hi> there is not an Affront or Injury offered or done unto her
by the Court, which do not at the same time reach and wound the Fanaticks. 'Tis
not her being for Episcopacy Cerimonies, and imposed set Forms of Worship, the
things about which she and the Nonconformists differ, that she is maligned and struck
at by the Man in power and his Popish Juncto; but it is for being Protestant, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed,
and Orthodox, Crimes under the guilt whereof Dissenters are equally
concerned and involved. Being therefore in opposition to the common Cause of
Religion, that the late Court of Inquisition is erected over her Ecclesiasticks, all
Protestants ought jointly to resent the Wrongs which she sustains, and not only to
sympathise with those Dignified and lower Clergy, which are called to suffer, but to
espouse their Quarrel with the same warmth that we would our own.</p>
            <p>And as we are to look upon those of the Episcopal Communion, to be the great
Bulwark of the Protestant Religion and Reformed Interest in <hi>England;</hi> so it is far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
incumbent upon Dissenters towards them, and a duty which they owe to God,
the Nation, and themselves, not to be accessary to any thing, through which the
legal Establishment of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> may by any Act of pretended Regal
Prerogative be weakned and supplanted. I am not counselling the Fanaticks to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce
their Principles, nor to participate with the Prelatical Church in all Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52139:11"/>
on the Terms to which they have straitned and narrowed their Communion,
For while they remain unsatisfied of the lawfulness of those Terms and Conditions,
they cannot do it without offending God and contracting guilt upon their Souls;
nor will they of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in Charity, Justice, and Honesty, expect it
from them: for whatsoever any man believeth to be in, it is so to him, and will
by God be impured as such, till he be otherwise englightned and convinced; nor are
the Fanaticks to be falie and cruel to themselves, in order to be kind and friendly
to them. But that which I would advice them unto, is that after the maintaining
the highest measure of love to the consormable Congregations as Churches of Christ,
and the esteeming their Members as Christian Protestant Brethren, notwithstanding
the several things wherein they judge them to err and to be mistaken, that they
would not by any Act and Transaction of theirs, betray them into the Despotical
Power of this Popish King, nor directly nor indirectly acknowledge his being vested
with an Authority paramount unto, and superceding the Laws, by which the Church
of <hi>England</hi> is established in its present form, order, and mode of Jurisdiction, Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,
and external Worship. Whatsoever ease arriveth to the Dissenters, through
the King's suspending the execution of the Penal Laws, without their Address and
Application, they may receive it with joy and humility in themselves, and with
thankfulness to God; nor is there hereby any prejudice offered on their part to
the Authority of the Law, or offence or injury given or done to the Conformable
Clergy. Nor is without grief and regret that the Church-men are forced to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
the harassing, spoiling, and imprisonment of the Nonconformists, while in the
mean time the Papists are suffered to assemble to the celebration of their Idolatrous
Worship without censure and controul. And were it in their power to remedy it,
and give relief to their Protestant Brethren, they would with delight and readiness
embrace the occasion and opportunity of doing it. But alas! instead of having an
advantage put into their hand, of contributing to the relief of the Fanaticks, which
I dare say many of them ardently wish and desire, they are compelled, contrary
to their Inclination as well as their Interest, to become instrumental in persecuting
and oppressing them, Nor does the King covet a better and a more legal Advantage
against the Conformists, than that they would refuse to pursue Dissenters, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline
molesting them with Ecclesiastical Censures and Civil Punishments: so that
their Condition is to be pitied and bewailed, in that they are hindred from Acting
against the Papists, though both enjoined by Law, and influenced thereunto by
motives of Self-preservation, as well as by ties of Conscience; while in the mean
time they are forced to prosecute their Fellow Protestants, or else to be suspended
and deposed, and put out of their Offices and Employs. And though I do believe,
that they would at last have more Peace in themselves, and be better accepted with
God in the great day of their account, should they refuse to disturb and prosecute
their Protestant Brethren, and scorn to be any longer Court Tools for weakning and
undermining the Reformed Cause and Interest; yet I shall leave them to act in
this as they shall be persuaded in themselves, and as they shall judge most agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
to Principles of Wisdom and Conscience. In the interim, the Fanaticks have
all the reason in the World to believe, that the Proceedings of the Clergy and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
of the Church of <hi>England</hi> at this season and juncture against them, are not the
Results of their Election and Choice, but the effects of moral compulsion and neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity.
Not will any Dissenter that is prudent and discreet, blame them for a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
which they cannot help, but bear his misfortune and lot with patience in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self,
and with compassion and charity towards them, and have his Indignation rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
only against the Court, which forceth them to be instrumental in their oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52139:12"/>
and trouble. And instead of being thereby provoked to petition the King to
suspend the execution of the Penal Laws, or that he would by an Act of his Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative
dispense with their Meetings for religious Worship in defiance of them; they
ought to consider that is what the Court aims at, by commanding their conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Brethren to molest and pursue them. For a power paramount and transcendent
to the Law is what the King is usurping, and which he would fain work his Subjects
one way or another to acknowledge. The Fanaticks cannot be so far void of sense,
as to think that the person now in the Throne bears them any good will, but his
drift is to screw himself into a Supremacy and Absoluteness over the Law, and to get
such an Authority confessed to be vested in him, as when he pleaseth he may sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert
the established Religion, and set up Popery: for by the same power that he
can dispense with the Penal Statutes against the Nonconformists, he may also dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pense
with those against the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks: and whosoever owneth that he hath
a Right to do the first, doth in effect own that he hath a Right to do the last; for
if he be allowed a Power for the superceding some Laws made in reference to mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
of Religion, he may challenge the like Power for the superceding others of the
same kind: and then by the same Authority that he can suspend the Laws against
Popery, he may also suspend those for Protestancy: and by the same Power that he
can in defiance of Law indulge the Papists the exercise of their Religion in Houses,
he may establish them in the publick celebration of their Idolatry in Churches and
Cathedrals. Yea whereas the Laws that relate to Religion are enacted by no less
Authority than those that are made for the preservation of our Civil Rights, should
the King be admitted to have an Arbitrary Power over the one, it is very like that
by the Logick of <hi>Whitehall</hi> he will challenge the same absoluteness over the other.
Nor do I doubt but that the <hi>eleven Iudges</hi> who have gratified him with a Despoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calness
over the former, will, when required, grant him the same over the latter.
I know the Dissenters are under no small Temptations, both by reason of being
hindred from enjoying the Ordinances of the Gospel, and because of many grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous
Calamities which they daily suffer for their Nonconformity, of making Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications
to the King for some relief, by his suspending the execution of the Laws;
but they must give me leave to add, that they ought not, for the obtaining of a
little ease, to betray the Kingdom, and sacrifice the legal Constitution of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
to the Lust and Pleasure of a Popish Prince, whom nothing less will serve
than being Absolute and Despotical. And were he once in the quiet Possession of
an Authority to dispense with the Penal Laws, the Fanaticks would not long enjoy
the benefit of it. Nor can they deny him a Power of reviving the execution of the
Law, which is part of the Trust deposited with him as supreme Magistrate, who
have granted him a Power of suspending the Laws, which the Rules of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
preclude him from. And as he may, whensoever he pleaseth, cause the Laws
to which they are obnoxious, to be executed upon them, so by virtue of having
an Authority acknowledged in him of superceding the Laws, he may deprive them
of the Liberty of meeting together to the number of Five, a Grace which the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
thought fit to allow them, under all the other Severities to which they were
subjected. Nor needs there any further evidence that the Prince's challenging such
a Power is an Usurpation, and that the Subjects making any Application by which
it seems allowed to him, is a betraying of the ancient Legal Government of the
Kingdom; than to consider that the most obsequious and servile Parliament to the
Court that ever <hi>England</hi> knew, not only denied this Prerogative to the late King, but
made him renounce it by revoking his Declaration of Indulgence, which he had
emitted <hi>Anno</hi> 1672. And as it will be to the perpetual Honor of the Dissenters
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52139:12"/>
to have chosen rather to suffer the Severities which the Laws make them liable unto
than by any Act and Transaction of theirs, to undermine and weaken either the
Church or the State; so it will be a means both of endearing them to future Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
and of bringing them and the Conformists into an union of Counsels and
endeavours against Popery and Tyranny, which is at this season a thing so indispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sably
necessary for their common preservation: especially when, though a new and
more threatning Alliance and Confederacy with <hi>France</hi> than that in 72, the King
hath not only engaged to act by and observe the same measures towards Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants
in <hi>England,</hi> which that Monarch hath vouchsafed the World a Pattern and
Copy of in his carriage towards those of the Reformed Religion in <hi>France;</hi> but
hath promised to disturb the Peace and Repose of his Neighbors, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence
a War in conjunction with that Prince against Foreign Protestants. For as
the Kings giving Liberty and Protection to the <hi>Algerines</hi> to frequent his Havens, and
sell the Prizes which they take from the <hi>Dutch,</hi> is both a most infamous Action for
a Prince pretending to be a Christian, and a direct violation of his Alliance with
the States General; so nothing can be more evident, than that he thereby seeks to
render them the weaker for him to assault, and that he is resolved (if some unfore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seen
and extraordinary Providence doth not interpose and prevent) to declare
War against them the next Summer, in order whereunto great Remises of Mony
are already ordered him from the French Court. So that the Indulgence which he
pretends to be inclinable to afford the Dissenters, is not an effect of kindness and
good Will, but an Artifice whereby to oblige their Assistance in destroying those
abroad of the same Religion with themselves. Which if he can compass, it is
easie to foresee what Fate both the Fanaticks and they of the Communion of the
Church of <hi>England</hi> are to expect. Who as they will not then know whither to
retreat for shelter, so they will be destitute of Comfort in themselves, and depriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
of Pity from others, not only for having through their Divisions made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
a Prey to the Papists at home, but for having been accessary to the ruine
of a Reformed State abroad, and which was the Asilum and Sanctuary of all those
that were elsewhere oppressed and persecuted for Religion.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
