<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A just and righteous plea presented unto the King of England, and his council, &amp;c. being the true state of the present case of the people, called Quakers, truly demonstrated, and justly pleaded, on their behalf : and this is laid down in six particulars ... / by ... Edw. Burroughs.</title>
            <author>Burrough, Edward, 1634-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-08">2004-08 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30531</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B6011</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14916</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12035063</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12035063</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52871</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A30531)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52871)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 861:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A just and righteous plea presented unto the King of England, and his council, &amp;c. being the true state of the present case of the people, called Quakers, truly demonstrated, and justly pleaded, on their behalf : and this is laid down in six particulars ... / by ... Edw. Burroughs.</title>
                  <author>Burrough, Edward, 1634-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Publication information taken from colophon.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52871:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52871:1"/>
            <p>A JUST and RIGHTEOUS
PLEA,
Presented unto the
King of England,
AND HIS
COUNCIL, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>BEING</p>
            <p>The true State of the present Case of the People, called
<hi>QVAKERS,</hi> Truly demonstrated, and Justly pleaded on
their behalf; For the True Information of the KING and
his COUNCIL, That they may well understand the
Truth and Verity of Doubtful Cases, and may shew
Just Judgment and Mercy.</p>
            <p>And this is laid down in Six Particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <head>Viz</head>
               <item>1. <hi>Concerning</hi> Swearing at all, <hi>and particularly of the</hi> Oath
<hi>of</hi> Allegiance.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Concerning</hi> Meeting together <hi>to Worship God.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Concerning</hi> Tythes <hi>among</hi> the Jewes, <hi>and among the</hi>
Christians, <hi>and why we Refuse to pay them at this day.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>Concerning</hi> giving Security by Bond, <hi>to live Peaceably,
or, to Answer</hi> Accusations <hi>then and there,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>5. <hi>Concerning</hi> Government <hi>it self, and particularly of this</hi>
present Government.</item>
               <item>6. <hi>Concerning</hi> Persecution, <hi>what it is in it self, and how
great an Enemy it is to the</hi> King <hi>and his</hi> Government;
<hi>laid down in Ten Particulars.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>All which Cases are truly stated and pleaded, And the Cause of the Innocent
vindicated: And this for the benefit of the King and his Government, that
they may be Just and Righteous, and perfectly according to God.</p>
            <p>By a Friend to Just Authority, <hi>Edw. Borroughs.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:52871:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52871:2"/>
            <head>The Epistle to the King, and his Council.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>OH</hi> Friends! this is your Day, that God hath given you
to try you, and to prove you what you will do, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
you will rule and judge, and exercise your Power
for God, or against him; and this is the hour of your
tryal, and the living God that made Heaven and Earth beholds you,
and his Eye is upon you, and he waits for Iustice, true Iudgment,
Mercy, Righteousness and Truth, to be brought forth by you in the
Land, that he might blesse you and prosper you; but and if the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
be abounding, and brought forth and exercised thorow you,
Blessings shall be turned into a Curse, and the Iust God will deal with
you after your deserts; for the Reward of the Almighty is Iust and
Equal unto all the sons of men, even according to their wayes and
works; and the Iudgment of you nor of any, is determined by Him,
but accordingly as He is served, obeyed and feared, or the contrary.</p>
            <p>And seeing you have a day to do <hi>good,</hi> and to forsake all <hi>evil,</hi> to do
Iustice, Mercy and Truth in the Earth, and to subdue the contrary;
if that you do the things you ought not, and leave undone what God
requires of you to do, and trifle away your time in matters of lesse va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue,
and spend your dayes in Pleasures &amp; Vanities, and neglect Mercy
and Iudgment in the Earth, and have no regard to the Cry of the
Poor and the Oppressed, <hi>to deliver them from their cruel Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi>
if it be thus with you in this your day, Who shall stand in
the Gap to prevent the Anger of the Lord from breaking out? or,
who shall plead for you in the day of your reward, when God himself
ariseth unto Iust Iudgment, to judge all flesh, and to deliver the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent?
Oh Friends! is this nothing to you? Is there no cause unto
you of Consideration in this matter? Ought you not to lay these things
to heart? Why, surely you are but men, and your breath is in your
nostrils, and your substance but dissolvable clay, and the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
and Earth can do what he will with you, and concerning you; if
ye please him, it might be well with you, but if the contrary, he can
answer you doings with an equal reward, and none can prevent him.</p>
            <p>And here is a Cry, and a very great Cry of <hi>Persecution under
your Authority,</hi> the Prisons filled with Vpright and Innocent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,
to the ruine of Persons, Wives and Families, if the great Mercy
<pb facs="tcp:52871:3"/>
of the Lord did not prevent more than the Iustice of men; Thousands
within these few months have been cast into Goals and Dungeons and
nasty holes; and divers have finished their lives, and dyed in Prisons;
many being taken out of their houses, and from their lawful Callings;
and many taken out of Meetings, where they have been waiting upon
God, and cruel Sufferings inflicted upon them, and all this for Truth
and Righteousness sake, and for their profession and Practice in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion;
when as no Plotting or evil-dealing towards the King nor any
of his Subjects, could be justly charged and proved against them. And
thus the Innocent have been made a Prey to Prophane Persons, and
their Sufferings have been woful, and all this under and by your Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority;
And, are these things nothing to you? or, do you judge this
is well doing? Is this Iustice and true Iudgment? Is this for your
Happiness and Prosperity? Let the God of Heaven and Earth judge
in this matter between this <hi>People</hi> and <hi>You,</hi> for the Cry of their
Sufferings are very Loud in the Ears of God, and they have been laid
before you, and you ought to have relieved them, and eased their heavy
burdens, and shewed Iustice, Pity and Love, and this would have
made for your Happiness; But if that you alwayes neglect to hear the
Cry of the Poor, and of the Oppressed, yet God hears, and takes notice;
and though this People should have no Helper in the Earth, yet He
is their Helper, and their Cause is committed unto Him.</p>
            <p>Can these things stand? and, can you be happy in these proceedings,
while the Innocent suffer under you? Is it in your hearts to destroy the
Heritage of God? do you think to extinguish an Innocent People from
off the Earth? Must none wait upon God, and worship Him, and pray
to Him, but after your Prescriptions and Limitations? And will you
kill and destroy all such as do not? who cannot for good Conscience sake
conform to every way of Worship and Religion imposed, but must wait
upon God, and worship Him and pray to Him according as his Spirit
teacheth and guideth; will you, I say, destroy all such? Is it in your
hearts to effect it? if it be, the God of Heaven will not prosper you in
such purposes; Will ye force men to forsake the Way of their God,
wherein they have found his Presence? will ye persecute men for
their Religion-sake, while yet they walk uprightly in their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sations
among men? Oh Friends! it is not Iustice and true Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
thus to do, it pleaseth not God, neither doth it unite the hearts
of Subjects in true Love and Unity, but it hath contrary effects, and
that you may find.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:52871:3"/>
Indeed, according to my judgment, such proceedings are not good
Policy nor humane Wisdom, for you to seek to establish one particular
Perswasion and kind of Religion, and impose that by force, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute
and seek to destroy all the rest that are otherwise minded, if
they will not deny their Principles and Consciences, and conform:
this seems, I say, no good Policy among men; for if it doth gratifie one
sort of men in their desires, it discontenteth and dissatisfieth many
more, and it breaketh Love and Unity amongst Subjects; and your
safety is in the uniting of Peoples hearts to you, and one to another in
Love and Liberty, and not in the Divisions and Distractions of people;
surely this canot be for your safety. When as if you did give Liberty
to all, that were <hi>peaceable in their Lives and Conversations, in
the exercise of their Religion in Faith and Worship to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards;</hi>
this would cause all to love you, and none to be discontented
with you in good reason: If one sort of People had as much Liberty as
others (in the way of their Religion I mean) and none more than
others, this doubtless would encrease Content among Subjects, and be
a blessing to you and your Authority; and to proceed in that way which
may keep the people in Love and Unity one with another, and to you<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,
this were good Policy for your Establishment to perpetuity;
and there seems to be no other way, than in shewing Iustice, Mercy,
and Liberty to all in all right wayes, and in the exercise of their
Consciences towards God. And this is my Iudgment, the way for you
to prosper, is, to leave the prescribing the way of Worship unto God, as
his Spirit shall teach and perswade the Conscience, and to leave the
Iudgment in all Cases of Conscience about Spiritual things, unto
Him, and not to meddle about imposing Religion, nor persecuting
men for that cause, for it is not your place to do it; but you are to
rule well over the outward man, and to judge in the Cases of wrong
between man and man, but not at all in the Cases between God and
mens Consciences.</p>
            <p>But you may say, Who art thou, inferiour man, that seemest to
advise us that are high and potent, and wise enough for our selves?
Well, though it be thus, though I am so, and not much acquainted
with the State-affairs, nor do I profess Policy in the Governments of
this World, yet this I say, What soever my Birth or quality be, and
whether I live or dye, yet these things you must find true one day;
(for I speak not as a <hi>Politician,</hi> but as a <hi>Servant of God</hi>) that your
Prosperity and Happiness in this World, and hereafter, standeth, in
<pb facs="tcp:52871:4"/>
shewing and executing true Iustice and Iudgment, and Mercy and
equal Liberty towards all, without respect of their Title in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession
and Practice of Religion, and in allowing Liberty of Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
in the exercise of Faith and Worship and Duty to God-wards, to
all Christian People, equally in your Dominions, and not to persecute
or destroy any in their Persons and Estates, for the exercise of their
Religion to God-wards: This is the way of your Prosperity, and the
contrary is the way of your Destruction, if that ye persecute men for
their Conscience sake, and exercise Lordship and Authority over
mens Conscience in Spiritual things; and if ye prescribe a way of
Worship, and seek to destroy all that cannot conform thereunto: if ye
do thus, this is not good Policy to establish you. Well, I shall say
little further, but that these things I write not as your Enemy, but
as your Friend, who would have you saved both soul and body, and
not as in any kind of harshness in my spirit towards you do I write,
but in love and compassionateness to you and these Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>And I have here in brief stated and pleaded the Case of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent
People, called <hi>Quakers,</hi> who are at this time under great
Afflictions and Tribulations by your Authority; and it hath been in
my heart divers times to declare the substance of these things unto
you, but at the last I have chosen to write my mind to present to you
concerning the matters very needful for you to be informed in, and it
is for your sakes as well as theirs, that I have done it, that you may
not run on to act any thing against them upon Suspitions and Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sations
of others, without hearing our Defence; And therefore it is
for the avoiding and stopping of <hi>Persecution</hi> in the Land, for this
cause have I taken in hand submissively, and not presumptuously, to
state this <hi>Plea</hi> before you, and I must leave it to your Considerations;
and cannot impose my Faith upon you, to believe as I believe, but
having laid the Truth before you, I shall leave it to the Lord to
work Faith and Love, and Iustice, Mercy, and all good things in
your hearts, that you may bring them forth in the exercise of them
in the World.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am a lover of Justice and Mercy,
Truth and Right<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>usness.
<hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. B.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>London,  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi>10<hi>th day
of the second moneth,</hi>
1661.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52871:4"/>
               <head>CHAP. I. The Case Stated and Pleaded concerning Swearing at all,
and particularly concerning the Oath of Allegiance.</head>
               <p n="I">I. VVE do acknowledge our selves to be Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born
People of this Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi>
the Land of <hi>our Nativity,</hi> and we do <hi>as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert,</hi>
that we have <hi>just</hi> and <hi>lawful Right</hi>
and <hi>Title,</hi> as such, to possess and enjoy <hi>our Lives, Liberties</hi> and
<hi>Estates,</hi> both by the Laws of God and Man; having never unto
this day, since we were a People, <hi>Forfeited</hi> our <hi>Birth-right as
men,</hi> by any <hi>Rebellion, Sedition, Contempt,</hi> or otherwise; but
have <hi>always been</hi> and are a People exercised in the Law of our
God, by walking <hi>justly towards all Men,</hi> and <hi>doing to others as we
would be done unto,</hi> &amp; have been and are a <hi>peaceable People</hi> under
every Government and Authority that hath been over us since
the Lord raised us up; And I do hereby declare, that we <hi>now
are,</hi> and <hi>shall be Faithful, Innocent,</hi> and <hi>Peaceable,</hi> in our seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
Stations and Conditions, under this present Government
of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, whom we acknowledge Supream
<hi>Magistrate</hi> and <hi>Governour</hi> over this Kingdom, and for Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
sake we are obedient and submissive to him, as such, in
all his Commands, either <hi>by doing</hi> and <hi>performing</hi> of what he
justly requireth, or by <hi>patient suffering</hi> under, whatsoever is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted
upon us in the matters for which we cannot be obedient
for Conscience sake, when any thing is required of us different
from the just Law of God: And to this subjection, to the King
and his Government, we are bound by the Law of Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
and such hath ever been our <hi>Principle</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> and is
unto this day, even <hi>to be quiet,</hi> and <hi>peaceable,</hi> and <hi>patient</hi> under
every Authority that is set over us, and not in unrighteousness,
<hi>to Plot,</hi> or <hi>Contrive,</hi> or <hi>Rebel</hi> against any <hi>Governours</hi> or <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:52871:5"/>
nor to seek our own <hi>Deliverance</hi> from <hi>Injustice</hi> and <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression,</hi>
in such a way. And we are perswaded to seek the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation</hi>
of the <hi>King's Person</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> by all <hi>just</hi> and <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
means,</hi> and not to <hi>Rebel</hi> against him with <hi>Carnal Weapons;</hi> and
so far as his Government is in <hi>Iustice, Mercy,</hi> and <hi>Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi>
we declare <hi>true</hi> and <hi>faithful subjection,</hi> and <hi>obedience</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto,
and wherein it is otherwise, we shall be subject by <hi>Patient
suffering,</hi> what is unequally imposed upon us, and yet not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel
in any <hi>Turbulent way</hi> of <hi>Conspiracies,</hi> and <hi>Insurrections;</hi>
For our Principles are not for <hi>War,</hi> but for <hi>Peace</hi> with all
men, so much as in us lyes; neither may we render <hi>evil</hi> for <hi>evil</hi>
to any, but are to be subject to the King and his Government
<hi>actively</hi> or <hi>passively,</hi> upon the Conditions aforementioned. And
we renounce all <hi>Forreign Authority, Power,</hi> and <hi>Iurisdiction,</hi> of
the <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>any else,</hi> from having any <hi>Supremacy</hi> whatsoever
<hi>over the King,</hi> or any the <hi>good Subjects</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> And this we
Declare, Acknowledge, and Testifie, in the Fear and Presence
of God (to whom we and all mankind must give an account)
and that without secret <hi>Equivocation,</hi> or any <hi>deceitful mental
Reservation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="II">II  But as for <hi>all Oaths</hi> and <hi>Swearing,</hi> we utterly <hi>deny,</hi> for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science
sake towards God, because Christ Jesus hath Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
us <hi>not to Swear at all,</hi> Mat. 5. And the Apostle saith,
<hi>Above all things, my brethren, Swear not,</hi> Jam. 5. and it was
the Principle and Practice of divers <hi>Holy Martyrs,</hi> even some
of the <hi>Protestant Church,</hi> since the Apostles days, in all Ages,
<hi>not to Swear at all in any Case:</hi> So for Conscience sake, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the Example of Saints in former Ages, we do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse
to Swear, in this Case of <hi>Allegiance</hi> to the <hi>King,</hi> and in <hi>all
other Cases</hi> whatsoever, and we cannot Swear <hi>at all;</hi> Though the
<hi>truth</hi> and <hi>verity,</hi> of <hi>all Things in all Cases,</hi> so far as known to us,
and as occasion requireth, we can acknowledge and testifie, with
Yea and Nay, as in the Fear and Presence of God, and with
true intent and meaning, to discover the Truth, as is needful
to be known; And in this manner we acknowledge <hi>just Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
to the King,</hi> and his <hi>Government;</hi> (that we shall live <hi>peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably,</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:52871:5"/>
and not <hi>Plot,</hi> nor <hi>Rebel</hi> against <hi>Him</hi>) according to the
Law of God and a safe Conscience; But without <hi>any Oath</hi> or
<hi>Swearing at all,</hi> for we may not break the Command of Christ,
nor walk contrary to the Example of the Apostles and Saints
by <hi>Swearing,</hi> though we suffer the loss <hi>of all</hi> because thereof;
And it is our known <hi>Principle</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> ever since we were
a People, that in <hi>no Case</hi> whatsoever, though of great <hi>dependancy</hi>
oft-times <hi>to our selves,</hi> both in respect of <hi>Advantage</hi> to us, and
also in avoiding of <hi>Sufferings,</hi> we have not taken <hi>any Oath,</hi> nor
<hi>Sworn at all;</hi> whereby it is manifest that our refusing chiefly to
take the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> is not because it is <hi>that Oath,</hi> but
because it is <hi>an Oath,</hi> and for Conscience sake we cannot
Swear <hi>at all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="III">III. And thus the state of our present Case about this <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance,</hi>
is different from some others, from all such who can
<hi>Swear</hi> and <hi>take Oathes</hi> in other Cases, to whom taking of an
<hi>Oath</hi> in it self is not matter of Conscience; but as for us, we
make Conscience of <hi>an Oath</hi> in it self, and that upon just
ground, as we are able to demonstrate, and therefore our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusal
of <hi>this Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> gives no ground at all, of doubt
or suspition, concerning us, as if we would not live <hi>peaceably</hi>
and <hi>quietly</hi> under this Government, or as if we would <hi>Rebel</hi>
against, or <hi>plot</hi> to destroy the <hi>King's Person</hi> or <hi>Authority,</hi> and so
denie to take <hi>this Oath,</hi> as if we would leave our selves clear to
proceed in such wayes; this Judgement cannot justly be given of
us, because <hi>we deny to Swear at all, in all Cases,</hi> which if it were not
<hi>so,</hi> but that we could <hi>Swear in other Cases,</hi> and not <hi>in this,</hi> then
we might be the more justly suspected that we had a reserve
against the King's <hi>Person</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> and our living <hi>Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,</hi>
might be the more doubted of; but being our <hi>known Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple</hi>
and <hi>practice</hi> always, not <hi>to Swear at all</hi> in any Case whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,
this removes <hi>all ground</hi> of <hi>Iealousie,</hi> or <hi>cause</hi> of <hi>Suspition</hi> of
us in this Case, and also we being ready to confess, <hi>all just Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi>
and <hi>Power</hi> to the <hi>King,</hi> to declare <hi>Obedience</hi> thereunto <hi>so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly</hi>
and <hi>sincerely,</hi> and that we shall live <hi>peaceable</hi> and <hi>quietly</hi>
under his Government, and not to <hi>Plot</hi> or <hi>Rebel</hi> against him,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52871:6"/>
and this to Confirm by <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay:</hi> Our Testimony of this
kind, may as justly be taken, and stand as effectual, and be as
faithfully performed, as the Oathes of any others; for we
make Conscience to perform what we say in <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay,</hi>
as much as any do to perform what they Swear, and this is
known of us in the Consciences of our Enemies; So that in
good Conscience and just Reason, and equal Justice, we are
excusable from all <hi>Penalties</hi> and <hi>Forfeitures</hi> in that behalf, of
denying the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="IV">IV. And the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Government</hi> is not the <hi>less safe</hi> and <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure,</hi>
though we refuse <hi>to swear Obedience to them,</hi> nor could they
be any <hi>safer</hi> or <hi>securer,</hi> if we, contrary to our Principles and
Consciences were forced by Penalties <hi>to Swear Allegiance;</hi> for
by the same Principle which keeps us <hi>from Swearing,</hi> and by
which we <hi>deny it,</hi> we must be <hi>preserved</hi> to live <hi>peaceably,</hi> and not
to <hi>Plot</hi> nor <hi>Rebel</hi> against the King; and if we renounce our Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple
and our good Conscience, and be induced to <hi>Swear</hi> against
our Consciences; what likelyhood is there to perform such a
forced <hi>Oath,</hi> taken contrary to our Consciences and Principles?
For if we <hi>Swear</hi> to the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Government,</hi> because of the
fear of men and to save our Estates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and this contrary to
our Conscience, it might well be suspected of us, that at oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity
we would <hi>break such Oathes,</hi> for fear of men or some
self end: On the other hand, if we had already renounced our
good Consciences, so that it more appears, we shall perform
good Obedience to the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Government</hi> acknowledged
by <hi>Yea,</hi> without an <hi>Oath,</hi> and in good Conscience; then by
swearing forced on us, contrary to our Consciences; therefore
<hi>our Yea</hi> may better be accepted in this Case, then <hi>Swearing</hi> can
be demanded of us: And also if we should <hi>change</hi> with the
<hi>Times,</hi> and <hi>renounce</hi> our Principles and Consciences, and <hi>Swear,</hi>
we should make our selves <hi>ridiculous</hi> and a <hi>scorn</hi> to all men, and
bring our selves into a capacity not ever to be trusted in any
Case, if we should <hi>bow</hi> and <hi>bend</hi> to <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Powers,</hi> and
for terrour of men, deny our Religion, as other Hypocrites,
And I very well believe that the King would not trust us in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52871:6"/>
our <hi>Albegiance</hi> any whit <hi>the better,</hi> but rather the <hi>worse,</hi> though
we did <hi>swear, fawn</hi> and <hi>flatter</hi> with him, contrary to our Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples;
neither could he reasonably judge himself the safer, not
more happy, not that we would be truly subject the more to his
Authority, if we <hi>swote</hi> and conformed in things by force, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
to our Consciences and Principles; for himself knows,
that <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Engagements</hi> made and taken by <hi>force,</hi> and for
<hi>fear,</hi> in <hi>straits,</hi> are seldom or never truly performed, but
alwayes broken. And of the like case there are large Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies
in the Kingdom, of many that have <hi>sworn, promised,</hi> and
<hi>engaged,</hi> and sometimes by <hi>force</hi> and <hi>fear,</hi> to this kind of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
and another; and yet at opportunies, and for their
own self-ends, have broken all <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Engagements,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled
against the very <hi>Persons</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> to which they
have <hi>sworn</hi> and <hi>engaged Fidelity</hi> and <hi>Allegiance;</hi> so that many
are not the more to be trusted, though they swear <hi>Allegiance:</hi>
for, the Proverb saith, <hi>He that will Swear, will Lye:</hi> and he
that is <hi>forced</hi> to <hi>swear</hi> against his Conscience, will hardly <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form</hi>
his <hi>Oath:</hi> And we are no less to be trusted, though we
<hi>swear not,</hi> for we never yet <hi>engaged</hi> our selves by <hi>Oath,</hi> to any
Governours or Government, and yet we never <hi>rebelled</hi> or
<hi>plotted</hi> against any, but have lived <hi>peaceably,</hi> and in a <hi>patient
suffering condition</hi> under all, that have sitten on the Throne since
we were a People: And therefore out living peaceably under
the King's Government cannot justly be doubted of, though
we cannot engage the same <hi>by swearing:</hi> But yet if we do not
live quietly and in good obedience, as peaceable People, but
do <hi>rebel, plot, &amp;c.</hi> then we refuse not to suffer the Pains, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties
and Forfeitures, as such that Swear and do not perform
their Oaths; I say, if we do not <hi>live peaceably,</hi> but <hi>plot</hi> and
<hi>rebel</hi> against the King and his Government, then let us suffer
the same in <hi>every particular,</hi> as if we had <hi>sworn;</hi> and <hi>not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed</hi>
our Oath.</p>
               <p n="V">V. All these things rightly considered, it doth fully appear,
1. That we are <hi>not Enemies,</hi> neither in present <hi>Action,</hi> nor
future <hi>Intent,</hi> to the <hi>King's Person</hi> or <hi>Authority.</hi> 2. Nor that
we refuse to acknowledge <hi>Iust Authority to King Charles</hi> the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52871:7"/>
                  <hi>Second,</hi> as Supream Magistrate over these Kingdoms. 3. Nor
doth it appear, that we are otherwise than <hi>Peaceable</hi> and <hi>Quiet</hi>
People under the <hi>King's Government.</hi> 4. Nor is it manifest,
but that we are ready to acknowledge so to continue, in all
good Conscience and Righteousness: And therefore we do
appeal to the <hi>God of Heaven,</hi> and to <hi>King Charles,</hi> and to
<hi>all People</hi> whatsoever, That our present Sufferings by <hi>Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonment,</hi>
and whatsoever else we may suffer in this Case, for
Refusing to take the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Alleagiance,</hi> it is not for <hi>Plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi>
against the <hi>King,</hi> nor for refusing to acknowledge <hi>Iust
Authority</hi> to the <hi>King,</hi> nor for denying <hi>Iust Obedience</hi> to him
and the <hi>Good Laws</hi> of the Land, nor for denying to live <hi>peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably</hi>
in the Kingdom under the <hi>King's Authority;</hi> Because to
all this we acknowledge solemnly in <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay:</hi> Neither
are our Sufferings in this case, for any <hi>Evil-doing</hi> towards God
nor Men; but our Sufferings are <hi>for keeping</hi> the Commands
of Christ, which to us is matter of Conscience to perform,
more than to save our own Lives or Estates; and our Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
are, because we <hi>cannot Swear at all,</hi> and not because we
are <hi>Rebellious,</hi> or that we <hi>deny Iust Allegiance</hi> to the King:
and such our Sufferings are not as <hi>Evil-doers,</hi> nor justly and
righteously as <hi>Offenders;</hi> because we are not guilty of Evil in
this case, towards <hi>God</hi> nor <hi>Man,</hi> and our Sufferings are <hi>Cruel
Persecution</hi> for our <hi>Tender Conscience sake,</hi> and for the <hi>Name
of Christ Iesus:</hi> And we call God and Just Men to witnesse
between <hi>Us</hi> and our <hi>Prosecutors,</hi> that as <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants
of God we suffer</hi> in this Case, and for our <hi>Faithfulnesse</hi>
and <hi>Obedience</hi> to the <hi>King of Heaven,</hi> and not for <hi>Evil-doing</hi>
or <hi>Disobedience</hi> to King <hi>Charles</hi> and his Authority: And if any
be persecuted in this case, for Refusing <hi>to take the Oath of
Allegiance,</hi> to the Ruine of <hi>Persons, Wives</hi> and <hi>Families</hi> in this
World; then we shall have cause to say, <hi>Occasion is wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
taken against us, to destroy us,</hi> and we are proceeded
against, contrary to the End of <hi>Iust Government,</hi> which is, to
<hi>preserve</hi> the Peaceable, and not to <hi>destroy</hi> them; and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
to the King's <hi>former Promises,</hi> who hath said, <hi>VVe should
not suffer for matters of our Religion and Conscience, living
peaceably in the Land;</hi> And if we suffer, because we cannot
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52871:7"/>
                  <hi>swear at all,</hi> such our Suffering is for our Conscience sake, and
we are therein persecuted unrighteously, as <hi>Innocent People,</hi>
and without <hi>just cause;</hi> And we must commit this our Cause
to God, who regardeth the Oppressions of his People, and
will avenge their Cause in his season. And for the present
this is all I have to say, and present, concerning this <hi>Case of
Swearing,</hi> and concerning the <hi>Oath of Allegiance.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. The Case stated and pleaded, concerning our Meeting
together to Worship God.</head>
               <p n="I">I. VVE do <hi>meet</hi> together in the Name of <hi>Iesus Christ,</hi> and
in his <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Spirit;</hi> and we do <hi>Come together</hi> in
the Fear of God, to wait upon Him, and to receive the
Teachings of his Holy Spirit, and his Counsel to direct us
in all our wayes, how to walk righteously towards God and
Men; and in our Meetings we practise our hearts and minds
in Godliness, and speak of the things of the Kingdom of God,
in Preaching the Word of God, and in Prayer to Him, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
as His holy Spirit guideth us, which is given us of God,
to lead us <hi>into all Truth,</hi> according to his Promise, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16. 13.
and that we may edifie one another in the wayes of Holiness
and Truth, for the benefit of our Souls: and this is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the Scriptures: <hi>For they that feared the Lord met
often together, and spake one to another, and edified one another:</hi>
And this is our Principle, That it is our Duty to Godwards,
to meet together, and that he requires it of us, and for the
exercise of our Consciences to Him, it hath been alwayes and
is our practice, to meet together in the exercise of the Worship
of God, as aforesaid, and not for any other end; as in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
of Authority,</hi> or to <hi>plot,</hi> or <hi>contrive,</hi> or to <hi>meditate Evil</hi>
towards the King or his Government, or any of his Subjects;
We have no such e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l (I say) in meeting together; but our
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52871:8"/>
alone, only, and absolute End in our Meeting, is to worship
the Lord our God, and to serve Him, and to wait upon Him,
in Obedience to his Will, and for good Conscience sake, as our
Duty towards Him.</p>
               <p n="II">II. And this our practice of <hi>Meeting together,</hi> for the End and
Cause mentioned, if it be in <hi>Publick Houses,</hi> or more <hi>private</hi> in
<hi>Upper Chambers,</hi> or in the <hi>Open Fields</hi> on <hi>what day soever,</hi> is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
and just in the sight of God, and is according to  the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
of the Primitive Saints, and provable by the Scriptures,
As in <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 13, 14. <hi>And when the Disciples and Saints returned
from</hi> Jerusalem, <hi>they went up into an Upper Chamber, both Men
and VVomen, and waited upon the Lord, and continued with one
accord, in Prayer and in Supplication.</hi> And in <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 7, 8.
<hi>The first day of the week the Saints met together, and</hi> Paul <hi>prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
unto them, and continued his Sermon till midnight; holding
forth the matters of the Kingdom of God; and they were met an
an Vpper. Chamber, from whence</hi> Eutychus <hi>fell down.</hi> And <hi>Acts</hi>
28. 30, 31. <hi>And</hi> Paul <hi>remained two fall years, preaching the
Gospel of the Kingdom of God, in his own hired house in</hi> Rome;
<hi>and he exhorted the Saints, not to neglect meeting together, as the
manner of some was, whom he reproved,</hi> Heb. 10. 25. By which
Testimonies, with divers others that might be given, it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest,
that the Saints of God in former Ages, <hi>did meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
to worship God, and to wait upon Him in <hi>Prayer</hi> &amp; <hi>Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching,</hi>
as the Spirit of the Father taught them, that dwelt in
them: And sometime they met <hi>publickly,</hi> and sometime more
<hi>private;</hi> and sometime on the <hi>day-time,</hi> and sometime in the
<hi>night-season,</hi> (and they met separate from the Synagogues and
wayes of publick Worship of the <hi>Iews</hi>) according to the Will
of God, and as it was ordered among them: And thus it is
manifest, that our Meetings for the Worship of God at this
day (though they are separate from the way of publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship
of the Kingdom, and are in more private houses) are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifiable,
being after the Example of the Saints, and according
to the Scriptures of Truth; and therefore out Meetings are
according to the Law of God, just and lawful.</p>
               <p n="III">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:52871:8"/>III. And forasmuch as by reason of the late <hi>Insurrection</hi> of some
few persons in <hi>London,</hi> our lawful Assembling of our selves
together in the Worship of God, is under <hi>present restraint</hi> and
<hi>prohibition,</hi> and by Proclamation forbidden, under the deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination
of <hi>Seditious</hi> and <hi>Unlawful Meetings,</hi> and our Friends
<hi>Imprisoned</hi> and <hi>Persecuted</hi> for that cause of Assembling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
to wait upon God. Now in this Case, this I plead un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the King, That we are no manner of way <hi>guilty</hi> of that <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection,</hi>
upon which the Proclamatian of forbidding our
Meetings was grounded; and therefore ought not to suffer
with the guilty, being innocent from the very <hi>occasion</hi> of that
Proclamation; and for the King to prohibit our Meetings, for
and because of the <hi>ill use</hi> that others made of theirs, this seems
a <hi>Condemning</hi> of the <hi>Innocent</hi> with the <hi>Guilty,</hi> which is no way
just in the sight of God nor Men, but altogether <hi>unequal</hi> that
we should suffer for <hi>other ments faults;</hi> though such did abuse
their <hi>Liberty,</hi> and pervert the end of their <hi>Meetings</hi> into
rising up with <hi>Carnal Weapons</hi> against the King; so did not we,
neither in <hi>intent</hi> nor <hi>action;</hi> and therefore our Meetings ought
not to be <hi>prohibited,</hi> for the cause of other mens <hi>faults</hi> and <hi>mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages</hi>
in that case; And also we have the <hi>King's Promise,</hi>
divers times, <hi>That we should not suffer for our Religion,
while we aded nothing against the Peace of the Kingdom and
Government;</hi> which yet we never have done, nor made any
<hi>ill use</hi> of our <hi>Meetings,</hi> nor of the <hi>King's Promises,</hi> nor forfeited
them, and therefore, according to his <hi>own Promises,</hi> we ought
to have our <hi>Meetings,</hi> and enjoy them <hi>without restraint,</hi> because
we have not <hi>farfeited</hi> the benefit of his former <hi>Promises</hi> in that
behalf, nor ever made use of our Meetings, to <hi>plot</hi> or <hi>conspire</hi>
against the <hi>Government,</hi> to its harm or detriment; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
of our innocency herein, the benefit of his former Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises,
are yet in force unto us, to protect our lawful Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
and not to prohibit them; and though upon <hi>suspition on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi>
out Meetings have been <hi>Restrained,</hi> and our Friends <hi>Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned</hi>
by the late <hi>Proclamation;</hi> yet we being proved <hi>innocent,</hi>
and without <hi>guilt</hi> of that which occasioned it, the <hi>King</hi> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52871:9"/>
                  <hi>Council</hi> may and ought in Justice and good Reason, to <hi>Reverse</hi>
and <hi>Revoke</hi> that part of the <hi>Proclamation</hi> related to us, as being
<hi>innocent,</hi> that we may <hi>enjoy our lawful Meetings,</hi> according to
the Scriptures and Example of Saints, and according to the
<hi>King's</hi> own <hi>former Promises.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="IV">IV. All these things considered and rightly understood by the
<hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Council,</hi> it will appear unto them, in good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,
1. That our <hi>Meetings</hi> are <hi>just</hi> and <hi>lawful</hi> in themselves,
because they are for the Worship of the Lord God, and to
wait upon Him. 2. They are according to the Example of
the Apostles, because the Scriptures prove the like Meetings.
3. And they are not contrary to his <hi>own Promises,</hi> and <hi>Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
that he gave for six Months after his coming in, Because
he said, <hi>VVe should not suffer for our Religion, if we lived
peaceably;</hi> and we were not disturbed by Authority from him
(that we know of) in our Meetings, till this occasion. 4. It
will appear, That we ought in <hi>Iustice</hi> and <hi>Equity</hi> to have our
<hi>lawful Meetings</hi> protected and preserved by the <hi>King's Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi>
and not <hi>prohibited;</hi> because we are not guilty of that which
occasioned this present <hi>Restraint:</hi> but what we have suffered
in this case, it hath been upon <hi>suspition,</hi> and without any <hi>just
cause</hi> on our part: And for these Ends and Causes I plead on
the behalf of the <hi>Innocent,</hi> that we may enjoy peaceably our
<hi>Meetings</hi> for the exercise of God's Worship, and not be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited
in the King's Dominions under his Authority.</p>
               <p n="V">V. But and if we are <hi>persecuted</hi> and <hi>imprisoned,</hi> and made to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
for this Cause of <hi>Meeting together,</hi> to worship God and
wait upon Him, in Conscience and Duty towards Him; and
for following the Scriptures Example, as the Saints of old, as
afore-mentioned; we must only commit our <hi>Cause</hi> to the <hi>God</hi>
of Heaven, and in <hi>patience</hi> suffer under whatsoever is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equally
inflicted upon us for this matter, if men shew the
<hi>height of Oppression</hi> towards us; and we must put on the spirit
of <hi>Long-suffering</hi> and <hi>Forbearance,</hi> and leave <hi>Vengeance</hi> to the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52871:9"/>
Lord, who will in his season redress our Cause, if that we are
persecuted for meeting together, and for worshipping of the
Lord, according as his Spirit perswades our Consciences;
and such our Sufferings are, not for <hi>evil-doing,</hi> not as <hi>Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressors</hi>
against God nor the King, but as Servants of God
we suffer, and for holding the Testimony of JESUS, and
a good Conscience. And thus I have brought the state of
our Case, as concerning our Meetings, unto the Kings know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
and must leave it to his <hi>serious view;</hi> and happy will
he be if he hath regard to the Afflicted; but if he stop his
Ear from the Cry of the Poor, and suffer them to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed,
who shall plead for him, or excuse him in the Day
of the Lord, when He comes to Judgement, to reward every
man according to his deeds.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. The Case stated and pleaded concerning Tythes, as paid
among the Jews, and also among the Christians; and
the Cause why we refuse to pay them at this day.</head>
               <p n="I">I. VVE do acknowledge that <hi>Tythes,</hi> as instituted, given,
and received in the Law of <hi>Moses,</hi> amongst the
<hi>Iews,</hi> and according to the Commandment of God, were of
<hi>Heavenly Ordination,</hi> and were for that <hi>Holy Use</hi> and <hi>End,</hi> of
maintaining the <hi>Levitical Priesthood,</hi> and the <hi>Poor,</hi> the <hi>Widows,</hi>
and the <hi>Strangers</hi> in <hi>Israel:</hi> and we know that whilest that
Livitical Priesthood of <hi>Signs,</hi> and <hi>Types,</hi> and <hi>Figures</hi> was
yet <hi>unfinished</hi> and <hi>unfulfilled</hi> by Christ Jesus the Everlasting
Priest, That Law that gave and received Tythes was in force,
and it was sinful against God, and contrary to his Law, in any
of <hi>Israel</hi> to withhold their <hi>Tythes,</hi> and not to pay them, and
such as did, robbed God and the Poor, and the Prophet
complained against them; for then the Ordination of <hi>Tythes</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:52871:10"/>
was of God, and the Practise and End of them was good and
blessed; But that Law and Priesthood, that gave and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
them, is finished and ended, with all the <hi>Types</hi> and <hi>Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows</hi>
of the <hi>first Covenant,</hi> Heb. 7. 12. and <hi>Christ Iesus</hi> the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting
<hi>Priest</hi> of God, is come, in whom is ended the <hi>first Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood</hi>
that took <hi>Tythes,</hi> and that Law that gave them, and he
hath put an end to <hi>Tythes, Temple, Priests-Office,</hi> under the Law
among the <hi>Iews,</hi> and all <hi>outward Types</hi> and <hi>Figures,</hi> and <hi>first Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi>
and is an <hi>High Priest</hi> for ever, and the <hi>everlasting Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance</hi>
of all <hi>Shadows</hi> pertaining to the <hi>first Covenant,</hi> and hath
finished them, and ended them; even that Law and Ordinance
that gave and received <hi>Tythes,</hi> and that <hi>Priesthood</hi> to whom
<hi>Tythes</hi> pertained, so that though it was <hi>unlawful</hi> in the <hi>first Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi>
to withhold the payment of <hi>Tythes,</hi> yet that <hi>Covenant</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
ended, and <hi>that Law</hi> and <hi>Priesthood,</hi> and another <hi>Covenant</hi>
and <hi>Priesthood</hi> established, to whom the Law of God allows not
the <hi>Tythes</hi> of mens estates, it seems now to be unlawful to <hi>pay,
receive,</hi> or <hi>demand Tythes,</hi> and for good Conscience sake we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
do it.</p>
               <p n="II">II.We cannot now <hi>pay Tythes</hi> according to the <hi>first Covenant,</hi>
nor uphold any part of the <hi>first Priesthood,</hi> that stood in <hi>Types</hi>
and <hi>Shadows,</hi> nor submit to that Law, by any obedience to it,
which one <hi>gave</hi> and <hi>received Tythes;</hi> Seeing <hi>Iesus Christ</hi> is
come in the flesh, who hath ended all <hi>that Covenant,</hi> with every
thing that <hi>pertained thereunto;</hi> and we believe in <hi>Iesus Christ</hi> as
the everlasting <hi>substance,</hi> and receive the <hi>Law,</hi> by which we
walk, in all things <hi>from him,</hi> and not <hi>from Abraham,</hi> nor <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses:</hi>
For he <hi>is with us,</hi> who is greater <hi>then they,</hi> whose <hi>Law</hi>
and <hi>Example</hi> we must follow, in the Administration of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,
and not the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Example</hi> of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Moses,</hi> in
the <hi>first Covenant,</hi> who did but prophesie of <hi>Christ,</hi> and did not
witness him fully come, but died in the Faith; Now if we
should pay <hi>Tythes</hi> according to the <hi>first Covenant,</hi> and so uphold
any part of that <hi>Priesthood</hi> which took <hi>Tythes,</hi> which was but <hi>a
Type</hi> of Christ the everlasting Priest, then we should deny
<hi>Iesus Christ</hi> to be come in the flesh, and turn back again to the
<hi>Law,</hi> and to the <hi>Iewes Ordinances,</hi> and prove our selves <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:52871:10"/>
and <hi>Antichristian;</hi> for he that denies <hi>Christ</hi> to be come
in the Flesh, is of <hi>Antichrist, 1 Iohn</hi> 4. 3. and we may as well
turn back to <hi>Circumcision, Sacrifices,</hi> and <hi>Burnt-offerings,</hi> as to
<hi>pay Tythes,</hi> being all pertaining to the <hi>first Covenant,</hi> and <hi>Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi>
which whomsoever doth uphold, denieth <hi>Iesus Christ</hi> to
be come in the Flesh, and so are of <hi>Antichrist;</hi> but we believe
<hi>Christ</hi> is come, and we have received him, as the <hi>end</hi> and <hi>finishing</hi>
of the <hi>first Priesthood,</hi> and we believe <hi>in him,</hi> as the everlasting
<hi>Sustance,</hi> who hath put an <hi>end</hi> to <hi>Tythes, Temples, Burnt-offerings,
&amp;c.</hi> And we confess <hi>unto him</hi> as our <hi>Iudge</hi> and <hi>Law-giver,</hi> and
have renounced <hi>all shadowes</hi> pertaining to the <hi>first Covenant,</hi>
whereof one <hi>was Tythes,</hi> and for Conscience sake, and that we
may continue in the Faith of <hi>Christ,</hi> the <hi>Substance,</hi> and not deny
him, therefore it is that we refuse, and cannot <hi>pay Tythes,</hi> for
we are <hi>Christians</hi> and <hi>Believers,</hi> and not <hi>Iewes,</hi> nor Children of
the <hi>first Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="III">III. And there is <hi>no Example</hi> by any of the <hi>Apostles</hi> or <hi>Saints,</hi> in
all the new Testament, that ever any of the Christians that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved
in <hi>Iesus Christ, gave, paid,</hi> or <hi>received Tythes;</hi> I say, there
is <hi>no Example</hi> at all, by either <hi>Precept</hi> or <hi>Practice,</hi> left us on re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord,
that any of the Ministers of the Gospel, in the <hi>Apostles</hi>
days, did <hi>pay</hi> or <hi>receive Tythes,</hi> for any <hi>Ministerial Office</hi> nor
otherwise; But we do believe, that none of the Christians
in the <hi>first</hi> nor <hi>second Age</hi> after <hi>Christ,</hi> since his Resurrection, did
<hi>Institute, Pay,</hi> or <hi>Receive Tythes</hi> as Maintenance of <hi>Gospel Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry;</hi>
but we believe that the <hi>Ministers of Christ</hi> whom he sent
forth to preach the Gospel after his Ascention, did bear witness
to the <hi>new Covenant,</hi> and to <hi>Iesus Christ</hi> the <hi>Substance,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<hi>Temple, Sacrifices, Tythes,</hi> and <hi>first Priesthood,</hi> and the
worship of the <hi>first Covenant,</hi> and said, <hi>that Covenant was found
faulty and none could attain perfection, as pertaining to the Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi>
in it, and therefore God took <hi>that Covenant</hi> away, that he
might establish <hi>a better,</hi> Heb. 8. 6, 7. Heb. 6. 19. And also
divers of the <hi>Holy Martyrs</hi> since the <hi>Apostles</hi> days, as <hi>William
Thorpe,</hi> and <hi>others,</hi> did Preach down <hi>Tythes,</hi> and denied the
<hi>Payment</hi> of them, and for Conscience sake to God, could nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<hi>give</hi> nor <hi>receive Tythes,</hi> but fully witnessed against them,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52871:11"/>
though they suffered for it in their days; So that,</p>
               <p>1. We have no <hi>Example</hi> from the <hi>Apostles</hi> nor <hi>Christians</hi> in
their dayes, to <hi>pay Tithes,</hi> but rather the <hi>Contrary;</hi> for
we have Testimony from them, that the <hi>first Covenant</hi>
and <hi>Priesthood,</hi> with all <hi>Shadowes</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> thereunto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing
(whereof <hi>Tythes</hi> was one) were <hi>disanulled, finished,</hi> and
<hi>ended</hi> by the coming of <hi>Christ;</hi> and <hi>a new Covenant established,</hi>
in which nothing is signified of <hi>paying Tythes:</hi> From whence
it may appear to all, <hi>that Tythes</hi> are <hi>ended,</hi> and not to be <hi>payed</hi>
in the <hi>new Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. We have <hi>clear Example</hi> from the <hi>Martyrs</hi> since the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles</hi>
days, <hi>not to pay Tythes;</hi> for divers of the <hi>Protestant Martyrs,</hi>
(called the <hi>Fathers</hi> of their Church) did witness <hi>against Tythes,</hi>
and refused <hi>to pay</hi> any.</p>
               <p>3. We believe in our own Consciences, <hi>That Tythes,</hi> as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived,
and payed in these dayes, are not of any <hi>Institution of
God,</hi> nor exercised <hi>to any good use and end,</hi> but that they are of
<hi>Antichrist,</hi> and <hi>Oppression,</hi> and <hi>unjust Exactions,</hi> and <hi>Impositions</hi>
upon the poor People of these Kingdoms; and therefore we
do refuse <hi>to pay Tythes,</hi> and we cannot for good Conscience
sake; and the exercise of our Consciences herein in denying <hi>to
pay Tythes,</hi> is well and lawfully grounded upon the <hi>Coming of
Christ,</hi> and upon the <hi>Example</hi> of the <hi>Apostles</hi> and <hi>Martyrs.</hi> And
thus in brief I have shewed concerning <hi>Tythes,</hi> and why
we refuse to pay them, and the matter of our Consciences in
that Case.</p>
               <p n="IV">IV. As for <hi>Tythes,</hi> as now <hi>demanded, paid,</hi> and <hi>received,</hi> in these
Kingdoms, we know they are not of <hi>heavenly Institution,</hi> nor
for a <hi>good use</hi> and <hi>end</hi> ordained and practised, but as they are
now paid, both in these Kingdoms, and through Christendom,
they are of <hi>Popish Institution,</hi> and were <hi>first ordained, paid,</hi> and
<hi>received</hi> by the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and were <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equally</hi>
imposed upon the Nations through her <hi>Authority,</hi> for the
<hi>use</hi> and <hi>end</hi> to <hi>maintain</hi> her <hi>Priests,</hi> and <hi>Clergy,</hi> and <hi>Church;</hi> and
the <hi>Instituiion,</hi> and payment of <hi>Tythes</hi> among <hi>Christians,</hi> was
not till near 400 <hi>Years</hi> after <hi>Christ,</hi> as <hi>Historians</hi> say; and for
divers Ages after that, there were no <hi>Lawes</hi> enjoyning and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52871:11"/>
forcing the <hi>payment</hi> of them, not till about the Year 786. that
<hi>Pope Adrian</hi> the <hi>first,</hi> sent <hi>two Legates into England,</hi> to make a
<hi>Decree, that the People of two Kingdoms</hi> (to wit) <hi>Merc-land</hi> and
<hi>Northumberland, should pay Tythes.</hi> By these and other Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies
it is manifest, that the <hi>Payment of Tythes</hi> amongst <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,</hi>
had their <hi>first Original</hi> from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> and by
<hi>Succession</hi> from thence, and not from the <hi>Apostles</hi> are <hi>Tythes
paid, given,</hi> and <hi>received</hi> at this day in these Kingdoms; and
the <hi>Institution, payment,</hi> and <hi>use,</hi> and <hi>end</hi> of them is not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to the Law of <hi>Moses</hi> at all: for <hi>Tythes,</hi> as then amongst the
<hi>Iewes, ordained,</hi> and <hi>payd,</hi> were for the happy use, to <hi>feed</hi> the
<hi>Poor,</hi> the <hi>Widows</hi> and the <hi>Fatherless</hi> in <hi>Israel,</hi> that there should
not be <hi>a Beggar amongst them:</hi> But the <hi>use</hi> and <hi>end</hi> of the <hi>payment</hi>
of them <hi>now</hi> in these dayes, is for the maintaining <hi>a company of
Priests,</hi> in their <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>fulness,</hi> and the <hi>poor</hi> and the <hi>strangers
may starve,</hi> and lie <hi>begging up and down</hi> at the <hi>corners of the streets;</hi>
So that we cannot for conscience sake at this day <hi>pay Tythes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. Because the first <hi>Institution</hi> of them among <hi>Christians,</hi> was
not <hi>from Heaven,</hi> nor from <hi>Christ Iesus,</hi> nor his <hi>Apostles,</hi> but <hi>from
the Pope</hi> and <hi>Church of Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. Because the <hi>use</hi> and <hi>end</hi> of <hi>Tythes</hi> is not according <hi>to God,</hi>
nor <hi>Righteousness,</hi> but for the maintaining the <hi>Priests</hi> in <hi>pride,</hi>
and <hi>fulness,</hi> and their <hi>Families;</hi> and in the mean time the <hi>Poor</hi>
want.</p>
               <p>3. Because the <hi>continued payment</hi> of them, is <hi>exaction</hi> and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position,</hi>
contrary to the <hi>Gospel</hi> of <hi>liberty</hi> and <hi>peace,</hi> upon the <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,
estates,</hi> and <hi>consciences,</hi> of many good People in these King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes.</p>
               <p n="V">V. All these things rightly and justly considered, it is manifest,
and plainly apparent to all good men, that this matter of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying
<hi>to pay Tythes,</hi> is a <hi>clear case</hi> of <hi>Conscience</hi> with us, and that
we have sufficient ground to make conscience hereof, and for
good conscience sake we may <hi>justly</hi> refuse and deny <hi>to pay Tythes;</hi>
and the exercise of our Consciences herein, is bottomed upon
a <hi>right foundation,</hi> as I have made appear, and it is not for <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tousness</hi>
to our selves, nor in <hi>contempt</hi> of <hi>Authority,</hi> nor in <hi>will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness</hi>
to wrong any man of his <hi>Iust right,</hi> nor for any other
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52871:12"/>
                  <hi>evil end,</hi> that we do refuse <hi>to pay Tythes;</hi> but it is for <hi>Conscience
sake,</hi> only &amp; alone for that end, that we may keep <hi>our Consciences
clear</hi> in the sight of God, by our <hi>Faithfulness</hi> in denying of
what we are convinced of <hi>to be evil</hi> and not of God, as I have
shewed, we are in this case of <hi>Tythes;</hi> and we dare not sin
against God by disobedience to him, nor uphold the payment
of <hi>Tythes</hi> in these Kingdoms, which are so <hi>evil,</hi> both in their
<hi>Ordination,</hi> and in their <hi>Use</hi> and <hi>End,</hi> as paid in these dayes, as
I have shewed; for if we should, we might offend <hi>his Spirit,</hi>
and our <hi>own Consciences,</hi> and bring anguish upon <hi>our Souls,</hi> and
be guilty of <hi>denying of Christ</hi> and his <hi>Coming,</hi> and of making
void the <hi>New Covenant;</hi> and of walking contrary to the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples</hi>
of the <hi>Apostles</hi> and <hi>holy Martyrs,</hi> and of upholding <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist</hi>
and his Kingdom: These, with many other Evils, we
run our selves into, if we should <hi>pay Tythes</hi> in these dayes, and
after the <hi>Romish Institution;</hi> and therefore it is for Conscience
sake that we do refuse to <hi>pay Tythes;</hi> And whatsoever we do
suffer because thereof, it is <hi>Persecution,</hi> and for, and because
we cannot sin against our God: and it is not for <hi>Evil doing,</hi>
for <hi>Rebellion,</hi> nor for <hi>Transgression against the Law of God,</hi> nor
the <hi>Iust Laws of Men;</hi> but it is for holding the <hi>Testimony of
Iesus</hi> and a <hi>Good Conscience;</hi> and in such our Sufferings, we
commit our Cause to the God of Heaven, <hi>patiently</hi> bearing
what is unequally inflicted upon us for this matter; and our
Cause is <hi>Iust</hi> and <hi>Innocent</hi> for which we suffer, and we have
more respect to keep <hi>our Faith</hi> and <hi>Conscience</hi> towards God, than
to save <hi>our Estates</hi> or <hi>Liberties;</hi> for could we transgress against
God, and <hi>pay Tythes,</hi> we might preserve <hi>our Liberties</hi> and
<hi>Estates,</hi> which we have endangered and lost often, because we
could not; which may shew that it is not for <hi>Covetousness</hi> nor
<hi>self-ends,</hi> that we refuse <hi>to do it;</hi> And this our Case about <hi>Tythes,</hi>
and the reason why we cannot pay them, is in brief stated and
pleaded, before the King and his Council, and I leave it to
their Considerations in the sight of God, only to warm them,
that they persecute not any for the Cases of Conscience, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
in this nor in any other thing, lest the effect of it be sad
upon them, in a day when God visits them with Judgments.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:52871:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. The Case stated and pleaded, concerning giving Security
by Bond, to live peaceably, or to answer Cases then
and there, &amp;c. as is often required of us.</head>
               <p n="I">I. FOrasmuch as we are often demanded, <hi>to give Bond of One
or two hundred Pounds</hi> (or the like) <hi>for Security</hi> (so called)
<hi>That we will live peaceably;</hi> or, <hi>that we will appear and answer
such Cases objected against us,</hi> or <hi>supposed of us.</hi> Now we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
give such kind of <hi>formal Engagements</hi> out of the Counsel
of God, to <hi>be</hi> or <hi>do,</hi> or <hi>to appear,</hi> or <hi>answer, this,</hi> or <hi>the other
Case,</hi> when as we are <hi>no Transgressors</hi> in the things <hi>objected</hi>
against us, and <hi>supposed</hi> of us; and when we are suspected
by prejudiced minds, of such and such matters, of which we
are no wayes <hi>guilty</hi> in the sight of God nor men; and then
it is demanded of us, <hi>to bind our selves, to find Sureties, and to
answer this and the other Objection and Supposition, only falsly sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed
and suspected against us, by men that seek occasion against us.</hi>
This Demand we cannot fulfill for Conscience-sake; because
<hi>we are clear,</hi> and <hi>not guilty</hi> of such <hi>Suspitions;</hi> nor can we <hi>bind
our selves</hi> (out of the Counsel of God) upon <hi>Penalties</hi> and <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures,</hi>
to <hi>appear</hi> and <hi>answer</hi> such and such <hi>groundless Objections;</hi>
for if we should in that manner <hi>bind</hi> and <hi>engage</hi> our selves not
to do so, or answer <hi>this</hi> and the <hi>other Objection</hi> against us, when
we know our selves <hi>innocent</hi> of that <hi>Accusation,</hi> to which we are
to answer, and that it is not in our hearts to do the thing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
we are doubted, but contrary to our Faith and Principles;
then this were a betraying of our <hi>own Innocency</hi> in that behalf,
and a rendring of us <hi>guilty to all men,</hi> when as we are <hi>clear;</hi> and
by binding our selves, as afore-mentioned, we should be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
Transgressors: for <hi>Bonds</hi> and <hi>Engagements</hi> by <hi>Forfeitures</hi>
and <hi>Sums</hi> of <hi>Money,</hi> are for the <hi>Guilty,</hi> and not for the <hi>Innocent;</hi>
and we may not betray our <hi>guiltless Cause,</hi> and bring it under
false reputation amongst men, by giving such <hi>binding Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
And again, when as we are <hi>clear</hi> of any such <hi>Suspitions</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:52871:13"/>
as are made against us, if we should <hi>bind our selves,</hi> as aforesaid;
it many times doth appear, that occasion is <hi>more</hi> taken against
us, in <hi>answering</hi> or <hi>appearing,</hi> and we made to be greater Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
than before; and there again our <hi>Innocency</hi> is betrayed,
when as <hi>innocent</hi> of the fact supposed against us, yet made <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders</hi>
in answering through <hi>formalities</hi> and <hi>tricks</hi> in the course
of Law practised at the time of Answering; and therefore we
do in good Reason and Equity, deny to <hi>bind our selves</hi> in that
manner, and to give such <hi>Security</hi> (so called) lest we should
betray our own Innocency, and render our Cause to <hi>false Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations</hi>
in that behalf; and lest we should fall into a <hi>Remedy,</hi>
to clear us of <hi>false Suspitions,</hi> worse than the <hi>Suspitions them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves,</hi>
by laying our selves liable to greater suffering in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering
to our <hi>Accusations,</hi> falsly objected, than our <hi>suffering</hi> can
be by the <hi>Accusations</hi> themselves; and evil-minded men, do
often take <hi>greater occasion</hi> against us in answering <hi>false Charges</hi>
and <hi>groundless Suppositions</hi> laid against us, than they can take by
the <hi>false Charges</hi> and <hi>Suspitions themselves;</hi> and so we cannot
bind our selves, as aforesaid, to fulfil the Wills of men, and
thereby expose our selves to a far <hi>greater suffering</hi> (to be taken
in it) for to escape <hi>a lesse.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="II">II. But as for <hi>living peaceably</hi> in the Land, and being subject in
all <hi>just</hi> and <hi>good things</hi> to the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Government;</hi> and not
to <hi>plot</hi> against them, nor to <hi>harm</hi> any person whatsoever, but to
be in love <hi>with all,</hi> and in good behaviour <hi>towards all,</hi> and to
answer to any thing <hi>justly</hi> required of us: This is our Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple
to do, and hath ever been <hi>our Practice,</hi> and we are bound
by the Law of God to perform this <hi>in every particular;</hi> and we
can fully make <hi>Confession</hi> hereof, and <hi>testifie</hi> it in <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay,</hi>
according to the <hi>New Covenant</hi> and <hi>Christ's Command,</hi> who hath
said, <hi>Let your <hi>Yea,</hi> be <hi>Yea,</hi>
                  </hi> and <hi>your <hi>Nay, Nay,</hi>
                  </hi> but not <hi>by
an Oath,</hi> nor binding our selves upon such <hi>Penalties</hi> and <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures</hi>
in <hi>Engagements</hi> by sums of Money, out of the Counsel
of God; and our <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay,</hi> in this and all other cases, <hi>is
more binding <hi>to us,</hi>
                  </hi> than all the <hi>formal Engagements <hi>of others;</hi>
                  </hi>
and we make as much Conscience to perform <hi>our <hi>Yea</hi>
                  </hi> and <hi>Nay,</hi>
as any others do <hi>their Oaths</hi> or <hi>Bonds;</hi> and if we do not, but
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52871:13"/>
do <hi>plot</hi> and <hi>rebel,</hi> and be of evil behaviour towards any, then let
us suffer the same, as if we had bound our selves in Forfeitures
of great sums of Money, and broken such <hi>our Engagements:</hi> and
no man need in any case <hi>bind himself</hi> upon such <hi>Pains</hi> and <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures,</hi>
not to break the Laws of the Land; when as the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice
of the Law will be executed upon him if he transgress it,
whether he bind himself, or not, beforehand, not to break it;
and this is the thing we alwayes offer: <hi>here we are, if we bave
broken any Law, let us suffer according to the Law;</hi> and if at any
time we are found guilty of transgressing the Law, <hi>let us then
suffer accordingly, whether <hi>Death</hi> or <hi>Bonds;</hi> we crave no favour,
but the Execution of just Law:</hi> And in the mean time, being we
are clear of <hi>Rebellion</hi> and other Transgression; Who shall accuse
us? or, who can reasonably require such or such <hi>Engagements</hi> of
us to <hi>do,</hi> or not <hi>to do,</hi> or answer <hi>so</hi> or <hi>so;</hi> seeing we must in Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice
suffer the <hi>punishment</hi> of the Law when we <hi>transgress</hi> it;
which we must do, if we are at any time guilty, whether we
beforehand <hi>bind</hi> our selves to the contrary or not? And also, if
we should <hi>bind</hi> our selves, by the <hi>Engagements</hi> of such and such
<hi>Sums of Money,</hi> to live <hi>quietly</hi> and not to <hi>rebel:</hi> yet we should
be no better trusted because thereof, for that would not slay
the principle of <hi>Strife</hi> and <hi>Wars</hi> in us, but rather cause us to
murmur because of our bondage, and strive for liberty; and
also if we were men of dispositions <hi>to war</hi> and <hi>plot,</hi> &amp;c. it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
be supposed by <hi>reasonable men,</hi> that any <hi>Engagement</hi> by any
sum of Money, would bind us from it, upon occasion, seeing
we might hope in such attempts to save our Sums of Money,
and to gain far more advantage, or else we hazarded to lose
all; and to gain a greater advantage (if we were men of <hi>strife</hi>)
we would not doubt to attempt to lose a lesse; and we being
men not of <hi>strife,</hi> we cannot <hi>bind</hi> our selves as aforesaid, in this
or any case; neither can any in good reason desire the same of
us, if they rightly consider the case.</p>
               <p n="III">III. These things considered, it is fully manifest, That upon
<hi>good Reason</hi> and a <hi>clear Conscience,</hi> we do <hi>refuse</hi> and <hi>deny</hi> to give
<hi>Bond,</hi> and make such and such <hi>Engagements</hi> by <hi>Forfeitures</hi> of
<hi>Sums of Money;</hi> It is, I say, in <hi>good Reason</hi> and <hi>Conscience,</hi> and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52871:14"/>
not in any <hi>wilfulness,</hi> or <hi>stubornness,</hi> or <hi>contempt</hi> of <hi>Authority</hi> that
we do it, nor as though we were guilty in such mater suspected,
and durst not answer the Law; but we do it to keep our <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency
clear,</hi> and not to <hi>betray it</hi> into real cause of doubt that we
are guilty. 2. That we may not lay our selves liable to a
<hi>greater suffering,</hi> by answering <hi>false Suspitions</hi> and <hi>Accusations,</hi>
as it often happeneth in the proceedings in course of Law.</p>
               <p>3. That we may not <hi>come under men of evil prejudiced minds,</hi>
that seek more occasion against us than they have; and we may
not fulfill their wills, and to give them occasion against us,
when as in the <hi>Accusations</hi> they have justly none. 4. That
we may not <hi>expose</hi> our selves to be <hi>entrapted</hi> and <hi>ensnared</hi> into
<hi>greater Sufferings,</hi> to avoid <hi>a less.</hi> 5. That we may walk in the
<hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Command</hi> of <hi>Christ Iesus,</hi> who hath commanded
to let our <hi>Yea <hi>be</hi> Yea,</hi> and our <hi>Nay</hi> be <hi>Nay;</hi> and whatsoever
<hi>Oath</hi> or <hi>Engagement</hi> (out of the Counsel of God) is more, <hi>comes
of the Evil,</hi> which we may not do.</p>
               <p>These, with some others, are Reasons and Causes why we
cannot for Conscience sake bind our selves in such kind of <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal
Engagements</hi> (out of the Will of God) <hi>to do,</hi> or not <hi>to do;</hi> to
answer this <hi>false Suspition</hi> or the other; but we do deny it out
of good Reason and Conscience. And also there is no Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
for it, that we know, among the Saints in former Ages, that
any of them ever bound themselves to any Kings or Rulers in
any such kind of <hi>Engagements,</hi> neither can we at this day; but
as I said, <hi>If we transgresse the Law, let us suffer by it;</hi> if we
are already, or hereafter be found guilty, we desire nothing but
the <hi>just execution of just Laws,</hi> and in <hi>patience</hi> we shall bear it;
but beforehand we may not <hi>bind</hi> our selves in <hi>formal Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi>
out of the Will of God, to <hi>promise</hi> upon <hi>Forfeitures</hi> and
<hi>Penalties</hi> what we will <hi>do</hi> or <hi>say,</hi> or what we will <hi>not do</hi> or <hi>say;</hi>
for at the Will and Disposure of the Almighty we are, in <hi>all
things</hi> and <hi>cases;</hi> and it is our Principle and Belief, <hi>That we
abiding in the Fear and Counsel of God, can be no other than <hi>peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,
just, righteous</hi>
                  </hi> and <hi>innocent <hi>in the Land;</hi>
                  </hi> So that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever
we <hi>may</hi> or <hi>do suffer</hi> for this case, of denying <hi>to give Bond,</hi>
or <hi>engage our selves so</hi> and <hi>so,</hi> as aforesaid, it is for <hi>Truths sake,</hi>
and such our Sufferings are <hi>Persecution</hi> and <hi>unequal;</hi> and we
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52871:14"/>
must commit our Cause to God, who will plead it in his sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,
if that we are <hi>persecuted</hi> for the cause of <hi>groundless Suspition,</hi>
and because we cannot engage to answer <hi>causeless Objections.</hi>
And thus I have sought out this matter, and laid it before <hi>the
King,</hi> and I leave it to him to consider; and to shew <hi>Iustice,
Equity, Mercy</hi> and <hi>Long-suffering,</hi> and in so doing he will be
blessed; but if the contrary be brought forth, the effect thereof
will be more <hi>miserable.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. The Case stated and pleaded, concerning Government it self,
and particularly of this present Authority, and our Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
to it.</head>
               <p n="I">I. VVE do acknowledge <hi>Government,</hi> and <hi>Rule,</hi> and <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracy</hi>
to be an Ordinance of God, ordained and insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted
of him, to be exercised among the Children of Men, <hi>for
to be a Praise and a Defence to all that do well, and to be a Terrour
and Correction to all that do evil.</hi> And we believe there ought to
be <hi>Rule,</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> exercised and executed
in every Kingdom, Nation, City and Country, for the end
aforesaid (to wit) That <hi>Evil-doers</hi> may be made <hi>afraid</hi> and <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected,
limited, restrained</hi> and <hi>subdued;</hi> and that <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression</hi>
may be <hi>suppressed;</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Righteousness promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted;</hi>
and them that do well, <hi>praised</hi> and <hi>strengthened:</hi> And this
is the very end of <hi>outward Government</hi> of Kings, Princes, or
others, amongst Men upon the Earth, Even that the <hi>Outward
man</hi> may be kept in <hi>good order</hi> and <hi>subjection</hi> in his conversation
in the World; and may be <hi>limited</hi> and <hi>restrained</hi> from all <hi>wrong
doing</hi> or <hi>speaking</hi> against his Neighbours <hi>Person</hi> or <hi>Estate;</hi> and
if he do, he is punishable by such <hi>Iust Authority.</hi> This is the
<hi>very end</hi> of <hi>outward Government</hi> in the Kingdoms of the World;
but it extends not over the <hi>Inward Man,</hi> to rule, govern, or
exercise Authority over the <hi>Consciences</hi> of any in Spiritual mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
and cases between <hi>God</hi> and a mans <hi>Conscience;</hi> This Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52871:15"/>
and Authority only pertains to the <hi>Inward Government</hi>
and <hi>Rule of <hi>Iesus Christ</hi>
                  </hi> by his <hi>Eternal Spirit,</hi> but not to any
<hi>Outward Government</hi> of <hi>Kings, Princes, Parliaments,</hi> or any
others; They, I say, ought only to exercise Authority over the
<hi>Persons</hi> and <hi>Estates</hi> of People in all just and lawful things and
matters, but not over the <hi>Consciences</hi> of any in the exercise of
Duty towards God, or in the Cases and Matters of Worship
and Religion.</p>
               <p n="II">II. The Exercise and Execution of this <hi>Iust Government</hi> over the
<hi>Outward Man,</hi> as afore described, ought to be committed into
the hands of <hi>faithful, just and upright men,</hi> such <hi>as fear the Lord,</hi>
and <hi>hate Covetousness,</hi> and <hi>every evil way,</hi> in all Kingdoms of
the World; The Execution of the Government in all Just
Laws, onght (I say) to be committed to such men, and not
to <hi>Drunkards, Lyars, Covetous</hi> or <hi>Evil-minded persons, Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi>
or <hi>Vain-glorious persons</hi> in any Nation; such as these ought
not to be entrusted with the Execution of the Government,
and the good Laws of any Kingdom; for such will not be a
<hi>Blessing</hi> unto the Land, nor unto any People, but a <hi>Curse,</hi> and
the cause of provoking God to <hi>Vengeance</hi> and <hi>Wrath</hi> against
themselves, the People and the Governments, if such men,
whom God chooseth not, be chosen to make Laws and execute
them, and to exercise Government in any Kingdoms of this
World; But men that <hi>fear God,</hi> and delight in <hi>Iustice, Mercy</hi>
and <hi>Truth,</hi> that are <hi>humble</hi> and <hi>meek</hi> and <hi>lowly persons,</hi> ought
to be called to the <hi>place of Government,</hi> and <hi>only such</hi> are fit to
exercise <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> and to make and execute Laws
in these Kingdoms, and in all the Kingdoms of the World; and
such would be a <hi>Blessing</hi> in the Earth, and the Governments
under such, and in the execution of their hands, would be <hi>blessed</hi>
and <hi>prosperous;</hi> and all <hi>good men</hi> would have cause to <hi>rejoyce</hi>
therein, and all <hi>evil doers</hi> and <hi>transgressors</hi> would be limited
and made <hi>afraid,</hi> if so be the Laws be <hi>just, holy</hi> and <hi>righteous,</hi>
and according to <hi>Equity</hi> and the holy Law of God <hi>in all things,</hi>
and the due Execution of such Laws committed to <hi>just</hi> and
<hi>righteous</hi> and <hi>meek men,</hi> that love <hi>Iudgment, Mercy</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi>
and would execute them in the Earth; Then the <hi>happy</hi> and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52871:15"/>
                  <hi>blessed Government</hi> will be exalted, and <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Righteousness</hi>
would reign as Judge on the Throne; and in this shall all
Nations and Kingdoms be prosperous and blessed when in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
to passe.</p>
               <p n="III">III. And as for this <hi>present Authority</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> now in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
under the name of <hi>King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second,</hi> we do believe
and acknowledge, That according to the Purpose and Will of
God, and of his bringing to passe, <hi>this present Government and
Authority is set up, and into its present being, established; The
Lord,</hi> I say, <hi>hath suffered it to be effected, for the Cause, and End,
and Time, and Purpose, known to Himself, and not to mortal man:</hi>
And thus this Government and Authority is of God, being
brought in and set up, in opposition <hi>to,</hi> and for the <hi>reproof</hi> and
<hi>correction</hi> of, such as <hi>went before,</hi> who had neglected <hi>Mercy,
Truth, Iudgment</hi> and <hi>Righteousness</hi> in the Earth, till it was time
for the Lord to cast them out, and reprove them, and make them
a Desolation before their Enemies; and this Authority was
judged of the Lord fit for <hi>that use</hi> and <hi>end,</hi> and reserved to be
brought in, as <hi>a Rod of God in his hand,</hi> to <hi>correct</hi> and <hi>smite</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
people; And it is right in the sight of the Lord, that this
Authority should have this time and season to be exercised in
these Kingdoms, to try and prove, both it self, and all under
it, if so be that Truth, Justice and Righteousness, Mercy and
Peace, may be brought forth in these Kingdoms through it,
that God may establish it for long continuance; and it is now
a <hi>trying</hi> and <hi>proving,</hi> to make it self <hi>happy</hi> and <hi>blessed,</hi> or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
to bring it self into <hi>contempt</hi> and <hi>dishonour;</hi> and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly,
as <hi>Truth, Iustice, Mercy, Iudgment</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> is brought
forth by it, or the contrary brought forth by it; so must the
just and equal effects and reward of it be from the Hand of
God; and it is only <hi>Iust Iudgment, Mercy</hi> and <hi>Truth, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness,
Relieving the Oppressed,</hi> and the doing thereof, that
can alone make the <hi>Person</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of the King <hi>Happy,
Blessed</hi> and <hi>Honourable</hi> in this World, and hereafter; and the
contrary, if it be brought forth, must needs bring <hi>Confusion,
Discontents,</hi> and all <hi>miserable Iudgments;</hi> and, to say no more
of it, this is my present Judgment of the King and his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52871:16"/>
both in respect of their Coming in, and the Cause there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
and the Fruits and Effects that must follow, which is not
otherwise determined of God, but according to <hi>desert</hi> and
<hi>merit,</hi> of walking in Truth, Justice, and Righteousness, or in
walking otherwise.</p>
               <p n="IV">IV. Our <hi>Obedience</hi> to this <hi>Authority,</hi> must be according, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
declared, in the <hi>Plea</hi> of the first Case concerning <hi>Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi>
(to wit) <hi>for Conscience sake to God,</hi> we are bound by his
<hi>Iust Law in our hearts</hi> to yeeld Obedience to it, <hi>in all matters
and cases <hi>actively</hi>
                  </hi> or <hi>passively;</hi> that is to say, in all just and
good Commands of the King, and the good Laws of the Land,
relating to our outward man, we must be obedient <hi>by doing,</hi> and
not withhold our Just Obedience; but in the Cases of Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
(to wit) in the matters of Duty to God, and of Worship,
Faith and Religion towards him, we must only be obedient to
God; for it is he that teacheth and requireth obedience in all
those things: and if any thing be commanded of us by the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
Authority,</hi> which is not <hi>according</hi> to <hi>Equity, Iustice,</hi> and <hi>a
good Conscience</hi> towards God, to be done by us, we must in such
Cases, obey God only, and deny <hi>active Obedience</hi> for Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
sake, and <hi>patiently suffer <hi>what is inflicted upon us</hi>
                  </hi> for such
our disobedience to men; and we must choose Obedience to
<hi>God</hi> rather <hi>than man,</hi> though we <hi>suffer</hi> because thereof: And
this is <hi>our Principle,</hi> and hath ever been <hi>our Practice,</hi> to obey
Authority, by <hi>doing,</hi> or <hi>suffering,</hi> not disputing whether the
<hi>Authority</hi> in it self be absolute of God, or not; yet being an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
over us, we are to obey it, either <hi>by doing,</hi> or <hi>suffering,</hi>
because it is an <hi>Authority;</hi> and not to <hi>plot, rebel,</hi> or <hi>rise up with
carnal weapons</hi> against it: and thus must our Obedience be to
the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Government.</hi> And if that in any thing of the
Commands of the King, we cannot be obedient for <hi>Conscience
sake,</hi> in the Cases of <hi>Conscience,</hi> and when ought is required
different or contrary to the Law of God, we have Example
hereof in the Scriptures, of many of the Servants of God that
could not <hi>in all things,</hi> yeeld Obedience to the <hi>Laws of Nations</hi>
and <hi>Commandments of Kings,</hi> when they required ought to be
obeyed, contrary to their pure Consciences; as in the Case of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52871:16"/>
the Three Children, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. they could not obey the Law and
Command of the King, though it was absolute, but refused
Obedience, and <hi>suffered</hi> for it; and <hi>Daniel</hi> also himself dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeyed
the Kings Law and Commands, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. and the
Apostles the same, when they were commanded by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
of that City and Country, <hi>To preach no more in the Name of
IESUS,</hi> Act. 4. 17, 18. They did not obey the Command of
the Rulers in that case, but went on and preached <hi>Iesus,</hi> in
<hi>disobedience</hi> and <hi>contrary</hi> to the Command of the Rulers. And
by these, and many other Exumples, it is apparent, that it is
justifiable in the sight of God, and that it was practised by the
Servants of God in former Ages, even <hi>Disobedience to Kings</hi>
and <hi>Authorities,</hi> in the Matters and Cases commanded <hi>contrary
to the Law of God</hi> and <hi>a good Conscience;</hi> and their Example
may justifie such now in the same Practice, in the same Case,
if they walk therein by the same Principle.</p>
               <p>V. And thus it is manifest, That if we at any time be found not
in full obedience <hi>by doing,</hi> in all Cases and Things, to the Laws
and Authority of this Kingdom; it is not out of <hi>Contempt</hi> unto,
or <hi>Rebellion</hi> against the Kings <hi>Person</hi> or <hi>Government;</hi> It is not,
I say, on that account, but for <hi>good Conscience sake,</hi> and because
we must <hi>obey God</hi> rather <hi>than man,</hi> when and where their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
stand in opposition the one to the other; and this is,
that we may keep our Consciences clear in the sight of God,
from disobedience against him, which is our care and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
by all means: and when any thing is required of us to be
done, which we cannot do with a clear Conscience in the sight
of God, such Commands we cannot yeeld Obedience unto;
and yet it is not out of Wilfulness, Stubornness, Contempt, or
Rebellion against the Authority; but it is for this End and
Cause, that we may not sin against God, nor against our own
Consciences, by doing any thing which is contrary thereunto,
lest we should bring the Wrath of God upon our own Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences:
So that all these things rightly considered, it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear,
1. That we acknowledge <hi>Magistracy</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> to be
the <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> to be exercised and executed in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms
of the World among men. 2. That <hi>Iust</hi> and <hi>Righteous
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52871:17"/>
men,</hi> are the only persons fit to execute <hi>Iust Laws</hi> and <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities</hi>
in the Earth. 3. That we <hi>acknowledge this present Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
of King <hi>Charles;</hi> and that according to the Purpose of
God it is now set up. 4. That we are to be obedient by <hi>doing,</hi>
or <hi>suffering</hi> in <hi>all things,</hi> to the Authority of the King, as the
<hi>Supream Authority.</hi> 5. That if in any case we are <hi>disobedient</hi>
thereunto, and cannot wholly perform every Command, <hi>by
doing,</hi> yet it is for <hi>Conscience sake</hi> to God, and that we may not
sin against him, and not out of <hi>Rebellion</hi> or <hi>Contempt of the King</hi>
or <hi>his Power.</hi> And all these things truly considered, if we do
suffer Tribulations, Afflictions and Imprisonments, under and
by this <hi>present Authority,</hi> for and because of our <hi>Profession</hi> and
<hi>Practice of Religion,</hi> without <hi>evil</hi> or <hi>wrong doing</hi> to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours
Persons or Estates, though we do not in the things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
to our Consciences obey <hi>actively</hi> this <hi>present Authority,</hi>
yet we are persecuted for the Name of Christ; and as so, we
receive our Sufferings, and not as for <hi>Contempt</hi> or <hi>Denyal of
Authority,</hi> or as <hi>Rebellious</hi> against it; but for <hi>Conscience sake</hi> to
God, our Sufferings are, and our unjust Persecution will be
upon our Enemies in the effect and reward thereof, with great
Indignation and Wrath from the Lord God, that rewards all
according to their works. Thus much about <hi>Government.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now I shall shew what <hi>Persecution</hi> is in it self.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. Concerning Persecution, what it is in it self, and how great
an Enemy it is to the Kings Person and Authority.</head>
               <p>1. <hi>PErsecution</hi> is, when a Person, or a People, do suffer <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation,
Affliction, Imprisonment, Bonds,</hi> or <hi>Death,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
by a Law or without the Law, for, and because of his or
their <hi>Principle</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> in <hi>Religion;</hi> As when a Person or a
People are reproached, falsly accused, imprisoned or put to
death, only for and because of their <hi>Religion sake;</hi> when as no
evil-dealing in the things between <hi>man and man,</hi> can be justly,
charged and proved against them, but only because they are
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52871:17"/>
righteous, and walk in the wayes of the Lord, and cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
to the wayes and vanities of this world, but are separated
from it in its <hi>Prophaness,</hi> and in its <hi>formal Profession</hi> also of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion;
and because thereof Sufferings are imposed upon them,
while yet they walk <hi>justly, innocently</hi> and <hi>harmlesly</hi> towards all
men: This is <hi>Persecution for Conscience sake,</hi> and such are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted,
if so be they suffer for and because of <hi>Righteonsness sake,</hi>
and because they will not deny their Principles nor Profession
of Religion, nor conform to <hi>Times,</hi> nor <hi>Laws,</hi> contrary to a
<hi>good Conscience,</hi> and yet suffer because hereof; this is <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. <hi>Persecution</hi> is, when a Person or a People is afflicted,
and any kind of Sufferings imposed upon them, whether by any
Authority, or without Authority, and only because they are
of such a <hi>Profession</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> in <hi>Religion;</hi> though yet their
<hi>Profession</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> in their <hi>Religion</hi> is not perfectly accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to God, nor by the exercise of that Spirit of God ruling in
their Consciences in such their Religion, yet if they suffer
only for their <hi>Religion sake,</hi> while yet they walk uprightly as
men, in all outward affairs relating to the <hi>outward man,</hi> This
also is <hi>Persecution,</hi> and such are <hi>persecuted for their Religion sake,</hi>
though not wholly for <hi>Righteousness sake;</hi> and none ought to
suffer as such, under the Authority of any King, Prince, or
Power; but if such do suffer, as I have said, and that for their
<hi>Religion sake only</hi> so, though yet their Religion is not perfectly
according to God, yet they <hi>are persecuted,</hi> and this is <hi>Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</hi>
And thus I have in short described and defined what
<hi>Persecution</hi> is in it self, and who it is that are <hi>persecuted,</hi> and I
shall now shew how great an Enemy Persecution for <hi>Conscience</hi>
and <hi>Religion sake</hi> is unto the <hi>King's Person</hi> and <hi>Authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Persecution</hi> for <hi>Conscience sake,</hi> and for <hi>difference</hi> in <hi>Matters</hi>
of Religion, is a <hi>great Enemy</hi> to the <hi>Person</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of
the King; it is, I say, a <hi>destroying</hi> and <hi>devouring Enemy,</hi> and the
fruits and effects thereof may work <hi>terrible destruction,</hi> yea,
this Enemy [<hi>Persecution</hi>] hath often wrought overthrow in
Kingdoms: Let the King strive to be delivered speedily from
this great Enemy, which is fierce and cruel, and may work
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52871:18"/>
woful effects in this Kingdom also, and the King may be more
blessed in his <hi>Person</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> if he remove far from him
this Enemy, <hi>Persecution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I. It is his Enemy, because its effect is, to eat out the Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
of many good and sober people from the King, and may
make their Love and Affections dye to the <hi>King's Government,</hi>
when they behold and consider the <hi>Persecution</hi> of many <hi>good</hi>
and <hi>peaceable People</hi> for <hi>Righteousness</hi> and <hi>good Conscience sake,</hi>
when as no <hi>evil doing between man and man</hi> can justly be laid to
their charge, but only for the <hi>matter of their Religion</hi> and the
<hi>exercise of their Consciences towards God;</hi> and if such suffer <hi>cruel
Imprisonment, unjust Fines,</hi> and <hi>grievous Vexations</hi> for such cause,
it may weaken and eat out the <hi>Affections</hi> of good People, and
divert their <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>good Desires</hi> from the King and his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
in which <hi>such Persecution</hi> is brought forth: and that
which diverts the Peoples Love from the King, is his <hi>great
Enemy,</hi> and such is <hi>Persecution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>II. <hi>Persecution</hi> is the King's <hi>great Enemy;</hi> because it may
kindle <hi>Heart-burnings, Envyings, Strifes,</hi> and <hi>Murmurings</hi>
among his Subjects, while some are tolerated in the <hi>Profession</hi>
and <hi>Practice</hi> of their <hi>Religion,</hi> and others <hi>persecuted</hi> and <hi>impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned</hi>
for the same cause; and this kind of dealing exerciseth
the King's Subjects in harsh dealing one towards another, and
gives great occasions for <hi>Quarrelling, Envyes, Debate</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice</hi>
one against another, even when some execute <hi>Persecution</hi>
upon others, haling them to Prison, spoyling their Goods, and
the like; and this kind of dealing, I say, whilst the Authority
of the Land persecutes one sort of the King's Subjects by the
hands of others, it tendeth much to <hi>great Division</hi> and <hi>Distra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi>
amongst the People; and it is not for the <hi>King's safety,</hi>
but for his <hi>great dishonour</hi> and <hi>disadvantage</hi> every way, to have
the People divided into <hi>heart-burnings</hi> and <hi>quarrellings</hi> against
one another; and therefore <hi>Persecution</hi> is the King's great Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,
because it worketh such evil effects.</p>
               <p>III. It is his <hi>great Enemy,</hi> because it is contrary to the
Trust which God hath reposed in him, in promoting him to be
King over these People; for God hath not committed Power
to him, to judge in the Cases of Mens Consciences, and to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52871:18"/>
persecute any because of the exercise thereof, whether they be
of <hi>this</hi> Profession and Practice in <hi>Religion,</hi> or the <hi>other,</hi> yet li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<hi>peaceably</hi> and <hi>uprightly</hi> as Men, he ought not to persecute
any, nor to suffer them to be persecuted by, nor under his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority;
but he ought to defend and preserve all mens Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
and Estates in their Just Rights, from the violence each
of others, without respect to what their <hi>Profession</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi>
of <hi>Religion is;</hi> but if the contrary be brought forth, it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,
and not answerable to the end of God's <hi>Restoring Him
to these Kingdoms;</hi> and if He do not what God hath justly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
him unto, but otherwise, this is his Enemy; and such is
<hi>Persecution for Conscience sake,</hi> it is contrary to the end of Just
Government, and wherefore God hath Restored him; and
therefore this <hi>Persecution is an utter Enemy both to the King's
Person and Authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>IV. It is <hi>his Enemy,</hi> because it provokes the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
and Earth over all, to be offended with him; for He is
provoked and vexed because of <hi>the Persecution of his People in
this Age,</hi> as ever He was in all Ages; and if the King be guilty
thereof, it incurreth God's great Displeasure against him: for
God was ever offended with Kings, Rulers, and whomsoever
that were <hi>Persecuters,</hi> and he is the same at this day; and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever
it is that provokes God to Anger against the King, <hi>that
is his Enemy:</hi> And such is <hi>Persecution of People</hi> for the <hi>Profession</hi>
and <hi>Practice</hi> of <hi>their Religion,</hi> when as no Evil can be charged
upon them in things between Man and Man: and therefore
let the King beware of this woful Enemy that waits to wound
him; for if the God of Heaven be provoked against him, How
great is that Enemy which brings it to pass?</p>
               <p>V. It is the King's <hi>Enemy,</hi> because it not only provokes the
Lord <hi>to Anger,</hi> but <hi>to Iudgment; Persecution</hi> is the cause where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
God brings <hi>grievous Iudgments</hi> and <hi>Vengeance</hi> upon whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever
are guilty thereof; and the effect of Persecution is
<hi>Plagues</hi> and <hi>Misery;</hi> and it incenseth God <hi>to Anger,</hi> and also
<hi>to Destroy:</hi> and therefore let the King beware of such a deadly
Enemy, as should cause God to destroy him: and such an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
is <hi>Persecution of Gods People for Conscience sake,</hi> it draweth
down the Wrath of God upon Kings and Kingdoms, upon Rich
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:52871:19"/>
and Poor, upon High and Low, that are guilty of it, for it is
the fulfilling of all other sins, and it hastens to bring destruction
upon all that are guilty; and this effect it will work upon the
King, even this his Enemy <hi>Persecution,</hi> if he turn not from
it, and overcome it, and banish it from him; for it is the cause
of both <hi>inward</hi> and <hi>outward,</hi> of both <hi>internal</hi> and <hi>external</hi>
Plagues and Judgments of God.</p>
               <p>VI. <hi>Persecution</hi> it is <hi>an Enemy to the King,</hi> because it will
work to weaken the hands of <hi>Iust</hi> and <hi>Sober</hi> and <hi>Righteous Men,</hi>
it will weaken their Love and Affections, and it makes their
hearts sad; and <hi>Wo is unto them that make sad their hearts, whom
God doth not make sad:</hi> and this doth <hi>Persecution;</hi> and it doth
not only weaken the hearts and the hands of the <hi>Righteous</hi> and
<hi>Sober Persons,</hi> but it strengthens the hands of the <hi>Rude, Ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi>
and <hi>Prophane</hi> through the Land, and that which strengthens
the <hi>Wicked</hi> and the <hi>Rude Multitude</hi> in Wantonness, Scorning
and Prophaness, that is the King's Enemy; but such is <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution
for a good Conscience sake;</hi> and because it weakens the
<hi>Righteous</hi> in their good and upright wayes, and strengthens
the <hi>Wicked</hi> in their evil wayes, therefore it is an Enemy unto
the King.</p>
               <p>VII. <hi>Persecution</hi> is an Enemy unto him, because it tends
to render him <hi>dishonourable both in the sight of God, and all good
Men through the World;</hi> for it will shew, that he is <hi>cruel</hi> and
<hi>bitter,</hi> and <hi>perverse,</hi> and that he wants <hi>Humility, Meeknesse,
Forbearance</hi> and <hi>Patience,</hi> if he be guilty; and this is dishono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,
to have and profess evil qualities and properties, and to
be without the good; and by <hi>Persecution</hi> this will be made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest
to all the World, and ever was in all Ages, that the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutors
of good Conscience gained unto themselves, <hi>Dishonour</hi>
and <hi>Reproach of all good men in all Ages after them:</hi> for they were
men full of Rage and Malice and Passionatness, and wanted
Patience and Humility, and this made them <hi>Dishonourable:</hi>
And the case will be the same with the King, if he be a Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor
for Conscience sake, and he will be dishonourable both
in this present time, and in Ages to come, and this by <hi>Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
and therefore it is his Enemy, that will work many Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs
and Evils upon him, if he be not wholly delivered
from it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:52871:19"/>
VIII. <hi>Persecution</hi> is an Enemy to the King's <hi>Person</hi> and
<hi>Authority,</hi> because Persecution for Conscience sake <hi>is of the
Devil,</hi> it is of his spirit, and not of the Spirit of God, to <hi>perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute,
imprison, kill</hi> and <hi>destroy mens Persons</hi> and <hi>Estates,</hi> because
of their <hi>Religion-sake,</hi> when as no <hi>unjust dealing,</hi> nor <hi>unrighteous
conversation</hi> can be justly laid to their charge, but only for, and
because of such <hi>Profession</hi> and <hi>Practice in Religion,</hi> to <hi>persecute
any,</hi> because hereof, this is of the Devil; and that which is of
the Devil, is the King's Enemy, and an Enemy to all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,
and such is <hi>Persecution;</hi> and therefore it is a deadly
mortal Enemy, which wounds <hi>Kings, Princes</hi> and <hi>Rulers</hi> that
ever have had friendship with it; and therefore let the King
avoid this great Enemy, lest its effects prove miserable.</p>
               <p>IX. It is the King's Enemy, because it is according to the
<hi>Example of all the wicked Kings and Rulers that ever have been
through Ages and Generations,</hi> as of <hi>Pharoah, Ahab, Herod,
Nero,</hi> and many more, who were <hi>Persecutors of People for Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
sake,</hi> who gained unto themselves thereby Reproach, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy
and Misery from God and men; and to follow their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,
is the King's Enemy, and such is <hi>Persecution,</hi> if he
should persecute for Conscience sake, and about Religion and
the Worship of God; then he follows the Example of wicked
Kings, and this will be his Enemy, and will work woful effects,
if so be he walk in the steps of the Persecutors of old, and love
that which is his Enemy.</p>
               <p>X. <hi>Persecution</hi> is the King's Enemy, because the end and
effects of it is <hi>Misery and Destruction upon all that persecute the
Heritage of God:</hi> What was <hi>Pharaaoh's</hi> end, and <hi>Herod's</hi> end,
and <hi>Nero's</hi> end? was not their end woful and miserable to God
and shameful to men? And <hi>Persecution for Conscience sake</hi> will
bring the same effects at this day; the end of all <hi>Persecutors</hi>
will be <hi>Misery</hi> and <hi>Shame</hi> even in the Day of the Lord, when
He comes with <hi>Iudgment</hi> and <hi>Vengeance,</hi> and <hi>to reward every
man according to his deeds,</hi> then will He reward <hi>Persecution</hi> and
<hi>Persecutors</hi> with his <hi>fierce Wrath,</hi> and they shall know the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice
of God's Judgments executed upon them: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
happy will the King be if he keep himself clear, and put
far from him this Enemy <hi>Persecution.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:52871:20"/>
            <head>Three CONSIDERATIONS I have to present
unto the KING for Conclusion.</head>
            <p n="I">I. THe Strength, and Safety and Prosperity of the King and
his Government, stands in the <hi>Union, good Affection</hi> and
<hi>Love</hi> of his Subjects, and the People of these Kingdoms, one to
another, and to the King; and the more that the People of the
Kingdoms are in <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Union</hi> and <hi>good Affection,</hi> one with
another and to the King, the <hi>more strong</hi> and <hi>safe,</hi> and <hi>prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi>
thereby is the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>his Government,</hi> and the more like
for <hi>a long</hi> and <hi>happy Continuance</hi> and <hi>Establishment:</hi> And it is the
<hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Union</hi> and <hi>Affection</hi> of the sober and grave, and just
and upright People, and of the Meek of the Land, that is the
Kings <hi>Strength</hi> and <hi>Safety,</hi> and will much tend to his <hi>Prosperity,</hi>
and to the <hi>establishment of his Government</hi> and <hi>Authority;</hi> and
the Kings <hi>Safety</hi> and <hi>Strength</hi> and <hi>Prosperity,</hi> doth not depend
upon the Affection and Acclamations of the Ruder sort, and
of the Wild Multitude, though such profess great subjection,
and cry up the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Government,</hi> and drink his <hi>Healths,</hi>
and <hi>swear the Destruction of all his Enemies;</hi> and have <hi>much love</hi>
and <hi>great Union</hi> for the King, and are for him <hi>to serve him,</hi> and
swear <hi>Fidelity,</hi> and engage themselves very highly in words
and gestures for the King; yet the King and his Government
is no whit the safer, nor more strong nor prosperous, because
hereof, for his Prosperity and Establishment depends upon the
Love and good Affection of the Just and Upright, and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate
and Meek Men of the Kingdoms, and not upon the love
of the Rude Multitude; such cannot be a blessing to him in
their Vaunting and Boasting, and Rudeness; nor can be stand
by them, but must stand in the Establishment of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
by the Love of such <hi>as fear the Lord,</hi> and <hi>depart from all
Iniquity;</hi> by the good Affection of such, and their Faithfulness
and Love may the King be happy and blessed: Therefore let
him strive to please such, and to gain their good Affections to
be united to him; and this may adde to his long Continuance.</p>
            <p n="II">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:52871:20"/>II. It is the doing of Justice and Truth, and allowing all just
and equal Liberty to all People under his Authority, that will
gain upon the hearts of all just and good People; and as
Righteousness, Mercy, true Judgment and Truth is brought
forth in the Land, and all the contrary limited in the King's
Government; this will gain much upon the Hearts and Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
of all good People, to be united in Love one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
and to the King; And this is the way of the King's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperity,
and to make his Government established, if so be that
he exercise his Rule and Authority in <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Meekness</hi> and
<hi>equal Iustice</hi> and <hi>Mercy,</hi> and love <hi>Righteousness</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> and
hate and deny all the contrary, and limit it; then the spirits of
all People in the Kingdoms would be subjected and subdued
under his Power, and he should rule over them, and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms
be established prosperously; and this is the way of an
happy Government: But if so be the King put on Rigour, and
be fierce and cruel, and think to subdue all under him by
<hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Force,</hi> without shewing Justice and Reason, to answer
the Consciences of his Subjects in all his proceedings: This
way can never be prosperous, nor establish him in his Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;
but it will work the contrary effect: For, if Oppression be
brought forth, and heavy Yoaks laid upon the back of the Poor;
then will the Wrath of God and of men, be kindled against
him, and Murmurings, Strifes and Contentions will arise in
the minds of men against him; and the Oppressions of the <hi>Poor</hi>
will reach unto Heaven, and God will hear and revenge their
Cause: So that it is ruling and exercising Authority in these
Kingdoms in Justice, Righteousness, Love and good Reason
that must gain the hearts of People unto right Subjection, to
make the King and his Government happy and established; and
Rigour, Force and Cruelty will never make the King happy,
but will work contrary: For the People are wise, and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing
will not long bear any degree of the yoak of slavery.</p>
            <p n="III">III .In as much as the People of these Kingdoms are divers and
divided, and contrary in Judgment one to another in many
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:52871:21"/>
things, and so are dis-united into several Opinions and Parties;
the King ought to rate in <hi>Wisdom</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> over them all, and
to shew <hi>equal Iustice</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> and to exercise <hi>Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi>
towards them <hi>all alike,</hi> notwithstanding their Difference in
Religion and Judgments; for if he shall give Liberty to some,
and oppress others; if he do joyn with one way, and promote
that, and the men of one Judgment be tolerated, and all other
wayes, and all others that are different in Judgment, be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted
and oppressed, and sought to be destroyed; this is not
the way for the King to prosper, nor to be established to perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity;
for there seems to be no one way so strong, or any one
sort of People so many for the King to cleave to and allow,
and seek to destroy all the rest; because there is of other sorts
of people that ballance that sort in opposition; and so the King
and his Government seems not secure, if he take hold of any
one sort of People, only to stand thereby, in opposition to all
the rest, persecuting of them; because there are many of other
Sects that will be discontented and murmur, if not more: So
that the King's Safety is, and the Prosperity of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
and the Establishment of it seems to be, by giving
<hi>Equal Liberty</hi> and <hi>Iustice,</hi> and <hi>shewing Love</hi> and <hi>Tenderness to
all</hi> of <hi>all Iudgments;</hi> and then he may stand by all, and none
will oppose him, but all will be ready to defend and preserve
him: for he may stand established, and be happy in his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
by engaging all Sorts to him through Love and
Righteousness, and Liberty towards all; but he cannot (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to my Judgment) be established nor prosperous, if he
choose only the men of one Judgment to stand by, and cleave
only to that, and persecute and seek to destroy all the rest that
are different, and so only make one Party his Friends, and
disengage all others in Love and Affection; This seems, I say,
not the way of Prosperity. Let the King consider it; and the
Lord give him a right understanding.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilson,</hi> at the sign of the <hi>Black-spread-Eagle</hi>
and <hi>Windmill,</hi> in <hi>Martins l' Grand,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
