<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Ballad</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2006-06">2006-06 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30515</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B599</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34204</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13978293</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13978293</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102083</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A30515)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102083)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1560:65 or 21241:253)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Ballad</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 broadside.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673 or 1674]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>First line reads: I Sing the praise of a worthy wight.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in Harvard University Library and British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="ballad">
            <pb facs="tcp:102083:1"/>
            <head>A BALLAD.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>I Sing the praiſe of a worthy Wight,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Father (— —) that never wou'd Fight,</l>
               <l>For his Face, but more for his A— made a Knight.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With a fa la la la la la la.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Knight ſoon after à Duke became,</l>
               <l>And got at the Iſland <hi>Rhee</hi> ſuch a Fame,</l>
               <l>That all true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Curs'd <hi>B</hi>—:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That Idol Duke to that Greatneſs did Swell,</l>
               <l>That Honours and Riches before him Fell,</l>
               <l>Till <hi>F</hi>— the Brave ſent his Soul to Hell: </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now you ſhall hear how his Mighty Son,</l>
               <l>With that very ſmall Sin of Inceſt begun,</l>
               <l>And then to Treaſon and Buggery went on:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For the Inceſt, Old <hi>R</hi>— can tell when and where;</l>
               <l>For the Treaſon, the Papers of Old <hi>Oliver,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>K</hi>—Arſe knows his Buggerer:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now he who ſo Bravely and Nobly begins,</l>
               <l>Muſt afterwards think when ſuch Glory he wins,</l>
               <l>Adultery and Treaſon but Trivial Sins:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For <hi>S</hi>— C—t loſt this Nation more</l>
               <l>Brave men than ever were Killed before,</l>
               <l>Or ſhall be hereafter for ſuch a Damn'd Wh—</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>More Seed has been Spilt in her Nauſeous Womb,</l>
               <l>Of all Nations, all Sorts from the Prince to the Groom,</l>
               <l>Then Martyrs Blood for the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet he that will after her Beaſtly Life hunt,</l>
               <l>May Swear and Venture his Soul upon't,</l>
               <l>She has nothing Catholick but her C—t:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Pox upon Pox has Eaten by Bits</l>
               <l>His T—, yet ſo well her purpoſe it Fits,</l>
               <l>That he Fathers the Children <hi>Doughty</hi> Begets:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now I have done with that Rampant Whore,</l>
               <l>And that Sink her C—t which is Cannon Bore,</l>
               <l>But his Grace F—ks oftner Behind than Before:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I come to his Farce, which muſt needs be well done,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Troy</hi> was not longer before it was won,</l>
               <l>Since 'tis more than 10 years ſince firſt 'twas begun:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet gathering from Plays, Pimps, and Table Chatt,</l>
               <l>With the Help of his own Canonical <hi>S</hi>—,</l>
               <l>And his Family Scribe, Antichriſtian <hi>M—:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With Tranſcribing of that, and Tranſcribing of thoſe,</l>
               <l>With Tranſmitting of Verſe, and Transfuſing of Proſe,</l>
               <l>He hath dreſt on his Farce with other mens Cloaths:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His Abuſing the Living, and Robbing the Dead,</l>
               <l>His Inſerting Fine Things which other men ſaid,</l>
               <l>Makes his own way Writing without Tail or Head:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But where the Devil his own Wit doth ly,</l>
               <l>They muſt have very good Eyes that can Spy,</l>
               <l>Unleſs in the Dances and Mimikry:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I confeſs the Dances were very well Writ,</l>
               <l>And the Tune and the Time by <hi>Haynes</hi> as well Hit,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Littlewood</hi>'s Motion and Dreſs had much Wit:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But when his Poet <hi>John Bayes</hi> did appear,</l>
               <l>'Tis known to more than half that were there,</l>
               <l>The greateſt part was his own Character:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For he many years Plagu'd his Friends for their Crimes,</l>
               <l>With Repeating his Verſes and other mens Rhymes,</l>
               <l>To the very ſame Perſons ten thouſand Times:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then his Grace has Tormented the Players more,</l>
               <l>Than the <hi>Howards</hi> and <hi>Fleckno,</hi> and all the ſtore</l>
               <l>Of Damn'd Dull Rogues they were Plagu'd with before:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At laſt Learned <hi>B</hi>— though it Fi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>To tell us the Ancients wanted Wit,</l>
               <l>For he eaſily underſtood all they had Writ:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſure he ſaid this in the Heat of his Blood,</l>
               <l>For if what the Ancients have Written be Good,</l>
               <l>'Tis in Languages he ne'r yet Underſtood:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When in <hi>France,</hi> and in <hi>Spain,</hi> and in <hi>Holland</hi> 'tis known,</l>
               <l>What mighty Wonders our Stateſman has done;</l>
               <l>'Twill make 'um all Tremble to hear his Renown:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For he that can Libel our Poets, and knows</l>
               <l>How to Mimick our Players in Geſture and Cloaths,</l>
               <l>With eaſe can Deſtroy all His Majeſties Foes:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now the Church he Contemns as much as the <hi>Quaker,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Kingdom he'd ruine if the Parliament forſake her,</l>
               <l>For he Serves his King as well as his Maker:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For he that Forſook him in all His Diſtreſs,</l>
               <l>Kill'd the Husband, and Keeps the Adultereſs,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Judas,</hi> would Sell him, and Sell him for Leſs:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He has Mimick'd the King and Duke o'er and o'er,</l>
               <l>That Merciful King who has Pardon'd more,</l>
               <l>Than all our Kings e'er Pardon'd before:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That King who if ever Committed a Crime,</l>
               <l>Which to Church or State may be Fatal in time,</l>
               <l>It was in Extending his Mercy to Him:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now God grant His Majeſty never may find,</l>
               <l>'Tis Fatal to be to a <hi>B</hi>— Kind,</l>
               <l>For his Father was ruin'd by what he Deſign'd:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With a fa la la la la la la.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
