<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The humble petitions of Mr. Burton and Dr. Bastwicke presented to the honovrable the knights, citizens, and burgesses of the Commons House of Parliament.</title>
            <author>Burton, Henry, 1578-1648.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-11">2004-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30641</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B6164</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29166</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10840141</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10840141</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46087</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A30641)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46087)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1418:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The humble petitions of Mr. Burton and Dr. Bastwicke presented to the honovrable the knights, citizens, and burgesses of the Commons House of Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Burton, Henry, 1578-1648.</author>
                  <author>Bastwick, John, 1593-1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: Print show through with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Freedom of the press --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Academic freedom.</term>
               <term>Censorship.</term>
               <term>Freedom of information.</term>
               <term>Freedom of speech.</term>
               <term>Teaching, Freedom of.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-06</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46087:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46087:1"/>
            <p>THE HVMBLE
PETITIONS
OF
M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Burton,</hi>
&amp;
D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Bastwicke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PRESENTED TO
THE HONOVRABLE
The KNIGHTS, CITIZENS, and
Burgesses, of the Commons house
of PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>Printed in the yeare. 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:46087:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46087:2"/>
            <head>TO THE
HONOVRABLE
The Knights, Citizens, and
Burgesses, of the Commons
house of Parliament.</head>
            <opener>The humble Petition of Henry
Burton, late exile, and close Prisoner
in Castle Cornet, in the Ile of Garnesey. In all humblenesse sheweth,</opener>
            <p>THat whereas your Petitioner, on the 5 of
<hi>Novemb.</hi> 1636, did preach two Sermons
in his own Parish Church, in St. <hi>Matthew
Friday-street, London,</hi> for the which hee was in
<hi>December</hi> then next following, summoned to
appeare before <hi>D. Ducke,</hi> one of the Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners
for causes Ecclesiasticall, at <hi>Cheswicke,</hi> in
the County of <hi>Middlesex:</hi> where (with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gister
of the High Commission Court) the said
<hi>D. Ducke</hi> tendred to the Petitioner, the Oath
<hi>Ex Officio,</hi> to answer to certaine Articles there
presented: which Oath the Petitioner refusing
to take, did then and there appeale from the
said Court, unto the Kings Majesty: which
appeale the said <hi>D. Ducke</hi> did admit, and the
said Register by <hi>D. Ducks</hi> direction, did then,
and there enter in writing.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:46087:3"/>
Notwithstanding which said appeale, a spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall
High Commission Court was shortly after
called at <hi>London,</hi> consisting of foure or five Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors,
where the said Commissioners proceeded
illegally, to suspend the Petitioner in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence,
by meanes whereof, as of the threatnings
of the said Commissioners, hee was enforced to
keepe his house, untill a <hi>Sergeant at Armes,</hi> with
divers Pursevants and other armed Officers,
assiisted by <hi>Alderman Abel,</hi> then Sheriffe of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi>
beset the Petitioners House, at 11 of the
Clock at night, and violently broke open his
dores with Iron crowes, and the like, and sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prised
him in his house, he making no resistance
at all: where having first searched his study, and
taking away such Bookes as they pleased, they
carried your Petitioner to prison, whence, the
next day being the second of <hi>Feb.</hi> by a preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
Order from the Lords of the Counsell, he
was conveyed to the Fleet, and there kept close
prisoner.</p>
            <p>During which imprisonment, an informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
was exhibited against the Petitioner, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
in his Majesties Court of Star-Chamber,
whereby he was charged (<hi>inter alia</hi>) with pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing
of a certaine Booke, containing <hi>an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology
for an Appeale,</hi> with his said two Sermons,
Intituled, <hi>For God and the King,</hi> wherein hee
taught Subjects to yeeld all manner of due obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
to their lawfull King, and reproved all
lawlesse Innovations in Religion, &amp;c. Which
Information, the Petitioner upon his Oath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:46087:3"/>
the hand of <hi>M. Holt,</hi> being then of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell,
assigned by speciall order from the said
Court, did put in his answer, wherein hee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged
such things onely, as his said Counsell
conceived to be materiall, and pertinent for his
just defence in publishing the said booke, but
denyed all other matters in the said Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
conteined, which said Answer, being admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
and received in Court, the petitioner (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
then a close prisoner) not onely attended
the exhibiting of Interrogatories, according to
the custome of that Court, but withall, after
some universall delay, did write unto the Kings
Attourney to hasten them: but before the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminer
came, the petitioner heard that his said
Answer was referred to S. <hi>Ioh Bramston,</hi> Knight,
Lord chiefe Justice of the Kings Bench: Sir
<hi>Iohn Finch,</hi> then chiefe Justice of the Common-pleas,
and was by them wholy expunged as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent
and Scandalous (save onely the not-guilty)
And the petitioner understanding the an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>swer
he was to make to the Interrogatories was
to be reckned as a part of his answer, admitted in
court, but afterward expunged as impertinent
&amp; scandalous (as aforesaid): so as if he should
then have answer'd the Interogatories, he shold
thereby have assented to the said act of the said
Iudges, and so to the condemnation of his cause
before the hearing, wherby he should have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted
his former Oath, that his said Answer
was a true Answer, and so should justly have
brought himselfe under the guilt of wilful per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46087:4"/>
and his cause under just censure. For that
very reason he held himselfe not bound, (as hee
conceived) to answer the Interrogatories, for
that his said answere was so expunged, and the
(<hi>Not-Guilty</hi>) as the foot so tied to the head with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
the maine body, (and that in the Judges
owne words) as the Petitioner could not in
any sort take or acknowledge it now for other
then the Judges owne answere, as may appeare
upon Record in the same Court.</p>
            <p>Neverthelesse, the Court taking the same in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation
<hi>Pro-confesso,</hi> and refusing to admit a
copie of the Petitioners own true answer, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
of his reasons of not answering the Interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatories,
both which at his Censure, he tendred
to the Court, desiring they might bee then and
there publikely read the 14. of June, 13. <hi>Caroli
Regis,</hi> proceeded to censure, wherby your Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner
was censured <hi>in a Fine of 5000. li. to his
Majesty, To be deprived of his ecclesiastical benefice,
degraded from his Ministeriall function and degrees
in the Vniversity, and ordered to be set on the Pillory,
where both his ears were to be cut off, confined to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual
close imprisonment in</hi> Lancaster <hi>Castle, debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
the accesse of his wife or any other, to come to him,
but onely his Keeper, and denied the use of penne,
inke, and paper.</hi> All which (except the Fine)
was executed accordingly. And after his close
imprisonment for twelve weekes in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
Gaole in the said Castle, hee was (by what
extrajudicial order he knows not) transported
by the conduct of one <hi>Brian Burton</hi> appointed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46087:4"/>
by the <hi>High</hi> Sheriffe of Lancaster, (who used
your Petitioner very basely and deceitfully,
(in that his transportation) which was in the
Winter season through dangerous seas; to the
apparant hazzard both of his health and life)
to the said Castle of <hi>Garnsey,</hi> where hee hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained
a close prisoner and exile almost three
whole yeares, his wife utterly prohibited upon
paine of imprisonement to set her foote upon
any part of the Iland, where shee might but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
how her husband did, contrary to the
Lawes of God, and the liberties of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>May it therefore please this Honourable
House, to take the Petitioners sad cause into
consideration, and for the better manifesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of his grievance in this cause, to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign
him for Counsel <hi>Master Serjeant At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins,
Master Tomlins, and Master Gurdon,</hi> to
assist him in his cause, and to command that
hee may take out such copies <hi>Gratis</hi> out of
the said severall Courts, as doe or may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne
his said cause.</p>
            <closer>And your Petitioner as in duty bound,
shall daily pray for your prosperities. <signed>HENRY BURTON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:46087:5"/>
            <head>TO THE
HONOVRABLE
The Knights, Citizens, and
Burgesses, of the Commons
House of Parliament.</head>
            <opener>The humble Petition of John Bastwicke,
Doctor in Physicke, lately retained close
Prisoner and Exile in the
Island of SYLLY. Most humbly sheweth;</opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat your Petitioner having a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
sixe yeares since set out a
Booke in Latine called <hi>Elenchus
Religionis Papisticae,</hi> with an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
thereunto called <hi>Flagel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum
Pontificis, &amp; Episcoporum Latialium;</hi> being
thereunto provoked by one <hi>Richard Short,</hi> a
Papist that maintained the Popes Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,
the Masse, and Papall Religion; In which
Booke your Petitioner (for preventing all
misinterpretations, of his pious, and good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions
therein) in his Epistle to the Reader,
fully declared himselfe, that your Petitioner
meant nothing against such Bishops as acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46087:5"/>
their Authority from Kings and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours,
yet because your Petitioner (the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
ever to shew the Papall usurpation of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Princes) therein, onely maintained by
way of Argument (as other Orthodox writers
of that Subject usually have done) a parity of
the said Bishop of <hi>Rome,</hi> or all other Bishops
or Presbyters, by the word of God, denying
his and their Supremacie over other Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters
to be by the Divine institution.</p>
            <p>Therupon a Pursevant by Authority from
the High Commission Court came into your
Petitioners house at <hi>Colchester</hi> in <hi>Essex,</hi> in his
absence; and the said Pursevant assisted with
the then Bayliffes and Constables of <hi>Colchester</hi>
aforesaid, ransacked his said house, together
with his Chests and Trunks, and with great
violence broke open your Petitioners Study,
which was in his Apothecaries house, and took
and carried away divers of your Petitioners
Bookes, Writings, Letters, and what else the
Pursevant pleased, without making of restitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of them to your Petitioner.</p>
            <p>And then your Petitioner was prosecuted
in the said high Commission Court, principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
for his said Booke; where after a long and
charitable prosecution, he was the 12. of <hi>Feb.
1634,</hi> fined 1000.<hi rend="sup">li.</hi> to the King, excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated,
debarred to practice Physicke, the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest
means of his liveli-hood, his said Booke
ordered to be burnt; That he should pay cost
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46087:6"/>
of suit, and be imprisoned till he should make
a recantation: the which heavy censure was
only for the said Book, wherin your Petitioner
maintained the <hi>Prerogative</hi> of a King against
the Papacy. Whereas one <hi>Thomas Chawney</hi> of
<hi>Essex,</hi> lately wrote a Booke in maintenance of
the Papall Religion, and in defence of the
Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and averres it to bee a true
Church, the which Booke is dedicated to the
<hi>Archbishop</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and was and is pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronized
and defended by the said <hi>Archbishop,</hi>
and the said <hi>Chawney</hi> never troubled for it.
After which censure declared as aforesaid; all
the Bishops that were then present denyed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly
that they held their jurisdiction from
his Majesty, and affirmed that they had it from
God only; and the <hi>Archbishop</hi> of <hi>Canterbury</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
many other erroneous sayings uttered
by him, maintained the said <hi>Chawneys</hi> Booke,
and maintained that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was
a true Church, and that it erred not in funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals:
and he, and other the said Bishops,
there defamed the holy Scriptures, and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
reverend Mr. <hi>Calvin.</hi> In regard whereof,
and for the vindicating of your Petitioners in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency
in the matters for which he was most
unjustly censured, as aforesaid, your Petitioner
published in print another Book in Latine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled,
<hi>Apologeticus ad Praesules Anglicanos,</hi>
expressing the truth of his proceedings, and
speeches of his said censure. For which last
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46087:6"/>
mentioned Booke, and his Booke called the
<hi>Let any</hi> (not then in print) an information was
exhibited against him and others in the Star-Chamber,
to which your Petitioners answer
being drawn and engrossed, was only subscri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed
by himselfe, because he could get no coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell
to set their hands to it: your Petitioner
tendred the said Answer first at the Starre-chamber
Office, and after in open Court at the
Star-chamber Bar, but it would not be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
for want of Counsellors hands to it, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
to former Presidents. But the Court of
Star-chamber tooke the said information <hi>Pro
confesso,</hi> and censured <hi>your Petitioner</hi> 5000.<hi rend="sup">li.</hi>
               <hi>fine to the King, to stand in the Pillory, and to loose
both his eares, and to be close prisoner in</hi> Lancaster
Castle <hi>in</hi> Cornewall: all which hath been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted
upon him with great extremity, to the
perill of his life. After all which extremitie,
your Petitioner (by what order he knoweth it
not, it being no part of his Censure in Starre-chamber)
was transported from the said Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle,
<hi>to the Iland of</hi> SYLLY, a place so barren,
that it affords not ordinary necessaries, where
he hath been inclose duration for three years
or more, and not suffered to have any of his
friends come at him, (his very Wife being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited
by the Lords of the Counsels order)
under paine of imprisonment, not to set her
foot upon any part of the said <hi>Iland</hi> to enquire
of his welfare. So that your, Petitioner hath
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:46087:7"/>
beene exiled from his wife and divers small
children 3. yeares and more, besides the great
straits and miseries which hee hath sustained
during the said time. All which is contrary to
the law of God and man, and the Liberties of
a free Subject, and to the utter undoing of your
Petitioner, his Wife and children.</p>
            <p>May it therfore please this Honourable
Assembly to take these pressing grievances
of your Petitioner into your considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
and to afford him such reliefe the rein,
as in your grave wisedomes shall seeme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonant
to Justice and equity, and to assigne
him for Counsell, Mr. <hi>Atkins,</hi> Mr. <hi>Ludbore,</hi>
Mr. <hi>Tomlins,</hi> Mr. <hi>Gurdon,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Randall,</hi>
to assist him in this his complaint, and to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
that your Petitioner may take out <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis</hi>
such Copies of the said Censures, War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants
and Orders, and other the proceedings
in the said severall Courts as shall or may
any way concerne this his sad, yet most just
complaint, with warrant from this Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
house, to bring in his witnesse.</p>
            <closer>And your Petitioner as in duty bound,
shall ever pray for your prosperities; <signed>IOHN BASTWICKE.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:46087:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
