<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proposall humbly offered for the farming of liberty of conscience</title>
            <author>Butler, Samuel, 1612-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-01">2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30777</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B6329</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37173</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16263843</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16263843</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105167</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A30777)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105167)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1089:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proposall humbly offered for the farming of liberty of conscience</title>
                  <author>Butler, Samuel, 1612-1680.</author>
                  <author>B. G.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London?] printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: B.G.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Butler by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Liberty of conscience --  Anecdotes</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-04</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-05</date>
            <label>TCP Staff (Michigan)</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105167:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A
PROPOSALL
Humbly Offered,
FOR THE
FARMING
OF
Liberty of Conscience.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1662.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proposal">
            <pb facs="tcp:105167:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105167:2"/>
            <head>A
PROPOSALL
HUMBLY OFFERED
For the Farming of Liberty of
Conscience.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince nothing can be dearer unto poor Christians,
then Liberty, for the Free Exercise of their Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
and Conscience, which hath kindled that
Fire in the Bowels of the three Kingdoms which
all the pretious Blood that hath been shed, during
these late Troubles, hath not been able totally to
extinguish: And since many of us, whose Names
are affixed, were so profitably Instrumental in
these late Combustions, as appears all along in our Sermons before
the Honorable House of Parliament, in the Years, 1642, 43, 44, 45,
46. in exciting the good People of this Nation, to seek and maintain
their Christian Liberty, against all Prelatical and Antichristian Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position
whatsoever. And considering, that the little Finger of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stacie,
from our first Love, would be a greater Burden upon our
Tender Consciences then the Loyns of Episcopacy, we being more
bound in Honour then Conscience, cannot totally desist; Neither need
any man fear, or so much as suspect, lest any inconvenience, or Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
should happen in Religion by the great diversity of Opinions,
Tongues and Languages, tolerated amongst us, unless in the great
Babel of Episcopacy that may possibly be pull'd down and destroyed
by this our notable Confusion: For if the Gospel was wonderfully
disseminated and spread abroad by every mans speaking in his own
Language, and the very Enemies thereof astonished and miraculously
wrought into a belief of it; how is it likely to be now obstructed, in
the free exercise of our Spiritual Gifts with these our cloven and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
Tongues?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:105167:3"/>And since many Worthy persons (from whom we might little ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
it, but far lesse deserve it) out of their Goodnesse and Clemency,
are pleased to incline to some Libertie, did not some persons, Aliens
and Strangers to the Commonwealth of Israel take up a reproach
against us, as persons reprobated into an impossibility of submission
<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o Principles of Concord, Peace, and Order in Church or State,
never being able hitherto to come to any Consistency amongst our
selves the Ark of God having for twenty years together been expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
to High-wayes Streets and worse places, for want of an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
amongst our own Brethren, where to rest it, or how to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
it.</p>
            <p>If this be our Case, and could we be sure of so much favour as
<hi>Saul</hi> once desired of <hi>Samuel,</hi> That the Bishops would but honour us
before the People, we would in a private Christian way lay our hands
upon our hearts, and acknowledg the hand of God and the Iustice
thereof, in turning us out of his Uineyard as wicked and unprofit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
servants, and to suffer the iniquity of our heels to overtake us,
Crying out with Reverend Mr. <hi>Calamy,</hi> The Ark of God is iustly
departed from us: But being not yet thus assured, do hope the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
will yet believe these to be only Bears Skins lappt about us by
Episcopal hands: And therefore, to the end that a Consistencie and
Onenesse of Iudgment of the whole separating Brethren, and their
Moderation may be known unto all men, and that the world may
know, there is a spirit of Rule and Government resting in us,</p>
            <p>It is humbly proposed, That the sole power of Granting Licenses and
Indulgences for Liberty of Conscience within the Kingdome of
<hi>England,</hi> Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> and Town of <hi>Barwick,</hi> may be vested
in the Persons under-named, for the Term of seven years, under
the Farm Rent of an Hundred Thousand pound <hi>per annum,</hi> to
Commence from the 25<hi>th</hi> day of <hi>March</hi> next, under such Rates
and Qualifications as are hereafter specified.</p>
            <div type="list">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:105167:3"/>
               <head>The Names of the Grand Commissioners and Farmers of Liberty of
Conscience; proposed on Munday, March 2. 1662.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Edmond Calamy</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Tilham, <hi>late of</hi> Colchester</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Philip Nye</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Feake.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Stanley Gower of Dorchester.
George Fox, <hi>Executor of the last
Will and Testament of</hi> Iames
Nailor <hi>deceased.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Doctor</hi> Lazarus Seaman</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Dell, late of Cambridge.</item>
                  <item>Doctor Owen</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Bryan, <hi>late of</hi> Coventry.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Matthew Mead</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Iohn Coppin</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Doctor</hi> Manton</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Kiffen</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> William Ienkins</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Fisher, <hi>late of</hi> Kent.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Doctor</hi> Thomas Goodwin</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Hammond, <hi>late of</hi> Newcastle.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Peter Sterry</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Bridges, <hi>late of</hi> Yarmouth.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Ioseph Carryll</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Tombes, <hi>late of</hi> Lemster.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Leigh, <hi>late of</hi> Lumbard-street.</item>
                  <item>The Executor of Mr. <hi>Venner</hi> lately
Executed.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Thomas Case</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Reynor, <hi>late of</hi> Lincoln.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Raph Venning</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Rogers</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Benn, <hi>late of</hi> Dorchester.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> George Griffith, <hi>late of</hi> Charter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house.</item>
                  <item>The Executor of <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> lately
Executed.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> George Newton, <hi>late of</hi> Taunton.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Dan Dyke, <hi>late of</hi> Hertford-shire.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> May<gap reason="illegible: over-inked" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>late of</hi> Kingston.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Ioshua Sprigg.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Henry Iessey.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Newcomen <hi>of</hi> Dedham <hi>in</hi> Essex.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Doctor</hi> Tuckney <hi>of</hi> Cambridge.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Doctor</hi> Cornelius Burges.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Zachary Crofton</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Doctor</hi> Holmes.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Iohn Cann</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Thomas Brooks.</item>
               </list>
               <p>That the Persons aforesaid, may be constituted <hi>Grand Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi>
and <hi>Farmers</hi> of <hi>Liberty of Conscience</hi> within the Kingdom of
<hi>England,</hi> Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> and Town of <hi>Berwick,</hi> and may be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powred
to set up one Publique Office within the City of <hi>London,</hi> and
to nominate and elect a convenient number of Registers, Clerk, and
other Officers: And for the more certainty of all Certificates to be
granted as is hereafter appointed, The said Grand Commissioners
and Farmers may form a common Seal to be kn<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wn, and called by
the name of <hi>The Publique Seal of the Grand Commissioners and Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers
of Liberty of Conscience</hi> engraven. <hi>An Ass without Ears, Bray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
with this Motto incircled <hi>Stat pro ratione libertas:</hi> And the said
Grand Commissioners and Farmers or any 24 of them in the said
Office assembled, may from time to time compound and agree for <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
of Conscience,</hi> with any person or persons, under such Rates
and Qualifications, as are hereafter specified.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="4-5" facs="tcp:105167:4"/>
That the said Grand Commissioners and Farmers, or any 24 of
<unclear>them,</unclear> may constitute and appoint, under the Publique Seal of the
Office, Sub-Commissioners, and other Officers, for every Countie
within the said Kingdom, not exceeding the number of 12. for each
County, whereof 7 to be a <hi>Quorum,</hi> who may compound and agree
for <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> with any person or persons, select Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations,
Ca<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, Towns Corporate, Parishes Hamlets, and Uillages,
by the great, or otherwise, within their respective Countries, not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
the Rates hereafter mentioned.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="table">
               <head>Rates to be observed in all Compositions for Liberty
of CONSCIENCE.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>Per</cell>
                        <cell role="label" cols="2">Annum.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A Presbyterian Minister</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A Ruling Elder</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A Deacon</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A Heater Male or Female in Fellowship to all Ordinances</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A Common Hearer only</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>An Independant Pastor</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A <unclear>Preaching</unclear> Elder</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A Helper in Government</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A Deacon</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A Hearer male or female in Fellowship to all Ordinances</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A common Hearer only</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A Baptist admitted to the Administration of all Ordinances</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A Preaching assistant</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>An Elder in Office</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eacon</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A Hearer in Fellowship male or female to all Ordinances</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A common Hearer only</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A Fifth Monarcher admitted to hold forth</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>An Elder under the same Administration</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A Deacon under the same Administration</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A Hearer male or female in Fellowship according to the value
of his or her Estate 2 s. <hi>per l. per annum</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A common hearer male or Female according to the value of his
or her Estate 12 d. <hi>per l. per annum.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A speaking male Quaker</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A speaking female Quaker</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A common Quaker male or female</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A Confessor</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A Seminary or Mass-Priest at large</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A private Mass-Priest</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A Roman Catholick in any other order</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A Roman Catholick not in order male or Female</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>An Officer under any Administration not mentioned in the rates
aforesaid being a Native of England, such only excepted as
stand Conformable to the Church of England</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A common person under any Administration not mentioned in
the rates aforesaid being a Native of England, such only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted
as stand conformable to the Church of England</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>An Officer under any Administration whatsoever not a Native
of England, except conformable to the Church of England</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>A private person under any Administration whatsoever not a
Native of England, except conformable to the Church of
England</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="table">
               <head>Rates to be observed in compounding for Liberty of Conscience in the
particulars following, viz.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>For Liberty to assert the Popes Supremacy</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>For Liberty to write, speak, or Preach against the Government
as they shall be inwardly moved</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>For liberty to keep on their Hats before Magistrates, or in Courts
of Judicature</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>For Liberty to rail publickly against the Bishops and Common
Prayer</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>For Liberty to refuse all manner of Oaths, of Allegiance and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy,
or in Cases Civil or Criminal</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>For liberty to deny Tythes and other Church Duties</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>For liberty to expound the <hi>Revelations</hi> and the Book of <hi>Daniel</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>For Liberty to disturb any Congregation after Sermon</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>For Liberty to assert the Solemn League and Covenant</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>For Liberty to instruct youth in the short Catechism set forth by the Assembly of Divines</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>That any person or persons gifted for any the Particulars above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said,
may have liberty therein either as an <hi>Itinerate,</hi> in private or
publique, at the Rates abovesaid.</p>
               <p>That no person or persons, be admitted to compound for <hi>Liberty of
Conscience,</hi> until he or they have first taken and subscribed, the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn
Protestation following, before the said Grand Commissioners
and <unclear>Farmers</unclear>, or their Sub-Commissioners respectively.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:105167:5"/>I A. B. do here solemnly protest, That I judg my self still
bound by the Solemn League and Covenant, by the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
by private Church-Covenant, or by any other Oath which
I have taken ever since the year 1641. and that so far as with
safety to my person and Estate I may, I will endeavour the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
extirpation of Episcopacy, and to the utmost of my power,
will abet and promote all Schism, faction, and discord, both in
Church and State, according to the best form and manner, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed
and laid open in the Sermons of many of the Grand-Commissioners
and Farmers, before the Parliament, appointed
to be Printed, and now called the Homilies of the Separated
Churches. And that I will never by what Conviction or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
soever, whether legall or Episcopall, ever consent to the
Establisht Doctrine and discipline of the Church of England.</p>
               <p>And I do likewise believe, That Liberty of Conscience was
a Mysterious, yet profitable talent committed to the Churches,
and that it may be lawfully Farmed out for advantage and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement.</p>
               <p>That no person within the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> Dominion of
<hi>Wales,</hi> or Town of <hi>Barwick,</hi> may, from, and after the 5 day of <hi>March</hi>
                  <unclear>next,</unclear> use or exercise any manner of <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> except per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
standing conformable to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> untill such per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
or persons shall first take the Solemn Protestation, and shall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound
with the said Grand Commissioners and Farmers for <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of Conscience,</hi> nor shall he be admitted or permitted to be a Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker
or Hearer, in any Meeting or Assemblies whatsoever.</p>
               <p>That the said Grand Commissioners and Farmers of <hi>Liberty of
Conscience,</hi> may have power to constitute under the Publique Seal
of the said Office, a convenient number of Spiritual Gagers, who
may have and exercise all such Powers, Priviledges, &amp; Authorities,
as the Gagers for Excize of Beer and Ale, have, or ought to have and
enjoy, and may at any time, in case of Suspition, enter into any house
or place, publike or private, to gage and try the Spirits and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of any person or persons; and by Praying, Preaching, or other
good Exhortation, disswade from Episcopacie, and the Common-Prayer,
the better to fit and prepare them to compound for <hi>Liberty of
Conscience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the said Grand Commissioners and Farmers of <hi>Liberty of
Conscience,</hi> may have power to fine any person or persons (not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
the sum of 20 l for every offence, who shall, after Composi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
for <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> and subscribing the <hi>Solemn Protestati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:105167:5"/>
be present in any Church or Chappel, within the Kingdom of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> and Town of <hi>Berwick,</hi> in the time of any
part of Divine Service, unless at the Funeral of his Father, or some
other like occasion: or, if being present at any such occasion, he shall ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
respond, be uncovered, or carry himself reverently, in the time of
Divine Service aforesaid.</p>
               <p>That the said Grand Commissioners and Farmers of <hi>Liberty of
Conscience,</hi> or any 24 of them assembled at the Office aforesaid, may
have and exercise a Iurisdiction of Appeal in all matters relating to
<hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> within the said Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and shall
have a conclusive power in all matters brought before them, by way of
Appeal as aforesaid.</p>
               <p>That for the better management of all such matters as shall be
brought judicially before the said Grand Commissioners and Farmers
of <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> by way of Appeal, the said Grand Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners
and Farmers shall have power to constitute and appoint Mr.
<hi>Oliver St. Johns,</hi> and such others, as they judge fit for their said Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,
to be of Standing-Councel with the said Grand Commissioners
and Farmers: And the said Mr. <hi>Oliver St. Johns,</hi> being so constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
and appointed under the Publick Seal of the said Office, shall, and
may be exempted and discharged from being in any Publike Office, or
place of Trust or Profit, for the said term of 7 years, any thing to the
contrary notwithstanding.</p>
               <p>That if any person or persons shall happen to be proceeded against in
any of the Ecclesiastical Courts of the Bishops of this Kingdome for
Contumacy, for Non-Conformity, for non-payment of Tythes, and
other Church-Duties, for publick rayling against the Bishops, the
Common-Prayer, or the Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or
shall speak Oprobriously or Scandalously against the Doctrine or Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline
thereof, as Antichristian, or shall maintain any Positions or
Doctrines contrary thereunto: Every such person producing a Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
from the said Grand Commissioners and Farmers under the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
Seal of the said Office, that such person or persons are under Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position
for Liberty of Conscience, shall actually be discharged, and all
further proceedings stayed; Any thing to the contrary notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>That if any persons shall happen to be Indicted or Criminally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded
against in any of His Majesties Courts at <hi>Westminster,</hi> or else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where
within the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> either for Treasonable Spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
or Practises, for publike raysing at the Government, or for Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous
words against either or both Houses of Parliament, or for Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressing
any of the Penal Laws and Statutes of this Kingdom; Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
such person or persons producing a Certificate from the said Grand
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105167:6"/>
Commissioners and Farmers under the publike Seal of the said Office,
that such person or persons are under Composition for Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science;
and that such words or practises were not spoken or acted <hi>mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiose,</hi>
but were only the natural and proper effects and product of Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of Conscience, shall be discharged, and all further proceedings stayed,
Any thing to the Contrary notwithstanding.</p>
               <p>That the said Grand Commissioners and Farmers of Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science,
may have power from time to time to Ordain Pastors, Elders,
and Deacons, or any other Officers under any Administration whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,
by the laying on of the publique Seal of the Office: Which said
Imposition of the said publique Seal being received with a Certificate;
shall be as lawful an Ordination, as if every such person had received
Imposition from the hands of the Presbytery, Any late Usage or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome
to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
               <p>That the said Grand Commissioners and Farmers may have power
from time to time, to set apart dayes for publique Fastings, and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation
and Thanksgiving; on which dayes it may be lawful for any
person or persons appointed to Officiate before the said Grand Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners
and Farmers, to stir up the people to a holy Indignation against
themselves, for having by their want of Zeal and Brotherly kindnesse
one towards another, lost many pretious enjoyments; and above all,
the never to be forgotten Losse of the late Power and Dominion, which
with the Expence of so much Blood and Rapine, was put into the hands
of the Saints. And to take up for a Lamentation and great thoughts
of heart, the Divisions of <hi>Ruben,</hi> That having our Sacks full, such an
evill spirit should be found in the midst of us, as to fall out by the way;
might it have beén with those that abode by the Stuff, as with those
that went out to the Battel, it had not beén with us as at this day.
Some starting aside, like a broken Bow, in the year 48; others conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing
to bear the burthen and heat of the day untill 60, being harness'd,
did then turn their backs in the day of Battel.</p>
               <p>That the twentieth day of <hi>April</hi> next, commonly called <hi>Easter-Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi>
be kept as a day of Solemn Fasting and Humiliation, for a Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
upon these Gospel—Undertakings, and that Mr. <hi>Edmond
Calamy,</hi> Mr. <hi>Peter Sterry,</hi> Doctor <hi>Lazarus Seaman,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Feake,</hi> be
desired to carry on the Work of the Day in Prayer and Preaching, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the said Grand Farmers, and that the particulars following, be
recommended to their Consideration in the Work of the Day.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:105167:6"/>
                  <item>1. To Bewail,
<list>
                        <item>1. All our Court Sins.</item>
                        <item>2. Our Bishops Sins.</item>
                        <item>3. Our Monk Sins.</item>
                        <item>4. Our Common-Prayer Sins.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. To Divert,
<list>
                        <item>1. Westminster-Hall Iudgments.</item>
                        <item>2. Our Old-Bayly Iudgments.</item>
                        <item>3. Our Tower-Hill Iudgments.</item>
                        <item>4. Our Charing-Cross Iudgments.</item>
                        <item>5. Our Tyburn Iudgments.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Lastly, For deliverance from the Hand of <hi>Dun,</hi> that uncercumcised
Philistine.</p>
               <p>That the said Grand Commissioners, and Farmers of Liberty of
Conscience, may have power to build Churches and Chappels in any
place or places, except upon such Ground only where Churches or
Chappels do already stand, in regard of the inconvenience of setting
up Altar against Altar; And forasmuch as the Custom of Reading some
part of the holy Bible before Sermon, commonly called first and second
Lessons, hath been found fruitless, That therefore the said Grand
Commissioners &amp; Farmers may have power to appoint instead thereof,
the Annual reading of those Sermons preached by many of the said
Grand Commissioners and Farmers, before the Parliament, Upon
special Occasions of Thanksgiving and Humiliation, from the Year
1641, to the Year 1648: Which said Sermons may be called, The
Homilies of the separating Churches.</p>
               <p>That the said Grand Commissioners and Farmers may have power
to require Mr. <hi>Gilbert Millington,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Luke Robinson,</hi> the lame
Evangelist, to deliver up all such Articles, Orders, Books, Papers,
and other Writings, as were transacted before the late Committee for
plundered Ministers; and likewise, all such as were passed and transa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
before Mr. <hi>Philip Ney,</hi> and some others of the now Grand Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners
and Farmers, and heretofore called Commissioners or Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
Tryers, to the end, the said Articles, Orders, Books, and other
Papers may be Printed and Published, and may be kept at the said
Office upon Record for ever, and appointed to be the Book of Canons
of the separated Churches.</p>
               <p>All this being done, we may upon Scripture Grounds expect, that
the door of Hope may yet be open to Us, and Our Children after Us, to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105167:7"/>
see the travell of our Souls, and to lett Us into the promised Land,
and to reap some of those Clusters of the Grapes of <hi>Canaan,</hi> which with
so much Labour and Toyl of Body and Mind were planted, especially
in the Years of 1641, 42, 43, 44, 45. by many of Us, and other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
Saints and Ministers of the Gospel, who are since fallen asleép,
and have, We hope, reaped the Fruits of those Labours, the Lord ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
in that Day put a mighty Spirit into Us, &amp; set Us as Watchmen
upon the Towers of <hi>Israel,</hi> to cry mightily, <hi>Curse ye Meroze, Curse ye
bitterly;</hi> the Lord Grant, That those Heart-breaking Labours of Ours,
those King-destroying Labours, these Kingdom-ruining Labours, those
Gospel-scandalizing Labours, those Church-subverting Labours, those
Soul-confounding Labors of Ours, may never be forgotten, but may be
written as with the point of a Diamond, upon the Heart of the King,
upon the Hearts of the Bishops, upon the Heart of the Parliament,
and upon the Hearts of all the People from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beersheba,</hi> that so
in Gods good time we may receive our Reward seven fold-into our own
Bosomes; and that the Genera<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions to come may hear and fear, and do
no more so wickedly.</p>
               <signed>So prayes,
B. G.</signed>
               <pb facs="tcp:105167:7"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
