<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An effort against bigotry, and for Christian catholocism being a discourse on Rom. 14, 17 / delivered at Andover in Hampshire by Henry Chandler.</title>
            <author>Chandler, Henry.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-10">2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31656</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1926</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32616</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12730451</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12730451</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66470</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A31656)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66470)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1522:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An effort against bigotry, and for Christian catholocism being a discourse on Rom. 14, 17 / delivered at Andover in Hampshire by Henry Chandler.</title>
                  <author>Chandler, Henry.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Lawrence ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 32.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans XIV, 17 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Religious tolerance --  England --  Protestant churches.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-08</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-11</date>
            <label>Celeste Ng</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-11</date>
            <label>Celeste Ng</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66470:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66470:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN
EFFORT
AGAINST
BIGGOTRY,
AND FOR
<hi>Chriſtian Catholiciſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being a Diſcourſe on <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 17. Delivered
at <hi>Andover</hi> in <hi>Hampſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> HENRY CHANDLER.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Nunquam de Dogmatibus Chriſtus diſſeruit, ſed ſaepe, &amp; ubique, imo
ſemper de vivendi Sinceritate.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mat. 23. 23.</bibl>
               <p>Wo unto you Scribes and Phariſees, Hypocrites; for ye
pay Tyth of Mint, and Aniſe, and Cummin, and have omitted the
<hi>weightier</hi> Matters of the Law—</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Jam. 3. 17.</bibl>
               <p>But the Wiſdom that is from above, is firſt pure, then
peaceable, gentle, and eaſie to be intreated.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Iohn Lawrence,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi>
in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:66470:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66470:2"/>
            <head>To my Generous and much Reſpected Friend,
Mr. <hi>Gabriel Goldney</hi> of <hi>Andover.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE following Diſcourſe was delivered in your hearing
with an honeſt Deſign, and 'tis now Preſented you in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance
with your Requeſt: You ſome time ſince intimated,
That the hearing of it was very grateful to you; I pray
God it may in the review be altogether as profitable. 'Tis not Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated
for the Intereſt of any Party of Chriſtians, as a Party need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly
Dividing from, or Hurtfully Oppoſing the reſt; but (if I mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake
not) equally ſerving the real Intereſt of all. Let my Tongue
cleave to the roof of my mouth, and my right hand forget her cunning,
rather than by Word or Writing I ſhould wilfully promote Faction to
the damage of Subſtantial <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncontroverted Christianity. No Man on
Earth more ſincerely wiſheth than my ſelf, that all Names of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction
amongst Protestants were for ever buried under a just and
righteous Accomodation; no Man more heartily laments the Schiſms
that are amongst us, or more unfeignedly longs for a thorough Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of them. I doubt not but that there are multitudes of different
Denominations that can eaſily more Skilfully Preſcribe for the Healing
of our Distempers than my ſelf, but other Perſons receiving more Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents
than my ſelf, is no Diſcharge to me from a faithful managing
and improving what I have receiv'd. Nor must a Senſe of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency
of my Performances ſo far diſhearten me as to prevent my
just Endeavours: Wherefore I am willing that you ſhould have
this Diſcourſe to read, after your hearing of it, and to communicate
it as you ſhall judge expedient: And to this I am the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined,
for that the Diſcourſe hath been expreſly approv'd by two wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<hi>Miniſters,</hi> whoſe Judgment we both value. One of them is
pleaſed thus to expreſs himſelf: <q>—As to the Diſcourſe it ſelf, I
could not but be pleaſed with it: It does with great Piety, Solidity
and Justice, expoſe that which I take to be the most prevailing
and dangerous Distemper of the Age, <hi>viz.</hi> a placing our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
in, and laying out our Zeal upon little inſignificant things (as
Words, or Phraſes, Speculative Opinions, or meer Circumstances
and Opinions) in being <hi>for</hi> or <hi>againſt</hi> theſe; in which, ſuppoſing
we be in the right, we are (we can be) but very little the better; but
if it ſhou'd happen we are under a mistake, we must needs be
greatly the worſe. To place the <hi>Kingdom of God</hi> in ſuch things
is the <hi>common miſchief</hi> of our Day; hence we are broken into
<pb facs="tcp:66470:3"/>
Parties, and by the ſame Spirit are our ſhameful Diviſions fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
and kept up; and 'tis the Cure of this Spirit that alone can
effectually heal the Breaches there are amongst us. Nor is this
over magnifying our ſelf-deviſed Religiouſneſs, and confining
thereupon the Kingdom of God within the Pale of our Reſpective
Parties, the leſs <hi>pernicious</hi> and fatal, for being ſo exceeding
common: Hence it is that there is ſo viſible a Decay of Christian
Charity; that there is ſo notorious a diſregard of the most impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant
and distinguiſhing Instances of Christianity, through the
miſapplying of Zeal to the little Impertinencies that neither need nor
deſerve it—If this Diſcourſe fall into the hands of ſuch as need
it most, and the Divine Spirit pleaſe to accompany it, I cannot
doubt but its ſucceſs will be ſuch, as will greatly promote and help
on a more Peaceful and Flouriſhing State of Christ's Kingdom
amongst us; for which end it ſhall be followed with the fervent
Prayers of your affectionate Brother, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> When I read theſe Lines, and conſidered the worth of the
Perſon that wrote them, and when I remember'd that another very
valuable Minister had ſaid of the Diſcourſe, That he wiſh'd there
were Ten Thouſand of ſuch Sermons Printed, and ſcattered up and
down; I found my ſelfleſs unwilling to venture upon appearing thus
in publick, than I was before. I doubt not but that the most diſeaſed
will find fault; no matter for that, let me be blamed by them, ſo
I may but heal them; but if that be not the Iſſue, I ſhall have the
ſatisfaction that occompanies an honest Deſign and Endeavour. May
the infinitely great and good God requite with Spiritual and Eternal
Bleſſings the Reſpect and Kindneſs you have ſhewn me. May you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience
more and more the Solid and Durable Comforts of Practical
and Peaceable Christianity; may you be the Temple of the Holy
Ghost, and your Family a little Church; may all good things be mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied
to you, and you made better by all; may I and mine meet You
and Yours with Joy, at the right hand of Jeſus in that Day; may
fiery Faction continually decreaſe, and Faith, Love and Holineſs grow
exceedingly every where: Theſe, Sir, are the Sincere and Fervent
Deſires of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Obliged Friend and Servant,
In the Work of the Goſpel,
Henry Chandler.</signed>
               <dateline>Andover, <date>Aug.
16. 1698.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:66470:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Romans XIV. xvii.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the Kingdom of GOD is not Meat and Drink.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Decay of Holy Zeal for Practical Godlineſs, and
its woful Degenerating into an Uncharitable Factious
Contending for little Notions, and the diſputable
Appendages of Religion, is too too viſible every
where. And of ſuch ſcandalous Aſpect, and deſtructive Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency
is it, that it deſerves to be lamented with (if it were
poſſible) Tears of Blood. And the Cure of this Diſtemper
(raging amongſt all ſorts) to be attended unto with the moſt
Speedy, Skilful, and Induſtrious Application. This is my Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
Thought, and the reaſon of my pitching upon this Text,
as the Foundation of the Preſent, and ſome following Diſcourſes.</p>
            <p>Which Text I purpoſe, with God's help, to manage with
the beſt of my Skill, and with all poſſible Faithfulneſs and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiality
for the aforeſaid End; not caring whether I do here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
Pleaſe or Diſpleaſe Men, ſo I may but be Approv'd of God,
as one that hath taken the proper Method to Build his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
in the World, and particularly in this Town.</p>
            <p>I ſhall endeavour to acquaint you with the Occaſion and
Senſe of the Words, that I may clear my way for raiſing the
Doctrine that I intend more largely to proſecute.</p>
            <p>The occaſion of theſe Words (as of the whole Chapter, which
is one continued Argument) was this;</p>
            <p>Many of the Jews being, by the Doctrine and Miracles of
the Apoſtles, convinced that Jeſus was the Promiſed Meſſiah,
Believed in Him, and became Chriſtians; but as yet not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
the full deſign of the Chriſtian Inſtitution; miſtaking
the Nature and Uſe of the Moſaick Diſpenſation, and poſſibly
miſunderſtanding the Words in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> ſignifying
the long duration of that <hi>Aeconomy,</hi> for Perpetuity, as though
God meant by them that it ſhould be continued to the end of
the World; they concluded that their Believing in Chriſt was
no diſingagement from <hi>Judaiſm,</hi> but thought they were as much
obliged to obſerve the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> (even the Ceremonial) as
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66470:4"/>
ever. They looked not on the <hi>Chriſtian Inſtitution</hi> as what was
now to ſucceed in the room and place of <hi>Judaiſm,</hi> to be laid
aſide, but as a Supplement to it with which it was to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued,
ſuppoſing they ſhould be never the worſe <hi>Chriſtians</hi> for
their Obſervation of the <hi>Jewiſh Rituals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nay, they not only ſtuck themſelves to the Ceremonial Law,
but alſo took upon them to oblige the</hi> Gentile Converts <hi>to the
ſame thing,</hi> Acts 15. 5. But there roſe up certain of the Sect of the
Phariſees which believed, ſaying, That it was needful to circumciſe
them, and to command them to keep the Law of Moſes.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Gentiles</hi> having never been under <hi>Moſes</hi> Law as ſuch,
nor apprehending any Obligation upon them now to come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
it, took no notice of what the <hi>Jews</hi> ſaid in Vindication of
their Superſtition, but ſtuck to their Liberty, and were as fond
of it, as the other were of their burdenſome Yoke.</p>
            <p>This occaſion'd uncharitable Contentions amongſt the two
Parties, rais'd Diſputes and Quarrellings, put 'em upon De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing
and Judging of one another, as is intimated by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition,
<hi>ver.</hi> 3. <hi>Let not him that eateth deſpiſe him that eateth
not; and let not him which eateth not, judge him that eateth.</hi> The
Gentile Chriſtians ate all Meats, even thoſe forbidden by the
Ceremonial Law, and looked upon the <hi>Jew</hi> as a ſcrupulous
humerſome Fool, for making a difference.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jewiſh Christian</hi> (or Chriſtianized Jew) regarding the
Injunctions and Prohibitions of the Ceremonial Law, ate but
ſuch Meats as that allow'd; religiouſly refuſing the reſt, judging
the Gentile Chriſtian as an ungodly Sinner, for his violation of
<hi>Moſes</hi> Law, and ſhunn'd his Communion, as a Prophane and
Unholy Perſon, as is intimated, <hi>ver.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>To Compoſe theſe Differences, and perſuade theſe two differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Parties of Chriſtians to Friendly Converſation and Chriſtian
Communion, the Apoſtle ſpends this whole Chapter, out of
which I have taken my Text, and the ſeven firſt Verſes of the
following Chapter.</p>
            <p>He maketh uſe of many Arguments to perſuade theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders
to an Accommodation; that which my Text affords
is the comparative Trivialneſs of the things that were the
Matter of Debate; they were ſuch as that Mens Opinions and
Practices about them contributed next to nothing to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting
of God's Kingdom in the World.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:66470:4"/>
Perſons of different, yea, contrary Judgment and Practice,
with reſpect to them, may be both good and acceptable Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
of the King of Heaven; both may be under the power of
Grace here, and dwell in Glory together hereafter. And, on
the other hand, Perſons of both Perſuaſions may be deſtitute of
Grace, and miſs of Glory, how ſtrict ſoever they may be in
their Practice, with reſpect to the Matters in Diſpute betwixt
them. <hi>For the Kingdom,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>q. d.</hi> Theſe things commend us
not to God, for neither if we Eat are we the better, neither if
we Eat not are we the worſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 8. It is not a Perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
one way or other, about theſe leſſer Matters, that beſpeaks
Perſons Govern'd by the Spirit of Chriſt, or Intitled unto, or
fit for Heaven. By <hi>Meat</hi> and <hi>Drink</hi> are <hi>Synecdochically</hi> compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended
all other Things of like nature that were then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted.
And when 'tis ſaid, <hi>Theſe are not the Kingdom of God,</hi>
the Expreſſion is <hi>Metonymical,</hi> ſignifying that they contribute
next to nothing, if any thing at all, either to the Building or
Deſtroying of the Kingdom of God amongſt Men. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
'twas ſinful Folly in either Party to be ſo Hot and Eager
in their Diſputes about them, and ſo diſaffected to each other,
upon account of a different Opinion and Practice, with reſpect
to them; this is the Senſe.</p>
            <p>The Text hath Two Parts;
<list>
                  <item>A Negative;</item>
                  <item>A Poſitive.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>1. A Negative. <hi>The Kingdom of God is not meat and drink.</hi>
The deſign of which is to prevent our making a miſtake about
the things that render us, through Chriſt, acceptable to God.</p>
            <p>The former ſtops up a by-path to prevent our ſtraying in
the way of Sin and Ruine, the latter directs us in the true
way to Preſent and Future Happineſs.</p>
            <p>I begin with the Negative Part, <hi>The Kingdom of God is not
Meat and Drink,</hi> which affords us this uſeful and ſeaſonable
Doctrine, <hi>ſc.</hi> A Zeal for the leſſer Matters of Religion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth
nothing to the promoting of the Kingdom of God in
our ſelves or others.</p>
            <p>In handling of this Point I ſhall obſerve this Method, <hi>ſc.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. I ſhall endeavour to prevent your making of Miſtakes, as
to the meaning of it.</item>
               <item>2. I ſhall give you the true Senſe and Meaning of it, and
prove it (both together.)</item>
               <item>3. Make Application.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:66470:5"/>
1. I ſhall endeavour to prevent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But firſt I will lay
down this Preliminary Propoſition, <hi>ſc.</hi> There are greater, and
there are leſſer Matters in Religion. <hi>All</hi> that is in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
Inſtitution taught and enjoyn'd, is not <hi>equally</hi> neceſſary to
be known and practiſed by us, in order to our acceptable
ſerving of the Redeemer here, or our comfortable appearing
before Him in another World. There are ſome things upon
account of which Men are more valuable in God's Eſtimation,
than they are upon the account of others; and there are things
that do more vaſtly advantage our Souls, improve our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
and promote our Felicity, than others. In a word,
there are Doctrines and Precepts that <hi>muſt</hi> be known and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd,
or we <hi>cannot</hi> be Happy, and there are ſuch, which tho'
we be ignorant of them (and conſequently do not <hi>deſignedly</hi>
addreſs our ſelves to the Obſervation of them) we may yet
be Happy. The Precepts that may juſtly be reckoned and
called the <hi>greater and weightier,</hi> are ſuch as enjoyn,</p>
            <p>Internal, Moral Rectitude, which is our neceſſary ſubjective
Capacity for Converſe with the Glorious God.</p>
            <p>Serious Application to the Lord Jeſus as the only Saviour.</p>
            <p>Such as reſpect the Eſſence and Subſtance of Chriſtian Religion,
the Life and Power of Godlineſs, as direct more immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to Holy Practice, as are clearly and plainly delivered,
and as are of conſtant and perpetual Obligation and Uſe.</p>
            <p>The leſſer Precepts are ſuch as direct about the Ornamental
Accidents of External Worſhip.</p>
            <p>Such whereof the Knowledge is not abſolutely neceſſary to
Salvation.</p>
            <p>Such as direct unto Duties of meer poſitive Inſtitution, and
as are but darkly and obſcurely delivered, and not at all Times,
or in all Caſes obliging.</p>
            <p>That theſe two ſorts of Precepts may be thus diſtinguiſhed
into greater and leſſer, that is more and leſs neceſſary, is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,
as by the expreſs Teſtimony of Holy Scripture, ſo from
this conſideration following, <hi>ſc.</hi> were it otherwiſe, one of the
two following Abſurdities muſt be granted. 1. Either that the
Obſervation of nothing in the Chriſtian Religion was neceſſary
to Salvation: Or, 2. That ſo much was neceſſary that no
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66470:5"/>
Man could be Saved. For there's not a Man upon the Earth,
that perfectly knows all the ſeveral Precepts that are couched
and intimated in the pregnant Stile of Holy Scripture, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
with them that lye upon the Surface of the Text, obvious
to the moſt careleſs Eye; and no Man can <hi>deſignedly</hi> addreſs
him to obſerve thoſe Precepts that he knows not. <hi>But we know
but in part,</hi> 1 Cor. 13. 9. The wiſeſt Man's Knowledge is
here neceſſarily imperfect, and therefore his Obedience cannot
be otherwiſe; wherefore it irrefragably follows, that all things
enjoyn'd in Holy Scripture, are not equally neceſſary; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the Diſtinction aboveſaid is juſt and needful.</p>
            <p>Now when I ſay, that a Zeal for theſe leſſer Matters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth
nothing to the promoting of the Kingdom of God in
our ſelves, or others, neither of theſe things immediately fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
is intended.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That theſe leſſer Things are utterly uſeleſs: or,</item>
               <item>2. That any Man hath a Licenſe to be ignorant of them, that
hath Capacity and Opportunity to Study them.</item>
               <item>3. That any Man may, without Sin, act contrary to his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion,
with reſpect to them: or,</item>
               <item>4. That a Man may not, in any caſe, give to another his
Senſe and Opinion about them: or,</item>
               <item>5. That a Man may Profeſs, Aſſent to what he knows to be
falſly affirmed, or approve as good what he knows to be badly
enjoyn'd by Men with reſpect to them, that he might avoid Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Neither of theſe Five Things is intended; for all the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture
being given by Divine Inſpiration, every part of it is
profitable, either for Doctrine, or Reproof, or Correction, or
Inſtruction in Righteouſneſs, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16. And every Man
ought to acquaint himſelf with the whole Book of God, for
his own and others good, as he hath Capacity and Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
he being the moſt perfect Chriſtian, who is moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly
acquainted with, and conformed to that bleſſed Rule of
Holy Perfection.</p>
            <p>Nor can any Man act contrary to the Dictates of a well
informed Conſcience, even in the leſſer Matters of Religion,
without ſin and danger; for our Lord ſaith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 19. <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
ſhall break one of the leaſt Commandments, and ſhall teach
Men ſo, he ſhall be called the leaſt in the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:66470:6"/>
Moreover, a Chriſtian may ſafely give his Opinion about
theſe leſſer Matters, when he is asked by a Perſon that deſires
to know for his own Direction, and not for Contentious Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villing.</p>
            <p>And undoubtedly, he that profeſſeth Aſſent to a known
Falſhood, and profeſſeth Approbation of that which he knows
to be evil, with reſpect unto theſe Matters, to avoid Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
is ſeeking to ſave his Life by thoſe Methods that tend to
Eternal Death, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 39.</p>
            <p>Having thus endeavoured to prevent your miſtaking the
Senſe of the Doctrine, I come now to tell you poſitively what
I do intend by it.</p>
            <p>And there are theſe things meant by it;</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That Mens employing their Gifts and Parts, and ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
their time chiefly in the Defence of their Notions and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions
about theſe Matters, renders them never the more
acceptable unto God. Nor,</item>
                  <item>2. Do they hereby at all better their own Spirits: Nor,</item>
                  <item>3. Are the Souls of others hereby ſerved: Nor,</item>
                  <item>4. Is God's Kingdom hereby enlarged, or his Honour and
Glory promoted. Of theſe in their order.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>1. Mens Employing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God Accepteth or Refuſeth no Man upon account of ſuch
little things as are (in a comparative Senſe at leaſt) the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable
Circumſtances of Religion. He accepteth holy Souls of
different Apprehenſions about them. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 18. <hi>For he that
in theſe things ſerveth Chriſt, is acceptable to God—i. e.</hi> Which
way ſoever he inclines with reſpect to the Matters in debate:
God rejecteth an Hypocritical, Unholy, Unregenerate Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor,
of what Party, Opinion, or Denomination ſoever he
be. If he be Orthodox as to theſe little things, it matters
not; <hi>For Circumciſion is nothing, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion is nothing,
but the keeping of the Commandments of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 7. 19. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
Mens over-fondneſs of theſe ſmaller Matters, their eager
Diſputes about them, their conſuming their Time in the Study
and Defence of them, with the neglect of Matters of greater
Neceſſity and Uſefulneſs, cannot (by ſober Perſons) be thought
what will recommend them to the Wiſe and Holy God, who
as He made Men capable of greater and better Studies, expects
that they employ themſelves about them. For the fuller Proof
of this Particular, let it be conſidered, That God taketh no
delight in Fools or Hypocrites.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:66470:6"/>
1. Not in Fools. <hi>He hath no pleaſure in fools,</hi> Eccl. 5. 4. But
Men that are Zealous for the ſmaller Matters, whilſt they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect
Things of greater Importance, are Fools. <hi>Ye Fools,</hi> ſaid
our Saviour to the Phariſees, whoſe Character (by Him given)
was, <hi>That they tythed Mint, Anniſe and Cummin, and neglected
the weightier Matters of the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Men of this Kidney, (eſpecially if they be ſucceſsful in their
little Factious Attempts) are ready to account themſelves
Wiſe, and thoſe of their Party are too prone (too prodigal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly)
to Applaud them as ſuch. But they are Fools. He's a
Fool that, being in a leaky Ship, minds the Painting of his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
Cabbin, more than the ſtopping of the Leak that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangers
the whole Ship. And what is he better that ſpends
his Time in the purſuit of thoſe Things, that ſerves only for
the recommending his particular Notions, and neglects to
promote that practical Godlineſs in the World, the general
decay of which threatens the whole Chriſtian Intereſt? He's
a Fool that being Sick of the Plague, ſlights the Advice of an
able Faithful Phyſician, becauſe he ſpeaks not the Dialect or
Idiom of his particular County, or had not his Licenſe grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
him by ſuch a particular College of Phyſicians. And he's a
far worſe Fool, that being a ſinful Creature refuſeth the help
of Charitable Skilful Chriſtians or Miniſters, becauſe they are
not in all Things of his Mind in leſſer Matters of Religion,
and that confines his Addreſſes for help to Perſons (it may
be far leſs Skilful) of his own Opinion and Party. How well
pleaſed ſoever ſuch Perſons may be with their Folly, 'tis utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
unreaſonable and impious to expect that God will ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
altogether ſuch an one as themſelves.</p>
            <p>2. God taketh no delight in Hypocrites. This is manifeſt
from the terrible Denunciation of Wrath againſt the Jewiſh
People, upon the account of Hypocrites amongſt them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. 17. <hi>Therefore the Lord ſhall have no joy in their young Men,
neither ſhall have mercy on their Fatherleſs and Widows: FOR
every one is an Hypocrite</hi>—And from our Saviour's oft re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated
Woe thundred out againſt ſuch, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. But ſuch
as are <hi>chiefly</hi> concern'd for the leſſer Matters of Religion are
Hypocrites, as appears by Chriſt's branding the <hi>Phariſees</hi>
(whoſe grand Fault this was) ſo oft with this Name, <hi>Woe unto
you Scribes and Phariſees, Hypocrites, Woe unto you Scribes and
Phariſees, Hypocrites,</hi> no leſs than ſeven times in that Chapter.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:66470:7"/>
And is not he an Hypocrite that plays with Religion? And
doth not he play with Religion, that ſpends his Fervour and
Vigour about the Appendages and Circumſtantials of it, whilſt
the great and weighty Matters are neglected?</p>
            <p>(2.) Men do not hereby better their own Spirits. I ſay
not that Men do not hereby pleaſe themſelves by gratifying
their wanton Fancies, and magnifying their idolized Friends.
I queſtion not but ſuch Fooliſh Zealots are as well pleaſed with
theſe their Childiſh Impertinencies, as their Children are with
their Jointed Babies and Hobby-Horſes. But their Laughter
is mad, and their Mirth what doth it? Certain it is, that their
Souls are not improved by the exceſſive Study and Purſuit of
thoſe things, there is no aptitude to promote ſuch a thing, I
mean when ſought and purſu'd with the neglect of the Life of
Religion. What will a Man's Orthodoxneſs, with reſpect
unto the Doctrine of the Externals, the Modes and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances
of Worſhip, contribute to the healing of his Pride,
Paſſion, or Worldlineſs, or any other Diſtemper of his Mind,
if he be continually diverted from a cloſe Application of the
Specificks that the wiſe and good Phyſician of Souls hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
for the Cure of ſuch and ſuch Diſtempers? If a Man
that hath a Tertian Ague, ſhould continually ſpend his Time
in ſtudying in what Vehicle ſuch a Medicine for his Diſtemper
ſhould be taken in, and when he hath fixed his Determination,
ſhould ſpend the reſt of his Time in endeavouring to bring
over his Neighbours that are otherwiſe minded to his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
would this cure his Diſtemper (think you) though he
never applied the proper Medicine that he hath by him?</p>
            <p>To Apply it. May not a Man be right as to the particular
(leſs Principal) Thing he contends for, and yet as Proud,
Contentious, Turbulent, Selfiiſh, Uncharitable, and Unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
as ever? If a Man be in Heart no true Chriſtian, will his
ſticking to, and contending for ſuch Things make him one?
If he be a weak languiſhing Chriſtian, will this revive the
Power of Religion in his Soul? Yea rather, will it not put out
the few Sparks that are left?</p>
            <p>(3.) Men do not hereby ſerve the Souls of others, whom
by theſe Methods they would Proſelyte to their particular O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions.
There are amongſt all Parties of Chriſtians in this
Nation, <hi>Some</hi> that act in this Matter with that unwearied In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry,
and rejoice in their Succeſs with ſuch an air of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placence,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66470:7"/>
as if they were in this matter as narrow of their
Charity as the Romaniſts, and counted none good Chriſtians
but thoſe of their own Party; they act as if there was nothing
required of Men in order to Salvation, but ſubſcribing their
Canons, ſubjecting themſelves to their particular Modes of
Worſhip, and walking with them in their Way. But as ſuch
an Imagination is altogether groundleſs, and very abſurd, ſo
thoſe are moſt wretchedly impoſed upon, that ſuffer themſelves
to be Captivated by it. And I will confidently aſſert, That
there is nothing in the Pureſt, moſt Orthodox, and Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical
Party of Proteſtants which the other Parties have not, to
make amends for ſuch a Deception. If any Man ſhould be
told by a Leader of any Party of Proteſtants, That if he will
be a good Chriſtian, pleaſe God, and go to Heaven when he
dies, he muſt be one of them; he muſt Subſcribe their Canons,
follow their Directory, take their Church-Covenant, he muſt
Pray by a Book, he muſt not Pray by a Book, he muſt go to
the Pariſh Church, he muſt go to Meeting, to this Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
to that Meeting; I ſay, whoſoever talk at this rate, do
miſerably deceive thoſe that they perſwade: Nor have they any
thing in their Communion, which other Societies have not, to
make their deluded Proſelites amends. Nay, ſo far is this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious
Proſelyting of Men to a particular Opinion from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
a piece of Service to Souls, that 'tis a manifeſt Injury to
them, as it fills the Chriſtian World with woful Schiſms, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts
from the more important Duties of Chriſtian Religion,
as it ſtumbles the Ignorant, and hardens the Prophane in their
Contempt of all Religion.</p>
            <p>(4.) God's Kingdom is not enlarged, nor his Honour and
Glory promoted by ſuch a Courſe. Men may thus People their
reſpective Aſſemblies, and encreaſe the number of Votaries
to their particular Faction or Party, but not one good Subject
is or can be hereby added to the King of Saints. Men may
hereby diſhoneſtly drein the Societies of Chriſtians differing
from them in their Opinion about theſe leſſer Matters, and
weaken their Hands by enticing their uſeful Friends from them,
but, not a Soul can they by this Method bring them from the
power of Satan into the Kingdom of God, it hath not the
leaſt Aptitude or Fitneſs to produce ſo noble an effect. For
the Perſons ſuch Sticklers would by this method gain over to
their Party, are either good or bad, now which ſoever be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66470:8"/>
the matter comes all to one. If he be a bad Man, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute
of the ſaving Grace of God, he is never the leſs ſo for
eſpouſing the Opinions, and conforming himſelf to the Cuſtoms
and Uſages of this or that Party. If he keep his Vicious
Habits, and remain an Impenitent Unbeliever, he is a bad
Man ſtill, with which Party ſoever of Chriſtians he ſides. If
he falls in with the Conformiſts, he is a wicked Man notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding;
if he ſhould thence be gotten over to the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,
he is a wicked Man ſtill; if he ſhould remove his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle
and pitch amongſt the Independents, he is a wicked
Man nevertheleſs: And let him change his Aſſociates as often
as he will, though he ſhould happen at laſt to light upon the
Truth, as to Matters in Controverſy, though he ſhould join
with the moſt Orthodox and ſtrict Party, though he ſhould
really and in Truth be of the ſame mind with them, as to their
diſtinguiſhing Opinions and Modes of Worſhip, though he
ſhould have and manifeſt a Zeal for them, yet he is a wicked
Man nevertheleſs, and no more the Hearty and Loyal Subject
of the Redeemer than he was before; <hi>For Circumciſion is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion is nothing, but the keeping the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 7. 19.</p>
            <p>'Tis not Conformity or Non-Conformity, 'tis not the Eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
the Intereſt of Dioceaſan Epiſcopacy, Presbyterianiſm,
Independency or Anabaptiſtry, that will make a good Man
of a bad. This will not contribute any thing to the changing
a Slave of Satan into a Freeman of Chriſt; wherefore 'tis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt
that <hi>Factious Zealots</hi> are not at all ſerviceable to the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
of God, by gaining over <hi>bad Men</hi> to their Party.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſome will ſay, If the Perſon gain'd be a good
Man, the caſe (ſure) is alter'd; if he be brought from a leſs
pure to a more pure way of Worſhip, this (doubtleſs) promotes
the Kingdom of God.</p>
            <p>I anſwer; Firſt remember that my Diſcourſe is confin'd to
the Matters controverted by Proteſtants, who ſeverally and
jointly hold to and practiſe the more neceſſary and important
Matters of Faith and Worſhip. Now I ſay, it muſt be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
that all Deviations from the Rule of the Word in the
Worſhip of God, are Sins, and every Sin is more or leſs ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive
of the Kingdom of God: It muſt alſo be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged,
that convincing Men of their Miſtakes, and reclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
them from their Irregularities in the Worſhip of God, is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:66470:8"/>
both Charitable and Pious. It is a friendly Office performed
for the Soul of our Neighbour, and an act of Service to the
King of Heaven. All this is readily granted. Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
it may be ſafely affirm'd that the Kingdom of God is
not ſerved by Perſons ſpending their Zeal about leſſer Matters.
For when Perſons lay a greater ſtreſs upon them than their
Nature requires, when they talk of them as if they were the
only, or chief and principal Things in Religion to be minded,
deſpiſing, or judging and ſeparating from thoſe that differ from
them in their Opinions and Practices, with reſpect to them:
I ſay, when it is thus (and this is the Caſe I have all along in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended)
though theſe Men ſhould be in the right, yet if they
endeavour to imprint their Image upon the Perſons they wou'd
Inſtruct, and if they are ſucceſsful as to the whole of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign,
'tis certain that they do more hurt than good. For, though
it be yielded that they are ſerviceable to thoſe they Proſelyte,
as they Correct their Miſtakes, and guide them into the way of
Truth, yet in as much as at the ſame time they cheriſh and
nouriſh in them Factious, Dividing, Uncharitable, Turbulent
Inclinations, 'tis manifeſt, that inſtead of making them better
Subjects to the King of Heaven, they make them much worſe
than they were. Such Mens new acquired Light having too
much Brimſtone in it, ſerves but to fire them, and all about
them. What though they are in ſome little thing more Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox
and Regular than they were before, if withal they grow
Conceited and Proud, Pragmatical and Cenſorious, Schiſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
and Turbulent; if with the increaſe of their Light there be
a decreaſe of their Love, Humility and Peaceableneſs, they are
no more better'd than Men are happily relieved againſt the
Darkneſs of the Night, by the Light that comes from their
Fired Houſes. Such a zealous promoting of Opinion may ſpoil
Chriſt's good Subjects, but it cannot mend them. Moreover,
the Honour and Glory of God is not promoted by ſuch a courſe.
God is then glorify'd by us, when in our Lives we ſhew by
ſome ſignificant Actions, that our Souls are impreſs'd with
the likeneſs of the Divine Perfections; as Wiſdom, Holineſs,
Juſtice, Goodneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſay, when by wiſe, holy, juſt and
good Actions, we ſhew to the World that our Souls are ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
with the Likeneſs of the Divine Wiſdome, Holineſs, Juſtice
and Goodneſs, then we may be ſaid to Glorifie God in the
World—But is a buſie, uncharitable, contending for, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:66470:9"/>
Matters of Opinion, to the prejudice of Practical God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs;
what will argue our Souls to be thus impreſs'd? Or,
will any ſober Perſon ſay, That God is hereby Glorified? Is it
conſiſtent with an Underſtanding Belief of the Wiſdom of God,
to imagine that He made our noble Souls to be only, or prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally
buſied about ſuch little things as many will Chriſten with
the Name of Religion? Or, can a Man that heartily believes
God is good, perſuade himſelf to think, that He ſhould oblige
us to ſpend our Time and Strength in recommending and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting
thoſe things that have nothing in their Nature to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain
our Minds to Satisfaction, Minds that are capable of
Converſing with the Glorious God, his high Perfections, and
excellent Works? They know neither God, nor their own
Souls, that can think ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Application,</hi> by way of
<list>
                  <item>Inſtruction,</item>
                  <item>Reprehenſion,</item>
                  <item>Exhortation.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>1. <hi>Inſtruction.</hi> This Truth leads us into ſeveral others, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. There ſhould be an Harmony in Affection amongſt thoſe
between whom there is a Difference in Opinion.</item>
               <item>2. Uniformity in Worſhip is not neceſſary to the Flouriſhing
of Chriſtianity.</item>
               <item>3. A further Union amongſt <hi>Proteſtants</hi> is truly deſirable.</item>
               <item>4. 'Tis no Sin for a Chriſtian in ſome Caſes to conceal his
Opinion. Of theſe in order.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. There ſhould be an Harmony, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Or thus, Chriſtians of
different Sentiments and Practices, with reſpect unto the leſſer
Matters of Religion, ſhould unfeignedly and affectionately love
one the other; their little Differings ſhould not occaſion the
abating of their mutual Love. God loves them all, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
they ſhould love one another. Thus the Apoſtle himſelf
improves this Doctrine, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 5. <hi>Now the God of patience,
and conſolation, grant you to be like minded,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
This Expreſſion is ſometimes uſed to ſignifie Agreement in
Opinion and Judgment; but here (I take it) 'tis put to ſignifie
Union and Affection; as the ſame Expreſſion is uſed, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 2.<hi>Fulfil ye my joy, that ye be like minded, having the ſame love.</hi>—
And the whole Context ſeems to favour this Interpretation,
for the deſign of the Apoſtle throughout the Fourteenth Chapter,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:66470:9"/>
ſeems plainly to be the begetting a good Underſtanding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
the contending Chriſtians of his Time, to perſwade
them to bear with, be friendly, and kind, and loving one to
another: And therefore 'tis very allowable to ſuppoſe, that
in the cloſe of his Diſcourſe upon this Subject, he doth by this
Expreſſion intend the ſame thing, eſpecially ſeeing 'tis manifeſt
that the words are to be ſo underſtood in that, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 2. and
that the very laſt words the Apoſtle ſpends upon this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
are theſe, <hi>ſc. Wherefore receive ye one another as Christ
alſo received us to the Glory of God,</hi> ver. 7. And Sirs, what
hinders that Chriſtians of different Opinions and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions
about leſſer matters, love not one another better?
Seeing the things they differ about are not things of great
weight, or flat neceſſity, ſeeing the Intereſt of God ſuffers not
by the variety of Mens Opinions about them, ſeeing God doth
not value or ſlight Men upon account of them, ſeeing both Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
may be acceptable to God, why ſhould they not love one
another? Why ſhould they not in Honour prefer one another?
Why ſhould they not have good thoughts one of another?
True it is, Men cannot think or believe as they liſt, or as their
Neighbours and Friends would have them, but one would think
they ſhould love according to their Saviour's Command and
Example: He loves all the pious and good, whether Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts
or Non-Conformiſts, Church-men or Diſſenters, Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian
or Independent, or whatever Fool's Coat of diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
their uncharitable envious Neighbours put upon them. He
by his Apoſtle commends a Catholick Love, or a Love to All
the Saints, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 15. wherefore 'tis a hard caſe if Chriſtians
of different Opinions cannot love one another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Objection</hi> But perhaps ſome will ſay, How can I love thoſe
that I ſee diſorderly and Erroneous?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> A wiſe Objection indeed! canſt thou love none
but thoſe that are in all things Orthodox and orderly? Then
thou muſt love thy Father, or Mother, or Wife, or Children,
or Miniſter, yea, or thine own ſelf no more, for all on this
ſide Heaven have their Miſtakes, and are guilty of their Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularities.
<hi>We know but in part,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 9.
<hi>and in many things we offend all, James</hi> 3. 2. But hark Chriſtian
what are thoſe Errors and Irregularities that hinder thy lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
of thy Fellow Chriſtian? Doth he deny the Catholick
Church, that one Body? Doth he deny the Holy Ghoſt, that one
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:66470:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:66470:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:66470:11"/>
Spirit? Doth he diſown the Belief of the Heavenly Glory, that
one hope of our Calling? Or doth he deny the One Lord Jeſus,
the one Faith; Baptiſm, or God and Father of all, who is
above all, and through all, and in us all? Perhaps thou wilt
ſay, No, no, he is not gone ſo far as that comes to, he owns
all theſe. Does he? then (to ſpeak a ſoft word) thou art a
fooliſh Wretch, if thou canſt not love him becauſe he thinks
and ſpeaks ſomewhat differingly from thee, about the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantials
of Religion—But thou ſay'ſt he is diſorderly—
what meaneſt thou? Is he Prophane, Intemperate, Unjuſt,
or Unmerciful? It may be thou wilt ſay, No, I can lay none
of this to his Charge; as to the main he ſeems to live a Sober,
Righteous, and a Godly Life, but he is not of my mind and
way in the Worſhip of God. he was not admitted to the
Lord's Supper as I was, he ſays not his Prayers as I do mine,
he comes not to the ſame place of Worſhip that I do—</p>
            <p>And is this the reaſon why thou canſt not love him? Let
me tell thee freely, whoever thou art, thou haſt great reaſon
to queſtion whether thou thy ſelf loveſt God or no, and for thy
reaſon why thou canſt not ſo heartily love thy Fellow Chriſtian;
thou wouldſt have given as good an one if thou hadſt ſaid the
reaſon was becauſe he hath a Mole in his Face, a ſpot upon his
Coat, or another faſhion'd Ribbon in his Hat than thou haſt;
for theſe are as ſolid Reaſons why thou ſhouldſt not heartily
love ſuch as I have deſcribed, as the others are.</p>
            <p>2. Hence learn, Uniformity in Worſhip is not neceſſary to
the Flouriſhing of Chriſtianity in the World. The Kingdom
of God may be in a proſperous and flouriſhing Condition,
though all do not Worſhip in the ſame manner, or with the
ſame Ceremonies exactly. Becauſe the Kingdom of God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth
not in ſuch little things. That there be Unity among
Chriſtians is neceſſary, they muſt be united in the ſame Object
of Worſhip the ever-Bleſſed and Glorious Trinity, in the ſame
Mediator the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; in the ſame Guide and Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor
in Worſhip the Holy Ghoſt, in the ſame Rule of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
(as to the ſubſtance of Worſhip at leaſt) the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;
in the ſame end of Worſhip, the Glory of God in their
Eternal Salvation. But that there ſhould be amongſt the ſeveral
Aſſemblies of Worſhippers an exact Uniformity as to all the
Modes and Circumſtances of Worſhip, this is (I think not
poſſible, but I am ſure) not neceſſary to the flouriſhing of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:66470:11"/>
Chriſtianity, for the Kingdom of God is not Circumſtance or
Ceremony.</p>
            <p>But alas! how do Perſons of all denominations (ſome at
leaſt) talk as if they thought the quite contrary; the high
Flyers of all Denominations talk and act as if they thought the
Kingdom of God was nothing elſe but Circumſtance and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.
Ask the rigid Church-man's Opinion, and he'll tell
you 'twill never be good days till all come to Worſhip God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty
with the laudable Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi>
he'll tell you, that there are no true Miniſters but thoſe
that have Epiſcopal Ordination, no true Sacraments but what
are Adminiſtred by ſuch Miniſters, no true Churches where
there are not true Sacraments, no Salvation out of the true
Church: That is, in a word, that there are no true Churches
or Chriſtians that are in a State of Salvation, but thoſe of his
Way; and thus we poor Diſſenters all are, what in him lieth,
left without the Pale of the Church, to be an eaſie Prey to the
next Herd of Devils that ſhall chance to light upon us. Theſe Men
make the Kingdom of God to be Ceremony and Circumſtance
with a witneſs, in as much as they will not vouchſafe to reckon
thoſe amongſt Chriſtians, that want but the ſuppoſed Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
or finiſhing of the Impoſition of the Hands of a Dioceſan
Biſhop on their Miniſters at their Ordination, though all other
requiſites be found amongſt them. Well, are there none of
the Diſſenters as Fooliſh in their way? Yes verily, there are
amongſt them ſome as Ignorant and Uncharitable as their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical
Neighbours: This wild Fancy walks ſometimes in a
Cloak as well as in a Gown and Caſſock; ſome there are that
think it can never be as it ſhould be with the Kingdom of
God, till all Ceremonies but their own (for 'tis impoſſible to
Worſhip God with external Worſhip, without ſome Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
or other) be laid aſide, they have ſuch extravagant
Conceits about the Ceremonies uſed by the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
that they be ready to conclude that the Salvation of ſuch
as uſe them, is almoſt as impoſſible, as 'tis for a Camel to go
through the Eye of a Needle. When they think fit to ſpeak
of a Church-man, in whom perhaps there's ſome good thing
that they cannot but ſee, they ſpeak of it with a <hi>But.</hi> But he
is a Church-man, But he is for the Liturgy; as if his not being
a Diſſenter, or not Worſhipping God juſt in ſuch a way and
manner as they, did marr all the good that was in him, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66470:12"/>
make it to be nothing—The truth is, there is ſuch a dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
domineering Spirit in Men of all ſorts, that every con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited
Man would be a Teacher and Ruler to all the reſt. The
conceited Epiſcopal Man would have all the Nation follow his
Faſhion, and bow down to his Idol (I mean, his exceſſively
valued Ceremonies); the proud Presbyterian would have all
obſerve his Directory; and the proud Independent would
have all take his Covenant, and conform to his Cuſtoms and
Uſages; and if theſe cannot have their Wills (and God forbid
they ſhould) they utter their Complaints, and vent their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions,
as if for want hereof all the Storms were raiſed that
have ſo long threatned the ſinking of the Church. Whereas
the wiſe, and humble, and peaceable among all ſorts conſider,
that ſeeing the Kingdom of God conſiſteth not in Ceremony or
Circumſtance of External Worſhip; a variety and diverſity
herein may well be allow'd unto Perſons of different Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
and Apprehenſions, without any damage done to the
Glory of the Divine Government. And that this was the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle's
mind is manifeſt from this, that when he conſiders the
difference between the <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> about the Obſervation
of Holidays, he doth not command one to conform his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
and Practice to the others, but adviſeth each to act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to his own Perſwaſion therein, at the ſame time main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining
a Charitable Frame of Spirit towards his differing
Neighbour, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 5. If he had thought that an exact Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity
in the Externals of Worſhip had been neceſſary, he
would not have given ſuch Advice as he there gives, no, he
would have Dogmatically determined which was in the Right,
and Authoritatively commanded the other to conform to
him.</p>
            <p>Third <hi>Inference.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A farther Union amongſt Proteſtants is very deſirable, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
theſe ſmaller matters that I have been diſcourſing of, are
of ſuch a nature, that a Man may be under the ſaving Influence
of the Spirit of Holineſs, and a good Subject to the King of
Heaven, which way ſo ever he acts with reſpect to them. 'Tis
ten thouſand pities that a Difference in Opinion and Practice
herein ſhould cauſe ſuch diſtances and withdrawings one from
another, as it doth. I acknowledge there is great cauſe of
Thankſgiving to God, that there is ſuch an Union in Doctrinals
amongſt us as there is, and I account the Governments calling
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:66470:12"/>
Proteſtant Diſſenting Miniſters to Subſcribe the Articles of the
Church of <hi>England</hi> a very good Providence, as their Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxy,
in matters of Faith, is thereby manifeſted to all the
World. But that this is all the Union that is to be wiſhed,
no Perſon of Underſtanding and Honeſty will dare to affirm.
It were to be wiſhed that what is ſinfully impoſed on one ſide
was dropped, and what is needleſly ſcrupled on the other ſide
was for Peace ſake complied with, that the Names of Church-men
and Diſſenters, Presbyterian and Independent might be
happily loſt in an honeſt and beneficial Union, that our Name
may be one, our Hearts as one, and our Way one, to the
painful Envy and Grief of Hell and <hi>Rome.</hi> I do unfeignedly
lament the Spirit of Faction and Partyiſm that I ſee amongſt
Diſſenters, as well as Church-men. Biggotry is not the Sin of
any particular Party. Ah what a diſmal thing is it, that when
our Holy Bible tells us plainly, that the Kingdom of God is
not promoted by theſe little Things, we ſhould ſtand aloof
from one another upon account of them, as if we were afraid
of being Infected with mortal Diſeaſe! Seeing a Man's accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
with God depends not upon his uſing this way of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
or that, why ſhould we <hi>totally</hi> ſeparate from thoſe who
Worſhip with ſome little Irregularities, as if they were Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers
of a falſe God? Or why ſhould they totally deny their
Preſence at our Aſſemblies, becauſe of the abſence of thoſe
Ceremonies that they themſelves acknowledge to be indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent?
Let us pray, that where Perſons are otherwiſe mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
about the Worſhip of God than the Word of God directs,
God would reveal it to them, as it is expreſſed <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 15. that
the domineering impoſing Humour on one hand, and the
needleſs hurtful Scrupuloſity on the other being laid aſide, we
may all walk together in Love, becoming the Goſpel of Love
and Peace. You that deſire the Peace of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> pray for
this, pray heartily, pray without ceaſing; you ſhall proſper
that thus love the Church of God, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 122. 6.</p>
            <p>Fourth <hi>Inference.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis no ſin for a Chriſtian in ſome caſes to conceal his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
as to theſe leſſer Matters. Yea, 'tis a plain Duty in ſome
caſes. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 22. <hi>Haſt thou Faith, have it to thy ſelf before
God. i. e.</hi> 
               <q>Haſt thou more knowledge than he, to believe
thoſe things to be lawful, which he judgeth to be ſin, keep
thy Knowledge and Belief to thy ſelf, to juſtify thy Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:66470:13"/>
to God,but uſe it not to the hurt of others. [Mr.
<hi>Baxter.]</hi>
               </q> This Text ſeems primarily to direct the ſtrong
Chriſtian who hath more Knowledge of his Chriſtian Liberty
than his Brother, and can without ſcruple do thoſe things
which the weaker Chriſtian ſticks at; and the Duty enjoined
ſeems to be this, that ſuch an one ſhould not needleſly divulge
his Opinion, nor uſe his Liberty to the Scandalizing of his
Brother. It is alſo of uſe to direct the weak ſcrupulous Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,
who though he hath a ſtrong Perſwaſion, that ſuch or
ſuch a Thing would be ſin to him, yet ſhould not needleſly
divulge his Scruples, when he is not call'd to do what he
ſcrupleth; and when the mentioning of his Scruples might
diſturb his Brothers quiet; who can do that thing without
wronging his Conſcience or [it may be] offending of God, the
thing being indiffent, and ſo lawful to be done or not done, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
as a Man is perſwaded in his Conſcience. And thus
the Apoſtle ſeems to mean by that in the <hi>5th verſe, Let every
Man be fully perſwaded in his own mind. Q. d.</hi> With reſpect to
theſe diſputed Matters, let every Man act according to the
Light he hath received, but not be forward to ſpread his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
for the diſturbing and troubling of others, ſeeing the
Glory of God is not promoted by our contending about theſe
leſſer matters; ſeeing the Kingdom of Chriſt is not furthered,
nor the Souls of Men advantaged by gaining Men to our Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions
about them. Let it ſuffice us that we have the liberty
of our own Thoughts and Actions, and not inſiſt upon them
when we have far greater and more uſeful things to talk of,
and preſs upon one another wherein we are all agreed. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
when a Man [that hath no manifeſt Call to declare his
Judgment about theſe ſmaller Matters] ſhall purpoſely for
peace ſake refuſe the diſtinguiſhing Name of [ſuppoſe] Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian
or Independent, and ſhall rather chuſe to be called
a Chriſtian, a Proteſtant, or an United Brother, he is not I
think to be looked upon and condemned as an Hypocrite,
walking <hi>Laodicean,</hi> or Linſy-woolſy Chriſtian. Nor will any
Perſon ſo judge ſuch, but thoſe whoſe Opinion is (as one
ſaid) more than their Religion, and who delight in the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
Honour [but real Shame] of being the Heads of Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical
Parties.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:66470:13"/>
Second uſe of Reprehenſion,</p>
            <p>And here theſe ſeveral ſorts following are to be reprov'd, <hi>ſc.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Tyrannical Church Impoſers.</item>
               <item>2. Factious Preachers.</item>
               <item>3. Schiſmatical Dividers.</item>
               <item>4. Proud Contemners.</item>
               <item>5. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitable Judgers.</item>
               <item>6. Hypocritical Triflers.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. <hi>Tyrannical Church Impoſers.</hi> I mean here all ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
or real Church-Officers, as make Conformity to their
Opinions and Practices about theſe leſſer Matters, the indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſible
condition of Communion with them. I call ſuch Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical
Impoſers, becauſe they act herein Arbitrarily without
the Divine Warrant, and hereby Lord it over God's Heritage.
This Spirit is too viſible in the World at this Day; ſome deny
Publick Baptiſm to Children, if their Parents will not conſent
to have them ſigned with the ſign of the Croſs, or if they
themſelves will engage for their Children, and refuſe to find
Sureties (or Godfathers and Godmothers) for them; though
neither of theſe be commanded in the Word, and both be
look'd on as unlawful and ſinful by thoſe who offer their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
to be Baptiſed. They refuſe to give the Sacrament of the
Lord's Supper to Perſons (in the Judgment of ſtricteſt Charity,
Penitent Believers competently inſtructed) except they will
receive it Kneeling; though Chriſt or his Apoſtles never ſo
Adminiſtred it, and though the Perſons that would join with
them think it would be ſin in them ſo to receive it. Others will
not admit Perſons to their Communion, unleſs they will ſubmit to
be examined by Officers that are neither Preachers of the Word,
nor Diſpenſers of the Sacraments; though. the Divine Right
of that Office be controverted by the Learned, and the Perſons
refuſing to be ſo examined verily think it is not an Ordinance
of Chriſt. Others will not admit Perſons to their Communion,
except they will (beſides their declaring their Knowledge of
the Doctrine of Chriſtian Religion, and profeſſing their Belief
of it, and purpoſes of living in all things ſuitable to it) be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged
to give an account of their Experiences to the Society,
or the Heads of them, that they may judge not only of their
Knowledge, but alſo of the Sincerity and Truth of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,
at leaſt of the Credibility of the Appearances of their
Sincerity and Truth. Others will have no Communion at the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66470:14"/>
Lord's Table with thoſe that have been Baptized in their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy,
unleſs they will renounce their Baptiſm, by being Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized
again. All theſe are to be blamed. Now I do not at
this time blame-one Party or other, for acting themſelves ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
as they are reſpectively perſwaded, nor for Admitting
others to do the like that are of the ſame mind with them, and
are Volunteers in what they do. But that which is juſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provable,
and which my Text and Doctrine directs me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove,
is Perſons looking upon thoſe that are otherwiſe mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
and dealing with them, as if they were meer impenitent
Pagans, denying to them the means of Salvation; as if theſe
things were of the Subſtance of Religion, and a Man could not
be a good Chriſtian, unleſs he was as to theſe Things altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of their Mind. This is but too like the hateful Cruelty of
the <hi>Athenian</hi> Robber, the condition of Lodging with whom
was, to be made juſt the length of his Bed, by disjointing,
ſtretching if too ſhort, or by diſmembring, chopping off if
two long. Away with this Church Tyranny, with this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenching
upon Chriſt's Prerogative, and let's be content with
ſuch Conditions of Church Fellowſhip, as he in Wiſdom and
Goodneſs hath appointed. Certainly, what I am ſpeaking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt,
is a wicked Lording it over the Conſciences of Chriſt's
Diſciples where-ever 'tis, whither in a Pariſh Church or ſeparate
Meeting, and 'tis directly contrary to that Precept, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 1.<hi>Him that is weak in the Faith receive ye, but not to doubtful Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. A ſecond ſort to be reproved are, <hi>Factious Preachers.</hi> Such
I mean whoſe Buſineſs it is to commend themſelves and Party,
<hi>meaſuring themſelves by themſelves, and comparing themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
themſelves,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 12. Such
Miniſters (by what Names or Titles ſoever dignified or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed)
as under pretence of Orthodoxy, Order, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency
employ their Wit, and ſpend their Time and Vigor in
juſtifying, commending, and magnifying the Expreſſions and
Phraſes, Habits, Geſtures, and Modes uſed by themſelves and
Party; villifying and nullifying the Ways and Manners of thoſe
that differ from them. O the Sin and Folly of ſuch a Courſe!
it cannot poſſibly be the effect of a better Cauſe than baſe Selfiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
Envy, or Ignorance. How abſurd and fooliſh doth this
appear, when we conſider the relation that Miniſters ſtand in
to the People. They are Ambaſſadors from God unto Men in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:66470:14"/>
Chriſt's ſtead, to perſwade them to be reconciled to God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi>
5. 20. Their buſineſs is by all proper Arguments to perſwade
Men to take off their Hearts from this World (whoſe Friendſhip
is Enmity againſt God, <hi>James</hi> 4. 4.) and ſet them upon God as
their chief Good and only Happineſs; in order hereunto they
ſhould with the beſt of their Skill diſplay before Men the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive
amiable Excellencies of God, as diſcover'd by the Works
of Creation, common Providence and Redemption, and diſgrace
the World as a Competitor and Rival with God, by ſhewing its
unſuitableneſs, uncertaintainty, and inſufficiency, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now
what madneſs is it, inſtead hereof, to be continually or frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
harping upon the Decency, Comlineſs, or Uſefulneſs of ſuch
and ſuch Ceremonies, and the Excellency of ſuch Churches as
make uſe of them?—How abſurd is it to be continually or fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
induſtriouſly crying of them down, and applauding ſuch
Churches as uſe them not, to be defending, juſtifying and
preſſing ſuch or ſuch particular Modes of expreſſing the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines
of Chriſtan Religion; and thereby, at leaſt tacitly, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning
and diſgracing others, that, it may be, are altogether
as Orthodox, neither being in terms the Expreſſions of Holy
Scripture? 'Tis indeed a deplorable Caſe, that the Ambaſſadors
of the King of Heaven ſhould ſo much miſtake the Deſign of their
Negotiation. If the King of <hi>England</hi> ſhould ſend an Ambaſſador
to Treat with his Enemies (his revolted Subjects) and proffer
them their Lives in caſe they will return to their Allegiance,
confeſs with Shame and Remorſe their Rebellion, would it not
be abominable trifling in the Ambaſſador, if he ſhould ſpend his
time chiefly in inſtructing them what Cloaths they ſhould wear,
and what Geſtures they ſhould keep when they come into the
King's Preſence? The Application is eaſie.—</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Schiſmatical Dividers</hi> are to be reprov'd. Such in Chriſtian
Societies, I mean, who, if they cannot have their Wills as to
little Trifles, ſtick not at renting and tearing all to pieces, by
faulting the Miniſters Methods, and prejudicing the Church
againſt him. There are a ſort of Men in the World, who,
tho' they have hardly ſenſe enough to apprehend the plaineſt
Preaching, are yet ſo conceited and proud, as to think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
qualified to be, at leaſt, Sides-Men with their Miniſter in
all his Acts of Rule and Government, if not wiſe enough to go
before and lead him. Theſe, if every thing be not done in the
Church according to their Capricio and Humour, if the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:66470:15"/>
do not Preach ſuch a particular Doctrine as they think will
be moſt Edifying, and in ſuch Words and Phraſes as they think
moſt ſound; if he proceed not in the Government of the Church
according to their Model, and take them not with him to judge
of his Adminiſtrations; they will never leave working like
Moles, till they have undermined him. Though they cannot
charge their Miniſter with Preaching or Ruling contrary to the
Word of God, yet if he do not theſe things juſt as they have
ſeen and heard them done in ſome other Churches, which they
are pleaſed to pronounce the moſt Pure; if all be not done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the Dictates of ſuch or ſuch a Miniſter, whoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
they have in Admiration, they will withdraw themſelves
from the Communion, buz about their Diſcontents, till they
have bred ſuch a Schiſm, as exceeds the Miniſters Skill to unite
and heal. I dare not ſay that all ſuch are of their Father the
Devil, but I will boldly affirm, that his Works they do, and
that they are <hi>herein and ſo far</hi> Peſts and Plagues to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
Societies. And 'tis my ſerious Thought, that if God in
Mercy doth not by ſome ſpeedy unexpected Providence prevent
it, this ſort of Men will ruine our Liberty, and bring us into
miſerable Confuſion. Friends, if you call this Railing, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
help it, but this ſhall ſupport me, that God hath command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
me to mark them which cauſe Diviſions, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 17. and
that if I uprightly do my Duty, God will at laſt acquit me,
tho' Men for the preſent condemn me; God will for Chriſt's
ſake ſhew me his reconciled Face, tho' Men (my Acquaintance
and Friends) turn their backs upon me, and will not vouchſafe
to hear me, I ſay to you as the Apoſtle in another caſe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi>
11. 1. <hi>Would to God you could bear with me a little, and indeed
bear with me.</hi> I have no delight in offending any Body, be ſure
not in troubling thoſe whom I have found Comforters of me,
and from whom I might poſſibly yet expect further Comfort: I
know Diſcourſes of this nature are not pleaſant to either the
Guilty or Innocent, and you may aſſure your ſelves I have as
little pleaſure in ſpeaking them, as you have in hearing them.
But I ſay as <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Eliah, 1 Sam.</hi> 17. 29. <hi>Is there not a
cauſe?</hi> Is not this that I am ſpeaking againſt a Sin? And hath
it not done Miſchief theſe many Years in this Nation, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
in this place? Doth not this dividing Spirit naturally
lead to the levelling the Miniſtry with the People, and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the neceſſary diſtinction of Teachers and Learners, Rulers
and ruled in Churches? And is not this the way, the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:66470:15"/>
to Chriſtianity-Ruining, Quakeriſm, and Fanaticiſm?
And am not I a Watch-man, and ſhall not a Watchman ſpeak
when he ſeeth Evil approaching? You will cut a Dog's throat
that will not open when he ſhould, and the Spirit of God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares
cowardly ſilent Miniſters (that tell not the People of their
Sin and Danger) to dumb Dogs that cannot bark; and what
the Lot of a People is like to be, that have ſuch Miniſters,
you may ſee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56 9, 10. <hi>All the Beaſts of the Field come to
devour, yea all the Beaſts in the Foreſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>Proud Contemners</hi> are to be reproved. Such, I mean, who
having Knowledge and a greater Latitude than others, do
therefore deſpiſe and contemn their Chriſtian Brethren, that,
having leſs Knowledge, make more Scruples than they. This
was the fault of the converted <hi>Gentile</hi> in the Apoſtle's Time,
and this is (without Rancour I ſpeak it) the fault of the more
Knowing (if more knowing) and leſs Scrupulous Church-man
at this Day. There was in the Apoſtles Day a diſpute between
the converted <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> about the Lawfulneſs of Eating
ſuch and ſuch Meats, and the neceſſity of keeping ſuch and ſuch
<hi>Moſaick</hi> Holy-days or Feſtivals, the converted <hi>Jew</hi> thought
that the coming of the Meſſiah was to Eſtabliſh the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Polity
and <hi>Moſaick</hi> Inſtitution; therefore, tho' he believed in Chriſt,
yet he durſt not but obſerve the Ceremonial Law. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
he conſcienciouſly kept the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Feaſts enjoined by that
Law, and forbore thoſe Meats that were by that Law pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced
Unclean.</p>
            <p>The Converted <hi>Gentile</hi> being better informed, took no notice
of the Precepts or Prohibitions of that Law, but eat any Meats,
and took no notice of thoſe Feaſts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 2, 5. This di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity
of Opinion and Practice in theſe two Parties of Chriſtians,
occaſioned a ſinful Diſtemper of Mind in both, one againſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other;
the Diſtemper of Mind that the converted <hi>Gentile</hi> ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
harbour'd againſt his Brother was proud Contempt, as
we learn by the Apoſtle's prohibition, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. <hi>Let not him that
eateth, deſpiſe him that eateth not.</hi> By this it appears, that he
did deſpiſe him; he looked upon him as a ſcrupulous humour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
Fool. Brethren, we have a like Caſe in this our day.
Some there are that think we be under the Goſpel tied up to
all the Circumſtances of Worſhip, as ſtrictly as the <hi>Jews</hi> were
heretofore under the Diſpenſation of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and that nothing
is to admitted in or about the Worſhip of God, but what is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:66470:16"/>
commanded in Scripture.—There are others who think that
we are not ſo ſtrictly tied up under the Goſpel, but that if the
Direction of Scripture be obſerv'd, as to the Object of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
the recommending Mediator, and the aſſiſting Spirit;
if God the Father, Son and Spirit be Worſhipped, and we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
our Adorations by the Lord Jeſus, in the ſtrength and
vertue of the Holy Spirit; if the Doctrine preach'd be accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to the Analogy of Faith, our Prayers ſuitable to the Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory
for Prayer commonly called the <hi>Lord's Prayer;</hi> if we uſe
no Sacraments but ſuch as Chriſt hath appointed, and all be
done in Sincerity and Truth, Decency and Order unto Edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
they think their Worſhip nevertheleſs acceptable to God;
if in it they obſerve ſome Ceremonies of Man's appointing: This
is the profeſs'd Judgment of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> for theſe
are her Words, <hi>ſc.</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>We think it convenient, that every Country
ſhould uſe ſuch Ceremonies as they ſhall think beſt to the ſetting forth
of God's Honour and Glory,</hi>—</q>
            </p>
            <p>I undertake not to determine at this time which is in the
Right here, but this I ſay, thoſe Church-men are to blame that
do deſpiſe and vilify thoſe who differ from them. 'Tis their
Sin, if they look upon and treat a Perſon as an ignorant hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mourſome
Fool, meerly becauſe he ſcruples thoſe things that
they can diſpenſe with in the Worſhip of God. 'Tis Unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
and Unchriſtian for ſuch to overlook the Subſtantial
Piety, and ſerious Godlineſs that may be in ſuch, meerly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
they have not the Compliment and Finiſhing of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
Orthodoxneſs, in the buſineſs of Circumſtance and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony,
of which even the Church of <hi>England</hi> her ſelf ſaith;
<hi>That the keeping or omitting of a Ceremony is in it ſelf but a ſmall
thing.</hi> When a Church-man therefore ſhall in ſcornful Pride
look a-wry upon an humble, peaceable, pious, juſt, charitable
Chriſtian, meerly becauſe he is a Diſſenter from his Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,
he ſins againſt the Law of Chriſt, and walks unſuitably to
the Principles of his own Church.</p>
            <p>5. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitable Judgers</hi> are to be reprov'd. Such, I mean, as
allow themſelves to Condemn Perſons as Graceleſs and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane,
upon account of their uſing ſuch Liberty as they ſcruple.
This was the fault of the Converted <hi>Jew,</hi> as we learn by the
Words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Let not him that eateth not, judge him that
eateth.</hi> And this (to ſpeak impartially) is the fault of the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious
Diſſenter. As the <hi>Jews</hi> heretofore condemned the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:66470:16"/>
as a prophane wicked Perſon for his eating of Meats for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden
by the Ceremonial Law; ſo ſome Diſſenters (thanks be
to God 'tis but ſome) are ready to condemn thoſe of the Church
of <hi>England</hi> as Prophane and Graceleſs, upon account of their
uſe of the Church Forms and Liturgy. Thoſe of them that are
not viſibly Prophane and Irreligious, they cenſure them as meer
Formaliſts; the beſt they can think of them is, that they are
ſober Moral Perſons, which by the way a meer Pagan may be.</p>
            <p>If it be ſaid that they are conſciencious and ſerious in their
Way, that they are frequent at their Devotions. O ſay theſe
Pragmatical Cenſurers, 'tis well if they don't reſt in their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
thereby intimating that they fear they do.—If their
Charity be mentioned, O ſay theſe, it may be they think to
Merit by their Alms; Are not the Papiſts Charitable? Thus
they audaciouſly ſtep into God's Throne, judging Mens Hearts
with which they have nothing to do.</p>
            <p>Brethren, I tell you faithfully, this is an evil and wicked
thing, 'tis againſt the plain Word of God, which ſaith, <hi>Judge
not, that ye be not judged,</hi> Matth. 7. 1. <hi>Let us not judge one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
any more,</hi> Rom. 14. 13. 'Tis a ſin againſt the Doctrine of
my Text: For if the Kingdom of God conſiſteth not in theſe
ſmaller Matters, Perſons of different, yea contrary Opinions
and Perſwaſions about them, may both (as you have already
heard) be the good and acceptable Subjects of the Lord Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.
Wherefore 'tis a very unrighteous Thing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn
a Man as a Diſloyal Subject of the Lord Jeſus for that
which will not, cannot poſſibly prove him to be ſo, let all be
ſaid againſt it which the nature of the thing will admit. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
ſuch a Spirit is contrary to the drift of the Goſpel, that
I have as little Charity for ſuch as for any ſort of Men what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever,
that carry the Face of Religion in their Lives. Let
but two Texts be conſidered and compared together, and it
will be I think an hard matter to make it out, how ſuch Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious
Perſons can be truly good, or (which is the ſame) real
Chriſtians: The Texts are, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 1, 2. <hi>Though I ſpeak with
the Tongues of Men and Angels, and have not Charity, I am be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
as ſounding Braſs, or a tinkling Cymbal: And though I have
the Gift of Prophecy, and underſtand all Myſteries, and all Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;
and though I have all Faith, ſo that I could remove Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains,
and have no Charity, I AM NOTHING.</hi> Now
compare <hi>ver.</hi> 5, 7. where 'tis ſaid of this Charity among
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:66470:17"/>
other Things, that <hi>it thinketh no evil, but hopeth all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this Text I am ſtrongly inclined to think, that Cenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
Perſons (thoſe that are habitually and prevalently ſo) do
really want that Charity which is eſſential to Chriſtianity, and
ſo in the midſt of their ſpecious Appearances and high Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
are <hi>Nothing.</hi> Wherefore methinks Perſons ſhould be
afraid of being Guilty of a Sin that brings ſuch a Spot as ſeems
not to be the Spot of God's Children. (To uſe the words,
<hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 5.)</p>
            <p>6. <hi>Hypocritical Triflers</hi> are to be reproved. Such, I mean,
as ſatisfy themſelves with adhering to the little things of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
with the Soul-ruining neglect of the Life of Practical
Godlineſs. And whoſe fault is this? Perhaps you'll ſay, Alas
Friends! this is the fault of moſt amongſt all Parties, this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent
Devil haunts Church and Meeting-Houſe too. <hi>By
him</hi> ſome are perſwaded to think well of themſelves, if they
keep their Church, ſay their Prayers Sundays and Holidays,
receive the Sacrament according to the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
and never go to Meetings. Others think they muſt needs go
to Heaven if they be zealous Diſſenters, and never hear the
Common Prayer; if they join with the ſtricteſt ſort, and but
get to be Church-Members, and zealouſly cry down all that
differ from them; they think they be as ſafe from the danger
of Damnation, as thoſe in <hi>Noah</hi>'s Ark were from the danger
of Periſhing by the Flood, Thus do ſome of both ſides dream,
though they be Ignorant, Earthly, Senſual, Impenitent, Proud,
Wrathful, and unto every good work Reprobate.</p>
            <p>Fooliſh Wretches, how do they mock their God, and cheat
their own Souls! How hateful is their Hypocriſy! They ſtrive
for a Ceremony, and neglect the Subſtance of Religion; they
ſcruple a Ceremony, and yet live in the Commiſſion of groſs
Sins. One he is for Decency and Order, but neglects Sincerity
and Truth. Another he is tooth and nail againſt Superſttion
and Will-worſhip, and the ſame time indulgeth himſelf in the
more hateful and miſchievous Sin of Diſſimulation and Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy.
Poor Souls! what will their Opinions avail them in
the Day of their Account, when their Hypocriſy ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected
and laid open, and they ſhall by the Sword of Juſtice
be cut in ſunder, and have their Portion with their Fellow-Hypocrites
in Hell! As high as their Confidences are built,
'tis certain they muſt (if they Repent not) fall into the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:66470:17"/>
Pit, where their Worm dieth not, and the Fire is not
quenched; where there is (Eternally) weeping, and wailing,
and gnaſhing of teeth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. 51. <hi>Mark</hi> 9. 44.</p>
            <p>I conclude my Diſcourſes on this part of my Text with this
one</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Exhortation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To poor weak Chriſtians that are ready to ſtumble, and be
turned out of the way upon account of the many and various
Opinions that there are amongſt Chriſtians at this day. Be
you aſſured, that you may pleaſe God, gain his Favour and
Bleſſing on Earth, glorify him before Men, be happy in your
Death, and be eternally Glorified with him in Heaven here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after,
of which Party of theſe differing Chriſtians ſoever you
be. Always provided you Act according to your Light, and
ſincerely live thoſe grand Duties which none diſpute or queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
That is to ſay, if you give up your ſelves to God as to your
chief Good and laſt End, to love and ſerve him before all,
if you accept the Lord Jeſus for your All-ſufficient Saviour,
and obey and truſt him, if you walk after the Spirit ſpeaking
in and by the Scriptures, endeavouring to die unto the World
to Crucify the Fleſh and reſiſt the Devil: If you live a Sober,
Righteous, and Godly Life, loving God with all your Heart,
and your Neighbour as your ſelves, and if you perſevere here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
unto the end, depending upon the Merits and Mediation of
Chriſt, for your Pardon and Acceptance, <hi>You ſhall be Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi>
which Party of Proteſtants ſoever you ſide with; or, if
you never trouble your ſelves with the Diſputes or Conteſts
amongſt them. Your being of one Opinion or other as to theſe
ſmaller Matters, cannot poſſibly hinder your eternal Salvation
at laſt, or your comfortable Walking with God here, ſo you
conſcientiouſly mind the Subſtance of Religion, wherein all are
agreed. For 'tis a certain Truth, (I pray you to remember
it) That no one Party of Proteſtants is ſo in the Right as to
Chriſtian Religion, that the other be damningly Wrong; for
the Controverſy amongſt them is not about thoſe Things that
are <hi>Neceſſary to Salvation,</hi> in theſe they are <hi>All Agreed.</hi>
Wherefore 'tis undoubtedly certain, that a Church-man may
be an Holy Man, and be Saved.—A Diſſenter, of one ſort or
another (whether Presbyterian, Independent, or Anabaptiſt)
may be an Holy Man, and be Saved. Yea, they will be ſuch
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:66470:18"/>
infallibly, if they live the Religion they profeſs, I doubt not,
but that Heaven is peopled with all theſe (though there they
be of one Mind.) Wherefore the queſtion is not, Which is
the Way to Heaven, by Church or by Meeting? If it was, I
would boldly ſay, either is the Way. But the queſtion is,
Which is the neareſt, neateſt, ſtreighteſt Way? And here I'll
leave every one to judge for himſelf. Only this for a Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.
I exhort you (having given up your ſelves to God by
Chriſt as aforeſaid) to put your ſelves under the Paſtoral Care
of ſuch a Miniſtry, as in your moſt deliberate Judgment you
think beſt qualify'd with Miniſterial Gifts and Graces, and moſt
Faithful in the uſe of them for the good of Souls, and ſuch as you
have found by real and undoubted Experience to be moſt uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
to you. And when you have made your Choice, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
your Duty, and in Humility, Meekneſs and Patience, learn
of them, as of your Spiritual Guides, and ſubmit your ſelves to
them as to your Spiritual Rulers under Chriſt, according to the
Word; and you will find the Bleſſing from Heaven deſcending
upon your Souls in ſuch a manner as will abundantly ſatisfy
you, that you are going to Heaven, whither you hear in a
Church or Meeting-Houſe. <hi>For the Kingdom of God is not Meat
and Drink, but Righteouſneſs, and Peace, and Joy in the Holy
Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>FIrſt Page Epiſtle line 5. penult, for <hi>Opinions</hi> read <hi>Ceremonies.</hi> Page 2.
line 10. for <hi>of</hi> r. <hi>our.</hi> Page 9. line 5. for <hi>him</hi> r. <hi>himſelf.</hi> Page 13. l. 5.
penult, dele <hi>them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:66470:18"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
