<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The saints transfiguration, or, The body of vilenesse changed into a body of glory a sermon preached at Martins Ludgate, October 19, 1654, at the funerall of that reverend and faithfull minister of Jesus Christ, Dr. Samuel Bolton, late master of Christs College in Cambridg : with a short account of his death / by Edmund Calamy ... ; to which are annexed verses upon his death, composed by divers of his friends and acquaintance.</title>
            <author>Calamy, Edmund, 1600-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-03">2005-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32058</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C265</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5821</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13693022</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13693022</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101409</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A32058)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101409)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 840:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The saints transfiguration, or, The body of vilenesse changed into a body of glory a sermon preached at Martins Ludgate, October 19, 1654, at the funerall of that reverend and faithfull minister of Jesus Christ, Dr. Samuel Bolton, late master of Christs College in Cambridg : with a short account of his death / by Edmund Calamy ... ; to which are annexed verses upon his death, composed by divers of his friends and acquaintance.</title>
                  <author>Calamy, Edmund, 1600-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Joseph Cranford ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bolton, Samuel, 1606-1654 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bolton, Samuel, 1606-1654 --  Poetry.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Philippians III, 20-21 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-12</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-01</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101409:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi>
Saints Transfiguration:
<hi>OR
The</hi> Body of Vilenesse <hi>changed into
a</hi> Body of Glory.</p>
            <p>A
SERMON
Preached at <hi>Martins Ludgate
October</hi> 19. 1654. At the Funerall of that
Reverend, and faithfull Minister of
JESUS CHRIST
D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>SAMUEL BOLTON,</hi> late Master
of <hi>Christs Colledge</hi> in <hi>Cambridg,</hi>
With a short account of his Death.</p>
            <p>By <hi>EDMUND CALAMY,</hi> B. D. Pastor of
<hi>Aldermanbury</hi> in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which are annexed Verses upon his Death,
composed by divers of his Friends and Acquaintance.</p>
            <q>The righteous perisheth, and no man layeth it to heart, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull
men are taken away, none considering that the righteous
is taken away from the evil to come. <bibl>
                  <hi>Isa.</hi> 57. 1.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Your fathers where are they? and the Prophets do they live for
ever? <bibl>
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 1. 5.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Joseph Cranford</hi> at the Sign of the Phoenix
in <hi>Pauls</hi> Churchyard, M.DC.LV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:101409:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101409:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE
ROBERT
EARL OF
WARWICK,
BARON OF
LEEZE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath pleased God to take unto himself
a <hi>Reverend, Learned and Pious Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister
D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> BOLTON,</hi> one who <hi>feared
God above many,</hi> who was (not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
just cause) highly esteemed by your
<hi>Lordship,</hi> whose memory is very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
to you, and who was very dear to
a <hi>Religious Daughter</hi> of yours now
with God (whom I mention for Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
sake) <hi>the Lady Lucy Roberts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ensuing <hi>Sermon</hi> preached at his <hi>sad Funerals,</hi> I crave
leave to <hi>dedicate</hi> to your <hi>Lordship,</hi> as a <hi>publike acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
of the many and great favours I have received from you.
<pb facs="tcp:101409:3"/>
The design of it is, to wean <hi>Christians</hi> from the overmuch <hi>love</hi>
of their <hi>bodies.</hi> All men by nature are prone <hi>curare cutem ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis
quàm animam,</hi> to take more care and spend more time for
their bodies, then for their souls: Hence it is that they think no
<hi>cost</hi> too much that is laid out for the feeding and cloathing of
their bodies, no <hi>gift</hi> too great that is given to the <hi>Physitian</hi> to
heal them when diseased, but <hi>any thing</hi> too much which is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
to a <hi>godly Minister</hi> for the good of their souls: Hence it is,
that the <hi>working dayes</hi> are too few, and too short for their bodily
profits and pastimes, but the <hi>Lords day</hi> which is the <hi>Queen of
dayes,</hi> because it is the <hi>Souls Market-day for Heaven,</hi> is bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>densome
to them, and very tedious. Hence it is also that they
are willing to lay out <hi>Nine</hi> parts of their Estate for their bodies,
but unwilling to part with the <hi>Tenth</hi> for soul-advantages. The
scope of this Sermon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is to shew the vanity and sinfulness of these
and such like practises.</p>
            <p>It tells your Lordship</p>
            <p>That the Body is the <hi>worst half of man,</hi> the <hi>boxe</hi> the <hi>shell,</hi>
the <hi>carcasse:</hi> That the Soul is the <hi>Jewel,</hi> the <hi>life,</hi> the <hi>man</hi> of
<hi>man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the Body is a <hi>Vile body</hi> made of <hi>vile materials,</hi> subject
to <hi>vile diseases</hi> and to <hi>vile abominations,</hi> and that he that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides
for his body and not for his soul, is like unto a <hi>husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
that in harvest time gathers in his <hi>stubble,</hi> and leaves his
<hi>Corn</hi> to be devoured by his <hi>Hoggs;</hi> or like unto a <hi>Goldsmith,</hi>
that weighs exactly his <hi>dross,</hi> but disregards his <hi>gold.</hi> And
also</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that provides for his Body with the neglect of his Soul, is
like unto a</hi> Merchant <hi>that</hi> overloads his Ship so as to drown
himself; <hi>or to a</hi> man that makes so great a fire to warm him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
by, as to burn his house and himself in it.</p>
            <p>It sheweth your Lordship also</p>
            <p>That this <hi>vile body</hi> will never be changed into a <hi>glorious
body</hi> till the great day of the <hi>resurrection,</hi> and that then the
<hi>Lord JESUS</hi> will come from Heaven on purpose to <hi>fashion our
vile bodies like unto his glorious body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That this life is not the <hi>time appointed</hi> for the <hi>good</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:101409:3"/>
our <hi>bodies</hi> only or chiefly, but of our <hi>souls</hi> principally and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially.</p>
            <p>That the only way to make our <hi>bodies glorious,</hi> is by getting
our <hi>souls</hi> to be made <hi>gracious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the <hi>happiness</hi> of the <hi>body</hi> depends upon the <hi>happiness</hi> of
the <hi>soul:</hi> If the soul be <hi>adorned</hi> here with <hi>Christs righteousness,</hi>
the body will be <hi>cloathed</hi> with glory unexpressible hereafter. If
the soul when separated from the body be polluted and belepred
with sinne, the body and soul will both of them be eternally mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
at the resurrection.</p>
            <p>These Lessons are very suitable and seasonable for all sorts and
degrees, but especially for you (Right Honourable) whose <hi>body</hi>
now begins to <hi>wax old,</hi> and will shortly <hi>go down to the house of
rottenness</hi> and be <hi>crumbled into dust.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I doubt not but God hath sufficiently taught you the</hi> vanity
and emptiness of all earthly greatness. <hi>That</hi> greatness with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
goodness, is like the greatness of a man with a Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie,
which is his disease not his happiness: <hi>That</hi> Riches
<hi>without</hi> Righteousness are but heaps of dung: <hi>And that
nothing but</hi> Grace <hi>will make you</hi> truly and eternally honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
            <p>God hath taken you off (out of love to your pretious soul)
from all publike employments, and thereby hath lent you much
time to provide for eternity. He hath given you a <hi>Noble Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tess,</hi>
a <hi>pretious Consort,</hi> a <hi>beloved Companion,</hi> a <hi>dear
Yoak-fellow</hi> (united to you not only by marriage relation, but
by true love and most entire affection) who will be glad to go <hi>hand
in hand</hi> with you in <hi>heavens way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To both of you my <hi>obligations</hi> are very many and very great,
the <hi>characters</hi> of your Love are <hi>visible</hi> and <hi>legible</hi> by all: All
that know me know my relation to you: My prayers to God for
you both shall be, That God would give you more of <hi>himself,</hi> and
of those <hi>mercies</hi> which <hi>cannot stand</hi> with <hi>damnation:</hi> That
he would keep you <hi>good</hi> in <hi>bad times,</hi> and <hi>constant</hi> to your <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi>
in <hi>Apostatizing times:</hi> That he would lengthen out your
dayes for his glory; and that this Sermon may be instrumentall
to make you minde your <hi>bodies lesse,</hi> and your <hi>souls more;</hi> that
<pb facs="tcp:101409:4"/>
when the great day of judgement shall come, <hi>your vile bodies</hi>
may be changed into the likeness of the <hi>glorious body of JESUS
CHRIST.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>So prayeth,
<salute>My Lord</salute>
               <signed>your servant in all spiritual things <hi>EDM. CALAMY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101409:4"/>
            <head>A
SERMON
PREACHED AT
D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> BOLTONS Funerall.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PHIL. 3. 20, 21.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>From whence also we look for the Saviour, the Lord Jesus
Christ.</p>
                  <p>Who shall change our vile body, that it may be fashioned like
unto his glorious body, according to the working whereby
he is able to subdue all things unto himself.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E are here met to perform the last of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
of love for a worthy, reverend and
godly Minister of Jesus Christ, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MUEL
BOLTON late Master of
<hi>Christs Colledge</hi> in <hi>Cambridge.</hi> And
this Text that I have chosen, will afford
us many suitable and seasonable medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations
and considerations for such a
meeting. For here you have.</p>
            <p>1. The Condition that the bodies of men (even the best of
men) are in in this life; they are vile and contemptible: Our
<hi>vile body.</hi> The Greek words are very emphaticall, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
the body of vilenesse,<note n="a" place="margin">Tremelius.</note> 
               <hi>corpus humilitatis nostrae,</hi>
or,<note n="b" place="margin">Beza.</note> 
               <hi>corpus nostrum humile.</hi> The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, signifieth,
<hi>vilem &amp; abjectam conditionem, qualis est vilium servorum,</hi> a vile
and abject condition, such as is of slaves and vassals. The same
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101409:5"/>
word is used,<note place="margin">Corpus humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis pro eorpore humili; Hebrais<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo non ignoto. <hi>Justinianus</hi> in locum.</note> 
               <hi>Luk. 1. 48. He hath regarded the low estate of his
handmaiden,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, It is is also used <hi>James</hi> 1. 10.</p>
            <p>2. The condition that the bodies of the Saints shall be in at
the glorious resurrection: They shall then be <hi>changed, and
made like unto the glorious body of the Lord Jesus Christ,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
shall then be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The <hi>body of vild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi>
shall then be a <hi>body of glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. The Persons whose bodies shall be thus changed, and they
are such who have their conversation in Heaven: <hi>But our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation
is in Heaven, from whence we look for a Saviour who
shall change our vile body.</hi> Not <hi>every</hi> vile body, but <hi>our</hi> vile bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.
The bodies of the wicked shall be ugly and loathsome, but
the bodies of those whose dispositions and actions are heavenly,
shall be beautifull and glorious.</p>
            <p>4. The Person that shall make this great change in our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies;
and he is <hi>the Lord Jesus Christ our Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. The time when this great transfiguration shall be made,
and that is at the great day of judgment, when our <hi>Saviour the
Lord Jesus Christ</hi> shall come <hi>from Heaven,</hi> for this very end
and purpose, to <hi>fashion our vile bodies like unto his glorious
body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>6. The means by which all this shall be accomplished, and
that is, <hi>According to the working whereby he is able to subdue all
things unto himself,</hi> and therefore able to make this glorious
transfiguration and transformation of our bodies.</p>
            <p>7. The use we are to make of all this, and that is, To wait
and expect, to long and <hi>look</hi> for the coming of our Lord Jesus
to judgment, for the accomplishing of this glorious Metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phosis—<hi>From
whence we look for a Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By what hath been already said, you may perceive, that this
Text is a <hi>pretious Cabinet,</hi> full of many excellent Jewels; for
here is</p>
            <p>The doctrine 1. Of the bodies vility, fragility and mortality.
2. Of the resurrection of the just. 3. Of the bodies immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
and glorification at the resurrection. 4. Of the great and
dreadfull day of judgment. 5. Of the great errand and mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage
for which Christ shall come to judgement, and that is to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101409:5"/>
glorifie our bodies: Now all these Doctrines are very suitable
to such an Assembly as this is; the Lord make them as profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
to you as they are seasonable for you,</p>
            <p>My purpose is to pick out only two of these Jewels, and to
shew you</p>
            <p>1. What is the condition of our bodies for the present.</p>
            <p>2, What our bodies shall be at the resurrection.</p>
            <p>First, To speak of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, then of the
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; first of the <hi>body of vilenesse,</hi> then of the <hi>body of
glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 1. That the bodies even of the best of Saints for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
are vile bodies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 2. That the Lord Jesus Christ at the great day of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
shall raise these vile bodies, and charge them into the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
of his own glorious body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 1. That the bodies even of th<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> best of Saints for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
are vile bodies.</p>
            <p>The holy Apostle foresaw how prone men and women would
be to be proud of their bodies, to pamper them, to spend all
their time, and lay out all their strength to provide for their
bodies, even with the neglect of their more pretious souls:
And therefore that he might wean people from the immoderate
love of their bodies, he purposely calls them <hi>vile bodies:</hi> and
1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 43, he calls them dishonourable bodies, or bodies of
dishonour, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> But you will demand; In what respects may the body
be said to be a vile body?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> The body may be said to be a vile body,</p>
            <p>1. In reference to its <hi>primitive constitution,</hi> even before it
was defiled with sin; for it was made of dust of the earth, the
and not of dust simply, but of dust mingled with water, of
clay and muddy dust, <hi>ex pulvero limoso &amp; lutoso:</hi> The body
was not made of coelestiall materials, of the Sunne, Moon or
Starres; nor of pretious materials, of gold or silver; but of
the worst and lowest of the elements, <hi>ex fragili &amp; vili mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riâ,</hi>
of frail and perishing, of ignoble and contemptible mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials,
and therefore may fitly be called <hi>a vile body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:101409:6"/>
2. Since the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> our bodies are called <hi>vile bodies,</hi>
because subject to <hi>vile diseases,</hi> thereis no disease so vile, but the
body of man is subject unto: <hi>Job</hi> was a man eminent in godliness,
yet his body was full of soars and biles <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>om the crown of his
head to the sole of his foot; and he saies of himself, <hi>Job 7. 5. My
flesh is cloathed with worms and clods of dust, my skin is broken and
become loathsome.</hi> Who can reckon up all the diseases that mans
body is liable unto? The Stone, the Govt, Leprosie, Plague,
Colick, Strangury, Diabolicall possession, Madness, Sciatica
and small Pox, are not the tithe of them; and therefore it may
fitly be called a vile body.</p>
            <p>3. Because subject to vile abuses by <hi>Tyrants</hi> and cruell <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutors:</hi>
A Tyrant cannot hurt the soul of a child of God,
but he can torture and kill his body. It is said of the blessed
Martyrs, of whom the world was not worthy, <hi>Heb. 11. 37. They
were stoned, they were sawed asunder, were slain with the sword;
They wandred about in Sheep-skins and Goat-skins, destitute,
afflicted and tormented.</hi> All these sufferings were bodily, and
therefore it may well be termed a vile body.</p>
            <p>4. Because subject to vile <hi>abominations</hi> and <hi>wickednesses.</hi>
For since the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> our bodies are instruments of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteousness
unto sinne, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 13. they are <hi>servants to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanness
and to iniquity unto iniquity,</hi> Rom. 6. 19 In some to
drunkenness, in others to adultery, theevery and murder; in
others to sodomy, by which the bodies of men are made vile
and dishonourable, according to the saying of the Apostle,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 24. Wherefore God also gave them up to uncleanness,
through the lusts of their own hearts, <hi>to dishonour their own bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
between themselves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. Because even in the best of Saints,<note place="margin">The Greek for a <hi>body</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>quasi</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, And <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>a</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> it is a great impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
and hindrance to their immortall souls, and therefore
called <hi>sepulchrum animae,</hi> and <hi>vinculum animae,</hi> The sepulcher
of the soul, the fetters and manacles of the soul. For the most
pretious soul,</p>
            <p>1. It is <hi>hidden</hi> in the body as a man in a <hi>dark dungeon,</hi> or
as a <hi>bright candle</hi> in a <hi>dark lantern,</hi> the excellent nature,
beauty, and glorious operations of it cannot be seen. For it
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101409:6"/>
may be said of the soul (as <hi>Plato</hi> saith of vertue) <hi>that if
a man could but see it he could not but love it:</hi> but it is hidden
in the body as in a prison.</p>
            <p>2. It is hindred by the body in three respects.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>It is hindred from</hi> Heaven:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.</note> 
               <hi>For</hi> whilest we are at
home in the body, we are absent from the Lord. This earthly
house must first be dissolved, before we can come to the house
made without hands, eternall in the Heavens.</p>
            <p>2. It is hindred from <hi>heavenly operations;</hi> for the body
takes up all the time from the soul. As the lean kine of
<hi>Pharaoh</hi> devoured the fat, so doth the body devour the
time that should be spent about the soul. It is with the
soul and body as it was with <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot, Abraham</hi>
had his servants and cattell, and <hi>Lot</hi> his, and the country
was too little for them. So the soul hath her work, and
the body his work, and there is hardly time enough for
both, so that the one must needs hinder the other, and
they will never be right till separated. Now this must
needs be a great bondage, when the <hi>handmaid</hi> shall have
more attendance then the <hi>Mistresse, Hagar</hi> preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<hi>Sarah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. It is hindred in all its heavenly operations; As a
bird that hath a stone tied to its leg, is weighed down and
cannot fly aloft: so is the heavenly soul in the best of
Saints, depressed and weighed down with the body, that
it cannot fly aloft in Prayer and heavenly meditations.
The body is quickly tired in holy services, As <hi>Sauls</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour
was a burden to <hi>David,</hi> so is the body to the soul.
Therefore the Apostle saith. 2 <hi>Cor. 5. 4. We that are in this
Tabernacle do groan, being burdened.</hi> The spirit is willing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
but the flesh is weak; like a strong man riding upon a
dull horse.</p>
            <p>3. It is defiled and made more sinfull by the body. God
gave man at first a <hi>heavenly</hi> soul and an <hi>earthly</hi> body, that
the <hi>heavenly</hi> soul might lift up the <hi>earthly</hi> body: But it
proves quite contrary; our earthly bodies have weighed
down our heavenly souls, and made them earthly and sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suall.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101409:7"/>
               <hi>Tamdiu versata est anima in Tabernaculo, ut ipsa versa
est in Tabernaculum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> As clothes when they are died lose their
Names, and are called scarlet or stammell: so the souls of
men have received such an ill tincture from their bodies, that
they may fitly be called worldly, sensuall and carnall. The
soul is diverted by the body from its true end: The true end
of the soul is to love God and to live to God, but the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
turns the stream, and ingrosseth all for back and belly,
and therefore may very justly be termed a <hi>vile body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>6. The body may be said to be vile, in reference to its <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution</hi>
and <hi>separation,</hi> For when it once dies, it is then evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
to an eye of flesh, that it is nothing but a rotten, stinking,
putrifying carcass; that body which while united to the soul
seemed very lovely and beautifull, when once the soul leaves
it, it becomes an ugly, deformed, gastly carcass, mouldring quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
into dust, <hi>That saith to corruption Thou art my Father, and to
the Worm Thou art my Mother and my Sister,</hi> Job 17. 14.</p>
            <p>7. It is called a vile body, in comparison of the precious soul.
The body is <hi>the worst half of man;</hi> it is half, but it is the worst
half: it is <hi>vilissima pars hominis:</hi> it is the <hi>box,</hi> the <hi>shell,</hi> the <hi>house</hi>
of man; but it is the soul that is the <hi>kernell,</hi> the <hi>Jewel,</hi> the <hi>inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant.</hi>
The <hi>soul of man</hi> is the <hi>man of man, Intus est quod homo est.</hi>
The <hi>soul</hi> is as an <hi>Angel</hi> dwelling in the body as in an house of
<hi>Clay. Plato</hi> tells us, that is is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an <hi>heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
plant,</hi> and of a <hi>divine offspring.</hi> The Scripture tells us, that it
was not made of the dust of the earth as the body was, but <hi>ex
ore Dei,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 7.</note> by the breath of God: made a <hi>Deo</hi> though not <hi>de Deo,</hi>
by God immediatly, though not of the essence of God. And
when a man dies, the soul is not turned to dust as the body is:
The soul doth not die with the body. <hi>Stephens</hi> soul was not
stoned when his body was stoned. When the <hi>body returns to the
earth as it was, the soul returns to God who gave it,</hi> Eccl. 12. 7.
And therefore in comparison of the soul, the body may be said
to be a vile body.</p>
            <p>8. Lastly, It is called a <hi>vile body,</hi> in comparison of what it
shall be at the great day of the <hi>r<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>urrection:</hi> for then it shall
changed and metamorphized, and made like unto the glorious
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101409:7"/>
body of Jesus Christ, and therefore in comparison of what it
shall be hereafter, it may well be stiled for the present a <hi>vile
body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us often meditate upon this <hi>appellation</hi> and <hi>Epithete</hi> that
is given unto the body:<note place="margin">Vse.</note> it is called a <hi>vile body,</hi> or a <hi>body of vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness:</hi>
Vile, when separated from the soul, vile whilest united to
the soul: Vile before defiled with sinne, but especially vile since
it was defiled with sinne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Vile because subject to vile diseases,
to vile abuses by wicked persecutors, to vile abominations:
Vile, because it is an impediment of the soul: Vile in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison
of the pretious soul, and in respect to what it shall be at
the glorious appearing of Jesus Christ. Let this Meditation
teach us these Lessons.</p>
            <p>1. A lesson of <hi>humility.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lesson 1.</note> The body we carry about us is but
a <hi>vile body,</hi> and therefore let us not be <hi>proud</hi> of it: It is <hi>corpus
humile</hi> (as <hi>Beza</hi> translates this Text) or <hi>corpus humilitatis,</hi> a
body of humility, and therefore let it teach us humility. God
on purpose hath made the body of man of the worst and lowest
element, that he might not be lifted up with pride, but have a
mean and low esteem of himself. Hence it is also that in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture
it is compared to things that are very mean and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible;<note place="margin">Isa, 40.</note>
To the <hi>grass</hi> of the field, to <hi>dry stubble,</hi> to a <hi>leaf</hi> driven
to and fro,<note place="margin">Job 13. 25, 28.</note> to a <hi>thing</hi> that is <hi>rotten,</hi> and to a <hi>garment</hi> that is
<hi>moth-eaten.</hi> It is compared to such mean things, that we might
learn to have a mean esteem of it. Why art thou proud oh dust
and ashes? What is Man but <hi>handsome mudd</hi> and <hi>guilded rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness?</hi>
What are Riches but <hi>brighter dust?</hi> And what are Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours
but <hi>heaps of dung?</hi> dust you are, and God will lay your
honours in the dust. Why art thou proud O dust and ashes?
The <hi>birds</hi> make their <hi>nests</hi> of that which thou art made of:
Every <hi>beast</hi> treads under his <hi>feet</hi> that which thou wert made of:
every <hi>crceping thing</hi> disposeth at pleasure of that which thou
wert made of: every <hi>blast of wind</hi> scattereth that which thou
wert made of, and why art thou proud oh dust and ashes?
<hi>Bernard</hi> in three expressions sets out the vileness of the body,
It is (saith he) <hi>sperma faetidum, saccus stercorum, esca vermium,</hi>
it is <hi>worms-meat,</hi> it is a sack of dung, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:101409:8"/>
I have read a story of a certain <hi>stone</hi> that was brought to
<hi>Alexander the Great,</hi> which being put into one part of <hi>a pair of
Scales,</hi> weighed down whatsoever was put into the other part:
but if a little dust had been cast upon the stone, then every thing
weighed down the stone. The Morall is t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue though the History
prove a fable; as one of his Wisemen told him; <hi>This stone</hi>
(said he) <hi>sheweth what thou art oh</hi> Alexander. <hi>Whilest thou li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest
thou weighest down all that oppose thee, the whole World
cannot new content thee, when a little dust is cast upon thee, that is,
when thou art dead, then every man will outweigh thee,</hi> &amp; minor
eris quam quicquid mundi, <hi>thou wilt be lesser then any man in
the world.</hi> Such another story is reported of the Father of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi>
that he kept a boy on purpose, to come to him every
morning and to bid him <hi>Remember he was a man.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Let us be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
mindfull that we are but dust, <hi>dust we are and to dust we
must return:</hi> Let us cast dust upon our silks and velvets, upon
our gold and silver, upon our beautifull faces: Let the great
Ladies make this Doctrine their Lookingglasses to dress them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
by every morning: Remember thy body is a vile body,
and therefore be not proud of it.</p>
            <p>2. A Lesson of <hi>Mortification:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lesson 2.</note> This vile body of ours is sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
to be abused by the devil to vile abominations, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
let us go to Jesus Christ, to get power <hi>to mortifie and cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
the flesh with the affections and lusts.</hi> There is a <hi>body of sinne</hi>
in all men, and this is that which makes this <hi>body</hi> of ours to be
so <hi>vile.</hi> Let us by a lively faith make application of the death of
Christ,<note place="margin">Rom. 6. 6.</note> that <hi>the old man being crucified, with him the body of sinne
may be destroyed, that henceforth we should not serve sinne.</hi> Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledt
is that expression of the Apostle, 1 <hi>Cor. 9. 27. But I keep
under my body, and bring it into subjection, least that by any means
when I have preached to others, I my self should be a castaway.</hi>
Upon which words <hi>Austin</hi> hath this saying, <hi>Si aries de grege,
quid tener agnus,</hi> &amp;c, If the great Ram of the flock hath need
to beat down his body and to bring it under subjection, how
much more should we <hi>tender Lambs</hi> use all means for the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of it under? The body is called by <hi>Hierom, jumentum animae</hi>
the beast of the soul, and when this beast begins to kick against
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101409:8"/>
the soul,<note place="margin">In vita ejus per Hierony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum.</note> we must labour to subdue it by fasting and prayer, and
say as <hi>Hilarion</hi> did, <hi>Faciam Asine ut non calcitres.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. A Lesson of <hi>Contentation:</hi> Let us be contented with our
condition though never so Poor:<note place="margin">Lesson 3.</note> Though thy apparel be mean,
and thy diet mean: <hi>mean things become a vile body.</hi> And if for a
good conscience thou be put into a <hi>vile prison,</hi> into a <hi>dark</hi> and
<hi>stinking dungeon</hi> as the Martyrs have been, let us be contented
with it, for our bodies for the present are <hi>vile bodies:</hi> Thou
canst not be poorer then thou wert at <hi>first,</hi> and wilt be at <hi>last;</hi>
for <hi>naked we came into the world, and naked we must return again.</hi>
And though thou hast a diseased and sickly body, and hast met
with many losses and crosses, yet be contented; remember
that the bodies of the best of Saints in this life are <hi>vile bodies.</hi>
I have read of <hi>Themistocles,</hi> that he invited many Philosophers
to dinner, and that he borrowed divers dishes of one <hi>Amyntas;</hi>
in the midst of dinner <hi>Amyntas</hi> comes and fetches away half
his dishes; the Philosophers asked <hi>Themistocles</hi> how he was
able to bear this affront? He answered mildly, He might have
took away all. If God hath taken away <hi>half</hi> thy children, <hi>half</hi>
thy estate, be contented, <hi>all is his,</hi> and he might have taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<hi>all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. Let this Epithete teach us a lesson of <hi>heavenly courage
and fortitude;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lesson 4.</note> let us not fear what the worst of men can do
unto us, for they can but kill this vile body. This our Saviour
teacheth <hi>Matth. 10. Fear not them that can kill the body, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
that can do no more.</hi> If a Tyrant could kill the soul, then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
he might be feared, but he cannot reach that, he can but
hurt the body, ths <hi>vile body,</hi> a <hi>body</hi> subject to a thousand <hi>disea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi>
and to innumerable <hi>abominatious;</hi> a <hi>body</hi> that will shortly
dye of its own accord; and why then should we fear what <hi>vile</hi>
man can do against this <hi>vile body?</hi> especially if we consider,
that when he hath done his worst against it, it shall in spite of
him <hi>rise again,</hi> and of a <hi>vile body,</hi> become a most <hi>glorious bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</hi>
Oh let us not make <hi>shipwrack</hi> of a <hi>good conscience</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve
this <hi>vile body;</hi> let us not destroy our precious souls to
save this vile carcass!</p>
            <p>5. If the body be vile in comparison of the soul,<note place="margin">Lesson 5.</note> then let us
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101409:9"/>
be encouraged unto <hi>soul-diligence.</hi> Let us not set the <hi>servant</hi>
on <hi>horseback,</hi> and suffer the <hi>Master</hi> to go on <hi>foot;</hi> let us not
preferre the <hi>handmaid</hi> before the <hi>Mistress,</hi> the <hi>box</hi> before the
<hi>Jewel,</hi> the <hi>vile body</hi> before our <hi>pretious</hi> and <hi>immortal souls.</hi>
The <hi>body</hi> is made of <hi>dust,</hi> and who ever advanced dust? we use
to sweep away dust from off our clothes, and out of our houses.
The body is but a lump of earth, a rotten carcass without the
soul, oh let us not preferre it before the soul! let us not bestow
that time, that heart, those affections and endeavours upon the
body, which are due unto the soul!</p>
            <p>It is a sad thing to consider, how most people, even those that
beleeve the Doctrine of the <hi>souls Immortality,</hi> do <hi>Jacob-like,</hi>
(though upon a different occasion) put their right hand upon
the <hi>youngest Sonne,</hi> and their left hand upon the <hi>eldest,</hi> spending
the best of their dayes, and strength, and affections upon these
<hi>vile bodies,</hi> and in the mean time neglecting to provide for their
<hi>eternal souls.</hi> Give me leave to illustrate this by a similitude:
Suppose a man should invite a <hi>Nobleman</hi> to his house, and only
provide provender for the Noblemans <hi>horses,</hi> without any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision
at all for <hi>himself,</hi> only such as his horses feed on,
would not this be a course entertainment? and yet so do most
men deal with their immortal souls. The <hi>soul</hi> is as this <hi>Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi>
lodging in a <hi>body of clay</hi> as in a poor cottage; the <hi>body</hi> is
(as you have heard) <hi>jumentum animae,</hi> the souls beast; and when
you consume your dayes in pampering and cloathing your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,
taking no care for your <hi>noble</hi> souls, this is but (as it were)
providing provender for the horses, without any provision for
the <hi>Nobleman:</hi> for the soul is never the <hi>richer</hi> for all our
worldly wealth, never the <hi>fatter</hi> for our delicate fare, nor ever
the <hi>finer</hi> for our silken clothes. I read that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John</hi> in 3 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.
prayeth for <hi>Gaius, That his body might prosper and be in health
even as his soul prospered.</hi> But if we should make such a prayer
for many of our people, we should rather curse them then pray
for them; for if they had no <hi>better bodies</hi> then they have <hi>souls,</hi>
they would have very <hi>poor, lean and naked bodies.</hi> Let Christians
labour so to live that this prayer may be fit for them, that we
may cheerfully put up this petition for them, <hi>That their bodies
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101409:9"/>
may prosper even as their souls prosper:</hi> Let the <hi>chiefest part</hi> have
the <hi>chiefest care,</hi> the <hi>best part</hi> the <hi>best</hi> of our <hi>strength</hi> and
<hi>dayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>6. Lastly,<note place="margin">Lesson 6.</note> Let us from this Epithete learn a lesson of <hi>thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullness:</hi>
Our bodies are <hi>bodies</hi> of <hi>vileness,</hi> and therefore if
God hath given thee a body more <hi>handsome</hi> and more <hi>health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi>
then others have; if God hath made any of us <hi>ex meliore
luto,</hi> of better earth; if he hath made us <hi>golden vessels</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
of our outward condition; if he hath raised any of us
from the dust, and set us in <hi>high places;</hi> especially if God hath
made us <hi>elect vessels,</hi> vessels of mercy in regard of our eternal
condition, as I doubt not but there are many such here, oh
give God a <hi>great deal of glory,</hi> and give him <hi>all the glory.</hi> If he
hath made thy vile body an instrument of righteousness unto
holiness; if he hath sanctified it, and made it a <hi>Temple</hi> fit for
the holy Ghost to dwell in, then let me speak to you in the
language of the holy Ghost;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 15. 19. 3. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Know you not that your bodies are
the members of Christ? will you take the members of Christ, and
make them members of an harlot? God forbid. Know you not
that your body is the Temple of the holy Ghost which is in you,</hi> &amp;c.
And <hi>If any man defile the Temple of God, him will God destroy.</hi>
Will you abuse that body that is the Temple of the holy Ghost
to sinne and iniquity? God forbid,</p>
            <p>I shall now pass from the first Observation to the second,
with which our <hi>worthy and dear brother was much refreshed,</hi> and
did often repeat in my hearing, and upon that account I made
made choice of this Text at this time. The Observation is,</p>
            <p>That the Lord Jesus Christ at the great day of judgment,<note place="margin">Doct. 2.</note> shall
raise these vile bodies, and change them into the likeness of his own
glorious body.</p>
            <p>This Doctrine is an <hi>Alablaster box</hi> full of pretious consola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
It was a great comfort and support to our <hi>dear brother</hi>
when he was going out of this world, and oh that it might
be a like <hi>pretious Cordial</hi> to us when we shall be in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
            <p>For the better understanding of the Doctrine, I shall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound
these five Questions,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:101409:10"/>
1. What is that change that Christ shall make in our vile
bodies at the resurrection?<note place="margin">Quest. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The bodies of the Saints when dead,<note place="margin">Answ.</note> and separated from
their souls, are not separated from Jesus Christ, and therefore
are said to be <hi>dead in Christ;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Thes. 4. 15.</note> while dead they are united to
Christ, and by virtue of this union <hi>Christ</hi> as their <hi>Head</hi> will
raise them at the last day, and at their resurrection they shall
be changed, <hi>non quoad substantiam sed quoad proprietates,</hi> the
substance of their bodies shall not be altered, but only the <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities,</hi>
As <hi>wool</hi> when it is died into a <hi>purple</hi> or <hi>scarlet</hi> die, is the
same wool for substance though it be made more glorious; so
the bodies of the Saints at the resurrection, shall be the same
for substance though made more excellent and more glorious.
This was <hi>Jobs</hi> comfort,<note place="margin">Job 19. 25, 26, 27.</note> that with <hi>those very eyes</hi> of his he
should see his Redeemer, and that <hi>he himself</hi> should see him
and <hi>not another.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 53.</note> The Apostle tells us, That <hi>this</hi> mortall body
must put on immortality, and <hi>this</hi> corrupt<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble body must put
on incorruption. The ancient Christians when they rehearsed
that article of the Creed, <hi>Credo resurrectioneme carnis,</hi> I beleeve
the resurrection of the flesh, were wont to add, <hi>Etiam hujus
carnis,</hi> even of this my flesh. It cannot stand with <hi>Gods justice</hi>
(saith <hi>Hierom)</hi> that one body should <hi>sinne</hi> and another body
be <hi>damned,</hi> that one body should <hi>serve him</hi> and another be
<hi>crowned;</hi> this is contrary to the justice of <hi>God,</hi> and to the very
nature of the <hi>resurrection;</hi> for a <hi>resurrection</hi> is, when the <hi>same
body</hi> that dieth riseth again, otherwise, it is rather a <hi>new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
then a <hi>resurrection.</hi> As the body of Christ after his resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,
was the same for substance though much more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
and glorious, so shall the bodies of the Saints be at their
resurrection. As a <hi>Goldsmith</hi> (saith <hi>Chrysostome)</hi> takes a little
gold and puts it into a refining pot and melts it, and then out
of that <hi>gold</hi> forms a <hi>golden vessel</hi> fit to be set before Kings:
so the Lord Jesus Christ melts the bodies of his Saints by death,
and out of their dead ashes and cinders will form a vessel of
gold, a glorious body, fit to live with God and sing Hallelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jahs
in Heaven to all enternity.</p>
            <p>2.<note place="margin">Quest. 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> What are those <hi>transfigurations</hi> and <hi>transformations</hi> that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101409:10"/>
Christ shall make in our bodies at this day? what is this <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamorphosis,</hi>
wherein doth it consist?</p>
            <p>It is impossible to set out all the glorious excellencies with
which Christ will adorn our bodies in the great day of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection.<note place="margin">Answ.</note>
               <hi>Quae sit &amp; quam magna spiritualis corporis gloria
quoniam nondum venit in experimentum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> de Civ. Dei, lib. 22.</note> 
               <hi>vereor ne temerarium sit
omne quod de illâ profertur eloquium,</hi> How great the glory of
our spirituall bodies shall be, because we have no experience
of it, I fear it will be rashness for any man (saith <hi>Austin)</hi> to
speak peremptorily about it: It will be the marriage day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
Christ and his Saints, and he will endow their bodies
with glorious qualities as well as their souls, for he assumed
their bodies as well as their souls, suffered in body as well as
in soul, died for their bodies as well as for their souls, and
therefore will glorifie their bodies as well as their souls.</p>
            <p>Give me leave to mention some of those glorious perfections
with which our vile bodies shall be beautified at that day.</p>
            <p>1. The bodies of the Saints at the resurrection shall be <hi>free
from all sinne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> shall not then complain of <hi>a law in his
members rebelling against the law of his minde,</hi> nor cry out, <hi>Oh
miserable man that I am, who shall deliver me from the body of
this death?</hi> we shall at that day not only have a <hi>posse non pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care,</hi>
a possibility not to sinne, as <hi>Adam</hi> had in innocency, but a
<hi>non posse peccare,</hi> an impossibility of sinning.</p>
            <p>2. Our bodies shall be made immortall and incorruptible,
1 <hi>Cor. 15. 53, 54. This mortall shall put on immortality,</hi> as a
garment never to be put off again; <hi>Death shall be swallowed up
in victory Adam</hi> in innocency, as he had a power not to sinne,
so also not to die; but the Saints at the resurrection shall have
an impossibility of sinning and of dying. Not but that our
bodies are naturally corruptible even at the resurrection, but
by the presence of God filling them, they shall be made like the
Angels, immortall. And if <hi>embalming</hi> the body can preserve
it from putrefaction for many years, much more will the
presence of God preserve it from death for ever.</p>
            <p>3. The third endowment is brightness and splendour, <hi>It is
sown in dishonour, but it is raised in glory,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 43. The
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101409:11"/>
body is not so miserable under the curse, as it is blessed in the
promise. As in the state of corruption it is abased lower then
all created bodies, so in the state of glory it is exalted higher
then all other bodies;<note place="margin">Mat. 13. 43.</note> 
               <hi>For the righteous shall shine forth as the
Sunne in the Kingdom of their Father.</hi> Not that they shall not
out-shine the Sunne, but because there is no more shining bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
visible to us, therefore are the bodies of the Saints in glory
compared thereunto.<note place="margin">M. <hi>Norton</hi> in his <hi>Orthodox Evangelist.</hi>
               </note> The glory of the body (saith one) will
<hi>exceed all the beauty and splendour of Gems, Pearls, Heavens,
Sunne, Moon and Starres, yea even the Heaven of Heavens,
though all were put together.</hi> This Text tells us, that our vile
bodies shall be made <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable
to the glorious body of Christ.</hi> This is abundantly sufficient
to set out the glory of our body at that day: for the body of
Christ now in Heaven is unexpressibly glorious. We have a
<hi>specimen</hi> of this in the <hi>transfiguration,</hi> Matth. 17. 2. <hi>Peter,
James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were not able to bear the sight of the glory
there manifested, which yet was but a glimpse of that glory
which he now hath in Heaven. Some Divines are of opinion,
that the <hi>brightness</hi> which <hi>Paul</hi> saw when he was strook blinde
and fell to the earth,<note place="margin">Acts 9.</note> was the <hi>brightness of the body of Jesus
Christ.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 22. 23.</note> Sure I am, that <hi>Christs body</hi> is the <hi>light of Heaven:</hi> And
if <hi>Stephens face</hi> in this life was seen as the <hi>face</hi> of an <hi>Angel;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 6. 15.</note> if
<hi>Moses</hi> his face did so shine in being fourty dayes with God,<note place="margin">Exod. 34. 30.</note> that
the people could not behold it, how glorious shall our bodies
be when we shall be for ever with the Lord, and when our <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi>
of <hi>vileness</hi> shall be fashioned like unto the <hi>glorious body of
Jesus Christ?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. The fourth endowment is <hi>beauty and comeliness:</hi> The
bodies of the Saints shall be perfectly compleat in all their
parts; if maimed and defective here, it shall be sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ied
at that day, which is a day of <hi>restitution of all things,</hi>
Acts 3. 21. And not only so, but all crookedness, lameness and
ill-favouredness, which are the fruits of sinne, shall be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
<hi>Jacob</hi> shall halt no more, nor <hi>Mephibosheth</hi> complain of
lameness, nor <hi>Isaac</hi> of dimness. As the body of <hi>Adam</hi> in inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency
was lovely and beautifull, compleat in all its parts, so
shall ours be at the resurrection.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:101409:11"/>
5. The fift is <hi>majesty:</hi> Great shall be the majesty of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
at the resurrection. If a good man in this life hath such a
majesty in his countenance, as to cause men to fear to sinne in
his company; If <hi>Valens</hi> the Emperour said of <hi>Basil, That he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
looked upon him, but his countenance strock an awe and terror
into him:</hi> oh what majesty will be in the faces and countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
of the Saints in that day?</p>
            <p>6. The sixth is <hi>spirituality: It is sown a natural body, it is
raised a spiritual body,</hi> 1 Cot. 15. 44. Not spiritual for substance
but for qualities: For 1. It shall have no need of meat or sleep,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> but shall be as the <hi>Angels of God,</hi> Matth. 22. 30. <hi>Non quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad
Angelicam essentiam, sed Angelicas proprietates. Tertullian</hi>
saith, That the Saints shall have <hi>corpora reformata &amp; Angelifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata.
If Moses</hi> was fourty dayes upon the mount without
meat and without sleep, upheld by the power of God in the state
of mortality, much more shall we be upheld for ever in the
state of immortality. 2. It shall be a spiritual body, because
it shall be absolutely subject to the spirit. In the state of glory,
the soul shall not depend upon the body, but the body upon the
soul. In this life the soul is as it were carnall because so service<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
to the flesh, but then the body shall be spiritual because
so serviceable to the spirit.</p>
            <p>7. The seventh is <hi>Agility and nimbleness:</hi> It shall be able to
move upwards and downwards,<note place="margin">Vbi volet spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, ibi protenus erit corpus.</note> like a bird in the aire; <hi>Luther</hi>
saith, That the <hi>body shall be able to move up and down like a
thought. Austin</hi> saith, <hi>It shall move to any place it will as soon as
it will.</hi> The Scripture saith some such thing, 1 <hi>Thes. 4. 17. We
shall be caught up together in the clouds to meet the Lord in the
ayre,</hi> as so many AEgles flying up to their blessed Carcass. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
this account also it is said, That we shall be as the Angels,
because we shall be able to move as they do:<note place="margin">M. <hi>Norton.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>If the Saints shall
be like the Sunne in its brightness, why not</hi> (saith one) <hi>in its mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
also, which the Learned allow to move a Million, and one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
sixty thousand miles in an hour:</hi> If so swift may be the
motion of natural, how swift the motion of glorified bodies
shall be, we shall know when we come to make use of it.</p>
            <p>The eighth endowment is <hi>Powerfulnes: It is sown in weakness,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101409:12"/>
but it shall rise in power,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 43. The power that the body
shall have will be wonderfull: <hi>Luther</hi> saith, That it shall have
a power to be able <hi>to tess the greatest mountains in the world
like a ball: Anselme</hi> saith, They shall be <hi>able to shake the whole
earth at pleasure;</hi> How true this is we shall know hereafter:
Sure I am for the present, That the weakest in glory shall be
stronger then <hi>Sampson</hi> in his greatest strength: and that the
bodies power shall be so great, as to be able to be the <hi>souls in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument</hi>
in the <hi>enjoyment of God</hi> in all the <hi>highest operations</hi>
without <hi>intermission.</hi> In this life when the soul is busied about
<hi>high</hi> and <hi>sublime</hi> matters, the body presently faints, <hi>Dan.</hi> 8. 27.
but then it shall attend without any <hi>faintness</hi> or <hi>weariness.</hi> In
this life the eye is dazeled at the brightness of the Sunne; but
then it shall be strengthened to behold glorious sights and not
be dazeled at it: the body shall be elevated and strengthened
by God, to bear that <hi>exceeding eternal weight of glory</hi> that shall
be put upon it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Unto all these glorious perfections and excellent indow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
I might add</hi> An admission to behold with our bodily eyes the
sight of Christ as man. <hi>That we shall see Christ as man with these
eyes,</hi> Job <hi>manifestly testifieth,</hi> Job 19. 25, 26, 27. <hi>And that this
sight will add much to our happiness is easily evinced: For the
sight of</hi> Christ <hi>as man is the next object unto the</hi> beatificall
vision it self: <hi>For the fullness of the Godhead dwels in him bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily,
and this doth as it were radiate through his body; hence
there</hi> must needs arise <hi>(as one saith)</hi> great joy unto the beholder,<note place="margin">Norton <hi>in his</hi> Orthodox E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelist.</note>
both from the eminency of, and our interest in this object. Christ in
glory, and Christ in glory ours; As much of the Creator as is
possibly visible in the nature of man, will be to be seen in Christ; as
much contentation as the creature can be made partakers of by the
sight of any one visible object, will be the portion of the beholders of
Christ, as he is man. <hi>All this is in answer to the second Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. How is it possible that ever these bodies of ours should
rise again,<note place="margin">Quest. 3.</note> and these vile bodies be made like unto the glorious
body of Christ?</p>
            <p>With <hi>man</hi> this is <hi>impossible,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Answ.</note> but with <hi>God</hi> nothing is <hi>impossible.</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:101409:12"/>
My text tells you how this shall be done, even <hi>according to the
mighty working whereby he is able to subdue all things unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self.</hi>
The Lord Jesus Christ is almighty, and therefore he is able
to do it.<note place="margin">Tertul.</note> He that can make a man being <hi>nothing,</hi> out of the dust
of the earth, can certainly repair him out of that dust when he
is <hi>something.</hi> It is as easie to God to give a <hi>body</hi> to a soul at
the resurrection, as to breathe a <hi>soul</hi> into a body at the first
creation. Both Philosophers and Divines write of the <hi>Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix,</hi>
that first she is consumed to ashes by the heat of the Sunne,
and that afterwards of her ashes ariseth a young one, which is
the same <hi>Phoenix</hi> risen from the dead. The Apostle tells us,
That <hi>the corn must first be cast into the ground,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.</note> 
               <hi>and there die and
rot before it will spring up;</hi> which sheweth, that a resurrection
from the dead is possible even in nature. What is every <hi>night,</hi>
but the <hi>grave</hi> (as it were) of the dayes <hi>light?</hi> What is the
<hi>morning,</hi> but the <hi>resurrection</hi> of the day? What is <hi>winter,</hi> but
the <hi>death</hi> (as it were) of fruits? and what the <hi>spring,</hi> but the
<hi>resurrection</hi> of them? What is <hi>death,</hi> but a <hi>pulling down</hi> of the
house of our bodies? and what is the <hi>resurrection,</hi> but the
<hi>building up</hi> of the same house more gloriously? And cannot
the Almighty God do this? We see by experience, that our
most curious <hi>glasses,</hi> are made by art even of <hi>ashes;</hi> and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
the omnipotent and everliving God, raise mens dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
out of ashes? The earth and sea are Gods <hi>stewards,</hi> with
whom he hath betrusted the bodies of men; and when God
shall call them to give an <hi>account</hi> of their <hi>stewardship,</hi> they
will faithfully discharge their trust, and will not keep back one
dead body. The grave is but the bodies <hi>withdrawing-room</hi> or
<hi>sleepi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g-place,</hi> and the time will come, when they that are
<hi>asleep in the dust of the earth shall awake,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 2. And it
is as easie for God to distinguish between <hi>dust</hi> and <hi>dust,</hi> and
to give to every man his <hi>own dust,</hi> as it is for a gardiner that
hath <hi>divers seeds</hi> in his hand to sever them, and know them one
from another. A curious <hi>Watch-maker</hi> can undo his Watch,
and put it together again. A skilfull <hi>Alchymist</hi> can extract one
mettall out of another: much more can Almighty God di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguish
<hi>one dust from another, as well as one man from another.</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:101409:13"/>
In a word: It is as easie for God to make our vile bodies glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,
as it is for a <hi>beggar</hi> to put off his <hi>raggs,</hi> and to put on
the <hi>apparrel</hi> of a <hi>King.</hi> Our dear and Reverend Brother did
fully beleeve this, and therefore he three times in my hearing
repeated these words; <hi>According to his mighty power, his migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
power, even his mighty power, he is able to change this vile
body of mine, and make it like unto his glorious body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. Shall all bodies be made thus glorious?<note place="margin">Quest. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>No:<note place="margin">Answ.</note> The bodies of the wicked shall rise at the last day, but
it shall be to their everlasting shame, ruin and confusion. They
shall be <hi>immortall,</hi> but they shall be <hi>immortall fuell to immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
flames.</hi> The bodies of the wicked shall come out of their
<hi>gravos</hi> as out of their <hi>prisons,</hi> and as so many <hi>malefactors</hi> to
appear before an <hi>angry Judg.</hi> They shall come out of their
graves as the <hi>chief Baker</hi> did out of prison, to be hung in chains
in hell for ever, where they shall endure all kind of extremities
figured out unto us by the sad condition of <hi>Dives,</hi> who could
not get a drop of water to cool his tongue. The bodies of the
wicked shall be as <hi>ugly, loathsome carcasses to look upon, and their
faces shall gather blackness and darkness,</hi> Isa. 66. 24. They shall
arise with great fear and trembling, and shall call to the <hi>hils and
mountains to cover and hide them from the presence of the Lamb.</hi>
Oh the horror and astonishment that shall be at that day, when
the foul of a wicked man shall come out of hell, and be again
united to the body: How will the body curse the soul, and the
soul the body? How will they befool one another? Certainly
this greeting will be very terrible; the Lord grant we may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
come to have experience of it.</p>
            <p>5. What are the Characters of those men and women,<note place="margin">Quest. 5.</note> whose
vile bodies shall be made like unto the glorious body of Christ?</p>
            <p>1. There is one Character of them in the text:<note place="margin">Answ. 1.</note> If thou art
one that <hi>hast thy conversation in Heaven,</hi> then thy body shall
be made glorious: <hi>For our conversation is in Heaven, from
whence also we look for a Saviour the Lord Jesus Christ, who
shall change our vile bodies, and make them like to his glorious bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi>
&amp;c. If thou beest a man that mindest earthly things; if ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious,
covetous or voluptuous; if given over to fulfill the lusts of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101409:13"/>
the flesh, thy body shall rise, but it shall rise to <hi>everlasting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation:</hi>
But if heavenly-minded; if thy disposition and
conversation be heavenly, when Christ comes from Heaven,
he will make thy body heavenly and glorious.</p>
            <p>2. If a <hi>reall</hi> member of <hi>Christs mysticall body,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Answ. 2.</note> thou shalt
be made partakers of the glory of <hi>Christs natural body.</hi> Christ
hath a double body, a body <hi>mysticall,</hi> and a body <hi>naturall:</hi> If
thou beest a <hi>reall member</hi> of Christs mysticall body, I say a
<hi>reall member,</hi> not only a member by <hi>outward profession,</hi> but by
a <hi>holy conversation;</hi> if truly united by a heart-purifying faith
unto Christs mysticall body, thou shalt be conformable in
glory to Christs naturall body: And therefore it is said, That
at the day of judgment Christ shall be <hi>glorified in his Saints.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Thes. 1. 10.</note>
Here he is glarified <hi>by</hi> his Saints, but then he shall be glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<hi>in</hi> his Saints, that is, in the glory that the members of his
mysticall body shall have at that day.<note place="margin">Col. 3. 3.</note> For Christ shall then
have a double glory; 1. A <hi>personall glory;</hi> for he shall come
with <hi>power and great glory,</hi> Matth. 24. 30. 2. A <hi>sociall glory,</hi>
a glory which he communicates to his Saints, and by which
glory he shall be glorified. For <hi>when Christ who is our life shall
appear, then shall we appear with him in glory.</hi> And the glory
of the <hi>members</hi> shall redound to the glory of the <hi>head:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the Saints are called, the <hi>glory of Christ,</hi> 2 Cor. 8. 23. If a
member of Christ, though but as the toe in his body, thou shalt
be filled brim full of glory at the resurrection.</p>
            <p>3. If thy soul be <hi>gracious</hi> here,<note place="margin">Answ. 2.</note> thy body shall be <hi>glorious</hi>
hereafter: If cloathed with Christs righteousness, if enriched
with the jewels of the Spirit, thy body shall be everlastingly
beautifull and glorious; for <hi>the happiness of the body depends
upon the souls happiness.</hi> If when thou diest thy soul goeth to
hell, thy body at the resurrection must go thither also: If to
Heaven, thy body will follow it thither also: according as thy
soul is, beautifull or deformed, so shall thy body be happy or
miserable. So much in answer to the five Questions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vse</hi> 1. To you that are the <hi>Saints</hi> of the most <hi>high God,</hi>
who have your <hi>conversation in Heaven while you are upon earth,</hi>
who are <hi>reall members of Christs mysticall body,</hi> whose <hi>souls</hi> are
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101409:14"/>
               <hi>adorned</hi> with the <hi>robe of Christs righteousness;</hi> To beseech you
to consider the <hi>blessed and happy condition</hi> that your bodies shall
be in at the <hi>resurrestion,</hi> for then your <hi>vile bodies</hi> shall be
made like unto the <hi>glorious body</hi> of Christ,<note place="margin">Matth. 13. 43.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
shall be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; then shall you <hi>shine forth as the Sun
in the Kingdom of your Father:</hi> All sinne, and all sorrow, and
all bodily deformities shall be utterly removed; you shall be <hi>as
the Angels of God in heaven,</hi> your bodies shall be honourable,
glorious, powerfull, spirituall, perfectly beautifull, lovely and
majesticall, and (as <hi>Aquinas</hi> saith) transparent like glass. Let
the consideration of this</p>
            <p>1. Comfort you against the <hi>fear of death:</hi> As God said to
<hi>Jacob,</hi> Gen. 46. 3, 4. <hi>Fear not to go down into Egypt, for I will go
down with thee, and I will also surely bring theo up again,</hi> &amp;c. So
let me say to you, <hi>Feat not</hi> to go down to the house of rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenness,
<hi>fear not</hi> to lay down your heads in the dust, for God
will certainly bring you out again, and you shall come out in
a most glorious manner: <hi>Fear not</hi> to have this house of your
body pulled down, for God will rear it up again, and make of it
a most glorious structure.</p>
            <p>2. Let this comfort you against the <hi>death of your godly friends;</hi>
for when a <hi>godly man</hi> dies, nothing dies <hi>totally and finally</hi> in him
but <hi>sinne:</hi> Death to a Saint is nothing else but <hi>sepultura vitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi>
a burying of his sinne. <hi>Non homo sed peccatum hominis mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritur,</hi>
the man dies not but his sinne; for the soul doth not die
at all, but is immediately taken up into the bosome of God; and
the body, though it be turned into dust, yet even this dust is <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
in Gods sight;</hi> this dust is part of <hi>Gods elestion,</hi> this dust is
united to <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> (and therefore when a Saint dies, he is
said to <hi>fall asleep in Christ,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 18. and to be <hi>dead in
Christ,</hi> 1 Thes. 4. 16.) and at the last day it shall be raised up
again. <hi>It is sown in corruption, but it shall be raised in incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
It is sown in dishonour, it shall be raised in glory: it is sown
in weakness, it shall be raised in power: it is sown a naturall body,
it shall be raised a spirituall body,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a Text in <hi>Job,</hi> which our <hi>Reverend Brother</hi> did men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
often in his sickness, and with which he did seem to be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101409:14"/>
much refreshed, it is <hi>Job 21. 33. The clods of the valley shall be
sweet unto him.</hi> Which words, though spoken of the wicked, yet
are in a more eminent manner applicable to the true Saint, who
sleeps quietly and sweetly in his grave as in his bed, free from
all trouble and molestation.</p>
            <p>3. Let this comfort those that have <hi>diseased or deformed bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi>
that are troubled with the Stone, Gout, Strangury, disi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
in the head, or any other disease whereby they are made
unserviceable, or at least not able to do that good they would:
there will a day come wherein they shall be perfectly healed and
cured: The <hi>Resurrection</hi> is the Saints <hi>best Physitian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. Let this encourage you to be willing (if God call you to
it) to part with your <hi>ears, eyes, leggs, hands, or head it self, for
the keeping of a good conscience;</hi> for you shall have all your
limbs restored to you again at the great day of <hi>restitution of all
things.</hi> Famous is the story that <hi>Josephus</hi> tells of one of the
seven Children in the <hi>Maccabees,</hi> who when he was to have his
tongue cut out and his ears cut off, he said to his Mother, <hi>These
members I have received from Heaven, and for the Law of my
God I despise them, and trust that I shall receive them again: I
shall have a better tongue at the resurrection of the just.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. Let this exhort you especially that are true Saints, whose
<hi>bodies</hi> by grace are become the <hi>Temples of the holy Ghost;</hi> to
labour to <hi>glorifie God in your bodies</hi> as well as in your spirits, for
they are <hi>Gods,</hi> and they are <hi>bought with a price</hi> as well as your
souls. To labour to <hi>keep under your bodies, and to bring them into
subjection:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 27.</note> 
               <hi>To yeeld your members as instruments of righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
unto God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 13. 14.</note> 
               <hi>and as servants of righteousness unto holiness.</hi> Let
me beseech you by the mercies of Jesus Christ who hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed
your bodies, that <hi>ye present your bodies a living sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,
holy, acceptable unto God, which is your reasonable service.</hi>
Think not any service too much for God with those bodies
which shall one day be made so beautifull and glorious. Let
godly Ministers be encouraged to wear out their bodies in their
Ministeriall imployments, for <hi>they that turn many unto right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eousness,
shall shine as starres for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vse</hi> 2. To you that are wicked, that is, who are <hi>members of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101409:15"/>
the devil, whose souls are beleapred with sinne, who minde earthly
things, whose God is your belly, whose glory is your shame;</hi> To be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech
you to consider the sad and miserable condition you shall
bn in at that day. Your bodies indeed shall rise, but they shall
rise unto <hi>everlasting cindemnation,</hi> Joh. 5. 24. and unto everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting
shame and contempt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 2. your <hi>vile bodies</hi> shall then
be <hi>cursed bodies,</hi> and your <hi>sinfull bodies</hi> shall be <hi>tormented for
ever with the worm that never dieth, and the fire that never go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vse</hi> 3. A <hi>divine project</hi> how to make your bodies beautifull
and glorious. If there were a <hi>Physician</hi> here upon earth that
could cure all your bodily diseases and deformities, and make
them immortall, how would you prize him? I have told you
this day of such a <hi>Physician,</hi> even the <hi>Lord Jesus Christ,</hi> who
shall one day come from Heaven on purpose to make our vile
bodies like unto his glorious body. Oh that this <hi>word</hi> were
<hi>mingled with faith!</hi> Methinks if any Motive could prevail with
you that are Gentlewomen and great Ladies, this should, <hi>Behold</hi>
a way how to make your bodies <hi>eternally beautifull!</hi> What
trouble and pain do many women that are crooked endure, by
wearing Iron bodies to make themselves strait? What vast ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences
are many at for the beautifying of their rotten carcasses?
Hearken unto me thou <hi>proud dust and ashes,</hi> thou <hi>guilded mud,</hi>
that labourest to beautifie thy body by vain, foolish and sinfull
deckings and trimmings, and thinkest thy self <hi>deckt</hi> in the want
of <hi>decking,</hi> that pamperest thy body in all voluptuousness, and
makest <hi>thy self by thy strange fashions so unlike thy self, as that if
our civil fore-fathers were alive again, they would wonder what
strange monster thou wert.</hi> Hearken unto me I say, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider
thy madness and folly: by labouring so much to adorn
thy <hi>body</hi> with the neglect of thy <hi>soul,</hi> thou undoest both <hi>body
and soul.</hi> The only way to make thy body for ever beautifull, is
(as I have said)</p>
            <p>1. To have thy conversation in Heaven while thou art upon
earth, and when Christ comes from Heaven, he will change thy
<hi>vile body</hi> and make it like his <hi>gloriom body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. To labour to be a <hi>reall member</hi> of Christs <hi>mysticall body,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:101409:15"/>
and then thou shalt partake of the <hi>glory</hi> of his <hi>naturall body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. To get a <hi>gracious soul</hi> here, and thou shalt be sure to have
a <hi>glorious body and soul hereafter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a saying of <hi>Bernard</hi> worthy to be written in letters
of gold: <hi>Christ hath a treble coming: Once he came in the flesh
for the good of our souls and bodies: Now he comes in the spirit
(by the preaching of his Ministers) for the good of our souls. At
the last day he shall come for the good of our bodies to beautifie them
and glorifie them. Noli oh homo praeripore tempora,</hi> do not oh
man mistake thy time! This present life is not the time for thy
body: It is appointed for the beautifying of thy soul, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorning
it with grace and holiness. The resurrection is the time
wherein Christ will come from Heaven to make thy body glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious.
How quite contrary to this do most people live? Let
it be our wisdom (with the children of <hi>Issachar) to have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing
of the times.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chro. 12. 31.</note> Study in this <hi>your day</hi> to get <hi>good and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
souls,</hi> and you shall be sure at the great day to have <hi>blessed
and most glorious bodies.</hi> Labour to get your souls <hi>beautified by
Christs second coming with justification and sanctification,</hi> and
<hi>Christ</hi> at his <hi>third coming</hi> will make thy <hi>body glorious above ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>HAving finished my discourse upon the Text, I know it is
expected that I should speak something of our <hi>Dear and
Reverend Brother,</hi> whose sad funerals we now celebrate. It
hath pleased God within a little space to take to himself many
godly and able Ministers, which without doubt is a very great
judgment; and the greater, because most people are so little
sensible of it. And not only a great judgment in it self, but a
presage of greater to come;<note place="margin">Isa. 57. 1.</note> 
               <hi>For the righteous perisheth, and no
man layeth it to heart, and mercifull men are taken away, none
cinsidering that the righteous is taken away from the evil to come.</hi>
The <hi>Rabbins</hi> have a saying, <hi>Quando Luminaria patiuntur
Eclipsim malum signum est mundo,</hi> It is an ill sign to the world
when the Luminaries of Heaven are eclipsed. God hath extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished
many glorious Lights of late, I need not put you of this
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101409:16"/>
City in minde of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Gouge,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Walker,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Whitaker,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Gata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi>
M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Strong,</hi> &amp;c. nor you of the University of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hill,</hi> and
now of this godly Minister D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Samuel Bolton</hi> late Master of
<hi>Christs Colledge</hi> in <hi>Cambridg.</hi> If I should enter upon his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
I may truly say what <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> doth of
his Sister <hi>Gorgonia,</hi> that there is more fear least I should speak
too little, then that I should speak too much. He was <hi>a burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
and shining light</hi> in this our <hi>Israel,</hi> an <hi>interpreter one of a
thousand:</hi> a man of excellent Ministerial abilities, a workman
that <hi>needed not to be ashamed, dividing aright the word of truth.</hi>
He was one that did study not only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not
only to <hi>preach well,</hi> but to <hi>live well:</hi> His life was an excellent
<hi>commentary</hi> upon his Sermons. As <hi>Nazianzen</hi> saith of <hi>John
Baptist</hi> (who is called <hi>The voice of the cryer,)</hi> that he was <hi>all
voice:</hi> a <hi>voice</hi> in his habit, a <hi>voice</hi> in his diet, a <hi>voice</hi> in his dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
a <hi>voice</hi> in his conversation, as well as in his preaching: So
may I truly say of our Reverend Brother, he was <hi>tota vox,</hi> all
voice; a <hi>voice</hi> in his <hi>life</hi> as well as in his <hi>Doctrine;</hi> he lived his
own Sermons, and preached louder by his <hi>good conversation</hi>
then by his <hi>heavenly doctrine. Nam Vita Praedicatorum est vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calissima.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gregorius vir per omnia in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparabilis, qui verbo &amp; operibus clarus splendididissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum lumen sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae Ecclesiae praebuit, dum ca docuit quae fecit, nec seipsum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnavit agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do contraria quam docebat.</note>
What <hi>Ruffinus</hi> saith of <hi>Gregory Nazianzen,</hi> may
fitly be applied unto our <hi>dear Brother;</hi> He did those things
himself which he taught to others, neither did he condemn him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
by practising contrary to what he preached. He had not
only <hi>dona honoraria,</hi> but <hi>dona salutifera:</hi> not only <hi>gifts</hi> for the
good of others, but <hi>graces</hi> for the good of his own soul. There
are many Ministers that have rare gifts, but they are like a <hi>Pearl</hi>
in a <hi>Toads-head,</hi> because their lives give a lye to their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines:
But this our Reverend Brother had not only <hi>gratias
gratis datas,</hi> but <hi>gratias gratum facientes,</hi> he was not only
<hi>learned</hi> but <hi>religious,</hi> and (which is his highest commendation)
he was an <hi>humble Saint.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are four things (saith <hi>Luther)</hi> that make a Minister,
<hi>Prayer, Reading, Meditation</hi> and <hi>Temptation:</hi> Our Christian
Brother was not only a man of <hi>Prayer, Reading</hi> and <hi>Meditation,</hi>
but a man assaulted with many <hi>Temptations,</hi> with more I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve
then many hundred of Ministers are. He was often buffeted
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101409:16"/>
by Satan, and therefore <hi>more able to comfort them that were in
trouble, by the comfort wherewith he himself was comforted of
God.</hi> And let me take the boldness to tell you, that he hath
left a <hi>writing</hi> behind him, wherein he hath recorded all the
<hi>outgoings of God</hi> towards him, and all the <hi>experiences</hi> of Gods
shining with the <hi>light</hi> of his <hi>countenance</hi> upon him, and also of
his <hi>withdrawings</hi> and <hi>hiding</hi> his face from him: He hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
down both the <hi>Apogaeum's</hi> and <hi>Perigaeum's</hi> (as I may so
speak) both those times wherein God was at a <hi>distance</hi> from
him, and when he <hi>approached</hi> neerer to him.</p>
            <p>His desire to win souls to Christ by preaching was so great,
that though he was head of a Colledge in <hi>Cambridg,</hi> and had no
Ministeriall charge of his own,<note place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Tuckney</hi> in his Funerall Sermon of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Hill.</hi>
               </note> yet notwithstanding he preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<hi>gratis</hi> once every <hi>Lords day</hi> for many years together. The
like is said in print of that Reverend and godly Minister D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hill</hi>
late Master of <hi>Trinity Colledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here I must not forget what hath been told me since the
preaching of this Sermon; That our <hi>dear Brother,</hi> in the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
course of his Ministry, had preached over the third
Chapter to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> to the latter end of the verse imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly
before my Text: and behold how by the overruling
<hi>Providence of God</hi> (unknown to me) it hath hapned, that the
last <hi>verse</hi> of the same <hi>Chapter</hi> (which he left unfinished) was
chosen for his <hi>Funeral Sermon.</hi> But though he lived not to
preach of this verse, yet he now lives in Heaven, waiting for
that blessed time, when his <hi>vile body</hi> shall be raised out of
the grave, and be made like unto the <hi>glorious body of Jesus
Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before he was Master of <hi>Christs Colledge,</hi> he preached three
or four years <hi>in this place,</hi> six or seven years at <hi>Saviours South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark,</hi>
and for some time at <hi>Andrews</hi> in <hi>Holburn,</hi> to the great
satisfaction of all the godly that waited upon his Ministry. And
though he be now <hi>dead,</hi> yet he still <hi>speaks,</hi> not only by the
<hi>holiness</hi> of his life and <hi>graciousness</hi> of his doctrine, but also by
the many <hi>Books</hi> he hath left in print, in which you may behold
a <hi>fair character of his piety and Ministeriall abilites.</hi> He was
very orthodox, and sound in judgment, he had no <hi>spiritual
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101409:17"/>
Leprosie</hi> in his head, witness those two Books of his, <hi>The Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignment
of Error,</hi> and <hi>A Vindication of the Rights of the Law,
and Liberties of Grace.</hi> He was of a publike spirit; witness
that Book of his <hi>A word in season to a sinking Kingdom.</hi> He was
very carefull in admitting men and women to the Sacrament of
the Lords Supper; witness that Book of his called, <hi>The Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
Garment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The time of his</hi> sickness <hi>was</hi> long, tedious <hi>and</hi> costly; <hi>his</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seases
<hi>many, very many, but his</hi> patience <hi>was exceeding great:
he would usually say,</hi> That though the providences of God were
dark towards him, yet he had light within. <hi>A little before he
died, he said to one that was lifting him up,</hi> Let me alone, let
me lie quietly, for I have as much comfort as heart can hold.
<hi>The last time I was with him, I found him wonderfully</hi> desirous
to be dissolved and to be with Christ: <hi>I heard him say,</hi> Oh this
vile carcass of mine, when will it give way that my soul may get
out and go to my God? When will this rotten carcass be consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
that I may mount up to Heaven? <hi>And when he saw any
probable symptoms of death (which he called the</hi> little cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vises
<hi>at which his soul did peep out) he was exceedingly joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was his desire to be buried without any Funeral pomp;
which puts me in minde of a saying recorded in the life of <hi>Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Melchior Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus in vita Pellicani.</note>
of an <hi>Vncle</hi> of his who would not be buried in his Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lastick
habit (as the custom then was) <hi>testamento cavit ne aliter
sepeliretur quam simplex alius Christianus,</hi> He ordered it in his
Will, to be buried as a private <hi>Christian,</hi> and not as a <hi>Doctor;</hi>
and the reason he gives is, because he hoped <hi>resurrecturum se
ad judicium, non ut Sacerdotem &amp; Doctorem, sed ut humilem
Christianum,</hi> That he should <hi>rise at the day of judgment, aud
appear before God, not as a Priest or Doctor, but as an humble
Christian.</hi> This was the desire and hope of our <hi>Reverend Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
and this text that I have preached on, was matter of
great rejoycing unto him whilest he thought of that day when
his <hi>vile body,</hi> subject to so many diseases, should be made <hi>like
unto the glorious body of Christ, according to the working, the
mighty working</hi> (as he three times repeated it) <hi>whereby he is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101409:17"/>
able even to subdue all things unto himself.</hi> And so I leave him
in the arms of his blessed Saviour, beseeching God to make
up this great loss of him to the <hi>Church of Christ</hi> in generall,
and to the <hi>Vniversity</hi> of <hi>Cambridg</hi> in particular.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:101409:18"/>
            <head>TO THE
Memory of the Right Worshipfull
SAMVEL BOLTON, D. D.
late Master of Chr. Coll. in Cambridg.</head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ome, let our Petty brooks of sorrow fall</l>
            <l>Into a full swolne stream of generall</l>
            <l>Sadness, in pursuit of that blest soul hence</l>
            <l>Put off to the eternal confluence</l>
            <l>And Ocean of goodness; Happy he</l>
            <l>Whose grief is swallow'd in that blissefull sea.</l>
            <l>Weep we once more (whose Fathers hast'ned death</l>
            <l>And Church-estate expiring with their breath,</l>
            <l>Make us a lower sort of Orphans) we</l>
            <l>Who found in Him still freshest memory</l>
            <l>Of whose we were, that tenderness of heart</l>
            <l>Which the deceased spirits seem'd to impart.</l>
            <l>And yet nor we nor she (from whose torn breast</l>
            <l>Death snatcht away th'indearing close lodg'd guest,</l>
            <l>Untimely, misaccounting his years summe</l>
            <l>And hudling up in's life, dayes yet to come.</l>
            <l>Such were our hopes, and such the promises</l>
            <l>Of a firm tempers seeming healthfulness.)</l>
            <l>Nor we nor she to private loss must pay,</l>
            <l>What we should in the common treasure lay.</l>
            <l>In universaller calamity,</l>
            <l>There's sacriledg in such a privacy.</l>
            <l>Such is the fright when the main body flies</l>
            <l>Or gives ground, or when a Souldier spies</l>
            <l>A breach in the chief-fortress; so were we</l>
            <l>(Who fanci'd a blest perpetuity)</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:101409:18"/>
Appaled when we saw his strength decline</l>
            <l>Whom we wisht as immortal as divine.</l>
            <l>The Colledg scarce could hear't, though by degrees</l>
            <l>We were dril'd on into our miseries.</l>
            <l>Was it death's mercy, or deaths cruelty?</l>
            <l>That we might feel, or fit our selves to dy?</l>
            <l>We languish'd all the while in him, at last</l>
            <l>Into th'Dead Colledg all our Fellow's past.</l>
            <l>This grief's too straight still, and he little knew,</l>
            <l>What the World ow'd, that thinks his tears undue.</l>
            <l>Doth not, if such a part of goodness fall,</l>
            <l>Goodnesses common spirit convey to all</l>
            <l>A members sadness? I'n't the Church throughout</l>
            <l>Its body pained when an Eie's put out?</l>
            <l>Where shall we now such a meek <hi>Moses</hi> finde</l>
            <l>To recall wrangling Brethren to one minde?</l>
            <l>Many will help it on, but who'le bemoan</l>
            <l>A sad Church rent into division?</l>
            <l>'Twas the work of a soul, as his, orecome</l>
            <l>With benigne sweetness, such a one in whom</l>
            <l>Dwelt th'image of full Goodness, as above</l>
            <l>Calme and serene in its firm peace and love.</l>
            <l>One to the World so dead that evermore</l>
            <l>In the worlds things he seem'd stept out of doore,</l>
            <l>As one that's gone for some few hours abroad,</l>
            <l>Or whom some small affairs call out of's road.</l>
            <l>Then was he at his home, then onely free</l>
            <l>When the employment was pure heavenly.</l>
            <l>How naturally in spiritual discourse</l>
            <l>Was his speech fluent, ready, without force</l>
            <l>And unaffected, one might safely say,</l>
            <l>Then he was in his temper, in's own way.</l>
            <l>Like him who tyred with a barb'rous sound</l>
            <l>In a strange country, happily hath found</l>
            <l>One of his natives: now he may reflect</l>
            <l>On his own home in's well known dialect.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:101409:19"/>
View his divine attendance, his soul prest</l>
            <l>On messages to Heaven, and addrest</l>
            <l>To his immortal Fathers, not with words</l>
            <l>Which malapert Buffons speak to their Lords:</l>
            <l>Nor peremptory sauciness, built on</l>
            <l>A fond God-levelling communion.</l>
            <l>But in beseeming reverence. By and by</l>
            <l>(As toucht by'illapses of Divinity)</l>
            <l>Rais'd into heav'nly ardors: while just as</l>
            <l>Bodies mov'd swifty, along where they pass</l>
            <l>By their own violence impress a motion</l>
            <l>Ev'n on by-standing dulness. His devotion</l>
            <l>Rouz'd and enliv'ned all the neighbour hearts</l>
            <l>By holy-magick touch more then the arts</l>
            <l>Of Pulpit-Orators, more motive he</l>
            <l>Snatcht our souls up by vigorous sympathy.</l>
            <l>Such was his zeal, a fire not nourished</l>
            <l>By earthy matter, purer then what's fed</l>
            <l>By popular applause and basest gain,</l>
            <l>His zeal was of a farre more heav'ly strain.</l>
            <l>It ner'e gave fire to Cannon, nor did light</l>
            <l>Musquitiers matches: in no civil fight</l>
            <l>Was it a conduct, or ere serv'd in flame</l>
            <l>To burn dissenters bodies or their Name.</l>
            <l>Such searching fires earths mixture do proclaime<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>When, like some wandring fires, from book to book</l>
            <l>Skipt it? From <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Littleton</hi> or <hi>Cook?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>'Twas pure and steady, powerfull, nor fierce.</l>
            <l>By gentleness it had the might to pierce</l>
            <l>A sinners heart, asham'd to see more sense</l>
            <l>In him then in himself who did th'offence.</l>
            <l>In preaching, prayer and life we well might see</l>
            <l>Divineness: Man now, in mortality.</l>
            <l>Plead not, blest soul, against us, that th'art gone</l>
            <l>As tyr'd with us dull to be wrought upon.</l>
            <l>That thou mad'st hast impatient of our stay</l>
            <l>Who fondly loytring would not hie away.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:101409:19"/>
'Tis but our guilt, Hee's more Good now, nor farre,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Christs</hi>-Colledg Keeper still and Tutelar.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>J.SEDGWICK. Chr. Col. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <head>An Epitaph on the truly Religious and Learned
Doctor BOLTON Master of Christs Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
in Cambridg.</head>
            <l>TYr'd with a <hi>Body,</hi> and the <hi>Age,</hi> here lyes</l>
            <l>One that was Holy, Learned, Just, and Wise;</l>
            <l>Liv'd when the <hi>Court</hi> seem'd heavy, and the <hi>See</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Grew proud, yet <hi>Patience</hi> preach'd and <hi>Modesty.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Though <hi>Fears</hi> urg'd <hi>Fears,</hi> and <hi>Hope</hi> pursued <hi>Hope,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Pulpits</hi> 'gainst <hi>Pulpits</hi> bandied, yet the scope</l>
            <l>Both of His <hi>Text</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> was peace; fair Peace!</l>
            <l>Heaven's <hi>Legacy,</hi> the busie world's scorn'd <hi>Ease!</hi>
            </l>
            <l>By taking <hi>Care</hi> of <hi>Souls He</hi> did not mean</l>
            <l>Providing <hi>Lordships</hi> for his heirs; so clean,</l>
            <l>So spotless were <hi>his</hi> Aimes: his greatest <hi>store,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Was <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Praise;</hi> Promotion made him <hi>Poor.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>'Twas not the practise of <hi>his Zeal</hi> to <hi>Grone</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Against <hi>Plurality</hi> and neglect his <hi>One.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>His <hi>Matter</hi> alwayes did become the <hi>place,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Diurnals <hi>never</hi> turnd <hi>the</hi> second Glasse.</l>
            <l>Call'd from the City, he succeed One</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Turnd out</hi> by Death, Fates <hi>Sequestration:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Which <hi>Place</hi> he serv'd with chearfull Love and Care,</l>
            <l>Firm Justice, open Candour, hearty Prayer,</l>
            <l>(Free from base shriveled <hi>Faction, hungry</hi> strife,)</l>
            <l>Ev'n to the <hi>loss</hi> of Riches, Health and Life.</l>
            <l>Stay, Reader, and bestow a <hi>Tear</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>On this</hi> Dusty Fruitfull Bed,</l>
            <l>The <hi>Spring</hi> will then dwell <hi>alwayes</hi> here,</l>
            <l>And <hi>Violets</hi> ner'e <hi>hang</hi> the <hi>head.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:101409:20"/>
Pray, the <hi>Earth</hi> may <hi>lightly presse</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Her entrusted Urne below;</l>
            <l>May the same <hi>prayer</hi> thy <hi>Reliques blesse,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>When they shall <hi>rest,</hi> as <hi>his</hi> do now.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. STANDISH.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <head>Upon the Death of the Pious and Learned SAMUEL
BOLTON, Doctor of Divinity and Master of Christs
Colledge in Cambridg.</head>
            <l>NOt that my gadding Muse affects to shew</l>
            <l>Her courser beauties to the common view;</l>
            <l>Not that she thinks such harsh ill-tuned Layes,</l>
            <l>As hers, are fit to celebrate thy praise;</l>
            <l>Dares she present these verses; but as they</l>
            <l>Who hundreds hold of others, yet do pay</l>
            <l>Nought but a Pepper-corn: by this she showes</l>
            <l>Though she brings little, yet 'tis much she owes</l>
            <l>To thy dear Memory and honour'd Name,</l>
            <l>Immortal <hi>BOLTON,</hi> Heir of lasting Fame.</l>
            <l>Whose known deserts and unreproved worth</l>
            <l>Needs not her slender skill to blaze it forth:</l>
            <l>But can commend it self to after-times</l>
            <l>Without the help of Elegiack Rimes.</l>
            <l>Though others under brasse and marble plac'd,</l>
            <l>Keep not their Names and Titles undefac'd;</l>
            <l>Though Monuments themselves decay, and must</l>
            <l>Confess their ruins, and resolve to dust;</l>
            <l>Though all things else be subject to the Laws</l>
            <l>Of fickle Change and Times devouring jaws;</l>
            <l>Yet wisdome hath a ne're decaying root</l>
            <l>And vertuous pains bring everlasting fruit:</l>
            <l>And they that labour'd have and liv'd like Thee,</l>
            <l>Their Names shall last to all eternity.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:101409:20"/>
Nor seems it strange that vertuous men should best</l>
            <l>Oblivion scape, which oft involves the rest</l>
            <l>Of things and persons, whose poor low desires</l>
            <l>Are not affected with such high aspires.</l>
            <l>The Principles by which most men do move</l>
            <l>Are private Interest and base self-love:</l>
            <l>So farre their friendship and their hate extends</l>
            <l>It self, as serves their own contracted ends.</l>
            <l>Hence as that Earth-begotten brood which grew</l>
            <l>From teeth which <hi>Cadmus</hi> in the furrowes threw,</l>
            <l>Within a while by civil discord slain,</l>
            <l>Return'd unto her Mother earth again</l>
            <l>And scarce left any token to appear</l>
            <l>To tell th'ensuing age that once they were:</l>
            <l>So bad men quickly vanish, and are gone</l>
            <l>Buried in earth and dark oblivion.</l>
            <l>But those like thee whose more enlarged breast</l>
            <l>With better thoughts and purer fire's possest;</l>
            <l>Who make themselves no scope to which they bend</l>
            <l>Their actions but the common good attend;</l>
            <l>Cannot pass unregarded hence but Fame</l>
            <l>Ennobles and perpetuates their Name.</l>
            <l>Who ere did to the infant world impart</l>
            <l>Some signal benefit or usefull art,</l>
            <l>Had Temples built unto him: Hence arose</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Ceres</hi> and <hi>Bacchus</hi> and such gods as those.</l>
            <l>Would truth dispense and piety admit</l>
            <l>Of such like Deities, 'twere farre more fit</l>
            <l>T'account Thee one then those that taught us how</l>
            <l>To tread the winepress first and hold the plow:</l>
            <l>Since this grand difference 'twixt thee we finde</l>
            <l>And them; they fed the <hi>body</hi> thou the <hi>minde.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> W <unclear>BRYCHE</unclear>.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:101409:21"/>
            <head>On the deplored Death of the Reverend Doctour
SAMUEL BOLTON Master of Christs
Colledge in Cambridg.</head>
            <l>TO mourn in verse, and write an Elegie,</l>
            <l>Is even grown as common as to die;</l>
            <l>Poëtick sorrow serves but for a mask</l>
            <l>To other passions; 'twere an easie task</l>
            <l>For grief that's feigned, or at best but fain'd</l>
            <l>To boast it self in eloquent complaint.</l>
            <l>But where internall sorrow hath possest</l>
            <l>The very vitals, and corrodes the breast</l>
            <l>With inward care, where the oppressed heart</l>
            <l>Doth inly languish with consuming smart;</l>
            <l>The soul is choaked, and the spirits spent</l>
            <l>With mutual conflict, e're they finde a vent.</l>
            <l>Such reall anguish, such unfeigned grief,</l>
            <l>Doth scarce admit the pitifull relief</l>
            <l>Of sighs and tears; such dolour scarce affords</l>
            <l>Imperfect sentences, and broken words.</l>
            <l>The case is ours, whom sorrows violence</l>
            <l>Hath strongly touched with a vigorous sense</l>
            <l>Of our calamity: whose deep distress</l>
            <l>Our mindes with grief astonish'd can't express.</l>
            <l>No wonder then in so just cause of tears</l>
            <l>And sad complaints, so little pomp appears</l>
            <l>Of mournfull Elegies, and funerall songs;</l>
            <l>This loss doth more affect our hearts then tongues.</l>
            <l>Our sincere mourning seeks not after fame</l>
            <l>In these iust Rites; let others then proclaim</l>
            <l>Their forced sorrow with exalted cries,</l>
            <l>Our reall grief makes silent Obsequies.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. LEIGH.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:101409:21"/>
            <head>Upon the Death of the Reverend, his never to be
forgotten Friend, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> BOLTON Master of Christs
Colledge in Cambridg.</head>
            <l>IS <hi>BOLTON</hi> dead? and shall not <hi>England</hi> weep,</l>
            <l>That we no longer such a <hi>Saint</hi> could keep.</l>
            <l>Alas! the world not worthy was of Thee,</l>
            <l>The <hi>Saints</hi> above did want thy companie.</l>
            <l>Thy virtues, graces, praises, and thy worth,</l>
            <l>No tongue alive is able to set forth.</l>
            <l>Thou wast a <hi>burning,</hi> and a <hi>shining Light</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In this ovr <hi>Orb;</hi> few left which shine so bright.</l>
            <l>Thy Minister' all Gifts, thy Zeal, were rare</l>
            <l>Thy Piety, no less thy gifts in Pray'r.</l>
            <l>And in a word <hi>(Blest Soul!)</hi> Thee to commend;</l>
            <l>Thy Praise knows no beginning nor no end.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOHN CROFTS Minist.
C. C. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
