<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamation against fighting of duels</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 3 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-09">2003-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32354</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3215AA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19476</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12115369</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12115369</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54277</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A32354)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54277)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 863:34 or 2287:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamation against fighting of duels</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Bill and Christopher Barker ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in Bodleian Library and Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>At head of title: By the King.</note>
                  <note>At end of text: Given at our court at Whitehall the thirteenth day of August in the twelfth year of our reign, 1660.</note>
                  <note>Copy at reel 2287:9 is improved copy over that at reel 863:34, which is cropped, lacking imprint, and is incorrectly identified as Wing C3215.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dueling --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  London (England) --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-08</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:54277:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head type="illustration">
               <figure>
                  <head>CR</head>
                  <head>DIEV·ET MON·DROIT</head>
                  <head>HONI·SOIT·QVI·MAL·Y PENSE</head>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <opener>By the King.</opener>
            <head>A PROCLAMATION Against Fighting of DUELS.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>CHARLES R.</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas it is become too frequent, especially with Persons of quality, under a vain pretence of Honour, to take upon them to be the Reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of their private quarrels, by Duell and single Combate, upon slight, and, which ought not to be, upon any Provocation. We consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that the Sin of Murther is detestable before God, and this way of prosecuting satisfaction, scandalous to Christian Religion, and the manifest violation of Our Lawes and Authority, having by Our Declaration Published at <hi>Brussels</hi> the Twenty Fourth Day of <hi>November,</hi> 1658. manifested to the World Our utter dislike of such im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious and unlawful Duells.</p>
            <p>Now, out of Our Pious care to prevent unchristian and rash effusion of Blood, do, by this Our Proclamation strictly charge and command all Our loving Subiects of what quality soe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, That neither they, by themselves, nor by others, either by Message, Word, Writing or other wayes or means, challenge or cause to be challenged any Person or Persons to Fight in Combate or single Duell; nor carry, accept or conceal any such challenge or appointment, nor actually Fight such <unclear>Duell</unclear> with any of Our Subiects, or others; or as a Second or otherwise, accompany or become Assistant therein.</p>
            <p>And We do hereby Declare, That every Person or Persons who shall offend contrary to this Our express command, shall not only incurre Our highest displeasure, but thereby become in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of holding or entertaining either Office or imployment in Our Service, and never af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards be permitted to come into Our Court or Presence. And further, He or They to suffer such other pains and punishments, as the Law shall inflict, upon Offences of that horrid na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>And We do further Declare, That if any Person or Persons whatsoever, do receave, accept or know of any Challenge, sent or delivered as aforesaid, and do not forthwith give notice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of unto some of Our Privy Councel, or otherwise to the next Iustice of Peace, near whereunto the said Offence shall be committed; He or They so offending, shall be lyable to the Penalties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore expressed, and proceeded against according to Law, with all rigour and severity.</p>
            <p>And Lastly, We do hereby forbid all Intercession or Mediation unto Us to be made, for or on the behalf of the Offenders. Hereby Declaring, That We will not extend Our Pardon to any Person that shall Contemn Our Command expressed by this Proclamation.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at Our Court at <hi>Whitehall</hi> 
                  <date>the Thirteenth Day of <hi>August</hi> in the Twelfth Year of Our Reign, 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
