<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Eben-ezer, a thankful memorial of God's mercy in preserving England from the gunpowder-treason, 1605 being a sermon on 1 Sam. 7:12, prepared for Novemb. 5th to be preacht at the cathedral, but preacht for the most part of it at the parish-church of Temple, in the city of Bristol, on the 6th of Novem. being the Lord's day / by John Chetwynd ...</title>
            <author>Chetwynd, John, 1623-1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32794</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3796</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19751</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12258721</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12258721</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57697</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A32794)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57697)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 176:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Eben-ezer, a thankful memorial of God's mercy in preserving England from the gunpowder-treason, 1605 being a sermon on 1 Sam. 7:12, prepared for Novemb. 5th to be preacht at the cathedral, but preacht for the most part of it at the parish-church of Temple, in the city of Bristol, on the 6th of Novem. being the Lord's day / by John Chetwynd ...</title>
                  <author>Chetwynd, John, 1623-1692.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 5-44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Tho. Wall ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gunpowder Plot, 1605 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:57697:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:57697:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Eben-ezer.</p>
            <p>A Thankful Memorial OF GOD'S MERCY In preſerving <hi>ENGLAND</hi> from the GUNPOWDER-TREASON, 1605.</p>
            <p>Being a SERMON on 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. 12. Prepared for <hi>Novemb. 5th,</hi> to be Preacht at the Cathedral; but Preacht for the moſt part of it at the Pariſh-Church of <hi>Temple,</hi> in the City of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> on the <hi>6th</hi> of <hi>Novemb.</hi> being the Lords Day.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Chetwynd,</hi> M. A. Prebend of the Cathedral, and Vicar of <hi>Temple,</hi> in the City of <hi>Briſtol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pſal. 118. 24. <hi>This is the day which the Lord hath made: we will rejoyce and be glad in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>Tho. Wall,</hi> Bookſeller at <hi>Briſtol.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:57697:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57697:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the VVorſhipful and his ever Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Friend and Kinſman,</hi> John Harington, <hi>of</hi> Kelſton, <hi>
                  <abbr>Esq</abbr> one of His Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace for the County of</hi> Somerſet.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have made bold to direct theſe Papers to you, as a Teſtimony of my reſpect, and as being aſſured, that you are a true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant of the Church of <hi>England</hi> eſtabliſhed by Law.</p>
            <p>As for ſuch as falſly, and with a contradiction, ſo term, and call themſelves <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> I expect no ſuch Readers.</p>
            <p>As for Proteſtants in Maſquerade, whoſe worldly deſigns make them ſit looſe to all Religions, they may ſee what may reform them, if not convince them.</p>
            <p>But as for your ſelf, and ſuch as are Proteſtants out of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, you and they, who are peaceable Sons of the moſt Apoſtolical Church of <hi>England,</hi> may read what may confirm them in their true faith and Worſhip, and what may comfort and ſupport them under any fears, dangers, hardſhips, that may attend them in and for their ſo being and doing: God being ſtill the ſame yeſterday, to day and for ever. He that hath delivered, doth deliver, will deliver.</p>
            <p>To his bleſſing I commend theſe Papers. To his protection and gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance your ſelf and ſecond-ſelf, with all your Family. And ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Briſtol,<date>
                     <hi>Novemb.</hi> 16. 1681.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your moſt Reſepctful Kinſman, and humble Servant, John Chetwynd.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:57697:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Memorial of God's moſt gracious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations of</hi> England <hi>from the Spaniſh Invaſion</hi> and Gunpower Treaſon. <hi>Of an unknown Author. Found by me among my Father's Papers, thus directed:</hi> To my Poſterity.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>GOD's</hi> ancient Church Two ſolemn Feaſts did keep,</l>
               <l>On Two ſet days, by his own word directed:</l>
               <l>When <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s Hoſt was drowned in the deep;</l>
               <l>And when proud <hi>Haman</hi>'s Treaſon was detected.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Two works of equal grace, but greater wonder.</l>
               <l>The Lord hath done ſor us paſt all mens Reaſon,</l>
               <l>When Papiſt did attempt to bring us under</l>
               <l>By <hi>Spaniſh Armado</hi> and by <hi>Piercy</hi>'s <hi>Treaſon.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I and my houſe theſe great things will remember.</l>
               <l>And in remembrance ſanctifie two days,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Auguſt</hi>one, <note n="*" place="margin">3.</note> 
                  <hi>the other in</hi> November. <note n="†" place="margin">5.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Both made by God for us to give him praiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Dear children, charge the children after you,</l>
               <l>Still to obſerve theſe Feaſts, as I do now.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:57697:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Eben-ezer.</head>
            <head>A Thankful Memorial of God's preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>England</hi> from the Gunpowder Treaſon, 1605.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 Sam. VII. 12.</bibl>
               <q>Then Samuel took a ſtone, and ſet it up between Mizpeh and Shen, and called the name of it Eben-ezer, ſaying, Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto hath God helped us.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>TO regulate my diſcourſe, I have made choice of this Scripture, as being in many particulars paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel to the occaſion of the day, and ſuitable to this great and ſolemn Aſſembly, whoſe outward luſtre and grandeur, and other circumſtances and expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of rejoycing, teſtifie our apprehenſions of this day to be, as it deſerves to be with us, a High Day, a Holy day, even a day which the Lord our God hath made marvellous in our eyes; a Day to be had in everlaſting remembrance, never-to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be <note place="margin">Pſ. 118 23, 24.</note> forgotten; a Day of Gods making. Some days may be ſaid to be made by Gods <hi>flat, Let it be made,</hi> as all creatures beſides man were. But other days, in which notable and memorable occurrences fall out, may be ſaid to be made with Gods <hi>faciamus, Let us make,</hi> as man was. And ſuch was this, which God by ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, preſerving and delivering our King, Church and State,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57697:4"/>
made marvellous in our eyes, and calls for our rejoycing in it. Such was the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Paſſover; ſuch the day of our Saviour's <note place="margin">Exod 12.</note> Reſurrection, to which this Scripture is applied; and ſuch is this day: The Memorial of the mercies, on which exhibited, we now celebrate.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Foelix &amp; fauſta dies, lux flava quinta</hi> Novembris.</q>
            <p>And may it be for ever celebrated by us and our Poſterity, as long as the Sun and Moon endureth? For this was the Lords do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and let it ſtill be marvellous in our eyes: So it was in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s day. Thus it was in ours. In <hi>David</hi>'s, a deliverance from great dangers; all by Gods might, all by Gods mercy, and that not in ſmall things (as yet in them God is to be ſeen), but <hi>uſque</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 118, 12, 15.</note> 
               <hi>ad miracula:</hi> and that not only marvellous in it ſelf (for ſo all <note place="margin">Zech. 9. 11.</note> Gods works are, which ſeem ſmall, becauſe uſual), but wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in our eyes, becauſe rare. In which we cannot but ſay, <hi>Digi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Dei eſt hic.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſuch was this <hi>our day.</hi> In a moſt eminent manner Gods day, both for the exceeding greatneſs of our danger, and Gods gracious and wonderful deliverance, when the Devils, and the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, and their bigotted Proſelytes, had laid their heads together, to deſtroy our King, and Church, and State, our Religion, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, Lives; when the <hi>Balak</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> and the <hi>Balaam</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Thus far was the Preface to my Sermon prepared for the Cathedral on the <hi>5th.</hi> but our Reverend Dioceſan preaching, upon my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, in my turn, I thought fit to preach it at <hi>Temple</hi> on the <hi>6th,</hi> being the Lords day in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon: omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Preface.</note> had conſpired together our utter deſtruction.</p>
            <p>We read <hi>Eſther</hi> 9. 20, 21. that <hi>Mordecai</hi> and <hi>Eſther</hi> ſent Letters with all Authority to all the <hi>Jews</hi> nigh and far, that they ſhould keep the <hi>14th</hi> and <hi>15th</hi> of the month <hi>Adar,</hi> yearly, as the days wherein the <hi>Jews</hi> reſted from their enemies, and the month which was turned from ſorrow to joy, and from mourning to a good day; that they ſhould make them days of feaſting and joy, and of ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Portions one to another, and of gifts to the poor; becauſe the Plot of <hi>Haman,</hi> the enemy of all the <hi>Jews,</hi> which he had deviſed againſt them, was b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Queen <hi>Eſther</hi>'s mediation to the King, turn'd upon his own head; and the <hi>Jews</hi> had ruled over them that hated them; and <hi>Haman</hi> and his Ten ſons were hanged: Therefore the <hi>Jews</hi> ordained and took it upon themſelves, and upon their ſeed, and upon all ſuch as joyned to them; ſo as it ſhould not fail (as it doth not to this day among them, wherever diſperſed, though it be two thouſand years ſince), that they would keep theſe two
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57697:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
days, according to their writing and according to their apppointed time every year. And that theſe days ſhould be remembred and kept through every Generation, every Family, every Province, <note place="margin">Eſt. 9. 27, 28.</note> and every City, and that theſe days ſhould not fail from among the <hi>Jews,</hi> nor the memorial of them periſh from their ſeed—Thus it was with the <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And have not we as much cauſe to remember with thankful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing the great deliverance vouchſafed our Fathers, and in them of us? Certainly we have; and therefore God having by a Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Mercy, prevented the barbarous and inhumane Deſign of the Papiſts, the implacable enemy of all Proteſtants, eſpecially of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants; it was then lookt upon as a principal part of their thankful reſentment, by King <hi>James</hi> of famous memory, and the then ſitting-Parliament, To enact the obſervation of one day, <hi>viz.</hi> the fifth of <hi>November,</hi> yearly to be obſerved as a thankful memorial of that wonderful Mercy.</p>
            <p>Now God having by his Providence ſo ordered, that this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent year, his day, the Lords day, the day which he hath made for the Remembrance of Chriſts Reſurrection, and all the Bleſſings that accrue by him (and all we enjoy, whether ſpiritual, or external, temporal or eternal, are all from him; deliverance from Hell, Death and Damnation of ſoul and body; deliverance from ſlavery and bondage, and all external preſſures, are all from him) and it being the principal work of this day, Gods Holy <note place="margin">Rev: 1,</note> day, the Lords Holy-day, to celebrate the thankful memorial of his Mercies.</p>
            <p>And this day of Gods appointing, immediately ſucceeding the day of the Kings appointment, I have not thought it unfit, nor any way inproper to lay before you what was prepared for yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days Solemnity, in another place. That ſo (though the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Pomp (a neceſſary circumſtance in that day) may be left; Yet the reality of our thankfulneſs might be expreſſed in this more private Aſſembly; and we all put in mind, and be ſtirred up, as the <hi>Jews</hi> by the two days of <hi>Purim,</hi> ſo we of <hi>England,</hi> and we now preſent, by the Solemnity yeſterday, according to the Law of Man; and by what ſhall be now ſpoken on this day, the day of our Reſt and Rejoycing, according to the Law of God, may be ſtirred up to rejoyceful thankfulneſs for Gods goodneſs vouchſafed to us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:57697:5"/>
And indeed the remembring, declaring and rejoycing in Gods wonderful works of Creation and providence, as well as of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, are to have a principal part in the due Sanctification of our Chriſtian Sabbath.</p>
            <p>For the helping you wherein, I ſhall lay before you what the Text firſt read, preſents us with: Having firſt ſhewn you,</p>
            <p>That we of <hi>England</hi> have as much reaſon, and as great cauſe to celebrate two days yearly in the memorial of our deliverance from the <hi>Powder Treaſon,</hi> as the <hi>Jews</hi> have for their deliverance from <hi>Haman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The deſign of <hi>Haman,</hi> and proſecution of it againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> was not ſo dangerous and miſchievous as this Conſpiracy of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> was againſt the <hi>Engliſh-</hi> and Proteſtant Religion, as will appear by many particulars, parallel Circumſtances in their <hi>Purim,</hi> and our <hi>Powder Treaſon.</hi> And indeed ours may be called <hi>Purim</hi> from the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifies fire, as that from the Hebrew word <hi>Pur</hi> that ſignifies a Lot.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Theirs by the ſword, from whence ſome might have eſcaped. Ours by a blaſt of fire that would have ſpared none.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Theirs would have deſtroyed Queen <hi>Eſther</hi> and her people; ours King <hi>James,</hi> Queen, Prince, Lords, Commons, the whole Flower of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation met in Parlament.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They had a ſet day which all knew; ours uncertain, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, known to none but themſelves.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Theirs was but an ordinary day; ours a moſt magnificent day, when the Kings Majeſty, and all the great States would have been in their Robes, and greateſt Glory.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They poor captive <hi>Jews</hi> ſcattered and diſperſed without power or policy, living in ſubjection.</p>
            <p>We a moſt flouriſhing Kingdom, for wealthl, power and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, under a moſt magnificent King, Illuſtrious Nobles, Reverend Prelates, Honourable, and worſhipful, and wealthy Knights, Citizens and Burgeſſes, even the Cream and Flower of the whole Nation.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Conſider the parties by whom; their enemy was but one <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> a ſtranger by Nation; a ſtranger in Religion, an heathen I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolater; ours no ſtrangers by Nation; all <hi>Engliſh men,</hi> no ſtrangers in Religion, profeſſing the ſame Chriſtianity; not Turks, nor Pagans, Infidels, Moors, or Indians (though indeed much worſe) but Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and ſuch as would be thought true Catholicks; yea the only
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57697:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Catholick Chriſtians; yea, ſome of them (which is among them more than Chriſtians) Jeſuits.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Haman</hi> was wicked, that is his title; but theſe exceeded him in wickedneſs. <hi>Haman</hi> was a declared enemy; but theſe ſecret Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers that eat through the bowels of their own Mother.</p>
            <p>The malice of all men, calling to it all the malice of the Devil, did never invent the like in all ill Circumſtances.</p>
            <p>A degenerate Chriſtian is the worſt of men, and the worſt of men is the worſt of Creatures; and it's grown into a Proverb amongſt other Nations; and theſe cruel treacherous Powder-Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors gave too much ground for it, An <hi>Engliſhman</hi> Italianate, is a Devil incarnate—</p>
            <p n="7">7. Conſider we the colour and the cauſe of both Deſigns. As all evil things uſually have one thing for their colour, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for their cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>In <hi>Haman,</hi> the cauſe was <hi>Mordicai</hi> his not bowing.</item>
                  <item>The colour was, they were of a different Law: Hereticks.</item>
                  <item>They were not for the Kings profit.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In ours, the Cauſe is not bowing to one, <hi>viz.</hi> The Old Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man at <hi>Rome;</hi> one prouder than <hi>Haman,</hi> who have had Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors to hold their Stirrups, Kings to lead their Horſes, and kiſs their feet.</p>
            <p>The Colour pretended, is zeal for Religion; we were and ſtill are in their accounts Hereticks; and therefore muſt be kill'd blown up, deſtroyed; and they think they have St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Warrant for it, for ſo it hath been urged.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hereticum devita,</hi> which we make but one word, and that a Verb, which we rightly tranſlate avoid, and they two words, <hi>viz.</hi> a Noun and Prepoſition; and ſo would have it ſignifie to kill. <hi>De vita,</hi> to take from life. They conſulted their Oracle the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial, who anſwered them as <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> did <hi>Haman, De populo fac quod libet,</hi> Do with them, as it ſeemeth good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee. <note place="margin">Eſth. 3. 11.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. Conſider we the event: The <hi>Jews</hi> delivered, <hi>Haman</hi> hang'd, we preſerved, the Traytors ſuffered: God was otherwiſe minded than <hi>Haman;</hi> he would have deſtroyed a Nation, but God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it; <hi>Haman</hi> put the Lot into the lap, but God drew it out.</p>
            <p>And in this event conſider,
<list>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:57697:6"/>
                  <item>1. Means.</item>
                  <item>2. Manner.</item>
                  <item>3. Time.</item>
                  <item>4. Iſſue.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Means: They, to God by faſting and prayer; to man, by Queen <hi>Eſthers</hi> Mediation to the King.</p>
            <p>We uſed none, nor could uſe any; neither faſted or prayed, ſuſpected no evil; and ſo could uſe no means to prevent it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Manner: Though no means to God, yet we had from God, and ſo had they too; but ours better, both from and by a King.</p>
            <p>Theirs from a King, but from him came the Danger, his Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation under hand and ſeal, without which <hi>Haman</hi> could have done nothing. Ours from a King, but no danger from him. He was as deep in the danger as we were.</p>
            <p>Theirs by a King ſet right by <hi>Eſthers</hi> Information in a regular and common way. Ours by no information, but inſpiration; by a Caſual rather than a Grammatical interpretation of the dangers being paſt as ſoon as the Letter was burnt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Time: The night before <hi>Haman</hi> intended to have beg'd <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai</hi>'s life, the King could not ſleep; calls for the Chronicles, reads therein what faithful and eminent ſervice <hi>Mordecai</hi> had done for him; and enquiring and underſtanding that he had received no recompence, he reſolves <hi>to honour him; Haman</hi> pronounceth how <hi>Mordecai</hi> ſhould be honoured, who was commanded to do what he propoſed himſelf, and as he thought for himſelf; and according to the great grief of him, he did perform the Kings Command, and his own deſigned honour towards him. <hi>Haman</hi> himſelf was by the King, upon the Queens Complaint, judged to be hanged; which was done on the ſame day, place, gallows, that he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for <hi>Mordecai.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Iſſue: Deliverance to both; the net broke, the Fowl eſcaped, yea, the Fowler himſelf taken, <hi>Iſrael</hi> delivered, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> drown'd, <note place="margin">Pſal. 124.</note> 
               <hi>Haman</hi> hang'd.</p>
            <p>So was it with us and the Powder-Traytors; they hoped that their deſigned puff and net ſhould have divided and ſcattered our Noble Senators, and ancient and glorious Structures; and they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57697:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
themſelves were deſervedly hang'd and quarter'd, and their heads and limbs ſet up on the tops of that houſe they deſigned to throw down.</p>
            <p>So that what we read concerning the <hi>Jews,</hi> may as fitly be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied unto us; in the day that the enemies of the <hi>Jews,</hi> of us Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, <note place="margin">Eſth. 9. 1.</note> hoped to have power over them, over us, it was turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the contrary, that the <hi>Jews,</hi> that our King, had rule over them that hated them.</p>
            <p>And oh! let it ſtill be marvellous in our eyes! Let us be glad <note place="margin">Pſ. 118. 24.</note> and rejoyce in it.</p>
            <p>And indeed Gods deliverances of <hi>England</hi> have been acts of Wonder.</p>
            <p>Not to inſiſt on the unexpected diſcovery of the preſent <hi>Popiſh Plot;</hi> and let us pray for the full defeating of it; the truth where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I hope no good Subject, or true conſciencious Proteſtant, dot\h any thing queſtion, being atteſted by ſuch undeniable Evidences; <hi>viz.</hi> his moſt Gracious Majeſty (whom God ſtill preſerve from it) the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the whole Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; and which we have ſtill cauſe to fear, though ſeveral Artifices are uſed to ſmother and ſtifle it; but let us remember, that many times the leſs noiſe, the more danger.</p>
            <p>But to paſs this, as not ſo pertinent at preſent. Our work is what the Pſalmiſt was, to conſider the days of old, and the years <note place="margin">Pſal 77, 5, 11, 12.</note> of ancient times; to remember the works of the Lord, even his wonders; to meditate of all his works, and to tell of all his doing.</p>
            <p>Now theſe ancient mercies, God hath made them that they <note place="margin">Pſal. 111. 4.</note> ſhould be had in remembrance; that we ſhould declare them to our Children.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpends the four firſt Chapters of <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> in recording of them; and God himſelf made a Statute-Law to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which they obſerved; for ſo we find them ſpeaking, <hi>I will utter dark</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 78. 2, 3, 4, 6.</note> 
               <hi>ſayings of old, which we have heard and known: and our Fathers have told us. We will not hide them from our children, ſhewing to the Generations to come the praiſes of the Lord, and his ſtrength, and the wonderful works that he hath done. That the Generation to come might know them, even the Children which ſhould be born: who ſhould ariſe and declare them to their Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to mention no more: There are two great deliverances; ancient deliverances which God hath given to his Church and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57697:7"/>
people in <hi>England</hi> from their inveterate and implacable enemies the <hi>Papiſs:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the <hi>Spaniſh Invaſion</hi> in 88 From the <hi>Gunpowder Treaſon</hi> in 1605. Two ſuch deliverances that our eyes have not ſeen, nor our ears have heard, nor could our Fathers tell us of the like. One by Strand, the other by Land. One from a Fleet, and as they call'd it an invincible <hi>Armado,</hi> ſent forth by the King of <hi>Spain's</hi> great and vaſt Charge, long Preparation, the <hi>Popes</hi> bleſſing, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with his beſt and moſt zealous Soldiers, all manner of Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Cruelty, Whips and Knives engraven in <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> with words which in <hi>Engliſh</hi> are, To cut the Throats of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks. The other from a Vault under ground, charged with many Barrels of Gun-powder, Billets and Faggots, &amp;c. A Monks Invention that would, had not God prevented, with one blaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed both King and Kingdom; the moſt ſudden, cruel and unmerciful inſtrument of Death.</p>
            <p>Both of theſe gracious deliverances from the hands of our moſt implacable enemies, the ſworn Vaſſal of the Papal Throne, that ſought not only (and they are ſtill of the ſame humour) our Land and Eſtates, and Livelihoods; but our Lives, our Souls, our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, even our utter Deſtruction, to have brought us under the Tyranny of a Foreign Prince, and the unutterable and unconceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Cruelty of the Papal Uſurpation and Inquiſition.</p>
            <p>Not from roaring Enemies, but ſuch as were Vipers, that ſting to Death without any hiſſing at all.</p>
            <p>Such was this deliverance, the thankful memorial whereof we now celebrate.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Hamans</hi> Plot, to ſome.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Babylons</hi> power and dominion, to the reſt.</p>
            <p>To thoſe who would not comply with them, and embrace their ſuperſtitious, idolatrous Principles and Practiſes, to them from Death.</p>
            <p>To thoſe that were Proteſtants in <hi>Maſquerade,</hi> or Atheiſtical, indifferent to all Religions; notwithſtanding fancy to the contrary, that deliverance was from ſervitude, ſlavery and bondage; <hi>Engliſhmens</hi> Land and Goods, let the Owners be what they will, will be always <hi>judged by</hi> Jeſuited Foreiners, heretical, when they are victorious over us, which God forbid. Have we then not great reaſon that are, and have been the redeemed of the Lord, whom he hath delivered from the <hi>Egyptian</hi> darkneſs of <hi>Popery,</hi> from the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57697:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
worſe than <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Cruelty and barbarous oppreſſion of Popiſh enemies, from the Deviliſh Treachery and Conſpiracy of others by the Diſcovery of the late Plot: Have we not great reaſon, I ſay, to ſing aloud with the Pſalmiſt, and ſay,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We will praiſe the Lord with our whole heart: in the Aſſembly of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 111. 1.</note> 
               <hi>the upright, and in the Congregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The works of the Lord are great, ſought out of all them that have</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2.</note> 
               <hi>pleaſure therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>His work is honourable and glorious, and his righteouſneſs endureth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">3.</note> 
               <hi>for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He hath made his wonderful works to be remembred: the Lord is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">4.</note> 
               <hi>gracious and full of Compaſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He hath ſent Redemption unto his people,</hi> &amp;c. <note place="margin">9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In furtherance of this common piety, and to refreſh our Memories, and quicken our Devotion, I have made choice of the Scripture firſt read as pertinent to the occaſion: Text <hi>Then Samuel took a stone and ſet it between Mizpeh and Shen, and called the name of it Eben-Ezer, ſaying, hitherto hath God helped us—</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which we have conſiderable,</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Something ſuppoſed.</item>
                  <item>2. Something expreſt.
<list>
                        <item>1. Suppoſed.
<list>
                              <item>1. Their danger from their enemies, who were the <hi>Philiſtines.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>2. The cauſe of it: Their profeſſion and practice of the true Religion, Reformation; putting away their Idols, <hi>Baalim</hi> and <hi>Aſhteroth v.</hi> 4.</item>
                              <item>Worſhipping at <hi>Mizpeh,</hi> faſting and praying. v. 6.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>2.Expreſſed. In which,
<list>
                              <item>1.Gods grace and favour towards them: <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto hath God helped us.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>2. Their ſenſe of it, Thankfulneſs for it, and care to continue the memorial of it.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Thus large is this little portion of Scripture, containing, like
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57697:8"/>
Gold, much value in a little compaſs. To handle each particular as they ought, would be too great a treſpaſs to your patience; and therefore I ſhall direct my diſcourſe, not to conſider the many Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinal truths that they would preſent us with, but apply my ſelf to ſhew you how ſuitable they are to the occaſion of this Solemnity; and that according to the Method propoſed: and firſt,</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <head>1. What's ſuppoſed</head>
                  <item>1. The danger.</item>
                  <item>2. The cauſe.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall joyn both together. Their danger was from the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines,</hi> becauſe of their Reformation, <hi>v.</hi> 3. and ſincere profeſſion, and exerciſing of Religion and religious Worſhip at <hi>Mizpeh. v</hi> 6. where they met to humble themſeves before God, and to conſult of their affairs. Then the Lords of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> went up againſt <hi>Iſrael, v.</hi> 7. and drew near to battel againſt them, <hi>v.</hi> 9. and they were afraid of the <hi>Philiſtines, v.</hi> 7. and intreated <hi>Samuel</hi> to cry un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord for them, that he would ſave them out of the hand of the <hi>Philiſtines, v.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Philiſtines</hi> were their neighbour Inhabitants, whom the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> ought to have expelled; but did not, nor could not; ſo that they continued amongſt them as thorns in their ſides; many times in ſubjection, always in oppoſition to <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and ſometimes hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the upper hand, as after the death of old <hi>Eli;</hi> when they took the Ark of God, kept it ſeven months, ſent it from City to City, but grew weary of it, and at laſt return it home; and it was ſetled at <hi>Kirjath-jearim,</hi> where it continued twenty years; during which time the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> lamented their Condition under the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> power, but took care to ſet up the Ark in the houſe of <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nidab,</hi> whoſe Son <hi>Eleazer</hi> was conſecrated to attend upon it.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Samuel,</hi> whom God had raiſed up in <hi>Eli</hi>'s place to rule and govern, called them to Repentance; and they obeyed that call, and reformed themſelves, put away <hi>Baalim</hi> and <hi>Aſhteroth,</hi> their He-Gods and She-Gods, and there ſolemnly humbled themſelves by faſting and prayer, and ſacrificing a Lamb, that ſignified their faith in Chriſt, and obedience to God, <hi>v.</hi> 9. Then the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> drew near to battel againſt them, at which they being unarmed, were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid; and knowing their own guilt, deſired <hi>Samuel</hi> to pray for them, which he did, and God delivered them in a miraculous way,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57697:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
thundering a great thunder on the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> and diſcomfiting of them. <hi>v.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>This was their Caſe—And is not ours the parallel to it?</p>
            <p>Their enemies were the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> that always maligned Gods <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ours the Papiſt, that always hate Gods true Catholick and Apoſtolick Proteſtant Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They had the Ark, Gods true Religion and Worſhip. Their Faith once famous throughout the World, their Religion pure, their Faith Orthodos, Their manners holy, and their Biſhops ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Martyrs.</p>
            <p>But this Ark they would not keep, they became corrupt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound in their Principles, and kept not the Faith once delivered to them; but changed the glorious truths of God to a lie, as the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <hi>Romans</hi> did; caſt away what they pleaſed of Gods commands, quite left out of their Catechiſms the ſecond; and to make <note place="margin">Rom 1,</note> up the number, divided the tenth into two. A ſorry ſhift to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port their idolatrous Worſhip; taught for Doctrines their own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable Traditions; cloſed up the Scriptures in an unknown tongue, made it piacular to have or read; and when to make ſome ſhew of owning them, they make uſe of them; they moſt ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly applied them: as to inſtance,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God made a greater light, and a leſſer light;</hi> therefore the Pope is as much greater than the Emperor, as is the Sun than the Moon; Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Peter, Kill and eat;</hi> therefore the Pope may excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate and kill Kings. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, <hi>Behold two Swords;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Pope hath both Spiritual and Temporal Juriſdiction. God ſaid to <hi>Jeremy,</hi> He ſhould plant and tranſplant; therefore the Pope may diſpoſe and tranſpoſe Kingdoms at his pleaſure. <hi>Domini ſunc Cardines terrarum,</hi> therefore the Cardinals are Lords of the earth <hi>Speed Hiſt. p.</hi> 213.</p>
            <p>But generally they ſuppreſs the Scriptures, and inſtead thereof, allow their lying Legend to be read in Churches. Added twelve new Articles to the Chriſtian Faith, impoſe Contradictions to be believed, a that moſt monſtrous Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, that contradicts not only Scripture, that doth aſſure us that Chriſts natural Body is in Heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but all that ſpeaks us men, our <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enſes, ſight, ſmell, taſte, touch; our Reaſon and Underſtanding, that cannot comprehend how one body may be in a thouſand places at one time; and that all the dimenſions of a man of full-grown ſtature
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57697:9"/>
can be hid under, made and contracted into the proportion of a ſmall Wafer; have conjoyned new, ſoul body-ſtate deſtroying prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, as that Dominion is founded in Grace.</p>
            <p>That Religion ſhould be promoted by the Sword. A Turkiſh Tenet. And that which is the <hi>Lerna Malorum</hi> that makes way (if believed and entertained) unto the eſtabliſhing of all manner of Villanies in practiſe, and falſhood in opinion; <hi>viz.</hi> That the Pope is infallible.</p>
            <p>Thus for matters of Faith: and as for their Morals, how im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure have been their practiſes? not only allowing of publick Stews, ſo that in <hi>Rome</hi> there were no leſs than twenty five thouſand Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Women in the year 1565. under the Popes protection, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <note place="margin">Bp. Jewel.</note> a Tribute from them; but thoſe houſes of inforced, and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually but pretended Charity, have proved no other than un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Brothel-houſes, and murderous habitations, witneſs thoſe 6000 Heads of Children taken out of a Pond near a Nunnery, by the Command of <hi>Gregory</hi> the then Pope.</p>
            <p>And as for Papal Veſtals that were at greater liberty, we read that <hi>Boniface</hi> an <hi>Engliſhman</hi> in the year 616 complained in a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter rent to <hi>Cuthbert</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> That the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nuns wandering in pilgrimage under ſhew of Devotion, lived in pleaſure and wanton Fornication through all the Cities of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Lumbardy. Speeds Hiſt. p</hi> 360.</p>
            <p>How holy and chaſt the <hi>Roman</hi> Court was, we have the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Cardinal <hi>Hugo</hi> who told them of <hi>Lyons</hi> in his farewel-Sermon, when the Pope had for ſome time ſo journed amongſt them, That of the many benefits that the Popes abode had brought them, this was a principal, that, when at his coming thither there were three or four houſes of Common-Women in <hi>Lions,</hi> now at their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture they leſt but one, but that indeed reached from the Eaſt-gate to the <hi>Weſt—facta eſt urbs tota lupana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And of what temper of manners they were generally of, even their devoted and religious perſons, in the days of King <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt of <hi>England,</hi> we may find by that anſwer which he made to one <hi>Fulco</hi> a <hi>French Prieſt,</hi> who had told him that he had three very had Daughters, which he wiſhed him to beſtow in marriage, or elſe Gods wrath would attend him. When the King had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, he had not any Daughter; yes, quoth the Prieſt, Thou haſt the<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Daughters, Pride, Couetouſneſs and Letchery. The King replied, My Pride bequeath to the haughty Templers and Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitallers; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Speed. Hiſt. p.</hi> 480.</note>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:57697:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
my Covetouſneſs to the white Monks of the C<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ary Order, and my Letchery to the Prieſts and Prelates; for therein they took their greateſt felicities. How profitable Gueſts they are, and have been to thoſe perſons and ſtates that <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and ſubmit to them, I ſuppoſe their proſlyted bego<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> the Laity, find to their great coſt. And we are informed by Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Hiſtory, that the Popes Authority hath been very charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and burdenſom to the Kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> not only by terrifying or alluring dving perſons to give their Eſtates from their own Children and lawful Heirs, under a pretence of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Church, and Charity to Souls, to free them from <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory</hi> (a place of the <hi>Popes</hi> own mai<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing) but by the owned and publick exactions many ways emptying and impoveriſhing the Realm; which King <hi>Henry</hi> the third was very ſenſible of, who when the <hi>Pope</hi> in perſon (and that was a leſs miſchief than the entertaining of his power) deſired to come into <hi>England,</hi> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied him, it being then ſaid (and it is, and would prove as true ſtill) That the <hi>Pope</hi> is as a Mouſe in a Sachel, or a Snake in ones boſome, that did ill repay the Hoſts for their entertainment. <hi>Speed Hiſt. p.</hi> 538.</p>
            <p>And their Exactions were ſo great in the days of that King, that a Cardinal truly told the <hi>Pope,</hi> That <hi>England</hi> was to the <hi>Pope</hi> as <hi>Baalams</hi> Aſs, which had been ſo often wronged, ſpur galled and cudgelled, it was no marvel that now at laſt ſhe opened her mouth to complain; and for themſelves and the <hi>Roman</hi> Court, they were like <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> every mans hand againſt them, and theirs againſt every one.</p>
            <p>How gentle and courteous, kind and innocent they have been, where they have had power, all Hiſtories record. The deſtruction of the innocent <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> the treacherous Maſſacre at <hi>Paris,</hi> the villanous and barbarous Murders of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>Ireland, Piedmont,</hi> and wherever they got power. And though they may ſeem as mild, innocent and harmleſs, as <hi>Gregory</hi> the firſt, when they have no ſtrength (they then do but hide their claws, which are ſtill ſharp) but when they have got power, as fierce as <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeventh, (that Brand of Hell, <hi>Hildebrand)</hi> who by poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeven of his Predeceſſors, made way to the Papal Throne; and when ſate down in it, managed it to the Ruin and Deſtruction of the <hi>German</hi> Emperor and Empire.</p>
            <p>And what ſafety or ſecurity can any Prince have from them, who
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57697:10"/>
not only teach it as lawful to kill or remove Kings, but alſo as meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious? and have brought their accurſed Doctrine into wicked practice, in the murdering of two Kings of <hi>France</hi> ſucceſſively, one of them always of the Religion, and the other turned to them, <hi>viz Henry</hi> the third and fourth of <hi>France;</hi> for the firſt of which, ſtab'd by a treacherous Monk, there was great rejoycing at <hi>Rome,</hi> and a Panigerical Oration belch'd out of the <hi>Popes</hi> own mouth in the Conclave; ſo that they not only think they may, but applaud it as meritorious; as appears by the writing of <hi>Mariana</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>But this is not the Divinity of the old primitive Chriſtians, but of the new Jeſuits, who more properly may be called <hi>Jehuſites,</hi> driving furiouſly as he did to the Ruin and deſtruction of Kings, by force and power of Arms, if they can; but if that fail, if they want <hi>Vires,</hi> they will try <hi>Virus;</hi> when Sword and Gun can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, Poyſon ſhall. How often was that excellent Princeſs Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> never to be mentioned without Honour, ſo aſſaulted? (and God preſerve his moſt excellent Majeſty that now is, from it) And if that fail, they will try what Powder will do; a Monks inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion found out by the help of the Devil, to the ruine and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Mankind; And had their wicked Plot took effect, would have been the ruine of the whole Nation.</p>
            <p>But bleſſed be God, the ſnare was broken, and we in our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors were delivered, and have a juſt occaſion of rejoycing in this day which the Lord hath made. <note place="margin">Pſal. 118. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And thus you ſee the parallel of the</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <head>Perſons</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Philiſtines.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Papiſts.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The cauſe of their Danger: The receiving of the Ark, the ſetting of it up, reforming from Idolatry, putting away <hi>Baalim</hi> and <hi>Aſhteroth,</hi> worſhipping of God, praying, faſting, meeting at <hi>Mizpeh; Then the Lords of the Philiſtines ſet the battel in array a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them,</hi> v. 10.</p>
            <p>Was not our caſe parallel? what makes the <hi>Pope</hi> and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices ſo maliciouſly ſet againſt the King and Kingdoms of Great <hi>Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland?</hi> was it not the bringing the Ark of true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which they deſpiſed and rejected, and ſetting of it up, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57697:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſanctifying thoſe that ſhould miniſter in it.</p>
            <p>Firſt begun by that Magnanimous and Heroick Prince King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, who like <hi>David,</hi> being a man of Blood, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan Gods Temple, but did not finiſh it, but left it unto that moſt excellent and virtuous Prince <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, the <hi>Joſiah</hi> of his age, that juſtly deſerved the ſtile of <hi>Titus, Delicium humani Generis;</hi> who carried it forward notwithſtanding the great op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition he met with from the <hi>Scottiſh Papiſts,</hi> who at <hi>Muſcle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough Field,</hi> were worſted by a ſmall handful of <hi>Engliſt Proteſtants,</hi> notwithſtanding their mighty Army which brought into the field with it their breaden-God-Altars, Crucifixes, and other Popiſh Trinkets, had 24000. ſlain in the Encounter; and of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> not above 100. And the ſame fate attended the <hi>Devonſhire</hi> and <hi>Corniſh</hi> Rebels that roſe upon the ſame occaſion.</p>
            <p>And though it met with a ſharp oppoſition and perſecution by fire and faggot, by the malice of thoſe wretched Apoſtates from it, <hi>Gardner</hi> and <hi>Bonner,</hi> and the miſguided zeal of Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> yet then the tree of Religion, though it withered in the leaf, yet grew in the root, being watered with the blood of many eminent Chriſtians of all ſorts, learned and godly Divines and Biſhops, who in the former Kings reigns had helpt to introduce it; and in hers, confirmed the truth of it with their Deaths for it; ſo that it quickly again flouriſh'd by the means of that moſt excellent Princeſs Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of bleſſed Memory, whom none except ſuch as that foul-mouth Lyar, and fugitive Jeſuit <hi>Sanders,</hi> will mention without Reverence, much leſs ſpeak ill of her. By her means, I ſay, God eſtabliſht his Ark in our <hi>Iſrael;</hi> his truth, his Worſhip amongſt us; removed <hi>Baalim</hi> and <hi>Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teroth,</hi> the <hi>He-Saints</hi> and <hi>She-Saints</hi> that were ſet up, and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in Gods place. Notwithſtanding,</p>
            <p n="1">1. All open oppoſition by force. In <hi>Ireland</hi> by <hi>Stukely</hi> and <hi>Sanders;</hi> in the North, by <hi>No folk North<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ela<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> and <hi>Weſtmore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> From <hi>Spains</hi> invaſion in 1508. which had it in any meaſure ſucceeded proſperous, would have been ſeconded by a it one bred Rebelion; of which Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh</hi> ſaith, That it only d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>need a Morice on our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Seas. And as another <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> not one bullet into the ſhore; loſt many thouſand m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, and near 20<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. ſhips; whereas we loſt but one in all Veſſel, and not an hundred men.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:57697:11"/>
2. All ſecret machinations, treacherous Contrivances by poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, piſtol, dagger, powder, by <hi>Campion</hi> a <hi>French, Lopez</hi> a <hi>Jew, Creighton</hi> a <hi>Scot,</hi> ſome vile Bygotted Gentleman, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>Thus that moſt excellent Princeſs, notwithſtanding all oppoſition by force and fraud that was made againſt her, maintained Gods Ark, not only twenty years as at <hi>Kirjath-jearim,</hi> but twice twenty and five years; and died in peace and ſerenity of mind in her bed in a good old age; even the age of man in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s time, ſeventy years; and doth well deſerve, notwithſtanding all the barkings of lying Papiſts, and the belchings of impure Mouths againſt her, that part of her Epitaph,
<q>
                  <l>She is, ſhe was, what can there more be ſaid,</l>
                  <l>In earth the firſt, in Heaven the ſecond Maid.</l>
               </q>
Which Ark ſo ſetled her Succeſſor King <hi>James</hi> of bleſſed Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the moſt learned and moſt peaceful Monarch of <hi>Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> maintained, continued and eſtabliſhed, which exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inly provoked the malice of the Popiſh <hi>Philiſtines</hi> againſt him. Hence they contrived, <hi>Watſon</hi> and <hi>Clark, Cobham</hi> and <hi>Raleigh</hi>'s Conſpiracy againſt him in 1603. and that failing, this moſt Helliſh <hi>Powder-Treaſon</hi> no doubt, deviſed by the Devil, but acted by his Inſtuments, <hi>Piercy, Katesby, Digby,</hi> and others, who intended to blow up the King, Queen, Prince and the great States, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the Land, then met in the Upper-Houſe of Parliament; and then to lay that horrid fact to the Puritans <hi>(Sham Plots,</hi> you ſee, are none of their new devices) and ſo to have taken up thence a pretence by the help of Foreigners, whom they had tampered with, to root out Proteſtants and their Religion, and eſtabliſh Popery; which (no queſtion) is, and will be their perpetual deſign and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour.</p>
            <p>But bleſſed be God, for ever bleſſed be his Holy Name, God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervened, and overruled, (and O let him do ſo ſtill) and turned <note place="margin">Eſth. 9. 1.</note> it into the contrary.</p>
            <p>God made that day, which had they had their wits, ſhould have been for Villany and cruelty, the moſt unfortunate day, ſuch as <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nov.</hi> 5.</note> eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard of, unto us moſt joyful, and moſt glorious; when by Gods infinite Goodneſs, and his then moſt excellent Majeſties moſt fortunate Interpretation of a paſſage of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57697:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
one of their own Letters, which paſſage was, <hi>The Danger will be over as ſoon as the Letter was burnt;</hi> which was, as a learned Prelate ſpeaks, more caſual than rational; not by Grammatical Learning, but by divine Revelation and Inſpiration; and by his <note place="margin">Bp. Andrews,</note> faithful Councils, diligent and diſcreet Inquiſition and ſearch, diſcovered and prevented, though thoſe Monſters of men, and the Vaſſals of the <hi>Pope</hi> had taken the Sacrament of ſecrecy, and the time was near for the execution of it.</p>
            <p>Thus was our great danger by our gracious God prevented, and their own deſerved ruine by themſelves procured.</p>
            <p>The remembrance whereof we ought in all ſolemn manner to celebrate every fifth of <hi>November,</hi> as we do, and long may we and our poſterity do it. And as we are directed in a Prayer and Thankſgiving in the Office appointed for that day, joyfully to bleſs God, and earneſtly to intreat him to root out that <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Sect, whoſe Religion is Rebellion, whoſe Faith is Faction, whoſe practice is murdering of ſouls and bodies; from whoſe Treachery, Cruelty, Rage, Malice, good Lord deliver us. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Text. <hi>Then Samuel took a ſtone,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſaying, hitherto hath the Lord helped us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having in the former diſpatched the firſt thing propoſed, <hi>viz.</hi> What was in the Text ſuppoſed, their danger, and the Cauſe of it, and their enemies. I now come to the ſecond thing, <hi>viz.</hi> What is expreſſed.</p>
            <p>Time will not allow particular inſiſting on thoſe many things which the Text in its parts would preſent us with.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſum up all in theſe two things,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Gods helping them.</item>
               <item>2. Their ſenſe of, and thankfulneſs for that help.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1 Gods helping them: which though laſt in words, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing firſt in nature, I ſhall firſt ſpeak to; and as I proceed, compare Gods helping them with his helping us.</p>
            <p>Now what their deliverance was, the Text ſhews us.</p>
            <p>After the Ark was taken by the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> at the news where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and of his two Sons death, old <hi>Eli</hi> died, and <hi>Ickabod</hi> was born <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the glory was departed, and they for twenty years were in an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57697:12"/>
and therefore lamenting Condition, <hi>v.</hi> 1. being fallen into the ſin of Idolatry, <hi>v.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>Under the bondage of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> who diſarmed them, left not a Smith, <hi>&amp;c. Samuel</hi> having been always a Prophet and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructor of them, never ceaſing to pray for them, <hi>Cap.</hi> 12. 1. He having reproved them for, exhorted and prevailed with them to put away <hi>Baalim</hi> and <hi>Aſhteroth,</hi> their He-Gods, and She-Gods, and to ſerve the Lord; now as a Judge, in which Office he ſeems now to be inaugurated, he ſummons them to <hi>Mizpeh</hi> in order to their further Reformation, to faſt and pray, and confeſs their ſins; which the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> hearing of, they gathered themſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with an hoſtile intention.</p>
            <p>No new thing for Satan to imploy his Inſtuments in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing of good actions.</p>
            <p>At the hearing of whoſe gathering together, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were afraid, being unarmed and unprepared to encounter with them, <hi>v.</hi> 7 and therefore deſpairing of their own, apply themſelves to <hi>Samuel</hi> to pray for Gods help, that he would ſave them, <hi>v.</hi> 8. They were ſenſible of their own ſinfulneſs, being Idolaters, and knew that God would not hear ſinners.</p>
            <p>They were aſſured of <hi>Samuels</hi> Holineſs and Innocency, and therefore of Gods favour towards him. Hence they deſired him to pray for them when they were apprehenſive of their own unfitneſs and indiſpoſition to pray for themſelves; where by the way obſerve:</p>
            <p>Though graceleſs ſinners in their proſperity ſcorn and abuſe Gods faithful Miniſters, yet have they then a Conviction in their own Conſciences of their Innocency: and in time of their diſtreſs, will ſeek to ſuch to pray for them; as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> the people to <hi>Samuel;</hi> they ſent not to their fellow-Idolate's, nor <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to the <hi>Magicians;</hi> then <hi>Moſes,</hi> then <hi>Samuel</hi> muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to pray for them.</p>
            <p>Thus it is, and will be with intelligent, though graceleſs peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in reference to ſcandalous and careleſs Miniſters, who do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfully aſſociate them in their ſinful and unwarrantable pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of drin<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, ſwearing, dicing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> even thoſe perſons who ſeem to applaud flatter, and admire them; yet in their ſober moods have ſo much conviction, that in their thoughts they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them as the blemiſhes of their Function; and in the'r extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miti<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s little regard their Prayers for them; then an Innocent
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57697:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Moſes,</hi> though many times rejected; then an holy and blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs <hi>Samuel</hi> ſhall be ſought to; then, pray for us; then, honour me before the people.</p>
            <p>The only way for Miniſters to keep up their Reputation with men, is to be careful of a blameleſs Converſation, a faithful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of their Miniſterial Function, a conſtant Converſing in their ſtudies with God by Meditation and Prayer, and with the beſt Companions, the holy Scriptures, and the Books of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and holy Writers; (no ſuch Companions in Taverns or Coffee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes) and the keeping their Conſciencies void of offence towards God and man; which ſhall they do, they will find love, as <hi>Samuel</hi> from a <hi>David,</hi> and Reverenee and Reſpect, even from a <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Herod,</hi> as <hi>Samuel</hi> and <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> did.</p>
            <p>This by the by: and I aſſure you, ſpoke with no ill intent; and I hope and pray it may be to ſome good effect.</p>
            <p>To return: 1. <hi>Samuel</hi> anſwers their deſire, makes teſtimony of his faith in the promiſed <hi>Meſſiah</hi> by his ſacrifice, and earneſtly crys to God for them, <hi>v</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>Faith and Prayer, the pious mans beſt defence: <hi>Preces &amp; Lacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae arma Eccleſiae,</hi> Prayers and Tears the Churches weapon. <hi>Non vires, non virus, nec pulvis Sulphureus;</hi> not Power, nor Poyſon, nor Powder: they are not the arms of Chriſts Followers, but of the Jeſuits and <hi>Romiſh</hi> Synagogue.</p>
            <p>The ſucceſs was, God heard his Prayers, thundred upon, and diſcomfited the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> gave the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> a great victory, whereby they regained the Cities they had loſt; ſo that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward they flouriſhed in peace, Juſtice and Religion all the days of <hi>Samuel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what manner of people theſe were, whom God thus helped, we may learn from the Context, and ſo we find them,
<list>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:57697:13"/>
                  <item>1. A ſinful people, Idolaters.</item>
                  <item>2. An aſſaulted people by the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> lording over them, coming in arms againſt them.</item>
                  <item>3. A penitent people, as is evident,
<list>
                        <item>1. By their Obedience to <hi>Samuels</hi> ſummons, coming to <hi>Mizpeh;</hi> they were no Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from the Magiſtrates-lawful Command.</item>
                        <item>2. By their Reforming, Putters away of <hi>Baalim</hi> and <hi>Aſhteroth.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3.By their Humiliation before God.
<list>
                              <item>1. Confeſſing their ſins.</item>
                              <item>2. Faſting.</item>
                              <item>3. Praying to God.</item>
                              <item>4. Praying to <hi>Samuel</hi> to pray for them.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. Uſing their own endeavours, as well as depending on Gods Power. They went forth.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Thus it was with the <hi>Iſraellites;</hi> and hath it not been ſo with us in many particulars, which time will not admit my ſpeaking to? Only in general.</p>
            <p>Their enemies were <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> Idolaters, that worſhipped <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,</hi> and other Heathen Deities; the firſt Inhabiters, in whoſe room the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſucceeded, but ſuch whom God had juſtly for their ſins when come to ripeneſs, appointed to be rooted out; and left Command to do it as the Land would bear, left the wild Beaſts ſhould increaſe upon them; and gave the Land unto the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> which did not, or could not expel them; ſo that they ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued amongſt them, ſometimes in ſubjection, many times in power over them; but always becauſe of a different Religion, at an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable enmity againſt them; and ſtill watching, and taking all opportunities to deſtroy them.</p>
            <p>And as for the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> though they had been Idolatrous Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of <hi>Baalim</hi> and <hi>Aſhteroth,</hi> yet were now truly penitent; had reformed themſelves, put away <hi>Baalim</hi> and <hi>Aſhteroth,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſincere in their Worſhip of the true God; and were now in the actual worſhipping of him by <hi>Samuels</hi> Command, which they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:57697:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
obeyed, congregated at <hi>Mizpeh,</hi> unarmed and unprepared, and not expecting of an enemy: <hi>Mutato nomine.</hi> Put we but Jeſuited Papiſts in the room of <hi>Philistines,</hi> and true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and our excellent and learned Prince, King <hi>James</hi> of happy Memory, inſtead of <hi>Samuel, Weſtminſter</hi> inſtead of <hi>Mizpeh,</hi> and the moſt ſolemn Aſſembly of Parlament brought thither by the Kings ſummons, to eſtabliſh and confirm true Religion, and whence to come immediately from the actual performance of Religious Worſhip in the ancient ſtructure of St. <hi>Peters;</hi> And you have the true Caſe of the occaſion of this times ſolemnity; and therefore I ſhall not, and I need not add any more, only in general obſerve,</p>
            <p>That quarrels that are grounded on matters of Religion, are not durable; moſt implacable, moſt miſchievous<hi>—Philiſtines</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Iſraelites, Papiſts</hi> againſt <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For though it be true, that many Atheiſtical <hi>Matchiavils</hi> that are of themſelves of no Religion, do make uſe of the name of it, as a politick engine to work their own purpoſes, and are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe indifferent to all. And many crafty-pated, or ſuch who have ſmall dealings, do profeſs this or that perſwaſion upon a Deſign of gaining a Trade to advance their worldly Intereſt, turn Diſſenters of every ſort, to gain a Trade amongſt thoſe they turn to; and are indeed crafty ſhavers that are of no Religion out of Conſcience, yet pretend to ſome out of their Covetouſneſs.</p>
            <p>Yet we know our Fathers have told us in their recorded Hiſtories, and we our ſelves have ſeen, and known many zealous Bygots in all perſwaſions, who have good intentions, but weak Judgments; that are indeed conſcientious, though erroneouſly ſo; and will not by flattery or force be perſwaded or prevailed with, to forſake that perſwaſion or opinion they have eſpouſed; yea, though their lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders who did ſeduce them into thoſe ſeditious, ſchiſmatical and phantaſtical Principles and Practices, turn from them themſelves, and many times earneſtly oppoſe them.</p>
            <p>Thus it was with <hi>Brown,</hi> the Father and Cognominator of our firſt Separatiſts, who had ſeduced many to a Separation from our Church, as Antichriſtian in her Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline, yet himſelf returned and became Miniſter of a Church, a place ſo named; but his followers (the ſource, ſpring, fountain and root of thoſe many <hi>Hydra-headed</hi> Diviſions in Religion, which have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded amongſt us ever ſince) ſtill continued obſtinate.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:57697:14"/>
Now in thoſe whoſe Conſciences, though erroneous, and not their worldly Intereſt ſway them, in ſuch the quarrel for Religion, and upon that occaſion, becomes ſetled, durable, implacable and miſchievous.</p>
            <p>And ſuch is, and hath been, and will be of the Bygoted Papiſts (the old and greateſt Fanaticks) againſt the Proteſtant Church of <hi>England,</hi> who ever ſince it hath had an eſtabliſhed being, they have and will oppoſe, and ſet themſelves againſt, as the <hi>Philistines</hi> did againſt <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Erroneous Conſciences (though in good men) are apt to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake their carnal paſſions for commendable zeal, under which (when their Intereſt lurks) it drives on unto furious motions. Thus the Diſciples, <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> being ignorant of Chriſts ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Kingdom, dream'd of an earthly Kingdom. And this ſoon made them ambitious (as appears by their Mothers motion, no queſtion, ſet on by themſelves) That the one might ſit on the right hand, and the other at the left, in Chriſts Kingdom.</p>
            <p>This Ambition makes them furiouſly zealous to call for fire from Heaven on the <hi>Samaritans</hi> that would not entertain their Maſter.</p>
            <p>But herein they were not like their Maſter, nor liked by him.</p>
            <p>Chriſts Paſſions were free from Concupiſcence, wherewith ours are defiled. Our Paſſions are like water that hath a muddy reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which when it is ſtirred, every part groweth foul with it; but our Savious Paſſions of grief, and anger, and ſorrow, were like clean water in a pure veſſel, which is never the fouler for the motion; ſo were not the two Diſciples, who thought their carnal Paſſion, zeal for their Maſter; and the Deſtruction of the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> well-plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Juſtice. Chriſt tells them, <hi>You know not what Spirit you are of,</hi> and that he himſelf was of another temper; who came to ſave mens lives, and not deſtroy.</p>
            <p>Oh! how like in this particular unto theſe two miſtaking Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſt, are thoſe that call themſelves the Followers of Jeſus, (but ſo called <hi>per Antiphraſin,</hi> as <hi>Lucus a non lucendo)</hi> who are not the Followers of the meek and holy Jeſus, but the Imitators of thoſe furious Soldiers, <hi>Jehu,</hi> and <hi>Ignatius</hi> their founder of accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Memory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John</hi> and <hi>James,</hi> Chriſts Diſciples, in a paſſionate zeal for their Maſter, would needs have <hi>Samaria</hi> deſtroyed with fire from Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:57697:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Our Jeſuits would, and did endeavour to deſtroy our King, Queen, Prince, Lords ſpiritual and temporal, Commons, our ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ancient Structures; yea, Friends as well as Foes, with fire from Hell.</p>
            <p>But as Chriſt rebuked his Diſciples raſhneſs, ſo God diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Jeſuits and their bygoted Proſelytes cruel malice.</p>
            <p>And the Evangeliſt in recording the Story, hath given a Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to that queſtion, Whether <hi>Jews</hi> may deſtroy <hi>Samaritans</hi> for not being of their Religion or Perſwaſion. Diſſent in Religion was the cauſe of their quarrel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Samaritans</hi> would not entertain <hi>Jews</hi> going to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but ſtarve them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> would by fire deſtroy the <hi>Samaritans;</hi> if they be He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, burn them, let them not live. The Woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> tells our Saviour, That the <hi>Jews</hi> have no dealings with the <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">John 4. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Non contuntur;</hi> yea, they abuſed each other, forgetting Humanity and Piety on either part, and ſo always continued till their own implacable diviſions made way for, and brought Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction upon them both in the days of <hi>Claudius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the Diſciples were not of the ſame Spirit with theſe two Zealots. The other ten, though they liked not the <hi>Samaritans</hi> unkindneſs to their Maſter, yet called not for fire from Heaven; neither were the <hi>Samaritans</hi> all ſo uncivil; for we read how he turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into another Town.</p>
            <p>And to comfort ſuch as be thus minded as the Ten Diſciples were, we may take notice, that our bleſſed Saviour was none of the Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, or ſhewed himſelf on their ſide, but inclined to Humanity, Peace, Familiarity, Friendſhip and Goodneſs toward all.</p>
            <p>He ſtill would converſe with the <hi>Samaritans;</hi> ask water, ſent his Diſciples to <hi>Samaria</hi> to buy meat; to this Town to take up lodging. In this journey he healed a <hi>Samaritan.</hi> Leper; yea, ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable towards them, and ſo ready to be uſed by them, that he was called a <hi>Samaritan</hi> for his labour. <note place="margin">John 8. 48.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt was in the right, and its ſafe being of Chriſts Temper, yea, its our duty to be ſo; <hi>Let this mind be in you which was alſo in Christ Jeſus.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But what are the Jeſuits and the Jeſuited Papiſts? God forbid we ſhould think ſo of all <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks. All the <hi>Samaritans</hi> did not refuſe Chriſt, ſome entertained him. All Papiſts are not of that miſchievous temper; but thoſe that are Jeſuits and Jeſuited,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:57697:15"/>
they are indeed like theſe two miſguided Diſciples, not in their goodneſs otherwiſe, but in their furious Zeal, who were moved by the barbarous indignity of denying harbour for a night to their Maſter (whom in his Transfiguration they had ſo lately ſeen in Glory; and this denial by a ſort of paltry Hereticks; and only becauſe his was as if he went to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> he was well affected in Religion) to call for fire from Heaven utterly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them.</p>
            <p>This made theſe two that were of the chiefeſt of Chriſts Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, one of them a Pillar in the Church, the other Chriſts belov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Darling, to make that motion of fire from Heaven. <note place="margin">Gal. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And was not that motion good? conſidering they had the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Elijah's</hi> ſo doing, whom they had ſo lately ſeen in Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? <note place="margin">John 21. 7.</note> Thus far the two Diſciples of Chriſt, and <hi>Ignatius Loyala's</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 9. 54.</note> ſociety, go together.</p>
            <p>But now they break Company; Chriſts Diſciples would have fire from Heaven; this curſed ſpawn of <hi>Ignatius</hi> would have it from under ground.</p>
            <p>Chriſts Diſciples askt their Maſters leave; theſe conſult not with Chriſt at all, but with their Father the Devil, who was a Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer.</p>
            <p>Chriſts Diſciples would have it done by a Miracle, wherein Gods finger might be ſeen; they by a baſe and treacherous Invention of the Devils contriving.</p>
            <p>They would do it like Diſciples in Gods Name, by their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Licenſe, call it down, not conjure it up; from Heaven its own Sphere, not from below. The Diſciples, like Eagles, fly to the Clouds; the Jeſuits like Moldwarps, creep into a Vault.</p>
            <p>Now though the Diſciples Circumſtances were right, yet the motion was wrong, which ſprang from the ignorance of their own and Chriſts Spirit; for which he rebukes them, <hi>You know not what Spirit you are of;</hi> and from ignorance can ſpring no good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You know not what you ask; you worſhip you know not what.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 20. 23.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are Chriſts own returns to theſe two Diſciples; and to <note place="margin">John 4. 22.</note> the Woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> wherein we may find rebuked by our Saviours own mouth,</p>
            <p>Ignorant Zeal, implicite Faith, and blind Devotion; the Popes three great Engines of State to maintain his power.</p>
            <p>Zeal muſt be according to knowledg, or elſe it will precipitate even Chriſts own well-meaning Diſciples into cruel and bloody
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:57697:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
acts; how much more ſuch looſe principled perſons as generally Jeſuits and Jeſuited Papiſts, into treacherous and miſchievous Plots and Contrivances, murdering of Kings, maſſacring of thouſands of Innocents, blowing up King and Kingdom in an Inſtant! And all this the fruit of ignorant zeal!</p>
            <p>But the example of <hi>Elias</hi> will not bear them out in it, for <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias</hi>'s Spirit was ſuitable to <hi>Elias</hi>'s time, and the legal Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, which was of Death; but Chriſt had altered the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, and brought in by the Goſpel, Peace and Life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Elias</hi> had a particular Commiſſion, they had none.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Elias</hi> only deſtroyed the culpable; theſe Diſciples had no more regard to the Innocent in that place, than <hi>Jonah</hi> had to thoſe in <hi>Nineveh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They were Chriſts Diſciples, and not <hi>Elia's;</hi> and therefore might not have the Spirit of <hi>Elias,</hi> but of their Maſter, who came to ſave life, and not deſtroy; and ſuch is, and ſhould, be the Spirit of Chriſts Diſciples, whoſe Office is not what <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> ſaith, St. <hi>Peter's</hi> is, <hi>Paſcere &amp; occidere,</hi> to feed and ſlay; but to ſeek and ſave. The ſecond Office <hi>Bellarmine</hi> attributes to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> viz. <hi>Occidere</hi> to ſlay, came from him who was a Murderer from the beginning, and not from the holy and meek Jeſus, who was, as his Name imports, a Saviour, and not a Slayer.</p>
            <p>Such then that are Chriſts Diſciples, muſt learn of him who was meek and lowly, not proud and cruel. Thus far of Gods help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them.</p>
            <p>Text. <hi>Then Samuel took a ſtone and ſet it between Mizpeh and Shen, and called it Eben-Ezer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words we have three things conſiderable,</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The ſenſe of their deliverance, <hi>Then</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Their preſent thankfulneſs, <hi>ſaying, Hitherto.—</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. Their care for the continuance of the memorial of it, <hi>Then Samuel took a ſtone—</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Of each of theſe in their order, and firſt of the</p>
            <p n="1">1. Their ſenſe of their Deliverance implied in the word <hi>Then;</hi> When God had thundred on the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> and diſcomfited them, <hi>v.</hi> 10. <hi>When the men of Iſrael went out from Mizpeh and purſued them, and ſmote them until they came to Beth car.</hi> v. 11.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:57697:16"/>
My preſent buſineſs is to parallel their Caſe with ours. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Caſe was whilſt they were unarmed, faſting and praying, and Confeſſing their ſins, and in all likelihood met at <hi>Mizpeh</hi> for the conſulting about their Concerns; <hi>ſo then Samuel judged Iſrael,</hi> v. 6. as likewiſe we read of <hi>Iſraels</hi> meeting there before that time, <hi>Judg.</hi> 10. 17. not thinking or being ſuſpitious, or afraid of any danger near them, but in profound Peace, as to men, and by hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling themſelves before God, making their Peace with him. <hi>Then the Lords of the Philiſtines went up againſt Iſrael, and drew near to battel,</hi> v. 10. with which ſudden and unexpected danger, they were very much terrified, and in that fear did not ſink under, and cowardly run away (as the Emperor <hi>Ferdinands</hi> Popiſh Army invad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Huſſites</hi> for their Religion, twice did, being ſtricken by God with a panick fear, never ſtriking one ſtroke) but they bethought themſelves, and betook themſelves to the beſt courſe they could for their own preſervation; they befought <hi>Samuel</hi> not to ceaſe to pray for them; they remembred (moſt likely) that it was <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi>'s hand lift up, that gave their forefathers victory; and they themſelves went out of <hi>Mizpeh</hi> and purſued them, and God himſelf thundred upon them ſo, that the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> were diſcomfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſmitten before <hi>Iſrael,</hi> until they came to <hi>Beth-car,</hi> v. 11.</p>
            <p>Lo this their deliverance, and their ſenſe of it appears by <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muels</hi> ſetting a ſtone, erecting a Monumental Trophy of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſhewn them in that place.</p>
            <p>Now ſhould we parallel our Deliverance from the Powder-Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Traytors, and theirs from the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> we ſhall find many remarkable Circumſtances that heightned the greatneſs of our danger, and ſo the value of our deliverance, above theirs.</p>
            <p>Which I may but touch.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Their danger was from open enemies, from whom they had deſerv'd, and could expect no other.</p>
            <p>Ours was from pretended Friends, who lived, yea, flouriſhed with Wealth and Honour under the Protection of that King and Laws that they endeavoured the Deſtruction of; were ſecret ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that lived as Friends in the midſt of us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> danger was known to them, and could not be hid from them; the Lords of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> went up againſt them in battel in an hoſtile manner as declared Enemies.</p>
            <p>Ours was altogether hidden from us, no ſign, token or ſuſpition of any miſchief towards, all things calm; and thoſe that call
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:57697:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
themſelves <hi>Romau Catholicks</hi> (a Contradiction in the terms, as a <hi>Particular <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal)</hi> had a very great ſhare in the Kings favour, and pretended greateſt ſatisfaction with it.</p>
            <p>Then the Lords of our <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> the enemies of our Peace and Religion, did not go up with an Army at their heels, though they had Proviſion to have ſuddenly raiſed one; but they went down into the Vaults and Cellars with the Devil at their elbows.</p>
            <p>Their under-ground-Contrivances prevented diſcovery, till our great and gracious God (whoſe name be ever magnified) who is <hi>Pan Ophthaelmus,</hi> and ſaw thoſe hidden works of darkneſs, made one of themſelves an Inſtrument of revealing of them and their moſt miſchievous deſign.</p>
            <p>And hence may all Gods ſaithful Servants comfort themſelves, That though the Devils claws be in all our enemies Plots, and our danger, yet ſtill God ſeeth them, though they do not; and hath, and will have a hand in their Diſcovery, and in his Servants Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, as he had in <hi>Iſraels</hi> Deliverance from the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> and in our forefathers, and in them our Deliverance from the Powder-Treaſon.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Danger was what they knew, provided againſt, and that by all the ways that could be imagined likely to deliver them, as,</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Humiliation, faſting, weeping.</item>
                  <item>2. Their own Reformation, they put away <hi>Baalim</hi> and <hi>Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teroth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. Their importunate deſires of <hi>Samuels</hi> praying for them.</item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Samuels</hi> anſwering their deſire, not only,
<list>
                        <item>1. Earneſtly praying; <hi>He cried.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. But likewiſe ſacrificing a Lamb. <hi>v.</hi> 9.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Samuel</hi> ſet Faith and Prayer on work; firſt he ſacrificed, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed and acted his Faith on Jeſus Chriſt the true Lamb of God, that was by the Levitical Lambs typified, as being ſlain from the beginning of the World; and then he earneſtly and fervently, not only prayeth, but crieth to the Lord for them.</p>
            <p>And having thus taken the right courſe to make God their friend, for this is the courſe of his own preſcribing, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7. 14. <hi>If my people which are called by my name, ſhall humble themſelves and pray, and ſeek my face, and turn from their wicked wayes: then will I hear,</hi> &amp;c. Having taken this courſe, they then</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:57697:17"/>
5. Set themſelves forth couragiouſly and valiantly to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; and God fought with them, and for them, and made them victorious over their enemies; inſomuch, that they drove them clean out of the field into their ſtrong-hold of <hi>Beth-car;</hi> the conſequence of which Victory was the recovering of their own City, and Peace with the <hi>Amorites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus conſidered theirs, let us now ſee what our Danger, and ſo Deliverance was.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Our Danger was not from open enemies, but pretended and ſuppoſed friends, who had been many ways obliged to gratitude and good Offices by the favour of their Prince, and the courteſie and kindneſs of their fellow-Subjects.</p>
            <p>Oh horrid and unnatural Ingratitude, and almoſt incredible, were it not that we have ſeen and known by woful experience, that the blind zeal of Jeſuit-ridden Papiſts carrieth them againſt all the tyes and obligations that flow from gratitude, kindred, friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Relation; and in the ſervice of the Devil and the Pope, makes them like <hi>Levi,</hi> to know neither Father nor Mother, Kin nor Relation, Friendſhip nor Gratitude, but tramples down all that's ſacred, that ſtands in the way of their promoting of the Intereſt of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; and if that be the caſe, then
<q>Tros Tyrius nullo diſcrimen agetur.</q>
Let them be Friend or Foe, Relation or Stranger, their fellow-Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, yea, fellow Plotters too, it's all one; if they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to be blocks in their way, they muſt be removed, if their ſtrength, teachers, and the ſeaſonableneſs of ſo doing, prompt to it. And our Progenitors found that obſervation before mentioned very true in thoſe <hi>Engliſh</hi> Powder-Traytors, <hi>viz.</hi> That an <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh man</hi> Italionated, is a Devil incarnate—</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our Danger was hid from us; no ſuſpition, nor fear, nor apprehenſion of it; all ſecure, <hi>Halcyon days of peace,</hi> without any diſturbance. The fear of danger that poſſeſt the Nation in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the death of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> was over.
<q>Sol occubuit nox nulla ſecuta eſt.</q>
Peace and Religion ſetled and maintained in the ſame Condition, Traffick and Trading, Merchandizing and Manufacturage encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:57697:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and by a ſetled peace with <hi>Spain,</hi> which before was always dubious, now enlarged to the exceeding Advantage of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Nation.</p>
            <p>The old enmity, and fear of enmity from <hi>Scotland,</hi> now quite removed by the uniting of the two Diadems in one Perſon, who was what his <hi>Motto</hi> (choſen by himſelf) ſpeaks him, <hi>Vere Pacificus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Learning encouraged under a moſt learned King; then indeed were <hi>Muſae regnantes;</hi> and all things in a moſt flouriſhing and moſt proſperous eſtate.</p>
            <p>Favour was equally, according to Demerits, extended unto the Catholick Nobility and Gentry.</p>
            <p>Books written by Catholicks to perſwade the Papiſts to a quiet ſubmiſſion unto their Princes peaceable Government; when all things carried a fair proſpect to a glorious and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Eſtate; even then
<q>—Latet anguis in herba.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Then the implacable enmity of Satan againſt all that is good and lovely; then the infatuated zeal of Prieſt-ridden Bygots, ſet them on work, to contrive that work of Darkneſs, that hath no parallel, as to all its Circumſtances, in any Hiſtory; which was invented by the Prince of Darkneſs, carried on by Children of Darkneſs, and laid in a place of Darkneſs; which when if had taken light by <hi>Faux</hi>'s Match, would have proved the blackneſs of darkneſs; and it is to be feared (conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the general ſecurity and impenitency of proſperous Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind) would have ſent many a ſhattered body to the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Death; and many a poor unprepared ſoul unto utter Darkneſs; and would have been ſuitable to an <hi>Italian</hi> Revenge, the Diſtruction of ſoul and body.
<q>Tantum Religio poterat fundere malorum.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Our danger could have no preparation againſt it; for as <hi>Ignoti nulla Cupido—</hi>ſo <hi>nullus Timor.</hi> The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> knew, and provided all poſſible means againſt their danger, by Humiliation, Reformation, Faſting, Prayers, praying to <hi>Samuel</hi> to pray for</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:57697:18"/>
them, and their own valour; but alas! none of theſe could, or were put in uſe, or were thought upon in our caſe.</p>
            <p>The Preparations for the Grandeur of the firſt days Seſſion of Parliament, had put away the thoughts of Humiliation; Feaſting excluded Faſting, and Complements and Courtſhip of Saluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Prayer.</p>
            <p>And, for any endeavours of our own, the nature of our dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger prevented all; ſo that we muſt ſay, That our Deliverance was <hi>digitus Dei</hi> alone; no <hi>Samuel</hi> to pray for us, no Army to go forth againſt our enemies, whom we knew not, nor where to find; and as for the way of their malice by Gun-powder, no poſſible eſcaping; ſo that we muſt ſtill ſay, <hi>Non nobis Domine,</hi> Not unto us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And, <hi>If the Lord had not been on our ſide, they had ſwallowed us up quick.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 115.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And let this be our encouragement ſtill, That God is, and <note place="margin">124.</note> will be on the ſide of his faithful, penitent and praying people, to defend and preſerve them (even when care is not, or cannot be taken) from all the Contrivances, and miſchievous Plots of the implacable enemies of our Religion, Laws, Lives, Liberties, Conſciences; for it is certain, That howſoever God be not in the beginnings of evil enterpriſes to ſet them forward, yet at the end he muſt be, or no end will be; for <hi>Domini ſunt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 21. v. 16.</note> 
               <hi>exitus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Horſe may be prepared for the battel, the Lot caſt into the Lap, the Counſel of <hi>Ashitophel</hi> may be taken, <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> may obtain the Kings Letters to deſtroy the <hi>Jews,</hi> the great Fleet at <hi>Ezion Geber</hi> may be prepared, <hi>Sennacheribs</hi> migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Army may be liſted, the Lords of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> may be upon their march, the Powder, and Billets, and Match may be all laid, and a wicked <hi>Faux</hi> ready with his dark-Lanthorn to put fire to it; and how near was our late Popiſh Plot ripe for execution, when it was diſcovered!</p>
            <p>Yet God defeats them all; for Counſel may be in the heart of man, and words at his Tongues end, and Acts at his fingers end, the Match laid to the Powder, yet nothing ſhall be ſaid, or done or take effect, except God will have it ſo; he giveth and denieth ſucceſs as hepleaſeth.</p>
            <p>And as for <hi>Samuels</hi> Prayers, or our own endeavour, our Caſe and Danger was ſuch as could not admit either in particular.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:57697:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
But the daily Devotions of righteous perſons (that would have kept fire from Heaven from falling on <hi>Sodom)</hi> and Gods infinite free Mercy prevented their fire from Hell from doing execution; ſo that for the greatneſs of our deliverance mani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſted in the greatneſs of our Danger, we muſt ſtill ſay, <hi>Not unto us, O Lord, not unto us: but unto thy Name give Glory,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 115. 1.</note> 
               <hi>for thy mercy and thy truths ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>had it not been the Lord, who was on our ſide, they had ſwallowed us up quick</hi> (had their Fire been kindled, it would <note place="margin">Pſ. 11<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.</note> have made but one mouthful of King and Kingdom).</p>
            <p>But <hi>bleſſed be the Lord, who hath not given us as a prey to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">6.</note> 
               <hi>their teeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our ſoul is eſcaped as a bird out of the ſnare of the Fowler:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">7.</note> 
               <hi>the ſnare is broken, or looſed, and we are eſcaped.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now (as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> obſerves) a thing is looſed two ways; either after we are ſnared, or before; ſo a Captivity may be ſaid to be turned two ways, by an after-deliverance, or a forehand prevention.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Grecians</hi> expreſs by <hi>Prometheus</hi> and <hi>Epimetheus;</hi> the <hi>Latins</hi> by <hi>anteverta</hi> and <hi>poſtverta;</hi> the <hi>Schoolmen</hi> by <hi>praeveniendo, ſubveniendo.</hi> The firſt is beſt.</p>
            <p>A good buckler to keep off the blow, is better than a good Plaiſter to heal the hurt.</p>
            <p>And ſuch was our deliverance, a prevention, concerning which we may ſay, That the Deſtruction intended was the Devils do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and it is monſtrous in our eyes; the deliverance was Gods doing, and let it ſtill be marvellous in our eyes, that we may be thankful at preſent; and in the eyes of our Poſterity; the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial of it perpetuated from Generation to Generation; which thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs was <hi>Samuels</hi> practice at the preſent, and care for the Children of <hi>Iſraels</hi> future remembrance of it, and comes in the laſt place to be ſpoken to.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Samuels</hi> preſent thankfulneſs expreſſed in theſe words, <hi>ſaying, Hiterto hath God helped us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He acknowledgeth that God had helped them, and had always helped them. And herein indeed conſiſts the proper form and eſſence (if I may ſo ſpeak) of our Thankſgiving, <hi>viz.—</hi> To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to his Honour what he hath been to us, and what he hath done for us—</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:57697:19"/>
Inſtances whereof we have in many of <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalms. The 136. throughout, and 145. which I ſhall only point to.</p>
            <p>In the two firſt verſes he tells us, That he will extol God his King, and bleſs his Name for and ever; every day he would bleſs God, and praiſe his name for ever and ever.—And how he did, we may ſee it in the following verſes, by declaring of Gods</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Greatneſs. v. 3, 4, 5, 6.</item>
                  <item>2. Goodneſs. v. 9.</item>
                  <item>3. His Works and Saints, v 10, 11, 12.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And having reckoned up from the fourteeenth to the twenty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firſt, many particular Inſtances of his Acts of grace, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and greatneſs, he concludes with declaring what was his own, and what he deſires ſhould be of others.<hi>—My mouth ſhall ſpeak the praiſe of the Lord. And let all fleſh bleſs his holy name for ever and ever,</hi> v. 21.</p>
            <p>Lo this is the Tenor of our bleſſing God, and declaring our thankfulneſs to him, when we recount to his Glory and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour what he hath done for us.</p>
            <p>Now this is a wide and comprehenſive duty: ſhall we paſs over the imperate, and only conſider the elicite Acts of it; ſuch as flow from, and conſtitute the very being of it? All which we may find in this of <hi>Samuels</hi> expreſſion of his, and the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> (for he was but their mouth) thankfulneſs unto God; <hi>Hitherto hath God helped us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the elicite Acts of thankfulneſs are five,</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Obſervation.</item>
                  <item>2. Remembrance.</item>
                  <item>3. Confeſſion.</item>
                  <item>4. Valuation.</item>
                  <item>5. Retribution.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Obſervation: For how can we be thankful for that we take no notice of?</p>
            <p>This was <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſin charged upon them, that made them <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. 1, 2.</note> worſe than Ox or Aſs. The Kindneſs, and the Circumſtances of it, muſt be obſerved by us. Thus <hi>David, Thou haſt brought me hitherto: what am I?</hi> Thus <hi>Samuel, Hitherto hath God helped</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:57697:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
2. Confeſſion with the tongue: Thus <hi>Samuel,</hi> he did not ſet a ſtone and ſay nothing, but he called it <hi>Eben-Ezer; ſaying, hitherto hath God helped.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We muſt not ſtifle, nor impriſon the Apprehenſions we have of Gods Goodneſs in our hearts, but declare them to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>Hence <hi>David: Come my Children, hearken unto me, and I will tell you what God hath done for my ſoul. And it is a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 92. 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>good thing to ſing praiſes unto thy name, to ſhow forth thy lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kindneſs in the Morning, and thy faithfulneſs every night.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence he calls his tongue his Glory: How is the mans tongue his Glory, but as it is an inſtrument imployed in the glorify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Pſ. 16 9.</note> of God, wherein ſtands mans higheſt praiſe. <note place="margin">Acts 2, 26.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Meer ſpeech, is the glory of a man above brute Creatures; Eloquent ſpeech is the Glory of the learned above the untaught. Gracious ſpeech Language of Prayer and Praiſes, is the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of a <hi>David,</hi> a man after Gods own Heart.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Remembrance: Hence the Pſalmiſt, when he preſſeth his ſoul to praiſe God, calls upon it not to forget any of his <note place="margin">Pſ. 103 2.</note> benefits.</p>
            <p>Reflect we muſt on the mercies we enjoy, or we ſhall never be thankful.</p>
            <p>Hence God himſelf inſtituted Trophies, Stones, and Days, and other Monuments to continue the memorial of them; and we read it as a commendable and praiſe worthy deed of the City of <hi>Zurich,</hi> who engraved the year of their deli<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rance from the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Antichriſt, upon Pillars in Letters of Gold.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Valuation: A d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e eſtimate of the mercies we enjoy at Gods hands If once we think meanly of them, we ſhall quickly be unthankful for them; if we ſay as <hi>Hiran</hi> or the Cities which <hi>Solomon</hi> gave him, What Cities are th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe? we ſhall ſoon forget the kindneſs, and brand with diſgrace; call them <hi>Cabul.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 King, 9. 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>If once ſay with the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> Nothing but this <hi>Manna;</hi> we ſhould ſoon prove Murmurers againſt, and not Praiſers of God. When <hi>Korah</hi> thought his being a <hi>Levite</hi> a ſmall thing, then he murmured. <note place="margin">Numb. 16. 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>If Gods Conſolation ſeems ſmall, our thankſgivings will be <note place="margin">Job 15. 13.</note> very ſlender.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:57697:20"/>
5. Retribution: an eſſential part of thankſgiving; hence the Pſalmiſt, <hi>quid retribuam,</hi> what ſhall I render?</p>
            <p>As <hi>Ahaſucroſh</hi> askt, What done for <hi>Mordecai?</hi> ſo we ſhould ask, what done for God, on his Command, to his Glory? Certainly all we are, have, can do, ſuffer, are leſs than the leaſt of Gods mercies.</p>
            <p>Yet an Obligation lieth upon us, render we muſt, give up our ſelves, ſouls, bodies, all we are, have; yet all will fall ſhort of what we owe to Gods Glory; and we can give him but his own, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Let us then own God in all we have, and honour him by all we can do or ſuffer for him.</p>
            <p>Own him in all our Mercies, all our Deliverances, this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, our preſervation. And thus expreſs our thankfulneſs as <hi>Samuel</hi> did, by a due Obſervation, Remembrance, Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment, Valuation and Retribution; and by taking care as he did, to tranſmit the memorial of it to Poſterity, which is the laſt that comes now to be conſidered.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Samuels</hi> care for the continuance of the memorial, in theſe words, <hi>Then Samuel took a ſtone,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>A practice that God himſelf had directed, to continue the memorial of his great Acts; and was practiced by <hi>Jacob:</hi> and <note place="margin">Joſh. 4. 5, 6.</note> here by <hi>Samuel,</hi> which he named <hi>Eben-ezer,</hi> the Stone of <note place="margin">Gen. 28. 18.</note> Help. <note place="margin">31. 15. 35. 14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe, though ſtones be very durable and laſting Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents, yet time, that is <hi>edax rerum,</hi> may conſume them, or otherwiſe they may be removed: therefore God was pleaſed to fix a memorial of his gracious Acts in time it ſelf, that ſo the renewing of that, might perpetuate the Memorial of them. To this end he had ſet apart fixt days, as the Paſſover, and the days of <hi>Purim</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Trophies and Momuments of Stone or Braſs, though the materials may be and continue, yet the Cauſe, Author and Reaſon of their erecting, may be utterly worn out. As the <hi>Pyramids</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Stonehinge</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> no certainty why or by whom placed. But when it's fixt on days in time itſelf, nothing can wear it out, till time be ſwallowed in eternity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:57697:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
There are three great National Deliverances mentioned in Scripture, each of which had its memorial-day appointed.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The Paſſover by Gods command. <note place="margin">Exod. 12.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Purim</hi> by <hi>Eſther</hi> and <hi>Mordecai.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eſth. 9.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. Dedication of the Temple, which Chriſt himſelf obſerved.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe ſet apart as monuments of thankfulneſs for <hi>Iſraels</hi> Deliverance from <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Bondage, <hi>Hamans</hi> Plot, and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylons</hi> Captivity.</p>
            <p>And ſhould we parallel <hi>Englands</hi> old and late Deliverances with theirs, we ſhould find that they come ſhort in nothing, but are in ſome Circumſtances more eminent and miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous.</p>
            <p>And therefore the Inſtitution of the fifth of <hi>November</hi> for an high and holy day, is a moſt juſtifiable Act; and the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of it a moſt neceſſary Duty on all true <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> good Subjects, and ſincere Proteſtants; wherein we call to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, confer of, and declare to others, and ſtir up our own hearts to a thankful admiration of Gods wonderful works in our deliverance. Let us ſay as <hi>Samuel. Hitherto hath God helped us:</hi> and with <hi>David, O how great is thy goodneſs! how terrible are thy works!</hi> and conſider with our ſelves what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <note place="margin">Pſ. 31. 15. 66. 3.</note> of perſons we ought to be in all holy and godly Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; And with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>What ſhall we render!</hi> And <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3. 11.</note> what is more fitting? Then ſince this is the Deliverance that God <note place="margin">Pſ. 116.</note> hath wrought, let us do, <hi>opus Dei in die ſuo,</hi> Rejoyce and be glad in it.</p>
            <p>O let us joyfully, thankfully and affectionately remember the Mercy of this deliverance vouchſaſed to us in our Forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; reflect upon the greatneſs of our Danger, and Gods wonderful goodneſs in our eſcape from it.</p>
            <p>Our Caſe was that of the Church, Men roſe up againſt, had <note place="margin">Pſ. 124.</note> ſwallowed us quick; and their miſchievous device, like proud and overflowing waters, againſt which there can be no defence, had gone over our ſoul; ſo that had not Gods mercy inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened, we had been a prey to their teeth; but bleſſed be God, our ſoul is eſcaped as a bird out of the ſnare of the Fowler. The Net was broken, and we were delivered, and all by the help
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:57697:21"/>
of the Name of the Lord, who made Heaven and Earth.</p>
            <p>In which caſe of theirs, as in ours, were joyned Cruelty, Malice, Violence, Policy, Subtlety, and an irreſiſtable Force, ſuch as is the overpowring of Fire and Water, that burns and deſtroys without Remedy.</p>
            <p>And herein ſee and conſider the greatneſs of Gods Mercy in this Deliverance. It was a great State-Mercy, but a greater Soul-Mercy; for hereby the glorious Goſpel of leſus Chriſt is continued to us. O ſay not of this, as <hi>Let</hi> of <hi>Zear, It is a little one.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 19. 20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Let this Mercy then be writ in the Records of our hearts, as well as Statutes, that as what <hi>Mordecai</hi> had done was read by <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> ſo this may be by us; not only that we may know it and minde it, but that we may as <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> did for <hi>Mirde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cai,</hi> and ſay, What hath been done for God? What ſhall we do for him?</p>
            <p>Let us therefore (I beſeech you) anſwer God's expectation, becauſe of this and all other his former and latter Deliverances, for therefore are we put in minde of them. And know we, that if we do not, we may expect that God will expoſtulate with us as he did with <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>I brought you out from Egypt, and brought you forth out of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Judg. 10. 8, 9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>the houſe of bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>And I delivered you out of the hand of the Egyptians, and out of the hand of all that oppreſſed you, and drave them out from before you, and gave you to <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>And I ſaid unto you, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Lord your God; ſear not the gods of the Amorites, in whoſe land you dwell; but you have not obeyed my voice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, we juſtly may fear that he will anſwer us in our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties and Dangers when we cry unto him, as he did them:</p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>Did not I deliver you from the Egyptians, and from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morties, from the children of A<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>, and from the Philiſtins?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Judg. 10. 11, 12, 13, 14.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>The Sidonians alſo and the Amalekites, and the Meabites did oppreſs you, and you cried unto me, and I delivered you out of their hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. <hi>Yet you have forſaken me, and ſerved other gods, wherefore I will deliver you no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. Go and cry unto the Gods which ye have choſen, let them <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:57697:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
you in the time of your tribulation.</hi> Change we the names, and the things agree.</p>
            <p>Let us then anſwer God's expectation, ſince God by this great Deliverance hath continued his Goſpel, (and, O Lord, continue it to us and our Poſterities.) O let us</p>
            <p n="1">1. Prize it: As that which exalts a Nation, lifts it up, as it did <hi>Capernaum,</hi> unto Heaven. <hi>He hath ſhewn his word unto Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob: his ſtatutes and his judgments unto Iſrael. He hath not done</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 147. 19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>ſo with any Nation, and as for his judgments, they have not knewn them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Improve it. Otherwiſe it will prove a Judgment to us; yea, the Judgment; <hi>This is the condemnation, that light is come into the world, and men love darkneſs.</hi> The neglect of the Goſpel <note place="margin">Joh. 3. 19.</note> caſts down to Hell, and makes our eſcape impoſſible. <note place="margin">Mat. 13 50.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Walk worthy of it, anſwerable unto it, and to God's ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation <note place="margin">Heb. 2 3.</note> from us, becauſe of it. <hi>Let your converſation be as becometh the Goſpel. Walk worthy of the Vocation wherewith we</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 27.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. 1.</note> 
               <hi>are called. And thereby adorn the Doctrine of God our Saviour in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 10.</note> 
               <hi>all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To theſe ends <hi>Joſhua</hi> minds <hi>Iſrael</hi> of what God had done for them; and amongſt other things, <hi>How Balak, Son of Zippor</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joſh. 24. 9. 10.</note> 
               <hi>King of Moab, aroſe and warred againſt them, and called Balaam the Son of Beor to curſe them: But he would not hearken unto Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam, but he bleſſed them ſtill, and delivered them out of Balak's hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And after many other ſignal Mercies ſhewed to them, he concludes with God's expectation from them. <hi>Now therefore</hi> 
               <note place="margin">14.</note> 
               <hi>fear the Lord, and ſerve him in ſincerity and in truth, and put away the gods which your Fathers ſerved on the other ſide the flood, and in Egypt; and ſerve ye the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as it was then, ſo it is ſtill; God's expectation from us upon our Deliverancs is, <hi>That we ſhould ſerve hem without fear,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 1. 74. 75.</note> 
               <hi>in holineſs and righteouſneſs before him all the days of our life.</hi> Not that we might exclaim againſt the foulneſs of the Fact, or inveigh againſt the Monſters that were the Actors of it, or bleſs our ſelves for ſo fair an Eſcape, or keep a day in the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial of it; much leſs were we liberate, that we ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Libertines: To ſit down to Eat, and to Drink Healths af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter new and unſeeming Modes, and to riſe up to Play; But
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:57697:22"/>
that we might ſerve God in Holineſs and Righteouſneſs all the days of our life.</p>
            <p>Serve we ought, though we ſhould not be delivered; as the holy Martyrs did: The three Princes in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Job</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved he would, though God ſhould kill him. How much <note place="margin">Job 11. 15.</note> more ought we, when we are delivered, (and that aforehand, by way of prevention) to render unto God Evangelical and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable Service and Sacrifice of Thankfulneſs and Love!</p>
            <p>Serve Him we muſt then, in Holineſs and Righteouſneſs, and that not only in the ſight of men, but before him; and that not for a ſpirt or fit, but all the days of our Life. Let not our Holineſs be as the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> in our Fringes and Phylacte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, in outward expreſſions, in hearing the Lectures of the Law, no matter how we live. Let not our Holineſs be like the <hi>Sadducees,</hi> live indifferently well; but believe neither Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, nor look for any Reſurrection: Not like <hi>Agrippa</hi>'s, who was half perſwaded. Not in Holineſs only, not in Righteouſneſs only, but in both, and that for ever.</p>
            <p>And as for our preſent deportment,</p>
            <p>Let us rejoice in the day which the Lord hath made.</p>
            <p>When God calls to faſting, it is a ſin to feaſt; and when to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing, it's a ſin to mourn. <note place="margin">Iſa. 20. 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Had this Plot taken effect to the deſire and expectation of the <note place="margin">Neh 8. 9, 10.</note> Projectors, there would have been a Jubile in <hi>Askalon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shall we not then rejoyce, and be glad outwardly in body, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in Spirit? let our joy be ſuch as may be ſeen and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by face, voice, countenance, habit and geſture; <hi>bind the ſacrifice with cords unto the horns of the Altar. Let our hearts</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 118. 27.</note> 
               <hi>be glad, and our Glory, our tongue rejoyce. Bleſs the Lord</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 16. 9.</note> 
               <hi>in the Congregation. Let the Singers go before, and the Players</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 68. 25. 26.</note> 
               <hi>on the Inſtruments follow after.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us ſay with the <hi>Pſalmiſt, My lips ſhall greatly rejoyce when I ſing unto thee: and my ſoul which thou haſt redeemed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Tongue alſo ſhall talk of thy righteouſneſs all the day long: for they are confounded, they are brought unto ſhame that ſeek my hurt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us be ſure that our joy and rejoycing may be in the Lord; ſuch as God may be pleaſed with.</p>
            <p>Not in the day of our Kings deliverance, make our ſelves
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:57697:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
or others ſick with bottles of Wine; not ſit down to eat, and <note place="margin">Hoſ. 7. 5.</note> drink healths, and riſe up to play; for with ſuch mirth God is <note place="margin">Exod. 32. 6.</note> not well pleaſed, but doth threaten to ſpread the dung of ſuch <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 5.</note> feaſts upon their faces, and curſe their Bleſſings. <note place="margin">Mal. 2. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now that our rejoycing may pleaſe God, we muſt begin with <hi>Halelujah,</hi> and end with <hi>Hoſannah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> gives us a pattern; <hi>Open to me the gates of Righteouſneſs</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 118. 19. 25.</note> 
               <hi>I will go into them, and I will praiſe the Lord. Save now, O Lord, I beſeech thee: I beſeech thee ſend now proſperity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus ſhould we be joyful in Gods houſe of prayer; but ſtill <note place="margin">Iſal. 56. 7.</note> remember to rejoyce in trembling, becauſe we know not what a <note place="margin">Pſal. 2. 11.</note> day may bring forth, <hi>Prov.</hi> 27. 1.</p>
            <p>Joyn we then praiſe and prayer; thankſgiving for the mercies we have received, and prayers for the mercies we ſtill ſtand in need of.</p>
            <p>All the Pſalms are reducible to two words, <hi>Halelujah</hi> and <hi>Hoſanna,</hi> not to be ſevered. Neither of theſe, if alone, will proſper, nor are acceptable when not united.</p>
            <p>O then! let us now do both; praiſe God for our former and latter Deliverances from the many attempts of our Popiſh Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Invaſion, Gunpowder Treaſon, many pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of bleſſed memory, and our own deliverance from their truly real Plot, and intended Miſchief (which God preſerve us from).</p>
            <p>Pray unto him for the continuance of his gracions providence over us, and protection of us. For, ſuppoſe that all were dead that ſought our lives: Say they are: but is the Devil dead too? If he be not, it ſteds not much if they were.</p>
            <p>His Powder Mill will ſtill be going, he will be as buſie as ever in turning over all his devices, in turning himſelf into as many ſhapes as <hi>Proteus;</hi> and all to turn us to miſchief. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have, and ſhall have always cauſe to follow our <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelujah</hi>'s with our <hi>Hoſanna</hi>'s, pray, as well as praiſe, in reference to our Popiſh Adverſaries; That God would abate their pride, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwage their malice, and confound their devices; That the Life of our moſt Gracious King may be preſerved; the Proteſtant Religion, our Lives and Liberties ſecured from all the deviliſh attempts of our implacable enemies the Jeſuits and their Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:57697:23"/>
Oh let all that are now in the Houſe of the Lord, eſpecially thoſe amongſt us that are of the Houſe of the Lord, earneſtly and affectionately pray for our moſt Gracious King, as in duty we are bound, becauſe God commands it; and out of reſpect to <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 2.</note> our own tranquility that is wrapt up in his ſafety, that God would continue forth his goodneſs towards him, and bleſs him with length of days, with ſtrength of health, with the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of all Honour and happineſs, with Terror in the eyes of his Enemies, with Grace in the eyes of his Subjects, with what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever <hi>David</hi> or <hi>Solomon,</hi> or any other King that was happy, was bleſſed with, a long continuance of the Peace and Glory of his Kingdoms on earth, and with the eternal Kingdom of Glory and Peace in the higheſt Heaven. To which God bring us all for his infinite mercy, through Jeſus our bleſſed Saviour. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:57697:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
