<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mr. Chutes petition of appeal consists of these nine points</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33140</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4279</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39217</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18275987</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18275987</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107287</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A33140)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107287)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1629:117)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mr. Chutes petition of appeal consists of these nine points</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 broadside.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Chute, Challoner, 1658-1685 --  Trials, litigation, etc.</term>
               <term>Chute, Challoner, 1658-1685 --  Estate.</term>
               <term>Decedents' estates --  England --  Hampshire.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:107287:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->
            <head>Mr. CHUTES Petition Of Appeal conſiſts of theſe Nine Points.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <list>
                  <label>The <hi>1ſt.</hi> point to be reheard (in Caſe the Lady <hi>Dacres</hi> is reheard) to a point decreed in Chancery againſt his late Father, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </label>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1ſt.</hi> The 5000 <hi>l.</hi> and Intereſt which ought not to have been; there being no breach of Covenant.</item>
                  <label>The <hi>2d. 3d.</hi> and <hi>4th.</hi> points to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain that the <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery</hi> has aparently diſobey'd the <hi>Lords</hi> Order, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </label>
                  <item>  
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2d.</hi> In allowing Mr. <hi>Chute</hi> but 380 <hi>l.</hi> for the value of the Legacy, which as well by the Decree in 66, as by the Lords Order, upon his Appeal in 1680. was ſettled at 900 <hi>l.</hi> and the particulars of the Legacy are ſo undervalued, that for one of thoſe particulars, making up the 380 <hi>l.</hi> (valued by the Chancery but at 40 <hi>l.</hi>) he has offered the whole 380 <hi>l. It appears as to part of the Goods, that the Perſons procured to make this new Valuation; only made it by what they gueſſed the Goods,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>might be worth</hi> 20 <hi>Years ago, (having never ſeen them before) as to the reſt of them (not in being) they are va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued by what the Lady</hi> Dacres <hi>her ſelf told the Witneſſes of them.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>3d.</hi> In not charging the Lady with the Summ of 1232 <hi>l.</hi> that ſhe receiv'd out of his Eſtate under her ſequeſtration, till the end of the Account, in which the Chancery ought to have charged her with it at the times ſhe received it (the Decree for the maintenance being reverſed, which before had juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied her keeping it) and the rather for that Mr. <hi>Chute</hi> pays her Intereſt all the time, <hi>and Intereſt upon Intereſt for a great part of her demand.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>4th.</hi> In not allowing any more then 2500 <hi>l.</hi> for the value of the Timber, tho proved worth 7. or 8000 <hi>l.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <label>The <hi>5th.</hi> and <hi>6th.</hi> points to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief againſt the late order in Chancery concerning.</label>
                  <item>  
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>5th.</hi> The Goods that the Lady poſſeſt her ſelf of at the Vine, and in <hi>Newport-Street,</hi> by virtue of her ſequeſtration, for which it is apparent, ſhe doth not charge her ſelf; nor the Chancery would not charge her with a quarter of the value; <hi>Mr.</hi> Chute <hi>having offered</hi> 200 <hi>l. for one parcel for which he is not allowed any more than five pound, and the ſame in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other particulars.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>6th.</hi> The 244 <hi>l.</hi> coſts of the former Suit with Intereſt (with which the Chancery has charged Mr. <hi>Chute</hi>) for 18 years, tho they were not taxed till Mr. <hi>Chute</hi> (the Father's) Death, and therefore ought not to have been taxed at all, it being a Perſonal wrong if any, and dying with him; there is not one Preſident in Chancery, where it was ever given thus, but very many to the contrary, and it comes to 500 <hi>l.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <label>The <hi>7th. 8th.</hi> and <hi>9th.</hi> points to have relief againſt the ſame Order charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lady <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres</hi> but with.</label>
                  <item>  
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>7th.</hi> 20 <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> for the Rent of the Vine-Houſe, proved worth (with other things that ſhe enjoyed) 50 <hi>l. per Annum.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>8th.</hi> 20 <hi>l. per Annum.</hi> for Fire-Wood, proved worth 70 <hi>l. per Annum.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>9th.</hi> And nothing for willfully under-litting ſome part of the Eſtate.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>After all to put an end to this unnatural diſpute between Mr. <hi>Chute</hi> and his Grand-mother the Lady <hi>Dacres,</hi> and to avoid troubling the Lords in Parliament further therein, Mr. <hi>Chute</hi> is ready to ſubmit the whole matter in diſpute, from the Death of his Grand-father to this preſent time, to the judgment of two Lords to be indifferently choſen between the Lady <hi>Dacres</hi> and him, and will give 5000 <hi>l.</hi> ſecurity toſtand to their Award.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
