<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The character of a turbulent, pragmatical Jesuit and factious Romish priest</title>
            <author>Care, Henry, 1646-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-01">2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33763</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C508</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5332</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13687169</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13687169</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101352</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A33763)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101352)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 841:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The character of a turbulent, pragmatical Jesuit and factious Romish priest</title>
                  <author>Care, Henry, 1646-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Langley Curtis ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by Henry Care.  Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>"Licensed, October 15, 1678."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jesuits --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-06</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-07</date>
            <label>Jason Colman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-07</date>
            <label>Jason Colman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101352:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101352:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE
CHARACTER
OF
A Turbulent, Pragmatical
JESUIT
AND
FACTIOUS
Romiſh Prieſt.</p>
            <p>Licenſed, <hi>October</hi> 15. 1678.</p>
            <p>LONDON<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <hi>Printed for</hi> Langley Curtis, <hi>in</hi> Goat-Court
<hi>on</hi> Ludgate-hill. 1678.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:101352:2"/>
            <head>The Character of a Turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
Pragmatical Jeſuite.</head>
            <p>A Turbulent Pragmatical JESUITE, is
the <hi>Bell-weather</hi> of the <hi>Roman</hi> Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds
Flock; a moſt truſty <hi>Janizary</hi>
to the Triple-Crown. A zealous
<hi>Hector</hi> for Popery, that wherever
he comes, plays the <hi>Devil</hi> for <hi>Gods-ſake.</hi> An Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical
<hi>Granadier</hi> to ſcatter the <hi>Wild<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fire</hi> of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention;
or, a Religious <hi>Flambeau</hi> to put King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
into a <hi>Combuſtion;</hi> ſo through-pac'd a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick,
that he has left off to be a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi>
and inſtead of the Evangelical Duties, <hi>Peace,
Obedience,</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> recommends <hi>Rebellion, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>
and <hi>Murder,</hi> as the beſt expedients to promote
<hi>Holy Church.</hi> The diſtinguiſhing <hi>Badge</hi> of other
Papiſts is <hi>Superſtition,</hi> but of him <hi>Sedition</hi> and
<hi>Subtlety,</hi> not <hi>Ignorance</hi> the Mother of his <hi>Devotion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He uſurps the Title of JESUITE, juſt as their
Popes are obſerved to have choſen <hi>Sirnames,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly
contrary to their Tempers; as, the moſt
Hatchet-fac'd <hi>Formoſus,</hi> the moſt prophane
<hi>Pius,</hi> the moſt cruel <hi>Clemens, &amp;c.</hi> For certainly,
never did any more interfere with the ſteps of the
<hi>Bleſſed Jeſus,</hi> than thoſe that blaſphemouſly call
themſelves his Companions or SOCIETY. He
diſclaimed his <hi>Kingdome to be of this World;</hi> but
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101352:2"/>
their whole endeavors aim no farther. Riches,
Dominion, Pomp and Glory, are the <hi>Butts</hi> they
ſhoot at; and if ever they appear <hi>Heavenly,</hi> by
tampering with Affairs of <hi>State,</hi> they mix <hi>Heaven
and Earth</hi> together, to bring all into <hi>Confuſion.</hi>
Let them magnifie the Travels of their Saint <hi>Xa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verius,</hi>
and boaſt the Multitude of Heathens they
have converted; look narrowly into that intrigue,
and you'll find it only an <hi>Huckſterly Charity</hi> of
mercenary Pedlars, rather than a free offer of
<hi>glad tidings.</hi> They did but <hi>Traffick</hi> to the <hi>Indies,</hi>
to <hi>Barter</hi> Religion for <hi>Gold;</hi> never car'd for
Preaching to <hi>Beggarly</hi> Nations, but always car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
the ſound of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> to <hi>Regions</hi> that had
rich <hi>Mines</hi> or precious <hi>Quarries,</hi> to make ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious
Returns. Not to mention their Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
in Baptizing far greater numbers in <hi>Blood</hi>
than <hi>Water,</hi> and making the <hi>Goſpel</hi> odious to thoſe
<hi>dark</hi> Souls, by their <hi>perfidious and Traiterous
Practiſes;</hi> for which, the King of <hi>Japan</hi> long ago,
and the Emperor of <hi>China</hi> ſince, baniſht them
their Territories, chooſing rather to relapſe into
honeſt Paganiſm, than entertain <hi>Truth</hi> ſullied by
ſuch <hi>Knaviſh</hi> Impoſtors.</p>
            <p>He owes his Original to <hi>Ignatius Loyala</hi> a Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
Souldier, about the year 1540. and though
found out long ſince the invention of the <hi>Cannon,</hi>
has not done leſs miſchief than that <hi>Butchering
Engine. Luther</hi> had now broke the Ice, and the
<hi>Dawn</hi> of reviv'd Learning having open'd mens
Eyes to ſee through the <hi>groſſer Cheats</hi> of Ignorant
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101352:3"/>
Monks; the Pope had no other play, but to
cheriſh this <hi>Society,</hi> who having devoted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
by a <hi>particular Vow</hi> to his Intereſts, employ'd
all their excellent parts and skill in the <hi>Sciences,</hi>
(wherein their diligence ſoon rendred them fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous)
to bolſter up his <hi>tottering <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations.</hi> The
better to effect this, laughing at the <hi>Naſty Auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities</hi>
of their more Melancholly Religioniſts, they
applied themſelves to the <hi>Politicks,</hi> and a ſociable
kind of life; to underſtand not only <hi>Languages</hi>
and <hi>Arts,</hi> but <hi>Paſſions, Humours, Prejudices,</hi> and
(as they ſpeak in Courts) <hi>Blind-ſides,</hi> in one word,
<hi>Perſons.</hi> Thus they became falſe Keys, to open
Princes <hi>Cabinets,</hi> and pry into their Councels,
by their <hi>oily</hi> Tongues, and plyable Behaviour; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuating
themſelves into the affections of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wary,
as gently, as malevolent <hi>Stars</hi> dart their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence,
or blaſting <hi>Mildews</hi> ſlide into the boſom
of a flower. In his Seminary, he acts the part of
a <hi>Fox;</hi> abroad, a <hi>Spaniel;</hi> but in the Inquiſition,
a <hi>Lion Rampant.</hi> The Mask which in <hi>Spain</hi> or
<hi>Italy</hi> he wears on his Heart, in Countreys he
calls Heretical he puts upon his Face; varying
<hi>ſhapes</hi> oftner, than a Strumpet ſhifts her Lodgings;
now a Courtier, to morrow a Souldier, then a
Cobler, by and by a Weaver; a <hi>Gallant</hi> amongſt
the Ladies, an <hi>Atheiſt</hi> with the Wits, and a <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi>
when he aſſembles with Friends at the <hi>Bull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and-Mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He regards the other duller Litters of <hi>Cloiſter'd
Cubbs,</hi> with an eye of Contempt, and devours or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101352:3"/>
eats them out of Credit (if planted neer them)
as faſt as a <hi>Pike</hi> does the ſmaller fry in a Fiſh-pond.
Indeed his Colledge is always furniſht with ſome
one <hi>Profeſſor</hi> in every <hi>Faculty,</hi> excellently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſht;
and the whole Society conſiſts of ſelect
perſons, either of extraordinary <hi>natural</hi> and <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired
parts,</hi> great <hi>Birth, Alliance,</hi> and <hi>Intereſts</hi>
abroad, or Heirs to large Fortunes; and the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,
ever govern the two latter, well knowing
how to make uſe of ſuch Tools for their main
deſigns, which are Aggrandizing the Court of
<hi>Rome,</hi> ſpreading Popiſh Doctrines, wheadling in
of <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> deſtroying, weakning, or <hi>dividing</hi>
Proteſtants, and heaping up <hi>wealth</hi> to their own
Seminaries. Hence not only the <hi>Reformed,</hi> but
the <hi>Dominicans, Franciſcans,</hi> and other <hi>Catholick</hi>
Brotherhoods, apprehending the growing great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
of this <hi>Leviathan-Order;</hi> nay, his Holineſs
himſelf, in the traverſe of the buſineſs, is but
their <hi>Vaſſal,</hi> and apt (like Conjurers) to dread
theſe buſie <hi>Imps,</hi> which himſelf firſt raiſed to Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief
others. Nor has it been the leaſt skill and
prudence of the <hi>Conclave,</hi> for the laſt Age, to
keep out any of this Fraternity from mounting
the <hi>Infallible Chair,</hi> left they ſhould Intail the
<hi>Popedome</hi> on its Members, and rifle the Neſts of
the Monks, to enrich their own <hi>Hives.</hi> And if
their own <hi>Tribe</hi> be thus jealous of them, what
ſentiments others ought to have for them, will not
be difficult to determine by any that has read their
<hi>deteſtable</hi> Writings and Poſitions, of <hi>Depoſing</hi> and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101352:4"/>
               <hi>Murdering</hi> Excommunicated Princes, abſolving
Subjects from their <hi>Allegiance,</hi> Faith not to be
kept with Hereticks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the common Popiſh Prieſt, though oft he has
not ſo much Learning, yet he puts in hard for an equal
ſhare of Malignity, being a Ghoſtly Factor to Retail out
his Holineſs's braided Wares; a kind of Spiritual <hi>Kidnapper</hi>
for Souls: One might take him for a <hi>Conjurer;</hi> for he
uſes an <hi>unknown</hi> Tongue, tranſacts moſt of his Buſineſs
in <hi>Hugger-mugger,</hi> comes in ſecretly, and <hi>crawls</hi> up and
down in <hi>Corners</hi> like a Serpent, and with a few <hi>frightful
words,</hi> as <hi>Hereſie, Purgatory, Catholick Cauſe, Infallibility,</hi>
and the like, Transforms people as he liſts, and <hi>Jilts</hi> them
firſt of their <hi>Wits,</hi> and next of their <hi>Money:</hi> For though
he pretends 'tis in pure kindneſs to your <hi>Soul,</hi> yet ſtill the
Plot is upon your <hi>Purſe;</hi> and therefore where he meets
with a <hi>fat Convert,</hi> he ſticks to him as cloſe as <hi>Ivie</hi> to the
<hi>Oak;</hi> and for the ſame reaſon too, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſuck out <hi>Sap</hi>
for his own Support and Maintainance. Thus he <hi>ſwitches
and ſpurs</hi> an honeſt Gentleman, or <hi>devout Lady,</hi> through
thick and thin, till the poor Soul look as <hi>lean</hi> and wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedly,
as if ridden Seven years by a <hi>Night-mare.</hi> The
Reins he manages them with, are <hi>Confeſſion</hi> and <hi>Abſolution,</hi>
whereby he becomes Maſter of their Secrets; and if they
will not <hi>pace</hi> as he would have them, on goes the <hi>Snaffle</hi> of
a ſevere <hi>Penance,</hi> to make them more eaſily rul'd.</p>
            <p>He makes a perpetual Din of true Religion, and the
Catholick Faith; but 'tis Reſtitution of all the old Abbey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands
that his fingers itch for; and if ever he get into the
Saddle, 'tis will if his <hi>quondam</hi> Patrons may be admitted
to hold the ſtirrop. In the mean time he ſometimes
makes uſe of them, as blind men of their ſtaves, to thruſt
them into Plaſhes and Sloughs, before they'll tread them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves;
and run them againſt Poſts, to ſave knocking their
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101352:4"/>
own heads. When any Combuſtible matter is to be fired;
theſe cunning Petardiers ram it into the hollow Cranium
of ſome zealous or deſperate Votary, and having enflam'd
the Fuzee of his Tongue, ſhoot him againſt Government,
not caring though he breaks himſelf into a Thouſand pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:
For though the Jeſuite has out-done them in the
Theory of Rebellion and Treaſon, the Monks preceded
him long in the Practical part. Was it not a Monk that
Poyſon'd our King <hi>John?</hi> was it not <hi>Bernardinus</hi> a Fryar
Mendicant, that <hi>Anno</hi> 1313. poyſon'd the Emperour <hi>H.</hi>
the 7th with the Conſecrated Hoſt? A Crime that might
ſeem to diſpute a ſhape of Guilt with that of the Proto-Rebels,
the faln Angels: For ſurely for a Prieſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to poyſon
his God (as they hold it to be) thereby to murder his
Prince, was ſuch an exquiſite piece of wickedneſs, that all
the Wit of Hell could never ſcrue any to an higher pitch.
Was it not <hi>Clement</hi> a Jacobin Fryar, that murdered <hi>Henry</hi>
the Third of <hi>France</hi> with a Sanctified Knife, to whoſe
praiſe Pope <hi>Sextus Quintus</hi> dedicated a Panegytical Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration?
And for us nearer home, hear what a Reverend Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late
aſſerts<hi>—This we may obſerve</hi>
(ſays he) <hi>That no Treaſon was ever
attempted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Carlton, <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Chicheſter, <hi>in his Book I<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> itu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed,</hi> A Thankful Remembrance of Gods Mercy. <hi>Printed</hi> Anno 1630. page 246.</note> 
               <hi>without a Romiſh Prieſt.
The Treaſons attempted in</hi> England,
<hi>have that proper and peculiar Mark,
to have a Prieſt in the Practice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet no doubt ſuch kind of Romiſh <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> will ſtill
tell us they quit their Seminaries, and come hither, hazard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
their lives meerly for our <hi>Souls health:</hi> That they <hi>love</hi>
us intirely, and deſire nothing but our <hi>Salvation:</hi> and a
thouſand other endearing Expreſſions.—But <hi>Good words
butter no Parſueps.</hi> All theſe <hi>ſugared Complements</hi> will
but put diſcreet men in mind of that Fable of the <hi>Birds
and Fowler:</hi> The Fowler in a cold morning caught good
ſtore of them, and ſtill <hi>nipt</hi> them on the head and put them
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101352:5"/>
up: His eyes in the mean time <hi>watering</hi> with the ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
of the Air; <hi>See,</hi> ſaid one of the Fowls, <hi>how the good
man pities us, he weeps to ſee us taken. Ah,</hi> ſaid the other,
<hi>look not to his Eyes, but to his Hands, there you ſhall ſee
what pity we finde from him.</hi> Or at leaſt may remember
us of St. <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> ſure Rule, to diſcern a <hi>Wolf from a
Sheep:</hi> 'Tis poſſible (ſays he) for the Wolf to clothe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
with the Sheeps <hi>Skin,</hi> ſo as that cannot deſcry him;
and to imitate the Sheeps <hi>Voice,</hi> ſo as that ſhall not betray
him, but <hi>look to his Chaps,</hi> and they cannot deceive you:
For you ſhall not finde either Graſs in the Wolfs mouth,
nor Blood in the Sheeps. Let us never be ſo raſh, or
fondly credulous, as to miſtake one for the other.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:101352:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
