<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The darkness of atheisme expelled by the light of nature, or, The existence of a deity, and his creation and government of the world demonstrated from reason and the light of nature only : with an appendix touching the most proper method of preaching the Gospel among the heathens / Englished by H.C.</title>
            <author>Care, Henry, 1646-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-01">2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33772</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C509</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7365</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13099381</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13099381</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97398</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A33772)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97398)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 410:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The darkness of atheisme expelled by the light of nature, or, The existence of a deity, and his creation and government of the world demonstrated from reason and the light of nature only : with an appendix touching the most proper method of preaching the Gospel among the heathens / Englished by H.C.</title>
                  <author>Care, Henry, 1646-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[35], 82 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for D. Brown ... and T. Benskin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Original title undetermined.</note>
                  <note>Written by Henry Care. Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Atheism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Atheism --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97398:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97398:1"/>
            <p>The Darkneſs of ATHEISME Expelled by the LIGHT of NATURE OR, The <hi>EXISTENCE</hi> of a DEITY: AND His Creation and Government OF THE WORLD. Demonſtrated from Reaſon, and the Light of Nature only. With an <hi>Appendix</hi> touching the moſt proper Method of Preaching the Goſpel among the Heathens.</p>
            <p>Engliſhed by <hi>H. C.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Animis, non Auribus.</q>
            <q>Nullus in Inferno eſt <hi>Atheos,</hi> ante fuit.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>D. Brown</hi> at the <hi>Black-Swan</hi> without <hi>Temple-barr,</hi> and <hi>T. Benskin</hi> in St. <hi>Brides-Church-yard,</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <pb facs="tcp:97398:2"/>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97398:2"/>
                  <l>Quiſquis profundâ mente veſtigat verum</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>upit<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> nullis ile devijs falli</l>
                  <l>In ſe revolvat intimi Lucem viſûs</l>
                  <l>Longòſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in Orbem cogat infle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctens motus</l>
                  <l>Animùm<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> doceat quicquid extra molitur</l>
                  <l>Suis Retrorſum poſſidere The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauris</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Quod atra dudum texit erroris nubes</l>
                  <l>Lucebit ipſo perſpicacius Phaebo</l>
               </lg>
               <bibl>Boet. de Conſol. Philoſ. Lib. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Metr.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:97398:3"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who e're profoundly ſearches after truth,</l>
                  <l>And would not be miſs-led by ſtragling paths;</l>
                  <l>Let him turn on himſelf his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt eye,</l>
                  <l>And bend into a Ring his rang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoughts,</l>
                  <l>Making his Soul ſee what ſhe ſeeks abroad</l>
                  <l>In her own native Treaſures ſtor'd up lies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then what errors black Cloud did hide, will ſoon</l>
                  <l>Shine clearer than the Sun it ſelf at Noon.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:97398:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THe publiſhing a Book to prove the <hi>Exiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of a Deity</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt People that have all Inrolled themſelves <hi>Chriſtians</hi> at the Font, may poſſibly be thought unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary; but it muſt be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch as are ſtrangers to this unhappy Age of ours,
<pb facs="tcp:97398:4"/>
where it is eſteem'd by too many a piece of <hi>wit to be Prophane,</hi> and all things <hi>ſacred</hi> have been made ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of Scoff &amp; Drollery; wherein <hi>Atheiſts</hi> have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared broad-faced, and with a prodigious impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence defied Heaven in the ſight of the Sun, underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to diſpute <hi>Divinity</hi> out of the World by <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and levying Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt that Power which gave them Being;
<pb facs="tcp:97398:4"/>
how requiſite then it is now to ſhew the abuſed World, that theſe <hi>Godleſs ones</hi> have all this while committed a Rape on their own <hi>Reaſon,</hi> who freely of her ſelf (would they but hear her ſpeak) leads them directly to the knowledge of a <hi>Deity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is it only theſe <hi>open Ranters</hi> that we are to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, there is a ſort of <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret demure Atheiſts,</hi> who verbally acknowledge a Deity, and perhaps make
<pb facs="tcp:97398:5"/>
the moſt zealous pretenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Religion too, but Hearts being not really poſſeſt with a firm belief and ſtable apprehenſion of a <hi>moſt Juſt and Holy Power, that being ever preſent takes an Account of, and will one day ſeverely judge all their Actions,</hi> They thereupon give no other Check to their exorbitant Luſts, than what external or politick reſpects may Bridle them in with, whence proceeds
<pb facs="tcp:97398:5"/>
that Innundation of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs that at this day o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verwhelms the World, and though theſe laſt may hypocritically Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit a veneration of the <hi>holy Scriptures,</hi> there is only this difference between them and the other Crew; that whereas the others diſclaim all regard to thoſe <hi>ſacred Oracles;</hi> theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to believe them, but really do not.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:97398:6"/>
To meet with them both, we recommend this brief <hi>Treatiſe</hi> to publick view, which not with <hi>flouriſhes of Rhetorick,</hi> or muſtering up <hi>Authorities, Fathers, Philoſophers,</hi> &amp;c. But meerly by Natures Light, and in an undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Mathematical Method,</hi> evinces <hi>the exiſtences of a Deity;</hi> which once firmly and unfeignedly believed with the neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences thereof would ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:97398:6"/>
much ſtop the Torrent of Impiety in Mens Lives, and prepare them for the reception of, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to other Articles of the <hi>Chriſtian Faith</hi> and <hi>Goſpel Duties;</hi> The main part of it is an Arrow bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from the great <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinus</hi> his quiver; He that was lately Royal Profeſſor of <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> when he firſt ſent it abroad in its Roman Dreſs 'twas wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comed with the applauſes
<pb facs="tcp:97398:7"/>
of the <hi>Sorbon</hi> and general approbation of the learned World for its perſpicuous Brevity, Orthodoxneſs, and cloſe Cogent Method of arguing.</p>
            <p>What entertainment it may meet with in this courſer Engliſh Garb, I cannot Divine, yet dare venture to ſay, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall Seriouſly and Underſtandingly read it over, cannot but confeſs a Deity, or diſown his
<pb facs="tcp:97398:7"/>
Reaſon, and muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge a <hi>God,</hi> unleſs he will deny himſelf to be <hi>Man.</hi> If it prove in the leaſt uſeful to reduce any to their Allegiance to their <hi>Soveraign Creator,</hi> I ſhall eſteem my pains moſt <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageouſly</hi> laid out in the Tranſlation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conclude with implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his <hi>Infinite Majeſty,</hi> that he would by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding a Bleſſing to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it, render it <hi>Effectual</hi> to that deſired end.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:97398:8"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>BY <hi>Dan. Brown</hi> next door to the Sign of the <hi>Queens Head</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> You may be furniſh'd with moſt ſorts of Plays, both New and Old, to be ſold, or lent to read.</p>
            <p>Where you may be alſo fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with all ſorts of Statio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Wares; As, Indentures, Recoveries, Blanck-Bonds, and Blanck-Writs of all ſorts; Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-Books, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Writings fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ingroſſed and Copied; and the Beſt Ink for Recoveries or Records.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:97398:8"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE OR INTRODUCTION.</head>
            <p>HOW ſpreading and Epidemical the Contagion of Atheiſm is grown of late, there are few ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py as to be ignorant, That
<pb facs="tcp:97398:9"/>
the ſame not only ſtrikes at the Root of all Religion, but takes away all ſenſe of Good and Evil, all Truſt and Obligations amongſt Men; and conſequently is moſt deſtructive to humane Society and Government, is no leſs evident: To put ſome ſtop to this fatal Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent which thus threatens all things ſacred and civil with a Deluge, not a few have attempted with endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours no leſs laudable than
<pb facs="tcp:97398:9"/>
laborious: Yet ſcarce at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining that ſucceſs as was wiſhed, by reaſon of their not proceeding in ſuch a Method of Proof, as the Adverſaries (who muſt be allowed to chooſe their Weapons, or they will never acknowledge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves vanquiſhed) have thought fit to expect for their Conviction; The authority of ſacred Scri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptures, which pious Souls devoutly reverence, They
<pb facs="tcp:97398:10"/>
Impudently deny; The ſenſe all Nations have of a Deity, they alledge is only a general cheat, and a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy Fancy blown into credulous heads by ſubtile Polititions. The Beauty and Harmony of the world they'l tell you, is only cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the curious motion of Dancing Atoms, or the apt, yet fortuitous concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Actives with Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſives: In brief, (for who without horrour can relate
<pb facs="tcp:97398:10"/>
their Blaſphemies?) what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you offer of that kind, they evade; yet ſtill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend highly to Reaſon, and intimate they would be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfyed, could they but meet with ſuch Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions might be neceſſarily concluſive to their Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, and enforce their Aſſent: And certainly, the goodneſs, and Infinite Mercy of God, (ever le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible in all his dealings with Mankind,) doth moſt il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtriouſly
<pb facs="tcp:97398:11"/>
diſplay it ſelf in this, That even when they not only (like deſperate Traytors) renounce all Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to Him, but deny his very Eſſence, from whence they received their own: Yet ſtill he affords them Natures Light, and deprives them not of thoſe common Principles, which if ſeriouſly conſulted, are able to reduce them from their horrid Phrenſie, and evidently demonſtrate the
<pb facs="tcp:97398:11"/>
Exiſtence of a Deity that Created the World, and continually Governs it by his Providence, and whom to acknowledge Love, and obey, is not only their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but their glory, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and chiefeſt Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs.</p>
            <p>To make it appear that Nature of it ſelf doth ſo far enlighten, and conduct us, is our preſent deſign, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the more to comply with their Humour, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends
<pb facs="tcp:97398:12"/>
ſo high a value for Reaſon, we have choſen to proceed in a Synthetick Method, familiar in <hi>Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry,</hi> whoſe Students glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the infalibility of their Demonſtrations, and may juſtly boaſt more certainty than the Votaries of any other Science, A happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs they principally owe to that excellent Mode of Arguing by <hi>Axioms</hi> and <hi>Theorems,</hi> which in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent Leaves, we have
<pb facs="tcp:97398:12"/>
endeavoured to imitate: Not doubting but the ſame may be practicable in all other Learning, as well as the <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> and that with greater ſucceſs than can be expected, from the vulgar <hi>Logick,</hi> or wrangling <hi>Sophiſtry</hi> of the Schools: The Foundation is laid on <hi>Definitions,</hi> truly ſtating the Nature of the Things treated of, and certain <hi>Ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioms</hi> or common Notions, ſelf-evident and univerſally
<pb facs="tcp:97398:13"/>
neceſſary, whence we are apt to conceive the ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Theorems</hi> by a due and continued connexion built hereon, muſt be confeſt undeniable, unleſs we ſhall abandon our Reaſon, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve abſolutely to Diſpute againſt Common-Sence, and proclaim our ſelves ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Brutes than Men.</p>
            <p>And that we may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed <hi>Orderly,</hi> we will</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:97398:13"/>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> give brief <hi>Definitions</hi> of the Terms which we are forced to make uſe of in the enſuing Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Lay down ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Self-evident <hi>Axioms,</hi> And,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Deduce thence <hi>Theorems</hi> neceſſarily ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing pertinent to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſcope.</p>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:97398:14"/>
               <head>DEFINITIONS.</head>
               <item>1. Eſſe <hi>is a Term uſed to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie a</hi> Principle <hi>of Being, or that whereby whatever</hi> Is, <hi>or can be</hi> Is.</item>
               <item>2. Ens <hi>(or a Being) is that which hath an</hi> Eſſe, <hi>(or ſuch Principle of Being) And is either Actual or Potential.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>An actual Being is that which actually doth exiſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>A Potential Being, is that which may come, or is able actually to exiſt hereafter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97398:14"/>
5. Nothing, <hi>is that which hath no</hi> Eſſe, <hi>(or principle of</hi> Being)</item>
               <item>6. A Finite Being, <hi>is that which is included &amp; boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded within ſome limits of</hi> Being.</item>
               <item>7. An Infinite Being, <hi>is that which tranſcends all, or is included in no bound of</hi> Being.</item>
               <item>8. Eternity, <hi>is an infinite duration; Or that which tranſcends all bounds of Continuance or Enduring.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>9. Creation, <hi>is the produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb facs="tcp:97398:15"/>
of a</hi> Being <hi>out of Nothing.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>10. Providence, <hi>is the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod or Reaſon of Ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things for ſome end.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>11. A pure Act, <hi>is the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of</hi> Being; <hi>to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude from it all Power to be another thing.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>12. Nature, <hi>(as here we take it) is every</hi> Finite Being <hi>ſo far as endowed with its proper Virtue; Or, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of</hi> Finite Beings, <hi>to to effect ſomething by their proper Virtues.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:97398:15"/>
               <head>AXIOMS.</head>
               <item>1. <hi>Every thing either</hi> Is, <hi>or</hi> Is <hi>not.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>It is impoſsible the ſame thing ſhould at the ſame time both</hi> Be, <hi>and not</hi> Be.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Nothing is</hi> before <hi>it is.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>That which</hi> is not, <hi>can</hi> do <hi>or</hi> effect <hi>nothing.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>That which</hi> is, <hi>is not in</hi> power <hi>to be that which already it is.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. <hi>Whatever</hi> is, <hi>is either by or from it ſelf, or hath its Eſſence from</hi> another <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides it ſelf.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97398:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
7. <hi>That which</hi> Is <hi>by it ſelf, is</hi> Independant <hi>on any thing beſides it ſelf; and ſo on the contrary.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8. <hi>Nothing can</hi> give <hi>that which it ſelf hath not.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>9. <hi>As a thing is in it</hi> ſelf, <hi>ſo is it in its</hi> poſſe, <hi>or power.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>10. <hi>The power of a</hi> Finite Being <hi>is</hi> Infinite, <hi>both its</hi> active <hi>power, and alſo its</hi> paſſive, <hi>ſo far as 'tis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducible to Art.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>11. <hi>The Effect of a</hi> Finite <hi>Virtue or power cannot be</hi> Infinite.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97398:16"/>
12. <hi>There is no finite thing, but ſomething more great, or</hi> more perfect <hi>may be aſſigned or conceived.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>13. <hi>Nothing can be, or be conceived greater, than that which is</hi> infinite.</item>
               <item>14. <hi>To every finite thing, another thing</hi> equal <hi>may be conceived.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>15. <hi>The</hi> whole <hi>is greater than its</hi> part.</item>
               <item>16. <hi>Thoſe things which are the</hi> ſame <hi>with any third thing, are the ſame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb facs="tcp:97398:17"/>
themſelves in that</hi> Third <hi>thing.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>17. <hi>That which is the</hi> Cauſe <hi>of the Cauſe, is alſo the Cauſe of the thing Cauſed.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>18. <hi>That which is not</hi> Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, <hi>begins to be in</hi> Time, <hi>or hath ſome other firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of duration proper to its ſelf.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>19. <hi>Of that which is Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, there can</hi> no begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>of duration be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>20. <hi>Everything that is</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded
<pb facs="tcp:97398:17"/>
                  <hi>is dividable into thoſe things of which it is compounded.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>21. <hi>Nature makes nothing out of nothing, nor</hi> any <hi>thing out of</hi> every <hi>thing.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>22. <hi>There is no progreſs to be made in</hi> Cauſe, <hi>or from Cauſe, to Cauſe</hi> infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="tcp:97398:18"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97398:18"/>

THEOREMS.</head>
         <div n="1" type="theorum">
            <argument>
               <p>1. An Infinite Being, is all that which is, or can be.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or otherwiſe, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite being it ſelf would be inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in ſome Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of being, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our <hi>7th</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition; and hence it follows, that Infinite being in its ſelf is every finite being, but without,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97398:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
or above all limits, or (as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers expreſs it) Abſolutely, Incontractedly, or Eminently.</p>
            <p>Nor let any over captious head, conceit that here at firſt ſtep, we ſtumble on a Paralo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſm, and fall to Beg the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, by taking that for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which is to be proved, <hi>viz.</hi> That there is ſuch a thing as Infinite being; For we here only treat of Infinite being ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractedly, as defined in our <hi>7th</hi> definition, whence this <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem</hi> is neceſſarily deduced; Now a definition doth not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily infer, that there is <hi>(ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parte rei)</hi> and indeed ſuch a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97398:19"/>
thing as is defined; <hi>For Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> The ſquaring of a Circle is the finding of a right line, which may be equal to the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of a Circle: this is a true definition, yet there is really no ſuch invention, nor yet is it known whether 'tis poſſible to be done, ſince it hath not yet been found out by any the moſt laborious Geometricians; But that there is really ſuch a thing as Infinite being, we ſhall prove by and by. <hi>Theorem</hi> 23.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="theorum">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:97398:20"/>
            <head>THEOREM. II.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Infinite being is a pure Act.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For otherwiſe it ſhould be in power to be ſome other thing; Definition the <hi>12th;</hi> And ſo would not be. All that which is, or can be, againſt our Firſt <hi>Theorem;</hi> or would be included in ſome limits of being againſt our <hi>7th</hi> Definition.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="theorum">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:97398:20"/>
            <head>THEOREM. III.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Infinite Being is an Infinite Act, or every Act that is, or can be.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For otherwiſe it would not be all that is, or can be againſt our firſt <hi>Theorem,</hi> nor a pure Act againſt our Second <hi>Theorem;</hi> Therefore Infinite being muſt be an Infinite Act, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence is good, true, potent, wiſe, and whatever elſe can be, or be conceived under the noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of an Act or perfection, and that in the higheſt degree.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="theorum">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:97398:21"/>
            <head>THEOREM. IV.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Infinite Being is unchangable.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For otherwiſe it ſhould be in power to be that, into which it is changable; and ſo would not be a pure Act againſt our ſecond <hi>Theorem,</hi> nor an Infinite Act againſt our third <hi>Theorem.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="theorum">
            <head>THEOREM. V.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>A finite being cannot be the ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate ſubject of an Infinite.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For if it would, The Paſſive Power of a finite being muſt be Infinite againſt our <hi>10th Axiom.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="theorum">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:97398:21"/>
            <head>THEOREM. VI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>There cannot be two Infinite Beings.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For ſuppoſe (if it were po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſible) <hi>A.</hi> and <hi>B.</hi> to be two In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite beings in any moment of time, now becauſe <hi>A.</hi> is an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite being, therefore it will be whatever is or can be at that moment of time; but what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is, or can be at the ſame moment of time, doth not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of any Generical Specifick, Individual or other difference from it ſelf, but is one and the ſame both in reaſon and things; And therefore neither <hi>A.</hi> nor
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97398:22"/>
               <hi>B.</hi> do admit of any difference at all between themſelves, but will be wholly the ſame in entity according to our <hi>16th Axiom,</hi> and ſo not two Infinite beings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> whence it is evident, there cannot be two Infinite beings.</p>
            <p>It may poſſibly be objected, that this <hi>Theorem</hi> concludes aright of two infinites in eſſence or entity, ſince ſuch an infinite is indeed all that is, or can be, according to the firſt <hi>Theorem,</hi> but not of two infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites, whereof at leaſt one is finite by Eſſence, but infinite by Accident; As Body which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97398:22"/>
may be infinite in extenſion, or quality by intenſion.</p>
            <p>But we anſwer, <hi>That the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite eſſence of Body, cannot be the ſubject of an infinite accident, as as Infinite extenſion would be, ſee our 5th</hi> Theorem; <hi>therefore there is no ſuch infinite; the ſame we ſay of Quality, and irrefraga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conclude, there cannot be two infinite beings.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="theorum">
            <head>THEOREM. VII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Infinite being is not dividable.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For <hi>Firſt,</hi> It cannot be divided into two infinite beings, becauſe a part cannot be equal to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97398:23"/>
whole, <hi>Axiom</hi> the <hi>15th,</hi> nor can here be two Infinites, <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orem</hi> the <hi>16th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor <hi>Secondly,</hi> Can it be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into two finites, for ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſuch finites may ſtill be conceived greater, or more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>Axiom</hi> the <hi>12th,</hi> and to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry finite thing, ſomething elſe may be conceived equal, and addition may be made of them, <hi>Axiom</hi> the <hi>11th:</hi> But by ſuch means ſomething would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived more great, large, or perfect, than that which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, againſt our <hi>13th Axiom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Is it diviſible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a finite and an Infinite; For
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97398:23"/>
when the finite is taken away, ſtill the Infinite Being remains, which hence plainly appears cannot at all be divided.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="theorum">
            <head>THEOREM. VIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>In an Infinite Being there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing before or after.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For if there ſhould, it would be dividable, <hi>viz.</hi> Into that which was before, and that which is after; But that cannot be by our <hi>7th Theorem.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="theorum">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:97398:24"/>
            <head>THEOREM. IX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Infinite Being is moſt ſimple and uncompounded.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For were it any way Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, it would be dividable into thoſe things whereof it is Compounded, <hi>Axiom</hi> the <hi>20th,</hi> But infinite being cannot be divided, <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>7th;</hi> Therefore is not Compounded.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="theorum">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:97398:24"/>
            <head>THEOREM. X.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Whatever is, or can be conceived in an Infinite Being is Infinite.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For whatſoever is, or can be conceived in an infinite being, is ſuch infinite being it ſelf, which is individable by our <hi>7th Theorem.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="theorum">
            <head>THEOREM. XI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Nothing any way Compounded can be Infinite.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For every compound is divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, <hi>Axiom</hi> the <hi>20th,</hi> But infinite being is undividable,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97398:25"/>
               <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>7th,</hi> therefore no Compound is Infinite.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="theorum">
            <head>THEOREM. XII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Infinite Being is neither a part, nor a whole.</p>
            </argument>
            <p n="1">1. Not a part; For it muſt be a part either of a Finite or an Infinite; if of a Finite, a part would be greater than its whole; if of an infinite, a part would be equal to its whole; both which are abſurd, and contrary to our <hi>7th Axiom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Neither is it a whole, for a whole, as a whole conſiſts of parts, into which therefore it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97398:25"/>
is Dividable, but infinite being is not Dividable, <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>7th,</hi> therefore is neither a part nor a whole, but above both theſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="theorum">
            <head>THEOREM. XIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The difference between a Finite Being and an Infinite, is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For ſince an infinite being exceeds a finite, which is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the infinite, if ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, want, or difference, were finite, the infinite might be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of two finites, or a finite and an infinite, and ſo
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97398:26"/>
would be dividable into them; againſt our <hi>7th Theorem.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="theorum">
            <head>THEOREM. XIV.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Infinite Being differs in (or of) its ſelf, from finite.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For otherwiſe, either the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fference between them would not be infinite, againſt our <hi>13th Theorem,</hi> or at leaſt there would be two ſeveral infinites againſt our <hi>6th Theorem.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="theorum">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:97398:26"/>
            <head>THEOREM. XV.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Eſſe (or the principal of Being) is of it ſelf.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For it is that whereby what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is is, Definition the firſt; now becauſe we ſee many things are, 'tis neceſſary that there be an <hi>Eſse</hi> (or ſuch principles) For otherwiſe nothing could be; But one <hi>Eſſe</hi> cannot be from another <hi>Eſſe,</hi> becauſe that were to run round from Cauſe to Cauſe <hi>in Infinitum,</hi> againſt our <hi>22d. Axiom;</hi> therefore it follows it is of it ſelf.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="theorum">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:97398:27"/>
            <head>THEOREM. XVI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>That only <hi>Eſſe</hi> is of its ſelf.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For otherwiſe, if any thing beſides were of its ſelf, <hi>Eſſe</hi> could not be that whereby whatever is, Is, againſt our <hi>1ſt.</hi> Definition.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="theorum">
            <head>THEOREM. XVII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>That <hi>Eſſe</hi> it ſelf is Infinite.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For it is included in no bounds of being, and becauſe there are not two infinites, <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>6th,</hi> therefore <hi>Eſſe</hi> and <hi>Infinite Being</hi> are the ſame;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97398:27"/>
and whatever is ſaid of this, may be ſaid of that.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="theorum">
            <head>THEOREM. XVIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Nothing can of it ſelf paſs from no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to an actual Exiſtence.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For either it muſt do ſo whilſt it is not, or whilſt it is; not the firſt, for that which is not, can do nothing; <hi>Axiom</hi> the <hi>4th,</hi> not the ſecond; for that which is, is not in power to be that which already it is; <hi>Axiom</hi> the <hi>5th,</hi> therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="theorum">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:97398:28"/>
            <head>THEOREM. XIX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>No Finite thing is of its ſelf, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neither as to Eſſence, nor as to Exiſtence.</p>
            </argument>
            <p n="1">1. Not as to Eſſence; for ſince every finite thing is inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in bounds of being this thing, and not another; if any finite being were of it ſelf as to Eſſence, it would follow, that ſuch beinu was bounded by it ſelf, or did impoſe Limits on it ſelf of being this and not another thing, which muſt be done ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before it was, againſt our <hi>4th Axiom;</hi> or after it was, which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97398:28"/>
will be againſt our <hi>5th Axiom;</hi> &amp; therefore cannot be done at all.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Not as to Exiſtence, for if it ſhould, then ſuch Finite being muſt be <hi>Eſse</hi> it ſelf, or the firſt principle of Being, which alone exiſts by, or of it ſelf, <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>16th;</hi> And then it would be infinite; <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orem</hi> 17th againſt the <hi>Hypotheſis;</hi> therefore no finite being is of it ſelf.</p>
            <p>The ſame may more briefly be demonſtrated another way. Thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Only</hi> Eſſe <hi>is of it ſelf,</hi> Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem <hi>16th, but</hi> Eſſe <hi>is infinite, therefore no Finite thing is of it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="theorum">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:97398:29"/>
            <head>THEOREM. XX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>In the production of things there can be no Circulation</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For if <hi>A.</hi> ſhould give being to <hi>B.</hi> and <hi>B,</hi> to <hi>C,</hi> and <hi>C,</hi> to the ſame <hi>A.</hi> it would follow, that <hi>A.</hi> in reſpect of the ſame <hi>C.</hi> were both an efficient Cauſe and an Effect, and ſo was before it was, which is abſurd, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our <hi>3d. Axiom.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="theorum">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:97398:29"/>
            <head>THEOREM. XXI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Every Finite being hath its being from Infinite being.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For it hath its being from <hi>Eſſe,</hi> which is that whereby whatever Is is, Deſinition the the Firſt; But <hi>Eſſe</hi> is Infinite Being, <hi>theorems</hi> 9th and 17th, Therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, whatever is, muſt either be of its ſelf, or have its being from ſome other being, <hi>Axiom</hi> 6th; for nothing, <hi>viz.</hi> That which hath no being can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not give being to any thing, <hi>Axiom</hi> the <hi>4th,</hi> but no finite
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97398:30"/>
thing is of its ſelf, <hi>Theorem</hi> 19th, and if it take being from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſuch other muſt be either a Finite or an Infinite; if you ſay the laſt, you grant our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Theorem;</hi> If the firſt, it will be replyed, That this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Being muſt have its being either from Infinite, or ſome finite being, and ſo you muſt ſtill either grant our <hi>Theorem,</hi> or elſe continue your progreſs from aſſigning one finite after another, which would be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our <hi>22d. Axiom;</hi> and though you ſhould be permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo to do to never ſo great a number, yet could not the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97398:30"/>
ſame be Infinite, becauſe Infi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nite, is undividable, <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>7th,</hi> but ſuch number (though never ſo vaſt) being compoſed of the unities of the finite beings produced, will be dividable into the ſame; <hi>Axiom</hi> the <hi>20th,</hi> and ſo will not be Infinite, but Finite, and by conſequence there may be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned the firſt of ſuch finite beings whereby the reſt were produced, and which it ſelf was produced by none of them, (for no Circulation can be, <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem</hi> the <hi>20th)</hi> And when ſuch firſt finite being is aſſigned, we ſhall ſtill ſay it is not of its ſelf,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97398:31"/>
               <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>19th,</hi> but hath its being from ſome other being either finite or infinite, but it cannot be from any finite; for then, this, not that ſhould be the firſt of finite beings, which is againſt the <hi>Hypotheſis;</hi> and therefore it muſt befrom infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite being.</p>
            <p>Then, agreeing the firſt fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite being to come from Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite being, It will follow that the other finite things produced by that firſt, are likewiſe from infinite being; for that which is the Cauſe of the Cauſe, is the Cauſe of the thing Cauſed; <hi>Axiom</hi> 17. whence appears the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97398:31"/>
truth of our <hi>Theorem,</hi> that every finite hath its being from that which is Infinite.</p>
            <p>That the number of finite things, produced by other finite beings, is not infinite, is thus alſo demonſtrable;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Suppoſe the number of Men hitherto produced to be Infinite, the ſame will contain all the Men that have been, are, or can be,</hi> Axiom <hi>13th; and ſo no Man would be henceforwards produci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; but experience ſhews us every day and moment freſh Men are produced (and that without Circulation) therefore the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Men produced, is not Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97398:32"/>
but finite; and conſequently there is a Firſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>as before, now what is here inſtanced in Men, holdingt, true by parity of reaſon in all other finite things which have being one from another, it therefore undeniably follows, that every finite being hath its being from a being that is infinite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here let us take breath a while, and conſider, that if a being which is confined to ſome limits of being, be properly termed finite, then a being which. tranſcends all bounds of being muſt be called Infinite; Of ſome of the proprieties of both theſe we have treated hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97398:32"/>
comparing them, one with the other, yet not at all determining whether there were any ſuch things, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly any Infinite being; ſo the explication of the firſt <hi>Theorem,</hi> but only have made it evident, that if there be ſuch things as Finite beings none of them can be of its ſelf; but every of them can only be from ſome being that is Infinite; and now we proceed thus.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="22" type="theorum">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:97398:33"/>
            <head>THEOREM. XXII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The World is Finite.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For the Tereſtical Globe is not the whole World, but a part thereof; the ſame we may ſay of the Sun, Moon, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Star, or even of Heaven it ſelf; whence it appears, that the World is a certain whole Compoſed of thoſe parts, and is therefore dividable into them, <hi>Axiom</hi> the <hi>20th,</hi> ſo not Infinite; <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>7th</hi> therefore Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="23" type="theorum">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:97398:33"/>
            <head>THEOREM. XXIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>There is really an Infinite Being.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For there is really a finite Being; As, the Earth, the Sun, the Moon, Man, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there muſt be an Infinite Being from whom theſe have their Being, <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>21ſt.</hi> For it cannot be ſaid, that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore indeed there was an Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Being that gave being to theſe Finites, but the ſame is now no more; for then ſuch Infinite being muſt have been included in Limits of duration, and conſequently not Infinite,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97398:34"/>
               <hi>Definition</hi> the <hi>7th,</hi> which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory and abſurd.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="24" type="theorum">
            <head>THEOREM. XXIV.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Infinite Being is of it ſelf.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For otherwiſe it hath its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from other beſides it ſelf, <hi>Axiom</hi> the <hi>6th,</hi> which muſt be either Finite or Infinite, but it could not from the firſt, becauſe the Vertue of a finite Being, being finite: <hi>Axiom</hi> the <hi>10th,</hi> Its effects cannot be Infinite; <hi>Axiom</hi> the <hi>11th,</hi> nor from the Second; for there cannot be two Infinite beings; <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>6th:</hi> therefore the <hi>Axiom</hi> is undeniable.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:97398:34"/>
Again, Infinite being, is <hi>Eſſe</hi> it ſelf, <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>17th;</hi> but <hi>Eſſe</hi> is of its ſelf; <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>25th:</hi> therefore Infinite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing muſt be of its ſelf.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="25" type="theorum">
            <head>THEOREM. XXV.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Infinite Being is Independent.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For it is of it ſelf, <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>24th,</hi> therefore Independent or any other; <hi>Axiom</hi> the <hi>7th.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="26" type="theorum">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:97398:35"/>
            <head>THEOREM. XXVI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Whatever is Independent, is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For, whatever is of its ſelf is <hi>Eſſe</hi> it ſelf, <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>16th</hi> but whatever is Independent, is of its ſelf, <hi>Axiom</hi> the <hi>7th:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whatever is Independent, is <hi>Eſſe</hi> it ſelf; but ſuch <hi>Eſſe <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> infinite, <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>17th;</hi> Therefore ſo is whatſoever is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="27" type="theorum">
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:97398:35"/>
            <head>THEOREM. XXVII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Infinite Being is Eternal.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For otherwiſe, either it hath its Being from ſome other, againſt our 24th <hi>Theorem,</hi> or paſt of it ſelf from nothing to an actual exiſtence, againſt our 18th <hi>Theorem,</hi> therefore Infinite being muſt needs be Eternal, or rather is its own Eternity, or Eternity it ſelf.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="28" type="theorum">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:97398:36"/>
            <head>THEOREM. XXVIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>No real matter flows from Infinite Being out of its ſelf, whereby it may produce a Finite Being.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For if there ſhould, Infinite Being would be dividable, againſt the 7th <hi>Theorem.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="29" type="theorum">
            <head>THEOREM. XXIX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Infinite Being produces a Finite Being by the ſimple Act of its will.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For ſince no real thing flows from it out of its ſelf whereby it may produce a Finite Being,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97398:36"/>
               <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>28th;</hi> Therefore it muſt needs produce the ſame by ſome Immanent Act, which can be no other than the meer Act of its will; for in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of finite things we muſt neceſſarily at laſt come to ſome firſt things produced by Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite being alone, as we have proved, <hi>Theorem</hi> 21ſt. But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable things there were producible, which of themſelves were equally indifferent to be produced; therefore when In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Being goes to produce ſomething out of it ſelf, either all things poſſible to be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, ſhould be produced toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97398:37"/>
at once, or nothing (both which it is plain are falſe and abſurd) or elſe Laſtly, we muſt admit an election or Act of ſuch Infinite Beings will whereby it produced one thing rather than another; ſince it is in its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing, ſuperlatively, free, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful and wiſe, yea ſupream liberty and infinite wiſdom and power it ſelf, <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>9th.</hi> Yet ſtill the production of a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite being is peculiarly attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the ſimple Act of its wil, and ſo to Love, which is the wills proper Act, and not to power or wiſdom, becauſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Infinite Being, be Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:97398:37"/>
Wiſdom and Power, as well as Infinite Love, yet it produces not at all that can be produced, nor all that it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands its ſelf able to produce but only that which it wills or is pleaſed to produce at that moment wherein from eternity, it will'd it ſhould be, becauſe the will of Infinite Being, is the ſame with its Omnipotence, <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>9th,</hi> and therefore is of its ſelf infinitely efficacious and needs nothing elſe either efficiently or ſubjectively to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt it in producing; for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it would not be ſupreamly free and Omnipotent, againſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97398:38"/>
the premiſes, therefore our <hi>Theorem</hi> ſtands undeniable, <hi>viz.</hi> That Infinite Being produces a finite by the ſimple Act of its will.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="30" type="theorum">
            <head>THEOREM. XXX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>A Finite Being once produced by an Infinite, is continually produced or conſerved by the ſame Infinite Being.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For ſince a finite being is produced by an Act of the Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite beings will, <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>29th.</hi> Therefore it is only ſo far a finite being as infinite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wills it to be; but how far
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:97398:38"/>
that wills it to be, ſo far it doth produce it, becauſe the Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent will of infinite being is moſt efficacious, <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>29th.</hi> Therefore a finite pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by the infinite, is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by continually produced, which continual production we uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call its conſervation, which ceaſing, ſuch finite being imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately drops into its original, nothing, and ceaſes to be.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="31" type="theorum">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:97398:39"/>
            <head>THEOREM. XXXI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Infinite Being concurrs efficiently and immediately to all the real effects of a Finite Being.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For ſince infinite being by an Act of its will continually pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces a finite being, by giving it both being and power of act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing according to the laſt <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem;</hi> therefore at whatever moment ſuch finite doth act, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite being wills it ſo to do; for otherwiſe either it ſhould give it power of acting in vain, and ſo would not be infinite wiſdom, againſt our <hi>9th Theorem.</hi> oratleaſt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97398:39"/>
a finite being ſhould Act contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the will of infinite being, which ſo would not be infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly potent againſt our <hi>29th Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem;</hi> but ſo far as infinite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, wills a finite being to Act or produce a new real effect, ſo far it cauſes it to Act, and what it wills, it alſo produces its will, being moſt efficacious: <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>29th.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="32" type="theorum">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:97398:40"/>
            <head>THEOREM. XXXII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Every Finite Being, immediately depends in its Being on Infinite Being.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For 'tis produced either by infinite being alone, or by ſome other finite being; if the firſt, the truth of the <hi>Theorem</hi> appears; if the laſt, then ſince in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite being doth ſo efficiently and immediately concur to all the real effects of a finite being, <hi>Theorem</hi> 31. Therefore alſo every finite being produced by another finite depends in its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing immediately on infinite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="33" type="theorum">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:97398:40"/>
            <head>THEOREM. XXXIII</head>
            <argument>
               <p>No Finite Being is or can be from Eternity.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For ſince every finite hath its being from infinite being, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our <hi>21ſt. Theorem;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if we ſuppoſe any finite being to have actually been from eternity, ſince it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by the ſimple Act of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite beings will, <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>29th.</hi> and thereby continually produc'd, <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>30th.</hi> Therefore if infinite being will, (as it may) that ſuch finite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhall from hence forwards be
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97398:41"/>
everlaſting, t'will follow that its duration being included in no bounds, muſt be infinite, and ſo individable; <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>7th.</hi> In which by conſequence there will neither be before, nor after; <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>8th.</hi> but it will be all at once; and therefore a true eternity accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our <hi>6th Definition;</hi> but infinite being is alſo eternal, or rather eternity it ſelf; now therefore the eternities of the finite and infinite are two, or munerically the ſame; if the firſt, then there will be two eternities againſt our <hi>6th Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem;</hi> if the ſecond, than ſince
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:97398:41"/>
the eternity of an infinite being is the very ſame with its entity, <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>9th.</hi> Therefore if infinite being can give to a finite being its own eternity, it will alſo give it its own infinite enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſo the finite muſt be Infinite againſt the <hi>Hypotheſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame is otherwiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated thus, no finite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing can be actually exiſting, but the ſame was producible from eternity; therefore no fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite being was, or could be from eternity; for if it ſhould, it would at the ſame time be both in Act and Power, or (which that implies) it would at
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:97398:42"/>
the ſame moment be actually, and not actually exiſting, the conſequence is plain, the ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent proved thus; becauſe every finite being is produced only by an Act of infinite beings will, which in producing is moſt free and unconfined, <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>29th.</hi> And therefore indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent in it ſelf, to give; or not give actual being to this thing, and therefore ſuppoſes ſuch fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite things to be only in power; for otherwiſe its indifferency would be about giving, or not giving being to a thing which already is in Act, or to a thing impoſſible, which on either ſide
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:97398:42"/>
is abſurd, wherefore there is no finite being can actually be from Eternity, though it may from all Eternity be poſſible.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="34" type="theorum">
            <head>THEOREM. XXXIV.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>This World had not its Being by any Phyſical, or Natural Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, nor concourſe' of Attoms.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For all Natural Generation tends to ſome one thing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally and by itſelf; but this World is not any one thing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally and by itſelf, but only by aceident; that is to ſay, Compoſed of ſeveral bodies,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:97398:43"/>
as Earth, Sun, Moon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Of different Species and diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuant, therefore could not owe its Being to any Natural Generation.</p>
            <p>Nor yet to the fortuitous concourſe of wandring Attoms according to the Dream of <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curus,</hi> whoſe ridiculous <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis</hi> being of late reviv'd, hath undeſervedly procured to many followers, and is in Sum no more but this. <hi>That in an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltramundane ſpace, there is an Infinite Troop of Attoms, or little Particles which have an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal motion that makes them En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter and juſtle each other; and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:97398:43"/>
that ſuch their caſual concourſe and ſhuffling together, made up this World and danced them by meer chance into all theſe beautious viſible Beings, and in that exact order and harmony which we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A conceit ſo abſurd and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant that it deſerves ſcarce any other Refutation but a hiſs; yet that we may continue our Method, we thus ſeriouſly and in brief raze its foundations, and ſay,</p>
            <p>That theſe imaginary At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms in this fancied vacuity were either eternally there, or not, if the laſt, than they were
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:97398:44"/>
placed thereby ſomewhat before and above them, and that leads us to our principles of an Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite being or Deity; if the firſt, then they muſt of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty have been without alteration there ſtill; for whatever is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal is unchangable, that is, can never ceaſe to be as it was, or produce any other thing by varying its own form; nor can any thing be Infinite in change, ſince what infinitely is, is the higheſt perfection of being; now Change is a perfect rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to imperfection, and to imagine a change in what is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, is to imagine a change
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:97398:44"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom the higheſt perfection, which is unimaginable.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="35" type="theorum">
            <head>THEOREM. XXXV.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>This World was Created in time by Infinite Being.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For ſince 'tis finite, <hi>Theorem</hi> 22. Therefore it is not eternal, <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orem</hi> 33. Beſides thoſe who with <hi>Aristotle</hi> conceit the World to have been from all Eternity, do ſuppoſe the motion thereof, or of Heaven to be Eternal, in that they confeſs the firſt mover of the World to be Eternal; which being ſuppoſed, either the number of the revolutions
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:97398:45"/>
of the <hi>primum mobile</hi> from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity hitherto, is finite or Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite; if the firſt, then its firſt revolution may be aſſigned, and conſequently the beginning of the Worlds duration, and ſo the ſame cannot be Eternal, <hi>Axiom</hi> the <hi>19th.</hi> If the ſecond, then ſuch number, will be no number againſt the <hi>Hypotheſis;</hi> for that every number is dividable, <hi>Ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iom</hi> the <hi>20th.</hi> Becauſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of a multitude of Unites; <hi>Definition</hi> the <hi>11th.</hi> But Infinite is undividable, <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orem</hi> the <hi>7th.</hi> Whence it follows, that no number can be Infinite and conſequently this World not Eternal.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:97398:45"/>
That the number of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutions, or turnings round of Heaven hitherto is not Infinite, may alſo otherwiſe be proved; for were it Infinite, it muſt comprehend all its revolutions that have been, are, or can be, <hi>Axiom</hi> the <hi>13th.</hi> And by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence no more Circulation would be poſſible, but every week we know there are new whirlings round of the firſt Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore this World cannot be Eternal, but must begin to be in time by a duration proper to it ſelf, but it neither received being from nothing,</hi> Axiom <hi>the</hi> 8th.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:97398:46"/>
               <hi>Nor had it by any Phyſical Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> Theorem 34. <hi>Nor Laſtly could it of its ſelf paſs from no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to actual exiſtence,</hi> Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem <hi>the</hi> 18th. <hi>And therefore muſt be brought out of nothing to ſuch actual being, immediately by that whence every Finite Being takes its</hi> Eſſe, <hi>viz. Infinite Being</hi> The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orem 32. <hi>But that which is ſo produced, is properly ſaid to be Created,</hi> Definition <hi>the</hi> 9th. <hi>Therefore this World was Created in time by Infinite Being, which is what we undertook to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, For Infinite Being having all things virtually exiſting in himſelf, made all matter out of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:97398:46"/>
no matter, but from his own active potentiality, who being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and above all cauſe, muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be acknowledged as the Author of all cauſes.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="36" type="theorum">
            <head>THEOREM. XXXVI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>This World, and the ſeveral Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings therein, are governed by the providence of Infinite Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For ſince Infinite being is the immediate efficient cauſe of this World, and the ſeveral beings therein produced, <hi>Theorem</hi> 32. And that every efficient cauſe Acts for ſome end, eſpecially
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:97398:47"/>
infinite being, becauſe it is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Wiſdom, <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>9th.</hi> Therefore either Infinite being muſt be ſaid in vain to Act for ſome end, or it will order this World, and all the ſeveral be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings by fit and agreeable means to ſome end intended and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned by its ſelf in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction; and this is properly called to rule by its providence, <hi>Definition</hi> the <hi>10th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame likewiſe appears otherwiſe thus, Since we mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly ſee there is a providence in all Animals; for Brutes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for their young; Parents for their Children; A Prince
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:97398:47"/>
for his Subjects, which finite providence muſt be from Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite being, <hi>Theorem</hi> 32. And therefore Infinite being it ſelf muſt be provident, as well by our 8. as 3. <hi>Axiom;</hi> yea muſt be Infinite Providence; that is, a Providence extended to every finite being; for otherwiſe it would not be infinite there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this World and all things therein are governed by the providence of Infinite being.</p>
            <p>Again, every finite being is continually produced by Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite being, which is called the conſervation of ſuch finite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>30th.</hi> But it
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:97398:48"/>
is produced by an Act of its will, which is the ſame with Infinite Wiſdom, <hi>Theorem</hi> 29. And therefore neither raſhly nor to no purpoſe, but for ſome end, and therefore it is conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually directed to ſuch end, by the ſame infinite being which indeed would not be infinite, if it were not provident, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if it were Infinite Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which leaves nothing any where wholly void of it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Now this Providence of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Being is found to diſcharge a threefold office.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>In placing the ſeveral finite
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:97398:48"/>
beings in their ſeveral ranks and orders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>In preſerving them in ſuch their places and order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>In moving and directing them to their reſpective proper ends according to every ones Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and therefore it provides that neceſſary cauſes ſhall act ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily, contingent, contingent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and free cauſes freely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And moſt conſonant it was to Infinite Wiſdom, to will, that ſome of its Creatures ſhould be free Agents; that is, endued with underſtanding and will, to the end, that infinite being might not remain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:97398:49"/>
amongſt all the finite beings produced by its ſelf, and have none to celebrate its Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and return the tribute of worſhip and admiration to their Creator; but that it might at leaſt by ſuch free Creatures (which in this behalf, it hath enabled and made after its own Image above others) be owned in their underſtandings to be of all things, the beginning, mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle (or preſerver) and laſt end, and by their wills might be above all Created things, Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, Loved and deſired; that ſo ſuch free Creatures by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming like to the Infinite Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:97398:49"/>
in Purity, Juſtice, Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Holyneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Should always tend thereunto, and at length obtain, and everlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enjoy the ſame.</p>
            <p>And here we may behold the Baſis of thoſe two grand Pillars of the World, Reward and Puniſhment; For theſe free Creatures being made capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of diſcerning Truth from Falſhood, and what is juſt and righteous, from that which is unjuſt; and thereby of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their own excellency, and conſequently their greater ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations above all other finite beings; therefore by decree of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:97398:50"/>
Infinite Providence, juſt things are by them either to be done, or ſuffered, ſo that if they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low not the one voluntarily, they fall into the other neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="37" type="theorum">
            <head>THEOREM. XXXVII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>There is ſome certain ultimate (or last) end of all Finite Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For every finite being is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by infinite being, <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem</hi> 32. And therefore is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for ſome end by ſuch infinite being, <hi>Theorem</hi> 36. Now this end is either the ultimare
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:97398:50"/>
end, and ſo our <hi>Theorem</hi> is granted, or only a mean to ſome ultimate end; and if there be ſuch an ultimate end, our <hi>Theorem</hi> is granted, if there be not, then ſuch other end could not be a mean thereunto, againſt the <hi>Hypotheſis;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there muſt neceſſarily be ſome certain laſt end of all the ſeveral finite beings, in which every finite being attains the complement of its perfection, according to its Nature.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="38" type="theorum">
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:97398:51"/>
            <head>THEOREM. XXXVIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Infinite Being is the ultimate, or laſt end of all Finite Beings.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For otherwiſe there would be a progreſs in ends Infinitely, whereby a finite being would never attain that end intended by Infinite Being in its produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and ſo it would be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained thereunto by Infinite Wiſdom to no purpoſe; or elſe there muſt ſome finite being be aſſigned, which was made by Infinite Being for no other end, than that it might be the end of all other finite beings, <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orem</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:97398:51"/>
the <hi>37th.</hi> And ſo ſuch other finite beings would like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be the laſt end of that, and they would mutually be cauſes to one another in the ſame kind which all Philoſophers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs cannot be.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the ultimate end is always extreamly deſired by thoſe things which tend there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, becauſe it ſatisfies them, and having obtained the ſame, they reſt; but if no finite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing can ſo much as ſatisfy it ſelf, but ſtands in need continually to be produced and conſerved, leaſt it ſhould ſink into nothing and ceaſe to be; <hi>Theorem</hi> the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:97398:52"/>
               <hi>30th.</hi> Much leſs can it ſatisfy any other finite being, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Mans Appetite which can never be ſatiated with any thing finite; ſo that we may ſafely conclude no finite being can be the laſt end either to its ſelf, or another.</p>
            <p>Once more ſince a rational creatures is obliged which its whole underſtanding and entire will to tend to that laſt end for which it is ordained, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if the ſame ſhall be any thing beſides Infinite being, it will be bound to turn it ſelf from that infinite being, which as we ſaid before, made ſuch
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:97398:52"/>
rational Creatures, meerly that by them through underſtanding and will he might be known and loved; nothing therefore but Infinite Being can be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined tg the laſt end of all finite beings, and which at laſt poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt by every thing tending thereunto according to its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Nature; and that immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately through the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and will, or knowledge, and love by rational Creatures, and through them by other things mediately.</p>
            <p>Now this infinite, only one, moſt ſimple, immutable, inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent, eternal being; the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:97398:53"/>
Creator, Preſerver, moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident Governour, and ultimate end of the World, and all things therein, is by the unanimous conſent of all Nations called God, who is infinite Goodneſs, infinite Wiſdom, infinite Love, infinite Juſtice, infinite, and whatever elſe is becoming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attributed to him; to whom every creature for its being, power of acting, and preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion received, whether imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately or by ſecondary cauſes, doth owe it ſelf, and its being, it power of acting, and all its operations, ſince the Cauſer, original, and maker of a thing,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:97398:53"/>
muſt needs have a property in it; nor can he be diſſeiſed of his right to a thing, that cauſed it firſt to be.</p>
            <p>But above all, every ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Creature ought wholly to devote and conſecrate to this Omnipotent and Ineffable Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the ſole and intire uſe of its underſtanding, and its will; ſince ſo to do, is both their duty, and their chief perfection and ſupream happineſs; which conſiſts in knowing and loving him, To whoſe moſt ſacred and infinite Majeſty, be thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, Praiſe, Honour, Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and all Glory, for ever and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="39" type="theorum">
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:97398:54"/>
            <head>THEOREM. XXXIX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>God in Acting is not bound to the Laws of Nature, but by his Power, Infinitely excells Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures Power.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>The firſt part is proved thus, The Laws of Nature are, that it can make nothing out of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, nor any thing out of every thing, <hi>Axiom</hi> 21. But only ſomething out of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, meet and idoneous for that purpoſe; but God makes and does whatever he pleaſes, <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>29th.</hi> And that out of nothing, <hi>Theorem</hi> 35. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:97398:54"/>
much more out of any thing; ſince there is a greater power ſhewn in producing a thing out of nothing at all, than in making it out of ſome other thing.</p>
            <p>The ſecond part is thus evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, as a thing is in its being, ſo is it in its Power, <hi>Axiom</hi> the <hi>9th.</hi> But God is infinite being, <hi>Theorem</hi> 38. And therefore his power is Infinite. But Nature is a finite being, <hi>Definition</hi> the <hi>12th.</hi> And ſo its power finite alſo, <hi>Axiom</hi> the <hi>10th.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſtrength or power of God doth infinitely excel that of Nature, <hi>Theorem</hi> the <hi>13th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:97398:55"/>
Now thoſe wretched votaries of Hell, the poſitive and dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Atheiſts, who with a brazen Impudence and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallell'd Ingratitude, diſown their Creator, by denying that there is a God; do yet general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admit of Nature, and confeſs it took its being from none, and therefore are forced to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that it is of it ſelf, <hi>Axiom</hi> the <hi>6th.</hi> And ſo that it is Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, <hi>Theorem 19th.</hi> And by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence omnipotent, <hi>Theorem</hi> 9. But this is abſurd and againſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience; for we daily ſee that Nature is very ſtrictly ſubject to rules and Laws, ſo that it is not
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:97398:55"/>
able to beget any thing out of every thing, but only out of its proper ſeeds; as Wheat from Wheat, a Wolf from a Wolf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Since Nature therefore is ſubject to Laws, Who is the Law-giver? If ſhe be a Subject, Who is the Lord? Certainly he who is truly Omnipotent, and did firſt impoſe theſe bounds, and circumſcribe her power in theſe Lymits; <hi>To wit,</hi> God the Infinite Creator of Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Nature.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="40" type="theorum">
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:97398:56"/>
            <head>THEOREM. XL.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>God can do whatever doth not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply a Contradiction.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>For God can do whatever is poſſible, otherwiſe he were not omnipotent, but whatever im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies not a contradiction is in it ſelf poſſible; Therefore God can do whatever implies not a Contradiction.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <head>The Concluſion.</head>
            <p>Thus far humane underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is able to dart its proper beams, what remains requires
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:97398:56"/>
ſome more excellent opticks, and can only be diſcovered by the aſſiſtance of Faiths celeſtial Tube; yet though our Reaſon, or that meer natural Light God hath planted in our Souls, be not able of it ſelf to fathom thoſe adorable Depths and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Myſteries of the Trinity, Hypoſtatical Union, Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and other verities of the Chriſtian Creed, yet in ſome meaſure, it prepares for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of the ſame, and when they are revealed by God, and declared by his Miniſters, It enforces our conſent to them by its proper light, ſince there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:97398:57"/>
it knows, Firſt, That God cannot Lye; and Secondly, That God in acting as well within as without himſelf, is not bound by the Laws of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Theorem</hi> 39. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore able to do whatever implies not a Contradiction, but in the premiſes and whole body of our Religion, no contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on offers it ſelf; and therefore the Soul lead on by a divine Faith, and ſupported by right Reaſon, embraces theſe ſacred truths when propoſed, and yields an unfeigned and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubting conſent and obedience thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:97398:57"/>
In Brief, The belief of this propoſition, that there is one ſupream, eternal, independent Being, infinite in Wiſdom, Power, and Goodneſs, and Maker, Governour, Preſerver, and ultimate End of the World and all Creatures therein, <hi>viz.</hi> GOD, is the firſt ſtep to Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo aſſerted by the Author of the Epiſtle to the Hebrews, <hi>He that comes to God muſt believe that he is;</hi> where by <hi>coming to God,</hi> according to the mode of expreſſion ordinary with the <hi>Hebrews</hi> is meant, <hi>worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him,</hi> to which none or can addreſs themſelves, without
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:97398:58"/>
believing <hi>that he is;</hi> So that a firm aſſent to the <hi>Exiſtence of a Deity</hi> neceſſarily precedes all adoration of, and obedience to him. For the more ready diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing perſons unto which (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially ſuch as have been ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced of Satan to entertain mean thoughts of thoſe ſacred oracles wherein God hath more fully and expreſly declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his will) 'tis hoped the premiſed Demonſtrations may prove in ſome meaſure Condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cive; Since 'tis certain that this proleptical principle of the Being of a God implanted in Mans Nature, with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:97398:58"/>
which do immediately flow, and may neceſſarily be inferr'd from thence, is the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal of all natural Religion, and the foundation of all that Virtue and Veneration which we admire in the pagan World; to this Idaea engraven in their Souls, were thoſe gallant He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro'<hi>s, Socrates, Plato, Tully, Seneca, Epictetus,</hi> and other Heathen Worthies, endebted for the ſeminal principles of all that ſolid honeſty and piety, which ſparkled with <hi>ſo much Luſtre</hi> in their Lives and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, that a ſerious reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereon, cannot but Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:97398:59"/>
up Bluſhes on the guilty Cheeks of moſt pretended Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, to ſee themſelves (to whom the Sun of Righteouſneſs vouchſafes to appear in a Goſpel Meridian) ſurpaſt in real good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by thoſe who had only Natures glimmering Light for their Conduct.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:97398:59"/>
            <head>
               <hi>AN APPENDIX</hi> Concerning the moſt <hi>Proper Method</hi> of Preaching to <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Infidels.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He mention of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans</hi> in the cloſe of the precedent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, invites us on this Opportunity to offer a few things, touching the moſt <hi>Effectual Courſe</hi> of dealing
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:97398:60"/>
with them, in order to their Conviction and Converſion to <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the Goſpel, <hi>viz. The glad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tidings of Mans Reconciliation to to God through a crucified Jeſus</hi> ſhall one day be proclaimed in <hi>every</hi> Land, even to the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt corners of the habitable World, and amongſt the moſt <hi>ſavage</hi> and <hi>barbarous</hi> of <hi>Adams</hi> Off-ſpring is part of our Belief, warranted by <hi>Authority</hi> no leſs then Infallible; and certainly 'tis very <hi>strange</hi> and very <hi>ſad</hi> to conſider, That too many, who appear ſo <hi>paſſionately zealous</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout what they apprehend,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:97398:60"/>
concerns the Honour of God in the skirts of Religion, and <hi>lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Adiapherous Circumstances,</hi> ſhould yet unconcernedly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold near three parts of the known World lie chain'd up by the <hi>Prince of Darkneſs</hi> in a ſtone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blind <hi>Paganiſme,</hi> or what is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually wretched, a filthy ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure <hi>Mahumatiſme,</hi> without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing ought but a lazy <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignificant <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tinam</hi> to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief. Do we not much too much buſie our ſelves about <hi>Mint</hi> and <hi>Cummin,</hi> and too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle regard the weightier mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, when we ſo fiercely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incounter each other to the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:97398:61"/>
               <hi>wounding of Charity,</hi> and bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing <hi>peace</hi> and Brotherly love out of our ſtreets for a few <hi>dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling opinions,</hi> in themſelvs no leſs <hi>indifferent,</hi> than to us <hi>uncertain;</hi> and yet in the mean time ſeem not at all affected with their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable condition, who ſcarce ever heard of a <hi>Redeemer.</hi> Have we not the higheſt obligations in the World upon us, to be thankfull to that mercifull hand of <hi>Providence,</hi> that hath order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our lott ſo graciouſly, and fixt our Habitations in thoſe Regions where <hi>Christianity</hi> is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſally profeſt? And can we any way more <hi>illuſtriouſly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:97398:61"/>
our <hi>gratitude</hi> in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, than by endeavouring with the pious <hi>Samaritan Lepers</hi> to make others ſharers in the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs we enjoy. 'Twould certainly be more <hi>glorious,</hi> if theſe <hi>great and fervent Spirits</hi> would turn the bright flames of their <hi>Zeal</hi> to the burning down <hi>Ethnick Temples,</hi> rather than to the waſting and unſettling <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Churches,</hi> and ſtrive more to enlarge the Tents of <hi>them</hi> in the borders of <hi>Japhet,</hi> than to promote unſeaſonable diviſions in <hi>Reuben,</hi> which muſt coſt each truly pious Chriſtian ſo many <hi>ſad thoughts of heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:97398:62"/>
In the <hi>Primative days,</hi> The Promulgers of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> went out ſupernaturally furniſht with the <hi>gift of Tongues,</hi> and ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to ſeal the truth of their Doctrine as well with working of <hi>Miracles,</hi> as laying down their lives, and by performing <hi>ſuch Actions</hi> as could not but be acknowledged the Effects of a <hi>divine</hi> aſſiſtance, did (as it were) <hi>enforce</hi> the Gentiles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief; But now thoſe extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary <hi>Gifts</hi> being generally cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, there ſeems a greater need of improving <hi>natural parts</hi> to the beſt advantage, and purſuing the moſt <hi>rational method</hi> of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:97398:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Inſtruction, which ſeems to be</p>
            <p>Firſt, To <hi>caſt out the ſtrong man armed,</hi> to ſhew the <hi>vanity</hi> of their preſent Apprehenſions, taking them off from their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping <hi>Idols</hi> or <hi>Devils,</hi> by ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>them, that it is no leſſe <hi>ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous</hi> then <hi>wicked and deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, To lead them by the moſt ſutable <hi>perſwaſives</hi> and demonſtrations to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>one true God, Creator and Governour of the whole World and all things therein;</hi> and that he is <hi>most good, most wiſe, most bleſſed, Eternal, Immutable,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:97398:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>
And that if he were not al this, he would want to be <hi>ſo,</hi> and ſo could not be God; for who in his witts would admit an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digent God</hi> into his <hi>Creed,</hi> ſince all <hi>want</hi> is Imperfection and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, After their minds are hereby ſettled in this great Principle, <hi>The Exiſtence of a Deity,</hi> they are next to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed concerning their <hi>own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> in what condition <hi>man</hi> was <hi>Originally created,</hi> and how he fell by Satans temptation from that glorious <hi>ſtate,</hi> which may eaſily be evinced; for ſince <hi>all other Creatures</hi> keep in the ſame
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:97398:63"/>
natural order ordained for them from the beginning; how ſhall we imagine that <hi>mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> (the nobleſt part of the Creation, and for whoſe ſake the reſt ſeem chiefly made) ſhould ſo prodigiouſly be <hi>depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> and become worſe than brutiſh, raging in quarrels, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines and cruelties againſt it<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelf, and abnoxious to igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, inconſtancy, ſloth, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, death, and a thouſand miſeries which would accuſe infinite wiſdome of an errour, <hi>unleſſe</hi> we believe that man firſt created upright, and endued with <hi>Free will,</hi> did by tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:97398:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>forfeit</hi> all his happy pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, and ſo became liable to all theſe evills as <hi>juſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> for ſuch his ſin.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, hence it follows, that man having offended againſt an <hi>Infinite God,</hi> there was no ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſing Divine Juſtice with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an Infinite ſatisfaction; This only, the <hi>Son of God</hi> could make, whoſe love to miſerable <hi>humanity</hi> cauſes him to quit his <hi>manſions of Glory,</hi> to take on him our nature, and by his <hi>death</hi> to open to us the gates of <hi>Life and Immortality:</hi> and here may be <hi>unfolded</hi> the whole myſtery of our bleſſed Saviours <hi>Incarnation,</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:97398:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the purity of his <hi>life,</hi> grievouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his <hi>Crucifiction,</hi> certainty of his <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> and glorious <hi>Aſcention,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Adde to all this the Excellency of the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> ſhewing, that there is nothing required in the whole Chriſtian profeſſion, but what is highly <hi>reaſonable</hi> in it ſelf, and mainly <hi>conducive to the accompliſhing and ennobling</hi> humane nature: not a few <hi>rigid perſons</hi> are apt to draw our <hi>Religion</hi> (the greateſt <hi>beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> in the World) in too ſad a <hi>habit,</hi> with a <hi>frowning counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> and <hi>ſower looks,</hi> more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to <hi>frighten</hi> than <hi>invite</hi> raw
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:97398:65"/>
               <hi>Proſelites</hi> to a more intimate converſe.</p>
            <p>The perſons that undertake this <hi>glorious work</hi> of propagating the Goſpel (which is attended with the <hi>Plaudites</hi> of Angels, and <hi>prayers</hi> of all good men) ought to be fitted for the ſame in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of <hi>miſſion</hi> and <hi>Abilites.</hi> 'Tis no ſleight nor trivial affair at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted out of <hi>wantonneſſe, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> or <hi>vain-glory;</hi> they are <hi>Gods Ambaſſadors,</hi> and ſhould ſee they have his <hi>Commiſſion</hi> and <hi>Warrant,</hi> without whom <hi>Paul plants, and</hi> Apollo <hi>waters, but all in vain.</hi> A lively vigorous faith is required to ſet forth the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:97398:65"/>
Word with <hi>power and authority,</hi> and carry them through all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, hazards and difficulties that may occur; they ought alſo to be very expert in the <hi>language</hi> of thoſe perſons they deſign to inſtruct, that they may readily in <hi>clear intelligible terms</hi> diſtill their diſcourſes into their ſouls. Thus our <hi>bleſſed Lord,</hi> though he choſe his Apoſtles <hi>Fiſhermen, and ordinary Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks</hi> (leſt vain men ſhould ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect his holy Doctrine for the contrivement of ſome <hi>great worldly wits</hi> or plot of ſubtle ſelf-intereſted <hi>Politicians;)</hi> yet before he ſent them abroad
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:97398:66"/>
into the Nations, he made them the beſt <hi>Linguiſts</hi> in the World; above all, <hi>ſweetneſſes of nature, and holyneſſe of Life</hi> are neceſſary. This is a <hi>Continual Sermon,</hi> and convinces more than all the charms of the moſt accompliſht <hi>Orator.</hi> How odious did <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and cruelty</hi> render the very name of <hi>Christianity</hi> to the poor <hi>Americans, Shew us thy Faith by thy Works</hi> is every mans propſal. Can we imagine they deſign any other but to put a <hi>cheat</hi> on us, who tell us of <hi>Crowns, and Glory, and everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting happineſs</hi> in the other world which we can only a ſpire to by
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:97398:66"/>
               <hi>Purity and Mortification, Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denial,</hi> &amp;c. in this; And yet themſelves practice things <hi>quite contrary</hi> to all theſe they ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly recommend.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Stumbling-blocks</hi> which cauſe <hi>the name of the Lord to be laſphemed amongſt the Gentiles</hi> ought to be removed; And theſe <hi>Fiſhers of men</hi> muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove themſelves <hi>Lights</hi> in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation</hi> as well as <hi>Doctrine;</hi> That ſo God may be glorified, the ſouls of their hearers ſaved, and themſelves enjoy that <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious promiſe</hi> made to ſuch as turn many to Righteouſneſſe;
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:97398:67"/>
               <hi>Of ſhining like Stars in the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:97398:67"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
