<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A lecture and sermon preached at different times by that faithfull minister of the Gospel, and now glorified martyr, Mr. Donald Gargill [sic]</title>
            <author>Cargill, Donald, 1619?-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-10">2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34191</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C568</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4928</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13682589</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13682589</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101324</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A34191)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101324)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 841:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A lecture and sermon preached at different times by that faithfull minister of the Gospel, and now glorified martyr, Mr. Donald Gargill [sic]</title>
                  <author>Cargill, Donald, 1619?-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Wing and BM suggest imprint date of 1681?  Catalog of McAlpin collection in Union Theological Seminary Library gives date of 1682 with note:  "Date doubtful; probably printed after 1700."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Chronicles, 2nd, XIX, 2 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah X, 3 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-08</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-12</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-12</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101324:1"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:101324:1"/>
A LECTURE AND SERMON Preached at Different Times by that Faithfull and Painfull <hi>Miniſter</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and now Glorified <hi>Martyr</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Donald Gargill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concerning</hi> Jehoſophat <hi>his</hi> Aſſociation <hi>with</hi> Achab, and the Difficulty where to make Recourſe, when Staged before the Tribunal of GOD.</p>
            <p>2 Chronicles 19. Chapter. 1, and 2. Verſes, and downwards. <hi>And</hi> Jehoſophat <hi>the King of</hi> Judah <hi>Returned to his Houſe in Peace to</hi> Jeruſalem.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And</hi> Jehu <hi>the Son of</hi> Hanani <hi>the Seer, went out to Meet him, and ſaid to King</hi> Jehoſophat, <hi>ſhouldeſt thou Help the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly, and Love them that Hate the LORD,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="lecture">
            <pb facs="tcp:101324:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101324:2"/>
            <head>A LECTURE</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Upon 2 <hi>Chronicles</hi> 19: Chapter, firſt and ſecond Verſes.</bibl>
                  <p>And <hi>Jehoſophat</hi> the King of <hi>Judah</hi> returned to his Houſe in Peace to <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And <hi>Jehu</hi> the Son of <hi>Hanani</hi> the Seer, went out to Meet him, and ſaid to King <hi>Jehoſophat,</hi> ſhouldest thou Help the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly, and Love them that Hate the LORD? <hi>&amp;c:</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Goodneſs of GOD does not always leave Man, when he ſtaps out of GODs Way; Indeed it might do ſo: And when we Depart from GOD, GOD might ſay now, go Good Providence and Leave them. But what does the Goodneſs of GOD, it ſtays and bides untill it bring ſome Folk back again to GOD; and then when they are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, the more that the Goodneſs of GOD has been with them, it makes them the more to Mourn when they Return again! We have an Inſtance of this in this Chapter: We have here a <hi>King,</hi> and a Good <hi>King,</hi> and he has gone out of GODs Way; and yet GODs Goodneſs has not left him, but it ſtayed, even after his ſinfull Acceſſion in Aſſociation with <hi>Achab.</hi> It's ſaid, <hi>he returned in Peace to his Houſe to</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</p>
            <p>Now in this Chapter, there are ſeveral Things ſpoken of him; For this Chapter ſpeaks not only of his Fall, and ſets out
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101324:3"/>
all his Goodneſs; But it ſpeaks, <hi>Firſt,</hi> Of his <hi>Deliverance,</hi> and then of the reſt. Firſt, <hi>And he came to his Houſe at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>in Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It ſpeaks of the <hi>Sharp Reproof</hi> he meets with from the <hi>Prophet</hi> upon the very entry. Any Body would have thought they ſhould have gone and met their <hi>King</hi> with Praiſe, and Flattery; Nay, but the <hi>Prophet</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> goes to meet with him with a <hi>Sharp Rebuke:</hi> Sharp Rebukes were meeteſt for him, meeter nor any other thing, even the beſt of them all: But here the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> marks the <hi>Sharp Rebuke</hi> he gate from the <hi>Prophet.</hi> We hear nothing of what Return he gave to the <hi>Prophet;</hi> but he took with it. It is a Rare Thing to ſee a Mean Perſon to take with a Reproof from a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet: But much more to ſee a <hi>King</hi> acknowledge &amp; ſay, <hi>Indeed I am Guilty.</hi> I ſay it's a Rare Thing to ſee a Mean Perſon to take with a Reproof; But here a <hi>King</hi> takes with a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke,</hi> Them that ſtands out againſt <hi>GODs</hi> Reproof, <hi>GOD</hi> will give over to Reprove them till the Day of Judgement, and then the <hi>Lybel</hi> will be altogether put in their Hand, and ſee who will Refuſe then. But here he takes a <hi>Reproof</hi> Sweetly from <hi>GOD.</hi> O bleſs <hi>him</hi> that <hi>he</hi> is Wairing a <hi>Reproof</hi> u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon You, and bid <hi>him</hi> now tell on, and ſay, What more has <hi>he</hi> now to <hi>Reprove</hi> me of? O! the Heart of Man is ſo Proud that it will not take with <hi>Conviction</hi> and <hi>Reproof.</hi> We ſay it again, The Heart of Man is ſo Proud that it will not take with <hi>Conviction,</hi> and the <hi>Reproof</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Humbling Grace.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Third Thing ſhown of him, is this, He takes with his <hi>Reproof,</hi> and that is a Token of it, for he goes on to the Work of <hi>GOD,</hi> notwithſtanding of the <hi>Prophets</hi> Reproving of him, he goes on I ſay, to the Work of <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation:</hi> We ſhall ſay this General, where ever there is an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociation with Wicked Men, they will forget <hi>Reformation,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:101324:3"/>
untill Aſſociation be broken again: Here he forgets <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> till the <hi>Aſsociation</hi> with <hi>Achab</hi> be broken, and then he goes on to <hi>Reformation.</hi> We ſhall ſay that one Word, our Sinfull <hi>Aſsociation</hi> with the <hi>Malignant-</hi>Party in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> not only has made us forget the Work of <hi>Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> but has ſhut the Door altogether, that none ſhould go fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in a <hi>National Reformation:</hi> And till this <hi>Aſsociation</hi> be quate, Miniſters nor People will never ſet foreward in <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> again. And wad ye know when the <hi>Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> began to be at a ſtand or ſtay, it was that Day when we took the <hi>Malignant-</hi>Party by the Hand; and it has ſtood all this time; &amp; till that be quate again, it will never be ſet foreward, &amp; when it is quate, it will ſet foreward, and that by every one of you in your ſeveral Places &amp; Stations; And then it will be ſaid, them that did moſt withſtand is now Removed out of the Way, and made to fly away; and then ye ſhall ſee nothing but <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> going on. O if it were come to that.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Fourthly,</hi> There is the <hi>Reformation</hi> it ſelf, which is ſet out in theſe <hi>Three.</hi> (1.) It is ſet out in the Body of the Land the Generality, or Body of the Land: What does he to them? <hi>Verſe</hi> 4 He went throw the People and brought them back to the <hi>LORD GOD</hi> of their Fathers: They were like Run-away-Servants; yea not only ſo, but like the <hi>Levit</hi>'s <hi>Concubine</hi> that had Departed from her Husband &amp; had played the Whore; And ſo he brings them back again to the <hi>Lord.</hi> But now you ſee what is the Duty or Office of a <hi>King,</hi> to bring back the People of <hi>GOD</hi> to <hi>GOD.</hi> Wa, What has the <hi>King</hi> done, and theſe <hi>Rulers?</hi> Wa, Their Exerciſe in theſe Kingdoms has been to Debauch Folk from their Obedience to <hi>GOD;</hi> And in a word, it has been to Exauterate that Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of <hi>GOD,</hi> and Introduce and Heighten Man's Authority; and has not that been that which all of them has been Carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on? Let the Commands of Men be Great with you, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101324:4"/>
the Commands of <hi>GOD</hi> be Small; This they have Imployed themſelves all into: But never a word of the Commands of <hi>GOD,</hi> nor <hi>his</hi> Authority. But, I ſay, this is the Work and Matter he Imploys himſelf into; He goeth throw <hi>Judah,</hi> &amp; he bringeth the People back again to <hi>GOD,</hi> like Run-away-Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, or the <hi>Levit</hi>'s <hi>Concubine.</hi> They had been away: But now this Holy <hi>King,</hi> he Imploys all his Power to bring them back again to <hi>GOD;</hi> and he thinks them Good Subjects, if they be Good Saints. But what is Obedience to him in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of Obedience to <hi>GOD;</hi> But the contrary is ſaid and done by the Men of this Generation: We are ſure we ſee this plain from the Scripture, or Word of <hi>GOD,</hi> that this is a part of the Office of a <hi>King:</hi> And he that hath no Regard to this, ought no more to be Eſteemed a <hi>King,</hi> but a Tyrrant and Enemy to <hi>GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, <hi>Secondly,</hi> A ſecond part of <hi>Reformation</hi> is done u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the <hi>Civil State,</hi> What doth he there? <hi>He ſets Judges in every City of</hi> Judah <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We will get Cuſtomers anew in all the Cities of <hi>Judah:</hi> But few <hi>Judges,</hi> more for Exacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Cuſtomes, nor for Judgement. Now undoubtedly as he was a Holy Man himſelf, ſo he ſet Holy and Good <hi>Judges</hi> in every City. For every <hi>King</hi> will chooſe out ſuch <hi>Judges</hi> as himſelf is. <hi>Officers</hi> and <hi>Judges</hi> will tell you what a Nature the <hi>Kings</hi> are of. <hi>Souldiers</hi> and <hi>Curats</hi> ſhews what's the Diſpoſition their <hi>Prince</hi> is of. Then we may know what is the Nature of the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Court.</hi> A Holy <hi>King</hi> will have Holy <hi>Judges</hi> that will give Juſtice and Equity to all; But now we need not look for Equity and Juſtice; if they would let us alone with their Injuries, Now I ſay, that is the ſecond part of <hi>Reformation (viz.)</hi> in the <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> he gives Holy <hi>Judges,</hi> and he has a particular Exhortation to them, when he puts them in their Office, <hi>Verſe</hi> 6. And, 1. It is Remarkable, that he ſays to them in the Entry of their
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101324:4"/>
Office: Any Body wade have thought that he wade have ſaid, See well to my Prerogatives and Priviledges, let not them be Wronged; Let not the <hi>Royal-</hi>Rents be Decreaſed; See that the <hi>Crown-</hi>Rights be no Way Diminiſhed. Theſe and the like ordinarly <hi>Kings</hi> Recommend at firſt. But what ſays he? He ſaid to the <hi>Judges, Take heed what Ye do, for Ye judge not for Man, but for GOD the LORD, Who is with You in Judgement.</hi> Remember this, I commit Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to You, but the Judgement is not mine, it is the <hi>LORDs;</hi> and Remember what ye do, is for <hi>GOD;</hi> Then do it as if <hi>GOD</hi> Himſelf would do it; Do it as if <hi>He</hi> were Sitting there. Now where is there any <hi>Judges</hi> that does this Way? And where is there a <hi>King</hi> that Deſires them to do ſo, or to do this Way? Says <hi>Kings</hi> now, Ye man Judge for Me, ye have your Office of Me, and therefore Judge for Me. But ſays he, I give you Authority of Judging; but Remember ye muſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to <hi>GOD</hi> for your Judgement, for <hi>GOD</hi> is with you in Judgement; That is to ſay, <hi>He</hi> is preſent with you to Help you if ye do Right, and to be Diſpleaſed with you if ye Judge Wrong; <hi>He</hi> is Preſent to Protect you, if ye do Right: But to be a Witneſs, &amp; to Puniſh you, if ye do Wrong: That's the Thing he Commends unto them. Now I have given you Power, and ſet you in a Capacity to Judge Matters Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; Then ſee ye well to it: For the Judgement is not Mine, but the <hi>LORDs;</hi> And if ye Judge Rightly, <hi>GOD</hi> will be with you in it; <hi>GOD he</hi> will Preſerve you and Protect you: But if otherways, no. But there is one word in the Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation before we proceed to the <hi>Third</hi> Thing, <hi>Wherefore let the Fear of GOD be on you, for there is no Reſpect of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons with GOD,</hi> &amp;c. O but this were Neceſſary, if every <hi>King</hi> when he puts a <hi>Judge</hi> upon the Bench, wade give him ſuch an Exhortation as this when he Sits down, ſaying, Take heed to your Selves, let the Fear of <hi>GOD</hi> be upon you. It
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101324:5"/>
is even but in Vain to ſpeak to Men, if there be not ſome thing of the Fear of <hi>GOD</hi> on them to make them do Rightly and Well; So if there be a Principle of the Fear of <hi>GOD</hi> in them, then an Exhortation may be Uſefull, and Profitable: But let the Fear of the <hi>LORD</hi> prevail, and if that make you not do Right, it will not be all the Exhortations of Men will do it otherways, or if that be not, ye will ſlip evermore when ye have the Opportunity, and ye will never be Sicker in Good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But now let the Fear of the LORD be on you, for there is no Iniquity in GOD; He</hi> will do no Iniquity <hi>himſelf,</hi> and the Unjuſt Counſel <hi>he</hi> will not allow of; So this is one Thing that every one wade Remember and look to. There is no I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquity in our <hi>GOD,</hi> and ye need not think that when ye do Wrong in Judgement that <hi>he</hi> will allow of it: For all Proceſſes and Judgements that have been given out by Men, will be ſeen by <hi>GOD</hi> at the long run; For <hi>He</hi> is like a Great <hi>King</hi> that muſt Survey every Thing. It's true <hi>Kings</hi> now never looks to the Judgements that Inferiour <hi>Officers</hi> does, if they be according to <hi>Law.</hi> So then, he ſays to them, ſee to it, <hi>GOD</hi> will be with you in Judgement; It will be ſeen by <hi>GOD</hi> how ye have judged, and according to the Judgement that ye have given, <hi>GOD</hi> will give you Judgement. Now GOD is no Accepter of Perſons. What is that? Give every one his Due, for GOD will give every one his Due. Think you GOD will ſpare a <hi>King</hi> more nor a <hi>Beggar?</hi> No, for all are <hi>his</hi> Creatures, <hi>he</hi> hath ſet up a <hi>King</hi> there: Therefore <hi>Kings</hi> are more bound to <hi>him</hi> than others. Said <hi>Chriſt</hi> who ought to Love moſt? It was anſwered, He to whom GOD has given moſt. So he that has gotten moſt Tokens of GODs Love, he ſhould be moſt Holy; And they to whom leſs has been given, leſs is expected of: And ſo they ſhould be moſt Holy who Command others; For with GGD there is no Reſpect of Perſons, and ſo there ought to be no Reſpect of Perſons with <hi>Judges,</hi> Folk thinks
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101324:5"/>
that <hi>Kings</hi> are above <hi>Laws:</hi> But let any Man ſhew us that <hi>Kings</hi> are above <hi>Laws,</hi> either from Scripture or Reaſon. GOD hath ſaid it, that with him there is no Reſpect of Perſons; So this will bring a <hi>King</hi> in under <hi>Law,</hi> as well as others. Then he who Judges for <hi>GOD</hi> muſt ſay that if he ſay Rightly: Even this with us, there ought to be no Reſpect of Perſons. Indeed we will add this one Word, which is neceſſary to be added in this Caſe: There is no Body that Rules, but they will be lyable to Failings in Ruling: And therefore if all Faults of <hi>Rulers</hi> ſhould be exactly looked to, there would be none who would Rule a Day to an end, but we might find Faults in them, for which to Depoſe them ere Night: But we will ſay this, it is one thing to be a Failing in Infirmity, and another thing to be in a conſtant Courſe of Wickedneſs, and Enmity againſt <hi>GOD.</hi> The firſt may be ſpared; but not the laſt. Then look where we are now: But whatever ye think of this, it is the Truth of <hi>GOD</hi> which we are Declaring unto you at this time.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Third Thing in the <hi>Reformation</hi> is anent the <hi>Prieſt-hood;</hi> So that in effect he takes up the whole Land. (1.) The <hi>Body</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> (2.) The <hi>State,</hi> or <hi>Civil-Magistrate.</hi> (3.) The <hi>Prieſt-hood,</hi> or the <hi>Miniſtry:</hi> And ſo a Perfect <hi>Reformation</hi> ſhould go on throw the Three altogether. Let every one bring it to his own Heart, <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Rulers</hi> muſt Reform without in the Land, under, or in a time of <hi>Reformation:</hi> But will ye not Reform your Selves, Verſe 8. <hi>He appointed</hi> Levits <hi>and</hi> Prieſts <hi>in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very City, and the Chief of the Fathers for the Judgement of the LORD, and for Controverſies, when they Returned to</hi> Jeruſalem. Verſe 9. <hi>He Charged them, ſaying, Thus ſhall ye do in the Fear of the LORD Faithfully, and with a Perfect Heart.</hi> This was the Great <hi>Judicatory</hi> that they had in the Land; It was made up with <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Law-men;</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:101324:6"/>
There was ſome <hi>Priests</hi> in it, and ſome <hi>Civil-men,</hi> and they judged together in the <hi>LORD</hi>'s Matters; The Matters of the <hi>LORD</hi> belonged to them, to wit, The <hi>Priests.</hi> And the <hi>Kings</hi> Matters belonged to the others: But all was to judge according to the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>GOD.</hi> We ſhall ſay this one word more, there is one Great Thing Folk ſtumbles at in that <hi>Paper</hi> that <hi>Kings</hi> ought to Rule or Judge according to the <hi>Judicial Law;</hi> and that theſe <hi>Laws Kings</hi> ought to Rule by, ought to be according to the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> And think ye this a Great Wrong? The <hi>People</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> was ruled Two Hundred Years and upwards by this <hi>Law</hi> only, and can any be fitter to be a <hi>Law-Giver</hi> than <hi>GOD?</hi> Have we <hi>Laws,</hi> have we them from <hi>Men</hi> or of GOD? If of <hi>Men,</hi> then they had them of GOD. Then the GOD of <hi>Nature,</hi> or the GOD that <hi>Created</hi> All is far better to Teach <hi>Laws</hi> than <hi>Man</hi> that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der GOD. We ſay ſtumble not that it is ſaid, the <hi>Laws</hi> of GOD ought to be the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Land;</hi> For it will never be Well with you (eſpecially the Mein of the Land) till the <hi>Laws</hi> of GOD be the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Land;</hi> Then we will not be faſhed with <hi>Great Ones</hi> to Oppreſs: For when they have <hi>Laws</hi> to make, they never do thing but Oppreſs the <hi>Poor.</hi> But when the <hi>Law</hi> of GOD ſpeaks, it will give Right to the <hi>Poor</hi> as well as to the <hi>Great.</hi> So the <hi>Law</hi> of GOD ſhould be our <hi>Law.</hi> Where the <hi>Law</hi> of GOD is received where <hi>Christians</hi> are; Let <hi>Christians</hi> go to the <hi>Law</hi> which GOD has found out; And let <hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> go to the <hi>Law</hi> that <hi>Nature</hi> finds out. <hi>Now they Judge in the Matters of the LORD, and in Controverſies,</hi> &amp;c. For Underſtanding this better; There was a Great <hi>Court</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and all the Difficult Matters came there. There were <hi>Courts</hi> and <hi>Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories</hi> throw the Land, and there was <hi>Judges</hi> of Hundreds, and other <hi>Officers;</hi> and <hi>Judges</hi> of Thouſands throughout the Land. But all Hard Matters they brought to <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> And
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101324:6"/>
now he ſets <hi>Judges</hi> to receive theſe Hard Matters that they could not Judge among themſelves, and they gave Judgement in theſe Matters.</p>
            <p>Now the Laſt Thing (and we will not go to ſpeak any more) is their <hi>Charge</hi> he gives them. Verſe 9. <hi>And he Charged them, ſaying, Thus ſhall ye do in the Fear of the LORD.</hi> There is great Neceſſity to be Earneſt with them that <hi>Kings</hi> commit <hi>Judgement</hi> too, that they be Faithfull; There is much need for it now: For if <hi>Kings Laws</hi> be ſeen too, there will be little Regard what come of the <hi>Law</hi> of GOD; We know this by Experience; All the <hi>Supplications</hi> of this Poor <hi>Land</hi> has been Rejected, and the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Man</hi> well ſeen too. We thought to begin to ſpeak to all theſe particularly; But <hi>Firſt,</hi> A Word of his <hi>Delivery; He comes in Peace to his Houſe.</hi> Why does the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> Mark this? If ye Obſerve the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter before, he was in a Dangerous Battle, where he had a Sore Aſſault; They ſet upon him for the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the LORD Delivered him out of that. And ſo the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> Marks this, <hi>He came Home in Peace.</hi> And the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> will have us to Mark this of it, that notwithſtanding of this Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Plight he was in, in <hi>Aſsociating</hi> with <hi>Achab,</hi> yet GOD Graciouſly brought him off. He <hi>Aſſociated</hi> with <hi>Achab,</hi> and GOD might have letten him fall with him; Yet <hi>Achab</hi> fell, and he is ſafe; The Battle is Loſt, and he Returns in Peace. We ſhall ſay this one Word, Who ever hath gotten ſuch ſpecial <hi>Deliverances</hi> from GOD (eſpecially when under Slips) they wade conſider Narrowly in their Hearts what they have been Doing: Wherefore they have met with ſuch <hi>Deliverances.</hi> But ye will ſay to us, We were not in a Sinfull <hi>Aſsociation;</hi> We were not <hi>Aſsociated</hi> with Sinfull, Wicked and Prophane Men. But we ſhall ſay this one Word, We were <hi>Aſsociate</hi> in a Sinfull <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion;</hi> And ſo there was as Sinfull. <hi>Aſſociation</hi> with an <hi>Evil Courſe.</hi> Now that many <hi>Fell,</hi> was it not Juſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101324:7"/>
and Holy Dealing in GOD that ſome were preſerved in ſuch a <hi>Fall</hi> as that. O! Conſider well wherefore it was that GOD has ſo Remarkably preſerved you, eſpecially when He might have taken away your Life. Now there are ſeverals here that have had a part of ſuch a <hi>Deliverance</hi> as this, not only once, but once and again. O! Great <hi>Deliverances</hi> has He given to ſome, even when they were <hi>Aſſociate</hi> with a Sinfull <hi>Cauſe:</hi> Then Mind now and Remember wherefore it is, that GOD has preſerved you; It is to Repent of Sin: Yet more, it is that ye may be ready at a Good Turn again when He calls for it at your Hands; But beware of this, tho' He let you go in a Sinfull <hi>Action</hi> once, beware of the next time by no more join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Sinfull <hi>Aſsociations;</hi> For Sinfull <hi>Aſſociations</hi> is ever Dangerous. Whatever the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly</hi> meet with in them, yet certainly the <hi>Godly</hi> never Thrives in ſuch <hi>Aſsociations.</hi> Now this is the Thing that we wade ſay, Let every Man that has a part in ſuch Remarkable <hi>Deliverances,</hi> ſay, Wherefore has Thou preſerved me? Wherefore is it that I have Life? Is it a Bleſſing? But I think not ſo much of it as I ſhould, that I have it ſo wonderfully. Is it not for ſome End, even that I may Imploy it ſome Way for GODs Glory; Go back and ask, Wherefore it is ſo Remarkable He gave you your Life when in Danger, and while ye were in a backſliding <hi>Courſe,</hi> and while ye were <hi>aſſociated</hi> in a Sinfull <hi>Way;</hi> and when ye were involved in a <hi>Courſe</hi> with the Deadly and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying <hi>Enemies.</hi> Conſider this therefore, Wherefore has GOD given you this Life? Say, Wherefore has Thou preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this Life? Is it that I may be for Thee? and Imploy it for Thee?</p>
            <p>The next Thing to be conſidered is, The <hi>Prophet</hi>'s <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof:</hi> He is an Miſleard <hi>Prophet,</hi> Wade any Body think that he ſhould ſpeak ſo to a <hi>King?</hi> Ay, but we muſt be Faithfull in Reproving <hi>Kings</hi> as well as others. Modeſty is Ruine here.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101324:7"/>
Modeſty in ſuch a Caſe is Ruine to <hi>Rulers:</hi> For if we had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one and told them their Sins, they had not gone on in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch a <hi>Courſe</hi> as they did. Silence or Modeſty here, it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot a Vertue but a Vice: It is but Unfaithfulneſs to GOD <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d Man, might he not have letten him come Home: Nay, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hy? Will he make him Sad? Why will he make him Sader <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d Sader? There is a moſt be. Why are you Sad? If it be Affliction you are Sad for, ye muſt not be ſo, that is not the thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e ought to be Sad for: There is Sin you muſt be Sad for: So ye would think Folk ſhould be ſpared that is in Affliction; Nay, but ſpare them not, for then they will beſt hear <hi>Reproofs</hi> when under Affliction, never better nor then. Now the thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e ſays to him is this, <hi>Shouldest thou Help the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly, and Love them that Hate the LORD?</hi> How fit is this to be applyed to our <hi>Times?</hi> See hence who ever Helps the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly</hi> is in the Fault. They now talk Good Men are upon both <hi>Parties,</hi> Whom ſhall we Condemn or Follow? We ſhall ſay this one word, be they Good or Evil, if they Love them that Hate the LORD, and Help the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly,</hi> they are to be <hi>reproved;</hi> See who does ſuch are on the Wrong Side, and to be <hi>reproved. Shouldeſt thou Help the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and Love them that Hate the LORD?</hi> Should ye Help them Higher for all the Little Good they have done with their Power which they have gotten already; They have too much of it already. O! that all the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly</hi> in the World, were many ſteps Lower nor they are. What will they do then when ye have ſet them up? They will ſet up <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> with it. O! Help GOD and the <hi>Godly;</hi> But beware to Help up the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly;</hi> They are High enough already, and there is none who will Help to Raiſe or Hold them up: But GOD will <hi>Reprove</hi> them; for they can do Nothing when they are raiſed up, but <hi>Wickedneſs.</hi> This Scripture ſpeaks plainly, <hi>Shouldeſt thou Help the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly?</hi> We ſhall ſay no more of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101324:8"/>
it but this, Whoever has Helped the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly</hi> at this <hi>Time,</hi> are worthy of a <hi>Reproof.</hi> We are in Two <hi>Parties</hi> now: There is one <hi>Party,</hi> the LORD and the <hi>Godly;</hi> And the other <hi>Party,</hi> the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly.</hi> See what <hi>Party</hi> ye will take now. <hi>Shouldest thou Love them that Hate the</hi> LORD, <hi>and Help the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly?</hi> Be what he will to you. <hi>Jehoſophat</hi> was joined in Affinity with <hi>Achab,</hi> and ſo came of it. But be who he will, <hi>Father,</hi> or <hi>Mother,</hi> or your <hi>King,</hi> ſhould ye Love and Help him that Hates the LORD? We ſhall only ſay this word, and take heed to it, for it is the Word of <hi>Truth,</hi> Enmity and Hatred againſt GOD, cuts off all Obligation. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed we will ſay that, tho' we were in the neareſt Obligation, that is to ſay, even in that Relation betwixt a <hi>Father</hi> and a <hi>Son;</hi> Yet in this Caſe it is cut off: The <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> ſays, <hi>That his Father and Mother ſhall thruſt him throw while he is Propheſying.</hi> We ſay this, then Hatred of GOD takes away all near and far off Obligation, for if they go on to Hate the LORD, and to Blaſpheme the <hi>Name</hi> of GOD afrontedly, and Oppoſe the <hi>Truths</hi> of GOD, and with <hi>Malice</hi> and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility</hi> Oppreſs the <hi>Work</hi> of GOD; We may not Help and Join with them: If any Man can give better <hi>Doctrine</hi> nor this, he may; But he cannot: But Remember he brings it not from the Scriptures of GOD, if he give you that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trare to this; but we ſhall leave it.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:101324:8"/>
            <head>A SERMON</head>
            <byline>BY Mr. <hi>Donald Gargill.</hi>
            </byline>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Iſaiah 10. Chapter, 3. Verſe.</bibl>
                  <p>And what will ye do in the Day of Viſitation, and the Deſolation that ſhall come from far, to whom will ye Flee for Help, and where will you Leave your Glory.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WE ſee here, the <hi>Feaſt</hi> is done, and the Reckoning is come. The moſt part of us that's here, has gotten already that which Sin can give us. I ſay the <hi>Feaſt</hi> is Small, and there is no Body, but they will ſay ſo, when it's over. O! but I have gotten Little. There are ſome Wofull Creatures that thinks they ſhall have their Penny-worths of Sin: But there was never a Man yet that got a Penny-worth at the Devils Hand, and ſo it is in his Hand now. Have ye gotten your Wills out? There are ſome Folk who muſt have
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101324:9"/>
out their Wills, coſt what it will. Well, it ſhall coſt you Dear enough. Has the <hi>Great Ones</hi> gotten their Wills out? Nay, They have not gotten it out yet; They have gotten out ſome of it, and ſome of it no yet; They will be keeped al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſhort of it: For when they ſhall be raiſed and reckoned with, they will begin and ſay then, I have not gotten my Will. And ye got your Will, the Earth would be made like a Hell. Now we muſt conſider whom he is ſpeaking this of, Whom is he ſpeaking it of? He ſpeaks it of Men like ours; that had made many a Sinfull <hi>Act.</hi> We call them ours. We deſire in the Sight of GOD to retract that word: But he ſpeaks to Men that had done many Sinfull <hi>Acts.</hi> In the firſt Verſe it is ſaid, <hi>Wo to them that Decree <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteous De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, and that Write Grievouſneſs that they have preſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> And if they have not Decreed Unrighteous Decrees, and preſcribed Grievouſneſs, let their <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Council</hi> and <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> Teſtifie. The Generation afterwards will Wonder that ever Men made ſuch <hi>Acts.</hi> It may be thought, there has been as Ill <hi>Acts</hi> made before. There was an Abominable <hi>Act</hi> made by a <hi>King</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> that all the World counted Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable: But they have over-paſſed that Filthy <hi>Law</hi> of King <hi>Kenneth:</hi> For their <hi>Laws</hi> are more Abominable, nor if they ſhould have Enacted Publick <hi>Whoredoms</hi> and <hi>Stew-Houſes.</hi> We ſhall ſay that one word, The firſt of <hi>Sinfull Laws</hi> lights on the <hi>Subjects;</hi> But the laſt and the heavieſt lights upon the <hi>Makers;</hi> I ſay the laſt: and the heavieſt. Now it has been heavy and ſad to us to Obey<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But it has been ſader and heavier for us to Suffer; That was the firſt: But what will come of the laſt and the heavieſt? And what will come of you when you come to Reckon for your <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Grievances.</hi> Shortly thir words ſhews that <hi>Great Law-Makers</hi> on Earth will be put to thir Queſtions. Yet <hi>Kings</hi> muſt come down off their Thrones, and ſtand at the <hi>Bar</hi> of the <hi>Tribunal</hi> of GOD, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101324:9"/>
their <hi>Laws;</hi> Which they have made will be laid down before them, and it will be ſaid to them, Will ye own them? Own them we muſt: He that will own them, muſt Diſown GOD, &amp; that Intaills him to the Wrath of GOD; and they own their <hi>Laws</hi> before GOD, as they own them now, it will be a ſtrange thing: But this is the thing that we are ſaying, and which we ſee here, that the Greateſt upon Earth, upon the account of thir <hi>Laws</hi> which they have made, will be put to thir Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before GOD, and there are Three <hi>Queſtions</hi> in thir words. O! that every one of us where at a Point, and could give an <hi>Anſwer</hi> and <hi>Solution</hi> to them.</p>
            <p>The firſt <hi>Queſtion</hi> is, <hi>What will ye do in the Day of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation?</hi> What <hi>you</hi> is this? Even you that made Laws What more theſe nor other <hi>Folk?</hi> Becauſe they made <hi>Evil Laws:</hi> How ſo? Ye did ſet up a direct contrary <hi>Judicatory</hi> to GOD. When <hi>Laws</hi> is directly a conrrare <hi>Judicatory</hi> to GOD, it ſays, Ye take upon you to give out <hi>Laws,</hi> and <hi>Laws</hi> that are contrare to GODs <hi>Laws. Now what will ye do?</hi> O! but this <hi>Queſtion</hi> will put to Silence and Amazement the great part of Men. What, we have nothing to do with their <hi>Sinfull Laws,</hi> we never made the <hi>Laws;</hi> Well, nevertheleſs, ye did give Obedience to their <hi>Laws:</hi> It will be, here the <hi>Law</hi> Maker, and the <hi>Law</hi> Obeyer. <hi>What will ye do in the Day of Viſitation?</hi> If ye Conſented to their <hi>Laws;</hi> Is there Nothing that you Fear? Dare you boldly come before GOD? Mind this, but till you get the Book of <hi>Items,</hi> it Concerns you all that you can give an <hi>Anſwer</hi> to this <hi>Question, What will you do in the Day of Viſitation?</hi> GOD will be through you all, <hi>He</hi> will be through us all; and ere long the Loweſt of us all will give an Account of his Doings. Now, <hi>What will ye do in the Day of Viſitation?</hi> Says ſome, I have done ells. What have ye done ells? I have Compted, I have Payed, I am Diſcharged: That's well, if you can ſay theſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101324:10"/>
               <hi>Three.</hi> I have Reckoned, I have Judged my Self, I have Payed, not by my Self, but by another, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Cautioner</hi> came in &amp; told down for me, and GOD Reckoned it up in my behalf. Have you Payed then? I have Reckoned, I have Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I am Diſcharged. Where is it? We have it in a Common <hi>Proverb,</hi> ſuch a Man is evident, that is to ſay, it is not Subſcribed, that is a Fools Evidence. Many ſays they have the Evidences, but they want the Subſcription. O to have the <hi>Seal</hi> of the <hi>Living GOD</hi> to every Diſcharge. There was Wreſtling before I got it, and I have laid it up, and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it well, and when I take it out at the <hi>Great Day, He</hi> will acknowledge that it is <hi>His own Hand.</hi> Now ſee to it. Then Wo to him that Ventures upon the <hi>Tribunal of GOD,</hi> unleſs he have theſe <hi>Three;</hi> I have Reckoned, I have Payed, I am Diſcharged.</p>
            <p>But now, <hi>What will ye do in the Day of Viſitation?</hi> Conſider it; It will put you ſore to it. Sin will ſeek out and find you out; <hi>Juſtice</hi> will Purſue you: And if ye let it come to that, Remember this, they that come to the <hi>Judgement of God</hi> Unpardoned, never goes without Condemnation. They uſe to ſay of ſome Priſoners, they that Enter by ſuch a Gate comes out to the Scaffold again: So they that Venture upon the <hi>Tribunal of GOD</hi> Unpardoned, What will come of them? They never come out Uncondemned. What will you do then? Even this, if you anſwer rightly; I muſt go to <hi>Hell.</hi> And what have I for that?</p>
            <p>A Second <hi>Queſtion</hi> is this, <hi>To whom will ye Flee for Help?</hi> That Imports this, Is there any in the World can Shelter you againſt GOD? Ye have GOD your <hi>Purſuer,</hi> remember that. Where will ye get a Sheltet? Where will ye Flee to? Is any Stronger nor GOD? Can any Hide you from GOD? Can any come between you &amp; GOD? and take off your Reproof from of your Hand, and ſay here I am to Anſwer for him, I
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101324:10"/>
bade him do ſo: Nay, nay, ye will have enough to do to Anſwer for your own. Your bidding is ſinfull, and his obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is ſinfull, and both ſhall Suffer. We ſhall ſay this one word, Let every Man look to what Obedience he gives to <hi>Powers,</hi> to <hi>Rulers,</hi> to <hi>Tyrrants;</hi> They are no <hi>Rulers</hi> but <hi>Tyrrants.</hi> It's true they are <hi>Powers;</hi> but not <hi>Powers</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of GOD, that is a Terrour to <hi>Evil Works,</hi> and a Praiſe to <hi>Good.</hi> Well, let every Man look to what Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence he gives to <hi>Wicked Laws:</hi> It will not be that it is the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Law;</hi> It will not be <hi>Kings-Courts,</hi> nor <hi>Councils,</hi> or <hi>Parliament;</hi> They muſt be looked over, if they have not the Character of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Equity,</hi> there muſt none of them be Obeyed. They will ſpeak of a Sacred Character on them; There is no Sacred Character on any: There muſt be another kind of a Stamp. But <hi>Laws</hi> muſt be Stamped with this, with <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Equity,</hi> and ſo they have the <hi>Authority</hi> of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> as well as the Authority of Men; And if ye Obey them without conſidering whether or no they have this <hi>Mark,</hi> in O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying of them, ye Diſobey GOD; and Remember this, ſtand to it. Now ye ſee the many Orders that hath gone forth, ſo that ye cannot do ſo much as give a Souldier Provenent for his Beaſt, but ye Diſpleaſe GOD. Let them take what they will, and be anſwerable to GOD for it; but my Hand ſhall not give it. There are many who thinks nothing of it. Wofull Creatures, think you nothing to Uphold <hi>Souldiers,</hi> all whoſe Works is to Fight againſt <hi>GOD</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi> Now ſee if ever there was an other Turn in their Hand. But before we proceed to the next <hi>Queſtion,</hi> we ſhall ſpeak a few words, <hi>To whom will ye Flee?</hi> Who will Shelter you againſt <hi>GOD?</hi> There was never a Man ſo Great, but there was ay ſome flee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from him, and there was ſome <hi>Power</hi> to which we might have joined our ſelves that would be able to Defend us from him. <hi>But where will you Flee? GOD</hi> is the <hi>Purſuer,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:101324:11"/>
Who can be the <hi>Defender?</hi> We ſhall ſay that one word, There would not be ſuch ready Obedience to the Sinfull Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of Men, if the <hi>Greatneſs</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> were Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered. It is a Dreadfull Thing to fall into the Hands of the <hi>Living GOD.</hi> I put my ſelf in the Hands of <hi>Juſtice</hi> by giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Obedience to <hi>Sinfull Laws.</hi> I Homologate their Deed, and my Obedience is as if I Conſented to their Deed; So they come to every Mans Door, obey, or not obey: He who o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beys, Conſents to their <hi>Laws;</hi> and he that diſobeys, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, and Proteſts: But the Thing that is evidently held out, (for we will not return again) is this, in all the World a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Juſtice and the Stroaks of <hi>GOD, Where will ye Flee, to whom will ye Flee for Help?</hi> Go your way, and do as ye will: But Remember, this you ſhall have, the <hi>Justice</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> to purſue you. Next, <hi>and to whom will you Flee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now the next and laſt <hi>Queſtion,</hi> is this, <hi>And where will ye leave your Glory?</hi> What means he by this? They would hide their Glory that it ſhould not be Stained. Nay, there is more in it nor that; There Glory ſhall be, as it were, a Sting. How are ye therein? It will be ſaid to <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Rulers,</hi> How got ye that Glory? Then they would gladly be quite of all their Ill-gotten Glory, leſt the Juſt Judgement of <hi>GOD</hi> come on them when they are upon their Thrones, becauſe they got them Ill, and uſed them VVorſe. <hi>Now where will ye leave your Glory?</hi> VVell then, Remember that the Day is coming when theſe Things that Men boaſt of, they would gladly hide them, becauſe it will be their Ruine, when <hi>GOD</hi> is <hi>Judge,</hi> Verſe 4. <hi>Without me they ſhall bow down under the Priſoners, and ſhall fall under the Slain,</hi> &amp;c. VVe ſhall ſay this one word from it; It is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to want <hi>GOD,</hi> but it is more to have <hi>GOD.</hi> One Enemy (without me) if Judgement come, ye ſhall fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, tho' they were Priſoners and Slain-Men, they ſhall
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101324:11"/>
be enough to Slay you; without me, ye cannot bide nor bear <hi>Judgements;</hi> but much leſs can ye able to bear, when I am not only abſent from you, but turned to be your Enemy. VVe ſhall now haſten to an end.</p>
            <p>The firſt Thing Obſervable, is this, <hi>There is a time of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation coming, and all has need to Prepare for it:</hi> For it will put all Sore to it. VVhat Sin have ye? VVhat Debt have ye Payed? VVhat Diſcharge have ye? There is a Two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold <hi>Viſitation,</hi> (to wit) Of <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Judgement. Firſt,</hi> Of <hi>Viſitation</hi> in <hi>Mercy;</hi> Theſe words are ſpoken. VVe heard that <hi>GOD</hi> had Viſited <hi>his</hi> People by giving them Bread. But, <hi>Secondly,</hi> There is another <hi>Viſitation</hi> of <hi>Judgement:</hi> The <hi>Justice</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> will go about and hold <hi>his Court;</hi> It will go about, and through all the <hi>Land</hi> and keep its <hi>Court,</hi> and Arraign all <hi>Subjects,</hi> all <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>Rulers</hi> are as well <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi> here, as the Meaneſt <hi>Beggar.</hi> O but it is wonderfull to hear tell that the <hi>Ministers</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> ſhould Talk at ſuch a Rate. VVhere was ever ſuch a Thing as that heard? VVhat <hi>Scripture</hi> can you get (ſay they) for to Excommunicat <hi>Kings.</hi> Are they not <hi>Creatures</hi> and <hi>Subjects</hi> to <hi>GOD?</hi> And are they not bound to be Holy as well as the Meaneſt. This word we ſhall ſay, Unworthy are they that ever they ſhould be Cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Authority that follows not GOD with it. VVill not GOD Judge <hi>Kings?</hi> And ſhould not the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> Excommunicate <hi>Kings?</hi> But the <hi>Scripture</hi> that ſays, <hi>Kings</hi> ought to be Excommunicat; ſays, put away the <hi>Wicked Perſon</hi> from amongſt you. And if a <hi>King</hi> be a <hi>Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Perſon,</hi> it ſays, put him away. But the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> has wofully perverted the <hi>Power</hi> which GOD has given them; For they have Excommunicat <hi>Godly</hi> and <hi>Holy-Men;</hi> and the Excommunication of <hi>Godly,</hi> and VVorthy, and Valiant <hi>Strachan,</hi> is lying upon the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and they have neglected the Excommunication of the moſt Vile
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101324:12"/>
and Profligate Perſons. Are <hi>Kings</hi> excemed then? There
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>Viſitation</hi> of <hi>Judgement,</hi> we ſay, and
it is of Two or Thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Kinds.</hi> There is a
<hi>Temporal Viſitation:</hi> GOD ſits a whil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> in one
<hi>Land,</hi> as it were, and a while in another <hi>Land,</hi>
an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>He</hi> Judges, and executes <hi>Judgement,</hi> and
makes the <hi>Pesti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lence</hi> ſometimes to be the <hi>Rope,</hi>
ſometimes the <hi>Sword,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>times the <hi>Famine;</hi> So
that all theſe are <hi>Viſitations of Judge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment. Scotland</hi>
has been long Unviſited; now the Long<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the Sorer; it will have a <hi>Sore Viſitation.</hi> O! for Wiſdom O! for Tenderneſs to Tremble: For Wiſdom to Foreſee, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> for Grace to Prepare againſt the Day of <hi>Viſitation,</hi> and a <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vere</hi> GOD. But next, There is a Great <hi>Viſitation</hi> of the whole when all the <hi>World</hi> ſhall be Viſited; and this is ſuch a Nar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>row <hi>Net</hi> that None will go throw: Ye may Eſcape <hi>Viſitati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons</hi> on <hi>Earth,</hi> and win by the ſides of that <hi>Net</hi> one Way o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> another by Providence: But there is a <hi>Net</hi> coming that wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Catch all. What will ye do? Tho' ye ſhould win by all Things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ye will never win by the <hi>Judgement of GOD,</hi> and the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bunal of GOD.</hi> What will ye do then when you come there?</p>
            <closer>Let us Pray.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
