<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christian supports under the terrors of death a sermon preached to Sir John Friend in Newgate, preparatory to his sufferings / by Shadrach Cooke ...</title>
            <author>Cooke, Shadrach, 1655?-1724?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34428</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6036</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41901</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19720091</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19720091</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109336</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A34428)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109336)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1698:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christian supports under the terrors of death a sermon preached to Sir John Friend in Newgate, preparatory to his sufferings / by Shadrach Cooke ...</title>
                  <author>Cooke, Shadrach, 1655?-1724?</author>
                  <author>Friend, John, Sir, d. 1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for E. Whitlock near Stationers-hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement : p. [3].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XXIII, 4 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Death --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109336:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Chriſtian Supports UNDER THE TERRORS of DEATH. A SERMON Preached to Sir <hi>John FRIEND</hi> in <hi>Newgate,</hi> Preparatory to his Sufferings.</p>
            <p>BY SHADRACH COOKE Prieſt of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>E. Whitlock.</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall.</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:109336:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109336:2"/>
            <head>Some Books to be ſold by <hi>Dan. Browne</hi> at the <hi>Black Swan</hi> and <hi>Bible</hi> without <hi>Temple Bar.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SEveral Practical Diſcourſes, in three Vol. <hi>viz.</hi> Vol. <hi>1ſt.</hi> On the bleſſed Sacrament. <hi>In 2. parts.</hi> Vol. <hi>2d.</hi> On Charity and Humility.</p>
            <p>Vol <hi>3d.</hi> On Gods Law to Mankind, on Redeeming of Time, on Prayer. By <hi>Edward Pelling</hi> D. D. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain in ordinary to His Majeſty, and Rector of <hi>Petworth</hi> in <hi>Suſſex.</hi> All of them to be ſold ſingle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Regular Christian's daily Sacrifice,</hi> or a Collection of Prayers, chiefly out of <hi>David's Pſalms</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Common Prayer Book,</hi> to be uſe by the People in their private Devotion, ons all ordinary and ſpecial oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, with a particular Office for Sacrament Days. By <hi>Edward Pelling</hi> D. D. Chaplain to His Grace the Duke of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> and Rector of <hi>Petworth</hi> in <hi>Suſſex.</hi> The ſecond Edition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtian Practice</hi> deſcribed by way of Eſſay, upon the Life of our Saviour, by <hi>Stephen Skinner</hi> Rector of <hi>Buckland</hi> in <hi>Hertford Shire,</hi> and late Fellow of <hi>Trinity</hi> Colledge at <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Cauſe and Cure of Offences,</hi> in a Diſcourſe on <hi>Math.</hi> 18. 7. By <hi>R. Kingſton</hi> M. A. Prebendary of <hi>Sou<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and Chaplain in ordinary to His Majeſty.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:109336:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109336:3"/>
            <head>Chriſtian Supports UNDER THE TERRORS of DEATH.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSALM. XXIII. 4.</bibl>
               <q>Yea tho I walk through the Valley of the Shadow of Death, I will fear no evil, for thou art with me.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THAT mighty and continual care which the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence hath over us, is very grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully repreſented by ſuch ſoft and tender expreſſions, and characters of God, as do be ſpeak an abundant Affection and regard for us, giving us all the aſſurance and ſecurity imaginable of an infinite kindneſs and compaſſion conſtantly ingaged for us.</p>
            <p>So when our Lord doth comfort his Diſciples with the Doctrine of Providence, he thus expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it, <hi>Your heavenly Father knoweth, that you have</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 6. 32.</note> 
               <hi>need of all theſe Things.</hi> What can be dearer and and more ſollicitous than the Affections and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment of a Parent? Another of the like kind to the ſame end and purpoſe, is here mention'd and apply'd by <hi>David,</hi> who ſeems to aſſure or chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge to himſelf, the extraordinary care and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:109336:4"/>
of God, under all, the very worſt circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, from the ſutable character of Kindneſs and and Indearment he aſcribes to him, <hi>ver. 1. The Lord is my Shepheard,</hi> and thence makes this natural Inference, <hi>I ſhall not want.</hi> He will moſt certainly take care of me, for to continue the Parallel or Similitude here before us, <hi>ver. 2. He maketh me lie down in green Paſtures,</hi> or, <hi>Paſtures of tender Graſs, he leadeth me beſide ſtill Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> or <hi>Waters of quietneſs:</hi> Which is ſpoken with alluſion to the moſt grateful things or conditions, that God will beſtow upon, or provide for his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; his goodneſs will take care, that they ſhall have what is moſt proper and convenient for them. And when they are brought to any diſtreſs, he will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them out of it, reduce them to a happy condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſet them right and ſafe in their wayes, <hi>ver. 3. He reſtoreth my Soul, he leadeth me in the Paths of righteouſneſs for his Names ſake,</hi> and which is more, when they are under the moſt unpromiſing circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, in that ſad and doleful condition, which we muſt all come to and lie under, the diſmal preſſure and ſtroke of Death; even herein the People of God are relieved and ſupported by this extraordinary Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine care and Goodneſs; <hi>Yea, tho I walk through the Valley of the Shadow of Death I will fear no evil, for thou art with me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words are two things conſiderable:</p>
            <p>Firſt, The terror or ſeverity of a dying State, <hi>Yea, tho I walk through the Valley of the Shadow of Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet Secondly under ſuch diſmal circumſtances God doth moſt abundantly comfort and ſupport us; <hi>Yea, tho I walk through the Valley of the ſhadow of Death I will fear no evil, for thou art with me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, 'Tis obſervable, that holy <hi>David</hi> doth here remember us of the terror and ſeverity of a Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109336:4"/>
State or Condition; <hi>Yea tho I walk through the Valley of the ſhadow of Death;</hi> which is greatly ſignified by almoſt every word in it, Yea <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amſi,</hi> Notwithſtanding, imploying the utmoſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs or extreamity, I walk <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ambulavero,</hi> I ſhall walk; intimating a leaſurely, and ſo a more tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting paſſage, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in Valle,</hi> the <hi>Septuagint</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the middle, the depth or extreamity of the ſhadow of death <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in Valle umbrae lethalis,</hi> in the thickeſt of the deadly ſhade, i. e. <hi>in ipſiſſimâ &amp; profundiſſimâ mortis umbrâ,</hi> in the deepeſt and utmoſt ſhade or ſorrow of death. The Words here ſaith one, <hi>Notat horribilem quandam mortis ſpeciem &amp; figuram (qualis morientium oculis obſervatur) tritiſſimam.</hi> It denotes a very horrid appearance of death, and that moſt diſmal apprehenſion of it, which Men uſually have when they come to die, every way beſet with horror and diſtraction, in a word, a terrible and <hi>approaching</hi> deſtruction, (<hi>qui enim ad umbram accedit non longe à corpore abeſt</hi>) He that is in the ſhadow, is not far from that Subſtance, or thing it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> repreſents a dying State as moſt ſevere and terrible, agreeable to what he<note place="margin">Pſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 55. 4, 5.</note> tells us of it from his own experience, <hi>My heart is ſore pained within me, and the pains of death are fallen upon me, fearfulneſs and trembling are come upon me, and horror,</hi> or as it is in the other Tranſlation, <hi>an horrible dread hath overwhelmed me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Death, or rather the preliminary paſſage to it, and the way into the other World, is attended with great horror and affliction, and is beyond ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion harſh and terrible; to which <hi>Job</hi> may have ſome reference, when he ſaith, <hi>O that my<note place="margin">Chap. 6. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 3. 4.</note>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:109336:5"/>
grief were thoroughly weighed, and my calamity laid in the ballances together, for now it will be heavier than the ſand of the Sea, therefore my words are ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up</hi> (that is, I want words to expreſs my grief) <hi>for the arrows of the Almighty are within me, the poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof drinketh up my ſpirit, the terrors of God do ſet themſelves in array againſt me.</hi> And that this was the utmoſt extremity of diſtreſs or affliction, he could think of, appears from that Standard of Sorrow, which he makes it, <hi>Chap. 24. 1<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. If one know them, they are in the terrours of the ſhadow of death,</hi> which he therefore <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ls <hi>The King of Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</hi> The greateſt of all humane Evils or Miſeries. And now that great terrour and ſeverity, which doth accompany a dying State or Condition, may be occaſioned;</p>
            <p>Firſt, From the pains or agonies of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Mens miſgiving thoughts of their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture State.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Their foregoing all the Pleaſures and Enjoyments of this World.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The ſence of Guilt or Sin, that will then crowd in upon us.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, The more and greater Aſſaults of our Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Adverſary.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, The thoughts and conviction of an enſuing Judgment, Upon all which accounts our dying Circumſtances will appear ſufficiently dreadful and terrible.</p>
            <p>The firſt great terrour of Death doth ariſe <hi>FROM THE PAINS OR AGONIES THAT <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ALLY ATTEND IT;</hi> For however it is to appearance, there may be, its very likely, even in the ſmooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt paſſage from this to the other World, ſome rugged and uneven paths, which can be percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109336:5"/>
by none, but thoſe that tread them, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is that in the general there is a great deal of hardſhip and difficulty at ſuch a time, and in ſuch Circumſtances as theſe, from thoſe pains and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows which do naturally attend that condition, for in looſing that knot, in diſſolving the cloſe Conjunction of Soul and Body, there muſt be, and we have reaſon to ſay there is, a great deal of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceivable Anguiſh and Affliction, 'tis an extream violence to Nature, and the utmoſt contradiction to it. And therefore muſt mightily fret and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt us, for whence (but from the moſt horrid pain and uneaſineſs) can proceed ſuch extravagant convulſions, cold ſweats, deadly faintings, ſhort breathings, diſtraction of the Eyes, and other dreadful Agonies that attend it? For if theſe and the like, which we obſerve in daily Spectacles of Mortality are dreadful to behold; What muſt they be to thoſe poor Creatures that do, and to us that ſhall ſuffer under them? And therefore a good man, that is not afraid of death, can't but ſhrink and tremble to think of the way to it, that is beſet with ſuch horror and diſtraction in every particular; O my God, may be the language of the moſt pious Soul, I am willing to die and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for thee, being <hi>deſirous to depart and to be with Chriſt,</hi> which is better than a continuance here, but my greateſt concern is, how to come to thee on the other Shore, there is a great Gulf between us, I muſt be toſs'd on a boyſterous Sea, and wrack'd by dreadful Wayes, and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts. Is there no way to <hi>Canaan,</hi> but through a deſolate <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> and muſt I go through <hi>the valley of the Shadow of Death, to that Land which flows with Milk and Honey, that Heavenly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109336:6"/>
Jeruſalem?</hi> Theſe are things contrary to Fleſh and Blood, and ſuch as will make the ſtouteſt courage faint and tremble, the pains and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of death can't be expreſt or conceived by any but who are paſt or under them. And doubtleſs the holy Spirit of God doth in ſome meaſure intimate to us the ſadneſs of them, when it mentions it as a great bleſſing to men that it is <hi>appointed</hi> to them, but <hi>once to die,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9. 27.</note> and that there ſhall be <hi>no more death</hi> in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">Rev. 21. 4.</note> State. One undoubted priviledge whereof, is, that there ſhall be no more of thoſe dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful forerunners or concomitants of it, where are ſorrows ſo ſevere and terrible as endanger the ſafety of our Souls as well as Bodies, by ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging us to impatience, diſtruſt, and the like; thence ſays our Church, <hi>ſuffer us not at our laſt hour through any pains of death to fall from thee.</hi> Our greateſt troubles and moſt dangerous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict in this World is uſually our departure out of it; ſo that to this caſe alſo we may apply<note place="margin">Zeph. 1. 14, 15.</note> that of the Prophet, <hi>The great day of the Lord is near, it is near and haſteth greatly, even the voice of the day of the Lord; the mighty Men ſhall cry therein bitterly, That day is a of wrath, a day of trouble and diſtreſs, a day of waſteneſs and deſolation, a day of darkneſs and gloomineſs, a day of clouds and thick darkneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the Pains and Agonies of a dying State render it moſt terrible and dreadful.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It will appear again to be ſo, <hi>FROM MENS MISGIVING THO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GHTS OF THEIR AFTER STATE.</hi> I do not mean their doubtfulneſs of it, for I am apt to think, that the greateſt pretenders that way are ſufficiently
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109336:6"/>
convinced when they come to die, and the ſenſe of that their languiſhing Condition will ſoon rub up their Belief of another Life; but now moſt or all Men are under no ſmall Diſtreſs and Perplexity from the conviction and conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that future Life, for which none is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently fitted and prepared, but hath reaſon, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially from himſelf, to have ſome diffidence, ſome diſtruſt or ſuſpicion of his condition in it, and it is what becometh a prudent and a good Man; for an over-weening opinion of our<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelves, and a confident preſumption of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for Heaven may be ill grounded and miſtaken, and ſeems to be inconſiſtent with a truly devout and penitent Soul. <hi>Be not high minded but fear,</hi> is the Rule that ſuch go by even in theſe circumſtances. We muſt be ſenſible, and ought to be eſpecially ſo, when we come to die, That we have had a great work to do in a little time; and being that God now calls us <hi>to give up an account of our Stewardſhip,</hi> it muſt put us into very great Fear and Conſternation to think with our ſelves what we have done, and whither we are going, and how can we but ſuſpect our condition, when we conſider that we are not able to <hi>anſwer God one word in a thouſand,</hi> muſt it not then moſt deeply concern, and mightily affect our Souls, to conſider that near approach to their endleſs and unalterable State, and the beſt of Men may have ſome Fear or Suſpicion: at leaſt of their Condition in it. This now is their grand Affair, and if they fail and miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry here they are irrevocably gone and loſt for ever: Who then can avoid being concerned at this great and weighty change, when he
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109336:7"/>
thinks with himſelf, that he is now haſting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another World, and at the Gate of Eternity, though he fears not Death, yet the Apprehenſions of another State muſt ſtrike a damp into his Soul, and make him hugely ſerious and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed in his Thoughts; <hi>Men's Hearts failing them for fear</hi> of what may become of them in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther State. Nor is it blamable or unchriſtian to be ſo, for beſides what Reaſon the beſt of Men may have to ſuſpect themſelves, ſuch a Temper as this, will diſpoſe us for all due Care and Circumſpection in that moſt ſolemn time and ſeaſon, and ſuch an humble diſtruſt of our<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelves may and will have better Effects, than a very daring confidence and preſumption: For the comfort of good Men, at the moſt depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon Hope, doth ſhew that at the beſt they lie under ſome Doubtfulneſs and Inſecurity: And therefore as you ſee Men's miſgiving thoughts, as to a future State, is no ſmall Trouble and Perplexity to them in their dying Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>Thirdly Their Trouble<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> herein doth further a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, <hi>FROM THE THO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GHTS OF PARTING WITH ALL THE PLEAS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RES AND ENJOY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENTS HERE BELOW.</hi> Men that have liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the World muſt needs have ſome intereſt and affections fixed in it, and there is ſcarce any that do or can ſit ſo looſe to theſe ſecular Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, as to bear the removal from <hi>them</hi> with an even and undiſturbed Spirit; nay ſo far is it from this, that theſe frequently prove the moſt pungent Conſiderations or Reflections in that diſmal State: <hi>Have I,</hi> ſaith one, <hi>laboured all my Life time for nothing but</hi> Vanity <hi>and</hi> Vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109336:7"/>
of Spirit, <hi>for I find it to be ſo now; I am to be removed, and to be taken from it: For this have I beat my Brains, wearied and moleſted my ſelf, for this have I cheated and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loin'd, for this have I over-reach'd or ſupplanted my Brother, wrong'd or oppreſs'd my Neighbour, and muſt I be deprived of all in a moment? What ſorrow like to my ſorrow</hi> will the Worldling ſay? And thoſe pleaſures that others have too much indulged, will but the more perplex their Thoughts when they are thus forced from them; nay, even the moderate and lawful enjoyment of theſe things, will occaſion in us no ſmall trouble and vexation of mind, at this final parting with them: Tho it behoves us to do it with Chriſtian cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and Reſignation, yet we cannot without extream ſorrow and concernment ſay at that time, <hi>Farewel Wife farewel Children, farewel Friends, farewel the World finally farewel whatever was here dear and valuable.</hi> And give me leave to add, the more have been Mens comforts, and thoſe of good Men have been the moſt and trueſt, the more and greater muſt be the grief and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for that utter removal, and diſmal ſeparation from them.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The troubles of a dying State muſt be again very great, <hi>FROM THE SENSE OF SIN OR G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ILT THAT WILL THEN CROWD IN <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PON <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi> However we may forget God and our<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelves in a time of Health and Proſperity, when theſe decline or forſake us, we are uſually brought to a ſober Senſe, and in ſuch a languiſhing State and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition can hardly avoid it; Conſcience, if ever, will certainly awake when we come to die, and we may have obſerved the greateſt Affliction that Men have then ſuffer'd under, was their not being able to avoid their own thoughts, which are now more bitter and terrible than ever, (and by the way 'tis
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109336:8"/>
not only Juſtice, but withal Goodneſs in God to make it ſo.) Now the Mind has quick and unbiaſs'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections on its own Actions, and ſets forth its Guilt in true and proper Colours, and therefore the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle may well ſay, <hi>The ſting of Death is Sin.</hi> No terror in this State like that which doth redound to us from our guilty Conſciences which have now got us under hold, and will laſh us ſeverely. We can't now diſguiſe or diſſemble our Guilt, there is no ſtifling of it by Riot or Intemperance; lewd and looſe Company can divert us no longer; all the live-long day our ſins will plague and fret us, and in the weariſom nights, when we count every minute, our Guilt will ruſh in upon our thoughts, attend us in every turn and motion, and render our Souls as reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and uneaſie as our Bodies. If what the Prophet ſaith of wicked Men be true at other times, 'tis much<note place="margin">Iſa. 57. 20, 21.</note> more ſo at this, <hi>That they are like the troubled Sea when it cannot reſt, whoſe waters caſt up Mire and Dirt. There is no peace, ſaith my God, to the wicked.</hi> When we come to die, the greateſt melancholy that ſhall then ſeize our Spirits, will be from the heavy load and burden of our ſins, that will be ready to oppreſs and ſink our Souls. Then we ſhall find that threatning verified in us, <hi>I will reprove thee, and ſet them in order before thine Eyes.</hi> And what grief or anguiſh can be comparable to that, which redounds from this? When we are going hence, and God gives us warning to remove, muſt it not concern and afflict us beyond all thought or expreſſion, to conſider the danger our Sins have now brought us to? They hide God's Face and Mercy from us, and in our greateſt Diſtreſs and higheſt need of Comfort, threaten us with utter Ruin and Deſtruction; and nothing now can be ſo cutting
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:109336:8"/>
and intollerable as the thoughts of a diſpleaſed and angry God. And well may that be ſo to us which was the greateſt of our Saviours troubles, for at his dying hour, the guilt of our ſins that lay on him, occaſioned the bittereſt Agony of his Soul, and that diſmal exclamation, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me.</hi> Moſt certainly the ſenſe of guilt will be the bittereſt Portion, and the very dregs of that <hi>Cup of trembling;</hi> our Hearts will faint, and our Souls will <hi>ſink within us,</hi> and we ſhall ſhake and fear, and <hi>cry mightly,</hi> and have on us ſuch paſſionate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment as is inexpreſſible, from the diſmal appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of the Divine Wrath and Indignation which our ſins have kindled and provoked againſt us. So that hereupon it may be ſaid with <hi>Cain, My puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 13.</note> 
               <hi>is greater than I can bear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, The troubles of a dying ſtate will appear further conſiderable, <hi>FROM THE ASSA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LTS OF O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R SPIRIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AL ENEMY, WHICH WILL BE THEN MORE AND GREATER THAN EVER.</hi> For to this we may apply what is ſaid of him, <hi>Woe to the Inhabitants of the Earth, for the Devil is come down unto you, having great</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 12. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Wrath, becauſe he knoweth that he hath but a ſhort time.</hi> And accordingly we may expect that he will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply his temptations now more vigorouſly than ever; for if he diſcharges this laſt part effectually, they are utterly loſt and gone, and he has gain'd them for ever. Wherefore he may be ſuppoſed now to ſet all his Engines on work, and to ply it cloſely, He takes all the advantages that may be of theſe extream and difficult circumſtances; herein he tempts us to fretfulneſs and impatience under God's hand,<note place="margin">Job. 2. 9.</note> to a diſtruſt or deſpair of his Goodneſs. <hi>Doſt thou ſtill retain they Integrity? Curſe God and die.</hi> If this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109336:9"/>
wil not do, he tempts us with too great preſumption on the Divine Goodneſs, to a neglect of due Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Repentance of our Sins, or diſtracts our thoughts with Secular Affairs: One way or other, he either keeps us from the Duties requiſite for that State, or endeavours to make us increaſe our Sin in it. Moſt certain it is, that the Devil doth now hope, and Induſtriouſly watch, for his Prey; the laſt effect of his Malice and Revenge. The caſe here may be ſomewhat likened to that mentioned of him, <hi>Rev. 12. 4. The Dragon ſtood before the Woman that was ready to be Delivered, for to devour the Child as ſoon as it was born.</hi> But may our Souls eſcape like that, and be <hi>caught up unto God and to his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Throne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, A dying State or Condition, is rendered very dreadful and terrible <hi>FROM THE THO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GHTS OR CONVICTION OF AN AFTER ACCO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NT OR J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DGMENT.</hi> The Priſoner when going to his Trial, hath all along every ſtep he takes, very ſtrange and perplexing thoughts, and is beyond ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion troubled and uneaſie within himſelf. And what muſt the caſe be with Men, when on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of another World, to think of that great and impartial Judgment and Tribunal, before which they are now ſummon'd to appear? And how muſt it effect and cut them, to conſider that they are now haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the preſence of that Righteous and Almighty Judge, who ſhall ſtrictly examine every thought and <hi>idle World, before whom all things are naked and open?</hi> To conſider that after <hi>Death</hi> comes <hi>Judgment,</hi> is that which makes a dying State the moſt Serious and weighty matter in the whole World. What concernment and anxiety muſt a man truly conſiderative, have at ſuch a time? I am dying, I am departing; that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109336:9"/>
is, in other terms, I am called to give up my Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts, I am going to be Judged before the Great God; behold, what Matter ſo weighty, what Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment comparable to this? This ſingle Conſideration duly weighed, renders ſuch circumſtances very ſtraight and terrible: No other can be the genuine effect of Mens thorough Belief and Conviction (at that time) of an approaching Judgment.</p>
            <p>But we have ſufficiently repreſented the black and tragical part, it may be high time now to draw the Curtain, and ſet forth a fairer Scene. Well then, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding a dying condition is thus ſevere and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, yet we have particular, extraordinary ſupports and comforts under it. <hi>Yea, though I walk through the Valley of the ſhadow of Death, I WILL FEAR NO EVIL, FOR THO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> ART WITH ME,</hi> to aſſiſt me in theſe ſtraights and neceſſities, and to afford ſuitable Helps and Advantages under them. And now thoſe great Supports which God doth give us in theſe moſt difficult circumſtances, may be conſidered under theſe following Particulars:</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, The thoughts of this State; as the Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God.</item>
               <item>Secondly, That God is therein peculiarly preſent with us, and gives us extraordinary helps and aſſiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his Divine Care and Goodneſs.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, The near approach to Heaven and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs.</item>
               <item>Fourthly, the Conſideration of Chriſt's Death and Sufferings.</item>
               <item>Fifthly, The Belief and Expectation of a future Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</item>
               <item>Sixthly, The Promiſe and Aſſurance of Pardon and Forgiveneſs.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:109336:10"/>Sevently, The Attendance of God's Holy Angels that are ready to receive our Souls.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Which duly and ſeriouſly conſider'd, will abundantly qualify and remove all the Terrours and Difficulties of a dying State.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>It is a very great Support at that time to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, That the STATE WE ARE NOW BRO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GHT TO, IS ACCORDING TO THE DETERMINATE ORDER AND ALLOTMENT OF GOD,</hi> in whom we live and move, and have our Being. He is the Breath of our Noſtrils, he put our Souls into theſe Tabernacles, and we are here only Tenants at Will, liable to be diſpoſſeſs'd at Pleaſure. And when we conſider, that <hi>'tis appointed for all men once to die,</hi> and that it is an irrevocable Decree of Heaven, that we <hi>M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ST</hi> all <hi>walk through the Valley of the ſhadow of Death,</hi> why ſhould we <hi>fear any Evil?</hi> Be diſmay'd or terrified, at that which is the will and pleaſure of the Almighty, as if ſome ſtrange and unexpected ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident did befall us? For may we not hereupon ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>That no man ſhould be moved with theſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 3. 3.</note> 
               <hi>afflictions, for your ſelves know that we are appointed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</hi> Is not God's hand in my ſuffering? Is it not in my death? 'Tis an undoubted mitigation even of this ſorrow and affliction, to conſider that God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed it as the unavoidable Lot and Portion of all Men living; ſo that, on this account, we may ſay, <hi>I will fear no evil, for thou art with me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, In our dying State or Circumſtances, <hi>GOD IS PEC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LIARLY PRESENT WITH <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, AND GIVES <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S EXTRAORDINARY HELPS AND ASSISTANCES OF HIS CARE AND GOOD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NESS. Thou art with me.</hi> That Providence which is always vigilant over us, hath then a more deep and ſpecial regard and concern for us. Are the very <hi>Hairs
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109336:10"/>
of our Head all number'd?</hi> And doth his Care extend ſo far, as that one of theſe <hi>ſhall not fall to the ground,</hi> but by <hi>the permſſion of our Heavenly Father?</hi> May we not hence juſtly conclude, that he is peculiarly careful of us in ſuch danger and extremity as this? <hi>Thou art with me;</hi> it is render'd <hi>Penes me, in loco quo ſto,</hi> Thou art near at hand, in the very place where I am, not as an indifferent unconcern'd Spectator, but to be <hi>a very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent help in trouble.</hi> Then this our good God is with us, to comfort our Souls, to ſupport our Spirits, to eaſe our Pain, and give us patience under it; to ſoften our cares, to mitigate the pangs and terrors of Death; then the <hi>Eternal God is thy Refuge,</hi> and <hi>underneath are</hi> the<note place="margin">Deut. 33. 27.</note> 
               <hi>everlaſting Arms.</hi> Such a mighty care of God over us, holy <hi>David</hi> was abundantly ſenſible of, and doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs very paſſionately, <hi>Thou art about my path, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout my bed. The Lord will deliver him in time of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>Thou wilt not deliver him into the will of his enemies. The Lord will ſtrengthen him upon the bed of languiſhing; thou wilt make all his bed in his ſickneſs.</hi> The <hi>Hebrew</hi> word ſignifies <hi>turn. Thou wilt turn all his bed in his ſickneſs,</hi> as it were to make him lie more ſoft and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. And he ſeems to have an undoubted reference hereunto, by what preſently follows in this verſe: <hi>Thou art with me, thy rod and thy ſtaff comfort me.</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>At quid adferunt ſolatii virga &amp; baculus? adferunt &amp; quidem plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ingeniouſly upon it, What com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort doth the <hi>rod</hi> and <hi>ſtaff</hi> here import? A great deal; <hi>adverſus latrocinia daemonum hoc molientium,</hi> They are thoſe Inſtruments whereby this great Shepherd doth defend his Flock from the rage and malice of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, that wait to devour us. I am not ignorant, ſaith he, that ſome of the Ancients, by the <hi>Rod</hi> here, underſtand <hi>ſome light affliction,</hi> wherewith God doth Chaſtize; by the <hi>ſtaff,</hi> ſome more ſevere and heavy
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109336:11"/>
Judgment, whereby he doth puniſh his People. An Opinion, though very pious, yet not ſo proper for this place; for obſerve, ſaith he, the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> doth not ſay, <hi>My rod and ſtaff,</hi> but <hi>thy rod and thy ſtaff,</hi> and therein ſpeaks more agreeably, to the Metaphor here of God's being a Paſtor; and ſo we may take the <hi>rod</hi> and the <hi>ſtaff</hi> here according to what is uſual in Scripture, the <hi>rod</hi> may be his <hi>aſſiſting Grace,</hi> the <hi>ſtaff</hi> our <hi>Defence</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our ravenous Enemy. <hi>Haec virga paſtoris Jeſu, hic baculus ſolatio ſunt gregi imbecilli adverſus terrores omnium malorum.</hi> 'This <hi>rod,</hi> this <hi>ſtaff</hi> of the <hi>ſhepherd of our ſouls, Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> will be our protection and ſecurity againſt all kind of evil. St. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaith he, mentions <hi>the fiery Darts of the Devil;</hi> theſe Chriſt keeps from us with his <hi>ſtaff</hi> here mentioned: <hi>Hoc an non magnum interim militaris itineris ſolatium.</hi> And is not this by the way, a great incouragement of our Warlike State? How dearly doth our Lord Jeſus love us, who, as you ſee, will neglect nothing that may any wiſe conduce to our Protection, our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment, and our Comfort?</q> Thus far he, which I have the longer inſiſted on, becauſe it is ſuch a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine, though unuſual Interpretation, and a ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble repreſentation of God's ſo great, and peculiar care, and regard for us, in this moſt ſtraight and difficult condition.</p>
            <p>To ſum up this Head; as nothing is ſurer than the day of Death, and our Departure out of this Earthly Body, which very likely may be attended with black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and terror, with dreadful Pains, and Agonies, too great to be expreſt; yet I may comfortably ſay, that herein <hi>the Lord is my helper;</hi> yea, though <hi>I walk thro' this Valley of the ſhadow of Death, I will fear no evil, for thou art with me. Tho' the Arrows of the Almighty <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in me, and his Hand preſſeth me ſore;</hi> though
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:109336:11"/>
my condition be painful and tormenting, and I be ſtretch'd upon my Bed with Grief and Anguiſh, and my Friends about me lament to think <hi>that the place which now ſeeth me, ſhall ſee me no more,</hi> notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Decree is paſt, <hi>That God hath number'd my Life and finiſhed it,</hi> and I am now beſet with gloomineſs<note place="margin">Dan. 5 26</note> and darkneſs, mine Eye-balls rowl, and my Soul is juſt on the wing, ready to take its flight into the unknown Regions of the other World, <hi>Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs I am continually with thee, thou haſt holden me by my right hand, thou ſhalt guide me with thy Council,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 73. 23.</note> 
               <hi>and afterwards receive me to glory. Whom have I in Heaven but thee, and there is none upon Earth that I deſire beſides thee. My Fleſh and my Heart faileth; but God is the ſtrength of my Heart, and my Portion for ever.</hi> Which brings us to another thing that will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and comfort us, in a dying State and Condition: And that is,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>THE THO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GHTS OR CONSI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DERATION OF O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R NEAR APPROACH TO HAPPINESS AND GLORY. Having hitherto run the race that is ſet before us,</hi> We may expect greater ſweats and troubles, and to be more tired, the nearer we come to the end of it. But this is the laſt Stage; if we can bear up under this only remaining difficulty, the day and the prize is ours; we may go on with Patience <hi>Looking unto Jeſus, the Author and Finiſher of our Faith.</hi> How muſt it incourage our endeavours, and ſupport our Spirits, under the ſoreſt preſſure of Death it ſelf, to behold, <hi>with an Eye of faith, the Glory ready to be revealed,</hi> and to ſee our Lord, with open arms, ready to receive us? Come, bear up under this, and as it is your worſt, it is your very laſt trial. There
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:109336:12"/>
are bleſſed Manſions prepared for you, <hi>where there ſhall be no more Death, neither ſorrow, nor crying; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 2. 4.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall there be any more pain, for the former things are paſſed away.</hi> Tho it may not ſeem conſiſtent with what I have already deliver'd, to leſſen the ſad and ſorrowful circumſtances of our dying hours, yet I may ſay, that if our Souls be duly fixed on Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Eternity, it muſt in a great meaſure abate, and will, I'm ſure, outweigh the worſt that can be ſaid or conceived of that State. This is able to out-ballance the utmoſt Tyranny of Pains and Agonies, and to diſpel all Clouds and Melancholy from our minds. The Night is come, but it brings us to the dawn of Eternity, and <hi>that ſhadow of Death</hi> is the confine of the days of Heaven. <hi>Yet a little while,</hi> and we are gone into <hi>YONDER</hi> World; and muſt it not be a mighty ſatisfaction to us now, to ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>We know that if our earthly Houſe of this</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Tabernacle were diſſolved, we have a building of God, an Houſe not made with hands, Eternal in the Heavens.</hi> To think that the pain will be over in a ſhort time, is ſome eaſe to my mind in the greateſt Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; but to add, and conſider withal, that it will be preſently ſucceeded with <hi>Joy unſpeakable and full of glory,</hi> muſt adminiſter to our Souls the higheſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation. <hi>I will fear no evil, for thou art with me;</hi> to ſay farther, and I ſhall be with thee, be transferred to that blisful State, to the preſence of God, <hi>where there is fullneſs of joys, and pleaſures for ever,</hi> is my moſt<note place="margin">Pſa. 16. 11.</note> unſpeakable ſupport, and the very height of comfort and ſatisfaction, <hi>The Years draw nigh in which thou ſhalt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.</note> 
               <hi>ſay I have no pleaſure in them, while the Sun, or the Light, or the Moon, or the Stars, are darkened. In the day when the Keepers of the houſe ſhall tremble. Alſo when they ſhall be afraid of that which is high, and fears ſhall be in the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109336:12"/>
way. The Silver Cord is looſed.</hi> Obſerve, upon that melancholy, and tho' Elegant deſcription, of our dying condition, <hi>Soloman</hi> ſubjoyns us a comfort againſt the diſmal thoughts of thoſe ſad circumſtances, and againſt Death it ſelf; the conſideration of our acceptance with God in the Immortal State, <hi>Then ſhall the duſt return to the Earth as it was, and the Spirit ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to God who gave it.</hi> In a word, this ſingle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, that we <hi>ſhall ever be with the Lord,</hi> duly weighed and rely'd on, will abundantly relieve and ſupport us againſt all the Powers of Death, in its moſt horrid and ghaſtly apperances, and ſufficiently ſubdue the great difficulties of the dying State.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, This is again render'd further eaſie and ſupportable <hi>FROM THE CONSIDERATION OF CHRIST'S DEATH AND S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>FFER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>INGS;</hi> not only as they do expiate our Sins, and ſo bring comfort to our Souls, as we may have occaſion to ſhew preſently, but withal, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his great and glorious conqueſt over Death and the Grave, which he vanquiſhed and ſubdu'd, in the very worſt, and moſt horrid circumſtances, that they might have leſs power, and exerciſe leſs Tyranny over us. Whereupon the Apoſtle trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantly ſpeaks, <hi>Death is ſwallowed up in Victory. O</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. 54.</note> 
               <hi>Death, where is they ſting? O Grave, where is thy vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory? Thanks be to God, which giveth us the Victory through our Lord Jeſus Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conſider that Chriſt our Lord underwent the ſame before us, and in a more diſmal manner than we are able to bear or imagine, is ſome mitigation in this moſt ſorrowful condition; conſidering withal, that in doing ſo, he hath made the way more ſmooth and paſſable for us. Death ſpent his moſt fiery Darts on him, and he hath ſo ſubdu'd his greateſt ſtrength
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109336:13"/>
and utmoſt power, that he either cannot, or dare not be over ſevere and rigorous with us; at leaſt, he can go no further than he will permit him, <hi>I am he that liveth and was dead, and behold I am alive for evermore,</hi> Amen: <hi>And have the Keys of Hell and of Death.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 1. 18.</note> Death is now purely under Chriſts command, and can do nothing but by leave from him; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, we may juſtly hope that our gracious Lord will not ſuffer him to exert his utmoſt fury upon us. How ſuitable then is that pious Prayer of our Church at this ſeaſon. <hi>O Saviour of the World, who by thy Croſs</hi>
               <note place="margin">Viſitation of the Sick.</note> 
               <hi>and precious Blood haſt redeemed us, ſave us and help us, we humbly beſeech thee, O Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, the troubles and Sorrows of a dying State, are again very much abated and ſubdu'd <hi>FROM THE THO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GHTS OF A F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RRECTION,</hi> which will ſatisfie our Minds and make abundant amends for all the doubts or troubles that do now attend us. What though we ſuffer under pains, and may be grieved to think that part of us ſhall be the Prey of Worms and Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet the belief of this truth will ſoon diſpel the ſorrows that ariſe from thence. The time is coming (and Lord, what joy is it in theſe ſtraights?) when my Soul now returning to God, ſhall meet this Body again glorious and refin'd, never more to be vext with, or ſeparated from it. <hi>This ſhadow of Death,</hi> and that ſorrowful Night, that is now beſet with Clouds and horrour, will conduct us to the morn of our Reſurrection; and how can we be <hi>ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful as Men without hope?</hi> This our Church looks upon as the moſt comfortable ſupport, for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of our own, or others diſſolution, when in its great Prudence and Piety, it appoints that Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon concerning the great Article of the Reſurrection
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109336:13"/>
in the Burial Service, a Doctrin if rightly fix'd and believ'd, that will render us <hi>ſtedfaſt and unmoveable</hi> in the deepeſt ſorrows. <hi>Thy Brother ſhall riſe again,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 11. 23.</note> was the comfort our Saviour gave to <hi>Mary,</hi> and is ſuch as will be able to bear up our Spirits, even in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vieſt Tryals of a Dying State. For how muſt it ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port me and others, at that time, to ſpeak after this, or the like manner? <q>You behold me, Brethren, ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly forſaken and diſtreſs'd; and, indeed, <hi>My Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint is bitter, for my Soul is exceeding ſorrowful, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto death, and my ſtroak is heavier than my groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</hi> But yet I would have you believe and think as I do, <hi>that I am only to withdraw for a ſmall ſeaſon; and as the Prophet ſpeaks, to enter into my Chambers, and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſai. 26. 20</note> 
                  <hi>ſhut my Doors about me, and to hide my ſelf, as it were, for a little moment, for thy dead men ſhall live; toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with my dead body ſhall they ariſe.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, obſerve what followeth: <hi>Awake and ſing, ye that dwell in the duſt.</hi> This long and ſolemn parting may cauſe grief in our hearts, and tears in our eyes; but ſhall we not be comforted, conſidering the time is coming, in which, <hi>All that are in the Graves, ſhall hear<note place="margin">St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 28.</note> the voice of the Son of God, and ſhall come forth?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, The Terrours of a dying State are mightily qualified and abated, <hi>FROM GOD'S MOST COMFOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TABLE PROMISE AND ASS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RANCE OF PAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DON AND FORGIVENESS.</hi> The greateſt and the trueſt ſorrow of a dying State, is that which is occaſion'd from the ſence of Sin &amp; Guilt: <hi>Hinc illae Lachrymae.</hi> This is the cauſe of our chiefeſt trouble and uneaſineſs at that time, and very juſtly too, for it is the moſt diſmal fate as ever was threatned; <hi>Ye ſhall dye in your ſins.</hi> But<note place="margin">St. <hi>John,</hi> 8. 24.</note> when I come with a meſſage of Pardon and Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and this be rightly receiv'd and well grounded,<note place="margin">St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 9. 2.</note> then 'tis, <hi>Son be of good chear, thy ſins be forgiven thee.</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:109336:14"/>
To be convinc'd that I have made my peace with God, and that my Pardon is ſealed in Heaven, this will ſtrengthen us in the midſt of ſorrows, even to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance of all pain and anguiſh: Inſtead of complaints, we may hereupon joyfully ſay, <hi>Lord, now letteſt thou thy Servant depart in peace.</hi> I do neither care nor va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue what I ſuffer, ſo I be reconciled to God, and have my ſins waſh'd away by the Blood of Chriſt. And ſuch may be the State of every one of us, for upon a ſincere Faith and hearty Repentance, <hi>God will have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 55. 7. Iſa. 1. 18.</note> 
               <hi>upon us, and abundantly pardon. Though your ſins be as ſcarlet, they ſhall be as white as ſnow; though they be red like Crimſon, they ſhall be as Wool.</hi> This bleſſed Promiſe takes away the <hi>ſting of Death,</hi> and puts us beyond the reach of its Terrour and Malignity; and therefore our Church may well preſcribe it as the great, or only Comfort, and Security, in ſuch a State or Condition. Thus ſaying, <hi>The Almighty Lord, who is a moſt ſtrong</hi>
               <note place="margin">Viſitat. of Sick.</note> 
               <hi>Tower to all them that put their truſt in him, to whom all things in Heaven, in Earth, and under the Earth, do bow and obey, be now and evermore thy Defence,</hi> and <hi>make thee know and feel, that there is no other name under Heaven given to</hi> Man, <hi>in whom, and through whom, thou mayeſt receive health and ſalvation, but only the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Seventh, and Laſt Comfortable Conſideration that we have againſt the great ſorrows of Death, is, <hi>THE ATTENDANCE OF GODS HOLY ANGELS READY TO RECEI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R SO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LS, AND TO COND<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CT THEM INTO THE MANSION OF THE BLESSED. For he will give his Angels Charge</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 91. 11.</note> 
               <hi>over thee to keep thee in all thy ways,</hi> certainly then in theſe, the moſt difficult of any. <hi>For are they not all</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Miniſtring Spirits ſent forth to Miniſter</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>for them that ſhall,</hi> or are ready to <hi>inherit Salvation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:109336:14"/>The Bleſſed God, whoſe Inſtruments the Angels are (and who is therefore alone to be ador'd for it) hath out of wonderful condeſcenſion towards us, aſſign'd thoſe glorious happy Beings, for our Safety and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in our dying Streights and Difficulties. For the Holy Scripture tells us, They carryed <hi>Lazarus</hi> his Soul<note place="margin">St. <hi>Luke,</hi> 16. 22.</note> into <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <hi>boſom.</hi> And in our Saviour's Dreadful Agonies, <hi>there appeared an Angel unto him from Heaven</hi>
               <note place="margin">St. <hi>Luke,</hi> 22. 43.</note> 
               <hi>ſtrengthening him.</hi> And if ſuch were able to bring him Relief in his Circumſtances, they may well do it to ours, which at the worſt, come vaſtly ſhort of his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful Death and Paſſion. Why now ſhould we be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maz'd, and terrified at the thoughts or approach of that moſt ſerious and ſolemn hour? <hi>Why art thou ſo</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 43. 5. 6.</note> 
               <hi>heavy, O my Soul? And why art thou ſo diſquieted within me? O put thy truſt in God.</hi> He and his Bleſſed Angels continually <hi>watch over us for good.</hi> God in the ways we have heard, or others, as he knows beſt, <hi>Will keep, thee from the hour of temptation, which ſhall come on all</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 3. 10.</note> 
               <hi>the World. God is our refuge and ſtrength; a very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent help in trouble: Therefore will we not fear, though</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 46. 1.</note> 
               <hi>the earth be moved. The</hi> Lord <hi>of</hi> Hoſts <hi>is with us; the God of</hi> Jacob <hi>is our refuge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In all time of our Tribulation, in the hour of Death, and in the Day of Judgment,</hi> Good Lord deliver us.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
