<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mr. De Sargues Universal way of dyaling, or, Plain and easie directions for placing the axeltree and marking the hours in sun-dyals, after the French, Italian, Babylonian, and Jewish manner together with the manner of drawing the lines of the signs, of finding out the height of the sun above the horizon, and the east-rising of the same, the elevation of the pole, and the position of the meridian ... / [edited] by Daniel King, Gent.</title>
            <title>Maniére universelle pour poser l'essieu. English</title>
            <author>Desargues, Gérard, 1591-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35744</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1127</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17188</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13154958</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13154958</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98167</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A35744)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98167)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 414:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mr. De Sargues Universal way of dyaling, or, Plain and easie directions for placing the axeltree and marking the hours in sun-dyals, after the French, Italian, Babylonian, and Jewish manner together with the manner of drawing the lines of the signs, of finding out the height of the sun above the horizon, and the east-rising of the same, the elevation of the pole, and the position of the meridian ... / [edited] by Daniel King, Gent.</title>
                  <title>Maniére universelle pour poser l'essieu. English</title>
                  <author>Desargues, Gérard, 1591-1661.</author>
                  <author>King, Daniel, d. 1664?</author>
                  <author>Bosse, Abraham, 1602-1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[17], 108 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Leach, and are to be sold by Isaac Pridmore ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Maniére universelle pour poser l'essieu.</note>
                  <note>Added illustrated t.p., engraved.</note>
                  <note>The diagrams are reproductions of the engravings by Abraham Bosse who published the original French edition.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [17].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dialing.</term>
               <term>Sundials.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-04</date>
            <label>Robyn Anspach</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-04</date>
            <label>Robyn Anspach</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. DESARGVES. <hi>vniverſall way of makeing all manner of Sun dialls<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Published by Daniell king<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; Sold by Isaake Pridmore at y, golden falcon in y ſtrand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> A<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 1659</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>De SAKG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ES</hi> UNIVERSAL WAY OF DYALING. </p>
            <p>OR Plain and eaſie directions for placing the Axeltree, and marking the hours in Sun-dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, after the <hi>French, Italian, Babylonian</hi> and <hi>Jewiſh</hi> manner.</p>
            <p>Together with the manner of drawing the lines of the ſigns, of finding out the heighr of the Sun above the Horizon, and the Eaſt riſing of the ſame, the Elevation of the Pole, and the poſition of the Meridian.</p>
            <p>All which may be done in any ſuperficies whatſoever, and in what ſituation ſoever it be, without any skill at all in Aſtronomy.</p>
            <p>By DANIEL KING Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Leach</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Iſaac Pridmore</hi> at the <hi>Golden Faulcon</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> near the <hi>New Exchange,</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:2"/>
            <head>TO THE ILLVSTRIOVS <hi>GEORGE VILLIERS,</hi> Duke, and Marqueſs of <hi>Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> Earl of <hi>Coventry,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Villiers,</hi> Baron <hi>Whaddon,</hi> and <hi>Ros,</hi> Knight of the moſt noble Order of the <hi>Garter,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving had the honour to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve your Graces great affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and love to Sciences and Arts, and your own excellency being moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent therein, together with your unparallel'd love and inclination to the ſplendour of your Native Country, in promoting Learning and Ingenuity. Theſe high merits with my own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb facs="tcp:98167:3"/>
obligations and attendance, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage my endeavours of the patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage to a new birth never preſented to the Engliſh Nation; preſuming by Gods aſsistance to bring forth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of worth that hathnot yet ſeen light, and if your Grace ſhall pleaſe to pardon my obſervant preſumption, you will hereby more strictly engage him ever to honour your Heroick worth, who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The very humbleſt of Your Servants,</hi>
Daniel King.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:3"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <head type="sub">Concerning the particulars of this TREATISE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas the Superficies or outſides whereon Dyals may be made, may be either flat, bowed, or crooked, plain or rugged, &amp; ſituated diverſly, the moſt part of the books treating of this matter, contain ſeverally the manner of making flat Dyals in all kinds of poſitions, Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zontal, Vertical, Meridional, Septentrional, Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ental, Occidental; Declining, Inclining; Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and Declining; and accordingly in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kinds of ſuperficies.</p>
            <p>They may alſo ſhew, for thoſe that are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of it, the way to find the elevation of the Pole, the Meridian line, the Declinings, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinings, and other particularities.</p>
            <p>But Monſieur <hi>de Sargues</hi> intention being to publiſh nothing, if it be poſſible, that is to be found in another Book, and to give you only the general Rule to make, and not to copy out a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of examples all differing one from another; I will give you but one example only in this vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume, by this univerſal manner, the diſcourſe
<pb facs="tcp:98167:4"/>
whereof may be applyed generally to all kinds of ſuperficies, and in what ſituation ſoever they be, without having any knowledge of the Pole, nor of the height of the Sun, nor of the declining or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining, nor of the Meridian line, nor of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing in Aſtronomy, and without a needle touch'd, nor of any kind of thing that may give a beginning to that, as you ſhall ſee yet better when we ſhall treat of the practice.</p>
            <p>And in practiſing this general Rule, you ſhall find at one and the ſame time, the elevation of the Pole, and the poſition of the Meridian, you ſhall know how to place the needle of your Dyal, and ſo you ſhall come to find the equal hours, which are called hours after the <hi>French</hi> way, <hi>alias</hi> Aſtronomical.</p>
            <p>The reſt being more curious than neceſſary, I thought to ſet down nothing elſe but thoſe two things; But I have been perſwaded, for the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction oſ ſome, to add alſo the manner of draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the ſame ſuperficies, the lines of the ſigns, the hours after the <hi>Italian</hi> and <hi>Babylonian</hi> way, and of the Antients, the height of the Sun, and the ſituation thereof, in reſpect of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Practice of Sun-Dyals.</head>
               <p>MAny diverſe things are repreſented in Sun-Dyals by the ſhadow of the Sun, to divers ends, the hour is ſhewn by them, and ſerves on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:98167:4"/>
for that purpoſe every day. Other things are repreſented alſo by it, as the ſigns, and other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularities, whereby it may ſerve ſometime for the divertiſement of a few</p>
               <p>In antient time the hours were not counted as they are now a dayes, and in <hi>Italy</hi> at this day they are counted otherwiſe than in <hi>France</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The manner that they count their hours in <hi>France</hi> is according to Aſtronomy, and here is at length a generall way of framing and making Dyals with houres equal to the Sun, according as the hours are now counted in <hi>France,</hi> after which way one may come to ſhew if need be, by the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of the Sun, and alſo of the Moon, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever can be ſhewn concerning other circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances to ſatisfie curioſity.</p>
               <p>There are two things which together do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thoſe kinds of Dyals of equal hours, after the <hi>French</hi> way, the one is as piece that ſhoots out or ſallies out of the ſuperficies of the Dyal, the ſhadow whereof falling upon this ſuperficies, ſhews what a clock it is, the other are the lines drawn upon the ſuperficies of the Dyal, each of them repreſenting one of the hours after the <hi>French</hi> way.</p>
               <p>They make Dyals after the <hi>French</hi> way where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there is only the ſhadow of one portion alone, as might be a button of the piece that ſhoots out, that ſhews what a Clock it is. But in this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral way, there is ſtill the whole ſhadow of all the length, in a direct line of this piece that ſhoots out, ſhewing continually what a Clock it is, of
<pb facs="tcp:98167:5"/>
which piece or length, you may take if you will a button, and mark the hours with that button only, together with all the other particularities that may be added to ſuch Dyals. Some call by one and the ſame name theſe two kinds of pieces the ſhadow whereof ſhews the hour, as well that ſame whoſe ſhadow ſhews continually the hour at length, as that which hath but the ſhadow of a button to ſhew it.</p>
               <p>But to the end we may diſtinguiſh both kinds of pieces one from the other, that ſame whoſe ſhadow ſhews the hour at length, and is the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal ſpring of all the others, I call it the axeltree of the Dyal.</p>
               <p>This axeltree may be made as well with a ſtraight, round, and ſmooth rod of yron or braſſe, as with a flat piece, and cut of one ſide in a ſtraight line.</p>
               <p>There are often other rods in the Dyals, which ſerve to bear up the axeltree that ſhoots out, and thoſe kind of rods I call the ſupporters of the ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltree.</p>
               <p>The lines that are drawn upon the ſuperficies of the Dyal, and that ſhew each of them one of the hours after the French way, I call them lines of the hours after the French way.</p>
               <p>In the innumerable number of ſuch kinds of Dyals as may be made after the French way, it happens that the ſuperficies of the Dyal, is either all flat, or is not ſo altogether.</p>
               <p>When the ſuperficies of the Dyal is all flat, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very line of the hours is a ſtraight line.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:98167:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>And when the ſuperficies of the Dyal is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together flat, it may be that every line of hours is not all ſtraight alſo.</p>
               <p>To make one of thoſe Dyals of equal hours af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the French way, by this univerſal way, there are two things to be done one after another. The firſt is to place the axeltree as it ought to be, that is, ſhooting out of the ſuperficies of the Dyal; The ſecond is, to draw the lines of the hours as they muſt be upon the ſame ſuperficies.</p>
               <p>And by means of this general way, you ſhall do thoſe two things without knowing in what day, nor in what time of the year, nor in what Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try you are, without knowing what the ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the Dyal is, whether it is plain or rough, nor which way it looks, without knowing any thing concerning the making and the placing of the parts of the world, or without any skill in Aſtronomy, without any needle touch'd with the loadſtone, or any inſtrument or figure that may ſerve for a beginning towards the making of a Dyal: But by the means only of the Beams of the Sun, by one general rule you ſhall place the axel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, and draw the lines of thoſe hours upon one of thoſe Dyals whatſoever the ſuperficies may be, and which way ſoever it looks, with all the celerity and exactneſſe that is poſsible in art; and if you are equally exact in every operation, you ſhall make by this means many Dyals upon diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſuperficies, and turned towards ſeveral parts of the world, which ſhall agree plainly among themſelves, and if you do not do it, you may be
<pb facs="tcp:98167:6"/>
ſure that the fault is on your part, and not in the rules, ſince that others do ſucceed well in it.</p>
               <p>There are ſome pieces that are requiſite for the framing of a Dyal, and whereof it is compoſed, ſuch are the axel-tree rod with its ſupporters.</p>
               <p>There are other pieces that muſt be uſed in the making of a Dyal, as Rules, Compaſſes, a Squirt, a lead with his two frames, one to mark with, and the other to level.</p>
               <p>There are ſome other things that you ſhall uſe alſo, as pegs, and rods, either of yron, or of braſſe, or of wood, ſome ſharp at both ends, the others ſharp at one end only, a table, either of wood, or of ſlate, or of any other ſtuff, flat and ſolid, to draw upon if need be, ſome ſtraight lines with the rule; and in caſe the ſuperficies of the Dyal were plain and even, you muſt uſe ſome fine ſtrings, ſupple and ſtrong, ſome maſtick, cement, or plaſter, or ſuch like ſtuff fit to ſeal with, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all which things you muſt have in readineſſe, whenſoever you will go about the making of a Dyal.</p>
               <p>And though you would learn to make but one of theſe Dyals well, it is fit you ſhould have ſome models of all thoſe pieces, and when you are upon thoſe chapters that concern them, as you ſhall underſtand an Article, it will be requiſite that with the models of thoſe pieces, you work at the ſame time an actual model of the thing which that article ſhall teach you to do, and ſo you muſt work from one end to another, till you have at laſt every way compleated an actual model of
<pb facs="tcp:98167:6"/>
this kind of Dyals, and you ſhall need to make but few of ſuch models of Dyals upon any ſuperficies, turned towards ſeveral parts of the world, to bring you acquainted with the practice of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Dyals to the life, or after the natural, in what kind or odd ſituation of ſuperficies ſoever they may be.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, you ſhall find the precepts and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions to be more troubleſome, than the actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al making or working, ſtudy only to be as exact in every one of theſe operations of making of theſe Dyals, as in the practice of other Arts.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:7"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Treatiſe being originally written in French, and generally approved of all thoſe that have any skill in the Art of Dyalling, I have thought it my duty to lay hold upon this occaſion, to ſhew how deſirous I have ever been to procure any good unto my Country. Therefore I have cauſed it to be carefully tranſlated into Engliſh, and have ſet it forth for the good and utility of all ſuch, as are curious, and true lovers of that Art; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting my ſelf moſt happy to meet with any occaſion, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I may contribute any thing towards the advancement of learning, and of the publick good,—<hi>Non enim no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis ſolum nati ſumus;</hi> We are not meant to be wholely and ſoly for our ſelves. As for the work it ſelf, I am ſo confident it will ſo gain the attentive Readers approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as that I ſhall forbear to ſay any more in commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, than that it is an expedite, and ſure way of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the ſite of the Axis, and of other requiſites in the framing of all ſorts of Dyals, of no leſſe curioſity, than uſe, performed without the ordinary rules and preſuppoſals of
<pb facs="tcp:98167:7"/>
the ſpiritual calculations and practice; I need premiſe no more, but adviſe to follow the directions that are ſet down through all the book, for effecting that which is promiſed, and thou ſhalt ſee the ſame plainly and readily performed. Accept then, Courteous Reader, this ſmall labour, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Testimony of my Love, as kindly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it cordially unto thee, hoping that God will enable me to give thee hereafter ſome thing of more conſequence,</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>So Farewell.</hi> Vtere &amp; fruere.
<signed>
                  <hi>Thine</hi> D. K.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:8"/>
            <head>To all <hi>Lovers</hi> of Ingenious Practices.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>French</hi> have excelled all other Nations in the Art of <hi>Perſpective</hi> for this laſt Age, their many Books and curious Writings ſo excellently compoſed do witneſſe for them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dyalling</hi> I accompt one kind of Perſpective, for that glorious Body the <hi>Sun,</hi> the Eye of the world, traceth out the lines and hour-points by his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urnal Courſe, and upon the reſubjected <hi>Plane</hi> by the laws of Picture, <hi>Scenographically</hi> delineates the Dyal.</p>
            <p>Many have writ upon this ſubject of ſeveral Countryes, in ſeveral Ages, many are the Rules and Practices ſet down; But among all thoſe of forein Parts, none hath performed the ſame with more eaſe, and leſſe trouble, than <hi>Monſieur du Sargues</hi> the Author; as wholy laying aſide thoſe tedious obſervations of Azimuth's, Decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, Reclination, Inclination, Meridian; Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and performing the operation only by three obſervations of the Suns ſhadow from a Point.</p>
            <p>It will not be amiſſe to give the Reader a ſmall conſideration hereof; the point B of the pin AB, in all the figures is alwayes one part of the Axis,
<pb facs="tcp:98167:8"/>
or <hi>Gnomon</hi> of the <hi>Dyal,</hi> and may be uſed to ſhew the hnur: this point B, you muſt imagine to be the Center of the Earth (for the vaſt diſtance to the Sun, maketh the ſpace betwixt the Center and ſuperficies of the Earth to be inſenſible) and from it at all times of the year (excepting the Aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial day) the Sun in its courſe forms two Cones, whoſe Apex is the point B, that next the Sun termed <hi>Conus luminoſus</hi> or the light Cone, the other whereof our Author makes uſe, termed <hi>Conus umbroſus</hi> the dark Cone, now in this dark Cone, if by any three points equally diſtant from the Apex B, the Cone be cut, the Section will be a Circle parallel to the <hi>Equinoctial:</hi> And thereby, as the Author ſhews many wayes, the poſition of the Axis or Gnomon may be found out, and the Dyal eaſily made.</p>
            <p>Now it reſts, courteous Countryman, that we be very gratefull, and every way forward to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage Mr. <hi>D. King,</hi> one very induſtrious in the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of Antiquities and Heraldry; who out of his deſire to ſerve his Country, hath cauſed this piece ſpeak Engliſh, hath been very carefull to ſee the Cutts well done, and will (no doubt) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to cauſe ſome of thoſe rare pieces of perſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive in French to be tranſlated.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then proſper</hi> King, <hi>untill thy worthy hand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The</hi> Gallick <hi>learning make us underſtand.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>JONAS MOORE
<hi>Matheſios Profeſſor.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:9"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>Iſaac Prid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Faulcon near the <hi>New-Exchange.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Rogue, or the life of <hi>Guſman de Alpherache</hi> the witty Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, written in Spaniſh by <hi>Matthew Aleman,</hi> Servant to his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Majeſty; the fifth and laſt Edition Corrected.</p>
            <p>A Phyſical diſcourſe, exhibiting the cure of Diſeaſes by ſignatures, whereunto is annexed a Philoſophical diſcourſe, vindicating the Souls prerogative in diſcerning the truths of Chriſtian Religion with the eye of reaſon, by <hi>R. Bunworth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seif-Examination or Self-Preparation for the worthy receiving of the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Supper; delivered in a Sermon concerning the Sacrament, by <hi>Daniel Cawdrey,</hi> ſometimes Preacher there, with a ſhort Chatechiſm: the third Edition.</p>
            <p>The Obſtinate Lady, a Comedy written by Sir <hi>Aſton Cockaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sportive Elegies written by <hi>Samuel Holland</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>A New diſcovery of the French Diſeaſe, and running of the Reins, with plain and eaſie directions for the perfect curing the ſame, by <hi>R. Runworths.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Vnſpotted high Court of Iuſtice, erected and diſcovered in three Sermons Preached in <hi>London</hi> and other places, by <hi>Thomas Baker,</hi> Rector of St. <hi>Mary the More</hi> in <hi>Oxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Chain of Golden poens, imbelliſhed with wit, Mirth, and Eloquence, together with two moſt exelent Comedies, <hi>viz.</hi> the Obſtinate Lady, and <hi>Trapolin</hi> ſuppos'd a Prince, by Sir <hi>Aſton Cockaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Aſcent to bliſſe by three ſteps, <hi>viz.</hi> Philoſophy, Hiſtory, and Theology, in a brief diſcourſe of Mans felicity, with many rem<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>keable examples of divers Kings and Princes.</p>
            <p>The Heroical Loves, or <hi>Anthcon</hi> &amp; <hi>Fidelta</hi> a poem, by <hi>Thomas Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croft.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Advice to <hi>Balams</hi> Aſſe, or <hi>Momus</hi> Catechiſed, in Anſwer to a certain ſcurrulous and abuſive ſcribler by, <hi>Iohn Heydon</hi> A<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>hor of advice to a daughter, by <hi>T. P. </hi> Gen<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>The Analyſis of all the Epiſtles of the new Teſtament, wherein the chief things of every particular chapter are reduced to heads, for the help of the Memory, and many hard places explained, for the help of the underſtanding, by <hi>Iohn Dale</hi> Maſter of Arts, and fellow of Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:10"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>1</head>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98167:10"/>
            <head>I Figure, To all ſorts of People.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>I come now to the firſt of thoſe two things that you are to doe for to make one of thoſe Dyals, which is the manner how to find the poſition, or the placing of the Axeltree.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen you have a mind to find out the right placing of the Axeltree of one of thoſe Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als by this general way, mark firſt which way the light of the Sun comes to the place where you will make your Dyal, and which way it goes out again.</p>
            <p>Then make faſt upon the place, as the figure above doth ſhew, with cement, plaiſter, maſtick, or the like, a peg or pin, AB, by the great end A, putting the other ſmall or ſharp end B as far out of the ſuperficies of that place as you can, In ſuch ſort that while the Sun doth ſhine upon that place, the ſhadow of the end of the pin B may fall always upon this ſuperficies, and for the reſt it is no matter how this pin or peg be framed, or placed, or turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, you are only to look to the ſmall end thereof, that muſt be in ſuch a manner, that you may ſet or apply upon it one of the feet of the Compaſs.</p>
            <p>Then in a fair Sunſhiny day, when the light is very clear, and the ſhadow very clean, whilſt it falls upon this ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in the figure below, mark in it, as the figure ſhews, in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98167:11"/>
one and the ſame day, at three ſeveral times as far aſunder as you can, three ſeveral points CDF, each of them at the end of the ſhadow of this pin AB that anſwers to the ſmall end of it B.</p>
            <p>You muſt nore that there is a certain time and place in which you cannot mark the points of the ſhadow; That is when this ſuperficies is flat, and ſituated after ſuch a manner, that the ground plot thereof being ſtretch'd at length, anſwereth and reacheth into the center of the Sun.</p>
            <p>For in that caſe how ſhort ſoever the peg or pin B may be, the ſhadow hereof cannot goe and fall in this ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, but at the end of an extreme length.</p>
            <p>Therefore when the days are equal with the nights, or very near, you cannot mark in this manner three points of ſhadow in a flat ſuperficies, which is ſituated in that manner called parallel to the Equator.</p>
            <p>When you have thus mark'd three points of ſhadow, you have no more need of the light of the Sun, and you may make an end of the reſt in any other time and ſeaſon, as well by night as by day, as I ſhall ſay three times toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for one and the ſame manner, in three ſeveral ways to be expreſſed, after I have briefly ſatisfied the Theori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciens that take pleaſure to ſee the reaſons of the precepts, or rules of the practice of the Arts, before they ſee the precepts themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98167:11"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>1</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:98167:12"/>
            <head>To the Theoriciens.</head>
            <head type="sub">This Reſolution will ſerve you.</head>
            <p>AFter you have conceived that the Sun in his full revolution of a natural day makes a Circle paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel to the Equator, and the reſt of this Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis, for Dyals.</p>
            <p>The three beams of the Sun or ſtraight lines, BC, BD, BF, make in their point or common end B. ſome angles or corners equal one to another; with an other ſtraight one that makes the fourth, which is the Axeltree of the Dyall.</p>
            <p>Now the poſition or placing of theſe three ſtraight lines BC, BD, BF, is given out; Therefore the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of this fourth which is the Axeltree of the Dyal is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven alſo.</p>
            <p>You ſhall have hereafter in the fourth figure an other reſolution of this kind, before you have the way to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſome problemes, or propoſitions about it.</p>
            <p>I ſaid to the Theoriciens, becauſe if you were not at all verſed in any kind of practice, either of Geometry or Art, you might hardly underſtand me at firſt concerning the 2d. &amp; third figures following, becauſe of the ſhort &amp; compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious way whereby I expreſſe my ſelf unto thoſe that are skilled in Geometry: but I can aſſure you, that when you have underſtood what is written in order for all ſorts of people, if you come again to theſe ſecond and third fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, you ſhall know at the very firſt ſight what they mean.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98167:12"/>
            <head>For the Theoriciens,</head>
            <head type="sub">And for thoſe that are skilled in Geometry.</head>
            <p>THe I figure is a plate of ſome thin, flat, ſmooth, and ſolid ſtuff<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as Iron tinned, or the like, being round, and having a hole juſt in the Center, greater or leſſer, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the occaſion.</p>
            <p>The II figure is a ſtraight rod, round, ſmooth, and ſolid, as of Iron, or the like, of the bigneſs of the hole in the plate.</p>
            <p>The III figure is as it were a whirl made of the plate, and of the rod put thorow the plate, in ſuch ſort that it is perpendicular to the ſaid plate, as the ſquire that turns round about doth repreſent unto you, and is ſo faſt that it cannot ſtir or move.</p>
            <p>In the V figure AB is the peg or pin that hath mark'd unto you the points of the ſhadow CDF, the rods or ſticks BC, BD, BF, are ſolid and ſtrong, as of wood, or the like, having each of them a ſlope edge in a direct line all along, going from the point of the peg B to each point of the ſhadow CDF, and are ſo turned or ordered, that in applying the whirl unto them, the edge of the plate may goe andtouch the three ſlope edges of the rods all at once; and the rods or ſticks are made faſt in this ſituation, in ſuch ſort that they cannot move nor ſtir.</p>
            <p>The rule that croſſeth over the three ſlope edges, BC, BD, BF, toucheth them all three, or elſe two at the time only, whereby it ſhews whether thoſe ſlope edges are all three in one and the ſame ſituation, or upon one and the ſame ground or no, and on which ſide is their hollowneſs when there is any.</p>
            <p>The hand applies the whirl unto it, and keeps it there till the Axeltree BO<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> come to touch the end of the peg or pin B, and that at the ſame time the edge of the plate EDH touch the three ſlope edges of the rods.</p>
            <p>And when the whirl is placed or ſetled after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98167:13"/>
the rod is the Axeltree of the Dyal, and placed as it ought to be, and there remains nothing elſe but to make it faſt in this ſituation or poſition.</p>
            <p>The IV figure doth ſhew, that if you goe to make uſe of thin and ſupple ſtrings in this practice or working, in pulling thoſe two mark'd with Ie, and Ih, to make them faſt in direct lines, they would make the two ſtrings mark'd with bc, bf to bend, ſo that you can doe nothing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly with them, which is the reaſon that <hi>Monſieur Deſar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues</hi> hath not thought fit to make uſe of them for the Beams of the Sun, but rather of the ſlope edges of the rods that are both ſtiff and ſtrong.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98167:13"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>2</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98167:14"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>3</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:98167:14"/>
            <head>To the Theoriciens,</head>
            <head type="sub">And others that are skill'd in Geometry.</head>
            <p>THis foregoing figure ſhews to the eye that all the pieces of the Inſtrument are made ſo ſtrong and firm, that they cannot bend.</p>
            <p>AB is the pin, by whoſe point B, you have had the points of ſhadow C, D, F.</p>
            <p>The three ſticks or rods BC, BD, BF, have each of them a ſlope edge in a direct line at length, going from the point of the pin B to the three points of ſhadow, C, D, F.</p>
            <p>The ſlope edges of the two longeſt ſticks or rods, BC, BF, have ſome portions made in them, equal every one to the third and ſhorteſt ſtick BD.</p>
            <p>The three ſticks IH<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ID, IE, are every one longer than BD, and all three made even, then they are joyned all by the end to one of the points EDH, of the ſlope edges of the other ſticks, BC, BD, BF, and their other ends I, are brought together in one and the ſame point, I.</p>
            <p>The rod BI<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is ſtraight, round, ſmooth and ſtrong as of yron or the like, it hath a ſtraight line BI, drawn from one end to an other, and one of the points B, of this line of the ſaid rod toucheth the point of the pin; And with an other point I of the ſame it toucheth the point I of the three rods or ſticks.</p>
            <p>This being ſo, the rod BI comes to be the Axeltree of the Dyal rightly placed, there remains nothing elſe but to make it faſt in this poſition or ſituation.</p>
            <p>The figure ſhews in the rods that goe from the point of the pin B, to the points of ſhadow CDE, how one may make faſt thoſe rods at one end to the pin, and alſo all together to one point, by binding them to it; And how they may be made f<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t at the otherend to one point of the ſuperficies of the Dyal, by faſtning them to it with maſtick, plaſter, cement, or thelike.</p>
            <p>This way is more ſure than that with the ſtrings; But
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98167:15"/>
yet it is not the eaſieſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor the leaſt troubleſome, in my judgement.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>To the Theoriciens,</head>
            <head type="sub">Another reſolution of the ſame kind with the former.</head>
            <p>THe poſition or placing is given of the four points BC DF, and the placing of the two ſtraight lines BE, BH, that divide in two the angles CBD, and DBF, and of the two ground plots that paſſe unto thoſe two ſtraight lines BE, and BF, and that are perpendicular to the ground plots of thoſe Angles CBD and DBF, are given out; Therefore the interſection or intercutting of theſe two ground plots ſo perpendicular is given.</p>
            <p>But this intercutting is the axeltree of the Dyal, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the poſition of the axeltree of the Dyal is given.</p>
            <p>Any one may frame at his pleaſure upon that which is granted concerning this compoſition, many other reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and divers compoſitions of problemes, and divers general ways of practice.</p>
            <p>In the mean time you ſhall have here three ſeveral ways one after another, to ſee which is the moſt advantagious for the actual practizing of the Art, and to induce you to ſeek or try if there is any other ſhorter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98167:15"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>4</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:98167:16"/>
            <head>For the Theoriciens.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Compoſition of the Probleme, or Propoſition, in Conſequence of the Reſolution made upon the lowermoſt figure of the firſt draught</head>
            <p>THe firſt figure is the place of the Dyal, with the pin and the points of ſhadow, CDF.</p>
            <p>Make a ground plot of it, II upon one ſtraight line BD, and with one point B, three Angles DBN, DBR, DBH, equal to the three Angles of the firſt figure, that are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the beams of the Sun, DBC, DBF, CBF, every one to his own reſpectively.</p>
            <p>From the Center B, II figure, and from any ſpace BD, draw a half circle that may meet in the points, DNRH, the ſtraight lines BD, BN, BR, BH.</p>
            <p>Make in the third figure a triangle DGV, with three ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, equal to the three ſpaces DH, DR, DN, every one to his reſpectively, as having the condition neceſſary for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Find the Center O of the circle EVGD, drawn about this triangle VGD.</p>
            <p>Draw two Diametters DOE, POB, of this circle, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicular one unto another.</p>
            <p>Lengthen one POB ſufficiently of one ſide and on the other.</p>
            <p>From one of the ends D, from the other EOD draw as far as that which is lengthened POB one ſtraight line DB, even with the ſtraight line DB of the II figure, for it muſt reach unto it, viz. In the Equinoctial at the point O, and in an other place at an other time, lengthen ſufficiently III figure this ſtraight line BD.</p>
            <p>Make in it the ſegments or cuttings even with the beams of the Sun of the I figure BD, BF, BC.</p>
            <p>Take in the III figure, in the ſtraight line POB, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently a point I other than B.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98167:16"/>Make in the IIII figure three rods or ſticks CI, DI, FI, each of them ſharp at both ends, and equal with the three ſpaces CI, DI, FI, of the third figure.</p>
            <p>Draw a ſtraight line along the Axeltree rod, mark in this line of the Axeltree conveniently figure IIII, one Cut BI equal with the ſpace BI of the III figure.</p>
            <p>Set figure IIII one of the ends of the ſtick CI to the point of ſhadow, C, one of the ends of the ſtick DI to the point of ſhadow, D, and one end<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the ſtick FI to the point of ſhadow F.</p>
            <p>Let the ends of thoſe ſticks or rods be ſo well faſtened to the points of ſhadow CDF, that they cannot ſtir.</p>
            <p>Bring together the other ends I, of thoſe ſticks in one point I.</p>
            <p>Put one of the point<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> B of the Axeltree rod to the point of the pin B, and the other point I with the three ends of the ſticks CI, DI, FI, ſet or joyned together. And if you have been very exact in the work, the point I of the pin will go and place it ſelf with the three ends of the ſticks ſet together in the point I, if not, you have not wrought exactly.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98167:17"/>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98167:17"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>6</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:98167:18"/>
            <head>To the Theoriciens.</head>
            <head type="sub">It is no matter whether the Figures come right to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, you are only to take notice what this inſuing Diſcours ordains you to do.</head>
            <p>MAke figure I with three ſtraight lines CQRD, DIPE, and CF, a Triangle even and like unto the Triangle figure III, of the three points of ſhadow CDF, upon the ſtraight line CQRD figure I. make a Triangle CBD, both like and equal with the Triangle figure III. of the Sun-beams CBD, and upon the ſtraight line FPID figure I. make a Triangle FDB, like to the Triangle figure III. of the Sun-beams FDB, make longer if need be figure I. on the ſide of D the ſtraight lines CQRD and FPID. By the points B and B draw a ſtraight line BRAYH per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicular to CQRD, and a ſtraight line BIAKL perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicular to the ſtraight line FPID, find out the end or point A, common to theſe two ſtraight lines BRAYH, BIAKL, and by this end A draw a ſtraight line AE perpendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular to the ſtraight line BRAYH, and a ſtraight line AG, perpendicular to the ſtraight line BIAKL, from the point R draw as far as the ſtraight line AE a ſtraight line RE even with RB, from the point I draw as far as the ſtraight line AG a ſtraight line IG even with IB.</p>
            <p>From the point E carry to the ſtraight line BRAIH a ſtraight line EH, perpendicular to the ſtraight line RE, from the point G, carrry to the ſtraight line BIAKL a ſtraight line GL, perpendicular to the ſtraight line IG, from the points B and B carry a ſtraight line BQ that may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide in half the Angle CBD and a ſtraight line BP that may divide in half the Angle DBF. By the points Q and H draw a ſtraight line QOH, and by the points P and L draw a ſtraight line POL, find the end or the point O common to the two ſtraight lines QOH and POL, and from the point A for center and ſpace AO draw an half circle that may meet with the ſtraight lines AL in K and AH in Y.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:98167:18"/>Now make in ſome other place even or flat, as in the ſecond figure in one and the ſame line BDFC three cuts BC, BD, BF, even with the Sun beams, figure III. BC, BD, BF, each of them to his own from the point B of this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond figure for center, and from the interval or ſpace EY or GK, of the firſt figure, draw an half Circle O from the point C figure II for center, and from the ſpace CO, of the firſt figure draw an other half Circle O from the point D of the II figure for center and ſpace DO of the firſt figure, draw an other half Circle O, and from the point F alſo of the II figure for center and ſpace FO of the I figure, draw an other half Circle O, and if you have done right, all theſe half Circles will meet in the ſame point O, if not, you have not been exact in working.</p>
            <p>By the points B and O draw a ſtraight line BO, take in this line a point at diſcretion, firſt make three rods even with the ſpaces CI, DI, FI of the ſecond figure, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one ſharp at both ends, make in the length of the ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltree rod figure III the ſpace BI, even with the ſpace BI of the II figure.</p>
            <p>Laſtly ſet theſe rods to the axeltree figure III as I have ſaid at the end of the fifth table, and the axeltree of the Dyal is placed.</p>
            <p>There are ſome ſituations of ſuperficies of Dyals, where practiſing this manner of drawing one or the other of the points LH or O comes ſo far from the ſtraight line CF, that you ſhould have need of too great a ſpace to come to it.</p>
            <p>But in what manner ſoever the ſuperficies of the Dyal may be ſituated, and at all times or ſeaſons of the year, I mean, in any ſtrange or odd kind of example that may be found, you may work or practiſe theſe kinds of draughts with as much eaſe as in the moſt eaſy pattern.</p>
            <p>And how irregular ſoever the example be, howſoever by the means of the points of ſhadow figure III CDF, you may make figure I an angle DBC even with the angle figure III of the beams in the Air DBC, and make alſo figure I the angle DBF even with the angle in the aire figure III of the beams DBF, and make alſo figure IIII an
<pb facs="tcp:98167:19"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>5</head>
               </figure>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:98167:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:98167:20"/>
angle CBF, even with the angle in the air figure III of the beams CBF.</p>
            <p>And by means of theſe three angles even with thoſe in the air between the beams of the Sun, you may chuſe at pleaſure within the lines that repreſent thoſe beams, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther points CDF and otherwiſe diſpoſed between them, then thoſe which the ſhadow of the point of the pin hath given upon the ſuperficies of the Dyal, and upon thoſe three points choſen out at pleaſure, you may make an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther triangle CDF, and practiſe afterwards this manner of drawing as far as the triangle CBO figure II than in this tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle; and in the ſtraight line BC, make BC, BD, BF, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with the beams in the air, BC, BD, BF, of the third figure, contained from the point of the pin B, to the points of ſhadow CDF in the ſuperficies of the Dyal each of them to his own, and after you have taken, as it is ſaid, the point I in the ſtraight line BO, you muſt make uſe of the points CDF, laſt made in the triangle OCB, for to ſet the rods CI, DI, FI, to the axeltree BI then to work on as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>To make other points inſtead of thoſe of the ſuperficies of the Dyal, you need only to make ſome at the two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities or furtheſt ends CF, and make BC, and BC, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual one to the other, and unequal with the middlemoſt BD but a little bigger, more or leſſe according as the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles DBC, DBF, are more or leſſe unequal among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and inſtead of making figure I the triangle CDF of the ſpaces between the points of ſhadow CDF of the ſuperficies of the Dyal, you ſhall make it of the ſpaces between the points that are ſet in the place of theſe points of ſhadow.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98167:20"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>6</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:98167:21"/>
            <head>To the Theoriciens.</head>
            <p>MAke in one and the ſame plain, as in the firſt figure, vith three right lines CgkD, CrtF, DieF, a triangle, CDF equal and like to the triangle of the three points of ſhadow, fig. IV. CDF make upon the ſaid three ſtraight lines CgkD, CrtF, DieF, three other triangles CBD, CbF, DBF, equal and like to the triangles in the air of the beams of the Sun, III. fig. CBD, CBF, DBF every one to his own. By the points B and b I. fig. draw a ſtraight line Bqg that may part in two the Angle DbF. Draw out of the point C at your diſcretion a ſtraight line aqkty perpendicular to the ſtraight line CgkD, and out of the point F, draw a ſtraight line hPirx perpendicular to the ſtraight line FeiD, make in the triangle Fcb the ſection or cutting Cl, equal with Ca, of the triangle CBD, and the ſection Fs, with Fh, of the triangle FbD, from the point t center, and ſpace tl, draw a bow lm, from the point k, center and ſpace ka, draw a bow am, that may meet with the bow lm, in m<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and draw along the ſtraight line km, from the point r center and ſpace rs, draw a bow sn, from the point i center and ſpace i, h, draw a bow in (hn) that may meet with the bow (sn) in (n) draw along the ſtraight line (in): Make in the ſtraight line (km) the ſection or cutting (ku) equal with kq. By the point (u) bring to the ſtraight line aqkty, a ſtraight line (uy) perpendicular to the ſtraight line (km); make in the ſtraight line (in) a ſection (iz) equal with iP; by the point (zx) carry to the ſtraight line (hPirx) a ſtraight line (zx) perpendicular to the ſtraight line (in) finde out the butt end (y) common to the two ſtraight lines (aqkty) and uy. And alſo the butt end x common to the ſtraight lines hPirx and zx, draw the ſtraight lines goy, and eox<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> find the butt end o common to theſe ſtraight lines gov, eox.</p>
            <p>Make in an other place figure II. a Triangle gqy, of the three ſtraight lines, as, gq, gy, and yu of the firſt
<pb facs="tcp:98167:21"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>7</head>
               </figure>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:98167:22"/>
figure; make in the II. fig, and in the ſtraight lines gy and gq, the ſection (go) equal to go of the I. fig. And the ſection gb alſo equal to go of the I. figure; draw if you will the ſtraight line (bo) of the ſecond figure. Make again in another place fig, 3. a Triangle (cbo) of the three ſtraight lines (bo) of the Triangle (gbo) of the ſecond figure. And of CB and CO of the firſt figure; and upon bc fig. 3. make the cuts bc, bd, bf, equal to the lines BC, BD, bF, of the firſt figure, every one to his own reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively. And if you have done rightly, the ſpaces fo, do, co of the Triangle cbo, fig. 3. are equal with the ſpaces FO, DO, CO of the firſt figure, every one to his own reſpectively. Take fig. 3. in the ſtraight line (bo) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your diſcretion the point (i) other then (b) make three ſticks ſharp at both ends, and equal to the three ſpaces ci, di, ſi, of the third figure: mark along upon`the rod or Axeltree the ſpace (BI) equal to the ſpace (bi) of the third figure: work as I have ſaid, and as the fourth figure doth ſhew you, and you ſhall find the Axel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree of the Dial placed in his right place. You may after this manner, as in others ſubſtitute, or bring in other points CDF in ſtead of thoſe of ſhadow of the ſuperficies, or face of the Dyal and work by this mean, every where with the like eaſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="illustration">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:98167:22"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 8,</hi> For thoſe that have skill in Geometry.</head>
            <p>THe higher figure is the place of the Dyal with the face unequal to the pin AB, and to the three points of ſhadow CDF, all markt, as it is ſaid.</p>
            <p>Get a flat and ſolid thing, as a ſlate, a board, paceboard, or the like.</p>
            <p>Draw upon it in the lower figure a ſtraight line BDFC, make in that line three cuts BC, BF, BD, equal with the three ſpaces BC, BF, BD, of the place of the Dyal, each of them to his own reſpectively, then from the point B of the lower figure for the center, and from the ſpaces BC, BF, BD, draw ſome circles DH, FE, CG.</p>
            <p>By this means you ſee whether the ſpaces BC, BD, BF, of the higher figure or Dyal, are equal or unequal one un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another, and when theſe ſpaces are unequal among themſelves, as it happens in this example, you ſee which is the leaſt, and which is the biggeſt, as in this example, the ſpace BD, comes to be the ſhorteſt of the three.</p>
            <p>Now from the point C of the lower figure for the center, and from the ſpace between the two points of ſhadow C and F of the higher figure, draw a circle E, that may meet in one point E, the circle of the ſpace BF, viz. the circle FE, for it muſt meet with it, then draw the ſtraight line FB, that may go and meet in one point H, the circle of the ſhorteſt ſpace BD, viz. the circle DH.</p>
            <p>Again from the point C of the lower figure for center, and ſpace between the two points of ſhadow C and D of the higher figure, draw a circle N, that may go and meet in the point N, the circle of the ſhorteſt ſpace BD, viz. the circle DH, for it muſt meet with it.</p>
            <p>From the point F in the lower figure for center, and from the ſpace between the two points of ſhadow FD of the higher figure, draw a circle that may meet in the point R, the circle of the ſhorteſt ſpace BD, viz. the circle DH,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98167:23"/>
for it muſt meet with it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> By this means the three ſpaces or ſtraight lines DH, DR and DN, of the circle DH, which is that of the ſhore<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſpace BD, have the conditions that are requiſite for the making of a triangle.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="illustration">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:98167:23"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 9,</hi> For thoſe that are skilled in Geometry.</head>
            <p>MAke in another place, as in the lower figure, a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle DGV of three ſtraight lines, equal with the three ſpaces, DH, DR, DN, of the higher figure, every one to its own.</p>
            <p>Find in the lower figure the center O of a circle, the edge whereof may reach to the points VDG, according as the lower figure doth declare.</p>
            <p>Draw a ſtraight line DOE, through the Diameter or midd'ſt of this circle.</p>
            <p>By the point O in the lower figure, draw a ſtraight line POQ, perpendicular to this Diameter DOE.</p>
            <p>From the point D in the lower figure, for the center and ſpace BD of the higher figure, draw a circle that may meet as in B, the ſtraight line QOP, for it muſt meet with it in one or two points, viz. In the times of the Equinoxe in one point only, which is the point O, and all the reſt of the year, in two points divided on both ſides from the point O.</p>
            <p>And that you may be exact in working, do as much on the other part, and of E for center.</p>
            <p>Draw in the lower figure the ſtraight line BD, which in the times of the Equinoxe is joyned with the ſtraight line OD, and all the reſt of the year is divided from it, and draw along this ſtraight line BD beyond the point D.</p>
            <p>Make in the ſtraight line BD of the lower figure two Sections BC and BF, equal to the two Sections BC, &amp; BF of the higher figure, each of them to his own reſpectively.</p>
            <p>Take in the ſtraight line QOP of the lower figure of one ſide or other of the point B, at your diſcretion, a point I, beſides the point B, and that may ſtand as far from the point B, as the occaſion may give you leave.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="illustration">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:98167:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 10,</hi> To thoſe that are skilled in Geometry.</head>
            <p>THen according as the lower figure ſhews you, cut three ſticks CI, FI, DI, ſharp at both ends, and equal to the three ſpaces CI, FI, DI, of the higher figure, each of them to its own ſpace reſpectively, and upon the rod be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, whereunto you mean to make the Axeltree of the Dyal, make a Section BI, equal with the ſpace BI of the higher figure.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98167:24"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>8</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98167:25"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>9</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98167:25"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>10</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:26"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>11</head>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:98167:26"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 11,</hi> For thoſe that are skilled in Geometry.</head>
            <p>AFterwards as you ſee in the lower figure ſet to the points of ſhadow CDF upon the place of the Dyal, the three ends CDF of the ſticks CI, DI, FI, each of them to his own point; and the point B of the Axeltree rod to the point of the pin AB, then bring into one point alone in the air I, the three other ends I of theſe three ſticks CI, DI, FI, and ſet them to the point I of the Axeltree rod.</p>
            <p>For the ends of theſe three ſticks, and the point I of the Axeltree ought to meet all four together in one point in the air I, and then you ſhall find the Axeltree rod placed as it muſt be in the Dyal. So that you need no more but to make it faſt afterwards in this poſition or pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, or elſe to place an other in an other place that may be a parallel to it.</p>
            <p>If the matter was only about that which is ſufficient to ſhew Geometrically the truth of the propoſition, it were ſufficient to have either the three ſticks only without the ſpaceBI of the Axeltree rod, or the ſpaceBI of the Axeltree rod with two ſticks, without a third. But to make the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſure and effective, you can not be confident that you have done rightly without a fourth ſtick that may ſerve for a proof; This is that which <hi>Monſieur de Sargues</hi> had a mind to impart unto you.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="illustration">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:98167:27"/>
            <head>Figure 8, The ſame thing over again, but in other Terms.</head>
            <head type="sub">To the workmen of many ſorts of Arts.</head>
            <p>VVHen you have markt the three points of ſhadow CDF in the place where you mean to make one of theſe Dyals, draw with the rule in ſome even or flat place, as you ſee in the lower figure, a line BD, FC, and make in that line a prick or point B where you ſhall think fit, or at your diſcretion.</p>
            <p>Then go to the place of the Dyal in the higher figure, take with the Compaſſes the ſpace from the point B, of the <gap reason="illegible: blotted" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pin<gap reason="illegible: blotted" resp="#APEX" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap> B to the point of ſhadow C. And with that ſpace come back to the line BD, FC of the lower figure, ſet one of the feet of the Compaſſes to the point B, and with the other foot go and mark in that ſame line BD an an other point or prick C, then with the ſame ſpace, give a ſtroak with the Compaſſe CG about the point B.</p>
            <p>Go back again to the place of the Dyal above, take with your Compaſſes the ſpace from the point B, of the pin AB to the point of ſhadow F, and with this ſpace come back to the lower figure; Set again one of the feet of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe to the point B, and with the other foot go and mark in that ſame line BC an other prick or ſtay F, and draw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain about the point B with the ſame ſpace of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe this half circle FE.</p>
            <p>Go back again to the figure above, take with your Compaſſes the ſpace from the point B of the pin AB, to the point of ſhadow D, and with this ſpace come back to the lower figure and put again one of the feet of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe to the point B, and with the other foot, make in the
<pb facs="tcp:98167:27"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>8</head>
               </figure>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:98167:28"/>
line BC an other prick or ſtay D, and draw again with the ſame ſpace about the point B at the ſame time a round ſtroak DH.</p>
            <p>Then look in the lower figure which of the three ſtroaks CG, FE, DH, is neareſt the point B, and which are the furtheſt off, as in this example you ſee that the ſtroak DH is nearer to the point B than any of the two others FE and CG, and if they were either two or three together it were no matter.</p>
            <p>When you know which of theſe ſtroaks of the lower fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure CG FE and DH, is the neareſt to the point B, and which are the fartheſt, as here, the ſtroak DH is the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and the two CG, FE are the fartheſt off.</p>
            <p>Go to the higher figure to the points of ſhadow C, and F, which are even with the two ſtroaks below CG, and FE, which are the furtheſt from the point B, and open your Compaſſes upon the points of ſhadow C and F, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member well the two letters or cotes upon which you have opened your Compaſſes, and with this ſpace come back to the lower figure, and ſet one of the feet of the Compaſſes to the point C, and with the other foot go and mark a point E, upon the ſtroak of the Compaſſe FE, for it muſt reach to it.</p>
            <p>Then draw with the rule by the two points E and B, a line EB, that may go and make a point H upon the ſtroak DH, which is the neareſt to the point B.</p>
            <p>Go back again to the higher figure, and open your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes upon the points of ſhadow C and D, and with this ſpace come back to the lower figure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſet one foot of the Compaſſe upon the point C, and with the other foot go and mark a point N<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> upon the ſtroak DH, which is the neareſt to the point B, for it muſt reach to it.</p>
            <p>Go back again to the higher figure, and open your Compaſſes upon the point of ſhadow F and D, and with this ſpace come again to the lower figure, and ſet one foot of the Compaſſe upon the point F, and with the other foot go and make a point R upon the ſtroak DH, which is the neareſt to the point B, for it muſt reach to it.</p>
            <p>After that, you have no more to do upon the place of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98167:28"/>
the Dyal, till you place the Axeltree as it ought to be, and you have in the lower figure upon the ſtroak DA, which is the neareſt to the point B, four ſeveral points or ſtayes DNRH to make three point perdus with, as you ſhall ſee, in the mean time remember when you open the Compaſſe upon the points of ſhadow in the place of the Dyal, to take great notice upon what letters you have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened your Compaſſe, that you may apply the ſame ſpace below upon the two ſtroaks which are equal with the two points of ſhadow upon which you have opened your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, and ſet one foot upon one of the ſtroaks, and the other upon the other ſtroak. And moreover that the points NR, may well come out from betwixt the points D and H; and that I have cauſed them to come in ſo betwixt them, by reaſon of the ſmallneſſe of the place, and what way ſoever they come to be diſpoſed, it is but one and the ſame thing ſtill.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="illustration">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:98167:29"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Fig. 9,</hi> To the workmen of many ſorts of Arts.</head>
            <p>SEt your Compaſſe upon the points D, and H, of the higher figure, and with that ſpace go to ſome flat or even place in the lower figure, and make two points D, and V, ſo that the ſpace DV below, may be even with the ſpace DH above.</p>
            <p>Then go to the figure above, and ſet your Compaſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the points D and R, and with this ſpace come back to the figure below, and ſet one foot of the Compaſſe to the point V, and with the other foot draw a line from the point D, to the point G, ſo that the ſpace VG below, may be even with the ſpace DR above.</p>
            <p>Go back again to the figure above, and ſet your Compaſs to the points D &amp; N, and with this ſpace come back to the lower figure, &amp; ſet one foot of the Compaſs to the point D, and with the other foot draw a line from the point V, to the point G, ſo that the ſpace DG below, may be even with the ſpace DN above, and may meet in G the other circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar line that you have drawn about the point V, for it muſt meet with it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">i.e. <hi>That are made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any aim, or heed.</hi>
               </note>And ſo you have made in the lower figure three points VGD that will be perdus or loſt. Now find a center O, upon which having ſet one of the feet of the Compaſs, and the other upon D, let this foot in turning the Compaſs about, go and paſſe by thoſe three points perdus VGD, then draw with the rule by the points, as it were O and D, a line DOE, and ſetting again one foot of the Compaſs to the point O, and turning the other foot to E, make in the line DOE, the ſide OE, even with OD.</p>
            <p>Then by the point O, draw a line QOP, that may cut the line DOE, in two equal parts; again ſet your compaſs to the points B, and D, of the figure above, and with this ſpace go to the figure below, ſet one foot of the compaſs to the point D, &amp; with the other foot draw from the point E, a line B, that may meet as it were in the point B, the line QOP, and make with this other foot of the compaſs a point B, in the line QOP, for it muſt meet with it, if you have done exactly.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98167:29"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>9</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98167:30"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>9</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:98167:30"/>When the dayes and the nights are equal, it meets with it in one point alone, viz. O, and at ſome other times it meets in two points, one of one ſide of the O, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the other ſide, as in the point E. Then remove your Compaſs out of his place, and with the ſame ſpace of the points B and D of the figure above, ſet one foot of the Compaſs to the point E, and with the other foot draw from the point D, with your Compaſs another line B, that may go and meet the line<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> QOP, with the line that you have traced with the Compaſs about the point D, and both of them in one and the ſame point B, for it muſt do it if you have been exact: And that ſerves to mark more exactly this point B, in the line QOP, how neer ſoever it is to the Point O. After that, Whether the Point B of the lower figure meets with the Point O or not, draw with the rule by the points B and D, the line BD, and draw this line BD, as you ſee beyond the point D.</p>
            <p>That being done, open your Compaſs upon the points B and C, of the higher figure, and carry this ſpace to the line BD of the lower figure, and from B into C.</p>
            <p>Set your Compaſs again upon the points B and F of the higher figure, and bring this ſpace to the line BD of the lower figure, and from B into F.</p>
            <p>And finally make in the line QOP, a point I, at your diſcretion of one ſide or other of the point B, and let it be as far diſtant from the point B, as occaſion will give you leave. And ſo you have in this lower figure from the point I to every one of the points BDFC, all the meaſures that are neceſſary for the placing of the axeltree or needle in your Dyal, in the manner hereafter following.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="illustration">
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:98167:31"/>
            <head>Figure 10,</head>
            <head type="sub">To the workmen of many ſorts of Arts.</head>
            <p>CUt three rods or ſticks ſharp at both ends as you ſee below, one CI of the length that is betwixt the point C, and the point I of the figure<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> above<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the other FI of the length that is betwixt the point F, and the ſame point I of the higher figure, the other DI of the length that is betwixt the point D, to the ſame point I of the higher figure, then open your compaſſe upon the points B and I of the higher figure, and bring down this ſpace up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Axeltree rod, and make in the ſame as you ſee, two points B and I with this ſame ſpace BI of the figure above.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98167:31"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>10</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:32"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>11</head>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:98167:32"/>
            <head>Figure 11,</head>
            <head type="sub">To the workmen of many ſorts of Arts.</head>
            <p>GOe to the place of the Dyal below which I have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed again, a purpoſe to avoid the confuſion of lines, and put the end of the rod CI to the point of ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow C, the end F of the rod FI to the point of ſhadow F, and the end D of the rod DI to the point of ſhadow D, and ſet the point B of the Axeltree rod to the point B of the pin AB.</p>
            <p>Then bring together into one point in the Air I, the three other ends of the three rods CI, DI, FI, for they muſt come in there together, and bring the point I, of the Axeltree rod, to the ſame point I in the Air together with the three other ends of the rods I, for theſe four things muſt come alltogether into one and the ſame point in the Air I, if ſo be you have been exact in working. And when theſe three ends of the rods and the point I of the Axeltree rod, are all four gathered together into one and the ſame point in the Air I, the Axeltree rod will come to be placed directly as it muſt be in the Dyal, and ſo you need no more but to make it faſt in that place, or to faſten an other either near it or farr from it, that may be even with it, or parallel to, or equally diſtant from it.</p>
            <p>If the four points I ſhould go and meet in the body of the Dyal, you muſt but take in it's figure the point I nearer, or in the other ſide of the point B, and make an end of the reſt as I have ſaid.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:33"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>8</head>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:98167:33"/>
            <head>Figure 8, I will ſay the ſame thing over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, but more at large.</head>
            <head type="sub">To all ſorts of People that have neither skill in Geometry nor in Arts; but are apt and ſit to learn them both<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </head>
            <p>BEfore you undertook to make this Dyal, you had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing about you, nor knew nothing wherewith to further you in it, and going about it, you have made uſe of the pin AB, as it were at a venture.</p>
            <p>Now you muſt conſider that having placed the pin AB, in this manner, you have given out of your ſelf in the end thereof a point alone unmovable and fixed in the air.</p>
            <p>Then by means, of this fixed point in the air B, and of the Sun-beams, you have found out three other unmovable and fixed points of ſhadow CDF, on the outward face of the place where you have a mind to make your Dyal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So you ſee that by means of this end of pin B, and of the Sun-beams, you have eſtabliſhed upon the place where you intend to make your Dyal four points fixed and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded one from another, viz, one in the Air, which is the point or the end B of the pin AB, and three in the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies of the Dyal which are the three points of ſhadow CDF.</p>
            <p>Whereby you have found alſo ſix ſpaces, that is to ſay, the lengths of ſix ſtraight lines unmoveable, fixed, diſtinct, and divided one from the other.</p>
            <p>For if you conſider well, you ſhall ſee that you have found out by this means the ſpaces, or lengths, or diſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that are from the point B of the pin AB, to every one of the three points of ſhadow CDF, viz. the ſpace from the point of the pin B to the point of ſhadow C, the ſpace
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:98167:34"/>
from the ſame point of the pin B to the point of ſhadow D, and the ſpace again from the ſame point of the pin B to the point of ſhadow F.</p>
            <p>And for your better inſtruction, if you will make theſe three lines viſible to the eye, ſet unto every one of them either a ruler or a ſtring ſtretch'd out in a direct line from the point of the pin B, to every one of the points of ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow CDF, as the points do ſhew it unto you; Aud ſo you may ſee the three lines BC, BD, BF, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe are inviſible in the Air.</p>
            <p>And beſides theſe three ſpaces or lengths, you have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo found out the three ſpaces or lengths that are from eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of the three points of ſhadow CDF, unto the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, viz. the ſpace from the point of ſhadow C, to the point of ſhadow F, the ſpace from the point of ſhadow C, to the point of ſhadow D, and the ſpaces from the point of ſhadow F to the point of ſhadow D, as you may ſee by the points that are there. So you have ſix ſpaces or lengths BC, BD, BF, CF, CD, DF, which you have already found unmovable, and fixed to the place wherein you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to make your Dyal, which are ſo great a furtherance unto your work, that there remains nothing elſe to do, but by the help and means of the ſaid ſix ſpaces or lengths, to find alſo three or four more, that you may have all that is requiſite for the placing of the Axeltree rod of your Dyal as it ought to be.</p>
            <p>You muſt know that there are ſeveral wayes whereby theſe ſix ſpaces which you have found already, viz, BC, BD, BF, CF, CD, DF, are made uſe of to find out thoſe three or four more, which you muſt have to inable you to place the Axeltree rod of your Dyal as it muſt be.</p>
            <p>And that of all thoſe ſeveral wayes a man may have a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to one for one reaſon, and another man to an other for ſome other reaſon, and of thoſe ſeveral wayes <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur de Sargues</hi> hath ſhewed me three or four at the moſt, viz. that which he hath ſet down in the figure of his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del or project page, and of the others for which you muſt know how to make ſometimes ſomekind of alteration, and which I have ſet down in ſhort, there is one in the ſixth figure, and another in the ſeventh.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:98167:34"/>As for this it is ſuch, that there is no occaſion but you may practiſe it in effectually, and with the like eaſe eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where, without you need either to add or alter any thing, as you ſhall ſee preſently.</p>
            <p>Draw with the rule, as you ſee in the figure below in ſome flat or even place a ſtraight line BD, FC, then go to the figure above, and open your Compaſſe, and ſet one of the feet to the point B of the pin AB, and the other foot to the point of ſhadow C, and by that means you ſhall take with your Compaſſe the ſpace or the lengths that are from the point of the pin B, to the point of ſhadow C, whereof you will be pleaſed to remember, to the end that when I ſhall bid you for brevity ſake, take after the ſame manner with your Compaſſe ſuch a ſpace, you may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do with your Compaſſe even as I told you juſt now of the ſpace BC in the figure above.</p>
            <p>Now with this ſpace BC of the figure above, come back to the figure below, and ſet at your diſcretion one of the feet of the Compaſſe upon the ſtraight line that you have drawn there, as for example ſet it to the point B, then turning the Compaſſe about upon this point B, draw with the other foot a circular line CG, which circle by this means ſhall have a ſpace BC equal with the ſpace BC of the higher figure, and will meet the line BD for example in the point C.</p>
            <p>Go back again to the figure above, take there after the ſame manner the ſpace from the end or point of the pin B to the point of ſhadow D, and with this ſpace come back to the figure below, and ſet again one of the feet of your Compaſſe to the point B, and holding it ſtill upon this point B draw with the other foot a ſecond circular line DH, that will be equal with the ſpace above BD, and that may meet the line BC, for example in the point D.</p>
            <p>Go back again to the figure above, and take with your Compaſſe the ſpace betwixt the point of the pin B and the point of ſhadow F, and with this ſpace come back to the figure below ſet one of the feet of the Compaſſe to the point B, and draw with the other foot a third circular line FE, with the ſpace BF of the figure above, and that may
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:98167:35"/>
meet the line BD for example in the point F.</p>
            <p>By this means you have ſet away and tranſported the three ſpaces BC, BD, BF, from the riſe or place which they had in the place of the Dyal above in a flat and even place below; and all of them united together in one ſingle line BDFC, in which you may ſee whether thoſe ſpaces be equal amongſt themſelves, as they may be in ſome oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions which is indifferent, or whether they be unequal, by ſeeing whether the points CDF, are united together two or three in one ſingle point, or whether they are diſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited or divided one from another, and when theſe three points CDF, are diſunited or divided one from the other which happens moſt commonly, and that theſe three ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces BC, BD, BF, are unequal amongſt themſelves, as it falls out in this example, you ſee which of theſe ſpaces are the greateſt and which is the leaſt, conſidering which of theſe three points CDF is the neareſt, and which is the furtheſt from the point B, that is to ſay alſo that by this means you ſee which of theſe circular lines CG, EF, DH, is neareſt to the point B, and which are furtheſt as in this example you ſee that of the three ſpaces BC, BD, BF, thoſe two BC and BF, are the greateſt, and BD is the leaſt; and of the three half circles CG, FE, DH, you ſee that DH is the neareſt to the point B, and that the circle FB is nearer to it than the circle CG.</p>
            <p>When you have thus found out which of the three ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces BC, BD, BF is the leaſt, and which of the three cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles CG, FE DH is the neareſt of the point B. Go back again to the higher figure to the points of ſhadow CDF, and take with the compaſſe the ſpace betwixt the points of ſhadow C and F, which are at the ends of the two greateſt ſpaces BC and BF, and with this ſpace CF of the higher fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, go to the lower figure to the ſame point CF, and ſet one foot of the compaſſe upon either of thoſe points C and F, that is the furtheſt from the point B, viz. C, and holding ſtill the point of the compaſſe upon this point C, go and mark with the other foot a point for example E, in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:98167:35"/>
the circle of the other of theſe two points C and F, viz. in the circle of the point <gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which is the circle FE, for this other foot of the compaſſe muſt reach to this circle of the point F, as for example in the point E; This being done<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> draw by this point E to the point B a ſtraight line EB, that may go and meet, in one point H the circle of the point D which is the neareſt to the point B, and mark in it this point H.</p>
            <p>Then go to the figure above, and take with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe the ſpace betwixt the two points of ſhadow C and D, and with this ſpace CD of the figure above go to the figure below, to the ſame points C and D ſet one foot of the compaſſe to that point of theſe two C and D, which is the furtheſt from the point B, viz. C, and keeping this foot of the compaſſe upon this point C, go and mark with the other a point, for example N in the circle of the other of the two points C and D, viz. in the circle of the point<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> D with the circle DH, for this other foot of the compaſſe muſt reach to the circle of the point D, for example in the point N.</p>
            <p>Go back to the figure above, take with your compaſſes the ſpace betwixt the two points of ſhadow F and D, and with this ſpace FD of the figure above, come back to the figure below to the like points F and D ſet one foot of the compaſſe upon that point of theſe two F and D, which is furtheſt from the point B, viz. F and holding ſtill the point of the compaſſe upon this point F, go and mark with the other foot a point for example R, in the circle of the other of theſe two points F and D to wit, in the circle of the point D which is the circle DH, for this other foot of the compaſſe muſt reach to the circle of the point D, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in the point R. This being done, you have no more to do in the place of the Dyal, till you go and place the Axeltree rod in it as it muſt be, and in the figure below in the circle of the point D, which is neareſt to the point B, you have found by this means four points DN, RH, diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and divided one from the other, and when the two points N and R ſhould be found united together, it were no matter. Now by the means of theſe four points you
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:98167:36"/>
have three ſpaces amongſt others from the point D, to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of the three points HR and N to wit, the ſpace from D to H, the ſpace from D to R, and the ſpace from D to N, of which ſpaces you ſee which is the greateſt and which is the leaſt, when they are all three unequal, as in this example, for it may happen that there will be two found equal amongſt them.</p>
            <p>And with the help of theſe ſpaces DH, DR, DN, you ſhall find preſently thoſe four that you muſt have for the placing of the Axeltree rod of your Dyal, as it ought to be.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="illustration">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:98167:36"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 9,</hi> To all ſorts of People<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </head>
            <p>TAke with the Compaſſe in the figure above, of theſe three ſpaces DH, DR DN, that ſame that is the greateſt of all, as in this example here, the ſpace DH and with this ſpace DH of the higher figure, go to ſome place that is flat, as in the figure below, and ſet at the ſame time the two feet of the Compaſſe upon it, as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to the two points D and V<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and mark theſe two points as it were D and V, which by this means will be diſtant one from the other, the length of the ſpace DH of the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure above.</p>
            <p>Go back again to the figure above, take there with the Compaſſe the ſpace from D to R, and with this ſpace go to the figure below, ſet one of the feet of the Compaſſe to the point V, and from thence draw with the other foot towards the point D a circle G, which by this means ſhall be made of the ſpace DR of the figure above.</p>
            <p>Go back again to the figure above, take with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe the ſpace from D to H, and with this ſpace go to the figure below, ſet one of the feet of the Compaſſe to the point D, and from thence with the other foot draw to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the point V another circular line that may meet, for example, in G the other circle, which you have drawn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the point V, for this other foot of the Compaſſe muſt meet the other circle in one or two points, and for example, in the point G for one.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:37"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>9</head>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:98167:37"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 9,</hi> To the workmen of many ſorts of Arts.</head>
            <p>SEt your compaſſe upon the points D and H of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er figure, and with that ſpace go to ſome flat or even place in the lower figure, and make two points D and V, ſo that the ſpace DV below, maybe even with the ſpace DH above.</p>
            <p>Then go to the figure above, and ſet your compaſſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the points D and R, and with this ſpace come back to the figure below, and ſet one foot of the compaſſe to the point V, and with the other foot, draw a line from the point D to the point G, ſo that the ſpace VG below, may be even with the ſpace DR above.</p>
            <p>Go back again to the figure above, and ſet your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe to the points D and N, and with this ſpace come back to the lower figure, and ſet one foot of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe to the point D, and with the other foot draw a line from the point V to the point G, ſo that the ſpace DG below, may be even with the ſpace DN above, and may meet in G the other circular line that you have drawn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the point V, for it muſt meet with it.</p>
            <p>And ſo you have made in the lower figure three points VGD, that will be perdus or loſt.</p>
            <p>Now find a Center O, upon which having ſet one of the feet of the compaſſe, and the other upon D, let this foot in turning the compaſſe about go and paſſe by thoſe three points perdus VGD, then draw with the rule by the points, as it were, O and D, a line DOE, and ſetting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain one foot of the compaſſe to the point O, and turning the other foot to E, make in the line DOE, the ſide OE, even with OD.</p>
            <p>They by the point O, draw a line QOP, that may cut
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:98167:38"/>
the line DOE in two equal, parts. Again, ſet your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe to the points B and D of the figure above, and with this ſpace go to the figure below, ſet one foot of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe to the point D, and with the other foot draw from the point E a line B, that may meet as it were in the point B the line QOP, and make with this other foot of the compaſſe a point B in the line QOP, for it muſt meet with it, if you have done exactly.</p>
            <p>When the dayes and the nightes are equal, it meets with it in one point alone, viz. O, and at ſome other times it meets in two points, one of one ſide of the O, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the other ſide, as in the point E, then remove your compaſſe out of his place, and with the ſame ſpace of the points B and D, of the figure above ſet one foot of the compaſſe to the point E, and with the other foot draw from the point D with your compaſſe another line B, that may go and meet the line QOP, with the line that you have traced with the compaſſe about the point D, and both of them in one and the ſame point B, for it muſt do it if you have been exact, And that ſerves to mark more exactly this point B in the line QOP, how near ſoever it is to the point O. After that, whether the point B of the lower figure meets with the point O or not, draw with the rule by the points B and D the line BD, and draw this line BD, is you ſee, beyond the point D.</p>
            <p>That being done, open your compaſſe upon the points B and C of the higher figure, and carry this ſpace to the line BD of the lower figure, and from B into C.</p>
            <p>Set your compaſs again upon the points B and F of the higher figure, and bring this ſpace to the line BD of the lower figure, and from B into F.</p>
            <p>And finally make in the line QOP a point I, at your diſcretion, of one ſide or other of the point B, and let it be as far diſtant from the point B, as occaſion will give you leave; And ſo you have in this lower figure from the point I, to every one of the points BD, FC, all the meaſures that are neceſſary for the placing of the axeltree or needle in the Dyal, in the manner hereafter following.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="illustration">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:98167:38"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 9,</hi> To all ſorts of People.</head>
            <p>THat being done open your compaſſe at your diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the more that the occaſion will permit you to open it, it will be ſo much the better, and with this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening, ſet one of the feet of the compaſſe to the point G of the figure above, then turning about this point of the compaſs upon this point G, draw with the other foot four circles H, L, M, S, about the point G. viz. two H, and L from the point D, and two M and S from the point V, then remove your compaſs, and ſet one of the feet upon the point D, and with the other foot draw from the point G, two circles that may meet in two points, viz. Land G, thoſe two circles that you have drawn about the point G, from the point D, if this ſame foot of the compaſs could not meet with theſe two circles HL, that you have drawn about the point G &amp; from the point D, it is becauſe you had not opened your compaſs enough, before you did ſet it upon the point G, and in ſuch a caſe you ſhall open it more, and ſet it again upon this point G, and when this ſame foot meets theſe two firſt circles, for example, in H and in L, matk theſe two points L, and H.</p>
            <p>Afterwards remove the compaſs and keeping ſtill the ſame open, ſet one foot to the point V, and turning the compaſs upon the point V, draw with the other foot from the point G, two circles that may meet likewiſe in two points as S, and M, the two circles that you have drawn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the point G, from the point V, and mark thoſe two points S and M, in which thoſe two circles meet with the other two: And therefore note that before you make yout compaſs to tutn upon the point G<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you muſt open it in ſuch a manner, that when you ſhall ſet it afterwards upon the points D and V, the other foot may meet with the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles that you have drawn about the point G.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98167:39"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>9</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:98167:39"/>Then draw by the two points H and L, a long ſtraight line H, L, O, and by the two points S and M, draw an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther long line and as ſtraight, M, S, O, and theſe two lines HL and MS, being ſufficiently drawn at length, will meet in one and the ſame point O.</p>
            <p>By the two points D and O, draw a ſtraight line DO, and draw it at length, as you ſee from the point O, then ſet one of the feet of the compaſs upon the point O, and the other foot upon the point D, and turn that foot of the compaſs which is upon the point O. The other foot which is upon the point D muſt go and touch every one of the points G and V, and when this other foot hath gone over the point D, G, V, go and mark at the very ſame time with it a point, as E in the line DOE, and ſo you ſhall make the portion OE of the line OD, equal with the portion OD.</p>
            <p>Then open your compaſs at diſcretion more than from the ſpace OD, and as much as the occaſion will give you leave, the more the better, and the compaſs being ſo open at diſcretion, ſet one of the feet to the point D of the lower figure, and turning that foot of the compaſs upon the point D, draw with the other foot from the point O, two circles, as P and Q then remove the compaſs, keeping ſtill the ſame diſtance, ſet one foot upon the point E, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it about, draw with the other foot from the point O, two other circles, that may meet in two points with the two circles that you have drawn about the point D, and as for example in the two points Q and P, and draw with the rule by theſe two points, as Q and P, a long ſtraight line QP, that muſt reach to the point O, if you have been very exact in the working; if it doth not reach to it you have not been very exact, and I adviſe you to begin it again: If it reaches to it, go back to the figure below, and take with the compaſs the diſtance between B and D, then with this ſpace go to the figure below, ſet one foot of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs upon the point D, and turning it about, draw with the other foot from the point O, a circle that may meet the line QOP, as for example in the point B, for this other foot of the compaſs muſt go and meet that ſtraight line
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:98167:40"/>
POQ either in one or in two points, becauſe the ſpace from B to D of the higher figure ought never to be ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler or leſſer than the ſpace DO of the figure above.</p>
            <p>It is true that twice in the year, viz. in <hi>Autumne</hi> and in the <hi>Spring,</hi> when the dayes and nights are equal, that ſpace BD of the figure above comes to be equal with the ſpace DO, of the figure below, and in thoſe times that other foot of the Compaſſe that tutns about the point D of the figure below, meets the line QOP juſt in the point O. But at all other times the ſpace BD of the figure above is ſomewhat bigger than the ſpace DO of the lower figure; And then the other foot of the Compaſſe that turns about the point D, meets the line QOP, in two points, one of each ſide of the point O, as for example in B, for one.</p>
            <p>And that you may be the more exact, remove the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe from one part of the ſtraight line BO unto the other, and with the ſame opening of the ſpace BD of the higher figure, ſet one of the feet upon the point E of the figure below, and turning this foot upon this point E, draw with the other and from the point D an other circle that will meet (if you have been exact in the working) the ſtraight line QOP, and the circle alſo that you have drawn about the point D, and both in one point; as for example in the point B, which will inable you to diſcern well the point B in the ſtraight line POQ; mark this point B in the line POQ, whether you find it united with the point O, and ſo both of them making but one and the ſame point, as it falls out, when the days and nights are equal, or whether you find it divided from the point O, as it falls out in other ſeaſons, and as you ſee in this example<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Then draw with the rule by theſe two points B and D a ſtraight line BD, which you ſhall ſtretch out ſufficiently beyond the point D. When the days and nights are equal, as in <hi>Autumne</hi> and in the <hi>Spring,</hi> and that the point B is found to be united with the point O, the line BD comes likewiſe to be united with the line OD, and both together make but one line; But at any other time, as the two points B and O are two ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral points and divided one from the other, ſo the two
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:98167:40"/>
lines BD and OD, are two ſeveral lines<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and divided one from the other,</p>
            <p>This being done, go to the figure above, mea<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure with your Compaſſe the ſpace from B to C, and with this ſpace go to the figure below, ſet one foot of the Compaſſe upon the line BD, to the point B, and ſet the other foot in any place of the ſame line BD where it may light upon; as for example in the point C, by this means you ſhall make the portion BC, of the line BD of the lower figure, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual with the portion BC, of the line BD of the higher figure, make after the ſame manner with the Compaſſe, the portion BF, of the line BD of the lower figure, equal to the Portion BF, of the line BD of the figure above.</p>
            <p>Finally, in the ſame figure below, and in the line QOP, mark at your diſcretion another point, I, of one ſide or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the point B, according as you ſhall find it moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for the place of the Dyal, and as far from this point B, as occaſion will permit, the further the better, and ſo you have found the four ſpaces that you wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the perfect placing of the Axeltree of your Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al.</p>
            <p>For in ſo doing, you have found in this figure below the diſtances that are from every one of the four points BDF C, to one and the ſame point I, that is to ſay the ſpace from B to I, the ſpace from D to I, the ſpace from F to I, and the ſpace from C to I, which diſtances BI, DI, FI, and CI, will ſerve you to place the Axeltree of the Dyal in the manner following.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="illustration">
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:98167:41"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 10,</hi> To all ſorts of People.</head>
            <p>CUt (as you ſee in the lower figure,) three ſticks ſharp it both ends, one CI of the length of the point C, to the point I, otherwiſe of the ſpace CI of the figure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove: The other FI, of the length of the ſpace FI of the higher figure, and take with your Compaſſes the ſpace BI of the figure above, and being ſo open, ſee both feet at once upon a ſtraight line, along the Axeltree rod of the lower figure, for example, in two points as B and I, and mark theſe two points B, I, in the Axeltree rod.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98167:41"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>10</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:42"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>11</head>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:98167:42"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 11,</hi> To all ſorts of People.</head>
            <p>THat being done, go to the place of the Dyal, the which, to avoid the confuſion or multiplicity of lines, I have ſet below in the lower figure, ſet in this lower fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure one of the ends of the ſtick CI, to the point of ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow C, one of the ends F, of the ſtick FI, to the point of ſhadow F, and one of the ends D, of the ſtick DI to the point of ſhadow D, and one of the points B of the Axeltree rod, ſet it to the point B, of the pin AB.</p>
            <p>And holding thus the three ends CDF, of the three ſticks to the points of ſhadow CDF, every one reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively to his own, and the point B of the Axeltree rod, to the point of the pin B, bring together the three other ends I, of the three ſticks or rods CI, DI, FI, into one point in the air I, for they muſt meet there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then bring the point I of the Axeltree rod, alſo to the point in the air I, with the three ends I of the ſticks, for it muſt come and meet there exactly, if you have done right, or if the ſtraightneſſe of the place hath not hindered you.</p>
            <p>If the ſtraightneſſe of the place of the Dyal hinders the three ends I, of the ſticks from meeting together in one point in the air I, take the point I in the figure below in the ninth cut, or that above in the tenth figure in an other place, than in that where you had taken it and according to the occaſion, then bring the ſticks to it as before (for you may take it any where, or in any place of the line POQ, of one ſide or other of the point B;) but the further you can take it from the point B, will be better, and take it in ſo many-places, that having ſet the ſticks of the points CDF, to this point I, and mark'ed the ſpace BI upon the Axeltree rod, the four points I, may at laſt meet together in one point in the air I.</p>
            <p>And when the point B of the Axeltree rod, is at the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:98167:43"/>
point B, of the pin AB, and when the three ends I, of the ſticks, and the point I of the Axeltree rod are met, as you ſee in the lower figure, all four together in one and the ſame point in the air I.</p>
            <p>The Axeltree rod will come then to be placed, juſt as it ought to be in the Dyal.</p>
            <p>That if you do not care to be ſure that your Dyal muſt be as juſt, as it is poſſible for art to do, in ſuch a caſe, you may ſpare one of the four lengths CI, DI, FI, BI, and content your ſelf with three only, as being ſufficient for the Theorie: But the fourth will ſerve you for a proof, to ſee whether or no you have been very exact in working, and will juſtifie the three others.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="illustration">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:98167:43"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 12,</hi> To all ſorts of People.</head>
            <p>THe figure above ſhews you how that which you have done with three ſticks, may be done either with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Compaſſes, with the help of ſome body, or elſe with other kinds of branches tyed or faſtened one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>The ſame figure above, as alſo the figures below, ſhew how every one of thoſe branches may be of two ſeveral pieces, which go in by couples into one hoop or ring, and ſlide along one by another, and are made faſt with a ſcrew to the meaſure where you will have them to ſtand upon, and theſe pieces may be made of tinn'd yron, or of yron, if you are afraid that their points will grow dull by often uſing them.</p>
            <p>Or otherwiſe they ſhew you that inſteed of one ſtick, you may have two, both ſharp at one end, which you ſhall faſten and bind together at the other end, of what length or meaſure you pleaſe.</p>
            <p>The ſame figures do ſhew you alſo, that two divers branches, viz. CI, and FI, may be faſtened together in the place where you will have them to ſtand together, with a preſſe and a ſcrew to faſten them with.</p>
            <p>The higher figure ſhews you beſides, that you may <gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en or bind with ſtrings or threds, the Axeltree rod with the point B, of the pin AB, and the two branches CI, FI, with the Axeltree rod, to make them ſtand faſt of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their place.</p>
            <p>When you have found thus the placing of the Axeltree rod, it is in your choice, either to ſeal it and faſten it in that place, or to place another inſteed of it, that may go the ſame way, and that may be every way equally diſtant from it; But that you may be the more exact, it will be as good to ſeal or faſten that in the place, where the practice of the Draught hath cauſed it to meet, than to place another, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe there was ſome occaſion or neceſſity for it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98167:44"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>12</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="illustration">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:98167:44"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 3,</hi> To thoſe that have underſtood what hath been ſaid before.</head>
            <p>HAving underſtood what I have ſaid before, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thoſe many wayes of finding the poſition of the axeltree of the Dyal, you may compoſe others beſides, making uſe partly of that of one figure, and partly of that of an other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For example, here is one way compoſed of two of thoſe that are afore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OVt of the third or fifth figure, you ſhall take in the Sun-beams or ſticks BC, BD, BF, three ſpaces e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual each unto the other; And out of the 5 and 6 figures, you ſhall make a triangle of three lines equal to the three ſpaces HE, DE, DH of the third figure, and you ſhall find the center O of the circle, circumſcribed about this triangle.</p>
            <p>You ſhall find alſo within the ground plot of the points HDE, the points like to A &amp; O of the 6 figure or cut, which in this caſe come to be united together in one and the ſame point O. That is to ſay, having found one of theſe two points A &amp; O, you have found alſo the other, becauſe they are united or gathered together into one.</p>
            <p>So you have in the ſecond figure of the third cut, the ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces DO, and DI, for two ſides of a triangle with ſtraight angles or corners ODI, whoſe ſide DI, holds up the ſtraight angle, and the ſides DO, and DI, do contain or comprehend it.</p>
            <p>Make this triangle ODI, with three ſticks, or with any other thing that may be ſtrong and ſmall as you will, ſo that you may at your need lengthen the ſide IO, from the right angle O.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98167:45"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>3</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:98167:45"/>Set the point D, of this triangle DIO, to the point of ſhadow D, and holding this point of triangle to this point of ſhadow D, make the ſide IO, of this triangle (drawn at length if need be) come and touch the point B, of the pin AB for if you have been very exact in working, it muſt touch it.</p>
            <p>Take a ſtick HI, of the length of DI, ſet one of the ends to the point H, and bring the other end to the point I, of the triangle ODI, without the ſide IO, leave the end B of the pin AB, for it muſt be ſo, if you have wrought exactly as you ought.</p>
            <p>You may have alſo an other ſtick EI, of the length DI, and ſet one end to the point E, and bring the other like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to the point I, of the triangle DIO, without the ſide OI, leave the end B of the pin AB.</p>
            <p>That being done the rod BI, comes to be the axeltree of the Dyal, and placed as it ought to be, and ſo of all the other wayes that you find beſides.</p>
            <p>You may, if you will make uſe of a triangle rectangular EOI. and of the ſtick HI, content your ſelf only with the three equal lengths EI, DI, HI, to find out the point thereby, that you may draw from thence a line to the point B, without making uſe of any thing elſe to know if you have done exactly or no, you can not be ſure whether you have done well or ill.</p>
            <p>But when you have together with that, either a fourth length BI<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or the ſtraight angle DOI, that will ſerve you to try whether or no you have been exact in your operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for as concerning an effectual execution, unleſſe you have from time to time ſuch a kind of proof, to ſhew whether you have wrought exactly as you ought, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not aſſure your ſelf that your work is as well as it can be done.</p>
            <p>One thing I muſt tell you, that in ſome certain occaſions according to the times and the placing, or according as the ſuperficies of your Dyal is, the ſhadow of the pin comes to be of ſuch a length, and the extremity or end thereof ſo weakned, and ſo diminiſhed in ſtrength, and ſo confuſe in the ſuperficies of the Dyal, that it is very hard to find out</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="illustration">
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:98167:46"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 13,</hi> To all ſorts of People.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>I come now to the next and ſecond thing that you are to do, which is to trace out the lines of the hours.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>IN this example I ſuppoſe that the Axeltree rod doth not meet the ſuperficies of the Dyal, about the place that you work in; and therefore I repreſent it ſuſpended in the air, with two or three ſupporters as you ſee, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe alſo that the ſuperficies of the Dyal is not ſmooth, but rough and uneven as I have ſaid.</p>
            <p>When you have placed the Rod BI, which is the Axel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree of the Dyal, as you ſee both in the higher and lower figure, you have made an end then of the firſt of thoſe two things that you were to do, for the making of your Dyal: Now there remains but the ſecond to be done, which is the finding and the tracing out of the lines of the hours in the Dyal; and for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Conſider in your higher figure, that the ſuperficies and the axeltree of your Dyal are two divers things, and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring one from an other, and there is no ſuch communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation from the one to the other, as that with them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone you may find out directly the place of the lines of the hours, without making uſe of a third thing that may be a means betwixt thoſe two.</p>
            <p>The meaneſt and the leaſt thing that you can have to be a means betwixt the ſuperficies and the axeltree of the Dyal, is a Ruler.</p>
            <p>You muſt have therefore beſides the ſuperficies and the axeltree of the Dyal, in ſome other place, at leaſt a Ruler, as you ſee in the lower figure the rule PQ, which rule may be a means between this ſuperficies and the axeltree of the Dyal, and that by means of this middle rule you may do ſo, that there may be ſuch a communication as
<pb facs="tcp:98167:46"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>13</head>
               </figure>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:98167:47"/>
you pleaſe, from the ſuperficies to the axeltree of the Dyal.</p>
            <p>To the end that this middle rule may ſerve you alike in all occaſions, it muſt have all the conditions that you ſee repreſented in the figure below. Firſt it muſt be as long as the place will give you leave, and it muſt croſſe over if need be the whole ſuperficies of the Dyal, and reach over on both ſides if it be poſſible.</p>
            <p>Secondly it muſt be in the air, and ſuſpended between the ſuperficies and the axeltree of the Dyal.</p>
            <p>Thirdly it muſt be placed as far from the axeltree rod, as poſſible may be.</p>
            <p>Fourthly it muſt be placed like a croſſe, in regard of the ſame axeltree rod.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="illustration">
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:98167:47"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 14,</hi> To all ſorts of People.</head>
            <p>TO place this middle rule well, and as it ought to be betwixt the ſuperficies and the axeltree of the Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al.</p>
            <p>Chuſe along the axeltree rod BI, of the higher figure, ſome fit or convenient place, as in the point O, and make a round and fixed ſtay in that place, by winding, or tying ſome ſtrong thing about this axeltree rod, as the figure doth ſhew.</p>
            <p>Tye a ſtring to the axeltree rod BI, by the means of a ring that may be ſo big, that you may turn the ſtring with it about the axeltree rod eaſily, as the lower figure ſhews you; Then with the corner of a ſquire ED, in the lower figure, thruſt on the ring where the ſtring is, and put it cloſe to this ſtay O, and holding the ſtring faſt between the ſtay O, and the ſquire ED, ſet the back of one of the ſides OE of this ſquires length, to the axeltree rod BI, and by this means, the other ſide DO, of this ſquire, will ſhoot out into the air like a wing from the axeltree rod BI, then ſtretch out the ſtring in a ſtraight line from the ſtay O of the axeltree, along the back of the other ſide OD of the ſquire. And holding ſtill in this manner the ring cloſe to the ſtay of the axeltree, by means of the ſquire, and the back of one of the ſides joyned at length to the axeltree rod, and the other ſide of the ſquire like a wing, and the ſtring ſtretcht out in a ſtraight line along this wing, turn both the ſquire and the ſtring altogether ſtill in this ſame manner about the axeltree rod, as the lower figure doth ſhew.</p>
            <p>And in turning them ſo, go with the ſtring which you may lengthen or ſhorten at your need, to ſeek or find out in the ſuperficies of the Dyal, thoſe two places that are fartheſt one from another, in which this ſtring ſo ſtretcht
<pb facs="tcp:98167:48"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>14</head>
               </figure>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:98167:48"/>
out may meet the ſuperficies of the Dyal, as you ſee here the places G and H.</p>
            <p>When you have found out thoſe two places that are fartheſt one from another, in which this ſtring turning in this manner with the ſquire along the ſide like a wing, may go and meet the ſuperficies of the Dyal, as here the places G and H.</p>
            <p>Make with maſtick, or plaſter, or cement, or ſuch like ſtuff, a little knob flat at the top in each of theſe places, as for example, one in G, and another as in H, which two knobs may ſhoot out of the ſuperficies of the Dyal, in ſuch ſort, that you may lay a Ruler on the top of them, going from one of the knobs to the other, as you ſee here in the lower figure.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:49"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>15</head>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:98167:49"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 15,</hi> To all ſorts of People.</head>
            <p>VVHen you have thus made thoſe two knobbs G, H, in the lower figure, take the ſquire again and the ſtring, and ſet them again cloſe to the ſtay O, of the axeltree rod, as you know they were.</p>
            <p>And make them go about again as before, both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther about the axeltree BI, and while you are turning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, the ſtring will fall right over againſt the two knobs, ſhorten or lengthen it ſo, that it may go and touch a point, at the top of each one of the two knobs, one after another<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> viz. a point as P, at the top of the knob G, and a point as Q, at the top of the knob H, and mark theſe two points Q and P, upon theſe two knobs.</p>
            <p>When you have mark'd two points in this manner, ſet a Ruler in the lower figure upon theſe two knobs, and place it ſo, that it may paſſe from one to the other, by thoſe two points Q and P, and make the Ruler faſt in this place with cement or plaſter, or the like, in ſuch wiſe that it may not ſtir any way.</p>
            <p>And this rule ſo placed, is the third and middle piece between the ſuperficies, and the axeltree of the Dyal, by means whereof you ſhall cauſe, as I ſhall ſay hereafter, this ſuperficies and this axeltree to have what communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſoever you pleaſe one with another.</p>
            <p>After you have placed this middle rule in this manner, between the ſuperficies and the axeltree of the Dyal.</p>
            <p>Conſider that in <hi>France</hi> now they reckon 34 hours, for one day and a night, and that theſe 24 hours, are divided in twice twelve hours, and that every one of theſe 12 hours is ſubdivided in twice 6 hours.</p>
            <p>So that in the 24 hours of one day and one night, as they are now reckoned in <hi>France,</hi> there are two hours that are each of them of 12, that is to ſay, one hour of 12 in the middeſt of the night, and another hour of twelve in the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:98167:50"/>
middeſt of the day, theſe two hours of 12, are called mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night and midday, then there are two other hours, each of them of 6. viz. an hour of 6 in the evening, and another of 6 in the morning.</p>
            <p>Where you muſt note, that both the two hours of 12, and the two hours of 6, come alwayes to meet together in one and the ſame line, though it may be lengthened if need be, viz. the two of twelve in one line, and the two of 6 in an other.</p>
            <p>And you ſhall know, that it is an infallible thing, that within the Compaſſe of the ſuperficies of the Dyal where you work in, if you have placed the axeltree pretty near it, there muſt needs be either one of the hours of 12, or one of the hours of 6, and ſometimes they meet there both at once, that is to ſay, one of the hours of 12, and one of the hours of 6.</p>
            <p>There be many ſituations of ſuperficies of Dyals, in which, within the Compaſſe, where one may trace in the hours, there is only the line of the hours of 12, and there is found not any one of the hours of 6, and others in which there is found only the line of the hours of 6, and not any one of the hours of 12. But there is no Dyal in which, within the Compaſſe where it is traced in, but the hours of 12, and any one of the hours of 6 are found in it, I mean that one may find in it, either one or other of the hours of 12, and of the hours of 6, by ſetting the axel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree near enough to the ſuperficies of the Dyal.</p>
            <p>And now ſince you are ſure, that there is without doubt in your Dyal, either one of the hours of 12, or one of 6.</p>
            <p>You ſhall begin to ſeek in it, firſt the place of that ſort of hours of twelve or of ſix, that may be in it.</p>
            <p>And when you have found the point, either of one of the hours of ſix, or of one of twelve; You ſhall find after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the points of the other hours, that meet with it in the Dyal it is in your choice to begin to ſeek the point, of which of the two ſorts of hours of 6, or of 12, you will, and I will ſhow you two wayes of ſeeking them out, both one after another, that when they come to be both in the Dyal, you may find them out both there if you will, for
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:98167:50"/>
they ſerve for a proof one unto another, if you have been exact in your operation.</p>
            <p>That you may finiſh your Dyal as you ought, ſeek in the middle rule the point which is there to be found, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the hours of twelve, or of the hours of ſix, for it is ſet there on purpoſe to ſerve for that chiefly.</p>
            <p>For example, ſeek out firſt in it the point of one of the hours of ſix, as I am going to ſhew, then I will ſhew you the way to find out the point of one of the hours of 12, and afterwards I will ſhew you the way to find out the points of all the other hours of the Day.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:51"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>16</head>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:98167:51"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 16,</hi> To all ſorts of People.</head>
            <p>TO ſeek out in the middle rule, whether the point of one of the hours of 6 be there.</p>
            <p>Take the ſtring that is made faſt to the axeltree, ſet it very cloſe again to the point or ſtay O, as it was when you made it turn about the axeltree, then ſtretch it out in a ſtraight line from the point O of the ſtay of the axeltree, to the middle rule PQ, and holding ſtill this ſtring ſo ſtretcht out, make it turn about the point O, carrying it from one to the other of the points Q and P<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> along the rule QP, and making it longer or ſhorter if need be, and ſet a Carpenters level or triangle over it, to ſee, while it turns thus, ſtretch't out in a ſtraight line about this point O, keeping along the middle rule, whether there is any place, wherein it comes to be found levell, as for example, you ſee in the higher figure (over the leaf) and when you find it to be level, you muſt make it faſt there.</p>
            <p>And that your level may be more faſt, you may ſet it by the middle upon the axeltree rod cloſe to the ſtay, or you may ſet cloſe to the ſtay a ruler notch't at one end, as you ſee the ruler N, is notcht, then guide it with the ſtring, And it will ſerve to faſten the level upon it.</p>
            <p>Or to ſay it again otherwiſe, you muſt, as you know, cauſe to go about the axeltree rod the ſquire and the ſtring ſtretcht out, as I have ſaid, in a ſtraight line, and made lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger if need be, this ſtring will go and paſſe all along the ruler PQ.</p>
            <p>And if it happens that the ſtring, ſo guided or carryed along the middle rule PQ, come to be found level, as the higher figure ſhews, mark in this middle rule the point 6, where this ſtring toucheth or reacheth unto when it is ſo level, and remember that this point 6, is the point of one of the hours of 6, either of the evening, or of the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:98167:52"/>
This is that which concerns one point of one of the hours of 6, that if the ſtring in turning thus, comes to paſſe from one end of the middle <gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>e to the other, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out falling to be level it is a ſign, that not one of the hours of 6, comes to be found in this Dyal, to frame it from the point that you have taken for a reſt or ſtay.</p>
            <p>Now that you may ſeek out the point of the hours of 12, in the lower figure.</p>
            <p>Faſten the center of a hanging plummet, with a ſtring S, to the middle of the body of the axeltree rod, above it or under, as the lower figure ſhews, it matters not, and as the occaſion will permit or require, and ſet this plummet ſo, that it may come and fall as near the middle rule as you can.</p>
            <p>Then tye to the axeltree rod, as far as you can from the ſuperficies of the Dyal, another ſtring I with a looſe knot, and when the plummet of the firſt ſtring S, comes to be at reſt, make it ſo faſt that it may not ſtir, then ſtretch out this ſecond ſtring I in a ſtraight line, in ſuch ſort, that comming from the axeltree rod, it may go and touch the ſtring of the hanging plummet S, without break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (or ſtirring) the ſtring nor the lead, and ſo holding this ſecond ſtring I, ſtretcht out cloſe to the ſtring with the plummet on S, ſee whether this ſecond ſtring ſtretcht out in this manner can, being made ſhorter or longer, if need be, go and meet the middle rule, in a point, or not.</p>
            <p>And when this ſecond ſtring ſo ſtretch'd out comes to meet the middle rule, in one point, as 12, mark in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle rule this point 12, in which this ſtring ſo ſtretcht out doth meet with it, and note that that point 12, is the point of one of the hours of 12.</p>
            <p>When you have found out and markt in the middle rule the point of one or other of the hours, either of 6, as you ſee in the figure above, or of 12, as you ſee in the figure below, if you have them both, they ſhall ſerve for a proof one to another, if you have but one, you may make uſe of that alone.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:98167:52"/>Let us ſuppoſe firſt, that it is the point of one of the hours of 6, as the point, 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> you ſhall go on in find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the points of the other hours, which may be found in your Dyal, in this manner following.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="illustration">
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:98167:53"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 17,</hi> To all ſorts of People.</head>
            <p>MArk at your diſcretion in the rule PQ. two ſeveral points MN, and conſider the point in the middle of the body of the axeltree, cloſe by the ſtay O, that is the Point about which you have turned the ſtring with the corner of the ſquire. You ſee there three ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral points unmoveable, and fixed, viz. the point M, and the point N, in the middle rule, and the point O, in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of the body of the axeltree rod, cloſe to the ſtay. And ſo having thoſe three points fixed, M, N, O, you have by this means the three ſeveral diſtances, viz. the meaſures of the diſtances that are from one of theſe three points, to the two others, viz. the ſpace or diſtance from the point M, to the point N, the diſtance from the point M to the point O and the ſpace from the point N, to the point O.</p>
            <p>Remember two things, one is, that the point O, is in the middle of the body, that is to ſay of the bigneſſe, and not in the out ſide of the axeltree rod. The other is, that theſe two points MN, that you have mark'd at diſcretion in the middle rule, are not for all that certainly the points of hour, and that they are to ſerve you to find out the points of hour, and perhaps they may chance to be ſome of them; and may be not, and perhaps you muſt blot them out after you have found out the points of hour.</p>
            <p>This being done ſo, take with your Compaſſe upon the middle rule, the diſtance from the point M, to the point N, and with this ſpace go to ſome place that is flat or ſmooth, and ſet both the feet of your Compaſſe therein at once, as in the figure below in the points M and N, and by theſe two points, draw a ſtraight line MN, as long at either end as the rule PQ.</p>
            <p>Then go back to the Dyal above, take with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe the diſtance which is from the poſnt M, to the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:98167:53"/>
of the bigneſs of the axeltree cloſe by the ſtay O, or elſe otherwiſe, take the diſtance which is from the point M, to the axeltree towards the ſtay O, and adde unto it half of the bigneſs of the Axeltree; and with this ſpace MO, come back to the figure below, ſet one of the feet of the Compaſſe to the point M, and turning this foot about upon this point M, trace with the other foot a line crooked like a bow O, go back to the figure above, take again with your Compaſs the diſtance which is from the point N, to the middle of the bigneſs of the axeltree cloſe by the ſtay O, and with this ſpace come back to the lower figure, ſet one of the feet of the Compaſs to the point N, and turning this foot upon this point N, trace with the other foot another crooked line that may meet with the other in one point, as O, for it muſt meet with it.</p>
            <p>Then open yout Compaſs at diſcretion, rather more than leſſe, and ſet one of the feet of the Compaſs ſo open at diſcretion to the point O, and turning this foot of the Compaſs upon this point O, trace with the other foot a round RGSH. Go back to the Dyal in the figure above, take with your Compaſs upon the rule QP, the diſtance which is from one of the points M or N, to the point of 6 hours, and with this ſpace, for example of M6, come back to the lower figure, ſet one of the points or feet of the Compaſs upon this point M, go and mark with the other foot in the line M, a point as 6, of the ſame ſide up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the rule.</p>
            <p>And ſo you have in the line MN, one and the ſame thing as you have in the Dyal in the middle rule, viz. the three points MN and 6, of the ſame diſtance, in each of theſe two ſtraight lines.</p>
            <p>This being done, draw in the figure below by the two points O and 6, a ſtraight line O, 6, which may divide the round RGSH, in two halfs RGS, and RHS.</p>
            <p>Open the Compaſs at your diſcretion, and as much as the ſpace will give you leave, and keeping your Compaſs ſo open at diſcretion, ſet one of the feet to the point S, and turning this foot upon this point S, trace with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:98167:54"/>
foot, two crooked lines L and D, then with the ſame ſpace, remove your Compaſs out of his place, and ſet one of the feet to the point R, and turning this foot about upon this point R, trace with the other foot two other crooked lines, that may meet in two points L and D, the two crooked lines that you have drawn about the point S, and mark thoſe two points L and D, and draw by thoſe two points a ſtraight line LD, which may paſſe by the point O, if you have been exact in your operations.</p>
            <p>So you have divided this round, into four quarters of a round, with the two ſtraight lines SOR, LOD, and if the ſtraight line LOD, drawn in length comes to meet the line MN, in a point as 12, it ſhews that there is alſo the point of the hours of 12, in your Dyal, viz. in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle rule between the ſuperficies and the axeltree; now di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide with your Compaſs every one of theſe quarters of the round, into ſix parts equal, as you ſee in the points that are upon the brim of the round RGSH, and by the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or middle point of this round O, and by every one of the points of theſe diviſions of the edge or brim of the round, draw ſome lines or beams, as you ſee ſome drawn already, that may go and meet the ſtraight line MN, as in the points, 5, 4, 3, 2, 1, 11. and theſe points are the points of the other hours, that are to be found in your Dyal.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98167:54"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>18</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:55"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>17</head>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:98167:55"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 18,</hi> To all ſorts of People.</head>
            <p>NOw take with the Compaſs in the figure above, the ſpace from 6 to 5, and with this ſpace go to the Dyal in the figure below, ſet one of the feet of the Compaſs to the point 6, and keeping this foot of the Compaſs upon this point 6, go and mark with the other foot in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle rule another point 5, and by this means you ſhall tranſport with your Compaſs the ſpace 6, 5, <gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rom the line of the figure above, which repreſents your table, or the flat place in the Dyal of the figure below, upon the middle rule MN, &amp; ſo accordingly take with your Compaſs every one of the other ſpaces, 5, 4, 4, 3, 3, 2, 2, 1, 1<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 12, 11, from the higher figure, and bring them in this manner to the Dyal upon the middle rule, in the lower figure, and ſo you have done in this middle rule in the Dyal of the lower figure, all and the ſame ſpaces as thoſe are, that are upon the table of the lower figure: And thoſe points of the middle rule of the lower figure, are as many points of hours that will be in the Dyal, among which you know that the point 6, is the point of one of the hours of ſix, either of the evening, or of the morning, whereby you ſhall come to know which are the other hours, whereof you have the points ſo mark'd in the rule of the Dyal.</p>
            <p>As for to let you know, whether this point of 6 hours, is either of thoſe in the morning, or of thoſe of the eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, I will not trouble this paper with it, becauſe that is plain enough of it ſelf: And you ſee well enough, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſhadow of the axeltree rod will fall upon this point, either in the morning about the beginning of the day, or elſe in the evening about the ſhutting up of the day. By this means you may ſee well enough, whether the hours of your Dyal are of thoſe of the forenoon, or of the afternoon, for to mark them accordingly, without
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:98167:56"/>
ſpeaking any further about it. If you have found upon the middle rule MN, the point of one of the two hours of 12, and not the point of one of the hours of 6, you are but to do with that point of hour of twelve, the ſame thing that I ſaid you ſhould do with the point of one of the hours of 6.</p>
            <p>When you have ſo tranſported the points of the hours from the Table of the figure above, to the Dyal in the lower figure upon the middle rule<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That which remains to do, is to tranſport thoſe points of hours from the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle rule, into the ſuperficies of the Dyal in the manner following, and to trace in it afterwards the line of the hours, as I will ſhew you.</p>
            <p>You ſee, there are two ſtrings tyed to the axeltree rod, in the figure below, ſet the rings of theſe two ſtrings, as far as you can one from another, and as from R in S, then take one of theſe two ſtrings, as that which comes from the point R, carry it ſtretcht out in a direct line from the axeltree rod, to one of the points of hours that are mark'd in the middle rule, for example in the point of hour 12, and cauſe this ſtring comming ſo from the axeltree, to paſſe to this point of hour 12, of the middle rule, and to go altogether in a ſtraight line as far as the ſuperficies of the Dyal; and mark in the ſuperficies of the Dyal the point in which this ſtring ſo carryed, meets it; By this means you ſhall tranſport this point or hour 12, from the middle rule into the ſuperficies of the Dyal to the point XII.</p>
            <p>And after the ſame manner, you ſhall tranſport one after another the points of hour 11, 12. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, from the middle rule, into the ſuperficies of the Dyal to the points XI, XII<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I, II, III, IV, V, VI.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:56"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 19,</hi> To all ſorts of People.</head>
            <head type="sub">How to trace the lines of the hours upon the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies of the Dyal.</head>
            <p>OF the two ſtrings, fig. above, that are made faſt to the axeltree rod, ſtretch out one in a ſtraight line, from the axeltree rod, as from the point R to a Point of hour of the middle rule, as to the point of hour I<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and holding this ſtring ſo ſtretcht, take the other or ſecond ſtring comming from the point S, and ſtretching it like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in a ſtraight line, make it croſſe over the firſt ſtring BI<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and let it touch it without breaking his ſtraight line, and let it go in a ſtraight line from thence, to the ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the Dyal as to the point D, and mark the point D, in the ſuperficies of the Dyal, wherein this ſecond ſtring ſo carried, comes to touch it; then make this ſecond ſtring to go and touch again the firſt in another place, and with this ſecond ſtring go and touch in the ſame manner, another point E, in the ſuperficies of the Dyal E, And ſo remove this ſecond ſtring along the firſt ſtring, as many times as you ſhall have need to mark any ſeveral points, as D, E, L, in the ſuperficies of the Dyal, to trace the line of that hour there, then draw a line as fine and delicate as you can by all thoſe points DEL, in the ſuperficies of the Dyal, that line ſhall be the line of that hour I.</p>
            <p>And after this manner, you ſhall trace in the ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the Dyal, the lines of all the other hours that are in the middle rule, and your Dyal will be finiſhed.</p>
            <p>The lower figure ſhews you to the eye, how that after you have tranſported as above ſaid, all the points of hour from the middle rule into the ſuperficies of the Dyal, you may take away this middle rule, and the two knobs that
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:98167:57"/>
hold it up, and make an end of tracing the reſt of the lines in the ſuperficies of the Dyal, as I have ſaid, with the ſtrings comming from R and I, and by means of the points of hours XI, XII, I, II, III, IV, V, VI.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:57"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 20,</hi> To all ſorts of People.</head>
            <p>AFter that you have placed the axeltree of the Dyal as it muſt be, if you deſire to find the points of the hours in the ſuperficies, with ſome extraordinary inſtruments, that which is the plaineſt of all, viz. a round flat plate, and ſtiff, as of tinn'd yron, or the like, and divided into 24 parts equal one unto another, and ſet up in the manner of a ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunda or whirl, by the ſquire, or with right angles about the axeltree of the Dyal, as the figure below doth ſhew, is the moſt common and the ſhorteſt way of all.</p>
            <p>The figure H, ſhews you this round alone, and how it is open of one ſide, that the center thereof may be placed with the center of the axeltree.</p>
            <p>The 1. figure ſhews the neck that may be applyed unto this round about the center, to the end that one may with this neck, ſet the round to the axeltree of the Dyal by the ſquire, or with angles ſtraight between themſelves, as you ſee in the ſecond figure.</p>
            <p>When you have thus ſet this round to the axeltree of the Dyal, the lower figure ſhews you how you muſt place the ſtring of the plummet, hanging upon the axeltree by a point of one of the diviſions of the edge of this round, that it may give you the points of the hours in the ſuperficies of the Dyal.</p>
            <p>The ſtrings which comming from the axeltree paſſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards to the points of the diviſion of this round in it's 24 parts, ſhew you, how you muſt afterwards bring the ſtrings from the axeltre, by the points of the diviſion of this round in 24 parts, equal to the ſuperficies of the Dyal, that you may have the points of the hours in this ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</p>
            <p>The ſtring LS, XII, that paſſeth to the ſtring with the plummet RS, gives the point of the hours of 12. The
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:98167:58"/>
ſtring LVI, that paſſeth to one of the points of this diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in 24, and is found to be level, gives the point of the hours of 6.</p>
            <p>The other ſtrings ſhew you, that the way of tracing the points of the other hours is the ſame as above.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98167:58"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>20</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:59"/>
            <head>
               <figure/>
            </head>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:98167:59"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 21,</hi> To all ſorts of People.</head>
            <p>VVHen you have brought, as I have ſaid, by means of this rotunda and the ſtrings, all the points of the hours, into the ſuperficies of the Dyal; You may take away the rotunda if you will, and make an end of tracing the lines of the hours as before with the ſtrings, and by means of the points of hours, which you have brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſuperficies of the Dyal, as you ſee in the figure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, the line DELKPQSYIZG.</p>
            <p>And for this purpoſe by means of the ſaid ſtrings, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a ſtring in a ſtraight line from the axeltree to the point of hour, for example I, and holding it there ſtretcht in a ſtraight line, carry of one ſide or other according to the occaſion, an other ſtring comming alſo from the axeltree, as from I, or from B, that may go in a ſtraight line as far as the ſuperficies of the Dyal, and let it go and touch, and croſſe over the ſtring IR, ſeveral times in ſeveral places, and at every time go with this ſecond ſtring to touch and mark a point in the ſuperficies of the Dyal, until you have enough, as you ſee the points D, E, L, K, P, Q, Y, I, Z, G, and carry by theſe points a line ſweetned, that ſhall be a line of hour, do the like for the lines of the other hours, and you have done.</p>
            <p>When you have mark'd in the ſuperficies of the Dyal, a point of every one of the hours that are to be found in it: If you deſire to trace the lines of the hours every one at once, without making uſe of the ſtrings, as in the figure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, you may do it when it is dark, as by night, with the light of a candle, in that manner as it is expreſt in the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er figure.</p>
            <p>Set a light behind the axeltree rod of the Dyal, and turn the ſame lightabout this axeltree, untill the ſhadow of this axeltree come to one of the points of hour I, and
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:98167:60"/>
trace in the ſuperficies of the Dyal a line DELKPQSYIZG, all along this ſhadow of the axeltree, that line ſhall be a line of hour, do the like for every one of the other points of hour, and you have finiſh'd your Dyal.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="22" type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:60"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>22</head>
                  <head>Inſtruments to work with all,</head>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:61"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>21</head>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:98167:61"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 22,</hi> Several Inſtruments to work withall in theſe occaſions hereafter ſpecified.</head>
            <p>I Did not intend to burden my memory with any thing in this matter, but with <hi>Monſieur de Sargues</hi> univerſal rules for the placing of the axeltree, and for the tracing in a Dyal the hours after the French way, without medling with the reſt, which is more curious than uſeful.</p>
            <p>But to follow the advice of many conſiderable perſons whom I do honour, I have ſet down alſo the way to mark that which is commonly called the ſigns: The hours after the Italian or Babylonian way: The hours after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Ancients: The elevations of the Sun above the Horizon; and the riſing of the ſame.</p>
            <p>And for as much as none can do any of theſe things uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally, without uſing theſe inſtruments more or leſſe; This table following ſhews to the eye all the pieces that are uſed in thoſe ſeveral occaſions. Theſe inſtruments are firſt a circle, a half circle, or the quarter of a circle, which is all one which is made to turn about its Diameter ſet faſt in it's due and convenient place, or down right, as in the fourth figure, or level, as in the ſecond or third figure, or elſe inclining or hanging downward, as in the firſt figure.</p>
            <p>The way to make this circle to move in all kinds of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, is to ſet two rings in it's Diameter, through which one may put in a ſtick ſtraight, round, and ſmooth, about which this circle may turn round like a weather cock about his needle or ſpear, as in the ſecond figure, and there muſt be within thoſe hoop rings, a ſcrew to faſten this cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle in that place, or which way ſoever you will have it to ſtand.</p>
            <p>The ſticks or rods are repreſented by the 7th. figure, with a fork at the end of every one, bored in the cheek, to put a pin through, as you ſee, that one may be ſet plum or down right, and the other level, being made faſt at one
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:98167:62"/>
end to the axeltree rod as in the 5th. figure. And for this purpoſe alſo the axeltree rod is bored in O.</p>
            <p>The 8th. figure ſhews the axeltree rod by it ſelf bored with O, and the pin Q, put through the hole, to ſhew more plainly that which the 5th figure repreſents, viz. all the pieces ſet or joyned together being mark'd with qo.</p>
            <p>You ſee that the hoop rings are near the edge or brim of the circle, a purpoſe to leave the center O, and a ſpace about it free, having commonly a piece taken off, that this circle may turn freely about the forked end, that is to ſay about his center, without any let or hinderance at all.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="23" type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:62"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:63"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>23</head>
                  <head>for the Signes.</head>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:98167:63"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 23,</hi> How to mark the Signs.</head>
            <p>GEt, figure 2 below, a half circle both thin and ſtiff ctsrd, draw there a beam OZS, perpendicular to the Diameter CPOQD, take on both ſides of this beam OS, 23 degrees and half, for example 23 degrees and half from s towards t, and as much from s towards r, draw the ſtraight line r, t, make upon Diameter t, r, a half, circle tzr, divide the edge or brim of that half circle in ſix e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual parts, as in the points that you ſee there; draw by thoſe points as far as the half circle CtsrU, ſome ſtraight lines that may be perpendicular to the ſtraight line r, t, bring from the center O, by the points that thoſe perpendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular have made upon the edge of the half circle CtsrD, ſome ſtraight lines, as you ſee that the ſtrings ſhew you, and with thoſe lines drawn out ſufficiently, you ſhall mark the ſigns in the Dyal, as I ſhall ſay.</p>
            <p>You ſee that the half circle is cut thorow, or made hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low from the point P, to the point Q, round about the center O, according to the circumference PZQ, which is notch'd alſo in the points that you ſee in it, which are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt every degree of the half circle; And the center O, and theſe notches, are there a purpoſe to faſten a ſtring up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, inſteed of bringing it from the center O.</p>
            <p>The two figures s32tgez, s45rbcz, both on the right and on the left ſide of the half circle CtsrD, ſhew as you may judge by their letters or coats, each of them one half of the figure tsrz, of the half circle CtsrD, which I have made thus bigger than each half of this fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, that one may ſet in the letters ge, cb, and ſome figures, 2345, about the edges of the two half circles, and alſo the ſigns, as you ſee, which I could not do in the middle figure without confuſion.</p>
            <p>The lines comming from the points t23s, s45r,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:98167:64"/>
towards the loweſt paſt of the figure or plate, comming near one an other, go and ſeek the center of the half cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle t23s45r, Every one of the three ſaces between thoſe ſtraight lines is to hold two ſignes, mark them there in the ſame order that you ſee them, cloſe by theſe ſtraight lines, one of one ſide, and an other on th'other ſide.</p>
            <p>And by this meanes the ſtraight line of the half circle t23s45r, which from the center of the half circle paſſeth to the points, is that of the ſignes of Aries, and of Libra; that which paſſeth to the point 3, is that of Taurus, and of Virgo; that which paſſeth to the point 2, is that of Gemini, or the Twinnes, and of Leo; that which paſſeth to the point t, is that of Cancer; that which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to the point r, is that of Capricornus; that which paſſeth to the point 5, is that of Sagittarius and Aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius; that which paſſeth to the point 4, is that of the Scorpion, and of the Fiſhes.</p>
            <p>The two figures s32cgez, s45rbcz, ſhew you alſo that with one quarter of circe mark'd on both ſides with 6 ſignes in one part, and 6 others in the other part, you may do the ſame thing as well as with the half cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, by turning this quarter of circle, as you ſee in the ſaid figures, once of one ſide, and once of th'o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>I ſhall for all that ſpeak to you alwayes as if you had the half circle in your hand.</p>
            <p>Therefore when you will mark the lines of the ſignes in the Superficies of the Dyall, The firſt figure ſhewes you how you muſt ſet up your half circle with the axeltree, for to turn it about the ſame, without going up or down along the axeltree.</p>
            <p>The firſt figure above ſhewes how you muſt make your half circle, <hi>viz.</hi> about the axeltree, ſet then the half circle to the axeltree of the Dyall, as you ſee in the figure that is under the firſt.</p>
            <p>Tye a ſtring with a looſe knot, juſt in the center of the circle.</p>
            <p>Turn the half circle about the axeltree, cauſe at the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:98167:64"/>
ſame time the ſtring comming from the center, to paſſe by one of the lines of the ſignes, holding it longer or ſhorter as need ſhall require, go and touch with the ſtring many ſeveral points in the ſuperficies of the Dyall one after an other.</p>
            <p>Draw a line ſweetned, by all thoſe points, and it is the line of the ſignes that are markt along the ſtraight line of the half circle which the ſtring doth cover, in turning with it about the axeltree.</p>
            <p>Do the like for every line of the ſignes, mark the ſignes in the Dyall by the lines ſo drawn according to the ſituation, in regard of the Country and of the place of the Dyall, and as the figure ſhews, you have marked the ſignes in the Dyall.</p>
            <p>And if the ſtrings could not come from the center, faſten them with a knot to the beames, comming from the center, in the notches or clefts of the circumference PZQ.</p>
            <p>Set a button or an other mark in the axeltree, in the place where the center of the half circle CtsrD hath been, and the ſhadow of the button will go and mark the ſigne that the Sun is in.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="24" type="illustration">
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:98167:65"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 24.</hi> To mark the houres after the Italian or Babylonian way.</head>
            <p>THE firſt figure ſhews how you muſt ſet on your half circle, and how to make it turn about the axeltree.</p>
            <p>Moreover, the line NO (ſhews you what kind of line comming from the center O of this half circle, you muſt make uſe of, in making the half circle to turn about.</p>
            <p>When you have drawn the lines of the houres after the French way at length, in the ſuperficies of the Dyall, as the figure below doth ſhew.</p>
            <p>Set on, as the ſame figure ſhewes you alſo, the half cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle O t rto the exeltree of the Dyall with a ſtring ON in it's center.</p>
            <p>Let this half circle hang down right or Plum, and when this half circle is juſt down and at reſt, draw the ſtring ON, in a ſtraight line comming from the center O, and cloſing with the half circle, in ſuch ſort as it may go, and touch it all at length, turn this ſtring as a beam of the half circle about the center O, till it be very levell, as the figure ſhewes by the ſetting on of the Carpenters levell A.</p>
            <p>When the ſtring ON is ſtretcht out very levell cloſe to the half circle, mark exactly upon the edge of this half circle, the point wherein the ſtring ON toucheth it, as doth the letter E.</p>
            <p>Then let the half circle turn about the axeltree.</p>
            <p>Make in the mean time the ſtring ON, to paſſe by the point t, which you have markt upon the edge of the half circle, and making it ſhorter or longer according as need ſhall require, go and touch with this ſtring many ſeveral
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:98167:65"/>
points one after an other in the ſuperficies of the Dyall in divers places, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</p>
            <p>Draw an obſcure line by thoſe points, as you ſee the line bowed or crooked, 23, 24, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, and which reacheth beyond the axeltree towards h.</p>
            <p>This line croſſeth over the ſuperficies of the Dyall, out of the Equinoctial line PQ, and meets by the way all the lines of the houres after the French way, as you ſee it doth in 23, 24, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</p>
            <p>There Remaines to trace the lines of theſe houres after the Italian or Babylonian way in the ſuperficies of the Dyall and when you know how to trace one, you ſhall be able alſo to trace the other.</p>
            <p>Therefore to trace a line of thoſe kinds of houres, It is no matter which you begin to trace firſt; Count upon the Equinoctiall line PQ fixs paces of houres equall, after the French way, one after an other, as from XII. to VI. Afterwards follow the lines of the houres, after the French way, that paſſe by the points XII. &amp; VI the two extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of theſe ſix ſpaces every one to the aforefaid line of which you have found the place, by turning the ſtring with the half circle about the axeltree by the point t, as you ſee, as farre as the points 24. And 6.</p>
            <p>Take conveniently in theſe two lines of hours after the French way, In each of them one of the points wherein it meets with the Equinoctial line PQ, or elſe the ſaid line found with the ſtring 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, that is to ſay in one, the point that the line placed with the ſtring makes in it, and in the other; the point that the Equinoctial line makes in it, for example, In the line, XII, 24, take in it the point 24. Wherein it meets with the line found with the ſtring: and in the other, VI, take in it the point VI. wherein it meets with the Equinoctiall line.</p>
            <p>Set either a ſtring or a rule by theſe two points ſo taken 24. and VI, as you ſee the line, 24. 6.</p>
            <p>Then with the ſtring comming from the center of the half circle Q go razing or laying even the ſtring 24. VI by making it longer or ſhorter as need requires; as you ſee in O, g, mark many ſeveral points in the ſuperficies of the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:98167:66"/>
Dyall one after an other, as for example 24, g, VI, more or leſſe, according as the ſuperficies of the Dyall is more or leſſe uneven.</p>
            <p>Draw an obſcure line by the points 24, g, VI, and it will be a line of houres after the Italian or Babylonian way, and ſo of all the reſt.</p>
            <p>The ſtring h, OH ſhews that you may if need be, do the like both of one and of the other ſide of the center O, to go and place of one part or other according to the occaſion, the line, as 2, 3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>And if you have a ſtraight line, as might be O, q, which may turn about the center O, and be perpendicular to the Axeltree BI, and you hold the half circle with this ſtraight line, ſet one at a convenient or reaſonable diſtance from the other: And let it be alwayes exactly of the diſtance of ſix hours after the French way: Firſt of all, this ſtring de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes the Equinoctial line in the ſuperficies of the Dyall, Secondly when one of the two, either the half circle or the ſtraight line O q, is found in one of the points of the hours of the Equator, th'other is likewiſe found in it, in an other point of hour, then drawing with a ſtring com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the center O, a ſtraight line that may go from the point, as t, to the end of the ſtraight line O q which you ſhall go drawing with this ſtring made ſhorter or longer, as need requires, and mark ſome points of line of hour, after the Italian or Babylonian way in the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies of the Dyall.</p>
            <p>And for this purpoſe there is nothing ſo eaſie as to have a circle of Equator, that may be fitted to the half circle, and where you may have alwayes a ſpace ready made for it's hour.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98167:66"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>25</head>
                  <head>To mark the houres after the Manner of the Iewes.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="25" type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:67"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>24</head>
                  <head>for the houres after the Italian way.</head>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:67"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 25,</hi> To mark the hours after the manner of the Ancients or the Jewes.</head>
            <p>YOu muſt know firſt that it would be very troubleſome to draw in the ſuperficies of the Dyall, the lines of this kind of hours in ſuch a manner as that they might be alwayes juſt and right in theory, all the year long.</p>
            <p>And therefore it is ſufficient to draw them juſt by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration in three points onely, <hi>viz,</hi> in their points of both ends, and of the middle, which are the points of thoſe circles that appear the greateſt above the Horizon being parallel to the Equator, and of the Equator it ſelf.</p>
            <p>The reſt goes as it may, and therefore it may be ſaid, that the lines of ſuch hours traced in this manner are falſe in the reſt of their length, yet Curioſitie makes them paſſe for current.</p>
            <p>Wherefore to mark this kind of lines of hours.</p>
            <p>The higher figure 4 ſhewes which way you muſt make this half Circle to turn about, <hi>viz.</hi> about a ſtraight axel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree line placed levell in the center of the Axel-tree of the Dyall.</p>
            <p>And to be ſhort, ſet up and make very faſt a rod in a ſtraight line paſſing to the center O, and let it be firſt within the joynt of the axeltree rod, ſecondly let it be level, as the figures do ſhew of a plummet P. and of a level A, this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done, tye ſome ſtrings with a looſe knot to this rod ſo levelled NL as you ſee NR, and LT.</p>
            <p>Take the ſtring from about the center O, ſtretch it out in a direct or ſtraight line from the center O to one of the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:98167:68"/>
points of hour, after the French way, of the Equinoctial line of the Dyall, for example to the point of 1 hour, as you ſee the ſtring OI.</p>
            <p>This ſtring being thus ſtrecht out, take the other ſtrings of one or th'other end NL, and Croſſe over this ſtring OI with them, and ſo go and mark many points in the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies of the Dyall, as TIR.</p>
            <p>Draw an obſcure line by thoſe points as TIR, it is a line of hours after the manner of the Ancients or the Jews, do the like with the other hours and half hours of the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial line.</p>
            <p>If you leave a rod in the Dyall, as NOL, the ſhadow thereof will go and ſhew theſe hours continually at length, if you will not leave it in, the button or center O of the axeltree of the Dyall will ſhew them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="26" type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:68"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>26</head>
                  <head>for the hight of the ſun.</head>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:69"/>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:98167:69"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 26.</hi> How to mark the Elevation of the Sun above the Horizon.</head>
            <p>THE higher fig. 3. ſhews which way you muſt turn the half circle, <hi>viz.</hi> about a ſtraight axel-line hanging down right.</p>
            <p>Set up your half circle, ſo that it may turn like a wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-cock about a rod hanging down right, or plum, above or below the axeltree of the Dyal, it matters not which.</p>
            <p>VVhileſt you turn it thus as it is above ſaid, cauſe in the mean time the ſtring comming from the center O to paſſe by one of the degrees of the edge of the circle; and make the ſtring ſhorter or longer as need ſhall require, mark with it many ſeveral points in the ſuperficies of the Dyal, according as you ſee them rankt one by an other, in four places.</p>
            <p>Draw a ſmall or obſcure line through all theſe points, and this will be one of the lines of the Elevation of the Sun.</p>
            <p>Count the Degrees in the edge of the circle, beginning at the firſt of the beam which is level, and ending at the 90. Beam which is down right or plum.</p>
            <p>Mark in the line of the Dyal, the number of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of the border of the circle, where the ſtring paſſes that hath mark't the points of that line, and ſo of all the others, and the ſhadow of the button of the axeltree which is in the center of the circle, will ſhew the Elevation of the Sum above the Horizon.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="27" type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:70"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Figure 27:</hi> How to mark the Sun riſing, or Eaſt riſing of the Sun.</head>
            <p>THE figure 2 above ſhews how you muſt place the half circle, <hi>viz.</hi> parallel unto the Horizon, I would not put a levell to it to avoid confuſion. It ſhews alſo that one of the Diameters of the circle muſt be ſet within the center of the Dyal, that is to ſay, thar it muſt go di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly from the ſouth to the North, and accordingly the Diameter which is perpendicular to it, will go from Eaſt to Weſt.</p>
            <p>When your circle is ſet faſt in this poſition, let a plum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met op in the lower figure hang from the center O.</p>
            <p>This being done, from each point of Degree of the edge of the circle, as from x and from z. mark with a ſtring XT or ZR. many points in the ſuperficies of the Dyal.</p>
            <p>Draw a ſmall or obſcure line through theſe points, as TY or SR. it is a line of the Suns Eaſtriſing-</p>
            <p>Mark in it the number of Degrees of the point of the circle from whence the ſtring comes, according as you will count them, to begin either from the Eaſt, or from the South. And ſo of all the other Degrees accordingly.</p>
            <p>And the ſhadow of the button O will ſhew which way the ſight of the Sun comes upon the Dyal.</p>
            <p>I will take here occaſion to tell you, that if for ſome reaſon or other, you could obſerve, in one and the ſame day, but two ſhadows of the Sun in ſtead of three, as we have ſaid in the placing of the axeltree in the Dyal, the declining of the Sun in that day, will ſerve you for a third ſhadow, or elſe two other ſhadows obſerved in an other day. I mean you may find equally the placing of the axeltree by one or other of thoſe ways above mentioned, and with 3 ſhadows; and with 2 ſhadows, and the declining of the Sun in that day, and with 4 ſhadows, two of one day, and two of an other, which are three wayes that come all to one.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98167:70"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>27</head>
                  <head>for the Eastriſing of the ſun.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="28" type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:71"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>28</head>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:71"/>
            <head>Figure 28.</head>
            <p>I do not ſpecifie in this volum theſe kinds of flat Dyals, wherein you may work without knobs or middle rule: And where you may draw the Equinoctial line; trace out and divide the circle Equator: in a word, where you may do all: yea and in the very ſuperficies of the Dyal, you may eaſily come to know them you ſelf, by putting this univerſall way into practice.</p>
            <p>Here is onely a way how to trace out all the twelue lines of the hours equal, after the French way, in the flat Dyals where the axeltree meets the ſuperficies athwart in the ſpace that you work in, ſo that you ſhall have no need of a greater place. And what I have already ſaid, and what I am now going to ſay again, will ſerve to find out the way to do the like in all kinds of Dyals univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally.</p>
            <p>When you have drawn upon your Dyal the Equinoctial line M 12 M, drawn conveniently and divided the circle Equator Q 12 Q bring to the Equinoctial line, the beam of the 12 hours Q, 12. Draw of both ſides of the Equator, and from the Equinoctial line a ſtraight line MQ parallel to the beam of 12. hours O 12. bring the beams of the other hours to the firſt, which they ſhall find of the Equinoctial in rt: and of MQ in c, d<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g, Q, Bring in the Dyal the line of the twelve hours B. 12. draw by the point M, of the Equinoctial line, and from the center of the Dyal B a ſtraight line ML parallel to the line of twelve hours B 12; make upon this line ML and upon the point M a triangle LMN like to the triangle in the aire OB 12. and let the angles of theſe triangles in the points L and B be equal one unto an other, Carry the ſpaces Mq, Mg, Md, Mc, from the ſtraight line MQ into the ſtraight line MN, <hi>viz.</hi> from M into N, into u, into i, into o, bring by the points
<pb facs="tcp:98167:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
N, u, i, o, ſome ſtraight lines NL, ub, if, oh, parallel to the ſide, NL of the triangle LMN: Carry from the center of the Dyal B by the points r, t, h, f, o, L, Some ſtraight lines, BL, Bh, Bf, Bh, Bt, Br; Theſe are ſuch lines of hours as you may continue beyond the center B, and mark them according to their orders.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98167:72"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
