<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A dialogue between a blind-man and death</title>
            <author>Standfast, Richard, 1608?-1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-03">2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35858</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1291</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184577</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19618950</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19618950</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109210</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A35858)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109210)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1685:16, 2046:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A dialogue between a blind-man and death</title>
                  <author>Standfast, Richard, 1608?-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 broadside.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Larkin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Richard Standfast by NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>"Licensed, According to Order."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Item at 1685:16 identified as D1291; entry cancelled in Wing (2nd ed.)</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Death --  Religious aspects --  Christianity.</term>
               <term>Dialogues.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:109210:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A DIALOGUE Between a Blind-Man and Death.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Blind-Man.</speaker>
               <l>The more men ſee, the leſs they do enquire;</l>
               <l>The worſe they ſee, the more they do deſire</l>
               <l>Others to grant what Blindneſs cannot give,</l>
               <l>And for Intelligence grow inquiſitive.</l>
               <l>They ask to be inform'd, who cannot ſee;</l>
               <l>I know't by ſad experience, Wo is me!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Death</speaker>
               <l>Where are you, Sir? What ſitting all alone?</l>
               <l>I did ſuppoſe 'twas you by that ſad moan:</l>
               <l>Coming this way to gather what's my due,</l>
               <l>I thought it not amiſs, to call on you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Blind-Man.</speaker>
               <l>I do not know that voice; 'tis ſure ſome Stranger;</l>
               <l>And by his words, he ſeemes to bode me danger.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Death.</speaker>
               <l>You gueſs aright, Sir; and before I go,</l>
               <l>I'll make you know me, whether you will or no.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Blind-Man.</speaker>
               <l>Why what are you? Pray tell me what's your Name,</l>
               <l>And what's your bus'neſs, and from whence you came.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Death.</speaker>
               <l>I will declare what no man can deny,</l>
               <l>There's none ſo great a Traveller as I:</l>
               <l>Yet you muſt know, I am no wandring Rover,</l>
               <l>For my Dominion lies the World all over;</l>
               <l>I march through Court and Country, Town and City,</l>
               <l>I know not how to fear, nor how to pity.</l>
               <l>The higheſt Cedar, and the loweſt Flower,</l>
               <l>Sooner or later do both feel my Power:</l>
               <l>The mightieſt Emperour doth ſubmit to me,</l>
               <l>Nor is the pooreſt tatter'd Beggar free;</l>
               <l>In Peace, I glean here one, and there another;</l>
               <l>Sometimes I ſweep whole ſtreets, both one and t'other.</l>
               <l>In time of War, thus much I can divine;</l>
               <l>Whoever gets the day, the Triumph's mine.</l>
               <l>I am a potent and a high Commander,</l>
               <l>'Twas I that conquer'd the Great <hi>Alexander,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Though mighty Nations under's foot he trod,</l>
               <l>And had th' Ambition to be thought a God;</l>
               <l>Yet, after all the Victories he had won,</l>
               <l>I made him know he was but <hi>Philip</hi>'s Son.</l>
               <l>Were you <hi>Goli<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>h</hi> great, or <hi>Sampſon</hi>-ſtrong,</l>
               <l>Were you as wiſe, as rich as <hi>Solomon:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Were you as <hi>Neſtor,</hi> Old; as Infant, Young;</l>
               <l>Had you the faireſt Cheeck, the ſweeteſt Tongue;</l>
               <l>Yet you muſt ſtoop, all theſe will nought avail:</l>
               <l>For my Arreſt does not admit of Bail;</l>
               <l>And to deal plainly, Sir, my name is Death,</l>
               <l>And 'tis my bus'neſs to demand your Breath.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Blind-Man.</speaker>
               <l>My Breath and Life ſhall both go out together,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Death.</speaker>
               <l>And on that Errand 'twas, that I came hither.</l>
               <l>I'll have both Breath and Life without delay:</l>
               <l>You muſt and ſhall diſpatch; come, come, away.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Blind-Man.</speaker>
               <l>What need ſuch Poſting haſte? Pray Change your mind;</l>
               <l>'Tis a poor Conqueſt to ſurpriſe the <hi>Blind.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Death.</speaker>
               <l>You may not call it <hi>Poſting,</hi> nor <hi>Surpriſe;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For you had warning when you loſt your Eyes.</l>
               <l>Nor could you hope your Houſe could long be free,</l>
               <l>After the Windows were poſſeſt by me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Blind-Man.</speaker>
               <l>But Life is ſweet; and who'ld not, if he might,</l>
               <l>Have a long day, before he bid good Night?</l>
               <l>O ſpare me yet awhile! ſlight not my Tears.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Death.</speaker>
               <l>Hard Hearts and hungry Bellies have no Ears.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Blind-Man.</speaker>
               <l>I am not yet quite ready for the Table.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Death.</speaker>
               <l>All's one to me; I am inexorable.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Blind-Man.</speaker>
               <l>Yet, by your favour, I may ſtep aſide.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Death.</speaker>
               <l>Be not deceiv'd, for 'tis in vain to hide:</l>
               <l>My forces are diſperſed through all places;</l>
               <l>And act for me without reſpect of Faces:</l>
               <l>I have a Thouſand ways to ſhorten Life,</l>
               <l>Beſides a Rapier, Piſtol, Sword, or Knife:</l>
               <l>A Fly, a Hair, a ſplinter of a Thorn,</l>
               <l>A little Scratch, the cutting of a Corn,</l>
               <l>Have ſometimes done my bus'neſs heretofore,</l>
               <l>So to the full, that I need wiſh no more.</l>
               <l>Should all theſe fail, enough of humours lurk</l>
               <l>Within your Body, Sir, to do my work.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Blind-Man.</speaker>
               <l>Well then, let ſome one run to my Phyſitian,</l>
               <l>Tell him I want his aid in this Condition.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Death.</speaker>
               <l>Run, Boy, and fetch him; call th' whole Colledge, do:</l>
               <l>For I intend to have them ſhortly too.</l>
               <l>I value not their Portions and their Pills,</l>
               <l>Nor all the Cordials in the Doctors Bills:</l>
               <l>When my time's come, let them do what they can,</l>
               <l>I'll have my due, ſo vain a thing is man.</l>
               <l>Should <hi>Gallen</hi> and <hi>Hippocrates</hi> both joyn,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Paracelſus</hi> too, with them Combine,</l>
               <l>Let them all meet to Countermand my ſtrength</l>
               <l>Yet ſhall they be my Priſoners at length.</l>
               <l>I grant that Men of Learning, Worth and Art,</l>
               <l>May have the better of me at the Start;</l>
               <l>But in long Running they'll give out and tire,</l>
               <l>And quit the field, and leave me my deſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>As for thoſe Quacks, that threaten to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> me,</l>
               <l>They are my Friends; and ſpeed ſome Patients to me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Blind-Man.</speaker>
               <l>Well, If I muſt, I'll yeild to you the day</l>
               <l>Tis ſo Enacted, and I muſt Obey:</l>
               <l>Henceforth I count my ſelf among you <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>rs,</l>
               <l>For 'tis, I ſee, the meaſure of my Bett<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>But tell me now, when did your Power <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ce?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Death.</speaker>
               <l>My Power began from <hi>Adam</hi>'s firſt Off<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Blind-Man.</speaker>
               <l>From <hi>Adam</hi>'s firſt Offence! O baſe beg<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ning!</l>
               <l>Whoſe very firſt Original was Sinning.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Death.</speaker>
               <l>My Riſing did from <hi>Adam</hi>'s Fail begin;</l>
               <l>And ever ſince, my ſtrength and ſting's <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Sin.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Blind-Man.</speaker>
               <l>To know wherein the Enemies ſtrength doth lie,</l>
               <l>In my Conceit is half a Victory:</l>
               <l>Have you Commiſſion now for what you do?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Death.</speaker>
               <l>I have Commiſſion: what's all this to you<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Blind-Man.</speaker>
               <l>Yes very much; for now I underſtand</l>
               <l>I am not totally at your command:</l>
               <l>My Life's at his who gave you this Commiſion;</l>
               <l>To him I'll therefore make with my Petition:</l>
               <l>I'll Seek his Love, and on his Mercy truſt;</l>
               <l>And when my Sins are pardon'd, do your worſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Death.</speaker>
               <l>That you may know how far my Power exterds</l>
               <l>I will divorce you from your deareſt Friends</l>
               <l>You ſhall reſign your Jewels, Money, Plate:</l>
               <l>Your Earthly Joyes ſhall all be out of date.</l>
               <l>I will deprive you of your dainty fare;</l>
               <l>I'll ſtrip you to the skin, naked and bare.</l>
               <l>Linnen or Woolen you ſhall have to wind y<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>As for the reſt, all muſt be left behind y<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Bound hand and foot, I'll bring you to my D<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Where conſtant dreadfull Darkneſs reigns, and then</l>
               <l>Your only Dwelling-houſe ſhall be a Cave;</l>
               <l>Your Lodging-Room, a little narrow Grave;</l>
               <l>A Cheſt, your Cloſet; and a Sheet, your Dreſs;</l>
               <l>And your Companions, Worms and Rottenneſs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Blind-Man.</speaker>
               <l>If this be all the miſchief you can do,</l>
               <l>Your Harbingers deſerve more dread than you.</l>
               <l>Diſeaſes are your Harbingers, I'm ſure;</l>
               <l>Many of which, 'tis grievous to endure;</l>
               <l>But when once dead, I ſhall not then Complain</l>
               <l>Of Cold, or Hunger, Poverty or Pain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Death.</speaker>
               <l>There's one thing more, which here to mind I call,</l>
               <l>When once I come, <hi>then come I once for all:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And when my ſtroke doth Soul and Body ſever,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What's left undone, muſt be undone for ever!</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Blind-Man.</speaker>
               <l>That's a great Truth, and I have learnt to know</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That there's no working in the Grave below.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To be before hand therefore I will try,</l>
               <l>That then I may have nought to do but dye.</l>
               <l>But tell me, Sir, do all men dye alike?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Death.</speaker>
               <l>To me they do; for whom God bids, I ſtrike;</l>
               <l>Look how the Fooliſh dye, ſo dye the Wiſe;</l>
               <l>As do the Righteous, ſo the Sinner dyes.</l>
               <l>There's afterwards a difference, though, 'tis true;</l>
               <l>But that's a thing with which I've nought to do.</l>
               <l>That I to ſome prove better, to ſome worſe;</l>
               <l>To ſome a Bleſſing, and to ſome a Curſe;</l>
               <l>That's none of mine; I may not undertake it;</l>
               <l>'Tis Gods appointment, and mens works, that make it.</l>
               <l>Hence 'tis that Sinners Troubles never ceaſe,</l>
               <l>And that the End of th' Upright Man is peace.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Blind-Man.</speaker>
               <l>There now remains but only one thing more;</l>
               <l>Will not thy pow'r be one day out of door?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Death.</speaker>
               <l>Yes, I muſt needs confeſs 'tis very true;</l>
               <l>There is a Death for Me, as well as You;</l>
               <l>And mine's the worſt, for I muſt die for ever;</l>
               <l>You may revive again, but I ſhall never.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Blind-Man.</speaker>
               <l>By all that hath been ſaid, I now do ſee,</l>
               <l>You needed not have been ſo rough with me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Death.</speaker>
               <l>Come, let that paſs — The kinder to appear,</l>
               <l>I will reveal a ſecret in your Ear.</l>
               <l>The Death of Chriſt upon the painful Croſs,</l>
               <l>Which ſeem'd to be my Gain, turn'd to my Loſs.</l>
               <l>As in his Hair, the ſtrength of <hi>Sampſon</hi> lay,</l>
               <l>And with his Hair, went <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s ſtrength away.</l>
               <l>So I've no ſtrength, but what I had from Sin;</l>
               <l>Nor have I Sting, but what lies hid therein:</l>
               <l>Chriſt Suffering Death, to put this ſting away,</l>
               <l>Hath made me his, whom I ſuppos'd my Prey.</l>
               <l>My Strength is now decay'd, my Sting rebated:</l>
               <l>My Boldneſs Check'd, and my Dominion mated;</l>
               <l>And I am now both faint and feeble grown,</l>
               <l>Much like poor <hi>Sampſon,</hi> when his ſtreagth was gone:</l>
               <l>In my own Craft I was Compleatly routed,</l>
               <l>My Jaws are broken, and my Holders outed.</l>
               <l>What now I catch, I have no pow'r to keep;</l>
               <l>My very Name is chang'd, from Death to Sleep:</l>
               <l>I ſeiz'd on Chriſt indeed, that I did do;</l>
               <l>Nay more, I bound him in my Priſon too;</l>
               <l>But all my ſtrongeſt Doors, Bars, Bolts, and Bands,</l>
               <l>Were but meer Nothing in his mighty Hands:</l>
               <l>He broke them all, and left my doors wide ope,</l>
               <l>And all his Servants Priſoners of Hope:</l>
               <l>For though they dye, yet with devout Affection,</l>
               <l>They do expect a joyfull Reſurrection;</l>
               <l>And with their Maſter to be brought again,</l>
               <l>That they with him for ever may Remain.</l>
               <l>Thus Chriſt by dying, did become Victorious:</l>
               <l>And from his Bed of Darkneſs roſe more glorious:</l>
               <l>And I by Binding Him, made my ſelf faſt;</l>
               <l>And His, I know will prove my Death at laſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Blind-Man.</speaker>
               <l>Theſe words give Comfort and Inſtruction too;</l>
               <l>Henceforth I ſhall be better pleas'd with you.</l>
               <l>Decreed it is for all men once to dye;</l>
               <l>After that Judgment, then Eternity.</l>
               <l>To Prayer therefore will I joyn Endeavour,</l>
               <l>So to live here, that I may live for Ever.</l>
               <l>And ſeeing they that have, and keep Chriſts words:</l>
               <l>Whether they live or dye, be all the Lords;</l>
               <l>Repentance, Faith, and New Obedience ſhall</l>
               <l>Fit and prepare me for my Funeral.</l>
               <l>From whence I truſt, my Saviour will tranſlate me,</l>
               <l>In Seaſon due, beyond their reach that hate me;</l>
               <l>Even to that place of Life and Glory too,</l>
               <l>Where neither Death, nor Sin, hath ought to do</l>
               <l>This hope in me, that Word of his doth cheriſh,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He that believes in Me, ſhall never periſh.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now welcome Death, upon my Saviours Score!</l>
               <l>Who would not dye, to live for Evermore?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Death.</speaker>
               <l>Sir, I perceive you ſpeak not without Reaſon:</l>
               <l>I'll leave you now, and call ſome other Seaſon.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Blind-Man.</speaker>
               <l>Call when you pleaſe, I will await that Call;</l>
               <l>And while I ſtand make ready for my Fall!</l>
               <l>In the mean time, my conſtant Prayer ſhall be,</l>
               <l>From Sudden and from Endleſs Death, <hi>Good Lord deliver me.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Judge not of Death by Sence, leaſt you miſtake it;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Death's neither Friend nor Foe, but as you make it.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Live as you ſhould, you need not then Complain;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For where to</hi> Live, <hi>is</hi> Chriſt; <hi>to</hi> Dye, <hi>is</hi> Gain.</l>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>LICENSED, According to Order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>George Larkin,</hi> at the <hi>Coach</hi> and <hi>Horſes</hi> without <hi>Biſhopſgate,</hi> a little beyond <hi>Old Bedlam.</hi> 1686.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
