<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mr. Tho. Dangerfield's second narrative wherein is contained a faithful charge against the Lady Powis, Mr. Stamford, (the Duke of Newburghs resident) and Mrs. Cellier relating to the murther of Sir Edmundbury Godfrey and the late plot made by the papists, to be cast upon the Protestants : wherein is I. A true account of methods used to invalidate the testimony of Captain William Bedloe and Mr. Prance, II. An account of the several papists imprisoned, and their crimes, with the charges it cost them to get out upon bail / written by his own hand.</title>
            <author>Dangerfield, Thomas, 1650?-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-03">2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36359</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D193</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20874</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12225943</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12225943</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56495</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A36359)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56495)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 913:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mr. Tho. Dangerfield's second narrative wherein is contained a faithful charge against the Lady Powis, Mr. Stamford, (the Duke of Newburghs resident) and Mrs. Cellier relating to the murther of Sir Edmundbury Godfrey and the late plot made by the papists, to be cast upon the Protestants : wherein is I. A true account of methods used to invalidate the testimony of Captain William Bedloe and Mr. Prance, II. An account of the several papists imprisoned, and their crimes, with the charges it cost them to get out upon bail / written by his own hand.</title>
                  <author>Dangerfield, Thomas, 1650?-1685.</author>
                  <author>Prance, Miles, fl. 1678-1689.</author>
                  <author>Bedloe, William, 1650-1680.</author>
                  <author>Cellier, Elizabeth, fl. 1680.</author>
                  <author>Powis, Elizabeth Somerset Herbert, Duchess of, d. 1691.</author>
                  <author>Stamford, Mr.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Cockerill ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Godfrey, Edmund Berry, --  Sir, 1621-1678.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-10</date>
            <label>Stephanie Batkie</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-10</date>
            <label>Stephanie Batkie</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-12</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:56495:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Do Appoint <hi>THOMAS COCKERILL</hi> to Print this my Second NARRATIVE, and that no other Print the same.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>February 6. 1679/80.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>THOMAS DANGERFEILD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56495:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Tho. Dangerfeild's SECOND NARRATIVE: Wherein is Contained A FAITHFUL CHARGE AGAINST THE Lady <hi>POWIS,</hi> Mr. <hi>STAMFORD,</hi> (the Duke of <hi>Newburghs</hi> Resident) and Mrs. <hi>CELLIER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Relating to the Murther of <hi>Sir Edmundbury Godfrey,</hi> AND The late PLOT made by the <hi>PAPISTS,</hi> To be Cast upon the <hi>PROTESTANTS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREIN IS</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. A True Account of Methods used to Invalidate the Testimony of Captain <hi>WILLIAM BEDLOE</hi> and Mr. <hi>PRANCE.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. An Account of the several <hi>PAPISTS</hi> Imprisoned, and their Crimes, with the Charges it cost them to get out upon Bail.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by his own Hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Cockerill</hi> at the <hi>Three Legs</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> over-against the <hi>stocks-Market,</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:56495:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56495:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable Sir <hi>ROBERT CLAYTON,</hi> Knight, Lord Mayor of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THough a too prevalent <hi>custom</hi> has rendred <hi>Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations</hi> little more than <hi>Complemental</hi> Follies, wherein Authors first make <hi>themselves,</hi> and next their <hi>Patrons,</hi> ridiculous, by extravagant Harangues; yet I cannot but be free from <hi>all suspitions</hi> of such vanity in Addressing these Papers to your <hi>Lordships</hi> hand, whose <hi>solid worth</hi> is as much <hi>above,</hi> as <hi>neglectful</hi> of popular <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plause.</hi> I come not to make you a <hi>Present,</hi> but to pay you a <hi>Tribute;</hi> The <hi>Loyalty, Prudence, Justice,</hi> and <hi>Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> your Lordship exercises in that Honourable, but <hi>weighty</hi> Charge wherewith you are entrusted, and the zeal and <hi>stedfastness</hi> you have shown to the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> in these tempestuous times (when some that seem'd <hi>fixed stars,</hi> have been found but Blazing <hi>Meteors</hi>), just<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intitles you to the <hi>Respects</hi> and Gratitude of all true <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants</hi> and <hi>Englishmen;</hi> not only in this mighty <hi>City,</hi> wherein (under His Majesty, whom God long preserve) you <hi>preside,</hi> but throughout the <hi>Nation</hi> too, by the influence of your generous <hi>Example</hi> to other Magistrates.</p>
            <p>Besides which, my own <hi>private</hi> Obligations to your Lordships <hi>Candor</hi> and Impartial Audience, when humbly requested, loudly call for some publick Acknowledgments from me, who cannot but receive comfort under all <hi>Discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements</hi> that have, or may happen, when I consider, That a person of your Lordships <hi>Integrity</hi> and <hi>Merit</hi> cannot es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape the <hi>Frowns</hi> (shall I call them? or rather <hi>Snarlings</hi>) of some little pretenders to the Protestant Interest, which really they <hi>desert</hi> through Ignorance, or maliciously endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to <hi>betray.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:56495:3"/>Nor know I how better to Implore your Lordships par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for the <hi>presumption</hi> of this Address, than by professing in all sincerity, That the Motives inducing me to publish this <hi>Narrative,</hi> were principally the <hi>Glory of God,</hi> the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> and <hi>Safety</hi> of the King, and the preservation of the true Protestant Religion; and secondarily in order to those ends, the <hi>strengthning</hi> of all Protestants against a most perverse, <hi>subtile</hi> and <hi>cruel</hi> Generation, who with restless Endeavours seek to overthrow the same; Rendred yet more <hi>dangerous,</hi> because some weak unthinking people are too easily deluded to own, Countenance and <hi>Abet</hi> (though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps unwittingly) such their mischievous Designs. And lastly, That if there be any <hi>Papists</hi> sincere in their mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guided Devotion, the horrid practises of the <hi>Leading men</hi> of that faction (nakedly display'd) may open their Eyes, and convince them so far, as to abandon that pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Communion, and embrace the Truth, thereby becoming at once true <hi>Christians</hi> and good <hi>Subjects</hi> to their true and natural Prince.</p>
            <p>This being the only <hi>scope,</hi> I am bold to promise my self a <hi>Connivence</hi> for any imperfections of <hi>stile</hi> or <hi>method,</hi> my aim herein being <hi>Truth,</hi> not <hi>Rhetorick.</hi> That the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty may ever bless your Honour, and preserve this Noble <hi>City</hi> both from the <hi>Treacherous Malice,</hi> and <hi>Crafty Insinuations</hi> of <hi>Romish</hi> Incendiaries, shall be the daily prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord!</salute> 
               <signed>Your Lordships most humble and devoted Servant,
THOMAS DANGERFEILD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56495:3"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>Dangerfield's Second Narrative,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THis age hath produced diverse strange demonstrations, of the many Damnable and Horrid Designs, such as possess the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick Religion which affords such Hellish Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, that the Bloud of Princes, Magistrates, Destruction of Nations, or what Hell it self can invent, cannot obstruct them or stand in their way, to hinder the promoting their excellent Religion, and as a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther detection of their villanies; I recommend to your consideration this ensuing Narrative, which had it taken the effect intended might have proved as dangerous to the Protestant Interest as any, for about the month of <hi>February,</hi> 1678. One Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> being a Prisoner in the <hi>K. Bench</hi> did after some time enter into a Correspondence with one <hi>Lionel Anderson</hi> alias <hi>Mounson,</hi> a Dominican Priest; and then also a Prisoner there: who pretending some better Opinion of Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> then of others, did invite him to his Chamber to drink, which favour he readily imbraced and very often; but at one time being somewhat over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken with Drink, the said <hi>Anderson</hi> alias <hi>Mounson,</hi> demanded of him of what Family he was, and the manner of his present Condition and also if he was a Roman Catholick, to which he answered he was not, but was a well-wisher to that Religion, then he demanded of him if he would undertake something that would produce him immediate Liberty, and his future Happiness and good Fortune, he answered, he would, and desired to know what it was, at which he exprest much satisfaction, and withall lanched out a discourse relating to the stifling the Evidence of Capt. <hi>William Bedloe,</hi> one of His Majesties Witnesses of this most Horrid Plot, which was thus. Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> you are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with one <hi>Phillip Marsh,</hi> who has formerly been a Servant to Mr. <hi>Bedloe</hi> and have often informed me you held a correspondence with <hi>Bedloe:</hi> now if so, I will put you in a way by that means how to create to your self a considerable Interest: provided you will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low my directions and to give a general satisfaction to all good Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, which Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> declared a seeming approbation of, and that from thenceforward he would be guided by the said <hi>Anderson</hi> alias <hi>Mounson</hi> who shewed his rejoycing thereat by imbracing Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> in his Arms, and said <hi>Bedloe</hi> was a great Villain, and had given false te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony against the Lord <hi>Powis,</hi> Lord <hi>Arundel,</hi> Lord <hi>Bellasis,</hi> Lord <hi>Stafford,</hi> Lord <hi>Petre,</hi> and divers other worthy Roman Catholicks, but had done it so weekly, that it was to be seen through every part. And therefore the aforesaid five Lords in particular were willing to use some means to bring Mr. <hi>Bedloe</hi> on the Stage, And then further
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56495:4"/>
added that no way could be so proper for accomplishing this Design, as for the said Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> to drink with <hi>Philip Marsh</hi> and enquire of him about the behaviour of his Master Mr. <hi>Bedloe,</hi> and what Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation he was of when the said <hi>Phillip Marsh</hi> lived with him, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired if the said <hi>Marsh</hi> should of himself or could by the said Mr. <hi>Strodes</hi> instigation be brought to say any thing material against <hi>Bedloe,</hi> that might any wayes lessen or invalidate his Testimony, that Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> should offer him a reward of money, or to that very Effect.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> being of better Principles, and therefore desirous to improve such an opportunity to the discovery of the Romish Villany, pretendedly, but untruly to encourage the said Mr. <hi>Anderson</hi> alias <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> to proceed in that design, told him no man was fitter to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in such an Affair then himself, in regard he had known Mr. <hi>Bedloe</hi> divers years and had during the time of his Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonment, received divers Letters from him in which he requested him to be true to him, as knowing he had or could produce some Papers that would much invalidate his Testimony, to prevent which he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten had by the said <hi>Marsh</hi> sent him money; and that by Mr. <hi>Bedloes</hi> means one Mr. <hi>Iohnson</hi> a Servant to the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> did often come to request his Testimony against the Lords in the Tower, and in order to it offered him divers summs of money all which he had refused to accept of, This feigned story so incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Mr. <hi>Anderson</hi> alias <hi>Mounson</hi> to proceed, that he began very hotly to urge Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> to use his utmost endeavours in Prosecution thereof, and accordingly some time after Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> acquainting him that he had Communicated the said matter to the said <hi>Phillip Marsh,</hi> whom he found was as ready as himself to be directed by him, but that to encourage the said <hi>Marsh</hi> he had promised him some Money, <hi>Anderson</hi> seemed to be very well satisfied therewith and then protested it should be performed both to <hi>Marsh</hi> and <hi>Strode.</hi> Provided, they would when occasion should require be ready to Swear such matter against Mr. <hi>Bedloe</hi> as he the said <hi>Anderson</hi> would inform them of, which was by Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> seemingly agreed on.</p>
            <p>Upon the ninth of <hi>March</hi> following <hi>Anderson</hi> and <hi>Strode</hi> meeting, the said <hi>Anderson</hi> desired to know of Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> if he would be true to him, to which he answered he would, then said <hi>Anderson</hi> I can beleive you, because I have been imformed you are nearly related to an inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Friend and Acquaintance of mine of your Name, and a person of great Worth and Honour; therefore I do assure my self no man of that name can break his Word, but notwithstanding that <hi>Mounson</hi> urged him to take an Oath of Secrecy, to be True to him which Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> seemed unwilling to do; but rather then he would lose so pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable an occasion to serve his King and Country in making himself ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of detecting so Villanous a Roguery, he did on his faith Promise
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56495:4"/>
to be true to him, which he being satisfied with, further to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> to proceed therein, then promised him five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pound, and to make him one of the greatest of his name, If He the said <hi>Philip Marsh,</hi> and others did so follow his directions, that Mr. <hi>Bedloes</hi> Evidence would be taken off, which Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> pretendedly undertook to do, but desired to know how he might be certain of the five hundred pound when the business should be finished, to which the said Mr. <hi>Anderson</hi> desired some time to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider of.</p>
            <p>In some short time after the said <hi>Anderson</hi> alias <hi>Mounson,</hi> meeting Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> in the said Prison, requested <hi>Strode</hi> to follow him into his Chamber, where he told Mr. <hi>Strode,</hi> he had made the design of subverting Mr. '<hi>Bedloes</hi> Evidence known to some persons of very great Quality, (by a scheme he had sent them in a Letter of the whole thing) who had returned him answer that they were very well pleased with the same and approved thereof, and gave him their thanks, and also order to give the said Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> such security as he should approve of for what he had promised, and directions where to find the said securities, or if Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> would nominate any Person of Credit and Trust, in whose hands the said summe of five hundred pound should be deposited for his use, it should be so done, and at a convenient time paid him, together with what he had promised to <hi>Marsh,</hi> then he ordered Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> to let the said <hi>Marsh</hi> and others, which were to be imployed with him in that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign, know that whatever sum they could in reason desire it should be granted, and immediately after (the business effected) Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>In order to the carrying on of this Affair some time after, the said Mr. <hi>Anderson</hi> invited Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> again into his Chamber, where he entertained him with discourse still relating to Mr. <hi>Bedloes</hi> busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, but he being very desirous (as may very well be supposed) to push on the same with all Expedition, was resolved to lose no time, and the better to incourage Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> he fetcht forth of his Study a quart-bottle of Brandy, and desired him to drink of the same, but Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> being cautious of the Liquor, did request him to drink first, which he did, but a very little, and desired to be excused for that his body would not bear drink, as Mr. <hi>Strodes</hi> would, who drank a considerable quantity of the Brandy, and then Mr. <hi>Anderson</hi> fetcht a Bottle of Wine and desired him to drink of that too, which after some little time he did, then the said <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derson alias Mounson</hi> told him, he had acquainted Sir <hi>Henry Tychbourne</hi> of the whole business against Mr. <hi>Bedloe</hi> in as full and ample man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56495:5"/>
as it really was intended, and that Sir <hi>Henry</hi>'s maid-servant had informed him the said <hi>Anderson alias Mounson</hi> from her Master, that he was exceeding well pleased, and that he had promised as a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther encouragement, he would assign him the said <hi>Strode</hi> an Estate in <hi>Hampshire</hi> worth one hundred pounds a year, for the space of two years, to be Rent free; and this Sir <hi>Henry</hi> would give of his own free will for the good of the Cause, and desired he should be infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of such a Reward intended for him, but that he might not know from whence it was to come, and then Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> left him.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> about a quarter of an hour afterwards, coming into <hi>Andersons</hi> Chamber again, was promised by <hi>Anderson</hi> that as soon as <hi>Marsh</hi> himself, and others were ready to receive the directions he had prepared for them, to swear against Mr. <hi>Bedloe,</hi> that then he would send one Mr. <hi>Nevil alias Paine</hi> (now a Prisoner at the Kings Bench, and Accused of High Treason) to a Person of High Quality, whom the said <hi>Anderson alias Mounson</hi> said was his very good Friend, and was sure would make way for the said <hi>Strodes</hi> Liberty in two dayes, which when accomplished the five Lords in the Tower did intend to Petition the Parliament for their Tryals, and to Subpoena the said Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> as a Witness in their behalfs, but he being as cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as the matter would bear, of Engaging himself too far in such dangerous matters, yet very desirous by that Correspondence though to his great hazard to be serviceable to his King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and the True Protestant Religion, he did continue the dissem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling his reality of being an instrument in that Hellish Practice de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed. But such was Mr. <hi>Strodes</hi> misfortune in the management of this Affair, that whether with cause or without, I know not; but its all one, with those of that Romish Religion, if they beleive other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, but now the scene was changed and Mr. <hi>Andersons</hi> Principles only the object, for now he having harboured a Jealousie in his thoughts that Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> was not real to him in this Catholick de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign, he presently forgets all-those little Vows and Execrations he he had uttered to make <hi>Strodes</hi> Fortune, and begins to cast about how to ruine him upon these grounds of suspicion.</p>
            <list>
               <item>First, He is possest with a beleif that Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> had Papers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the Plot and concealed them from him.</item>
               <item>Secondly. That he was likely to be a Witnesse for the King, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that or some other account relating to it, and had not discovered it to him the said <hi>Anderson.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:56495:5"/>And Thirdly, That in regard he could not get those Papers nor into those secrets, <hi>Strode</hi> might become very prejudicial to himself upon these Accounts, presently there is a Consultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by him with the Countesse of <hi>Powis,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> my Self, Mr. <hi>Nevil alias Paine,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Celliers</hi> maid-servant, and Mr. <hi>Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish.</hi> And now, Reader observe, how these holy members, of this holy Carholique Church proceeded.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>First, I must be by</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi>removed to the</hi> Kings Bench, <hi>and kept a Prisoner there, in order to be an Instrument in this Design on</hi> Mr. Strode, <hi>but to induce me to undertake it, and stir up zeal in me for this good Catholique Cause,</hi> Mrs. Cellier <hi>takes upon her to let me know that one Mr.</hi> Strode <hi>who was a Prisoner there, held a strong Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>respondence with Captain</hi> Bedloe, <hi>and that</hi> Bedloe <hi>sent him Money and Lette<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s very often, which when</hi> Strode <hi>was drunk he would boast of and had often said, it lay in his Power to do much prejudice to</hi> Bedloes <hi>Testimony, and that he had such Papers in his Pocket as would do the L<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ds in the Tower much service, or to that purpose; which at that time</hi> (<hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fully believed by me</hi>) <hi>wrought very effectually with me. And to second this, Mr.</hi> Anderson alias Mounson <hi>took upon him to come and instruct me how to attaque Mr.</hi> Strode <hi>for the said Papers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And that in regard of my former acquaintance with him, I might easily drink him to a pitch, for he was free to drink; and when he was in such disorder, I might easily pick them out of his Pocket, or otherwise get them from him, which in regard of our former acquaintance I readily undertook and I did frequently converse in the Prison with him without any Sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion from him, as I believe, of any design intended against him by me, at least at that time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But sometime after he observing I was somewhat full of mony, and more then ordinarily obliging to him, and always rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day to pay for what ever we had drank; made him then suspect me: and the rather for that it seems he had heard of my being wounded in <hi>Sommer set shire,</hi> where I had made known to my Chirurgion the great desire I had to converse with one Mr. <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> then a known Popish Priest, to a Person of Quality of that Religion, and in the same County; by which it was apparent to him I was of the same stock or Religion. These suggestions together with the former Dealings or works of Darknesse, he had been endeavoured to be perswaded to by <hi>Anderson,</hi> made him somewhat cautious; but these things having no certainty in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56495:6"/>
them, I prevailed with him to accept of my Company, which was the easier effected, because he wanted money and I did not, during this time; in regard neither Wine nor other Liquors would attain my ends, I was furnished by some of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned other parties with a dose of Opium, to lay him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sleep; but either by Sight or Tast he finding it in the Drink, spilt it, or otherwise avoided it; but by my insinuations I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with him to cast off all suspicion of any Design intended by me, and rather impute it to the neglect of the People of the House.</p>
            <p>About the five and twentieth of <hi>May</hi> last 1679. <hi>Mr. Strode</hi> coming into my Chamber, he found me very busie in Writing, and in some of the Papers which lay on the Table before me, he read his name in divers places, but the full meaning thereof he could not understand, yet conceived it could not be of any good Consequence to himself; then he went up to his Chamber fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and Communicated to him the substance of the whole Affair, and also that of <hi>Anderson's,</hi> and desired hi<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ice, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no he should hold any farther Correspondence with any of Us, as <hi>Strode</hi> informs me, and he advised him not to do it; for said he, <hi>Anderson</hi> offered me a conside<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> Reward, if I would by any means procure him some Papers, which you have, that concerned <hi>Mr. Bedloe,</hi> but I have denied to <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erve him, and so I would have you do, meaning <hi>Mr. Strode:</hi> after this he qui<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my Company for the space of a <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eabouts, but I Attacking him one day very ea<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>stly, <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> prevail with him to drink with me again, to which he yeil<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d; at which time from the same hands I had received nine g<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of Opium, to give him, which I accordingly a<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> t<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> time conveyed into a Tankard of bitter small Beer for him to drink, but the Beer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby Thick, and of an unpleasant Tast, it displeased both his Eyes and Palate, in so much that he cast it on the ground and never after that would come into my Company, for which both he and I have cause to praise God, as <hi>Strode</hi> to <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> present time does own.</p>
            <p>When all these Engines and Wayes, that had been set on foot, to carry on this Holy Catholique cause, would take no effect; I was then released out of that Prison to manage something of greater moment, but yet was willing to joyn with <hi>Anderson</hi> in a Revenge to be taken on Mr. <hi>Strode,</hi> lesthe should be made use of as a witness for the King, and so discover our deeds of darkness,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56495:6"/>
and in Order to it, we agreed upon a Letter to be written by Mr. <hi>Anderson</hi> to a Lady of Quality, the Copy whereof for a better sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, is, as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>Iune the first, 1679.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe great respects I owe to Your Ladyship, Obliges me to acquaint Your Ladiship with the most minute Passages, which I learn in Prison; which may reflect in the least upon a Person Your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diship hath so great a concern for, as the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here is a great Rogue whose name is <hi>William Strode</hi> a Clothier, who hath formerly been burnt in the Hand at <hi>Bristol,</hi> for Felony; and at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent here in Prison, and Condemned to dye at <hi>Winchester</hi> Assizes, for willful Murther; but by the Dutchess of <hi>York's</hi> Intercession was promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed a Pardon which he expects next Term. This Rogue hath reported to me and several ot<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rs, that the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> hath by one <hi>Johnson</hi> his Lordships Servant, offered him several sums of Money to joyn Evidence with <hi>Bedloe</hi> against the Lords in the Tower, threatning to Obstruct his Pardon, if he will not joyn with <hi>Bedloe</hi> in Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusing the Lords, or reveal any thing that may do <hi>Mr. Bedloe</hi> any harm, whom he saith if he durst he could hang; I have seen some Guinnies that <hi>Johnson</hi> hath (as he said) given him, but yet he sayeth that although he hath promised to Io<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n with <hi>Mr. Bedloe,</hi> (And therefore after his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don is got out, expects to be Subpoen<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'d by <hi>Mr. Bedloe</hi>) he shall before the Lords declare, my Lord <hi>Shaftsburie's</hi> proceedings with him as suborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to Perjury, this is, Madam, what I think fit that my Lord <hi>Shafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> (for whom, as Your La<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ship knows, I alwayes have had a great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and value) should know, but so as to be ignorant of the Person your Ladiship hath the Intelligence from, fo<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fear if the Rogue upon knowledge that I have discovered him, should invent also some Villany against</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>(Madam)</salute> 
                     <signed>Your Ladiship's humble Servant Lionel Anderson.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Now the Truth is, this Letter was designed to be an obstru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to <hi>Strode's</hi> Pardon, for first, it was directed to the aforesaid Lady, who was to present it to his Lordship, as an accidental thing; though 'twas indeed a contrivance in general amongst
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56495:7"/>
Papists as well no doubt as with the said Lady, if she were <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere may all good Protestants discover their Romish Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> For first <hi>Strode</hi> was to be suborned by them, to swear such <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as they should direct, though never so false, and upon the <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of that he must be hanged, stifled, poisoned, or any <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g to be gotten out of the World rather than they discovered, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>w these Persons who can so easily combine, to take away the Life of one private Person, to accomplish a part of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign, doubtless would as readily wade through a Sea of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants Blood to finish the whole; 'tis most miraculous that God does suffer the Earth to bear such Vipers. Nay, to have Accomplished this piece of Roguery, how they hoped to insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate a belief into his Lordship, when they had even at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry same time, with the greatest Confidence, and in the highest nature villified him? and no doubt would have been as ready to have taken his Lordships Life as any others, which they did afterwards endeavour as much as in them lay, had not God of his infinite Mercy prevented my hand from being the instrument thereof: can these people call themselves Christians, and hold such bloody doctrines, or ever think their ramping Priests who ('tis plain) had dispensations to dye with lyes in their mouths, or their <hi>Babylonian</hi> Midwives, hope to bring any more Sham-Plots too Bed in this Kingdom; no, the whole Nation are well acquanited with and too sensible of such their Treachery; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so their Witchcraft dayly exercised on many of the Nobility of the Nation, who 'tis admired should be induced from a sound Faith, to follow such Anti-christian doctrine. The Letter I tell you of in my first Narrative, I was sent with by the Countess of <hi>Powis</hi> to the Right Honourable Lord Privy Seal, was (as I understood by his Lornships answer) to pray some favour on the behalf of <hi>Anderson.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I was sometime after that, by the said Ladie's Order, to wait on his Lordship, and to represent <hi>Strode's</hi> Case, as <hi>Anderson</hi> had drawn it up agreeable to that in the afore-recited Letter, in order to the stopping the passage of his Pardon, as it was intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the right Honourable the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> whose great wisdom easily saw through the design, and what the meaning was. By which may plainly be seen what Audacious Impudence they Act withal.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:56495:7"/>And for your better satisfaction herein, that that part they represented to the Lord <hi>Privy Seal,</hi> was not inferiour to the former<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I have Inserted part of the papers first sent by <hi>Anderson</hi> to the Lady <hi>Powis,</hi> and by her hand given to me, who at the same time gave me her Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships Order to carry them immediately to the Lord <hi>Privy Seal,</hi> who ordered me to read the same papers to his Lordship at his house at <hi>Kensington,</hi> which were in Contents thus, as they came from <hi>Ander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> who pretended to have them originally from me, and so did still con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue them as taken in my Name from <hi>Strode, viz. May.</hi> 11. 1679. <hi>Strode</hi> did acquaint me that about 15 years since, he knew <hi>Bedlow,</hi> who was then but a servant to Alderman <hi>Blackwell</hi> at <hi>Bristoll;</hi> at which time he scarce had any Stockens or Shooes to his Feet. But <hi>Strode</hi> denyes he ever see <hi>Bedlow</hi> since, till <hi>he</hi> and <hi>Oates</hi> came to the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> to view the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soners which were in about the <hi>Plott;</hi> and once since that, Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi> came with his Brother who was the Night after wounded. He denies the holding of any correspondence with Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi> either by Letter or otherwise, but sayes that one <hi>Philip Marsh</hi> (who is either a friend or a servant to Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi>) is his friend (that is to say, <hi>Strodes</hi> friend) and that they said <hi>Philip Marsh</hi> has often sent Letters to <hi>Strode,</hi> in which Letters it has been desired that the answers thereto should be left at <hi>Bedlows</hi> lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but the Contents of the said Letters either were not worth while to repeat, or he was unwilling so to do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May</hi> the 12. 1679. <hi>Strode</hi> told me this day, that <hi>Bedlows</hi> occasion of giving him Money was to the intent he should conceal something he knew of <hi>Bedlow,</hi> which if discovered would be of consequence enough to hang him, if prosecuted on the same; and the summes which <hi>Bedlow</hi> sent him was the greater, for that <hi>Strode</hi> should take particular notice of the behaviour of the Priests which are here, and who they did correspond with; which <hi>Strode</hi> has done, and has sent some to follow divers persons which have come to Mr. <hi>Anderson,</hi> which persons and their abodes are, as <hi>Strode</hi> sayes, well enough known, and hereupon swore <hi>Damn his soul,</hi> if they should not be better known if ever he could obtain his liberty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May</hi> the 13. <hi>Strode</hi> acquainted me, that his business was either past, or in great probability so to be, and when he could get his enlargement, there were some in the world should soon feel the effects of his fury: But amongst the rest, Mr. <hi>Anderson,</hi> who as <hi>Strode</hi> said, was very uncertain of ever being so near his liberty; but if there ever be any probability for <hi>Andersons</hi> liberty, <hi>Strode</hi> makes no doubt but to prevent the same. By this I find <hi>Strodes</hi> thoughts to be laden with venom (as having been thwarted in his temper by some of the <hi>Catholicks</hi>) and to his power he designs a Revenge on them, but for what I know not.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:56495:8"/>
               <hi>May</hi> the 14. <hi>Strode</hi> did this day acquaint me, that his wife had in a <hi>Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> at home in the Countrey, the original papers which concerned Mr. <hi>Bedlow,</hi> and when he can be at Liberty to go home he will be very brisk in exposing the said matters contained in the said papers to a publick view; but whilest he remains in Custody he will not impart the said matters to any person whatsoever, for that he will not bring himself under Mr. <hi>Bedlows</hi> Lash.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May</hi> the 15. <hi>Strode</hi> did tell me, that one Mr. <hi>Iohnson</hi> (a Servant to the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>) did often come to visit him, and bring him Guinneys, in order to the prevailing with him for to joyn Evidence with <hi>Bedlow:</hi> but <hi>Strodes</hi> answer was (as he informed me) that he would not perjure himself for ten thousand worlds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May</hi> the 16. <hi>Iones</hi> (<hi>Strodes</hi> Bedfellow) did inform me, that he had this day seen in <hi>Strodes</hi> hands some papers which did contain the whole matter of the Popish plott, in a more plain manner than either <hi>Oats</hi> or <hi>Bedlow</hi> could make out.</p>
            <p>And that the Earl of <hi>Shaftsburies</hi> servant (whose Name was Mr. <hi>Iohn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi>) came often to <hi>Strode,</hi> to court him to give his Testimony against the Lords in the Tower, and had offered <hi>Strode</hi> most considerable sums of money if he would do the same.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May</hi> the 17. <hi>Iones</hi> did tell me, <hi>Strode</hi> had in some discourse informed him, that <hi>Bedlow</hi> in the time of his padding was entertained at <hi>Strodes</hi> house, and particularly when there had been a Robbery committed but a day before, and at the same time a Hue and Cry all over the Country to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend him: And that it is not long since that <hi>Strode</hi> sent to his wife at <hi>Shepton Mallet</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerset,</hi> for the Copyes of some Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings which were in her custody, which said writings are the original of those he shewed <hi>Iones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>May</hi> the 18. <hi>Iones</hi> sayes, <hi>Strode</hi> has often prayed his advice what to do in a matter of such weighty Consequence as was to be made out from the aforesaid papers: <hi>Iones</hi> answered him, that in regard he was in Reversion of a good Estate, and had divers good and honorable Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to support him, it would perhaps be much more both for his Credit and advantage to be silent in things of such a nature, than to stir, unless he could make every particular thereof visible by a Lively Testimony. Upon which Advice <hi>Strode</hi> did promise to let it fall, rather than run the hazard of disobliging his Relations and Friends, and become altogether obnoxious:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:56495:8"/>But for your more full satisfaction in these matters, I do not only think it proper to referre you to my former Narrative, so far as it concerns these particulars, but also to the Examination of Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> and others: Which I hope will not only give a full satisfaction to the good Protestant Reader, but a full Conviction of the Romish Reader: In order to which, I will shew you the Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sential parts of the matters herein contained, as they were severally delivered upon Oath; that it may not be said to be the Device of my self, to insinuate a good Opinion in the people, without just Cause.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="testimony">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Somerset.</hi> The Information of <hi>William Strode</hi> of <hi>Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Mallet</hi> in the County aforesaid, Clothier, taken upon Oath the <hi>19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                           </hi> day of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> Anno Regni <hi>Caroli</hi> secundi nunc <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae,</hi> &amp;c. xxxi. Anno<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> Dom. 1679. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>John Speake</hi> 
                           <abbr>Esq</abbr> one of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Iustices of the Peace for the County aforesaid.</head>
                        <p>THis Informant saith, that about the middle of <hi>February</hi> last past, <hi>Philip Marsh</hi> came to the <hi>Kings Bench</hi> Prison in <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark</hi> to see me, (<hi>viz.</hi>) this Deponent, and one <hi>Welsh</hi> a Prisoner there: after the said <hi>Marsh</hi> his going from the Prison, <hi>Welsh</hi> informs the Prisoner, That <hi>Philip Marsh</hi> was a Servant to Mr. <hi>William Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,</hi> and that he knew that they had been long acquainted: Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after <hi>Lionel Anderson</hi> alias <hi>Munson</hi> asked me, (<hi>viz.</hi>) this Informant, how long I had known <hi>Philip Marsh;</hi> I replyed, that my first acquaintance with him was in <hi>Winchester</hi> Prison, a little before I was removed to the <hi>Kings Bench;</hi> also <hi>Anderson</hi> alias <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> asked me, if I knew <hi>Philip Marsh</hi> to be a Servant or Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi>'s? I answered, that I knew no such thing: Then <hi>Anderson</hi> replyed, I must needs know the said <hi>Marsh</hi> to be acquainted with the said Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi> as well as <hi>Welsh:</hi> and at that time <hi>Anderson</hi> enquired when <hi>Philip Marsh</hi> came to see me again? I told him, I knew not: Upon the 26<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day of <hi>February</hi> last past, the said <hi>Anderson</hi> offered me, (<hi>viz.</hi>) this Examinant, 500 <hi>l.</hi> Sterling, to subvert Mr. <hi>Bedlowes</hi> Evidence, and to make me the greatest of my Name. Some time afterwards, and before the Ninth of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56495:9"/>
                           <hi>March</hi> last past, <hi>Philip Marsh</hi> came to see me again, and after <hi>Philip Marsh</hi> was gone, <hi>Anderson</hi> enquired of me, whether I had discoursed with <hi>Philip Marsh</hi> any thing concerning Mr. <hi>Bedlow?</hi> I answered, No: Whereupon I asked, what I should say unto <hi>Philip Marsh? Anderson</hi> replyed, To enquire of him what he knows of Mr. <hi>Bedlows</hi> Concerns relating to the Plot: I told him, I knew not how to begin, unless he would give instructions. Then <hi>Ander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> asked of me, whether the Fellow, (meaning <hi>Philip Marsh</hi>) would drink? I told him, I knew not; for in his Visits here, he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver spent at one time above a Groat to his own part; So <hi>Anderson</hi> desired me to drink the fellow up: said he, If you have no mind to drink your self, here be those in the house that would be glad to do it, and cost what it will, come to me, and I will pay it; and when you find his Temper, come to me, and I'le further instruct you. But <hi>Marsh</hi> at that time drank little, and so took his leave. On the ninth of <hi>March</hi> or thereabouts, Mr. <hi>Anderson</hi> said to me, Will you be true to me? And I (<hi>viz.</hi>) this Deponent said, I would. I can believe you, said <hi>Anderson,</hi> because you have told me you were a neer Relation to Collonel <hi>Strode,</hi> Governour of <hi>Dover</hi> Castle, who is as honest a Gentleman as any in <hi>England:</hi> and I know, said <hi>Anderson,</hi> no man that is of that name can be worse than his word: However, swear that you will be true to me. I asked him, How I must swear to him? <hi>Anderson</hi> answered, Swear by your Faith; and I said, By my Faith I would be true. And on the said Ninth of <hi>March</hi> or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts last past, <hi>Anderson</hi> offered me (<hi>viz.</hi>) the Deponent 500 <hi>l.</hi> and to be made the greatest of my Name, for to hire <hi>Philip Marsh</hi> and others together with my self, to subvert Mr. <hi>Bedlows</hi> Evidence: And that he the said <hi>Anderson</hi> had sent to the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and the Dutchess of <hi>York,</hi> to acquaint them of this his design; And <hi>Ander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> said, that they had returned him thanks. Also <hi>Anderson</hi> further told me, he had provided Security for the 500 <hi>l.</hi> which was offered me, or would lay it in any mans hands whom I should Nominate; and whatever summe the other Subverters please to have, he was ready to serve it unto them; but 500 <hi>l.</hi> he would give upon his own account. I asked <hi>Anderson</hi> what we should all do for this 500 <hi>l.</hi> His answer was, it was to subvert Mr. <hi>Bedlows</hi> Evidence. In a short time after there came two young men out of the City to see me, one of them his name was <hi>Trist. Anderson</hi> seeing them two with me, inquired of me quick and very earnest, whether one of them (pointing at <hi>Trist</hi>) was not a servant to the Lord of <hi>Shaftsbury?</hi> I considering his earnestness, imagined with my self he had more to say to me of the former business: I answered him, Yes, Yes; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I knew him to be another; and <hi>Anderson</hi> also inquired of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56495:9"/>
me, whether his name was not <hi>Iohnson?</hi> I answered, Yes; then <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derson</hi> said, That is the man, I know. At which confident mistake of his I wondred. Withall he then said, I hope you have not revealed any thing to <hi>Iohnson,</hi> concerning our former discourse. I answered, I had not: Moreover he said, he would not have my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> know it for all the world. So after that discourse, Mr. <hi>Anderson</hi> was speaking concerning the Lords in the Tower, how Mr. <hi>Rockly</hi> had been with some of them, and that the Lords were very merry. Mr. <hi>Anderson</hi> said, that Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi> was the main Evidence against the Lords in the Tower; and if they escape, we shall all escape. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, <hi>Anderson</hi> said to me, as soon as he got out of Prison he would leave <hi>England,</hi> and go into another Countrey. I asked him into what Countrey he would go? but he did not tell me. Some time after that Mr. <hi>Anderson</hi> had these Conferences with me, I informed my Chamber-fellow Mr. <hi>Iones</hi> of it, and shewed him the Heads of it as I had wrote them in my Almanack. And further this Deponent saith not.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>William Strode.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Iurat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> coram me</hi>
                           </p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>John Speake:

In the presence of
<list>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Tho. Westly.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Rob. Plimpton.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Tho. Browne.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </signed>
                           </closer>
                        </postscript>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="testimony">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Somerset.</hi> The Information of <hi>William Strode</hi> of <hi>Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Mallet</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerset,</hi> Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier, taken upon Oath, the <hi>9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                           </hi> day of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember, 1679.</hi> before <hi>John Speak</hi> 
                           <abbr>Esq</abbr> one of the Iustices of the Peace within the said County.</head>
                        <p>THis Informant saith, that about three years since, he knew Mr. <hi>Willoughby,</hi> and that whilest Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> was a Prisoner in the <hi>Kings Bench,</hi> he, this Informant, was very intimate with the said <hi>Willoughby,</hi> whom he was informed by others was also named <hi>Dangerfield.</hi> Some time after Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> was brought in a Prisoner to the <hi>Kings Bench,</hi> he takes me this Informant with him into the Garden, and told me, he heard, I was kept in Prison the longer, because I knew something which I must swear concerning the Plot. I answered him, If I was kept in Prison for that, it was more than I knew. But <hi>Willoughby</hi> said unto me, that he knew as much of the Plot as any body: And this Informant hath been very often in his Company whilest he remained a Prisoner in the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi>
                           <pb n="14" facs="tcp:56495:10"/>
in his Chamber; where most times this Informant found him writing in great sheets of paper, seeming to him as if he were Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pying out the writing that lay before him this Informant came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Chamber of this <hi>Willoughby;</hi> and all the written papers which this Informant saith he saw, were just alike Indented, and spaces and figures about the same distance left in the papers: some of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers were as if he were drawing Articles; for in the Margent I saw Figures, 1, 2, 3. and so on to a considerable number; but as soon as the said <hi>Willoughby</hi> could, he conveyed those writings out of this Informants sight. Likewise other papers this Deponent hath seen in his Room, written in Characters, which sometime he left to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue on the Board, but I understood them not: This Informant hath seen Footmen come to him, their Cloaths covered with Campagne Coats, so that this Informant could see nothing of their Liveries, but only when they were going out of the Chamber. Also this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant hath seen several Women, at least seemingly so by their Apparel, come unto him most commonly in the Evenings, with Masks on: This Informant hath sometimes seen <hi>Willoughby</hi> in the Evenings go into Mr. <hi>Andersons</hi> Chamber; and after he was out upon Bail, when he came to the Prison, he always went into <hi>Andersons</hi> Chamber: This Informant did tell Mr. <hi>William Bedlow</hi> in the <hi>Kings Bench</hi> Garden, that he had something to relate unto him concerning himself; his brother <hi>Bedlow</hi> was then there with him; and it was his next time of being there after the calling over the Prisoners, by his and D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Oats</hi>'s occasion, as it was reported. And further he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth not.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>William Strode.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Iurat. coram me</hi>
                           </p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>John Speake:
In the presence of
<hi>Tho. Westly,</hi>
                                 <hi>Robert Plimpton,</hi>
                                 <hi>Tho. Browne.</hi>
                              </signed>
                           </closer>
                        </postscript>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="testimony">
                        <head>
                           <hi>London ss.</hi> The Examination of <hi>William Strode</hi> Clothier of <hi>Shepton Mallett</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerset,</hi> taken before the Right Honourable Sir <hi>Robert Claiton</hi> Lord Maior of the City of <hi>London</hi> this <hi>15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                           </hi> day of <hi>January,</hi> 1679.</head>
                        <p>THis Informant first referres to two former Examinations taken before <hi>Iohn Speak</hi> 
                           <abbr>Esq</abbr> one of his Majestyes Justices of the Peace for the County of <hi>Somerset,</hi> dated the 19 of <hi>November,</hi> 1679. and now he comes upon a third Examination of what he then omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which is as follows, (<hi>viz.</hi>) That in or about the Months of <hi>April</hi> or <hi>May,</hi> 1679. Mr. <hi>Lionel Anderson</hi> alias <hi>Munson,</hi> who was then a Prisoner in the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> did then invite this Informant
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56495:10"/>
to his Chamber, and there gave this Informant a quart Bottle of Brandy, desiring him to drink a good draught of the same; but the said <hi>Anderson</hi> himself to be Excused from drinking rhereof: But immediately after brought forth a bottle of Wine and did desire this Informant to drink of that too; then when this Informant had drank, <hi>Anderson</hi> alias <hi>Munson</hi> told this Informant, that he had acquainted Sir <hi>Henry Tichburn</hi> of the converse which <hi>Anderson</hi> alias <hi>Munson</hi> and this Informant had concerning Mr. <hi>Bedlow;</hi> and that Sir <hi>Henry Tichburn's</hi> Maid-servant had informed him the said <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derson</hi> alias <hi>Munson,</hi> that her Master was well pleased with what the said <hi>Anderson</hi> alias <hi>Munson</hi> had informed him of; which was the Discourse concerning Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi> contained in the aforementioned Examinations: And also that Sir <hi>Henry Tichburn</hi> did promise for this Informants Reward, an Estate in <hi>Hampshire</hi> of 100 <hi>l. per Ann.</hi> for two years to be Rent-free. Then this Informant left him; and about a quarter of an hour afterwards he returned into the said <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derson</hi> alias <hi>Munson</hi>'s Chamber again, where he told this Informant, that as soon as Mr. <hi>Marsh,</hi> this Informant, and others, were ready to swear to such Instructions as he the said <hi>Anderson</hi> alias <hi>Munson</hi> had formerly said he would give this Informant concerning the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting Mr. <hi>Bedlows</hi> Evidence, he would send one Mr. <hi>Nevill</hi> alias <hi>Paine</hi> to the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Anglesey,</hi> whom the aforesaid <hi>Anderson</hi> alias <hi>Munson</hi> said was his very good Friend, and was sure would get this Informants Pardon (for a Crime he then was a Prisoner) in two dayes: And at the same time the said <hi>Ander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> alias <hi>Munson</hi> told this Informant, that the Lord <hi>Powis,</hi> Lord <hi>Arundel,</hi> Lord <hi>Peters,</hi> and the rest of the Five Lords in the Tower, did intend (that is to say, after this Informant was prepared with Instructions he was to receive from the said <hi>Anderson</hi> alias <hi>Munson</hi>) to petition for their Tryals, and to Suppena this Informant as a Witness for them. This Informant further saith, that on the Ninth of <hi>March,</hi> 1679. <hi>Anderson</hi> alias <hi>Munson</hi> told him, he had made the design for subverting Mr. <hi>Bedlows</hi> Evidence known to the Duke and Dutchess of <hi>York,</hi> who returned him thanks, and an Order to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide such Security as this Informant should Approve of, for the Money formerly promised this Informant by the said <hi>Anderson</hi> alias <hi>Munson:</hi> And further this Informant saith not.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>William Strode.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                           <p>Iurat. coram me</p>
                           <closer>
                              <dateline>
                                 <date>15<hi rend="sup">o</hi> die <hi>January,</hi> 1679.</date>
                              </dateline>
                              <signed>Robert Clayton <hi>Maior.</hi>
                              </signed>
                           </closer>
                        </postscript>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:56495:11"/>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="testimony">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Surry ss.</hi> The Information of <hi>Tho. Hill</hi> now a Prisoner in the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> taken upon Oath, the <hi>9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                           </hi> day of <hi>December,</hi> 1679. Anno Regni <hi>Caroli</hi> Secundi nunc Angl. &amp;c. xxxi. Anno<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> Dom. before me <hi>Thomas Foster</hi> 
                           <abbr>Esq</abbr> one of his Maj<hi rend="sup">ties</hi> Iustices of the Peace for the County aforesaid.</head>
                        <p>THis Informant saith, that he was acquainted with <hi>Tho. Danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> about 18 Months since, and he afterwards see him when he was brought to the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> a prisoner: The Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant saith, he saw a Gentlewoman twice with the said Mr. <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerfield</hi> at the <hi>Kings Bench.</hi> This informant at another time saw 2 person in Livery with a Campagne Coat over the same, come to the said <hi>Dangerfield:</hi> He also saith, he saw Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> go into Mr. <hi>Munsons</hi> Chamber, but knows nothing of their business: He al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so sayes, that Mr. <hi>Strode</hi> told him, this informant, he had a paper in the Country, of which he had a Copy then by him, that did concern the Plot. And <hi>Strode</hi> also said to this Informant in these words, Why may not we make our Fortunes as well as other men, for we may get two or three thousand pounds? Then this Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant demanded, How? The said <hi>Strode</hi> answered, By the said paper. This Informant further saith, <hi>Strode</hi> told him, Mr. <hi>Munson</hi> had either promised or offered the said <hi>Strode</hi> Five hundred pounds. <hi>Strode</hi> also told him this Informant, he had been with Mr. <hi>Iohnson</hi> several times, and had received Money of him; and that the said <hi>Iohn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> was the Earl of <hi>Shaftsburyes</hi> Servant: This Informant saith, <hi>Dangerfield</hi> told him, he had been in Mr. <hi>Kemishes</hi> company, and that <hi>Dangerfield</hi> desired this Informant to use his Endeavour to help him to the sight of Mr. <hi>Strodes</hi> papers, saying, there was a person of Quality that was his good friend; and that it would do the said <hi>Dangerfield</hi> a particular kindness if he could get the said papers from <hi>Strode,</hi> who had some other time told this Informant, he could hang <hi>Bedlow.</hi> This Informant saith, <hi>Strode</hi> shewed him an Almanack, and at the same time said, Mr. <hi>Munson</hi> had offered him the said <hi>Strode</hi> five hundred pounds to take off <hi>Bedlows</hi> Evidence. And this Informant fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther saith, when he found the design against Mr. <hi>Bedlows</hi> Evidence, he was cautious of medling, or discoursing <hi>Strode</hi> any further. This Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant saith, he heard <hi>Strode</hi> say, it would not be long before he should have his liberty, and that then some in the world should soon feel the Effects of his fury; or to this effect. This Informant at another time asked <hi>Strode,</hi> where the said <hi>Munson</hi> should have the aforesaid 500 pounds? <hi>Strode</hi> replyed, it was sure enough, or to that purpose. <hi>Strode</hi> also told this informant, he had given <hi>Munson</hi> a Copy of the aforesaid paper which related to the Plot. This Informant saith, he has seen in <hi>Dangerfields</hi> Chamber divers papers or writings, but the said <hi>Dangerfield</hi> would never let this informant see any of the contents of the said pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Tho. Hill.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                           <p>Iurat. coram me <date>nono die <hi>Dec.</hi> Anno Regni Regis Tricessimo primo. 1679<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                              </date>
                           </p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Tho. <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>ster</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </postscript>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:56495:11"/>
            <p>And one thing more as notable as any, as another Character of the Excellency of these Romish Christians, I must acquaint you with, which is as follows.</p>
            <p>That about the tenth day of <hi>February</hi> 7 8/9: one Mr. <hi>Thomas Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amson</hi> Citizen and Merchant-Tayler of <hi>London,</hi> being a man some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what inclined to favour (to his power) those of the Romish Church, out of his great pitty, having once relieved a Romanist who informed Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> (to whom he was a Proselite) of the said Charity he had received, she according to the practice of the godly Members of that Church, found Mr. <hi>Williamsons</hi> Habitation, whither she repaired divers times before he was to be found. But at a certain time meeting with him at home, they entred into some discourse, amongst which, after she had well searched his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, she demanded if he understood the prosecuting or soliciting of business at Law, he replied he either did of himself, or easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly could by the help of his Friends, who studyed as well as practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the same. Then Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> requested him to undertake the Bayling out of Prison divers Papists, as well such as were accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed of the Conspiracie against the Kings most Sacred Majesty (whom God preserve) the present Government, and the true Protestant Religion, as those who were barely imprisoned for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Romish Church. Mr. <hi>Williamson</hi> answered he would readily undertake the same, upon which Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> did promise his Reward should be for so doing, fifteen Pounds for each Person, besides an allowance of all Prison Fees, and all other ordinary and extraordinary Charges whatsoever, which once being delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to her by Bill, should forthwith be paid, in order to which Business she gave him ten Shillings, and a List of the Persons Names who he was to Solicite for, and to let you know—how many he enlarged their Names are as followeth (<hi>viz.</hi>)</p>
            <list>
               <item>Doctor <hi>Southwel</hi> for refusing the Oaths, Bayled out of the Gatehouse, his Charges. 02 <hi>l.</hi> 15 <hi>s.</hi> 00 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mrs. <hi>Green</hi> Bayled from the same place. 02 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>s.</hi> 00 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mrs. <hi>Iane Everstone</hi> from the same place. 03 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>s.</hi> 06 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Garret</hi> a Papist Bayled from the same place. 04 <hi>l.</hi> 13 <hi>s.</hi> 00 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Cooke</hi> a Glover Bayled from Newgate for refusing the Oathes. 06 <hi>l.</hi> 17 <hi>s.</hi> 00 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Mollineux</hi> a Papist Bailed from the Gatehouse. 03 <hi>l.</hi> 09 <hi>s.</hi> 06 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ieffrey Hudson</hi> her Majesties Dwarfe Bayled from the Gatehouse. 05 <hi>l.</hi> 04 <hi>s.</hi> 00 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Shelton, alias Napper,</hi> for being in the Plot, Bayled from the Gatehouse. 04 <hi>l.</hi> 06 <hi>s.</hi> 09 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:56495:12"/>
                  <hi>Penelope Walford</hi> Bayled from New-Prison, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a Papist. 02 <hi>l.</hi> 08 <hi>s.</hi> 07 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dorothey Wright</hi> Bayled from the Gatehouse, but a Protestant. 03 <hi>l.</hi> 19 <hi>s.</hi> 04 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>John <hi>Woodman</hi> a Botcher Bayled out from New-Prison for being a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist, his Charges. 05 <hi>l.</hi> 06 <hi>s.</hi> 00 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Marina Pyott,</hi> from New-Prison, a Papist. 02 <hi>l.</hi> 04 <hi>s.</hi> 05 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Stephen Harrys</hi> a Papist Bayled from New-Prison. 02 <hi>l.</hi> 07 <hi>s.</hi> 03 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>One <hi>Snig</hi> a Prisoner for debt in Ludgate, but a Papist, Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> paid his Debt, which amounted to 09 <hi>l.</hi> 08 <hi>s.</hi> 06 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Peter Lanton</hi> a Papist, Bayled from New-Prison. 02 <hi>l.</hi> 05 <hi>s.</hi> 06 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iohanna Davice</hi> a Papist, Bayled from New-Prison. 02 <hi>l.</hi> 06 <hi>s.</hi> 00 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Arthur Woolgard</hi> a supposed Priest Bayled, but burnt in New-Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son. 04 <hi>l.</hi> 17 <hi>s</hi> 06 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Robert Goade</hi> a Papist Bayled from New-Prison. 02 <hi>l.</hi> 13 <hi>s.</hi> 09 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Madam <hi>Fitzherbert, Williamson</hi> was bound for, when she went into <hi>France</hi> for that she should not go into any Cloister or Nunnery. 01 <hi>l.</hi> 17 <hi>s.</hi> 08 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Benjamin Haynes</hi> a Papist, Bayled from the Gatehouse. 03 <hi>l.</hi> 09 <hi>s.</hi> 07 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iane Overton</hi> a Papist, Bayled from the Gatehouse. 02 <hi>l.</hi> 17 <hi>s.</hi> 09 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iohn Woodman</hi> the Botcher Bayled from Newgate, for being suspect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have Fyred New-Prison. 07 <hi>l.</hi> 08 <hi>s.</hi> 08 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Snig</hi> the Papist Bayled from Newgate. 05 <hi>l.</hi> 07 <hi>s.</hi> 09 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Daniel Edmonds, alias</hi> Captain <hi>Kelley</hi> Bayled out of the Marshalseas, whose Name was sometime after in the Gazet. 09 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>s.</hi> 09 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Sum is</hi> 101 <hi>l.</hi> 14 <hi>s.</hi> 09 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Now when he had given her the Signification of his great diligence by procuring the Liberty of the aforesaid Persons. He also return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the List of those Persons he could not get enlarged on Bayle, whose Names are—</p>
            <list>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Meales</hi> at the Marshalseas, not bayled out.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Roach</hi> at the Gatehouse.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Thomas</hi> at the Gatehouse.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Lloyd</hi> at the Gatehouse.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Oakely</hi> at the Kings Bench.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Thomas Thorne</hi> at the Gatehouse.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Anderson aliàs Munson</hi> at the Kings Bench.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Kemesh</hi> at the Kings Bench.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Barnesly</hi> at the Kings Bench.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Doudal</hi> at the Gatehouse.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Cullun</hi> at the Gatehouse.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ralph Carter</hi> at the Gatehouse.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Vahan</hi> at the Gatehouse.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:56495:12"/>Mr. <hi>Iohn Parsons.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Richard Ganes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Ireland alias Douting.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Harcourt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Gavan</hi> and others.</item>
            </list>
            <p>At which time he went to Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi>'s house to receive his Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges expended in that Affair, where she acquainted him that his great Care in prosecuting their Business should raise him a consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Interest, designing by this to encourage him, as appears by what she said to him at the same time, which was as he affirms upon Oath in these very words, <hi>viz.</hi> These are but small things which you have yet done. But I will put you upon greater things if you will be just, for which you shall be well rewarded.</p>
            <p>Now 'tis to be suppos'd Mr. <hi>Williamson</hi> did enter into a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise in this as well as the former affair before he took his Leave; but not long after Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> sent <hi>Anne Blake</hi> her Nurse to Mr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamson</hi>'s house, to let him know how earnestly her Mistress did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire his Company at her house, she having some mighty Business for him; he being at home went with the said Nurse to Mrs. <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier</hi>'s house in <hi>Arundel</hi> Street, where he found the Mistress who cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him into her Lodging-room, and acquainted him after some short discourse that she had a Business of a great consequence to imploy him in, for which he should have a considerable Reward, at which he being desirous to raise his Fortune, did demand what the said Business was, to which Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> replyed, 'twas thus, <hi>viz.</hi> if you can procure me two men of undaunted Spirits, that will be prevailed with to swear to some directions that I have drawn up to take off the Evidence of Mr. <hi>Prance,</hi> I will give them 20 <hi>l.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece for their Rewards.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Williamson</hi> demanded what the Contents of those directions she intended for the two Persons were: At which Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> at the same time gave him a Copy. But enjoyned him to keep it private, only when he had procured the aforesaid two persons she did allow he should communicate and debate the matter with them, he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving first ingaged them to undertake the said matter: Now the Contents of the said Note of directions was to this effect, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That they should both agree to one and the same thing, by swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that at a certain time when they were passing under <hi>Newgate,</hi> they heard a most hideous noise, at which they were somewhat startled, and demanded of a stander by what noise that was, to which the said person replyed 'twas one <hi>Prance,</hi> who was brought into that Prison about the Murther of Sr. <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey,</hi> and for that he should confess the same, he was tortur'd with vast
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56495:13"/>
weights of Iron on his Legs, on his Hands, on his Neck, and fastned down with Bolts and Staples to the ground, so that he could lie only on his back, and that such intollerable Torture he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured for some time.</p>
            <p>Now, their design by this, was to represent <hi>Prance</hi> his Testimony Invalid, for that in as much as the Law hath provided, that no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son was to be wrack'd or tortur'd for his Testimony in no case what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, they did conceive that to be <hi>Prance</hi>'s Case, and therefore according to the intent of the said Directions it plainly appears, their play (I mean the Papists, who were undoubtedly equally concerned in the thing) was to baffle <hi>Prance</hi> to save the Convicting of <hi>Berry, Hill,</hi> and <hi>Green:</hi> (as Mr. <hi>Williamson</hi> on his Oath tells us, Mrs. <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier</hi> informed him) amongst which said three persons one was a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant and no doubt but they greatly feared that he was not zealous enough, though the rest were to die with a damnable Lie in their Mouths.</p>
            <p>At the same time Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> being apprehensive of some considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons those two men of undaunted Courage might enter into, concerning the dangerous affairs they were to be ingaged in, she thought fit to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire Mr. <hi>Williamson</hi> to acquaint them, provided any jealousies did arise, that they should not fear a Prison, for if it should so happen that they or either of them, should be discovered and sent either to <hi>Newgate</hi> or any other uneasie Prison, she would make such Interest, That if they could not be immediately discharged, they should be from such Prison remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to the Fleet, which is accounted by most experienced persons the easiest of Prisons, at which place during the time of their confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they should have paid them by the hand of M. <hi>Williamson</hi> 40 <hi>s. per</hi> week to defray their expences there, which said money was to be given to <hi>Mr. Williamson</hi> by <hi>Mrs. Cellier;</hi> All which proposals <hi>Mr. Williamson</hi> seemed to like well and agree to, but to confirm the Bargain, <hi>Mrs. Cellier</hi> according to her usual custom, gives him an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest penny, praying withal his speedy prosecution thereof, whereupon he took his leave, and returned home where he had time to consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and advise what to do in that ill Cause, which was easily deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, for when he came to lay his hand on his heart, and to enter into a serious consideration of the great scandal must undoubtedly accrue to him in this World if discovered, and if not, perhaps the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Damnation of his poor Soul in the next, he in some little time returned to <hi>Mrs. Cellier,</hi> saying, for that the time of <hi>Berry, Hill,</hi> and <hi>Greens</hi> Tryals did so nearly approach, 'twas not in his power to perform his promise in that Respect and beg'd her pardon. At which she was not a little concern'd, for if you take the true measures of the whole thing, 'tis most apparent <hi>Mrs. Cellier</hi> was making provision,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56495:13"/>
as if those two desperate Blades, were Cock-sure to carry on the work she intended them for; but according to all the rest of their Practises, so is it in this, for when she found him to evade that Design, in which she had lay'd herself open to him, she might think it expedient rather than suffer him to fall off, and so expose herself to imploy him in an Affair somewhat (in his part) Inferiour to the former, which was to this effect; <hi>Green, Hill,</hi> and <hi>Berry</hi> being then convicted of Sr. <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey</hi>'s Murther, Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> gave him a Note, desiring him to shew the same to all his Acquaintance, which Note was as follows, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="section">
                        <head>The Execution of <hi>Henry Berry.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>He made no farewel-Speech, but he had prayed a long while. The Ministers were very Importunate with him to make a publick Confession of his Sins, then he said as follows. I must confess I am a great Sinner; but as for what I am brought hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Suffer, I had no more to do with it then the Child new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly born. I cannot but blame my Judge and Jury, for they have dealt wrongfully with me, I do not Condemn, but I cannot but blame them, for they have wronged me, I pray God forgive them, and I do truly forgive them, God bless the King and Queen, and the whole Kingdom; Amen.</p>
                        <p>Then he and the Ministers prayed a long while, when they had done they left him to the Mercy of God. As the Cart was drawing from under him, he spake these last words. I die as I was born and bred a Protestant, and beg of God to be mercyful to me as I am Innocent.</p>
                        <p>And then she the said Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> imployed him to go to Newgate for the Coppie of the Commitment of one Mr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby</hi> (which was the Name I went by) and from thence address himself to Mr. <hi>Recorder,</hi> taking Bayl with him to offer in the behalf of the said <hi>Willoughby.</hi> Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing at the same time to make such an Interest with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corder, that it should be easily Accomplished, whereupon Mr. <hi>Williamson</hi> did accordingly make his Address, but was then Refused, In regard as he supposed the Person who was to pray that Favour, had not been to wait on Mr. <hi>Recorder,</hi>
                           <pb n="22" facs="tcp:56495:14"/>
then he advised with Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> who ordered him to go a second time, saying Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> must be had out, whoever remained, and ordered him to allow some reasonable time for the <hi>Recorder</hi> to be treated with, which he did, and the Bayl he offered was accepted, and Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi>'s Discharge Granted. Then Mr. <hi>VVilliamson</hi> went to the Prison to visit there Mr. <hi>VVilloughby,</hi> for whose Enlargement Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> was so earnest, but Mr. <hi>VVilliamson</hi> at his return to Mrs. <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier,</hi> amongst other discourse happened to say he had been to see <hi>Mr. VVilloughby,</hi> who he thought was a brisk Man, to which <hi>Mrs. Cellier</hi> replyed in these words, if he was not so, he would not be fit for our business; in a short time after Mr. <hi>VVilloughby</hi> was discharged, who soon crept in between Mr. <hi>VVilliamson</hi> and the business he had so long been imployed in.</p>
                        <p>Not long after Mr. <hi>VVilliamson</hi> waited on Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> with his Bills to be paid, amongst which he received four Pounds for Mr. <hi>VVilloughby</hi>'s Enlargement from the Hands of <hi>Mrs. Cellier.</hi> At which time he saith there arose between him and <hi>Mrs. Cellier</hi> some discourse concerning the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Sir <hi>Edmundbury-Godfrey.</hi> To which she answered in these Words, 'tis laid on us now, but it will appear it was done by the Presbyterians, adding that if any change were (That is to say, if ever Popery came uppermost (which God of his great Goodness prevent) for at that time un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly they had a fair Prospect to that Effect, whatever they have now) there would be more Favour found from the Papists then they now found from the Presbyterians. And so ended their Correspondence.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="testimony">
                        <head>The Information of <hi>Thomas Williamson</hi> of the Parish of St. <hi>Brides,</hi> Merchant-Tayler and Citizen of <hi>London</hi> taken upon Oath, before the Right honourable S. <hi>Robert Clayton</hi> Knight, Lord Mayor of the City of <hi>London</hi> this twentieth sixth day of <hi>January;</hi> 1679.</head>
                        <p>This Informant saith that about the tenth day of <hi>February</hi> in the year 1678, one <hi>Mrs. Cellier</hi> came to his house to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56495:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
him to Bail Papists out of several Prisons, for which she promised this Informant 15 <hi>s.</hi> each person, besides an allowance for all extraordinary expences: which business this Informant did readily undertake, and was by Mrs. <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier</hi> encouraged with 10 <hi>s.</hi> earnest, some time after; when this Informant had bayled ont diverse Papists, the said Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> did at her house in <hi>Arundel-Street</hi> say to this Informant as follows, <hi>viz.</hi> these are but small things which you have yet done, but I will put you upon great things, if you will be just, for which you shall be well rewarded; some time after, the said Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> sent her Nurse for this Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant to come to her house, which he did, where she called him into her Lodging-room, and acquainted him that she had a business of consequence to imploy this Informant in, for which he should be well rewarded, then this Informant demanded what it was, she the said Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> replyed it was thus, <hi>viz.</hi> if he this Informant could help her to two men of undaunted Spirits, that would swear to some dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions that she had drawn up to shake off the Evidence of <hi>Prance,</hi> hopeing thereby to save the Convicting of <hi>Berry, Hill,</hi> and <hi>Green,</hi> for which she the said Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> promised this Informant that the said persons which he should procure; should have for their rewards the Sum of 40 <hi>l.</hi> or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts, and that this Informant was desired by the said Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> to tell the said persons they should not fear a Prison for if it should so happen, she would make such Interest that they should only be Prisoners in the Fleet-Prison, where they should have by this Informants hand paid duly 40 <hi>s. per</hi> week, which was to be given first to this Informant by the said Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> who gave this Informant 5 <hi>s.</hi> in earnest, to go about the said business, but this Informant did not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form his promise to Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> in that respect, but some time after this Informant was by Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> employed to bayl out of Prison one Mr. <hi>Willoughby,</hi> she being very earnest with this Informant, saying that, the said <hi>Willoughby</hi> must be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten out whoever remained, and then she promised this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant to make such an Interest to the Recorder that it should be easily accomplish'd, as this Informant affirms was
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56495:15"/>
done soon after, for which business the said Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> paid this Informant the summ of 4 <hi>l.</hi> or thereabouts, but before Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> was discharged, this Informant told Mrs. <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier,</hi> he having first seen the said <hi>Willoughby,</hi> that he was a brisk man, to which Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> replyed, if he were not brisk he would not be fit for our business, and this Informant further on his Oath affirmeth, that he had not been at any time conversant with the said <hi>VVilloughby</hi> in any other thing whatsoever, &amp;c. And this Informant saith, that upon discourse with the said Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> about the murder of Sr. <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey</hi> she said it is laid on us, but it will appear it was done by the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians. And further added that if any change were, there would be more kindness found from the Papists than the Presbyterians.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Thomas VVilliamson.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="collection">
                        <p>These that follow are Copies of the Papers sent to <hi>Williamson</hi> by Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> of her own hand-writing.</p>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. Go to Sr. <hi>Iohn Nicholas Clark</hi> and ask for an order con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Mr. Doudal</hi> or <hi>Mr. Cullumb, Mrs. VVright, Ralph Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Mr. Vahan.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. <hi>Mr. Iohn Parsons, Richard Ganes, Mr. Thomas Ffloyd, Mr. Ireland aliàs Douting, Mr. Cullumb.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>3. Sr. I am to desire you to call upon me to morrow at the Earl of <hi>Powis</hi>'s house in <hi>Lincolnsinn-fields</hi> at seven of the Clock in the morning, and you will oblige him who is</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                           <salute>Sr.</salute> 
                           <signed>your affectionate Friend and humble Servant Edward VVood.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Now, since I have so fair an opportunity, it may be meet to let you know what I in my first Narrative omitted. And the Reason why I did so, is fair; for at that Juncture most per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons were desirous to know the meaning of my Discovery, And I as desirous to satisfie each persons Curiosity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:56495:15"/>1. In or about the Month of <hi>Iune,</hi> 79. at <hi>Powis</hi>'s House, the Countess of <hi>Powis,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> desired me to go to one <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Stubbs,</hi> who then Lived in <hi>Stephens-Alley</hi> in <hi>Kings-Street, West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster;</hi> and was (as they had been informed) Bed-ridden, and highly dis-satisfyed in Mind, for some false Testimony which he had given against one <hi>Gifford,</hi> a <hi>Romish-Priest.</hi> With this <hi>Stubbs</hi> I was to treat about the Usage, which he received in Prison; and to endeavour to bring him to a Denyal of what he had before Affirmed on Oath: Which was to this Effect; That he, being a Dying-Man, and touched with a true Remorse of Conscience did on his Death-Bed declare, that he knew not any such Man as Mr. <hi>Gifford;</hi> or that there was any such thing, as Burning of Houses, intended. But that, when he found himself Impeach't for a Crime of such a Nature, and most barbarously Tortur'd in Prison, inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that his Body could no longer indure the same, he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained to give those Answers he did, as best agreeing to the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions propos'd: But now he pray'd <hi>God</hi> Almighties Pardon; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring himself truly sorry for what he had done.</p>
            <p>Here I have thought fit, for a general Satisfaction, to insert an Information taken from <hi>Iane Stubbs;</hi> which is as follows.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="testimony">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Westm. ss.</hi> The Information of <hi>Iane,</hi> the Wife of <hi>Nicholas Stubbs,</hi> of St. <hi>Stephens-Alley</hi> in <hi>Kings-Street, Westminster;</hi> taken upon Oath, this <hi>13th.</hi> day of <hi>December,</hi> 1679. before me, <hi>Edmond Warcup,</hi> 
                           <abbr>Esq</abbr> one of His Majesty's Justice the Peace, in the said City.</head>
                        <p>THis Informant saith, That about the Month of <hi>June,</hi> last past, Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild,</hi> now present, came to this Informant's House, when her Husband lay very sick; and he then asked, whether Mr. <hi>Stubbs</hi> (her Husband) had not been much Tortured, while he was in Prison, about the Fire in <hi>Fetter-Lane?</hi> to which her said Husband answered, That while he was in the Dungeon, he was hardly used, being double-Ironed, and Staked to the Board: But was well enough used afterwards. And the said <hi>Danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feild</hi> enquired into the Condition of this Informant's Husband, and gave Five Shillings; and promised to get Money to pay the Rent of her House, which was Five Pound: and promised to return again, but came not. And asked, Whether this Informant knew Mrs. <hi>Cellier?</hi> but this Informant knew her not. And the said <hi>Dangerfeild</hi> said, He would acquaint Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> with the Poorness of this Informant's Condition; and would endeavour to get some Subsistance for him. And further saith not.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Jane Stubbs.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                           <p>Jurat. die &amp; Anno Superdict. cor. me,</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Edmond Warcup.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </postscript>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:56495:16"/>
            <p>Now, you are to note, the afore-said Denyal was (if Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity had served) to have privately possest him with, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mising to take care of his Wife, and the many Children he was like to leave behind him, if he should dye: But when I found the Man under a most violent Feavor, and the Wife still present, I was discouraged for making any Progress, according to Order; but rather was inclined to pitty his miserable Condition, which both his Wife, and Himself, began to relate to me. After I had stayed some time, and asked some Questions, and I finding no such Answer as I expected, gave him a Crown; and promised to bring with me (the next time I came) Five Pound, to pay their Rent; as being sollicited to that purpose, by them both: and in the mean time, to make Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> sensible of his great Necessity, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as he desired. I returned to the Countess; to whom I related the Success I had in that Affair: Telling her Ladyship, That my opinion was, nothing Matterial could be had from <hi>Stubbs.</hi> To which she replyed, 'Twas no great matter. But since 'twas her Lord's Advice, her Ladyship was willing to make Trial of the same. Further adding, That the Lords in the <hi>Tower,</hi> did measure out Wit, as Pedlers do Juckle; and that whil'st they beat their Brains on Things of mean Consequence, they let greater slip. Then I demanded, how that could be? Her Ladyship's Answer was, That in the time I had been gone to <hi>Stubbs,</hi> she had been inform'd by Person of good Credit, that one Mr. <hi>Boyce,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Praunce,</hi> were fallen out; and that now there was a fair oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, for them to come within <hi>Praunce,</hi> at the same time: Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering me to go, and Drink with the said Mr. <hi>Boyce,</hi> (who, as her Ladyship informed me, lived in <hi>Bell-Savage-Yard,</hi> on <hi>Ludgate-Hill</hi>) and to endeavour (if I found by his Discourse, that <hi>Praunce</hi> and <hi>He</hi> were separated) if he would embrace any opportunity, to be Revenged on Mr. <hi>Praunce:</hi> Which if he did, according as I should find him inclined, I was to make some offer, to encourage him. Whereupon I did that very Day, go to the said Mr. <hi>Boyces</hi> House, after I had first been to Converse with one Mrs. <hi>Dorothy Sherborne,</hi> a Sempstress, living near St. <hi>Clement</hi>'s-<hi>Church</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> how to frame a Discourse which might be agreeable to the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, which was then between <hi>Boyce</hi> and <hi>Praunce:</hi> For, as I was informed by Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> the said Mrs. <hi>Sherborne</hi> (who is Sister to Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi>'s Wife) was the Person, who first gave notice of this Affair by one Mrs. <hi>Mary Quina,</hi> who then lived in or about <hi>Rus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell-Street,</hi> near <hi>Covent-Garden.</hi> But when I found <hi>Boyce,</hi> and had prevailed with him to Drink, I did enter into some Discourse (which appears by this Information, which follows) relating to <hi>Praunce;</hi> but found no Encouragement to proceed, according as
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56495:16"/>
the Countess of <hi>Powis</hi> expected. But upon our parting, I promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to visit him again: Adding, (when I found no Complyance in that) I would employ him to cut some Amber for me. And in order to that, sometime after, I made another Visit or two; but never gave him any Amber to cut: Nor could I get from him any thing, that would amount to the Prejudice of Mr. <hi>Praunce.</hi> So that Designe fell. But you may perceive by the Information of <hi>Boyce,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Sherborne,</hi> that the Scheam thereof was well enough laid, had <hi>Boyce</hi> but performed his Part. Here follows their Informations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="testimony">
                        <head>The Information of <hi>William Boyce,</hi> in <hi>Bell-Savage-Yard, Ludgate-Hill,</hi> Joyner; (taken upon Oath) before the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, Sir <hi>Robert Clayton,</hi> Knight, Lord-Mayo<gap reason="illegible: broken type" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> of the City of <hi>London,</hi> on <hi>Fryday</hi> the <hi>30th.</hi> of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> 1679.</head>
                        <p>THis Informant saith, That about the middle of last Summer, one Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild</hi> came to this Informant's House, Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate in <hi>Bell-Savage-Court, London,</hi> afore-said: And told this Informant, That he came from Mr. <hi>Praunce,</hi> concerning the Cutting of Amber; and desired to Drink privatly with this Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant. But this Informant being Suspicious of him, did request the Man of the House where they drank, to come into the Room, as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as he could. In which Room, the said <hi>Dangerfeild</hi> acquainted this Informant, that he understood, this Informant had been very kind to Mr. <hi>Praunce,</hi> and serviceable to him; but Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> spake very unkindly of this Informant, behind his back. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon this Informant made answer, that he had no Reason so to do, if he consulted <hi>God,</hi> and his own Conscience. And this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant further saith, That on the Morrow, the said <hi>Dangerfeild</hi> came again to this Informant at his own House; and they went to drink at the same Place, as before<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> At which Place, the said <hi>Dangerfeild</hi> renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Discourse that had passed between them, the Day before; which was, as this Informant did then conceive, to provoke him to say something, that might have ensnared this Informant, in regard this Informant had been an Instrument to perswade Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the Truth, touching the Murther of Sir <hi>Edmund-Bury God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey.</hi> But when the said <hi>Dangerfeild</hi> had found this Informant could not be provoked to Discourse, he would have perswaded this Informant, to meet Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> and him, the said <hi>Dangerfeild,</hi> at the <hi>Horse-Shoo-Tavern</hi> in <hi>Drury-Lane;</hi> at which Place, he acquainted this Informant, he kept a Clubb, and was used to meet there every Night: But this Informant refused so to do; and more sayeth not.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>William Boyce.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                           <p>Dominus die &amp; Anno, Iurat. cor. me,</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Robert Clayton,</hi> Maior.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </postscript>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:56495:17"/>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="testimony">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Comitt. Midd'. Civit. Westm.</hi> The Examination of Mrs. <hi>Dorothy Sherborne;</hi> taken on Oath before Sir <hi>VVilliam VValler,</hi> one of His Majesty's Justices of the Peace, for the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Middlesex,</hi> and City and Liberty of <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster,</hi> the <hi>31st.</hi> of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> 79.</head>
                        <p>THis Examinant saith, That sometime last Summer, she went with some Linnen to <hi>Powis</hi> House, to Mr. <hi>Willoughby;</hi> who, as she supposed, Lodged there, at that time. Sometime af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this Examinant acquainted the said Mr. <hi>Willoughby,</hi> of a Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, as she was informed; that had happened between Mr. <hi>Boyce,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Praunce,</hi> Brother to this Examinant: At which time, the said <hi>Willoughby</hi> told this Examinant, that he would go and see Mr. <hi>Boyce;</hi> and try to find out by him, what the said <hi>Praunce</hi> had endured in Prison. And that not long after, the said Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> returned, and told this Examinant, That he could get nothing out of the said <hi>Boyce;</hi> but that he would go again, for the same purpose: And not long after, returned to this Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant's Shop; and told her, that he (the said <hi>Willoughby</hi>) had been with the said Mr <hi>Boyce,</hi> and Drank with him; but could get nothing out of him. And further this Examinant saith not, at present.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Dorothy Sherborne.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                           <p>Capit. &amp; Jurat. die Superdict, coram. 1.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>William Waller.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </postscript>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>About the Month of <hi>September,</hi> 1679. when Mrs. <hi>Celliers,</hi> and my self, went to visit Mr. <hi>Stanford,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Newburgh</hi>'s Resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; whose Lodgings was then in the <hi>Hay-Market.</hi> He Entertain'd us with Discourses to this effect; <hi>viz.</hi> That Dr. <hi>Tongue</hi> did imploy divers Persons to write; and that to be done so warily, that no Person knew more, than just that Part which he was concerned in: Which Mr. <hi>Stamford</hi> did then promise, to acquaint the King's Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty withal. And farther added, that he would lay down his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the said Writing, in words to this effect; <hi>viz.</hi> That he did believe the said Dr. <hi>Tongue,</hi> and his Clarks, were writing out Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for Dr. <hi>Oates,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bedloe,</hi> how to proceed in the Plot, against the <hi>Roman-Catholicks;</hi> hoping thereby, as I suppose, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinuate a Belief into the King, that there was no such thing as a Plot intended, by that Party; but a Contrived Fiction, by some other. At another time, not long after, I went by my self, to wait upon Mr. <hi>Stamford,</hi> with that Paper entituled, <hi>The Cloak in its Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours;</hi> which was wrote by some, if not all, the Lords in the <hi>Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> as Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> informed me. At which time, Mr. <hi>Stamford</hi> bound himself in a Promise; and took upon him to say, That
<pb facs="tcp:56495:17"/>
If ever the Duke of <hi>York</hi> come to the Crown of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> he should have Interest enough to make my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune there; promising at the same time, in regard things stood then in so ill a posture, for the present he would make such Interest to the <hi>Spanish</hi> Embassador, when he returned from <hi>Fl<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nders,</hi> that I should be entertained in his Family and Service; adding, that my business would be to furnish his Excellency with Intelligence both from City and Countrey, as well as other parts, for which he doubted not but to procure for my Sallery, at least One hundred pounds a year: But when I should be in such an imploy, Mr. <hi>Stamford</hi> proposed a way how I might be as service<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to himself, as the Embassador, which was to give him the same Intelligence.</p>
            <p>Now this I do suppose was used only as a wheedle to encourage me in the prosecuting the many Affairs I then was engaged in for the good of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Cause, more than a thing really intended by him, in regard I never was prefer'd to the said imploy he then proposed; but 'twas his usual custom when I came to wait on him in a Morning before 10 a Clock, to entertain me with a Mass or two before I left him, always admonishing me, and rather indeed enjoyning me to come and hear Mass with him; which I often did, where I constantly found a full Congregation, for the most part of <hi>English</hi> people; and I doubt not but that he still continues the same exercise.</p>
            <p>Now to let you know why I did not insert the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations of my many Witnesses in my first Narrative, as well as some in this, I hope this following Reason may satisfie each Reader; for that in as much as I had the most subtile and wary people perhaps of the whole Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse to deal withall, I neither could, nor yet can think it proper to discover to them the whole strength of my Testimony.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
