<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the honourable knights, citizens, and burgesses of the House of Commons assembled in Parliament the humble remonstrance of William Davenant, anno 1641.</title>
            <author>D'Avenant, William, Sir, 1606-1668.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-12">2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37190</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D345</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R171691</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08630268</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08630268</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41501</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A37190)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41501)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1255:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the honourable knights, citizens, and burgesses of the House of Commons assembled in Parliament the humble remonstrance of William Davenant, anno 1641.</title>
                  <author>D'Avenant, William, Sir, 1606-1668.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 broadside.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>D'Avenant, William, --  Sir, 1606-1668.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-07</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:41501:1"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOURABLE
KNIGHTS, CITIZENS,
AND BURGESSES, OF THE
HOUSE OF COMMONS
ASSEMBLED IN
PARLIAMENT.
The humble Remonſtrance of William Davenant, Anno 1641.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Humbly beſeech you to conceive, that I have abſented to appeare before
this honourable Aſſembly, rather from a befitting baſhfulneſſe, as being an il<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
object, then of outward ſence of guilt, as being a delinquent. I did beleeve
if I were layed aſide a while, my Cauſe would be forgotten, becauſe I knew
nothing ſtronger but ſuſpicions and meere opinions can be brought againſt
me; unles I may particularly ſuffer for the old infirmity of that Nation which,
hath been ever bred with liberty of ſpeaking: and the very Mechanicks of
<hi>Spaine</hi> are glad they are <hi>Spaniards,</hi> becauſe they have liberty; and thinke,
when over-ſpeaking becomes dangerous, that then they chiefly loſe the
liberty of Subjects.</p>
            <p>Confeſſion is the neereſt way to forgiveneſſe, therefore I will make haſt to
accuſe my ſelfe, and ſay it is poſſible I may be guilty of ſome miſ-becoming words, yet not words
made in dangerous principles and maximes, but looſe Arguments, diſputed at Table perhaps, with
too much fancy and heat. And as in ſpeaking, ſo in writing, I meane in Letters, I have perhaps
committed errours, but never irreverently or maliciouſly againſt Parliamentary government.</p>
            <p>I have been admitted into the company of theſe noble Gentlemen that are abſent, but never
was taken into their councels: and ſure for two of them, Maſter <hi>Jarmin,</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn Suckling,</hi> with
whom I was more particularly acquainted, they were ſtrangely altered, and in a very ſhort time, if
it were poſſible they could deſigne any thing againſt your happy and glorious proceedings, who
both in their writing, and ſpeech, have ſo often extol'd the naturall neceſſity of Parliaments here,
with extreame ſcorne upon the incapacity of any that ſhould perſwade the King he could be fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
without them.</p>
            <p>And it is not long ſince I wrot to the Queenes Majeſty in praiſe of her inclination to become this
way the Peoples advocate, the which they preſented to her; for the Arguments ſake it is extant in
good hands, and now mentioned, in hope it may be accepted as a Record of my integrity, to the
Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>It becomes not me to meddle with buſineſſes ſo farre above my reach, but that I perceive I am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunately
miſtaken to be ill-affected.</p>
            <p>I do not certainely know, I proteſt before God and you, that I have ſpoken or written any thin<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
that may indanger me, but as I urged before, it is generally whiſpered, and upon the publication <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
your Warrant men did avoyd me, even my old friends, like one ſtricken with an infectious kind <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
death, ſo terrible already is every marke of your diſpleaſure growne, therefore I humbly beſeech
your pardon. If a ſingle courage flye from your anger, and begg you would not interpret as diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience
my not appearing, ſince it did rather proceed from a reverend awe your diſpleaſure bred
in me; which two wayes I conceive I might incurre.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by knowing of the departure of an ingenious Gentleman named in the Proclamation, who
lay in my houſe. And ſecondly, by ſomething which might either have eſcaped my tongue or pen.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I moſt humbly implore, that as you daily leave to future times ſome examples of your
Iuſtice, ſo this day you will leave me to poſterity as a marke of your compaſſion, and let not my flight
or other indiſcretions be my ruine, though contrary to <hi>Davids</hi> opinion, I have fled from Divine
power, which is yours by derivation, and choſe to fall into the hands of men, which are your Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers
that apprehended me.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41501:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
