<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The badger in the fox-trap, or, A Satyr upon satyrs.</title>
            <author>Dean, J. (John), fl. 1679-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-10">2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37302</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D492</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8512</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13106482</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13106482</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97515</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A37302)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97515)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 413:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The badger in the fox-trap, or, A Satyr upon satyrs.</title>
                  <author>Dean, J. (John), fl. 1679-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A political satire in verse on Shaftesbury.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to J. Dean. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, --  Earl of, 1621-1683 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-10</date>
            <label>Celeste Ng</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-10</date>
            <label>Celeste Ng</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:97515:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97515:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE
BADGER
In the FOX-TRAP,
OR A
Satyr upon Satyrs.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>COmus</hi> nor <hi>Momus,</hi> now muſt be my Theam,</l>
               <l>My Muſe muſt Mourn in a more Serious ſtrain.</l>
               <l>Since I, who ne'r could write to humor men,</l>
               <l>To humor Beaſts, muſt now indulge my Pen.</l>
               <l>One <hi>April</hi> Evening, I alone did lye,</l>
               <l>In my Chamber Window, ſome three Stories high,</l>
               <l>To view the proſpect of the welcom Spring,</l>
               <l>And hear Night's Choriſters their Anthems ſing.</l>
               <l>But all thoſe Chanting Quire ſoon were ſcar'd,</l>
               <l>By a voice unhallowed, they and I both heard<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>The more the Calm, the more the noiſe Increaſt,</l>
               <l>Voice like a man, but call'd it ſelf a Beaſt.</l>
               <l>With Hemns, and Haws, and Groans, did thus begin,</l>
               <l>Did ever God Create ſo Vile a thing!</l>
               <l>Internal and External Hoddy-doddy,</l>
               <l>A perfect Monſter both in Soul and Body.</l>
               <l>Beſides my Names and Titles are as numerous,</l>
               <l>As all my Actions, various ſtill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (and Humerous)</l>
               <l>Some call me <hi>Tony,</hi> ſome <hi>Achitophel;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Some <hi>Jack a-dandy,</hi> ſome old <hi>Machiavil.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Some call me Devil, ſome his Foſter-Brother,</l>
               <l>And Turn-Coat Rebel all the Nation over.</l>
               <l>And ſome compare me to a Sneaking Snail,</l>
               <l>Who keeps its Shell in Storms of Wind and Hail.</l>
               <l>Some call me <hi>Hydra</hi> with a hundred Heads,</l>
               <l>And ſome a Monſter, all of Matchleſs Legs;</l>
               <l>Others the Scab, from whence the Infection Breeds.</l>
               <l>Some call me <hi>Hedg-Hoge</hi> in a Prickly Skin,</l>
               <l>And that a treble Fiend is wrapt within.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But a <hi>Badger</hi> now, caught by a Fatal Snap,</l>
               <l>By th' longeſt Leg, within the <hi>Foxes</hi> Trap.</l>
               <l>Which here was laid for ſome ſuch Animal.</l>
               <l>When e're I'm freed, I ſurely drop to Hell.</l>
               <l>The more I Lug, the more the Spring doth bind me,</l>
               <l>Nay one Tug more leaves all my Legs behind me.</l>
               <l>My Limbs and Sinews, are ſo Feeble grown,</l>
               <l>That were I looſe I cannot ſtand alone.</l>
               <l>Each Member doth each others grief bemoan.</l>
               <l>Tho' I from God deſerve this puniſhment,</l>
               <l>Why ſhould the Devil ſuch a Friend torment,</l>
               <l>Whom I have ever took for my <hi>Protector,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And for ten thouſand Souls he is my Debtor.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97515:2"/>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:97515:2"/>
Can he at laſt a Treacherous Guardian be,</l>
               <l>As I to all, that ever Truſted me.</l>
               <l>'Tis for his ſake, that I'm Deform'd and Hiſt at,</l>
               <l>As Wizards all their Life; like Rams-horns Twiſted.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But poor <hi>Devil,</hi> now perhaps ſuſpected me,</l>
               <l>That I'd Recant to get my Liberty.</l>
               <l>And therefore Hampers me in this Crampt Jail,</l>
               <l>That I have ſcarce room to wag my poor old Tail;</l>
               <l>Which I'l ne'r do, to gain three Kingdoms more,</l>
               <l>Then my Ambition, hop'd to make me ſure.</l>
               <l>Who knows what <hi>Nick</hi> hath yet for me in ſtore?</l>
               <l>Poor Fiend on me, uſed to have tender Care,</l>
               <l>And made me Eminent in Peace and War,</l>
               <l>And yet I have Senſe, Children, and Fools to Scar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>By Teaching <hi>Ben</hi> and <hi>Franck</hi> to Write great Lies;</l>
               <l>How mighty Monſters quarrel in the Skies.</l>
               <l>Viſions at <hi>Hatfield,</hi> either White or Green,</l>
               <l>Far more Prodigious then the <hi>Fairy Queen.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To make them believe the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſtill are Plotting,</l>
               <l>To Cut the Throats o'th' Saints whilſt they are Napping.</l>
               <l>And that they Burnt the City down about us,</l>
               <l>As ſure as I was ever ſtout or Honeſt.</l>
               <l>And that they'l endeavour for to do't again,</l>
               <l>To lay the Land in Univerſal Flame;</l>
               <l>Tho' they themſelves be ſtifled in the ſtream.</l>
               <l>And how to make the Neighbours Hate each other,</l>
               <l>And for Rvenge to Murder one another;</l>
               <l>And to make a King to Sell a Royal Brother;</l>
               <l>And to make the great Ones like Pikes in a Pond,</l>
               <l>To Devour the Smaller over all the Land.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe are but petty Symptoms of the Shams,</l>
               <l>When my Familiar gave but ſingle Drams.</l>
               <l>But when for ſickly State we do contrive,</l>
               <l>Oh! <hi>Roger, Roger,</hi> Oh! my Dribling ſide</l>
               <l>Come bring a Spoon, before I am quite Spent,</l>
               <l>And from this Tap receive my Excrement.</l>
               <l>Why <hi>Roger, Harry, Tom, Will, Martha—</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where's all the Rogues and Bitches, ſome of you come forth a-</l>
               <l>The great Defluction of my Canker'd Spleen,</l>
               <l>The Scum o'th' Poiſon will not ſtay within,</l>
               <l>But Drains from th' Conclave of declining Parts,</l>
               <l>And quite obſtructeth my Etherick Arts;</l>
               <l>Well, I keep Currs, But I am the Dog that Barks.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then he himſelf unbuckled, and let fly</l>
               <l>Venemous Extraction, till his Pump waxt dry.</l>
               <l>Which he perceiving, tug'd and Pumpt the more,</l>
               <l>Till all his Engines he in pieces tore,</l>
               <l>Them like an Aſs, the <hi>Badger</hi> he did Roar.</l>
               <l>He Snarl'd, and Curſt, and Swore he was undone,</l>
               <l>Expos'd to the Scorn of every Mothers Son.</l>
               <l>Having loſt the Sluice which many years had ſtood,</l>
               <l>And at his pleaſure Drown'd the Land in Blood.</l>
               <l>And tho' to's ruine it made the wider Gap,</l>
               <l>He found himſelf the Faſter in the Trap.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97515:3"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:97515:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
He Hal'd his Limbs, which had his Soul long hated,</l>
               <l>But the Badger's Faſt, and Fears he ſhall be Baited.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But am I now forſaken by my Friends,</l>
               <l>Fools, nor Knaves, Servants, nor none Attends.</l>
               <l>Hells Damn'd Fiends, break off thoſe Slaviſh Chains,</l>
               <l>Releaſe your Friend, in theſe unpitied Pains.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where's my Companions, o'th' ſame Imputation,</l>
               <l>My Fellow Sharers in the Ruine o'th' Nation.</l>
               <l>Where's my Cabals, and Mercenary Men,</l>
               <l>Where's Silly <hi>Perkin,</hi> where's <hi>Franck, Dick</hi> and <hi>Ben;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where's my Nurſery, that Piſt all in a Pen?</l>
               <l>Where's all our Senat, with their lowd Debates,</l>
               <l>Where's our Committes, thoſe Imps, and Quaeks of States?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What no Redreſs?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fiends, Furies, Goblins, Uſhers of Black Shades,</l>
               <l>Infernal Hell-Hounds, I Conjure your Aides.</l>
               <l>Riſe up and Tear my Tired Limbs aſunder;</l>
               <l>Let me like <hi>Fauſtus</hi> be a ſecond Wonder.</l>
               <l>Then one in Black came Limping with all Speed,</l>
               <l>I thought the Devil had been come indeed;</l>
               <l>So did the <hi>Badger,</hi> and on his Tail did Squat,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> Good Mr. <hi>Devil,</hi> do not take me yet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> I am no <hi>Devil,</hi> but Chief Doctor in the Synod,</l>
               <l>Who came from <hi>Salamanca</hi> in a Minuit:</l>
               <l>Lets feel your Wounds, to Cure you I will try:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> Oh! Curſed <hi>R—</hi> thou'rt as foul within as I.</l>
               <l>What needſt thou feel me Dog, thou wilt undo me,</l>
               <l>My <hi>Victim's</hi> gone, a man may ſee quite through me.</l>
               <l>I am paſt the help of <hi>Doctor,</hi> or of <hi>Devils,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nothing but Death, can Cure theſe growing Evils.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> But ſince your Diſtemper is ſo Deep and Bloody,</l>
               <l>And I a Doctor both for Soul and Body;</l>
               <l>Prepare your ſelf to make a True Confeſſion,</l>
               <l>Be it what it will, I'l give you Abſolution.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I am not like thoſe common ſort of <hi>Prieſts,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who Abſolve none but their own <hi>Silly Geeſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I Pardon all, both—Biter, Dipper, Pendant,</l>
               <l>Tho' Perjury and Treaſon hang at the end on't.</l>
               <l>All ſorts of Rebels, Hypocrites and Atheiſt,</l>
               <l>I Pardon all, but Cavaliers and Papiſts.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> Some of my Sins are Forty years of Age,</l>
               <l>Muſt I bring thoſe again upon the Stage?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Yes thoſe to chooſe, they are old, and now grown Hory,</l>
               <l>Shake out the Bag, and make an end of th' Story.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> But how ſhall I begin this great Confeſſion?</l>
               <l>Which in my Soul doth make this deep Impreſſion:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> Not like the Papiſts with a Bleer'd Contrition.</l>
               <l>Speak boldly Sir, with Conſcience like a Tanner,</l>
               <l>Make every Sin a Trophy of your Honour.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> Why in Forty one, and two, and three, and Four,</l>
               <l>I then began to Love a Handſom W—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> Very good Sir, well and how much more?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> The reſt are State-Affairs, not to be diſclos'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>And by <hi>Malignants,</hi> are too much ſuppos'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97515:4"/>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:97515:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
And ſo all that, may well be thus Excus'd;</l>
               <l>I own I have, both Church and K. Abus'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> But you muſt Specifie each dubious Query,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> Nay then 'twill laſt from <hi>June</hi> till <hi>January.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> Well, we muſt follow Order, Courſe and Form,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> Plague Dam the Order, I ſuch Cuſtom Scorn.</l>
               <l>It has been my Study, ever from my Cradle,</l>
               <l>To break all Formal Order, far as I was able.</l>
               <l>And muſt I now, to Save an Old Dam'd Soul,</l>
               <l>Go diſimbogue, each Cranny, Chink and Hole.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> The more you own, your Crime will be the Leſſer,</l>
               <l>Hear to your Reverend Father, and Confeſſor.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> Prophane Impoſtor, Reverend do'ſt thou ſay,</l>
               <l>That haſt been Perjur'd twenty times a day:</l>
               <l>In Capital and Mortal Bloody Caſes,</l>
               <l>To Murther Innocents with thy Diſgraces.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> 'Twas to Oblige our Sworn Fraternities,</l>
               <l>And to deſtroy the Cauſes, Subtil Enemies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> Well <hi>Dr.</hi> now I find you are much Reform'd,</l>
               <l>Since our Cabals have Falter'd and Diſſolv'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> 'Twas ſtill my Nature to Sail with the Wind;</l>
               <l>Come Scrape the Kettle, out with what's behind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> Lord Father, you have ſuch Influence o're me,</l>
               <l>I wou'd ſpeak all, but that you'l quite Abhor me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> Oh! you Little Baſhful, Old Arch Wag,</l>
               <l>You know, I neither dare Divulge nor Brag.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> Why, in Forty Three, I then began to Feel,</l>
               <l>Which way Dame Fortune wou'd bring round her Wheel.</l>
               <l>Then I laid hould on that great Inſtrument,</l>
               <l>And left the K. for K. and Parliament.</l>
               <l>Me they Embrac'd, and my Advice did Crave,</l>
               <l>Finding I'd Wit enough to be a Knave.</l>
               <l>Then I fell on, 'gainſt Church, and King, and Heaven;</l>
               <l>And Still my Conſcience with Times kept Even:</l>
               <l>And ne'r Recanted what I Undertook,</l>
               <l>Till K was Kill'd, and 'th Son the Land Forſook.</l>
               <l>And then the Scepter fell in Traitors Hands,</l>
               <l>And I was ready to Aſſiſt Commands.</l>
               <l>Then I was made a Miniſter of State,</l>
               <l>And found a way, the Church to Extirpate.</l>
               <l>Then I helpt <hi>Noll</hi> to ſet up <hi>Presbyters,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And Pull'd the <hi>Biſhops</hi> Surpleſs o'r their Ears;</l>
               <l>And made the Clergy look like Privateers.</l>
               <l>As they went down, Tub-Preachers they did Riſe,</l>
               <l>Preach'd Order, Altar down, and Sacrifice.</l>
               <l>I made him know, through States great Policy,</l>
               <l>Thoſe were the men, to Maintain Tirany.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Noll</hi> being Safe, by what I had done for him,</l>
               <l>Suſpected me, 'cauſe I Betray'd my King.</l>
               <l>Then to our Tribe he openly Proclaims,</l>
               <l>He'd never Truſt a man that had three Names.</l>
               <l>He Smoak'd my Soul, from its Minority,</l>
               <l>Still to be Oppoſite to all Authority.</l>
               <l>Then I was forc't new Meaſures for to take,</l>
               <l>With the Kings Friends, ſome ſmall Contracts did make.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97515:5"/>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:97515:5"/>
I Beg'd they wou'd with Patience be contented,</l>
               <l>For the Kings Return, a means was juſt invented;</l>
               <l>But this was done, wh<gap reason="illegible: blotted" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n I could not prevent it.</l>
               <l>I put my ſelf i'th' Front o'th' Sufferers,</l>
               <l>Tho' like to them, I had neither Wounds nor Scars.</l>
               <l>When he Arriv'd with Glorious Acclamations,</l>
               <l>And fill'd with Joys the Longing Expectations,</l>
               <l>All Loyal Hearted Souls of theſe three Nations.</l>
               <l>And every Heart that had been Musket Proof,</l>
               <l>For K. and Country under Fortunes Roof:</l>
               <l>Had Broak the Fatal Spells of Slaveries,</l>
               <l>With Joys did Meet the K. upon their Knees.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I, like a Spaniel-Whelp, did Lurk a Loof,</l>
               <l>And Squint quite through the Opticks of my Hoof.</l>
               <l>Expecting when the K. on me would Call,</l>
               <l>And cry my Merits up above them All.</l>
               <l>But when I found He did mind me no more,</l>
               <l>Juſt to His Feet, I Crept upon all Four.</l>
               <l>Then Clutch'd his Royal Hand between my Paws,</l>
               <l>As if I'd never been for <hi>Good Old Cauſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then His Clemency, Remitted what was paſt,</l>
               <l>With Place and Title, he my Honour Grac'd.</l>
               <l>Which I Improv'd, till I was grown ſo High,</l>
               <l>That I again did Envy Monarchy.</l>
               <l>Which being Smelt by <hi>York,</hi> I was Degraded,</l>
               <l>And out of all my Dignities Defeated.</l>
               <l>And ever ſince my Brain has been a Working,</l>
               <l>For Sweet Revenge, my Soul hath ſtill lain Lurking.</l>
               <l>To ſeveral Attempts I did Aſpire,</l>
               <l>E're I could pitch on one that would take Fire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Till I had got this <hi>Fatal-Plot</hi> well grounded,</l>
               <l>With Seconds, and with Sham-Plots to Surround it.</l>
               <l>Which ſerves as Paint upon an Old Bawds Face,</l>
               <l>To Fill up Furrows, and to give a Grace;</l>
               <l>As Painters always Imperfection Blaze.</l>
               <l>And here we'l make Friendly, Fair Concluſion,</l>
               <l>I prithee <hi>Dr.</hi> give me Abſolution</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> Nay hold a while, your Crime's but now begin Sir,</l>
               <l>Theſe were but Vertues to your later Sins Sir:</l>
               <l>You muſt rub up your Brains, and Face about,</l>
               <l>We have the Plot Miſtick, yet to Hammer out.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> God Dam your Reverency, let that go by,</l>
               <l>You are as deep i'th dirt in that as I;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> Pox rot your Honour, that's a Plaguy Lie.</l>
               <l>You have Confeſt, you were the Engeneer,</l>
               <l>That Draw'd the Lines, which way the <hi>Plot</hi> would Bear;</l>
               <l>That who ſhou'd keep the Front, and who the Rear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> And had not your Impudence, ſtill over-Acted,</l>
               <l>Our Purpoſe long e're this, had been Perfected.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> 'Zwounds 'twas for that, that I by you was choſen,</l>
               <l>Cauſe I could Out-face all the Truth in Heaven.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> But not to Snap the Council up like Peaſants,</l>
               <l>And call them Raſcals in the Royal Preſence.</l>
               <l>Nor yet to call the Life-Guards <hi>Papiſh Traitors,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As if we were their Makers and Creators.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97515:6"/>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:97515:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Nor to throw an <hi>Odium</hi> on them at their Inns,</l>
               <l>When you ſaw our party Totter like Nine-pinns;</l>
               <l>Too late to make the World eſteem u<gap reason="illegible: blotted" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Kings.</l>
               <l>Nor to call Inn-keepers Rogues, for entertaining</l>
               <l>The King's Life-Guards; thoſe things divulg'd our meaning.</l>
               <l>Nor to call your ſelf <hi>the Saviour of the Nation;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As if there had been <hi>Oats</hi> from the Creation.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> 'S death, Have you not acted worſe than this?</l>
               <l>You vex me ſo, I ſcarce have time to Piſs.</l>
               <l>You have theſe ſeven years, made it your ſtudy</l>
               <l>To draw diſguſted Parties to a Body.</l>
               <l>You held Communion with Tub-preachers juggling,</l>
               <l>And draw'd their Brethren altogether, ſmuggling</l>
               <l>Their holy Siſters, with whom they Ingender,</l>
               <l>And bring forth Brood that's light with th' ſame Tinder:</l>
               <l>Who are bred up in <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wherewith you daily blind their pur-blind eyes.</l>
               <l>And thus you draw the hearts of ſilly Subjects</l>
               <l>From their own Sovereign, to be odious Objects:</l>
               <l>For this Impreſſion in their Infancy</l>
               <l>Deprives them of the ſence of <hi>Loyalty.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus you ſeduce the Land for future Ages,</l>
               <l>To be a Den of Bruits; for wild out-rages;</l>
               <l>Worſe than wild Beaſts, who ſtill own ſome Supreme;</l>
               <l>Both Infidels and <hi>Indians</hi> do the ſame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> Had you this Doctrine from <hi>Salamancha,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where you ne're were, I know well, Sir, I thank ye?</l>
               <l>You need not inſtance theſe moſt biting twinges,</l>
               <l>Since our Deſigns are all flung off the hinges.</l>
               <l>You're ten times worſe, were your faults ſum'd together,</l>
               <l>Tho' thou pretend'ſt to be my Ghoſtly Father;</l>
               <l>For thou art neither <hi>Prot. 'Byter,</hi> nor <hi>Papiſt:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Beſt thou canſt boaſt of is <hi>Inhumane Atheiſt.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> You croſs old Cur, reſolve me theſe few Queſtions,</l>
               <l>And I'le importune for no more Confeſſions.</l>
               <l>Who was the Cauſe of <hi>Scotland</hi>'s late Rebellions?</l>
               <l>Who promis'd to aſſiſt their Force with Millions?</l>
               <l>Who was't draw'd <hi>Perkin</hi> from his Royal Father,</l>
               <l>To he cajoll'd into the Peoples Favour?</l>
               <l>Who was't contriv'd the Plotting of <hi>Petitions,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To gull the Nation into blind <hi>Seditions?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who was't contriv'd Caballing in the City,</l>
               <l>And to ſchool <hi>Evidence</hi> choſe a Committee?</l>
               <l>Who firſt contriv'd to Peach both Peers and Judges,</l>
               <l>And make them ſcrape before the Bar like drudges?</l>
               <l>All thoſe in Eminent Places, and great Favour,</l>
               <l>Yet never could be brought in Guilty neither?</l>
               <l>Who told the <hi>Commons</hi> that, 'gainſt every Trial,</l>
               <l>They muſt ſeclude all Members that were Loyal?</l>
               <l>That none might ever paſs for due Elected,</l>
               <l>Unleſs approv'd on by the diſaffected?</l>
               <l>Who was it firſt that curſed Maxim mov'd,</l>
               <l>That every Act for Money be reprov'd,</l>
               <l>Unleſs <hi>Prerogative</hi> were ſqueez'd or ſhov'd?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97515:7"/>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:97515:7"/>
Who was't contriv'd to have the Guards Indicted,</l>
               <l>When we our ſelves the City-Guards united?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who was it cry'd,</hi> No money for the King,</l>
               <l>Till Kingly Powers into your hands we bring?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who was it cry'd,</hi> The King muſt not be trusted</l>
               <l>With his own Life, while we are thus diſguſted?</l>
               <l>And that the People they were ſtill in danger</l>
               <l>Of Native <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and of <hi>Popiſh</hi> Stranger;</l>
               <l>Till th' <hi>Militia, Cinque-Ports, Navy</hi> and the reſt,</l>
               <l>Were all expos'd unto our Care and Truſt?</l>
               <l>Who was't that writ the <hi>Addreſs</hi> for Shire,</l>
               <l>As if all had been Subſcribers that were there,</l>
               <l>A voting for the Members, and had lear'd on't,</l>
               <l>Tho' ten in all the number never heard on't?</l>
               <l>Who was it firſt invented the <hi>Black Box,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And the <hi>Black Bills</hi> which were to give ſuch knocks?</l>
               <l>Who was made privy unto <hi>Godfrey</hi>'s Death,</l>
               <l>For which three men already loſt their breath?</l>
               <l>Who was't converted Law into a Cloak,</l>
               <l>To ſhelter Knaves, and Innocents to choak?</l>
               <l>Who was't that gave the Synod Approbations,</l>
               <l>For to contrive Committees for vexations,</l>
               <l>And made a Conventicle Synod for three Nations?</l>
               <l>Who gave Advice to Libel Church and State,</l>
               <l>And none muſt mind the meaning, till too late,</l>
               <l>And the King's Friends made odious, out of date?</l>
               <l>Who was't perſwaded thoſe turn'd out of Places</l>
               <l>Of great Authority, to make ſtrange faces;</l>
               <l>And cry out Popery is now approaching;</l>
               <l>Tho' they before conceived no ſuch poaching?</l>
               <l>Who was't gave out that a thouſand Watermen</l>
               <l>Had all conſpir'd to Petition, when</l>
               <l>The Parliament to <hi>Oxford</hi> were conven'd,</l>
               <l>That they might ſit at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> for them;</l>
               <l>But ne're were heard of more from <hi>Smith</hi> nor <hi>Ben?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who was't endeavour'd all that preparations,</l>
               <l>To guard the City Members in their ſtations</l>
               <l>To <hi>Oxford;</hi> which look'd far more Arbitrary</l>
               <l>Than <hi>Forty One,</hi> or abſolute Old <hi>Harry?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who was the occaſion of the late obſtruction</l>
               <l>Of the Addreſſes of the Cities Loyal Production;</l>
               <l>Was't not the Canker of your Taps defluction?</l>
               <l>Who ſchool'd <hi>Fitz-Harris</hi> for two years together,</l>
               <l>And tann'd his Conſcience thick as Bullocks Leather;</l>
               <l>And kept him for reſerve to ſweep the Court</l>
               <l>Of King and Queen, and all that them ſupport?</l>
               <l>And now the Fool begins to ſtink for fear,</l>
               <l>And is in danger quite as much as we are:</l>
               <l>But makes ſuch ſcruples to put by the Coller,</l>
               <l>As if he meant to hang Sir <hi>W. W.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who hath influenc'd all this <hi>Perjury,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which hath out-fac'd both Law and Loyalty?</l>
               <l>Who is't that holds the Plot ſtill by the tail,</l>
               <l>As Seamen tugg, to tack about their Sail;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97515:8"/>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:97515:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
And now by one ſmall breeze of Juſtice breath,</l>
               <l>Fear to be ſhipwrack'd to eternal Death?</l>
               <l>Who animated the wild Votes of late,</l>
               <l>To make themſelves Comptrollers of the State;</l>
               <l>And that their Votes, without concurrence, might</l>
               <l>Impeach the Crown or Peers in ſpight of Right?</l>
               <l>Who was't deſtroy'd both Monarchy and Law,</l>
               <l>And would make it lawful by a ſecond blow?</l>
               <l>Who cry'd, Theſe Viſions and ſtrange Revelations,</l>
               <l>Tells us for Wars we muſt make preparations,</l>
               <l>Whilſt we know no danger but our own Damnations?</l>
               <l>Who made the Speech burn'd by the Hangman's hand,</l>
               <l>Which did both Threaten, and the King Command?</l>
               <l>In ſhort, Who was this <hi>Helliſh Plot</hi>'s Contriver?</l>
               <l>Who was its Plaintiff-Engine; who its Driver?</l>
               <l>If it was You, ingeniouſly confeſs't,</l>
               <l>And I'le give you Abſolution for the reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> Nay, Doctor, now I find you'l not abhor me,</l>
               <l>For you your ſelf makes my Confeſſion for me.</l>
               <l>Then nods and fleers, and at this motion grins;</l>
               <l>Theſe are but Title-pages of my Sins.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> Nay, for the reſt we'le ne're ſtand to unhole,</l>
               <l>They're only ſymptom-Inſects in your ſoul,</l>
               <l>Flaws of diſtinction between fair and foul.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> Well, ſince I find that all my hopes are paſt,</l>
               <l>E're to ſhake off what I pull'd on ſo faſt,</l>
               <l>But that I, at worſt, can hang my ſelf at laſt.</l>
               <l>Rather than live under this ill, true notion,</l>
               <l>After your kind Advice and friendly Caution,</l>
               <l>I muſt confeſs, tho' with a feign'd Devotion,</l>
               <l>All theſe black Crimes which to my charge you lay,</l>
               <l>And many a thouſand, ten times worſe than they.</l>
               <l>Since I'm imperfect to perform the reſt.</l>
               <l>He whiſper'd then, and I ſuppoſe confeſt;</l>
               <l>Thus far degenerated from a Beaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> And then the <hi>Doctor,</hi> with his bended Chin,</l>
               <l>Canted ſome words, and ſo abſolv'd his ſin.</l>
               <l>And ſwore by the <hi>Holy Doom</hi> of his beſt Trade,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Badger</hi> thou art a <hi>Papist</hi> now, as good as e're was made:</l>
               <l>By this Canonick <hi>Salamancha</hi> Gown,</l>
               <l>I give to 'thee my beſt Benediction.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> The <hi>Badger</hi> then began to frisk and ſquail,</l>
               <l>As a Cow that's ſtung with Hornets in the Tail.</l>
               <l>Thou Popiſh Dog, had I but power to rally,</l>
               <l>I'd make thee know I hate all Chriſtian Folly.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But in the interval, to prevent new Broils,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aurora</hi> roſe, and all the Sequel ſpoils;</l>
               <l>VVhoſe ſplendrous looks, with <hi>Phaebus</hi> in the Rear,</l>
               <l>Drives all Malignants to a darker Sphere.</l>
               <l>Their Conſcience then with fear began to crack;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Doctor</hi> hol'd, with the <hi>Badger</hi> at his back.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
