<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An act for suppressing the detestable sins of incest, adultery and fornication</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-05">2004-05 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37573</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1081</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9989</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12713867</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12713867</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66145</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A37573)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66145)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 689:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An act for suppressing the detestable sins of incest, adultery and fornication</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 827-831 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Field ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Incest --  England --  Law and legislation.</term>
               <term>Adultery --  England --  Law and legislation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66145:1"/>
            <p>AN ACT For suppressing The Detestable SINS OF Incest, Adultery and Fornication.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Die Veneris, Decimo Maii, 1650.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>ORdered by the Parliament, That this Act be forthwith Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Published.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Hen: Scobell, Cleric. Parliamenti.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Iohn Field,</hi> Printer to the Parliament of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:66145:2"/>
            <pb n="827" facs="tcp:66145:2"/>
            <head>AN ACT For suppressing The Detestable SINS OF Incest, Adultery and Fornication.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the suppressing of the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable and crying Sins of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cest Adultery and Fornication, wherewith this Land is much defiled, and Almighty God high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly displeased; Be it Enacted by the Authority of this present Parliament, That if any person or persons whatsoever, shall from and after the Four and twentieth day of <hi>June,</hi> in the year of our Lord, One thousand six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty, Marry, or have the carnal know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Body of his or her Grandfather or Grandmother, Father or Mother, Brother or Sister, Son or Daughter, or Grandchilde, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Brother or Sister, Mothers Brother or Sister, Fathers wife, Mothers husband, Sons wife, Daughters husband, Wives Mother or Daughter, Husbands Father or Son; all and every such offences are hereby adjudged and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared Incest: And every such offence shall be, and it is hereby adjudged Felony; and every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son offending therein, and confessing the same,
<pb n="828" facs="tcp:66145:3"/>
or being therefore convicted by verdict upon Indictment or Presentment; before any Iudge or Iustices at the Assize or Sessions of the Peace, shall suffer death as in case of Felony, without Benefit of Clergy: And all and every such Marriage and Marriages are hereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared and adjudged to be void in Law, to all intents and purposes; and the children begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten between such persons, notwithstanding any contract or solemnization of Marriage, to be illegitimate, and altogether disabled to claim or inherit any Lands or Inheritance whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, by way of descent from, or to receive or challenge any childes portion in any Goods or Chattels of their said parents, or any other An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors of such Parents. And be it further En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by the Authority aforesaid, That in case any married woman shall from and after the Four and twentieth day of <hi>June</hi> aforesaid, be carnally known by any man (other then her husband (except in case of Ravishment) and of such offence or offences shall be convicted as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid by confession or otherwise, every such Offence and Offences shall be, and is hereby adjudged Felony; and every person, as well the man as the woman offending therein, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing the same, or being thereof convicted by verdict upon Indictment or Presentment as aforesaid, shal suffer death as in case of Felony, without benefit of Clergy. Provided, That this shall not extend to any man who at the time of such Offence committed, is not knowing that such woman with whom such Offence is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted is then married. Provided also, That the said penalty in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> case of Adultery aforesaid, shall not extend to any woman whose husband shall be continually remaining beyond the seas
<pb n="829" facs="tcp:66145:3"/>
by the space of three years, or shall by common fame be reputed to be dead; nor to any woman whose husband shall absent himself from his said wife by the space of three years together, in any parts or places whatsoever, so as the said Wife shall not know her said Husband to be living within that time. And be it further En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by the authority aforesaid, That if any man shall from and after the Four and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth day of <hi>June</hi> aforesaid, have the carnal knowledge of the Body of any Virgin unmar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried woman or widow, every such man so offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and confessing the same, or being thereof convicteed by verdit upon Indictment or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentment, as also every such woman so offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and confessing the same, or being thereof convict as aforesaid, shall for every such offence be committed to the common Goal, without Bail or Mainprize, there to continue for the space of three Months; and until he and she re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectively shall give security, to be taken by one or more Iustice or Iustices of the Peace before whom such confession or conviction shall be had, to be of the good behavior for the space of one whole year then next ensuing. And be it fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That all and every person or persons who shall from and after the Four and twentieth day of <hi>June</hi> aforesaid, be convicted as aforesaid, by confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion or otherwise, for being a common Bawd, be it man or woman, or wittingly keeping a common Brothel or Bawdy-house, shall for his or her first offence be openly whipped and set in the Pillory, and there marked with a hot Iron in the Forehead with the Letter <hi>B.</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards committed to prison or the House of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, thereto work for his or her living for
<pb n="830" facs="tcp:66145:4"/>
the space of three years, without Bail or Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, and until he or she shall put in sufficient Sureties for his or her good Behavior, during his or her life: And if any person by confession or otherwise shall be convicted of committing, after such conviction, any of the said last reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted offences, every such second offence shall be, and is hereby adjudged Felony; and the person and persons so offending shall suffer death, as in case of Felony without benefit of Clergy. And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That the Iustices of Assize in their respective Circuits, and the Iustices of Peace in every County, at their usual and General Sessions, are hereby authorized and required to give in charge to the Grand Iury, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of all and every the Crimes aforesaid: And the said Iustices of Assize, Iustices of the Peace in their General Sessions, and all and every Major and Iustices of Peace of any City, Borough or Town Corporate, that have power to hear and determine Felonies at their usual Sessions, shall have full power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to enquire by verdict of twelve or more good and lawful men, within the said respective counties and places aforesaid, of all and every the crimes and Offences aforesaid; and upon Indictment or presentment, to hear and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the same, as in other cases of Felony or Trespass, Any Law, Vsage or Custom to the contrary notwithstanding. Provided, That no Attainder for any Offence made Felony by this Act, shall make or work any corruption of Blood, loss of Dower, Forfeiture of Goods, disinherision of Heir or Heirs. Provided also, That no person or persons shall incur any of the penalties in this Act mentioned, unless the
<pb n="831" facs="tcp:66145:4"/>
said person or persons be therefore indicted within twelve Months after the Offence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, Provided also, That it shall be lawful for any person or persons who shall be indicted for any the Offences aforesaid, to produce at their respective Tryals any witness or wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses for the clearing of themselves from the said Offences whereof they shall be so Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: And the Iustices before whom such Tryal shall be so had, shall have power, and are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by authorized to examine the said witnesses up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Oath. Provided, That no parties confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion shall be taken as Evidence within this Act against any other, but onely against such par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty so confessing; nor the husband shall be taken as a witness against his wife, nor the wife a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst her husband, for any offence punishable by this Act.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <head>Die Veneris, decimo Maii, 1650.</head>
            <p>ORdered by the Parliament, That this Act be forthwith printed and published.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hen: Scobell, Cleric. Parliamenti.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
