<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Exact and faithful account of the late bloody fight between Captain Hastings, commander of the Saphire, Captain Showel, commander of the James galley, and Jonas Raile, captain of the Half-Moon of Algier a ship of 32 guns, and 246 men, with the particulars of the engagement, sent from on board the James galley, lying in Tangier Road : September the 22d. 1681.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38876</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3595A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41142</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19639454</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19639454</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109259</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A38876)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109259)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1685:65)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Exact and faithful account of the late bloody fight between Captain Hastings, commander of the Saphire, Captain Showel, commander of the James galley, and Jonas Raile, captain of the Half-Moon of Algier a ship of 32 guns, and 246 men, with the particulars of the engagement, sent from on board the James galley, lying in Tangier Road : September the 22d. 1681.</title>
                  <author>Shovell, Clowdisley, Sir, 1650-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 broadside.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for E.L. by John Gain, and are to be sold by Mrs. Andrews ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Text in double columns.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Sir Clowdisley Shovel by NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: torn and creased with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Shovell, Clowdisley, --  Sir, 1650-1707.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History, Naval --  Stuarts, 1603-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:109259:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
            <head>An Exact and Faithful Account of the late BLOODY FIGHT BETWEEN <hi>Captain Haſtings Commander of the Saphire.</hi> Captain <hi>SHOWEL,</hi> Commander of the <hi>JAMES</hi> Galley, AND JONAS RAILE, <hi>Captain of the</hi> Half-Moon <hi>of</hi> Algier; <hi>a Ship of</hi> 32 <hi>Guns, and</hi> 246 <hi>Men, with the Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of the Engagement, ſent from on Board the</hi> James <hi>Galley, lying in</hi> Tangier <hi>Road,</hi> 
               <date>September <hi>the</hi> 22d. 1681.</date>
            </head>
            <p>SEptember the 9th. about ten in the Morning, we ſaw a Ship <hi>S. W.</hi> by <hi>W,</hi> about five Leagues from us, we immediately chaſed, the Wind was then at <hi>E.N.E,</hi> and <hi>N.E.</hi> by <hi>E,</hi> where it continued all day, he ſteered <hi>S.</hi> by <hi>W;</hi> at eight this Evening we were within Call, he hailed us in ſeveral Languages, we anſwered, we did belong to the King of <hi>France,</hi> he told us, they were the <hi>Half-Moon</hi> of <hi>Algier,</hi> and had been from thence about ten weeks, we asked for <hi>Salle</hi>-Men, and told him we ſuſpected he was of <hi>Salle,</hi> and commaded his Boat on Board (all which he denied) in ſuch like diſcourſe we held him, until we were along his Larboard ſide, which was the weather ſide, I reſolving to board him thwart the Harſe, by reaſon there went ſuch a Sea, that I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident of bringing his <hi>Bolt ſprit</hi> and <hi>Fore-Maſt</hi> by the Board, but he ſuſpecting my deſign, put his Helm a-port, and made his Starboard ſide the weather-ſide: I fired all my guns into him: the <hi>Saphire</hi> being a quarter of a mile a Stern of us, took the advantage, and before the <hi>Turk</hi> could trim his Sails, run him on Board the <hi>Starboard</hi> ſide abaft the Fore-Chains, it was then half an hour paſt 8: I endeavoured to be thwart his Harſe, and twice miſſed, the third time I laid him on Board, that his <hi>Boltſprit</hi> was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our Main-Shrouds, but with the way we had brought his Ship a little about, and our Fore-Braces be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, could not back our Head-Sails, that we ſhot <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap>er of him in little more than a quarter of an hour; <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> after the <hi>Saphire</hi> was clear of the <hi>Algerine,</hi> and fell a <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>en, which was occaſioned by the loſs of her <hi>Boltſprit</hi> and <hi>Fore-Maſt,</hi> it was then three quarters paſt nine: I <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen having the <hi>Algerine</hi> to deal withal alone, with all <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Maſts ſtanding, Stearing away before the Wind, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olved to be thwart his Harſe, for my guns being but ſix <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap>nders, t'was not to be hoped they could do much good in ſhooting down their Maſts: ſoon after ten, with <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Sails full, I ſheared thwart his Harſe, he broke two of my Main-Shrouds, alſo our Main-Chains, and two of our Mizon-Shrouds and Mizon-Chains, and our Gunnel down to the Deck, but broke his Boltſprit, Head, Cutwater, Knee, and Cheeks of his Head, ſo that he had a ſmooth Stern quite below the waters edge, we lay thwart his Harſe about half an Hour, and then being entangled with his Rigging, we fell along his Side, with our Head to his Stern, where we lay about half an Hour, in which time the Rig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging broke, and he got off from us, but I again laid him on Board, on the Starboard Bow, where we lay to keep him from ſecuring his Maſts, which I expected would fall every moment, for the Knees of his Head being gone, the Collar of his Main Stay came on the Deck, ſo that both Main and Foremaſt were equally in danger, and at a quarter after one his Foremaſt came by the Board and ſoon after his Main and Mizon Maſts, I laid my Sails aback, and called to them, they anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they yielded the Ship, we immeditely went to work to ſecure our Maſts, and mend our Boat that it might ſwim which was not done before day light, at which time we vvent on Board and took Poſſeſſion, it vvas the <hi>Half-Moon</hi> of <hi>Algier,</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried 32 Guns, and came out of <hi>Algier</hi> with 246 men, whereof 39 were Chriſtians, of which 20 <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> they had taken a ſmall <hi>Engliſh</hi> Veſſel bound for <hi>Bermudoes,</hi> with 20 <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, which they took on Board, and ſunk the Veſſel. The Captains Name was <hi>Jonas Raile,</hi> a <hi>Turk,</hi> the Lieutenant an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negado, which I cauſed to be hanged at my Yard Arm; the damage we received, was 18 men killed, and 32 men wounded, and both Main and Fore-maſt ſpoiled. We took him 45 Leagues <hi>S. W.</hi> by <hi>W.</hi> half <hi>W.</hi> from Cape <hi>Spartel:</hi> There were killed on Board the <hi>Half-Moon</hi> 93 <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Moors,</hi> and moſt of the Living wounded; the <hi>Turks</hi> poſitively inform me, that there is but, two better Ships in <hi>Algier,</hi> which are <hi>Canaries</hi> and the <hi>White-Horſe.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>E. L.</hi> by <hi>John Gain,</hi> and are to be Sold by Mrs. <hi>Andrews</hi> in <hi>Lambs-Chappel,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
