<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The examination and tryall of Margaret Fell and George Fox (at the severall assizes held at Lancaster the 14th and 16th days of the first moneth, 1663, and the 29th of the 6th moneth, 1664) for their obedience to Christs command who saith, swear not at all also something in answer to Bishop Lancelot Andrews sermon concerning swearing.</title>
            <author>Fox, Margaret Askew Fell, 1614-1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-01">2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38972</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3710</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20823</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12117593</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12117593</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54376</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A38972)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54376)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 66:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The examination and tryall of Margaret Fell and George Fox (at the severall assizes held at Lancaster the 14th and 16th days of the first moneth, 1663, and the 29th of the 6th moneth, 1664) for their obedience to Christs command who saith, swear not at all also something in answer to Bishop Lancelot Andrews sermon concerning swearing.</title>
                  <author>Fox, Margaret Askew Fell, 1614-1702.</author>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Pages 3-6 are supplied in manuscript.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Andrewes, Lancelot, 1555-1626.</term>
               <term>Trials --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2000-00</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2001-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2001-09</date>
            <label>TCP Staff (Michigan)</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2001-09</date>
            <label>TCP Staff (Michigan)</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2001-11</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54376:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54376:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE EXAMINATION AND TRYALL OF <hi>Margaret Fell</hi> and <hi>George Fox</hi> (at the severall Assizes held at <hi>LAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CASTER</hi> the 14th and 16th days of the First Moneth 1663. And the 29th of the 6th Moneth 1664.) For their Obedience to Christs Command who saith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ALSO Something in Answear to Bishop <hi>Lancelot Andrews</hi> Sermon Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning SWEARING.</p>
            <p>Thus have you made the Commandment of God of none Effect by your Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Mat. 15. 6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1664.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:54376:2"/>
            <gap reason="replacement" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page supplied later〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:54376:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="replacement" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page supplied later〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:54376:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="replacement" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page supplied later〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:54376:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="replacement" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page supplied later〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:54376:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:54376:4"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:54376:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:54376:5"/>
            <p>owe Allegiance and obedience to the King of Kings Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, who hath commanded me not to swear at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> That is no answer, will you take the oa<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h or will you not take it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M. F.</hi> I say I owe Allegiance and obedience unto Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, who commands me not to swear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> I say unto you thats no answer, will you take it or will you not take it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M. F.</hi> If you should ask me never so often, I must answer to you the reason why I cannot take it, is because Christ Jesus hath commanded me not to swear at all, I owe my Allegiance and obedience unto him.</p>
            <p>Then one of the Justices that committed her, said, Mrs. <hi>Fell</hi> you may with a good Conscience. (if you cannot take the Oath) put in security that you may have no more meetings at your house.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M. F.</hi> Wilt thou make that good, that I may with a safe Conscience make an engagement to forbear meetings, for fear of losing my Liberty and Estate; wilt not thou and you all here judge of me that it was for saving my Estate and Liberty that I did it, and do I not in this deny my testimony; and would not this defile my Conscience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> This is no answer, will you take the Oath? we must not spend time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M. F.</hi> I never took an Oath in my life, I have spent my days thus far, and I never took an Oath, I own Allegiance to the King as he is King of <hi>England,</hi> but Christ Jesus is King of my Conscience — Then the Clerk held out the Book and bid her pull off her Glove and lay her hand on the book.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M. F.</hi> I never laid my hand on the book to swear in all my life, and I never was at this Assize before, I was bred and born in this County and have led my life in it, and I was never at an Assize before this time, and I bless the Lord that I am here this day upon this account, to bear testimony to the truth. — Then they asked her if she would have the Oath read, she answered, I do not care if I never hear an Oath read, for the Land mourns because of Oaths.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> Then the Judge cryed take her away, then thy took her ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villy away, and asked her if she would give security that she would have no more meetings.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:54376:6"/>
               <hi>M. F.</hi> Nay, I can give no such security, I have spoken e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for that.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>George Fox</hi> was called before Judge <hi>Twisden,</hi> being a Prisoner the Goaler brought him in.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> What do you come into the Court with your Hat on, and then the Goaler took it off.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G. F.</hi> Peace be amongst you all, (and said) the Hat was not the honour that came down from God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> Will you take the Oath of Allegiance <hi>George Fox.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>G. F.</hi> I never took Oath in my life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> Will you swear or no?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G. F.</hi> Christ commands we must not swear at all, and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle; and whether must I obey God or man judge thee, I put it to thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> I Will not dispute with thee <hi>George Fox,</hi> come read the Oath to him, and so the Oath was read, and when it was read, give him the book said they, and so a man that stood by him held up the book and said lay your hand on the book.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G. F.</hi> Give me the book in my ltand, which set them all a gazing, and as in a hope he would have sworn; then when he got the book in his hand, he held up the book and said, this book commands me not to swear if it be a Bible I will prove it; and he saw it was a Bible, and he held it up, and then they pluckt it forth of his hand again, and cryed will you swear, will you take the Oath of Allegiance yea or nay.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G.</hi> F. My Allegiance lies not in Oaths, but in truth and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness, for I honour all men, much more the King; but Christ saith I must not swear, the great Propher, the Saviour of the world, and the Judge of the world, and thou sayest I must swear, whether must I obey Christ or thee; for it is in tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of Conscience that I do not swear, in obedience to the command of Christ and the Apostle, and for his sake I suffer, and in obedience to his commands do I stand this day; and we have the word of a King for tender Consciences, besides his Speeches and Declarations at <hi>Breda;</hi> and dost thou own the King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> Yes, I own the King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G.</hi> F. Then why dost not thou own his Speeches and Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54376:6"/>
concerning tender Consciences, to the which he reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing but <hi>George</hi> said it is in obedience to Christ the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the world, the Judge of the world, before whose judgment seat all men must be brought, that I do not swear, and am a man of a tender Conscience, and then the Judge stood up.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> I will not be afraid of thee, thou speaks so loud thy voice drowns mine and the Courts, I must call for three or four cryers to drown thy voice, thou hast good Lung.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G. F.</hi> I am a Prisoner here this day for the Lord Jesus, that made heaven and earth, and for his sake do we suffer, and for him do I stand this day, and if my voice were five times lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, yet should I sound it out and lift it up for Christs sake, for whose cause I stand this day before your Judgment-seat, in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to Christs commands, who commands not to swear, before whose Judgment-seat you must all be brought, and give an account.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> Sirrah will you take the Oath.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G.</hi> F. I am none of thy Sirrah, I am no Sirrah, I am a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, art thou a Judge and sits there to give names to Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, thou ought not to give names to Prisoners.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> I am a Christian too.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G.</hi> F. Then do Christian works.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> Sirrah thou thinkest to frighten me with thy words, and looked aside, <hi>I</hi> am saying so again,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G.</hi> F. I speak in love to thee, that doth not become a Judge, thou oughtest to instruct a Prisoner of the Law and Scriptures if he be ignorant and out of the way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge. George Fox, I</hi> speak in love to thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G.</hi> F. Love gives no names.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> Wilt thou swear, wilt thou take the oath yea or nay.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G.</hi> F. As I said before, whether must I obey God or man judge ye, Christ commands not to swear, and if thou, or ye, or any Minister, or Priest here will prove that ever Christ or his Apostles after they had forbidden swearing, commanded men should swear, I will swear, and several Priests being there, yet not one did appear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge. George Fox</hi> will you swear or no.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G.</hi> F. It is in obedience to Christs commands I do not swear,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54376:7"/>
and for his sake we suffer, and you are sensible enough of swearers, how they first swear one way then another, and if I could swear any Oath at all upon any occasion, I should take that, but it is not denying Oaths upon some occasion, but all Oaths according to Christs Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge. I</hi> am a servant to the King, and the King sent me not to dispute, but he sent me to put his Laws in execution, wilt thou swear? tender the Oath of allegiance to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G.</hi> F. If thou love the King, why dost thou break his word, and not own his Declarations and Speeches to tender Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences from <hi>Breda,</hi> for I am a man of a tender Conscience, for in obedience to Christs commands I am not to swear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> Then you will not swear, take him Goaler.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G.</hi> F. It is for Christs sake I cannot swear, in obedience to his commands I suffer, and so the Lord forgive you all.</p>
            <p>And so the mighty power of the Lord God was over all.</p>
            <p>The appearance of M. F. The second time being the 16th day of the aforementioned moneth 1663/4.</p>
            <p>Jud. 1. Mrs. <hi>Fell</hi> you stand here indicted by the Statute, because you will not take the Oath of Allegiance, and I am here to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form you what the Law provides for you in such a case, <hi>viz.</hi> First, if you confess to the indictment the Judgment of a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire is to pass upon you, Secondly, if you plead you have liberty to Traverse. Thirdly, if you stand mute and say no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, Judgement will be passed against you, so see what you will chuse of those three ways.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M.</hi> F. I am altogether ignorant of these things, for I had never the like occasion, so I desire to be informed by thee, which of them is the best for me, for I do not know, and so se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral about the Court cryed, Traveise, traverse.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> If you will be advised by me put in your Traverse, and so you have liberty untill the next Assizes to answer your indictment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M.</hi> F. I had rather according to thy own proposal have a Process, that I might have liberty untill the next Assize, and then to put in a Traverse.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> Your Traverse is a Process.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M.</hi> F. May not I have a Process, and put in my Traverse the next Assizes, I am informed that was the thing that thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54376:7"/>
that I should have.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> You shall have it.</p>
            <p>M. F. That is all I desire. — Then a Clerk of the Crown Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice stood up and whispered to the Judge and said it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Law, and said I must put in my Traverse now.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge. I</hi> would do you all the favour <hi>I</hi> can, but you must enter your Traverse now.</p>
            <p>M. F. I acknowledge thy favour and mercy, for thou hast shewn more mercy then my Neighbours hath done, and I see what thou hast done for me, and what my Neighbours have done against me; and I know very well how to make a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction, for they who have done this against me they have no reason for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> I have done you no wrong, I found you here.</p>
            <p>M. F. I had not been here but by my Neighbours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> What say you, are you willing to Traverse.</p>
            <p>M. F. If I may not be permitted to have that which I desire (that is) longer time, I must be willing to Traverse till the next Assizes, and that upon this account, that I have something to inform thee of, which I did not speak on the last time when I was brought before thee: The Justices which committed me, they told me they had express order from above, but they did not shew me the order, neither indeed did I ask them for it, but I heard since that they have given it out in the Country that they had an order from the Counsel, others said they had an order from the King. — The Sheriff said there was express or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and also Justice <hi>Fleeming</hi> said there was an order from the King and the Counsel, so the Country is incensed that I am some great enemy to the King, so I desire that I may have this order read, that I may know what my offence is that I may clear my self.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge. I</hi> will tell you what that order is, we have express order from the King to put all Statutes and Laws in execution, not only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst you, but all other people, and against Papists if they be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of.</p>
            <p>M. F. Will that order give the Justices of Peace power to fetch me from my own house, to tender me the Oath.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> Mrs. we are all in love, if they had an order believe they had one.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:54376:8"/>M. F. If they have one let them shew it, and then I can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> Come, come, enter the Traverse.</p>
            <p>M. F. I had rather have had more time, that I might have informed the King concerning these things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> You may inform the King in half a years time, so now let us have your friend called up.</p>
            <p>Then after she was gone down, the Judge called her back again and said, if you will put in Bail you may go home, and have your liberty till the next Assizes, but you must not have such frequent meetings.</p>
            <p>M. F. I will rather lie where I am, for as, I told you before, I must keep my Conscience clear for that I suffer.</p>
            <p>The 16th day of the same moneth G. F. Was brought before the Judge the second time, where he was a little oftended at his Hat, being the last morning before he was to depart away, and not many people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> The Judge he read a Paper to him which was, whether he would submit, stand mute, or Traverse, and so have judgment past; he spake these and many more words so very sofily and in baste, that <hi>G. F.</hi> Could not tell what he said.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G.</hi> F. Desired it might be Traversed and Tryed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> Take him away, then I will have no more with him, take him away.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G.</hi> F. Well live in the fear of God and do Justice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> Why, have I not done you Justice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G.</hi> F. That which thou hast done hath been against the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Christ.</p>
            <p>This with much more was spoken which could not be Collected.</p>
            <p>And then G. F. was called up.</p>
            <p>The 29th day of the 6th moneth in the year 1664.</p>
            <p>At the Assizes holden at <hi>Lancaster,</hi> M. F. Brought to the Bar, the Indictment read to the Judge, come will you take the Oath.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M.</hi> F. There is a Clause in the Indictment, that the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Wardens informed of something which seemeth, that that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54376:8"/>
should be the ground or first occasion of this Indictment, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to know what that Information was, and what the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression was by which I come under this Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> Mistress, we are not to despute that, you are here indicted, and you are here to answer, and to plead to your indictment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M.</hi> F. I am first to seek out the ground and the cause where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am indicted, you have no law against me except I be a trangressour, the law is made for the lawless and trangressours, and except I be a transgressour ye have no law against me, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought you to have indicted me, for being that the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Wardens did inform, my question is, what matter of fact they did inform of, for I was sent for from my own house, from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst my Children and Family, when I was about my out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward occasions, when I was in no meeting, neither was it a meeting day; therefore I desire to know what this first foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation or matter of Fact was, for there is no law against the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent and righteous, and if I be a transgressour let me know wherein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> You say well, the Law is made for transgressours, but Mistress do you go to Church?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M.</hi> F. I do go to Church, Judge, what Church, M. F. To the Church of Christ.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> But do you go to Church amongst other people, ye know what I mean.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M.</hi> F. What dost thou call a Church the house or the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the house ye all know is Wood and Stone, but if thou call the people a Church, to that I shall answer; as for the Church of <hi>England</hi> that now is, I was gathered unto the Lords truth, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which I now stand a witness before this Church was a Church, I was separated from the general worship of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when there was another set up then that which is now, and was persecuted by that power that then was, and suffered much hardship, and would you have us now to deny our faith and our principles which we have suffered for so many years; and would you now have us to turn from that which we have born witness of so many years, and turn to your Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to our Conscience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> We spend time about those things, come to the matter in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54376:9"/>
hand, what say ye to the Oath and to the indictment?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M.</hi> F. I say this to the Oath, as I have said in this place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now, Christ Jesus hath commanded me not to swear at all, and that is the only cause and no other; the righteous judge of heaven and earth knoweth, before whose throne and justice ye must all appear one day, and his eyes sees us all and beholds us all at this present, and he hears and sees all our words and actions; and therefore every one ought to be serious, for the place of judgment is weighty, and this I do testisie unto you here, where the Lords eye beholds us all, that for the matter or substance of the Oath, and the end for which it was intended; I do own one part and denies the other, that is to say, I do own truth and faithfulness and obedrence to the King, and all his just and lawful demands and commands; I do also deny all plotting, contrivings against the King, and all Popish Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy and Conspiracy, and I can no more transgress against King <hi>Charles</hi> in these things, then I can disobey Christ Jesus his commands, and by the same power and vertue of the same word, which hath commanded me not to swear at all, the same doth bind me in my Conscience, that I can neither plot nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive against the King, nor do him nor no man upon the earth any wrong; and I do not deny this Oath only because it is the Oath of Allegiance, but I deny it because it is an Oath, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause Christ Jesus hath said I shall not swear at all, neither by heaven, nor by earth, nor any other Oath; and if I might gain the whole world for swearing an Oath I could not, and what ever I have to lose this day for not swearing of an Oath, I am willing to offer it up.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> What say you to the indictment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M.</hi> F. What should I say, I am clear and innocent of the wronging any man upon the earth as my little Child that stands by me here, and if any here have any thing to lay to my Charge, let them come down and testifie it here before ye all; and if I be clear and innocent you have no law against me: Then Colonel <hi>Kirby</hi> and the Sheriff whispered to the Judge, and I looked up and spoke to Colonel <hi>Kirby,</hi> and said let us have no whispering, I will not have so many Judges one of one side, and another of another, here is one Judge that is to be judge,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54376:9"/>
and the judge said no no I will not hear them; and then I cals<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Colonel <hi>Kirby,</hi> and said if thou have any thing to lay to my charge, or to speak against me come come down here and testifie against me, and I said the judge represents the Kings person and his power, and I own that.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge.</hi> Jury take notice she doth not take the Oath.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M.</hi> F. This matter is weighty to me, whatsoever it is to you upon many accounts, and I would have the Jury to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it, and to consider seriously what they are going to do; for I stand here before you upon the account of the loss of my Liberty and my Estate.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I stand here in obeying Christs commands, and so keeping my Conscience clear, which if I obey this law and King <hi>Charles</hi> commands I defile my Conscience and transgresseth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Christ Jesus, who is the king of my Conscience, and the cause and controversie in this matter, that you all are here to judge of this day, is betwixt Christ Jesus and King <hi>Charles;</hi> and I am his servant and witness this day, and this is his cause, and whatsoever I suffer it is for him, and so let him plead my cause when he pleafeth.</p>
            <p>And the Judge said to the Jury are ye all agreed have ye found it, and they said for the King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M.</hi> F. Then spoke to the Judge, and said, I have counsel to plead to my indictment, and he said he would clear them after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in arrest of judgment; so the Court broke up that time, and after Dinner when they came again, they intended to have called us at the first, and they had called G. F. out and was call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of me, and I stepped up to the Bar and desired the Judge that he would give us time till the next morning to bring in our Reast of Judgment, and the Judge said at the first we should and I was stepping down to go my way, and the Judge called me back again, and said Mistress <hi>Fell</hi> you wrote to me concerning your Prisons that they are bad and rains in, and are not fit for people to lie in, and I answered, the Sheriff doth know and hath been told of it several times; and now it is raining if you will send to see at this present, you may see whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be fit for people to lie in or no; and Colonel <hi>Kirby</hi> stood up and spoke to the Judge to excuse the Sheriff, and the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54376:10"/>
badness of the room, and I spoke to him and said if you were to lie in it your selves you would think it hard, but your minds is only in cruelty to commit others, as <hi>William Kirby</hi> here hath done, who hath committed ten of our friends, and put them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a cold room where there was nothing but bare boards to lie on, where they have laid several nights, some of them old an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient men above threescore years of Age, and known to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest men in their Country where they live, and when <hi>William Kirby</hi> was asked why they might not have liberty to shift for themselves for beds, he answered and said they were to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to prison, but not to provide Prisons for them; and we asked him who should do it then, and he said the King: And then the Judge spoke to him and said they should not do so, they should let them have Prisons fit for men, with several more such like words; and then at that time we were retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to our Chambers again, the next day we were called about the 10th hour, and I stood up to the Bar, and said I had Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel there and named them that the Judge might assign them to speak, and I said I had two or three words to speak before them, and I said I did see all sorts of Prisoners that did appear before the Judge received mercy, what the Law would afford them; but we desired only to receive Justice and Law, and the Judge said what are we hear for else; so I stepped down and the Lawyers spoke and shewed the Judge severall errours, and defects, and places of contradiction, and confusion in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment; at which the Judge seemed to give ear to some of them, others he seemed to wave, but he made a pause and a stop, and seemed dissatisfied, and then called G. F. and so then when he came to plead, and bringing that by which his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment was quite quenched, and then they put the Oath to G. F. Again the Judge spoke to the Lawyers, and said he would consider of those particulars they had spoken to, and he would speak to his Brother <hi>Twisden</hi> before he passed Judgment upon me; but if I do pass Judgment you may have a Writ of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and the Lawyers answered him again, will you pass a erroneous Judgment my Lord, so after they had called the Grand Jury, and tendered G. F. the Oath again, they retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned us to our Chambers, and when they had drawn another
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54376:10"/>
indictment of G. F. and found it, they called us again in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon, and G. F. pleaded to his indictment and entred his Traverse, when he had done the Judge spoke to me and said, if such a word had been in, which was not in mine, but it was in G. Fs. (and yet it was neither of those words, by which his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment was quashed;) but if that had been in mine he said he would not have passed sentence, but being that it was not there he passed sentence of Premunire, then I stood up and told him that he had said to my Counsel, that I might have a Writ of Errour to reverse it, he said I should have what the Law would afford me, so I said the Lord forgive thee for what thou hast done, and this Law was made for Popish Recusants, but ye pass sentence but on few of them.</p>
            <p>Margaret Fell.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The last Assizes holden at <hi>Lancaster</hi> the 29th of the 6th Moneth 1664.</head>
            <p>I <hi>George Fox</hi> being called before the Judge, was put amongst the Fellons and Murtherers, and there stood amongst them above two hours, the people, and the Justices, and Judge gazing upon me; and there they tryed many things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Judge, and they called me to the Bar, and then the Judge causted me to be brought, and he then caused the Jury to be called, and then he askt the Justices whether they had tendered me the Oath at the Sessions, and they said they had, and the Judge caused the book to be given to the Justices for them to swear, they tendered me the Oath according to the indictment, and some of them would have refused, and the Judge said he would do it to take away occasion, that there might be no occasion; and when the Justices and Jury was sworn, the Judge askt me whether I had not refused to take the Oath the last Assize, and I said I never took an Oath in my life, and Christ the Saviour and Judge of the world saith swear not at all; and the Judge askt me whether or no I had not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused to take the Oath the last Assizes, and I answered, the words that I said to them was, That if they could prove either
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54376:11"/>
Priest, or Teacher, or Justices, that after Christ and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles had forbidden swearing, that afterwards they commanded that men should swear, I would swear.</p>
            <p>The Judge said he was not at that time to dispute whether it was lawful to swear, but to enquire whether or no I did refuse to take the Oath.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Georg.</hi> Those things as concernining plotting and the Popes forreign powers, &amp;c. Contained in that Oath I utterly deny.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Judge.</hi> Said, I said well in that.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>George.</hi> I said to them again as before, that if they could prove that after Christ and the Apostle forbad swearing, that again they commanded to swear, I would swear, but Christ and the Apostle commanded not to swear, therefore I should shew forth Christianity, for I am a Christian.</p>
            <p>The Judge askt me again, whether I had denyed the Oath, what did I say?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>George.</hi> What would thou have me to say, I have told thee before what I have said.</p>
            <p>The Judge askt me if I would have those men to swear that I had taken the Oath.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Geo.</hi> Would thou have those men to swear that I have refused to take the Oath, at which the Court burst out into laughter; I asked them if this Court was a Play-house, where is Gravity, and Sobriety, for that did not become them, and so the indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being read, I told the Judge I had something to speak to it; &amp; I askt him whether all the Oath was not to be put into the indictment, and he said yes, why then said I here is (pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be derived and his Heirs and Successours) left out, and I askt him whether the Oath was to be put to the Kings Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and he said yes.</p>
            <p>I answered, why am not I put in as a Subject, but the word (Subject) left out of the indictment which is in the Oath, and so makes it not the same Oath, Jury take notice of it, but the Judge said I must speak to the Jury, at which words the Judge read the Oath, and found it was as I had said, so he stood up and said he could put the Oath to me, or any man in the Court, and so they began to be disturbed in themselves also the Justices;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54376:11"/>
And there began to be a murmuring against the Clerks, and the Judge he got up and began to cover the errour, so I askt whether the last eleventh day of <hi>January</hi> the Sessions was kept at <hi>Lancaster,</hi> which they call Munday, and whether or no the Sessions was not on that they call Tuesday the twelfth of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary,</hi> all people take your Almanacks, and see whether any Oath was tendred, G. F. the 11th of <hi>January,</hi> whether the Ses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions was not upon the 12th and the Clerks and people lookt their Almanacks, and saw it was the 12th and the Judge askt whether the 11th was not the first of the Sessions, and they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered there was but one day, and it was the 12th and the Judge said then it was a great mistake; and then all the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices was struck, and some of them could have found in their hearts to have gone off, and said they had done it on purpose, and said what Clerk did it, and a great stir was amongst them. and then I spoke to the Jury how that they could not bring me in guilty according to that indictment, and the Judge said I must not speak to the Jury, but he would speak to them, and said they might bring me in guilty I denying the Oath; then I said what should you do with a form then, and do not go ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to it, then you may throw the form away, and then I told the Jury that it lay upon their Consciences as they would answer the Lord God before his Judgment-seat, before whom all must be brought, and so the Judge spoke to me, and said he would hear me afterwards any reasons that I could alledge wherefore he should not give Judgment against me, and so he spoke to the Jury, and I bid him do me Justice and do Justice, and so the Jury brought in for the King guilty.</p>
            <p>And I told them then the Justices had forsworn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves and the Jury both. and so they had small cause to laugh as they did a little before, and to say I was mad, and before I had brought forth my reasons I stood a little while, and the Judge said he cannot dispute, but then the people said he is too cunning for them all, after I had brought forth my reasons, how contrary to their own indictment they had done and sworn, and brought me in guilty; Oh the envy, and rage, and malice, that was among them against me and lightness, but the Lord confounded it all, that abundance of it was slain, and so I
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54376:12"/>
told them I was no Lawyer, and the Judge said he would hear me what I could alledge before he did give Judgment, and so I cryed all people might see how they had forsworn themselves, and gone contrary to their own indictment, and so their envy and malice was wonderfully stopt, and so persently M. <hi>Fell</hi> was called, who had a great deal of good service amongst them, and so the Court broke up near the second hour, many more words was spoken concerning the truth.</p>
            <p>And so in the afternoon we were brought up to have sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence passed upon us, and so M. <hi>Fell</hi> desired that Judgment and sentence might be deferred till the next morning and we desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red nothing but law and justice at his hands, for thieves had mercy, and I desired the Judge to send some to see my prison being so bad, they would put no creature they had in it, it was so windy and rainy, and I told him that Colonel <hi>Kirby</hi> who was then on the Bench said I should be lockt up, and no flesh alive should come at me, and most of the Gentry of the Country be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gathered together, expecting to hear the sentence, but they were crost that time, so I was had away to my prison, and some Justices with Colonel <hi>Kirby</hi> went up to see it, and when they came up in it they durst scarcely go in it, it was so bad, rainy, and windy, and the badness of the floor, and others that came up said it was a Jakes house, I being removed out of the prison which I was in formerly, and so Col. <hi>Kirby</hi> said I should be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from that place ere long, that I should be sent unto some fecurer place, for he spake to the Judge in the Court, saying, he knew that the Justices would joyn with him, but the Judge said after I have past sentence I will leave him to the Jaylor and how I was not a fit man to be converst with, none should con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse with me, and all the noise amongst the people was that I should be Transported and so the next day towards the 11th hour we was called forth again to hear the sentence and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but M. <hi>Fell</hi> was called first before me to the Bar, and there was some Counsellours pleaded, and found many errours in her indectment, and so she was taken by, after the Judge had acknowledged them, and then the Judge askt what they could say to mine, and I was willing to let no man plead for me, but to speak to it my self and though M. <hi>Fell</hi> had some that plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54376:12"/>
for her, yet she spoke as much her self as she would, and though they had the most envy against me, yet the most gross errours was found in mine, and before I came to the Bar I was moved to pray, that the Lord would confound their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and envy, and set his truth over all, and exalt his seed; the thundering voice answered I have glorified thee, and will glorifie thee again, and I was so filled full of glory, that my head and ears was filled full of it; and that when the Trumpets sounded &amp; the judges came up again, they all appeared as dead men under me, and so when I was to answer to the errours of the indictment, seeing that all the Oath as he said himself was to be in, I told him there was many words of the Oath left out, which was (pretended to be derived, and his Heirs and Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sours) and I bid them look the Oath and look the indictment, and they might see it, aud they did, and found it according to my words; and I askt them whether the last Assizes holden at <hi>Lancaster</hi> was in the 15th year of the King, which was the 10th day of <hi>March,</hi> and they said nay it was the 16th year; then said I look your indictment, and see whether or no it is not the 15th year, and then they were all of a fret both Judge and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices, for it was the 15th in the indictment; then the Judge bid them look whether M. <hi>Fells</hi> was so or no, and it was not so: I told them I had something else to speak concerning the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment, but they said nay, I had spoken enough, so the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment was thrown out, so I told them that they had small cause to laugh as they had done a little before, for they might see how the Justices and the Jury was sorsworn men, and so I bid him do me justice, and he said I should have law, and the Judge said I was clear from all the former, and he started up in a rage and said but he would proffer the Oath to me again; I told him they had example enough for swearers and false swearers, both Justices and Jury yesterday before their faces, for I saw be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mine eyes both Justices and Jury had forsworn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, who heard the indictment, and so he askt me whether I would take the Oath, I bid him do me justice for my false im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisonment all this while. for what had I been prisoner all this while for, for I ought to be at liberty, then he said I was at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, but I will put the Oath to you again: Then I turned
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54376:13"/>
me about, and cryed all people take notice this is a snare, and all was mighty quiet, and all people was struck and astonisht, and he caused the Grand-Jury to be called, for he had called them before when I was there, when he saw they would be overthrown, and the Jury would fain have been dismist, but he told them he could not dismiss them, for he had business for them, and they might be ready when he called them, and I felt his intent, that if I was freed he would come on again, so I lookt him in the face, and he was judged in himself, for he saw that I saw him, so he caused the Oath to be read to me again, and caused the Jury to be called, and then when the Oath was read he askt me whether I would take the Oath or no, and the Jury standing by, I told him I never took Oath in my life, and he bid them give me the book and I bid them give it me in my hand and I opened it, and he bid me swear, and I told him the book bid swear not at all, again he bid me swear, and I told him the book said I should not swear, and held it open to them, and said by the book I would prove that men should not swear.</p>
            <p>And if they would prove after Christ and the Apostle had forbidden swearing, that afterwards they commanded to swear, then I would swear, for I was a man of a tender Conscience; and if they had any sense of a tender Conscience they would consider this, and the Judge askt me whether I would take the Oath, and bid them give me the book again, I told them ye give me the book to swear, and the book saith I should not swear at all; and so you may prison the book, the Judge said he would imprison <hi>George Fox,</hi> I answered nay, you may prison the book, which saith swear not at all, and the Sheriff and the Judge said the Angel swore in the Revelations, I answered, I bring forth my first begotten Son into the world saith God, let all the Angels in heaven worship him, who saith swear not at all, and the Judge said often he would not dispute, and so then I spoke much to the Jury how that it was for Christs sake, that which I did; and therefore none of them to act contrary to that of God in their Consciences, for before his Judgment-seat they must all be brought, and for all those things contained in the Oath, as plots and persecuting about Religion, and the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54376:13"/>
Popes power, &amp;c. I denyed them in my heart, and I am a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, and shall shew forth Christianity this day, and it is for Christs sake that I stand for it is <hi>Lotish shabim be Coldabor,</hi> and they all gazed, and there was a great calm, and they took me away, but there was many more words both to the Jury and to them.</p>
            <p>Then in the afternoon we was called again, where I stood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the thieves a pretty while with my Hat on, at the last the Goaler took it off, and when I was called to the Bar the Jury brought in guilty for the King, and the Judge askt me what I could say for my self. I bid them read the indictment, I would not answer to that I did not hear, and as they read, the Judge bid them take heed it was not false again, and they read it so amazedly, that when they spoke to me I did scarcely under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand what they said, and the Judge askt me what I would plead, I told them I desired to have a Copy of that indictment, and to have some time to answer to it, for the last I had but lately, and never heard it read but once, and then in the Court, and so the Judge askt me what time I would have, and I said till the next Assizes, and the Judge said I should, then he askt again what I would plead, I told him I was not guilty at all of denying Swearing, Swearing obstinately and wilfully, and those things contained in the Oath as Jesuitical plots, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign powers, &amp;c. I utterly denyed them, and he said I said well in that, and the Judge said the King was sworn, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was sworn, and the Justices and he was sworn, and the law was upheld by Oaths; I told them they had sufficient ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of mens swearing, had not the Justices and Jury for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sworn themselves, and had they not read the book of Martyrs, how many of the Martyrs suffered because they could not swear, both in the ten persecutions, and in <hi>Bonners</hi> days, and the Judge said I would the Laws were otherwise, then I said our yea is yea, and our nay nay all along; and if we transgress our yea and nay let us suffer as they do that do break an Oath, and so to deny swearing is not a new thing in obedience to Christs command, and I said this we had sent to the King who said it was reasonable, and so after several more words I was had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to my Chamber being (as I was before) to answer to the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54376:14"/>
indictment, and so the truth and power of the Lord God was glorious over all, and many spirits was crost grievously in their envy and malice.</p>
            <p>There was many things spoken both to Judge, Jury; and People, which were too large to mention.</p>
            <p>And so the Judge told <hi>Margaret Fell</hi> her Sentence, and I lie upon a new indictment.</p>
            <p>G. F.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Something in Answer to Bishop <hi>Lancelot Andrews</hi> Sermon concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Swearing, being one of his Sermons upon the Third Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the place that he trea<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s upon is in Jer. the 4th the words are these: <hi>And thou shalt swear the Lord liveth in Truth, in Judgment, and Righteousness.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ANd further, to prove the lawfulness of swearing, he brings <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.13. <hi>Isa.</hi> 45.23. — <hi>Psal.</hi> 63. and last ver. and how <hi>Abraham</hi> sware. <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.24. and <hi>Isack</hi> sware, <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.31. and <hi>Jacob</hi> sware. 31.33. and <hi>Abrahams</hi> servant sware, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.24. and <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.3. &amp; <hi>Numb</hi> 30.3. Which saith he, an Oath is to the lifting up of a burthen as to the entring of a Bond.</p>
            <p>First, He saith an Oath is to be used in solemn matters, and he brings these Scriptures following out of the Old Testament to prove it, <hi>Psal.</hi> 144.8. <hi>Numb.</hi> 30.3. <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.106. <hi>Psal.</hi> 15.15. <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.36,9. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 17.12. <hi>Psal.</hi> 110.4. <hi>Psal.</hi> 89.35. <hi>Kings</hi> 1.22,16. <hi>Lev.</hi> 5.1.1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.15. <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.3 &amp; 47.29.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For the nature of an Oath he quotes 119.<hi>Psal.</hi> 9 <hi>ver.</hi> &amp; <hi>Numb.</hi> 10. and last ver.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, He speaks of the manner of an Oath, and produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth for Confirmation these Scriptures following, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.8. <hi>Numk.</hi> 5.18 <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.5. <hi>Kings</hi> 1.8,31. <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.8. — <hi>Neh.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Numb.</hi> 5.19 <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.24. <hi>Judg.</hi> 17.2. <hi>Lev.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.3,27. <hi>Kings</hi> 1.22,16. <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.33. <hi>Kings</hi> 1.1.43. <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.8.</p>
            <p>First, As for all the above mentioned Scriptures which he hath quoted in the time of the Law, and before the Law, and the Angels swearing in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> do not prove that Christians may swear; and we do grant ye the time before the Law men
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54376:14"/>
did swear, and also the Angel swore, <hi>But Christ is come the first begotten whom God hath brought forth into the world,</hi> and saith, <hi>Let all the Angels worship him; And this is my beloved Son hear ye him</hi> saith God: And Christ saith how that in the old time men was to perform their Oaths to the Lord, these were their true oaths which they were to perform and they were not to swear falsly, but to perform their Oath to the Lord; so here Christ in his Doctrine lets them see the false oaths and the true oaths in the old time, and that was the true oath to swear by the Lord, and to swear the <hi>Lord liveth:</hi> And every tongue should swear, and <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Isaack,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Joseph,</hi> and the Prophets sware, but Christ is the end of the Prophets, and doth fulfil the Law, &amp; reigns over the house of <hi>Jacob,</hi> &amp; <hi>Joseph,</hi> &amp; before <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was, I <hi>am saith Christ;</hi> And so though they sware before the law and under the law, and the Angel in the <hi>Revelations</hi> sware, &amp; the Angel that sware sware by the Lord as the oath was in the time of the Law, and before the law, and this was the oath that Christ minds them on in his Doctrine here, that they were to perform to the Lord, yet now mark his Doctrine, which he himself lays down and commands, <hi>But I say unto you now swear not at all,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Matthew</hi> 5.24. In the Hebrew language it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>But let your Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation be yea, yea, nay, nay, whatsoever is more then these cometh of evil;</hi> in the Hebrew its <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> And further proof, see how <hi>Jamse</hi> lived in the same Doctrine and practice, and held it forth to the 12 tribes which was the Jews, who had the oath of God, and was to swear in the time of the law; see his general Epistle in the 5th Chap. and also speaking in the second Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of such as drove them before the Judgment-seat, but in the 5th Chapter this is his command above all things, <hi>My brethren swear not at all, neither by heaven nor by the earth,</hi> in the Greek its <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> This you may call creatures or made things: But mark <hi>James</hi> goes further, and faith <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> — nor by any other oath, but let your <hi>yea,</hi> be <hi>yea,</hi> and your <hi>nay,</hi> be <hi>nay, lest you fall into Condemnation,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:54376:15"/>Mark the danger now, and whether we have not ground e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in the fear of the Lord God to obey Christs commands and the Apostles Doctrines, <hi>Lest we fall into condemnation an<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> evil,</hi> we have set some words down in the Greek tongue, that those it most concerns may see the original, but the Spirit is ours, and the commands of Christ, and the Apostles doctrine to be obeyed in what tongue soever it be written in, but we would Query the thing with any, whether the Apostle <hi>James</hi> who wrote to Jews and not to Gentiles, did not write in the Hebrew tongue and not in Greek, and if so, then his words to them in this particular are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Pricks, Points, and Accents, and the plain and naked interpretation of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew word we have left for them it most concerns to adde.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As for all the Scriptures he brings against rash swearing, and false swearing, it would rejoyce our hearts to have the Priests do that, and the Magistrates punish it for a cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Railing Priests come the other day and sware before our faces lightly and vainly, and justifyed it when they had done; it would become Magistrates and them better if they did not suffer an oath to be heard in the Towns, or Markets, or Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houses, or Streets, you that have power, not to suffer those things; for you would have work enough to restrain such things, and such persons, and not to fall upon the innocent which in obedience to Christs commands and the Apostles do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine cannot swear for Conscience sake: For imprisoning such emboldens people to swear, and would it not be better for people, and would ye not shew forth more Christianity to keep to yea and to nay in all their Communications according to Christs commands and the Apostles doctrine.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, There was Bond in the old time by oath, but Christ he looses from the Bonds and brings to peace and liberty, and makes free, and saith, <hi>swear not at all:</hi> And so though we be in outward Bonds, it is for Christ Jesus sake, and the word of God is not bound.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, And though <hi>Moses</hi> sware in the time of the law,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54376:15"/>
and <hi>Abrahams</hi> servants sware, yet Christ the Son saith, <hi>swear not at all</hi> and we are to hear him in all things the great Prophet.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, And as for the ceremonies of the oaths, Christ is the substance of all ceremonies, that saith, <hi>swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, And though <hi>David</hi> sware, he that <hi>David</hi> called Lord saith, <hi>swear not at all,</hi> and he is upon his Throne.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, And where he saith, thou shall swear by the Lord, and swear the Lord liveth, they were not to swear by them that were no Gods, nor creatures, nor by the earth, nor by heaven, or by the hand, or by <hi>Jerusalem;</hi> now what are the oaths that all Christendom swears, both Papists and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants? whether it be the oath that was amongst the Jews, and whether or no they practise the oath that they do now, and whether or no is that ceremony now used, if not, when did God alter it; where about in Scripture, and in what place of Scripture is it that he sets this way and ceremony of swearing in Christendom, both amongst Papists and Protestants, which is to swear by the book, and by the Evangelists? is this beyond the Jews swearing, by the City, or by Head, or by the Temple which Christ forbid, and not only those oaths, but the oath of God, which the Jews was to swear by, Answer these things.</p>
            <p>Eightly, And as for <hi>Zedekiahs</hi> oath to <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> and <hi>Josephs</hi> oath to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> this was in the time that oaths were to be Performed amongst the Jews and Patriarchs, and what is this to Christs doctrine which forbids oaths, which oaths was before Christ came.</p>
            <p>9thly, And as for the oath of Supremacy &amp; the other, it is to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the King of <hi>Eng.</hi> and Allegiance to him, which things hath been manifest and practised by us, but not by such as sware Allegiance to the Kings father, and swore the one way and the other way, and hast not thou and many of you taken the oath against him, and such as have sworn one while for him, and another while against him; how are they in Allegiance to him that swears one way and another way? and cannot there be in truth and faithfulness Allegiance to the King without swearing? for now how should we stand in Allegiance to Christ if we did not obey his commands the King of Kings <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for he commands us not to swear, but keep to yea
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54376:16"/>
and nay, and one of his great Embassadours to Nations that went with his Message to the twelve tribes saith, <hi>above all things my Brethren swear not at all, lest you fall into condemna<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tenthly, There were two states of oaths, the one was that people was to perform to the Lord and swear, and the other was that God sware by himself concerning his Son Christ Jesus, which when he came who fulfilled Gods oath, he ended the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther oath and saith, <hi>swear not at all,</hi> and calls the first oath the old time; he fulfilled the truth, and let them see how in the time of the law false oaths were forbidden in the old time, and heathenish oaths were forbidden in the time of the law, for they were not to swear by <hi>Baal,</hi> but they were to perform their oaths to the Lord, which Christ saith unto them, <hi>swear not at all,</hi> and so he ended that oath; so there is no oaths before the fall, and there is no oaths in the restauration again by Christ Jesus but yea and nay, according to his doctrine, but amongst <hi>Moses</hi> and the Prophets, and in the old time before <hi>Moses</hi> and the Prophets men did swear, as <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Isaack,</hi> &amp;c. But he the great Prophet is come that is to be heard in all things, and he the oath of God Christ Jesus stands and remains.</p>
            <p>Eleventhly, The Apostles speaking to the Hebrews, swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by a greater which was an end of controversie and strife a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them, he brought this as a similitude, not that the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews should swear, for if he had, he had contradicted <hi>James</hi> which wrote to the twelve tribes his doctrine to them, which were Hebrews, but he brought it as a similitude, that the oath which men swear by the greater ended strife; but God not finding a greater then himself, he sware concerning his Son which is Christ, who ends the strife, who destroys the Devil and his works, the Author of strife; for the oath in the time of the law ended the strife, but we see oaths now adays begins it, and why, the matter is because in Christ Jesus men do not live, who is the peace and Gods oath.</p>
            <p>Twelfthly, Where as the Bishop saith, that they hold in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity that to swear of and by it self considered, is an act for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden no less then to kill &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> In the time of the law they killed and swore, but Christ saith, <hi>swear not at all,</hi> and also he saith, <hi>love enemies;</hi> and how
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54376:16"/>
do these agree to <hi>kill</hi> and to <hi>love enemies,</hi> and love one another, <hi>And if one strike thee on the one cheek turn the other to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this paralleling the Magistrates executing justice upon Malefactors; <hi>As he that sheddeth mans blood, by man shall his blood be shed again:</hi> Is not a paralleling with Christs doctrine, who saith, <hi>swear not at all,</hi> for that may be done by witnesses, without oath, as thou maist read the Scriptures in the old time, when oaths were denyed in the primitive time among the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Christians, who were in Christs doctrine, thou maist read how they did things by witnesses, as the Apostle speaks in the mouth of two or three witnesses, &amp;c. Which place he instances of what was done in the time of the law, which was a statute of judgment among the Jews, <hi>Whosoever killeth any person, the murtherer shall be put to death by the mouth of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses,</hi> &amp;c. But no oaths are mentioned here, <hi>Num.</hi> 35. 30. with <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 28 read that throughout, and also <hi>Deut.</hi> 19. 15. &amp; 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21. 10. &amp;c And many more Scriptures might be alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed which you that have read Scriptures are not ignorant of.</p>
            <p>Now for the practice amongst the Saints, see <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 16. Christ who bids them keep to yea and nay, in that place lays down a practise to be used amongst them in matter of fault and transgression how it should be ended by two or three witnesses, read the words that in the mouth of two or three witnesses every word shall be established, and what dost thou think that he would order them to swear, who had once forbidden it? and read the 8. Chap. of <hi>John</hi> and 17. ver. And we do not find that the witnesses againstChrist that he should speak blasphemy, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 65. That they did swear, and also you may see in <hi>Acts</hi> 6. 11, 12, 13. How they that were hired against <hi>Stephen,</hi> no mention is made of their swearing, moreover you may see in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 1. The Speech of the Apostle amongst the Saints, how he tells them of of his coming unto them in the mouth of two or three witnesses; he doth not tell that he is coming to them with oaths in their mouths, Mark, the Apostle was an Elder and had care of the Churches. — And again the Apostle that writes to <hi>Tim.</hi> a Bishop, an Overseer of the Churches, saith he, against an Elder receive not an accusation, but before two or three witnesses. -Now he doth not say before two or three men
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:54376:17"/>
that swears, for if he had he would have contradicted Christs doctrine and <hi>James,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 19. &amp; 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. Saith the Apostle to <hi>Tim.</hi> the Bishop, <hi>The things that thou hast heard of me amongst many witnesses, the same commit to faithful men who shall be able to teach others also.</hi> Now he received this by witnesses, not by oath, and he was to commit it and not by oaths, and were not these the things that the whole Church came to be ordered by? And this was amongst the Christians in the primitive times when oaths were ended, and many more things might be alledged which were two tedious for you to read.</p>
            <p>Thirteenthly, And whereas he brings that objection of the Anabaptists, which is that it standeth not with Christian profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, but was tollerated as an imperfect thing under the law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> Which objection of theirs we do not own, as we do not own the Bishop for swearing; for it was the way of the Lord, and the way of the Lord was perfect, and the Commandment for swearing was good in it self, untill the time of Christ who is perfect that ends the law, and people must live in him Christ Jesus and walk in him that saith, <hi>swear not at all,</hi> that ends the oath, and is the oath of God; dost thou not read of a people in the <hi>Galatians</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> that was turned back into the law, from the law of the Spirit, and the Apostle told them he that broke one point was guilty of all, and he brought them to the law of love which fulfilled the law.</p>
            <p>Fourteenthly, And as for all the Scriptures the Bishop brings to prove that the Christians sware in the primitive time they are nothing to the purpose, though the Bishop say that Christ admits of some swearing, which both his own words and the Apostles contradicts; Christs words are, <hi>swear not at all;</hi> And the Apostles are above all things, &amp;c. — And so he goes on and lets them see what was in the law, committing Adultery was forbid under the law, but in the time of Christ looking upon a Woman and lusting after her was committing Adultery. — And he sets forth in the justice of the law an eye for an eye, and a tooth for a tooth, and shews how that in the time of the law thou shalt not kill, and whosoever shall kill shall be in danger of judgment, but I say unto you, that whosoever shall be angry with his Brother without cause
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:54376:17"/>
shall be in danger of judgment; and so he tells both swearing and killing to be in the old time, and said except the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness exceed the Righteousness of the Scribes and Pharisees you shall in no wise enter into the kingdom of heaven.</p>
            <p>Fifteenthly, And as to that of the Apostle speaking in the 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 2. God was his witness that he did not make Covetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness his Cloak.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> It were well if the Priests could say so now, but this doth not prove that he swore, and there are many men that takes man to be his witness; and that is not an oath, surely is it? Thou understands that? And if this were an oath, why do you cast friends into prison? </p>
            <p>Sixteenthly, And that of the <hi>Galatians</hi> Chapter 1. 2. There is nothing in that place like unto an Oath which he brings.</p>
            <p>Seventeenthly, And as for the 2 <hi>or.</hi> 4. 23. Verse, there are not so many Verses in that Chapter. — And as for the <hi>Ephesians</hi> th 4th and 15th which he brings for Christians to swear, which he says we are bound at all times to speak truth to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> He doth not say we are to swear truth at all times, but to speak it at all times.</p>
            <p>Eighteenthly, And that which he brings in <hi>Acts</hi> 23. 3. How the Apostle reproved the High Priest, that caused him to be smitten contrary to law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> Here the Apostle was preaching the Gospel and Christs doctrine to them, to the Priests that had the Law and outward things; this was nothing to the purpose, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle should swear, or that Christians should swear. — And in the 14th Verse which he quotes. <hi>Answ.</hi> Those were the bad people that bound themselves with a Curse, that they would neither eat nor drink till they had killed <hi>Paul</hi> that preached the Gospel, this is nothing at all that Christians should swear.</p>
            <p>Nineteenthly, We say there were Heathens oaths annd Jews oaths which were to swear by the Lord, which Christ calls the old time, which they were to perform, which oath Christ ends; and saith, <hi>swear not at all,</hi> for in the time of the law the Jews were to deny all false oaths, and heathenish oaths, and they were not to swear by <hi>Baal,</hi> but the true oath which
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54376:18"/>
Christ ends: And did not the Christians suffer in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times, because. they could not swear by the Prosperity of <hi>Caesar;</hi> and was not that oath then imposed upon them? And by the good fortune of the Emperour, was not that another oath? And did not many Christians then suffer because they could not swear, read the ten persecutions which was a long time before the Pope got up, and then did not the Pope when he had got up over the Churches, give forth both Oath and Curse, with Bell Book and Candle? And was not the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his oath to lay three fingers a top of the book to signifie the Trinity? And two fingers under the book to signifie Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of body and soul if they sware falsly. — And was not there a great number of people that would not swear, and suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered great persecution, as read the Book of Martyrs but to <hi>Bonners</hi> days, and its little above an hundred years since the Protestants got up; And they gave forth the Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and the Oath of Supremacy, the one was to deny the Popes Supremacy, and the other to acknowledge the Kings of <hi>England;</hi> So we need not to tell you of their form, and shew you the ceremony of the oath, it saith kiss the Book, and the Book saith kiss the Son; which saith, <hi>swear not at all,</hi> and so cannot Allegiance be to the King in truth and faithfulness, as was said before without an Oath, yea and more then many that swears.</p>
            <p>So you may see to deny swearing is no new thing, for it was the practise of the Christians in former times to deny it, both in Heathens and the times of Popery before Protestants; and so it is in obedience to the command of Christ that we do not swear in our loves to him, &amp; if we say he is Lord &amp; Master and do not the thing that he commands, that is but deceit and hypocrisie. And so rash and bad swearing that was forbidden in the time of the Law, it was not that which Christ came to fulfill, but true Oaths, and the true Types, Figures, and Shadows, and he saith, <hi>swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Twentiethly, And as for <hi>Acts</hi> the 13th there is nothing spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of swearing, there as all people may read.</p>
            <p>21thly, And whereas the Apostle often speaks, and taking to witness a Record upon his own soul by his rejoyeing in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:54376:18"/>
Christ Jesus, what is all this to swearing and taking an oath, or where did ever the Apostle take a solemn oath, or command the Brethren and Churches to do the same? for often he speaks of the witness our of the mouth of two or three witnesses shall every word be established. — And the Bishop often brings the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 31. <hi>By our rejoycing which I have in Christ Jesus, I die daily;</hi> This place cannot be brought for a proof that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle sware; If so, when thou saist by thy meat thou art refresh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and by the fire thou art warmed, and people tells thee thou must go by such a lane to such a Town, they all swear then, do they not?</p>
            <p>22thly, As for the Particle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Bishop says its never used but in an oath only.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> And what is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is it not (<hi>truly</hi>) as also the Primitive word <hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> which signifies <hi>yea?</hi> and is not that word <hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forementioned, 5th of <hi>Matthew</hi> and 5th of <hi>James,</hi> where swearing is denyed — for is not <hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in Greek <hi>yea</hi> in English; and is not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in Greek <hi>truly</hi> in English, and if every man that says <hi>yea</hi> and <hi>truly</hi> sweareth, then the Bishop proves his Asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. — And is not there a difference between <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> — So in Meekness and Love read this over in that from which it was sent.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POST-SCRIPT.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Christ Jesus who is the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, the Beginning and Ending, First and Last, him by whom God will Judge the World in Righteousness.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>WE Quaery of you whether he or any of his Apostles, after they had given forth a Command that none should Swear, but keep to yea and nay in all their Communications, can any Minister or Teacher prove this in express words out of the New Testament that they ever commanded to swear or did swear, that will satisfie, that will end all: But that we should be cast into prison for our obedience to Christs command, by you that professes your selves to be Christians, and own Christ Jesus as you say, is not right: And he commands you to love
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:54376:19"/>
Enemies if you did obey his commands, and love one another; for they that are Christians and own Christ Jesus they should love one another: For this was a mark by which they were known to be Disciples learners of him. And so they that are lovers of him, own him and obey him and his doctrins, so though we do suffer here by you all the Sessions or As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sizes; we do commit our cause and you that do persecuters to the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Assizes and terrible day wherein God will Judge the world in Rightconsness, by the man Christ Jesus whose commands we obey in tenderness; and there we know we shall have true Judgment without respect of persons, there our Hats will not be looked at before the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, but the action and transgression, and who hath served God, and who hath not served him; for Christ hath told you before hand what he will say to them that visits him not in prison, where he is made manifest in his Brethren: Then what will become of them that casts them into prison for tenderness towards God, for obeying his D<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctring, and keeps to yea and nay in their Communications according to his words — And so those things we leave to the General day, Though we can say the Lord for give you that deth thus persecute in if it be his will freely from our hearts, for we do you nor no man harm, but seek the good and peace of all men, and for this cause for obeying the truth we do suffer.</p>
            <p>G. F.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:54376:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
