<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Elegy upon the death of Mr. Mason late minister of Water-Stratford, near Buckingham, who departed this life on Monday last, the 12th of this instant May, at his house called the New Noah's Ark, at Water-Stratford.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39191</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E466B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34876</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14877275</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14877275</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102810</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A39191)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102810)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1569:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Elegy upon the death of Mr. Mason late minister of Water-Stratford, near Buckingham, who departed this life on Monday last, the 12th of this instant May, at his house called the New Noah's Ark, at Water-Stratford.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 broadside.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for A. Milbourn ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Printed inside mourning border, with allegorical headpiece.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mason, John, 1646?-1694 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb n="198" facs="tcp:102810:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <p>MEMENTO MORI</p>
                  <figDesc>outline of tombstone, which surrounds text, often including depictions of emblems of Death</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>AN ELEGY Upon The Death of Mr. Maſon, LATE <hi>Miniſter of Water-Stratford, near Buckingham,</hi> Who departed this Life on <hi>Monday</hi> laſt, <date>the <hi>21th.</hi> of this Inſtant <hi>May,</hi>
               </date> at his Houſe, called, the <hi>New Noah's Ark,</hi> at <hi>Water-Stratford.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <p>Licenſed according to Order.</p>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>THE <hi>Buckingham</hi> Great <hi>Seer,</hi> that <hi>Non-parel,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Moſes</hi> t' his new wandring <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fame</hi>'s mournful Trump brings the ſaid News to Town,</l>
               <l>Has his Mortality in Duſt laid down.</l>
               <l>True <hi>Moſes</hi> like indeed, his Lifes laſt Sand</l>
               <l>Too ſhort to reach even his own <hi>Promis'd Land.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Strange ſighted Prieſt of Fate, to have fore-known</l>
               <l>The Worlds approaching <hi>End,</hi> but not thy <hi>own:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What though thoſe loud Attendants on thy Death,</l>
               <l>Wafted in Tempeſts thy expiring Breath;</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Storms,</hi> or <hi>Fiery Chariots,</hi> wait thy Call,</l>
               <l>Only we hope thou'aſt let no <hi>Mantle</hi> fall;</l>
               <l>No double-ſpirited Relique left behind,</l>
               <l>No, in thy own great Self conclude thy Kind:</l>
               <l>In thy Enthuſiaſt mold no ſecond caſt,</l>
               <l>Be an <hi>Original Prophet,</hi> firſt and laſt.</l>
               <l>And what, though all thy <hi>Oracles</hi> miſtook,</l>
               <l>Have thy falſe Opticks read in Dooms dark Book:</l>
               <l>Yet as that <hi>Heav'n</hi> has all thy Study been,</l>
               <l>Thou haſt truly ſought, though falſly haſt foreſeen;</l>
               <l>Since only erring Zeal has made thee ſtray,</l>
               <l>Let not that innocent Meteor loſe thy way:</l>
               <l>But in Reward of Piety well-meant,</l>
               <l>May the bad Prophet make not the worſe Saint?</l>
               <l>Yes, thou fond Viſioner of Heav'n, for all</l>
               <l>The Pious Pains thou'aſt took for Gains ſo ſmall,</l>
               <l>(For eaſy 'tis to Dream, but hard to take</l>
               <l>A Dream ſo ſound, as never lives to wake)</l>
               <l>Tho' thy great <hi>Pentecoſt</hi> now diſappears,</l>
               <l>And greater Empire of a Thouſand Years,</l>
               <l>Tho' thou haſt look'd, and gap'd, and hop'd in vain,</l>
               <l>A zealous Waiter for a Worldly Reign.</l>
               <l>Thy Earthy Hopes all vaniſht, may'ſt thou make</l>
               <l>In Death, at leaſt, this happier miſtake,</l>
               <l>Find thy ſelf call'd by a more kind Remove,</l>
               <l>T' attend a truer, Bright Crown'd Head above.</l>
               <l>Such Bliſs above may thy good Life beſtow,</l>
               <l>But what are the ſad Rites thou meet'ſt below,</l>
               <l>Here, Oh, what Funeral Griefs, what blubber'd Eyes?</l>
               <l>Ev'n Joy it ſelf, all droops, when <hi>Maſon</hi> dyes.</l>
               <l>The once ſweet Chorus of thy Spiritual Grove,</l>
               <l>All the whole Brotherhood of Song and Love,</l>
               <l>Their Sanctify'd <hi>Hoſannas</hi> all give o're,</l>
               <l>The Timbrels ſound, and Minſtrels play no more.</l>
               <l>Though their new Guide, and their new <hi>Canaan Land,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Both loſt, thy poor Diſciples muſt disband,</l>
               <l>The Voyage to their <hi>Paleſtine</hi> fair Coaſt,</l>
               <l>And their <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> whole <hi>Cargo</hi> loſt;</l>
               <l>The Rams and Bullocks, once reſerv'd to blaze</l>
               <l>In flaming Hecatombs, turn'd out to graze,</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Water-Stratford</hi> Camp its Fame ſhall keep,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Hounſlows</hi> and <hi>Black Heath</hi>'s forgotten ſleep.</l>
               <l>And now, for Monuments we'll build thee none:</l>
               <l>Nor carve thee Epitaphs in Braſs or Stone;</l>
               <l>No, thy far talking Name has ſpread ſo wide,</l>
               <l>As is its ſelf its own proud Piramide.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed for <hi>A. Milbourn</hi> in the <hi>Little Old-Baily.</hi> 1694. <add>192.</add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
