<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Approved medicines of little cost, to preserve health and also to cure those that are sick provided for the souldiers knap-sack and the country mans closet / written by Richard Elkes, Gent. ...</title>
            <author>Elkes, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-10">2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39240</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E536</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20307</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12354612</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12354612</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60098</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A39240)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60098)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 142:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Approved medicines of little cost, to preserve health and also to cure those that are sick provided for the souldiers knap-sack and the country mans closet / written by Richard Elkes, Gent. ...</title>
                  <author>Elkes, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Ibbitson, and are to be sold by Tho. Vere ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine, Popular --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Self-care, Health --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Therapeutics.</term>
               <term>Herbs --  Therapeutic use --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicinal plants.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:60098:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:60098:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Approved Medicines OF Little coſt, to preſerve health and alſo to cure thoſe that are SICK. Provided For the Souldiers Knap-ſack, and the Country mans Cloſet.</p>
            <p>Written by RICHARD ELKES Gent. Student in the Art of Phyſick, living at <hi>Bagſhot</hi> in the County of <hi>Surry.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Medicos &amp; Chirurgos ſubinde mutare; aegris tae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium non levamen eſt. </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Eccleſ. 38. 4. </bibl>The Lord hath created Medicines out of the earth, and he that is wiſe will not abhorre them.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Ibbitſon</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Tho: Vere</hi> at the Angel in the Old-Baily. 1651.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:60098:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60098:2"/>
            <head>TO THE High and Honourable Court of Parliament, <hi>Rich. Elkes</hi> wiſheth health, peace, and tranquility.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR as much as all men ought in their ſeverall pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and callings to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to doe good in that Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, wherein they live, your poor Subject hath ſeen many men, both Souldiers and others looſe their lives, by a careleſſe demeanour, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ignorantly, ſome times wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſometimes for want of a Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and Chyrurgeon, ſometimes neglecting the means when it may
<pb facs="tcp:60098:3"/>
be had, for the prevention thereof, I do here make bold to preſent unto your view ſome Defenſives and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, for all that deſire Health.</p>
            <p>In the abſence of a Learned Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian and Chyrurgion, theſe eaſie Medicines may both cure and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve health; as the learned ſaith, the Phyſitians duty conſiſteth, in two principall points, Firſt, <hi>To preſerve health.</hi> Secondly, <hi>To cure the ſick,</hi> which I have and will indeavour to doe, according to that Tallent that Almighty God hath beſtowed upon me, and reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>your obedient Servant
To Command, in all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and diligence.
RICHARD ELKES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60098:3"/>
            <head>The Directions of an old Souldier in <hi>Ireland</hi> about forty years ſince, which became a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian there.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I travelled through the Countie of <hi>Clare,</hi> I heard of an excellent Phyſitian which had accompliſhed manie rare cures, but eſpecially the Bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Flux. After ſome time ſpent I found the man, and conferred with him touching his Art, which he ſeemed willing to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, requeſting the like of me, and ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout fortie years before that time, he came out of <hi>England</hi> a Souldier into that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, which was in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> daies; before a month was expired the Bloodie Flux ſeized upon him, and as he ſuppofed it came by eating of freſh meat, freſh fiſh, lying upon the ground being hot, and ſuch like; he remembred ſome directions that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60098:4"/>
was given to him before he came out of <hi>England,</hi> That when you eate, give over with an appetite, drinke no more but to quench thirſt, if you drink when you are hot, march after it, or ſtirre your body, when you reſt at your fires ſit not upon the cold ground, but upon wood, ſtraw, or ſuch like; put off your wet cloathes, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally your Stockings and dry them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And carrie in your Knap-ſacke a peece of ſteele to heat red hot, and quench it in your beer, water or milke, and as you tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel gather the leaves and bark of the Oake, and the leaves of the black-Thorn, a bagge of Salt and Oatmeale, that if the Flux ſhould take you, you might helpe your ſelfe. So this old Souldier remembred his directions, and obſerved it diligently, when he came to their fires, to dry his cloathes, and ſit upon wood, or ſuch like, and he caſt his peece of ſteele into the fire to warme his drink, and when they had fiſh or fleſh boiled, he would caſt into the boiler, a handfull of Oaken leaves, or bark of the Oak, or a handful of leaves of Black-Thorn, Salt and Oatmeale; and grated into his
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60098:4"/>
beer ſome of the Oake bark; this being obſerved, cured himſelfe, and many of his fellow Souldiers. The Wars being end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he became a Phyſitian, and gained both monie and credit, by curing the Flux, and ſome other infirmities.</p>
            <p>Thus may any Souldier obſerve and do for their healths in <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> if need require. Alſo the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers may provide in their Knap-ſacks three ſorts of Earth, that is Terra Lemnia, it is called in the Apothecaries ſhops, Terra Sigillata, Bolarmonicke, and Chalke; this Terra Lemnia commeth out of the Iſland of <hi>Lemnos</hi> in the <hi>Turkes</hi> Dominion, the quantity of a Bullet ſwallowed whole or beaten topowder, and taken in Broth or other liquor faſting, it cureth the Flux, and preſerveth from the Peſtilence; the beſt Bolarmonick commeth out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and may be taken faſting in like quantity, or in ſome broth, the quantity of two Bullets to cure a Flux; the common Chalke which we have in <hi>England</hi> may be beaten to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and boiled in milke or broth, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken faſting it cureth a Flux, if it be often
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60098:5"/>
taken the quantity of a ſpoonfull twice in the day. Thus much of medicines with lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle coſt.</p>
            <div n="2" type="remedy">
               <head>2 To proceed to the cure of the Flux, metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dically according to Art.</head>
               <p>YOu muſt conſider what kinds of Flux the parties are grieved with, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion that doth predominate; firſt, whether it be the Flux Diarrhea, Lienteria, or Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteria, if it be Dyſenteria which is moſt dangerous, I have read of foure kinds, but it requires a long diſcourſe concerning al the ſorts, but I omit that, becauſe the cure differ eth but little, only this, if you find the exhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceration to be in the upper &amp; ſmal guts, you muſt miniſter medicines at the mouth, but if it be at the bigger or lower bowells, you muſt caſt in gliſters often, if the party be without a Feavour, give him milke newly milked, wherein a gad of ſteele hath been quenched, you may make Suppings or Broth with Quinces, Knot-graſſe, Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain-leaves, Willow-leaves, Cumfrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roots, and ſuch like, you may make Rice-Milke, or boile white Starch in Milke, eate no fleſh but Partridges, Culvers, or
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60098:5"/>
Birds of the mountaine, Goates and Hares fleſh may be permitted; a good diet wel ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, the cure is halfe accompliſhed.</p>
               <p>If ſtrength doe permit, you may purge down the vicious humors with two drams of Rubarb, infuſed in halfe a pint of white wine, with Currans and ſweet Fennell ſeeds, and drink it faſting to purge the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious humors, after purging, take a dram of Diaſcordium, thus may you purge every other day; for in a week after this, make a drink with running water of two quarts, put ſeeds of Sorrell, Pumgranat rindes, Knot-graſſe, Cumfery roots, Bryer roots, Plantain leaves, Cinamon, Bolarmonicke, Dragons blood, and Sugar; drinke this as an ordinary drinke: Likewiſe you may make a drink with red wine, Cinamon, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, Knotgraſſe, and Cumfery roots to drink three times a day four ſpoonfuls at a time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="remedy">
               <head>2 To make a Gliſter glutinous.</head>
               <p>REc: three pints of water, quench ſteel in it, untill one third part be waſted then boile in it Cumfery roots, Knotgraſſe, Bryer leaves, red Roſe leaves, and Plantain leaves, of each a little handfull of Acatia,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60098:6"/>
hypociſchidis, <hi>ana.</hi> ℈ij. Bolarmonack; <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis Dragonis: ana.</hi> ℈j. the juyce of Quinces <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. Goates Tallow ℥j. if it may be had, and yolkes of three eggs, commixe this to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and make a Gliſter, adminiſter this as often as you ſhall ſee cauſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="remedy">
               <head>3 For an Implaiſter.</head>
               <p>REc. of the Oyles of Quinces, Roſes Maſtick <hi>ana.</hi> ℥j. of the meale of Fenny Greeke and Barley <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. <hi>Sanguis Dragonis Balauſtia</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>
                  <hi>ſs.</hi> Bolatmonicke ℥j. <hi>acalia</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ij. as much wax and Roſen as is ſufficient, and make a Plaiſter, ſpread it upon leather, and apply it to the Navill over the neather Ventrick where the party complaineth moſt. Much more might be ſpoken but I leave it to the ingenious practitioner, and wiſh all men to be temperate, for intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is the cauſe of this and many other incurable diſeaſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="condition">
               <head>4 Of the Peſtilence or Plague.</head>
               <p>THe Peſtilence is a Fevor in the higheſt degree, which may bee taken ſeverall waies, by living amongſt ſick people, by a corrupted Aire, by rotten and corrupt Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, which filleth the body with rotten
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60098:6"/>
and corrupt humors, but ſome bodies are ſtronger then others, ſome are more tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in eating and drinking then others, in them rotten humours abound not, and, the infection faſteneth not ſo ſtrongly upon them, but nature expelleth it, this is the reaſon that ſome people never catcheth the Peſtilence, though all be in a roome toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſometimes the infection happeneth, by living with the ſick, and lodging in bed with them, drawing the breath that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from the ſick party, if they approach near to them; as the office of the Lunges is to draw in freſh Aire to comfort the heart, inſtead thereof it drawes in a veno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous breath, which may be the deſtruction of the heart: the cauſe of a corrupted Aire, is by ſtanding Ponds, or Marſhes in the heat of Sumer, rotten Coleworts, rotten Roots, and fruits, &amp; many people continuing in a cloſe room, many dead Bodies unburied: which may happen in the time of War, dead Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion and ſuch like, immoderate heate of the Aire, and moiſture in Summer time, thick Miſts, eſpecially about Autumn, that in a morning it may be ſmelt. The cauſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60098:7"/>
of corrupt humors in the body, is by eating corrupt meates and drinks, as fleſh long un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalted, rotten fruits, Cole-worts, and rotten Cabbig, and roots: and corrupt water, or wine, or beer made with evill water, breeds rotten humors in the body, which I wiſh al men to have reſpect unto, and the beſt means to preſerve their bodies from the Peſtilence that is, is not to continue in a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilent Aire, make fires often, burne Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary, Sage, Juniper-wood and Berryes, Frankinſence, Myrrh, Pitch, and ſuch like, what you eate let it be wholeſome, glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonizing doth corrupt the blood &amp; produce dangerous diſeaſes, as the Meaſles, the Pox which are the fore-runners of the Plague, alwaies eate with your meate ſharp things, as Vineger, Vargis, Oringes, Lemons; let your pot-hearbs be Sage, Iſope, Balme, Bugloſſe, and Burrage, drinke no wine but alay it with good water, eate <hi>Terra Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> or fine Bolarmonack as before is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, carry in your Knap-ſack a Box of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſcordium, and Methridate, a handfull of Rue the root of Setwall, in ſhops <hi>Zedoary,</hi> and Elicampane roots, take either of theſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60098:7"/>
it may preſerve from the Infection, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, if you come into a houſe, or place that you doubt you have taken the Infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, go preſently and dig a hole in the freſh earth, put in your mouth and noſe, and breath into it a quarter of an hour, then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move from that place and dig another hole and do likewiſe, this you may do three or four times, and by Gods bleſſing the freſh earth will draw the venome from your heart, which I have proved alſo, if a man be in a ſound, or choked in a roome, where a multitude of people are, it will as it were fetch life againe.</p>
               <p>Further if you go into a roome which is infected, hold a turffe of freſh earth to your mouth and noſtrills, it will preſerve you from the contagion, as I have proved: you muſt avoid Bathing, <hi>Venus,</hi> and violent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, which openeth the Pores, then the venomous Aire will have no entrance into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he body to deſtroy it: to be Coſtive is hurtfull, for prevention thereof you may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ive a ſoft Gliſter or Purge, with <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iludie Rufi,</hi> alſo it is good for young peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to be let blood, but remember to uſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60098:8"/>
a good dyed after it, and keep in untill the blood be ſettled again: and avoid all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations of the minde, as wrath, melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly, and ſuch like: Many more reme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dies might be ſhowed, which for brevity I omit; only this antidote you may cauſe to be made at any Apothecaries to carry in your Knap-ſack, and for the Country man to keep in his houſe, to uſe if occaſion be; Rec: of <hi>Saffron</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>
                  <hi>ſs.</hi> of <hi>Alloes Epaticke</hi> of <hi>Mirrh</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ij. <hi>Maſtick</hi> ℈i. <hi>Bolearmonacke</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Lemnia</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ij. <hi>harts-horne</hi> burnt <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j <hi>ſs.</hi> the bone of the <hi>Harts-heart, red Corrall ana.</hi> ℈j. <hi>Walnuts</hi> in number 20. <hi>Figs</hi> 13. <hi>Bay ſalt</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. of <hi>Rue</hi> a little handfull, Roots of <hi>Scabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Ariſtolochia Rotunda</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ij. <hi>Tormentil</hi> and <hi>Pimper-nell, ana.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>v. <hi>Bitany</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. <hi>Zedoary</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j Seeds of <hi>Sorrell,</hi> and Seeds of <hi>Purſlain, ana.</hi>  
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>
                  <hi>ſs.</hi> and make all theſe into an Electuary with clarified hony, or with Syrrup of Gillyflowers, and Marygolds, take every morning upon the poynt of a knife, the quantity of a Nut, it wil preſerve from the infection, in like manner you may take it at any time when you come among infect<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed perſons: thus farre I have ſhewed you
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60098:8"/>
how the Peſtilence happeneth, and how to prevent it; Now I will ſhew you brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſimptomes and ſignes of it, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the cure. When the wind is often in the South and Weſt, the Aire much al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, ſpecially in Autumn, many pimples riſing: the Meaſles and Pox in divers places increaſing, are the ſignes of the Peſtilence enſuing: the ſimptomes are, the extreame parts of the ſick perſon wil be cold, and the inward parts very hot; heavineſſe, lazy and ſleepy with a great pain in the head; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſadneſſe, ſometimes raving, vomit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, purging, loſſe of appetite, great thirſt, the Pulſe frequent low and deep, the tongue red, at firſt growing black; the Urine thick and troubled, but ſometimes like the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine of a healthy man, (therefore I wiſh you to obſerve other ſignes) moſt ſpecially if there be any riſings behind the eares, armepits, or groine, theſe are cheifly to be obſerved: And now I proceed to the cure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="remedy">
               <head>5 The Cure of the Plague.</head>
               <p>IF you come to the ſicke party, the firſt or ſecond day of falling ſicke, the common uſe hath been to open a veine in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60098:9"/>
that fide that the Botch appeareth, or that ſide he complaineth of: for if you let blood in the contrary ſide, you draw venome over the heart, and deſtroy the body, alſo if the greife be above the ſhoulders, cut the Cefallick veine, if below the ſhoulders, cut Baſilica, ſo if it be below the neather Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick, cut the vein in the Ham, or the Anckle; but the practice of ſome is not to bleed, you may apply cupping-glaſſes: if the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence ſhould ſeize upon a man at dinner, or Supper, give him a vomit: If it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen other times, you may give the party of the Antedote before written, the quantity of a Nut in ſome <hi>Scabius</hi> water, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him very warm to ſweat an hour, and cool him gentlely, it will both cure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him from it: or you may give this Medicine following: Rec: <hi>Methridatum</hi> ℈j. <hi>Theriaca Londinenſis</hi> ℈ij. <hi>Bolearmonack</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared <hi>℈jſs.</hi> waters of <hi>Bugloſſe</hi> and <hi>Scabius</hi> as much as is ſufficient to make it into an Electuary, give to the ſick the quantity of a dram, and lay him in a warme bed, and cover him with clothes that he may ſweat four hours, then let him be cooled gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60098:9"/>
by taking off the clothes one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; this being done, uſe the ſame the ſecond day, and by Gods bleſſing it may drive the venome from the heart, unto the extreame parts, which I wil direct for the cure thereof hereafter: you may alſo take <hi>Electuarium de ovo</hi> the quantity of a dram or a ſcruple, according to the ſtrength of the party, it is commended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all by ſome Phyſitians; but <hi>Bolar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monick,</hi> or <hi>Terra lemnia,</hi> I have proved them the quantity of a nut given in poſſet-drink or in ſurrup of Gilloflowers, and 3 grains of Saffron powder, this will drive out the venome into Botches like Carbunckles when other Medicines be wanting, ſo the party hath recovered, it is alſo good to drive out the Meaſels and the Pox, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in the time of ſweating, you muſt not let the party ſleep, nor in ſix houres after; you may give him Julips, made with waters of <hi>Scabius, Sorrel, Endive</hi> and <hi>Succo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> ſurrup of <hi>Gilloflowers,</hi> of <hi>Wood ſorrel, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, Violets,</hi> and ſuch like, for his meate, you may boile a Chick, with Sorrel, the juice of Lemons, and Burrage-flowers, or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60098:10"/>
Marigold-flowers are very good; alſo you may diſſolve a little Saffron in his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to dip his meat in it, but let the Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron be very finely poudered, or tyed in a linnen cloth (as Saffron is a Cordinal, ſo if much be taken it hurteth) Many other cordial things may be uſed, wood of Aloes and Sanders grated into his beere is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="remedy">
               <head>6 The Cure of the ſwelling or Plague ſore in the extream parts.</head>
               <p>IF the ſwelling wil not break it ſelfe, you may apply that plaiſter called <hi>Diachylon compoſitum,</hi> or <hi>Galbanum</hi> ſpread upon Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and applyed to the place: or an Onyon cut off the top, and dig out the middle, and put in <hi>London Treacle,</hi> and three or foure leaves of <hi>Rue,</hi> put this to the fire and roſte it, when it is wel roſted, lay it warm to the Botch or ſwelling, if it break put in a Tent, and let it run what it wil, when the corruption is out; <hi>Diachilon</hi> wil heale it up againe, alſo you may uſe this; Rec. great <hi>Raiſons</hi> halfe an ounce, <hi>Bay ſalt</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. <hi>Figs</hi> 6 Oyle of <hi>Cammomell,</hi> and <hi>hony,</hi> as much as wil make this into a Playſter, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearbs,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60098:10"/>
ny other medicines might be ſet downe, but theſe wil eaſily be gotten; if you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire further, repaire to your learned Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="condition">
               <head>7 Of the Calenture and ſpotted Feavor.</head>
               <p>THeſe Feavors are very near unto the Peſtilence, which doth often happen unto Mariners at ſea, by feeding upon ſalt Beefe, Bacon, ſalt Fiſh, and evil water, pulſe and worm-eaten bread, which cannot be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided at Sea, this Feavor is known, by feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the outward me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers cold, &amp; thoſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as the Peſtilence, ſleepy, and heavie, the pulſe very low: This Feavor bringeth death in 24 hours many times if not ſpeedily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented: furthermore, you ſhal perceive the Patient as it were diſtracted, ready to leap into the Sea, ſometimes vomit, the tongue white underneath, and black at the top, cold ſweats, cramps, with many other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, like as in the peſtilence: For the cure thereof, if the patient be able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure Flebothomy, open a vein in the arme, if he complain moſt in the head, cut the veine called <hi>Cephalia,</hi> if at the cheſt, the <hi>Baſilicke</hi> vein, remove the ſick into a freſh
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60098:11"/>
room, make a fire in it firſt, then put out the fire, and refreſh the room with ſweet wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or what elſe may be had at the Sea; if at Land caſt Ruſhes in the Roome, and green Boughs; if the Aire be hot, miſty, and moiſt, ſhut the windowes, if clear and pure let in the freſh Aire to comfort the heart: At the firſt you muſt not let the ſick ſleep overmuch, that will draw the venome to the heart, until it is defended by giving cordials, ſuch as is preſcribed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the chapter of the Peſtilence, his dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et muſt be Broth, made with cordial Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and a little Saffron tyed in a cloth, after the third day you may give crums of Bread in his Broth; for the cure, if time wil permit, give him a Gliſter before letting blood, in this manner make your decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with cordial flowers, after boyling diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve into it <hi>Diaſcordium, ſurrup</hi> of <hi>Violets, Roſes</hi> and ſuch like; after Phlebothomy give him a cordial, and lay the party to ſweat, as is taught in the chapter of the Plague: After ſweating and Phlebothomy, the ſick may drinke <hi>Barly-water,</hi> made with coole
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60098:11"/>
Raiſons of the Sun ſtoned, and a ſcruple of Saffron tyed in a cloath and boyled in the water, Lemons boyld in Milke both rinde and pulpe, untill it is turned to Curds, and Whay, drinke the Whay continually as you thirſt, I have proved it of good effect.</p>
               <p>And when he hath recovered a little ſtrength, and the venome expelled from the heart, let him be purged with this Potion; Rec. a quart of running water, or more, a handfull of cordiall Flowers, a little <hi>Cardus Benedictus,</hi> a root of Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til, a legg of a Poultry, theſe being boyled, take a pint of that liquor or thereabout, diſſolve in it of <hi>Diaphenicon,</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. <hi>Diacatholicon</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j <hi>ſs.</hi> electuary of Roſes <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ij. give the ſick this to purge the dregs of the Feaver, as you ſhal ſee cauſe, adding ſome cordial ſurrups after purging, made with Diaſcordium, Amber Beaſer, ſurrup of Violets, and ſurrup of Lemmons, waters of Bugloſſe, Burrage and Wood Sorrell to drinke at night, ſo by the bleſſing of God the ſick may reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver health againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="condition">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:60098:12"/>
               <head>8. Of the Scurvie.</head>
               <p>THere is the ſea Scurvie, and the land Scurvie, both of theſe are a putrifa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of bloud which commeth by the neglect of exerciſing the body, and eating rotten meates, and corrupt drinke, or wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as is ſhewed in the former Chapter; the obſtructions of the Spleen doe increaſe this evill, and the Morphew and blacke ſoult, the ſimptoms are theſe; the gums ſwell, the teeth looſe, the leggs wil ſwell, and have ſpots about the anckles, ſome will have many tawny ſpots about their breaſt, other ſome have complained with a great paine in the head, with a ſore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe all over the head; I cured a Tanner that laboured with this evill ſeven yeares, chiefly in the Springe, and at the fall of the Leafe; by his owne relation in his youth he was laborious, but after he had gained a competent eſtate he took eaſe, and eate much, but of groſſe meat; his drinke was made of ſtanding water, which as he ſuppoſed made the ſtrongeſt drinke, his bread was made with Barme, or Yeaſt, but in his youth he eate leavened bread,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60098:12"/>
ſo from this and ſuch other of the ſame I have obſerved, that evill water, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leavened bread doe breed this and many other dangerous diſeaſes, for drink made of ſuch water, the venome doth purge by the Barme, and is in it, of which bread is made, and he that eateth ſuch bread (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in Cities and Townes) may have the Scurvie, and Feavers of all ſorts, for if there be any venome in the drinke it will be in the Barme; therefore I wiſh all men to eate leavened bread if he can have it, and drinke made of cleare water ten dayes old at leaſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="remedy">
               <head>9 For the Cure of the Scurvie.</head>
               <p>THe firſt intention is to keep a good dyet, and exerciſe the body mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, his meat muſt be meates of the beſt nouriſhment, as Birds of the Field, Mutton, or Veale, Rabbets, and Chickings, broath made with Agremony, Avins, Scabius, or Bitony, and ſuch like; all ſalt meats muſt be avoyded, the firſt three dayes let him take a draught of Oximell in the morning faſting, and laſt at night, which is to be made in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60098:13"/>
Rec. a quart of cleane water, a root or two of Fennell, three or foure roots of Parſley, a ſprigge of Roſemary, a little Fumotery if it be to be had, Fennell-ſeeds, and Parſley-ſeeds of each a Dram, three ſpoonfuls of the beſt Honey, let this boyle gently, and ſcum it, and in the boyling put into it two ſpoonfuls of Vinegar, after this hath been taken three dayes, take of <hi>Rubarbe</hi> 3ij. of <hi>Sena</hi> 3j. 40 Rayſons of the Sun ſtoned, a race of Ginger ſliced, ſweet Fennel-ſeeds, Anniſ-ſeeds of each 3j. let theſe be infuſed all night upon Coales, the next morning take halfe a pint of this and diſſolve in it a Dram of <hi>Diacatholicon,</hi> take this three mornings, after this let Bloud if need require; the body being thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, make your Scurvye-graſſe Drinke in this manner: Take a peck of Scurvie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graſſe, and a gallon of Water-creſſes, and a gallon of Brook-limes, one handfull of Egremony, one handfull of Tamariske, or the buds or barke of the Aſhe, Rayſons of the Sunne ſtoned a pound, of Licoriſh halfe a pound, concuſed Fennell roots pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, and Parſley roots, Anniſ-ſeeds, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60098:13"/>
Fennell ſeeds a quarter of a pound, put all theſe into a thin Bagge, in five gallons of Beere or Ale, put the Bagge into the Barrell when the drinke is ready to be tunned, with a ſtone in the bottome of the Bagge, let it hang within three or foure inches of the bottome of the Barrell, let this drinke worke with theſe ingredients in it, then ſtop it cloſe, and at eight or ten dayes drinke of it and none other (except a little at meate) untill the Party be well; moſt eſpecially in the morning drinke a pint, and exerciſe untill the party is ready to ſweat, and keep him warme after it; the ſpoon-wort is good for the land Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie, uſed as before is directed, and taken forty dayes together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="condition">
               <head>10 Of the Flux called, the Plague in the Guts.</head>
               <p>THis Flux in <hi>England</hi> which is called by many, the Plague in the Guts, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious as I conceive, a venomous matter cleaving to the neather or great Guts for the moſt part, ſome ſeeme to have no Feavor, other ſome have a Feavour, and complaine moſt in the middle Ventricle;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60098:14"/>
in briefe, I ſuppoſe the Cure is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed by giving Cordials, and ſweating, and by Gliſters, if the Flux appeare to be bloudy, or like ſcraping of Guts; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Feavour, you may proceed as I dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted before in the Chapter of the Flux Dyſenteria; at the firſt comming of this Flux, take a quart of Milke, boyle in it a handfull of Marigold Flowers, Sage, and Roſemary, Bryer leaves, and knot graſſe, this being boyled take one pint of this, put into it ſurrup of Slowes, ſurrup of Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-flowers, <hi>anna</hi> ℥j. the yolke of an egge, and a dram of Diaſcordium, give this bloud warme, the next day if ſtrength per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit give the other pint of Milke in a Gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter as before is directed, but after the firſt Gliſter hath done working, give a Cordiall thus prepared, take of the water fo <hi>Burrage, Scabius,</hi> and <hi>Marygolds, ana.</hi> ℥j. <hi>Diaſcordium</hi> ℥j. <hi>Confectio Alcermis</hi> ℈j. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thridates</hi> ℈ <hi>ſs.</hi> ſurrup of <hi>Violets,</hi> ſurrup of <hi>Gillo-flowers, ana.</hi> ℥j. commix all this to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and drinke it warme, preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter let the ſick be covered warme, to ſweat two houres if ſtrength permit; in ſweat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60098:14"/>
drinke Poſſet wherein Saffron is boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, this being uſed three times may cure it, for it hath recovered many of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove named Flux, keeping a good dyet without fleſh; thus briefly of the Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, which deſtroyeth many, if meanes be not uſed to prevent it in time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="remedy">
               <head>11. The cure of the Itch, and Lice.</head>
               <p>FOr cure thereof Methodically, is firſt to obſerve a good dyet (that is to ſay) you muſt eate and drinke ſuch things that breed good bloud, and to avoyd all things that breeds evill and rotten humours, as you may ſee in the Chapters before going; then purge the body with <hi>pilule de fumo terrae,</hi> or <hi>pilule Inde haly,</hi> which you may have at any Apothecaries, the ſecond day let bloud in the Baſiliske veine, then make this water following; Rec. A gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon of running water, or the water that Smiths uſe, and quench in it a gad of ſteele red hot untill halfe the water be waſted, then boyle in it a quarter of a pound of leafe Tobacco, of Dock roots, Willow leaves, and leaves of the Birch, of each a handfull, of Brimſtone tyed in a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60098:15"/>
Cloath 3 ij. waſh the ſore places twice in the day and you ſhall be cured (except the Itch be incorrigible, which with long continuance doth bring it to paſſe; alſo if you make ſo much of this water as will wet your ſhirt twice in the weeke, the ſhirt being cleane waſhed and dryed, then dipped in this liquor, and dry it againe, it will both kill the Itch, and deſtroy the Lyce that are about you) I have read a ſtory of ſome Souldiers that would boyle Saffron, Pepper, and Graines in running water, and in that liquor dip their ſhirts twice in the weeke, it will make the ſhirt yellow, but it deſtroyed Lice and Itch; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the inferiour ſort would boyle Staveacre and Tobacco in water and dip their ſhirts in it, and cure both Itch and Lice. Many more Medicines for the Itch have been uſed, as Brimſtone pounded to Powder with Ginger, and tyed in a cloath, and infuſed in fallet Oyle nine dayes in the Sun, annoynt the ſore places with this oyle and be whole (but this will ſmell) alſo Mercury ſublimate ℥ <hi>ſs.</hi> bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to powder, and put into a quart of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60098:15"/>
Running water three or four dayes, then with a little cloth wet the ſore places, it may cure the Itch, but it is dangerous, and muſt not be uſed unto raw places, for it may poyſon the blood, therefore I wiſh that none would uſe it without the advice of his Chyrurgion.</p>
               <p>So I come to ſpeake of the incorrigible Scab called by ſome the <hi>Naopolitan</hi> diſeaſe, which happen, and hardly found out, the firſt cure (as <hi>Vigo</hi> ſaith) of this foul diſeaſe is called <hi>Morbus Gallicus,</hi> I wil ſpeak little of the cure in this place, becauſe divers have written largely of it, and the maledy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chronicled it wil require a long time to perfect, I will onely give you ſome cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to preſerve from the infection; if you be infected before it be confirmed, to expell it: The infection of this evill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth cheifly 4 wayes, but ſeldome or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver by eating and drinking, with the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed as many think, the moſt dangerous way of catching this Maledie is by a clean body carnally acting with an unclean bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; the next way of taking it is, man and man, or woman and woman lying in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60098:16"/>
bed, the one cleane the other uncleane, the heate of their bodies do as it were par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate of each others Itch, Scab, Pox or Peſtilence; The third way of taking this Infection, is by approaching ſo near the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed party, as to draw in its corrupt breath, as in the Peſtilence; The fourth way is, Infants ſucking an unclean woman. Signes how to know this diſeaſe, if it be newly taken not ſo eaſily diſcerned, if of long continuance, the face of ſome will be wan and pale, the eies hollow, and blew ſome ſcabs about the noſe, ſometime Vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, ſometimes no Ulcers, a full paine in the head, great paines in the joynts, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the night, the Shin bones conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually pained, the Vvula and neck ſwoln, the Spade bone and ſinewes in pain, Lazy, and Lumpiſh, Gonorrhea ſwelling, in the Arme-pits little Knobs or Ulcers, about the privy Members, and Fundament, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Scabs over all the body, with many more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="remedy">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:60098:16"/>
               <head>12 For cure hereof newly taken, and not confirmed.</head>
               <p>FIrſt of all you ſhal obſerve a good dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, that is, eate Veale, Mutton, roſted Birds of the Mountaine, Hens, Chickings, Partridges, or Pheſants, and ſuch like: All ſalt meat is hurtful, al fiſh, but Cra-fiſh; Garlicke Onyons, Salt, Pepper, Swines<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleſh, and White-meates, and <hi>Venus</hi> is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden; ſometimes the Patient may uſe Burrage, Lettis, White beets in Rice broth, when he is wearyed with meat dry roſted; The ſecond intention is to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt the corrupt Matter with ſurrup of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olets, ſurrup of Fumotary, of each halfe an ounce, water of Endiffe, and Maiden haire, a ſpoonfull of Vineger, let this be taken over night, the next morning give him this potion, take a handfull of Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage Flowers, a handfull of Mary-goldes: 40 Rayſons of the ſun ſtoned, boile them in a quart of water, to a pinte, then take a dram of <hi>Rubarh,</hi> and inſuſe in it all night, in that pinte of liquor, diſſolve of <hi>Diacatholicon</hi> and <hi>Diaphenicon,</hi> of each half an ounce, in the ſame liquor, and take it
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60098:17"/>
faſting, and faſt two houres, in the interim provide ſome thin Broth to drinke as he Purgeth, after purging give ſome Cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſurrups with Diaſcordium; the ſecond day Purge againe, the fourth day Sweat 4 hours, the ſixth day Sweat 4 houres, and the eight day ſweat 4 houres; in this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terim provide this drink, take of <hi>Lignum vite</hi> li. j. of the Barke of the ſaid wood li. . <hi>ſs. Raiſons of the Sun</hi> ſtoned, li. j. <hi>Chinaroot</hi> ℥ij. <hi>Saſſafras</hi> ℥vj. <hi>Salſaperilla</hi> ℥ix. <hi>Cardus Benedictus,</hi> and <hi>Maiden-haire</hi> Mj. of <hi>Liquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,</hi> and <hi>Annyſeeds</hi> li. <hi>ſs.</hi> of each, and 16 pintes of water, put all theſe in a pot ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cloſe ſtopped, and let it ſtand upon the coales 24 hours to infuſe, then let it boyl 24 houres gently; in the boiling, put in of white wine &amp; quart, ſcum it, and ſave the ſcum, to apply to the ſcabby or ſoate pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſtrein this liquor and keep it in a veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, cloſe ſtopped, drink this drink and no other 40 dayes (except at meate) a little ſmall drink may be permitted, thus havel cured many, at the firſt, before the evil be confirmed; alſo this drink wil cure al diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Liver, as the Dropſie, &amp;c. if right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60098:17"/>
uſed: Further, if the party be Scabby, or Itchy, make this Bath following, Rec. of the Roots and Leaves of Docks, Chick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weed, Fumoterry, of each a little bundle, Lentils, and Lupins, four handfuls bruiſed, Elicampane Roots, Walwort, or the roots inſtead of Walwort, Elder, li. ij. <hi>Black heli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor</hi> ℥iiij. <hi>Kneeholme</hi> li. ij. Brimſtone li. ij. boyle all theſe in ſo much water as will bath a man, when the third part is waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then let the diſeaſed Bath and ſweat in it, two or three times in a week, after Bathing, let the patient go to bed, and keepe warme, and drinke the aforeſaid drinke, this hath cured many but if the Scab be more inveterate, uſe this unction, Rec. of <hi>Quick-ſilver</hi> killed with faſting ſpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, ℥j, in areadineſſe, then take the Oyle of <hi>Bayes,</hi> and <hi>Maſticke</hi> of each an ounce, and of the liquor of the Bath aforenamed a pinte, of freſh Butter, and Swines greaſe, ℥iij. of each; ſeeth all theſe until the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor be waſted, then adde clear <hi>Turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> ℥j. of <hi>Storax liquidam</hi> ℥<hi>ſs. White wax</hi> ℥iiij. <hi>Rock Allum</hi> burnt ℥j. <hi>Litarge</hi> of gold and ſilver ℥ij. of each, of <hi>Myrrh</hi> and <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenſence,</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:60098:18"/>
                  <hi>ana.</hi> ℥ij. juyce of <hi>Lemons,</hi> ℥iij. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixe all theſe together with the <hi>Quick-ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> quenched, and annoynt the Scabs, this will cure; if you annoynt and ſweat untill the Flux be moved, but if this evill be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed and ulcerated it will require a long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er diſcourſe, which you may have hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter if time permit; thus briefly I thought good to direct the Souldier, and others to prevent the danger thereof. I have read that <hi>Charles</hi> the eighth, King of <hi>France,</hi> comming to <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Naples</hi> with his Souldiers, they brought this Diſeaſe into <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Spaniard</hi> inſtead of Silver and Gold, brought it from the <hi>Indies,</hi> but I hope better of our Country-men, and reſt, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="condition">
               <head>13. Of the Flux of bloud in wounds, and the remedies thereof.</head>
               <p>IF the Flux be little it is the eaſier re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, but if it flow out abundantly, there muſt be ſpeedy remedy, for bloud is the treaſure of life, ſometimes it chanceth in the inward parts, ſometimes outwardly, inwardly by violent moving, and ſuch like may breake a veine, outwardly by
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60098:18"/>
Swords, Guns, Pikes, and other Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; alſo it doth happen by venomous medicines applyed to wounds, corrupting the veines, which cauſe a Flux; if the Flux happen in the inward parts, as in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Lungs, Reines, and Bladder, it is of hard curation, yet it muſt not be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, for which purpoſe all ſtipticke and conglutinating things muſt be uſed, as Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey roots, knot-graſſe roots, Gum Draga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gante, Terra Lemnia, Bolearmoniacke, Rice, Quinces, Lentils, Pomgranats, and ſuch other cooling drinkes are beſt, and broths made with the above-named ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples may help forward the cure, but this Medicine following I have proved; Rec. <hi>Pomgranat Rindes</hi> ℥j. <hi>Pulveriſ. Bolearmonack</hi> ℥ ſs. <hi>Terra Sigillata</hi> ℥ij. <hi>Knot-graſſe</hi> and <hi>Cumphrey roots</hi> pounded, and the juyce preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed out, <hi>Gum Dragagante</hi> ℥ <hi>ſs.</hi> intuſed in that juyce, make the ſaid Powders into Pills, like little Bullets with this infuſion, and give the ſick ſix of them in a day, three faſting in the morning, and three of them laſt at night, continuing this ten dayes, and it will make you whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="condition">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:60098:19"/>
               <head>14: The Flux in outward wounds</head>
               <p>ARe chiefly two, if it flow from the veines it is groſſe and red, if it come from the Arteries, it is of a purple colour, and commeth out by heaps, both theſe muſt be ſpeedily cured, if the Orifice be large; to cure this, take of <hi>Bolearmoniack, Terra Sigillata, ana.</hi> ℥j. <hi>Dragons bloud,</hi> ℥<hi>ſs. Alloes,</hi> and <hi>Frankenſence, ana.</hi> ℥ij. <hi>Hares haire</hi> cut in peeces, of Spunge of the Sea dryed and burnt, <hi>Dragagant</hi> brayed, mingle all theſe together and binde it to the wound, and let it reſt to the third day; ſo mans bloud dryed into powder will ſtench the bloud, the wound being filled: alſo, if need require you may binde the extreame parts, or open a veine in the contrary part, as if the right Arme be wounded, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen a veine in the left; you may cautorize the place, wet Lint in Vinegar, or a cloath wet in Vinegar and put about the Codds, hath been uſed with good effect; beſides all theſe, <hi>Gerrard</hi> in his <hi>Herball</hi> ſpeakes of an Herbe called <hi>Clownes all-heale,</hi> that was found out by a Mower which wounded himſelfe with his Sithe dangerouſly, he
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60098:19"/>
not having any Chirurgion neare, by accident gathered an Herbe which ſtenched the bloud, and after made a Medicine of the ſame Herbe and healed the wound; this being knowne to <hi>Gerrard</hi> he called it <hi>Clownes all heale,</hi> this I have proved. Alſo it hapned that I was comming from <hi>Winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> I met with a Souldier comming from a Fight neare <hi>Ailsford,</hi> which was woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded largely in the neck, ſo that the Flux of bloud could not be ſtopped, I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bered an Herbe ſhewed me by an old Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife that groweth in ſhadowed places, I ſearched under an Apple-tree and found the ſame Herbe, and gathered a handfull, and rubbed it in my hands, and filled the wound there-with, it ſtenched immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, after I made a Salve of the ſame Herbe, and cured the wound in 14. dayes, only I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nnoynted it with Oyle of <hi>Hipericon</hi> the ſecond dreſſing, and gave directions to him to doe likewiſe; the ſame Souldier <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame to my dwelling in 14. dayes perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y whole, and gave me thankes; this I have often proved ſince that time, the name of the Herbe is, <hi>Archangel,</hi> or <hi>dead Nettle,</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:60098:20"/>
which carryeth a purple Flower, this I made triall of when all other Medicines could not be gotten; I write this becauſe any Country people and Souldiers may finde this Herbe when Chirurgions be not preſent, and other Medicines farre di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, unleſſe the Souldier carry them in his Knap-ſack, and the Country-man keepe them in his Cloſet untill time of need.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="condition">
               <head>15 Of Wounds.</head>
               <p>VVOunds in generall are according to the ſeverall Members, as wounds in the head, face, neck, ſhoulders, and armes, &amp;c. but Wounds chiefly to be obſerved are two, that is, Mortall, and Curable; alſo wounds curable may be made mortall by ignorant Chirurgions, therefore I wiſh all men to haſten to an able Chirurgion. As wounds that are mortall is in the Braine, the Heart, the ſtomack, the ſmall Guts and the Bladder, nevertheleſſe I wiſh all Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgions not to neglect the meanes, for I have ſeen Gods mercy wonderfully ſhewn in giving ſtrength to Nature when the judgement of man faileth; As touching wounds ſuperficiall or deep after the Flux
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60098:20"/>
of bloud is ſtopped as before directed, and that your Chirurgion cannot be had; firſt conſider whether there be any diſlocation of bones or fractures, or whether any veines, Arteries, ſinews, ligaments, tendons, or Muſcels be wounded, if you finde any of theſe you muſt proceed to the Cure very carefully, or elſe you may make that wound gangred or rotten, which at the firſt might be cured; this I have ſeen by ignorant people, applying hot Medicines to hot and chollerick wounds, and cold Medicines to the cold cauſes, as <hi>Hemlock, Henbane,</hi> and ſuch others, which I omit, and come to ſhow you whether there be any Diſlocation or Fracture; Firſt, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare one member with the other, as if the ſhoulder be depreſſed it will be lower then the other, neither can the party lift it to his head; if the elbow be out of joynt, the hand cannot be turned about, neither wil it be like the other, for the reducing of ſuch a member, haſten to your Bone-ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but in his abſence if ſuch a thing hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in the fingers, toes, or the elbow, two men graſping the member very faſt, a third
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60098:21"/>
man directing them to pull in the joynt, and the ſaid third man with his right thumbe upon the place, the left hand turning the member into his right place, which the Patient will ſoone finde eaſe, if rightly performed. Further, if the ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der be out, let that man put his arme over the round of a Ladder, or over the head of another man that is higher then he that is diſlocated, the Chirurgion, or he that ſetteth the joynt put both his thumbs to the place, a ſecond miniſter or two holding faſt the lame Arme over the Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or over the ſame mans head, ſo the ſick may be above the ground, and the weight of his body with this help may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce this joynt into his proper place; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other wayes there are, but I omit, and come to Fractures, which muſt be very di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently placed, if in the thigh, or above the elbow where is but one bone it may be broke ſhort off, ſo the member wil be ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the other; this muſt be drawn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his proper place as before is ſhewed, if riven or ſhaken into ſplinters, they muſt be all placed and bound up in ſome frame or
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60098:21"/>
ſpleets, paſt-board, or Iron made accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the form of the member, if wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through the fleſh, there muſt be a place left for the dreſſing of the wound, and an implaiſter made with <hi>Bolearmonick, Terra ſigilata, Gum Dragagante, Dragons bloud, whites of Eggs</hi> laid upon Flax, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed round the member grieved, put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wound Oyle of <hi>Elder,</hi> and Oyle of <hi>Hipericon,</hi> alſo make Tents with Lint rowled in the ſame Oyle (but be ſure make them ſo, that you leave none of them behind when you take them out of the wound;) above all be ſure that no duſt nor haires fall in the wound, nor Lint left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind that commeth off the Tent; alſo there muſt be care had of wounds of dry bodies, and of moyſt bodies, as tender bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are more moyſt then thoſe that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and travell, if you finde them to be moyſt bodies, you may uſe drying powders, as <hi>Bolearmoniack,</hi> if proud fleſh, or dead fleſh, then uſe burnt Allum, or Precipitat, or you may make this powder: Rec. <hi>Sarco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colle,</hi> ℥j. <hi>Oliban.</hi> ℥ij. <hi>Aloes Epatick</hi> ℥iij. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick</hi> ℥j. <hi>Frankinſence,</hi> ℥ij. <hi>Dragons bloud</hi> ℥j <hi>ſs.</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:60098:22"/>
                  <hi>Balauſtia</hi> ℥j make this into fine powder and it will incarn wounds, if you finde the wound to be dry you may uſe the ſaid oyle of <hi>Hipericon,</hi> oyle of Lillies; if the ſinews be wounded, oyle of Elder is very good. To preſerve a wound from Impoſthumati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Rec: of Mallowes, Beets, Violet leaves, and Landebeef, of each a handful, boyle them until they be ſoft, then put in oyle of Roſes, and white Lillies, make a Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaſme or Poultis, with Roſes, Rye meale or Barley meale, adding ſome Hoglard, apply this warme until the Impoſtume be removed, for no wound can heale until the Impoſtume be cured.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe a Member may Cancern if not ſpeedily removed, that Member muſt be taken off; to prevent this you muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, whether the Member about the wound, do alter in coulour, gliſſen and of a blew colour, the member doth not quite rot, but the ſpirits being hindred from comming to that place, it doth mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie; which commeth by applying veno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Medicines, ſometimes by over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tying of a member when a bone is broken;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60098:22"/>
ſometimes by applying things that are cold, ſtipticke, and ſharpe, theſe and ſuch others may cauſe Cancerna, now to preſerve the Member wounded from can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerna; Rec. oyle of <hi>Roſes, Umphacin,</hi> oyle of <hi>Mirtive ana:</hi> ℥iij. the juice of <hi>Plantaine</hi> and <hi>Nightſhad, ana:</hi> ℥ij. <hi>ſs.</hi> let them ſeeth all together until the juice be waſted, then put to <hi>white Wax</hi> ℥j. <hi>ſs.</hi> Flower of <hi>Beanes, Lintiles,</hi> and <hi>Barley ana:</hi> ℥ij. <hi>ſs.</hi> of all the <hi>Sanders pulveriſed ana:</hi> ℥j. <hi>ſs. Bolarmenacke ℥j. graines</hi> and <hi>mirtiles</hi> a Dram, make this into a Plaiſter, with oyle of <hi>Elder,</hi> labour it in a morter into a plaiſter, beſides all theſe, there happneth Feavors, Cramps, Convulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and many other by applying evil Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines to a wound which muſt be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, before the cure wil be ended; if there be a Feavor, you muſt give cooling Gliſters and purge with Potions following, make a decoction with Cordiall flowers, in a ciate ful of that decoction, diſſolve of <hi>Diacatholicon</hi> of <hi>Diaprunis, ana: ℥ſs.</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup of <hi>Roſes ℥ſs.</hi> take this faſting as a poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if pained in the head, take <hi>Pilule cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie</hi> or <hi>Pilule aure,</hi> and ſuch like; if the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:60098:23"/>
Crampe aſſaile the body, rub the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber with warm clothes, or oyle of <hi>Hedg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hog;</hi> if a Convulſion, rub the pole and the member with oyle of <hi>Caſtoreum</hi> and <hi>Sage.</hi> Theſe impediments being removed, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed with the Cure as followeth; If the wound be large or dangerous, let his dyet be good Broths, and meats of eaſie dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, as Birds of the Hils, <hi>Mutton, Veale, Chickins</hi> and <hi>Rabbits;</hi> he muſt avoid ſalt meates, <hi>Beefe, Poulſe, Cabbig,</hi> and windy meates, as fruits, nor drink no inflaming drink: The next intention is to keep the body ſoluble, with potions, Pils, or Gliſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, then you muſt waſh the wound with this lotion, take <hi>Plantain water, Bugloſſe,</hi> or <hi>Burrage water, odoriſerous Wine, Pomgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net flowers, Plantain leaves,</hi> the flowers of <hi>St. Johns wort,</hi> boyle this together and waſh the wound, then make Tents and roule them in oyle of <hi>Hipericon,</hi> and fill the hollow places with them, then make Plaiſters to mundiſie: Rec. of clear <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine</hi> ℥ij. <hi>Hony</hi> of <hi>Roſes</hi> ℥j. <hi>Smallege</hi> ℥j. let them boyle together a little time, adde thereto the yolke of an <hi>egge, Saffron,</hi> a
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60098:23"/>
little <hi>Myrrh</hi> ℥ij. of <hi>Alloes</hi> ℥j. make this into a ſtiffe Plaiſter, with oyle of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and flower of Barley, this wil mundifie and clear a wound in two daies, if not very foule; after the wound is clear, you may proceed again with healing Medicines; if not mundified, you may uſe <hi>Unguentum E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giptiacum, or unguentum Baſilicum;</hi> and for a healing-Plaiſter, the wound being mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dified take of <hi>Clownes all-heale, falilly, Archangell, ana:</hi> one handful, pound them, and boile it in Hoglard, then ſtraine it, let it ſtand to be cold, take the top of it, poure away the bottome, and boile it with wax and Roſen, ſo much as is ſufficient to make a Plaiſter, this, or one of theſe Hearbs made in a Salve, will heale a green wound, or you may have this Implaiſter made at any Apothecaries, Rec. <hi>Salet oyle</hi> ℥iiij. <hi>white Wax</hi> ℥j. <hi>Turpentine</hi> ℥<hi>ſs. Greek Pitch,</hi> ℥j. <hi>Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,</hi> and <hi>Maſtick ana:</hi> ℥j <hi>Saffron</hi> ℈j. mingle theſe and boile them upon a gentle fire, and make Plaiſters: So I end for old Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, you may mundifie the Soare with <hi>White wine,</hi> and <hi>Aquavitae,</hi> or with the Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dificatives before written, as <hi>Egiptiacum,</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:60098:24"/>
or <hi>unguentum apoſtolorum,</hi> and finiſh the Cure with the above named Medicines.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="remedy">
               <head>16 To cure a Gun-ſhot.</head>
               <p>THe Chyrurgeons firſt intention muſt be to ſtop the Flux of blood, next to ſearch diligently, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the bullet do remain in the member wounded, or whether the bullet have carryed any thing before it into the wound, as Paper, cloath or ſuch like if ſo, the next intention is, with a <hi>Terra-bellum</hi> or other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to take it out. Make this Digeſtive, <hi>Rec:</hi> Turpentine waſhed in Aquaviter ℥iv. Vitelorum o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorum number ij. oyle of Roſes ℥<hi>ſs.</hi> Precipitat twice calcined <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. Saffron ℈j. commix this and make a Plaiſter, after this you may waſh the wound with Plantain water, red Roſe water, with oyle of Roſes and oyle of Elder, after mundific the wound with this: <hi>Rec:</hi> Venice Turpentine waſhed in Aquaviter ℥iij. oyle of Egges ℥j. or Yolkes of Egges number ij. Hony of Roſes, and ſurrup of Roſes, <hi>ana:</hi> ℥ij. the bran of Fetches, Frankinſence, Maſtick of each ℥<hi>ſs.</hi> cover your Tents, and make Plaiſters, until the wound bee cleane, then you may proceed to end the cure with the forcnamed oyle of Hipericon, and healing Salves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="remedy">
               <head>17 To cure Burning with Gun-Powder, or burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with fire and ſcalding.</head>
               <p>IF it happen that any part of the body be burned with Gunpowder or fire; take the Juyce of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyons ℥iv. and common ſalt ℥<hi>ſs.</hi> beat them well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60098:24"/>
and if the burn bliſtered, anoint it three or four times in a day, for three dayes, then you ſhall proceed as followeth: but if the skin be burnt, and made raw, you muſt cover it all over with the fineſt Lawn and, anoynt it with the Juice of Onyons, and Salt, letting the Lawn lye upon the wound, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it is whole; but if deeply burned, uſe this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, <hi>Rec.</hi> the fineſt <hi>Hoglard li.</hi> iv. Linſeed oyle <hi>li.</hi> ij. oyle of Roſes <hi>li. ſs.</hi> of Mallow-Leaves, Violet leaves, the Brood of Bees; Plantain leaves, Burnet, Peny-wort, Tulſon, Live-ever <hi>ana:</hi> Mj. infuſe theſe 6 dayes upon a gentle fire, adde thereto white Wax <hi>li: ſs,</hi> white Niter ℥vj. alſo you may put to Shoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers peece-greace, this being uſed will cure it, chipping off the Lawne, as it health: if there be Bliſters you muſt not cut them, it wil be painefull: you may make part of this Medicine if you need not the whole Receipt; Alſo if the burn or ſcald be not much, you may pound Onyons, and a little Salt, or Leeks with a little Salt, ſo much as will cover the ſoare, and let it lye 24 houres, in the interim, take a handfull of Houſe-Leek, and the inner bark of the Elder, bruiſe it and boyle it in a quart of Creame into an oyle, ſcum off the cleare oyle as it ariſeth, keep it and anoynt the ſoare place twice or thrice in the day, and it wil be whole, this I have often pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: You may beate into the Cream the white of an Egge, if your eyes or eye-lids ſhould be burned. <hi>Rec:</hi> Roſe water ℥iij Womans Milke ℥ij. the oyle of whites of two Eggs, Sugar Candy halfe a quartern,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60098:25"/>
mingle theſe and make an oyntment and annoynt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the eye-lids, and about the eyes: or you may make this, <hi>Rec:</hi> oyle of Roſes ℥vj. white Lead waſhed in Red Roſe water ℥ij. white Wax, oyle of the Whites of four Egges, the Gum called <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher,</hi> make this into an Unguent, to take away the ſpots and ſcarres, take oyle of Egges, and oyle of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, and waſh the face it cleareth the skin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Courteous Reader,</hi> Seeing many people, as wel Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers as others, have neglected the means in time of danger to preſerve their health, I thought good to ſhow you briefly ſome eaſie medicines, which may be had moſt of them with little coſt (other Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines may be made for you at the Apothecarys) to keep in your Cloſets, or Knap-ſacks untill time of need to make uſe of them in the abſence of your Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian or Chyrurgion, which I wiſh you to haſten unto for advice.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="apothecaries_weights_and_measures">
            <head>A Table of the Weights uſed by Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians,</head>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>A Scruple. ℈</item>
                  <item>A Dram. <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>
                  </item>
                  <item>An Ounce. ℥</item>
                  <item>A Pound. li.</item>
                  <item>A Quarter. q.</item>
                  <item>A Halfe: ſs.</item>
                  <item>A Handfull. M.</item>
                  <item>Of every one. ana.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
