<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The worlds prospect, or, A commentarie upon the 33 of Isaiah and the 14 vers[e] in these words, The sinners in Sion are afraid in which words are declared how farre the saints may sinne against knowledge and conscience and yet not sinne the sin against the Holy Ghost / delivered and set forth by John Emersone ...</title>
            <author>Emersone, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-10">2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39381</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E706</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2332</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12265916</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12265916</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58070</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A39381)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58070)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 142:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The worlds prospect, or, A commentarie upon the 33 of Isaiah and the 14 vers[e] in these words, The sinners in Sion are afraid in which words are declared how farre the saints may sinne against knowledge and conscience and yet not sinne the sin against the Holy Ghost / delivered and set forth by John Emersone ...</title>
                  <author>Emersone, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[54] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E.P. for Nicholas Gamage, and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah XXXIII, 14 --  Commentaries.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-10</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-11</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-11</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58070:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE
VVORLDS
PROSPECT:
<hi>OR,</hi>
A Commentarie upon
the 33 of ISAIAH, and the
14 verſ. In theſe words:
<hi>The ſinners in Sion are afraid.</hi>
In which words are declared,
how farre the Saints may ſinne
againſt Knowledge and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
and yet not ſinne
the ſin againſt the
holy Ghoſt. Delivered, And ſet forth by JOHN
EMERSONE ſometime paſtr, Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer
of the word in private.</p>
            <p>LONDON:
Printed by <hi>E. P.</hi> for <hi>Nicholas Gamage,</hi>
and are to be ſold at his ſhop on London-Bridge
neere the Gate. 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:58070:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58070:2"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <p>THe poynt from the Text is this:</p>
            <p>That ſinnes againſt Knowledge and
Conſcience, are ſinnes of a high nature;
and when God doth once ſet them upon
the Conſcience, they cauſe horror and vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,
both in the Saints and Rebrobates.</p>
            <p>From the poynts, there be theſe nine
particulars derived.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. All ſinnes committed againſt Knowledge
and Conſcience, are not the ſinnes againſt the
holy Ghoſt; for, ſinnes againſt Faith, are not
this ſinne.</item>
               <item>2. All ſinnes done wittingly and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly,
and willingly, are not this ſinne.</item>
               <item>3. The ſinne of unbeliefe, which ſome main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
to be the ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt, is
not that ſinne.</item>
               <item>4. Every for ſwearing and denying of the
truth of Chriſt, is not this ſinne.</item>
               <item>5. What ſinnes of Knowledge be, and how
they come to be the ſinnes againſt the holy
Ghoſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58070:3"/>6. A Declaration of this ſinne againſt the
holy Ghoſt.</item>
               <item>7. A reaſon given, why it is a ſinne unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable.</item>
               <item>8. Who the perſons be that commit this
ſinne.</item>
               <item>9. With what knowledge they muſt be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued,
that commit this ſinne againſt the holy
Ghoſt.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In this enſuing Treatiſe, Every one of
theſe particulars are fully proved; As alſo,
with a word of comfort, ſpoken in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
to troubled Conſciences, ſhewing that
they need not feare the aſſurance of their
eternall wel-being.</p>
            <p>With many other poynts, which are not
named in this preamble.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:58070:3"/>
            <head>THE
Worlds Proſpect.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ISAIAH 33. 14. verſ.</bibl>
               <q>The ſinners in Sion are afraid.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN theſe words, there be theſe three
things conſiderable:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The perſons who they are, in theſe
words, <hi>Sinners.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The place they dwelt, which was, <hi>in
Sion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. The effect of ſins, in theſe, <hi>Sinners.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In the laſt part of my Text, in theſe
word, <hi>They are afraid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From whence, I obſerve (by the way)
this obſervation; That ſinne is the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
cauſe of wicked mens feare.</p>
            <p>In the word ſinners, I note onely theſe
two ſorts of ſinners.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:58070:4"/>
The firſt ſort of ſinners that have the
guilt of ſinne lying upon their ſoules, which
guilt of theirs ſhall never be waſhed off
with the blood of Chriſt, for theſe two
Reaſons:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe Divine Wiſedome did
never ſet love and mercy on worke for the
ſatisfying of Divine Juſtice in their behalf.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God the Father did never ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynt
the blood of his Sonne to waſh off
the guilt that is upon their ſoules; and
therefore they muſt dye in their guilt
which lyeth upon their ſoules.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort of ſinners, which have
the guilt of ſinne lying upon their ſoules,
yet ſhall not dye in that guilt, for theſe two
Reaſons:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe God the Father did wiſely
contrive wayes, to ſatisfie Divine Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
in their behalf.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God the Father loved them,
and did freely waſh them in the fountaine
of his Sons blood; therefore, though they
were in guilt, yet they ſhall not dye in their
guilt.</p>
            <p>Now, in the handling of my Text, in the
fore-named particulars, I ſhall ſhew from
whence, ſinners were firſt derived, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:58070:4"/>
               <hi>Adam</hi> was the firſt man that ever ſinned,
and thus: The firſt ſinne that ever was in
man, was firſt found in our firſt Parents
<hi>Adam:</hi> And ſo, I ſay, by that meanes, the
ſinne of our firſt Parents <hi>Adam</hi> was impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
unto <hi>Rom. 5. 12.</hi> and ſo called our ſin,
<hi>Rom. 4. 25.</hi> Sinne was the onely cauſe of
<hi>Adams</hi> feare, <hi>Gen. 3. 9.</hi> So in like manner
ſinne is an originall of our feare, who are
the poſteritie of ſinfull <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come now to ſpeake of the place
where theſe ſinners dwelt, and that place I
told you was in <hi>Sion,</hi> a place, I ſay, which
God did chooſe above all other places, there
onely of purpoſe to put or place his
Name in. This place <hi>Sion,</hi> is a place un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable,
and therefore in the Scriptures
called, <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> of old, called <hi>Salem,</hi>
being the Mount on which <hi>Davids</hi> houſe
and Caſtle was placed, being in the City of
<hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to the Eaſt part of the ſame,
1 <hi>King. 11. 36. Deut. 11. 7, 11. Pſal. 132. 14.
Pſal. 125. 1. Rev. 14. 1. Sion</hi> a place where
the meanes of grace was; out of which
place, came alſo Perfection of Beauty,
<hi>Pſal. 52. 2.</hi> Jehovah, there was found in the
puritie of Ordinances, <hi>Sion</hi> was the Saints
inquiring place in the old time; I ſay, it was
<pb facs="tcp:58070:5"/>
their place of Reſidence,☞ there was their
hopes in times paſt in an ordinance-way,
and there is ſtill their hopes to enjoy Chriſt
in a viſible and glorious way for ever.
<hi>Though all the earth be mine, yet Sion have I
choſen to be the place of my habitation for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
and there will I dwell amongſt my people,
and will goe in and out before them for ever,
leading them forth even as a Shepheard doth
his flock. Glorious things are ſpoken of thee thou
City of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 35.</note> 
               <hi>for it is the place and City of the
great King (even Chriſt Jeſus) And I heard
him ſay unto me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 43. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 8.</note> 
               <hi>Sonne of Man, this is the
place of my Throne, and the place of the ſoales
of my feet, where I will dwell in the middeſt
of the Children of Iſrael for ever, and then
my holy name ſhall the houſe of Iſrael no more
defile, neither they nor their Kings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe ſinners which my Text ſpeakes of,
had their names given unto them from the
hainouſneſſe of their ſinnes. I ſay, as they
were ſinners, ſo they had the names of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
given unto them; And becauſe they
ſinned againſt the gift of grace in <hi>Sion,</hi> ſo
they were called ſinners of <hi>Sion,</hi> and in the
place where they dwelt <hi>They were afraid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sinnes committed againſt Knowledge,
be ſinnes of a high nature, and cauſe feare,
<pb facs="tcp:58070:5"/>
from theſe three particulars which were
conſiderable in my Text: From them, I
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay, are theſe poynts derived, which are
theſe:</p>
            <p>That ſinne committed againſt Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
and Knowledge, be ſins of a high na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure,
and when God doth charge them upon
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Conſcience, they cauſe terror and vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion,
both in the Saints, and alſo in the
Reprobates.</p>
            <p>In the opening of the poynt, I ſhall ſhew
unto you, how that all ſinnes committed
againſt Conſcience and Knowledge, is not
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt:</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <p>1. All ſinnes committed againſt Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
and Conſcience,<note place="margin">Luk. 1. 20.</note> are not this ſinne,<note place="margin">Numb. 2. 12.</note>
                     <hi>2 Sam. 12. 9. 1 King. 15. 5.</hi> ſinne againſt
faith is not this ſinne.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>2. Sinnes done wittingly and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ingly,
againſt Knowledge and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
are not this ſinne.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>3. All ſinnes againſt gifts and graces, are
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot this ſinne, 1 Cor. 1. 7, 11, 12. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 25. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 9.
The ſinne of unbeliefe, which ſome
maintaine to be the ſinne againſt the holy
Ghoſt, is not that ſinne; if it had bin this
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nne, then had the Diſciples of Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb facs="tcp:58070:6"/>
this ſinne. For, the Lord did often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
diſcover heavenly truths unto them
yet notwithſtanding, they beleeved not.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>4. Every forſwearing and denying o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
the truth of the Lord Jeſus, are not this
ſinne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Francis Spyra</hi> forſwore the truth o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
Chriſt, and denyed the ſame, againſt the
Knowledge of Conſcience, and againſt the
voice and dictate of the Spirit; yet for all
that, ſome thinke that he obtained mercy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
Alſo,<note place="margin">Mat. 26. 70, 72, 74, 75.</note> 
                     <hi>Peter</hi> denyed and forſwore the truth
of the Lord Jeſus, yet not damned.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>5. I will ſhew you what ſinnes of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
be, and will ſhew you how they
come to be the ſinne againſt the holy
Ghoſt.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>6. I will diſcover unto you, what the
ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt is.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>7. I will diſcover the Reaſon, why it is
a ſinne unpardonable.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>8. Who the perſons be that commit
that ſinne.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>9. With what knowledge they muſt be
endued that commit this ſinne.</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe nine particulars I ſhall endeavour
to draw into one compleat body, as if I had
named them one by one.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:58070:6"/>
I ſay, all ſinnes committed againſt Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edge
and Conſcience, are not the ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the holy Ghoſt: If it had been that
ſinne, then had <hi>David</hi> committed the ſinne
againſt the holy Ghoſt; for he ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
his Knowledge and Conſcience,
wittingly, willingly, and contrivingly.</p>
            <p>As for inſtance, in the matter or <hi>Uriah:</hi>
Firſt, he ſinned ſeeingly; Secondly, he ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
by the way of ſinfull fore-caſt. For the
firſt, he ſinned ſeeingly, in that he ſaw that
<hi>Berſhebah</hi> was with-child, he thought to
have fathered the child upon innocent <hi>Uri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi>
although he never knew of the beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
of it; he thought, if that he could have
got this good man unto his hands, all had
beene well, much more if <hi>Uriah</hi> had beene
with his wife. Take notice, I pray you,
how <hi>David</hi> ſeemingly loved this good
man, <hi>Vriah,</hi> 2 Sam. 11. 8, 12. <hi>And David
ſaid unto Vriah, Goe downe to thine houſe, and
waſh thy feet. And Vriah departed out of the
kings houſe and there followed him a meſſe ef
meat from the king. And David ſaid unto
Vriah, cameſt thou not from thy journey? why
then didſt thou not goe downe to thy houſe?
And David ſaid unto Vriah, Tarry here to
day alſo, and to morrow I will let thee depart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:58070:7"/>
I ſay, here was <hi>Davids</hi> faire love to <hi>Uri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi>
for his owne ſelfe-ends, for the preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
of that open ſhame which was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
upon him: I am verily perſwaded
that his Conſcience told him then, that he
had ſinned in this matter of <hi>Uriahs</hi> wife
and that made him by might and policy to
ſeeke ſome cloake to cover his ſhame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
for if that he had not knowne it, it had not
beene a ſinne to covet his nighbours
wife, eſpecially to commit adultery with
her, he would never have ſought out for a
cloake to have covered his ſhame.</p>
            <p>I ſay, his knowledge was ſo effectuall by
education, that he knew the breach of the
ſeventh and the tenth Commandement:
the tenour whereof is thus, <hi>Thou ſhalt not
covet thy neighbours wife:</hi> Alſo, he knew
the breach of the ſixth Commandement,
<hi>Thou ſhalt not kill;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet I ſay, by way of ſinfull fore-caſt, he
knew how to act the breach of the ſixth
Commandement, as you may ſee, how he
acted his wicked action by a wicked Agent;
he had no better way to contrive the
death of ſo good a man as <hi>Uriah</hi> was, but
onely making of <hi>Joab</hi> an Agent, to make
<hi>Vriah</hi> privily to carry the ſecrets of his
<pb facs="tcp:58070:7"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wne death, as by this Story at large appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth
in 2 <hi>Sam. 11. 15, 16. And it came to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſſe in the morning, that David wrote a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
to Joab, ſaying, Set Uriah in the fore-front
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the hotteſt battell, and retyre ye from him,
that he may be ſmitten and dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe words, you may obſerve <hi>Davids</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nfull fore-caſt, for the bringing about of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is ſinfull action; he would not be ſeen to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave a hand in this good mans death: yet
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he holy Ghoſt doth to all poſteritie ſet
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orth, That this holy man <hi>David</hi> had a hand
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>Uriahs</hi> death, 2 <hi>Sam. 12. 9. Thou haſt
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aine Uriah with the ſword:</hi> As if the holy
Ghoſt had ſaid thus, Though unto the eye
of the world thou art not ſeene to have a
and in this good mans death, yet this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ret
act of thine is not hid from the All-ſeeing
eye of Jehovah. I pried into thine
heart, and there I ſaw thy ſecret intention
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted, before ever thou didſt uſe the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
meanes to bring it to paſſe. Yea, I
ſaw in thine heart the Agent that thou
didſt aſſigne, for to bring to paſſe this thy
ſinfull action. I ſaw all thy turnings and
windings concerning <hi>Uriah,</hi> which by thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
were contrived; and becauſe thou didſt go
ſo cunningly to worke, to make the world
<pb facs="tcp:58070:8"/>
believe that thou hadſt no hand in this
mans death, I therefore thought good
to diſcover to all poſterities after thee
that which thou didſt ſo ſecretly act and
contrive.</p>
            <p>I will relate the chiefe heads of thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings
concerning <hi>Uriahs</hi> death; Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
thou didſt uſe <hi>Joab</hi> as thy Agent to
act thy wicked intent and purpoſe; yet I
will lay the guilt of that ſinne, not upon
<hi>Joab</hi> the Actor, but upon thee the contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
thereof; <hi>Thou haſt killed Uriah with the
ſword:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I could relate more of it then this, but I
ſtand not upon a publique relation, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to let the world ſee that thou art not
without publique ſinnes: I did looke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
thee at that very time of ſinning, as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
a perfect man, <hi>Save onely in the matter
of Urias,</hi> 1 King. 15. 5.</p>
            <p>David<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>becauſe he would be ſure of the
death of ſo good a man as</hi> Vriah <hi>was, he
went politickly to worke, That if there
were but two or three men ſlaine,</hi> Vriah
<hi>without queſtion might be one of them, as
appeared afterwards in the</hi> 2 Sam. 11. 17.
And it came to paſſe, when Joab obſerved the
City, that he aſſigned Vriah unto a place, where
<pb facs="tcp:58070:8"/>
he knew that valiant men were. And the men
of the Citie went, and fought with Joab; and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here fell ſome of the people of the ſervants of
David, and Vriah the Hittite dyed alſo.</p>
            <p>In the 2 of <hi>Sam. 12. 5.</hi> ſee how holy <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>
ſeemed to be ſorrowfull when the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<hi>Nathan</hi> came unto him, and ſpake
parabolically concerning <hi>Vriahs</hi> death, and
concerning the coveting of his wife. See,
I ſay, how <hi>David</hi> expreſſed ſorrow for <hi>Vri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs</hi>
wrong (not yet being convinced of his
death) untill God by the miniſtry of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi>
did ſet home the ſinne, and alſo the
guilt thereof, upon the Conſcience of this
good man, <hi>David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay, that although this good man, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi>
did ſinne grievouſly, both wittingly
and contrivingly; yet he ſinned not that
ſin againſt the holy Spirit: Yea, although
<hi>David</hi> ſinned deepely againſt his owne
knowledge and conſcience, yet he found
and obtained pardon, 2 <hi>Sam. 12. 13. And
Nathan ſaid unto David, The Lord hath put
away thy ſinne, thou ſhalt not dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay, that mercy which he obtained
from the Lord,<note place="margin">Iſa. 55. 3.</note> is called in the Scriptures,
<hi>His ſure mercies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 32. 15</note> Iſa. 55. 3. <hi>Jehovah</hi> had
ſworne that he would never faile <hi>David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:58070:9"/>
Thoſe whom <hi>Jehovah</hi> ſweares to ſhall
never want protection.</p>
            <p>I ſay, though this holy man ſinned ſo
grievouſly, yet he found and obtained par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,
and was accounted of God a perfect
man; yea, even in that very time of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">1 King. 15 5.</note>
               <hi>ſaving in the matter of Vriah, 1 King.
15. 5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All ſinnes committed againſt great gifts
and graces, are not this ſinne againſt the
holy Ghoſt. If it had beene this ſinne,
then had <hi>Solomon</hi> alſo committed this ſin
againſt the holy Ghoſt;<note place="margin">The Reaſ.</note> for he ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the graces and eſtate of a Saint-ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
ſpirit,<note place="margin">1 King. 11 9.</note> who was angry with him.
1 <hi>King. 11. 9.</hi> God appeared unto him
three ſeveral times, and did diſcover him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
unto him in an aboundant manner, as
you may ſee in 2 <hi>Chro. 1. 7, 11, 12. 1 King.
3. 5, 12. 1 King. 9. 3. chap. 11. 9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay, <hi>Solomon</hi> ſinned in a high nature a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the largeſt requeſts that ever man
had granted unto him; yea, he ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
all thoſe graces which <hi>Elſhaddai</hi> the
ſtrong Omnipotent God infuſed into him.
He angred the Lord; yea, he <hi>did evill in
the ſight of the Lord, 1 King. 11. 6.</hi> He is
ſaid, To walke contrary unto the good
<pb facs="tcp:58070:9"/>
wayes of <hi>David</hi> his Father; and as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>
angred the Lord, even ſo the Lord
was angry alſo with him, <hi>verſ. 9. who had
then appeared unto him twice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was a man endued with more know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
then ever any meer creature was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued
with; yea, he dived into the nature
and uſe of Plants; yea, into the very Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſop
that ſprung upon the wall. I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded,
if that the writings of <hi>Solomon</hi> had
not beene loſt (in the Capitvity) which he
had written upon the nature and uſe of
Plants and Herbs, then our Phyſitians
would have beene (next under God) able
to have cured all manner of diſeaſes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever,
except Hereditary diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>If God did furniſh him with ſo much
humane knowledge and skill in naturall
things, then much more did God indue
him with all heavenly graces. I ſay, <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah,</hi>
the ſtrong Omnipotent God, gave
unto him aboundantly all wiſedome and
graces, at his requeſt, 2 <hi>Chro. 1. 7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He had a great inlargement of graces;
yea, grace I ſay, as large as the waters in
the Ocean Seas: He had the largeſt ſtock
of grace that ever any man had, ſave the
Lord Jeſus, who was God and Man in one
Perſon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:58070:10"/>
If any man ſhall aske me the queſtion,<note place="margin">Queſt.</note>
whether ever any meer man ſhall attaine
unto the like meaſure of gifts and graces as
<hi>Solomon</hi> did?</p>
            <p>I anſwer,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> 
               <hi>Solomon</hi> was a Type and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure
of our Lord Jeſus; and therefore, it
was neceſſary that he ſhould be endued with
more gifts and graces then any other after
him ſaving the Lord Chriſt, whom he Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pified,
that ſo he might, in that age of the
world, repreſent the Subſtance of him, of
whom he was the ſhadow,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomon</hi> was a true figure of Chriſt, as
he was a ſubject of grace, and not as he was
a ſubject of foul ſinnes. I ſay, that all theſe,
and ſuch like Typicall repreſentations of
Chriſt, are now, ſince his comming in the
fleſh, ceaſed, he being the Subſtance of all
thoſe Types, figures, and ſhadowes.</p>
            <p>But as the Ceremoniall Law was a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure
of Chriſt in its Typicall obſervations,
as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Heb. 10. 1.</hi> Saying:
<hi>Now the Law is the ſhadow of good things to
come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, although beleevers now doe
not enjoy ſuch a larg meaſure of grace as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi>
did, yet they ſhall enjoy as true grace
(according to meaſure) as ever he did.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:58070:10"/>
I ſay, no man ſhall ever enjoy ſuch a
large meaſure of common grace as he did;
yet there's the ſame meaſured fulneſſe, as
is by Chriſt meaſured out for his Saints,
without being figures as <hi>Solomon</hi> was,
though he moſt grievouſly ſinned againſt
ſo large a ſtock of grace as he poſſeſſed;
yet not withſtanding, he obtained pardon,
2 <hi>Sam. 7. 15. Pſal. 89. 24. 3, 34. 2. Sam. 12. 24.</hi>
according to this promiſe of <hi>Jehovah</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
in theſe words: <hi>My loving kindneſſe
will I never take away from him, my truth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
and my mercy ſhall be with him, he ſhall
cry unto me, thou art my Father, my God, and
the Rock of my Salvation. My covenant wil
I not breake, nor alter the thing that is gone
out of my mouth.</hi>☜</p>
            <p>Although in truth, theſe words of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>
doe moſt truly and properly allude un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
Chriſt himſelfe, as the Subſtance, with
whom the everlaſting covenant was made
by the Father, for the worke of Salvation
in due time; yet they are ſhadowed out un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
us by the perſon of <hi>Solomon,</hi> who was the
ſhadow of the Subſtance, Chriſt; and whoſe
very Name, <hi>Solomon</hi> (being Wiſedome)
carries in it ſelfe the true portraiture of
Chriſt the Subſtance, who is the true
<pb facs="tcp:58070:11"/>
               <hi>Solomon,</hi> the true Wiſedome of the
Father.</p>
            <p>In theſe words is the purpoſe &amp; promiſe of
<hi>Jehovah</hi> confirmed, from his former reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution
in the ſhewing and beſtowing mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
on <hi>Solomon;</hi> notwithſtanding, all his
ſinnes committed againſt Gods great love
and mercy ſhewed unto him.</p>
            <p>He ſinned deepely and in a very high
meaſure, and did, as it were, out-live
grace (in regard of the life and ſweet ſenſe
and being of grace.) Yet, I ſay, he enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
the former ſenſe and ſweet enjoyment of
grace againe.</p>
            <p>I might aboundantly confirme the truth
of this poynt more fully, but I have other
matter to deliver.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Francis Spyra,</hi> Though he denyed the
truth of the Lord Jeſus againſt his Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
and Conſcience, and againſt a ſecret
Dictate and a ſudden voice, which forbad
him not to doe that which he was reſolved
to doe. I ſay, a ſecret Dictate bad him take
heed unto himſelfe, and to looke back un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
his former eſtate, and not to deliver up
all into the hands of thoſe that would bring
both him and his into bondage, and not to
yeeld unto that <hi>Legate,</hi> who told him that
<pb facs="tcp:58070:11"/>
if he would forſwear the truth of the Lord
Jeſus, and yeeld to them in all poynts, he
and his ſhould be maintained.</p>
            <p>When this <hi>Francis Spyra,</hi> was going
about to ſubſcribe unto their wicked
aſſignment then, even then, he heard a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
Dictate, which forbad him not to goe
againſt that truth which he formerly had
profeſſed: yet notwithſtanding, he did
wilfully deny the truth of the Lord Jeſus,
yet afterwards he had remorce of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
and was deeply wounded in his ſoule
and conſcience: Yea, he afterward made
Recantation, and was deeply wounded,
and his conſcience tormenting him, he
made a large Confeſſion of his ſinnes, and
the hainouſneſſe of them, and withall, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging,
that there was aboundance
of mercy in God if he could repent,
ſaying, If I could but Repent, then
there would be mercy for me, but I cannot
Repent of my preſent ſtate &amp; condition, it
being like the ſtate of <hi>Cain, Saul,</hi> and <hi>Judas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſſe, that if God ſhould damne
me, he might be juſt in all his dealings with
me: When thoſe which were about him bad
him pray, he told them, that he could not
pray; yet afterward they got him to pray,
<pb facs="tcp:58070:12"/>
and it is reported of him, that he prayed in
the Latine tongue, and expreſſed ſuch hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly
expreſſions, that no Reprobate could
expreſſe the like heavenly expreſſions.☞</p>
            <p>If you doe but looke into the book, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<hi>The Relation of Francis Spyra,</hi> therein
you may ſee more fuller of him then my
tongue ſhal expreſſe at this time, my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
bidding me keep within the compaſſe
of Chriſtian charitie, judging him to be a
glorified Saint in heaven; uſing, in I ſay, the
time of his diſtreſſe, ſuch unexpreſſable
words, which I in all the dayes of my life
never heard nor read of, could be in any
dying or living Reprobate.</p>
            <p>I doe alſo bring in S. <hi>Peter,</hi> who with
him denyed the truth, forſwore that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
knew him, whom formerly he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed,
yea, wittingly, though not willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
he denyed the Lord Jeſus, who by his
moſt precious blood bought him, yet he
for all that found and obtained pardon:
For, it is ſaid, that the Lord Jeſus, after he
had denyed him, looked back upon him;
Then ſaith the Text, <hi>Peter</hi> remembred the
words of Chriſt, who ſaid unto him, <hi>Before
the cock crow twice, thou ſhalt deny me thrice;
Then he remembred the words of Chriſt and</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:58070:12"/>
               <hi>went out, and wept bitterly.</hi> I ſay, Chriſt
told him, that <hi>Satan had a deſire for to win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now
him, as wheat was ſifted:</hi> But Chriſt
told him, that <hi>he had prayed him, that his
faith ſhould not fayle,</hi> Luk. 22. 31. intimating
thereby, that this fall of bleſſed <hi>Peter</hi> was
but a permiſſion of Satans temptation and
tryall of his faith (rather then eternall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection)
to ſhew unto after-poſterities that
Satan may ſometime (by permiſſion) have
power given him to batter the faith of
the ſtrongeſt Saint, and to make him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time
lye downe in ſorrow, as the holy
Ghoſt uſeth the phraſe in <hi>Eſaiah, 50. 10,
11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Peter,</hi> after his Converſion, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
the manifeſtations of pardon, he was
more couragious then before: And the
reaſon why bleſſed <hi>Peter</hi> fell ſo grievouſly,
was (as I conceive) only to let him know,
that the ſtrength he had was not his owne,
neither could he ſtand by that ſtrength, but
onely in, and by the ſtrength of a ſtronger
then himſelfe was, and afterward to make,
and to cauſe him to wait on the Lord, that
ſo he, in the time of want, might renew
his ſtrength as the holy Ghoſt doth uſe the
phraſe in <hi>Iſaiah, 40. 31, 32.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:58070:13"/>
The ſinne of unbeliefe, which ſome
maintaine to be the ſinne againſt the holy
Ghoſt, is not this ſinne; If it had bin this
ſinne, then had there ſome of Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies
committed this ſinne. As for inſtance,
<hi>Moſes,</hi> although a beleever, and faithfull in
his place, <hi>Heb. 3. 2. 5.</hi> yet in the very time of
tryall, was found unbeleeving, <hi>Numb. 20. 11.</hi>
And to ſhew, that he was found unbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,
the Lord told him, that he ſhould
not bring the people into the Land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi>
as the 12 <hi>verſ.</hi> tells you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zachariah,</hi> though a juſt man, as the word
teſtifieth, <hi>Luk. 1. 6.</hi> yet he was found un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeving,
<hi>verſ. 20.</hi> and to ſhew unto all
poſteritie this, that it was a ſinne, God did
inflict a temporall judgement upon his
body.</p>
            <p>Alſo, bleſſed <hi>Thomas,</hi> although a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever,
yet he was found unbeleeving,
<hi>Joh. 20. 25.</hi> And to confirme that which
I have ſpoken, reade to the 26. <hi>verſ.</hi>
In which <hi>verſ.</hi> the Lord Jeſus ſtoops
unto the act of <hi>Thomas</hi> his unbeliefe, and
and confirming his faith with his willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
to cure his unbeliefe.</p>
            <p>I will but give you one inſtance more,
to confirme what I have hitherto ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:58070:13"/>
concerning this ſinne of unbeliefe,
which is alſo ſuppoſed of ſome to be the
ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>I will bring in theſe places, which they
unskilfully name, to prove this ſinne of
unbeliefe, to be the ſinne againſt the holy
Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>I ſay, the Diſciples of Chriſt were in the
maine poynt of Faith, found unbeleeving,
queſtioning the truth which Chriſt did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly,
and at that time diſcover unto them,
<hi>Mark. 9. 10. Luk. 24. 21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to ſhew that it was a ſinne not to
beleeve, he gently reproves their unbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
ſpirits, <hi>v. 25. 26.</hi> and afterwards labours
by the exppoſition of thoſe Prophets which
had before propheſied of him, was now
ſince his reſurection manifeſted to be a
cleare truth which they before beleeved
not, <hi>verſ. 27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus <hi>I</hi> have proved,☜ that the ſinne
of unbeliefe, which ſome maintaine to be
the ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt, is not this
ſinne.</p>
            <p>I <hi>come now to handle their proofes,
which they produce for their conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi>
Ioh. 8. 24. If you beleeve not that I am
he, yee ſhall dye in your ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:58070:14"/>
Upon theſe words, <hi>I</hi> thus paraphraſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
The Lord Jeſus convinces the Jewes of
their unbeliefe, becauſe that they beleeved
not that he was the Chriſt: And the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
of their unbeliefe, was, becauſe they
beleeved not that it was he that was to
come, even the <hi>Meſſias;</hi> but they
looked on him with a carnall eye, being<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
I ſay, more carnall then ſpirituall, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
onely for a King, whoſe Kingdome and
Reigne ſhall be altogether temporall. And
ſo I ſay, dreaming to Reigne with him
in this world, they looked that he ſhould
have eſtabliſhed and reſtored that their
Kingdome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But then, they ſeeing the perſonall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
of Chriſt, ſo contemptible (as the
Prophet</hi> Jeremiah <hi>ſaith, and alſo the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi>
Iſaiah, His preſence ſhall be by us not
deſirable (or) contemptible: When we ſee
him, he ſhall have neither forme nor beauty.</p>
            <p>Therefore, theſe Jewes, when they ſaw
Chriſt with their naturall eyes onely, they
did not beleeve that he was he which was
to com. And in the 18. <hi>verſ.</hi> There the
Lord Jeſus tells the Jewes. That he was
one that did beare witneſſe of himſelfe,
and that the Father did alſo beare witneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:58070:14"/>
of him. And in the 19. <hi>verſ.</hi> They had a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſire, that he would ſhew them his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her.
Whereupon he tells them, That if
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey had knowne the Father, they would
alſo have known him: And from hence did
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſecond cauſe of their unbeliefe ariſe: And
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur Saviour Chriſt tells them plainly, That
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f they did not beleeve he was that Chriſt,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey ſhould dye in their ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Another place is the 1 of</hi> Judges, 5 verſ.
<hi>How that the Lord having ſaved the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
out of the Land of Aegypt, afterwards
deſtroyed them that beleeved not. Alſo,</hi>
Mark. 16. 16. He that beleeveth not ſhall
be damned. Joh. 3. 18. He that beleeveth
not is condemned already, becauſe he beleveth
not in the Name of the onely begotten Sonne
of God.</p>
            <p>Unto this place I doe thus reply:</p>
            <p>That our Lord Jeſus doth not abſolutely
ſpeake of an eternall condemnation, if it
were ſpoken of an eternall eſtate of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation,
then muſt the Elect themſelves
be in that eſtate, for their is no difference,
<hi>Rom. 3. 23.</hi> The Elect themſelves, before
they be in the eſtate of faith, are firſt in the
eſtate of unbeleeving, 2 <hi>Cor. 6. 11. Such
were ſome of you, but now ye are waſhed, but</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:58070:15"/>
               <hi>yee are ſanctified, but yee are justified in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
Name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
of our God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe words, you may ſee the cond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of beleevers ſet forth unto you, ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
that they are prone unto all manner of ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
as well as the ſinne of unbeliefe, but no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
you ſee a bleſſed change in them: Ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fore
the ſinne of unbeliefe cannot be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt, as ſome ide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
have affirmed.</p>
            <p>I now will in a word or two ſhew yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
how that the Saints of God can fall into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
unpardonable ſinnes, though they may fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
into many great ſinnes (as you heard.) Yet
ſay, for the comfort of all diſtreſſed conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
that are incumbred with falſe feare
from falſe grounds; whoſe feare, becau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
their ſinnes appeare great in their appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion,
and ſo from a falſe ground as
ſaid before.</p>
            <p>Therefore, from hence they conclude
that they have ſinned againſt the holy
Ghoſt, and that thus, their ſinnes are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable.
Therefore, for the helping o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
ſuch poore diſtreſſed conſciences out of
theſe falſe feares, and to ſatisfie their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences
that they have committed this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable
<pb facs="tcp:58070:15"/>
ſinne. I addes theſe two reaſons
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r their ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>The firſt Reaſon is this, becauſe all the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ints of God, are all borne of God,
<hi>Joh. 5. 18.</hi> That is, they are Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d,
and thus made new creatures, <hi>Joh. 3. 3.</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d ſo are ſaved, <hi>Tit. 3. 5.</hi> and clenſed,
<hi>Cor. 6. 11.</hi> by the Spirit of their God,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d ſo enter in with the Lord Jeſus, who is
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e doore, <hi>Joh. 1. 10.</hi> and enter into the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ait gate, <hi>Luk. 13. 24.</hi> who is <hi>the Way, the
truth, and the life,</hi> Joh. 14. 6.</p>
            <p>You Saints that are full of falſe feares,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t me ſpeake unto you, I ſay, that you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
commit this unpardonable ſinne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uſe
the Father gave his Sonne unto this
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ery end and purpoſe, for to redeeme his
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ople from their ſinnes, <hi>Tit. 2. 14.</hi> I ſay,
<hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ehovah</hi> hath for his owne names ſake for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ven
all your ſinnes, <hi>Iſa. 43. 23, 44, 22.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er. 31. 22, 32, 31, 33, 33, 6.</hi> And <hi>Heb.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 12. Mich. 7. 18, 19. Pſal. 103. 13. Who
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a God like unto thee, that will pardon the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iquities of the remnant of his heritage, and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill ſubdue them into the bottome of the Seas?</hi>
The ſecond Reaſon is, The Lord Jeſus
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd his Saints have all one oneneſſe,
<hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 5. 7.</hi> They that be joyned unto the
<pb facs="tcp:58070:16"/>
Lord Jeſus, they be one Spirit, yea, one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
union, one in love, one with the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,
and with all the three Perſons in all the
glorious Trinitie. See to this purpoſe
<hi>Ioh. 17. 23, 25, 26. I in them, and they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
me.</hi> I ſay, God is aboundantly glorious
unto beleevers, yea, to multiply pardon
<hi>Iſa. 55. 7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And for a farther Relation of Gods fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
mercy, in pardoning of thoſe that turn
unto him, I note theſe ſeverall places <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
Scriptures for confirmation,</hi> 2 Chron. 30<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
33, 12, 13. Gen. 18. 15. Exod. 6. 1, 9, 11, 26, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>,
7, 20, 6, 34, 7, 8. Numb. 20. 8. Deut. 4. 30, 31,
5, 10, 17, 18, 28, 1, 15, v. 30, 1, 11, 32, 4, 3, 6,
10. 2. Sam. 7, 8, 9, 15, 12, 13, 24, 10, 11, 13,
1 King. 8. 23. Levit. 20. 5, 10. Nehem. 9. 17.
Pſal. 21. 7, 35, 5, 7, 5, 10, 86, 5, 10, 111<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4. Pſal.
145. Iſa. 30. 18, 54, 8, 9, 10, 55, 3, 7. Ier. 12. 15,
16, 18, 8. Ezek. 18. 32, 33, 14, 15, 16. Hoſ. 2. 14,
19, 23. Ioel. 2. 13. Ion. 4. 2. Ier. 3. 2, 12, 14,
Luk. 1. 50, 58, 72. Luk. 18. 4, 6, 36. Luk. 7. 47,
23, 34, 43. Rom. 4. 7. 2 Cor. 1. 3. Epheſi. 2. 4.
1 Tim. 1. 13, 15, 16, 18.</p>
            <p>Theſe places of Scripture doe ſet forth
the freeneſſe of Gods love unto all belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers:
Yea, I ſay, they doe ſhew the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
of Gods love in his ſhewing of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
<pb facs="tcp:58070:16"/>
and in manifeſting of it unto all belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,
who, I ſay, ſhall never come into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation,
becauſe the Lord Jeſus Chriſt
hath caſt out of them the ſin of condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<hi>Rom. 8. 1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus you may ſee, that all beleevers be
happy and bleſſed. Oh! the bleſſedneſſe of
that man, as it is in the originall,</hi> Rom. 8. 32,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>9, verſ. Who ſhall lay any thing unto the
charge of Gods choſen? It is God that juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth:
Who ſhall condemne? It is Chriſt which
is dead, yea, rather, which is riſen from the
dead, who is alſo at the right hand of God, and
maketh requeſt for us. Who ſhall ſeparate us
from the love of Chriſt? ſhall Tribulation, or
Anguiſh or Perſecution, or Famine, or Naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
or Perill, or Sword? <hi>As it is written,</hi>
for thy ſake are we killed all the day long,
we are accounted as ſheepe for the ſlaughter.</p>
            <p>In theſe words, the ſure ſtate of the
ſaints is ſet forth unto us, to ſhew
Gods Omnipotent will and purpoſe which
never changes: It is not the Divell, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
belonging unto him, can alter Gods
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ove to his Saints or doe them any wrong.</p>
            <p>Chriſt, I ſay, hath ſet them in a glorious
libertie, <hi>Gal. 5. 1. Ioh. 8. 38.</hi> Now I come to
ſhew unto you what the ſinne againſt the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oly Ghoſt is.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:58070:17"/>
The ſinne againſt the holy Spirit i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
when a man hath been inlightned with the
heavenly truth (Chriſt Jeſus) by the holy
Spirit of the Father,<note place="margin">What the ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt is.</note> who is that Spirit of
truth ſpoken of, <hi>Ioh. 14. 26.</hi> Whoſe office
is to <hi>ſeale us unto the day of redemption<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
Epheſi. 4. 30.</p>
            <p>And then, not onely ſtrive againſt that
truth, but alſo blaſpheme that truth, as the
Jewes did, ſaying, <hi>He caſteth out Devill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
by Belzebub the Prince of the Devills.</hi> And
thus ſhall wittingly and willingly againſt
the checks of his owne conſcience, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute
that truth in his members, the Saints<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
becauſe he knows, that it is the truth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
he is of purpoſe reſolved to oppoſe that
ſacred truth, and to deſpiſe that ſacred light
wherwith he was inlightned; &amp; alſo, eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
that ſacred blood of Chriſt as nothing,
treading it under foot: And thus, out of a
pernicious ſpirit, moſt wickedly perſecutes
the truth in his members, even the ſons and
daughters of truth, becauſe he knowes, that
they are the ſubjects of that ſacred truth.
This is the ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>I ſay, The perſons that commit this
ſinne, muſt be knowing perſons, and men
of knowledge.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:58070:17"/>
Such a one was <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate,☞ who
notwithſtanding his certaine knowledge
of Chriſt to be the Sonne of God, yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
knowledge, fell off and became a
great perſecutor of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>They muſt be ſuch as are acquainted
with the Truth, even the Lord Jeſus, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
enlightened with the ſaving Light of
the holy Spirit; ſuch were the Scribes,
and <hi>Judas,</hi> and many other Reprobates,
which the Scripture ſpeakes of in many
places.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judas</hi> ſinned againſt his Knowledge and
Conſcience; <hi>Cain</hi> alſo in like manner a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
Knowledge and Conſcience, his
Conſcience at that very time informing
him, that <hi>Elſhaddai,</hi> the ſtrong and om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent
God, had reſpect unto the offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
of righteous <hi>Abel;</hi> and that his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
was accepted, according unto the rule
of the Law, <hi>perfect ſhall it be accepted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although <hi>Cain</hi> knew, that God had a
reſpect unto his brother <hi>Abel,</hi> and to his
offering; yet notwithſtanding, hee did
againſt his knowledge perſecute his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:
as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſayth, <hi>Abels workes were
good, and Cains evill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sinne againſt Knowledge is this: as
<pb facs="tcp:58070:18"/>
when a man or woman is informed of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
Truths, and by the judgement of
their underſtanding give an approbation
unto thoſe Truths diſcovered unto them,
and yet notwithſtanding will ſinne; this
is called by me, ſinnes againſt Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p>Sinne againſt Conſcience is, when a
mans Conſcience is enlightened with
Knowledge, concerning the acting this
thing or that thing, which is evill, and yet
is reſolved to doe it; this is called, ſinne
againſt Conſcience.</p>
            <p>I ſay, all that be damned ſinne not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
Knowledge, openly diſcovered unto
them; as the Heathen, who knew God no
farther but onely by the inſtinct of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
having <hi>the Law written in their hearts,
Rom. 2. 15.</hi> Which Law ſhall not leave
them without excuſe at the laſt day: for
they know ſo much of God, as ſhall be a
meanes for to condemne them, their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences
bearing witneſſe againſt them,
and ſo leaving their Conſciences void of
all excuſe; telling them, that there is a
God before whoſe Judgement-Seat they
muſt one day appeare.</p>
            <p>I am perſwaded, that the Conſciences
<pb facs="tcp:58070:18"/>
of the Heathen cannot chuſe but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
caſt forth ſome light of terror unto
them, and ſo cauſe an amazement unto
them; although they as Heathen be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
the knowledge of Conſcience towards
God and man.</p>
            <p>I ſay, ſinnes committed wittingly
and willingly, are the originall cauſe of
ſorrow both in the Saints and Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates.</p>
            <p>The ſorrow of the Saints for ſinne,
comes from an apprehenſion of Gods love
in the Lord Jeſus, looking upon the love
of God and his holineſſe, and then caſting
back his eye upon his owne ſinfulneſſe,
which produceth a mourning in them;
whereby, from an apprehenſion of Gods
abundant goodneſſe towards him, hee is
inforced with bleſſed <hi>Paul</hi> to crie out, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">Rom. 7. 24</note>
               <hi>O wretched man that I am!</hi> O, how
unlike unto God am I in holineſſe! O
that God would once lift up upon me
the light of his countenance, and ſmile
graciouſly upon my ſoule, in the face of
the Lord Jeſus! O that God would but
goe into my ſoule, and diſcover Chriſt
there unto me, and goe out againe by the
manifeſtation of his holy Spirit, that ſo my
<pb facs="tcp:58070:19"/>
ſoule may be acquainted with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings
in of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <p>The ſenſe of a Reprobate, is onely from
an apprehenſion of Gods wrath for ſinne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
and ſo, out of a ſlaviſh feare, confeſſes hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
ſinne, becauſe he ſees the wrath of God
appearing readie to be poured out upon
him for thoſe ſinnes which he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
againſt God: and ſo cryes out, as
being void of all hope of mercie, like
<hi>Cain, Saul,</hi> and <hi>Iudas,</hi> concluding that their
ſinnes are unpardonable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſay againe, the perſons that commit
this ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt, muſt be
ſuch perſons as in ſome meaſure knew the
maine fundamentall grounds of Religion,
and withall they muſt have ſome ſoule-taſte
of heaven, yea of heavenly things, as
bleſſed</hi> Paul <hi>ſpeaketh in</hi> Heb. 6. 4. For it
is impoſſible for thoſe who were once enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened,
and have taſted of the heavenly gifts,
and were made partakers of the holy Ghoſt,
and have taſted of the Word of God, and the
powers of the world to come, if they fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,
to renew them againe vnto repentance,
ſeeing they crucifie unto themſelves the Sonne
of God afreſh, and put him to open ſhame.</p>
            <p>In theſe words you ſee, that thoſe that
<pb facs="tcp:58070:19"/>
commit this ſinne, muſt be knowing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons:
they may have a taſte ſeemingly of
the holy Ghoſt; I ſay, the holy Ghoſt may
ſeemingly diſcover Truths unto them, yet
they ſhall never taſte of them ſavingly;
yet they ſhall taſte of them ſo fully, as to
their thinking they ſhall be, as it were, ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated
into heaven, and raviſhed with a kind
of ſweetneſſe ſo farre, as that they ſhall
conceit themſelves to be in a heavenly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iudas</hi> taſted of the heavenly gifts ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly,
and was endued with great light;
yea, with ſuch a meaſure of gifts, that he
was inabled by them to walke ſo warily,
that he was not found out to be an hypocrite
untill he made a diſcovery of himſelfe: he
had the ſame power given unto him as the
reſt of the Diſciples had, <hi>Mat. 10. 2:</hi> He
had a legall faith, but not a ſaving faith: he
poſſeſſed a common enjoyment from the
holy Ghoſt in regard of gifts, I ſay, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
taſte; he enjoyed not ſuch a taſte as
the Saints doe taſte, it is impoſſible for
wicked men to enjoy that true inward
taſte, and ſweet ſaving enjoyment of the
holy Ghoſt, as the Saints doe; Yet the
common enjoyment of the Spirit of God
<pb facs="tcp:58070:20"/>
they doe poſſeſſe, which ſhall leave them
without excuſe. Sometimes a wicked
man may goe in ſome things beyond the
Child of God, and may find more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
in the way of Ordinances, then the
true child of God doth (for a time.) Yea,
he may alſo walke more warily, then thoſe
who have more truer relation unto God,
even as the Scribes and Phariſees did, who
in hypocriſie lived more preciſely then the
true Children of God, for that none could
tax them of any thing, but onely Chriſt,
who knew their hypocriſie and corruption
of their hearts; as alſo the vanitie of their
Traditionall workes.</p>
            <p>The Diſciples of Chriſt knew not <hi>Iudas</hi>
to be an hypocrite, untill he diſcovered
himſelfe. And as I ſaid before, the perſons
that commit this ſinne againſt the holy
Ghoſt, muſt be knowing perſons, ſuch as
<hi>Iudas</hi> was, and the Scribes and Phariſees. I
told you, that the heathen could not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
this ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt, nor
can any infant commit this ſinne, although
God may juſtly damne infants, for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall
ſinne of their firſt parents.</p>
            <p>It followes now,<note place="margin">Why it is called the ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt.</note> that I muſt according
to my power, ſhew unto you the Reaſon,
why this ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt is an
unpardonable ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:58070:20"/>
It is called the ſinne againſt the holy
Ghoſt, becauſe he diſcovers and reveales
truth: And it is unpardonable, ſo long as
thoſe do commit ſinne againſt him, who is
called the third Perſon, and is the repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative
power of the whole Deitie: when
they ſinne againſt the holy Spirit, they ſin
againſt the whole Trinitie, as it is ſaid,
<hi>They grieved the Spirit of God,</hi> even him,
whoſe office is to ſeale the Saints unto the
day of redemption.</p>
            <p>Men, I ſay, by ſinning againſt this Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
confirme their guilt upon their owne
ſoules. To give you a bigger Reaſon then I
have yet done, why this ſinne againſt the
holy Ghoſt is unpardonable, I ſay, the full
Reaſon is,</p>
            <p>Becauſe it is his place to reconcile, or
worke reconciliation betweene the other
two Perſons and the ſinner, which before
were unreconciled: By this meanes the
ſinner comes to ſtand before the other
two Perſons the Father and the Sonne,
and thus finds acceptance. And on the
contrary, when this Perſon will not recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile
the ſinner unto God the Father, not he
himſelfe pleaſed to be reconciled unto the
ſinner; I ſay, it is then a very ſad and heavy
<pb facs="tcp:58070:21"/>
time with that ſoule. It cannot be, but
that ſoule muſt remaine in a ſtate of guilt,
and that for ever, and it muſt be guilt of a
deepe dye, that cannot be waſhed (and in
reſpect of the majeſtie and honour of the
Trinitie) muſt not be waſhed off with the
blood of the Lord Jeſus, becauſe ſo decreed
by <hi>Iehovah</hi> from all eternity.</p>
            <p>I ſay, unto all you that ſtand to heare
me this day, That it will prove a very ſad
time with you, if that the Lord Jeſus hath
not by his blood waſhed off your guilt,
that doth as yet lye upon your ſoules: ſad
will it be with you, and black will be your
day, when God comes to avenge the black
ſinnes of guilt, beſides your other ſinnes;
There is therefore but two wayes with
you, either to be purged from your guilt,
or elſe for ever to dye in your guilt of ſin.
Sad will be your condition, if ever God
ſhould ſay unto you now, or at the laſt
day, <hi>What make you here among theſe, whoſe
guilt of ſinne, my hath Sonne by his moſt preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
blood waſhed off?</hi> What doe you here?
Depart, I know you not: my Sonne never
dyed for you, nor ſhed one drop of his
blood to waſh off your guilt. If my Sonne
had ſhed but one drop of his moſt preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:58070:21"/>
blood for you, then ſhould you have
beene, at this time, made partakers of it:
For my part, I would never have detained
that bleſſedneſſe from you, that ſhould
have accrued unto you by it, one drop of
it being able to have waſhed off all your
guilt: But ſeeing it is not ſo, therefore
you have no part nor portion in the Sonne
of my love: Away therefore from me you
Reprobates, goe along with the reſt of
your fellowes the Reprobates, into the
lake that burneth with the flames of my
eternall vengeance, and there remaine for
all eternitie: Yea, I will inable you to
ſuffer eternall torments, ſo long, as I am,
which is, God, bleſſed for ever; yea, I will
hold you up in torments ſo long as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine
amongſt my Saints in glory, which
is, for evermore. And as I doe delight to
fill my Saints full of joy and glory un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable;
ſo will I in like manner delight
to ſatisfie the juſtice of my eternall male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction
upon you, that thoſe guiltie ſoules
and conſciences of yours, unto all eternity
may undergoe the portion of my wrath
aſſigned them, <hi>For I know your workes,</hi> Iſa.
6618. Hoſ. 7. 2. <hi>I remember all their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
And ſo Hoſ. 9. 9. <hi>Therefore he hath</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:58070:22"/>
               <hi>remembreth their iniquities, he will viſit their
ſinnes.</hi> Ezek. 9. 10. <hi>And as for me alſo,
mine eye ſhall not ſpare them, neither will I
have pittie; but I will recompence their wayes
upon their owne heads.</hi> And ſo, <hi>Ezek. 7. 9.
Hoſ. 12, 14.</hi> the 9, 15.</p>
            <p>I ſay, The ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt is
unpardonable, for this one Reaſon more,
which is more conſonant then any which I
have given you hitherto. I ſay, this ſinne
is an unpardonable ſinne, becauſe the holy
Sanctifying Spirit doth, as it were, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre
a Bill of Indictment againſt the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
that hath ſinned againſt him.</p>
            <p>By the way, give me leave to bring in a
Suppoſition (which ſhall never be brought
to paſſe.) Suppoſe I ſay, That God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
ſhould take a ſinner that had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
the ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt, and ſet
him before the Barre of his juſtice, and
there ſhould appeale unto his juſtice in the
ſoules behalfe, ſaying, Juſtice, I am come
unto thee in this ſinners behalfe, what
ſayeſt thou unto me? Art thou willing to
be reconciled to this ſinner? he is a great
ſinner. Juſtice gives in (as it were) his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
unto God the Father, ſaying, I am
willing to be ſatisfied in this ſinners be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe,
<pb facs="tcp:58070:22"/>
be his ſinnes never ſo great; yea, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
the ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Then God (as it were) goeth unto the
Lord Jeſus, and tells him, that he hath
beene with Juſtice, and Juſtice is willing
to be reconciled in this ſinners behalfe:
What ſayeſt thou unto me? Art thou wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
to bind thy ſelfe over to ſatisfie my
Divine Iuſtice in this ſoules behalfe? Art
thou willing to become a fountaine of
blood, to waſh off the infiniteneſſe of this
ſoules guilt, that ſo this ſinne againſt the
holy Ghoſt, which this ſoule hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
might be forgiven, and for ever par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned?</p>
            <p>I am, ſayth Chriſt, (as it were) unto
God his Father, very willing to yeeld
unto this, concerning this ſoule that
ſtands here at the Barre of Iuſtice, for
mercy.</p>
            <p>Father, if it be thy will, to have this
ſoules guilt waſhed off, I am willing to give
conſent, that ſo this ſoules guilt by my
blood might be waſhed off, that ſo this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable
ſinne which this ſoule hath
committed againſt thy holy Spirit might
be forgiven, and for ever pardoned,
that ſo he might not for ever dye in his
guilt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:58070:23"/>
If this were ſo indeed, as I have ſaid,
then were there ſome poſſibilitie of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie
to that ſoule, that ſtands thus at the
barre of Juſtice. But if the third perſon
comes not in like manner with a propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,
and ſo anſwers the ſuppoſition; then
I ſay, is that (which was onely ſuppoſed to
be) quite overthrowne: for, a ſuppoſition
dependeth upon a propoſition.</p>
            <p>God goeth (as it were) unto the third
Perſon, and (as it is onely ſuppoſed)
asketh him in like manner, ſaying:</p>
            <p>I have beene with Juſtice, and I have
beene with my Sonne, and asked his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
and he is willing to ſatisfie me and
my Juſtice, and wee are all agreed, and
have given in our conſents concerning
this ſoule, and in his behalfe wee want the
conſent of none, but onely thy conſent;
Art thou willing to ſeale unto this ſoules
pardon, if I waſh off his guilt with the
bloud of my Sonne, wilt thou doe thy of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,
and ſeale to him the aſſurance of his
pardon?</p>
            <p>If thus the ſinners guilt be pardoned,
the holy Ghoſt then looking upon the
guiltie ſoule, appeales unto God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
(in this ſuppoſed manner ſaying)
<pb facs="tcp:58070:23"/>
What have you done here? You gave in
your conſents to appeaſe Juſtice. Is there
a pardon by bloud granted, and doe you
want nothing thereunto, but onely the
Seale, to give aſſurance to that pardon? I
ſay, you want nothing but my conſent in
this ſinners behalfe. If that you had but
my conſent equally unto yours, then
might this ſoules ſinnes be pardoned,
though he hath ſinned againſt me in ſuch
a high manner as he hath done. I ſay, it
is not with my conſent, that this ſinner
ſhould ever finde pardon, for hee hath
beene a very great ſinner againſt me wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly,
as alſo againſt thoſe divine diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries
which I according unto my office
did diſcover unto him; againſt all which
hee hath moſt wittingly and wilfully
tranſgreſſed, yea, hee hath out of a
pernitious ſpirit ſinned againſt me and
all thoſe fore-named diſcoveries which
I did infuſe into him. If that hee had
not ſinned againſt me out of malice,
and out of a ſet purpoſe; it would
never have grieved my holy Spirit ſo
much as now it doth: hee ſtrove a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
that Light which I enlightened
him with.
<pb facs="tcp:58070:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:58070:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:58070:25"/>
Shall I give in my conſent to have the
ſinnes of ſuch a ſoule as this pardoned? I
can in no wiſe yeeld, and ſo goe againſt
Juſtice. Juſtice, according unto truth,
muſt be a ſubject unto me, becauſe I am
the very Spirit of Truth it ſelfe, and have a
proper relation and dependancy upon the
other two Perſons in the moſt ſacred and
glorious Trinitie; And therefore, I ſay,
Juſtice muſt yeeld unto me as well as to
you.</p>
            <p>You know, that ſoule that ſinneth, that
ſoule ſhall dye: But this ſoule hath ſinned,
therefore this ſoule ſhall dye.</p>
            <p>And becauſe thy Divine Wiſedome did
never appoynt thy willed act wiſely to
ſet thy love and mercy on worke, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive
a way for ſuch wilfull ſinners, that ſo
their guilt might have beene waſhed off:
Therefore, as they are in guilt, even ſo let
their guilt remaine to all eternitie.</p>
            <p>This ſinner hath out-lived grace, and
the day of redemption is paſt, and all hopes
of mercy is now expired.</p>
            <p>Shall therefore ſuch a ſoule find mercy,
who hath thus wilfully oppoſed me, and
turned from me? Shall he, I ſay, find par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:58070:25"/>
He that hath often ſent me away ſad,
ſhall ſuch a ſoule as this find mercy?
This ſoule, I ſay, that hath more then
once or twice ſent me away ſad, whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
I came to execute my Office: This
vild wretch, that hath made flight of me,
and of thoſe Sacred Dictates which I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered
unto him, at ſuch a time, and at
ſuch a time.</p>
            <p>Surely, as I am God, equall with you
this ſoule that hath thus and thus ſinned'
he ſhall never find mercy. If he find mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
if he be waſhed in thy Sonnes blood
from this his guilt, then where is the
unitie in us? The glorious Trinitie, and
the moſt glorious conformitie in our uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie?
If that this Soules ſinnes be pardoned,
where then is the firmneſſe of our Decree?
If this ſoules ſinnes be pardoned, then is
our unitie in Trinitie, and conformity in
unitie overthrowne, and the word of truth
is falſifyed, which ſhewed unto the world,
what oneneſſe there was with us before
theſe worlds were created. What, ſhall all
our oneneſſe be diſ-joyned for this ſoules
ſake?</p>
            <p>Upon this (ſuppoſed) ſpeech, the other
two Perſons give in (as it were) their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb facs="tcp:58070:26"/>
againſt the ſoule then ſtanding at the
Barre of Iuſtice, and God ſpeaking to that
guiltie ſoule in this manner, As a Iudge
doth unto a Malefactor, being caſt by the
the Iury that goeth upon life and death;
The Iudge telling the Malefactor, that he
can doe no leſſe then the Iury of life and
death hath done: And therefore I muſt,
and doe pronounce ſentence of death a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
thee, according unto the Iuries
Verdict, it being according to righteous
judgement.</p>
            <p>I ſay, God in like manner ſpeakes unto
the guiltie ſoule, ſaying (as it were) in
this manner: I have pleaded hard in thy
behalfe, and we cannot prevaile in a full
conſent for thy perſonall recovery, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
we cannot attaine unto the third
Perſons conſent. The Sentence of death
is paſſed upon thee, according unto the
Sentence of a Divine Law, and according
unto our everlaſting Decree, written and
eſtabliſhed in our Divine Law, and ſealed
by all our unanimous conſents. Upon this
one Sentence, we hold all in Oneneſſe,
we cannot diſ-joynt our unitie in Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
and unitie in a glorious conformity.
The Law of the third Perſon, is alſo the
<pb facs="tcp:58070:26"/>
Law of the firſt Perſon, and the Law
of the firſt Perſon is alſo the Law of
the ſecond Perſon; and ſo a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
ſtabilitie in a bleſſed and glorious
Trinitie.</p>
            <p>And thus the Law of the three glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
Perſons is in one Seame; like unto
the Lawes of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi>
which altereth not.</p>
            <p>Now, becauſe I would not have the
Conſciences of men troubled, becauſe
I have ſhewed you the ſad condition
of the ſoule, that hath the guilt of
ſinne upon it; I will, I ſay, ſpeake a
word in due ſeaſon unto thoſe diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
Conſciences, and I will a little
enlarge my ſelfe; although, in regard
of the weakneſſe of body, I am almoſt
ſpent.</p>
            <p>My beloved friends, <hi>I</hi> ſpeake unto
all of you, but eſpecially unto belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers:
<hi>I</hi> ſay, there is abundance of
mercie in God for you; <hi>I</hi> ſay it ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
hid, and treaſured up in the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els
of Divine goodneſſe, and thus to
be revealed in due time unto you in
the Lord Jeſus, when God his Father
<pb facs="tcp:58070:27"/>
breakes out in the ſweet influences of
his Love, in the object of his Love, who
is the Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <p>The breathings out of the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the Lord Jeſus, ſhall be the
breathings out of thy Graces, and of
thy Solaces; and the in-comming of
the Lord Jeſus ſhall give light unto
all thoſe manifeſtations of thy ſoules
pardons, which thou haddeſt ever ſince
that thou wert eſtated in Chriſt, which
for a long time hath layne hid in the
Hive of thy unbeleefe, and hath beene
the originall cauſe of making you to
call in queſtion your eſtate in Chriſt,
and your intereſt in the Lord Jeſus,
and that object upon whom your ever-being
dependeth.</p>
            <p>There is, <hi>I</hi> ſay, this one thing,
which is the onely cauſe which makes
many a diſtreſſed Conſcience to call
in queſtion his ſoules intereſt in Chriſt,
becauſe hee findes in his owne ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion
a world of ſoules-dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
and weakneſſe in his growth of
grace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> ſay unto thee, whoſoever thou art,
<pb facs="tcp:58070:27"/>
that ſtandeſt to heare me this day, that
thou, in thy ſoules diſtreſſe, art al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
unfit to bee thine owne judge
in the want of thy ſoules comfort, thou
wilt be ready to ſay that, which thou
wilt be againe ready to unſay, in thy
injoyment of true comfort, as <hi>David</hi>
did, <hi>Pſal. 116. 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You know, that there may be in the
midſt of Winter aboundance of Bees
in the Hive, although unto the eye of
our ſenſe and reaſon there be but two or
three playing about the Hives mouth:
Even ſo I ſay, although there but a few
graces in thy ſoule now in the time of
this thy affliction;</p>
            <p>I ſay, this time of thy affliction hath
not leſſened any of thy former graces
which thou formerly didſt enjoy. I ſay,
it hath but covered over thoſe thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
in thy ſenſe and feeling: Thy graces
be all ſtill where they were in thy firſt
inſtallment into the ſtate of grace.
Wee have a Proverb, That the Spring
brings forth all thoſe Herbs and Plants
which lay dead all the Winter before:
Even ſo I ſay unto thee, That the
<pb facs="tcp:58070:28"/>
Spring, which is the Morning of the
in-comming of the Lord Jeſus, ſhall
receive all thoſe boſome-diſcourſes which
lay dead in thy ſoule.</p>
            <p>In the time of thy aſcenſion, the
Sonne of Righteouſneſſe ſhall ariſe, and
ſhine upon thee by the bleſſed force and
glorious power of God the Father, and
ſo cauſe the Spirit of God to caſt into
thy ſoule a glorious diſcovery of the
intereſt of thy well-being.</p>
            <p>It is not thy want of grace that is the
cauſe of thy ſoules complaints, but it
is the onely want of thy diſcoverie of
them, that is the cauſe of thy ſoules
grievance: There's but a curtaine (as
it were) drawne betweene thee and thy
injoyments of all thy graces, all thy
graces are within that curtaine, as the
Prieſts of the old Law were ſometimes
within the holy place.</p>
            <p>When this curtaine is once drawne,
then will all thy injoyments appear, then
ſhalt thou be ſwallowed up in the very
life of diſcovery.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe, Sometimes the life of
diſcoverie may bee diſ-joynted from
<pb facs="tcp:58070:28"/>
the life of injoyment for a ſmall
time.</p>
            <p>The Saints have an abſence in the
midſt of their injoyment. Yet bleſſed
bee that Divine abſence, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards
wins us unto a Divine en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment
of him, who for a time
was pleaſed to abſent himſelfe.</p>
            <p>I ſay, here is the comfort of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers,
that a temporall abſence is
not an eternall withdrawment.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed bee God, who though hee
doth ſometimes withdraw the ſence
and feeling of a Divine preſence in
their enjoyment, yet in the want
of that enjoyment, the Saints enjoy
a Divine enjoyment of the Lord
Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Although the Lord Jeſus, in thy
ſenſe and feeling, bee with-drawne
from thee, yet note this one Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence;
It is impoſſible that hee
ſhould ever with-draw himſelfe from
thee.</p>
            <p>Thou doſt enjoy the ſame preſence
now, which thou didſt enjoy ever ſince
<pb facs="tcp:58070:29"/>
thy very firſt eſtatement in the ſtate of
grace.</p>
            <p>Yeſterday thou didſt injoy the Lord
Jeſus, and ſo thou ſhalt enioy him
in like manner for ever; Yea, with
an eternall, moſt glorious, unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
inioyment.</p>
            <closer>So much for this time.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
