<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Animadversions upon a late discourse concerning the divinity, and death of Christ Edmund Elys.</title>
            <author>Elys, Edmund, ca. 1634-ca. 1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2006-06">2006-06 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39338</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E662</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41114</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19636953</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19636953</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109230</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A39338)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109230)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1685:36)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Animadversions upon a late discourse concerning the divinity, and death of Christ Edmund Elys.</title>
                  <author>Elys, Edmund, ca. 1634-ca. 1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>"Eccles. Chap. IX. Ver. 10."</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Divinity.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Ecclesiastes IX, 10 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:109230:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109230:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ANIMADVERSIONS
UPON
A late Diſcourſe Concerning
THE
Divinity, and Death of CHRIST.</head>
            <byline>By EDMUND ELYS, ſometime Fellow of
Baliol Colledge in OXFORD.</byline>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ECCLES. Chap. IX. Ver. 10.</bibl>
               <q>Whatſoever thy hand findeth to do, Do it
with thy Might: for there is no work, nor
device, nor knowledge, nor wiſdom in the
Grave, whither thou goeſt.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IF the Author of this Diſcourſe did real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
deſign to Maintain the Profeſſion of
the CATHOLICK FAITH, how is it
Poſſible that He ſhould not ſpeak one
good Word of the Creed of St. ATHANASIUS,
of the NICENE Creed? How is it Poſſible
He ſhould ſo Contemn the <hi>Ancient Fathers,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:109230:2"/>
if His Sentiments, touching <hi>the Faith,</hi> were
the ſame with Theirs? I Appeal to any Man,
that has the Fear of God before his Eyes, to
Judge whether He do not plainly Deny the
Eternity of the PERSON <hi>of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
in that He ſays, <q>That from the Humane
and Divine Nature United there did Reſult
<hi>the Perſon of the Meſſius,</hi> who was both
GOD, and Man.</q> Certainly That which Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults
from the <hi>Union</hi> of the Humane Nature
with the Divine is not <hi>Eternal,</hi> or <hi>From
Everlaſting.</hi> 
               <q>We can Frame, ſays He, no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct
Idea of that Infinite Eſſence, and it
were not Infinite if we could.</q> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi>
But we may REFLECT upon that IDEA,
which <hi>God Himſelf,</hi> the ONE BEING <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely
Infinite,</hi> has Impreſt upon all Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
Souls. To know God is to have a <hi>Diſtinct
Idea</hi> of Him. He that Pretends to Frame
to himſelf any Idea of God, Knows not God:
For God is LIGHT, and we can have no <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivance</hi>
of Him, but by the <hi>Influence,</hi> or
<hi>Impreſſion</hi> we receive from Him. He ſays
that <q>
                  <hi>One Opinion</hi> concerning Chriſt is, That
Chriſt was a Divine Perſon, miraculouſly
Conceiv'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Tho' he had no Exiſtence
before he was Formed in the Virgins
Womb.</q> Here I deſire that the Chriſtian
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109230:2"/>
Reader would Obſerve the Subtlety of ſome
<hi>Deceivers,</hi> who, by calling Our SAVIOUR a
<hi>Divine Perſon,</hi> would Avoid the Abhorrence
and Deteſtation they Deſerve, becauſe they
will not Acknowledge that He has a Nature
<hi>Truly Divine,</hi> or <hi>Eternal.</hi> He tells us <q>That
ſome Philoſophers thought that Souls were
propagated from Souls; and the Figure by
which this was explain'd, being that of one
Candle's being lighted at another; this
ſeems to have given the Riſe to thoſe
words, <hi>Light of Light.</hi> It is certain many
of the Fathers fell often into this Conceit,
and in this way of explaining this Matter,
they have ſaid many things, which inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate
that they believ'd an Inequality be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
the Perſons, and a Subordination of
the Second and Third to the Firſt: So that
by the <hi>ſame Subſtance,</hi> or <hi>Eſſence,</hi> they do
in many places expreſs themſelves, as if
they only meant the ſame Being in a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
Senſe, as all Humane Souls are of the
ſame <hi>Subſtance;</hi> that is, the ſame Order,
or ſort of Beings; and they ſeemed to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title
them to different Operations; not
only in an Oeconomical way, but thought
that one did that, which the other did not.</q> 
Here He plainly endeavours to Perſwade us
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:109230:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:109230:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:109230:4"/>
to believe that Many of the Fathers were
no True Chriſtians, but had a Conceit that
there were Three Gods: For moſt certainly
if they thought that The Father, The Son,
and The Holy Ghoſt, are of the ſame Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
no otherwiſe than <hi>As all Humane
Souls are of the ſame Subſtance,</hi> and that they
have different Operations, not only in an
Oeconomical way, but ſo that one Does what
the other Does not, they Thought (in <hi>Effect</hi>)
that there are Three Gods. If He would
name any One of thoſe, who have Publiſht
ſuch Monſtrous Conceptions, we ſhould give
him a Punctual Anſwer. In the mean time
we muſt Aver to all the World, that not one
of the Holy Fathers, of the <hi>Four Firſt Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
Councils,</hi> were ſubject to any ſuch <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lirium:</hi>
And Every one of thoſe, that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
the Name of <hi>Fathers,</hi> ſhall Riſe up in
Judgment againſt Him, for laying ſo foul an
Imputation upon MANY <hi>Fathers,</hi> not Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
One of them; ſo that he might Inſinuate
a Contempt of them All into the Minds of
Unwary Readers. <q>Others, ſays He, took
another way of explaining this, making
it their Foundation, that the Deity was one
Numerical Being.</q> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <hi>Ancient
Fathers</hi> did not ſay that the Deity was <hi>One
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109230:4"/>
Numerical Being:</hi> what they ſaid manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
imports that the Deity is BEING <hi>Simply
and Abſolutely,</hi> viz. BEING <hi>Abſolutely In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite,</hi>
ſo that it implies the moſt palpable
Contradiction that the True, and Eternal.
GOD ſhould not be <hi>Abſolutely</hi> ONE. I De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
that the Learned Reader would be ever
Mindful of theſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Words of <hi>Saint</hi> BASIL,
in his 141 <hi>Epiſtle:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
He tells us that <q>Many have
thought that the Term SON did not at all
belong to the Bleſſed Three.</q> If He would
Name One of theſe Many, and ſhew us
where we may find this Execrable Hereſy in
Writing, we ſhould undertake, by the Help
of GOD, to Manifeſt the Madneſs, and
Folly of it. He Slights this Poſition of the
Schoolmen, <q>That GOD being Infinite,
every Offence againſt Him has an Infinite
Guilt, and muſt be expiated either by Acts
of Infinite Value, or of Infinite Duration;
and that a Perſon of an Infinite Nature
was only capable of Acts of an Infinite
Value; that ſuch a One was neceſſary for
Expiating Sin. But in all this Gradation,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109230:5"/>
there is one Defect, That the Scripture ſets
none of theſe Speculations before us.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There's nothing more Evident in
the Holy Scriptures than this, That thoſe
that are SAV'D are REDEEM'D <hi>with the
Precious Bloud of</hi> CHRIST: And is not
that Bloud of Infinite Value? Is not the
<hi>Wrath of GOD</hi> againſt All Sin Infinite?
Is not Infinite Wrath againſt All Sin as
Fully Demonſtrated in an Infinite Holy
PERSON, Suffering For All the Sins of the
Whole World in the Nature of Man, which
He Aſſum'd that He might be Capable of
Suffering, As that Wrath could ever have
been Shewn, or Demonſtrated to Men, and
Angels in the Everlaſting Deſtruction of All
Sinners? As for thoſe <hi>Scoptical</hi> Words,
<q>thoſe Subtle weighings of Infinities one
againſt another,</q> I ſhall make no other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection
on them, but only to declare that I
Hope the Learned, and Pious Reader will
joyn with Me in a juſt Abhorrence and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation
of them. He uſes this very Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
Expreſſion: <q>The offering this to us
on ſuch eaſy terms, and the exacting only
a Sincere Obedience as the Condition of it,
without inſiſting on an Entire Obedience,
is another part of the Grace of it.</q> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:109230:5"/>
SINCERE Obedience is ENTIRE Obedience,
or the <hi>having Reſpect to All the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of GOD.</hi> He Acknowledges that
<q>GOD would Pardon Sin in ſuch a manner,
as ſhould ſhew how much He Hated it, at
the ſame time that He ſhew'd ſuch Love,
and Compaſſion to Sinners.</q> But, ſay We,
He had not Shewn how much He Hated
<hi>Sin,</hi> and how much He Lov'd <hi>Sinners,</hi> if
He had not Shewn this Hatred, and this
Love to be Both INFINITE, which He
ſhew'd with all Poſſible Evidence in <hi>the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
of the Death of Chriſt,</hi> a PERSON In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
in All Excellency, and Perfection.
<q>Every Sin, ſays He, gives a wound, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires
Repentance to waſh, and heal it, but
every Sin does not ſhut us out from a right
to the Bleſſings of the Covenant.</q> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi>
Every <hi>Known Sin</hi> does not render us Unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable
of Repentance; but Every <hi>Known
Sin</hi> Expoſes us to the <hi>Wrath of God,</hi> and the
Sinner has no Grounds to hope for Pardon,
unleſs he ſincerely Repent, ſtedfaſtly Purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,
by the Help of GOD, to lay down his
Life, rather than be Guilty of any <hi>Known
Sin</hi> by <hi>Commiſſion</hi> or <hi>Omiſſion.</hi> I pray GOD
to Affect the Heart of this Man, and of
Every other Learned Perſon, throughout the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109230:6"/>
whole Chriſtian World, with a due Regard
to the Writings of the <hi>Ancient Fathers.</hi>
Their Following of thoſe Excellent <hi>Holy
Men</hi> both in Life, and Doctrine, as they were
Followers of <hi>Chriſt, and his Apoſtles,</hi> would
moſt certainly Reduce this, and all other
Nations, Profeſſing Chriſtianity, to a True
State of Chriſtian Peace, and Tranquillity.</p>
            <closer>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:109230:6"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
