<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The declaration of Thomas Lord Fairfax, and the rest of the lords, knights, esquires, citizens, ministers and freeholders of the county and city of York.</title>
            <author>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Baron, 1612-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2006-02">2006-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39959</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F154</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R211574</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99835057</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99835057</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39710</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A39959)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39710)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1758:60)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The declaration of Thomas Lord Fairfax, and the rest of the lords, knights, esquires, citizens, ministers and freeholders of the county and city of York.</title>
                  <author>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Baron, 1612-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for James Williamson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated at end: Leeds Febr. 13. 1659; the year is given according to Lady Day dating.</note>
                  <note>Praying for a Free Parliament.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 16. 1659".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library (Thomason Tracts), and the Harvard University Library (Early English books, 1641-1700).</note>
                  <note>Tempnote Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>York (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-01</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:39710:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE DECLARATION OF Thomas Lord Fairfax, And the reſt of the Lords, Knights, Eſquires, Citizens, Miniſters and Freeholders of the County and City of YORK.</head>
            <p>WHereas this Famous County, Honoured formerly for its puiſſance and ſtrength by which they have always been taken for the Bulwork of this Nation, are now reputed ſo inconſiderable that they have not at this time a Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive in Parliament: and being deeply ſenſible of the Confuſions and Diſtractions of the Nation, the particular Decay and Ruine of the Cloathing-Trade of this County, which neceſſarily bears an influence upon the Publick: as alſo the Future Evils that will attend this <hi>Vacancy of Government</hi> during the imperfection and incompleatneſs of <hi>Our Parliaments,</hi> whoſe entireneſs, and <hi>Full Number</hi> hath been in <hi>all Times</hi> (as to a <hi>Right Engliſh Conſtitution)</hi> the only <hi>Conſervative</hi> of our <hi>Liberties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We the <hi>Lords, Knights, Eſquires, Gentlemen, Miniſters</hi> and <hi>Citizens</hi> aforeſaid do Declare. That we finde a <hi>Corrupt Intereſt</hi> in the preſent Government, abetted by <hi>Factious Parties,</hi> and carried on with an <hi>Irreconciliable Violence</hi> againſt our Peace: Predominant, and ſitting at the Helm, whereby the <hi>Freedom</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> of the <hi>Subject</hi> is ſo far <hi>endangered,</hi> that we judge it paſt Application, or any other <hi>Wording Remedy</hi> to Retrive it. And as this is not only our own opinion, but the <hi>general Senſe of the Nation,</hi> fruitleſly hitherto made known to the World: We will therefore allow our ſelves the precedency of <hi>Aſſerting</hi> and <hi>Defending</hi> the <hi>juſtice</hi> of this our <hi>Common Right</hi> by open <hi>Armes,</hi> if no other preſent Temperament and Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient can be adjuſted or fitted for our Grievances.</p>
            <p>We do therefore require <hi>A Free and Full Parliament</hi> to be ſtraitwith Convened, according to the Directions and Proviſions made in the <hi>Act for the Triennial Parliament;</hi> the intent and deſign whereof, after ſuch a <hi>bloody Conteſt</hi> we may not ſee eluded and fruſtrated with <hi>ſtrange VOTES</hi> and <hi>Qualifications:</hi> Therefore we deſire a <hi>Free Parliament,</hi> or elſe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of the <hi>ſecluded Members</hi> by the force of the Army in 1648. (to which his Lordſhip Proteſts he was unwittingly and unwarily acceſſory) to the remaining Diſcharge of their <hi>Truſt,</hi> they having given <hi>ſingular</hi> and <hi>ſuperlative</hi> evidence of their <hi>capacity</hi> and <hi>fitneſs</hi> for it, by their <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>judicious moderation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſhall in their <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Counſels</hi> acquieſce, and otherwiſe ſhall not be ſatisfied, for that our preſſing <hi>Calamities</hi> will give no <hi>Reſt</hi> to the Kingdom, till theſe our <hi>Deſires</hi> are accompliſhed. To which purpoſe, we have at this our <hi>general Meeting</hi> or <hi>Rendevouz</hi> Signed this our Declaration to be forthwith Communicated to the <hi>NATION.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Leeds</hi> 
                  <date>Febr. 13. 1659.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Signed
Thomas Fairfax, &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>James Williamſon.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
