<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great wickedness, and mischievous effects of slandering, represented in a sermon preached at St. Giles without Cripplegate, on Sunday Nov. 15, 1685 by Edward Fowler, D.D. ; together with a preface and conclusion in his own vindication.</title>
            <author>Fowler, Edward, 1632-1714.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-03">2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40081</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1707</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10722</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12927416</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12927416</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95580</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A40081)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95580)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 692:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great wickedness, and mischievous effects of slandering, represented in a sermon preached at St. Giles without Cripplegate, on Sunday Nov. 15, 1685 by Edward Fowler, D.D. ; together with a preface and conclusion in his own vindication.</title>
                  <author>Fowler, Edward, 1632-1714.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Brabazon Aylmer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Libel and slander --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-07</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:95580:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>C. Alston,</hi> R. P. D. <hi>Hen.</hi> Episc.
<hi>Lond</hi> a sacris Dornest.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>16. <hi>Nov.</hi>
1685.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95580:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE
Great Wickedness,
And Mischievous Effects of
Slandering,
Represented in a
SERMON
PREACHED AT
St. <hi>GILES</hi> without <hi>Cripplegate,</hi>
On Sunday <hi>Nov.</hi> 15. 1685.</p>
            <p>By <hi>EDWARD FOWLER,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>Together with a <hi>Preface</hi> and <hi>Conclusion</hi>
In his Own VINDICATION.</p>
            <q>Thou shalt not bear False Witness against thy Neighbour.</q>
            <q>
               <p>They are Grievous Revolters Walking with Slanders,</p>
               <bibl>Jer. 6. 28.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Brabazon Aylmer,</hi> at the <hi>Three
Pidgeons</hi> against the <hi>Royal-Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:95580:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95580:2"/>
            <head>THE
PREFACE.</head>
            <p>IF the Readers of the Following <hi>Sermon</hi> knew
how very little Time I had for the Composing
of it, They would not be Offended with its
Plainness: Nor Those that are <hi>Ingenuous,</hi> Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical
in observing Faults or Over-sights. The
<hi>Conclusion</hi> of the <hi>Sermon,</hi> which contains the <hi>Occasion</hi>
of my Penning and Preaching it, I have here Publisht
with some small Additions, which I think fit to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
because those of whose Humanity I have had
such plentiful Experience, will be forward enough, I
presume, to give out, upon their finding any Passa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
they did not hear from the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> that I have
<hi>Lyed</hi> in the <hi>Title-Page.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Design of this Preface is to Vindicate my self
from a great <hi>Slander</hi> of <hi>theirs</hi> (and I am prepared to
do the like, as to all the <hi>Other</hi> I have heard of) which
notwithstanding my Endeavours, both by <hi>Word of
Mouth</hi> and <hi>Letters,</hi> to Clear my Self of, doth (as I
understood the <hi>Last Week)</hi> still stick upon me: And
'tis <hi>this,</hi> That I should give, about a Year and three
Quarters since, to a certain <hi>Fanatick, a Knavish Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate,</hi>
to bring him off, in a <hi>Court of Iustice,</hi> from
<pb facs="tcp:95580:3"/>
an <hi>Indictment</hi> of so Scandalous a Crime, as the <hi>Depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
of the Common-Prayers.</hi> And in short, That I Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified
him to be a good <hi>Church-Man,</hi> whereas he <hi>never</hi>
came to the <hi>Communion</hi> but <hi>once,</hi> in order to his being
Qualified for the Office of <hi>Common-Council-Man.</hi> And
if I ever gave to any such Person such a <hi>Certificate,</hi>
I will freely acknowledge, I was a <hi>Knave</hi> indeed.</p>
            <p>But before I proceed farther, I will say <hi>this,</hi> That
I know not that I ever Repented of <hi>any Certificate</hi> I
gave in my Life, except of <hi>One</hi> that two of my grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test
Enemies, before they discovered their Malice to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
me, did unawares draw me into; which was
to this <hi>Effect,</hi> and, to the best of my remembrance,
in these very Words, <hi>That for ought I know, they were
Men of Peaceable and Christian Spirits;</hi> which <hi>Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate</hi>
was of their own Penning. I must Confess, I <hi>then</hi>
shrewdly <hi>suspected</hi> that they were not Men of <hi>such</hi>
Spirits, but because I had no certain <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the
<hi>Contrary,</hi> upon a little deliberation I Subscribed it.
But within a <hi>few dayes.</hi> I was made sensible what a
<hi>Trapan</hi> this was, being informed, That these very Men
had Represented me, at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> as an Encourager
of <hi>Fanaticks</hi> in our <hi>Freedom-Vestry.</hi> This was told
me by a <hi>Person of Honour,</hi> who had it from Mr. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary
Ienkins.</hi> But I Appeal to the present <hi>Recorder
of London,</hi> and to the <hi>Alderman</hi> of our <hi>Ward,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
in their <hi>Presence,</hi> I did not abundantly Clear my
Innocence, as to this <hi>Charge.</hi> The <hi>Latter</hi> of these
Gentlemen, meeting me in, or near, <hi>Cornhill,</hi> some dayes
after the Hearing which we had in the <hi>Recorders</hi> Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
desired me to <hi>Pardon</hi> the <hi>Chief</hi> Man of them; and
the <hi>Recorder,</hi> at the Conclusion of the Hearing, I think
before most of the <hi>Vestry-Men</hi> were gone out (for there
<pb facs="tcp:95580:3"/>
was a full Appearance of <hi>them</hi> too) was pleased to
Declare <hi>(my Self</hi> standing by him, and <hi>divers Others)
That he would justify my Honesty</hi> (that was, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect
to my Proceedings in the <hi>Vestry) on any Ground
in England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Adversaries thus failing of their Design, they,
with <hi>one</hi> or <hi>two</hi> more, have, almost ever since <hi>that</hi>
time to <hi>this,</hi> turned every Stone to Ruine me: And
<hi>London</hi> Rings of their Carriage towards me. Nor hath
it Satisfied them to abuse <hi>Me</hi> in the grossest manner,
but they have put an intolerable Abuse upon a <hi>Great-Man</hi>
or <hi>Two;</hi> for when they have been Expostulated
with, for making my Life so <hi>Vneasy,</hi> they have En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured
to remove all Blame from <hi>themselves,</hi> by
pretending that what they had done, was in meer
Obedience to <hi>their</hi> Commands. And when it was
replyed (as once it was by my Self, to this Effect)
<hi>You first instigate Great Persons by your wretched Stories,
and then Hypocritically pretend that my Troubles Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally
proceed from them;</hi> there was no Answer, but
perfect <hi>Silence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It might make a Competent <hi>Volume,</hi> to give an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
what <hi>Slanders</hi> they have devised, and <hi>Methods</hi>
they have taken, from time to time, to do <hi>Me</hi> Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief.
I have a <hi>Narrative</hi> by me of the <hi>Molestations</hi>
they have given me, to about <hi>Half a Year</hi> since, which
I intended <hi>then</hi> to Publish, but upon <hi>Second</hi> Thoughts
I judged it more prudent to hold my hand for some
time longer.</p>
            <p>But to return to this <hi>Knavish Certificate;</hi> The Person
I certified for, was one Mr. <hi>R. W.</hi> who is one of my
nearest Neighbours. The <hi>Occasion</hi> of the Certificate
was <hi>This,</hi> Two of these <hi>Three</hi> or <hi>Four</hi> Men, who have
<pb facs="tcp:95580:4"/>
so long been my Adversaries, accused this Man to me
before his face (which fair play they rarely use) of
having called the <hi>Common-Prayers</hi> an <hi>Innovation,</hi> upon
a Motion to have them Read, at the meeting of their
<hi>Quest,</hi> in the <hi>Quest-House.</hi> Mr. <hi>W.</hi> Professed that he
only called the Reading of them upon <hi>That Occasion</hi> so,
for that never any such thing had been done before,
that ever he heard of in this Parish: And that he op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed
the bringing up of such a Custome, for the
<hi>Poors</hi> sake, because he presumed they would pay the
Reader out of the <hi>Purse,</hi> that at <hi>That Meeting</hi> annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
was made for <hi>Them.</hi> But he told me he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
to them, that if they would pay the Reader out
of their <hi>Own Purses,</hi> they might have the <hi>Prayers</hi> in
the <hi>Church</hi> with all his heart; and acknowledged then
that he gave them a Proverbial Saying, which they
made a mighty business of, that signified no more than
that every Body might have his Liberty, either to <hi>go,</hi>
or to <hi>stay away;</hi> which, though it might be decently
enough used in most Cases not relating to Religious
Affaires, yet I told him it was <hi>Irreverendly</hi> done of
him to use it in <hi>this</hi> Case; And though I could not
impute it to his <hi>Disaffection</hi> to the <hi>Prayers</hi> (he having
ever since I came to this <hi>Parish,</hi> and I understand, for
some Years before was a constant attender on them
upon <hi>Sundayes)</hi> but to meer Rashness and Inconside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
they being then in the heat of Passion; yet
at that time, and more then once since, I rebuked
him for it with severity enough. And I further Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved
him before these Men, for not being as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
as <hi>any</hi> to so good a Motion; though it was
evident enough, that the Motion was not made from
so good a Principle, as that of true Love to the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship
<pb facs="tcp:95580:4"/>
of God, but upon a design that was very Obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.
I farther added, that to encourage the Reading
of the Prayers, at this Yearly Meeting, I would <hi>My
self</hi> first read them at their Meeting again the next
Year, and so for the future, which accordingly I did
the last <hi>Christmas.</hi> They had another Story of a
<hi>most</hi> indecent <hi>Scoff</hi> at our <hi>Church Musick,</hi> but <hi>this</hi> he
utterly <hi>denied,</hi> and <hi>persists</hi> in doing so; and the Truth
is I never <hi>Believed</hi> it, but now, for a reason I won't
mention, I <hi>disbelieve</hi> it.</p>
            <p>After all the Passionate Fending and Proving was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,
and I had, as I said, smartly enough reproved
Mr. <hi>W.</hi> I told them 'twas evident, he did not call the
<hi>Prayers</hi> an <hi>Innovation,</hi> but only the <hi>Reading them in
the Quest-House,</hi> or <hi>upon that Occasion,</hi> and then Exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
them to <hi>more</hi> Christian behaviour towards one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
and to be Friends again; Having heard that there
was an elder Grudg between <hi>one</hi> or <hi>both</hi> of these
Men, and this Mr. <hi>W.</hi> And that the Difference did not
begin now: Although <hi>one</hi> of them had been some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time
before his great Intimate, and he Constantly
gave Mr. <hi>W.</hi> the Title of his <hi>Master.</hi> Hereupon they
<hi>Drank</hi> to each other, more than once, and shook hands.
But the <hi>Next</hi> News I heard of them, which surprized
me much, was, that they had made a Complaint of
him to Mr. <hi>Recorder,</hi> and that the <hi>Constable</hi> had carried
him away to <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> and <hi>that</hi> there he was bound
over to answer for his <hi>Depraving the Common-Prayer;</hi>
upon these Mens Oaths, at the <hi>Kings Bench Barr.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
this Mr. <hi>W.</hi> signified to me, That the <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> had
advised him, to get a good <hi>Petition</hi> drawn up to my
<hi>Lord Chief Iustice,</hi> and as good a Certificate as his Minister
and other Creditable People of the Parish, could give him;
<pb facs="tcp:95580:5"/>
and that His Lordship promised him to present <hi>both</hi> with
his <hi>own</hi> hand, and accordingly <hi>He</hi> performed that Promise.
Hereupon I again Reproved him, and told him I hoped this
would be for the future a <hi>Warning</hi> to him; and finding him
much dejected, I said I would willingly certifie for him
<hi>whatsoever</hi> I knew to be true of him. And the Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficate
I gave him was <hi>this, That he was a Constant
Attender on the Prayers of the Church, a Frequenter of
the Holy Communion, in the way of the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
<hi>and a forward man to Publick good Works in the
Parish, and particularly at</hi> that <hi>time, to the Repairing
of our Church and Steeple.</hi> And in the <hi>close,</hi> I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed
how far I was from going about to excuse
his fault; but in <hi>what Words</hi> I did this, I don't now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member.</p>
            <p>This is the plain and Naked Truth of this matter,
and I am yet to learn where lay my fault. Nay I
am still fully satisfied in my Conscience, that I did
nothing but what I might <hi>Lawfully</hi> do, <hi>nay</hi> nor any
thing but what I was bound in <hi>Common Iustice</hi> to
do. For I never knew him other, than a Constant atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
on the Prayers of <hi>the</hi> Church, nor than a Frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
of the Holy Communion, I mean upon his <hi>Knees</hi>
and at the <hi>Rayles.</hi> And, whatsoever Faults he may
have been guilty of, I have found no one Parishioner
more Publick Spirited, both in reference to the <hi>Church</hi>
and <hi>Parish.</hi> And he was one of the best <hi>Church-Wardens</hi>
(I finding him in that Office when I first came hither)
that I believe the Parish ever knew. It hath been
Objected to me, that he behaved himself <hi>Disloyally</hi> at
the Election of <hi>Sheriffs,</hi> and therefore this Certificate
was taken the <hi>Worse</hi> at my hands. But I need make
no <hi>other</hi> Reply, than that this was more than I <hi>Knew.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:95580:5"/>
I have but <hi>little</hi> Acquaintance in this Parish to <hi>this</hi>
Day, and had <hi>less then,</hi> so that I might very well be
a stranger to his Behaviour at that Election. For my
part, I never perceived any <hi>Disloyalty</hi> in him, but the
Contrary, when he hath come to me, which he does
very <hi>rarely,</hi> but when Business brings him, though
he lives <hi>close</hi> by me. And had he discovered <hi>Disaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection</hi>
to the <hi>Government,</hi> either in <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State</hi>
to <hi>Me,</hi> What is commendable in him should not have
made with <hi>Me</hi> an Atonement for it. But there is no
end of these my Obliging <hi>Friends</hi> Stories; I hope
though, for the future they'l be more <hi>Innocent</hi> ones; I
mean, that their <hi>Tongues will be no Slander.</hi> The
worst thing I knew of this man was, that he would
be too easily <hi>Provoked,</hi> but as <hi>soon</hi> (that I'le say for him
too)
<hi>Pacified.</hi> But why should I better know what this
<hi>W.</hi> was, than what <hi>These</hi> Men were? I was I confess
often <hi>told</hi> what <hi>Two</hi> of them were, but I would not
<hi>believe</hi> it, till they did me the kindness to make me
understand them whether I <hi>would or no;</hi> and since I
have been sufficiently upbraided with my Charitable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulity.
But in order to the more Blackening of
<hi>Me, One</hi> or <hi>More</hi> of my good Friends have reported,
That he was upon the <hi>Scaffold</hi> when the <hi>King was Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered.</hi>
I never heard of <hi>This</hi> till this very day, but
I concluded 'twas a Wicked Lye, before I sent for him
to ask him the Question. His Reply was, that he was
then but a Boy about sixteen Years Old, (as any one
may believe that knows him) and that he was at that
time <hi>Fourscore</hi> Miles from <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In short, Mr. <hi>Attorney General</hi> had a full Hearing of
the forementioned Cause, was fully satisfied of the
<hi>Baseness</hi> of it, and gave Mr. <hi>W.</hi> a <hi>Noli Prosequi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:95580:6"/>My Enemies after this, made an Article against me
of this <hi>Certificate,</hi> at <hi>Doctors Commons,</hi> and it was
thrown out again with Contempt enough. And yet,
it is still made a hainous Crime in me, and if it must
be so for the future, after this pains I have taken to
clear my self of being faulty therein, <hi>so let it. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicaciae
nullum opposuit remedium Deus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul.</note> But I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
farther, that if I had refused to certifie what
I knew to be true of this Man, I had not only been
<hi>Vnjust,</hi> but highly <hi>Dis-ingenuous.</hi> For at my first com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to this Parish, though he was a meer <hi>Stranger</hi> to
me; and I never once <hi>heard</hi> of him before; he high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
obliged me by standing up for my Right to Houses
that were Built on the Church-Yard Ground, and
which I recovered without going to Law, and by no
<hi>Mans</hi> Assistance more than by his. And so much for
<hi>That.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am accused too of this very <hi>Whiggish</hi> Trick, and
in <hi>My</hi> mind a <hi>More</hi> Knavish one, than the pretended
<hi>Certificate,</hi> viz. That the <hi>Lord Mayor,</hi> or <hi>some Great
Man</hi> (no body knows who) <hi>sending to me to give my Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of Persons fit to be chosen</hi> Common-Council-Men,
<hi>and to do my best towards procuring the Choyce of Loyal
Persons, I recommended Fanaticks, or at least Whigs, and
stickled for them.</hi> But the Reader shan't need to be
scared with the fears of another tedious Tale, for a
<hi>Word</hi> or <hi>Two</hi> will do this business, <hi>viz.</hi> I solemnly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess
both upon the Word of a <hi>Christian</hi> and a <hi>Divine,</hi>
That I never concerned my self, either directly or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly,
in that Affair, nor ever was defired by any
Mortal to <hi>Meddle</hi> in it. But yet this Goodly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint
of me, was told me by no less a Man than a
<hi>Lord,</hi> this last week. And I am not to seek to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand,
<pb facs="tcp:95580:6"/>
why just at <hi>This</hi> Nick of time, (I mean with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
this Week or Fortnight) there are such Strenuous but
Secret Endeavours used by these Men, to make me all
that's naught to our <hi>GOVERNOVRS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be expected I should here Clear my self of
Discouraging my <hi>Church-Wardens</hi> from Presenting <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senters,</hi>
which they made an <hi>Article</hi> of, but I need to
say no more than <hi>this</hi> to it, That as they could make
nothing <hi>like a Proof</hi> of it in the <hi>Court,</hi> so the <hi>contrary</hi>
appeared <hi>there,</hi> by the Deposition of the Principal of
their <hi>own</hi> Witnesses. And I had full Evidence ready
to prove, That I only Charged them to Present <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially,</hi>
and not to Gratify any ones Revengeful Piques,
but it was not <hi>produced</hi> because 'twas <hi>needless.</hi> And
I had, after a full Hearing, <hi>Ten Pounds Costs</hi> given me
against them. And now my Hand is in, a <hi>Word</hi> or
<hi>Two</hi> to their <hi>Grand Article,</hi> That I gave the <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi>
to two of my <hi>Church-Wardens</hi> together, <hi>Who were
Excommunicated in the Court,</hi> near a <hi>Year</hi> and <hi>half</hi> since.
But as I had <hi>Leave</hi> to <hi>Defer</hi> the <hi>Publishing</hi> of that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication,
so the <hi>Sacrament</hi> was given them <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi>
'twas Publisht; and I had then great Assurance,
That <hi>Excommunications</hi> can take no <hi>Effect</hi> till they are
<hi>Publisht;</hi>
and what I did, was done upon the <hi>best Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice</hi>
I was capable of having, and I Relyed upon the
Authority of more than <hi>One Ecclesiastical Iudge;</hi> and
the same Article had been Exhibited against many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Divines besides <hi>my self,</hi> had they been so unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
as to have had in their Parishes any People of
such <hi>Venomous</hi> Spirits, as those Few I am infested with.
So that, if this were a Fault in me, it was a Fault of
most <hi>Excuseable,</hi> if I may not say <hi>Invincible,</hi> Ignorance.
I no way Consulted mine <hi>own Interest</hi> in doing this
<pb facs="tcp:95580:7"/>
thing, and I Abominate the breaking of any <hi>Order</hi> of
the <hi>Church</hi> to Gratify any Person whatsoever.</p>
            <p>There is one thing more which I ought not to omit,
<hi>viz.</hi> That whereas I might say (but that it may be
replied, <hi>I live far from Neighbours)</hi> that no Man could
live more <hi>Peaceably</hi> than I have done in this place, nor
have been more forward to <hi>Oblige</hi> all Men, I have
wondred sometimes, and so have others too who know
my Conversation, how I should happen to have in my
Parish such <hi>Bitter</hi> Enemies, though, I thank God, I
have but a very few that I know of. But I have been
for some time satisfied, that my <hi>Impartiality</hi> in Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
hath netled some, and particularly my frequent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing
certain Vices of some among us, who value them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
mightily upon their Loyalty and Conformity,
whom I have plainly told, That they are a Disgrace
both to the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Church;</hi> and it may be I
have but seldom dealt Severely with the <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> and
Men of Factious, Seditious, and Rebellious <hi>Principles,</hi>
but I have had a <hi>Bout</hi> with <hi>them</hi> too. Now this is a
Fault I will not make the least Excuse for, and if it be
a Fault, I believe most of the good Service I have done
here to the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> hath been principally
Owing to it.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Second</hi> Cause of my Troubles I am too sure (and I que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion
whether I can name a <hi>Third)</hi> is, My Refusing to
part with Mr. <hi>S.</hi> after all Endeavours that have been
used to Set me against him. And for my great Avers<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
to Gratify his Enemies herein, I will Exercise my
Readers Patience with this short Apology. <hi>viz.</hi> That,
besides one Personal Pique, I soon perceiv'd, the
Bottom of the Emnity against him, to be some Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
he Preached of the <hi>Absolute Necessity of Restitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:95580:7"/>
that grievously Galled some, who were too well
known, to have Wronged the Poor, together with his
declaring his Mind <hi>Else-where</hi> with some Severity,
against several unjust Practices, before I had any
Relation to this Parish. And it would have lain
heavy upon my Conscience, while I had a Day to
Live, should I have Joyned with <hi>Those</hi> against him,
who, I was Satisfied, did Set themselves in Oppositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
to him, for the Zeal he had expressed upon so high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Commendable an account, as that of endeavouring to
do Right to <hi>Those</hi> who are not in a Capacity of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<hi>Themselves.</hi> Besides, should I have dismissed Mr. <hi>S.</hi>
I could not but expect the Curses of Hundreds of
Needy Families, for, excepting two Noted Citizens,
I know not his Fellow for bestirring himself, to get Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief
for Poor People. I am Confident, That never was
a Parish so obliged to a <hi>Curate,</hi> as this Parish hath been,
for <hi>many</hi> Years, to <hi>Him,</hi> as <hi>Ill</hi> as he hath now, for
a long time by <hi>some few,</hi> been Requited for it. And,
to speak my Conscience, I am certain this Parish could
very much better spare <hi>my Self,</hi> than it can <hi>Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Confess, at my first coming, there was <hi>some Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>understanding</hi>
between <hi>Him</hi> and <hi>Me,</hi> which some hoped
would have ended in a <hi>settled Enmity</hi> like to <hi>Theirs:</hi>
But in a very short time, We came to know each
Other <hi>Better,</hi> and then immediately all <hi>That</hi> Vanished,
and hath never been in the <hi>least</hi> Revived to <hi>this</hi> Day.</p>
            <p>And, as to his Preaching up <hi>Loyalty,</hi> and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity
to the <hi>Church,</hi> I know not a Divine in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi>
that is, or, ever since I came hither, hath been
more Zealous; as <hi>many Hundreds,</hi> I may say some <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands,</hi>
can bear me Witness. I will make no other A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology
for troubling the Reader with this long Scrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb facs="tcp:95580:8"/>
than this very short one, <hi>viz. Meer Necessity hath,
sorely against my Inclination, Compell'd me to it.</hi> But,
<hi>for all that,</hi> I expect to have the old lame <hi>Distick</hi> flung
in my Dish, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Hoc mihi pro certo est, quòd si cum sterc<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re Certo,</l>
               <l>Vinco, seu vincor, Certè Ego Maculor.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And if I have <hi>this Wipe,</hi> I'le take it Patiently, though
of all <hi>Gibes,</hi> I confess, I <hi>Most</hi> hate <hi>True</hi> Ones.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>St. Giles Cripplegate,
<date>Nov. 16. (85.)</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95580:8"/>
            <head>THE
Great Wickedness,
And Mischievous Effects of
SLANDERING
Represented.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Psalm. 101. 5.</bibl>
               <q>Whoso privily Slandereth his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,
him will I Cut off.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Shall not detein you with any thing of
<hi>Preface,</hi> but fall immediately upon the
Business I designed in the choice of these
Words, for my Present Subject.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Just and Pious KING, who was the</hi>
Pen-Man, <hi>spends this short</hi> Psalm <hi>in declaring
to his People, how he was resolved to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage
himself, in reference to the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of Piety and Virtue among them; and the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95580:9"/>
discouragement of Vice and Wickedness. And
among other particular Vices which he tells
them should by no means escape Punishment,
that of</hi> Slandering their Neighbours <hi>comes in,
in the</hi> Words of my Text. <hi>Nor is here any
one Vice which he expresseth so great an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence
of, or so severely Threatens, as this
of</hi> Slandering. <hi>For, whereas he saith,</hi> A fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
Heart shall DEPART FROM ME:
I will not KNOW a Wicked Person: And
him that hath a High Look, and a Proud Heart
will not I SUFFER: And he that Worketh
Deceit shall not DWELL WITHIN MY
HOUSE: And he that telleth Lies shall not
TARRY IN MY SIGHT; <hi>He makes</hi>
Slandering their Neighbours, <hi>a</hi> Capital <hi>Crime,
and declareth That</hi> Whoso Slandereth his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,
him would He CUT OFF.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> I will endeavour to shew, what is
here <hi>Meant</hi> by <hi>Slandering ones Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Upon <hi>What accounts</hi> we may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume
this Good King did <hi>thus</hi> Threaten
those that should be Guilty of this
Practice.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:95580:9"/>I. What is here <hi>Meant</hi> by <hi>Slandering ones
Neighbour.</hi> Thus to do, is either to <hi>Devise</hi> a
Tale of another and then <hi>Tell</hi> it; That is,
<hi>Such</hi> a Tale, as tends to the bringing of a
<hi>Blot</hi> upon the Person of whom 'tis invented
and told: Or to tell a false Story from <hi>other</hi>
hands as true, and with a design to have it
<hi>Believed</hi> without sufficient Evidence of the
truth of it. Now although this <hi>Latter</hi> way
of <hi>Slandering</hi> be a very Great Sin, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
from great want of Charity, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
perfectly opposite to that Golden Rule of
our Saviour, <hi>What you would that Men should do
to you, do you even the same to them,</hi> (than which
no Maxim in Morals is more plainly taught
by the Law of Nature, <hi>i. e.</hi> Right Reason
unassisted by Divine Revelation, and which
a <hi>Pagan</hi> Prince gives us in Negative Terms,
<hi>viz. Quod tibi fieri non vis, alteri ne feceris.
Whatsoever thou wouldst not have done to thy self, do
not offer to do to another:</hi> I say, as this <hi>Latter</hi>
way of <hi>Slandering</hi> is for these reasons a very
<hi>Great Sin,</hi> and consequently will meet with,
where it is not timely repented of, very <hi>Sore
Punishment</hi> from <hi>Gods</hi> hands) yet the <hi>Former</hi>
way, <hi>viz. Slandering</hi> by <hi>Inventing</hi> of Stories to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95580:10"/>
the Blemishing of any ones <hi>Good-Name,</hi> is a
<hi>Greater Sin,</hi> (as is evident at first hearing) and
therefore deserves <hi>Greater Punishment.</hi> And the
more the Tale <hi>Blackens</hi> his Reputation of whom
it is told, and the greater, or more useful the
Person is in the World who is defamed, as also
the greater the Injury is that is designed him in
telling it of him, the greater still is this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly
great Sin. Now the <hi>Slanderers</hi> that
King <hi>David</hi> must needs mean here in the
<hi>Text,</hi> and whom he threatneth with being
<hi>Cut off,</hi> are such as shall <hi>Devise</hi> and <hi>Invent</hi>
Lies to the Injuring of their Neighbours, <hi>i. e.</hi>
of <hi>any</hi> Persons, be their Rank and Quality
what it will; which the word <hi>Neighbour</hi> doth
import. And they are only <hi>such Slanderers</hi> as
<hi>these</hi> which must be here thus threatned, because
the <hi>other</hi> Sort <hi>(viz.</hi> Such as do not <hi>Invent,</hi> but
only <hi>Rashly give Credit</hi> to and <hi>Report</hi> Lies of
their Neighbours) though <hi>They</hi> are great Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
too, yet we cannot think that the King
would doom them to so great a Punishment.
For in all Places, there are too <hi>many</hi> of <hi>these</hi>
Offenders to be made Obnoxious to so severe
a Sentence. And besides, it is not so easy a
matter for the Magistrate to find Evidence suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95580:10"/>
in such a case as <hi>this,</hi> to found such a
Sentence as that of <hi>Death</hi> upon it.</p>
            <p>II. I come to shew upon <hi>what Accounts</hi> this
Good King did <hi>thus</hi> threaten such as <hi>Privily
Slandered their Neighbours.</hi> There is very great
reason for his being thus Incensed against them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> Because Inventers of Slanders are in
the number of the most <hi>Injurious</hi> and <hi>Mischievous</hi>
People in the World.</p>
            <p>1. They are most Mischievous to those Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
who are the <hi>Objects</hi> of their <hi>Slanders;</hi> None
are <hi>more</hi> so, except those Instruments of <hi>Satan,</hi>
who by drawing others to <hi>Sin</hi> destroy their
<hi>Souls.</hi> After the Divine Graces and Virtues,
which are necessary to Qualify for the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Happiness, a Man's <hi>Good-Name</hi> is the most
highly Valuable. It is not only <hi>Better than pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
Oyntment, and rather to be chosen than Silver
and Gold</hi> (as the Wise Man saith) but 'tis to be
prefer'd before all <hi>Temporal</hi> Enjoyments whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,
not excepting <hi>Life</hi> it self. For who can
take any <hi>Comfort</hi> in his Life, (unless he be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vested
of all Humanity, and strangely sunk into
the Brutish Nature) that is sensible of having <hi>Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liv'd</hi>
his <hi>Good-Name?</hi> And as for those that are
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95580:11"/>
               <hi>so sunk,</hi> it would be much better for <hi>themselves</hi>
as well as for the <hi>World,</hi> if they were out of
Being. And as it is <hi>Natural</hi> to those Men who
have any thing of Generousnes and Ingenuity
in their Tempers, above all things to Covet a
<hi>Good-Name;</hi> So there is <hi>this great reason</hi> why they
<hi>should,</hi> namely, Because it is the chief Thing
that makes Men <hi>useful</hi> in the World; and there
are no such <hi>unprofitable</hi> or <hi>insignificant</hi> Creatures
upon God's Earth, as those are who have <hi>lost</hi>
their Reputation, or had <hi>never any</hi> to lose. I
mean by a <hi>Good-Name</hi> and <hi>Reputation,</hi> that of
a <hi>Good-Man:</hi> Of a Man that hath imbibed good
<hi>Principles,</hi> and is <hi>true</hi> to them: Of a Man Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering
the Great God, and Fearing to break
wilfully any of His Laws. That which either
in the <hi>Sacred Writings,</hi> or in the Books of the
<hi>Philosophers</hi> is called a <hi>Good-Name,</hi> is wholly
Founded upon Good <hi>Morals.</hi> A <hi>Large Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing,
shrewdness of Wit and Parts, High Titles
of Honour,</hi> &amp;c. have, 'tis Confessed, acquired to
their Owners <hi>Great Names,</hi> but these alone never
made any Man the Possessor of a <hi>GOOD-Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now so far as any Man's Reputation, in
reference to his <hi>Morals,</hi> is Eclipsed, so much
the less Capable doth he immediately become
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95580:11"/>
of being Serviceable in his Generation. The
less of a <hi>Good-Name</hi> any one hath, the fewer
Opportunities and Advantages will he have, of
being Beneficial to his Fellow-Creatures, either
in their Temporal or Spiritual Concerns, but
especially in their Spiritual. And as it is cheifly
upon <hi>this</hi> account that a <hi>Good-Name</hi> ought to
be so Highly esteemed; So to Esteem it upon
any <hi>other</hi> account, <hi>separate</hi> from <hi>this,</hi> is nothing
better than a Gratification of <hi>Animality</hi> or <hi>Fond
Fancy.</hi> But <hi>this</hi> Consideration makes it highly
reasonable to prize a <hi>Good-Name</hi> above Rubies,
and above the Wealth of both the <hi>Indies,</hi> and
to reckon our Sufferings <hi>herein</hi> in the number
of the greatest Worldly Sufferings. So, it is
manifest, King <hi>David</hi> did, by divers Passages
in his <hi>Psalms:</hi> As particularly in <hi>Psal.</hi> 35. 11,
12. saith he, <hi>False Witnesses did rise up against
me, they laid to my charge things which I knew not</hi>
(or which I was altogether Guiltless of) <hi>they
rewarded me evil for good</hi> (or this Evil of <hi>Slander</hi>
for all the good Services I have done them)
<hi>to the spoiling,</hi> or (as 'tis in our <hi>Old</hi> Translation)
<hi>to the great discomfort of my Soul.</hi> And <hi>Psal.</hi> 69.
19, 20. he <hi>thus</hi> Complaints; <hi>Thou hast known my
Reproach and my shame and my Dishonour, mine Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95580:12"/>
are all before thee, Reproach hath broken my
heart and I am full of Heaviness.</hi> So that a <hi>Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer</hi>
being a Robber of <hi>that</hi> which is deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly
so Precious, or at least he alwayes being
so in his <hi>Endeavour,</hi> there was great reason why
this Holy King should so Abominate him, as
we find by our Text he did: But,</p>
            <p>2. As the <hi>Slanderer</hi> is thus highly Injurious
to Those who are the <hi>Objects</hi> of his <hi>Slanders,</hi>
so is he the most Pestilent Creature to the
<hi>Community</hi> of which he is a Member. Those
who invent <hi>Slanders,</hi> are the greatest Pests and
Plagues to a Body Politique. They are conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually
stirring up Strife and Contention, Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mosities
and Emulation: And where <hi>these</hi> are,
St. <hi>Iames</hi> tells us, <hi>There is Confusion, and every evil
Work. One</hi> of these is sufficient to set a whole
<hi>Neighbourhood</hi> together by the Ears, and a <hi>Few</hi> of
them are enough to enflame a whole <hi>City,</hi> nay a
whole <hi>Kingdom.</hi> King <hi>Solomon</hi> saith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16. 27.
<hi>An ungodly Man diggeth up Evil, and in his Lips there
is a burning Fire.</hi> And St. <hi>Paul, 2 Cor.</hi> 12. 20.
brings in <hi>Swellings</hi> and <hi>Tumults</hi> immediately af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<hi>Backbitings</hi> and <hi>Whisperings.</hi> Which he had
good reason to do, since <hi>those</hi> are the <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi>
Consequents and Effects of <hi>these.</hi> For
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95580:12"/>
they not only sow Seeds of Division among
the <hi>People,</hi> but beget a mutual Mis-understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
between <hi>them</hi> and their <hi>Governours.</hi> These
Backbitings and Whisperings render <hi>Governours</hi>
jealous of their <hi>People,</hi> and the <hi>People</hi> as jealous
of their <hi>Governours.</hi> Princes <hi>see</hi> with <hi>other</hi> Mens
<hi>Eyes,</hi> as they <hi>Act</hi> by <hi>other</hi> Mens <hi>Hands;</hi> and
therefore 'tis the most difficult Thing, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
next to impossible for them, ordinarily to
discern between <hi>Calumnies</hi> and <hi>True Stories.</hi> They
have greater Matters alwayes to mind, than
to have Leisure to Dive to the bottom of
those <hi>Reports</hi> that are brought to them. And
therefore, no wonder if they are frequently
Abused and Imposed upon; and so, perswaded
to take <hi>some</hi> for their <hi>Worst,</hi> who are in the
number of their <hi>Best</hi> Subjects; and <hi>others</hi> for
their <hi>Best,</hi> who are really their <hi>Worst.</hi> And
while the Slanderers are as Cunning and Dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous
as they are Wicked and Malicious, What
can alwayes prevent this, and the horrible Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs
occasioned thereby, but such a degree
of Wisdom and Knowledg, as no where resides
but in <hi>GOD</hi> himself?</p>
            <p>Now King <hi>David</hi> had great reason to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve
upon doing his Utmost towards the Root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95580:13"/>
out of his Kingdom such People as <hi>These,</hi>
when he knew them to be the great Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of their Father the <hi>Devil,</hi> in making his
Subjects uneasy to <hi>himself,</hi> and to <hi>one another,</hi>
and <hi>himself</hi> too as uneasy unto <hi>them:</hi> When he
knew that all good Order and Government,
was inconsistent with the Encouragement, or
Toleration of such a Crew of vile Miscreants.
When he was so well aware, that let such pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
to what <hi>Loyalty</hi> they pleased, 'twas im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible
for him to have Naughtier Subjects
than <hi>These</hi> are.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let us Consider what St.</hi> Iames <hi>saith of a</hi>
Slandering <hi>Tongue,</hi> Ch. 3. v. 5. The Tongue is a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
member, and boasteth great things; behold how
great a matter a little fire kindleth! And the
Tongue is a Fire, a VVorld of Iniquity. So is the
Tongue <hi>(or a</hi> Calumniating Backbiting <hi>Tongue)</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
our Members, that it defileth the whole Body,
and it is set on Fire of Hell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> As Inventers of <hi>Slanders</hi> are the most
Mischievous and Destructive sort of People; so,
whilst they are neglected and let alone, they
are the most <hi>Successful</hi> in their wicked De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs.
They are so Successful, that what our
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95580:13"/>
               <hi>Proverb</hi> saith of a <hi>Flayl,</hi> is much truer of a <hi>Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
Tongue,</hi> that, <hi>There is no Fence against it.</hi> If
any thing be a sure Protection from it, one
would think the most Spotless Innocence, and
the most Exemplary Virtue needs must, but
the Example of our Blessed <hi>Saviour</hi> assures us
of the Contrary. No Man ever arrived to
<hi>His</hi> Innocence or Vertue; but for all that, never
was any one so strangely Wronged in his <hi>Good-Name</hi>
as <hi>He.</hi> Though no Man more Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
or Taught <hi>Loyalty,</hi> yet was He Represented
as an Enemy to <hi>Caesar.</hi> Though never had
the <hi>Devil such</hi> an Enemy, yet was he Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niated
as a Great <hi>Wizzard,</hi> in league with <hi>Beel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebub</hi>
the <hi>Prince of the Devils.</hi> Though never
was the Breast of any one so possessed with
Divine <hi>Love,</hi> nor any man's Mind with so
great a Reverence and Veneration of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<hi>Majesty,</hi> yet was He Stigmatized with the
Blackest of all Marks and Characters, <hi>viz.</hi> That
of a <hi>Blasphemer.</hi> And as the most horrid <hi>Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi>
were invented and published to the World
of Him, so were they generally <hi>believed</hi> too.
There is Nothing we are Owners of that's so
Exposed to the Mercy of others, as are our
<hi>Good-Names.</hi> Whosoever hath a Tongue in his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95580:14"/>
Head, if he be but <hi>Wicked</hi> enough, and not
Universally <hi>known</hi> to be a Wicked Man, can,
when he pleaseth, do our Names a mischief.
The <hi>Wise man</hi> saith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 25. 18. that <hi>A Man
that beareth false Witness against his Neighbour, is
a Maul, and a Sword, and a Sharp-Arrow.</hi> That is,
He is made up and Compounded of all fatal
Mischiefs. A <hi>Maul</hi> cannot give greater Bruises,
nor more effectually Fell to the ground, than
<hi>this</hi> sort of Weapon: Nor a <hi>Sword</hi> pierce <hi>deeper,</hi>
or Cut and Slash <hi>more</hi> Cruelly: Nor a sharp
<hi>Arrow</hi> wound at a <hi>greater</hi> distance, no nor at
nothing <hi>so great</hi> a distance; for there is no get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
out of the Reach of a Slandering Tongue;
nor is there any where to be found Security
against it: I mean, besides the <hi>Special</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary</hi>
Providence of God. St. <hi>Iames</hi> tells
us in the fore-mentioned <hi>Chapter, ver.</hi> 7. &amp;c. that
<hi>Every kind of Beasts, and of Birds, and of Serpents,
and things in the Sea, is tamed, and hath been tamed
of Man-kind; But the Tongue (viz.</hi> The Tongue
of a <hi>Slanderer,</hi> as is plain by <hi>ver.</hi> 9.) <hi>can no Man
tame, it is an unruly Evil,</hi> (such an Evil as there
is no <hi>dealing</hi> with it) <hi>full of deadly Poison:</hi> Such
as is too strong for the most Sovereign An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:95580:14"/>Many (<hi>saith the</hi> Son of Syrack) have fallen by
the Edge of the Sword, but not so many as have
fallen by the Tongue: Well is he that is defended
from it, and hath not passed through the Venome there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.
Who hath not drawn the Yoke thereof, nor hath
been bound in its bands? For the Yoke thereof is as
a Yoke of Iron, and the bands thereof as bands of Brass.
The death thereof is an evil death, the Grave were
better than it. <hi>So that the</hi> Slanderer <hi>being an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy,
against whose Assaults the greatest Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
Power, Policy or Wisdom, cannot whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
defend us; well might King</hi> David <hi>conceive
so high a displeasure against him, as he here
expresseth. And the like displeasure doth he
declare against him, Psalm.</hi> 120. 2, 3, 4. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver
my Soul, O Lord, from lying Lips, and from a
deceitful Tongue. What shall be given unto thee, or
what shall be done unto thee thou false Tongue?
Sharp Arrows of the Mighty, with Coals of Iuniper.
<hi>Or, with</hi> hot burning Coles, <hi>according to the</hi>
other <hi>Translation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I proceed now to make some <hi>Application</hi> of
what hath been said; And it shall be <hi>This.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> This little we have discoursed on this
Argument, is abundantly enough to render the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95580:15"/>
Sin of <hi>Slandering our Neighbour</hi> most abominable
in our Eyes. I mean,</p>
            <p>1. The Sin of <hi>Devising</hi> and <hi>Inventing</hi> Defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations
and <hi>Slanders.</hi> This indeed is <hi>such</hi> a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness
as one would think it should be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less
to caution those against it, I will not say,
who profess <hi>Christianity,</hi> but who have not
bid adien to all <hi>Humanity.</hi> It is such a <hi>Black,</hi>
such a <hi>Hellish</hi> Sin, as that the <hi>Devil</hi> hath
both his chief <hi>Names</hi> and <hi>Characters</hi> from it.
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> This Name <hi>Devil,</hi> signifies
<hi>the Slanderer. Satan</hi> signifies the <hi>Spiteful Enemy.</hi>
The chief <hi>Characters</hi> we meet with in Scripture
of the <hi>Devil,</hi> are these two, <hi>The Father of
Lies,</hi> and <hi>The Accuser of the Brethren.</hi> And
therefore nothing can denominate us more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly
like the <hi>Devil,</hi> than this forging of Lies
and Calumnies against our Brethren. And we
see, <hi>Psalm. 50. 19, &amp;c.</hi> with what severity the
Great God expresseth himself against those that
dare to commit <hi>This Sin.</hi> Saith <hi>He, Thou givest
thy Mouth to Evil, and thy Tongue frameth Deceit.
Thou sittest and speakest against thy Brother, thou slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derest
thine own Mothers Son. These things hast
thou done, and I kept silence; thou thoughtest
that I was altogether such an one as thy self: But
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95580:15"/>
I will reprove thee, and set them in order before
thine Eyes.</hi> And <hi>v.</hi> 16. He asks such as <hi>These,
What they had to do to declare his Statutes, or that
they should take his Covenant into their Mouths:</hi> Or
to make profession of his Religion, or indeed
of <hi>any</hi> Religion. And <hi>v. 22. He threatens</hi> them
<hi>that He would tear them in Pieces, and there should
be none to deliver,</hi> if they would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider
what he now had said, and lay it to
heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>King</hi> Solomon <hi>putteth this Practice of</hi> Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering,
<hi>in the number of those Sins, which God
Abominates in a more</hi> Especial <hi>manner.</hi> Prov.
6. 16. &amp;c. These six thing doth the Lord hate,
yea seven are an Abomination to him. A Proud Look,
a Lying Tongue, and Hands that shed Innocent
Blood: An Heart that deviseth Wicked Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:
Feet that be swift in Running to Mischief:
A False Witness that speaketh Lies: And he that
soweth Discord among Brethren. <hi>And indeed all
these Seven things, except the</hi> first, <hi>are such as
make the proper Character of</hi> This sort of Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers
<hi>I am now exposing. And</hi> Rev. 22. 15.
Whosoever loveth and maketh a Lie, <hi>is reckoned
with</hi> Dogs <hi>and</hi> Sorcerers, <hi>and</hi> Whoremongers, <hi>and</hi>
Murtherers, <hi>and</hi> Idolaters; <hi>who are to</hi> have their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95580:16"/>
Portion in the Lake that burneth with Fire and Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone.</p>
            <p>2. Let us no less hate the Practice of <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
up Evil Reports</hi> against any, that <hi>that</hi> of
<hi>Inventing</hi> them. We learn from <hi>Psal.</hi> 15. 3.
That <hi>This</hi> also will exclude us the Kingdom of
<hi>Heaven;</hi> in that 'tis here said, that among those
<hi>that shall abide in Gods Tabernacle, and dwell in
his Holy Hill, He</hi> is one that <hi>Backbiteth not with
his Tongue, nor doth Evil to his Neighbour, nor
taketh up a Reproach against his Neighbour:</hi> Or
doth not without <hi>Good Evidence</hi> give credit to it,
and much less spread and propagate it. The
<hi>Wise Man</hi> maketh <hi>him</hi> a <hi>VVicked doer, who giveth
heed to false Lips;</hi> and a <hi>Lyar, who giveth ear to
a naughty Tongue. Prov. 17. 4. This</hi> is as much a
Transgression of the forementioned <hi>Golden Rule,</hi>
Of <hi>doing as we would be done unto,</hi> as is <hi>Devising</hi>
and <hi>Forging</hi> Slanders. I doubt there is not much
<hi>less Malice</hi> in this Practice, but I am sure it
savours of <hi>every whit</hi> as little <hi>Charity,</hi> as that
<hi>other</hi> Practice doth. I can have no <hi>Charity</hi> for
that man, against whom I am forward to believe
and report whatsoever of evil I chance to hear
of him. Nay, <hi>VVhisperers</hi> and <hi>Backbiters,</hi> as well
as <hi>Inventers of Evil things,</hi> are reckoned by Saint
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95580:16"/>
               <hi>Paul,</hi> among those obdurate Sinners, of whom
he Pronounceth, That God <hi>had given them over</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>to a Reprobate mind,</hi> Rom. 1.
29, 30.</p>
            <p>Hasty Believers and Spreaders of false Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports,
are the Tools and Instruments of those
that invent them, for the doing of the Mischief
they design by them. And it is almost whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<hi>Long</hi> of these, that <hi>Those</hi> wicked People are
in a Capacity of doing <hi>any</hi> Mischief by their
Forgeries.</p>
            <p>We are Bound therefore by the strictest Bonds,
by the Bonds of <hi>Charity,</hi> of <hi>Iustice,</hi> and of <hi>Self-Preservation,</hi>
to be extremely Cautious of lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
our Ear to <hi>Tale-Bearers,</hi> lest we be Invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
in their <hi>Guilt,</hi> and so brought to share with
them in their dreadful <hi>Punishment.</hi> Since this
is an express Law of God, <hi>Thou shalt not go up
and down as a Tale-bearer among thy People,</hi> Lev.
19. 16. Surely 'tis as <hi>much a Law of His,</hi> That
we should not give incouragement to those
whom we know to be <hi>Tale-bearers,</hi> by <hi>Listning</hi>
to their <hi>Tales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, We are obliged to be so far from
Believing a Report against our Neighbour,
meerly from the Information of any <hi>One</hi> or a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95580:17"/>
               <hi>Few</hi> Persons, of whose Integrity, and of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
certain Knowledge of the Truth thereof, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
have not great Assurance, that we may not ne<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ther
conclude any Man <hi>Guilty,</hi> from his being
Accused by the <hi>Generality.</hi> There is indeed a
common saying, <hi>Vox-Populi est vox Dei, The
Voice of the People is the Voice of God.</hi> And in
a certain Sence it may well pass for a true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb.
But as it is vulgarly understood, The
<hi>Voice of the People</hi> is <hi>not</hi> the <hi>Voice of God,</hi> as we
of this <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Kingdom</hi> have often found by
sad Experience. All Wise and Honest Men
cannot be, at this time of day, to seek for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction,
What great Sufferers, even our <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours</hi>
themselves have been <hi>Wrongfully</hi> made to
be, by the <hi>Voice of the People.</hi> And I dare Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm,
That he who now takes the common
Vogue for unquestionable Evidence, had he
lived in the Dayes of our Blessed <hi>Saviour,</hi> would
have been made One among that wicked Crew,
who applauded the Sentence pronounc'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
Him.</p>
            <p>And there is this weighty Reason, why Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
Fame it self is not to be Confided in, <hi>viz.</hi>
For ought we can tell this Fame might first
arise from but <hi>One</hi> Man, and <hi>that</hi> Man a <hi>Liar</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:95580:17"/>
too; and this we <hi>Certainly</hi> know, that the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality
are so void of Charity, as hastily to
Catch at Scandalous Stories, and are much more
easily perswaded to <hi>think</hi> and <hi>report Evil</hi> Things
upon very <hi>slight</hi> Grounds, than <hi>good</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable</hi>
Things, upon the most <hi>evident</hi> and <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent</hi>
Ones. And none have so sad Experience
of the Truth of <hi>this,</hi> as <hi>Those</hi> of whose Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
we are obliged to be the <hi>most tender.</hi> I
mean our Governours in Church and State.</p>
            <p>But suppose we have certain Assurance, that
such an ill Report did take its first Rise from
<hi>not a few,</hi> yet we may not be sure but that
<hi>these</hi> might be <hi>United</hi> in one common <hi>Interest</hi>
and <hi>Design;</hi> but in <hi>this</hi> Case, the Report of <hi>many</hi>
carryes no whit stronger Evidence with it, than
if it came but from <hi>One</hi> Mouth. And this was
the very Case of our <hi>Blessed Lord:</hi> They were
<hi>many</hi> who first divulged vile <hi>Slanders</hi> of Him,
but they were All acted by one and the same
<hi>Principle, viz.</hi> That of <hi>Malice;</hi> and by the same
<hi>Design, viz.</hi> That of <hi>Disgracing Him among the
People,</hi> and Incencing of King <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pontius
Pilate</hi> against Him.</p>
            <p>But Lastly, Suppose we could be certain,
That the many 'first Reporters of Bad Stories
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95580:18"/>
were <hi>not</hi> Linked together by one Common Tye,
yet even in <hi>this</hi> Case too we are bound to use
Caution and Deliberation, before we give them
undoubted Credit. Especially if those Stories
relate to Words or Actions that are capable of
a <hi>two-fold</hi> Interpretation. The same <hi>Actions</hi> may
be Faulty or Commendable, according to the
<hi>Circumstances</hi> wherewith they are attended. And
the same <hi>Words</hi> may be so too, according to
the <hi>Occasion</hi> or <hi>Connexion</hi> of them. But People
are generally, even those who have no <hi>Malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi>
Intention, Rash, and Heady in judging of
<hi>Actions</hi> without weighing <hi>Circumstances;</hi> and in
running away with <hi>half</hi> Sentences; or with
<hi>whole</hi> ones, without Considering, What <hi>went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</hi>
or <hi>followed after.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that, I say, as we would not fall under
the Guilt of that <hi>Sin,</hi> the exceeding Heinous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
of which I have been representing, Look
we to it, that we be not Hasty in taking up
Evill Reports of any Body, let them come to
us from never so <hi>many.</hi> If this be warrantable,
as I have already intimated, the joyning with
those who ran down our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and at last
Nailed <hi>Him</hi> to the <hi>Cross,</hi> had been very Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuseable,
not to say <hi>Defensible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:95580:18"/>And let us believe as <hi>well</hi> as, without offering
Violence to our Reason, we can of <hi>all</hi> Men;
and chuse much rather in our Judging, and
in our Reports of Men, to offend on the <hi>Right</hi>
than on the <hi>Left</hi> hand. I am certain, thus
much is implied in those <hi>two Precepts</hi> of our
Lord, viz. <hi>Iudg not that ye be not Iudged; for
with what Iudgment ye Iudge ye shall be Iudged, and
with what Measure ye mete, it shall be meted to
you again.</hi> Matth. 7. 1, 2. And <hi>Iudge not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to the appearance, but judg Righteous Iudgment,</hi>
John 7. 24.</p>
            <p>2. Ought the <hi>Slandering</hi> of our <hi>Neighbour</hi> to
be so detested by us, then what an Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
thing is it, to Slander, and injure the <hi>Good-Name</hi>
and Reputation of the <hi>Kings Majesty,</hi>
and of those that under <hi>Him</hi> have Authority
over us! 'Tis an express Law of God, <hi>Exod.</hi>
22. 28. &amp; repeated by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> viz. <hi>Thou shalt not
revile the Gods, nor Curse</hi> (or speak evil of) <hi>the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler
of thy People.</hi> And as to the <hi>King,</hi> 'tis so
great a wickedness to defame <hi>Him,</hi> or say any
thing to the lessening of his Honour, that the
<hi>Wise Man</hi> thus chargeth us, <hi>Eccles. 10. 20. Curse
not the King, no not in thy thought.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:95580:19"/>And 'tis as much the <hi>Peoples</hi> interest, as it
is the <hi>Kings,</hi> that He be not <hi>Slandered<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> or <hi>Spoken
Evil</hi> of. For Seditious and Rebellious Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
do usually arise from Mens first taking this
Wicked Liberty; as we have all known by ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
woeful Experience. And we know by the
like experience, that the <hi>King</hi> suffers not more
by those leud Practices, than the <hi>People</hi> necessarily
must.</p>
            <p>It was a good saying, as I remember, of
<hi>Aristotle,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<hi>VVhosoever defames the Prince, is Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
to the Common-VVealth;</hi> or Mischiefs his <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for those that take liberty to <hi>Invent</hi>
or <hi>Tell</hi> Stories reflecting upon their <hi>Ecclesiastical</hi>
Governours, Pastors, or Teachers, they are in
a special manner injurious to the <hi>Souls of Men.</hi>
For nothing so tends to the prejudicing of their
People against their <hi>Doctrine,</hi> as their having an
Evil Opinion of their <hi>Persons.</hi> And for <hi>this</hi>
Reason, I think none are so much concerned
to keep their <hi>Good-Names</hi> as unspotted as they
can, and to clear themselves of whatsoever As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persions
are cast upon them, as <hi>They</hi> are.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:95580:19"/>
            <head>The Conclusion.</head>
            <p>ANd now I will take this Occasion to inform
you, That <hi>Some</hi> having greatly concerned
themselves of late, to carry Tales of Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
Passages which they pretend to have heard
from the <hi>Pulpits</hi> of divers of my Brethren in <hi>this
City,</hi> there are <hi>Others</hi> who have very lately
done the like good Office for <hi>My self.</hi> I am
too well aware <hi>Who</hi> they are, I will tell you
who they are <hi>Not;</hi> I am very confident, they
are <hi>not Papists,</hi> at least not <hi>Professed</hi> ones. But
you of <hi>this</hi> Parish may have a shrewd guess
within a very few; for you must needs know
some to have long expressed as bitter and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable
enmity against me, as if we had been
of <hi>two Churches</hi> and <hi>Contrary Religions:</hi> And that
without the least provocation on <hi>My</hi> part. And
I doubt not there are many of the <hi>Roman Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi>
from whom I should have had much more
<hi>Iust, Fair,</hi> and <hi>Christian</hi> Treatment. As <hi>silent</hi> as
I have been hitherto, this is not the <hi>first</hi> nor
<hi>second</hi> time neither, that I have been in the self-same
manner most vilely abused by <hi>These</hi> People,
as in due time, I trust in God will be made
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95580:20"/>
manifest. My last Accusation was this, (or
at least the last I have <hi>heard</hi> of) That I vent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in <hi>this</hi> Pulpit, on <hi>All-Saints-</hi>Day, <hi>viz.</hi> This day
<hi>Fortnight,</hi> a <hi>Bitter Curse</hi> against the <hi>Papists,</hi> together
with all those (for which I trust to the <hi>Memory</hi> of
an Extraordinary Person) <hi>who give them encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
And the Curse I understand was worded to
this Effect; <hi>I wish their Names and Memories may Rot
Eternally.</hi> Whatsoever the <hi>Express Words</hi> were,
I hear they perfectly <hi>Agreed</hi> in the <hi>self-same,</hi>
which is so far from Evidence of their telling
<hi>Truth</hi> of me, that 'tis a much stronger Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of their being <hi>Conspirators</hi> against me.
But may this <hi>Curse,</hi> instead of falling upon the
<hi>Papists,</hi> or those that <hi>Encourage</hi> them, light up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
my <hi>Own</hi> Name and Memory, if I either
Pronounced <hi>It,</hi> or any Curse <hi>like it</hi> against ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
the <hi>One</hi> or the other, or any <hi>Curse at all</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
either. And as I solemnly Appeal to
<hi>God Almighty,</hi> so I Appeal to <hi>You</hi> my <hi>Auditors,</hi>
Whether there were the least <hi>Appearance</hi> or <hi>Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow</hi>
of an <hi>Occasion</hi> given by me, for such an
Information <hi>as this</hi> against me. I Appeal to
<hi>You</hi> also, Whether you can think it <hi>Possible,</hi>
that such an Accusation as <hi>this</hi> could arise from
<hi>meer Mistake.</hi> I am Confident, That All who
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95580:20"/>
               <hi>minded</hi> my Sermon, will pronounce, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<hi>this Charge,</hi> nor <hi>any</hi> Charge that hath the
least <hi>likeness</hi> to it, be it <hi>Worded</hi> how it will, must
be nothing better than <hi>pure Invention;</hi> which
we have shewn is the most <hi>Horrible</hi> way of
<hi>Slandering.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I prevailed with a most Worthy Prelate to
hear that Sermon read out of my Notes word
for word, and I cannot call to mind my having
said above three or four Words more than are
in my Notes, and <hi>those</hi> I acquainted his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship
with, meerly that I might <hi>truly</hi> say, That
He had nothing of the Sermon Concealed from
Him. And after it was read, not one <hi>Bit</hi> of
a Sentence could be fixed upon, that might put
my Enemies in <hi>mind</hi> to Invent such a Slander
as <hi>this</hi> of me, unless it were <hi>this,</hi> viz. <hi>If we do
not justify to all the World</hi> (meaning, as before
was expressed, <hi>we Divines</hi> of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land)
the Representations we have made of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
(viz.</hi> the <hi>Roman) to our People, let our Names
stink, and our Memories be covered with Eternal shame.</hi>
And <hi>these</hi> words next follow, <hi>'Tis a most wicked thing
to Slander a particular Person, and much more to
Slander and Be-lye a whole Church, and that so Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
and Famous a Church, as that of</hi> Rome <hi>once
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95580:21"/>
was.</hi> So that if I had been Accused of Curse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<hi>my Self,</hi> or my <hi>Brethren,</hi> instead of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists,</hi>
and <hi>those</hi> that <hi>Encourage</hi> them, there had
been a much more Colourable Pretence for such
a Calumny.</p>
            <p>I know I han't lived such a Life as that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
so Solemn Appeals as I have now made,
my perfect Innocence, as to <hi>this Charge,</hi> should
be in the least Questioned by those, who have
the least Knowledge of me. Bur as for those
that are <hi>Acquainted</hi> with me, I am certain they
<hi>need</hi> no such <hi>Appeals</hi> to Satisfy <hi>them,</hi> that I could
not be Guilty of so <hi>Un-Christian</hi> a thing, as the
Cursing of <hi>any</hi> Man, upon <hi>any</hi> account; and
much less, as the Cursing of <hi>any Sort</hi> of Men,
upon the account of their being of a <hi>different</hi>
Religion from <hi>my Self.</hi> For as to all <hi>such,</hi>
I have very rarely been blamed for any
<hi>Defect of Charity</hi> towards them; but I have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
been Censured as being in the <hi>other</hi> Extreme,
<hi>viz.</hi> Of the <hi>Excess</hi> of Charity, which I have
alwayes concluded to be <hi>much</hi> the <hi>safest.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Good Lord, That any, who profess them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
<hi>Christians,</hi> should be so <hi>depraved,</hi> as to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
our Preaching God's holy Word, with
no <hi>better</hi> a Design, than to be <hi>Spyes</hi> upon Us,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95580:21"/>
and to catch at all advantages (and when they
can <hi>find</hi> none, to <hi>make</hi> them) for the <hi>Ruining</hi> of us
and our <hi>Families;</hi> Nay, and which is <hi>worse,</hi> if
worse <hi>can</hi> be, that such should dare to receive the
<hi>Holy Communion,</hi> and that at <hi>Their</hi> hands too, against
whom they are alwayes <hi>Contriving of Mischief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God Grant that such People may at length se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously
lay to heart, the wretched State they are
in, and consider what a severe Reckoning, they
shall one day be called to for such Practices. And
that, if timely Repentance prevent it not, there
will most certainly be <hi>Bitterness in the Latter End.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have sometimes e'ne <hi>Trembled</hi> to think, what
horrid Crimes the Devil in time may draw <hi>such</hi>
into, who are so forsaken of the <hi>Divine Grace,</hi> as
to be <hi>Able</hi> to do such things as <hi>These.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have long Remembred my Adversaries par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
in my <hi>Daily</hi> Prayers, that God would
be pleased to give them true Repentance for the
many great Injuries they have done me, and for
their <hi>other</hi> Sins, that their Souls may be saved in
the day of the <hi>Lord Iesus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am under a greater necessity than you are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware
of, <hi>thus</hi> to clear my Innocence; and what
I have now done, hath not been without the best
Advice.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:95580:22"/>Thanks be to God, His <hi>Majesty</hi> is so Just and
Gracious a Prince, as instead of readily crediting
ill Stories of us, to give us <hi>Opportunities</hi> for the
clearing of our Innocence: And very willingly
Condescends, <hi>Audire alteram Partem,</hi> to the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of our <hi>Vindications.</hi> Nor is His <hi>Majesty</hi> less
forward to the receiving of Satisfaction concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
our Innocence, than Patient in <hi>Hearing</hi>
Complaints against us. Which <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>His</hi>
lays a <hi>Farther</hi> Obligation upon us, to Pray for
His <hi>Majesties</hi> Long and Happy Reign over us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will now Conclude, with that most</hi> Christian
<hi>Petition of our</hi> Church <hi>in the</hi> Litany. We beseech
thee Good Lord, That it may please Thee to forgive
our Enemies, Persecutors and Slanderers, and to turn
their Hearts. <hi>And with the</hi> Intercession <hi>of our
Blessed</hi> Saviour <hi>upon the</hi> Cross, <hi>for his Bloody
Enemies:</hi> Father forgive them, for they know not
what they do.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:95580:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
