<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An account of Muscovy, as it was in the year 1689 In which the troubles that happen'd in that empire from the present czar Peter's election to the throne, to his being firmly settled in it, are particularly related. With a character of him, and his people. By Monsieur de La Neuville, then residing at Moscow.</title>
            <title>Relation curieuse et nouvelle de Moscovie. English.</title>
            <author>Foy de la Neuville.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 157 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-01">2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40372</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2046A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201277</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825130</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825130</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29503</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A40372)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29503)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1829:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An account of Muscovy, as it was in the year 1689 In which the troubles that happen'd in that empire from the present czar Peter's election to the throne, to his being firmly settled in it, are particularly related. With a character of him, and his people. By Monsieur de La Neuville, then residing at Moscow.</title>
                  <title>Relation curieuse et nouvelle de Moscovie. English.</title>
                  <author>Foy de la Neuville.</author>
                  <author>Baillet, Adrien, 1649-1706, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 119, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Edward Castle, next Scotland-Yard-Gate, by Whitehall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed, apparently erroneously, to Adrien Baillet.</note>
                  <note>A translation of: Relation curieuse et nouvelle de Moscovie.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Monsieur de la Neuville's account of Muscovy.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Peter --  I, --  Emperor of Russia, 1672-1725.</term>
               <term>Russia --  History --  Peter I, 1689-1725 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29503:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29503:1"/>
            <p>AN ACCOUNT OF <hi>MUSCOVY,</hi> As it was in the Year 1689.</p>
            <p>In which the TROUBLES that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd in that Empire from the Preſent <hi>Czar</hi> PETER'S Election to the Throne, to his being firmly ſettled in it, are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly related.</p>
            <p>With a Character of Him, and his People.</p>
            <p>By Monſieur <hi>DE LA NEUVILLE,</hi> Then Reſiding at <hi>Moſcow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Edward Caſtle,</hi> next <hi>Scotland-Yard-Gate,</hi> by <hi>Whitehall.</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29503:2"/>
            <head>
               <pb facs="tcp:29503:2"/>
TO THE KING.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Marqueſs of <hi>Bethune</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inform'd in <hi>July, 1689.</hi> that the <hi>Swediſh</hi> and <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denbourg</hi> Envoys were gone to <hi>Moſcow;</hi> he judg'd it neceſſary for Your Majeſty's Service to ſend ſome Perſon thither to diſcover the purport of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiation of thoſe Envoys; he was pleas'd to Honour me with this Truſt, at which I was ſtartled, having been there for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, and been apprehenſive more than once of being ill us'd by thoſe Barbarians; but conſidering 'twas for Your Majeſty's Service, I readily obey'd, only reminding the Marqueſs that no Perſon was ſuffer'd to enter that Kingdom, unleſs as an Envoy, or a Merchant. He undertook to engage the
<pb facs="tcp:29503:3"/>
King of <hi>Poland</hi> in the buſineſs; but that Prince told him 'twas hardly poſſible but I ſhould be known at <hi>Moſcow,</hi> and either be diſcover'd by the <hi>Czar</hi>'s Miniſter, or others, that had ſeen me at his Court, and then I ſhould be treated as a Spy, and ſent to end my days in <hi>Ziberia;</hi> but ſince His Majeſty's Service requir'd my going thither, he would ſend me in a Poſt that ſhould ſecure me, and give me a means of ſucceeding in my Commiſſion. Accordingly he gave me Letters of Recommendation to the <hi>Czars,</hi> and Paſsports, and I ſet forward with an Equipage ſuitable to my Character. For by the laſt Treaty betwixt the <hi>Poles,</hi> and the <hi>Muſcovites,</hi> 'tis agreed not to defray the Envoys Charges, nor furniſh them with Carriages. In fourteen Days I reach'd the Frontiers, though the diſtance from <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw</hi> to <hi>Caſime,</hi> the laſt Town in <hi>Poland,</hi> is One hundred and ſixty <hi>German</hi> Leagues. I gave notice of my Arrival, and my Commiſſion, to the <hi>Palatin</hi> of the Dutchy of <hi>Smolensko,</hi> whither I went next day, and was receiv'd as I have related in the Account of my Journey; and having tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried ten Days till the Courier came back, whom the <hi>Palatin</hi> ſent to the Court for Orders concerning me; I went thence to <hi>Moſcow,</hi> and was lodg'd in a Houſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb facs="tcp:29503:3"/>
for me by the Prime Miniſter, One hundred and fifty Paces diſtant from the City, whither the <hi>Priſtave Spatarus,</hi> a <hi>Walachian,</hi> came to Complement me in his Name, and keep me Company. A Week after, he conducted me to the <hi>Pretache</hi> or Council; after which I had leave to viſit the Miniſters of <hi>Poland, Sweden, Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> and <hi>Brandènbourg,</hi> and ſome <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Officers; and was ſo happy as to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, that all the buſineſs which the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voys of <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Brandenbourgh</hi> came about, was to render the King of <hi>Poland</hi>'s Conduct ſuſpected to the <hi>Muſcovites,</hi> who they alledg'd was in Your Majeſty's Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and would make a ſeparate Peace with the <hi>Turk,</hi> to the prejudice of the League; after which he would make a Diverſion into the <hi>Ducal Pruſſia</hi> in Your Favour. And the <hi>Dutch</hi> Envoy to enforce what they ſaid, aſſur'd the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> that I was a <hi>Frenchman,</hi> and was come to <hi>Moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cow</hi> to pry into their Secrets. Theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations made them reſolve to confine me within my Houſe for eight Days toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Envoy made ſuch loud Complaints of it, as an Injury done to his Maſter in my Perſon; that the Council diſcharg'd me, and ſaid they had no other deſign in taking away my Liberty,
<pb facs="tcp:29503:4"/>
than to ſave me from the Inſults of the People, who were incens'd againſt me. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which I took occaſion to declare, That I knew <hi>France</hi> very well, and that that King with all his Millions would not give a hundred Crowns to diſcover the Deſigns of the <hi>Czar;</hi> and that being the King of <hi>Poland</hi>'s Miniſter, I did not fear the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. In ſhort, the Miniſters of <hi>Sweeden</hi> being ſent back without any ſucceſs, I gave notice of it to the Marquiſs of <hi>Bethune,</hi> deſiring him to recall me, well foreſeeing the Troubles that were coming on. In the beginning of the Commotions, I was forc'd, for my Security, to keep within Doors, not daring to ſtir abroad; where all the Diverſion I had, was the Converſation of my <hi>Priſtave,</hi> who had been ſent to <hi>China,</hi> and was come back two Months. The Information I got from him, being pretty curious, and likely to be of uſe of Your Majeſty, ſhewing the eaſineſs of eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Commerce with that Country by Land, I have thought fit to relate the Particulars of what I learnt. Sometime after my return from <hi>Poland,</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>de Bethune</hi> underſtanding that the Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nover,</hi> were to meet together at <hi>Carel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtad</hi> in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> he deſired the King of
<pb facs="tcp:29503:4"/>
               <hi>Poland</hi> to ſend me to Complement the Duke of <hi>Hanover</hi> upon the Death of his Son, which he had juſt given him advice of, in hopes I might find out the Deſign of the Interview between theſe two Princes. I went thither, and gave an Account to the Marqueſs of <hi>Bethune</hi> of all that I diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd, which was no more than that ſome Propoſitions had paſt on both ſides about the Dutchy of <hi>Lavembourg,</hi> but they could not come to an Accommodation.</p>
            <p>To conclude, <hi>Sir,</hi> Your Majeſty having acquainted the King of <hi>Poland</hi> with the Death of Madam the <hi>Dauphine,</hi> he nam'd Prince <hi>Rzarſtoeki,</hi> now at the Academy at <hi>Paris,</hi> to pay his Complement of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolance to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Your Majeſty. But the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs of <hi>Bethune</hi> deſiring me to accept of that Office, in hopes that under that Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter I might with more ſafety carry the Diſpatches which he gave me for Your Majeſty, and for Your Miniſter at <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> as I did, and that paſſing through ſome Courts where I was very well known, and had been always well receiv'd, I might inform my ſelf what Condition their Affairs were in; I found them all out of Order, and except the Duke of <hi>Hanover</hi> and his Houſe, all in great need of a Peace with Your Majeſty. I have been
<pb facs="tcp:29503:5"/>
honour'd with the Character of Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Envoy; and beſeech You, <hi>Sir,</hi> to accept favourably all that my Zeal for Your Service has made me undertake; and the Account I render, which contains ſuch Particulars as Your Majeſty may be Curious to know, when You are at leiſure from Your Application to decide the Fate of <hi>Europe,</hi> which Your Victories, and the Juſtice of Heaven have put into Your Hands.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am, Your Majeſty's Moſt Humble and Faithful Subject and Servant, De la Neuville.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29503:5"/>
            <head>AN ACCOUNT OF <hi>MUSCOVY,</hi> As it was in the Year 1689.</head>
            <p>THE King of <hi>Poland</hi> having honour'd me with the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of his Envoy Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary to <hi>Muſcovy</hi> the firſt of <hi>July</hi> 1689. I departed from <hi>Warſaw</hi> on the 19<hi>th.</hi> of the ſame Month, and took my way by <hi>Smolensko,</hi> becauſe the way of <hi>Kiovia,</hi> which is the ſhorteſt, was at that time infeſted by the <hi>Tartars.</hi> As ſoon as the Palatine or Governour of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince (who is a more polite Man than the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> generally are) heard that I had left <hi>Cazine,</hi> and was coming to <hi>Smolensko,</hi> he ſent a Priſtave, or Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:29503:6"/>
with an Interpreter to meet me, which they did within half a League of the City, and conducted me into the Suburbs on the other ſide of the <hi>Nieper,</hi> carrying me to a Houſe till they knew where the Palatine wou'd appoint me a fit Lodging: Immediately one of them went to him with the news of my arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val; whereupon he ſent me his Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſome refreſhments, <hi>viz.</hi> a ſmall Cask of <hi>Brandy,</hi> another of Sack, and a third of Honey, together with ſome Fowls, two Sheep, and one Calf, a Cart-load of Fiſh, and another of Oats. He alſo offer'd me a Houſe, either with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Town or the Suburbs; I choſe to be in the latter, becauſe there is no Gate to it, but the City-Gate is ſhut up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times. Next day I made him a Viſit at his Caſtle, where he expected me with the Metropolitan, and ſome Perſons of Quality.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſay nothing of this City, the Buildings being all of Wood here, as well as all the Country over; ſurrounded with a ſlight Stone-wall to ſecure them from the Inroads of the <hi>Poles.</hi> To do the greater honour to me, or rather to himſelf, 6000 of the Militia were drawn out, being Peaſants of thoſe parts,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:29503:6"/>
which are form'd into Regiments upon ſuch occaſions, and have pretty hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Coats given them; they are paid by the <hi>Czars</hi> four Crowns a year, and three Buſhels of Salt. All the Boys at ſix years old are Liſted, and receive Pay, ſo that theſe Forces are made up of Old Men and Children, for no body is excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from ſerving till they die. I paſt through this noble Body of Soldiers, who ſtood rank'd in two Lines from my Houſe to the Governor's, being in my Coach follow'd by the <hi>Poſtſtaroſta,</hi> or the King's Lieutenant of <hi>Mohilova,</hi> and twelve Officers belonging to that Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who were order'd by the King of <hi>Poland</hi> to accompany me hither; as ſoon as the Palatine ſaw me alight before the Caſtle, he came and receiv'd me at the top of the Steps, from whence he led me to his Apartment; where we did not ſit down, but after ſome Compliments on both ſides, which were interpreted by Major General <hi>Meneſius,</hi> a <hi>Scotchman,</hi> who ſpeaks all the <hi>European</hi> Languages, the Palatine order'd ſome large Cups of Brandy to be brought in, which were drank off to the King of <hi>Poland</hi>'s and <hi>Czars</hi> Health. After which I took my leave of him, and he waited on me back
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29503:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
again half way down the Steps, and ſtood to ſee me take Coach. I return'd in the ſame order I came, and found General <hi>Meneſius</hi> attending my coming, being order'd by the Palatine to keep me Company, while I continued here. I was very agreeably ſurpriz'd to find a Man of his merit in ſo Barbarous a Country; for beſides his skill in Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, which he ſpeaks perfectly well, he is very knowing in the Affairs of the World, and has ſomething in his Story worth relating.</p>
            <p>After having ſeen moſt parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> he went into <hi>Poland,</hi> deſigning to return from thence to <hi>Scotland;</hi> but having an Intriegue with a <hi>Lithuanian</hi> Colonel's Lady, the Husband grew jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of his frequent Viſits, and laid ſome Servants in wait to kill him; but his Miſtreſs giving him timely notice of it, he found a way to draw the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel to a Duel, and kill'd him; upon which he was forc'd to fly, but for want of a Guide fell in with a party of <hi>Muſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites,</hi> who at that time were at War with the <hi>Poles;</hi> at firſt they treated him as a Priſoner of War; but upon tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them the cauſe of his flight, they gave him his choice, either to ſerve
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29503:7"/>
the <hi>Czar,</hi> or elſe to go into <hi>Ziberia:</hi> He took up with the latter, out of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to ſee thoſe parts. But the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the preſent <hi>Czars</hi> deſiring to ſee him, and finding him a comely Man, took him into Court, and gave him ſixty Peaſants, (each Peaſant brings in to his Maſter about Eight Crowns a year.) Beſides, he made up a Match between him and the Widow of one <hi>Marcellus,</hi> who was the firſt that made Iron in <hi>Muſcovy,</hi> which now brings in to the <hi>Czars</hi> a Revenue of 100000 Crowns <hi>per Annum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame Prince ſent him to <hi>Rome</hi> in the year 1672, to offer Pope <hi>Clement</hi> a Re-union of the <hi>Ruſſian</hi> to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church upon certain conditions; but returning without ſucceſs, he was made Major-General, and ſometime after, the <hi>Czar Alexis Samuel Errick,</hi> a little before his death, declar'd him Governor to his Son the young Prince <hi>Peter,</hi> with whom he continued all along till the beginning of the Reign of the <hi>Czar John,</hi> when the Princeſs <hi>Sophia</hi> and Prince <hi>Galiſchin,</hi> not being able to make him abandon the Intereſt of Prince <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> oblig'd him to retire to <hi>Smolensko,</hi> and make the laſt Campaign, in hopes to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29503:8"/>
be rid of him. But this Diſgrace was the occaſion of his preſent fortune; for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an opportunity to get acquainted with Prince <hi>Peter</hi>'s Uncle on the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's ſide, a Colonel in that Gariſon, he took him with him to <hi>Moſcow,</hi> as ſoon as his Nephew became Maſter of that City, where he has often treated me very friendly at his Houſe, with the <hi>Naraskins</hi> Father and Son: The Prime Miniſter under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that I was at <hi>Smolensko,</hi> the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital of the Dutchy of that name, which the King of <hi>Poland</hi> yeilded to the <hi>Czars</hi> by the Treaty in 1686, ſent order to the Palatine that I ſhou'd be conducted in the uſual manner to <hi>Laſtoliſtz,</hi> which ſignifies the Court, and is improperly call'd by us <hi>Moſcow,</hi> which is the name of a River that runs through it. I began my Journey upon the 20<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> attended by a <hi>Priſtave,</hi> a Captain, and ſix Soldiers: The firſt proof of their courage that theſe Gentlemen gave me, was in our paſſage through a Wood of twenty Leagues long, having never a Houſe in it. So we made our Lodging as commodious as we cou'd in our Waggons, our Horſes Grazing by us. In the Night we had a violent ſtorm, and the Horſes broke out of the <hi>Tabor,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:29503:8"/>
(or Incloſure made by our Waggons) and ran into the Woods for ſhelter; I bid the Officer ſend ſome of his Men for them, and others to cut down Wood for Firing; but the Officer and Soldiers an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd unanimouſly, that they wou'd not ſtir out of the <hi>Tabor</hi> for a hundred Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cats a Man, becauſe that ſeven years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome of their Comrades that were ſent on ſuch an Errand, were murder'd in this very place; ſo that we ſtaid till Morning, and then all the Horſes at one Whiſtle came back to the <hi>Tabor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From thence I continued my Journey till I arriv'd in the Suburbs of <hi>Laſtoliſtz,</hi> which is divided from the City by the River <hi>Moſcow,</hi> which is fordable in that part; the Officer that came with me carry'd me to a Houſe, and deſir'd me to tarry till he return'd from the Prime Miniſter, whom he went to acquaint with my Arrival. In two hours he came back with Orders to bring me over the River, and conduct me to a Houſe that was appointed for me, where the <hi>Priſtave Spatarus</hi> quickly came to Compliment me in the name of the Prime Miniſter, who commanded him to continue with me; and likewiſe according to cuſtom an Officer and ſix Soldiers were appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29503:9"/>
for my Guard, who were ſtrictly charged to admit no perſon into my Houſe for eight days; at length Prince <hi>Galiſchin</hi> ſent for me to the <hi>Prerarche,</hi> which is a ſpacious Building in form of a ſquare; there are ſeveral Halls in it, in each of which particular Councils are held, which before <hi>Galiſchin</hi> came into the Miniſtry, us'd to meet in Barns; I found him ſeated at the upper end of a great Table with many <hi>Boyars</hi> on each ſide; he caus'd a Chair to be ſet for me, and then an Interpreter ask'd me in <hi>Latin</hi> for my Letters: I preſented him thoſe which the Grand Chancellor of <hi>Lithua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> directed to him, wherein he inform'd him, that the King had ſent me into <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covy</hi> about his Majeſty's Buſineſs, and had given me a Letter to the <hi>Czars;</hi> he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd that he wou'd acquaint the <hi>Czar John,</hi> who was then at <hi>Moſcow</hi> with it, and that he hoped I ſhou'd have Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence very ſpeedily; after which he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd, as the cuſtom is, whether the Chancellor was in good health? for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing out of reſpect to ask how the King did. Then I riſe up to retire; he roſe up too, and wiſh'd me the happineſs of ſeeing the <hi>Czar</hi> in a ſhort time. Some days after, I ſent in Civility to deſire Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29503:9"/>
of him at his Houſe, where I was receiv'd as handſomely as if I had been at the Court of ſome Prince of <hi>Italy.</hi> During the converſation in <hi>Latin,</hi> upon the Affairs of <hi>Europe,</hi> and my thoughts of the War betwixt <hi>France</hi> and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, and eſpecially concerning the Revolution in <hi>England,</hi> He preſented me with all ſorts of Strong waters and Wine; adviſing me at the ſame time with a great deal of Complaiſance not to taſte of them. He promis'd to get me my Audience in a few days, which he certainly would have done, had he not fallen into diſgrace, which produced ſuch a great change of Affairs, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry moment there was an out-cry of Fire and Murder; and if the <hi>Czar Peter</hi> had not had the courage to ſeize the leading men of the Princeſſe's Party, his Life and Crown had been loſt.</p>
            <p>Such was the face of Affairs for ſix Weeks together, that one cou'd not tell who to addreſs one's ſelf to; which made me reſolve to write a Letter to the Young <hi>Galiſchin,</hi> the <hi>Czar Peter</hi>'s Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite, ſignifying my ſurprize, that no Anſwer was given me in relation to my Audience, and the Letters which I had to deliver; he excus'd the matter to me on account of the late Troubles, and aſſur'd
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29503:10"/>
me, that the <hi>Czar</hi> would ſoon come to <hi>Laſtolitz,</hi> as indeed he did the firſt day of <hi>November.</hi> As ſoon as I heard of his arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, I went to ſee his Favourite, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Audience; he did not carry him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf like his Kinſman, but treated me with Brandy, and all the Converſation paſs'd in drinking; all that I cou'd ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from this Drunkard, was, that I ſhould have Audience in three days, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which I might depart when I thought fit; but before that time came about, he fell into diſgrace, and I was oblig'd to take other meaſures. The Office of <hi>Dommith Diak,</hi> or Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, was at that juncture gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to one <hi>Emilian;</hi> this Name, which in the <hi>Sclavonian</hi> Tongue ſignifies a Claw or Talon, befits him well; for he is very covetous, and lets nothing ſlip that comes within the reach of his Talons. Though this man was one of the great <hi>Galiſchin</hi>'s Creatures, and owed his Fortune to him, being originally but a mean Notary, yet he was one of the firſt to traduce the memory of his <hi>Benefactor;</hi> and taking a pique againſt me for not addreſſing my ſelf to him for leave to depart, but always to <hi>Galiſchin,</hi> the <hi>Czar Peter</hi>'s Favourite, as ſoon as he ſaw him in diſgrace, he refus'd to execute the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29503:10"/>
Command which <hi>Galiſchin</hi> had perſuaded the <hi>Czar</hi> to give him, concerning me; <hi>viz.</hi> to tell me, That either I muſt ſtay for my Audience till <hi>Twelfth-day,</hi> or (fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the King of <hi>Poland</hi>'s Orders, who apprehended the conſequence of theſe Troubles) might be gone when I pleas'd. Nay, he took occaſion to excuſe himſelf to the <hi>Czar Peter,</hi> by perſuading him that I ought to be detain'd for a while; inſinuating that the King of <hi>Poland</hi> had ſent me to <hi>Moſcow</hi> only to negotiate with the Prime Miniſter, and to aſſure the Princeſs and <hi>Galiſchin</hi> of his Protection; and as a ground for ſuch a Suſpicion, he urg'd, that contrary to the uſual cuſtom in this Country, and the honour of my Character, I had made ſeveral private Viſits to that Prince. Being inform'd of all that paſs'd, I bethought my ſelf of an Expedient, <hi>viz.</hi> To offer ſome Money under-hand to <hi>Emilian</hi> for leave to depart, which he having promis'd to give me for 100 <hi>Ducats,</hi> inſtead of ſending them to him, as had been agreed betwixt him and the Perſon I had employ'd, I went under pretence of paying him a viſit to carry the Money my ſelf; now my Friend <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themonerrich,</hi> to whom I diſclos'd the matter, popp'd in upon him juſt at the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29503:11"/>
time this Secretary had appointed me to come, and I had the pleaſure to tell him my mind very roundly in this young Lord's preſence; for I knew what mettle the <hi>Moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covites</hi> are made of; that they underſtand nothing of Civility or Honeſty, and therefore 'tis in vain to deal with 'em up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe Terms, much leſs to beg a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of 'em, becauſe that makes 'em de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe one; but they muſt be handled roughly when a man deſigns to bring 'em to reaſon. I told him the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions was violated in my Perſon; that I perceiv'd the King of <hi>Poland</hi> was miſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, when upon giving me my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, he aſſur'd me that the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> were no longer <hi>Barbarians:</hi> That I was ſo weary of living among 'em, that I could wiſh I were allow'd to buy a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to return; but foraſmuch as I had the honour to be the Miniſter of a great King, a Neighbour and Ally to the <hi>Czars,</hi> I could do no otherwiſe than give him advice, that I was hindred from obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Orders he had ſent me, No longer to ſollicit an Audience, but with all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition to leave the Country.</p>
            <p>After I had deliver'd my ſelf to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in <hi>Latin,</hi> which my Friend <hi>Harthemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerrick</hi> interpreted to him, and had taken
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29503:11"/>
off ſeveral Cups of Brandy and Sack to the <hi>Czar</hi>'s Health, I took my leave of him, ordering a <hi>Poliſh</hi> Gentleman to give him the 100 <hi>Ducats,</hi> which I intimated were for his under Secretary, but he never durſt touch 'em. Upon which I reported a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad how generous he was, being given to underſtand there was no other means of obtaining my <hi>Congé.</hi> Mean time the <hi>Czar Peter</hi> having recall'd his Favorite <hi>Galiſchin</hi> to Court, I went to viſit him, and congratulate his return. He told me, he was much ſurpriz'd to hear that <hi>Emilian</hi> had not diſpatch'd my Buſineſs according to the directions he had caus'd to be given him before he left the Court; that he would complain of it to the <hi>Czar,</hi> who thought I was gone already; and that ſince I had waited ſo long to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to kiſs His Majeſty's Hand, he would take care I ſhould have that honour.</p>
            <p>Two days after, I was well pleas'd to ſee two Gentlemen of the <hi>Czar</hi>'s Bed-Chamber come to my Houſe; the truth on't is, theſe ſame Gentlemen have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the Name, they are very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable People, and have nothing to live upon but a Penſion from the <hi>Czar</hi> of 200 <hi>Livres per Ann.</hi> After their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomary Ceremonies, which are making
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29503:12"/>
many Signs of the Croſs, and bowing their Heads to ſome Picture of the <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin,</hi> which is always plac'd in a Corner, they ſaluted me, and enquir'd in the <hi>Czar</hi>'s Name how I did; to which I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving anſwer'd by Cups of Brandy in abundance, they told me the <hi>Czar</hi> had a mind to ſee me, to make me ſome Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and defray my Charges ſince my coming to <hi>Moſcow,</hi> to the day I ſhould leave it; that in the mean time he had ſent me his Dinner. I repli'd, I would not fail to acquaint the King of all the marks of diſtinction the <hi>Czar</hi> ſhould ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour me with, which was punctually perform'd. This Dinner conſiſted of a piece of ſmoak'd Beef of 40 pound weight, ſeveral Diſhes of Fiſh dreſs'd with Oil of Nuts; half a Pig, a dozen of Pies half bak'd, made of Meat, Garlick and Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron, and three great Flaggons of Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, Sack, and Honey. 'Tis eaſy to gueſs from this Bill of Fare, that the beſt part of the Treat was the honour that was done me in ſo extraordinary an Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment.</p>
            <p>Next day came another Gentleman to give me notice to get ready for my Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience the next day; but inſtead of the Audience, I was told, the <hi>Czars</hi> being
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29503:12"/>
then going a Pilgrimage together, I could not have the honour of ſeeing them till they came back. Upon which I went preſently to <hi>Galiſchin</hi>'s Houſe, where I found <hi>Harthemonerrick.</hi> They both que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion'd me how I lik'd the Dinner which the <hi>Czar</hi> ſent me, I made anſwer, that to my misfortune, the <hi>French</hi> Cooks had ſo debauch'd my Palate, that I could not reliſh the <hi>Ruſſian</hi> Dainties. Now they having formerly expreſt a deſire of taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>French</hi> Ragouſt, I invited them to an Entertainment of mine next day, which they accepted of, upon condition none ſhould be there but their Friends, whom I deſir'd 'em to invite themſelves; they were the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Commiſſary, and ſome other Merchants, at whoſe Houſes they now and then go to drink to ſave their own Wine. They both ſeem'd ſo well pleas'd with this Repaſt, that they ſent ſeveral Diſhes home to their Wives, and carri'd away with them, without any Ceremony, all the dri'd Sweetmeats, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring me they had never far'd ſo well in their lives, and that erelong they would make me amends at their Houſes. Three days after, <hi>Harthemonerrick</hi> invited me to dine with him, and treated me very no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. 'Twas in their time of <hi>Lent,</hi> which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29503:13"/>
began the day before; ſo the Treat was of Fiſh catcht in the <hi>Caſpian Sea,</hi> and the <hi>Wolga.</hi> To ſhew me the more honour, he brought in his Lady, and preſented her to me; I ſaluted her after the <hi>French</hi> Faſhion, and ſhe drank to me in a Cup of Brandy, and then gave it me to pledge her. She's the only Woman in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try that never uſes any Paint, and indeed ſhe's pretty handſome.</p>
            <p>Prince <hi>Galiſchin</hi> was to have been with us; but the young <hi>Czar</hi> having ſent for him in the Morning, we contented our ſelves with drinking his and ſome other Healths till Midnight. The Gueſts were the ſame that were at my Houſe. This young Lord has a great deal of Wit, ſpeaks <hi>Latin</hi> well, loves Reading, is migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily pleas'd to hear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> talk of what is do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Europe,</hi> and has a particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination for Foreigners. I perſuaded him to learn <hi>French,</hi> aſſuring him that being but two and twenty years old, he would eaſily be Maſter of it, and then might ſatisfie with eaſe his Paſſion for Books; all good Authors Ancient and Modorn being turn'd into that Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. He is Son of <hi>Athemon,</hi> a <hi>Lithua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> and had a <hi>Scotch</hi> Woman to his Mother. He learnt <hi>Latin</hi> of a <hi>Pole,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:29503:13"/>
whom his Father was allow'd to carry with him in his Exile. He was diſgrac'd by <hi>Theodore,</hi> whoſe Prime Miniſter he was; after the Death of that Prince, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both recall'd, he had the grief juſt after their return from Baniſhment to ſee his Father aſſaſſinated in the Rebellion rais'd by <hi>Couvanki.</hi> The <hi>Czars</hi> had now been return'd from their Pilgrimage three days, and hearing nothing farther, I ſent to young <hi>Galiſchin</hi> to know what I was to expect; he anſwer'd that the Council not judging fit to grant me an Audience before <hi>Twelfth-day,</hi> I was at my liberty either to go or ſtay, and that every thing was ready, go when I would. I was not a little ſurprized at this alteration; but underſtanding by the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Commiſſary, that the <hi>Naraskins</hi> taking it ill that I had never paid them a Viſit, and being jealous of the Entertainment I gave to <hi>Galiſchin,</hi> who began to decline in the <hi>Czar</hi>'s fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, had taken ſuch meaſures with <hi>Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> that the <hi>Czar</hi> had chang'd his Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which that Favourite had enclin'd him to in my favour. I gladly accepted of an offer to be diſmiſs'd, and the more willingly, for that I had done the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs I came into the Country about; little valuing the Audience that was promis'd
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29503:14"/>
me, and even leſs the Honour they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended I ſhould receive in ſeeing the <hi>Czars.</hi> Beſides, I was perfectly tir'd of the behaviour of theſe <hi>Barbarians,</hi> and heartily diſſatisfi'd with having beheld in ſpite of me ſo much diſorder and miſchief as happen'd while I ſtaid there, not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to ſtir abroad, and having no other Company than my Priſtave, who was a man of Senſe, 'tis true, and very agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in Converſation, and wou'd have diverted me more, and leſſen'd the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſineſs I underwent, had he been more open and free, and had not been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd through fear, as one may eaſily judge, from diſcovering to me many cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Paſſages which he knew very well, and particularly concerning the Court, which have eſcap'd my knowledge; and I am not a little vex'd at it, for they would have been worth inſerting into theſe Memoirs. I declar'd my Reſolution by him to the Miniſters, and two days after, being the 16th of <hi>December,</hi> ſet out for <hi>Poland</hi> with the ſame Attendance that came with me. The 20th, betimes in the Morning I reach'd <hi>Smolensko,</hi> and without delay preſently went to pay my Reſpects to the <hi>Palatin,</hi> from whom I receiv'd a thouſand Civilities; thence I
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29503:14"/>
continu'd my Journey with the ſame <hi>Priſtave,</hi> Interpreter and Soldiers, as far as <hi>Kaſime,</hi> from thence to <hi>Vilna,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Warſaw,</hi> where I arriv'd <hi>Jan.</hi> 3. 1690. The reaſon of my making ſo much expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, was, becauſe the moſt conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Seaſon for travelling in <hi>Muſcovy</hi> is the Winter; for that Country lying the loweſt in <hi>Europe,</hi> and conſequently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Marſhy, in the Summer one can't go above four or five Leagues a-day, and often one muſt cut Wood to make Bridges to paſs over the Marſhes and Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Streams; for their Cauſeys, of which ſome are laid with Wood for 10 or 12 Leagues in length, are very ill kept, and frequently unſerviceable; whereas in Winter they travel in Sleds, where a man lies as in a Bed, drawn by a ſingle Horſe over the Snow at a good rate; thus one may go Night and Day for 15 or 16 hours, and make a <hi>German</hi> League an hour with eaſe.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:29503:15"/>
               <head>The State of <hi>Muſcovy</hi> from <hi>1682.</hi> to <hi>1687.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>Czar Theodore Alexerwich,</hi> Son of the <hi>Czar Alexis Sancueli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mich</hi> dy'd in the 22d year of his Age, leaving no Iſſue behind him. His Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>John</hi> and the Princeſs <hi>Sophia</hi> were of the ſame Venter; <hi>Peter,</hi> though the Younger, and by another Mother, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded him at firſt, his Elder Brother being uncapable of governing; but ſoon after, <hi>John</hi> was Elected, Proclaim'd and Crown'd likewiſe, by the management of the Princeſs <hi>Sophia</hi> his Siſter, though he was in the Falling-ſickneſs, and was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with it every Moon; his Brother <hi>Theodore</hi> dy'd of it. This Princeſs being ambitious of the Government, and well foreſeeng that ſhe might make her ſelf Abſolute Miſtreſs of ſo great an Empire, becauſe of the Weakneſs of <hi>John,</hi> and the Minority of <hi>Peter,</hi> who wou'd only have the Name and Title of <hi>Czars,</hi> and She all the Authority; and that She had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to fear but the Officers of the Crown, and the Grandees, who might oppoſe her Deſigns, each out of their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29503:15"/>
Ambition, or all out of general diſcontent to ſee themſelves govern'd by a Woman, ſhe prevail'd upon <hi>Couvanski</hi> to be of her Party, and rais'd the <hi>Eſtreles,</hi> a kind of <hi>Militia,</hi> like the <hi>Janiſaries</hi> of the Port, who under colour of revenging the Death of the <hi>Czar Theodore,</hi> who they gave out was poiſoned, made ſo cruel a ſlaughter among the great Lords, that if to appeaſe the Tumult, the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs <hi>Sophia,</hi> perceiving they went far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than ſhe intended, had not come out of the Imperial Palace and ſhew'd her ſelf, they would have gone on to cut off the Innocent with the Guilty, and encreas'd the number of the Dead for the ſake of plundring them; The <hi>Boyars,</hi> or Senators, and the Patriarch interpos'd likewiſe to ſtop the effuſion of more Blood; and the heat of their fury being allay'd, the <hi>Czarvuich Peter Alexerwich</hi> was crown'd <hi>Czar,</hi> to the general joy of <hi>Ruſſia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Prince is graceful and well made, and the acuteneſs of his Wit gives great hopes of a glorious Reign if he be guided by able Counſellors.</p>
               <p>The Princeſs <hi>Sophia</hi> did not expreſs much ſatisfaction upon this Occaſion; ſhe wou'd rather have had the Crown up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29503:16"/>
the Head of <hi>John Alexerwich</hi> her Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the ſame Father and Mother, ſingle without a Conſort, who was rightful Succeſſor; and her Ambition did not ſuffer her to conceal her uneaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs long, for ſhe publickly withſtood the Crowning of <hi>Peter,</hi> pretending 'twas doing wrong to his Elder Brother; 'twas to no purpoſe for the <hi>Boyars</hi> and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch to repreſent to her the incapacity of <hi>John,</hi> that he was an infirm Prince, blind, and impotent of Body: to gain her Point, ſhe was reſolv'd to make uſe of the <hi>Eſtreles,</hi> of which betwixt 18 and 28000 Regiments uſually quarter in <hi>Moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eow</hi> for the <hi>Czar</hi>'s Guard; the <hi>Boyar Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanski,</hi> Preſident of the Chamber of theſe Soldiers, was her Creature, and ſo by open force ſhe rais'd this great Body of Troops, Crown'd and proclaim'd <hi>John</hi> Chief <hi>Czar</hi> to reign jointly with <hi>Peter,</hi> and in concluſion by theſe means, both the Princes being very young, ſhe got the Adminiſtration of the Government into her own hands. 'Twas hop'd that now all Troubles were at an end, and that every thing wou'd reſt in a perfect Calm; but there were Factions form'd in the <hi>Militia,</hi> which is compos'd partly of <hi>Eſtreles,</hi> and partly of the Citizens,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29503:16"/>
who are moſt of them rich Merchants, and are fond of liſting themſelves, and being counted Soldiers; when they mount the Guard they have Coats gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them, which they return again, with this Circumſtance, that they receive ſo many Blows with a Stick over the But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tocks as they have made Spots upon their Cloaths, when they give them in, for theſe Coats never go out of <hi>Moſcow</hi> except thoſe given to the <hi>Eſtreles,</hi> who follow the <hi>Czar</hi> on Horſeback into the Country; the Citizens are allow'd, when 'tis their turn to mount the Guard, to ſend a Servant in their rooms, they or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily buy off the Blows, by preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a new Coat, whereby this Livery is always renew'd and kept neat.</p>
               <p>The Court upon advice of ſome De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign being on foot, for what reaſon is not known, but ſuſpecting the <hi>Czarian</hi> Houſe was in ſome danger, withdrew from <hi>Moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cow,</hi> and retired into <hi>Trinity</hi> Convent, 12 <hi>German</hi> Leagues off; a few days after the <hi>Militia</hi> roſe again, and the abſence of the Court increaſing the Tumult and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, the <hi>Boyar Convanski</hi> let looſe his <hi>Eſtreles</hi> to plunder and murder all that were not of his Party, upon pretence of their being concern'd in the death of the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29503:17"/>
late <hi>Czar;</hi> the Chief Phyſician to the Deceas'd <hi>Theodore,</hi> accus'd of poiſoning his Maſter, was cut in pieces; the Grand Chancellor <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rrenimik Delgorouka,</hi> and his Son, were aſſaſſinated. In a word, ſo exorbitant was their Licentiouſneſs and Cruelty, that I find no pleaſure in relating it. The Princeſs <hi>Sophia</hi> hearing what paſs'd at <hi>Moſcow,</hi> ſent to compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the <hi>Boyar Couvanski</hi> for the Zeal he had ſhewn in revenging the death of her Brother, aſſuring him that ſhe was oblig'd to him for it; this ſhe did out of policy to wheedle a Mad-man, who was to be fear'd with his Sword in his hand; at the ſame time theſe. Cajolements were of very ill conſequence in the end, and produc'd other Effects than ſhe imagin'd: The <hi>Boyar</hi> believ'd, that after what he had done for her, and theſe Expreſſions of her Friendſhip and Acknowledgments, he might venture to do any thing, even to take the Crown; the thing appear'd to him very eaſy and feaſible, he ſaw that the Maſſacres he had caus'd to be committed of all the moſt Conſiderable Noblemen, who had Intereſt and Power, and conſequently might have ſtood in his way, were approv'd, nay that he was thank'd for his pains; he concluded, not
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:29503:17"/>
without reaſon, that the Militia were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely at his devotion, after having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulg'd them in their Plundering; he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded himſelf that not a man of them but wou'd blindly undertake any thing he ſhou'd put them upon, ſome out of gratitude, and others in hopes of gain, and of making their Fortunes in a Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution: Moreover he had inſinuated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them a great contempt of the <hi>Czars;</hi> of <hi>John</hi> upon the account of his Infirmities and Incapacity, and of <hi>Peter</hi> for his want of Years, and that it was to be expected in all likelihood he would be ſubject to the ſame Diſtemper his Brother had, and ſo there was no hopes of ſeeing a Prince upon the Throne that wou'd value Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Merit, and know how to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence them: In fine, he determin'd to puſh his Fortune, but he conſider'd, that to accompliſh his Ends with greater decency, 'twas expedient for him to make an Alliance with the <hi>Czarian</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, which wou'd better diſguiſe his Deſigns, and give ſome colour to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of them, when he ſhou'd attempt it. He propos'd then a Marriage between his Son and the Princeſs <hi>Catherine,</hi> younger Siſter to the Princeſs <hi>Sophia;</hi> but his boldneſs had not that ſucceſs he
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29503:18"/>
expected, the Court was diſpleas'd at the inſolence of the Offer, and reflecting that ſuch an Alliance cou'd not but be preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to the ſafety of the young <hi>Czars,</hi> the Princeſs <hi>Sophia</hi> her ſelf found a way to prevent an Inconvenience ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to the Empire of the <hi>Ruſſians;</hi> judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wiſely that her Authority was in greater hazard from the Ambition of <hi>Couvanski,</hi> than from all thoſe whom ſhe had caus'd to be murder'd, and was firſt perſuaded that he ought to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatch'd and puniſh'd for all thoſe Crimes, the greateſt part of which ſhe had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to. 'Tis a Cuſtom in <hi>Muſcovy</hi> to celebrate the Birth-days of the Royal Family with great ſolemnity; the Prince or Princeſs, whoſe Birth-day it is, makes a Feaſt, and receives the Compliments of the Nobility; the Court reſolv'd to celebrate in <hi>Trinity Convent</hi> the Feaſt of St. <hi>Catherine,</hi> whoſe name that Princeſs bore, which the <hi>Boyar Couvanski</hi> deſign'd for his Son: The Princeſs <hi>Sophia</hi> gave notice of it to all the <hi>Boyars,</hi> and in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular invited <hi>Couvanski,</hi> who continued his Cruelties at <hi>Moſcow,</hi> which the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs ſeemingly approv'd of; mean time 'twas contriv'd how to rid themſelves of this Aſpirer to the Throne, the Prince
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:29503:18"/>
                  <hi>Boyar Bazile Baſilervick Galiſchin,</hi> of whom we ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak further in the Sequel of our Story, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd not to delay the matter; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly there was no time loſt, for he was way-laid by 200 Horſemen in the Road to <hi>Trinity.</hi> Convent, was ſeiz'd and carri'd into a Houſe, where his Sentence was read to him, and both he and his Son beheaded. The <hi>Eſtrels</hi> were aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd when they firſt heard of it, it ſtunn'd 'em like a Clap of Thunder, but they ſoon recover'd out of their Surprize, and grew furious and enrag'd, they ran up and down, and exclaim'd they had loſt their Father, and proteſted ſolemnly and unanimouſly they would take Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance upon his Murtherers and all their Adherents of what Quality ſoever. They poſſeſs'd themſelves inſtantly of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenals and Ammunition, and ſeem'd to threaten a general Deſtruction. The Court perceiving the danger the State was in, rais'd the other Forces, who have ever born an implacable hatred to the <hi>Eſtreles,</hi> and commanded the <hi>German</hi> Officers, who are very numerous among 'em, to render themſelves without delay at <hi>Trinity</hi>-Convent. Every one of 'em obey'd their order, left their Wives and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:29503:19"/>
Children, to ſerve their Prince; nor was any man withheld from his duty, through fear of their Families being ill uſed by the <hi>Eſtreles</hi> for their Loyalty to the <hi>Czars.</hi> At the ſame time they had reaſon to be jealous of them; for the <hi>Germans</hi> dwelt in the Suburbs of <hi>Moſcow,</hi> in that part call'd <hi>Kakouvi,</hi> and the <hi>Eſtreles</hi> really went thither in their firſt Fury, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to butcher all they met with; but they were reſtrain'd by ſome of their old Comrades, who repreſented to 'em very prudently, That if they put to the Sword the <hi>Germans</hi> Wives, their Husbands as ſoon as they had drawn together their Troops, would think of nothing but Revenge: That they would never reſt till they had cut 'em off to the laſt man with an irreconcilable Enmity; and that there was no hopes of Peace or Pardon, after ſo bloody an Action. The <hi>Eſtreles</hi> conſidering on't were perſuaded to ſpare them; and now their hearts ſinking, and ſeeing themſelves without a Leader, they ſought to make their Peace, which they found the Court readily diſpos'd to grant, for in truth they had no great Stomach to new Broils. So the Militia firſt kill'd their Collonels and other Officers, and then ſent Meſſengers to Court to ask Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:29503:19"/>
they obtain'd it without much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, and immediately the <hi>Czars</hi> came to <hi>Moſcow,</hi> accompanied by the Nobility and the <hi>German</hi> Officers. The <hi>Eſtreles</hi> met them, proſtrated themſelves upon the ground, and cried for Mercy: The <hi>Czars</hi> having made a ſign that they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gave them, the Penitent Soldiers rais'd themſelves up, conducted the <hi>Czars</hi> to the Palace, and pour'd out Tears of Joy to ſee their Princes return'd into their Capital City in ſo mild a Diſpoſition.</p>
               <p>The ſame day Prince <hi>Bazile Baſilervick</hi> was created Grand Chancellor, and <hi>Wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimienk,</hi> or Temporary Miniſter of the State, that is, Adminiſtrator of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire during a limited time. This Prince <hi>Galiſchin</hi> is, without diſpute, one of the Ableſt, moſt Ingenious, and Polite Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that ever was in this Country, which he nobly deſign'd ſhould make as good a Figure as the reſt of <hi>Europe.</hi> He ſpeaks <hi>Latin</hi> very correctly, and is migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily pleas'd with the Converſation of Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners, and treats 'em without forcing them to drink to exceſs; he drinks no Brandy himſelf, for he delights in Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe altogether.</p>
               <p>Having little value for the great Lords becauſe of their inſufficiency, he regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29503:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:29503:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:29503:21"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:29503:21"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:29503:22"/>
nothing but merit, and preferr'd none but ſuch as he judg'd worthy, and would be faithful to him.</p>
               <p>This Chancellor began his Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration with an exact Scrutiny after thoſe <hi>Eſtreles</hi> that were culpable, he executed the Ring-Leaders, and baniſh'd others. Four Regiments were form'd of theſe Exils, one was ſent away to <hi>Bialogrod</hi> ſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate upon the Frontiers of <hi>Tartary,</hi> another to <hi>Seberka,</hi> upon the <hi>Wolga</hi> in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Cazan,</hi> the third to <hi>Kourſkay,</hi> in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>krain,</hi> and the fourth to <hi>Sueſka</hi> in the ſame Province. This Affair be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſetled, Prince <hi>Galiſchin</hi> ſeiz'd upon the Offices that were vacant by the Death of thoſe that fell in the Maſſacre, and among others of the <hi>Precaſinoy Zemeske,</hi> or War-Office, in which are kept the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts of the Forces that are upon the Foreign Eſtabliſhment, Foot, Horſe, and Dragoons.</p>
               <p>This Employment had been formerly manag'd by a Boyar Senator of the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaz Bialtouski,</hi> or Office of the White <hi>Roupee,</hi> in which the Affairs of the <hi>Coſaques</hi> and of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>krain,</hi> are commonly deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. The Chancellor pitch'd upon <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickelavitau,</hi> a Wealthy man, and one of the under Secretaries of State, to be
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:29503:22"/>
Supreme Judge over the <hi>Eſtreles,</hi> which is the next Poſt to the <hi>Boyar Senator.</hi> He likewiſe gave to his Couſin German, the <hi>Precaz Caſanskir,</hi> or Office in which the Affairs of <hi>Caſan, Daſtrakan,</hi> and <hi>Circaſſia</hi> are treated. To <hi>Dominiak Emilian Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renxau,</hi> the <hi>Morafeuski Precaz</hi> or Office for the Towns ſituated upon the <hi>Tanais.</hi> The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> or Great Treaſury was conferr'd upon the <hi>Alkalnik Talakorou</hi> of the <hi>Duvoski Precaz;</hi> that is, the Chamber of the Revenues of the Crown. In ſhort all theſe Offices formerly held by the <hi>Boyar Senators,</hi> who were all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to perplex the Chancellor in his undertakings, were fill'd up with Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who would be willing to be his Creatures, and not his Collegues. This procedure drew upon Prince <hi>Galiſchin,</hi> the hatred of all the Noble Families, to ſee themſelves excluded from their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives, and oblig'd to make their Court to him more obſequiouſly than they had done to his Predeceſſors. But this did not hinder him from exerting his Authority, and ordering every thing as he judg'd moſt for his advantage. He advis'd the making of a General Peace with the <hi>Swedes,</hi> whoſe Ambaſſadors being then at <hi>Moſcow,</hi> had all their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:29503:23"/>
granted. Some years after the Concluſion of this Treaty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the <hi>Imperia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts</hi> and <hi>Poles</hi> were engag'd in a War with the <hi>Turks.</hi> The firſt wou'd engage the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> to make a League with them, but their Embaſſy came to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; the <hi>Poles</hi> took this occaſion to propoſe a General Peace, and to get the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> to be on their ſide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which end they ſent an Em<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to <hi>Moſcow,</hi> compos'd of three Lords of the Crown, and three of <hi>Lithuania;</hi> the Palatine of <hi>Poſnania Grzemontarvick,</hi> and the Counts <hi>Ptzyemski</hi> and <hi>Potourski,</hi> were thoſe on the part of the Crown; the Grand Chancellor, his Nephew <hi>Oquenoki,</hi> and Count <hi>Sapiha,</hi> where thoſe for <hi>Lithua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> the laſt was detain'd in <hi>Poland</hi> by the Death of his Brother; but the other five arriv'd ſafe at <hi>Moſcow.</hi> After divers Conferences, and even after their Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of <hi>Congè</hi> they came to an Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation, the <hi>Poles</hi> gave up their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>krain,</hi> or Country of the <hi>Coſſacks,</hi> to the Dutchy of <hi>Smolensko,</hi> and other Territories conquer'd by the <hi>Muſcovites;</hi> and the <hi>Czars</hi> obliged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to make War upon the <hi>Precops,</hi> and oppoſe their Incurſions into <hi>Poland.</hi> This Agreement was ſolemnly ratifi'd,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:29503:23"/>
the Ambaſſadors were treated, and the <hi>Czars</hi> themſelves drank to them by a great Lord, after having laid their hands upon the Cup; an Honour which had never before been conferr'd upon Perſons of their Character.</p>
               <p>Upon this the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> ſent Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors to all the Courts in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> to anim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> them to a General League againſt the <hi>Turks.</hi> The <hi>Boyar Borice Pietreuvick Cheremitau</hi> was ſent to <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and thence to <hi>Vienna:</hi> The <hi>Kenas Jacob Seudrewick Dolgoroka, Eſpalenick</hi> or Gentleman of the <hi>Czars</hi> Bed-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber was ſent into <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain;</hi> he is of the moſt Ancient Family in the Countrey; he mightily admir'd the moſt Chriſtian King, and has declar'd, that tho his Maſter was affronted in <hi>France,</hi> he likes that Court better than that of <hi>Spain,</hi> where the <hi>Czar</hi> was better treated. His Nephew, whom he left in <hi>France</hi> to learn the Language, is the only <hi>Muſcovite</hi> that ſpeaks <hi>French.</hi> There are but Four throughout this vaſt Countrey that can talk <hi>Latin,</hi> and they are beholden for it to their <hi>Poliſh</hi> Tutors. In ſhort, every Prince in <hi>Europe</hi> had an Envoy from the <hi>Czars</hi> upon this occaſion. They prepar'd to take the Field in 1687, and enter the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29503:24"/>
                  <hi>Crim:</hi> The Choice of their General took up ſome time; Prince <hi>Galiſchin</hi> nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſeveral Lords fit for that Command; but he was told on all hands, that ſince he had made up the Peace with <hi>Poland,</hi> he ought to give himſelf the trouble of trying whether the Conqueſt of <hi>Precop</hi> was ſo eaſy as he imagin'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He did all he could to excuſe himſelf fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> this Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy; rightly conjecturing he ſhould find great difficulties, and all the ill ſucceſs would be laid at his door, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his utmoſt Precaution and Prudence. That tho the Army he commanded was formidable for Numbers, yet they were but a multitude of raw undiſciplin'd Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants, with whom he could never under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take any vigorous Action, and come off with Honour. Being a greater Stateſman than Soldier, he foreſaw that his Abſence might do him more Prejudice than the Conqueſt of the <hi>Crim</hi> bring him Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and eſpecially ſeeing he could not raiſe himſelf higher by it, nor have a greater Sway in the Government by commanding the Army: He ſaw beſides, that thoſe who inſiſted moſt upon his ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this Charge, did it only out of the Jealouſy they had of him, and with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to ruin him, under a ſpecious ſhew
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:29503:24"/>
of honouring him with the Title of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neraliſſimo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis true, the Lords that preſs'd it moſt, were thoſe that did not conſent to the Agreement with the <hi>Poles;</hi> beſides, they underſtood very well, how difficult ſuch an Invaſion of the <hi>Crim</hi> would prove, and were glad to remove <hi>Galiſchin</hi> from <hi>Moſcow,</hi> that his too great Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity might be leſſen'd by his Abſence. The Majority voted <hi>Galiſchin</hi> General, to his great diſcontent, and ſo he was bound in Honour to take upon him the Conduct of the Expedition. The Particulars of which take as follows.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Expedition of the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> into the <hi>Crim,</hi> from <hi>1687</hi> to <hi>1689.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter mature Debates in Council, the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> being determin'd to ſend a Numerous Army into the Leſſer <hi>Tartary,</hi> choſe Prince <hi>Galiſchin Woivode; Bolſchoy,</hi> or <hi>Generaliſſimo:</hi> The <hi>Boyar Alexis Simonewich Chein, Woyevode</hi> of <hi>Novogrodiski,</hi> General of the Forces of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:29503:25"/>
                  <hi>Cazan:</hi> The <hi>Domini</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>voranin Irran Georharrich Lerrenteteau Woivode Darta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olski,</hi> General of a ſmall Body of <hi>Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacks,</hi> and other light-arm'd Troops, who always march before the Army, and may properly be call'd the Forlorn Hope. The <hi>Akalnick Levanti Romanorrick Pleuvan, Woivode</hi> of <hi>Serene,</hi> General of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Serene:</hi> And <hi>Kencas,</hi> or Prince <hi>Michael Andrumich Galiſchin, Vaivode</hi> of <hi>Bialogrod,</hi> General of the Forces of <hi>Bia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logrod;</hi> he was Couſin German to the great <hi>Galiſchin;</hi> he had ſo great a Love for Foreigners, that when he ſet out to his Government, he carried with him as many as were willing to accompany him, and among the reſt a <hi>Frenchman,</hi> who taught <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Language.</p>
               <p>All the Forces of the <hi>White Ruſſia</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus provided with Leaders, and the <hi>Coſſacks</hi> with their <hi>Hettman,</hi> 'twas con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted how to raiſe Ammunition and Proviſions for them. All the Subjects of the great Empire of the <hi>Czars</hi> were immediately tax'd at a <hi>Rouble</hi> a Houſe; and the Value of a <hi>Rouble</hi> being Five <hi>French Livres,</hi> we leave the Reader to judge what an immenſe Sum it amount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:29503:25"/>
Prince <hi>Galiſchin</hi> obtain'd ſurther, that his Son ſhould be made his Collegue in the Chancellorſhip; which was a new Mark of the Princeſs's Eſteem for him.</p>
               <p>The General Rendezvouz was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>krain,</hi> in the Countrey of thoſe <hi>Coſſacks</hi> who are independent of the <hi>Hettman,</hi> and are commanded by <hi>Polkowniks</hi> or Collonels. The Forces of <hi>Moſcow</hi> were quarter'd at <hi>Arteek;</hi> thoſe of <hi>Novogrod</hi> at <hi>Auski;</hi> thoſe of <hi>Cazan</hi> at <hi>Rouplauski;</hi> thoſe of <hi>Serene</hi> at <hi>Kraſtena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kouſt;</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Bialogrod,</hi> who were to remain upon the Frontiers, were poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Bialogrod.</hi> The <hi>Hettman</hi> drew to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether his Troops at <hi>Calitch;</hi> and all the Army being order'd to be at their Stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by the firſt of <hi>March,</hi> the Soldiers march'd all the Winter of 1686; and the firſt of <hi>May</hi> they muſter'd, and took the Field 300000 Foot, and 100000 Horſe, and encamp'd beyond the River <hi>Marle:</hi> In a few days they began their March by the way of <hi>Poltaw,</hi> a Town belonging to the <hi>Hettman;</hi> and advanc'd as far as <hi>Scarſin,</hi> upon the River <hi>Avit,</hi> where they made a halt for ſome days, to ſtay for a certain Image of the Virgin, which was reputed to worlk Miracles, by the credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous <hi>Muſcovites.</hi> A Monk aſſur'd the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:29503:26"/>
Generals that he had been bleſſed with a Viſion, in which the Virgin told him, That without her their Attempt upon the <hi>Crim</hi> ſhould be unſucceſsful, and therefore they muſt take her Image with them. The Commanders out of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſance, and the Soldiers out of Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, to which the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted the moſt of any people in the world, tarried here 15 days, and did not ſet forward till they had receiv'd the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous Image with all the Ceremonies requiſite. <hi>June</hi> the 15th, they reach'd <hi>Samare-Rzeka,</hi> which as well as the other Rivers before-mention'd, falls into the <hi>Boriſthenes;</hi> they made Bridges, and the Army paſſed over it with all Expedition. The 20th they left <hi>Samare,</hi> keeping the <hi>Boriſthenes</hi> upon their right, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camp'd next at <hi>Tartarska-Rzeka,</hi> or Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of the <hi>Tartars;</hi> from <hi>Tartarska-Rzeka</hi> they march'd to <hi>Mouſcau-Rzeka;</hi> thence to <hi>Kaminka,</hi> thence to <hi>Kouskiorda,</hi> and thence to <hi>Kerachekeſa;</hi> whence the Army could paſs no further, becauſe of the Drought, which was ſo great, that for 50 Leagues round they were inform'd the Sun had burnt up the Graſs, ſo that there was no ſtirring further for want of Forage. The General greatly ſurpriz'd
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:29503:26"/>
at this News, was forc'd to alter his Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; he chang'd the deſign of ruining the <hi>Cham</hi> with his 500000 men, to a ſpeedy Retreat; and ſo he broke up from <hi>Kerachekeſa,</hi> and came and pitch'd upon the Banks of the <hi>Boriſthenes,</hi> both for the convenience of Foraging where the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had overflow'd, and likewiſe to faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Return: For 'twas reaſonable to ſuppoſe that the <hi>Tartars</hi> would come and fall upon the Army, which indeed was ſtrong enough, but extremely em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baraſs'd with ſo prodigious a Train to carry their Baggage, that I have heard the <hi>German</hi> Officers affirm there were above a Million of Horſes; which ſeems incredible, but yet may be true; for in an Army of 24000 men that the King of <hi>Poland</hi> led to the Black Sea in 1686, there were 45000 Waggons. 'Tis evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, abundance of Men and Horſes muſt needs periſh by the exceſſive Heats, and want of Forage; the Bloody Flux, and want of Victuals fit to be eaten, ſwept away great numbers, and rendred more unfit for Service; for the Soldiers were forc'd to feed upon Salt-fiſh half putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd, to keep <hi>Lent,</hi> which the <hi>Ruſſians</hi> hold in <hi>Auguſt.</hi> Nevertheleſs a Detach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of 30000 men, headed by <hi>Levanti</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:29503:27"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:29503:27"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:29503:28"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:29503:28"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:29503:29"/>
                  <hi>Romanorrick,</hi> Commander of the Forces of <hi>Serene,</hi> was order'd to advance as far as <hi>Zarparogny,</hi> with intent to make the <hi>Tartars</hi> believe that the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> had none of their Army left. The <hi>Hettman Juan Samuelerrick</hi>'s Son was ſent out like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with a Body of <hi>Coſſacks.</hi> The reſt of the Army march'd back to the River <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mare,</hi> where the Prince obſerving the Situation of the Place, projected to build a City there, to bridle the <hi>Coſſacks,</hi> and even the <hi>Tartars,</hi> tho the laſt can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Ruſſia</hi> on ſeveral ſides. The next year this City was actually begun, as ſhall be told in the Sequel. From the River of <hi>Samare</hi> they removed to the River <hi>Marle,</hi> where they waited for Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from <hi>Moſcow</hi> to disband the Army. And in the mean time the Prince, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe himſelf at Court for the ill ſucceſs of his Campaign, left no Stone unturn'd to lay the blame of his Miſcarriage upon the <hi>Hettman Juan Samuelerrich;</hi> and notwithſtanding that he was powerful, and commanded all the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>krain,</hi> which revolted from the <hi>Poles</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> the laſt of that Name, tho he has 100000 of the Militia always ready to take the Field; yet <hi>Galiſchin,</hi> having the Princeſs on his ſide, contriv'd to ruin
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:29503:29"/>
him. He wrote to Court, charg'd the <hi>Hettman</hi> with being the cauſe of all that had happen'd, and ſollicited an Order to depoſe him, and chuſe another into his Place. This Order being come, <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſchin</hi> caus'd the <hi>Hettman</hi> to be ſeiz'd at midnight by thoſe very <hi>Eſtreles</hi> which he had deſired for his Guard, becauſe he miſtruſted the <hi>Coſſacks:</hi> He was carried bound in Cords to a place within the Main Body of the Army, call'd <hi>Chatra,</hi> that is to ſay, the Tent of Juſtice, which in all the <hi>Ruſſian</hi> Armies is conſtantly pitch'd in the General's Quarter: In the Morning <hi>Galiſchin</hi> ſummoned all the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Noblemen to attend him in a Body: The <hi>Boyar</hi> Generals took their Seats, and the <hi>Hettman</hi> was brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them; the Emperor's Order was firſt read to him; then they confronted him with the principal <hi>Coſſacks,</hi> who were taught their Leſſon, and accuſed him of holding Intelligence with the <hi>Cham,</hi> and directing him privately to burn up the Forage. The poor General found his Fortune quickly chang'd; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>Vielmozny,</hi> or Moſt Puiſſant, they ſaluted him with <hi>Scourwecin,</hi> or Son of a Whore; nay, his own Servants loſt all Reſpect to him, and one of his Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:29503:30"/>
named <hi>Dimitrouki,</hi> drew out his Sabre to kill him; but <hi>Galiſchin</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented the Blow, and told him, the <hi>Hettman</hi> was there to be Tried Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, and not to be Butchered. This Council of War being broke up, and the <hi>Hettman</hi> put under a ſure Guard, a Courier was diſpatch'd to <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanti Romanorrick</hi> with Orders for him to ſecure the <hi>Hettman</hi>'s Son, who was detach'd at the ſame time with <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norrick;</hi> but ſome faithful <hi>Coſſacks</hi> were got thither before him, and warn'd him to ſave himſelf. Romanorrick could not eaſily come at him, for he kept with his Troops perpetually as far off as he could; but the principal <hi>Coſſacks</hi> being acquainted with the Order to ſeize their Leader, the <hi>Compachiks,</hi> or the Cavalry, agreed to deliver him up; the <hi>Sardou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiks</hi> or Infantry encompaſs'd his Tent, and would not permit him to be taken; but at length they ſuffer'd themſelves to be prevail'd upon, and ſo with a general Conſent the <hi>Hettman</hi>'s Son was put into <hi>Romanorrick</hi>'s Hands, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proud of his Prey, and over-joy'd that he had now an opportunity of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing his Credit, which he had loſt in a Skirmiſh with <hi>Sultan Naradin,</hi> near
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:29503:30"/>
                  <hi>Kamiſton</hi> upon the <hi>Nieper,</hi> return'd with his Priſoner to the Army.</p>
               <p>While they were ſeizing the Son, the <hi>Boyar</hi> Generals conſulted how to puniſh the Father, and ſet up another <hi>Hett<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Samuelerrich</hi> was ſent into <hi>Ziberia,</hi> and the <hi>Coſſacks</hi> choſe one <hi>Mazepa, Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtazy</hi> or Secretary of State, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim'd him <hi>Hettman.</hi> This Prince is not comely in his Perſon, but a very knowing Man, and ſpeaks <hi>Latin</hi> in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. He is a <hi>Coſſack</hi> born, and was one of King <hi>Cazimir</hi>'s Pages, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards an Officer in his Guards. He is a very good Friend to the <hi>Poles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus Prince <hi>Galiſchin</hi> ſucceeded in his Deſign; but a great Party of <hi>Coſſacks,</hi> who were not call'd to the Election, expreſs'd their diſlike of it; ſome Towns revolted, and ſome of the Colonel's Houſes were pillag'd in their abſence: The new <hi>Hettman</hi> being minded to quell theſe Diſorders, deſir'd ſome Troops of <hi>Galiſchin,</hi> who gave him three thouſand Foot of the Forces of <hi>Smolensko,</hi> and a thouſand Horſe to attend him to <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turin,</hi> where the <hi>Hettmans</hi> uſually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide.</p>
               <p>The Order to disband the Army ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd ſoon after with a Letter from their
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:29503:31"/>
Czariſh Majeſties, which was read in the preſence of all the Officers, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well pleas'd they were to hear them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves thank'd for their good Services. Every General had a Golden Medal gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, having the two Emperors Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figies on one ſide, and the Princeſs's on the other, faſten'd to a Chain of Gold, the whole worth ten Ducats; every Colonel had a Medal without a Chain, worth a Ducat; each Lieutenant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel and Major, one of half a Ducat; and every Soldier and <hi>Eſtrelle</hi> had a Copique of Gold, of about twenty five Pence in value, a Silver Copique is worth no more than one. Prince <hi>Galiſchin</hi> by means of theſe Preſents, which he obtain'd of the <hi>Czars,</hi> or rather of the Princeſs, to be given to the Army, appeas'd the Murmurs that were rais'd through the Army againſt him. He likewiſe gain'd the Chief Noblemen by beſtowing Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments upon them that reimburs'd their Expences; inſomuch that at his arrival at <hi>Moſcow</hi> he found no body a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; he was receiv'd by the Princeſs with all the Marks of Favour he could wiſh, and took the Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the State upon him with as much Authority as ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:29503:31"/>
The firſt thing that <hi>Galiſchin</hi> propos'd to the Council, was the Advantages that would ariſe from building a City upon the River <hi>Samare,</hi> in which might be ſtor'd up Ammunitions of all ſorts: The matter being approv'd, the <hi>Akalnik Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanti Romanorrick</hi> was ordered to put himſelf at the Head of 30000 Men, and go and build the City. The <hi>Hettman</hi> with his Troops had the ſame Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and the place being mark'd out by a <hi>Dutch</hi> Colonel and Ingineer, nam'd <hi>Wauſale,</hi> theſe Forces met at <hi>Niski,</hi> and march'd to <hi>Samare</hi> by the laſt day of <hi>May.</hi> In a Months time the City was finiſh'd, for 'twas little better than an Entrenchment to ſtop the Incurſions of the <hi>Tartars</hi> and <hi>Coſſacks,</hi> and nam'd <hi>Nowobogrodilla,</hi> or Town of our Lady the Widow: A Gariſon was left in it, and the reſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd; the <hi>Akalnik,</hi> as a reward for his good Services was made a <hi>Boyar;</hi> and 'twas found by experience in the Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign of 1689. that this City was of great uſe in ſupplying the Army with all Neceſſaries out of its Magazines.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:29503:32"/>
               <head>The Expedition of the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> into the <hi>Crim,</hi> in <hi>1689.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>PRince <hi>Galiſchin</hi> perceiving that the <hi>Czar Peter</hi>'s Party grew ſtronger every day, and fearing their Power would encreaſe in his Abſence, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd underhand by all means to get the Command of the Army given to ſomebody elſe this Campaign; but find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it very difficult to compaſs his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, he frankly offer'd himſelf, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rightly that 'twas more honourable for him to propoſe it voluntarily, than ſtay to ſee himſelf compell'd to accept of it; and he took ſuch meaſures as he thought proper to make this Campaign more proſperous than the firſt; for this Prince was a better Politician than a Captain, and having eaſily obtain'd what he thought fit to demand, 'twas reſolv'd the Army ſhould take the Field ſooner than they did in the former Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign; the ill Succeſs of which was owing to the ſlowneſs of their Motions; wherefore all the Forces were appointed to be at the Rendezvous on the firſt of <hi>February.</hi> Which Order was punctually
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:29503:32"/>
obſerved; the Troops began to march from all Parts in <hi>December,</hi> except thoſe of <hi>Ziberia,</hi> who becauſe of the War which they maintain againſt the Inhabitants of <hi>Great Tartary,</hi> their Neighbours, are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd from ſending any Soldiers. The Preparations were more formidable than thoſe of the preceding Campaign. But the People were not tax'd higher than before, for they paid but one Rouble <hi>per</hi> Houſe. The Forces of <hi>Moſcow</hi> had their Quarters at <hi>Sont;</hi> thoſe of <hi>Novo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grod</hi> at <hi>Riski;</hi> thoſe of <hi>Cazan</hi> at <hi>Bago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douka;</hi> thoſe of <hi>Bialogrod</hi> at <hi>Kamminski;</hi> thoſe of <hi>Serene</hi> at <hi>Kalentar;</hi> all which Armies were commanded by the ſame Lords that ſerv'd in the firſt Expediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, except that of <hi>Bialogrod,</hi> which was given to <hi>Borice Pitrowick Cherimetau,</hi> upon the Death of <hi>Michael Andrewich Galiſchin;</hi> they did not lie long in their Quarters, for the General order'd all to march before the Froſt was broke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the River <hi>Marle,</hi> which was pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently order'd, becauſe ſeveral Rivers that were to be croſs'd in that March, make great Inundations when the Thaw comes. The Foot were encamp'd on the other ſide of the River at the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of a Wood; the Cavalry was
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:29503:33"/>
poſted in the Towns that are ſituated on the Banks. After he had ſtaid for the Thaw, the Prince arriv'd and pitch'd his Tent on the further ſide of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, <hi>April</hi> the 1ſt; the Generals did ſo likewiſe; and on the 6th they march'd towards the <hi>Samare,</hi> where all the Forces joyn'd.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Hettman Mezepa</hi> came thither likewiſe; on the 13th they all paſs'd the River without delay, and advanc'd as far as <hi>Precop</hi> in a Month's time: The Baggage hinder'd 'em from making long Marches in a day, every Soldier carri'd with him Proviſion for four Months, beſides what was diſtributed to them at <hi>Samare,</hi> and in the Deſarts which they paſs'd through; ſuch a quantity of Proviſion ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much encumber'd 'em in their March; the Artillery conſiſting of 700 pieces of Cannon, and many Mortars, help'd to delay them the more; at length they arriv'd at <hi>Keratchekeſa,</hi> and there en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camp'd. The Horſes were put to graze, for the Graſs was too ſhort to be mow'd, and the Troops repos'd themſelves till Midnight, at which time they were alarm'd by a great Noiſe without the Camp, which the Neighing of Horſes, and the Cries of Men, made very terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:29503:33"/>
They believ'd they were ſurpriz'd by the <hi>Tartars;</hi> but 'twas diſcover'd that ſome Horſes which had broke looſe, and ran up and down, had caus'd this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order; next day they found that 6000 belonging to the Army of <hi>Moſcow</hi> were run away into the Deſart, though their Legs had been tied; whereupon they were oblig'd to halt to give every Man time to look for his Horſe, and moſt of them were brought back to the Camp. Next day they decamp'd, and after ſome days arriv'd at <hi>Kairka</hi> upon the <hi>Bori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthenes,</hi> where a Party took ſome <hi>Muſcovite Tartars,</hi> of whom they learn'd that the <hi>Cham</hi> was not at <hi>Precop,</hi> but at <hi>Budziac,</hi> and that they had not the leaſt Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of ſo formidable an Army coming upon them; that indeed they had heard the Troops were upon the March, but thought 'twas only to Build ſome Place as they had done laſt Year, and that they themſelves were ſent by <hi>Sultan Kalga,</hi> to get Intelligence of the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> deſigns. From <hi>Kairka</hi> they march'd to <hi>Kairka Meſchenſa,</hi> where Prince <hi>Galiſchin</hi> order'd every Waggon to carry ſome Faſcines, Paliſades, and ſome Water, becauſe there was no Wood any further. From thence they left the <hi>Boriſthenes,</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:29503:34"/>
and march'd towards <hi>Precop,</hi> and the Army was two days without Water. <hi>May</hi> the 13th, they had word brought by their Scouts that the Enemy was at hand; they put themſelves in Order to receive them; the Baggage guarded by the Foot, and Artillery march'd on the right, the Horſe were poſted on the left of every Diviſion. The Forces of <hi>Moſcow</hi> headed by Prince <hi>Galiſchin</hi> kept in the middle, the Forces of <hi>Novogrod</hi> mov'd on the right, the <hi>Hettman</hi> on the left; on the <hi>Hettman</hi>'s left was <hi>Cherre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitau</hi> and <hi>Dolga Kourka;</hi> and <hi>Romanor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> made up the Rear. The <hi>Tartars</hi> charg'd the Vanguard of <hi>Schein,</hi> from thence, after ſome Skirmiſhes they wheel'd on a ſudden from right to left, and fell upon <hi>Cherremitau</hi>'s Forces, who being over-power'd, were quickly put to the rout: The Horſe took to their Heels, the Enemy ran to the Baggage, which had like to have been carried off; but Prince <hi>Galiſchin</hi> preſently ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Succours to <hi>Cherremitau,</hi> the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> were forc'd to retire, and leave the <hi>Ruſſians</hi> a free paſſage till they got to <hi>Thorna d'Oliva,</hi> where they encamp'd for the convenience of Water, the place being Marſhy, and five Leagues diſtant
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:29503:34"/>
from <hi>Precop.</hi> A ſmall Body of <hi>Tartars,</hi> under <hi>Sultan Garka,</hi> advanced to diſcover their Enemies march; and being deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to know wherein the Weakneſs and Strength of the Army lay, took ſeveral Priſoners, from whom they drew ſuch Information as they wanted. Then they carried them to the <hi>Cham,</hi> who lay but three Leagues off encamp'd at <hi>Kalan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techek,</hi> a little River two Leagues from <hi>Precop,</hi> which riſing in the Deſart, runs into the <hi>Palus Meotides,</hi> or <hi>Black-Sea.</hi> For the <hi>Cham</hi> hearing the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> had invaded the <hi>Crim,</hi> was come from <hi>Budziac</hi> with 4000 Horſe to defend his Territories; he got to <hi>Katanſchek</hi> two days before the <hi>Muſcovites,</hi> and paſs'd the <hi>Boriſthenes</hi> at <hi>Aſſenan Kirman,</hi> a Town ſeated on that River belonging to the <hi>Turks.</hi> The 16th the Army de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camp'd and mov'd to <hi>Zelona Dolina,</hi> a League from <hi>Tharn;</hi> here the <hi>Cham</hi> came to meet the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> with all his Forces, which by what we are able to conjecture, might amount to thirty or forty thouſand Horſe, marching in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral little Diviſions. The <hi>Ruſſians</hi> found themſelves inſenſibly ſurrounded by the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and were oblig'd to halt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:29503:35"/>
They ſtar'd upon one another, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out attempting any thing, though one would have thought the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> ſhould have begun the fight, but they were glad to keep themſelves out of harm, fenc'd in with ſtrong Paliſades, which were brought in the Waggons. The Foot and Artillery defended the Camp ſo ſtrenuouſly, that the <hi>Tartars</hi> could not break into it. The Horſe were not entrench'd, which invited three or four Detachments of <hi>Tartars,</hi> of 1000 Horſe each, to Charge them; they were no ſooner attack'd but they fell into diſorder, and the Baggage was very ſerviceable to them, for from thence the Cannon and ſmall Shot gall'd the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and laid three or four hundred of them upon the Ground, and with them ſeveral of the <hi>Muſcovites.</hi> Mean time, on the other ſide, Sultan <hi>Naradin</hi> with his Troops charg'd the <hi>Coſſacks</hi> of <hi>Sont</hi> and <hi>Akrerko,</hi> who were commanded by <hi>Emilian, Everecunau Dominidiak,</hi> or Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary of State; he knew little what belong'd to War, and like a true <hi>Muſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite,</hi> was ſo frighted, that he could not ſtand before the <hi>Tartars,</hi> who broke in among the Baggage, and killing the Horſes, prevented the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> from
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:29503:35"/>
drawing off their Waggons; the Enemy pierc'd as far as the Center of thoſe Waggons, and carried off twenty Pieces of Cannon, which they found mounted upon Carriages, and Horſes harneſs'd to them. In ſhort, if the <hi>Boyar Rouka</hi> had not advanc'd with his Troops, the <hi>Coſſacks</hi> had been entirely cut off. <hi>Cher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remitau</hi> was attack'd at the ſame time by another Body of <hi>Tartars,</hi> who broke in as far as his Baggage, but it muſt be own'd he defended himſelf much better than <hi>Emilian,</hi> and forc'd the <hi>Tartars</hi> to retire. He behav'd himſelf very hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely on this occaſion, having a ſtock of perſonal Courage, and being a Man of Merit, but a mortal Enemy to <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſchin,</hi> who would gladly have been rid of him, and he had certainly been loſt, but that he was ſeaſonably ſuccour'd. In theſe Skirmiſhes the <hi>Tartars</hi> being repuls'd, though the Advantage and ſome Plunder fell to them, the <hi>Muſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites</hi> mov'd forwards to get to ſome freſh Water; ſo the next day they march'd to <hi>Kalentchek,</hi> and foraſmuch as they had found it inconvenient for the Cavalry to keep at a diſtance from the Baggage, they were order'd to min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle with the Waggons and Carriages,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:29503:36"/>
and all the Army, which till then had been divided, joyn'd into one Body with 200000 Waggons, and made a ſquare Figure, the Baggage as we ſaid before was ſurrounded with the Cannon and Infantry, who carried their Palliſades upon their Shoulders to be the readier in planting them. As they march'd in this order, the <hi>Tartars</hi> appear'd again, and having view'd the Army on all ſides, and found the Horſe had ſecured themſelves, they forbore Action, and were content to keep the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> in fear of them; but they ſoon withdrew, and went to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend <hi>Precop,</hi> which they thought would be attempted by the numerous Army of the <hi>Muſcovites.</hi> The ſame day the laſt encamped at <hi>Kalanſehck,</hi> and next day paſs'd the River, and ſaw no <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars,</hi> which encourag'd ſeveral <hi>Muſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites</hi> to leave the Baggage, and aſcend the Hills to diſcover <hi>Precop,</hi> which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd in Flames; for the <hi>Tartars</hi> had ſet Fire to the Suburbs leſt the <hi>Muſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites</hi> ſhould have poſſeſs'd themſelves thereof. The 16th they march'd ſtrait on to <hi>Prerop,</hi> and ſat down within Cannon-ſhot of the Town, having the <hi>Black-Sea</hi> on their right, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart on the left: They made no Shot
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:29503:36"/>
from the Town, becauſe 'twas too far to do Execution, but they fir'd inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly from a Tower that ſtands on the Shore of the <hi>Black-Sea.</hi> 'Twas about Ten or Eleven a Clock when the <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covites</hi> arriv'd here, and they thought of attacking <hi>Precop</hi> in the Night; but in the Evening, when the Officers came for Orders, they wonder'd to hear that they were to return next day. This re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat being ſomewhat extraordinary, 'tis worth while to give the Cauſes of it. The Army being encamp'd pretty nèar the Town, the <hi>Nogays</hi> and <hi>Kalmouchs Tartars,</hi> Subjects to the <hi>Muſcovites,</hi> skirmiſhing often with the <hi>Precopians,</hi> a <hi>Nogay,</hi> who ſerv'd the <hi>Cham,</hi> ſaw by chance a <hi>Muſcovite</hi> of his Acquaintance, and call'd out to him: What do we contend for, ſaid he? What occaſion is there for us to fight together? Why don't you adviſe your <hi>Boyar</hi> to make Peace with our <hi>Cham?</hi> The <hi>Muſcovite</hi> replied, That if the <hi>Boyar</hi> believ'd the <hi>Cham</hi> was that way inclin'd, he might be diſpos'd to it likewiſe; but if the <hi>Cham</hi> had an earneſt. deſire for Peace, he ſhould ſend and treat about it. Very well, ſays the <hi>Precopian Nogay,</hi> do you break it to your <hi>Boyar</hi> or General, and aſſure him
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:29503:37"/>
the <hi>Cham</hi> is willing to come to terms. The <hi>Muſcovite Nogay</hi> goes preſently to <hi>Galiſchin,</hi> and acquaints him with what the <hi>Tartar</hi> had ſaid, and found the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral lik'd the motion, and was very ready to return without coming to blows. Accordingly <hi>Galiſchin</hi> caus'd a Letter to be written in the Name of this <hi>Muſcovite</hi> to the <hi>Tartar Nogay,</hi> to this purpoſe, <hi>I have related to the</hi> Boyar Galiſchin <hi>what paſs'd between us; he is content to come to an Accommodation; it lies upon you to get ſome Perſon to be ſent to him with the</hi> Cham<hi>'s Propoſals.</hi> This Letter being deliver'd to the firſt <hi>Tartar</hi> that appear'd, was carri'd to the <hi>Cham,</hi> who was conſulting with his <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaz</hi> how to rid himſelf of ſo formidable an Enemy. The <hi>Cham</hi> having read it, ſent to ask <hi>Galiſchin,</hi> whether 'twas writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by his order; and being anſwer'd, Yes; he ſent <hi>Suilech Murza;</hi> and the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> a Lord, nam'd <hi>Eſmeyan,</hi> in exchange for Hoſtages. The Treaty was ſet on foot. The <hi>Muſcovites</hi> propos'd the five following Conditions: That all the <hi>Ruſſian</hi> Slaves ſhould be reſtored. That the <hi>Tartars</hi> ſhould make no more Inroads into the <hi>Czar</hi>'s Dominions. That they ſhould quit their Claim to 80000
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:29503:37"/>
Crowns, annually due to them from the <hi>Muſcovites;</hi> That they ſhould not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt the <hi>Poles,</hi> nor aſſiſt the <hi>Turks.</hi> The <hi>Murza</hi> gave ſome hopes of an agreement, and ſpun out the Conference to keep 'em in ſuſpence till next day, well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo great a multitude could not long ſubſiſt there without Forage and Water: but the next day he anſwer'd, That the <hi>Cham</hi> would accept of a Peace upon no other Terms than thoſe he was already engag'd in with the <hi>Czar:</hi> That he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted upon the Payment of the yearly Tribute, and expected to be paid 240000 Crowns in Arrears for the three laſt Years. Prince <hi>Galiſchin</hi> did not at all like this Anſwer; and judging it very incommodious to lie longer encamp'd upon the Sandy Plain, reſolv'd to retreat. For fear of being purſu'd, he took the <hi>Murza</hi> along with him as far as <hi>Kalant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zek;</hi> and from thence ſent him back, and receiv'd his own Hoſtage. This is a ſhort Account of all this Campaign in the <hi>Crim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this they march'd for three weeks together to reach <hi>Samare;</hi> where leaving all the heavy Luggage behind them, they paſs'd the River, and in ſix days more got to the River <hi>Marle.</hi> But
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:29503:38"/>
in the mean time Prince <hi>Galiſchin</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch'd Couriers to the <hi>Czars,</hi> and to the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> boaſting that he had beaten the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and driven them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their own Country. The Princeſs upon this News order'd publick Rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings throughout the Kingdom, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Cuſtom ſent an <hi>Akalnik</hi> with a Letter of Thanks and Commendations to all the Army, and Golden Ducats for Rewards: In concluſion, Orders for Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding the Army being come, the <hi>Boyar Valenski</hi> was left at the River <hi>Samare</hi> with about 5 or 6000 Men. This mighty Succeſs had the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> in their two great Expeditions into the <hi>Crim;</hi> which far from gaining them any honour or profit, on the contrary produc'd the greateſt damage the Nation could ever ſuffer, in the Ruine of their General, which happen'd ſoon after his Return. I learn'd all that I have related, from the King of <hi>Poland</hi>'s Miniſters, who have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſided at the <hi>Czars</hi> Court, and follow'd the Armies ever ſince the Death of the <hi>Czar Theodore,</hi> to this preſent. I ſhall next give the Particulars of the Troubles that I was an eye-witneſs of, having of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ventur'd in diſguiſe to go about the City, and even to <hi>Trinity-Convent.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:29503:38"/>
               <head>A Relation of the Troubles in <hi>Moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cow,</hi> occaſion'd by the Princeſs <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia,</hi> upon her Brother <hi>Peter</hi>'s be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made <hi>Czar.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>PRince <hi>Galiſchin,</hi> at his Return to <hi>Moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cow,</hi> found Affairs in quite another poſture than he expected; his Enemies had inform'd themſelves of the truth of the matter, and render'd him odious to the <hi>Czar Peter.</hi> He was refus'd Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and hardly, through the interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Prnceſs, cou'd he be admitted to kiſs the <hi>Czar</hi>'s Hand; he underwent bitter Reproaches, and could not ſay any thing that would paſs as a juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Conduct. For ſome days <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſchin</hi> was left at Quiet, but the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs's Liberality gave occaſion to new Commotions. She had a mind to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute among the <hi>Boyars</hi> conſiderable Preſents in recompence of the good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice they had done to the Empire; but the <hi>Czar</hi> oppos'd it, and would enquire firſt into the Merits of their Services, that their Rewards might be proportionable. The Princeſs would bear no reſtraint, but found means to bring the <hi>Czar</hi> to a
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:29503:39"/>
compliance with her Deſires. She gave then to Prince <hi>Galiſchin</hi> 1500 Peaſants Houſes, in ſeveral Villages; to other Commanders in the Army, 300; to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Officers, in proportion to their Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and likewiſe to all the Gentlemen that ſerved in the Expedition, deſigning to make 'em all of her own Party. Such Gifts had never before been us'd to be beſtow'd in <hi>Muſcovy;</hi> the <hi>Czar</hi> always gave a Royal Veſt to thoſe they would honour, but no more.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Galiſchin</hi> govern'd with his uſual Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; and being aided by the Princeſs, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook a bold attempt. Ever ſince the <hi>Hettmans</hi> were under the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, they never enter'd <hi>Moſcow. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſchin,</hi> under pretence of doing the <hi>Hett<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> the honour of preſenting him to do homage to the <hi>Czar;</hi> but having ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end in't, ſo order'd it, that <hi>Mazepa</hi> came to <hi>Moſcow</hi> with 500 of his chief Officers, but could not be admitted to ſee the <hi>Czar.</hi> I went to him ſeveral times diſguis'd in the night-time, accompany'd by a <hi>German</hi> Phyſician of the <hi>Czar</hi>'s who aſſur'd him of the King of <hi>Poland</hi>'s Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection. The <hi>Czar Peter</hi> was then at one of his Country-Houſes, call'd <hi>Obro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gensko,</hi> ſituate upon the River <hi>Yarus,</hi> a
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:29503:39"/>
ſhort League from <hi>Moſcow,</hi> whilſt the Princeſs <hi>Sophia</hi> and <hi>Galiſchin</hi> laid a Plot, which we are going to give an account of. The Princeſs foreſaw all along that the <hi>Czar Peter</hi>'s Life wou'd one day be the ruin of her Authority, and a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous obſtacle to her Ambition, in caſe ſhe did not remove it in time; and now ſhe repented that ſhe had follow'd the wiſe and moderate Counſels of <hi>Galiſchin;</hi> ſhe reflected on the difficulty ſhe met with in procuring him a diſgraceful Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; was concern'd at it, and the Reproaches that were made him; and though ſhe had gain'd her Point in get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>Czar</hi> to conſent ſhe ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow her Bounty as ſhe pleas'd; yet ſhe could not forget how dear it coſt her, and what Oppoſitions ſhe ſtruggled with. All this ſhe reſented the more deeply, becauſe ſhe had rul'd the State without controul, according to her fancy, for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral years; ſhe judg'd rightly, that for the future ſhe ſhould not be ſo Abſolute; and that the beſt ſhe cou'd expect, was to have her Authority leſſen'd, as her Brother's encreas'd, and gueſs'd 'twas upon that account he did not directly deny her; but that in proceſs of time, inſtead of conferring Favours upon her,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:29503:40"/>
they would take pleaſure in croſſing her Deſires, which her Brother's Party would ever be ready to do, and to deſtroy her Creatures; and after all theſe Vexations, ſhe ſhould be oblig'd to quit the Court, and retire into her Convent.</p>
               <p>Theſe Conſiderations made this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, who is Ambitious and Daring above her Sex, reſolve to venture all to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain her ſelf in the Poſt ſhe was in. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her Regency, ſhe had done what ſhe could to engage all to be her Creatures, and 'twas with the ſame deſign that ſhe beſtow'd thoſe Preſents on the Army, though under colour of rewarding their Services; for ſhe thought they would think themſelves more oblig'd to her upon the ſcore of ſuch valuable Gifts, than they could have been to the <hi>Czar</hi> for a Veſt, with which his Predeceſſors us'd to gratify 'em. She aſſur'd Prince <hi>Galiſchin</hi> he ought to apprehend that their Enemies would not be ſatisfied with diminiſhing her Power by degrees, but would proceed further, and force her to return to her Convent; which could not be effected without involving Himſelf, his Family and Friends, in her Fall.—He was prevail'd upon by theſe Reaſons; and though he was prudent and diſcreet,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:29503:40"/>
and naturally averſe to all violent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, he no longer oppos'd her deſign; he deſir'd only, before ſhe put it in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, that he might ſend his eldeſt Son into <hi>Poland</hi> upon a feign'd Embaſſy, with the greateſt part of his Riches, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he might ſhelter himſelf from the ſtorm which he ſaw coming upon him, and knew not what would be the iſſue of it. But the impatient Princeſs over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rul'd him; ſhe repreſented to him, that they were not to loſe a minute; that his precaution was needleſs, being they were certain of ſucceſs. After ſhe had taken ſuch meaſures as ſhe had long before concluded upon, ſhe determin'd at laſt to give the Blow; and pitch'd upon <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore Thekelavitau</hi> for the purpoſe; he was Preſident of the Chamber of <hi>Eſtreles,</hi> and was rais'd by the Princeſs from a mean Scrivener to be an <hi>Akalnik</hi> or Sword-bearer, a Dignity next to that of <hi>Boyar</hi> Senator. This <hi>Theodore</hi> promis'd to execute the Princeſs's Order punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally. He drew together at the Caſtle of the <hi>Crim,</hi> where the <hi>Czar</hi> and the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch uſually reſide, and in which all the Courts of Judicature are held, 600 <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreles,</hi> all truſty Fellows, Commanded by Collonel <hi>Rojannau; Theodore</hi> put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:29503:41"/>
at the head of them, and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to follow him to <hi>Obrogensko;</hi> but whilſt he was giving out his Orders, two of his <hi>Eſtreles,</hi> whoſe hearts miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gave them, reſolv'd not to ſtain their hands with their Prince's Blood; and ſtealing off, they ran and gave notice to the <hi>Czar Peter,</hi> who in a dreadful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternation leap'd out of bed, ſent for his Uncles, his Mother's Brothers, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted in all haſte what was to be done. 'Twas reſolv'd to ſend to the City to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into the certainty of the matter; one of the <hi>Czar</hi>'s Uncles, and Prince <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice,</hi> were diſpatch'd upon this Errand, who in their way met <hi>Thekelavitau</hi> at the head of his <hi>Eſtreles;</hi> they hid them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves whilſt they paſs'd by them, and then haſten'd back to ſave the <hi>Czar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Peter</hi> had but juſt time enough to get into his Coach with his Mother, his Wife, and her Siſter, and follow'd by ſome faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Servants, he fled towards <hi>Trinity-Convent.</hi> The Conſpirators being arriv'd, ſearch'd all about for the <hi>Czar;</hi> but the <hi>Eſtreles</hi> of the Prince's Guard knowing nothing of the matter, and amaz'd at his ſudden flight, told their Preſident or Judge that his Majeſty was gone with all the ſpeed he could.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:29503:41"/>
                  <hi>Thekelavitau</hi> having miſs'd his aim, next day return'd to the Princeſs, whom he found no leſs concern'd than himſelf at their diſappointment. Every body in <hi>Moſcow</hi> was aſtoniſh'd at the News of this flight, for none could divine what ſhould be the Cauſe of it; but towards Evening 'twas known that the <hi>Czar Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> had ſent to the Princeſs to reproach her with her Treachery, and that ſhe denied the matter abſolutely, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted they had been deceived in taking thoſe for Conſpirators who came only to relieve the Guard, and that they wrong'd her extreamly in thinking ſhe could harbour ſo black a deſign as to kill her Brother. This Excuſe of Relieving the Guards appear'd a weak one to moſt people, for they uſually reliev'd them in the day-time, and theſe <hi>Eſtreles</hi> came to <hi>Obrogensko</hi> at night. But be that as it will, the <hi>Czar Peter</hi> being got ſafe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Trinity-Convent,</hi> wrote to all the <hi>Boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars</hi> to render themſelves there without delay; he wrote alſo to all the Gentry, and ſent Orders to all the Towns to raiſe the <hi>Militia;</hi> and having publiſh'd through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Empire <hi>Thekelavitau</hi>'s Attempt, they came in to him from all Parts, and in leſs than eight days he had a nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:29503:42"/>
Body of the Gentry about him; immediately he ſent Orders to <hi>Galiſchin</hi> to attend him at <hi>Trinity-Convent,</hi> but he excus'd himſelf upon pretence of being withheld by the <hi>Czar John.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mean time the Princeſs did all ſhe could to get the <hi>Eſtreles</hi> on her ſide; ſhe call'd together all the <hi>Pieceſtniks</hi> and <hi>Dieceſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi> Subaltern-Officers, who on ſuch occaſions can prevail more with the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diery than their Colonels; and having order'd them to be planted at the foot of the Stairs, the <hi>Czar John</hi> and ſhe coming from Maſs, ſtood at the top of the Stairs; whence the <hi>Czar</hi> ſpoke to them to this purpoſe: <hi>My Brother is retir'd into</hi> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity-Convent, <hi>I know not for what reaſon; doubtleſs he deſigns to diſturb the Peace of the State, and, as I am told, has command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you to attend him; but we forbid you upon pain of Death to obey his Order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Princeſs reiterated this Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but the <hi>Eſtreles</hi> little heeded it: They march'd to <hi>Trinity,</hi> and aſſur'd the <hi>Czar Peter</hi> of their Fidelity; which the Princeſs having conſider'd, and that moſt of the <hi>Boyars</hi> had joyn'd with <hi>Peter,</hi> ſhe reſolv'd to make her Peace with him; to which end ſhe ſent to her Brother two of his Aunts, his Father's Siſters,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:29503:42"/>
the Princeſs <hi>Ann Michaelwa,</hi> and one of her Siſters <hi>Marfa Aleyewa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before we proceed further, 'tis fit the <hi>Reader</hi> ſhould be told, That the Regen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Princeſs had encourag'd ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Princeſſes of the <hi>Czarian</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily to leave their Convents, and come to the Imperial Palace, where ſhe her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelf reſided, which ſhe tolerated during her Regency, for fear the Reaſons and Cuſtom which ſhe could alledge for their Confinement, ſhould be laid to her Charge; and leaſt thoſe who envied her, and were tir'd with her Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, ſhould make uſe of them to oblige her to return to her Monaſtry. Beſides theſe three already nam'd, <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine Sophia, Maria,</hi> and <hi>Sediaſſa,</hi> are Siſters by Father and Mother of the <hi>Czar John Alexerwich,</hi> their Mother's Name was <hi>Miraſſelawka.</hi> The <hi>Czar Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and the Princeſs <hi>Natalia,</hi> are by a Second Marriage with a Lady of the Family of <hi>Naraskin.</hi> The <hi>Czar John</hi>'s Wife is of the Houſe of <hi>Salliskau,</hi> her Name is <hi>Martha,</hi> ſhe has had a Daughter by him. The <hi>Czar Peter</hi> is married to a Lady of the Houſe of <hi>Poukin,</hi> nam'd <hi>Marfia,</hi> or <hi>Martha.</hi> This Princeſs was ſo frighted at being forc'd
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:29503:43"/>
to follow her Husband in his Flight by Night, almoſt naked, to eſcape being murder'd, (which had unavoidably hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd, but for the warning that was given to Young <hi>Galiſchin)</hi> that ſhe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carried a few days after; but has ſince brought a Young Prince into the World in <hi>February</hi> laſt, which has for ever ruin'd the Princeſs's Party.</p>
               <p>To return to our Story; The two Aunts, and the Princeſs's Siſter, went to <hi>Trinity</hi> in hopes of reconciling their Nephew and Niece; being come before the <hi>Czar,</hi> they beſeech'd him not to give credit to thoſe Rumours which had frighted him: They aſſur'd him there was ſome miſunderſtanding in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; that ſome were maliciouſly deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make a Breach between him and his Siſter, and that he might come back to <hi>Moſcow</hi> with ſafety and ſecurity. The <hi>Czar Peter</hi> made anſwer to theſe Ladies, That he had not fled in a panick Fear; that there was a plain Conſpiracy to Murder his Wife, his Mother, his Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and himſelf; and he laid before them ſo many Circumſtances of the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, that his Aunts could not deny the truth of it. Then the Princeſſes fell a crying, and proteſted they were no
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:29503:43"/>
way concern'd in that horrid Deſign, and ſwore they would not return again to <hi>Moſcow,</hi> but would live and die with him.</p>
               <p>The Princeſs <hi>Sophia</hi> having Intimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the bad Succeſs of her Aunts Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiation, and not knowing what courſe to take, appli'd her ſelf to the Patriarch, expreſs'd her Grief to him, and ſo wrought upon him, that the good Man offer'd himſelf for a Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor: He went that very day to the <hi>Czar Peter,</hi> told him his Errand, and ſaid all that can be imagin'd to beget a Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation betwixt him and his Siſter; but he was ſtrangely ſurpriz'd, when he underſtood that he himſelf was to have been taken off; that <hi>Ligomede,</hi> or the Abbot <hi>Sylveſter</hi> was in the Plot, and was to have been made Patriarch had it ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded. This News extreamly troubled him, and he judg'd 'twould not be amiſs for him to tarry at <hi>Trinity</hi>-Convent till the Affair was clear'd up, and things better ſettled; at the ſame time he pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd a Proclamation to cauſe the Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to be apprehended.</p>
               <p>The Princeſs in a worſe plight now than ever, aſſembled her Creatures, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted what to do. 'Twas reſolv'd that the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:29503:44"/>
                  <hi>Akalnik Thekalavitau</hi> ſhould be ſecur'd in the Palace, and that the Abbot <hi>Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſter</hi> ſhould be ſav'd; and then ſhe her ſelf, accompani'd by Prince <hi>Galiſchin,</hi> and all her Friends, took her way to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Trinity</hi>-Convent, to endeavour to appeare her Brother, who had ſent a ſecond Order to the <hi>Eſtreles</hi> to render themſelves with all ſpeed at <hi>Trinity,</hi> and bring the Traitors with them. She was not got half way thither, when the <hi>Boyar Trokourau,</hi> ſent on purpoſe by Prince <hi>Peter</hi> to meet her, came and told her, ſhe muſt go back, for ſhe would not be receiv'd. The Princeſs being of opinion 'twas dangerous for her to ſtir any further, and that her Brother would give her a very ill Reception, return'd to <hi>Moſcow.</hi> Next day the <hi>Eſtreles</hi> and <hi>Germans</hi> made their appearance at <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi>-Convent; the <hi>Boyars</hi> met and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd among themſelves, to ſend and ſeize the Traitors where ever they might be found. Colonel <hi>Sarque</hi> with three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Men, was commanded to execute this Reſolution, and immediately parted for <hi>Moſcow;</hi> upon his arrival he march'd directly to the Imperial Palace, and there demanded loudly that <hi>Fiska Theke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lavitau</hi> ſhould be deliver'd to him; for
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:29503:44"/>
after the Treaſon was diſcover'd, they no longer call'd him <hi>Fiedor,</hi> or <hi>Theodore,</hi> but by his Diminutive or Nickname, which among the <hi>Ruſſians</hi> is a term of Contempt. The Princeſs made ſome Reſiſtance at firſt, but ſeeing the Colonel reſolutely bent to take him, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the ill Conſequences of her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſing too far, ſhe deliver'd up. <hi>Fiska</hi> and his Adherents. The Criminals load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Chains, were carry'd in aſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Wagon to <hi>Trinity.</hi> On the other ſide, Prince <hi>Galiſchin</hi> ſeeing himſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the brink of Ruin; yet, not to be wanting to his own Preſervation, deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd to go likewiſe to the Convent: He took with him his Son <hi>Alexis</hi> his Colleague, <hi>Talachanau, Woski</hi> the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlain to the <hi>Czars; Riquenski,</hi> the Great Treaſurer; <hi>Romanorrick,</hi> the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of <hi>Serene,</hi> his Councellor and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite; <hi>Eſmayan</hi> his Creature, who was Commiſſary-General to the Army; and a particular Friend of his, nam'd <hi>Kaſſantau;</hi> but the Gate of the Convent was ſhut againſt him and his Friends; and after he had been refus'd Entrance, there were Guards ſent back with him and his Followers, with Orders not to let them ſtir out of their Houſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:29503:45"/>
As ſoon as <hi>Fiska</hi> was brought to <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> he was carried into a Great Hall, in which the <hi>Czar</hi> had call'd together the <hi>Boyars;</hi> he was examin'd for four Hours, and thence conducted to a Tower in the Convent, where he was tortur'd, or rather whipp'd. They call this Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment <hi>Kenouſe;</hi> the Malefactor is ti'd upon a ſtrong Man's Back, who ſtands upright, and lays his Hands upon a Benoh as high as his Head. Thus the condemn'd Perſon receives two or three hundred Laſhes, more or leſs, upon the Back, beginning at the Neck, and ſo down the whole length of the Back; the Executioner ſtrikes ſo exactly, that at every laſh he fetches off a piece of Fleſh as broad as the Whip, which Kills or Lames moſt that ſuffer; then they ti'd his Hands behind his Back, and hoiſted him up, and the Executioner laſh'd him with a Whip as long as a Coachman's, but the Thong is made of a thick and hard Leather, which cuts deep into the Fleſh, and put him to exquiſite Pain; after he had undergone a few of theſe Strokes, he confeſs'd that he was to have kill'd the <hi>Czar,</hi> his Mother, and her three Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Upon this they carri'd him back to Priſon, from whence he wrote to the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:29503:45"/>
                  <hi>Czar Peter,</hi> and acquainted him at large with all the particulars of the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy; pleaded that he was over-per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded to this cruel Enterprize, and nam'd the Perſons that put him upon it. The <hi>Czar,</hi> though fully ſatisfi'd of his Siſter's Barbarity, would not pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly expoſe a Princeſs of the Blood; and Prince <hi>Borice Alexewich Galiſchin,</hi> had need of all his Credit with the <hi>Czar,</hi> to ſave the Prince, his Couſin, from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing executed, to the diſhonour of his Family.</p>
               <p>After this, ſeveral others who were to have been the Aſſaſſins, were examin'd. They gave them the Queſtion, or extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Torture, which is more ſevere than the former. They ſhav'd their Heads, and having tied them faſt, they pour'd boiling Water drop by drop upon their Skulls, which put them to ſuch intoler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Pain, that they immediately ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged their Crime, and diſcover'd their Accomplices, as <hi>Fiska</hi> had done: Two days were ſpent in conſulting how to puniſh the Criminals. Prince <hi>Galiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin,</hi> his Son, and Friends, were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd to Baniſhment, and the Sentence was read to them by a Secretary of State at the foot of the Stairs. He ſtood
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:29503:46"/>
up to hear it, encompaſs'd with the Guards, who brought him from his Houſe. And this was the Form of it:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>You are order'd by the <hi>Czar</hi> to go to <hi>Karga,</hi> a Town under the <hi>Pole,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main there as long as you live, remov'd from, and in Diſgrace with his Majeſty; whoſe Goodneſs nevertheleſs is ſuch, that he allows you Three Pence a day for Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence. His Juſtice ordains that all your Goods be forfeited to his Treaſury.</p>
               </q>
               <p>The miſerable Prince having bow'd his Head, and only anſwer'd, That 'twas hard for him to juſtify himſelf to his Majeſty, retir'd, and was conducted to the place of his Exile by a Colonel. A Secretary of State was diſpatch'd to <hi>Moſcow</hi> to ſeize upon his Palace, and make an Inventory of what was in it. They found there very rich Moveables; a hundred thouſand Ducats in a Trunk, buried in a Vault, which were thought to be the Spoils of the <hi>Hettman Jean Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meuelewick;</hi> four hundred Veſſels of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, weighing forty Pounds each, and ſome Money. The Wife of this Prince, and his Son's Wife, were baniſh'd with them; but they were not admitted to
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:29503:46"/>
take any thing with them; thirty Rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles was all that theſe four Perſons were allow'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Galiſchin</hi> being diſpos'd of, the <hi>Boyar Romanorrich,</hi> Woywode of <hi>Serene,</hi> was brought to the foot of the Stairs, and condemn'd to go to <hi>Poſtozora,</hi> a Town further North than <hi>Karga Poka,</hi> there to ſpend the reſt of his Days; his Eſtate was confiſcated likewiſe. <hi>Wedenik An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewik Eſmeyan</hi> was charg'd to confine himſelf at home till further Order. <hi>Kaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantau</hi> was turn'd out of all his Places, and confin'd to his own Houſe and Lands. <hi>Talachanau</hi> was made for his Life Woywode of <hi>Prziacelavaka,</hi> a Town not far from <hi>Kiau</hi> upon the <hi>Nie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per;</hi> and the Great Treaſurer was made Woywode of <hi>Novogrod,</hi> upon the River <hi>Samare,</hi> as long as he liv'd. Next day <hi>Fiska</hi> had his Head cut off upon a Block; and two <hi>Eſtreles</hi> that were to have been the Aſſaſſins ſuffered the ſame Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Colonel that commanded the Detachment was whipp'd, had his Tongue cut out, and was ſent to end his Days in <hi>Ziberia,</hi> with an allowance of a Penny a day; the five other <hi>Eſtreles</hi> had their Tongues cut out likewiſe, and were ſent into <hi>Ziberia</hi> to kill Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:29503:47"/>
All theſe Executions being over, the <hi>Czar Peter</hi> acquainted the Princeſs with what he had done, and deſir'd her to leave the Palace, and retire into a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtry, which ſhe had built out of Town; but ſhe refus'd to comply with his requeſt, not being able to prevail with her ſelf to enter into a place for Life, from whence ſhe had cunningly deliver'd her ſelf contrary to Cuſtom; ſhe lik'd better to retreat into <hi>Poland,</hi> of which the <hi>Czar</hi> being inform'd, he ſent Order to the Commander of the <hi>Eſtreles</hi> to Conduct her either willingly, or by force, to the Monaſtry, and ſet Guards upon all the Avenues, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer no Perſon to come to her; which was accordingly done. And two days after the <hi>Czar Peter</hi> return'd to <hi>Moſcow,</hi> and made his Entry on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back; there was nothing remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in it, but 18000 <hi>Eſtreles</hi> of his Guards arm'd. A quarter of an Hour after, his Wife and Mother came in a Coach, and all together alighted at the Palace. The <hi>Czar John</hi> ſtood to receive his Brother at the top of the Steps; they embrac'd; <hi>Peter</hi> ask'd <hi>John</hi> to be Friends; and he that anſwer'd for him, having aſſur'd him he was ſo, each re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir'd
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:29503:47"/>
to his Apartment; and ſince that time no mention has been made of <hi>John,</hi> but at the beginning of their Acts. Thus ended the Regency of the Princeſs <hi>Sophia,</hi> who had been Miſtreſs of the Great Empire of <hi>Ruſſia</hi> for ſome Years, but for endeavouring through a bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Ambition to get all the Power into her hands, which ſhe held in the Name of her Brothers, and to be abſolute and independent, was confin'd and ſhut up for the reſt of her Life, with eight hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Religious Women, whom ſhe had caus'd to come from <hi>Kiovia,</hi> with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to make her ſelf the more Creatures through their aſſiſtance; for they have nothing of Religion in them, but the Name; and not doubting but they would be more in her Intereſt than in her Brother <hi>Peter</hi>'s, whoſe Subjects they were made in 1666. when the <hi>Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> and City of <hi>Kiovia,</hi> were yielded by the <hi>Poles</hi> to the <hi>Muſcovites.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:29503:48"/>
               <head>The Cauſes of the Troubles in <hi>Moſcow.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFTER having given an ample Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Conſpiracy againſt the <hi>Czar Peter;</hi> it may be proper to ſhew, That the Troubles that Court has been embroil'd in, and thoſe that may hereafter happen, were and will be ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Intrigues of the Princeſs <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia,</hi> whoſe Wit and Merit is of another Stamp than her Perſon; for ſhe is very ugly, being of a monſtrous Size, with a Head as big as a Buſhel; ſhe has Hair upon her Chin, Tumours upon her Legs, and is at leaſt forty Years old. But though her Shape be deform'd, her Judgment is regular and piercing; and though ſhe never read <hi>Machiavel,</hi> ſhe has by Nature all his Maxims, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially this, That they may attempt any thing, and ſtick at no Crime, who are reſolved to Reign: And had ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented her ſelf with the Adminiſtration of the Government, and had not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to rid her ſelf of her Brother <hi>Peter,</hi> no body durſt have form'd a Party in Favour of the <hi>Czar Peter</hi> againſt
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:29503:48"/>
her. Towards the end of the <hi>Czar Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore</hi>'s Reign, the Princeſs <hi>Sophia</hi> having thoſe Qualifications we have mention'd; and foreſeeing that Prince could not live long in his infirm State of Body, ſhe contriv'd how to get out of her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, notwithſtanding the ſettled Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom which obliges the Female Iſſue of the <hi>Czarian</hi> Houſe to paſs their Lives in that Confinement unmarried. To which end ſhe pretended an extraordinary kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for her Brother, and complained of her unhappineſs that ſhe could not viſit a Perſon whom ſhe loved ſo ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, and attend him in his Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; when he was in the Fits of his Diſtemper, ſhe ſent every moment to ask how he did; and at other times ſhe let ſlip no occaſion of teſtifying her Love for him, and the Grief ſhe felt in being oblig'd to be abſent from him. At length, by theſe Methods having pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared a way for her intended Deſign, ſhe left the Convent under pretence of ſerving her Brother, and adminiſtring to him in his Sickneſs, which ſhe did, not ſuffering any body to come near him, nor give him Medicines but her ſelf; for ſhe wiſely conſidere'd, that the more ſhe did for him, the more ſhe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:29503:49"/>
ſhould be belov'd, both by the <hi>Czar</hi> himſelf, and every body elſe. Thus ſhe inſinuated her ſelf into the good Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Grandees, to whom ſhe car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried her ſelf very obligingly, and won the Peoples hearts by her affable Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, ſtudying to make all approve her Conduct, and excuſe her leaving the Convent. One would have thought ſhe ſhould have been ſatisfied with being at liberty; but being determin'd never to return to her Confinement, ſhe thought her beſt way would be to make her ſelf abſolute Miſtreſs; which Deſign being not to be carried on without a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable number of Friends, ſhe pitch'd upon Prince <hi>Galiſchin,</hi> as the fitteſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be the chief of her Party.</p>
               <p>He was a Man of great Quality, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from the laſt Duke of <hi>Lithuania,</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>Jagelon:</hi> The Courtiers at firſt ſeem'd well enough pleas'd with this Choice, imagining he would only have the Name of Chief Miniſter, and they ſhould ſhare the Power with him; but the Prince having more cunning than all the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> put together, eaſily managed them during the Reign of <hi>Theodore,</hi> who dying ſuddenly, <hi>Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanski,</hi> a bold Man, and a declar'd Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:29503:49"/>
of <hi>Galiſchin</hi>'s, made an Inſurrection, and cut off all the great Men that he thought would oppoſe his Deſign of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king himſelf <hi>Czar,</hi> under pretence of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging his Maſter's Death upon thoſe, who as he gave out, poyſon'd him. When thinking himſelf ſure of the Crown, and fearing no body, he was taken and puniſh'd for his Temerity and Cruelties; as we have related at large already.</p>
               <p>The Death of this Rebel, gave riſe to the Princeſs's Regency, who conferr'd the Office of Grand Chancellor upon her Favourite <hi>Galiſchin,</hi> in which Poſt never any Man in this Country govern'd with ſo great Authority.</p>
               <p>The Princeſs <hi>Sophia</hi> thinking now ſhe might do any thing; for the eaſe of her Conſcience, ſhe was minded to change her ſcandalous Familiarity with this Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite into a Marriage; all the difficulty lay in getting rid of <hi>Galiſchin</hi>'s Wife, whom the Prince was loath to part with, as well out of a Natural Principle of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as becauſe he had a great Eſtate and Children by her, and did not love the Princeſs but upon the Account of his Fortune.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:29503:50"/>
But Women being ingenious in ſuch Affairs, ſhe found means to make him perſuade his Wife to go into a Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry; in which Caſe, according to the Religion of the <hi>Muſcovites,</hi> the Husband being of too Sanguine a Conſtitution to live unmarried, obtain'd leave of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch to Marry again; the good Lady having conſented to it, the Princeſs no longer doubted of ſucceeding in her De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, that that moſt troubled <hi>Galiſchin</hi> was the Murder of the two <hi>Czars,</hi> which ſhe had abſolutely reſolv'd, to ſecure the Crown intirely to her ſelf. The Prince more Politick than Amorous, laid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her the Barbarity of ſuch a Deſign, in which ſhould ſhe ſucceed, ſhe would infallibly draw upon her the hatred of all Men; and which, though never ſo ſecretly hid, might one day be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd, and give occaſion to ſome Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content to raiſe ſuch a Sedition as <hi>Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanski</hi> had done, under Colour of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging their Deaths, and indanger the Crown. But he adviſed her to take a Courſe leſs bloody, yet in all likelihood as proper to effect her Deſigns, which was to Marry the <hi>Czar John,</hi> and give his Wife a Gallant to ſupply his Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, which the Lady might be more
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:29503:50"/>
readily inclin'd to comply with, for that her Heirs would ſucceed to the Empire, that when the <hi>Czar John</hi> ſhould have a Son, the <hi>Czar Peter</hi> would looſe all his Friends and Intereſt, and then they might Marry; and to give a better Grace to their Marriage, they would get choſen for Patriarch, Father <hi>Silveſter,</hi> a <hi>Poliſh</hi> Monk of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, who ſhould immediately propoſe by an Embaſſy to <hi>Rome,</hi> the Re-union of the two Churches; which being brought about, would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them a general Eſteem, and then they would compel <hi>Peter</hi> to go into Orders; or elſe they might find means to diſpatch him out of the way more eaſily, and with leſs Odium, than ſhe could propoſe to do it now. And then they would make <hi>John</hi> complain of his Wives Incontinence, and ſhew that the Children that ſhe had could not be his; which would be eaſy for them to prove, who were themſelves in the Secret, whence would follow a Divorce, and the Wife be confin'd to a Convent; after which they would get a permiſſion to Marry him again to one who they would take care ſhould bring him no Children. Thus without fear or danger, or even of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuſpected of foul play, they ſhould
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:29503:51"/>
Rule the State during the Life of <hi>John,</hi> and after his Death ſucceed him for want of Heirs Male in the <hi>Czarian</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</p>
               <p>The Princeſs liked this Project well, and left the Conduct of it to <hi>Galiſchin;</hi> it never entered into her head that this Prince had further Deſigns, ſince by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uniting <hi>Muſcovy</hi> to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, provided (as he hoped) the Princeſs ſhould die before him; He did not doubt to prevail with the Pope to make his own Legitimate Son Heir to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, inſtead of any he ſhould have by the Princeſs during the Life of his Wife.</p>
               <p>He began then with marrying <hi>John;</hi> and whereas the <hi>Czars</hi> never Match with Foreigners, they publiſh an Order for all the handſomeſt Maids in all <hi>Ruſſia</hi> to be brought to Court, who are viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the <hi>Czar</hi>'s Mothers, Siſters, and Kinſwomen, with the Phyſicians and Surgeons, and ſhe is choſen that is beſt lik'd; it was not difficult to find one that was proper for their Deſigns, whom they provided with an <hi>Italian</hi> Surgeon for her Gallant, who ſoon got her with Child, but as ill fortune would have it, prov'd a Girl; mean time <hi>Peter</hi>'s Friends
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:29503:51"/>
being acquainted with the roguery, caſt about how to Counter-plot them; but finding they wanted ſufficient power, they engaged on their ſide another Prince <hi>Galiſchin,</hi> Couſin to this, who was deſpiſed by him for his Drunkenneſs, and made him the Young <hi>Czar</hi>'s Favourite; then under pretence of honouring him, they obliged the Great <hi>Galiſchin</hi> to take upon him the Command of the Army a ſecond time, and in his Abſence married Prince <hi>Peter</hi> in ſpight of the Princeſs. This bold Stroke increas'd <hi>Peter</hi>'s Party; all the Young Men, whoſe Fathers affected to follow the Princeſs, declared for <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  </hi>ter. <hi>Galiſchin</hi> upon his Return ſeeing his Meaſures broken by the Marriage of the Young <hi>Czar,</hi> whoſe Wife was with Child, he agreed at laſt to take off the <hi>Czar Peter;</hi> but the Plot miſcarrying, as we have before related, he thought it high time to fly, which he might have done, had not the Princeſs oppoſed it, who aſſured him all along, that no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy durſt call to Account a Perſon of his Authority. His deſign was to ſend his eldeſt Son Ambaſſador to <hi>Poland,</hi> with his younger Son, his Grandſon, and all his Riches, and to follow himſelf, if the Conſpiracy did not ſucced to his wiſh,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:29503:52"/>
hoping to engage the King of <hi>Poland</hi> to protect him, upon promiſing him to raiſe ſome Troops in his Kingdom, with which he deſign'd to go over to the <hi>Coſſacks</hi> and <hi>Tartars,</hi> and then he would undertake that by Force, which he could not effect by Policy. 'Tis probable this Deſign might have ſucceeded, he having great Intereſt in thoſe Parts: But the Princeſs not being able to part with him, hindered his Retreat till the very Night before his Diſgrace, when he might ſtill have ſaved himſelf, having all the Seals in his own Hands, and having but forty <hi>German</hi> Leagues from <hi>Moſcow</hi> to the neareſt Town in <hi>Poland:</hi> And I am perſuaded he would then have fled if he had done what he projected; but ſeeing the Precipitation and Violence of the Princeſs <hi>Sophia</hi> had prevented him, he choſe rather to ſuffer the utmoſt Stroke of Fortune, and even Death it ſelf, rather than by his Flight to expoſe his Family that he muſt leave behind, to all the Outrages which his malicious Enemies could invent; and to ſee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf reduc'd from ſuch a height of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, to be a poor wandering Fugitive in a Foreign Country.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:29503:52"/>
               <head>The Preſent State of <hi>Muſcovy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHEN <hi>Galiſchin</hi> was gone into Baniſhment, <hi>Naraskin,</hi> the <hi>Czar Peter</hi>'s Uncle by the Mother's ſide, found but one Obſtacle to his Deſign of ſucceeding his Nephew, <hi>viz.</hi> The Young <hi>Galiſchin,</hi> Prince <hi>Peter</hi>'s Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, whom he could not eaſily deſtroy, becauſe he himſelf had been the cauſe of his riſe; but young <hi>Peter</hi> and his Favourite being little read in Politicks, this old Fox inſinuated into his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew, that his Favourite muſt needs have been concerned with the Great <hi>Galiſchin,</hi> as might be judged from the zealous Endeavours he had made to ſave his Life; but the <hi>Czar</hi> repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him how hard it was for him to ſuſpect a Man that had ſaved his Life three times, <hi>Naraskin</hi> accompani'd by his Daughter and Sons with Tears in their Eyes, declared to <hi>Peter,</hi> That if he did not remove that Favourite, he might even as well recal the Great <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſchin.</hi> A Prince of more underſtanding than he, would have been ſhock'd at leaſt with this; but he readily promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:29503:53"/>
to confine his Favourite to live upon his own Lands; whither that Prince being advertiſed of the matter, was already gone without ſtaying for Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as the <hi>Czar</hi> heard of it, he ſent to him Courier after Courier, to ask the Cauſe of his Retirement: To whom he gave no other Anſwer, Than that ſeeing his paſt Conduct could not convince His Majeſty of his Fidelity, he would never more come to Court. The <hi>Czar Peter</hi> was ſo ſenſibly affected with this, that he ſent two <hi>Boyars</hi> to viſit him; and ſome days after impatient to ſee him, he ſent two others to deſire him to return, which he preſently did. The <hi>Czar Peter</hi> careſt him extreamly upon his return, which ſo alarm'd the <hi>Naraskins,</hi> and their Party, that they reſolved to endeavour to be Friends with him; for a little while he made a great Figure by the Favours that he conferr'd upon his Friends; but at laſt, this Prince, who had nothing of the Merit of his Couſin in him, began to follow his Maxims, in cauſing the Grandees to be diſgrac'd, and their Places given to ſuch Drunkards as himſelf; but he ſoon
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:29503:53"/>
fell into Diſgrace himſelf; for his Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents making as if they would reſtore the Princeſs, partly wrought ſo far up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Peter,</hi> that in the end he reſolved to give the Place of the Great <hi>Galiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin,</hi> which his Couſin expected, and which till then had been managed by Commiſſioners, to <hi>Naraskin,</hi> his Mother's Father. This Action, at a time when 'twas leaſt expected, determin'd all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to follow the Party of the <hi>Naras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins,</hi> whoſe Sons were ſoon put into Places of the greateſt Truſt; among the reſt, his Eldeſt Son was made Great Chamberlain, and Young <hi>Galiſchin</hi> turn'd out of that place; which ſo incenſed him, that he could not forbear expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his Reſentment, by charging the <hi>Czar</hi> with Weakneſs. His Enemies made their advantage of this Conduct, and determin'd the <hi>Czar,</hi> who has no other Merit than Cruelty, to Baniſh this Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite ignominiouſly; and he has ſince given Orders to put both the exil'd <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſchins</hi> to Death. Thoſe that rejoyc'd moſt at the fall of the Great <hi>Galiſchin,</hi> are now ſenſible of the loſs of him; for the <hi>Naraskins</hi> that Govern now, are Ignorant and Bruitiſh, and begin to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, contrary to all Policy and good
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:29503:54"/>
Senſe, all that that Great Man had done with ſo much prudence for the Glory and Advantage of the Nation, and would gladly recommend themſelves by reviving their ancient barbarous Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms.</p>
               <p>Theſe Brutes have already forbid Strangers to come into their Country, and have forbid the Exerciſe of the Catholick Religion: The Envoy of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is allowed a Chappel indeed, but he obtain'd it with a great deal of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty. Nay, it is thought that ere long they will oblige the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> to learn only to Read and Write as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, that in that as well as in other things their Government may be abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely Tyrannical, which will make the loſs of <hi>Galiſchin</hi> the more lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>For he built a very noble College of Stone, and put into it twenty <hi>Grecian</hi> Doctors, and a great many Books; he adviſed the Noblemen to give their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren learning: obtained leave for them to ſend ſome of their Sons to the <hi>Latin</hi> Colleges in <hi>Poland,</hi> and to ſend for <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Tutors to thoſe they would Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:29503:54"/>
at home, and permitted Strangers to come into, or go out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which before his time was never allow'd. 'He would alſo have the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility travel abroad, and learn the Art of War in Foreign Countries; his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign being to lay aſide thoſe Legions of Peaſants, whoſe Lands were left uncul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated when they went to the Wars; and inſtead of that uſeleſs Charge upon the People, to lay a reaſonable Tax up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every Houſe. He adviſed that Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſhould be ſent to reſide in all the chief Courts of <hi>Europe,</hi> and to give a Liberty of Conſcienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hroughout the Country.</p>
               <p>He had already receiv'd the Jeſuits into <hi>Moſcow,</hi> with whom he very often converſt; but the next day after his Diſgrace, they were all ſent away with a Declaration from the <hi>Czars</hi> to the Emperor, and King of <hi>Poland,</hi> who had ſent them, that they would never again let any come into the Country. Accordingly, in <hi>March</hi> 1690. they refuſed to let the King of <hi>Poland</hi>'s Envoy (who requeſted it in his Maſter's Name) to paſs through their Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and likewiſe Father <hi>Grimaldi</hi> from
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:29503:55"/>
the Emperor, who is now in <hi>Poland</hi> for the Emperor of <hi>China.</hi> If I ſhould ſet down all that I have learnt concerning this Prince, I ſhould never have done. 'Tis ſufficient to ſay, That he deſign'd to people Deſarts, to enrich Beggars, to make Men of Brutes, good Soldiers of Cowards, and Palaces of Cottages; all which advantages <hi>Muſcovy</hi> has loſt by the fall of that Prince. His own Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace is one of the moſt Magnificent in <hi>Europe;</hi> 'tis cover'd with Copper, and hung within with rich Tapeſtries, and noble Paintings; and during his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, three th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>nd Houſes were built of Stone in <hi>Moſcow,</hi> which will not be thought ſtrange by thoſe that know there are five hundred thouſand Inhabitants in that City, and that it is compoſed of three Towns, one within another, each ſurrounded by a great Wall, and a Ditch full of Water to defend them from the Incurſions of the <hi>Tartars;</hi> the firſt is call'd <hi>Kzim;</hi> the ſecond <hi>Bialo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grod,</hi> or the White Town; and the third <hi>Novogrod,</hi> or the New Town.</p>
               <p>The greateſt Curioſity in it to a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, is to ſee in <hi>December</hi> two thouſand Wooden-houſes ſet up for the <hi>Eaſtern</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:29503:55"/>
and <hi>European</hi> Merchants. Prince <hi>Galiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin</hi> alſo built upon the River <hi>Moſcow,</hi> which runs into the <hi>Occa,</hi> a Stone-bridge of twelve Arches, and of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious height, becauſe of the Floods; 'tis the only Stone-bridge in all <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covy,</hi> and was contriv'd by a <hi>Poliſh</hi> Monk.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Manners and Religion of the <hi>Muſcovites.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>Muſcovites,</hi> to ſpeak proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, are Barbarians, Suſpicious and Miſtruſtful, Cruel, Sodomites, Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, Covetous, Beggars, and Cowards; all Slaves except three Families of Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners; Prince <hi>Sirkache,</hi> formerly Lord of the Country of that Name, who is vaſtly rich; <hi>Galiſchin,</hi> and <hi>Harthemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerrich.</hi> Beſides, they are ſo dull and brutiſh, that were it not for the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> who are very numerous in <hi>Moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cow,</hi> they could do nothing well. They are very naſty, though they often Bathe themſelves in places built on purpoſe, and made ſo exceſſive hot, that no
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:29503:56"/>
body but they could ſupport it. Men and Women mingle together in thoſe Bagnio's which uſually ſtand upon the Water-ſide, that thoſe who Sweat may jump into the cold Water, which they do as well in Winter as Summer; but though they are very hardy, yet they are more ſenſible of Cold than the <hi>Poles.</hi> They Eat and Drink very ill; their uſual Food is only Cucum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and Melons of <hi>Aſtrakan,</hi> which they pickle in Summer, in Water, Flower, and Salt. They eat no Veal out of a ſcruple, too infamous to be nam'd; nor Pigeon out of Superſtition, becauſe the Holy Ghoſt is repreſented to us under that Figure. The Men are cloath'd much like the <hi>Poles;</hi> thoſe that are Rich, in Winter wear Cloath-Gowns brought from <hi>Holland,</hi> lin'd with fine Furs, and Jewels, or little Pearls, that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in their Country, in their Caps: In Summer, <hi>Perſian</hi> and <hi>Chineſe</hi> Stuffs and Silks.</p>
               <p>The Women are dreſt like the <hi>Turks;</hi> the pooreſt of 'em are proud of having a Cap of <hi>Perſian</hi> Stuff, more or leſs Rich, ſuch as they can purchaſe. The richeſt garniſh 'em with Pearls and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:29503:56"/>
Stones. Their Gowns or <hi>Sulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naes</hi> in Winter are made of Stuffs flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er'd with Gold, lin'd with Sables, and in Summer of <hi>Chineſe</hi> Damask. They wear no Hair in their Head-dreſſes. They walk very uneaſily, for their Shooes are made like Sandals, and too big for their Feet. They paint their Faces, ſhave their Eye-brows and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour 'em as they fancy. Are very fond of Strangers, little ſcrupulous about the Nearneſs of Blood; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe their Husbands above all things. The <hi>Muſcovites</hi> love to go abroad, and are always in haſte; their Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page is very pitiful, moſt of 'em ride about Town upon a ſcrubbed Horſe, with their Footmen running barehead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before 'em: In Winter this Beaſt is harneſs'd to a Sledge, and this is all their Carriage. As for the Women, they have moſt of 'em a ſcurvy kind of a Coach made like a Litter, drawn commonly by a ſingle Horſe; they go 5 or 6 together in't, and ſit ſquat down, for there's neither Seat nor Cuſhion in it. Though there are Five or Six hundred thouſand Inhabitans in <hi>Moſcow,</hi> there are no more than Three hundred of theſe Coaches, but above
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:29503:57"/>
a Thouſand little Chariots with one Horſe, which for a ſmall matter carry people from one place to another.</p>
               <p>Some of the Richeſt have Coaches made after the <hi>French</hi> faſhion, brought from <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Dantzick.</hi> Thoſe of the <hi>Czars</hi> are very old; the reaſon is, they never buy any, hoping to have 'em preſented by foreign Princes or Ambaſſadors. The beſt they have are made after the Mode of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, ſome with Boots, and others like Litters. Their Sleds are very fine; thoſe that are open, are made of Gild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Wood lin'd within with Velvet, and broad Galoons: They are drawn by Six Horſes, whoſe Harneſs is cover'd with Velvet. Thoſe Sleds that are cover'd, are made like a Coach with Glaſſes, cover'd on the outſide with Red Cloth, and within with Sables: They lye down and ſleep in them when they travel, which they commonly do in the Night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time in Winter.</p>
               <p>When the <hi>Czars</hi> go through the City either in Coach or Sled, they change their beſt Equipages for ſuch as they uſe in the Country. They
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:29503:57"/>
have ſeveral Wooden Houſes about <hi>Moſcow,</hi> which they improperly term Pleaſure-houſes, for there's neither Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens nor Walks, they are only ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with Walls, for fear of being carried off by the <hi>Poles</hi> or <hi>Tartars,</hi> which often happen'd fifty years ago.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Czar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Peter</hi> is very tall, and pretty well ſhap'd, and has a Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Face; his Eyes are large, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteady, which makes it no pleaſant thing for any body to look upon him; his Head ſhakes continually, though he is but Twenty Years old. His diverſion is to make his Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites ſhoot at one another, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they kill one another to ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate themſelves with him. In Winter he cauſes great holes to be made in the Ice, and forces his fatteſt Lords to paſs over 'em in Sleds; they fall in and are drown'd ſometimes, when the holes are not froze over again hard enough to bear 'em. Now and then he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the Great Bell to be toll'd, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing pleaſes him better than to ſee houſes on fire; which happens very often in <hi>Moſcow,</hi> for they never take pains to put out the fire till there are
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:29503:58"/>
four or five hundred burnt. The truth on't is, there's ſeldom much damage done, for theſe houſes are little better than our Hogſties in <hi>France</hi> or <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many:</hi> They are bought in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket ready built. In 1688 there were Three thouſand burnt; and within four Months laſt Year I ſaw three fires, in each of which five or ſix hundred houſes at leaſt were burnt. Theſe fires are occaſion'd by their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Drunkenneſs, and their negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to put out the many Tapers that they ſtick about the Pictures in their Chambers. They prepare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for <hi>Lent</hi> by a Carnival of as many days, during which the diſorder is ſo great, that the Foreigners who live in the Suburbs dare hardly venture into the City, for they butcher one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like Wild Beaſts, and make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves drunk with Brandy and other Liquors, ſo ſtrong and yet ſo abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, that no body but they can drink 'em; ſo that 'tis no wonder they loſe the little reaſon they have natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and ſtab one another with great Knives like Bayonets. A fellow ſhall kill his beſt Friend and Comrade there, if he hopes to rob him of a
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:29503:58"/>
Penny. All they do to hinder or at leaſt leſſen theſe outrages, is to rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the Guards; but the Soldiers, who are no ſoberer than the reſt, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come in till the miſchief's done; and provided they have their ſhare of the Plunder, the Criminal is ſure to eſcape; inſomuch that no body's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in this Countrey to ſee peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple murder'd daily in the ſtreets. They eat ſo greedily, that they are forc'd to ſleep three hours at leaſt after din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and go to bed as ſoon as they've ſupp'd; but they make amends by riſing betimes in the morning. Nay, they live thus in the Army, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry private Soldier takes a Nap at noon. In the Summer they ſtrip themſelves naked, and bathe, and ſo they lye down to ſleep. They can't endure Rain, and 'tis very rare in theſe parts. They all wear little Caps, and when they meet their Friends they make a ſign of the Croſs, and ſhake hands. This they do, I ſuppoſe, to call God to witneſs to their Infidelity, for cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing's one of their Virtues.</p>
               <p>The Religion of the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> is that of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> and may be call'd
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:29503:59"/>
Archiſchiſmatical, for 'tis ſo full of horrible Superſtitions, which their Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance has introduc'd into it, that they may paſs for half Idolaters. They have kept up the Sacerdotal Order among 'em, but they treat their Prieſts and Monks with very little reſpect; for they make no ſcruple when they catch 'em out of their Churches, to take off their Caps, and when they have threſh'd 'em ſufficiently, to put 'em upon their heads again very or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly.</p>
               <p>The Patriarch of <hi>Muſcovy</hi> reſided formerly at <hi>Kiovia,</hi> but the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> have obtain'd ſince that City ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd to 'em, that his Seat ſhould be transferr'd to <hi>Moſcow.</hi> This Patriarch is uſually choſen from among the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitans, and confirm'd by the <hi>Czar.</hi> He cannot be depos'd but by thoſe of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> and <hi>Antioch.</hi> In the Reign of the <hi>Czar Theodore,</hi> one was ſent thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the <hi>Czar</hi>'s Charge; he died laſt year, and was choſen at firſt purely for his handſome Beard. The Patriarch and Metropolitans always wear their Pontifical Habits, and go abroad in them either in a Coach or
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:29503:59"/>
on Horſeback. Their Croſs is carri'd before them by a Footman, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways is bareheaded; for let the Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be as 'twill, the Servants that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to cuſtom walk before their Maſters, are never cover'd. Their Copes differ from thoſe of our Biſhops in this particular, that they have lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Bells hung all round 'em. The Prelates carry their Beads in their hands, which reach down to the ground, and are always mumbling over 'em. Their chief Devotion is in Proceſſions, which are perform'd in the following manner. All the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy in magnificent Copes, moſt of them edg'd with Pearls, come out of ſome Church, but all in a Crowd without any order, to go to another where the Solemn Service is to be held. Every Prieſt carries ſomething in his hand, ſome a Book, others a Croſs, and others a Croſier. Thoſe that march next to the Metropolitan or Patriarch, carry great Pictures of the Virgin richly adorn'd with Gold, Jewels, and Chaplets or Bead-rolls of Pearls, others great Croſſes richly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn'd likewiſe, and ſo heavy, that ſome are carri'd by four Prieſts. Then
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:29503:60"/>
come thoſe that carry the Goſpels, which without diſpute are the moſt magnificent in <hi>Europe,</hi> for a ſingle Leaf coſts betwixt Twenty five and Thirty thouſand Crowns. I have ſeen one which the <hi>Czar Peter</hi> had made for him by a <hi>French</hi> Jeweller, on each ſide ſet with five Emeralds, the leaſt of which is worth Ten thouſand Crowns, and enchas'd in four Pound of Gold, for theſe people value no Work but what is weighty. After theſe come the Abbots, follow'd by the Metropolitans, and laſt of all at ſome diſtance comes the Patriarch, having his Bonnet on, thick ſet with Pearls, and faſhion'd, excepting the Three Crowns, like the Pope's <hi>Tiara.</hi> He ought to be ſupported by the <hi>Czars,</hi> but they having more occaſion when they walk, to be led themſelves, nominate ſome Lords to do that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. Theſe Proceſſions are preceded by about a hundred men, ſome with Brooms to ſweep the way, and others to ſtrew Sand upon it. Before Prince <hi>Galiſchin</hi>'s Miniſtry they were oblig'd to march ſometimes through the dirt, which he remedied by cauſing all the Streets to be plank'd, for there's no
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:29503:60"/>
paving in <hi>Muſcovy;</hi> but ſince his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace they have kept none but the great Streets in repair. All the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion of the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> lies in aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Maſs, which their Prieſts begin at Midnight; though their Service is very long, they never ſit down at Church, nor ever pray but in Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, for moſt of them can neither write nor read, and not one of 'em, no not among their Prieſts, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands <hi>Greek.</hi> They have abundance of Holidays, which they obſerve no otherwiſe than in ringing all the Bells from the Eve before the Feſtival to the Morning after it, and they work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all the days in the year indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. They are likewiſe very fond of making Pilgrimages: The <hi>Czar John,</hi> though he be ſo Paralytick, ſpends his Life in them, though 'twould be more to his Credit not to ſhew himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad ſo often, but keep within his Palace, for he is a frightful ſight, ſo very ugly, that 'tis irkſome to look upon him, tho he is but Twenty eight years old. When they arrive at the place, they begin their Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by kiſſing the Earth, making ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſigns of the Croſs, and bowing to
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:29503:61"/>
ſome Images, or places where they ought to be. Their Prieſts are mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, but muſt not lye with their Wives the Night before their Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals. The Biſhops and Abbots are oblig'd to live ſingle. When a <hi>Roman</hi>-Catholick turns to their Religion they baptize him anew, and if he be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and his Wife won't turn too, he may marry another. They keep <hi>Lent</hi> three times a year; the firſt is ours, the ſecond ſix Weeks before <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> and the third fifteen days before our Lady's day in <hi>September.</hi> They dreſs their Fiſh in Oyl, which next to themſelves is certainly the filthieſt ſtuff in the world: This kills moſt of the Soldiers, for the Fiſh they uſe being dried in the Sun, and in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner putrified, breeds great diſtempers among 'em; and ſo does their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Drink, which is nothing but Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Flower.</p>
               <p>They love to build Churches; and whenever a Nobleman builds a Houſe, he erects a Chappel, and maintains in it as many Monks as he can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford. There are in <hi>Moſcow</hi> Twelve hundred Churches built of Stone,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:29503:61"/>
which have every one five Turrets with Bells in them, and at top of each Turret is a Croſs, the leaſt of which is four Foot high. The moſt magnificent Churches are thoſe of the <hi>Virgin,</hi> and St. <hi>Michael,</hi> which ſtand near the <hi>Czar</hi>'s Palace, the Dome and Turrets are cover'd with Copper gilt, and the Croſſes are painted Red. The Inſide of theſe Churches is painted like Moſaic Work, over-againſt them is a great Steeple, in which hang ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral great Bells, among the reſt one that is twenty Foot in Diameter, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in heighth, and a Foot and a half thick; they have ſhav'd forty thouſand Weight of Metal out of it, to make it ſound well. They never ring it out but on <hi>Twelfth-day,</hi> which is kept very ſolemnly by the <hi>Muſcovites:</hi> And they ſtrike upon it when the <hi>Czar</hi> lies with the Great Dutcheſs, to warn the people to pray for the Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Prince, for they make little account of a Daughter. Half the Lands in <hi>Muſcovy</hi> belong to the Monks, becauſe the great Piety of the <hi>Muſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites</hi> conſiſts in building Cloyſters, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of which hold a hundred Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, who live in great Plenty and
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:29503:62"/>
perfect Ignorance. There are likewiſe many Convents for Nuns. All ſorts of Religions are permitted in <hi>Muſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy,</hi> except the Catholick, which they look upon as the only good one next to their own. If a Foreigner of any Religion ſoever goes into their Churches, they make him turn <hi>Ruſſian,</hi> becauſe formerly thoſe that look'd in, us'd to laugh at their Ceremonies and ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which is very like the humming of dumb People.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:29503:62"/>
               <head>An Account of a Way by Land through <hi>Muſcovy</hi> to <hi>China,</hi> and of the Commerce betwixt them and the <hi>Muſcovites.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Trade of Furs is of long ſtanding in <hi>Muſcovy,</hi> but is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd now from what it was; the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles were little known there formerly, and they dealt only in ordinary Furs, except Ermins, which they exchang'd for ſuch Goods as they wanted. But the Grandfather of the preſent <hi>Czars, Baſile Bazillewik,</hi> Sirnam'd the Tyrant, (he was juſtly ſo call'd, for he took pleaſure in ſpilling the Blood of his Subjects, and particularly once made his Coachman drive the Coach in which was his Wife, over a Lake that was thinly frozen within a quarter of a League of <hi>Moſcow,</hi> in which ſhe, and all that were with her were drown'd); having conquer'd the Kingdoms of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrakan</hi> and <hi>Cazan,</hi> diſcover'd at length part of that vaſt Country, ſince call'd <hi>Ziberia,</hi> which in the <hi>Sclavonian</hi> Tongue ſignifies a Priſon, becauſe that Cruel
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:29503:63"/>
and Barbarous Prince ſent into that Country, which had then no Name, thoſe that diſpleaſed him; to whom is owing the Diſcovery of the Sables, or <hi>Zibelin Martins;</hi> and alſo of a Way to <hi>China</hi> through thoſe vaſt Deſarts, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd with impaſſable and unknown Woods, which probably ſtretch as far as the frozen Sea, by advancing ſtill forward, and penetrating further in chace of theſe Creatures, Black Foxes, Wolves, and other Wild Beaſts, with which theſe uninhabited Foreſts abound, and whoſe Skins are ſo valuable.</p>
               <p>After the Death of this Tyrant, his Son ſucceeding him, ſtudied how to make an Advantage of his Power, by permitting Foreign Merchants to come and Trade in the Country. The <hi>Dutch</hi> were the firſt that attempted to paſs by Sea to <hi>Muſcovy;</hi> but not being able to ſucceed in it, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> adventur'd with ſucceſs, and arriv'd at <hi>Arch-Angel,</hi> a Port ſituated in the Sea or Gulf of St. <hi>Nicholas.</hi> The <hi>Czar</hi> hearing of it, granted them large Priviledges, <hi>viz.</hi> To pay no Cuſtom inwards and outwards, to engage them to ſettle a Trade. The <hi>Dutch</hi> being piqu'd at this Diſcovery,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:29503:63"/>
endeavour'd all they could to break off this Agreement; but the <hi>Czar</hi> fearing the Eſtabliſhment of Commerce with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> would be delay'd by ſuch a proceeding, forbid the <hi>Dutch</hi> to enter into the Port. And ſo the <hi>Engliſh</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd ſole Maſters of this Trade, till the Death of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. of which this Prince, though a <hi>Barbarian,</hi> being inform'd, took away from the <hi>Engliſh</hi> out of Policy, though he term'd it a Puniſhment for beheading their King, all their Priviledges, and gave leave to the <hi>Dutch</hi> to come into the Port, upon Condition to pay 15 <hi>per Cent.</hi> for all that they imported and exported; and they have ſince carried this Trade on ſo advantagiouſly, that at preſent they maintain above two hundred Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors in the Country; of whom the greateſt part come and Winter at <hi>Moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cow,</hi> becauſe of the exceſſive Cold. It was upon this occaſion that Money was firſt brought into <hi>Muſcovy,</hi> which is now as common there as in <hi>Poland;</hi> for there are in the Suburbs of <hi>Moſcow</hi> above a thouſand Merchants, <hi>Engliſh, Dutch, Hamburghers, Flemings,</hi> and <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians;</hi> theſe Trade in <hi>Ruſſia</hi> Leather and Cavear, which are Sturgeons Eggs,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:29503:64"/>
which they make up in Cakes, as thick as ones Finger, and as broad as ones Hand, and ſalt and dry them in the Sun; it is a Commodity to be had here in great Quantities, for there is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible number of Sturgeons taken at the Mouth of the <hi>Wolga,</hi> and other Rivers, that fall into the <hi>Caſpian-Sea;</hi> they are brought up by Water to <hi>Moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cow,</hi> and from thence are diſtributed all over <hi>Muſcovy,</hi> and the Neighbouring Countries, as Herrings are among us; and is of great ſupport to the <hi>Muſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites</hi> in their three Lents, which they keep very regularly. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> truck their Cloth and Spices for Corn, Hemp, Roſin, and Pot-Aſhes. The <hi>Flemings</hi> and <hi>Hamburghers</hi> deal with them for Wax and Iron. The Ships of theſe Nations come to <hi>Arch-Angel</hi> in <hi>July,</hi> and depart in <hi>September;</hi> they that ſtay longer, run the hazard to be loſt. The paſſage from <hi>Bergen</hi> to <hi>Arch-Angel,</hi> is commonly perform'd in fifteen or twenty Days, either going or coming. This Commerce is very conſiderable, yet there does not come above thirty Ships a year into that Port. The <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> come from Hiſpa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n croſs the <hi>Caſpian-Sea</hi> to <hi>Aſtrakan</hi> at the end of
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:29503:64"/>
                  <hi>October,</hi> thence they Travel in Sleds to <hi>Moſcow</hi> at the <hi>Czar</hi>'s Charge in five Weeks; when they go back, they go down the <hi>Wolga</hi> in thirty or forty Days. The <hi>Dutch</hi> got leave of the Great <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſchin</hi> to ſend ſome of their own Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penters and Pilots to <hi>Aſtrakan,</hi> where they built two Frigots, and croſs'd over the <hi>Caſpian-Sea</hi> to <hi>Chemakay,</hi> the firſt Town in <hi>Perſia,</hi> and traded with the <hi>Perſians;</hi> but the <hi>Tartars</hi> having burnt them about eighteen Months ago, the preſent Miniſters have forbid the building any more, which will be very pernicious in the conſequence, for the <hi>Muſcovite</hi> Veſſels are very incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious. The Deſign of this Prince was to make this State like the reſt in <hi>Europe;</hi> he procured Memoirs of all their Methods of Government; he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to begin with giving the Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants their Liberty, and the Lands they cultivate now for the <hi>Czars</hi> profit, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Annual Tribute; by which, as he computed the <hi>Czar</hi>'s Revenues would be increaſed one half, which does not amount to leſs than ſeven or eight Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of <hi>French</hi> Livers in ready Money; for as to the Commodities that make up the reſt of his Revenue, it is very
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:29503:65"/>
hard to compute their Value. He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd the ſame thing in Relation to their Drinking-Houſes, and other Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, thinking by theſe means to make the People Laborious and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious, in hopes of inriching them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>As to the Hunting of Sables, he made no Alteration in it; that is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on by Criminals, who are baniſh'd into <hi>Ziberia;</hi> and Soldiers who are ſent thither in Regiments, Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a Collonel, and ſtay there com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſeven Years; they are all obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to bring in a certain Quantity of Furs weekly; they muſt take particular care that the fine Furs have no Holes in them, nor ſtain'd with Blood; and eſpecially the Sables, which they ſay ſpoils them; and therefore they are bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten if they commit any ſuch Fault; this makes them very dextrous at Shooting them, which they always do in the Head with a ſingle Ball. The ſucceſs of this Hunting depends upon much Patience and Aſſiduity; wherefore they allow the Officers to encourage the Soldiers by ſharing with them the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus of what they muſt kill weekly
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:29503:65"/>
for the <hi>Czar,</hi> which makes this Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment very conſiderable, for a Colonel may get in Seven Years by this Service Four thouſand Crowns, the Subalterns in proportion; but a Common Soldier never makes more than Six or ſeven hundred Crowns, and they muſt have good Friends to get that; for a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman at <hi>Moſcow</hi> has nothing in the World to live upon, but a thouſand Crowns a Year, half of which is paid in Sables, valued ordinarily at more than they are worth: A Colonel has Four hundred Crowns a Year, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alterns proportionably, paid the ſame way. <hi>Galiſchin</hi>'s deſign for the <hi>Czar</hi>'s, and his Officers Profit, was to defray the Charge of the State in Money, and for that end ſent ſuch as he could Truſt into Foreign Countries, with Sables and Furs, either to ſell or truck them for ſuch Goods as might be ſold again for the <hi>Czar</hi>'s Profit. What he did to ſettle a Commerce with <hi>China</hi> by Land through <hi>Ziberia</hi> and <hi>Tartary,</hi> deſerves to be particularly related.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Spatarus,</hi> a <hi>Walachian,</hi> was baniſh'd out of his own Country, after having had his Noſe cut off, for diſcovering to the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:29503:66"/>
                  <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> a Secret Treaty that the <hi>Hoſpodar</hi> of <hi>Walachia,</hi> his Kinſman, had made with the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and which was the occaſion of the <hi>Hoſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar</hi>'s being depoſed, who is kept by the King of <hi>Poland</hi> now in his Court. He retir'd firſt to the Elector of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgh,</hi> who receiv'd him very kindly, becauſe he was very Ingenious, and ſpoke <hi>Latin, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Italian,</hi> very well; but the King of <hi>Poland</hi> informing the Elector of his Infidelity, he was forced to fly from thence; and not knowing what to do, went into <hi>Muſcovy; Galiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin</hi> receiv'd him, and gave him Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence; ſome time after he ſent him to <hi>China,</hi> to diſcover by what means to eſtabliſh a Trade by Land betwixt that Country and <hi>Muſcovy;</hi> he ſpent two Years in this Journey, and met with great difficulties; but he took ſuch Obſervation of the Places he paſſed through, that at his return he put <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſchin</hi> in hopes, that in a ſecond Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age he would take ſuch a Method, that the way ſhould be made as eaſy as through any part of <hi>Europe. Galiſchin,</hi> upon his Aſſurances, began to think of ſome commodious ſhort Road, and having pitched upon it, he contrived
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:29503:66"/>
how to ſettle convenient Carriages, <hi>viz.</hi> to build from <hi>Moſcow</hi> to <hi>Tobolk,</hi> the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital of <hi>Ziberia,</hi> ſome Wooden Houſes every Ten Leagues, to put Peaſants into them, and to allow them ſome Lands, upon condition they ſhould maintain in every Houſe Three Horſes, he giving them the Three firſt; who ſhould have a Right to demand of Paſſengers to and from <hi>Ziberia</hi> upon their own buſineſs 3 <hi>d. per</hi> Horſe for every Ten Mile: He likewiſe planted Poſts upon this Road, as upon all the reſt in <hi>Muſcovy,</hi> to mark the Way and the Miles; and in thoſe Parts where the Snow is ſo deep that Horſes cannot travel in it, he built ſome Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which he beſtowed upon ſome peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who were condemned to perpetual Exile, and furniſhed them with Money, Victuals, and great Dogs to draw the Sleds over the Snow, and ſo to <hi>Tobolk,</hi> which ſtands upon the great River <hi>Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtik.</hi> He had erected ſome Magazines, and laid up Proviſions in 'em; he built ſeveral great Barks to go up that River as far as <hi>Ketilbas,</hi> a Lake at the foot of the Mountains <hi>Pragog,</hi> where he had provided neceſſary Carriage for the reſt of the Voyage. <hi>Spatarus</hi> aſſur'd me he went his laſt Journey in five Months,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:29503:67"/>
with as much eaſe as he could have tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd in our parts of <hi>Europe.</hi> I earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſir'd to learn all particulars, as the Names of Rivers, Mountains, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces through which he went; but I found him very ſhy and reſerv'd, and that he durſt not communicate himſelf freely to me, for fear it ſhould come to be known that he had diſcover'd a thing to me that the <hi>Czars</hi> would have kept ſecret; and leſt his Complaiſance to me in telling me all I deſir'd, ſhould coſt him a drubbing; for the <hi>Czars</hi> never ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt any one whom they have a mind to give that Correction to, from the <hi>Boyar</hi> to the Peaſant. He told me how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, that he did not queſtion to find an eaſier and ſhorter Way the next time he went. But the <hi>Hollanders</hi> being always jealous of their Neighbours (as they have ſhewn by all their Eſtabliſhments in the <hi>Eaſt)</hi> and deſigning to get into their hands the Trade of all the world, and exclude every body elſe if they could, oblig'd the <hi>Muſcovites,</hi> after the diſgrace of <hi>Galiſchin,</hi> to forbid all other Foreign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to come into the Countrey; fearing leſt if that Road ſhould once be known, and eaſy to be travell'd, the <hi>French</hi> would attempt it; who carrying thither
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:29503:67"/>
ſo many curious ſorts of Work as they make, which the <hi>Chineſe</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> mightily eſteem, and for which in return they might bring back the richeſt and moſt valuable Merchandizes, in time might damage their Commerce to the <hi>Cape of Good Hope, Batavia, Malaca,</hi> and other places in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> which they took from the <hi>Portugueſe</hi> and <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and foreſeeing that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modiouſneſs of this Way by Land being once ſettled, all other Merchants would chuſe it, rather than venture all the Tempeſts, Diſtempers, and other ill Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents that happen at Sea, beſides the tediouſneſs of the Voyage; and that thus a great Trade would one day be carried on, which they don't apprehend from the <hi>Muſcovites,</hi> who they know want underſtanding to make any thing conſiderable of it, and that they are too poor to buy the rich Commodities of thoſe Kingdoms, and could bring away nothing but a few Silks, Tea, Wooden Ware, and ſuch like Baubles; ſo that they have nothing to fear from them, who can never do 'em much harm, nor diſturb their Trade. Some time after the King of <hi>Poland</hi> made Complaints by his Envoy at <hi>Moſcow</hi> againſt this Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:29503:68"/>
which is directly contrary to the Treaty of 1686, in which 'tis expreſly ſaid, That his Subjects might go and come through <hi>Muſcovy</hi> to <hi>China:</hi> But all the Anſwer he could get, was, That the <hi>Czars</hi> had ſo order'd it. They gave the ſame Reply to the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> whoſe Ambaſſador <hi>Fabricius</hi> made the like Agreement with 'em in 1686. They thought they did a great deal in ſuffering the King of <hi>Poland</hi>'s Envoys to paſs through their Dominions to <hi>Aſtrakan</hi> at their Charge, who from thence went to <hi>Perſia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Poland</hi> inſerted this Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle in the Treaty of 1686, at the requeſt of the Jeſuits, who hop'd to go by Land to <hi>China;</hi> but <hi>Galiſchin</hi> with all his Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt could not get leave for thoſe to go, whom Count <hi>Siri,</hi> Envoy from <hi>Poland</hi> to <hi>Perſia,</hi> brought with him to <hi>Moſcow</hi> in 1688, with Order from his Maſter to facilitate their Journey to <hi>China;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Dutch</hi> Reſident hinder'd it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derhand, by informing the <hi>Muſcovites,</hi> that among the Twelve Jeſuits were Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Avril</hi> and <hi>Beuvolier, Frenchmen,</hi> which the Moſt Chriſtian King had ſent thither to diſcover the way by Land to <hi>China.</hi> This made theſe Brutes declare
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:29503:68"/>
to the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Envoy, That he might take His Maſter's Subjects with him into <hi>Perſia;</hi> but for the <hi>French,</hi> whoſe King had lately affronted the <hi>Czar</hi>'s Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, they could ſhew 'em no other Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, than ſend them back the way they came: At their Return the King of <hi>Poland</hi> took care to convey them ſafe to <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> but in all likelihood, when the King of <hi>France</hi> has made a Peace, he will force the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> to ſuffer his Subjects to paſs through their Country, and ſettle a Trade that way to <hi>China.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:29503:69"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:29503:69"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
