<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dr. Daniel Featley revived, or, The faithfull shepheard a sermon preached at the consecration of three bishops, the lords elect of Oxford, Bristoll, and Chester, in His Graces chappell at Lambeth, May, 9, 1619 / by ... Daniell Featley ... ; and now reprinted at the sole charge of George Vineing ...</title>
            <author>Featley, Daniel, 1582-1645.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-08">2004-08 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41006</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F580</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5460</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12580774</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12580774</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63740</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A41006)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63740)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 960:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Dr. Daniel Featley revived, or, The faithfull shepheard a sermon preached at the consecration of three bishops, the lords elect of Oxford, Bristoll, and Chester, in His Graces chappell at Lambeth, May, 9, 1619 / by ... Daniell Featley ... ; and now reprinted at the sole charge of George Vineing ...</title>
                  <author>Featley, Daniel, 1582-1645.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[23] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consecration of bishops --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-01</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63740:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63740:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> DANIEL FEATLEY <hi>revived.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR THE
FAITHFULL
SHEPHEARD.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached at the Consecration of
three Bishops, the Lords Elect of <hi>Oxford, Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoll,</hi>
and <hi>Chester,</hi> in his Graces Chappell at
<hi>Lambeth, May,</hi> 9. 1619.</p>
            <p>By that most Learned Pillar of our Church
<hi>Daniell Featley</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> in Divinity, Rector of <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi>
and <hi>Acton,</hi> Provost of <hi>Chelsey-Colledge,</hi> and
Chaplain in ordinary to his late Majesty. Unto
whom is Dedicated his large Volume <hi>Clavis
Mystica.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now Reprinted at the sole charge of <hi>George
Vineing,</hi> sometimes Servant to the right Honourable
<hi>Henry</hi> Earl of <hi>Manchester,</hi> Lord Privy
Seal, Deceased.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed in the Yeer, 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:63740:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63740:2"/>
            <head>To the Courteous Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HErein is shewn the Originall and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of Bishops and the singular union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
Regall, and Episcopall right and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority:
drawn from Constantine, after the
Church begun to have a little vigor against
the persecuting Arians. And because the
works of this famous Author should be
had in Endlesse remembrance by all Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants,
as he is and ever will be, to the terror
of all Papists. And if any shall demand why I
the Reprinter should take upon me to publish
this famous Sermon: my answer is as ready
as true, (because; for the sincere love that I
bear unto the truth; and the Endlesse true
love that I owe unto my Deceased spirituall
Father, who begat me in 1624. out of blinde
Popery from dumb'd and dead Idols; and
brought me into the clear light, to serve the
true and living God) that he may have
<pb facs="tcp:63740:3"/>
glory by it, and every Reader the benefit of it:
I have thought no time so seasonable, nor
none of all the Authors works so sutable as
this small volume is, that all those who never
knew his person, much lesse were conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant
with him, or never read him in his large
field of his manifold unparallel'd works, may
herein have a most sweet taste of his worth,
which may make them desirous to know him
more in his larger works: so this small piece
is to inform the ignorant, to reforme the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinate,
to conform the moderate: and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm
all to communicate in the Church of God.
That all Christians may so do, is the hearty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires
and daily prayers, of the meanest of the
Sons of the Church.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. V.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:63740:3"/>
            <head>THE
FAITHFULL
SHEPHEARD.</head>
            <head type="sub">A Sermon Preached at the Consecration of
three Bishops, the Lords Elect of Oxford, Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoll,
and Chester, in his Graces Chappell
at Lambeth, May 9. 1619.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 PET: 5. 2, 3, 4.</bibl>
               <q>Feed the flock of God which is among you, taking the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight
thereof, not by constraint, but willingly: not for fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
lucre, but of a ready mind: not as being Lords over
Gods heritage, but being ensamples to the flock. And when
the chief shepheard shall appear, you shall receive a Crown
of glory that fadeth not away.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>
               <salute>Most Reverend, Right Honourable, Right reverend, Right worshipfull, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Rchilocus</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Arist. R<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. c. 2.</note> sharpning his quill, and dipping
it in gall against <hi>Licambes;</hi> that his satiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
invectives might be more <hi>poignant,</hi> put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
the pen in <hi>Archilocrus</hi> his fathers hand,
and by an elegant <hi>prosopopeia</hi> maketh him
upbraid his sonne with those errors and
vices, which it was not fit that any but his father should in
such sort rip up. And<note n="b" place="margin">Orat. pro M. Coeli<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Tully</hi> being to read a lecture of
<pb facs="tcp:63740:4"/>
gravity and modesty to <hi>Clodia,</hi> which became not his yeers
or condition, raiseth up, as it were, from the grave, her old
grandfather <hi>Appius Caecus,</hi> and out of his mouth delivereth
a sage and fatherly admonition to her. In like manner
(Right Reverend) receiving the charge from you to give
the charge unto you at this present, and being over-ruled
by authority to speak something of the eminent autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
and sacred dignity into which ye are now to be
<hi>invested;</hi> I have brought upon this holy stage the first of
your ranke, and auncientest of your Apostolical order, to
admonish you with authority both of your general calling,
as Pastours set over Christs flocke; and your speciall,
as Bishops set over the Pastours themselves: That in
the former words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>feed;</hi> this in the latter, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<hi>bishoping,</hi> or taking the over-sight of them. Both
they are to perform,
<list>
                  <item>1 Not by constraint.</item>
                  <item>2 Not for lucre.</item>
                  <item>3 Not with pride.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>1 Not by constraint: constraint standeth not with the
dignity of the Apostles successors.</p>
            <p>2. Not for filthy lucre: filthy lucre sorts not with Gods
Priests.</p>
            <p>3 Not in, or with Lord-like pride: Lord-like pride com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth
not with the humility of Christs Ministers.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Tully</hi> the aged wrote to <hi>Cato</hi> the ancient, of old age;
so in the words of my text <hi>Peter</hi> the <hi>Elder</hi> writeth to
<hi>Elders,</hi> of the calling, life and reward of <hi>Elders</hi> in the
Church of God.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Their function is feeding, and overlooking Christs
flock, enjoyned, ver. 2.</item>
               <item>2 Their life is to be a pattern of all vertue, drawn
ver. 3.</item>
               <item>3 Their reward is a Crowne of glory, set before
them ver. 4.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:63740:4"/>
               <item>1 Their function <hi>sacred,</hi> answerable to their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
which is <hi>divine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 Their life <hi>exemplary,</hi> answerable to their fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
which is <hi>sacred.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 Their reward, <hi>exceeding great,</hi> answerable to
the eminency of the one, and excellency of the
other.</item>
            </list>
            <p>May it please you therefore to observe out of the words,
<list>
                  <item>1 For your instruction, what your function <hi>is.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 For correction, what your life <hi>should be.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 For comfort, what your reward <hi>shall be.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>As the costly<note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 28. 14.</note> ornaments of <hi>Aaron</hi> were fastned to the
Ephod with <hi>golden chaines of writhen works,</hi> so all the parts
and points of the Apostles exhortation are artificially joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
and tyed together with excellent coherence, as it were
with <hi>chaines of gold.</hi> This chain thus I draw through them
all.<note place="margin">Feed.</note>
            </p>
            <p>1 There are some of the Ministery fitter to be fed and led
like sheep, than to feed or lead like shepheards; they are
hunger-starved themselves, having no better provision than
the Apostles had in the wildernenesse after Christs miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
feast,<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 14. 20.</note> 
               <hi>a few baskets full of broken meat.</hi> Saint<note n="e" place="margin">Tantae cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis sunt per quos nobis flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enta coelestia emanant, ut antea effun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere quam ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundi velint, loqui quam audire paratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, prompti docere quod nunquam di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicerunt. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi>
admireth at their Charity, saying, <hi>they by whom the
streams of heavenly doctrine flow to us, are of such superabun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant
charity, that they desire to empty themselves before they
are half full, nay many before they have any drop of saving
knowledge, and divine learning, most ready to deliver that
which they never received, and teach what they never learned.</hi>
Such a one was that<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lactant. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin. instit. l.</hi> 5. Cum coecus ipse esset, alios illuminate sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepit in se.</note> 
               <hi>Bithynian</hi> whom <hi>Lactantius</hi> taketh up
for taking upon him to cure dimme and dark eyes, when
himself was stark blind. I find nothing whereunto I may fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
resemble them, than to <hi>squibs</hi> or small <hi>fire-works,</hi> which
as soon as they take fire, never leave <hi>popping and shooting,
and making a hidious noise,</hi> till all the powder be spent: so
these having rammed a little stuffe together, and being <hi>kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:63740:5"/>
with blind <hi>zeal,</hi> never leave <hi>shooting and spitting fire</hi>
in the pulpit, as long as their poor <hi>provision</hi> lasteth. These
men howsoever they are lyable to many other exceptions,
yet all men will free them from the imputation which <hi>Felix</hi>
laid upon Saint <hi>Paul</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Act. 26. 24.</note> 
               <hi>much learning hath made thee mad.</hi>
And as secure are they from the danger of the <hi>killing letter,</hi>
as the Poet in his witty Epigram playeth upon an ignorant
Priest in time of Popery.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">Tho. Morus in epig.</note> Tu bene cavisti ne te ulla occidere possit</l>
                  <l>Litera, nam nota est litera nulla tibi.</l>
               </q>
Thou hast taken good care that the killing letter shall not
hurt thee, for thou knowest <hi>never a letter</hi> in the book. The
measures of the Sanctuary contained twice as much as the
common measures, the shekel of the Sanctuary weighed
down two other shekels; to shew us that the gifts of a Pastor
ought to carrie a <hi>double proportion</hi> to those of his flocke,
else he had need to be fed himself; and is not qualified for
this duty required in my text, in the first place, <hi>Feed</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2 Of those that are able to <hi>feed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The flock.</note> some <hi>feed</hi> themselves,
not their <hi>flock;</hi> like <hi>Varus,</hi> taxed by <hi>Velleius Paterculus,</hi>
who came poor into a rich Province, but went rich out of
the poor Province; making a very gainfull <hi>exchange,</hi> by
leaving them the poverty he brought with him, and taking
with him the wealth he found there. <hi>Feed</hi> yee not <hi>your selves</hi>
but the <hi>Flock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3 Of those that feed the <hi>Flock,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Of God.</note> some feed not Gods <hi>Flock</hi>
but Satans <hi>heard;</hi> teaching in <hi>Conventicles</hi> of Hereticks, or
Schismaticks. Waspes have their hives as well as Bees, and
Pirats have their Pilots as well as honest Merchants: be not
ye like them; feed not the droves of Satan or Antichrist,
but the <hi>Flock of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4 Of those that feed the Flock of God,<note place="margin">Among you.</note> some feed not the
Flock which is <hi>among them,</hi> they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops
in other mens Diocesses; they thrust their sickle into
anothers harvest, and <hi>discharge without a charge:</hi> they may
rightly say with the Spouse in the <hi>Canticles,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Cant. 1. 6</note> 
               <hi>They have
<pb facs="tcp:63740:5"/>
made me</hi> (or rather I have made my self) <hi>a keeper of vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards,
but mine own vineyard I have not kept.</hi> If the frogs
<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Plin nat. hist<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> l.</hi> 8. Ranae mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae sunt etiam nune in Sery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plio insula, eae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem alio tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flatae canunt, &amp;c.</note>
               <hi>Seryphus</hi> could speak they would claim kindred of these
men; for as those frogs in <hi>the Island where they are bred
are dumb, and make no noise at all, but carried to any other
Country, fall on singing or croaking, and never give over:</hi> so
these are <hi>silent</hi> and quiet in their own <hi>cures,</hi> but when they
are out of them none can be <hi>quiet</hi> for them: they who can
scarce afford a Sermon in a moneth at their own home, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
nothing of <hi>lecturing</hi> every day in the week abroad.</p>
            <p>5 Of those that <hi>feed the flock of God which is among them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Taking the over-sight thereof.</note>
that is, preach painefully and powerfully, some are not
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Overlookers; they that take the over-sight of
their flock, they have not an eye to their life and manners,
they never use the reine, or rather curbe of ecclesiasticall
discipline; forgetting that in the <hi>Arke of God,</hi> together
<hi>with the Table of the Testimony, and the Pot of Manna, the
Rod of</hi> Aaron <hi>that budded was laid up:</hi> and that where<note n="l" place="margin">Psal. 23. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>
compareth God to a shepheard, he maketh mention both
of his <hi>rod and staffe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>6 Of those that <hi>feed the flock of God that is amongst them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Not by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint.</note>
               <hi>and take the over-sight thereof,</hi> that is, both rule well, and
labour in the word, some deserve not the double honour,
because they do it <hi>by constraint,</hi> not wilingly, like those
Calves, and Bullocks, and Rams, that were pulled and
haled to the Altars of the heathen gods, wherewith<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Plin. l. 8. nat. hist. c.</hi> 45. Hoc quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> notatum est vitulos ad aras humeris homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num allatos, non fere litare nec alienâ ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiâ placari deos, nec tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hente se ab aris.</note> 
               <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi>
observeth that the Paynim deities were never pleased,
nor gave good successe to them which offred such sacrifice
unto them. Nature it self giveth a prerogative to that<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Plin. nat. hist. l. 1. c.</hi> 15. In omni melle quod per se fluit, ut mustum, ole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> quod appellatur acaeton, maxime laudabile est. <hi>Not for filthy lucre.</hi>
               </note> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
which drops out of the combe, before that which is
forced or squized out; and to that<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Plin. nat. hist. l. 12. c.</hi> 15. Inciduntur bis, sudant autem sponte priusquam incidantur stact<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n dictam.</note> oyle which sweats out
of the Myrrhe trees, issuing from thence of its own accord,
before that which runneth after pricking or incision. The
noblest pallate wine is made of that liquor of the grape
<pb facs="tcp:63740:6"/>
which spinneth out upon the smallest touch, without any
violent pressure.
<q>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Theog. gnom.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q>
            </p>
            <p>7 Of those that take the over-sight of the flock, <hi>not by
canstraint but willingly,</hi> some do it not freely, or of <hi>a ready
mind, but for filthy lucre.</hi> The Eccho taught by <hi>Erasmus,</hi>
rings this in the ears of the Laity, and they hear it briefe,
<hi>Quid venatur sacerdos?</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Plat. in Bon.</hi> 3. Re<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>verâ pace bonorum dicam, multi episcopatum desiderant, explendae avaritiae suae causa, non quo communi utilitati ut eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum exposcit officium &amp; nomen consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant: quaeritur enim quantum reddat episco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patus, non quot oves pascuae in eo <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>int.</note> 
               <hi>Platina</hi> giveth a
touch thereof in the life of Pope <hi>Goodface</hi> the third; the
first question is, after a man is chosen Pope, what is the
Bishoprick of <hi>Rome</hi> worth? Filthy lucre carrieth such an
ill savour with it, the precious oyntment of <hi>Aaron</hi> cannot
take away the smell thereof: Covetousness is a spot in any
coat, but a stain in the linnen Ephod: what so unfit? what
so incongruous? nay what so opprobrious and scandalous, as
for those who in scripture are stiled Angels, and should like
Angels, by continual meditations, and divine contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<hi>behold the face of God in heaven,</hi> to turne <hi>earth-wormes,</hi>
and lye and feed upon very muck? How dare they deliver
the holy Sacrament with those hands that have received
bribes? or are defiled with the price of Blood? or are foul
with telling their use-money? Holinesse (which of all other
most befitteth our sacred calling) in the Greeke implyeth a
contradiction to earthlinesse: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which we render holy,
is all one in that language as unearthly. If a glasse be soy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
with dust, or besmeared with dirt, it reflecteth no image
at all: in like manner if the minde be soyled with the dust
of earthlinesse, the image of God cannot appeare in it; the
fancie of such a man will represent no spirituall forme, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
no divine or heavenly imaginations. If we seeke our
own and not the things that are Jesus Christs, the Goods
not the good of our flock, we lose the first letter of our
name in the Prophet<note n="r" place="margin">Ezek. 3. 17. Sonne of man, I have made thee a watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</note> 
               <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> and of <hi>speculatores</hi> become
<hi>peculatores,</hi> and are not to be termed <hi>praedicatores</hi> but <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datores.</hi>
But I will not make this blot bigger by unskilfully
going about to take it out.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:63740:6"/>
            <p>8 Of those that <hi>feed,</hi> and <hi>take the over-sight of Gods flock
that is among them, not by constraint, but willingly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Not as Lords.</note> 
               <hi>not for
filthy lucre, but of a ready mind,</hi> some carry themselves, <hi>like
Lords over the flock, not as ensamples to their flock,</hi> they go
in &amp; out before them in a lordly gate, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="s" place="margin">Concil. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thag. 4. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. fumosus seculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>typhus.</note>
in swelling pride, not in exemplary humillty, seeking rather
to <hi>over-rule them</hi> with terror and violence, then <hi>rule over
them</hi> with the spirit of meekness. These though they are
put up in the highest forme, yet have not learned the first
lesson in the schoole of Christianity,<note n="t" place="margin">Mat. 11. 29.</note> 
               <hi>to be meeke and lowly
in heart:</hi> neither understand they that divine graces, which
are the plants of Paradise, are like to the tree in the Poet
that beare golden boughes.
<q>
                  <l>—<note n="u" place="margin">Virg. Aen. 6.</note> Quae quantum vertice ad auras</l>
                  <l>Aetheras tantum, radice in Tartara tendit.</l>
               </q>
whose root was just somuch beneath the earth as the top
was in height above it. The higher Gods Saint grow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
to perfection, the deeper they take root downward
in humility, considering that they have nothing of their
own, but sin; and what a foolish and impious sin of pride is
it, to be proud of sin? He that presumes on his own strength,
saith holy <hi>Austine,</hi> is conquered before he fight. To repose
trust in our selves, saith<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern. serm. 20. in vigil. nat. dom.</hi> Sibimet ipse fidere non, fidei sed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiae est, nec confidentiae sed diffidentiae magis, in semetipso ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere fiduciam.</note> 
               <hi>Bernard,</hi> is not of faith, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiousnesse,
neither breeds it true confidence, but diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.
To be proud of knowledge, is to be blind with
light: to be proud of vertue is to poyson himself with the
Antidote: and to be proud of authority, is to make his
rise his downfall, and his ladder his ruine. It is the darke
soyle that giveth the Diamond its brightest luster: it is the
humble and low, and obscure conceit of our own worth
that giveth luster and grace to all our vertues and perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
if we have any; <hi>Moses</hi> glory was the greater because
his face shined, and he knew not of it.</p>
            <p>Thus have I <hi>numbred</hi> unto you the <hi>severall linkes</hi> of the
Apostles golden <hi>chaine</hi> of instructions for Pastors, now
<pb facs="tcp:63740:7"/>
let us gather them together in a narrow roome.</p>
            <p>1 Be not such as need to be fed but are able and willing
to <hi>feed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2 Feed not your selves but the <hi>flock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3 Feed not the flock or droves of Antichrist, but the
flock of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4 Feed the flock of God, not out of your charge, or
without you, but the flock of God <hi>which is among you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5 Content not your selves with feeding them onely with
the word and Sacrament, but <hi>over-looke them also,</hi> have an
eye to their manners.</p>
            <p>6 Doe this not constrainedly, but <hi>willingly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>7 Not out of private respects, but <hi>freely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>8 Not proudly but <hi>humbly,</hi> not to shew your authority o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
the flock, but to set before them an ensample in your
selves of humility, meekness, temperance, patience, and all
other vertues.</p>
            <p>Thus feed the flock of God that is among you, thus rule
those whom you feed, thus carry your selves towards those
whom you rule, thus give good ensample in your carriage;
and when the chief Shepheard and Bishop of your souls
Christ Jesus shall appear, you shall receive instead of a Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sier
a Scepter, of a Miter a Crown, of a Diocesse upon earth a
Kingdom in heaven.</p>
            <p>You see I have a large and plentifull field before me, yet
I purpose at this time to follow the example of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles,
<note n="x" place="margin">Matth: 12. 1.</note>who as they passed through the corn field, <hi>plucked
only an ear or two, and rubbed them in their hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To rub the first ear,</hi> that you may see what <hi>grain</hi> it yeeld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.
To feed, saith<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>l. 1. de Rom. pont.</hi> c. 15. In scripturis pascere passim accipitur pro regere, ut Psal. 2. reges cos in virgâ ferreâ in Heb. est pasce <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>&amp; Apoc.</hi> 2: 27. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> signifieth to rule with
princely authority, to sway the scepter as a spiritual Prince
over Christs flock; and to this purpose he alledgeth that
text in the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> 2. 27. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> he shall feed (or rule)
them with a <hi>rod of iron,</hi> hard feeding for Christs sheep;
he had need to have an <hi>Estridge</hi>'s stomack that can digest
this interpretation here. Feed, not over-ruling <hi>ver.</hi> 3. that
is, over-rule them, not feeding: this is as natural an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation
<pb facs="tcp:63740:7"/>
of this Scripture, as the glosse upon the word
<hi>statuimus</hi> in the Canon law, <hi>id est, abrogamus,</hi> or <hi>statuimus
quod non;</hi> we enact, that is, we abrogate; we command,
that is, we forbid; we appoint this, that is, we appoint that
this shall not be. If this be a right interpretation of this
place, and the other parallel to it in Saint<note n="z" place="margin">Ioh. 20. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn,</hi> then St.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bernard. de considerat. ad Eugen. l.</hi> 2. I ergo tu &amp; tibi usurpare aude aut dominans apostolatum, autapostolicus dominatum, &amp;c.</note>
               <hi>Bernard</hi> was in the wrong, for he infers the clean con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
from it; and which is most <hi>considerable,</hi> in a book of
consideration dedicated to the Pope himself: <hi>Peter could
not give thee that which he had not, what he had, that he gave
thee, care over the Churches: but did he not also give thee
dominion? heare what himself saith, not as being Lords over
Gods heritage, but being made examples to the flock: least a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
man should think that this was spoken onely in humility,
and not in truth, it is the voice of the Lord in the Gospel,
Kings of the Nations beare rule over them, but it shall not be
so with you; it is plain that Lord-like dominion is forbidden
to the Apostles: goe too therefore now, and assume to thy self
if thou dare, either the office of an Apostle, if thou be a Lord,
or Lord-like dominion if thou be an Apostle.</hi> Howbeit I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
not that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here used, sometimes signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
to rule with Princely authority, and Lord-like com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
both in Scriptures and prophane Writers: as
<note n="a" place="margin">Hom l<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.</note>
               <hi>Homer</hi> stileth King <hi>Agamemnon</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard
of the people:</hi> so God himself calleth <hi>Cyrus</hi> his<note n="b" place="margin">Esay 44. 28. That saith of Cyrus, he is my shepheard</note> 
               <hi>Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard;</hi>
and which is very observable, <hi>Cyrus</hi> as if he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
notice of this name imposed by God upon him before
his birth, was wont usually to say,<note n="c" place="margin">Xen. Cyr. paed. l. 8. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>That a good Prince was
like a good Shepheard, who can by no other means grow rich,
than by making his flock to thrive under him;</hi> the prosperity
of the subject is not onely the honour but the wealth also
of the Prince. All this maketh nothing for the Popes <hi>triple
Crowne,</hi> to which he layeth claime by vertue of Christs
<hi>threefold pasce,</hi> or <hi>feed (Ioh.</hi> 21. 15, 16, 17.) for neither
doth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> originally, or properly, nor usually signifie
<hi>to reigne as a King,</hi> especially when <hi>oves meae,</hi> or <hi>grex domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,
my sheep,</hi> or <hi>the flock of God</hi> is construed with it; nor can
<pb facs="tcp:63740:8"/>
it be so taken here, or <hi>Ioh.</hi> 21. as the light of texts set toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
reflecting one upon the other will clear the point.
For that which Christ enjoyneth <hi>Peter, Ioh.</hi> 21. that <hi>Peter</hi>
here enjoyneth all Elders: the words of the charge are the
same, <hi>Feed my sheep,</hi> there; <hi>Feed the flock of God,</hi> here. But
Saint <hi>Peter</hi> enjoyneth not all Elders in these words to rule
with soveraigne authority as Kings over the whole flock, or
as Lords over their own peculiar: for this he expressely
forbiddeth, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. therefore to usurpe authority over the
whole Church, or to domineere over any part thereof, is
not to feed according to Christs charge to Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> or
Saint <hi>Peters</hi> to all Elders. What is it then? if you have
reference to the Etomology <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to
feed, as the word imports in the original, is to reside upon
our cure, or abide with our flock, where the spouse is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
to seeke Christ,<note n="d" place="margin">Cant. 1. 8.</note> 
               <hi>go thy way forth to the footsteps
of the flock.</hi> And indeed where should the Sentinel be but
upon his watch tower? Where the Pilot but at the sterne?
where the intelligence but at his orbe? where the Sun but
within his ecliptick line? where the candle but in the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-stick?
where the diamond but in the ring? where the
shepherd but among his flock? whom he is to feed, for
whom he is to provide, of whom he is to take the over-sight,
to whom he ought to be an example; which he cannot be if
he never be in their sight. But because this observation is
grounded only upon the Etymology, I will lay no more
<hi>stresse</hi> upon it. The proper and full signification of the
word is, <hi>pastorum agere,</hi> to play the good shepherd, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise
the function of a Pastor, which consisteth in three
things especially.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Docendo quid facere debeant.</item>
               <item>2 Orando ut facere possint.</item>
               <item>3 Increpando si non faciant.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:63740:8"/>
               <item>1 In teaching those of his flock what they ought
to do.</item>
               <item>2 In praying that they may do it.</item>
               <item>3 In reproving if they do it not.</item>
            </list>
            <p>All which may be reduced to a threefold feeding.
<list>
                  <item>1 With the Word, <hi>Ier.</hi> 3.</item>
                  <item>2 With the Sacraments,<note place="margin">Ier. 3. 15. I will give you pastors accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to mine own heart, that shall feede you with knowledg and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</note> 
                     <hi>Apoc. 2. &amp; Ioh.</hi> 6.</item>
                  <item>3 With the Rod, <hi>Micah</hi> 7. 14.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>To feed with the Word and Sacrament is the common
duty of all Pastors, but to feed with the rod is reserved to
Bishops: they are <hi>Seraphims,</hi> holding the spiritul <hi>sword of
excommunication</hi> in their hands, <hi>to guard the tree of life:</hi>
whose speciall office, and eminent degree in the Church is
implied in the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which the vulgar latine
rendreth <hi>providentes,</hi> but Saint<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. de civ. l 19. c.</hi> 19. Supervidentes appellantur, ut intelligant se non esse episcopos qui praeesse dilex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erint, non prodesse.</note> 
               <hi>Augustine</hi> more agreeable
to the Etymology, <hi>supervidentes,</hi> super-visors, or super-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendents.
Yet this is but a generall notation of the name;
every Bishop is a super-visour or over-seer, but every super-visour
is not a Bishop. The Lacedaemonian Magistrates were
called <hi>Epori,</hi> which is an equivalent stile to <hi>Episcopi:</hi> and
<note n="f" place="margin">Euseb. vit. Constant. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>Constantine</hi> the great spake as truly as piously to his Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops;
Yee reverend Fathers are Bishops of them that are
within the Church, but I of them that are out of the Church:
where your pastoral staffe is too short, I will <hi>piece</hi> it out and
lengthen it with my scepter. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the most pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
and restrained signification is to exercise Episcopal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
(or perform the office of a Bishop) which consisteth,
in two things:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 In ordaining.</item>
               <item>2 Ordering.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>1 Giving orders.</item>
               <item>2 Keeping order.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:63740:9"/>
Saint <hi>Paul</hi> giveth<note n="g" place="margin">Tit. 1. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Titus</hi> both in charge: <hi>for this cause
I left thee in Crete, to ordain Elders in every Church,</hi> there is
the first, to wit, ordination; and to <hi>set in order things that
are wanting,</hi> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to correct things out of order,</hi>
there is the second viz. ordering or reformation. <hi>Timothy</hi>
likewise the first Consecrated Bishop of <hi>Ephesus</hi> is put in
mind of these branches of his Episcopal function: of the first,
<note n="h" place="margin">1 Tim 5. 22. <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.</note>
               <hi>Lay hands suddenly on no man:</hi> of the second, <hi>Against an
Elder receive not an accusation but under two or three wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses;</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Ve<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 20.</note>
               <hi>Them that sinne rebuke before all, that others also
may fear. Be not</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">ver. 22.</note> 
               <hi>partaker of any mans sinnes,</hi> to wit, by
not censuring or punishing them. These two offices to be
most necessary in the Church, every mans reason and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
experience will inform us. For how shall we have Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters
at all without Ordination? and how shall we have
good Ministers or people without visitation? Now for Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters
or Ministers, who are equal in degree to exercise au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
one over the other, and lay hands upon themselves,
and so to become their own ghostly Fathers, is to make
order it self a <hi>confusion.</hi> Therefore God in the law put a
difference between the Priests and Levits: and Christ in
the Gospel between the Apostles and Disciples; and the
Apostles after Christs death between Bishops and Elders.
Which the primitive Church kept so religiously, that to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose
it in practise was accounted no lesse them<note n="l" place="margin">Act. Concil. 1. Chalced. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> sacriledge;
in doctrine, flat heresie. The first that I find ever to have
gone about to break down the partition wall between Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops
and Presbyters, was <hi>Aerius,</hi> a man like this name,
was <hi>light</hi> and aery, easily carried away with the winde of
ambition. For as<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiph haeres.</hi> 71. Cum epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copatus spe excidisset Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stathiopost ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitus ut se consolaretur hanc haeresem excogitavit. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Apiphanius</hi> writeth, standing for a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoprick,
and missing it, he invented this heresie to comfort
himself; and because he could not raise up himself to the
high rank of Bishops, he sought to pull them down to his
lower rank of Elders. <hi>What difference, saith he, is there
between a Bishop and Priest? none at all, their order, and
honour, and dignity, is one and the self-same.</hi> But for this
his sawcy malepartnesse he felt the smart of the <hi>Crosier staffe,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:63740:9"/>
and for <hi>ranking</hi> Bishops among Presbyters or Elders, he was
himself <hi>ranked</hi> among hereticks. God who made greater
and lesser lights in the firmament, and set Angels in ranks
one above another, hath erected an<note n="*" place="margin">See King <hi>James</hi> his Cyg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nea Cantio. <hi>Bilson</hi> his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual govern<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment.</note> Hierarchy upon earth:
which as he hath ever yet, so I hope he still will to the end
of the world establish and support and propagate it, as it
hath wonderfully supported and propagated the Church.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bancroft</hi> his survey of the holy pretended discipline, c. de episc.</note>
The bounds thereof extended by the preaching, and kept
by the Government of Bishops; the Hereticks and Schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks
in all ages suppressed by Councels and Synods of
Bishops;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Downam</hi> his sermon at the consecration of the Bishop of Bath &amp; Wells. <hi>Andrew</hi> opus posthum.</note> the Rubricks of Ecclesiastical Kalendars coloured
with the blood of so many martyred Bishops, are sufficient
evidence thereof. And as the Church soon after her first
plantation exceedingly prospered under the shade of <hi>Iames</hi>
Bishop of Hierusalem, <hi>Titus</hi> of Crete, <hi>Timothy</hi> of Ephesus,
<hi>Mark</hi> of Alexandria, <hi>Ignatius</hi> of Antioch, <hi>Antipas</hi> of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamus,
<hi>Polycarpe</hi> of Smyrna,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hallier</hi> defenc. ecclesiast. hier. l. 1.</note> and divers others ordained
by the Apostles, or their immediate successors; and in suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
ages received her best sap and nourishment from
the Greek and Latine Fathers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aurelius</hi> vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciae censurae tit. 3. de epis. &amp; curatis.</note> who for the most part were
Bishops: so<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Beza de grad. Min. evang. cap. 18:</hi> Non tantum insignes Dei martyres, sed etiam prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantissimos doctores &amp; pastore.</note> 
               <hi>Beza</hi> himself acknowledgeth it to have been
the <hi>singular happinesse of the Church of England, which he
prayeth may be perpetual, that this reverend and sacred or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
hath yeelded not only famous Martyrs, but also most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
Doctors and Pastors,</hi> As the Poet blazing the vertues
of the Emperour then reigning, said,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">Mart. epig. l. 1.</note> Te volet invictus pro libertate Camillus.</l>
                  <l>Si Cato redd<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tur, Caesarianus erit.</l>
               </q>
               <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Camillus</hi> and <hi>Cato,</hi> the greatest sticklers for the
liberty of the Commonwealth, if they were now alive would
turn Royalists: so we may truly affirm that the greatest ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
of Episcopal Jurisdiction, could not but approve of such
Bishops as now sit at the stern in our Church. And what if
all are not such? must the whole order suffer for their
sake?
<pb facs="tcp:63740:10"/>
               <q>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Ovid. l. 1. de <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rt.</note> Desine paucorum diffundere crimen in omnes.</q>
lay not upon all the fault of some. If one or other bud of
<hi>Aarons rod,</hi> the Bishoprick of Rome and the dependants
thereon, are turned into serpents, shall the whole rod be
cast out of the Arke, and <hi>Ionah</hi>'s <hi>gourd</hi> put in the place
thereof? I mean the new sprung up <hi>mushrome,</hi> the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of lay Elders; <hi>Elders</hi> whereof no <hi>Elder</hi> age of the
Church ever took notice, and younger cannot tell yet how
to <hi>Christen</hi> them: because they are a kind of epicoens, of
both genders, plant-animals, partly Animals, partly plants<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
like a sort of Nuns at <hi>Bruxels,</hi> partly regular, partly secular;
in the morning wearing the cowles and habit of Recluses,
in the afternoon the feathers and other attire of Gallants.
For they are Clergy-laickes, and Lay-clerkes: of their
clergy they are, for they together with their Ministers ordain
Ministers, and inflict Ecclesiastical censures; and yet laicks
they are, for they may not preach nor baptize. Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
they are, for they bear rule in the Church; yet Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
they are not, for they may receive no maintenance
from the Church. They are the <hi>Elders that rule well,</hi> and
<hi>labour,</hi> not in <hi>the word,</hi> for such they will have intimated
by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> yet the honour which their own Interpreters
there expound honourable maintenance, is not due unto
them. Spare me Men, Fathers, and Brethren, if I spare not
them who go about to bereave us of our spiritual Fathers,
<hi>qui saeviunt in plagas &amp; vulnera ecclesiae,</hi> who seek to ruine
the ruines, and spoile the very spoiles of Ecclesiastical dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
and distinction left among us. To place such <hi>Bats</hi> as
these, rather mice than birds, must Christs Apostles and
their successors be displaced, and all ranks of Ecclesiasticall
order confounded: is there any justice in this, to break all
Crosier staves, and tread all Miters under foot, and teare
all Rochets in pieces.
<q>Vnius obnoxam &amp; furias Ajacis Oilei.</q>
               <pb facs="tcp:63740:10"/>
for the usurpation and tyranny of one Bishop the Pope of
Rome? By this reason take away the Reverend order of
the Apostles for <hi>Iudas</hi> sake, take away the sacred order of
Prophets for <hi>Balaams</hi> sake, take away the soveraigne order
of Princes for <hi>Iulians</hi> sake, take away the glorious orbs of
stars for the stars sake called<note n="q" place="margin">Apoc. 8. 11.</note> 
               <hi>wormwood</hi> in the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi>
nay take away the highest regiment of Angels for <hi>Lucifers</hi>
sake, &amp; the rest of his faction, sometime in the highest order
in heaven, but now <hi>reserved in chaines of darknesse till the
great day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This may suffice to be spoken of, and for your calling:
<hi>two</hi> words of the <hi>two</hi> dutie; implyed in the words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>feed</hi> and <hi>take the over-sight.</hi> You are <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors</hi>
and <hi>Bishops,</hi> make good your titles, feed as Pastors, take
the over-sight of your Diocesse as Bishops. The three or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
in the Church, Bishops, Priests, and Deacons, resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
the three faculties of the soule, the vegetative, sensitive,
and reasonable. For as the sensitive faculty includeth the
vegetative, <hi>&amp; aliquid amplius</hi> and somewhat more, to wit,
sense; and the reasonable implyeth the sensitive, <hi>&amp; aliquid
amplius</hi> and somewhat more, to wit, reason; for a Priest
implyeth a Deacon, <hi>&amp; aliquid amplius;</hi> and a Bishop im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth
a Priest, <hi>&amp; aliquid amplius.</hi> Yee are (my Lords)
both Bishops and Priests, and as you are invested into a
double honour, so you have a double charge: as Bishops
you are to <hi>rule well;</hi> as Priests to <hi>labour in the word;</hi> as
Priests you are to preach, as Bishops to ordain Priests, and
countenance Preachers: as Priests you are to smite simony
and sacriledge, schisme and heresie, impurity and impiety,
<hi>gladio oris, with the sword of your mouth;</hi> as Bishops, <hi>ore
gladii, with the mouth,</hi> that is, <hi>the edge of the sword,</hi> the
sword of ecclesiastical censures which Christ hath put into
your hand: bear not this sword in vain, be not pertakers
of the sinnes of any of the Clergy, or <hi>bribes</hi> of the laity; use
this your sword for, not against the Church.
<q>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">V<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Aen. 4.</note> Non hos quaesitum munus in usus.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:63740:11"/>
Hold not too strict a hand over your too much oppressed
Clergy; let it not be said of the clergy of your Diocesse, as it
was said of the Roman souldiers under <hi>Severus,</hi> that they
were more affraid of their Captain then of the enemy. For as
St. <hi>Paul</hi> speaketh to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> if I make you sad who
shall comfort you? so I may say to you, if you dishearten poor
Ministers who shal comfort them, or stand for them? the laity?
no, they take two much of the nature of the stone, from
whence they have their name given them,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> signifieth people, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> stone.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: if a
faithful Minister of Jesus Christ, if a diligent preacher, that
spends all his Oyle and Week, his body and soul to give
them light, sue but for his dues, especially if he mutter but
a word against their great <hi>Diana,</hi> their <hi>sacrilegious customes,</hi>
which oft deprive the Ministers of the Gospel of nine parts
of the Tenth, and leave them but <hi>decimam decimae,</hi> the tenth
of the tenth: they will all fall upon him, and unlesse your
power and authority relieve him, grind him to powder.
They use their godly Preachers, whom the world cannot
parallel, as the Hawk in <hi>Hesiod</hi> dealt with the melodious
Nightingale,<note n="s" place="margin">Hesiod. op. &amp; <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ies, l. 1.</note> they plum them and devour them, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
although they be the sweetest singers of Israel. Many
of them after they have spent their strength in preaching in
<hi>season and out of season,</hi> catechizing and lecturing on the
Lords day, and on the week dayes, may truly say as <hi>Syne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sius</hi>
sometimes complained that they carried nothing away
from their parishes or cures, but <hi>bonam conscientiam &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam
valetudinem,</hi> a good conscience, and an ill crazed body.</p>
            <p>No more of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, taking the over-sight: but a
word of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>feed,</hi> lest whilest I exhort you to <hi>feed,</hi> I
detain you from better <hi>feeding, viz.</hi> upon the blessed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament
now set before you. As in Churches and Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens
Halls, where there hang great Candlesticks with many
branches, the lights are first let down to be tinded, and when
they are fully lighted, then they are drawn up by degrees
to give light to the whole room: so our Church first send<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
her sweet wax lights, made and formed in private
schools, down to the Universities to be tinded, and when
<pb facs="tcp:63740:11"/>
they are fully enlightned with knowledge, then draweth
them up by degrees, first to pastoral charges, then to digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
Deanaries, and Bishopricks; not that then they should
be put out, but to the end that as they are set higher they
should give more light. You are, Right Reverend, the <hi>sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
Trumpet of Zion,</hi> whom God lifteth up on high that you
may sound the louder and <hi>shriller,</hi> as bells are hung higher
in the steeple, that they may be heard further. Let it be
never said of you as it was of <hi>Saul,</hi> that <hi>when he came to
the high places he made an end of prophecying.</hi> The more
God hath honoured you, the more you ought to honour
him; the higher Christ hath preferred you, the more you
ought to love him, and shew this your love by your treble
diligence in feeding his sheep. To which end these words,
<hi>Peter lovest thou me? feed my sheep,</hi> &amp;c. are by the order of
our Church appointed to be read for the Gospell at your
consecration. I grant you feed many ways: you feed when
you appoint pastors to feed, you feed when you instruct them
how to feed, you feed when you censure them for not feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
their flocks, or not feeding them with wholesome food,
you feed in a Synode when you make good Canons, you
feed in your visitations when you encourage good Ministers,
and reform abuses in the Church; lastly, you feed at your
tables when you keep good hospitality. And after all these
manners the Apostle; and ancient Fathers fed; yet they
thought themselves in danger of a <hi>vae,</hi> or curse if they fed
not by preaching the Gospel in their own persons. <hi>Wo be to
me,</hi> saith St.<note n="t" place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Paul, if I preach not the Gospel.</hi> Saint <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi>
was a Bishop himselfe, and that of a very large and
troublesome Diocesse (for he was Pope of Rome) yet he
deeply chargeth Bishops with this duity, thus inferring upon
Christs words to <hi>Peter, lovest thou me? feed, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Greg in verb. evang. secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Iohan.</hi> Si dilectionis ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentum est cura pastora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, quisquis virtutibus pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens gregem Dei renuit pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scere, summum pastorem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincitur non amare.</note> 
               <hi>If care
and diligence in a pastoral charge be an argument, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
evidence of the love we bear to Christ, whosoever furnish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
with gift, and abilities thereunto, refuseth to feed Christs
flock, is to be taken</hi> pro convicto, <hi>that he bears no good affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
to the chief Pastor and Bishop of our souls.</hi> If the love of
<pb facs="tcp:63740:12"/>
Christ constrained us not to <hi>stirre up the grace of God in us,</hi>
which we have received by imposition of hands, and even
like lambes to spend our selves to give light to our flockes,
yet methinks the excellency of this function should inflame
us thereunto. Where can we fix our thoughts with more
delight and contentment than upon heaven and heavenly
objects? how can we put our tougues to a better use than
to declare the word of life? to preach the Gospell of the
Kingdome? to sound out our makers praises? how can our
hands be better employed than about the seales of grace?
Hear Saint<note n="*" place="margin">Chrysost. ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. 1. in Matth</note> 
               <hi>Chrysostome</hi> open his golden mouth, and weigh
his words in the scales of the sanctuary; <hi>Seest thou not,</hi> saith
he, <hi>how thine eyes water whilst thou stayest in the smoak, but
are cleared and refreshed if thou go out into the open ayre, or
walkest a turn in a pleasant garden? so the eye of our mind is
cleared, and our spirituall senses much revived by walking in
the garden of holy Scriptures, and smelling to the flowers of
Paradise; but if we run about in the smoak,</hi> that is, <hi>busie our
selves about earthly affairs, we shall shed many a tear, and be
in danger of quite loosing our sight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will conclude, and briefly represent all the principall
points of the Apostles exhortation to your view in one type
of the law. In the Ark of the covenant there was <hi>the rod
of</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 24. 25.</note> 
               <hi>Aaron that budded, and about it a Crown of gold.</hi> By
the <hi>rod of Aaron</hi> you easily apprehend the Priests office or
pastoral charge: the buds of this rod, or parts of this charge
are two, <hi>feeding and overseeing;</hi> which ought to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
not by constraint, but willingly, as the buds were not
drawn out of <hi>Aarons</hi> rod, but <hi>put forth</hi> of their own accord.
And herein we are not to respect our own good, but the
good of our flock: we must do nothing for filthy lucre, but
of a free mind to benefit others, as the rod of <hi>Aaron</hi> bare
not blossomes or fruit to, or for it self, but to, and for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.
By the fruits of <hi>Aarons</hi> rod you may understand the
good life of a faithful Pastor, who is to be an example to
his flock; this fruit enclineth him to true humility oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site
to Lord-like pride, as the fruit of a tree weigheth the
<pb facs="tcp:63740:12"/>
branches down to the earth. Lastly, by the <hi>Crowne above
the rod, and round about the Ark,</hi> is represented the reward
of a faithful Shepheard and vigilant Bishop<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> You have the
embleme of your office, the word or <hi>Motto</hi> shall be <hi>Germi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net
virga Aaronis, Let the rod of Aaron blossome in your
mouth by preaching the word, and bud in your hands by the
exercise of Ecclesiasticall discipline, and bear fruit in your
lives by being ensamptes to your flock, and the crown above the
rod, and about the Ark shall be yours,</hi> as it is promised <hi>ver. 4.
And when the chief shepheard shall appear, you shall receive a
crown of glory that fadeth not away;</hi> 
               <q>Which God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
grant for the price of his Sonnes blood, to whom with
the holy Spirit be all honour, glory, praise, and thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving,
now and for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
