<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A friendly apology, in the behalf of the womans excellency together with some examples of women-worthies : as also the character of a virtuous and accomplished woman : wherein ladies of pleasure are taxed and admonished / written in verse by J. Golborne ...</title>
            <author>Golborne, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41370</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1009</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6976</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12143982</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12143982</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54895</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A41370)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54895)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 597:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A friendly apology, in the behalf of the womans excellency together with some examples of women-worthies : as also the character of a virtuous and accomplished woman : wherein ladies of pleasure are taxed and admonished / written in verse by J. Golborne ...</title>
                  <author>Golborne, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Mortlock ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Women --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54895:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54895:1"/>
            <p>A Friendly
APOLOGY,
In the behalf of the
Womans Excellency:
Together with ſome Examples of
<hi>Women-Worthies.</hi>
As alſo the <hi>Character</hi> of a <hi>Virtuous</hi>
and <hi>Accompliſhed Woman:</hi>
Wherein <hi>Ladies of Pleaſure</hi> are taxed
and admoniſhed.</p>
            <p>Written in Verſe by <hi>J. Golborne,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time
Fellow of <hi>Trinity</hi> Colledge
near <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Si Natura negat, facit admiratio verſum
Qualemcun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> poteſt.—</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed, for <hi>Henry Mortlock,</hi> and are
to be ſold at the Sign of the Phoenix
in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, and
at the White Hart in <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi>
Hall. 1674.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54895:2"/>
            <head>TO THE
Moſt Virtuous
AND
Pious LADY
M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>. Katharine Booth.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <l>SInce famed <hi>Laureates</hi> never durſt</l>
            <l>Adventure on the nobleſt Themes at firſt,</l>
            <l>But were ſo modeſt doubtfully to peep</l>
            <l>Out of their private <hi>Cells,</hi> and then to creep</l>
            <l>In arguments much lower, till well how</l>
            <l>To truſt their wings they knew, from bough to bough</l>
            <l>Of various ſubjects flutter'd, judging beſt</l>
            <l>So to attempt that danger might be leaſt,</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:54895:3"/>
Till arts had been more lib'ral thought, they might</l>
            <l>Not ſafely venture an <hi>Heroick</hi> flight.</l>
            <l>Pardon this boldneſs, that preſumes to try</l>
            <l>Firſt hand on piece of <hi>Curioſity;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Which better would deſerve the richeſt vein</l>
            <l>Of ſmooth conceipt, out of the pregnant brain</l>
            <l>Of one, to whom kind Nature firſt had been</l>
            <l>Of much more virtue than the <hi>Hippocrene.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>My fancy (not well vers'd when firſt put to't)</l>
            <l>Would not perſwaded be to ſtir a foot</l>
            <l>On other ſubjects; yet did freely run,</l>
            <l>That her due ſervice might in part be done</l>
            <l>Unto your ſex; and if ſhe limps, the fault</l>
            <l>She calls her own: <hi>lameneſs</hi> doth make her halt,</l>
            <l>You cauſe her move; and what is to expreſs</l>
            <l>Her <hi>gratitude,</hi> will make crime ſomewhat leſs.</l>
            <l>In this Eſſay, I have ſought to no <hi>Fairy,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Call'd Muſe, that keeps her wild haunts at <hi>Canary.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Your mind is ſober; nor durſt I think fit</l>
            <l>To offer you poor <hi>gathering</hi> of wit.</l>
            <l>You need not ſuch collection, which is more</l>
            <l>Fit for thoſe perſons, that in worth are poor.</l>
            <l>Grant very ſmall allowance: bate the Verſe</l>
            <l>That waited on your pious S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſters horſe:</l>
            <l>And charge not ſome choice ſentences which you</l>
            <l>Know well, to whom their ſervice beſt is due;</l>
            <l>And what is ſtoln will not amount to be</l>
            <l>Fit to be charg'd with <hi>Pettit-larceny.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Should I call women <hi>Deities,</hi> you'd be</l>
            <l>Diſpleaſed (Madam) with the blaſphemy:</l>
            <l>Or phraſe them nobler creatures than men are,</l>
            <l>You likewiſe might, condemn the flatterer.</l>
            <l>Should I paſs bounting Laſſes and the Jigs</l>
            <l>Uncivil, of the City-whirligigs;</l>
            <l>Their pride, their luxury, their antick dreſſes,</l>
            <l>Their bare necks, painted faces, and their treſſes,</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:54895:3"/>
Whereby they would enſnare their wanton tongues</l>
            <l>In loveſome Catches and laſcivious Songs;</l>
            <l>Their going unto <hi>Church,</hi> bringing no more</l>
            <l>From thence, than what new dreſſes Gallants wore;</l>
            <l>Frequenting Playes, leſt therein they ſhould do</l>
            <l>Too little, there becoming <hi>Actors</hi> too.</l>
            <l>I ſhould unworthily at leaſt ſuggeſt</l>
            <l>That you ſo little baſeneſs do deteſt</l>
            <l>Of ſhameleſs <hi>Hippia</hi>'s, as not to admit</l>
            <l>They ſhould be laſh'd by Scorpions of wit.</l>
            <l>Whereas I know you loath that hateful <hi>Crew</hi>
            </l>
            <l>That brag of breeding, brave, and fruitful too,</l>
            <l>Uſe broad words, and large liberties as ſeat</l>
            <l>Of gallantry, the way to become great-</l>
            <l>Belly'd, that they may bear their ſhameful ſin,</l>
            <l>And ſuffer plague of birth and lying in.</l>
            <l>Should I forget my <hi>Goſſip,</hi> that can tell</l>
            <l>How to turn over tongue a ſpic'd-cup well,</l>
            <l>With whoſe loud tittle tattle thoſe folks are</l>
            <l>Troubled, that deal not in ſuch peddling ware;</l>
            <l>But mind their own concerns, and do not pry</l>
            <l>Into concerns of the next family:</l>
            <l>Should I paſs her, whoſe ſpungy lungs, as ſayls</l>
            <l>Are ſwoln, but not when dry, with telling tales</l>
            <l>Of private merriments, ſcarce <hi>Civil</hi> jars</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Familiar</hi> talk, and of <hi>Domeſtick</hi> wars;</l>
            <l>Where will be next, and where was the laſt wedding,</l>
            <l>And all the pretty paſſages at bedding;</l>
            <l>How Madam <hi>Haſty</hi> gave to little <hi>Grace</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Her chamber-maid, a blew and broken face,</l>
            <l>Becauſe ſhe came not at firſt call; how ill</l>
            <l>Her Maſter took it, that ſhew'd his good will;</l>
            <l>How <hi>Nell</hi> came to miſchance by <hi>Knavery</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Of <hi>Will;</hi> how <hi>Joan</hi> beat ſilly <hi>Ralph,</hi> and why:</l>
            <l>Not to chaſtiſe ſuch groſs defectives muſt</l>
            <l>Shew me more Civil to the Sex, than Juſt</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:54895:4"/>
Unto the virtuous, who bear others ſhame,</l>
            <l>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſhing at boldneſs of the wan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on <hi>Dame,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And their impertinence vain, that are grown</l>
            <l>Knowing in all concernments, but their own.</l>
            <l>To ſet off virtues of your ſex, a whole</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Venus</hi> if painted, will but make a mole.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Apolles</hi> when he drew his maſter-piece,</l>
            <l>And ſummon'd in the <hi>Paragoas</hi> of <hi>Greece</hi>
            </l>
            <l>For beauty, as their excellence did very</l>
            <l>Unto his pencil to be tributary,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Venus</hi> her mole forgate not; but did place,</l>
            <l>And make, her comely with it in her face.</l>
            <l>Praiſe of a ſex, without exception, may</l>
            <l>Fit only people of <hi>Utopia;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Cannot ſincerely be adapted to</l>
            <l>The ſtate of ſinful mortals here below,</l>
            <l>Where thoſe few perſons do appear moſt rare</l>
            <l>And excellent, in whom leaſt vices are.</l>
            <l>They cannot be from <hi>Adam</hi> of th' whole blood,</l>
            <l>That are without all humane faileurs good.</l>
            <l>Let idle brains make ſilly ſport to vex,</l>
            <l>And force their fancies to diſgrace your ſex</l>
            <l>With all the virtuous; vainly they do try</l>
            <l>To level at the Stars which are too high.</l>
            <l>This moſt will fret them, and ſtir up their gall,</l>
            <l>That they provoke, and move you not at all:</l>
            <l>When unconcern'd you gain the victory,</l>
            <l>And overcome them by your paſſing by.</l>
            <l>The <hi>Ruſtick</hi> that all day hath toyl'd at plough,</l>
            <l>Puts off his clogs at night, begins to woo</l>
            <l>At a ſtrange rate; in Complementing <hi>Amy</hi>
            </l>
            <l>He takes up phraſe befitting <hi>Academy.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Not ſingle flow'rs of <hi>Tropes</hi> will do, but cluſter'd,</l>
            <l>That with conceit do make him fouly fluſter'd,</l>
            <l>And ſtrangely elevated: he ſcorn now</l>
            <l>To term her Pigſney, darling, <hi>Ladicow.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:54895:4"/>
His heighten'd fancy longer will not truckle,</l>
            <l>In pleaſing her his Primroſe, Honeyſuckle.</l>
            <l>The Gardens fair ſweet; ſerve him not in proſe;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Talip,</hi> Clovegilliflower, Lilly, <hi>Roſe.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Out of the Sun, Stars, and the brighteſt <hi>Roſie</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Bluſhes of morn he gathers her a <hi>Poſie.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And if he gets ſome little Scribe to write,</l>
            <l>He makes ſmall matter, matter to endite.</l>
            <l>Hearing of <hi>Po'ſie,</hi> ſhe thinks to diſcloſe</l>
            <l>Meaning, by holding letter to her Noſe;</l>
            <l>Or ſticking it in boſome, knows not well,</l>
            <l>That paper flow'rs are for the ſight, not ſmell.</l>
            <l>The frantick gallant eyes his <hi>Ladies</hi> look,</l>
            <l>More than young <hi>Chanter</hi> doth his Singing-book:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Dancing</hi> attendance moſt officiouſly</l>
            <l>After the leſſons of her fidling eye:</l>
            <l>Like Statue ſtands in admiration of</l>
            <l>Each ſyllable, ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p, frown, ſmile, glance, and coff.</l>
            <l>The ſacred <hi>Laurell</hi> he will need invoke,</l>
            <l>That never learnt ſo far as <hi>Holioke;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To celebrate grace that was never in her,</l>
            <l>And yet condemn himſelf a mortal ſinner</l>
            <l>For his <hi>Omiſſion:</hi> but that is not it</l>
            <l>Makes him ſo bad: but what he could commit.</l>
            <l>How like a Malefactor doth he ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d,</l>
            <l>Expecting ſentence? What is her command?</l>
            <l>Shall he or live or dye? Upon one breath</l>
            <l>Depends his happy life, or woful death.</l>
            <l>Great <hi>Empreſs</hi> ſhe, that with a pleaſant <hi>I?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Can make him live; and with a <hi>No</hi> to dye;</l>
            <l>Though much dejected, and caſt down erewhile,</l>
            <l>Yet ſhe can ſet him up with a kind ſmile.</l>
            <l>When his brains thin'd are almoſt into ayr</l>
            <l>Turned by Sun-beams of her face, he'l ſwear</l>
            <l>He plainly ſees the tippling <hi>Graces</hi> ſip</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Nectar</hi> diſtilling from her ruby-lip:</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:54895:5"/>
Though dazzled, <hi>Angels</hi> yet that he eſpyes</l>
            <l>Sporting within thoſe <hi>Cryſtal</hi> Spheres her eyes.</l>
            <l>There's no ſuch <hi>Muſick</hi> in the heavenly Spheres</l>
            <l>As in her voyce, which alwayes charms his ears.</l>
            <l>She's in each ſound, he hears no ring of bells,</l>
            <l>But what of her ſome pretty ſtory tells.</l>
            <l>The little chirping ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngſters in his thought</l>
            <l>Speak her ſo plain, as if they had been taught</l>
            <l>To ſing their <hi>Sapp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ks;</hi> and her praiſe in Rhyme</l>
            <l>His head well ſtuft with fumes doth learn to chyme;</l>
            <l>All this is nought, he is below his Theme</l>
            <l>Unleſs he be right <hi>Artiſt</hi> to blaſpheme.</l>
            <l>What is his heaven here on earth? her love;</l>
            <l>And there's no heaven that he ſeeks above.</l>
            <l>Were not his admiration without</l>
            <l>True object, you would think him <hi>Saint</hi> devout.</l>
            <l>He cringes, and with ſuperſtitious fear</l>
            <l>Standeth, as her <hi>Divinity</hi> draws near.</l>
            <l>Good cauſe, if you believe his precious ſtories</l>
            <l>Of the ſtrange <hi>brightneſs,</hi> and <hi>celeſtial</hi> glories</l>
            <l>He ſees incircling her, theſe witneſs'd by</l>
            <l>Thoſe that are ſick of his love lunacy.</l>
            <l>The man thus <hi>Planet-ſtricken,</hi> gives full rein</l>
            <l>Unto his fancy, th' utmoſt he can feign</l>
            <l>Of Complements beſtows, runs on the ſcore,</l>
            <l>Until his Worſhip can take up no more.</l>
            <l>If ſhe contract her countenance, and frown</l>
            <l>Upon him, that is death, he's tumbled down</l>
            <l>From all his hopes, and happineſs, which now</l>
            <l>He did enjoy in ſmoothneſs of her brow.</l>
            <l>How wretched is the man, ſince faln from grace,</l>
            <l>And excommunicated from her face?</l>
            <l>He hates the light, his life, you cannot give</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Greater</hi> affront, than wiſhing him to live.</l>
            <l>What can you love him, and be ſo unkind</l>
            <l>To wiſh him bear ſuch torments in his mind,</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:54895:5"/>
As while he lives he muſt? Then ſnatches ſword</l>
            <l>Kiſſes it as dear friend, that will afford</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Deliverance:</hi> but ſtay, before good night</l>
            <l>Pray give him leave to take up Pen and write</l>
            <l>Some doleful Verſes of his faithful love</l>
            <l>In his brave death for <hi>Phillis,</hi> which may move</l>
            <l>Her to relent, and to vouchſafe a tear,</l>
            <l>Or ſhew her more unkind than Marbles are.</l>
            <l>He orders <hi>Ceremonies</hi> to attend,</l>
            <l>And lively to ſet out a Lovers end</l>
            <l>In his laſt Will and Teſtament; forgets</l>
            <l>His ſoul to God to bequeath. And what lets?</l>
            <l>She was his only <hi>Deity,</hi> alone</l>
            <l>To her he payed his <hi>Devotion.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>What hence will follow, reaſon muſt not tell,</l>
            <l>His madneſs doth ſuppoſe a milder hell</l>
            <l>Than her diſpleaſure: this this makes him ſnatch</l>
            <l>His ſword again, reſolved to diſpatch</l>
            <l>Himſelf: but that he wiſely thinks withal</l>
            <l>He ſhall not have a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> burial</l>
            <l>As <hi>felo de ſe,</hi> and he ſcorns to be</l>
            <l>Guilty of any act of <hi>Felony.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Is he content to live? fye on't: he'l go</l>
            <l>Unto ſome forreign broyls, and force his fo</l>
            <l>To do, what friends would not, though beg'd, and ten</l>
            <l>To one time, wars do make him wiſe again.</l>
            <l>But if quite deſperate he ſeeks relief,</l>
            <l>And with his Rapier makes a vent for grief</l>
            <l>What hazard runs he? leaving friends this ſad</l>
            <l>Ground for their charity that he was mad.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Phrenetick</hi> paſſions of ſuch men may ſerve</l>
            <l>Thoſe that do not know what it's to deſerve</l>
            <l>Sober affections, would not well reſent</l>
            <l>Any thing, that were truly excellent.</l>
            <l>Let the inamoured <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſs painted <hi>Jayes,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Addreſs them to the Idol of their praiſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:54895:6"/>
Here the deſign is honeſt, to give due</l>
            <l>Honour to Ladies, that be ſuch as you</l>
            <l>Are, and would be; not living juſt by ſenſe</l>
            <l>Of ſome folk good eſteem; but <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Not pleaſing humour of that ſort who have</l>
            <l>Great fear leſt that they ſhould be thought too grave.</l>
            <l>Diſcretion you make not to withſtand</l>
            <l>Civility, but give it more command;</l>
            <l>Obligingly that it may entertain</l>
            <l>The civile perſon, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ongue-tye the vain.</l>
            <l>Such was deportment of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Dame</l>
            <l>Of old, which gave a luſtre to her name</l>
            <l>Over the world: but with diſdainful brow</l>
            <l>Is look'd upon as out of faſhion now.</l>
            <l>Amongſt vain Gallants ſtrait lac'd modeſty</l>
            <l>Is ill b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, ruſtick; too preciſe, too ſhye.</l>
            <l>Amongſt parts of <hi>Philoſophy</hi> we range</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Ethicks,</hi> and with the reſt they bear a change.</l>
            <l>As ſome young <hi>Empiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ks</hi> their skill muſt try</l>
            <l>Body to pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge of <hi>Phyſiologie,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Which they ſay <hi>Phyſick</hi> wants, and principles</l>
            <l>Her bodies head, are head of her diſeaſe.</l>
            <l>Though purged ſoundly, her they think not ſound</l>
            <l>Enough, until with her the world turn round.</l>
            <l>It may be viſit Miſtris <hi>Dialectick,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Feel her pulſe, find her in a fearful <hi>Hectick:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Her <hi>Terms</hi> are naught; her <hi>Syllogiſms</hi> all</l>
            <l>Obſtruct her, they muſt out both great, and ſmall.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Sorites</hi> fears he ſhall be laid in chains;</l>
            <l>And <hi>Violent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m</hi> looks for horrid pains:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Exemplum</hi> to be made example: ſcorns</l>
            <l>Cauſe poor <hi>Dilemma</hi> to pull in her horns.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Celarent</hi> wiſhes ſhe were ſafely hid.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Feſtino</hi> runs in danger to be chid.</l>
            <l>And <hi>Barbara</hi> the beſt of all abus'd,</l>
            <l>Fears to <hi>Bocardo</hi> ſhe ſhall be reduc'd.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:54895:6"/>
But <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rio</hi> will not be baffled ſo,</l>
            <l>If he muſt out, he'l leave a parting blow.</l>
            <l>Thus <hi>Phyſicking</hi> of her, they'r find no ſeaſon</l>
            <l>To end, until they leave her void of reaſon.</l>
            <l>So have ſome wantons quite rejected old</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Moral Philoſophy,</hi> as dry, and cold:</l>
            <l>Queſtion'd all principles, and practice too</l>
            <l>Of antient<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> virtue, and ſet up a new</l>
            <l>Model of modeſty, which you preſents</l>
            <l>With much more ſtrange, than ſafe experiments.</l>
            <l>They ſay, a place that's fortified doth ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eak</l>
            <l>The outward ſtrength, but City to be weak.</l>
            <l>That City's ſtrong, that hath not its defence</l>
            <l>From walls; but valour of the <hi>Citizens.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Strength of their virtues only way to try,</l>
            <l>Is to expoſe it to the enemy.</l>
            <l>If you'l believe, their honour by the tryal</l>
            <l>Is brighter; for they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>empt to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke denyal.</l>
            <l>Their husbands living they contract and call</l>
            <l>It innocence; may paſs the <hi>Ordeal,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Run through hat coulters blindfold, ſafe and ſound;</l>
            <l>And yet not fear the danger of a wound.</l>
            <l>Theſe can miſtake their husbands beds, and be</l>
            <l>Not to be charged with diſloyalty.</l>
            <l>Such reſolution, that can make defence</l>
            <l>At diſadvantage, is the quinteſſence</l>
            <l>Of virtue: if you can, you may believe</l>
            <l>(Like <hi>Tutia</hi>'s on tryal) in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ieve,</l>
            <l>That they can water carry, lead and bring</l>
            <l>A ſhip b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſanded by their ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on-ſtring,</l>
            <l>As <hi>Claudia,</hi> have heaven ſtanding by</l>
            <l>And witneſſing unto their chaſtity.</l>
            <l>They muſt give leave to fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k to be more wiſe,</l>
            <l>To judge by charity of ſober ſize,</l>
            <l>And then their virtue in <hi>Heroick</hi> ſenſe</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Elixar</hi> is of higheſt impudence.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:54895:7"/>
Your virtue (Madam) taketh it all one</l>
            <l>To forfeit, and to give occaſion</l>
            <l>To folly; and for med'cine doth not lye</l>
            <l>At the <hi>Betheſda</hi> of worlds charity.</l>
            <l>A moſt heroick, and approv'd repute,</l>
            <l>Neither makes way for baſeneſs, or diſpute.</l>
            <l>The <hi>Libertine,</hi> before that knew no Law</l>
            <l>To curb him, muſt confeſs your power to awe</l>
            <l>Into Civility feign'd; what he hates,</l>
            <l>Charm'd by your preſence, yet he perſonates.</l>
            <l>Aſham'd you are not piety to own</l>
            <l>Amongſt ſo many, when a ſcorn it's grown:</l>
            <l>And for <hi>Religion</hi> publickly appear,</l>
            <l>To practiſe which, in private ſome do fear.</l>
            <l>May I preſume, here to preſent to view</l>
            <l>Beauties, ſuch as <hi>Apelles</hi> never drew:</l>
            <l>May I adventure to defend their Rights</l>
            <l>Of old, that try'd the <hi>Chivalry</hi> of Knights,</l>
            <l>To plead their cauſe, ſince they are made unfit</l>
            <l>For want of Learning, not for want of Wit.</l>
            <l>May this my Pencil venture on a face,</l>
            <l>Where ev'ry taking feature is a Grace.</l>
            <l>May this not ſeem in vain, which ſeldom done,</l>
            <l>Yet is the duty of each Mothers ſon.</l>
            <l>May theſe few Rhymes (Madam) accepted be,</l>
            <l>And gain your Licence, but to publiſh me,</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,
JOHN GOLBORNE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:54895:7"/>
            <head>THE
WOMANS
EXCELLENCE.</head>
            <l>WHen man againſt unclean concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence</l>
            <l>Had a pure mind an <hi>adamantine</hi>
fence,</l>
            <l>And heart more cleanly, than
which doth poſſeſs</l>
            <l>The breaſt of moſt <hi>Religious</hi> Votareſs,</l>
            <l>Without ſo much as thought of vain deſire,</l>
            <l>And ſpark of that baſe <hi>culinary</hi> fire:</l>
            <l>Alone, it was not good that he ſhould be</l>
            <l>Without a woman, and good company.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>When</hi> Sophy, Preſter, <hi>and</hi> Imperial</l>
            <l>Highneſs, <hi>with</hi> Monarch Oecumenical,</l>
            <l>Were ſummed up in <hi>Adam;</hi> yet a ſhe</l>
            <l>Is made to peer him in his dignity.</l>
            <l>The glorious Angels, thoſe bright morning ſtars</l>
            <l>Too high were, to be his <hi>familiars.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The plants, and ſenſitives were not thought meet</l>
            <l>For him, as being ſet below his feet.</l>
            <l>But <hi>Eve</hi> created is, and made his Bride,</l>
            <l>Firſt taken out of, then unto his fide,</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:54895:8"/>
To be one with himſelf, that he may ſee</l>
            <l>In her a rational <hi>Imagery.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Pictures are dark reſemblances, they can</l>
            <l>Give outward form, and figure of the man.</l>
            <l>Glaſſes afford obſcurely (ſave the ſhape</l>
            <l>Of man) ſcarce any thing but <hi>Antick</hi> Ape.</l>
            <l>She is the lovely glaſs, where he may find</l>
            <l>The lively picture of his noble mind.</l>
            <l>Likeneſs of outward frame, and inward too</l>
            <l>Creates affection, makes the wiſe man woo.</l>
            <l>Not without likeneſs of the ſame ſoul can</l>
            <l>The outward feature make <hi>help meet for man.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Who can then think, that any man ſhould be</l>
            <l>Beſot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed with a piece of <hi>Maſonry,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Or marble? that <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wife petrify'd,</l>
            <l>Should chance to have been courted for a Bride?</l>
            <l>That man ſo monſtrouſly ſhould play the <hi>Ape,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Upon a cloud, as to commit a <hi>Rape?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Yet is it certain, fleſh, blood, ſhape affects</l>
            <l>The moſt, much more than reaſon of the ſex.</l>
            <l>Men gaze at colou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, and neglect the coal</l>
            <l>From heaven that is ſent, a prudent ſoul</l>
            <l>That ſuffers not by time; but pure doth laſt,</l>
            <l>When feature and complexion are defac'd.</l>
            <l>He ſheweth not leaſt part of man, to whom</l>
            <l>A marble <hi>Madam</hi> is companion.</l>
            <l>And with inceſtuous <hi>Pygmalion</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Carveth the Statue that he dotes upon.</l>
            <l>Though what her husband did command to be</l>
            <l>Done, or undone, he found her alwayes free:</l>
            <l>And ſilent ſhe could bear, what heart of ſtone</l>
            <l>Would mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, to be call'd <hi>Slut, foul Carrion;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Though this rare property were in his Bride,</l>
            <l>In all her time ſhe ne're was heard to chide;</l>
            <l>Nor with ſome coſtly <hi>Dames</hi> was at vaſt charge,</l>
            <l>That ſhe might follow each new Mode at large;</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:54895:8"/>
Nor with new faſhions keep an equal pace;</l>
            <l>Nor had brave <hi>Flanders</hi> prancing on her face;</l>
            <l>For back or belly though ſhe rais'd no ſcore,</l>
            <l>And like good huſwife, ne're ſtir'd out of door:</l>
            <l>Yet ſince ſhe wanted reaſon, ſenſe, and life,</l>
            <l>She could not make a comfortable Wife.</l>
            <l>That Gallant is not half ſo wiſe as nice,</l>
            <l>That is afraid of wiſdom in his choice.</l>
            <l>Is ſhe a wiſe woman? That makes him ſtart,</l>
            <l>As if ſhe were a <hi>Miſtris</hi> of <hi>Black Art.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>He fears ſhe will be proud, and learn the foul</l>
            <l>Practice of ſome Wives, Husbands to controul</l>
            <l>With ſweet advice, which makes the Bedlam roar,</l>
            <l>Fret, fume, ſwear, ban, and ſo much rage the more.</l>
            <l>For to his great diſparagement ſhe'l be</l>
            <l>Not without cauſe eſteem'd more wiſe, than he.</l>
            <l>Give him a Wench that knows no more than how</l>
            <l>Her cloaths to put on, when he ſpeaks to bow</l>
            <l>With reverence; and not without a Sir</l>
            <l>Before his Worſhip ſuffers tongue to ſtir;</l>
            <l>And as well diſciplin'd doth underſtand</l>
            <l>How to obey what he's pleas'd to command;</l>
            <l>That's troubled with the ſofts, and while he tires</l>
            <l>His wiſer hearers, ſtare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, gapes, and admires</l>
            <l>At every ſentence; this, this is a Laſs,</l>
            <l>That for a moſt obedient Wife may paſs:</l>
            <l>She ſtirs not, though he have her not in ſtring:</l>
            <l>At a proud word hath learnt to fetch and bring:</l>
            <l>A creature tame; and therefore thought more meet,</l>
            <l>Becauſe ſhe lyeth <hi>couchant</hi> at his feet.</l>
            <l>Who, though all manhood he hath qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e withdrawn,</l>
            <l>And ſpit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth in her face, begins to fawn,</l>
            <l>They that ſay women have no humane ſouls</l>
            <l>If true; they are not men, but may be foals</l>
            <l>Of ſome wild Aſs, and ſhould they be ally'd</l>
            <l>As husbands, they would be quite brutifi'd.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:54895:9"/>
And more like beaſts than <hi>Centaurs</hi> were, and then</l>
            <l>They might beget a monſtrous race of men,</l>
            <l>Much worſe, than where the pye-bald iſſues ſight</l>
            <l>Preſents with <hi>Negro's</hi> black, <hi>Europa</hi>'s white.</l>
            <l>Theſe from themſelves do only differ in</l>
            <l>The outward colour, in a ſpotted skin.</l>
            <l>But they are <hi>preternaturals,</hi> at beſt</l>
            <l>A ſort of <hi>Mongr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lls</hi> ſtrange, half man, half beaſt.</l>
            <l>They may deny them ſouls, and judgement too,</l>
            <l>If that they think thoſe men are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it to woo,</l>
            <l>And make their applications with ſucceſs</l>
            <l>In complements, and humours that profeſs</l>
            <l>By all their carriage in their loveſome fits</l>
            <l>That they are mad, and quite beſide their wits.</l>
            <l>Elſe certainly they could not be ſo baſe</l>
            <l>In face ſo foully virtues to miſplace,</l>
            <l>Where beauty playſter'd wantons to invite,</l>
            <l>Is but a <hi>Pict,</hi> and odious <hi>hypocrite.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>She's odly ſelf-conceited, that thinks praiſe</l>
            <l>He throws at randome on her, what he brayes,</l>
            <l>Rather than ſpeaks of virtue, to be due;</l>
            <l>Or (if perchance it ſhould) that he ſpeaks true,</l>
            <l>That keeps no meaſure in his paſſions heat,</l>
            <l>Nor aims to ſpeak what's ſuitable, but great,</l>
            <l>Nothing doth limit whoſe invention vain;</l>
            <l>But that he cannot reach an higher ſtrain.</l>
            <l>She that hath real worth, and ſober thought</l>
            <l>Of it, muſt needs diſdain the fancie brought,</l>
            <l>Upon pretence (forſooth) to make her more</l>
            <l>Admired; ſome think upon another ſcore.</l>
            <l>Whereas blew envy could not have ſpit forth</l>
            <l>Venome that's more malignant to her worth.</l>
            <l>Enough amongſt moſt to have this effect</l>
            <l>To make them real goodneſs to ſuſpect.</l>
            <l>As drones do very much i feſt the hive,</l>
            <l>Eat what by labour of the Bees would thrive.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:54895:9"/>
So, though theſe <hi>Humble-be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> devour, and bring</l>
            <l>Nothing; yet what is ſtrange, they have their ſting.</l>
            <l>What thinks, the wild phantaſtick ornament</l>
            <l>Of virtue, needs a flatterer to invent?</l>
            <l>Cannot ſhe be with virtues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ully ſtor'd,</l>
            <l>Unleſs made object fit to be ador'd?</l>
            <l>True honour ſtrictly looks for this its due,</l>
            <l>That all its praiſes (if not great) be true.</l>
            <l>Is not beholding as a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Saint</l>
            <l>For glories, not to vertue, but the paint.</l>
            <l>Would he be credited? that cannot be,</l>
            <l>Unleſs ſhe forfeit all ſobriety.</l>
            <l>If not, he doth his folly but proclaim,</l>
            <l>And maketh it not hard to know his Name.</l>
            <l>Alas, (good Madam) be not too ſevere,</l>
            <l>To call him knave, or fool, and domineer</l>
            <l>Over his weakneſs; for deſire to have</l>
            <l>Your love, doth make him in ſuch faſhiors rave</l>
            <l>From the firſt ſight of you, ſome influence</l>
            <l>Hath quite bereft him of all ſober ſenſe.</l>
            <l>Do you not ſee in yonder ſecret grove,</l>
            <l>Him Courting the <hi>Idea</hi> of his Love?</l>
            <l>How one while he creeps poorly, proudly ſtalks</l>
            <l>As <hi>antick ſtraight,</hi> ſtands ſilent now, then talks</l>
            <l>Unto himſelf in a low voice: ſee how</l>
            <l>He doth his honour in a Civil bow,</l>
            <l>Since he hath miſt it in ſome point, he'l try</l>
            <l>Do it with much more curioſity,</l>
            <l>To pleaſe himſelf and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ncy: then accoſts</l>
            <l>The ſhrub, where he can find no painted poſt,</l>
            <l>And to it ſpeaks words in an humble mutter,</l>
            <l>More ſweet than honey, and more ſoft than butter.</l>
            <l>What is it thus tranſports, dejects him too?</l>
            <l>Its fancy (Madam) which is type of you.</l>
            <l>He cons how Civilly he may addreſs</l>
            <l>Into your preſence, and with life expreſs</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:54895:10"/>
The paſſions of a lover, what will be</l>
            <l>Your anſwer? How to make a ſafe reply,</l>
            <l>And thoſe odd poſtures which you ſo admire,</l>
            <l>Are but the ſtrange fruit of that frantick fire</l>
            <l>You kind'ed in him: for you ſpeak no word</l>
            <l>But what he treaſures up, and doth afford</l>
            <l>Matter of thouſand thoughts: with what a Grace</l>
            <l>You did oblige; What Majeſty took plac:</l>
            <l>In your commands; how with your looks you read</l>
            <l>Lectures at once, to make him hope and dread;</l>
            <l>How ſweet was ſuch a ſmile corrected by</l>
            <l>Too harſh a Miſtris your ſeverity;</l>
            <l>How killing were your frowns: and thus in pain</l>
            <l>He's toſs'd with thoughts of favour, and diſdain.</l>
            <l>He claſps the air contain'd you: not to look</l>
            <l>On your track ſerveth him, unleſs he ſnook</l>
            <l>On ſaucy ſervant, when you do beſtow</l>
            <l>Flap on the lips for talk, to make her know</l>
            <l>Her diſtance; wonders that ſhe takes it ill,</l>
            <l>To be ſo dealt with: if ſhe had his skill</l>
            <l>She would deſerve more; he doth underſtand</l>
            <l>It no unpleaſant kiſſing of your hand</l>
            <l>Would you not (Madam) bring him to deſpair?</l>
            <l>Then you muſt be more kind, or elſe leſs fair.</l>
            <l>Let pity move, wherelove will not, t'impart</l>
            <l>A ſmile, or ſorrow ſoon will break his heart.</l>
            <l>And can you think your triumph glorious,</l>
            <l>If you deſtroy a Vaſſal-lover thus?</l>
            <l>How cruel, and hard-hearted need muſt you</l>
            <l>Appear to all the world, if it be true,</l>
            <l>That you wou'd not be at ſmall coſt, and pains</l>
            <l>Of one good word, to keep him out of chains,</l>
            <l>And Bedlam? for ſome hink could he obtain,</l>
            <l>No doubt he would be his own man again.</l>
            <l>You may command his reaſon; for he's bent</l>
            <l>Not to be cur'd, unleſs you do conſent.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:54895:10"/>
Your harmony will ſet him right, they ſay</l>
            <l>Thus of the man ſtung by <hi>Tarantula,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>That would to death dance, were he not cur'd by</l>
            <l>The vertue of harmonious melody.</l>
            <l>If you reſolve to be wiſe, and to laugh</l>
            <l>At all his follies, are not catch'd with chaff</l>
            <l>Of vain pretences; if you think it true,</l>
            <l>When cur'd, he will revenge himſelf on you</l>
            <l>For all his folly paſt, and will not pauſe</l>
            <l>Upon his bondage baſe, but hate the cauſe.</l>
            <l>Yet let me beg one kindneſs, to adviſe</l>
            <l>The Gentleman, to let you be more wiſe:</l>
            <l>If he will not himſelf, then think it fit</l>
            <l>To entertain that love, which ſpoils his wit:</l>
            <l>And to condemn the incivility</l>
            <l>That wiſhes you may be as mad as he.</l>
            <l>The horrid Courtſhips that did paſs between</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Nero,</hi> and <hi>Sporus</hi> his he-concubine.</l>
            <l>The <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umpetter,</hi> and <hi>Gracchus</hi> as they break</l>
            <l>Natures chaſte tye, ſo they forbid to ſpeak</l>
            <l>Their ſhame; for nothing can be worſe than thus,</l>
            <l>Unleſs the wedding of an <hi>Incubus.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>He truly doth deſerve the term of wiſe,</l>
            <l>Whom no perfections outward do ſurprize,</l>
            <l>To make him forfeit; ſince they may adorn</l>
            <l>A ſhameleſs <hi>Meſſaline,</hi> and be a ſcorn</l>
            <l>To time, like flower fading, which doth laſt</l>
            <l>Small time, and at its prime is almoſt paſt</l>
            <l>Its glory; yet when wither'd quite, and gone,</l>
            <l>Gives hope of budding reſurrection.</l>
            <l>But <hi>Beauty</hi> is a ſuperficial thing,</l>
            <l>That, when by age decayed, knows no ſpring.</l>
            <l>What <hi>folly</hi> many men ſo far bewitches,</l>
            <l>To make them fondly Court an heap of riches;</l>
            <l>And vainly wiſh, that they were bleſs'd with ſuch</l>
            <l>A faculty <hi>as</hi> Midas <hi>in his touch?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:54895:11"/>
And then be ſure, they ſoon would change the mold</l>
            <l>Of their dear Dames, and turn them into Gold,</l>
            <l>That thoſe whom they look'd not upon to prize,</l>
            <l>But with diſguſt, might be luſt of their eyes.</l>
            <l>How do they Court you Ladies? Is your faith</l>
            <l>So eaſie to what this, or that man ſaith?</l>
            <l>Can you believe, what their pretences vain</l>
            <l>Make ſhew of? when they truly do but feign</l>
            <l>Love to your perſons fair, and virtues: <hi>Money!</hi>
            </l>
            <l>O that that is their Dear; and that's the honey</l>
            <l>That may be help meet for them if they ſpeed.</l>
            <l>That's double help, which is an help at need.</l>
            <l>And their eſtates in deep conſumption call</l>
            <l>For preſent help, and the beſt cordial</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> is, all agree,</l>
            <l>For weak eſtates not paſt recovery.</l>
            <l>Your Lands their <hi>Chymiſtry</hi> can ſoon diſſolve</l>
            <l>Into ſome ready <hi>Caſh;</hi> or elſe involve</l>
            <l>In deep incumbrances with your conſent:</l>
            <l>Nor will their ſervile kindneſs quite be ſpent,</l>
            <l>Till all is gone; and then, however large</l>
            <l>Your portions were, you will be thought a charge.</l>
            <l>He that with vile ſubmiſſion did approach</l>
            <l>As humble Orator erewhile, did crouch</l>
            <l>And bend like any <hi>Willow,</hi> will revoke</l>
            <l>His kindneſs, and be ſtiff, as any <hi>Oak,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To your requeſts, when he hath in his hands</l>
            <l>Your <hi>thouſand pounds</hi> of portion, or your Lands.</l>
            <l>Now you are coſtly, now the man begins</l>
            <l>To grudge you money, but to buy you pins.</l>
            <l>And if more kind, yet what he doth, muſt be</l>
            <l>Reputed as an act of Charity.</l>
            <l>So by your ſoft belief, you'l ſoon be grown</l>
            <l>At his command, and beggars of your own.</l>
            <l>With ſilly eaſineſs thus you contrive</l>
            <l>To give the loaf, and after beg the ſhive.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:54895:11"/>
Yet him, if covetous, you ſhall not ſtir,</l>
            <l>Although you come with <hi>I beſeech you Sir.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>It may be, what leſs tolerable is</l>
            <l>He can the charge bear of a coſtly Miſs.</l>
            <l>Nor is it rare to find theſe two agree,</l>
            <l>One paltry hard, and prodigally free.</l>
            <l>There are accompliſhments of higher kind</l>
            <l>Such as do give a luſtre to the mind,</l>
            <l>Are not leſs pretious, though they latent are,</l>
            <l>Contribute much to make the perſon rare.</l>
            <l>A quiet frame of temper, and a meek</l>
            <l>Demeanour, which occaſions ſtill doth ſeek</l>
            <l>To pleaſe, and keep all calm; and modeſty</l>
            <l>Not too adventurous, nor weakly ſhye,</l>
            <l>More than meer baſhfulneſs, that bloſſoms caſt,</l>
            <l>If once ſaluted by unwholſome blaſt.</l>
            <l>An holy temperance, which taketh place</l>
            <l>Of Nature in its ſtrength, and is a Grace</l>
            <l>A prudent ſoul to comfort, counſel, prove</l>
            <l>Reproof may be an argument of love:</l>
            <l>Where through a waſpiſh, and weak rage are bred</l>
            <l>No words ſo hard to break her husbands head,</l>
            <l>But ſoft as oyle; and if the oyle be warm,</l>
            <l>It may do much good; but if ſcalding, harm.</l>
            <l>And her diſcretion underſtands the art</l>
            <l>To dreſs the wound, and yet prevent the ſmart.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Romes</hi> triple-headed <hi>Cerberus,</hi> ſo fell</l>
            <l>Againſt a marry'd li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e doth loudly yell,</l>
            <l>With reſolution never to diſpenſe</l>
            <l>With ſtate ſo well befitting innocence,</l>
            <l>In any of his Clergy: yet theſe Maſters,</l>
            <l>Or Fathers rather, are but <hi>Demicaſters</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Of Chaſtity: but read you ſome Popes lives,</l>
            <l>You'l find it ſafer to keep Whores, than Wives.</l>
            <l>This chaſte Divinity (long ſince foretold</l>
            <l>The Devils Doctrine) is not grown ſo old,</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:54895:12"/>
But it can yield a Nephew now, and then</l>
            <l>The baſtards of the <hi>Romiſh Arch-flamen.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>It is myſterious that one ſhould be</l>
            <l>His Holineſs, and yet want honeſty.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Pope Joan</hi> is wonder ſtranger than the other,</l>
            <l>An Holy Father, and diſhoneſt Mother.</l>
            <l>Thus <hi>Cretan Town-Bull</hi> in the Fable odd</l>
            <l>Bore <hi>Bacchus</hi> in his thigh, was feign'd a god.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Tom Dove</hi> the traveller will tell you news.</l>
            <l>What's that? at <hi>Rome</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> admits of Stews,</l>
            <l>Some hundreds of foul Bawdy-houſes. How?</l>
            <l>Such places can his Sanctity allow?</l>
            <l>What elſe, when they their annual rents disburſe,</l>
            <l>And only do their pennance to his purſe?</l>
            <l>The man of Miracles beyond his ſtrain</l>
            <l>Of skill muſt ſtretch, to make this honeſt gain.</l>
            <l>Are women by his Highneſs here below,</l>
            <l>Taken to be no higher than his <hi>Toe?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Great <hi>Toe</hi> indeed! Would it diſgrace his pride</l>
            <l>If women were advanced to his ſide</l>
            <l>In Matrimony? without charge of <hi>Trope</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Adam</hi> we call much greater than the <hi>Pope;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Whoſe <hi>Holineſs</hi> with baſeneſs tax't hath been,</l>
            <l>And to be perfect is not ſuch a ſin.</l>
            <l>What though he pleads <hi>Infallibility,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>That when ſet in the Chair he cannot lye?</l>
            <l>He lyes in that, or elſe pretence muſt go</l>
            <l>For quibble good <hi>ſenſu Compoſito.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>So Merchant brought to very hard condition,</l>
            <l>Payes off his debts by broken Compoſition.</l>
            <l>We ſay for <hi>Adam</hi> thus with reaſon good,</l>
            <l>That then he could not fall, juſt when he ſtood.</l>
            <l>By the <hi>Popes Holineſs</hi> we ſafely mean</l>
            <l>With mental reſervation what is clean (contrary.)</l>
            <l>I would not have <hi>Eve</hi> plead her nobler birth,</l>
            <l>Sith ſhe was made of man, and man of earth.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:54895:12"/>
Nor (as from bodies Politick is bred)</l>
            <l>Argue that ſhe ſprang from him as an head;</l>
            <l>That ſhe may rule, a ſtranger Title bring,</l>
            <l>His Mother was a Subject, hers a King;</l>
            <l>Nor have her daughters to preſs inſtance, ſince</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Xerxes</hi> of old that was the <hi>Perſian Prince,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Becauſe his Brother to a private man</l>
            <l>Was born, he to the ſame as Soveraign.</l>
            <l>Nor would I have them due ſubjection call</l>
            <l>Forbidden bowing of the knee to <hi>Baal:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Since that in Paradiſe the ſocial ſtate</l>
            <l>Did ſtand with reaſon of ſubordinate.</l>
            <l>There's no pretence to ſay, that God did give</l>
            <l>To male, and female, power alternative.</l>
            <l>Profanely think not, that to work his bane,</l>
            <l>God did create the woman for the man:</l>
            <l>That the wiſe, juſt, good, Orderer of all</l>
            <l>Made her an help meet, but to cauſe his fall:</l>
            <l>That man himſelf had never fal'n ſo low</l>
            <l>Without her, ſince the Word tells us not ſo.</l>
            <l>Contemn her not, that was ſince man, but rather</l>
            <l>Conſider, who was Mother to the Father</l>
            <l>Eternal: ſhe was from the man her Brother,</l>
            <l>Of the ſame Father, grant that he, as Mother,</l>
            <l>Had ſuch a Daughter, what elſe do we find</l>
            <l>But him to bear the praiſe of womankind?</l>
            <l>Bluſh then to urge that pitiful pretence,</l>
            <l>A crooked, croſs-grain'd piece of innocence.</l>
            <l>Since ſhe was ta'ne out of his ſide, that he</l>
            <l>Hath been ſtitch't by an irkſome <hi>Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uriſie.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>By ſuch little conceits play not with wit,</l>
            <l>Leſt that it chance thereby thou forfeit it,</l>
            <l>And fall to cry out with a <hi>Gotham</hi>-brother,</l>
            <l>That thou art troubled with fits of the Mother.</l>
            <l>Why may it not be likely? to ſay true,</l>
            <l>Toy wit is ill of the Greenſickneſs too.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:54895:13"/>
Her, whom thou ought'ſt to pity, ceaſe to call</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Dam</hi> of damnation in the dreadful fall,</l>
            <l>The <hi>woe</hi> of <hi>man,</hi> the ever curſed <hi>Eve</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To all the black dayes of our ſaddeſt grief.</l>
            <l>'Tis true, ſhe did procure the fall of men:</l>
            <l>The womans ſeed doth raiſe us up agen.</l>
            <l>Some are elaborate, and mighty pains</l>
            <l>Take needleſly, to ſhew that they want brains.</l>
            <l>This is the moſt they bring from learned Schools:</l>
            <l>With reaſon they can act ingenious fools,</l>
            <l>And argue ſtifly: <hi>Eve</hi> was kept alive,</l>
            <l>Her native reaſon only to ſurvive:</l>
            <l>That it is lawful, in the <hi>Logick</hi> tree,</l>
            <l>Man ſhould have one ſide, and the other ſhe,</l>
            <l>As 'tis in <hi>Eden</hi> pictur'd. Did the men</l>
            <l>Impropriate all Wiſdom: ſurely then</l>
            <l>Children half-witted are; yet will they call</l>
            <l>Their Mothers fools, for fear leſt naturals</l>
            <l>They ſhould be thought; when they that are moſt fit</l>
            <l>To be thought fools, do want their <hi>Mother-wit.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The <hi>Pagans</hi> were more humane far than theſe,</l>
            <l>Of famed Ladies that made Goddeſſes,</l>
            <l>Would have three Graces female, and did feign</l>
            <l>The wiſe <hi>Minerva</hi> ſprang out of <hi>Joves</hi> brain.</l>
            <l>Invoke no more the Muſes: none will ſide</l>
            <l>With thee, to mother thy foul <hi>Matricide</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In wronging of this S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>x; make haſte, and run:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Timon</hi> may chance t' adopt thee for his ſon;</l>
            <l>For ſweetneſs of thy Nature, thou maiſt be</l>
            <l>Made to inherit his humanity.</l>
            <l>Thy ſlender wit true wiſdom ne're begate,</l>
            <l>No learned School will it <hi>Matriculate,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>If it be <hi>Alma-mater.</hi> Learn agen</l>
            <l>What petty Scholar means by <hi>Epicene,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Or fall out with <hi>haec Homo</hi> (if you can)</l>
            <l>To ſave the head of Mr. <hi>Priſcian.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:54895:13"/>
Correct you <hi>Lilly's</hi> candour, that doth render?</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Dux, Praeſul, Pugil</hi> in the Common-gender.</l>
            <l>Were women all <hi>(Leaena</hi>-like) among</l>
            <l>Grateful <hi>Athenians</hi> without a tongue,</l>
            <l>That choſe to be ador'd, for being Mutes,</l>
            <l>They juſtly might be pictured as Brutes,</l>
            <l>As ſhe was, for her praiſe. Debaſing thought</l>
            <l>Of their diſcourſe, though ſober, ſolid brought</l>
            <l>Reproach that they are wordy, if they go</l>
            <l>Beyond the narrow bounds of I, and No.</l>
            <l>The want of learned rules, their miſery</l>
            <l>Is call'd their fault, and great infirmity</l>
            <l>Of Nature. Had their fit endowments been</l>
            <l>Favour'd by men, as Nature, we had ſeen</l>
            <l>Scholars divided into Sexes, and</l>
            <l>Some Females challenging the better hand</l>
            <l>Of them for wit, that do vouchſafe to call</l>
            <l>Them creatures but made up of tedious braul,</l>
            <l>And empty noiſe; with fury (when they dye)</l>
            <l>In <hi>Vulcan</hi>'s quiet anvill chooſe to lye,</l>
            <l>For fear of clamour; leſt their Oratory</l>
            <l>Should vex them in that ſilent <hi>Dormitory.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Some ſuch wiſe <hi>Rabbies</hi> ſurely did invent,</l>
            <l>That on a time the bounteous Heavens ſent</l>
            <l>Ten quarts of Speech into the world, and men</l>
            <l>Got to their ſhare but one poor part of ten:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Women the reſt.</hi> If that the caſe were thus,</l>
            <l>They cannot but be thought too gluttonous,</l>
            <l>To take nine cabs of pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, when a quart</l>
            <l>Is not ſcarce half enough to make a part</l>
            <l>For the good men, that laviſhly eſtate</l>
            <l>Spend in good fellowſhip, and endleſs prate.</l>
            <l>Gownmen are not all ſpeechleſs, nor the Hall</l>
            <l>Of Juſtice freed from their litigious braul.</l>
            <l>Had it been ſo: then the loud wranglers had</l>
            <l>For all their joyful <hi>Hilaries</hi> been ſad.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:54895:14"/>
That <hi>Ens</hi> of reaſon <hi>Sophomore</hi> not able</l>
            <l>Had been to make a tedious empty ſquabble</l>
            <l>About ſome Logick nicety, nor ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt</l>
            <l>So many hours in eager battlement</l>
            <l>With ſtrange <hi>Chimaera.</hi> Then what ſhould the men</l>
            <l>Have done, that are ſtout Champions at the pen;</l>
            <l>Whoſe worthy parts muſt not be ſized by</l>
            <l>The Childiſh ſeventeens, but ſeventy;</l>
            <l>Whoſe skulls are ſo well futur'd, that not any</l>
            <l>Air can offend them through the ſmalleſt crany</l>
            <l>To make them vain; yet fight <hi>Antagoniſts</hi>
            </l>
            <l>With rayling <hi>Rh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>torick</hi> to ſave their fiſts.</l>
            <l>Their mighty reaſon ſcarce preſents a <hi>For,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>But ſuch as drops from the <hi>Poſterior,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Scornful diſdain. The dealing is not ſquare</l>
            <l>That men ſhould be advanced to the Chair,</l>
            <l>And women not ſuch Scolds by far to rule</l>
            <l>Their laviſh tongues preſented to the ſtool.</l>
            <l>Women have got no priviledge to write</l>
            <l>Books ſtuft with ſlander, baſe contempt and ſpite,</l>
            <l>Which purged of their choler might be meet</l>
            <l>As skeletons bare for a winding-ſheet.</l>
            <l>Although their words are ſpightful, keen men can</l>
            <l>Yet get them reckon'd as Patritian</l>
            <l>Sobriety: ſo well have ſome men ſped</l>
            <l>To have their malice meekneſs Chriſtened.</l>
            <l>Brag'd of tame tempers: ſuch tame creatures be</l>
            <l>Safely preſented through a grate to ſee:</l>
            <l>On ſweetneſs of their temper true Comment</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Is</hi> Pius, Clement, Urbane, Innocent.</l>
            <l>The privacy of womens narrow ſphere</l>
            <l>Domeſtick, makes their virtue leſs appear.</l>
            <l>Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing occaſion their parts buryed lye</l>
            <l>In the dark vault of baſe obſcurity,</l>
            <l>That have not only unconquered charms</l>
            <l>Of winning beauty, but affrighting arms.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:54895:14"/>
It therefore is unhappineſs of ſtate</l>
            <l>So much embaſes word <hi>effeminate,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And keeps their ſpirits under: Had they wayes</l>
            <l>And opportunities to get them praiſe:</l>
            <l>Were they inur'd to hardſhips, they'd outvye</l>
            <l>Thoſe that do hold eſtates in Chivalry:</l>
            <l>Or have done brave Knights-ſervice, and afford</l>
            <l>More gallantry than thoſe that were ador'd.</l>
            <l>Though mention of their due praiſe envy call</l>
            <l>A Tattle more than <hi>Hyper-prodigal,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And the ſurmiſe of feats that might be done</l>
            <l>In arms by them, an idle Fiction:</l>
            <l>For what they have atchieved nobly, fame</l>
            <l>Will ever ſtand indebted to their Name.</l>
            <l>And if they do not ſue the jangling Laſs,</l>
            <l>It is becauſe amongſt them ſhe doth paſs</l>
            <l>Not worthy of regards, too baſe to be</l>
            <l>Sought unto by their true <hi>Nobility.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Yet famous men have Courted much her honour,</l>
            <l>Of fawning titles caſt whole leads upon her,</l>
            <l>Were humble ſuitors they might be among</l>
            <l>Thoſe, who had intereſt in her idle tongue,</l>
            <l>Promiſing they would be her Champions bold</l>
            <l>To do great feats: but only to be told.</l>
            <l>When ſlattering fame commended did not cry</l>
            <l>Out with this womaniſh Loquacity,</l>
            <l>Let her be packt out of the way, and go</l>
            <l>Seek place in <hi>Pſittacorum R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gio.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Amongſt the</hi> Vegetables, nobler trees</l>
            <l>Fruitleſs have been, we read, without their ſhees:</l>
            <l>So on the <hi>Erythrean</hi> barks, for wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t</l>
            <l>Of other dwellers, noble <hi>Palms</hi> do plant</l>
            <l>And grow in couples; ſhewing <hi>that th' entail</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Of Honour runs not to the iſſue male</l>
            <l>In ſpecial; he would have a barren root,</l>
            <l>But that the gen'rous female bears the fruit.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:54895:15"/>
It's reaſonable women have as well</l>
            <l>The pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe, as they have power to excell.</l>
            <l>They that deny them honour, muſt profeſs,</l>
            <l>And likewiſe ſeem to prove their worth is leſs.</l>
            <l>Would they attempt it, they'd deſire no more</l>
            <l>To make them ſee their Hereſie before;</l>
            <l>And ſhew them that a Volume ſhould be ſpent,</l>
            <l>And not a ſingle Sheet when they repent.</l>
            <l>Are faults and blemiſhes in them ſo thin</l>
            <l>Scatter'd, that works of God muſt be clapt in</l>
            <l>To make crimes more: that his works are ſo large</l>
            <l>To them, is full enough to ground a charge</l>
            <l>Againſt them; whereas had he but leſs ſpent</l>
            <l>On them, they had been judged innocent.</l>
            <l>Since their great beauties to ſome become ſnares;</l>
            <l>Fault (Tarbox) ſtraight muſt be concluded theirs.</l>
            <l>If this be Logick, let us borrow tools</l>
            <l>From Crafts-men of the Chair to make us fools,</l>
            <l>Condemn the light, becauſe ſome over-wiſe</l>
            <l>By ſtaring at it chance to hurt their eyes.</l>
            <l>We'l ſtrain our fancies, and conceipts to think</l>
            <l>Aqua Coeleſtis, which the Stars do drink</l>
            <l>Too lib'rally, makes them to blink, and keep</l>
            <l>Their heavy eyes ſcarce ope for want of ſleep.</l>
            <l>Dark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the luſtre of thoſe radiant lights,</l>
            <l>That we may favour weakneſs of our ſights.</l>
            <l>If in the womens feature crime be known,</l>
            <l>The fault of right ſhould not be call'd their own:</l>
            <l>This noble fabricks beauty muſt reflect</l>
            <l>Upon the goodneſs of the <hi>Architect,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>That made the work ſo rare, as to entice</l>
            <l>To folly curious ſpectators eyes.</l>
            <l>Good form by wiſe men hath been made to go</l>
            <l>For that, which is <hi>Dignum Imperio,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Teaching in outward features how to find</l>
            <l>A correſpondent beauty in the mind.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:54895:15"/>
Let them ſmart under cenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>res, that delight</l>
            <l>To walk, in habits like <hi>Hermaphrodite;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>That by their manlike looks, garbs, faſhions rare,</l>
            <l>Make it a queſtion of what Sex they are;</l>
            <l>Debaſing thus <hi>Virago</hi>'s nobler ſence,</l>
            <l>And making it to hide their impudence.</l>
            <l>May they be hateful to all modeſt ſights,</l>
            <l>That turn into almoſt half <hi>Adamites,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Whoſe viſage muſt not Natures power expreſs,</l>
            <l>But their pride, and affected wickedneſs;</l>
            <l>Deſpiſing nature of their ſex they call</l>
            <l>A meal-mouth'd-modeſty, baſe, ruſtical.</l>
            <l>Talk what the ears of wantoneſt might load</l>
            <l>To make their wanton tongues too <hi>Alamode.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>May thoſe ſlye cheats (that modeſty do own</l>
            <l>For nought, but baſe immodeſt ends) be known:</l>
            <l>Who baiting with a pretty ſober look,</l>
            <l>Make the young fool to ſwallow down the hook.</l>
            <l>In men and women when the fault is ſame,</l>
            <l>How cometh it to paſs they ſhare not blame</l>
            <l>
               <hi>By</hi> equal moieties? In men a Beam</l>
            <l>Is call'd a Mote; a Mote, a Beam in them.</l>
            <l>Upon what ground taketh the ſaying place?</l>
            <l>This fault is bad in man, in woman baſe.</l>
            <l>Shall we thus aggravate? they've wiſdom more:</l>
            <l>But very few will charge them on that ſcore.</l>
            <l>Precedence by none will be granted in</l>
            <l>Knowledge, although it were to leſſen ſin.</l>
            <l>Is it their inclination leſs to vice</l>
            <l>At firſt unto the ſcandal that gave riſe?</l>
            <l>They that to wickedneſs are leſs inclin'd</l>
            <l>Muſt be acknowledg'd to have purer mind,</l>
            <l>Which makes ſpots more conſpicuous: oftentimes</l>
            <l>Better the perſons are, the fouller crimes</l>
            <l>Appear in them. <hi>Deformities</hi> are not</l>
            <l>Obſerv'd in darker bodies; when each ſpot</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:54895:16"/>
Shews it ſelf in the brighter; thus we ſoon</l>
            <l>Eſpye the ſpots, that do obſcure the Moon.</l>
            <l>So Authors <hi>Venus</hi> mole do <hi>Memorize,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>So leaſt pearl blemiſheth the brighteſt eyes.</l>
            <l>If this will not be granted, all muſt ſay,</l>
            <l>That men in ſomethings, and in others they,</l>
            <l>Plead excellence. Let guilt, as equal then</l>
            <l>Be charg'd upon the women, as the men.</l>
            <l>Yet women, knowing freedom doth not lye</l>
            <l>In what is but licentious liberty,</l>
            <l>Are well content with honour of their ſtate,</l>
            <l>That doth their crimes ſo highly aggravate.</l>
            <l>Hath <hi>Brittain</hi> ſuffer'd any prejudice,</l>
            <l>By being called <hi>Womens Paradiſe,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Giving them thirds, the higheſt ſeats, and wall</l>
            <l>So Civilly, with ſo great ſhare of all</l>
            <l>Their husbands lands? This they return agen,</l>
            <l>Their free-born children make the braveſt men.</l>
            <l>They cannot have their ſouls ſcarce half ſo brave</l>
            <l>Where Father is a Tyrant, Mother Slave.</l>
            <l>In vain <hi>Italian</hi> women are kept faſt</l>
            <l>By Husbands Jaylorſhip to make them chaſte.</l>
            <l>How many vex'd, and tempted by the thought</l>
            <l>Of Jealous-pated-men have been made naught?</l>
            <l>Thinking diſloyalty would nothing coſt</l>
            <l>More than what had been quite already loſt</l>
            <l>In his eſteem: ſetting more vainly by</l>
            <l>A good repute, than real honeſty.</l>
            <l>Security for virtue, if undone</l>
            <l>By wrongful, and but bare ſuſpicion,</l>
            <l>Is ſmall; if what the <hi>Husband doth invent,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Is cauſe enough for Wives impriſonment.</l>
            <l>On as good ground the poor might be bereft</l>
            <l>Of all their liberty for fear of theft.</l>
            <l>Here by <hi>Lucretian</hi> chaſtity might fall</l>
            <l>Under the black rod of foul <hi>Criminal;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:54895:16"/>
That cannot teſtimony give confin'd,</l>
            <l>Before the fact, to honeſty of mind.</l>
            <l>The felons priſon, ſhackles, bolts impart</l>
            <l>What is according to the mens deſert;</l>
            <l>It's not enough againſt him to alledge,</l>
            <l>By witneſs, that he looked o're the hedge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>In Goal, when he is laid, we make no doubt,</l>
            <l>But as he ſtole in, ſo he would ſteal out.</l>
            <l>Theſe Dames for nothing elſe, but being Wives,</l>
            <l>Are made the cloſeſt priſoners for lives,</l>
            <l>Never but in the Husbands death to ſee,</l>
            <l>Or their own death, a Goal-delivery.</l>
            <l>Barbarian <hi>X<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ifs-concubines,</hi> eſcape,</l>
            <l>'Tis ſaid, if they but ſee a man, a rape;</l>
            <l>Before their count begins they muſt cry out,</l>
            <l>For what? to bring their honeſty in doubt,</l>
            <l>Rather than ſhield it. He who them eſpyes</l>
            <l>By chance, is not beholding to his eyes:</l>
            <l>Whoſe caſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>(Actaeon-like)</hi> preſents ſtrange kind</l>
            <l>Of miſery, which is not to be blind.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Proud Maſters</hi> think their rule entrenched on,</l>
            <l>If the good Wives their reaſons dare to own.</l>
            <l>When they make queſtion whether muſty Muſt</l>
            <l>Of canker'd ſpirits ſhould be born as Juſt,</l>
            <l>Or with due reverence beſeech, and pray,</l>
            <l>They may not be expos'd as f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ols in play.</l>
            <l>This boldneſs makes the ſottiſh ſoul invent</l>
            <l>A plot, and wiſh an Act of Parliament,</l>
            <l>That each man in his houſe may rule, and be</l>
            <l>Inveſted with a full authority</l>
            <l>To domineer, command, controul, make Laws</l>
            <l>Void of all reaſon; but a proud becauſe.</l>
            <l>Scripture without a Word of God they bring</l>
            <l>To juſtifie their tyranny. The King</l>
            <l>
               <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>erus</hi> cited is: the <hi>Queen</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Vaſthi</hi> arraign'd, as groſly overſeen,</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:54895:17"/>
That would not ſhew her ſelf; make Majeſty,</l>
            <l>She did partake of with the King, to be</l>
            <l>As picture ſhew'd to ſubjects; and moreover</l>
            <l>In this command they think the King was ſober:</l>
            <l>That a decree ſo neceſſary was</l>
            <l>Fit to be made a Monument in braſs.</l>
            <l>I leave them with <hi>Memucan</hi> to prevent</l>
            <l>Imperiouſneſs, the woman never meant,</l>
            <l>And to ſue out the formalleſt decree</l>
            <l>Againſt what never was, will never be.</l>
            <l>The thing call'd <hi>Matrimony</hi> thus beguiles,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>And makes a</hi> John a Nokes, <hi>a</hi> John a Stiles,</l>
            <l>To ſwell with mighty titles: for his Cur-ſhip</l>
            <l>To his proud haſty humours pleads for worſhip,</l>
            <l>With prayers, tears, ſhe our <hi>John</hi> may not aſſault,</l>
            <l>When dub'd Sr. <hi>Walter Walter</hi> Knight of Malt.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Sarah</hi> call'd <hi>Abraham</hi> Lord; his Wife muſt do</l>
            <l>So to his honour, he'l be <hi>Baron</hi> too.</l>
            <l>If ſhe thinks, all her livelihood too much is</l>
            <l>To be expoſed to his greedy clutches,</l>
            <l>Since he reels all away, that ſhe can ſpin,</l>
            <l>Spends faſter than hard labour can bring in:</l>
            <l>Her cheſts, and coffers, boxes ſtraight he breaks</l>
            <l>Open, to ſhew his Licence to play <hi>Rex.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>If <hi>Caj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tanes</hi> vote carry, he may hope</l>
            <l>To be elected as <hi>Doneſtick Pope;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>That, ſith the womans head is man, doth call</l>
            <l>His power by title that is <hi>Myſtical,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Hard to be underſtood: what doth infer</l>
            <l>As <hi>Myſtick</hi> ſomething, that he's <hi>Myſtick Sir.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The toyling Wife may give her ſelf the caſe,</l>
            <l>And judge it fit that <hi>Peter</hi> keep the keyes</l>
            <l>In his power o're her, children, ſervants ſee</l>
            <l>Mark of the Beaſt a <hi>Triple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Soveraignty,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And be forbidden ever for to own</l>
            <l>That ſhe believes the ſtory of <hi>Pope Joan.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:54895:17"/>
If he do tyrannize, and reaſon fail</l>
            <l>For what he doth, he puts on Coat of Male,</l>
            <l>Pleads he's an husband: ſo right, or behoof,</l>
            <l>Or promiſe ſhall not pierce him: this is Proof.</l>
            <l>If <hi>Layſhip</hi> cannot well abſolve the man,</l>
            <l>Nor give indulgence, <hi>Myſtick Headſhip</hi> can.</l>
            <l>This ſpeckled creature, without charge of pelf,</l>
            <l>May do wrong, give a pardon to himſelf.</l>
            <l>We need no antient Hiſtories to tell us,</l>
            <l>That meaner ſort of <hi>Dames</hi> may grow good fellows,</l>
            <l>Follow the trade of Goſſippings; they can</l>
            <l>Toſs jovially their pots like any man:</l>
            <l>If the poor <hi>Gaffer</hi> have weak jacks, their wills</l>
            <l>May not be ſerv'd without their luſtier Gills;</l>
            <l>Whoſe ſpirits make them keep moſt woful rackets</l>
            <l>It may be fall hard on their husbands jackets</l>
            <l>If ſo <hi>Viraginous,</hi> that muſt allow</l>
            <l>What ſuch Wives ſay, or do; cannot tell how</l>
            <l>To help it; ſcarce may think that expence ſad,</l>
            <l>Which beggars families, and makes them mad.</l>
            <l>For me, <hi>Xantippe</hi> ne're ſhall be too old,</l>
            <l>To bear the <hi>ſtigma</hi> of an odious ſcold.</l>
            <l>As puniſhment juſt let her alwayes be</l>
            <l>Under the <hi>tongue-ſtrappado</hi> Railery.</l>
            <l>Yet this may ſober Civil women vex,</l>
            <l>That faults, not general, upon the ſex</l>
            <l>Are caſt. What made <hi>Philoſopher</hi> to load us</l>
            <l>With ſilly <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſinus habendi Modus?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Was there no matter for the wiſe to write</l>
            <l>Upon, but <hi>womens eager appetite</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>To men?</hi> by ſlender matter firſt begot</l>
            <l>To ſerve, they ſay themſelves, they know not what;</l>
            <l>The moſt for which this poor conceipt can bid,</l>
            <l>Is little ſomething called <hi>Neſcio quid.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>What means unkind <hi>Dilemma,</hi> that ſayes women</l>
            <l>If beautiful, muſt therefore needs be common?</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:54895:18"/>
Such baſe <hi>Dilemma's</hi> alwayes in diſpute</l>
            <l>Deſerve to bear the <hi>Odium</hi> of <hi>Cornute.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Leave</hi> off your tyranny, you pieviſh elves,</l>
            <l>Whilſt you do harm your Wives, you wrong your ſelves.</l>
            <l>Making their grieving hearts through eyes expreſs,</l>
            <l>What tongues would not, the great unhappineſs</l>
            <l>Not to be ſuffer'd, that they are brought to,</l>
            <l>Endeavouring moſt vainly to pleaſe you.</l>
            <l>What can you ſwagger, ſtorm at, and confine</l>
            <l>Them wrongfully, and call it Maſculine</l>
            <l>Thus to inſult? It is but fooliſh mind,</l>
            <l>Seeks to advance the Sex, debaſe the kind.</l>
            <l>Is't mercy to thy family to make</l>
            <l>Subſiſtence of Wife, Children lye at ſtake,</l>
            <l>And run a ſad adventure; when they All</l>
            <l>Muſt be expoſed by a doubtful fall,</l>
            <l>And but uncertain caſt at Dice? wherein</l>
            <l>She ſuffers much, although thou chance to win.</l>
            <l>But (if ſome unexpected hap do croſs</l>
            <l>Thy greedy aims) ſhe muſt ſit down with loſs.</l>
            <l>When all is caſt away, may ſhe not gain</l>
            <l>The liberty of loſers to complain?</l>
            <l>Canſt thou think to run through all in thy ſport,</l>
            <l>And not endure thou ſhouldſt be blamed for't?</l>
            <l>Or make it run through thee by drunken fit,</l>
            <l>And yet not ſuffer her to grieve for it?</l>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:54895:18"/>
               <head>Women-Worthies.</head>
               <l>EXamples croud upon us, leſt the flaws</l>
               <l>Of ſome irregulars ſhould wrong their cauſe,</l>
               <l>The innocence of others blemiſh, and the blame</l>
               <l>Of envy ſhould be charg'd, i'le further name</l>
               <l>Out of thoſe many, thought to equal beſt</l>
               <l>Of men, ſome few, that did outſhine the reſt.</l>
               <l>Since the great <hi>Amazonian</hi> Ladies ſeats</l>
               <l>Are mention'd by good Authors, and their feats</l>
               <l>Of War, ſucceſſes, progreſs, and the Dates</l>
               <l>Of theſe related with Confederates,</l>
               <l>Their government, declenſions, and laſt Queen,</l>
               <l>But to ſuppoſe they have not been, is ſpleen</l>
               <l>In them, in queſtioning that make us know,</l>
               <l>They are aſhamed much that it ſhould be ſo.</l>
               <l>The greatneſs of the things they did atchieve,</l>
               <l>Puts the world ſo much to it to believe.</l>
               <l>Others do talk at a prodigious rate,</l>
               <l>And that which noble was, call deſperate.</l>
               <l>As though their valour in firſt gallant fight</l>
               <l>Were to be thought a better ſort of flight.</l>
               <l>Were we diſpos'd this reaſon to allow</l>
               <l>As likely, poſſibly who could tell how</l>
               <l>To vindicate great Warriors; for men,</l>
               <l>When deſperate, fight their way back agen.</l>
               <l>In dangers vileſt <hi>Recreants</hi> are made ſtout</l>
               <l>Only to make way <hi>to creep poorly out.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But they conſult not ſafety to make peace,</l>
               <l>Which ſoon might have been done; ſince cauſe did ceaſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:54895:19"/>
For their exile, and ſufferings: but go on,</l>
               <l>Leaving their names to fame <hi>Thermodoon.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Revenge was not the main cauſe; for that lamp</l>
               <l>When flaſh is over, ſoon is quench'd by damp</l>
               <l>Of fear. Their courage in the proof was clear,</l>
               <l>If not from wild-fire-raſhneſs, yet from fear.</l>
               <l>Not a few ages puts this out of doubt,</l>
               <l>Wherein their valour through defeats held out.</l>
               <l>Many Commanders courage did commence</l>
               <l>Famous, at the Acts of <hi>Experience,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That need not be aſhamed to confeſs,</l>
               <l>They owed almoſt all unto ſucceſs:</l>
               <l>Or yield they have deriv'd their famous ſpirit</l>
               <l>From Anceſtors ſucceſs, which they inherit.</l>
               <l>Succeſſes caus'd not valour, but from hence,</l>
               <l>Their native courage, ſprang experience.</l>
               <l>Their Mothers victories, got in late fight,</l>
               <l>They could not look upon as their own right.</l>
               <l>Or ſith their husbands proſpered in Deed</l>
               <l>Of arms, think therefore they muſt need ſucceed.</l>
               <l>Had ſucceſs only rais'd their ſpirits, then</l>
               <l>Some few defeats had beaten down agen.</l>
               <l>They that are bred under the tyranny</l>
               <l>Of long, and hard oppreſſion, will be ſhye</l>
               <l>To own their Native-freedom, have no thought</l>
               <l>Higher, than to do what they have been taught:</l>
               <l>In time are brought to this degenerate ſenſe</l>
               <l>To think their reaſon piece of Impudence.</l>
               <l>They have Heroick Spirits, truly great,</l>
               <l>Whoſe mettle loſeth little by defeat.</l>
               <l>If over-powr'd by force, yet can maintain</l>
               <l>Their minds ſo high, that Victors ſcarce ſhall gain.</l>
               <l>Thus may we find the valiant <hi>Amazon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Conquer'd, and conquering, to ſeem all one.</l>
               <l>Not that ſubjection, ſince firſt ſin began,</l>
               <l>Adjudg'd a curſe of woman unto man;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:54895:19"/>
Not weakneſs of her ſex, made weaker by</l>
               <l>Her liberty to rule but <hi>Infantry;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Not baniſhment from friends, and native s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oil,</l>
               <l>Not murder of her husband; not her ſpoil;</l>
               <l>Not inexperience in war that can</l>
               <l>Daunt courage of the <hi>Amazonian.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Theſe in their firſt engagement bravely know</l>
               <l>The way to fight, and how to overthrow,</l>
               <l>Turning the Diſtaff into Lance: the Wheel</l>
               <l>They caſt away; get Gorgets made of ſteel,</l>
               <l>Having their minds moſt ſtout (as bows were) bent</l>
               <l>To make a ſtrange unheard Experiment.</l>
               <l>Whether their nature, or condition brought</l>
               <l>Them to ſubjection, and ſo dreadful thought</l>
               <l>Of wars; when they aſſault the enemy</l>
               <l>Think it ſecureſt way for life to fly</l>
               <l>Not in a Complement; but forc'd give place,</l>
               <l>As if the <hi>Aſian</hi> bounds were but a Chaſe,</l>
               <l>Where they do follow pleaſant warlike ſport,</l>
               <l>And each one carries in her heart a fort.</l>
               <l>All other forts they leave, and Champion</l>
               <l>By them is fitteſt to be trod upon.</l>
               <l>By providence they ſeem to have a Charter</l>
               <l>To rule o're men. The ſtrongeſt ſpirit of <hi>Tartar,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Was weak to theirs. Now we read of a <hi>Quarum.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To put in Maps <hi>Inſulam foeminarum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is no great courteſie. It ſeems they meant</l>
               <l>To prove the world but narrow Continent</l>
               <l>To their deſires. <hi>Maragnon</hi> banks do pay</l>
               <l>Honour to their Names in <hi>America.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And the ſuppoſed head of <hi>Nile</hi> will dare</l>
               <l>To challenge that they once were ſeated there.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Euxine</hi> looks black at that, ſuppoſing thanks</l>
               <l>For them, was chiefly due unto his banks.</l>
               <l>Where ere they came they made Crowns uſe another</l>
               <l>Phraſe; and great Kingdom to obey their Mother.</l>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:54895:20"/>
                  <head>Of Menalippe.</head>
                  <l>GReat <hi>Hercules</hi> for ever famous is</l>
                  <l>For all his labours, and not leſs for this</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Menalippe</hi> that engag'd to fight,</l>
                  <l>Who could not be match'd but by ſuch a Knight.</l>
                  <l>The Victory with hardſhip ſhe let go</l>
                  <l>At laſt, and glad was he he go it ſo,</l>
                  <l>Not by pure valour; then my Author lyes,</l>
                  <l>That gives the greateſt part unto ſurprize.</l>
                  <l>If moſt renowned of the <hi>Greeks</hi> comes here</l>
                  <l>As chapmen, ſhe will ſell them conqueſt dear.</l>
                  <l>The Conquerors by Chariot that lead</l>
                  <l>Their Vaſſal-Kings might be thus vanquiſhed</l>
                  <l>With honour too: 'tis credit more by ſome</l>
                  <l>To get a foyle, than elſewhere overcome.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:54895:20"/>
                  <head>Of Pentheſile.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>PEntheſile</hi> brought (with a kind intent</l>
                  <l>Of helping <hi>Priam)</hi> her Maid-Regiment</l>
                  <l>As ſome affirm, and had ſhe ſooner come,</l>
                  <l>Deſpairing <hi>Greeks</hi> with ſhame had ridden home</l>
                  <l>On Wooden Horſe. They now that dare to tax</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Troyes</hi> folly, yet do dread the Battle-ax,</l>
                  <l>Which ſhe invented: heart was fully try'd</l>
                  <l>Of great <hi>Achilles</hi> Son before ſhe dy'd.</l>
                  <l>Such brave <hi>Virago's</hi> not by ſmoother words</l>
                  <l>Of Complements, were overcome, but Swords.</l>
                  <l>The gallant <hi>Grecian</hi> yonkers, that did Court,</l>
                  <l>Before they wan their love, fought ſtoutly for't.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:54895:21"/>
                  <head>Of Artemiſia.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>HAlicarnaſſus</hi> Queen her ſelf did ſhew</l>
                  <l>Fit to command the <hi>Archipelago.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>While <hi>Perſians</hi> ſtand at gaze, the <hi>Grecians</hi> are</l>
                  <l>Forc'd to make way for more than Men of War,</l>
                  <l>Which ſhe conducted; as though ſhe would glory,</l>
                  <l>And make the Sea part of her <hi>Territory.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Perſian</hi>-Carpet-Knights with courage cold</l>
                  <l>Run, to ſecure themſelves, into the Hold:</l>
                  <l>Giving <hi>Achaians</hi> leave to underſtand,</l>
                  <l>Ships overcharg'd with ſuch, were poorly man'd.</l>
                  <l>The ink may bluſh, and Scribes, that are to write</l>
                  <l>At her ſtout heart of Oak, their wings for flight.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Xerxes</hi> ſpectator is aſham'd to ſee</l>
                  <l>The Queens top, and top-gallant-gallantry.</l>
                  <l>More are the <hi>Greeks</hi> enrag'd, that overcome,</l>
                  <l>And ſcarce can carry - half the honour home.</l>
                  <l>Her moſt renown'd <hi>Mauſoleum</hi> could not be</l>
                  <l>For braveneſs half ſuch wonder as was ſhe.</l>
                  <l>What was for honour of her husband meant</l>
                  <l>Of her great praiſe is made the Monument.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:54895:21"/>
                  <head>Of Zenobia.</head>
                  <l>WE'l boaſt <hi>Zenobia</hi> in triumph led,</l>
                  <l>Yet by <hi>Aurelian</hi> not conquered.</l>
                  <l>Not having life; nor begging pitteouſly,</l>
                  <l>To live not bluſhing, nor aſham'd to dye;</l>
                  <l>For when her army's broken and command,</l>
                  <l>She more undaunted, than the Victor ſtands:</l>
                  <l>Though outward ſplendour muſt be left behind,</l>
                  <l>She will reſerve the greatneſs of her mind.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Of the Queen of Sheba.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>ARabia</hi> the Happy boaſts of her,</l>
                  <l>That by her wiſdom made it happier;</l>
                  <l>And from <hi>Saboean-land</hi> did come upon</l>
                  <l>Errand, of proving wiſeſt <hi>Solomon</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With queſtions hard, ſhe queſtionleſs gave much</l>
                  <l>Aſſurance, that ſhe was another ſuch.</l>
                  <l>The greateſt Warriers were prov'd, we ſee,</l>
                  <l>By women in the feats of Chivalry.</l>
                  <l>The wiſeſt meer man in the Holy Writ</l>
                  <l>Is ſaid to be try'd by a womans wit.</l>
                  <l>With men in nobleſt exploits they'l compare,</l>
                  <l>That in the wonders of the world had ſhare.</l>
                  <l>Are they ſo equal? We may therefore render</l>
                  <l>Acts, that are glorious, in the <hi>Doubtful Gender.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:54895:22"/>
                  <head>Of Deborah.</head>
                  <l>WHen oppreſs'd <hi>Iſrael</hi> did ſadly moan</l>
                  <l>Under their loſſes, which they might not own:</l>
                  <l>When government was needful to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ppeaſe</l>
                  <l>Thoſe, who in reſtleſneſs take greateſt eaſe:</l>
                  <l>When by what Laws command, and Rulers ſay</l>
                  <l>People take pattern how to diſobey:</l>
                  <l>When Malefactors need make no defence</l>
                  <l>For their outrages, but more violence:</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Deborah</hi> is rais'd; for none ſo free</l>
                  <l>From fear, ſo wiſe, ſo ſtout, ſo good as ſhe.</l>
                  <l>Here Widows, Orphans, ſtrangers freely might</l>
                  <l>Have their cauſe pleaded, and receive their right</l>
                  <l>Aſſoon as richeſt; for ſhe knew right well</l>
                  <l>How to give Judgement; but had none to ſell.</l>
                  <l>No tedious demu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rers here; no witty</l>
                  <l>Cobweb-exceptions, Courts of fooliſh pitty.</l>
                  <l>For Chancery, no argument ſhe draws</l>
                  <l>From Topick of the perſon, but the cauſe.</l>
                  <l>They that ſtood by her could not but invoke</l>
                  <l>God, when they heard the Oracles ſhe ſpoke.</l>
                  <l>Nay bifront <hi>Ja<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us</hi> could not put a face</l>
                  <l>Upon't, if there to deny her the place.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Barak</hi> gives her right hand, is glad to be</l>
                  <l>Beholding for his branch to her Palm-tree.</l>
                  <l>She gave firſt blow in the attempt, and lead</l>
                  <l>The hoſt, and <hi>Jacl</hi> knock'd nail to the head.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:54895:22"/>
                  <head>Of Eſther.</head>
                  <l>THe proud <hi>Amalekite</hi> fate daily at</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Pur Pur,</hi> like a Melancholly Cat,</l>
                  <l>Blood<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mad and rageful that ſtraight at his call</l>
                  <l>The lucky lot did not prepare to fall.</l>
                  <l>Since <hi>Mord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cai</hi> to bow refuſed, he</l>
                  <l>Seeks by Jews downfall to revenged be.</l>
                  <l>Thirſt of his malice cannot be by blood</l>
                  <l>Of one man quenched, he can drink a flood</l>
                  <l>Of tears and go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e : therefore <hi>Eſther</hi> adventures</l>
                  <l>Though with the hazard of her life, and enters</l>
                  <l>Into the preſence againſt Law: the Queen</l>
                  <l>Redeems lives that were purchas'd for his ſpleen.</l>
                  <l>Since he's not tall enough, doth ſtill aſpire,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he will advance him forty cubits higher.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Haman</hi> will not be a man, yet his fate</l>
                  <l>With twiſt doth take away the <hi>aſpirate.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thus under God the Feaſt of <hi>Purim</hi> may</l>
                  <l>Be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eckon'd as the <hi>Jewiſh Eſther day.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:54895:23"/>
                  <head>Of Judith.</head>
                  <l>WHat to diſtreſs'd, deſpairing, <hi>Iſrael</hi> was</l>
                  <l>Too much to think; <hi>Judith</hi> doth bring to paſs.</l>
                  <l>Proud <hi>Holofernes</hi> thought his words ſo ſtout,</l>
                  <l>Enough among the Jews to make a rout.</l>
                  <l>Wiſhing them heart to make reſiſtance great</l>
                  <l>To heighten his courage, and their defeat</l>
                  <l>To aggravate, ſhe ſilenceth thoſe boaſts,</l>
                  <l>And at two blows, ſtoutly beheads an hoſt.</l>
                  <l>No petty Forts aſſails, but chief of all,</l>
                  <l>Their main ſtrength, and ſoon takes the <hi>Capitoll.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When to <hi>Bethulia</hi> ſhe returns, and calls,</l>
                  <l>There ſtraight ariſe ſome ſtatues on the walls.</l>
                  <l>So great amazing joy in every one</l>
                  <l>Made them ſeem part of th' wall turn'd into ſtone.</l>
                  <l>So once <hi>Meduſa's</hi> beauty left no vigour</l>
                  <l>Of men to the beholders, but a Figure.</l>
                  <l>She fear'd not living Monſter, ſome do doubt</l>
                  <l>From the fierce head leſt body ſhould grow out</l>
                  <l>As heads of <hi>Hydra</hi> from the body; ſeeing</l>
                  <l>Dead Tyrant them ſhe ſcarce can keep from flying.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bago's</hi> with ſhame doth find his Maſter dead,</l>
                  <l>And proves a truſty keeper of his head.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> camp in great confuſion ſtands.</l>
                  <l>They that want head, have little uſe of hands.</l>
                  <l>Women in triumph walk that day like hoſt,</l>
                  <l>And they have greateſt right to rule the roaſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Judith</hi> led <hi>Van,</hi> and ſhe the Olive bore</l>
                  <l>The other branches as the Dove before.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:54895:23"/>
                  <head>Of Queen Elizabeth.</head>
                  <l>WOnder of women, and of Queens, the breath</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Englands</hi> glory, was <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That quenched bonefires, which loud did proclaim</l>
                  <l>The Popiſh cruelty with tongues of flame.</l>
                  <l>To Proteſtants when ſhe brought liberty</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Friar-Bacons</hi> in their greaſe did fry.</l>
                  <l>That ſhe deceiv'd their wicked art, and fell</l>
                  <l>Not within power of their Magick ſpell,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Romiſh</hi> Bats afraid of Goſpel Light,</l>
                  <l>As much aſham'd, pull out their eyes for ſpight.</l>
                  <l>They to their private Maſſes run, one reads</l>
                  <l>He knows not what, yet ſtifly plyes his beads,</l>
                  <l>Sayes what he mindeth not; but makes a patter</l>
                  <l>When he poor ſoul knows nothing of the matter.</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Delver</hi> now are <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bibles found,</l>
                  <l>And brought to light, that were hid under ground.</l>
                  <l>Now are the clouds diſpel'd of that dark night,</l>
                  <l>Wherein the Word muſt not be brought to light.</l>
                  <l>From bondage Proteſtants are brought, before</l>
                  <l>They did lye under, promiſe have of more.</l>
                  <l>The Pope grows horn-mad, he will diſannull</l>
                  <l>All by (like wicked Holineſs) a Bull.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Spain</hi> (as moſt dutiful) the office bore</l>
                  <l>To be accounted beſt Son of the Whore,</l>
                  <l>And did appear with ſtout <hi>Rodomontado</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A ſudden, great, invincible <hi>Armado:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Cloſe link'd together: but the powe'rful One</l>
                  <l>Deſign'd to break them by their Union.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:54895:24"/>
The winds do blow till they are out of breath,</l>
                  <l>The ſeas are troubled threatning their death</l>
                  <l>That croſs'd them, and with proud intent durſt come</l>
                  <l>Of joyning Narrow Seas to Sea of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By envying command in them they gain</l>
                  <l>This fort, ſhe will be Lady of the <hi>Main.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Their intercepted, laden, ſhips amount</l>
                  <l>To their fear, loſs, ſhame, and to her account.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Denmarkian</hi> name was not a little bound</l>
                  <l>To her for riches, glory of its Sound.</l>
                  <l>Through her ſincerity <hi>Batavian,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When others loſe by forreign aids, did gain.</l>
                  <l>This was rare inſtance, for no o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her end,</l>
                  <l>To help diſtreſſed, but them to befriend:</l>
                  <l>When we are taught in <hi>Machiavellian</hi> School,</l>
                  <l>Firſt give aſſiſtance, after take the rule.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants the bounteous God do bleſs</l>
                  <l>With ſeaſonable ſuccours, and ſucceſs.</l>
                  <l>No more ingrate, than miſerable they,</l>
                  <l>Firſt diſoblige her, then become a prey.</l>
                  <l>Merchants, that Convoys ſlight, to Pyracies</l>
                  <l>Become an eaſier, and ſo richer prize:</l>
                  <l>So ſilly ſheep, when once the Shepherd's gone,</l>
                  <l>By lurking Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ves may ſoon be fed upon.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When 'tis too late</hi> they know to be more wiſe,</l>
                  <l>And learn the treach'rous Leaguers cruel <hi>Gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The forreign Lands, that boſomes had, have been</l>
                  <l>Moſt joyful there to lay our Merchants in:</l>
                  <l>That making their diſcoveries, did paſs</l>
                  <l>Through dreadful Lands of Ice, and S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as of Glaſs,</l>
                  <l>And what is ſtrange ſcarce ſuffered <hi>Terra</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Auſtralis</hi> to remain <hi>In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ognita.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of Navigation in each point did try</l>
                  <l>To make a perfect <hi>Encyclopedye.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:54895:24"/>
                  <head>Of Mary Magdalen.</head>
                  <l>OUr Saviour hath foretold, the lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gs of fame</l>
                  <l>Should ſtill indebted be to <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ies</hi> name;</l>
                  <l>That mirror of Gods mercy, once poſſeſt</l>
                  <l>By many evil ſpirits, made a bleſt</l>
                  <l>Houſe for the Holy Ghoſt. The blackeſt night</l>
                  <l>Of ſinful ſtate turn'd into glorious light.</l>
                  <l>Do not upbraid her that her crimes were ſuch:</l>
                  <l>All was forgiven, and ſhe loved much.</l>
                  <l>The coſtly Spicknard which ſhe poured forth</l>
                  <l>Upon his head, did not come near the worth</l>
                  <l>Of her great love. To thoſe, who grudged there</l>
                  <l>At needleſs waſte, Chriſt was not half ſo dear.</l>
                  <l>This humble handmaid judged it moſt meet</l>
                  <l>To ſit, as a Diſciple, at his feet,</l>
                  <l>And gather up the precious words, that fell</l>
                  <l>From the mouth of <hi>Rabbi Immanuel.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>His feet ſhe bathes in fountain of her eyes,</l>
                  <l>Them with the flaxen of her hairs ſhe dryes.</l>
                  <l>Her ſober ſadneſs he blaſphemes that jeers,</l>
                  <l>From her derives the cheat of Maudlin-tears.</l>
                  <l>And ſhe as holy women did ſupply</l>
                  <l>With purſe the humbled Alſufficiency.</l>
                  <l>And follows him at laſt, with drowned eyes</l>
                  <l>And broken heart, beholds him as he dyes;</l>
                  <l>Who at his death, and after was moſt dear,</l>
                  <l>His laſt care firſt appearance makes appear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Venus</hi> a female Planet ſo doth run</l>
                  <l>Her courſe, to wait upon the ſetting Sun;</l>
                  <l>And ſhe again gives notice by her bright</l>
                  <l>Rayes, of the coming of the Monarch light.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:54895:25"/>
                  <head>Of the Bleſſed Virgin Mary.</head>
                  <l>FEmales the holy Virgin did advance,</l>
                  <l>In bringing forth the worlds deliverance,</l>
                  <l>The bleſſed Child, of whom it's only ſaid,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe he could not lye, not credited;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe innocence, works, Miracles and all</l>
                  <l>Made him eſteem'd a greater Criminal;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>teſt ſervice, and ſouls anguiſh great,</l>
                  <l>We read in Rubrick of a bloody ſweat;</l>
                  <l>More deep concerns for man, than thoſe that riſe,</l>
                  <l>And freely ſpout out of the blood-ſhot-eyes;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſufferings ineffable impart,</l>
                  <l>Through pierced ſide, view of a weeping heart;</l>
                  <l>Who taſted bitter ſowre, that we might meet</l>
                  <l>In greateſt troubles, but with bitter ſweet.</l>
                  <l>Methinks at the report of thy Child's fame,</l>
                  <l>I ſee worlds wonders wonder, and to blame</l>
                  <l>Their builders proud, and coſtly folly, which</l>
                  <l>When he was made ſo poor, would make them rich.</l>
                  <l>When Lum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>narie of the day draws near,</l>
                  <l>The leſſer lights cannot for ſhame appear.</l>
                  <l>So greateſt Wonders at his coming fall,</l>
                  <l>Own him as Wonder greater much than all.</l>
                  <l>The ſtately Pyramids, the <hi>Memphian</hi> pride,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> abaſhed ſeek to hide,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of ſight and mind; for ſhame</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> bluſheth into flame.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>my</hi> ſeems to be,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> him that is Immenſity.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:54895:25"/>
Aegyptian <hi>Pha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>os</hi> wou'd officiouſly</l>
                  <l>Hold candle to this Wonder paſſing by:</l>
                  <l>But that poor watch-light nothing could confer,</l>
                  <l>To help the brightneſs of the Morning Star.</l>
                  <l>Olympick <hi>Jupiter</hi> like Statue ſtands,</l>
                  <l>For empty ſhew, with eyes, ears, mouth and hands.</l>
                  <l>In thee was Maſter-piece of Heaven aid;</l>
                  <l>Moſt curious work that ever Heaven made.</l>
                  <l>Had there gone out tax on the wit of all</l>
                  <l>Men on this Globe, wiſdom Angelica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>They could have carv'd with curioſity,</l>
                  <l>But better ſhap'd piece for <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Father hath expreſs'd his Image on</l>
                  <l>Pure Virgin-wax, and ta'n to Union</l>
                  <l>With God the ſecond Perſon; hence our true</l>
                  <l>Service, and adoration are due.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Carian</hi> boaſt <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſoleum</hi> dare not call</l>
                  <l>For any Rights, but ſilent burial</l>
                  <l>In rubbiſh; for its greateſt pride can go</l>
                  <l>For nothing more than Worms <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>raglio.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Much greater wonder is the Virgin Tomb,</l>
                  <l>Where never man was laid before. The womb</l>
                  <l>That bore him is more glorious; when the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>right</l>
                  <l>Sun for nine m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hs in <hi>Virgo</hi> lodg'd h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s light.</l>
                  <l>The ſtrong, and ſtately <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Compar'd to him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s no defence at all.</l>
                  <l>He's wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, much ſtronger than one made of ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e,</l>
                  <l>Or braſs, impregnable ſalvation.</l>
                  <l>To take the height of which, requ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>res much rather</l>
                  <l>Than a poor <hi>Jacobs Staff,</hi> a <hi>Jacobs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:54895:26"/>
               <head>The Character of an Accompliſhed and
Virtuous Woman.</head>
               <l>THy mind is happy, being ſeat of wit,</l>
               <l>More happy ſince diſcretion governs it:</l>
               <l>The former is the pretty fable, this</l>
               <l>Diſcretion grave the uſeful Moral is.</l>
               <l>As there irrationals do ſpeak what ſuites</l>
               <l>With ſolid reaſon, that men turn not brutes:</l>
               <l>So here child's taught the riddles to unfold</l>
               <l>Of gravity, a ſtripling to grow old.</l>
               <l>It ſtains not freſhneſs of thy youth to have,</l>
               <l>And to deſerve the Epithete of grave,</l>
               <l>Hated by them, whoſe bodies now grown cold,</l>
               <l>Make them in all reſpects, but prudence, old:</l>
               <l>But much concerns thee, time runs on ſo faſt</l>
               <l>With winged feet, and thou no better haſte</l>
               <l>Canſt make in judgement, that thy tender age</l>
               <l>By Antedate of prudence may be ſage.</l>
               <l>Leaveſt them to bluſh at their idle fears,</l>
               <l>That reckon it as Int'reſt in their years,</l>
               <l>To ſeem diſcreet, but yielding viler rate</l>
               <l>To Ladies, that are worn quite out of Date.</l>
               <l>Thou think'ſt not gravity doth then look beſt,</l>
               <l>Expoſed when to laughter in a jeſt,</l>
               <l>Or that becoming wit, which doth afford</l>
               <l>To make the author of it more abſurd.</l>
               <l>Thou ſeek'ſt with grandam-virtues to adorn</l>
               <l>Thy ſelf, when youthful vanities are worn</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:54895:26"/>
By perſons much more aged, to yield ſtrong</l>
               <l>Preſumption to the world that they are young:</l>
               <l>That ſeem to reckon it as an exceſs</l>
               <l>Either to practiſe virtue or profeſs:</l>
               <l>Admit into their <hi>Ethicks</hi> modeſty</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Apocope'd,</hi> without a Civil tye:</l>
               <l>Serving all wanton modes : thus pieviſh wag</l>
               <l>Spoileth the lace by pulling off the Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>Thoſe, that in too great freedom draw not near</l>
               <l>Occaſions foul, are judged too ſevere:</l>
               <l>As though plain Modeſty deſerv'd no thanks,</l>
               <l>Careful, how it approaches nigh the banks</l>
               <l>Of fouleſt baſeneſs: their preſumption thinks,</l>
               <l>It's want of reſolution fears the brinks.</l>
               <l>A vulgar unapproved innocence</l>
               <l>Deſerving not at all Heroick ſence.</l>
               <l>They'l have you think, if you have faith enough,</l>
               <l>They're innocent as child new born, although</l>
               <l>They tempt the wanton Reveller to try</l>
               <l>What guard is kept upon their honeſty.</l>
               <l>Strength of thy reſolution is bely'd,</l>
               <l>If it be thought to be leſs fortifi'd</l>
               <l>Becauſe of caution : rather might it tell,</l>
               <l>Againſt wild ſtorms it is impregnable.</l>
               <l>If any, in repute grown outlaw'd, comes,</l>
               <l>Aſſaults with levity, and beats the drums</l>
               <l>Of thy chaſte ears, he finds there is no charm</l>
               <l>To win thy heart, but make thy virtues arm,</l>
               <l>Vileneſs of his attempts expoſed lye</l>
               <l>Set out in colours of <hi>Vermilion-dye.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That he may ſee his rudeneſs, take the ſhame,</l>
               <l>Thou lend'ſt the <hi>Taper</hi> of thy modeſt ſlame.</l>
               <l>When exhalations thick the air do muddy,</l>
               <l>So the bright Ruler of the morn looks ruddy.</l>
               <l>If highneſs to debaſe upon the ſtage,</l>
               <l>And folly mask with an abſtemious rage;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:54895:27"/>
If to feed corrupt fancy with the veins</l>
               <l>Of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>evity in ſome Romantick ſtrains;</l>
               <l>If lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty traverſing muſt be alone</l>
               <l>Accounted gallant education;</l>
               <l>Thou wilt take up with grave, and antient ſort</l>
               <l>Of b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eeding, and not be leſs nobler for't.</l>
               <l>The Lillyes candour, and the bluſhing Roſe,</l>
               <l>A temper neither frolick, nor moioſe,</l>
               <l>Pleaſantneſs mixed well with gravity,</l>
               <l>A grace deportment, ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ron-like, and free;</l>
               <l>The ſweeteſt condeſcenſion, not abject,</l>
               <l>Or ſordid to command, and to affect</l>
               <l>Obliging carriage, which admired makes</l>
               <l>Rather than feared, as it was it takes,</l>
               <l>Not too high, nor familiar, to prevent</l>
               <l>Both the extreams of hatred, and contempt</l>
               <l>Are thy true glories, not for ſhew, but uſe,</l>
               <l>Need not bear judgement true, or beg excuſe.</l>
               <l>Let loſty Mounters proudly ſcale the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kye</l>
               <l>With fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zled, ſparkling bravery, and dye.</l>
               <l>Let <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t vis</hi> with exhalations fed,</l>
               <l>Glutted with vapour, be ſoon famiſhed.</l>
               <l>Let Potentares be ſwoln up big with Titles</l>
               <l>In Honours Volumes but the ſmalleſt tittles.</l>
               <l>Let proud <hi>Phantaſtes</hi> much admire his Minion</l>
               <l>A ragged, ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and beggarly Opinion.</l>
               <l>Thy praiſe is in thy ſelf, not put to death</l>
               <l>By ſpiteful ſtopping of anothers breath.</l>
               <l>To thee, without true excellence, 'tis naught,</l>
               <l>Great, and right Honourable, to be thought:</l>
               <l>Since it is more to be, than only ſeem;</l>
               <l>To merit glory, than to have eſteem.</l>
               <l>To appear great to world doſt not aſpire,</l>
               <l>But (if to vulgar ſight leſs) to be higher,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt haughtineſs fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dly advancing Creſt</l>
               <l>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'eth her own Fools-Coat the Nobleſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:54895:27"/>
Becauſe it's gaudy: Scripture He aldry</l>
               <l>Gives the much better plain Humility.</l>
               <l>Thy ſelf-denyal is a noble feat,</l>
               <l>For greateſt <hi>Alexander</hi> far too great;</l>
               <l>Too high for them whoſe ſoaring aims were bent</l>
               <l>To gain the title of Magnificent.</l>
               <l>It's truly honourable to deſpiſe</l>
               <l>That which the greateſt Monarcl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s idolize.</l>
               <l>Ambition lawful is, and the intent</l>
               <l>Bleſſed, in goodneſs to be excellent;</l>
               <l>After good facts performing to Commerce,</l>
               <l>And take the high degrees of Eminence.</l>
               <l>The touring thoughts of pride, that do advance</l>
               <l>Their lofty heads by Goſpel Ordinance,</l>
               <l>Thou batter'ſt down. Pray'r, faſtings do confer</l>
               <l>To make thee humble, a ſelf Leveller.</l>
               <l>Before thou waſt ſince that thy power to be</l>
               <l>Depended on Gods Alſufficiency;</l>
               <l>That could produce. Thy futurition ſtated</l>
               <l>Was from the will, and virtue that created.</l>
               <l>Beauty, wit, greatneſs, honour thou'lt confeſs,</l>
               <l>But as they are deriv'd from God, are leſs</l>
               <l>Than nothing in act ſafely canſt maintain</l>
               <l>Them leſs than leſs than Nothing told again:</l>
               <l>Nor are nor can be real, but hang on</l>
               <l>The judgements greateſt Contradiction.</l>
               <l>Theſe realliz'd thou thankfully doſt own,</l>
               <l>Becauſe that they are thine, and not thy own;</l>
               <l>Thine, as to payment of a grateful mind;</l>
               <l>Thine, not to free from duty, but to bind;</l>
               <l>So not thine own a worthineſs to raiſe</l>
               <l>In ſelf, but what redoundeth to his praiſe.</l>
               <l>In this God muſt be ſole without compare,</l>
               <l>Since it is granted, Nothing hath no ſhare.</l>
               <l>Beauty ſo many envy, and admire;</l>
               <l>Honour few ſeek to merit, but acquire.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:54895:28"/>
Riches that ſuffer not the owner ſleep;</l>
               <l>Health many ſeek to Court, but few to keep.</l>
               <l>Thouſand degrees are ſhort of parallel</l>
               <l>To Grace, wherein thou ſtriveſt to excell</l>
               <l>Tranſcendently becoming humble, ſo</l>
               <l>What moſt advanceth thee, ſtill makes thee low,</l>
               <l>Thy native vileneſs truly to confeſs;</l>
               <l>And real greatneſs makes thee ſo much leſs</l>
               <l>In the eſteem of ſelf, yet on this ſcore</l>
               <l>Thy worth and modeſty deſerve the more.</l>
               <l>Thy ſpeeches pithy, ſolid, give a light</l>
               <l>Compoſed to inſtruct, and to delight,</l>
               <l>Serious, and pleaſant, witty, pertinent,</l>
               <l>Grave, pat, and proper, fit for each intent,</l>
               <l>With pleaſure hearer, that may entertain</l>
               <l>And recompence with profitable gain.</l>
               <l>Much unlike theirs, who troubled with the lask</l>
               <l>Or looſneſs of the tongue relate, and ask,</l>
               <l>Not with deſire to be inform'd, or break</l>
               <l>Somewhat material to be known, but ſpeak</l>
               <l>What ſavours ill. Let men pretend their fears</l>
               <l>How to ſuch laviſh tongues they lend their ears,</l>
               <l>Pleaſant their fancies too in laying ten</l>
               <l>To one they never have them back agen,</l>
               <l>Or not without the wrong of foul abuſe.</l>
               <l>Thou payeſt precious ear-rings for the uſe</l>
               <l>Of ſome few ſhort-liv'd Minutes, what is heard</l>
               <l>From thee, ſhall be their pleaſure, and reward.</l>
               <l>Thy words as they imploy ſo do they whet,</l>
               <l>Both exerciſe attention, and beget,</l>
               <l>They ſatisfie, not cloy. By what is ſaid</l>
               <l>Hearer indebted it, as well as paid.</l>
               <l>Thy Counſels are reſolving Medicines,</l>
               <l>Swaſions, attractives, reproofs, Anodynes,</l>
               <l>Where the diſcreet, and tender management</l>
               <l>Make not the ſmalleſt part of Argument.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:54895:28"/>
Whilſt vain talk Melancholy doth increaſe;</l>
               <l>Inſtead of helping, adds to the diſeaſe,</l>
               <l>Lifts up the ſpirits in tranſports, withall</l>
               <l>By their depreſſion gives the ſadder fall.</l>
               <l>Good Cordials skilfully compounded hit</l>
               <l>The cauſe, and ſo alleviate the fit:</l>
               <l>So thy well temper'd ſpeeches are more ſure</l>
               <l>Way to give eaſe, and to effect the cure.</l>
               <l>Thy prudent humble meekneſs beſt can tame</l>
               <l>Anger, when fury would the more inflame.</l>
               <l>When over-haſty <hi>Romans</hi> do oppoſe</l>
               <l>The ſtronger cunning <hi>Carthaginian</hi> grows,</l>
               <l>And more ſucceſsful, but ſoon melts away</l>
               <l>By greater force of <hi>Fabian</hi>-delay.</l>
               <l>Quitting is ſtratagem to win the field,</l>
               <l>The way at once to overcome, and yield;</l>
               <l>Never the baſe regarding, petty harms</l>
               <l>Shall caſt diſgrace upon thy Coat of Arms.</l>
               <l>Thy Victories are not diſhonoured,</l>
               <l>As where the Conquerour is vanquiſhed.</l>
               <l>They of true triumph want the greater half,</l>
               <l>That conquer other Monarchs, but not ſelf.</l>
               <l>You that will have your nature judged by</l>
               <l>Laughter at good (ſome Ladies property)</l>
               <l>Come ſee the ugly face of your offence,</l>
               <l>In Mirror of unmoved Patience.</l>
               <l>By wrong would you provoke her? That doth move</l>
               <l>Her to provoke you ſo much more to love.</l>
               <l>Or will you calumn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es caſt? Her defence</l>
               <l>Is not the like reproach; but Innocence.</l>
               <l>In vain contend you with her, whoſe conteſt</l>
               <l>Is (not to get the better) to be beſt.</l>
               <l>She knows, they who by paſſion moſt have won,</l>
               <l>Will ſo much ſooner prove to be undone.</l>
               <l>They run in debt, that ſltrive to give offence</l>
               <l>To others, owe the greater recompence,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:54895:29"/>
An undeſerved taunt or wicked curſe</l>
               <l>Can make her virtue not a jot the worſe,</l>
               <l>What malice caſts upon, whilſt not within,</l>
               <l>Is the reproach of others, not her ſin.</l>
               <l>Were talk true Judge, the good then only might</l>
               <l>Be good by favour, and be bad by ſpight:</l>
               <l>Whilſt ſome do in their needleſs viſits rome,</l>
               <l>Till they be greateſt ſtrangers to their home;</l>
               <l>Gadding as though they to the world were ſent</l>
               <l>To be imploy'd in what's Impertinent;</l>
               <l>As if their birth did priviledge by right</l>
               <l>Them to caſt off the care, and overſight</l>
               <l>Of houſe-concerns: thou keep'ſt thy wonted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rack</l>
               <l>Through each task of thy painful <hi>Zodiack.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Like the bright Champion of the day, that rowls</l>
               <l>His flaming eye toward the diſtant Poles</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arctick Antarctick,</hi> vieweth both the <hi>Tropicks,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Seas <hi>Tartarian,</hi> and <hi>Aethiopicks.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou art accompliſhed with quickeſt ſenſe</l>
               <l>In wiſe forecaſt, and careful Providence,</l>
               <l>With memory fitly to recollect,</l>
               <l>And care in all things makes thee circumſpect.</l>
               <l>Not ſuff'ring Medler in thy houſe to grow</l>
               <l>That's open-headed, nor unuſeful ſlow:</l>
               <l>For ſlothful ſervants ſhould there be no blame</l>
               <l>When idle, lazy thou wouldſt force for ſhame</l>
               <l>By thy example them, that wait on thee,</l>
               <l>To be affected to good huſwifry.</l>
               <l>They in their orbs muſt take their light from thine,</l>
               <l>So they are made to ſerve, as well as ſhine.</l>
               <l>By friends perſwaſions, or thy fancy catch'd,</l>
               <l>To ſome prodigious temper art thou match'd,</l>
               <l>Or marry'd rather, to draw out in care</l>
               <l>Thy vexed life with a familiar;</l>
               <l>One that proves moſt unſuitable, whoſe gall</l>
               <l>O'reflowing fills the houſe with hateful braul.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:54895:29"/>
Thy Phyſick is not uſual by keen</l>
               <l>Reproofs, ill-ſavouring to mend his ſpleen,</l>
               <l>Repreſs his choler, ſweetly to endure</l>
               <l>Thy Ethicks tell thee is the way to cure.</l>
               <l>Where bombards cannot any breaches make,</l>
               <l>A milder fiege is found the way, to take.</l>
               <l>Aſſoon the ſhackles of the <hi>Perſian</hi> King,</l>
               <l>Or idle Ceremony of a Ring</l>
               <l>Preſented by Pope to his <hi>Zani,</hi> may</l>
               <l>Bind <hi>Helleſpout,</hi> oblige rough <hi>Adria</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To calmneſs, as ſharp quips, loud bluſt'ring can</l>
               <l>Correct the madneſs of the chur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h man.</l>
               <l>This piece of rigour, <hi>Nabaliſme,</hi> rage,</l>
               <l>If curable, thou'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t break by <hi>Saxifrage</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of patience, and diſcretion. When dint</l>
               <l>Of reaſon cannot, meekneſs breaks the flin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>But, if ſome paſſion break forth, 'tis thy ſtrong</l>
               <l>Deſire, endeavour that it dye when young.</l>
               <l>Thou wilt not be at fruitleſs pains to nurſe</l>
               <l>That, which as it grows elder groweth w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſe.</l>
               <l>Is he with fury charcoal'd, of deſire</l>
               <l>That ſofteſt breath makes him ſpit ſparks of fire.</l>
               <l>Thy ſilence from his rage ſhall take ſupply.</l>
               <l>Anger, as fire, if't have no air will dye.</l>
               <l>If glitt'ring pretences do'nt abuſe</l>
               <l>The can dour of thy judgement; but thou chooſe</l>
               <l>With love that is not blind aſſociate,</l>
               <l>That may yield double comfort to thy ſtate.</l>
               <l>Not Cynical, nor worthleſs paſſions ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve,</l>
               <l>But with a ſweet complayſance that is grave,</l>
               <l>Whoſe gentle nature more deſigns to draw</l>
               <l>With moſt obliging carriage, than to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</l>
               <l>With ſtern looks, inſolent commands: then you</l>
               <l>Cannot but hit the Golden Rule of two</l>
               <l>In Matrimonial fellowſhip, where one</l>
               <l>Heart, joy, concern, care, tongue make U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſon.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:54895:30"/>
No emulation, who ſhall be above</l>
               <l>To govern, rule, command, controul; but love.</l>
               <l>Strive who ſhall pleaſe moſt, and contention</l>
               <l>Is ſtrong on both ſides that there may be none.</l>
               <l>Thy ſnares are harmleſly to gain. Each gin</l>
               <l>Diſcreetly by thee laid is but to win.</l>
               <l>In joy, ſucceſs, his ſorrows, loſſes too</l>
               <l>Thou challengeſt for Joynture half as due.</l>
               <l>With his content thy cheerfulneſs will mingle;</l>
               <l>Thy perſon is not, nor are croſſes ſingle.</l>
               <l>By Catechizing, good inſtruction</l>
               <l>To help fault of the firſt Tranſgreſſion,</l>
               <l>And ſad fruit thence ariſing to redreſs</l>
               <l>To moſt things ſteril: but to barrenneſs</l>
               <l>Thou doſt endeavour, that thoſe of the earth</l>
               <l>May be made happy by a ſecond birth</l>
               <l>To holineſs; and thus thy pray'rs, and toyl</l>
               <l>May be rewarded by a fruitful ſoyl:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With the</hi> ſincere milk of the Word <hi>doſt nurſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To make them bleſſings, and take off the curſe,</l>
               <l>Whereby they growing up afford the gain</l>
               <l>Of joy much greater than thy former pain.</l>
               <l>So toyling husband-man beholding fate</l>
               <l>And curſe upon the earth degenerate</l>
               <l>Grubs up the ſhrubs, thorns, bryars, and then ploughs,</l>
               <l>Harrows, and ſowes his ſeed with ſweating brows;</l>
               <l>And thus by manifold encreaſe obtains</l>
               <l>Againſt the curſe, what will reward his pains.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Midas</hi> may wiſh for golden ſhowres and Mountains,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Atla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tick</hi> hortyards and true Cryſtal fountains,</l>
               <l>That all his Roms might bear as precious fleece,</l>
               <l>As that which was fetch'd by the youths of <hi>Greece.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His fields were <hi>Or,</hi> and <hi>Argent,</hi> nought to breed</l>
               <l>But precious money-wort, and ſilver-weed;</l>
               <l>Or pray that all his Cockle Oyſter-ſhells</l>
               <l>With precious pearls were fil'd, and nothing elſe;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:54895:30"/>
That he may keep his <hi>Lent</hi> upon each fiſh,</l>
               <l>As rich as that in <hi>Polycrates</hi> diſh.</l>
               <l>Thy earneſt prayer is a great deal wiſer,</l>
               <l>Than what obtain'd would alwayes make a Miſer.</l>
               <l>Therefore doſt thou implore the power above,</l>
               <l>Thy heart may be good ſoil for Johns-wort-Love,</l>
               <l>Contentment which yields hearts eaſe, and true hope</l>
               <l>Directed unto Chriſt as <hi>Heliotrope;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With reſolution which ſtill groweth beſt,</l>
               <l>As famous Palm the more it is oppreſs'd,</l>
               <l>And ſober temper, wherein doth conſiſt</l>
               <l>More virtue than in precious <hi>Amethyſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As <hi>Corals</hi> colour's ſaid to ſympathize</l>
               <l>With the diſtemper'd wearer, that thine eyes</l>
               <l>May Weather-glaſſes be, whereby to ſhew,</l>
               <l>Whether with Gods Church it be high or low.</l>
               <l>Thy Alms are ſtirring, not to get a Name,</l>
               <l>As other people do to do the ſame;</l>
               <l>Turning what is by bounteous Heaven ſent,</l>
               <l>Not into pity by a complement.</l>
               <l>But thy Compaſſion joyn'd to Gods command</l>
               <l>Enlarge thy tender heart, make lib'ral hand.</l>
               <l>An heart without good works, is in true ſenſe,</l>
               <l>No part of charity, but a pretence.</l>
               <l>Where is ability, the poor have part,</l>
               <l>And a large ſhare both in thy goods, and heart.</l>
               <l>Many do pamper up themſelves in luſt,</l>
               <l>With diſhes, which <hi>Apician</hi> fancy muſt</l>
               <l>Be tortur'd for, the Appetite to fill,</l>
               <l>Whilſt they make Reaſon baſeſt Manciple.</l>
               <l>Yet when the poor are almoſt famiſhed,</l>
               <l>Can nothing more afford than <hi>Be ye ſed</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Have guts, no bowels to receive the cry</l>
               <l>And moans of pining hard <hi>Neceſſity.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But what is debt, thy wiſdom makes a Loan,</l>
               <l>Which layeth out for him what is thine own;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:54895:31"/>
Knowing for his that be diſpos'd is juſt,</l>
               <l>Which no way's thine, but only upon truſt.</l>
               <l>When wanton <hi>Venuſſes</hi> do plait their hairs,</l>
               <l>With frizled treſſes make pernicious ſnares,</l>
               <l>Whileſt theſe <hi>Ara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nes</hi> weave their Cobweb thin</l>
               <l>Better to catch unwary Gallants in;</l>
               <l>Disfigure nature, and deform themſelves,</l>
               <l>By patching, painting to take loveſome <hi>Elves;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With <hi>Heliogabalus</hi> Monopolize</l>
               <l>Adventures of the ſtrangeſt rarities;</l>
               <l>Torment <hi>Phantaſtes</hi> brain, till he can find</l>
               <l>Out modes, and faſhions changing with their mind;</l>
               <l>Put the <hi>Cameleon</hi> to't, and <hi>Proteus</hi> too</l>
               <l>To put on ſhapes, and colours that are new;</l>
               <l>Take Adders hearts to raiſe their jolly ſtrains;</l>
               <l>Drink Viper-wine, till it drink up their brain,</l>
               <l>To keep them freſh: By <hi>Cleopatra</hi> taught,</l>
               <l>Swallow ten thouſand drachmas at a draught;</l>
               <l>Thus vainly giving up into the hand</l>
               <l>Of viler Corporal the chief Command,</l>
               <l>About the body taking chiefeſt care,</l>
               <l>Make it appear, how idle ſouls they are,</l>
               <l>No pains, no coſt is thought too much, that can</l>
               <l>Contribute to enrich the inner man</l>
               <l>With glorious excellencies, and impart</l>
               <l>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> greater gracefulneſs unto thy heart.</l>
               <l>Thy wiſe concern is deeper than the skin,</l>
               <l>Truly to be all beautiful within.</l>
               <l>Thy ornaments are ſuch, as we are told,</l>
               <l>Were made the Matrons bravery of old.</l>
               <l>If things be duly prized, when they are</l>
               <l>The fartheſt fetch'd, and deareſt bought; how rare</l>
               <l>Are they, which from the throne of Heaven ſought,</l>
               <l>By no leſs than the blood of God were bought?</l>
               <l>If things have value, which do ſo much pleaſe</l>
               <l>The eyes of men; how precious then are theſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:54895:31"/>
That take Gods heart, whoſe approbation</l>
               <l>Gives worth unto the things which elſe have none?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eaſtern,</hi> and <hi>Weſtern Indies,</hi> that entomb</l>
               <l>So much admired riches in their womb;</l>
               <l>The great adventures which were purchas'd by</l>
               <l>The <hi>Romiſh Catholick</hi> humanity,</l>
               <l>And fill'd the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> coffers, are much leſs</l>
               <l>Than what from Heavens gift thou doſt poſſeſs.</l>
               <l>Ten thouſand millions, if ſum'd up, are ſmall</l>
               <l>And nothing, when compared to thine All.</l>
               <l>Moſt precious Diamonds to fight can bring</l>
               <l>But dazled luſtre, or weak glimmering.</l>
               <l>The Queen of Heaven, Conſtellations bright</l>
               <l>Make not the day, but mend the diſmal night.</l>
               <l>When Heavens Champion doth but ſhew his face,</l>
               <l>Affrighted darkneſs ſoon reſigns its place.</l>
               <l>Thou art thrice happy, that receiveſt ray</l>
               <l>Of Chriſt the glorious Sun, that makes thy day.</l>
               <l>What did the Learned Heathens once advance</l>
               <l>But ſubtle piece of ſplendid ignorance?</l>
               <l>Led by the Taper of their Reaſons light,</l>
               <l>That farthing-candle mended but their night,</l>
               <l>That had no ſaving knowledge. <hi>Argus</hi>'s eyes</l>
               <l>Leſs power have, than this one to be wiſe.</l>
               <l>The pleaſant picture ſeems to ſport, and play</l>
               <l>With wanton glance converted ev'ry way,</l>
               <l>Or ſtand before, or turn to either ſide,</l>
               <l>Look at it, and you ſeem to be eſpy'd:</l>
               <l>So carnal minds ſeem great things to eſpy,</l>
               <l>Yet all but with a dead, and painted eye,</l>
               <l>Compar'd to thine, where the moſt real ſight</l>
               <l>Proceedeth from a clear celeſtial light.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dives</hi> with delicates was daily fed</l>
               <l>Yet he poor ſoul did want thy daily bread,</l>
               <l>Who ſet at Wiſdoms table doſt enjoy</l>
               <l>Dainties, that do refreſh, feed, fill, not cloy.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:54895:32"/>
Worldlings like Serpents, or Cameleons, are</l>
               <l>Nouriſh'd with clogging duſt or empty air:</l>
               <l>Deſire inſatiate hath painted diſhes,</l>
               <l>That more inflame the heart with idle wiſhes.</l>
               <l>As riches multiply upon men; ſo</l>
               <l>The dropſie of their greedineſs doth grow,</l>
               <l>And vaſtneſs of eſtate doth make them ſcant,</l>
               <l>Greater the fulneſs is, the greater want.</l>
               <l>Thy lowlineſs of mind, doth make thee higher;</l>
               <l>By want thou art enrich'd with good deſire;</l>
               <l>Which makes thee after Living God to pant,</l>
               <l>To gain more plentiful eſtate by want.</l>
               <l>The greateſt Monarchs would much richer be,</l>
               <l>Were they enriched by thy Poverty.</l>
               <l>The baſer ſons of earth do fall upon</l>
               <l>Ignoble game, and feed on carrion.</l>
               <l>Thy nobler mind aſpireth to attain,</l>
               <l>Though at expence of loſſes, more to gain</l>
               <l>Of the Angelical, and pleaſant food</l>
               <l>Moſt ſatisfying, and eternal good.</l>
               <l>Nor will thy ſtrong deſires ceaſe to aſcend,</l>
               <l>Until enjoyment to hope put an end.</l>
               <l>Circumvolution of few ſliding hours</l>
               <l>In ſeaſon leſs benign fade ſweeteſt flowres;</l>
               <l>The mighty works of Architecture pay</l>
               <l>At length their debt to Nature in decay,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Hieroglyphick</hi> Serpent that ſets bounds</l>
               <l>To mortals beings with its numerous rounds,</l>
               <l>That will have gnaw'd to pieces in ſome while</l>
               <l>The world, though it were mettal hard as file,</l>
               <l>Hath bury'd tombs, and monuments ſhall be</l>
               <l>The ſpoil and triumph of eternity.</l>
               <l>Thy ornaments are of celeſtial mould</l>
               <l>By longeſt tract of time that grow not old,</l>
               <l>Not ſubject to the thief, moth, ruſt, or waſte,</l>
               <l>Or to be leſſen'd by the time that's paſt;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:54895:32"/>
Still ſhall be freſh, have no relation</l>
               <l>To the vile worm or baſe corruption.</l>
               <l>To thee that makeſt it thy care to look</l>
               <l>For happieſt eſtate in Doomeſday Book,</l>
               <l>And waiteſt for the everlaſting bliſs,</l>
               <l>A Term too ſhort Fee-ſimple ever is.</l>
               <l>Each gate of th' heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is repreſented by a precious Gem.</l>
               <l>How glorious then ſhall daughter of the King</l>
               <l>Appear? whoſe grace will have eternal ſpring</l>
               <l>And perfect growth; who treading on the Moon,</l>
               <l>Shall be compleatly clothed with the Sun</l>
               <l>Of righteouſneſs; to whom <hi>Don Phoebus</hi> bright</l>
               <l>That rules the day, affords but Gloworm light:</l>
               <l>When there ſhall be no ſhadow, nor decay,</l>
               <l>No ſhowres, no clouds, to ſtain the perfect day.</l>
               <l>Here learn you to be wiſe, whoſe careleſs care</l>
               <l>Is to ſleep, dreſs, feaſt, chat, and take the air;</l>
               <l>Whoſe idle work when rarely ſet upon,</l>
               <l>And to do nothing almoſt are all one;</l>
               <l>Whoſe planetary lives are chiefly ſpent</l>
               <l>In the Exchange of frothy Complement.</l>
               <l>With you the antient virtues are much more</l>
               <l>Grown out of faſhion than the clothes they wore:</l>
               <l>Your ſhame is to be fix'd amongſt the Stars,</l>
               <l>By vanity of your lewd <hi>Jupiters,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That much admire you, to enſnare their eyes,</l>
               <l>As do the painted, powd'red Butterflyes</l>
               <l>Some little children, and for nothing elſe</l>
               <l>To be admir'd by Merchants; but your ſhells</l>
               <l>Like ſcented <hi>Panthers</hi> that deſtroy, and pleaſe</l>
               <l>And poyſon, as the bright <hi>Cantharides.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Why ſo high born brave Dames? None of you can</l>
               <l>Draw out your lives inch longer than the ſpan</l>
               <l>Deſign'd. Why ſwell you big with thoughts of birth?</l>
               <l>The Worm's your Siſter, and your Mother Earth.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:54895:33"/>
Are you with travel of your Mother grown</l>
               <l>Noble? The labour then was not your own</l>
               <l>Or doth your honour come by being march'd?</l>
               <l>That light is borrow'd from the fool you catch'd.</l>
               <l>Do you your ſelves by fame, that's common, prize?</l>
               <l>That, when the giddy humour's over, dyes.</l>
               <l>As bubble ſwoln with empty' air doth laſt</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me thoughts, not many, longer than the blaſt.</l>
               <l>One breath blows up, and breaks this wat'ry bail,</l>
               <l>And half a Minute is its Spring and Fall.</l>
               <l>What, is it not enough, ſome to imploy</l>
               <l>To <hi>Indies</hi> moſt remote, to fetch a toy,</l>
               <l>Or precious tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fle, yet all this to dreſs,</l>
               <l>And to equip your rotten carkaſſes?</l>
               <l>But that the Artiſt black muſt run to Hell</l>
               <l>To fetch your fortunes, and return to tell?</l>
               <l>Shall wandr'ing Gipſies, and that wicked Crew</l>
               <l>Of Vagrants, that pretend as if they knew</l>
               <l>Future Contingents, have your charity,</l>
               <l>And be rewarded for the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r cheating lye?</l>
               <l>Whereas the godly Miniſters that bear</l>
               <l>Affection to your ſouls ſcarce gain your ear?</l>
               <l>When they declare the woful ſtate of ſin,</l>
               <l>And miſery you are involved in</l>
               <l>By nature, ſhew reſtor'd you cannot be</l>
               <l>To ſight, unleſs you know you do not ſee;</l>
               <l>And ſend you to the Son of God, whoſe bright</l>
               <l>Rayes to the Saints in Heaven give a light.</l>
               <l>They tell you you are dead in ſin, and give</l>
               <l>This token of their love, to wiſh you live.</l>
               <l>Direct you unto Chriſt, your life, whereby</l>
               <l>You may have health, wealth, and true liberty.</l>
               <l>Since you will know the things that are to come,</l>
               <l>Out of the Word they read the dreadful Doom</l>
               <l>Of all that have no intereſt in him,</l>
               <l>If they continue in their death and ſin.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:54895:33"/>
Shall yet a coſtly patch amount to more</l>
               <l>Than what ye ever gave unto the poor?</l>
               <l>Shall they that ſighing do reprove you, have</l>
               <l>No better thanks than Clown, or ſaw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Knave?</l>
               <l>May your faults acted be, and not be told?</l>
               <l>Will you not be perſwaded you are old?</l>
               <l>Or ſo ſhall be e'relong? Why bring you down</l>
               <l>The rate of A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e which is a glorious Crown</l>
               <l>In righteouſneſs? Would you have death to come</l>
               <l>And Complement your Honours to the Tomb?</l>
               <l>Or will you bid him ſtay below? For why,</l>
               <l>You are not yet in humour brought to dye.</l>
               <l>And to prevent his viſit, ſend to tell,</l>
               <l>That you are buſie, or not very well.</l>
               <l>Death is a Doctor, ſuch you'l ſcarce endure,</l>
               <l>That killeth all; yet not a few doth cure.</l>
               <l>Will you like <hi>Jezabels</hi> your faces paint,</l>
               <l>And think withal, that Serjeant grim to daunt</l>
               <l>With your imperious looks? In vain ye do'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</l>
               <l>He'l not be ſcar'd, but tread you under foot.</l>
               <l>Thy body to neglect, thou'lt not endure;</l>
               <l>And muſt thy ſoul be then a <hi>ſine Cure?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O fooliſh thoughts, pains, wiſhes vain, which are</l>
               <l>Not to be holy, humble, meek, but fair!</l>
               <l>For ſhame let not ſuch golden ſeaſons paſs</l>
               <l>Upon your boards, beds, ſports, or looking-glaſs.</l>
               <l>Cut off ſome minutes toward the concern</l>
               <l>Of what the world deſpiſeth ſempitern.</l>
               <l>Why look you on Religion as a Dame,</l>
               <l>That is too homely, beareth not a name</l>
               <l>Amongſt vain Ranters; with ſeverities</l>
               <l>Of mortifying zeal doth blear her eyes;</l>
               <l>Deforms her viſage, and forbids all airs</l>
               <l>Of merriment to pine her ſelf with cares,</l>
               <l>And dreadful thoughts in a tormented life,</l>
               <l>That none but fools would chooſe her for a Wife,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:54895:34"/>
Gallants will ſcarce afford Civility,</l>
               <l>To ſerve the Cuſtome of a Cap, and knee.</l>
               <l>Her noble quality well underſtood,</l>
               <l>Would ſhew her great, and of the Royal blood.</l>
               <l>It's not below beſt of moſt Princely houſe,</l>
               <l>To Court her Ladyſhip, and to eſpouſe.</l>
               <l>So excellent is beauty of this Saint,</l>
               <l>It cannot be worſe injur'd than by paint.</l>
               <l>Her vaſt eſtate is not confined by</l>
               <l>The bounds too narrow of <hi>Geography.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>All the Gold, Silver, Pearls, Fruits this Globe bears</l>
               <l>To one of many Jewels that ſhe wears,</l>
               <l>Bear no compare in value; if not you,</l>
               <l>Yet this the wiſeſt Merchants have found true,</l>
               <l>The teſtimony of good Conſcience,</l>
               <l>That there hath been a thorough ſight, and ſenſe</l>
               <l>Of odious ſin, ſo pow'rful as to make</l>
               <l>The ſoul, with hatred, ſin and ſelf forſake,</l>
               <l>And cleave to Chriſt, reſting on him alone,</l>
               <l>With conſtant holy life reflected on</l>
               <l>Through Gods great mercy do afford more true,</l>
               <l>Laſting, great, cordial joy than that which you</l>
               <l>Conceive to be had by the looſing reins</l>
               <l>Of Civil temper, to run into ſtrains</l>
               <l>Of jollity, ſcrew'd up to higheſt pin</l>
               <l>Of madneſs, that you may not feel your ſin:</l>
               <l>Yours is but heartleſs laughter; for your ſinning,</l>
               <l>Maketh a foul, and but convulſive grinning;</l>
               <l>Not unlike the <hi>Sardinian</hi> herb, whereby</l>
               <l>Men only ſeem to laugh; but ſurely dye.</l>
               <l>You ſay Gods mercy you rely upon:</l>
               <l>Is it good hope, or bold preſumption?</l>
               <l>Speak out your meaning; and be underſtood:</l>
               <l>Will you be wicked, becauſe God is good?</l>
               <l>And is it gratitude, ſo to abuſe</l>
               <l>The mercy, which you thankfully ſhould uſe?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:54895:34"/>
To ſerve the perfect Being with decayes,</l>
               <l>And him that's alwayes preſent, with delayes?</l>
               <l>At diſtance pleaſures of the earth appear</l>
               <l>Greater; grow leſſer much, as they draw near.</l>
               <l>Their promiſes ſhifting delayes you find,</l>
               <l>Why do you not then ſerve them in their kind?</l>
               <l>Say, this were granted, you might on ſtill run</l>
               <l>In vanity to your <hi>Declining Sun,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And meet with no arreſt to ſtop career</l>
               <l>Of mirth, or cauſe the ſadneſs of a tear.</l>
               <l>What will the end be? Will dry bones, dim eyes,</l>
               <l>Decrepit acts, be fit for Sacrifice?</l>
               <l>Is it meet, Sin, World, Devil have the prime</l>
               <l>Of vigour, beauty, action, ſtrength, and time?</l>
               <l>And he that for all mind, heart, might doth call</l>
               <l>Have moſt deformed, weakeſt part of all?</l>
               <l>Will you preſent the firſt fruits unto ſin?</l>
               <l>Leave the poor ſhare, and gleanings unto him?</l>
               <l>And what, I pray, are offers like to get,</l>
               <l>When you are old, but a prolong'd <hi>Not yet?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Although to act your follies, nought can move</l>
               <l>With ſo much pleaſure; Will you ceaſe to love</l>
               <l>The vanities you cannot act? What force</l>
               <l>Muſt be requir'd to make a full <hi>Divorce?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is it too much, to be at ſmall expence</l>
               <l>Of ſome few minutes coſt in reference</l>
               <l>To ſoul-concerns? when frightful death draws near</l>
               <l>To do its work <hi>Repentance</hi> will be dear.</l>
               <l>A true Repentance never is too late:</l>
               <l>But true Repentance ſeldom bears that Date.</l>
               <l>What perſon in her wits, if once begun,</l>
               <l>Would proſecute the thing muſt be undone;</l>
               <l>Make work for ſorrow, run upon the ſcore;</l>
               <l>Strive to have leſs to pay with, owe the more?</l>
               <l>Did the oppreſſor, or the filcher own</l>
               <l>Neceſſity of Reſtitution</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:54895:35"/>
In his Repent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce, 'twould do more than brand,</l>
               <l>To cure him of the felons in his hand.</l>
               <l>Real belief would cauſe you to prevent</l>
               <l>What being done, doth call you to repent.</l>
               <l>When pious women ready are to give</l>
               <l>Account of life, then you'l begin to live.</l>
               <l>Amendment you reſolve on, make that good,</l>
               <l>And that you are reformed I'le conclude.</l>
               <l>What thou doſt purpoſe from a ſincere heart,</l>
               <l>Not what thou wilt be ſhews, but what thou art.</l>
               <l>Thus to deſign, will make thee God advance</l>
               <l>Above the world in brighteſt Circumſtance,</l>
               <l>And doſt thou thus the world deſpiſe, when it</l>
               <l>Advantage hath, to gain thy Appetite?</l>
               <l>If not, to pleaſure thou art but in thrall;</l>
               <l>For all pretence, thou lov'ſt not God at all.</l>
               <l>Two wayes, that come to one, of ſaying Nay</l>
               <l>To the words Now I'le never, or delay.</l>
               <l>Suppoſe thy mind ſtill ſame to Heavens call,</l>
               <l>Not yet will prove the ſame, as not at all.</l>
               <l>To promiſe then is groſs impertinence,</l>
               <l>Forſake thy wicked life, or this pretence.</l>
               <l>Behold one, that hath ſwagger'd in the world</l>
               <l>With riches, honour; great retinue buri'd</l>
               <l>Into a loathſome priſon, there to ſee</l>
               <l>His folly paſt, and preſent miſery;</l>
               <l>And view thy deſtiny. His higher rate</l>
               <l>Of living, makes the ſadneſs of his ſtate:</l>
               <l>His former plenty makes his want the more:</l>
               <l>If not ſo rich, he had not been ſo poor.</l>
               <l>His titles that gave ſplendour to his name,</l>
               <l>Remembred now, do but augment his ſhame.</l>
               <l>Thy matchleſs beauty, whileome which eſpy'd</l>
               <l>Begat the lovers do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>age, and thy pride;</l>
               <l>(When nothing thou canſt find conſulting glaſs,</l>
               <l>But ruines only of one form that was)</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:54895:35"/>
Will render thee far more deſpis'd, and be</l>
               <l>The aggravation of deformity.</l>
               <l>Affected blemiſhes, and ſpottings were</l>
               <l>The wicked artifice to make thee fair:</l>
               <l>Now wrinkled age will glory in her ſpoil</l>
               <l>To riſing beauties making thee a foil.</l>
               <l>Wiſdom hath more truſt, and eſteem when ſage:</l>
               <l>And Reliques too gain credit by their age:</l>
               <l>But thou muſt be con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emned and forlorn;</l>
               <l>Deſerving ſubject for the Gallants ſcorn;</l>
               <l>Not able to bear up againſt diſdain;</l>
               <l>Or to redreſs by turning young again.</l>
               <l>Shall I black Mantle borrow of the night,</l>
               <l>To wrap thy diſmal caſe in? 'Tis too ſlight.</l>
               <l>Or midnight-ſable-robe, although</l>
               <l>Without Moon, Stars? 'Twould not be ſad enough.</l>
               <l>Nothing mans mind affords ſo black to tell</l>
               <l>The blackeſt darkneſs of thy ſtate, but Hell.</l>
               <l>Thy ſoul is ſolitary wilderneſs,</l>
               <l>A fearful ſhade of ſaddeſt wretchedneſs.</l>
               <l>Thy thoughts are Vultures. Conſcience with her ſting</l>
               <l>Torments thee: Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yrs dance, as Scriech-Owls ſing.</l>
               <l>The pleaſant fancies, that refreſh thy mind,</l>
               <l>Are Fairy Devils, each ſad thought black Fiend:</l>
               <l>Enjoyment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of honour, pleaſure, pelf,</l>
               <l>Cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> from the dread of ſelf.</l>
               <l>How wilt thou bear Gods wra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h? Men paint not fire</l>
               <l>So fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tly as that fierceneſs of his ire.</l>
               <l>To ſlight that mercy, do not then preſume;</l>
               <l>Which, if it may not win thee, will conſume.</l>
               <l>Let truſt in mercy this at leaſt impart</l>
               <l>Unto thy Conſcience, that thou ſerious art.</l>
               <l>The Satyriſt condemns thy vain <hi>(I will</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To morrow)</hi> that will be to morrow ſtill.</l>
               <l>To morrow which thou beggedſt yeſterday,</l>
               <l>Is loſt, yet without bluſhing thou canſt ſay</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:54895:36"/>
To morrow yet: but were it lent, thou'dſt pray</l>
               <l>To have the leiſure of another day.</l>
               <l>As haſtening hinder-wheel, doth ſeem in Coach</l>
               <l>To promiſe it will make more near approach</l>
               <l>Unto the former; when rowl'd o're and o're,</l>
               <l>Yet keeps ſame diſtance that it did before:</l>
               <l>So thou, although thou talkeſt of to morrow,</l>
               <l>That gain'd, would'ſt be at no leſs need to borrow</l>
               <l>A further day: purpoſe and to amend,</l>
               <l>Would keep an equal diſtance to</l>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
