<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The infants advocate against the cruel doctrine of those Presbyterians who hold, that the greatest part of dying infants shall be damned : in answer to a book of Mr. Giles Firmin's entituled, Scripture warrant, &amp;c. / by Tho. Grantham.</title>
            <author>Grantham, Thomas, 1634-1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41781</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1538</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43209</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">27021099</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 27021099</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109913</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A41781)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109913)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1718:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The infants advocate against the cruel doctrine of those Presbyterians who hold, that the greatest part of dying infants shall be damned : in answer to a book of Mr. Giles Firmin's entituled, Scripture warrant, &amp;c. / by Tho. Grantham.</title>
                  <author>Grantham, Thomas, 1634-1692.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.D. for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, print show-through, and slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Firmin, Giles, 1614-1697. --  Scripture-warrant sufficient proof.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109913:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Infants Advocate, AGAINST The cruel Doctrine of thoſe <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> who hold, <hi>That the greateſt part of Dying Infants</hi> ſhall be DAMNED. In Anſwer to a Book of Mr. GILES FIRMIN'S, entituled, <hi>Scripture Warrant, &amp;c.</hi> By <hi>THO. GRANTHAM.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>Exod. 32. 32, 33.</bibl>
            <q>Yet now, if thou wilt, forgive their Sin; and if not, blot me, I pray thee, out of thy Book which thou haſt written. And the Lord ſaid unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever hath ſinned againſt me, him will I blot out of my Book.</q>
            <bibl>Matth. 18. 10, 11, 14.</bibl>
            <q>Take heed that ye deſpiſe not one of theſe little Ones; for I ſay unto you, that in Heaven their Angels do always behold the Face of my Father which is in Heaven. For the Son of Man came to ſeek, and to ſave that which is loſt—Even ſo it is not the Will of your Father which is in Heaven, that one of theſe little Ones ſhould periſh.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> for the Author. 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:109913:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109913:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honeſt Reader;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Could not have thought that a Man reputed wiſe, an old Profeſſor, and one who ſo bears himſelf upon his Father's Covenant (whom he will have to be a Son of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſo himſelf to be <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Son alſo) could have given ſuch evident Proof of the contrary, as by his Book he has brought forth. Sure I am, I anſwered his <hi>two Queſtions</hi> in much Love and Faithfulneſs, according to my Ability, being thereunto deſired by ſome of his Neighbours: And I hope no Impartial Reader will cenſure me to be a Scoffer, as Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> does: But truly I think he was pleaſed to throw that Dirt, that he might have ſome pretence to give ſcope to his ill Spirit, to exerciſe it ſelf that way.</p>
            <p>I confeſs I uſe theſe words upon the occaſion of his talking ſo high of his Father's Covenant [<hi>that it would even make a well Man ſick, to ſee what pitiful work he makes of it.</hi>] And here I will give thee an account of it, and then judg of me as thou pleaſeſt.</p>
            <p>Saith Mr. <hi>F. When I could not tell where to lay hold</hi> (meaning in his diſmal Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) <hi>my Parental Covenant and Infant Baptiſm was a ſupport to me. So that I bleſs God, 1. For</hi> Abraham'<hi>s Covenant. 2. I bleſs God that I had Godly Parents. 3. I bleſs God my Parents were no Anabaptiſts,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Only a word, ſome may think you had Godly Parents, mine were not ſo: It may be I had a Godly Grandfather, or a Mother; Had you ſo? no doubt but you may improve the Covenant from him. The ſecond Commandment will help you—others may ſay, Baptized I am, but my Parents bad enough. Well, art awake? and art in earneſt for Chriſt and the ſaving Bleſſings come by him? you may improve your Covenant.</hi> A Woman putting a Queſtion, how ſhe might know whether ever ſhe had theſe Qualifications? Mr. <hi>F.</hi> tells us, that <hi>whilſt he was troubled about making out theſe Qualifications, there comes a Motion into my Mind,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>What ſay you to your Father's Covenant? you know your Parents were Godly—will you ſtand to your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Covenant?</hi> Here my Qualification <hi>was the choice of my Father's God, who was mine before by an external Covenant: But now to have him my God, my Portion by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Covenant, and Efficacy, here I was pent up. Will you</hi> chuſe or refuſe <hi>him?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now whether this Diſcourſe will not almoſt make a well Man ſick (I mean a ſerious Chriſtian troubled) to hear a wiſe Man talk at this rate? And whether he does not lay his Foundation upon his <hi>Qualification?</hi> for by that, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> was the choice of my Father's God. And does he not alſo ſet up his <hi>Will</hi> as high as ever any did, in <hi>chuſing</hi> or <hi>refuſing God to be his God, his Portion by internal Covenant and Efficacy?</hi> Sure he doth.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>F's</hi> great buſineſs is to abuſe and diſgrace me, by falſe and fooliſh Stories, which have been told him by others, which I paſs by as unworthy obſervation. And then he falls in with the Papiſts againſt me, in the caſe of abſtaining from, or eating Blood, juſtifying himſelf and them in the latter. Tho he confeſſes the believing Gentiles were forbidden to eat Blood by that Decree, <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 29. And when theſe Decrees were repealed; he cannot tell; and whilſt he makes us for obſerving them, ſuch as do not believe the Blood of Chriſt to be our Atonement; and that we hold ſome things to be unclean of themſelves; he condemns alſo the Primitive Chriſtians, who religiouſly abſtain'd from Blood for ſeveral hundred
<pb facs="tcp:109913:3"/>
Years after Chriſt, and makes himſelf wiſer than the Apoſtles; for had they known ſuch to be the conſequence, they would not have made them, nor have deliver'd them to be kept as they did, <hi>Acts</hi> 16. 4.</p>
            <p>We know that that which goes into the Man defiles not, and therefore Blood defiles not, but acting againſt God's Word defiled <hi>Evah,</hi> even <hi>by eating that which was good for Food;</hi> and ſo may Mr. <hi>F.</hi> defile himſelf, for he ſays he will eat Blood Puddings, <hi>S. A.</hi> by which he means, <hi>Sir Anabaptiſt:</hi> and indeed a ſcornful Spirit breaths in many Pages of his late Books.</p>
            <p>He is pleaſed to throw Dirt upon me very freely, about an eſcape of the Pen or Preſs, I am not ſure which, and yet he being a Scholar, and acquainted with ſuch over-ſights, could not but diſcern, unleſs Malice blinded him, that it was an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight. The Paſſage is about the time when <hi>Tranſubſtantiation came into the World,</hi> and the Book which he quarels has it thus: How rigidly do they impoſe the Decrees of the <hi>Trent-Councils:</hi> Where note, the word <hi>Councils</hi> being <hi>plural,</hi> he might eaſily have ſuppoſed <hi>Lateran,</hi> which was wanting; for thus it ſtands in the <hi>Catechiſm of the Papiſts</hi> (of which I give notice <hi>Pag.</hi> 55.) The <hi>Lateran</hi> and <hi>Trent Councils,</hi> and from thence I took the date of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> Not but that I have read the ſame in other Authors. But here he brands me with <hi>groſs Ignorance,</hi> and I grant I am not ſo well read as himſelf, if that will pleaſe him. And my rejoycing is this, that in Simplicity and Godly Sincerity I wrote that Book which he deſpiſes; and I hope God will bleſs my Endeavours, in which I truſt, I have no other ſcope but his Glory and the good of <hi>all Men;</hi> heartily deſiring that all Truth were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to its Primitive Purity and Simplicity.</p>
            <p>As to his three firſt Chapters, I ſhall ſay little to them at preſent, being very well ſatisfied with my Anſwers to his two Queſtions, notwithſtanding all that he has ſaid to render them invalid. The chief thing which I deſign in this Reply is, to maintain (what in me is) <hi>the Mercy of God to all dying Infants,</hi> againſt Mr. <hi>F.</hi> and others, whoſe cruel Doctrine ſends them by <hi>Millions to Helliſh Torments,</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by this Book of Mr. <hi>Firmin's,</hi> p. 8. <hi>If all dying Infants ſhall be ſaved; there will be Millions in Heaven</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in whom the Spirit of God—had nothing to do in their Salvation.</hi> I ſay, to maintain the Salvation of all dying Infants againſt thoſe who would thus damn them, is eſpecially my preſent undertaking. And if Mr. <hi>F.</hi> be diſpoſed to urge me further, it is a Subject I am willing to debate with him, when and how he pleaſes, ſo that we may diſcourſe in Love<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as becomes Chriſtians. And as to the <hi>Queſtions</hi> about <hi>Sacred Baptiſm,</hi> that Work may perhaps be undertaken in a particular Treatiſe by it ſelf. In the mean time, let it be conſidered, that it has been granted both by <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> (and thoſe of the more Learned ſort too) That <hi>there is no Scripture for Infant-Baptiſm.</hi> That <hi>the Scripture ſhews us no other way of baptizing, but by dipping.</hi> Yea, I lately asked a <note n="*" place="margin">It was not the Bp of <hi>Norwich,</hi> for I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw him, nor did I ever diſpute any Doctor out of the room, as Mr. F. hath both fooliſhly and falſly reported in Print, with no leſs than ſix o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther falſe and very fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous Tales, in half a Page<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> Doctor of the Church of <hi>England</hi> very ſeriouſly, <hi>Whether he held Infant-Baptiſm to be of Divine Inſtitution?</hi> Who very freely gave me this Anſwer, <hi>No truly, I only look upon it as a Church-Rite.</hi> But then, whether the Church have ſuch Power, as to make <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies in Religion,</hi> and particularly thus to alter the ſubject and manner of Baptiſm, as has confeſſedly been done by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and in part by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is the buſineſs for this preſent Age to take into their moſt ſerious Conſideration.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. G.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:109913:3"/>
            <hi>The</hi> INFANTS ADVOCATE, <hi>againſt the cruel Doctrine of thoſe</hi> Presbyterians, <hi>who hold, That the greateſt part of Dying Infants are</hi> DAMNED.</head>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <head>Diviſion 1.</head>
            <p>MR <hi>Giles Firmin</hi> was pleaſed to print <hi>two Queſtions,</hi> and deſires thoſe, whom he calls <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> to anſwer them; and at the requeſt of ſome of his Neighbours, I wrote a brief, and I hope, a modeſt Anſwer to them, not for Contention, but for Satisfaction to ſuch as deſire to know the truth in the matters thereby put to the Queſtion by Mr. <hi>F.</hi> who finds himſelf aggrieved, tho nothing is done but what he deſired; that is, his Queſtions anſwered: And tho he ſays they are not, yet that ſhall not provoke me to ſay much to him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them. But ſeeing by this occaſion we are unavoidably fallen upon the buſineſs of <hi>Infants-Salvation;</hi> Whether God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty ordained <hi>Baptiſm, or any other Rite to be neceſſary to their Salvation?</hi> or, <hi>Whether the greateſt, or any part of Dying Infants ſhall be damned in Helliſh Torments?</hi> A Queſtion of great weight and importance; I find my ſelf concern'd to proceed in oppoſing that cruel Doctrine, which would ſend <hi>Millions</hi> of dying Infants to Hell Torments.</p>
            <p>It was the Judgment of <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and many others, that unleſs <hi>Infants were baptized, and received the Lord's Supper, they could not be ſaved:</hi> And Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> ſeems to be of the ſame Mind with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to their Baptiſm: and moreover, he holds that Infants muſt have Faith and Repentance, as neceſſary to their Salvation, or they muſt all periſh. I will ſet down his own words.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Pag.</hi> 90. of his <hi>Plea,</hi> he ſpeaks thus: <hi>To return to Infants, They muſt be regenerate, and have Faith ſome way, elſe they muſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh.</hi> And in his Book entituled, <hi>Scripture warrant,</hi> &amp;c. he ſpeaks thus, <hi>Pag. 76. They who are regenerate, have Faith and Repentance.</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:109913:4"/>
               <hi>But all Infants ſaved, are regenerated: Therefore all Infants ſaved, have Faith and Repentance.</hi> And in <hi>Pag.</hi> 21. he counts it an Error in me for ſuppoſing, <hi>If</hi> Iſaac <hi>had died before he was eight days old, he might have been ſaved.</hi> So (ſaith he) <hi>this Covenant</hi> (meaning the Covenant of Circumciſion) <hi>might have been ſpared.</hi> And in <hi>Pag. 40. The ſame</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I may ſay for Baptiſm, being Chriſt's own Inſtitution, This is</hi> the Hand of the Spirit <hi>accompanying it, when and where he pleaſeth, ſhall be the means to convey Spiritual Bleſſings to the Hearts of</hi> ſome <hi>Infants, and prove to them the waſhing of Regeneration.</hi> So that, I think, I have done him no wrong in the account I have given of his Opinion. To all which I anſwer.</p>
            <p>To intermit a little the buſineſs of <hi>Infants Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> we will conſider what he ſays of <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He tells us, <hi>Pag. 39. That he cannot conceive how it can conſiſt with the Wiſdom, Holineſs, and Goodneſs of God, to inſtitute an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in his Church, for ſpiritual and ſaving Ends, and ſtrictly to command this Ordinance to be adminiſtred to ſuch Subjects as Children of eight days old—and he himſelf not work with his own Inſtitution, when and where he pleaſes, to the good and benefit of that Subject to whom it is adminiſtred, this Subject having need of the Spiritual Good, ſignified and ſealed thereby. It doth implicitly charge the Inſtitution with Vanity.</hi> To which I reply.</p>
            <p>1. Conſidering what Mr. <hi>F.</hi> ſays of <hi>Iſaac</hi> dying before the eighth day, (which I noted before) his ſenſe is this; that from the time that Circumciſion was inſtituted, it makes that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Circumciſion a Vanity, to think any of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed (tho but Infants of eight days old) could be ſaved if not circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed: And then, I pray, what is like to become of all the World beſide, who had no Intereſt in the Covenant of Circumciſion? Muſt they not all periſh? We ſhall hear more of that anon.</p>
            <p>2. And beſides this, tho he makes Circumciſion thus neceſſary to the Salvation of Infants, yet he does not believe that all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants that were circumciſed were ſaved; for theſe words of his [<hi>when and where he pleaſes</hi>] carry this ſenſe in a Presbyterian Breaſt, that tho Circumciſion did by expreſs order belong to all the Males of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, being eight days old, yet perhaps but few of many of them ſhould be ſaved: which I evidently ſhewed in my Anſwers to Mr. <hi>F</hi>'s Queſtion, and to Mr. <hi>Petto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now here I do profeſs to believe, that Almighty God did not thus ordain Circumciſion to be abſolutely neceſſary; becauſe they,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109913:4"/>
to wit, Infants, can neither underſtand his Will herein, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it, neither hinder it; it wholly depends on others to do it for them, and why then they ſhould periſh if it be not done, no reaſon can be ſhewed: but that which is the hardeſt thing of all, is, that if <hi>Iſaac</hi> had died before the eighth day, he ſhould not be ſaved, when yet it was not lawful to circumciſe him. What is this? Does God damn Infants for dying before they be eight days old? or for not having that done to them which by God's Law ought not to be done before the eighth day? This is the cruelſt Doctrine that can be. And I will ſhew how contrary it is to the Doctrine of Learned Proteſtants. One ſaith thus upon <hi>Gen. 17. 14. It is no good reading to ſay the uncircumciſed Man-Child, but</hi> [Zachar] <hi>the Male,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall be</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Willit</hi> Hexap. in Gen. p. 196, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>cut off; for the Infant of eight days old, mentioned</hi> ver. 12. <hi>is of purpoſe omitted here. Hence then it is inferred, that there was no ſuch abſolute neceſſity of Circumciſion, that Children wanting it ſhould be damned.</hi> Again, <hi>This place cannot be underſtood of Infants that are uncircumciſed, 1. That addition, the eighth day, is uſed only by the Septuagint, it is not in the Hebrew. 2. The words are,</hi> qui non circumciderit, <hi>he which ſhall not circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe. So readeth the Original, the</hi> Chaldee <hi>Paraphraſt,</hi> Junius, <hi>&amp;c. which ſheweth that it muſt be underſtood of them that are</hi> Adulti, <hi>and not of Infants—. If Infants be not circumciſed it is the Parents fault—as may appear in the Example of</hi> Moſes, <hi>whom the Lord puniſhed, and not the Child for neglecting it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. Concerning Baptiſm, I do believe it to be a very ſolemn Ordinance, and alſo very uſeful in the Church of God; yet I do not find that it is the Hand of the Spirit to convey Grace to the Heart of any Infant, ſeeing what it conveys, it doth it by Faith and by its Figure; repreſenting the Death, Burial, and Reſurrection of Chriſt, and ours with him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of all which Infants know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, being ſprinkled, as I formerly ſhewed, very often when they are faſt aſleep; and if awake, they know nothing of the Myſtery of Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>F.</hi> brought three Scriptures to prove his Doctrine, we ſhall now conſider them; Epheſ. 5. 26. <hi>Chriſt loved his Church, and gave himſelf for it; that he might ſanctify and cleanſe it by the waſhing of Water, through the Word.</hi> I allow Baptiſmal Water to be here meant; but then we ſee it does not cleanſe but by or through the Word, nor doth the <hi>Word profit unleſs it be mixed</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:109913:5"/>
               <hi>with Faith in them that hear it;</hi> Heb. 4. 1, 2. The Church <hi>is puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in obeying the Truth through the Spirit;</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 22. And <hi>Baptiſm ſaves us, as it is the anſwer of a good Conſcience towards God, by the Reſurrection of Chriſt.</hi> And to this agree his other two Scriptures, <hi>Tit. 3. 11. 1 Pet.</hi> 3. 21. Now Infants being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of being cleanſed by Baptiſm according to the ſenſe of theſe Scriptures, we may in no wiſe apply them to Infant-Baptiſm.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <head>Diviſ. 2.</head>
            <p>And becauſe it may be moſt convenient to treat of Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this place, we will here conſider Mr. <hi>F's Arguments to prove that Infants have Faith and Repentance.</hi> His firſt Argument is as followeth.</p>
            <div n="1" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>Arg. 1.</hi> If all, even adult Perſons, are paſſive in the work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, then Infants are capable of Regeneration. But the Antecedent is true.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Here we are told that grown Perſons are paſſive (that is, they do nothing at all) in the work of Regeneration; this is the meaning of his Antecedent. Now if this be true, as he ſays it is, then if they do nothing, they neither hear the Word, nor believe it, nor repent, nor hate nor turn from Sin; for theſe are at leaſt ſome of the parts of the work of Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Now I would fain know who is active in all this, if the Party regenerate be not? St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>With the Heart Man believeth unto Righteouſneſs, and with the Mouth Confeſſion is made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Salvation,</hi> Rom. 10. 10. When <hi>Peter</hi> ſhewed the Jews their Sin, and preached Chriſt to them, they were pricked to the Heart: Now obſerve, they came to hear the Word, they gave Audience, they gave Credit to it, God bleſſed the Word with Power: Now <hi>they cry out, What ſhall we do? Peter</hi> exhort them to repent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and they gladly receive his word, and had the waſhing of Regeneration the ſame day. Now let God have the Glory of this, and all Converſions, who is the firſt Mover in it, and the Efficient Cauſe of it; yet he is abſurd that will ſay, Man is as paſſive as an Infant that can neither hear, nor receive any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction at all. And therefore I deny his Antecedent, it is not true, the Adult are ſome way active in the work of Converſion;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109913:5"/>
yea all that know the work, do know what wreſtling with Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption is, and how unable they are to overcome in the Conflict with Satan and Fleſh, without Supernatural Strength, or Aid from Heaven, but yet They act, and wait for help in all their actings.</p>
               <p>2. Men are commanded to hear, that their Souls may live, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. If they hear and obey not, they ſin againſt God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 16, 17, 18. We grant that the Power Converting, is not of the Creature; <hi>We are not ſufficient of our ſelves to think any thing as of our ſelves.</hi> All our Faculties are given us of God. It's our duty to put theſe Faculties into Act; to hear, repent, and believe, is Man's Duty. It is not the Duty of Infants to hear, repent, believe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> therefore they are not regenerated this way. What you urge from the <hi>Shunamite's Son</hi> and <hi>Lazarus,</hi> being both dead, and ſo equally paſſive as to riſe from Death, is wholly imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and being put into Argument, is falſe; for thus you muſt argue, if you ſay any thing, <hi>Infants dead are as capable to riſe as the Adult, being dead.</hi> Ergo, <hi>They are as capable of hearing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiving, and repenting as the Adult.</hi> The Conſequence is falſe; many Inſtances we have of the Adult, who hear, believe, and repent; but no Inſtance of one Infant ever regenerated this way.</p>
               <p>3. As for your captious Demands about our being quickned, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> you may well ſpare them, till you give better Evidence of your own Converſion; for your Books do evidently ſhew, that a jeer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing idle Spirit has dominion in you. Howbeit this we ſay; The Original Cauſe of our Converſion, is the Love of God: The meritorious Cauſe, is the Blood of Chriſt: The miniſterial Cauſe, is the Evidence of Truth, or the Word of Truth: The efficient Cauſe, is the Power of God's Grace, <hi>John</hi> 1. 12. The formal Cauſe, is believing and obeying the Truth through the Spirit: The final Cauſe, is God's Glory and our Salvation; to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of which all our Faculties of Hearing, Underſtanding, Will, and Affection, are given us of God to be put into Act. This is not required of Infants; and how they are ſanctified by the Spirit, God only knoweth.</p>
               <p>4. But now, ſaith Mr. <hi>Firmin, I will not have him for my God, who cannot moſt omnipotently make me both will, and do what he will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I reply, Theſe are great ſwelling words of Vanity, and nothing to the purpoſe: We diſpute not what God can do; for he can, of a Stone in the Street, make a better Man than either
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109913:6"/>
of us. And we deny not, but God hath ſometimes, and may ſtill, if he pleaſe, convert ſome by <hi>miraculous Operations.</hi> But to ſay that <hi>all Converſions are miraculous,</hi> as Mr. <hi>F.</hi> does, is very falſe. <hi>Paul</hi> was converted miraculouſly, ſo was not <hi>Lydia.</hi> What I ſay upon <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 19, 20. is miſtaken by you, for I extend it further than to the Reſurrection of the Body; <hi>for I expreſly ſay he has power to do whatſoever he pleaſes, and ſo to raiſe us up,</hi> &amp;c. but if I was ſhort or obſcure, this is my meaning, The Faith of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians is agreeable to the power which God ſhewed in Chriſt when he raiſed him from the dead; and I think 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 3. doth very well explain <hi>Epheſ. 1. 19, 20. Bleſſed be the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which according to his abundant Mercy, hath begotten us again to a lively Hope, by the Reſurrection of Chriſt from the Dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> argues thus; <hi>They who are regenerated, have Faith and Repentance: but all Infants ſaved, are regenerated: Therefore all Infants ſaved, have Faith and Repentance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Here is a fault in your Logick, <note n="*" place="margin">You bid me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what that Fallacy <hi>Ignoratio E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenchi</hi> is, and here you are fallen into that Fallacy your ſelf.</note> your <hi>Major</hi> ſhould have been univerſal, or elſe you conclude nothing rationally.</p>
               <p>2. Therefore I deny the <hi>Major,</hi> and ſay, <hi>Some</hi> may be regenerated (I mean cleanſed from Sin, renewed by Chriſt, and made fit for Heaven) without Faith and Repenuance, <hi>namely, Infants;</hi> and ſure I am Mr. <hi>F.</hi> ſhall never be able to prove his <hi>Major,</hi> being taken univerſally; and if he like not to mend his <hi>Major,</hi> I reject his Argument, and retort it thus.</p>
               <p>3. <hi>They that are regenerated, do continue in the Apoſtles Doctrine and Fellowſhip, and in breaking of Bread, and in Prayers. But all Infants ſaved are regenerated.</hi> Ergo, <hi>All Infants ſaved continue ſtedfaſtly in the Apoſtles Doctrine and Fellowſhip, and in breaking of Bread, and in Prayers.</hi> Now as this Argument is fallacious, ſo certainly is yours. Again,</p>
               <p>4. You that make all Converſion miraculous, how can you tie Regeneration to Faith and Repentance, as it reſpects Infants? Do not you contradict your ſelf, Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> in this? May not God ſanctify Infants what way he pleaſeth, but muſt be limited to your Methods? Sir, what he doth in the Regeneration of Infants is a Secret, let it alone to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:109913:6"/>5. But let us hear Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> one of your own Mind as to Poedo-baptiſm, yet he ſaith, <hi>Let Infants be preſſed with all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies which are conſequent to Original Sin; yet it will not be laid to their Charge, ſo as to condemn them: Or if it could, yet the Mercy and abſolute Goodneſs of God will ſecure them, if he take them away before they can glorify him by a free Obedience—For as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants without their own conſent—contracted the Guilt of</hi> Adam'<hi>s Sin, and are liable to all the Puniſhments which can with Juſtice de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend upon his Poſterity, who are perſonally innocent: ſo Infants ſhall be reſtored—by the ſecond</hi> Adam, <hi>by the Redemption of Jeſus Chriſt, by his Righteouſneſs and Mercies, applied either immediately, or how, or when he pleaſes to appoint.</hi> And here Mr. <hi>F.</hi> may learn from Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> how Infants may be guilty of Sin, and yet Innocent; which he would make a Contradiction in me.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>F.</hi> tells us his <hi>Major</hi> (laſt denied) is clear from our own Confeſſion, in that we ſay Faith and Repentance are the two parts of Regeneration: but he that grants this, extends it only to the Adult, of whom theſe are things required; and not to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, of whom they are not required; ſo that this is a meer Caption, unbecoming a grave Diſputant. But let us hear how he proves his <hi>Minor. They</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>who are born unclean, that are ſinful and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt by Nature, muſt be regenerated before they can be ſaved. But ſo are Infants born. Therefore,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is not denied by us that Infants are born unclean, and we grant that before they come to Heaven they muſt be cleanſed, ſo that you might have ſpared this Argument. The thing you are to prove is, <hi>That Infants cannot be cleanſed without Faith and Repentance.</hi> But this you cunningly ſlide over, and you will find it to be an undertaking too hard for you, and I think you are the firſt Man that ever attempted it.</p>
               <p>It is not your telling us again of your <hi>Seminal Faith</hi> that will do it, which, as you refer it to Infants, is a meer <hi>Chimera</hi> of your own Brain. But when you ſpeak of the <hi>Adult,</hi> you ſeem to ſpeak ſenſe in theſe words, <hi>When God regenerates an Adult Perſon, he doth firſt infuſe the Principles, Seeds, Habits of all the Graces of the Spirit. When the Sower went out to ſow,</hi> Mat 13. 3. <hi>it was but the Seeds of Faith and Repentance which he did ſow, which was firſt received, and theſe Seeds grew up,</hi> Mark<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4. 27.</p>
               <p>Now, Sir, if you will ſtand to this, and theſe Texts to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109913:7"/>
your Speech, we may very well come to agree. What then is the Seed here ſpoken of? Our Saviour tells us, <hi>it is the Word of God, which Men hear</hi> preached unto them; Is this the <hi>Seminal Faith and Repentance</hi> which you talk on? Then this Seminal Faith is not in Infants, for as they cannot hear the Word, ſo no Sower, or Preacher is ſent to them. And I ſuppoſe you would not bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize an Adult Perſon, tho he has heard the Word, unleſs you ſee ſome effect of it, at leaſt that the tender blade appear: for Perſons are not made Diſciples or Chriſtians by being bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed; but they are baptized becauſe they are made Diſciples, <hi>John 4. 1. Mat. 28. 19. Mathetuſate panta ta ethne Baptizantes autous.</hi> And Diſciples may be called Chriſtians, <hi>Acts</hi> 11. Now with what Conſcience then can you baptize an Infant, that never to your knowledg received this Seed at all?</p>
               <p>But Mr. <hi>F.</hi> bids us <hi>twy-fallow and try-fallow our Ground, and ſow no ſeed, for according to your Doctrine</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>you may have a Crop without it.</hi> But by his favour this is not our caſe, but his own, for he ſows no Seed to Infants, and yet he will have a Crop of them; for he will have them baptized aſleep or awake by force. Now Baptiſm is an Act of Obedience ſpringing from the Word (<hi>the Seed</hi>) ſown; <hi>Acts 2. 38, 40. Act.</hi> 8. 12. Nay more, he exacts this Crop of Infants not only before he ſow any Seed, or before any be ſown by any other that he knows of, but alſo before he ſo much as <hi>Twy-fallow,</hi> or plow at all. And thus whilſt he thought to kick the Husbandman on the breech, he hath kick'd up his own Heels.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>F.</hi> quotes 1 <hi>John 3. 9. It is the Seed which remains.</hi> Peter'<hi>s Faith failed ſadly</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as to the Act, but the Seed remained.</hi> This would lead us to another Queſtion [as it is his manner to confound his Diſcourſes with Diverſities] but I ſhall hold him to the Parable of the Sower, alledged by himſelf <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. And then I may tell him the Seed only remains in good and honeſt Hearts, but not in every place where it is ſown, nor in every place where it is received; remember the <hi>High-way,</hi> and the <hi>Stony</hi> and <hi>Thorny</hi> Ground.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> F's <hi>Arg. 2.</hi> No unclean Perſon ſhall ſee God; <hi>Heb. 12. 14.</hi> But Infants by Nature are unclean. If the Scripture be believed, they muſt bear the Image in which they were created by God, that ever ſee the face of God.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:109913:7"/>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Should I retort this Argument, I might ſhew the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of its form. But I ſhall take your Senſe. I ſuppoſe by the <hi>Major</hi> you mean no unclean or wicked Perſon, <hi>as ſuch,</hi> ſhall ſee God. And by the <hi>Minor</hi> you mean that Infants <hi>are</hi> born of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Parents, polluted by Original Sin, and ſo under Condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; And therefore before they can come to Heaven they muſt be cleanſed from theſe Pollutions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If this be your Senſe I agree with you. But then your Argument touches not the Queſtion, which is, <hi>Whether Infants are not made clean from their Pollutions, and freed from Condemnation, without having Faith and Repentance?</hi> I ſay they may, becauſe God requires not theſe things of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants. But you argue further.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>F. All the Members of the Kingdom of Heaven are holy: but Children are Members of the Kingdom of Heaven: Not by Birth, it is by Regeneration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, Here I think you have given your Cauſe its deaths blow. It ſeems now that the Infants of Believers are no more holy by their Birth of believing Parents than others; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be regenerated you cannot tell, for you do not hold that all the Children of Believers are ſaved. What is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the Birth-priviledg ſo much gloried in by Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and others? <hi>We have been told Infants are holy by Birth, if one Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent be but a Believer;</hi> and <hi>that Children of Believers are holy by Prerogative of Seed.</hi> But now you confeſs the Truth, and I grant Infants are not holy by Birth, let their Parents be never ſo Chriſtian. And I have already granted that Infants muſt be cleanſed from all Sin before they come to Heaven. But yet you touch not the Queſtion, <hi>Whether they cannot be cleanſed from Sin without they have Faith and Repentance;</hi> one would think you begin to be afraid of the Queſtion, and I am ſure you have cauſe ſo to be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="argument">
               <head>Arg. 3. <hi>Mr.</hi> F. <hi>tells us,</hi> If <hi>Adam</hi> had continued in Innocency, his Children had born the Image of God from the Birth: I never heard it denied. That which I infer hence is, that Children are capable of the Image of God, and receiving the Seeds of all Grace it was ſo then, why not now?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> What manner of the Image of God Infants ſhould have born, had <hi>Adam</hi> continued innocent, is unknown to Man;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109913:8"/>
and 'tis but vain to concern our ſelves about that which cannot be known: but this we know, it ſhould not have ſtood in Faith and Repentance as now, becauſe in both theſe we confeſs our ſelves Sinners, and this is enough to ſhew the vanity of your Queſtion, <hi>if ſo then, why not now?</hi> But you proceed thus;</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>F. Shall the sin of one Perſon be ſo miſchievous, to deprive</hi> Adam <hi>and all his Poſterity of the Image of God, and bring the Seeds of all Corruption into their Nature, and ſhall the Grace of God be denyed to renew his Image in little Children, when and where he pleaſeth? Children being a great part of the World, ſhall the Spirit of God have nothing to do in their Hearts?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I know no Man more faulty than Mr. <hi>F.</hi> in this matter; for he will not allow the Grace of God to have any thing to do with the greateſt part of Infants. I doubt not but God doth all things needful for them, to make them holy, by <hi>the Blood of Chriſt;</hi> his <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Spirit.</hi> But all this ſhall be done without Faith and Repentance; becauſe God does not require it of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants; if he does, name your Text.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>F. now tells us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Adam's Diſobedience far<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> exceeds the Obedience of Chriſt, which he compares in Juſtification,</hi> Rom. 5. 16, 17, 18. <hi>for his Diſobedience could defile all his Poſterity, but Chriſt's Obedience doth not cleanſe and regenerate one Child.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Come St. <hi>Paul,</hi> thou haſt told us that <hi>ſuch as thou art by Letters when abſent, ſuch thou wilt be indeed when preſent,</hi> 2 Cor. 10. 11. Wherefore I ſhall give place to thee to anſwer for thy ſelf, by the very places which Mr. <hi>F.</hi> has quoted out of thy <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Romans,</hi> Chap. 5. 16, 17, 18. <hi>And not as it was by one that ſinned, ſo is the Gift: for the Judgment was of one to Condemnation; but the free-Gift is of many Offences to Juſtification. For if by the Offence of one, Death reigned by one much more they which receive abundance of Grace and of the Gift of Righteouſneſs, ſhall reign in Life by one, Jeſus Chriſt. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>refore as by the Offence of one, Judgment came upon</hi> All Men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>to Condemnation;</hi> even ſo, <hi>by the Righteouſneſs of one, the free-Gift came upon All Men unto Juſtification of Life.</hi> And whereas Mr. <hi>F.</hi> boldly tells us, that Chriſt's Obedience doth not cleanſe and regenerate one Child. I ask him whoſe Obedience then does cleanſe Infants? Let St. <hi>Paul</hi> anſwer again, <hi>ver. 19. As by one Man's Diſobedience many were made Sinners:</hi> SO <hi>by the Obedience of one ſhall many be made</hi> Righteous. Bleſſed <hi>Paul,</hi> thou haſt anſwered to the Life. Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> ſays, <hi>Chriſt's Obedience doth</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:109913:8"/>
                  <hi>not cleanſe and regenerate one Child.</hi> Thou ſayſt, <hi>Chriſt's Obedience made many righteous;</hi> and they that are made righteous are clean and regenerated ſufficiently. Bleſſed Apoſtle! thou haſt turned the Wiſdom of the Wiſe into Fooliſhneſs. What follows in this Paragraph is anſwered before, and for his uncivil Expreſſions in the cloſe of it I ſhall paſs them by.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Firmin's <hi>Arg. 4.</hi> If all Children dying ſuch are juſtified and ſaved, then there will be Millions in Heaven, in whom the Spirit of God, as the third Perſon in the Bleſſed Trinity, had nothing to do in their Salvation.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, I take notice that Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> by this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would have <hi>Millions of Infants damned,</hi> becauſe in his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Spirit of God hath nothing to do with <hi>Millions</hi> of them in the buſineſs of Salvation. This, this is that wicked Doctrine which I oppoſe.</p>
               <p>2. But how will he prove that the Spirit hath to do in the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of the Salvation of any of them, more than I ſhall prove he hath to do in the Salvation of all dying Infants? He would prove it by two things, (1.) <hi>Becauſe the diſtinct Subſiſtences have their diſtinct manner of working. (2.) Becauſe Regeneration is given to the Spirit.</hi> Now, ſuppoſe this be true, it does not prove that ſome Infants have the aſſiſtance of the Spirit, and ſome dying Infants have no aſſiſtance from him. Thus he beats<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the <hi>Air,</hi> but proves not any thing at all relating to the Point in Queſtion.</p>
               <p>3. But I will prove that all dying Infants have all that aſſiſtance of the Spirit (in the buſineſs of Salvation) which is any way needful for them. I do it thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All thoſe dying Infants, for whom Chriſt ſhed his precious Blood, have ſufficient aſſiſtance from the Spirit, in the buſineſs of their Salvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But Chriſt ſhed his precious Blood for all dying Infants:</hi> Ergo, <hi>All dying Infants have ſufficient aſſiſtance from the Spirit in the buſineſs of their Salvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is evident, becauſe no dying Infant does <hi>reſiſt the Holy Ghost,</hi> and becauſe <hi>God is no Reſpecter of Perſons.</hi> The <hi>Minor</hi> is evident becauſe <hi>Chriſt died for all, taſted Death for every Man; he bought them that deny him, and bring upon themſelves ſwift Deſtruction:</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:109913:9"/>
                  <hi>And ſeeing his tender Mercies are over all his Works,</hi> the holy Spirit is not wanting to further the Salvation of any dying Infant. <hi>Deut. 10. 17, 18. 1 Tim. 2. 6. Heb. 2. 9. 2 Pet. 2. 1. Pſal.</hi> 145. 9. Come Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> let me come near you; it may be you have had ſome Children that died in their Infancy as well as I. Shew me a reaſon now why my dying Infants might not have the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of Chriſt's Blood by the holy Spirit, as well as yours? As for the manner of the Spirit's operation herein, I ſuppoſe we know it both alike, that is, not at all. Nevertheleſs I do believe the <hi>Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>holy Spirit</hi> does what is needful in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective operations, tho I know not in all Points <hi>how</hi> it is done in the caſe of dying Infants. It is enough that we have Chriſt's Teſtimony, that to them <hi>belongs the Kingdom,</hi> that is, to all in that ſtate, for he rejects not any one of them, neither in theſe words, nor in any other that proceeded from his ſacred Lips, nor from the Pens of the Writers of the Holy Scriptures; And then what is Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> that he ſhould by this preſumptuous Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument ſend many Millions of them to Hell? becauſe in his conceit, the Holy Ghoſt has nothing to do with them in the buſineſs of their Salvation; the Spirit's Operations being li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited by him herein to the Infants of Believers only; and if you look well to his Notions, there is not a few of them too, who have no help from the holy Spirit, for they being not all elect, muſt be damned for all their Baptiſm; and this is the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs he has to write <hi>a Plea for Infants.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <head>Diviſ. 3.</head>
            <p>Wherein is conſidered, whether the Covenant of Grace was taken from the whole World, and appropriated only to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, from the time of the making the Covenant of Circumciſion, <hi>Gen. 17.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Firmin, p. 20.]</bibl>
            <q rend="margQuotes">Now I come to my Queſtion, and ſhall make it appear your Anſwer ſignifies nothing. You tell me of a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace made with the whole World in the promiſed Seed to <hi>Adam,</hi> &amp;c. I tell you, while <hi>Adam, Noah,</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> lived under that Covenant made with the whole World, God was pleaſed to make a Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and with none other but <hi>Abraham,</hi> to be his God, and the God of his Seed, and ſealed this Covenant, by which Covenant and Seal, God did ſeparate and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:109913:9"/>
divide all <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed from the World, living under the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant you ſpeak of.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It is evident, that either Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> holds, That the Covenant made with <hi>Adam, Noah,</hi> and <hi>Abraham,</hi> before that mentioned <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. was not the Covenant of Grace; or elſe that Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. was not the Covenant of Grace; or that the Covenant of Grace was now taken from all the World, and appropriated and reſtrained to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed only. The latter is clearly his ſenſe, that God was now <hi>only</hi> the God of <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed in the Covenant of Grace, and of <hi>none other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this Doctrine is moſt falſe and abſurd, as I evidently ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Mr. <hi>Petto,</hi> to this effect. We ought to underſtand that <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed was not the <hi>only Perſons</hi> in the World, which were under the Covenant of Grace, at that time when God made with <hi>Abraham</hi> the <hi>Covenant of Circumciſion,</hi> Gen. 17. For (as Mr. <hi>Broughton</hi> obſerves) <hi>Sem</hi> lived 50 Years after the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Circumciſion was made with <hi>Abraham;</hi> and divers other holy Men lived long after the Covenant of Circumciſion was made; who were all true Worſhippers of God according to the Covenant of Grace: <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> bleſſing <hi>Abraham,</hi> (from whence St. <hi>Paul</hi> infers, that he was greater than <hi>Abraham,</hi> Heb. 7. 7.) yet neither he, nor the reſt of the Patriarchs were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in the Covenant of Circumciſion.</p>
            <p>And as neither theſe, nor their Infants or Poſterity, were liable to any loſs of the Covenant of Grace, by their not being Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed after the manner of <hi>Abraham;</hi> ſo neither <hi>Job,</hi> nor other Worthy Men that were not of the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> had no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity at all to be concern'd in the Covenant of Circumciſion: From whence it muſt needs follow, That God did not intend the Sign of Circumciſion, as neceſſary to entitle Men to the Covenant of Grace, nor that none could be Saved who were not under the Covenant of Circumciſion. But certain it is, the Covenant of Circumciſion was appropriate to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>to his Seed,</hi> for ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great Ends, reſpecting ſpecial Preſervation to the Family of <hi>Abraham,</hi> as being now the Family from whence Chriſt ſhould proceed according to the Fleſh: And with whom God would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence himſelf in a Land of Promiſe, by a diſtinct way of Worſhip from all other Nations, who were then falling very faſt to Idolatry.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:109913:10"/>Again, Mr. <hi>F.</hi> telling us, <hi>That God made that Covenant of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion with</hi> Abraham, <hi>and none other.</hi> By this he has given a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Blow to his Cauſe, which he is ſo zealous to defend. Becauſe by this, it is evident, that the <hi>Covenant</hi> made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 17. conſidered as it was peculiar to him and his Seed, and <hi>no other,</hi> no not of the Patriarchs then living, it was therefore (at leaſt ſo conſidered) <hi>not the Covenant of Grace.</hi> But it was only, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered; the Covenant of Circumciſion, as it is alſo called, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 8. without any ſuch adjunct as <hi>the Covenant of Grace;</hi> as if all that were not in that peculiar Covenant throughout the World, muſt be damn'd without Mercy. No, no, God had his tender Mercies for others, tho this Covenant was peculiar to <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God was no ſuch reſpecter of Perſons when he made the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 17. But in <hi>every Nation,</hi> from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning even to the end of the World, all that feared the Lord, and wrought Righteouſneſs, found acceptance with him. This old Truth, <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf (being tinctured with this Notion, that God had no Grace for any but <hi>Abraham's Seed</hi>) could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, till God by Miracle did reveal it to him; no tho his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19, 20. did oblige him to teach all Nations, and to preach the Goſpel to every Creature, yet till now he durſt not preach to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> Acts 10.</p>
            <p>And therefore it is the leſs ſtrange, that Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> and ſuch as he, who take themſelves to be <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, becauſe they are born according to the Fleſh of ſuch as they take to be Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, ſhould be ſo cruelly dark in this glorious Truth, <hi>that God is no reſpecter of Perſons.</hi> Nor do I ſee any thing more liable to puff Men up with Pride, than this, that they were in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace from their Infancy, becauſe their Parents were Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, or at leaſt one of them, or their Grandfather, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was ſo; as Mr. <hi>F.</hi> words it.</p>
            <p>This Opinion undid the <hi>Jews</hi> generally, and I doubt it has ſpoiled many of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> Our bleſſed Saviour, <hi>John</hi> 8. has a long Diſputation to deliver the <hi>Jews</hi> from this their vain Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which they built upon their being <hi>Abraham's Seed.</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> bent his Stile againſt the ſame thing, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 26, 27, 28, 29. and <hi>Chap. 3. ver.</hi> 19. to the end. But the more they laboured to undeceive theſe deceived <hi>Jews<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> the more they were hated by them; and if we meet with the ſame meaſure, we muſt bear it. For indeed, ſcarce any ſo fierce againſt us, for extending the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109913:10"/>
Grace of God to all Men, as being therein <hi>no reſpecter of Perſons,</hi> and yet ſhewing to Sinners <hi>the neceſſity of actual Repentance towards God, and Faith towards our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as neceſſary to their Memberſhip in the Church Militant, by the Baptiſm of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for Remiſſion of Sins; I ſay, none ſo fierce againſt us, as thoſe who boaſt they are <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, becauſe deſcended from <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who they ſuppoſe to be Believers. But let me have a care, I muſt now Anſwer for my ſelf, for Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> demands of me, <hi>Page</hi> 21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By what Scripture-Warrant do you reduce our Children, into the ſtate of the Children of</hi> Adam, <hi>or</hi> Noah, &amp;c. <hi>ſince we are never cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led their Children, but only</hi> Abraham'<hi>s, whoſe Seed differ from theirs by a ſpecial Covenant made with Them, and ſealed with Them. To which of them did God ſay, I will be the God of thy Seed, and I will ſeal it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I reply. Theſe ſeem to me to be great ſwelling words of Vanity, much worſe in a <hi>Gentile</hi> than in a <hi>Jew.</hi> And I would know what ſpecial Covenant hath God made with Mr. <hi>F.</hi> and his Seed, which he hath denied to <hi>Tho. Grantham</hi> and his Seed? But to the Queſtion.</p>
            <p>1. I am far from denying <hi>Abraham's Fatherhood over the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Chriſtians;</hi> but I deny that every Believer that hath an Infant, is the Father of the Faithful. And I deny many to have any right to that Title, who boaſt much of it, becauſe they do not the works of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but deſpiſe thoſe that worſhip God according to his Will. Thus did not <hi>Abraham:</hi> But thus does Mr. <hi>Firmin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. I find that <hi>Adam</hi> was the Son of God, <hi>Luke</hi> 3. Whether called ſo meerly for his Creation, or for that after the Promiſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 15. He walked with God, or for both, I will not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute. And I find that Chriſt's Deſcent is reckoned from <hi>Adam,</hi> and the Saviour of the World was firſt promiſed to him, and to proceed from him; and therein was the Covenant of Grace in the firſt place made with him, and in him with all Mankind who then were in him: Nor do I find that this gracious Covenant was ever repealed, but is in force to this day, as is granted by Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. I find that <hi>Noah</hi> found <hi>Grace</hi> in the ſight of the Lord, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing righteous before God. And I know that Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and other Learned Chriſtians, acknowledg the Covenant made with <hi>Noah</hi> and his Generations, to be a Covenant of Grace, and of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Duration, being indeed the renewal of the Covenant made
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109913:11"/>
with <hi>Adam.</hi> I find alſo, that <hi>Noah</hi> became <hi>Heir of the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which is by Faith,</hi> and that his Faith did lead him to believe that which was as difficult to Senſe, as that <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhould have a Son, <hi>viz. That the whole World ſhould be Drowned:</hi> His Faith alſo was made perfect by Works, for, <hi>Whatſoever the Lord Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that did</hi> Noah.</p>
            <p>4. I find that all men from the time of the Flood, are the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations of <hi>Noah,</hi> and that he was perfect in his Generation, a Juſt Man, and one that walketh with God; and as one of his Sons proved wicked, ſo did one of the Sons of <hi>Abraham.</hi> I do alſo find in Scripture, that we are all called the Sons of <hi>Adam; To you, O Men, I call, and my Voice is to the Sons of</hi> Adam, <hi>or Man,</hi> Prov. 8. 4. And as the Sons of <hi>Adam,</hi> God ſhews them what is Good, even to <hi>do Juſtly,</hi> to <hi>love Mercy,</hi> and to <hi>walk humbly with their God,</hi> Mich. 6.</p>
            <p>Now from theſe Scripture-Warrants, I honour my Great Grandfather <hi>Adam,</hi> becauſe to him was committed the firſt Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of God, making known the Covenant of Grace: I honour my Grandfather <hi>Noah,</hi> becauſe he was Heir of the Righteouſneſs of Faith, and had the ſecond Edition of the Covenant of Grace, extended to all his Generations, till by Sin they eject themſelves. I likewiſe honour my Father <hi>Abraham,</hi> becauſe he had the third Edition of the Covenant of Grace, as a Bleſſing to all Nations, or to all the Families of the Earth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. And alſo for that God was pleaſed to chooſe his Poſterity, as the People from whom Men ſhould look for their Saviour, with reſpect to his Deſcent ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Fleſh, and of this Covenant, as alſo of the Land of Promiſe was Circumciſion given as a <hi>Sign</hi> to his Poſterity, that they might not mix with other Nations, in Life or Religion; but to <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf, as a Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith, which he had near 30 Years before he was Circumciſed.</p>
            <p>But for all this, I know that in Goſpel-times, unleſs <hi>we crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Fleſh with the Affections and Luſts, we cannot be</hi> Abraham'<hi>s Seed, nor Heirs according to the Promiſe,</hi> Gal. 3. 29. And the Seal of our Sonſhip and Right to the Inheritance, is the Holy Spirit, <hi>Epheſ. 1. 13. Gal. 4. 6. Epheſ.</hi> 4. 30.</p>
            <p>Mr. Firmin. <hi>Now ſuppoſe that were true which is the great buſineſs of your Pamphlet, to prove that all dying Infants are ſaved. That there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you may take off the Odium which lies upon you for ſhutting the Children of Believers out of the Church, and denying them Baptiſm,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109913:11"/>
they being under the Covenant of Grace made with</hi> Adam, (as you ſay) <hi>Tell me, Is this Covenant of God with</hi> Abraham's <hi>Seed in vain? Does the holy One make vain Covenants? As to his Seed, they were well enough before: If Iſaac die before the 8th day, he is ſaved, ſo that this Covenant might have been ſpared.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> 1. I hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaid enough to ſhew that <hi>Abraham's Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> Gen. 17. was not in vain; but I am ſure you here make a vain uſe of it. For had <hi>Iſaac</hi> died before he was Eight Days old, in your Judgment he had not been ſaved, and conſequently no Male Infants which died before they were Circumciſed were ſaved. This is that wretched Doctrine which I oppoſe. And ſeeing you make Baptiſm as neceſſary to Salvation as Circumciſion was, and call it the Seal of the Covenant; you either make Infants which die unbaptized, ſaved by an unſealed Covenant, (as you ſpeak) or elſe you <hi>damn all Infants which die unbaptized.</hi> No other ſenſe can be made of your ſtrange Queſtions, P. 73.</p>
            <p>Your Queſtion is this. <hi>Are they all Juſtified and Saved? then it muſt be by a Covenant of Grace. And ſhall they be under the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ſo, as to be in a juſtified and ſaved ſtate by it, and not have the Seal of the Covenant?</hi> As if the Covenant of Grace were of no uſe to poor Infants, without the <hi>Croſſing, Sprinkling,</hi> or (as you) <hi>Pouring</hi> a little Water on their Forehead, for which you have no Rule at all in the Word of God. I cannot but admire your great Blindneſs.</p>
            <p>2. The Covenant of Circumciſion might not now be ſpared, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God had now deſigned, to honour <hi>Abraham's Faith,</hi> and to make him and his Poſterity famous both for <hi>Multitude, Religion,</hi> and other Excellencies, but chiefly to point out all Nations from whence to look for a <hi>Saviour;</hi> which accordingly was foreknown and expected by many other Nations, by means of the Covenant made with <hi>Abraham.</hi> But you add:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If their Seed die while little ones, I hope they are not further from Salvation by this Covenant, nor Parents the leſs hope—two ſtrings to a Bow are good.</hi> But I anſwer:</p>
            <p>1. You ſo ſtring your Bow of Salvation for Infants that you break it, and ſo kill more Infants than you ſave, yea, <hi>an Iſaac him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> cannot eſcape you, but muſt periſh, if he die before the 8th day. Pray, Sir, what manner of Doctrine is this? is it in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Infants to live till the 8th day? And if God take them away before the 8th day, will God damn them becauſe they were
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:109913:12"/>
not Circumciſed, when yet by his own Law they might not have it? Are theſe the comfortable Strings you give Parents to the Bow of Infants Salvation?</p>
            <p>2. Hence it is evident that it is you, not I, that make Infants further off from Salvation by the Covenant of Circumciſion. For I ſay, (though all the Commands of God be good in their place and uſe) yet he never ordained any Rite, to be neceſſary to the ſalvation of poor Infants. But according to your Doctrine, if Infants died before the Covenant of Circumciſion was made, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the firſt, ſecond, third, fourth, fifth, ſixth, or ſeventh day, their Salvation was never the more doubtful for that. But now the Caſe is very hard, for if <hi>Iſaac</hi> himſelf die before the 8th day he is loſt, according to your ſenſe of the Covenant. What fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, I have anſwer'd before.</p>
            <p>Mr. Firmin. <hi>Yet again, as to that Notion wherein you ſo much glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, I have made five remarkable Demonſtrations, as you call them, to prove it; you muſt make three more Demonſtrations, or elſe theſe five will not do the Feat. 1. That God does ſave thoſe that are under that Covenant, without any Condition in it. Name that Text, I pray.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Here obſerve again, Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> is in good Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, that no Infants can be ſaved, unleſs they keep the Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Covenant. And he makes Heart-Circumciſion, and the Circumciſion of the Fleſh, both neceſſary Conditions of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, for Infants Salvation in the time of the Law, or ever ſince <hi>Abraham</hi>'s time. And Repentance, and Faith, and Baptiſm, the Condition in the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>2. I am to demonſtrate the contrary, which with much eaſe (by God's Grace) I ſhall do. I ſay then, Almighty God made a Covenant of Grace with <hi>Adam</hi> in the Promiſed Seed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. in which Covenant ſtood the Salvation of all dying Infants; and yet no Condition was there to be annexed on the part of Infants; howbeit, Faith was neceſſary on <hi>Adam's</hi> part, or elſe he had ſinned in not belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Promiſe <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>In the Book of Wiſdom, we read,</hi> That Wiſdom preſerved the firſt Father of the World, and brought him out of his Offence, <hi>Chap. 10. 1.</hi> which is agreeable to the Canonical Scripture, <hi>Luke 3. 38.</hi> becauſe <hi>Adam</hi> is called the Son of God. <hi>Dr. Willit. Hexap. in Gen. p. 56.</hi>
               </note>. And its evident, <hi>Abel</hi> had Faith in this Promiſe by his offering a Lamb, a Figure of Chriſt the <hi>Lamb ſlain from the foundation of the World.</hi> See Diod. on <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>To prove that God requires nothing of Duty, as a Condition of the Covenant
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:109913:12"/>
on the part of Infants in order to Salvation, I will ſet down two Texts, <hi>Deut. 11. 1. to 10. Rom.</hi> 5. 14, 18. And I alſo give you this Argument: <hi>Circumciſion it ſelf was not appointed to be a Condition of the Covenant of Grace, neceſſary to the Salvation of ſo much as one In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant.</hi> Ergo, <hi>There was never any thing impoſed or required of Infants as a neceſſary Condition of the Covenant, for the Salvation of Infants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Conſequence I ſuppoſe will not be denied, becauſe nothing can be pretended with ſo much probability this way, as Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion: And for the <hi>Major</hi> it is clear from the caſe of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Child, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4. 24, 25. where we find that God ſought not to kill the Child, becauſe it was not Circumciſed the 8th Day, but he ſought to kill <hi>Moſes;</hi> which ſhews the Child was not guilty of Sin in this Caſe. And that this Note may be the more acceptable, I ſhall make ſome Addition to the Teſtimonies formerly given, and here ſhew the Judgment of ſome Learned Writers in this Caſe. <hi>Cajetan</hi> (a Man no leſs Zealous for Infant-Baptiſm than Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> yet) writes thus: <hi>Conſentaneum eſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>It is ſit that none ſhould be Puniſhed, but they which had committed the Fault: But Infants can commit no Fault, therefore the puniſhment here aſſigned doth belong to the Adult only, they only be rightfully Puniſhed, which only are juſtly blamed for the omiſſion of Circumciſion.</hi> And ſaith a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Doctor upon this Sentence, <hi>Put Baptiſm</hi> (meaning of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants) <hi>in the place of Circumciſion, and this Sentence is moſt true of the one, as well as of the other.</hi> Yea, the Ancients, quoted by the ſaid Doctor, tell us, <hi>Circumciſion did</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Diodat.</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 14. who is alſo clear in this Point.</note> 
               <hi>not profit the Soul, but was only a ſign of Grace: For Children when they underſtand not what is done to them, can reap no profit thereby to their Souls,</hi> Chryſ. Hom. 9. in Gen. And <hi>Irenaeus</hi> is alledged to ſay, <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion was only given as a Sign to the People.</hi> The concluſion is, that as it is certain that Infants ſhall be cleanſed and renewed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they come to Heaven; ſo God hath not tied this Mercy to any Ritual, or thing to be done by us, but by the Obedience of Chriſt, and his Free-Grace, ſanctifies them in a manner un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to us.</p>
            <p>Mr. Firmin. 2. <hi>You muſt demonſtrate</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that by this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant he ſaves thoſe who have loſt the Image of God, and are corrupt by Nature, for Infant-Regeneration, and Heart-Circumciſion, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied by you, and yours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:109913:13"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Demonſtration alſo will eaſily be made, or elſe I am ſure Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> and <hi>my ſelf,</hi> ſhall not be Saved, for that we are as corrupt by Nature, and have loſt the Image of God as much as any Infant; nay, we are ſent to Infants to learn the Qualifications we want.</p>
            <p>And as <hi>all have ſinned, and come ſhort of the Glory of God;</hi> ſo they <hi>are Juſtified freely by his Grace, through the Redemption which is in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> Rom. 3. 23, 25. And tho Chriſt is <hi>ſet forth to be a Propitiation through Faith in his Blood, for the Remiſſion of Sins that are paſt through the forbearance of God;</hi> yet this Faith is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of Infants, becauſe they cannot believe on him of whom they have not heard, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. And tho you reply, <hi>That this is ſpoken of the Adult,</hi> yet you are to know as it is the <hi>Adult only</hi> to whom the Goſpel is preached, ſo it is the <hi>Adult only</hi> who are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to believe. As for the Way of the Almighty in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Infants Regeneration, 'tis a thing not revealed; and therefore you do but vainly pretend to know it. And ſeeing it is ſaid, <hi>That we know not the Way of the Spirit, nor how the Bones do grow<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the Womb of her that is with Child.</hi> It is ſtrange that Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> ſhould know after what manner the Hearts of Infants are Circumciſed, and how they are Regenerate. It is enough for us to know that they are redeemed by Chriſt, and ſaved by Grace; for in knowing this, we know our Gracious God will deny them no Supplies which is needful for them.</p>
            <p>If this do not ſatisfie Mr. <hi>F.</hi> then let him give ſome account to the World now he is grown up, how the Spirit did work in the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of his Regeneration in his Infancy; and if he can give no account of his own Infant-Regeneration, then, I think, it will be hard for him to give it of the manner of the Regeneration of other Infants.</p>
            <p>Mr. Firmin. 3. <hi>You muſt demonſtrate, that tho Infants have not actually ſinned againſt the Covenant of Grace, yet they have not unbelief and impenitency ſeminally, which are quite oppoſite to the Covenant of Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. I conceive nothing can be ſpoke more irrationally, nor unrighteouſly, than to ſuggeſt that poor Infants have Unbelief and Impenitency in them. And yet ſo 'tis, the ſeeds of thoſe Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties at leaſt Mr. <hi>F.</hi> will have to be in them: And I demand of him, how he knows this? And how he can tell when theſe Sins againſt the Covenant of Grace, are purged from Infants? Seeing he has
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109913:13"/>
told us they are not holy by their Birth, I would know whether they be purged before their Birth, or after? But let us hear our Saviour's Judgment of little Children, which all will grant to be more worth than Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi>'s.</p>
            <p>He ſpeaks of ſome <hi>juſt Perſons which need no Repentance,</hi> whom he oppoſes to ſuch as have gone aſtray. I will not preſume, that this is only meant of Infants, to whom our Lord tells us the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven belongs; but I humbly conceive, as it is true of them, ſo it does include them, as being of that Number.</p>
            <p>Again, He tells us, <hi>Except we be Converted and become as little Children, we cannot ſee the Kingdom of God.</hi> But if Infants be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief</hi> and <hi>Impenitency,</hi> in ſuch a degree, as theſe Sins in them <hi>are quite oppoſite to the Covenant of Grace,</hi> we ſhould have but little benefit by ſuch Converſion: And thus he reflects upon Chriſt in his Directions to his Followers, as if Chriſt gave not good Counſel herein.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts Chriſtians, as touching Malice, to be Children; in which Speech he is directly contrary to Mr. <hi>F.</hi> And St. <hi>Peter</hi> would have us like <hi>new-born Babes, i. e.</hi> to lay aſide all <hi>Malice, Guile, Hypocriſie, and evil Speaking.</hi> But if Unbelief and Impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency be in them <hi>Seminally,</hi> theſe Impieties are there alſo; and then they are bad Preſidents, being as wicked as it is poſſible for them to be, in Mr. <hi>F</hi>'s judgment.</p>
            <p>However, Mr. <hi>F.</hi> is compelled to confeſs, <hi>Infants are not guilty of any Actual Sin againſt the Covenant of Grace.</hi> And then, who made you a Judg of their Hearts, Sir? Sure this is an Attempt too high for any Man.</p>
            <p>But I muſt <hi>demonſtrate that Infants have not unbelief ſeminally.</hi> Well, I will plead their Cauſe as well as I can; and I Argue for them thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They who have no object of Faith propounded to them ſeminally, can have no unbelief ſeminally. But Infants have no object of Faith pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to them ſeminally.</hi> Ergo, <hi>They can have no unbelief ſeminally.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If Mr. <hi>F.</hi> deny the <hi>Minor,</hi> I will hold him to his own Law, <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmanti incumbit probatio.</hi> If he affirm that Infants have an object of Faith propounded to them <hi>ſeminally,</hi> let him prove it. As for the <hi>Major,</hi> our Saviour's words, <hi>John</hi> 15. 22. do eſtabliſh it; and indeed, <hi>This is the Condemnation, that Light is come—, and Men love Darkneſs.</hi> He that has no Light cannot be blamed, becauſe he cannot ſee. Our Lord charges not the ſin of Unbelief, till means
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109913:14"/>
to <hi>believe was rejected;</hi> And will he be more unkind to the Infant, than to the grown Perſon? Who can have ſo vile an opinion of the Almighty!</p>
            <p>But I muſt <hi>demonſtrate</hi> alſo, that <hi>Infants have not Impenitency ſeminally, yea, ſuch Impenitency as is quite oppoſite to the Covenant of Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, I reply, firſt, by way of Admiration, That ever ſuch <hi>wild Notions</hi> ſhould iſſue from a Learned Head, that ſo he might have ſome ſpecious pretence to damn poor Infants: But God hath ſaid, <hi>He will turn the Wiſdom of Wiſe Men backward, and make Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viners mad,</hi> Iſa. 44. 25.</p>
            <p>2. Impenitency ſuppoſes the Party charged, firſt, to be guilty of ſome Sin committed, <hi>or deſired,</hi> or conceived. But nothing of this can be juſtly charged againſt Infants. Conſider them acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of Original Sin, by the Mercy of God in their Redeemer; Who ſhall lay any thing to their charge? What have they done?</p>
            <p>Mr. Firmin. <hi>Do you ask what have they done? Did you never ſee Revenge, Wrath, Pride, Envy, Rebellion againſt, and Striking of Parents, acting in little Children?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Theſe are not Infants of Eight days old, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but ſuch who by the ill Example of their Tutors, quickly may learn theſe things. Otherwiſe, if the Child thinks it has cauſe to be Angry, and to make Defence, it does no more than you will vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate in your own Cauſe. And why does not Charity make you think the beſt of Infants, ſeeing you ought to think no evil of the weak actions of grown Perſons? O, thou that canſt ſee ſuch Beams, as <hi>Revenge, Wrath, Pride, Rebellion,</hi> &amp;c. in the Eyes of poor Infants! pluck theſe Beams out of thine own, which evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently are thy Diſtempers from the Books which thou haſt writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, in which, not many Pages are free from Tincture of ſome of theſe Diſeaſes. But you add:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bleſſed</hi> Auſtin <hi>obſerved a Sucking Child, that was not able to arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate one word, look with a Countenance even pale with Envy, upon his fellow-Suckling, which ſhared with him in the ſame Milk; which made the holy Man cry out,</hi> Ubi, Domine? Quando, Domine?</p>
            <p>Reply, How did <hi>Auſtin</hi> know that the Child was <hi>pale with Envy?</hi> Suppoſe this good Man himſelf had ſat down to Dinner, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſnatch it all away from him, perhaps he would have look'd Pale alſo; for ſuch we muſt ſuppoſe the Child's caſe to be, when another takes the Breaſt, it thinks all is gone, for it yet underſtands
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:109913:14"/>
not the Rules of Hoſpitality, or Good-fellowſhip, being unſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the others Neceſſity. The poor Child attended its own preſervation as Nature taught it; a poor ground on which to build ſo ſevere a Charge. Should the beſt of God's People be tried, how duly they make others ſharers in their Bleſſings, who have need of Relief, they may perhaps be more juſtly charged than that Sucking Child; <hi>Judg no poor Infants, leſt ye be judged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude: <hi>Seminal Faith, Seminal Repentance, Seminal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief,</hi> and <hi>Seminal Impenitency,</hi> are things of which we have no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in Scripture. And though I would not offend Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> nor at all diſparage his Scholarſhip, which I acknowledg to be abundantly more than mine; yet when I conſider Learning in Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s ſenſe, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 14. I cannot but think theſe to be very <hi>wild and unlearned Notions,</hi> which <hi>no Man can be aſſured of,</hi> nor give a good account that he <hi>learned them of any of the Maſter-Builders, the holy Apoſtles.</hi> And who ever aſſerts theſe things, ſhall never be able to prove them, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>ſome Infants have Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance ſeminally;</hi> and others have <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief and Impenitency ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally.</hi> And (which is another Impoſſibility) no Man can diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the Infants one from another. Nor can it ever be proved, that Seminal Faith and Repentance (if yet any Body can tell what it is) do give us any ground to baptize any Body. For,</p>
            <p>Suppoſe we take this Seminal <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Repentance</hi> to be the faculties of <hi>Credence</hi> and <hi>Sorrow:</hi> Or ſuppoſe ſome take them to be ſome ſecret Inſpirations of the Spirit, yet ſith they appear not to us, it is as if they were not. For that Rule is good in this Caſe, <hi>De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> non apparentibus, &amp; non exiſtantibus eidem eſt ratio.</hi> It is the profeſſion of Faith and Repentance, that qualifies a Perſon (in reſpect of us) for Sacred Baptiſm; the Church is not judg of of Hearts, they are only known to God infallibly.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="part">
            <head>Diviſion 4. Concerning Original Sin.</head>
            <p>It would even grieve a Sober Chriſtian, to read the ſtrange Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations which Men have Publiſhed about Original Sin; and the Extreams they have run into on the Right Hand, and on the Left, cenſuring one another very ſeverely for their differing appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions in this Matter. And it is remarkable, how <hi>cruelly Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarious</hi> Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> is againſt my ſelf in particular, repreſenting
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:109913:15"/>
me as a <hi>Maſter</hi> among the worſt ſort of <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> who, he ſays, denies <hi>Original Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning which, he tells you, we are <hi>Rotten.</hi> That <hi>the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Anabaptiſm</hi> lies <hi>in denying Original Sin.</hi> That in this <hi>we are given up to more blindneſs than the Heathens,</hi> &amp;c. To all which I Anſwer:</p>
            <p>1. If I be one of the worſt of my Brethren in this Point, I hope the reſt will be better thought of by Men of Moderation for my ſake, when they have had (what violent Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> hath not) patience to conſider what I have publiſhed upon the account of <hi>Original Sin,</hi> (and that long before I heard there was ſuch a Man in the World as Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi>) in my <hi>Chriſtianiſmus Primitivus, Book 2. Pag.</hi> 77, 78. thus you read me.</p>
            <p>2. <q rend="margQuotes">For the better attaining to a powerful conviction of Sin, and a ſence of Man's wretchedneſs by reaſon of Sin, it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to underſtate the general ſtate of Tranſgreſſion, into which Mankind is involved; concerning which we find the Scripture gives this Teſtimony, <hi>That all have ſinned, and come ſhort of the Glory of God,</hi> Rom. 3. 23. <hi>And that by one Man Sin entred into the World,—for that all have ſinned. And that the whole World lieth in wickedneſs;</hi> which is alſo evident by common Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, every Nation being greatly corrupted through the abounding of Iniquity; and the univerſality of the ways of Sin does evince the ſame—that the Apoſtle might well ſay, <hi>Both</hi> Jew <hi>and</hi> Gentile <hi>are all under Sin.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>3. <q rend="margQuotes">The Sin of Mankind is either <hi>Original,</hi> or <hi>Actual.</hi> The firſt is come upon all, even the very Infant-ſtate of Mankind lie under it, of whom that ſaying is true, <hi>They have not ſinned after the ſimilitude of</hi> Adam'<hi>s Tranſgreſſion;</hi> yet, Death reigning over them, proves the Tranſgreſſion of <hi>Adam</hi> to be upon them. This is that Root-Sin, called the <hi>Sin of the World,</hi> John 1. 29. whereof none are free. Nor is it convenient to extenuate or leſſen this Sin, either in its nature, or the puniſhment it brings with it; it being indeed the <hi>Filum certiſſimum,</hi> or Leading-Thred to all other Iniquities, Mankind being hereby corrupt <hi>Ab Origine,</hi> and wholly deprived of the Glory of God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the intervening Mercy of a Saviour.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">And hence we find <hi>David,</hi> when complaining of his ſinful ſtate, looks back to his corrupt Original, amongſt the reſt of his Iniquities, complaining, Pſal. 51. 5. <hi>Behold, I was ſhapen</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:109913:15"/>
                  <hi>in Iniquity, and in Sin did my Mother conceive me.</hi> Knowing as <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, <hi>None can bring a clean thing out of an unclean one.</hi> So that they are not to be deſpiſed, who ſay, that in our Humiliation for Sin, we ought to bewail this our Sinful Original, which had been to <hi>Adam</hi>'s Poſterity like the Sin of Traytors, which bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with it corruption of Blood to their Off-ſpring, for which they muſt bear the ſhame of ſuch Tranſgreſſions. How do we find that the Sin of Progenitors was wont to be lamented by their Off-ſpring among the <hi>Iſraelites?</hi> And is there not the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>Adam</hi>'s Children ſhould do the like, as being ſenſible of the evil Conſequences thereof? We alſo may ſay, <hi>Our Father hath ſinned, and we have born his Iniquity.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>4. And hence I like the ſaying of <hi>Irenaeus</hi> well, which I will give in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> becauſe Mr. <hi>F.</hi> is pleaſed to lock it up in <hi>Latine. Omnes enim venit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Chriſt came to ſave all by himſelf, all I ſay, who are born again in God; Infants, Little ones, Boys, and Young Men, and Old Men:</hi> But as for his, <hi>Ideo per omnem venit aetatem,</hi> I let that alone, for I do not find that Chriſt paſſed through the age of Old Men; yet I ſay, he came to Sanctifie every Age, and therefore every Age who do not profane the Blood of Chriſt by which they were Sanctified (as I am ſure no Infant doth) they ſhall certainly be Saved by him, and hence the Salvation of all dying Infants, is apparent enough. But <hi>how Infants are born again in God,</hi> is a ſecret, and not to be Demonſtrated by Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> nor any other. Surely had I written as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> doth, he would have ſaid I exclude the Operation of the Holy Ghoſt; for <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus</hi> ſays, he came to ſave all by himſelf, yet as 'tis certain that the Holy Spirit is not wanting to the Aged Sinner, there is no ground to doubt of his care of poor Infants.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="part">
            <head>Diviſion 5. Of Free-Will.</head>
            <p>Concerning Free-Will, Mr. <hi>F. calls it our</hi> Diana, <hi>and an Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Majeſty, repreſenting us to deny God to be moſt Bleſſed, becauſe if his Will be reſiſted, he failing of his End, is to want a degree of Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> &amp;c. I Anſwer:</p>
            <p>1. Then it ſeems, according to Mr. <hi>F.</hi> all that God wills to be ſaved, muſt, and therefore ſhall be Saved; and the reſt he wills to be Damned, and they ſhall therefore be Damned. But how he can reconcile his Doctrines to theſe Scriptures, I cannot tell, which
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:109913:16"/>
ſaith, <hi>I live, I Will not the death of the Wicked.</hi> And that <hi>this is good in the ſight of God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>who will have all Men to be Saved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. Was it God's Will, that when he brought <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> that their Carcaſes ſhould fall in the Wilderneſs? If it were not, then he wanted a degree of Bleſſedneſs. Was it God's Will that <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould fall, and bring himſelf and his Poſterity into ſo many Miſeries? If not, God was not moſt Bleſſed, becauſe he failed of his End. If you ſay, it was God's Will that <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould fall, and that <hi>Iſrael</hi> muſt fall in the Wilderneſs, you had as good tell us, that God has Decreed all the evil Actions that Men do, and that they muſt do them, elſe God cannot be moſt Bleſſed, becauſe he ſhould fail of his End, if theſe evil Actions were not done. This is his Logick, let him look to it. But,</p>
            <p>3. What I conceive to be Truth concerning Free-Will, I will give you a ſhort account from what I have formerly publiſhed in a little <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> where in <hi>Page</hi> 21. I put theſe Queſtions and Anſwers following.—<hi>What mean you by the third part of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance?</hi> Anſw. <hi>I mean, firſt, a boly loathing of Sin, becauſe it is of the Devil,</hi> 1 John 3. 8. <hi>and becauſe God hates it. And becauſe Chriſt died becauſe of it. 2. To abſtain from the act of Sin, in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, Word, and Deed, as much as poſſible.</hi> God ſaw their Works, that they turned from their Evil Ways. Break off thy Sins by Righteouſneſs: Repent ye therefore and be Converted. <hi>This is to bring forth Fruits meet for Repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> Hath Man any liberty of Will, and any meaſure of Power thus to hate and forſake Sin? Anſw. 1. <hi>By the Bounty of God, Man hath ſome liberty and power this way. He is not chained to his Sins of Neceſſity.</hi> Chuſe you this day whom you will ſerve. To day if ye will hear his Voice, harden not your Hearts. <hi>Mary</hi> hath choſen the good part. 2. <hi>Man's infirmity in the exerciſe of this Liberty and Power is ſo great, that he is not to depend upon this Liberty and Power, but upon the Strength of God in the uſe of them,</hi> Hoſ. 14. 2. 2 Cor. 3. 5.</p>
            <p>Now let any Sober Chriſtian tell me, how it is poſſible to make the Will of Man an Imperial Majeſty out of my Words, that is, a Majeſty that hath no Peer; for no leſs than ſuch a Slander would ſerve Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> to fix upon us, eſpecially upon my ſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For what cauſe he is ſo inveterate, I know not.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:109913:16"/>But come, Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> will the Doctrine of a chief Man of your own pleaſe you? if ſo, you and I may agree in his Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. Thus he ſpeaks; <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>Auſtin</hi> as well as <hi>Pelagius<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Calvin</hi> as well as the <hi>Arminians;</hi> the <hi>Dominicans</hi> as well as the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> all generally maintain that Man hath Free-will. <hi>Origen</hi> is condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> for ſaying that Man had loſt the Image of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>—This Image is two-fold, 1. <hi>Natural,</hi> i. e. <hi>Reaſon and Free Will. 2. Qualitative,</hi> or <hi>Ethical, i. e.</hi> Our Holineſs, and this is loſt, and by Grace reſtored. No Man of Brains can deny, that Man hath a Will naturally free; it is free from Violence.—It's a ſelf-determining Principle, but is not freed from evil Diſpoſitions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               </q>
               <bibl>Mr. Baxter's <hi>Preface to his Call to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>converted.</hi>
               </bibl> I think I need ſay no more to a Wiſe Man: And I am ſure, this is as much as any Wiſe Man among us will ſay in this Matter.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <head>CONCL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SION.</head>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> ſeems diſpleaſed at the multitude which will be Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; if my Opinion be true, that all Dying Infants ſhall be Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: I will give you his own words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I pray</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>whoſe Opinion are you of,</hi> Huberus? <hi>the promiſcuous Salvation of all. Or are you of</hi> Caelius Secundus Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio'<hi>s Opinion, That the number of the Elect and Saved is much great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than the number of the Reprobate and Damned? Whether you, or theſe, or Chriſt, be trueſt,</hi> (Mat. 7. 14. few find it) <hi>the Day of Judgment will determine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here, Sir, you ſhew your Spirit. But for anſwer: Although I know that <hi>God is not willing that any ſhould Periſh, but that all ſhould come to Repentance,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 9. 1 Tim. 2. 4. yet I ſee too much cauſe to fear, that but very few of the many, to whom God is ſo <hi>long ſuffering to lead them to Repentance,</hi> will conſider his Goodneſs therein: And that the far greater part will <hi>deſpiſe the Riches of God's Goodneſs, and treaſure up unto themſelves Wrath againſt the Day of Wrath, and Revelation of the Righteous Judgment of God.</hi> And in this very reſpect, I fear, ſome old Profeſſors, ſuch eſpecially as have been Teachers of others, and yet have not learned either Civility, or Honeſty, in treating thoſe who differ from them in Opinion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:109913:17"/>As to the Text, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 14. bleſſed be God, Infants are in no danger by it, they may all be Saved, and ſo the number of the Saved be much the greater by them; for ſeeing they none of them are <hi>walking in the Broad-way which leads to Deſtruction;</hi> they muſt needs go the Way which leads to Life, Tho as it is a ſtrait way of Faith and Obedience, and many Croſſes for Chriſt's ſake, they can neither ſeek nor find it; yet their Redeemer hath found it for them, and has declared their Right to Heaven, and will therefore in his own Time and Way, bring them to the Enjoyment of that Kingdom which he hath prepared for them, as well as others. But here alſo we ſee, you are unkind to many Dying Infants, whilſt you are ſending them to Hell with thoſe who walk in the Broad-way.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
