<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief narrative and deduction of the several remarkable cases of Sir William Courten, and Sir Paul Pyndar, Knights, and William Courten late of London Esquire, deceased their heirs, executors, administrators and assigns, together with their surviving partners and adventurers with them to the East-Indies, China and Japan, and divers other parts of Asia, Europe, Africa and America : faithfully represented to both houses of Parliament.</title>
            <author>Graves, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-03">2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41836</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1605</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39444</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18419452</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18419452</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107521</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A41836)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107521)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1634:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief narrative and deduction of the several remarkable cases of Sir William Courten, and Sir Paul Pyndar, Knights, and William Courten late of London Esquire, deceased their heirs, executors, administrators and assigns, together with their surviving partners and adventurers with them to the East-Indies, China and Japan, and divers other parts of Asia, Europe, Africa and America : faithfully represented to both houses of Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Graves, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 12, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Graves by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>(from t.p.) "Reduced under the four principal heads, viz.--I. the discovery and plantation of Barbadoes -- II. Their undertakings and expeditions to the East-India, China and Japan-- III. The denyal of justice upon their civil actions depending in Holland and Zealand--IV. Their loanes and supplyes for the service of the crown, upon the collection of fines and compositions out of the popish recusants estates, &amp;c."</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Courten, William, d. 1655.</term>
               <term>Courten, William, --  Sir, 1572-1636.</term>
               <term>Pindar, Paul, --  Sir, 1565 or 6-1650.</term>
               <term>Nederlandsche Oost-Indische Compagnie.</term>
               <term>Merchant ships --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Stuarts, 1603-1714.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  1603-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107521:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Brief NARRATIVE And Deduction of the several Remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Cases of Sir <hi>William Courten,</hi> and Sir <hi>Paul Pyndar,</hi> Knights; and <hi>William Courten</hi> late of <hi>London</hi> Esquire, Deceased: Their Heirs, Executors, Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistrators and Assigns, together with their Surviving Partners and Adventurers with them to the <hi>East-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, China</hi> and <hi>Iapan,</hi> and divers other parts of <hi>Asia, Europe, Africa</hi> and <hi>America</hi>: Faithfully represented to both Houses of Parliament.</p>
            <p>Reduced under four Principal Heads, viz.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>I.</hi> The Discovery and Plantation of <hi>Barbadoes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>II.</hi> Their Vndertakings, and Expeditions to the <hi>East-India, China</hi> and <hi>Japan.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>III.</hi> The Denyal <hi>of</hi> Iustice upon their civil Actions depending in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>IV.</hi> Their Loanes and Supplyes for the Service of the Crown, upon the Collection of Fines and Compositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons out of the Popish Recusants Estates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Recollected out of the Original Writings and Records, for publick Satisfaction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:107521:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107521:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal: And to the Honorable, the Knights, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens and Burgesses, in Parliament, Assembled.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable, and most Worthy Patriots;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE following Narrative, and Deduction of the several Cases, gives a brief Account of the vast Improvement and Riches of <hi>England</hi> by Trade and Enterprises of those two famous Merchants, <hi>Sir William Courten</hi> and <hi>Sir Paul Pyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar,</hi> Knights, Deceased, who for their Publick Spirits and Loyalty, had not their Equals in the Age they lived: Their Names being as well known, as their Memorable Actions throughout the World: Their great disburse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon several emergent Occasions, and their Greater Losses, occasioned by the unhappiness of the late troublesom Times, when Iustice was not only Obstructed, but pervert<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed to their great prejudice and oppression. Wherefore the Complaynants thought it most seasonable and conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to give this following Relation of their Services and Sufferings; and consequently of the Losses and Damages sustained by their Heirs, Executors, Administrators and Creditors, which include many Hundred Families within the City of <hi>London</hi> and this Kingdom. The causes of Complaint continuing so long are the more grievous, under a Government so renowned for the Laws, Liberties and Properties of the Subjects. Yet since it is the Priviledg of <hi>English</hi> men to represent their Grievances in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Complaynants have modestly done it, being rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy with their Vouchers upon Record to justify every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular of their Charge, promising to themselves in this Iun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture,
<pb facs="tcp:107521:3"/>
that the Cause of the Widdows and Fatherless may be heard and relieved.</p>
            <p>It is very remarkable, That the Ancestors of <hi>Sir Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Courten,</hi> fled out of <hi>Flanders</hi> into <hi>England</hi> for Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of their Lives, Liberties and Estates in the time of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> from the <hi>Spanish</hi> Inquisition, under <hi>Duke de Alva</hi>: And that <hi>William Courten</hi> 
               <abbr>Esq</abbr> was forced out of <hi>England,</hi> to preserve himself from Want and Imprisonment: And even his Son <hi>William Courten,</hi> the Grand Child of <hi>Sir William,</hi> constrained to live in Exile, to escape the Prosecutions of his Fathers and Grandfathers Creditors <hi>(inter alia)</hi> for those very Moneys lent, to supply King <hi>James</hi> and King <hi>Charles</hi> the First, towards the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and Relief <hi>of Rochel</hi> and the <hi>Isle of Ree.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The several Abstracts of these following Cases, being of very high import to the Honour and Interest of the King and Kingdom, may easily invite every person that is a Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of his Country, to a through perusal, and even to grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy himself with some remarques not vulgarly known,</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Obliging thereby, Among all the rest of the persons interessed and concern'd</hi>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your most Obedient and Devoted Servants,</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Edward Graves</item>
                     <item>Thomas Townesend</item>
                     <item>Elizabeth Whitaker</item>
                     <item>Iames Boeve</item>
                     <item>Gilbert Crouch</item>
                     <item>Thomas Norton</item>
                     <item>Richard Powell</item>
                     <item>Nath. Hill</item>
                     <item>George Carew</item>
                     <item>Thomas Coppin</item>
                     <item>William Hinton</item>
                     <item>Volentina Lloyd</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="narrative">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107521:3"/>
            <head>A Brief Narrative, and deduction of the several remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Cases of Sir <hi>William Courten,</hi> and Sir <hi>Paul Pyndar,</hi> Knights; and <hi>William Courten</hi> late of <hi>London</hi> Esquire, Deceased: Their Heirs, Executors, Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistrators and Assigns, together with their Surviving Partners and Adventurers with them to the <hi>East-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, China</hi> and <hi>Iapan,</hi> and divers other parts of <hi>Asia, Europe, Africa</hi> and <hi>America</hi>: Faithfully represented to both Houses of Parliament.
Reduced under four Principal Heads, viz.
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>I.</hi> The Discovery and Plantation of <hi>Barbadoes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>II.</hi> Their Vndertakings, and Expeditions to the <hi>East-India, China</hi> and <hi>Japan.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>III.</hi> The Denyal <hi>of</hi> Iustice upon their civil Actions depending in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>IV.</hi> Their Loanes and Supplyes for the Service of the Crown, upon the Collection of Fines and Compositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons out of the Popish Recusants Estates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <p>As followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>I. Barbadoes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT Sir <hi>William Courten</hi> at his own proper Costs and Charges first Discovered, Planted and Possessed the Island of <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any Subject or Inhabitant belonging to any Nation or Kingdom whatsoever.</p>
               <p>That he Fortified the said Island, and expended 28600 <hi>l.</hi> ster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in Fortifications, Buildings and settling Plantations, before he had a Patent under the Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> for the Government thereof, in the third year of King <hi>Charles</hi> the First, which subjected the same to the Dominion of the King: And being in the quiet Possession of the said Island, for the space of two years and upwards, had allotted out several Plantations to others, under acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments of Quit-Rents, so that he could not be disseised thereof without
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:107521:4"/>
manifest Injustice. That by the Law of <hi>England,</hi> The Heirs and Assigns of Sir <hi>William Courten</hi> retain a Freehold in the said <hi>Island,</hi> according to the Original of all Propriety, Notwithstanding <hi>Iames</hi> late Earl of <hi>Carlisle</hi> by an Arbitrary and pretended Power and Authority, as Lord Proprietor of all the <hi>Carribee</hi> Islands, in the year 1628. with his Complices Subjects of <hi>England</hi>) entred the said Island of <hi>Barbados</hi> by force of Arms, and spoiled Sir <hi>William Courten,</hi> his Servants and Planters of their Lands, Houses, Fortifications and Possessions, which In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trusion doth not create a Right to any that claim under the said Earl, or others that got into Possession afterwards by Colour of his pretended Title. The Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the King being to be preferred before the Profit of the King: <hi>Bracton lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. <hi>de acquirendo rerum dominio si insula in Mari nata sit occupantis, sic oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupanti conceditur</hi>; and the Book saith, It is <hi>tantum divina natura aperante.</hi> That these wrongs and oppressions have been divers times made appear both in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Fact and Law. But in regard there was no Parliament held in <hi>England</hi> for the space of 13 years after the said Force and Injury committed: Sir <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Courten</hi> and his Son could not find any relief against the said <hi>Earl of Carlisle</hi> or his Agents and Complices, the said Earl being so powerful with the chief Ministers of State at that time. And by reason of other Spoils and Depredati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons committed upon Sir <hi>William Courten</hi> and his Son by the <hi>East India</hi> Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> (hereafter particularly mentioned) all further prosecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for satisfaction and reparation of Damages was suspended <hi>pro tempore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That <hi>William Courten,</hi> Son and Heir of the said <hi>Sir William</hi> fled into <hi>Italy,</hi> where he died indebted to his own Creditors 64000 <hi>l.</hi> And as Heir and Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to his Father, in the Summ of 146000 <hi>l.</hi> more, unto those Creditors, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted upon Accounts of the Linnen Trade, <hi>Barbados</hi> and <hi>East India.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That several Addresses were made by your Complaynants between the years 1646 and 1660, to the Powers then in being, setting forth Sir <hi>William Courtens</hi> Right and Title to the <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> which were most evidently made out before several Committees of Parliament, and other special Commissioners appointed to examine the same, as by the Depositions of the first <hi>Planters</hi> and Servants of Sir <hi>William Courten</hi> ready to be produced may appear: but the many Changes and Revolutions of Government in those days, and the Domestick and Forreign Wars obstructed the determination of the said Cause.</p>
               <p>In which Juncture several discontented persons prompted your Complay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants to transfer their Interest and Property in the said Island to some Foreign Prince, then Mr. <hi>Kendal,</hi> a chief Agent for the Planters that Claimed only by a bare possession indeavored to get an Act of Parliament to annex the said Island to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> and was willing to give a Considerable Summ of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to your Complaynants for their concurrence in the same, for the quieting of the Possessions to the said Planters and their Heirs for ever, but meeting with some Opposition, nothing proceeded farther than meer Proposals.</p>
               <p>That since His Majesties most Happy Restauration your Complainants con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued their Claim by several Addresses to the <hi>Council Board</hi> and the <hi>Parliament,</hi> And the Lord Chancellor <hi>Hyde</hi> gave for Answer at the <hi>Council Board,</hi> That the Complainants Right should be preserved, but that they must have Patience un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the Government of the said Island was settled, and all matters compos'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween His Majesty and other Neighbouring Princes and States.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Lord Willoughby</hi> clayming a Lease of several Plantations in the said Island, and the Government thereof under the pretended Title of the said <hi>Earl of Carlisle,</hi> went over present Governor, Whereupon your Complaynants rested in expectation of some seasonable time to be relieved upon the whole
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:107521:4"/>
matter by the Justice of Parliament, (the Committee for Grievances, seldom sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in any Session of the last long Parliament, dissolved in the Year 1678. and now Humbly hope the Cause of the Widdows and the Fatherless may be heard, and such Sums of Mony raised out of the said Island in compensation of Sir <hi>William Courtens</hi> Original Costs, Charges and Damages, or in lieu thereof, such a yearly Quit-Rent out of the Lands of the said Island forever, as may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to the said Costs and Damages; Many Families having raised great Estates out of the Ruins of the said Sir <hi>William Courten</hi> his Right and Property.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>II. <hi>East-India</hi> Expeditions.</head>
               <p>IN the second place it is Humbly represented, That whereas King <hi>Charles</hi> the first, being truly informed in the year 1635. by Captain <hi>Iohn Weddal</hi> and <hi>Nathaniel Mountney</hi> Merchants (who formerly had been in the <hi>East-India</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies Service) That since the erection of that Company, notwithstanding the manifold Priviledges granted them, They neither had so Planted nor Settled Trade in those parts, nor Fortified themselves in any places of Strength, as might secure and encourage others in Future times to Adventure and Trade thither: whereas the <hi>Portugeeze</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> had Planted and Fortified themselves so considerably, That they were likely to establish a Rich and Lasting Trade in those parts of the World, for the good of their Posterity, and by the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of which Improvements they not only rendred the <hi>English</hi> Subjects Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding there, lyable to their Insolencies and frequent Injuries, but in a manner had beaten them out of that Trade, which usually had employed the Shipping of <hi>England,</hi> and vented great quantities of <hi>English</hi> Manufactures. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Majesty gave a special Commission and Charter under the great Seal of <hi>England</hi> to Sir <hi>William Courten, Endimion Porter, Thomas Kynaston,</hi> Captain <hi>Weddal,</hi> Mr. <hi>Mountney</hi> and their Partners and Adventurers with them, in the Eleventh Year of His Reign, to fit out Ships for Trading Voyages, to Traffick with a Joynt Stock in several Goods, Moneys and Merchandizes to <hi>Goa,</hi> the parts of <hi>Mallabar,</hi> the Coasts of <hi>China</hi> and <hi>Iapan,</hi> and divers other parts adjacent, in which Joynt Stock Sir <hi>Paul Pindar</hi> advanced the Summ of 36000 <hi>l.</hi> at several times.</p>
               <p>In pursuance of this Grant the said Sir <hi>William Courten</hi> and Company settled several Factories at <hi>Maccao, Carwarr,</hi> and other Places on the Coast of <hi>India,</hi> and freighted from thence the good Ships named the <hi>Draggon, Catharine</hi> and <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> which were (as hath been made appear by many Circumstances) destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Men and Ships by the <hi>Dutch</hi> homewards bound, with Goods to the value of 150000 <hi>l.</hi> Sterling, for which the Lord <hi>St. Iohns</hi> being sent in the late Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blesom Times in Quality of an Embassador, to the <hi>States General</hi> Demanded Satisfaction at the <hi>Hague</hi> with Interest for the same. That divers others of <hi>Courten</hi> and Companyes Ships escaping the Danger of the Seas and some Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> returned Safely home.</p>
               <p>Afterwards the Ship <hi>Bona Esperanza</hi> loaden with Goods, Monys and Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, Bound from <hi>Goa</hi> to <hi>Maccao,</hi> was in a Hostile manner in the year 1643. seized in the Streights of <hi>Mallacca,</hi> by the Men of War belonging to the <hi>East India</hi> Company of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> who converted the said Ship and Goods to their own use, designedly to spoyl the Trade of Sir <hi>William Courten</hi> and Partners, and destroy their Factories in <hi>India.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the same Year, the said <hi>Dutch</hi> Company took into their Possession another
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107521:5"/>
of <hi>Courtens</hi> Ships called the <hi>Henry bona Adventura,</hi> with her loading, which they also converted to their own use, to the Damage of <hi>Courten</hi> and Company 75000 <hi>l.</hi> Sterling. whereof Proof being made in the High Court of <hi>Admiralty,</hi> The Complaynants made their Addresses to the Lords and Commons in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Year 1646. for relief; Setting forth the Circumstances of the said spoils and depredacions, and that they were done in time of Peace, contrary to the Laws of common Amity and Alliance between both Nations, and that the <hi>Dutch East India</hi> Company had refused to make Satisfaction and Reparation of the Damage. Whereupon a War followed in the nature of <hi>General Reprize</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Commons of <hi>England</hi> and the States General, which continued for several years, till at last <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> having Usurped the Government, made a sudden and disadvantagious Peace, for his own present Security, with the said States in the Year 1654. taking only 84000 <hi>l.</hi> for the Spoils and Barbarous Murthers committed by the Officers and Ministers of the <hi>Dutch East India</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany at <hi>Amboyna</hi>; referring the satisfaction for the loss and value of the said two Ships <hi>Bona Esperanza</hi> and <hi>Henry bona Adventura</hi> to the Arbitrament of the Protestant Cantons of <hi>Switzerland,</hi> who were not only to compose that diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the said two Ships, but all other Spoils and Dammages that the <hi>Dutch</hi> had committed upon the <hi>English</hi> ever since the Year 1611. But the said Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons refusing to undertake or meddle therein, all things remained in <hi>statu quo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Soon after the said Spoils and depradations, <hi>Maurice Thompson,</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> Merchant, and others upon a private Account, set forth several Ships for Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Voyages to the <hi>East Indies,</hi> upon the same Foundations laid by Sir <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Courten,</hi> (The said <hi>Thompson</hi> having first gotten the Books and Papers of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions for that Trade, from the Lady <hi>Katharine Courten</hi>) and made Returns of Ten for one upon those Trading Voyages, as the said <hi>Thompson</hi> himself Confessed before Credible Witnesses, yet living.</p>
               <p>Afterwards the Usurper <hi>Cromwell</hi> having setled the <hi>East-India</hi> Company by a New and Large Charter of Priviledges, conformable to Sir <hi>William Courtens</hi> Grant from the King;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Which Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed to the</hi> East-India <hi>Company since his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stauration.</hi>
                  </note> Three of the Companies Ships called the <hi>Postillion,</hi> the <hi>Frederick,</hi> and the <hi>Francis</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> upon the like Trading Voyages, being stopt in their passage in the <hi>East India</hi> (by the Officers and Men of War belonging to the <hi>Dutch East-India</hi> Company) and their Voyage spoiled. Upon their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint to <hi>Cromwell,</hi> he immediately required, by his Embassador at the <hi>Hague,</hi> sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction and reparation to be made for the said Loss and Damages sustained, which the <hi>East-India</hi> Company of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> were enjoyned by the <hi>States General</hi> upon his Demand, forthwith to satisfy and pay, at the Price Currant, upon a computation of Returns, as if they had made their Voyages home from those Parts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Farther Prosecutions since the <hi>29th. of May 1660.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Upon the Kings most Happy Restauration, the Complaynants made fresh Applications to his Majesty in Council, for Satisfaction of the said Spoils, and Damages of the <hi>Bona Esperanza,</hi> and <hi>Henry Bona Adventura</hi>: and after sixteen Months debate between the <hi>Dutch</hi> Embassadors in <hi>England,</hi> and the Kings Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners, appointed to Treat with them at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> it was agreed in the Treaty of Peace concluded at <hi>Westminster,</hi> the 14<hi>th</hi> of <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1662. That the said spoils and Damages of the <hi>Bona Esperanza,</hi> and <hi>Henry Bona Adventura</hi> should be reserved from the general Abolition and extinguishment of all Offences, Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Losses and Damages whatsoever, for satisfaction and reparation to be-composed in an amicable way.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:107521:5"/>In pursuance whereof, two several Memorials were given in at the <hi>Hague</hi> to the <hi>States General</hi> by Sir <hi>George Downing,</hi> Envoy Extraordinary from his Majesty, yet nothing could be obtained but impertinent Offers of Commencing Suits at Law against <hi>Iacob Pergens</hi> and <hi>Peter Boudaen,</hi> at that time Bayl for the said <hi>Pergens,</hi> who had defrauded the <hi>Dutch East India</hi> Company of 85000 Gilders, upon false pretences of Assignments from <hi>William Courten</hi> of his Interest and Share in the said Ships, which he had formerly granted to Sir <hi>Paul Pyndar,</hi> the said <hi>East-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> Company having intimation thereof.</p>
               <p>After all which fruitless applications and endeavours at a great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, Dr. <hi>Exton,</hi> Judge of the High Court of Admiralty in <hi>England,</hi> by the Kings Command, upon the proofs made before him, reported the Damages to amount to 151612 <hi>l.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then upon the Humble Petition of <hi>Francis</hi> late Earl of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Ayton,</hi> Knight, <hi>Charles Whitacre,</hi> and others of the Complaynants on the behalf of themselves and the rest. His Majesty with the Advice of the Lords of his Privy Council<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was gratiously pleased to grant Letters of Reprizal for the said Summ of 151612 <hi>l.</hi> under the great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> in due form of Law, grounded upon several Acts of Parliament and Statutes of this Realm (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in every Subject of <hi>England</hi> hath an Interest) unto Sir <hi>Edmund Turner</hi> Knight, and <hi>George Carew</hi> 
                  <abbr>Esq</abbr> their Executors, Administrators and Assigns, for the Use and Benefit of your Complaynants, to continue in full force and effect, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the summ of 151612 <hi>l.</hi> should be recovered with damages, or the matter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed between the <hi>East-India</hi> Company of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> and your Complay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, concerning whom, his Majesty hath declared in his Grant, That he was obliged in Justice and Honor to see them satisfyed and repayed, And that no Treaty whatsoever between his Majesty and the said States should obstruct the Recovery or Payment thereof by force or a fair agreement, the said 151612 <hi>l being the only Debt liquidated, ratified and confirmed, judicially to be satisfyed, as is more at large recited in the Letters Patents, bearing Date at</hi> Westminster, <hi>the</hi> 19<hi>th. day of</hi> May <hi>in the Seventeenth Year of the Reign of King</hi> Charles <hi>the Second, and Inrolled in the High Court of</hi> Chancery.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Actions at Law depending in</hi> Holland <hi>and</hi> Zealand <hi>against</hi> Iacob Pergens, <hi>and the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of</hi> Peter Boudaen <hi>and</hi> David Goubard, <hi>at the Suits of the Executors, Administrators and Assigns of Sir</hi> William Courten, <hi>Sir</hi> Paul Pyndar <hi>and</hi> William Courten <hi>
                        <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>An Action upon the Accompts concerning the Linnen Trade against the Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Peter Boudaen,</hi> for <hi>122000</hi> l.</p>
                  <p>An Attachment in the Bank for <hi>12000</hi> Gilders of <hi>David Goubards.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>An Action against <hi>Jacob Pergens,</hi> and the Heirs of Sir <hi>Jacob Gats,</hi> for <hi>3000</hi> l. lent by Sir <hi>William Courten</hi> upon Bond.</p>
                  <p>An Action against the said <hi>Jacob Pergens</hi> for <hi>5500 l.</hi> sterling, upon his Covenant, for Moneys received in Trust for <hi>William Courten <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Three several Actions against the Heyres and Executors of <hi>Peter Boudaen</hi> for <hi>4000 l.</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacies, given to Sir <hi>William Courten, James Boeve</hi> and <hi>William Courten <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                     </hi> by <hi>Sir Peter Courten</hi> and <hi>John Money.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>These Actions came not under any Consideration whatsoever upon Publick Treaties, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can they fall under the construction of Offences, Injuries, Damages and Losses, arising by Spoils and Depredations upon the Sea, for which another proper Remedy is Granted.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>Nevertheless, The War having continued between the King and the <hi>States General,</hi> for the space of two years and a half. A Treaty was concluded at <hi>Breda</hi> on the 21 of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1667. Old Style, mentioning, that all <hi>Offences, Injuries, Damages</hi> and <hi>Losses</hi> should be extinguished, without any notice taken in the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:107521:6"/>
said Articles of any compensation to be made to the Complaynants that lay under all the Circumstances aforesaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Iustice denyed in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the Third place, your Complaynants do most humbly represent the Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice done them by the States of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand,</hi> as followeth, viz. Sir <hi>William Courten,</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> Merchant; Sir <hi>Peter Courten,</hi> of <hi>Middleburgh</hi> in <hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Merchant; and <hi>Iohn Moncy</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> Merchant; entred into Partnership in Trade, with a Joynt Stock, in the year 1606, the moiety of the said Stock belonging to Sir <hi>William Courten,</hi> and to each of the other a fourth part, with which they Traded to <hi>Italy Spain, Portugal,</hi> the Coast of <hi>Barbary,</hi> and other parts of the World, But chiefly carried on a great Stock in the Linnen Trade, both from <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> during their Lives: Besides, they yearly employed four or five Ships fitted out of <hi>Zealand,</hi> for <hi>Greenland,</hi> with <hi>Biscayners</hi> for their Harponeers in the Whale Fishing.</p>
               <p>This Copartnership continued thirty years, wherein they made Returns of Two Hundred Thousand pounds Sterling <hi>per Annum</hi> at least. But the Accompts were not liquidated in Fourteen years before the Death of Sir <hi>William Courten,</hi> who took up of your Complaynants divers great Sums of Money upon Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change and Obligations on the accompt of their Copartnership.</p>
               <p>That Sir <hi>Peter Courten</hi> at the time of his Death stood indebted to the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Stock 129426 <hi>l.</hi> 00 <hi>s.</hi> 10 <hi>d.</hi> as by the Ballance of the Books of Accompts, kept in <hi>London,</hi> appears, which rests in the hands of <hi>Peter Boudaen,</hi> and his Sons, Executors of Sir <hi>Peter Courten.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the Executors of Sir <hi>Peter Courten</hi> and <hi>Iohn Moncy,</hi> living in <hi>Middleburgh</hi> aforesaid, refused upon the Death of Sir <hi>William Courten,</hi> to come to any Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt for the said 129426 <hi>l.</hi> 0 <hi>s.</hi> 10 <hi>d.</hi> in their hands, whereupon a Suite was commenced against them by Mr <hi>Iames Boeve</hi> in <hi>Middleburgh</hi> (the said <hi>Boeve</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been formerly a Servant and Book-keeper to <hi>Iohn Moncy,</hi>) who had a Procuration for that purpose, and advanced very far in the prosecution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, until the <hi>Boudaens</hi> caused the said <hi>Boeve</hi> to be Arrested upon a great feigned Action, and kept him several years in Prison, on purpose to obstruct him in carrying on the Action of Accompt Commenced against them, and depending in the ordinary Courts of Judicature in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand,</hi> And to avoid the said Action, do now insist, That by the general Words of the Articles of the Treaty at <hi>Breda,</hi> (viz. all <hi>Offences, Injuries, Losses and Damages,</hi>) the Executors of Sir <hi>Peter Courten, Iohn Moncy, Peter Boudaen</hi> and <hi>Iacob Pergens</hi> are discharged and released of all Actions relating to Accompts, Obligations, particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts or Covenants whatsoever with <hi>English</hi> men, upon which any Suite was depending before the said Treaty at <hi>Breda,</hi> And that the States of <hi>Holland</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made that Construction upon the said Articles, and consequently interdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted their Courts of Judicature from doing Justice to your Complaynants, they hold themselves discharged accordingly, Which is a <hi>President of that dangerous Consequence against all Civil Society and Commerce, that no</hi> English <hi>man can be safe in his Property and Estate that Trade with the</hi> Hollanders, <hi>if such forced interpretations shall take effect. Which are left to the great Wisdom and apprehension of this Parliament, to report their Opinion, with an effectual recommendation thereof to the King.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:107521:6"/>
               <head>Further Prosecutions concerning the <hi>Bona Esperanza, &amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>That new Differences arising betwen the King of <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>States Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> in the Year 1671. another War was Proclaimed against them in <hi>London,</hi> and about the same time the <hi>French</hi> King also denounced War against the said States, your Complaynants then made farther applications to the King and Council at <hi>Whitehall</hi> for relief in the Premisses, which were referred to a Select Committee of the Lords, who fully represented the said Spoils, Debts and Damages to his Majesty, with their Opinion, That the States not performing their Covenants and Agreements with the King, the Obligations of all past Treaties were Cancelled and of no force: and that it was Just and Seasonable for his Majesty to insist upon satisfaction and reparation for the Complaynants, as freely as if no such Treaties had ever been made, as by their Report un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Hands, Dated the 29 of June 1672, appeares. <hi>And which will be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual claim from one Generation to another, until an actual Satisfaction and Repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be made to the persons interessed and injured.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That in pursuance thereof, several Letters from the King, and Orders from the Council Board, with special Instructions from the Principal Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of State, were sent to the Lords Ambassadors and Plenipotentiaries from his Majesty, during the Treaties both at <hi>Utrecht</hi> and <hi>Cologne,</hi> to insist upon Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction and Reparations for your Complaynants; His Majesty having decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red under His Sign Manual, that His Care in this Singular Case should be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplarily manifested in protecting his Subjects in their Just Rights, as well as to assist them in Recovery thereof.</p>
               <p>The said <hi>States General</hi> and their Subjects then lying under a necessity of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Justice, (the last War having continued for the space of two years in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with <hi>France</hi>:) The Queen Regent of <hi>Spain,</hi> interposed on the behalf of the <hi>States General</hi> with offers to the King for a separate Peace, excluding <hi>France,</hi> promising to secure the payment of <hi>eight Hundred Thousand Pattacones</hi> to his Majesty, which was proposed by the <hi>Spanish</hi> Ambassador, the Marquess <hi>del Frenzo,</hi> who had a special Procuration from the <hi>States General,</hi> to treat upon Articles ready framed, and sent to him from the <hi>Hague</hi>: who found Friends in Parliament to promote that Treaty by Addresses to the King, although at the same time the Plenipotentiaries at <hi>Cologne</hi> were Treating upon better Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for your Complaynants?</p>
               <p>Yet a sudden Peace was concluded at <hi>White Hall,</hi> and the Articles Signed and Sealed the 9 of February 1674. New Stile, by <hi>H. Finch,</hi> C S. <hi>Latimer, Ormond, Arlington</hi> and <hi>H. Coventry,</hi> Commissioners from the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and <hi>Al Marquess del Frenso,</hi> Commissioner for the <hi>States General,</hi> wherein the Seventh Article was worded as follows: <hi>Quod Tractatus Bredae conclusus</hi> Anno Domini 1667, <hi>sicut etiam omnes alij praecedentes tractatus per illum tractatum confirmari reno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventur &amp; maneant in plena vi ac vigori in quantum praesenti tractatus nullatenus contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Breda</hi> Treaty (which the <hi>Hollanders</hi> style their Glorious Peace) being attended with those Horrid Circumstances, after the expence of five Millions and half of pounds Sterling, in those three dreadful years of Plague, Fire and War: The very nomination of <hi>Breda</hi> sounds doleful in all <hi>English</hi> mens ears, that suffered under the Conduct of those persons, who drived on their own private Ends and Advantages, before the Honor and Interest of the King and Kingdom: and still the Politick States-men, would eternize the Glory of their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107521:7"/>
Nation, by recording the Infamy of others. In their own Words, That the Treaty of <hi>Breda,</hi> made in the year 1667, as all other former Treaties Confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the said Treaty, be renewed and remain in their full force and vigour, so far forth, as they contradict nothing in this present Treaty.</p>
               <p>The Complaynants being surprised at the last Treaty, finding no other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision made but the Pattacones, concerning their reparation, notwithstanding the report aforesaid, so lately made to his Majesty by a Committee of the Lords of his Council (viz.) <hi>that all Obligations of past Treaties being Cancelled, it was most Iust and Honorable for his Majesty to insist upon satisfaction of the Debt and Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages ascertained under the great Seal of</hi> England, <hi>as aforesaid</hi>: And there being a rumor spread abroad in the <hi>Hague</hi> and <hi>Amsterdam,</hi> That the Lord <hi>Latimer,</hi> Lord High Treasurer of <hi>England,</hi> and another Minister of State, had perswaded the King to Assign three parts of those Pattacones to the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> for an Old Debt, due to Prince <hi>Henery Fredrick</hi> (his Grandfather) from King <hi>Charles</hi> the First, and the remain for other Services, after all the Blood and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure spent upon account of the Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> which ought to be strictly inquired after,</p>
               <p>Iure naturae aequam est neminem cum alterius detrimento &amp; injuria fieri locupletiorem.</p>
               <p>Then the Complaynants, for preservation of their Right, caused a Protest to be made in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand,</hi> by a Publick Notary, who delivered Copies thereof to the chief persons concerned, reciting the Substance of all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, with a praecaution to the <hi>Directors of the</hi> East-India Company, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Patacoones, and to the States of <hi>Holland</hi>; concerning their Letters to the Ordinary Courts of Judicature, prohibiting any Justice to be done upon the Actions depending upon Obligations, Covenants and matters of account in Trade, protesting for all Damages aleady sustained, or that should be sustained by reason thereof.</p>
               <p>Afterwards the Complaynants Addressed themselves by their Humble Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to his Majesty, and the Lords of his most Honourable Privy Council, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the 151612 <hi>l.</hi> so ascertained under the Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> might ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be payed out of the said Pattacones, Or otherwise, that the Complaynants might be at liberty to reprize the said Debt and Damages, by force of their Grant remaining upon Record: and as to the Civil Actions depending in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand</hi> upon Obligations, Covenants and Merchants Accompts, (whereupon Justice was positively denied) that satisfaction and reparation might be requir'd of Monsieur Van Beuninghen, <hi>then Ambassador Extraordinary from the States Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral,</hi> or that Commissioners might be appointed to determine the same; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon two several Orders were made on the 23. of July 1677. that all parties concerned should be heard at the Council Table, on the 10th. of <hi>October</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to which purpose the Complaynants attended with their Council and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates from time to time, but could not obtain any hearing thereof, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any satisfaction or reparation to this day, in the Premises either at home or abroad.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Loanes and Supplies for the Service of the Crown.</head>
               <p>IN the fourth and last place, your Complaynants do Humbly take leave to represent and offer to your Consideration: That Sir <hi>Paul Pindar</hi> most faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully served King <hi>Iames</hi> and the Honorable <hi>Turky</hi> Company, for the space of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107521:7"/>
Eleven Years together at <hi>Constantinople,</hi> in the quality of an Embassador, where he much improved the <hi>English</hi> Woollen Manufactures, and the <hi>Levant</hi> Trade. And at his return into <hi>England</hi> set up the Allome Works in <hi>York-shire</hi> and other Counties, wherein he employed many Hundreds of poor People, out of which improvement, a certain Revenue of Ten Thousand pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> did accrew to the Crown, and as much more to the Stock of the Kingdom, by importation of ready Money and Staple Goods for Allome exported: which Allome Works are now of little or no Advantage to the Crown or King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
               <p>That Sir <hi>Paul Pindar</hi> in the years 1638 and 1639, having lent and advanced of his own Estate, and of Moneys taken up upon his Credit, Eighty five Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand pounds, to Furnish the Crown with Jewels, and to supply the Queen of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and her Children in their Wants and Necessities, as also for Supplies of Foreign Embassadors and other Services in his Majesties Domestick affairs, The late King <hi>Charles</hi> was Gratiously pleased to Assign for the Security and Repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the said Moneys, with usual Interest, part of the Revenue arising by Fines and Compositions upon Recusants Estates in the Northern Counties, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Collection of <hi>Thomas Viscount Wentworth,</hi> And also other Moneys pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able out of divers branches of the Revenue, as by Tallies struck upon the same, and the several Assignments under the Great Seal of <hi>England</hi> appears, which Payments were diverted in the late Troubles, before any considerable part of the said Debt was paid, that still remains a Charge upon the Crown, to the value of Fifty Thousand pounds and upwards.</p>
               <p>That the said several Assignments under the Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> and all Writings concerning the same, and all Summs of Money whatsoever payable from the Crown, upon the said Assignments, being Granted, Transferred, and Assigned to <hi>Richard Powel</hi> of the <hi>Inner Temple,</hi> 
                  <abbr>Esq</abbr> and <hi>Nathaniel Hill,</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> Gent. their Executors, Administrators and Assigns, in Trust, for the Use and Benefit of themselves, and all the rest of the Persons interessed; according to their several and respective Debts and Demands: They lately exhibited their Humble Petition to his Majesty, setting forth the State of their Debt, and for other reasons contained in their Petition <hi>(more especially, for that</hi> Sir Paul Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar, <hi>for the Preservation of the Royal Family, and transportation of his now Majesty when he was Prince of</hi> Wales, <hi>in the time of the late Troubles, had Voluntarily supplyed the late King with Moneys to a considerable value in Gold, which Loyalty and Care, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty hath lately owned for a most acceptable Service,)</hi> Humbly prayed, That his Majesty would be gratiously pleased to grant them Satisfaction for their said Debt, out of the Fines and Compositions, payable by Recusants, vested in the Crown by several Acts of Parliament. Whereupon His Majesty was Graciou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sly pleased, to refer the Consideration of the said Petition to the Right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, the Lords Commissioners of the Treasury, to Report their Opinions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the same, what was fit for his Majesty to do therein, for the Petioners relief, and then His Majesty would declare His further Pleasure. Whereupon the Petitioners attended several days at the Treasury Chamber, to be Heard; and being once called in, their Lordships informed the Petitioners, that the then Parliament intended to appropriate the said Revenue, and that it was proper for the Petitioners to apply themselves to the Parliament, and that the Petitioners might have a Report from their Lordships at any time, when they thou
ght it Convenient: The Complaynants therefore Humbly hope, That if this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment enter upon the Consideration of appropriating that Revenue, they may be secured their Just Debt by a Proviso, in any Bill that shall Pass to that effect,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107521:8"/>
They having already made a great Retrospect into that Revenue, and are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at their own Charge and Expences, to make a perfect return into the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer of all the Papists in every County throughout <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> with the true value of their Estates, which will bring in a considerable yearly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue to the Crown, and be a great Satisfaction and Safety both to the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament and the whole Kingdom.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Brief State of the <hi>Allome-Works.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEfore <hi>Allome</hi> was made in <hi>England,</hi> the Kingdom was served with <hi>Romish Allom,</hi> being the Popes Commodity, whereof he made a large Revenue, it being sold here for 50 and 60 <hi>l. per Tun,</hi> and sometimes more: To gain this Manufacture, King <hi>Iames</hi> undertook the management, and perfected the said Work, at a vast Charge; whereupon Sir <hi>Paul Pyndar</hi> and <hi>William Turnor</hi> took a Lease of the said <hi>Allome-Works</hi> for 12 years, paying the yearly Rent of 11000 <hi>l.</hi> to the King, for the sole making and vending of <hi>Allome,</hi> it being the Kings Manufacture by Purchase, whereby many hundreds of poor Families were main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to the great increase of Shipping and Marriners, the saving of much Treasure within the Realm, and his Majesties Kingdoms served with their own Native Commodity.</p>
               <p>This great Work was so acceptable to the Kingdom, that in the Statute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Monopolies 22 <hi>Iacobi,</hi> The Parliament amongst other Grants, made this Provisoe following.</p>
               <p>Provided also and be it Enacted, That this Act or any Declaration, Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soe, Disablement, Penalty, Forfeiture or other thing, before mentioned, shall not extend to any Commission, Grants, Letters Patents or Priviledges heretofore made, or hereafter to be made, of, for, or concerning the digging, compounding or making of <hi>Allom</hi> or <hi>Allom Mines,</hi> But that all and every the said Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Grants, Letter Patents and Priviledges shall be and remain in like force and effect and no other, as free from the Declarations, Provisoes, Penalties and Forfeitures contained in this Act, as if this Act had never been made.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Hillary Term,</hi> 9 Carol. prim. <hi>Edmund</hi> Earl of <hi>Mulgrave</hi> and others, levy a Fine to the King and his Heirs and Successors of the Castle and Mannor of <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave,</hi> and of all the Lands and Tenements in and belonging thereunto, former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly granted to the Ancestors of the said Earl by Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Primo Martij</hi> 9 <hi>Carol. prim.</hi> the King being seized in Fee of the said Mannor of <hi>Mulgrave</hi> with the <hi>Allom Mines</hi> and <hi>Allom Works,</hi> did by his Deed Indented, Demise the same <hi>Allom Mines</hi> and <hi>Allome Works</hi> within the said Mannor of <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave</hi> to Sir <hi>Iohn Gibson</hi> Knight, (Trustee for the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> his Executors and Administrators, for 31 years, after the expiration of the Lease of 12 years, to Sir <hi>Paul Pyndar</hi> and <hi>William Turnor,</hi> under the yearly Rent of 12500 <hi>l.</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of 10860 was to be paid to the King, and 1640 <hi>l.</hi> to the Trustees of the Earl of <hi>Mulgrave.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then the King 4th. of <hi>March,</hi> 9 <hi>Carol. prim.</hi> by his Letters Patents, did Grant to the said <hi>Edmund</hi> Earl of <hi>Mulgrave</hi> and his Heirs the said Mannor of <hi>Mulgrave</hi> reserving the Rents for the <hi>Allome Works.</hi> In the year 1640, the Earl of <hi>Straf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn Gibson</hi> assign over the remainder of their Lease of 31 years to Sir <hi>Paul Pyndar</hi> upon a valuable consideration, which expired <hi>Anno</hi> 1668.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:107521:8"/>And the said <hi>Allome-Works</hi> were accordingly injoyed, and the Rents paid, and his Majesties Title and Interest to the said <hi>Allom-Works</hi> never questioned by any Parliament since <hi>Allom</hi> was first made in <hi>England,</hi> but on the contrary Protected and Strengthned by them until the year 1647. The then Earl of <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave</hi> being very powerful in the House of Lords, and the Ruling Members of the House of Commons, made it his business to destroy the Kings Grant, for the sole making and vending of <hi>Allom</hi> (and those Priviledges and Liberties in the Letters Patents,) under the notion of a Monopoly.</p>
               <p>And consequently made his Addresses by Complaint, to both Houses of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, whereupon concurrent Votes passed, that the said Letters Patents, Granted to Sir <hi>Iohn Gibson</hi> for the sole making and Sale of <hi>Allome</hi> were Illegal and Void, and that the same and all Assignments of them, should be called in and cancelled, (notwithstanding King <hi>Iames</hi> expended 120000 <hi>l.</hi> in accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing the said Art and Manufacture,) without any regard to the Provisoe aforesaid.</p>
               <p>Then he also procured an Order in the Lords House 4<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>May</hi> 1648. that the said Earl should enter into and upon all the said <hi>Allom Works, Mines</hi> and <hi>Houses</hi> and should take the profits of them, from March 31, 1648, by force whereof, he entred and took possession of all the Materials, Works and the Kings Stock.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Paul Pyndar</hi> being so outed by Votes and Orders, without any proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings at Law, or any thing passed into an Act, depended upon the Kings Grant and the equity of his Cause, having advanced many considerable Sums of money upon that Account into the publick receipt of the Exchequer.</p>
               <p>IT is to be remarqued that Sir <hi>Paul Pyndar</hi> paid the Rent of <hi>1640 l.</hi> yearly to the Earl of <hi>Mulgrave</hi> and his Trustees, to the time of those Votes and Resolves in Parliament, notwithstanding the interruption of making <hi>Allome</hi> during the War, and had also paid the Crown Rent of <hi>10860 l.</hi> before hand to that time, although the soyl of the Land whereupon the <hi>Allome-Works</hi> were erected, and the <hi>Mines</hi> or <hi>Rocks</hi> imployed, were not worth <hi>40 l. per annum,</hi> That the Earl of <hi>Mulgrave</hi> and his Trustes enjoyed the said <hi>Works, Materials, Mines</hi> and <hi>Rocks,</hi> and made <hi>Allome,</hi> during the remainder of <hi>Sir Paul Pyndars</hi> Assignment of <hi>Sir John Gibsons</hi> Lease; out of which in equity, <hi>Sir Paul Pyndar</hi> ought to have been repayed all those sums of money due from the Crown up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that <hi>Allom</hi> Account, according to the Conditions and Covenants by way of allowan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and defalcations, contained in the Letters Patents to <hi>Sir John Gibson</hi> and his As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs, which do amount unto the summ of <hi>55301 l. 18 s. 6 d.</hi> as by a stated Accompt under the hands of Auditor <hi>Bingley</hi> and Auditor <hi>Beale</hi> in the Year <hi>1647,</hi> delivered to the Committe of the Revenue appears. And the Earl of <hi>Mulgrave</hi> and <hi>Sir John Monson</hi> having made <hi>15301</hi> Tun of <hi>Allom,</hi> during <hi>Sir Paul Pyndars</hi> Lease by which means they raised a very considerable Estate, that in Iustice and Equity stands accomptable and chargeable to the Administrators and Assigns of <hi>Sir Paul Pyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar,</hi> for that no <hi>Act of Oblivion</hi> hath taken away <hi>Sir Paul Pyndars</hi> Right, neither did he forfeit the same.</p>
               <p>It is very observable, that neither the Heirs, Executors or Administrators of <hi>Sir William Courten</hi> and <hi>Sir Paul Pyndar,</hi> or either of them, have at any time since the Kings Restauration, received any kind of Preferments, Favors or Advantages from the Crown, otherwise than the <hi>Letters Patents</hi> for the recovery of <hi>151612 l. Sterling,</hi> from the <hi>States General</hi> and their Subjects, who pretend they have satisfied the King.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:107521:9"/>
               <head>Postscript. Several Weighty Considerations upon the Letters Patents for special Reprisals against the <hi>States General,</hi> and their Subjects.</head>
               <p>THE said Patent being grounded upon the Laws of Nations, and upon seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Acts of Parliament, Statutes of this Realm; the King was not deceived in his Grant; it being consistent with Prerogative and Law, to resort unto Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Reprisal in times of Peace, without any breach of Amity and Alliance, where the parties will not give satisfaction.</p>
               <p>And if a particular Debt so established, should be Sacrifized for a publick Peace (all Circumstances aforesaid considered) its most reasonable that the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate loss should be recompenced out of the publick Purse, and of this there are divers Presidents and Examples, otherwise it will revive again.</p>
               <p>Treaties of Peace being mutually and reciprocally binding, if either party breaks one link, the whole Chain falls to the ground, and sets the other party at liberty. By the I. and V. Articles of the Treaty Marine, concluded at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> between the King and the States General, on the first day of <hi>December,</hi> 1674. grounded upon the IX. Article of the last Peace, for a Free and undistur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed enjoyment of Trade and Navigation, and to take away all differences by Sea and Land, it was agreed, That it shall and may be lawful for every of his Majesties Subjects freely and safely to Sail and Trade in all Kjngdoms, States and Countries, in Peace, Amity or Neutrality with the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> so that they shall not be hindred or any way molested in their Navigation and Trade by any Military Forces, nor by the Ships of War or Vessels whatsoever, belonging to the <hi>States General</hi> or their Subjects, and being entred into any Road or Port under the Obedience of the said States towards their Voyage, they shall not be obliged to pay any Toll or Custom, only shew their Passports to what places they are bound, and from whence they came. Notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all this, some of the Complaynants have been stopt by a Man of War near <hi>Lillo,</hi> by the Military Forces of the <hi>States</hi> upon that Ancient and Navigable Stream the <hi>Scheld,</hi> since the said Treaty, and their Voyage from <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Antwerp</hi> spoiled, contrary to the said Treaty Marine, and to the Ancient Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the Dukes of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> whereas the <hi>States General</hi> themselves, do claim their freedom of Fishing upon the <hi>English</hi> Coast under the XIV. Article of the same Treaty, concluded between <hi>Henry</hi> the 7th, and <hi>Philip</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> in these Words, <hi>Poterunt ubique ire Navigare per mare secure piscari absque a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquo impedemento licentia sen salvo conducto,</hi> &amp;c. And why the Freedom of Trade shall not be open for <hi>English</hi> men from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Antwerp,</hi> as for <hi>Hollanders</hi> from <hi>Amsterdam</hi> to <hi>Hull</hi> or <hi>Bristoll,</hi> but be forced to unlade their Goods and lade them again at <hi>Flushing</hi> or <hi>Rotterdam</hi>; and from thence to <hi>Antwerp</hi> to the Damage of his Majesties Subjects 200000 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> is a question fit for the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to resolve. And why the <hi>Hollanders</hi> and <hi>Zealanders</hi> are suffered to keep those two small Islands called <hi>Stacia</hi> and <hi>Sabia,</hi> near St. <hi>Christophers,</hi> purposely to take in Goods there, from the <hi>English</hi> Plantations, and Transport them into their own Provinces, without touching in <hi>England,</hi> contrary to the Act of Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, is a National Concern, fit for the Parliaments Inspection and Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letters_patent">
            <pb facs="tcp:107521:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Copy of Letters Patents for Especial Reprisals from the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> (under the Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi>) against the <hi>States General,</hi> and their Subjects, Inrolled in the High Court of Chancery.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HARLES the second by the Grace of God, of England, Scotland, France and Ireland, King, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</hi> To all Christian People to whom these presents shall come, <hi>Greeting: Whereas</hi> our loving Subject <hi>William Courten</hi> 
               <abbr>Esq</abbr> deceased, and his Partners <hi>Anno 1643.</hi> by the depredation and hostile act of one <hi>Geland,</hi> Commander in chief of two Ships belonging to the <hi>East-India</hi> Company of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> was betwéen <hi>Goa</hi> and <hi>Maccao</hi> in the Streights of <hi>Malacca,</hi> deprived and most injuriously spoiled of a Ship named the <hi>Bona Esperanza,</hi> and of her Tackle, Apparel and Furniture, and all the Goods and Lading in her, upon a very hopeful Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Voyage to <hi>China,</hi> which were carried to <hi>Batavia,</hi> and there all <hi>de facto</hi> without due Process of Law confiscated; And that also in the same Year another Ship of our said Subject, called the <hi>Henry Bonad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture</hi> being come on ground near the Island <hi>Mauritius,</hi> was there both Ship and Goods seized upon by some of the Officers and Ministers, and others under the Command of the said <hi>East-India</hi> Company, and utterly detained from the right Owners. <hi>And whereas</hi> the said <hi>William Courten,</hi> and his Assigns in his life time, used all possible endeavours to recover the said Ships and Goods, and to procure further Iustice against the Malefactors, and yet could obtain no Restitution or Satisfaction, whereby they became to be much distressed, and utterly undone in their Estate and Credit: And that thereupon, and upon the most humble supplication and Addresses of <hi>Francis</hi> Carl of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> and <hi>William Courten</hi> 
               <abbr>Esq</abbr> Grand-child and Heir of the said Sir <hi>William</hi> deceased, Sir <hi>John Ayton</hi> and Sir <hi>Edmond Turnor</hi> Knights, <hi>George Carew</hi> and <hi>Charles Whitaker</hi> Esqs; on the behalf of themselves and divers others Interested in the said two Ships <hi>Bona Esperanza</hi> and <hi>Henry Bonadventure,</hi> and in the Estates of the said Sir <hi>William Courten</hi> deceased, Sir <hi>Edward Littleton</hi> Baron. and Sir <hi>Paul Pyndar</hi> knight deceased, that We would take their Case into Our Princely Consideration. <hi>We out of a just Sense</hi> We then had, and still have of their <hi>unjust sufferings</hi> in that business, both by Our own Letters under Our <hi>Sign Manual</hi> to the <hi>States General</hi> of the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> and by Sir <hi>George Downing</hi> Knight and Baron. Our Envoy Extraordinary, to whom We gave special Command so to do; required satisfaction to be made according to the rules of Iustice, and the Amity and good correspondence which We then desired to conserve with them firm and inviolable. <hi>And Whereas</hi> after several Addresses made to the said <hi>States General</hi> by Our said Envoy, and nothing granted effectual for Relief of our said Subjects, (whom We take Our selves in Honour and Iustice, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned to be satisfied and repaid,) We lately commanded the said Sir <hi>George Downing</hi> to intimate and signifie to the said States, that We expected their final Answer concerning satisfaction to be made for the said Ships and Goods by a time then prefixed, and since elapsed; that We might so govern Our selves thereupon, that Our aforesaid Subjects might be relieved according to Right and Iustice; And yet no sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory Answer hath been given, so that We cannot but apprehend it to be, not only a fruitless endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, but a prostituting of Our Honour and Dignity, to make further Application after so many denyals and flightings. <hi>And Whereas John Exton</hi> Doctor of Laws, Iudge of our High Admiralcy Court of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> upon Our Command, to certify to Us the value of the Losses and Dammages sustained by the said <hi>William Courten</hi> and Partners, whose Interest is now vested in Our Loving Subjects, Sir <hi>Edmond Turnor</hi> Knight, and <hi>George Carew</hi> 
               <abbr>Esq</abbr> and Partners, hath upon full Examination, and Proofs thereof made by Witnesses in Our High Court of Admiralty, reported and certified under his Hand, that the same do amount to the sum of One Hundred Fifty One Thousand Six Hundred and Twelve Pounds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now Know Ye,</hi> That for a full restitution to be made to them for their Ships, Goods and Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes; of which the said <hi>William Courten,</hi> and the Assigns of the said <hi>William Courten</hi> and Partners, were so despailed as aforesaid, with all such Costs and Charges as they shall be at for the recovery of the same, We by the Advice of our Privy Council have thought fit, and by these presents do grant Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence and Authority under our great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> unto Our said Subjects <hi>Sir Edmond Turnor</hi> and <hi>George Carew,</hi> their Executors, Administrators, and Assigns, for and on the behalf of themselves, and other Persons interessed as aforesaid, to equipp, victual, furnish, and to set to Sea from time to time, such and so many Ships and Pinaces as they shall think fit. <hi>Provided</hi> always that there be an entry made and recorded in the Admiralty Court of the Names of all Ships and Uessels, and of their Burthen and Ammunition, and for how long time they are victualled; And also of the Name of the Commander thereof, before the same or any of them be set forth to Sea; And with the said Ships and Pinaces by force of Arms to set upon, take and apprehend any of the Ships, Goods, Moneys and Merchandizes of the said States General or any of their Subjects, inhabiting within any their Dominions or Teritories where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever the same shall be found, and not in any Port or Harbour in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> unless it be the Ships and Goods, of the Parties that did the wrong. And the said Ships, Goods, Moneys and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizes, being so taken and brought into some Port of Our Realms and Dominions, an Inventory thereof shall be taken by Authority of Our Court of Admiralty, and Iudgement shall be given in Our Court of Admiralty by the Iudge or Iudges thereof, for the time being, upon proofs made before him, or them, that the said Ships, Goods, Wares, Merchandizes, or Money, did belong to the States General,
<pb facs="tcp:107521:10"/>
or any <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>George Carew,</hi> their Executors, Administrators and Assigns as aforesaid, to retain and keep in their or any of their Possessions, and to make fale, and dispose thereof in open Market or howsoever else, to their and every of their best Advantage and Benefit, in as ample manner as at any time here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore hath béen accustomed by way of Reprisal, and to have and in joy the same as lawful prize, and as their own proper Goods, <hi rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>so that neither Captain Master nor any of the Company, that shall serve in his own Person, or shall promote and advance the said enterprize in manner and form aforesaid, shall in any manner of wise be reputed or challenged for any Offendor against any of Our Laws. And that also it shall be lawful for all manner of persons as well Our Subjects, as any other to buy the said Ships, Goods and Merchandizes so taken, and apprehended by the said Captains, Masters and others, and adjudged as aforesaid, without any damage, loss hinderance trouble or molestation, or incumbrance, to befal the said Buyers, or any of them, in as ample and lawful manner, as if the Ships Goods Wares and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, had been come and gotten by the lawful Traffique of Merchants, or of just prizes in the time of open War.</hi>
               </hi>
               <hi>Provided</hi> always that all Ships, Goods, and Merchandizes, taken by virtue of this Our Comission shall be kept in safety, and no part of them wasted, spoiled, or diminished, or the Bulk thereof broken, until Iudgement have first past as aforesaid. That they are the Ships and Merchandizes of the States General or some of their Subjects aforesaid. And if by colour of this our Comission, there shall be taken any Ships, Goods, or Merchandizes of any of our loving Subjects, or the Subjects of any Prince, or State in good League, or Amity with us (except the States General) or their Subjects as aforesaid, and the Goods therein laden, sold &amp; imbezelled or diminished, or the bulk thereof broken in any place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they shall be adjudged to belong to the States General or some of their Subjects as aforesaid.
That then this Commission shall be of no sufficient Authority to take the said Ships, Goods, &amp; Merchandizes, or to warrant, or save harmless such as shall receive buy or intermeddle therein, but that the prizes so taken, and the said Ship of War, shall be confiscated to Our use. <hi rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>And further We do hereby declare that it is Our will and pleasure, that this Our Commission shall remain in full force and power, to all intents and purposes, until the said Sir Edward Turnor and George Carew their Executors, Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistrators, and Assignes, as aforesaid, shall by vertue thereof have by torce of Arms apprehended, taken, seised, recovered, and received from the said States General, or their Subjects,</hi> one hundred fifty one thousand six hundred and twelve pounds <hi>according to the appraisement to be made by sufficient Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praisers upon Oath nominated and authorised in Our said Court of Admiralty, of all such Ships<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Goods, Wares, and Merchandizes, as shall be taken from the said States General, or any of their Subjects, by vertue of this Commission, or shall otherwise receive satisfaction of the Debt aforesaid, by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position to be made between those of the East-India Company of the Netherlands, and the said Sir Edward Turnor, and George Carew, their Executors, Administrators and Assignes as aforesaid, Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing it so happen, the present difference between Us, and the States General depending upon gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Reprisals, may be agreed and composed, and that in the interim a Peace and good Correspond may be renewed between Us and the said States General; In which case nevertheless, it is Our will and pleasure, that in the execution of this Our Commission no violence shall be done to the Persons of the said Subjects of the said States General, but only in case of resistance, and that after in cold blood, the Subjects of the said States General, if hurt or wounded shall be used with all convenient office of humanity and kindness. And Further Our will and pleasure is, that although it shall happen that all hostility between Us, and the States Generall and Our respective Subjects shall cease, yet this Our Commission shall remain, and be in full force and power, to the said Sir Edmond Turnor and George Carew, their Executors, Administrators, and Assigns, as aforesaid, by vertue thereof to apprehend, take, and seize by force and Arms, so many more of the said Ships and Goods of the States General, or any of their said Subjects, as besides the said sum before mentioned shall countervail satisfie, and pay all such Costs and Charges as the said Sir Edward Turnor and George Carew, their Executors, Administra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, or Assigns as aforesaid, shall from time to time make proof to have disbursed and paid towards the equipping, manning, paying, furnishing, and victualling of the said Ships so licensed and Authorised as aforesaid, by this Our said Commission to be equipped, manned, furnished, and victualled by the said Sir Edward Turnor and George Carew, their Executors, Administrators, and Assigns, as aforesaid for the purpose aforesaid.</hi>
               </hi>
               <hi>And Our Will</hi> and pleasure is, and We do hereby require Our Iudge or Iudges of Our High Court of Admiralty, for the time being, and all other Officers of the Admiralty, and all other Our Iudge, or Iudges, Officers, Ministers, and Subjects whatsoever to be aiding and assisting to the said <hi>Sir Edward Turnor,</hi> and <hi>George Carew,</hi> their Executors, Administrators, &amp; Assigns, as aforesaid, in all points in the due Execution of this Our Royal Commission, and to proceed to adju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication, and adjudge all Ships, Merchandizes, Monies, and Goods by vertue hereof to be taken accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our Princely intention, hereby signified and expressed, and to take care that this Our Royal Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission be duely executed, and favourably interpreted and construed in all respects, to the benefit and best advantage of the said <hi>Sir Edward Turner</hi> and <hi>George Carew,</hi> their Executors, Administrators, and Assignes, as aforesaid. <hi>In Witness</hi> whereof, We have caused these Our Letters to be made Patents.</p>
            <closer>Witness Our self at <dateline>
                  <hi>Westminster</hi>
                  <date> the <hi>19.</hi> day of <hi>May,</hi> in the <hi>17.</hi> Year of Our Reign.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Per ipsum Regem.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
