<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Memento's to the vvorld, or, An historical collection of divers wonderful comets and prodigious signs in heaven, that have been seen, some long before the birth of Christ, and many since that time in divers countries, with their wonderful and dreadful effects together, with ample discourses, and profitable observations, upon that admirable star which appeared at the birth of Christ, to the eastern magi : as also upon that comet which appeared in the constellation of Cassiopea, after the horrid massacre of the French-Protestants, Anno 1572, and several other comets, with their effects to this present time / by W.G., minister of the gospel ; likewise, Stella nova, or, The new star, or, An account of the natural signification of the comet, or blazing-star, that hath so long been visible in England, and other countreys, and is yet hanging over our heads, by William Knight ...</title>
            <author>Greene, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41979</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1813</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13426</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12846767</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12846767</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94465</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A41979)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94465)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 713:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Memento's to the vvorld, or, An historical collection of divers wonderful comets and prodigious signs in heaven, that have been seen, some long before the birth of Christ, and many since that time in divers countries, with their wonderful and dreadful effects together, with ample discourses, and profitable observations, upon that admirable star which appeared at the birth of Christ, to the eastern magi : as also upon that comet which appeared in the constellation of Cassiopea, after the horrid massacre of the French-Protestants, Anno 1572, and several other comets, with their effects to this present time / by W.G., minister of the gospel ; likewise, Stella nova, or, The new star, or, An account of the natural signification of the comet, or blazing-star, that hath so long been visible in England, and other countreys, and is yet hanging over our heads, by William Knight ...</title>
                  <author>Greene, William.</author>
                  <author>Knight, William, fl. 1680-1699. Stella nova.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Haly, for T. Passinger ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680 [1681]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Usually ascribed to William Green, the author of Abyssus mati.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Comets.</term>
               <term>Halley's comet.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-12</date>
            <label>David Karczynski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-12</date>
            <label>David Karczynski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:94465:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:94465:1"/>
MEMENTO's TO THE VVORLD; <hi>OR,</hi> An Hiſtorical Collection of divers Wonderful Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets and Prodigious Signs in Heaven, that have been ſeen, ſome long before the Birth of Chriſt, and many ſince that time in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Countries, with their wonderful and dreadful Effects.</p>
            <p>Together, with ample Diſcourſes, and profitable Obſervations, upon that admirable Star which appeared at the Birth of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to the Eaſtern <hi>MAGI.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo upon that Comet which appeared in the Conſtellation of <hi>Caſſiopea,</hi> after the horrid Maſſacre of the <hi>French-Proteſtants,</hi> Anno 1572. And ſeveral other Comets, with their Effects to this preſent time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> W. G. <hi>Miniſter of the</hi> Goſpel.</p>
            <p>LIKEWISE, STELLA NOVA; OR, <hi>The New</hi> STAR, Or, An Account of the Natural Signification of the COMET, <hi>or</hi> Blazing-Star, That hath ſo long been Viſible in <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> and other Countreys, and is yet hanging over our Heads.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> William Knight, <hi>Student in Aſtrology.</hi>
            </p>
            <l>Men in vain did never gaze,</l>
            <l>When a <hi>Comet</hi> in the Heavens blaze.</l>
            <p>Printed by <hi>T. Haly,</hi> for <hi>T. Paſſinger,</hi> at the Three Bibles, on <hi>London-Bridge,</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:94465:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94465:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Right Honourable Sir PATIENCE WARD,</hi> Lord-Mayor of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IDedicate unto you this <hi>Hiſtorical Collection,</hi> or <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of Comets,</hi> and other prodigious Appearances and Signs in <hi>Heaven:</hi> Theſe are the <hi>Torches</hi> and <hi>Voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of <hi>God</hi> ſpeaking and Preaching out of <hi>Heaven:</hi> for not only his Majeſty is in a lively manner ſet forth unto us, in the <hi>Generation, Magnitude, Figure,</hi> and <hi>Motion</hi> of theſe Bodies, but alſo ſomething is propounded to be further learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them; for whatſoever doth not come to paſs after the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual manner, although it hath <hi>Natural cauſes,</hi> yet it altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther portendeth ſomething or other, and is put for a <hi>Sign</hi> of <hi>certain Events.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore let us neither <hi>deſpiſe</hi> nor <hi>deride</hi> theſe <hi>fore-Meſſengers</hi> of the Lord; neither let us imitate <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> the Emperour, of whom <hi>Suetonius</hi> relates in his Life, That when a <hi>Comet</hi> had been ſhewed unto him, he anſwered jeſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that That <hi>Hairy Comet, or Prodigy, did belong to the King of the</hi> Parthians, who nouriſhed long Hair: As if he had ſaid, <hi>It appeareth not to me, becauſe I am not Hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> But he was ſuddenly puniſhed for his Inſolence, for he dyed ſhortly after; admoniſhing us by his Example, That <hi>it is better ſporting with any thing than with the Works of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:94465:3"/>
It is a great contempt of an Artificer, if he ſet before us an admirable piece of <hi>Work,</hi> and we will not behold nor regard it, the contempt of the <hi>Creature</hi> redoundeth unto the <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</hi> Let us therefore imitate the Emperour <hi>Ludovious Pius,</hi> Son of <hi>Charles</hi> the Great; for when he had beheld a great <hi>Comet,</hi> and <hi>Egmundus</hi> the Aſtrologer being unwilling to make him ſad, alleadged thoſe words of <hi>Jeremiah, Be not diſmayed at the Signs of Heaven, for the Heathen are diſmayed at them,</hi> Jerem. <hi>10. 2.</hi> He devoutly Anſwered, <hi>Let us fear the maker of this Comet, not the Comet it ſelf; and let us praiſe his clemency, who ſeeing we are ſinners, reproveth our ſluggiſhneſs by theſe ſigns.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is Gods clemency before he puniſheth us, to ſend ſome Meſſengers to <hi>fore warn</hi> us. <hi>Herodotus</hi> ſaith, <hi>When God is about to puniſh a City or Nation, he is wont firſt of all to ſignifie it by Signs and wonders.</hi> And a certain famous Aſtronomer thus writeth; <hi>As God is affected towards us, the Stars in his ſtead do ſhine as the Face and Eyes of God, that in them, as in a Glaſs, we may be able to ſee what ſhall come to paſs.</hi> Moreover, theſe <hi>Signs</hi> are Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Glaſſes of Gods wrath, who ſpeaketh to us not onely by <hi>Mans</hi> Tongue, by <hi>Prophets, Apoſtles,</hi> and <hi>Miniſters,</hi> but ſometimes alſo by the Elements themſelves, compoſed into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers forms and Images for the terrour of Men: <hi>That the Name of God is neer,</hi> (that is the Wiſdom, Power, Goodneſs of God) <hi>his wondrous Works do declare</hi> to all judicious be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders; better it were for us not to ſee the works of God, than not to have a ſight of God in them: Now that all Gods Works may lead us unto God himſelf, is the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt Affectionate Servant, VV. G.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="collection_of_accounts">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94465:3"/>
            <head>Memento's to the world.</head>
            <p>IN the year of the world 3854 upon <hi>Demetrius</hi> his death, there appeared a Comet no leſs in ſhew than the Sun. At firſt the Orb was fiery and ruddy, and caſting a clear light, whereby the night was enlightened. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Senec. na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. queſt. l.</hi> 7. <hi>ca.</hi> 15.</note> Afterwards it began to leſſen in bigneſs, and it's bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs vaniſhed, and at laſt quite diſappeared. This was a little before the <hi>Achauk</hi> war.</p>
            <p>In the ſame year that <hi>Mithridates</hi> was born there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared a great Comet. The very ſame doth <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeak of.</p>
            <p>In the time of <hi>Attlus</hi> his reign, there appeared a Comet at firſt but ſmall; but afterwards it elevated and ſpread it ſelf, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Juſtin. lib.</hi> 37. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and came as far as the Equinoctial Circle: ſo that its extent equalized that Region of the heaven which we call the milky way. There alſo appeared another Comet in the firſt year of the Reign of <hi>Mithridates,</hi> which ſhined ſo bright night and day for LXX days together, that the whole heaven ſeemed to be all on fire. For, both the Tayl of it covered the fourth part of the Heaven (or 45 degrees of the upper Hemiſphere) and outvyed the Sun in brightneſs: and alſo it's riſing took up the ſpace of four hours, This hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the year of the world, 3881.</p>
            <p>In the year from the building of the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> 480 blood was ſeen to iſſue from the earth, and milk to ſlow from heaven in the likeneſs of rain. A great Peſtilence fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in the City; and the number of thoſe that periſhed was more than thoſe that remained alive.</p>
            <p>Three Suns appeared the next day after the death of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Caeſar,</hi> which by little and little were brought back in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one ſolar body.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:94465:4"/>
In the year of the world 3960, on the 14 Kalends of <hi>May, Octavianus</hi> having heard of <hi>Caeſar's</hi> death, came to <hi>Naples,</hi> and as he was coming to <hi>Rome,</hi> a vaſt company of his friends met him, and when he entred the City, the Globe of the Sun ſeemed upon his head equally bent, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vellieus lib.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 59.</note> rounded like a bow (as it were putting a Crown upon the head of him that hereafter was to be ſo great a man. And <hi>Julius Obſequens de prodigiis,</hi> ſaith; when he entred the City with a great multitude about him, the Sun being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the round of a pure and unclouded sky, comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſed about with the utmoſt part of the Circle (as the Rainbow is wont to be bent in the Clouds) namely, a Circle of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Senec. na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. quaest. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 28.</note> Colours, as is wont to be in the Rainbow, did at that time compaſs about the Sun, as it is in <hi>Seneca.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the year of the world 3960, on the VI Kalends of October, <hi>Octovianus,</hi> to gain the peoples favour, made thoſe plays that were inſtituted for the finiſhing of <hi>Venus</hi>'s Temple, at his own charges, as pertaining to him, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he came from that ſtock, and which ſome during <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar's</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dio. lib.</hi> 45</note> life-time had undertook that they ſhould ſolemnize, but yet neglected them. Which whilſt he was ſetting forth, <hi>Seneca</hi> ſheweth. That a Comet ſuddenly brak forth, where <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Senec. na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. quaest. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>ca.</hi> 17.</note> he relateth theſe words of <hi>Octavianus</hi> himſelf. In the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry days of my Plays (ſaith he) there was a Comet ſeen ſeven days together in the North-part of the heaven: it aroſe about the eleventh hour of the day, it was clear and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous <note place="margin">
                  <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ton. in Julio. ca.</hi> 88.</note> in all lands. The people then generally thought, that by this Star was ſignified <hi>Caeſar's</hi> ſoul to be received into the number of the Gods. And under that notion was that mark added to the Image of his head, that we (ſaith he) newly conſecrated in the market place; which is alſo to be ſeen in ſome Coyns that were ſtamped after his death, with the Inſcription. DJVL JULII, and ſignified in that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aemed.</hi> 8.</note> of <hi>Virgil, Thy fathers Star appeared in the North.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dio</hi> reporteth, that many Prodiges fore-ran the bondage of <hi>Egypt</hi> under the <hi>Romans;</hi> for it rained (as he ſaith) in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dio. lib.</hi> 51. <hi>pag.</hi> 445.</note> thoſe places, in which before there never any drop had fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, and that not only with water, but with blood alſo;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94465:4"/>
neither did water alone drop from the clouds, but there appeared Armies there alſo. A Dragon of an huge vaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was ſuddenly ſeen among the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> which hiſſed horribly: there appeared alſo Comets, and the images of the dead: the Statues ſeemed to be ſorrowful, and <hi>Apis</hi> made a mournful lowing, and ſhed tears.</p>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the Star that appeared to the Eastern</hi> Magi <hi>after the birth of Christ.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>One notable conſequent of Chriſt's birth was the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parition of a Star unto the wiſe men of the Eaſt, the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi</hi> of <hi>Perſia;</hi> whereby it was manifeſted unto them, that there was born a king of the Jews; which, (doubtleſs) the Spirit of God did reveal unto them by his inward light, without which this ſtar-light had not been ſufficient. Theſe wiſe men were ſuch as had knowledge in Aſtronomy, and ſuch profound Sciences, which the ordinary ſort were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with. But they had as much need of Chriſt as the poor Shepherds of <hi>Bethlehem.</hi> Hereupon they take an exceeding long journey to viſit, yea to worſhip an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant, which to the eye of the world was of a poor deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed eſtate; for now at his birth there was no room for him in the Inne. Theſe Eaſtern <hi>Magi,</hi> or Privy-Counſellours to the King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> (as is probable) come to the Court of the king of <hi>Judah,</hi> and there they ask the Queſtion; <hi>Where is he that is born king of the Jews; for we have ſeen his Star in the Eaſt, and are come to worſhip him, Math.</hi> 2. Strange news in a Princes Court, that men of that dignity of a Countrey ſo far diſtant, and of that wiſdom and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſhould come to worſhip a Child that was born king of the <hi>Jews,</hi> a people ſometime in Captivity under the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> State, and now in likelihood deſpiſed by them, and that his Star ſhould appear unto them in their own Countrey.</p>
               <p>The Gentile Prophet <hi>Balaam</hi> Propheſied, <hi>that there ſhould ariſe a Star out of Jacob, &amp;c.</hi> Numb. 24. 17. and <hi>Zoroa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Juſtin. lib.</hi> 1.</note> king of the <hi>Bactrians,</hi> a man excellent in all learning,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94465:5"/>
left this as a Tradition among the Gentiles. And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it was was more plainly publiſhed by the <hi>Sybiles,</hi> that a Day-ſtar ſhould appear before the riſing of the Sun of Righteouſneſs, This was freſh among the Gentiles until the coming of Chriſt; for <hi>Virgil</hi> (though miſapplying the ſame) ſaith,
<q>Ecce Dionaei praec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t Caeſaris aſtrum.</q>
Rightly applyed thus; That the glorious Star long expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhould precede, and foreſhew the coming of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> Yet <hi>Fulgentius</hi> ſaith, <hi>Puer natus novam Stell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m fabricav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t,</hi> Chriſt being born did of nothing frame this new Star. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fulgent. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="11 words">
                           <desc>〈11 words〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 2. <hi>oper. im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect. in Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>His Star,</hi> becauſe he made it, and his Star becauſe it bare witneſs of him; for the <hi>Magi</hi> being upon the mountain <hi>Victorialis</hi> worſhipping their God (as <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſaith) a Star did appear unto them in the ſimilitude of a little Child, and ſo ſhewed unto them and to all others, that this Child, even the Son of God was born. And as the Poet ſaith,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>This Star ſtill ſhining through the heavens doth glide,</l>
                  <l>And to the Sun which never ſets doth guide.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>This ſtar was no common ſtar,</hi> For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. All ſtars (as we ſee) are carryed from the Eaſt into the VVeſt, but this went from the Eaſt into the South, for <hi>Paleſtine</hi> ſtands Southward from <hi>Perſia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. A ſtar loſeth his light in the day-time, the Sun a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er light obſcuring it but this ſtar was ſeen night and day, becoming the more bright in the midſt of the Sun's bright ſhining.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This Star ſhined not continually; but intermiting for a certain time appeareth again. They ſaw it all the way till they came to <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> as the guide of their journey. But when they were come to <hi>Herod,</hi> it was hidden, and then it appeared again: when they ſtood ſtill, it ſtood ſtill, being ordered for the beſt benefit of them in their journey. And being inſtructed at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that <hi>Bethlehem</hi> was the place where Chriſt ſhould be born; the wiſemen hereupon go to <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> and there by the conduct of the ſtar they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94465:5"/>
find the Babe and his mother, and down they fall and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him, and forth they bring their preſents, or gifts, of <hi>Gold, Frankincenſe,</hi> and <hi>Myrrhe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When they had heard the king (who charged them to go, and bring him word when they had ſound the young Child, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> &amp;c.) they departed, and <hi>Lo the ſtar which they ſaw in the Eaſt, went before them, and ſtood over where the young Child lay.</hi> Either (it ſeemeth) this ſtar appeared unto them being in the Eaſt, and then vaniſhed out of their ſight (which is probable) becauſe it is ſaid, <hi>The ſtar which they ſaw in the Eaſt,</hi> or elſe, it ceaſed to be ſeen when they came to <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, when they ſaw the ſtar, they rejoyced with exceeding great joy, Math.</hi> 2. 10. The ſtar did but appear before, now it goes leiſurely (as it were) and directeth them in their way to the houſe where the Babe lay. This ſtar (as one obſerveth) was not placed where the reſt of the ſtars are, but in the lower Region of the <hi>Air,</hi> for otherwiſe they could not have known by it the place where Chriſt was, ſeeing that a ſtar by reaſon of the great height, ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be over one houſe as well as another within a great Compaſs. Moreover it is noted, that this ſtar went and ſtood over the place where Chriſt was.</p>
               <p>One obſerveth, To <hi>Bethlehem</hi> the <hi>Magi</hi> come to make enquiry after Chriſt, whom none ever ſincerely ſought but <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fullers Piſgah ſight. lib.</hi> 2 <hi>cap.</hi> 14.</note> they found him.</p>
               <p>This ſtar by moving (probably in the low Region of the <hi>Air,)</hi> ſheweth them their way, by ſtanding ſtill at the end of their journey; Coming into the houſe they find the Royal Babe, and preſent him with gifts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:94465:6"/>
               <head>Of other great Lights, Comets, and Ominous Stars, &amp;c. appearing after the birth of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saul</hi> breathing out threatnings and ſlaughter againſt the Diſciples of the Lord, obtains of the High-prieſt <hi>Annas,</hi> (as it is <hi>Act.</hi> 4. 6.) and the Councel, of which he was then Preſident, letters to the Synagogue of <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> that if he found any that were Chriſtians, he ſhould bring them bound to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that they might be puniſhed. And as he came nigh to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> at midday a light from heaven, above the brightneſs of the Sun, ſhined round about him, and them that journeyed with him: and when they were all fallen to the earth, he heard a voice ſpeaking to him in the Hebrew Tongue, <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me? it is hard for Thee to kick againſt the pricks, &amp;c..</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the men that journeyed with <hi>Saul,</hi> were ſo amazed, that they were ſpeechleſs, ſeeing indeed a light, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſound of words, but neither ſeeing Chriſt which ſpake, nor underſtanding any thing that he ſpake, Act. 9. 1, 7. XXII. 5. 14. XXVI. 12. 18.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saul</hi> aroſe from the earth, and being blinded with the glory of the light, being led by the hand, he comes to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcus,</hi> Act. 9. 8. &amp; 22. 11. And he was three days with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſight, and did neither eat nor drink. <hi>Ananias</hi> being ſent unto <hi>Saul,</hi> entred into the houſe, and laying his hands on him, ſaid, <hi>Brother Saul, the Lord Jeſus which appeared un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee in the way as thou cameſt, hath ſent me that thou maiſt receive thy ſight, and be filled with the Holy-Ghoſt, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently there fell from his eyes as it were ſcales, and he received his eye ſight forthwith, Act.</hi> 9. 9. 18. And <hi>Ananias</hi> ſaid, <hi>The God of our fathers hath choſen Thee, that Thou ſhouldeſt know his will, and ſee that Juſt one, and ſhould'ſt hear the voice from his mouth; for Thou ſhalt be a witneſs before all men of thoſe things that Thou hast heard and ſeen, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Saul</hi> aroſe, and was baptized, and when he had received meat he was ſtrengthened.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:94465:6"/>
But what was revealed from the Lord to <hi>Saul</hi> at <hi>Damaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> that he ſhould do, St. <hi>Luke</hi> ſheweth not in the <hi>Acts;</hi> but out of thoſe things which in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Galathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> he ſaith hapned to him immediatly after his converſion, it appears, that among other things it was commanded him that he ſhould not confer with fleſh and blood, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to them that were Apoſtles before him, but that he ſhould go for ſome time into <hi>Arabia,</hi> or places near <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> where he ſhould receive the knowledge of the Goſpel: <hi>Not being taught of men, but by the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Jeſus Chriſt, Gal.</hi> 1. 12, 16, 17. <hi>Saul</hi> then returns to <hi>Damaſcus, verſe</hi> 17. and tarries with the Diſciples there a few days, and ſtraitway in the Sinagogue he preached that Chriſt is the ſon of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the Signs that appeared before the deſtruction of the City and Temple of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>by the</hi> Romans.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſaith, that Seducers and authours of lies <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſib. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. hist. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 8. <hi>Joſeph. de bello Judaic. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>ca.</hi> 12.</note> againſt God, deceived that wretched people of the Jews before the deſtruction of the City and Temple at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem;</hi> ſo that they neither marked thoſe Prodigious ſignes foreſhewing the deſolations to come, nor gave any credit thereunto; but as aſtoniſhed, both blind and ſenſeleſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned the divine demonſtrations.</p>
               <p>A ſtar ſtood over the City like a ſword, and a Comet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during the ſpace of a whole year. Again, at the feaſt of unleavened bread, on the eighth day of the moneth of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pril</hi> (a little before their rebellion and warlike tumult) in the night at nine of the Clock, ſo great a light over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread the Altar and the Temple, that it ſeemed to be clear day, continuing the ſpace of half an hour. At the ſame feaſt the Eaſt gate of the inner Temple, though of braſs, and moſt ſtrong, ſo that in the evening twenty men could
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94465:7"/>
ſcarce ſhut it, being bolted with iron bars, and ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with long poſts and pillars: in the night-time about the ſixth hour was ſeen to have opened voluntarily of it ſelf.</p>
               <p>A few days after the feaſt <hi>(viz. May</hi> 21.) there was ſeen the figure and ſhape of the Devil. Before Sun-ſet there were ſeen in the air throughout the Countrey, Chariots and armed Souldiers marching in the Clouds, and encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing the City round about.</p>
               <p>In the feaſt of <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> when the Prieſts (after their manner) went into the Temple in the night ſeaſon to offer ſacrifice; they reported that they heard a commotion, and a ratling ſound with this voice, <hi>Migremus hinc,</hi> let us go hence. The afflictions which followed hereupon were cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent to the ſigns. Eleven hundred thouſand of the Jews periſhed in the ſix moneths ſiege of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> But for thoſe that periſhed out of <hi>Jeruſalem, Lipſius</hi> hath made <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Juſt. Lipſ. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Conſtant. cap.</hi> 21.</note> a large Catalogue out of <hi>Joſephus</hi> the Jew, who was a commander in that war, and wrote the Hiſtory of it, which number of the dead being added to the eleven hnndred thouſand that periſhed at the ſiege of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> makes up the number of 1337490. an innumerable company, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ommitted, that periſhed through famine, baniſhment, and other miſeries.</p>
               <p>Whilſt diverſe men were plotting and conſpiring againſt the Emperour <hi>Domitian;</hi> among other ſigns which then were ſeen, there appeared for many dayes together round <note place="margin">Pedocot. Mexio. histor. Roman. Imperat.</note> about the Sun a great bright ſhining Crown, that did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs it about, which reſembled the Rain-bow againſt foul weather, but that was a whole Crown that did environ the Sun in ſuch manner, as it bereaved and Eclipſed the ſame of its brightneſs. Which ſignal, men did interpret to ſignifie a change and alteration in the Empire, with the death of <hi>Domitian.</hi> And in as much as <hi>Stephanus</hi> in Greek ſignifies a Crown, there were ſome which conceived, that <hi>Stephanus</hi> who was Steward to his wife and Empreſs <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micilla</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:94465:7"/>
ſhould kill him, notwithſtanding thev knew nothing of the Conſpiracy of <hi>Stephanus</hi> and others then againſt him, by whom he was ſhortly after ſlain.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Emperour prepared to ſight with <hi>Maxentius,</hi> and ſtood in fear and doubt of the iſſue of the Battel, as well for the great number of the Enemies, as for <hi>Maxentius</hi> his enchantments, wherewith he amazed the World, he was in great care and perplexity. And as he gave credit to the Chriſtians, and was their Protector and Defender, (albeit, he was not yet baptized) but had a firm ſtedfaſt hope in Jeſus Chriſt.) <hi>Euſebius Caſſiodorus,</hi> and others write, That he ſaw in the Heavens a Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Pillar, of a Fiery Colour, in form of a Croſs, and therewith he heard this voice, <hi>In hoc ſigno vinces,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, or by vertue of this ſign thou ſhalt overcome. The which Viſion ſo amazed the Emperour, that he miſtruſting his own ſight, demanded of them that were preſent, whether they perceived the Viſion, which when all with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent had aſſirmed, the wavering mind of the Emperour was ſetled with that wonderful ſight, ſo as he preſently aſſured himſelf of Victory, and therefore cauſed the ſign of the Croſs to be made in his Imperial Standard; and joyning with the Enemy right over againſt <hi>Rome,</hi> near to a Bridge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the River <hi>Tiber,</hi> called <hi>Pons Milvius,</hi> at the beginning of the fight <hi>Maxentius</hi> was overcharged by <hi>Conſtamius</hi> his Vantgard, and fled: and entring upon the Bridge which he had made of Barks and Boats near to the other; both he and his <hi>Horſe</hi> fell into the River, where he was drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which Bridge himſelf had cauſed to be made; to the end therewith, to have deceived his Enemy.</p>
               <p>In the dayes of <hi>Sigebert, Chitperic,</hi> and <hi>Gunthran,</hi> Kings of <hi>France,</hi> certain Comets and prodigious ſigns were ſeen in the Heavens. A fire falling from <hi>Heaven,</hi> conſumed the City of <hi>Orleans</hi> (whereof, and the Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory about it, <hi>Gunthran</hi> was King) and the City of <hi>Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux,</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:94465:8"/>
together with the fruits of the Earth. There followed atmoſt throughout all <hi>France</hi> a malignant Cough and bloody Flux, which deſtroyed multitudes of men and Women; by which means that evil Woman <hi>Auſtigil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis,</hi> Wife of King <hi>Gunthran,</hi> periſhed. The ſaid King <hi>Gunthran</hi> died within a year following.</p>
               <p>After the death of <hi>Theodoricus,</hi> who had made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Lord of all <hi>Italy,</hi> there appeared many ſigns in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: In the North the Heaven ſeemed fiery, and certain ſhining Spears were ſeen, and the Moon was much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured. And a Comet appeared at <hi>Tholouſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Terrible ſigns were ſeen by Night in <hi>Italy</hi> in the year of our Lord 570. For fiery ſwords appeared in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and blood diſtilled from the Clouds, which ſignified the effuſion of much blood, which hapned afterwards, and many great ſtorms continuing many dayes. The River <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> was increaſed with ſo great a force of waters, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny people that lived in low places were drowned. Two Animals appeared in the form of a Man and Woman, from the Morning till Nine of the Clock, with long hair hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down to the Loynes. The Water covered their other parts. And they write, That a Mountain in <hi>France,</hi> with a great Noiſe was cleft aſunder.</p>
               <p>In the time of the Emperour <hi>Juſtinian</hi> the firſt, (as <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copius</hi> writeth,) for the greateſt part of one whole year, the Sun gave ſo little Light, that it was but equal to, or little more then the Light of the Moon, the Sky being clear, and without Clouds, or any other thing to ſhadow the ſame. And ſo without any apparent occaſion it was obſcured all that time; which (as it was afterward conjectured) was the Prognoſtick of the Famine and want of grain, which generally enſued throughout all the World, and of the Wars and effuſion of Blood which followed in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94465:8"/>
                  <hi>Italy;</hi> and of the taking, burning, and deſtruction of <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>Totila.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the time of the Emperour <hi>Heraclius,</hi> (who took upon him the Government of the Empire in the year of our Lord 611.) at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> Fire fell from Heaven, and there appeared a great Bow in the Heavens, ſo that Men thought that the end of the World was at hand, by reaſon of the great Thundrings and Lightnings. There followed a moſt grievous Peſtilence, which conſumed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in the Summer Months. And many Prodigies, and dreadful things appeared at this time in <hi>Greece,</hi> which ſeemed to portend the future Calamities under <hi>Mahomet.</hi> And in one and the ſame year a very bright Comet was ſeen at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and a Child was born with four Feet. And in the Iſle <hi>Delon,</hi> two very great Monſters were ſeen, having altogether humane ſhape. And many other things here and there like unto this did appear.</p>
               <p>In the Reign of the Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> IV. an hairy Comet appeared three Months, which was the forerunner of great Slaughters: And there happened ſo many, and ſo great Tempeſts and alterations in the air, as it ſeemed, that the four Elements had conſpired againſt Mankind; for the Winds were ſo furious and violent, as that they overthrew many buildings, and rent up many Trees by the roots, and the rain likewiſe was ſo great, and tempeſtuous, as it deſtroyed all their Tillage, as well for Bread-Corn as all other kinds of Herbs and Seeds. And therewith fell an infinite number of Thunderbolts, and Fires from Heave, which ſlew a great number of Men and Cattel, eſpecially on this ſide of the <hi>Alps.</hi> And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a great Eclipſe of the Sun and Moon, the City of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia</hi> was almoſt utterly deſtroyed by a raging Peſtilence, ſo that the People which ſurvived, fled to the Mountains, and graſs grew in the City.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:94465:9"/>
About the time of King <hi>Luitprand</hi> King of the <hi>Lombards,</hi> two Comets appeared in the Month of <hi>January,</hi> and the Sun was darkned, and loſt his light for fifteen dayes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of one went before the Sun, the other followed it in the Evening.</p>
               <p>About the Death of Pope <hi>Leo</hi> tho third, who crowned and declared <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, King of <hi>France</hi> to be Emperour, a Comet appeared, and the Sun loſt his light for Fifteen dayes. This Pope died, <hi>Anno</hi> 816.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond year of <hi>Lotharius,</hi> Son of the Emperour <hi>Ludovicus Pius,</hi> and Grandſon to <hi>Charles</hi> the great, there appeared a Comet; Hail of great bigneſs fell in <hi>France,</hi> which ſlew many men, and much Cattel. There was alſo ſeen in thoſe Hail-ſtones Corn of a wonderful Length; and of an hard ſubſtance. An Earthquake alſo ſhook <hi>Italy,</hi> and in certain places divers Mountains were overwhelm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and divers Cities periſhed. <hi>Lotharius</hi> warred againſt his brethren <hi>Lewes,</hi> and <hi>Charles;</hi> and a great Battel being fought, the Flower of the <hi>French</hi> Nobility was ſlain, and in number more men died, than in any other Battel had hapned in <hi>France</hi> ever ſince the Battel which was fought between <hi>Ecius</hi> and <hi>Attila,</hi> King of the <hi>Hunnes</hi> in the Fields of <hi>Catalonia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About this time, an innumerable Company of Locuſts, having ſix Wings, and two Teeth harder than ſtones, covered the Earth in <hi>France</hi> like Snow. At length being caſt into the Sea, and upon Land by the Shore, there fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowed great putrefaction; which infecting the Air, cauſed a general deſtruction of men.</p>
               <p>In the beginning of the Reign of the Emperour <hi>Lewes</hi> the Second, for three dayes it rained Blood at the City of <hi>Breſcia</hi> in <hi>Lombardy</hi> ſo freſh, and ſo perfect, as if it had
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94465:9"/>
been of a Bull, or of ſome other Beaſt lately killed.</p>
               <p>In the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the Son of <hi>Edgar</hi> King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> appeared a Comet, after which followed a great Dearth and Mortality to men, and murrain upon Beaſts, and there aroſe a great contention between the Prieſts and Monks.</p>
               <p>In the days of Pope <hi>Leo,</hi> VII. the Sun ſeemed to reign blood, as <hi>Maſſeus</hi> writeth. and after it followed a great Peſtilence among men.</p>
               <p>In the firſt year of Pope <hi>Martin</hi> III. a great Blazing Star appeared in <hi>Italy,</hi> after which followed an extream Famine. And again, the Sun appeared very dreadful. <hi>Martin</hi> died, <hi>Anno</hi> 947.</p>
               <p>A little before the death of the Emperour <hi>Otho</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, many Prodigies appeared in <hi>Italy;</hi> for a Stone of wonderful bigneſs fell from Heaven in the midſt of a great ſtorm and tempeſt. And the ſign of the Croſs appeared on the Garments of many; and ſome of them were of a bloody colour; which many did interpret to portend great Slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and the Calamity of the Church. In <hi>Italy</hi> a Comet of wonderful bigneſs appeared, preſaging the Famine which followed.</p>
               <p>In the time of Pope <hi>John</hi> XVI. appeared a Comet, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which followed both Famine and Peſtilence, with terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Earthquakes, which ſhook both <hi>Benevent</hi> and <hi>Capua. John</hi> died <hi>Anno</hi> 985.</p>
               <p>In the third year of the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, a Comet appeared dreadful to behold, diſperſing his Flames hither and thither. And in the ſeventh year of his Reign there was a great Eclipſe of the Sun, and the Moon ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ee to be turned into Blood; and there was a great Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94465:10"/>
and a burning Torch like a Bow fell from Heaven with great noiſe; there ſuddenly followed a great Famine, and a little after a great Peſtilence raged almoſt all the World over, but chiefly in <hi>Italy,</hi> ſo that the dead were account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more than the living; And in <hi>Lorrain</hi> there was a Fountain turned into Blood.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the Third came to the Empire, <hi>Anno</hi> 1040<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and in his time there was ſeen a Fiery Beam of wonderful greatneſs between the South and the Eaſt, running upon the Sun, which at the Sun ſetting fell upon the Earth.</p>
               <p>In the Reign of <hi>Herold</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> a fearful Comet appeared, which laſted ſeven days, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> being now ready for a War.</p>
               <p>In the time of King <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, a Blazing Star appeared upon <hi>Palm Sunday,</hi> being the <hi>16th.</hi> of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Holin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheds Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle in</hi> Will. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>April,</hi> 1076. about ſix of the Clock, when the Air was fair and clear. About the ſame time was a general Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake in <hi>England,</hi> and in the Winter following, a Froſt that continued from the firſt of <hi>November,</hi> until the middle of <hi>April.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the time of <hi>Baldwin</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> an unuſual Star appeared the firſt week in <hi>Lent,</hi> in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening in the South Weſt, and ſhined at one and the ſame hour for Twenty Five dayes. After this, were ſeen two Moons a little before day, one in the Eaſt, and the other in the Weſt; and not long after a Comet putting forth long and flaming Hairs, appeared, which <hi>Elmerus</hi> the Monk beholding, ſaid, did threaten the deſtruction of that Countrey.</p>
               <p>In the year 1094<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the Reign of <hi>William Refus,</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> many hideous ſights were ſeen in <hi>England,</hi> as Hoſts of Men fighting in the Air, flaſhes of Fire, Comets, and falling Stars, and ſuch like Prodigies. And the ſame year both <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Normandy</hi> were ſore vexed with Mortality both of Men and Beaſts, inſomuch that Tillage
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94465:10"/>
of the Ground was laid aſide in divers places, by reaſon whereof there followed great Dearth and Famine.</p>
               <p>About the year of our Lord 1100. Fiery Swords appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Heaven, which being diſperſed through the whole Heaven, were ſeen the greateſt part of the Night, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry many Stars ſeemed to fall from Heaven upon the Earth. And the ſmoak went out with an hiſſing, as by Waters poured upon it. A moſt ſharp Winter followed, and a great Famine followed it, and a Mortality of Men, and murrain of Beaſts, both Wild and Tame; and Birds fighting together in great Numbers, deſtroyed one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; Moreover, a great Earthquake in <hi>Italy</hi> laſted the ſpace of Forty days; ſo that divers Towns and Villages were overthrown. And the Moon being in an Eclipſe, was turned into a bloody colour. And a Woman brought forth a Monſter, having a double Body, having alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Face of a Man, and behind the Face of a Dog. About this time died <hi>Johannes de Temporibus,</hi> who had been an <hi>Eſquire</hi> to the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lived 361 Years.</p>
               <p>In the Seventh year of <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt, King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> upon a Friday night in the firſt week in <hi>Lent,</hi> there was ſeen a ſtrange Star between the South and the Weſt, which appeared every Night at an hour, and ſo continued for the ſpace of Twenty Five dayes; and over againſt that Star out of the Eaſt appeared a great and bright Beam, which ſtretched it ſelf toward the ſaid Star. And not long after were ſeen two Moons, one in the Eaſt, the other in the Weſt.</p>
               <p>In the Thirteenth year of the ſame Kings Reign, at <note place="margin">Fabian. <hi>Chronicle.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Shrewsbury</hi> was a great Earthquake, and at <hi>Nottingham</hi> from Morning until Evening. The River of <hi>Trent</hi> was ſo dryed up, that men went over on foot dry. Thereupon followed an hard VVinter, great Mortality of People, and ſcarcity of Victuals by reaſon of the great murrain of Beaſts. A Comet, or Blazing Star appeared in a ſtrange form, for riſing in the Eaſt, when once it came aloft in the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94465:11"/>
Firmament, it kept not its courſe forward, but ſeemed to go backward, as if it had been retrograde.</p>
               <p>About the year 1157 three Suns appeared together in the Weſt; after two hours the other ſailing, that which was in the middle did alſo ſet. After the ſame manner in the next year three Moons appeared, and in the middle of one the ſign of the Croſs. Theſe ſigns were interpreted by ſome to be a token of the grievous diſcord of the Cardinals in the Election of the Pope; and of the Princes in the Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Emperour. Earthquakes about this time where almoſt every where, and did ſhake ſome Provinces many years, eſpecially <hi>Syria,</hi> and <hi>Silicia<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> in which many Cities did long ſhake, and ſome of them were overwhelmed with great deſtruction of People.</p>
               <p>In the third year of <hi>John,</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> there were ſeen in <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> five Moons; one in the Eaſt, the ſecond in the VVeſt, the third in the North, the fourth in the South, and the fifth (as it were) ſet in the midſt of the other, having many Blazing Stars about it, and went five or ſix times encompaſſing the other, as it were the ſpace of one hour, and ſhortly after vaniſhed away. The following VVinter was extreamly cold, more than the natural courſe had been aforetime; and in the Spring time there fell ſuch abundance of Rain, as cauſed the Rivers to ſwell with high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er floods then they had been accuſtomed, which cauſed great inundations. This Kings Reign was full of troubles; Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> III. Excommunicated and depoſed him, and put <hi>England</hi> in interdict, beſtowed it upon <hi>Philip Auguſt,</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> upon condition of Conquering it, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards takes off the Interdict, receives homage from King <hi>John,</hi> and makes <hi>England</hi> a fee of the <hi>Roman</hi> See, and that King his Vaſſal.</p>
               <p>In the year of our Lord 1256<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the Reign of King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> III. many wonders hapned. A Comet appeared; the Sea roſe with moſt high Tides; Rivers were ſo filled with abundance of water by reaſon of the great and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued Rain, that wonderful Flouds followed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereupon;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94465:11"/>
and many high Buildings were beaten down by the force of Tempeſts.</p>
               <p>In the ſame Kings Reign, there appeared a Comet very dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to behold, for the ſpace of 30 days together. Moreover on the Coaſt of <hi>England,</hi> there was a great Battel among the Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the Sea, ſo that there were eleven Whales caſt on Land, beſide other huge and monſtrous Fiſhes, which appeared to be dead of ſome hurts received: And one of thoſe mighty Fiſhes coming into the <hi>Thames</hi> alive, was purſued by the Fiſher men, and it could ſcarce paſs through the Arches of <hi>London-Bridge.</hi> At length with Darts and other ſuch Weapons, they ſlew him before the Kings Mannor at <hi>Mortlack</hi> whither they followed him. There was alſo a great ſound heard the ſame Year in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry parts of <hi>England</hi> at one and the ſame time, as if it had been the noiſe of ſome mighty Mountain that had fallen into the Sea.</p>
               <p>A Comet of notable magnitude appeared in the Heavens in the Year 1263, riſing from the Eaſt, above three Months with great brightneſs, and did ſend forth his rays to the midſt of Heaven, ſetting towards the Weſt: When he firſt appeared Pope <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> IV<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> began to be Sick, but in the ſame Night that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> Dyed, he began to diſappear.</p>
               <p>Soon after the Corronation of <hi>Edward</hi> I. King of <hi>England,</hi> there hapned ſuch an Earth-quake with Lightning and Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and therewithal the appearing of a Burning-Drake, and a Blazing-Star, or Comet, that the people were filled with great fear and aſtoniſhment.</p>
               <p>In the time of <hi>Wenceſlaus</hi> the Third, King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> there Appeared in the Heaven a large Comet, which did preſage the great Deſtruction which followed; in which Year upon Saint <hi>Andrew</hi>'s Day there hapned a great Earth-quake, which laſting divers Days by Intervals, overthrew many Buildings.</p>
               <p>In the Year 1314, Three Moons Appeared together in the Heaven, and a Comet was ſeen in the North, which laſted Three Months: It vaniſhing, in the ſame Year in the Month of <hi>November, Phillip</hi> King of <hi>France</hi> dyed, a Boar breaking the Legs of his Horſe as he was Hunting, he fell from his Horſe, of which fall he dyed ſhortly after.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:94465:12"/>
In the Ninth Year of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Second, before <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> a blazing-Star, or Comet, Appeared in the North part of the Firmament, for the ſpace of a Month together: After it followed a woful Famine, for Victuals was ſo ſcant and dear, and other Grain raiſed to ſo high a price, that the poor people were conſtrained through Famine, to eat the Fleſh of Horſes, Dogs, and other wild Beaſts, and many ſtarved, having nothing to feed upon throughout the Land. After this Dearth and ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of Victuals, enſued a great Mortality of people; ſo that what with the War with the <hi>Scots,</hi> and with the Famine and Peſtilence, the people of <hi>England</hi> were wonderfully waſted and conſumed.</p>
               <p>In the Year 1337, in the Tenth Year of the Reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> III. a Comet, or Blazing-Star Appeared with long and terrible Streams paſſing from it, which continued thirty Days. Soon after the <hi>French</hi> burnt <hi>South-hampton,</hi> which they almoſt wholly conſumed to Aſhes, and did many other miſchiefs with their Ships on the Coaſts of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Year 1351, in the North there Appeared a Comet in the Month of <hi>December,</hi> which being extinct, violent Winds followed, and a Coeleſtial Beam was ſeen to glide along the Heavens, the former part of it burning. And they write, that before the Death of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> VI. there was ſo great a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Sun, as the like had not been before ſeen.</p>
               <p>In the Month of <hi>March,</hi> in the Year of our Lord 1402, and third Year of <hi>Henry</hi> IV. King of <hi>England,</hi> there Appeared a Blazing-Star, firſt between the Eaſtern part of the Firmament, and the North flaſhing forth Fire and flames round about, and laſtly, ſhooting forth Fiery ſtreams towards the North, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewing (as was thought) the great effuſion of Blood which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed about the parts of <hi>Wales</hi> and <hi>Northumberland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Year 1438, there was a great Eclipſe of the Sun, and divers Wars and Diſſentions followed. A Comet alſo Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and there followed a ſlaughter of Men in <hi>Liege.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Three and Thirtieth Year of the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> VI. King of <hi>England,</hi> during the Civil Wars between the Houſes of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> and <hi>York,</hi> a Comet Appeared in the Month of <hi>June,</hi> the Beams whereof extended it ſelf into the South, of which King <hi>Henry</hi> and his Son felt the ſad effects.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:94465:12"/>
In the Year 1456, a Comet was ſeen in the Eaſt in the month of <hi>June,</hi> in the Fifteenth degree of <hi>Cancer,</hi> a very great Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake followed on the <hi>5th</hi> Day of <hi>December,</hi> at Eleven a Clock at Night; And another on the Thirtieth Day of the ſame Month, ſuch as in the memory of Man there had not any where been ſeen the like for vehemency; eſpecially in <hi>Apulia, Naples, Beneventum,</hi> and many other Cities and Towns round about, many Temples and Pallaces, and other Houſes, were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed, with the Deſtruction of many Men and Cattel. The like hapned at <hi>Cajeta, Capua, Averſa,</hi> and the reſt of the Cities of old <hi>Campania.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Year 1457. another followed, which they called a black Comet, in the Month of <hi>June,</hi> in the 20 degree of <hi>Piſces,</hi> which was ſeen for the ſpace of a month, and did variouſly affect the minds of Men.</p>
               <p>A great Comet Appeared throughout the month of <hi>January,</hi> in the beginning of the Year 1472, in a Fiery colour, with long and black hairs bending towards the Weſt, whoſe body was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the entrance of <hi>Libra;</hi> afterwards it bended it ſelf onely in the North, that it might be judged that it went out without the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> and it continued Fourſcore days. But this Comet being ſcarce diſſolved, another Appeared, of a fiery hair, which ſeemed to be ſeated in the Sign of <hi>Aries,</hi> and its Tayl ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out it ſelf towards the Eaſt: A grievous Drought follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and a Peſtilence, and moſt cruel and bloody Wars in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places.</p>
               <p>There were Two Comets ſeen before the Battel of <hi>Creſcy</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> where though the <hi>Engliſh</hi> got a great Victory over the <hi>French</hi> by the Sword, ſo it ſeemeth (as our Chronicles do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late) that the Sword of the Deſtroying Angel ſlew a multitude of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at home.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Phillip</hi> the firſt, King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and Father to the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> V. being at <hi>Tudele</hi> of <hi>Duero,</hi> there Appeared a ſtrange Comet in the Firmament, foreſhewing (as they ſaid afterward) the Approaching Death of King <hi>Phillip,</hi> which happened ſoon after in the City of <hi>Burgos,</hi> to the general grief of all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; the Comet ſtill Appearing, whereunto he did Attribute his Death, ſaying often in his pains and agonies, <hi>Ha Cometa,</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:94465:13"/>
                  <hi>ha Cometa.</hi> He dyed in the Year of our Lord, 1506, haveing Reigned one Year and Ten Months: His Body was laid ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Years after by his Son <hi>Charles</hi> in the Royal Chappel of <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nado,</hi> having remained in divers places.</p>
               <p>In Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Reign, in the Year of our Lord, 1556, a Blazing-Star was ſeen at all times of the Night, on the Sixth, Seventh, Eighth, Ninth, and Tenth of <hi>March,</hi> a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Burning of <hi>Thomas Cranmer,</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Horrid Maſſacre of the Proteſtants in <hi>France,</hi> being Acted <hi>Auguſt</hi> 24, &amp;c. 1572, a Grave Writer relates, That about a quarter of a Year after, <hi>Viz. November</hi> 17. there Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared a Star in the Conſtellation of <hi>Caſſiopea, Mirae magnitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinis, &amp; perſpicua luce praefulgida,</hi> of Wonderful bigneſs, and very reſplendent with a perſpicuous light; He ſaith, That many Men paſſed their Judgments upon it, <hi>Eruditorum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> hac dere jactati verſus; Beza</hi> hath divers Verſes upon it, I take it the laſt was this,
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tuvero</hi> Herodes <hi>Sangui notente cave.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And thou bloody <hi>Herod</hi> beware.</l>
                  </q>
Pointing (I ſuppoſe) to the <hi>French</hi> King, <hi>Charles</hi> the IX. and others, Authors of and Actors in that Barbarous and Bloody Tragedy. He addeth, <hi>Illa totos novem menſes in coeto Emicait.</hi> That Star ſhined clearly for the ſpace of nine whole Months in the Heaven. The King himſelf Dyed <hi>May</hi> 30. 1574. about one year and three quarters after the Maſſacre; and one year and an half after the appearing of the <hi>Comet.</hi> Of whom my Author ſaith; <hi>Profluvio ſanguinis illum laboraſſe certum eſt. Conſtans vero fert fama, illum dum evarijs corporis partibus ſanguis emanaret, in lecto ſaepè volutatum, inter horribilium blaſphemiarum diras, quibus ab ineunte aetate aſſuetus erat, Monmoren ciorum nomen ſaepè concita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ excandeſcentiâ ſolitum appelare. Quum vero magna erat veneni ſuſpitiorut vomitus facilior eſſet, ajunt pulvinaribus impoſitum, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuo capite, &amp; Paulo erectoribus ſurſum pedibus, tantam ſanguinis vim projeceſſe, ut paucas poſt horas Mortuus fuerit: inter ultimas autem voces meras Blaſphemias auditas fuiſse.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:94465:13"/>
It ſeemeth before he died he laid Siege to <hi>Rochel,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> there ſtood upon their Guard, and would not put themſelves into the Butchers hands; where the Duke of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merle,</hi> Uncle to the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> was ſlain, and about twenty thouſand others; whereof many (not moſt of them) were Actors in that prodigious Cruelty: and the reſt ſeemed to have made themſelves acceſſary to it by this after Act, in joyning with the Murtherers to root out the remainders of the <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> and King of <hi>Poland,</hi> ſucceeded his Brother <hi>Charles,</hi> by the Name of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, and became very deſpicable; the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> giving him Check-mate, his Subjects ſlighting him, and adhering to <hi>Guiſe.</hi> The King finding him too ſtrong for him, took a courſe to Entrap him, ſending for him to <hi>Blois,</hi> under pretence of making him Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour over the Kingdom under him, and cauſed him there to be Stabbed with his Brother the <hi>Cardinal.</hi> And thus fell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother principal Contriver of, and Agent in the Maſſacre; and it is thought in the ſame Chamber where that <hi>Cockatrice-Egg</hi> was hatched. But upon this Execution the <hi>French</hi> were more enraged againſt their King then ever, taking the Government of the Kingdom out of his Hands, as if he had been already dead, and ſetting up the Duke of <hi>Mayenne,</hi> Brother to <hi>Guiſe,</hi> as their Chief, who by the help of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> headed the Faction, and carried on the Deſign. The King reduced to great extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, was conſtrained to deſire aid from the King of <hi>Navar,</hi> and his <hi>Proteſtant</hi> followers, whom he had ſo cruelly perſecuted; who proved faithful to him, being in a likely way to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhed him: But one <hi>James Clement</hi> a <hi>Jacobine Monk,</hi> ſtabbed him about the year 1589.</p>
               <p>His younger Brother the Duke of <hi>Alenzon,</hi> being choſen by the Netherlanders for their Governour, and Protector againſt the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and moſt unworthily taking advantage of that truſt, they repoſed in him to oppoſe their Liberty, and Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize over them: the Plot being diſcovered, and both his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign and Honour being loſt, he Dyed in the flower of his Age, as was thought, of Grief, before his Elder Brother. Thus theſe three Sons of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, were taken away in the ſpace of ſeventeen years after the Maſſacre, or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94465:14"/>
without Iſſue Male, beſides an Elder Brother <hi>Francis</hi> the Second, who Dyed very young before that Tragedy: And the Crown was Tranſlated to another Family, namely, that of <hi>Bourbon. Henry</hi> of <hi>Navar</hi> being called by his Predeceſſor from the remote parts of the Kindom (Providence ſo ordering it) as it were to receive the Royal Diadem on the other ſide the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> who ſeemed almoſt extinguiſhed (divers of the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh</hi> Nobility joyning with them for Politick ends, and Aid coming in from <hi>Germany,</hi> eſpecially under <hi>Caſtmire</hi> of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine</hi> Family) they obtained better Conditions, and enjoyed their Liberty in a more ſetled way than formerly.</p>
               <p>Upon the <hi>8th.</hi> day of <hi>October,</hi> in the Two and twentieth year of the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth, Anno</hi> 1580, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after the New Moon, there appeared a <hi>Blazing-Star</hi> in the <hi>South,</hi> pointing towards the <hi>Eaſt</hi> with its Streams; which was ſeen every night (the Air being clear) more than two Months: Shortly after there arrived upon the Weſt-Coaſt of <hi>Ireland,</hi> a certain company of <hi>Italians</hi> and <hi>Spaniards,</hi> ſent by the <hi>Pope</hi> to the aid of the Earl of <hi>Daſmond</hi> in his Rebellion, which were defeated by the Lord <hi>Gray</hi> of <hi>Wilton,</hi> Deputy of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Reign of King <hi>James,</hi> in the Year of our Lord, 1618. there appeared a <hi>Comet</hi> with a very long Tayl, ſeen here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and in other Countries, for almoſt two months together. After it followed the dreadful Calamity of <hi>Germany; Prague</hi> was taken in the year 1620. and the <hi>Palatinate</hi> was loſt. And the Edicts of the Emperour <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Second, were publiſhed in <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Moravia,</hi> in the Year 1624, againſt all the Goſpel Miniſters, commanding, That whoſoever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to forſake their Hereſie (as their Goſpel-profeſſion was called) and come into the Boſome of the Church (namely of <hi>Rome)</hi> ſhould depart from their Native Country, and never return more. Of the <hi>Comet</hi> that appeared in the year 1618 aforeſaid, <hi>Antonius de Dominis,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Spalato,</hi> who ſaw it, ſaith thus: <hi>Cometes qui his diebus pobis fulget, eſt unum xe phe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomenis</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Spalat. de Eccleſiaſt. Repub.</hi> li 5. P. 166.</note> 
                  <hi>Aſtronomicis, ex ijs quae Phenomena vera ſunt, non Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtica, et Oculum fallentia: et tamen res eſt vera et realis, Exha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio nempe acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſa et ardens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A terrible Comet appeared in the Year 1652. which the Mother princeſs, the Mother of <hi>Racoci,</hi> prince of <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:94465:14"/>
ſaw with her Court, living, and being then in the Caſtle of <hi>Munkary,</hi> there came forth the debates of divers Aſtrologers, deſcribing his Pale face, and the Compaſſes of his moſt ſwift courſe, as ſcarce was ever of any Comet before. <hi>Comenius</hi> tells us, that himſelf hapned to ſee the Judgments of four divers <note place="margin">Comen. <hi>Hiſtor.</hi> German. <hi>Prophet.</hi>
                  </note> Authors, not diſagreeing in the Event; <hi>Michael Guller</hi> the <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſian</hi> very neer touching the Mark. This proved Ominous to the Houſe of Prince <hi>Racoci.</hi> In the Year 1657 and 1658. the Prince going with an Army into <hi>Poland,</hi> and not entring into an agreement with the <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Tartar,</hi> but hiding his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize from the <hi>Turk</hi> he conceiving a ſuſpition of Rebellion, ſent the <hi>Tartar</hi> upon his back; and ſhortly after came Letters in a threefold courſe from <hi>C. S.</hi> the Secretary of the Prince of <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> Hiſtorically relating the Ruine of his Prince.</p>
               <p>And for the two Comets that appeared in the Year 1664. divers Aſtrologers then gave their Judgements, conceiving, That that in the Morning being Red and Fiery, portended War; That in the Evening being of a Pale and Melancholick colour, ſignified Death and Mortality; and ſome of them did ſhake their heads, fearing ſad Conſequents upon the appearance of two ſuch Stars ſo ſuddenly after each other; and ye know what ſad Effects followed the next Summer enſuing, <hi>Viz.</hi> In the Year 1665. namely, the of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> with the War <hi>Dutch,</hi> and that Devouring Plague that ſwept away above an Hundred Thouſand Perſons in the City of <hi>London</hi> and many Hundreds alſo in divers other places of this Kingdom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1677. A Comet appeared in <hi>April,</hi> the next Year the Helliſh <hi>Popiſh-Plot,</hi> was by the mercy of <hi>God</hi> happily diſcover'd.</p>
               <p>And now again, God hath ſhewed us other Signs in Heaven, by the appearance of two New Prodigies, one appeared in the <hi>South-Eaſt</hi> in the Morning, the other in the Evening. What elſe (I pray) doth God by theſe Signs ſeek to ſhew, than his Wrath to an Impenitent World? He is the God that <hi>maketh Signs and Wonders in Heaven and in Earth,</hi> Dan. 6. 28. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whoſoever feareth God, let him ſay with <hi>David, Come, and ſee the Works of the Lord, how Terrible he is in his Doings to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Children of Men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now ſeeing theſe Signs in the Heavens are of God, let us
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94465:15"/>
take heed that we do not deſpiſe God in his Works. Among the <hi>Romans,</hi> when the General cauſed a Purple Coat to be hung out over his Pavilion, and the Trumpet to ſound, what Souldier in the Camp durſt to Neglect it, and not take notice of it as a Sign of Battel? How much more when the Lord of Hoſts holds forth his Flagg, and diſplayeth his Enſignes, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying what he is about to do; and if not making it known what it is in particular, yet ſhewing, that he hath ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Work in hand, how carefully ſhould we obſerve theſe things, and prepare for the worſt that may happen. But the blindneſs of Carnal Reaſon darkens the minds of many world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-wiſe perſons, that they cannot ſee far off, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks in another caſe. Carnal Reaſon is of too low a ſtature in this caſe, our thoughts muſt climb the Sycamore-Tree like <hi>Zacheus;</hi> or we muſt get up into our Watch-Tower like the Prophet <hi>Habakkuk;</hi> we muſt take our ſtanding higher, and look above the whole Creation, and ſeriouſly think of the Creatour, God himſelf, the firſt mover and Principal Worker in all theſe things.</p>
               <p>Moreover, Men and Women are ſo generally in love with the World, and do ſo earneſtly deſire, mind, ſeek, and affect earthly things, either their Pleaſures, Profits, or Earthly hopes, &amp;c. that they have no leiſure to mind the ſpecial works of God, which are Signs of the times, and give Warning of things at hand. Therefore, ſaith <hi>Solomon, Eccl.</hi> 9. 12. Man knoweth not his time; <hi>As the Fiſhes that are taken in an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Net, and as the Birds that are caught in the Snare, ſo are the Sons of Men ſnared in an evil time, when it falls ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly upon them.</hi> As the Bird wholly minding the Bait, is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the Snare which it minded not: So the Sons of Men wholly minding the profits or pleaſures, or other things of this World, heed not the Signs of the times, and ſo are ſnared in an evil time.</p>
               <p>The love of Sin alſo poſſeſſing the Hearts of Men, keeps many from diſcerning the Works of God: It is Wonderful to conſider, how the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were beſotted this way, ſo as not to ſee the viſible and apparent ſigns of the times, as they had before their Eyes; The Thunderings and Lighten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94465:15"/>
upon Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> the ſound of the Trumpet exceeding loud, the Voice of God ſtriking an awful Terrour into their Hearts, the Cloudy Pillar every Day, the Pillar of Fire every Night was continually as a ſhining light before their Faces; the Glory of the Lord often Appearing: Bread ſent them down all the Six Days of the Week from Heaven; the Rock becomming as a Fountain of Water to them in the Wilderneſs, which Water followed them in their ſeveral ſtations: Were not theſe Signs to them of an extraordinary time, wherein God was more than in an ordinary manner preſent with them, and would be ſanctified in them, ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h he had brought them ſo neer unto himſelf: And yet, as if it had been but an ordin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary time, and as if they had <hi>had</hi> no more to do with the onely true God than other people; nor any more ſpecial relation to him, as if he had done no more for them than for the <hi>Aegypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> they gave themſelves over to divers ſins, as to foul Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try (it ſeemeth) in the ſight of Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> to luſting after Quails and Delicates, to commit Fornication with the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Idolaters, and then alſo to joyn with them in ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Whoredom and Service of their Idols: Some of them to Ambition, contending with <hi>Aaron</hi> for the Prieſthood, whom God had called and conſecrated to that Office; ſo ſtrangely had the love of Sin bewitched and blinded their minds, that without regarding the Signs of the times, they ran into the Snare, and oftentimes brought many ſtroaks upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>Great alſo is the ſecurity of Men and Women: This is a general Diſeaſe to which the World is ſubject, and as the old World was in a dead Sleep of Wretched ſecurity, until the Flood-Gates of Heaven, with the noiſe of an unreſiſtable Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Awakened them, when they Awoke to ſee themſelves pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; neither <hi>Noah</hi>'s Preaching, nor the knocking about the Ark before, could Awaken them; ſo there are many who lye ſlumbering and ſleeping in deep ſecurity, and no loud crys from the Word do Awaken them to make them open their Eyes, to ſee the ſigns of the times, that they might either avoid the evil which the time is about to bring forth, or embrace the Good which the opportunity of the time offereth to them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:94465:16"/>
Gods Judgements are there moſt heavy, where his greateſt mercies are moſt Abuſed: <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> had <hi>had</hi> ſuch mercies, as no City under Heaven ſince the beginning of the World in ſome reſpect; and theſe ſhe moſt grievouſly Abuſed, and was moſt unthankful to the Giver; and therefore the Lord brought on her ſuch miſery as no City ever felt: No City had ſinned like <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> none had ſuch mercies againſt which they could ſin; no City ſuffered like to her, when once the Lords Abuſed patience turned into Anger and heavy diſpleaſure: This ſhould Awaken <hi>England,</hi> which is the Field which God hath Sowed in his Love, but through our unthankfulneſs ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to have buried or loſt a multitude of mercies: No Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on under Heaven at this preſent, hath ſo many mercies to reckon for as we: If the Lord ſhould deal in Juſtice with us, what people ſince the beginning of the World hath deſerved greater puniſhments? If every Pariſh, every Family, every Perſon, would look into themſelves, and ſee what mercies, what means they have had, or might have had for Soul or Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, what Catalogues might they make, and what wrath might they think they had deſerved? Let us all look home, and know, that nothing ſhall plead more ſtrongly againſt impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and unthankful perſons at the laſt day, than mercies them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>The Great God of Heaven and Earth doth not onely ſpeak to Men with the Tongues of Prophets, Apoſtles, and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; but ſometimes alſo by the Elements, Compoſed or wrought into divers Forms and Shapes. if we will believe what is Credibly reported, the Heavens have been of late Chequer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Strange and Prodigious Sights: but what is moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, is, That a <hi>Comet</hi> or <hi>Blazing-Star,</hi> for many Weeks have been Viſible to all, or moſt parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> and other places, as the <hi>Gazettes</hi> teſtifie; and there's ſo many people in <hi>England,</hi> nay in <hi>London,</hi> that by <hi>Occular</hi> Experience can Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to the truth of it, that there needs no further Narrative.</p>
               <p>When God intends to puniſh a Nation, Country, or City, he is firſt pleaſed to give them notice thereof by Apparitions or Prodigies; and there hath never been any notable Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rition or Prodigy ſeen in the Heavens, but it hath been atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94465:16"/>
in the Sequel with ſome more then ordinary Troubles, or Change here on Earth, according to this Illuſtration of <hi>Dubar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas:</hi> Viz.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Here in the Night appears a</hi> Flaming Spire,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>There a Fierce</hi> Dragon, <hi>folded all in</hi> Fire:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Here a Bright</hi> Cornet, <hi>there a</hi> Fiery Stream,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Here</hi> Flying Launces, <hi>there a</hi> Burning Beam:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Here ſeems a</hi> Horned Goat, <hi>Environ'd round</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>With</hi> Fiery Flakes, <hi>about the Air to bound;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>There with Long</hi> Bloody Hair, <hi>a</hi> Blazing-Star,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Threatning the World with</hi> Famine, Plague, <hi>and</hi> War:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To Princes</hi> Death, <hi>to Kingdoms many</hi> Croſſes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To all Eſtates,</hi> Inevitable Loſſes:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To</hi> Herds-men Rot, <hi>to</hi> Plow-men <hi>Hopleſs Seaſons,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To</hi> Saylors Storms, <hi>to Cities</hi> Civil Treaſons.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Thus much of Prodigies in general, now to know the Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of each particular Comet, for they have not all one and the ſame portences; we muſt, according to the Docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> obſerve their Colours, place, and moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Heavens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that I may be well underſtood by thoſe for whoſe ſakes I undertook this Task, <hi>viz.</hi> the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar or Common people of this Kingdom; I ſhall not ſtrive to uſe any Cramp words or Quaint Language, but in a homely and plain Stile, deliver unto them, the Signification of this <hi>Blazing-Star,</hi> according to the Rules of Art; as followeth.</p>
               <p>By the account we had of this Comet firſt from <hi>Falmous,</hi> in the Weſt of <hi>England;</hi> it was then of a Bright and clear Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, but its Tail was of a pale colour towards the end. So then we may conclude, the Star was then of a Jovial nature, but its Tail of a <hi>Saturnian</hi> Hue; and by the ſaid account, it was then in the Caeleſtial Sign <hi>Scorpio,</hi> but is now in the Sign <hi>Aries,</hi> and the Star really <hi>Saturnian</hi> ſo well as its Tail: it is true, when it had but newly paſt the Conjunction of the Sun,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94465:17"/>
and firſt became Occidental, its Tail was very Red, and at leaſt Sixty Degrees long; but there was then a Tincture, or mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the aforeſaid Colours in it. Its Tail is not Forty Degrees long now, and will be ſhorter as the Star gets further from the Sun. Now it being ſince its firſt appearance, of the Colour of the Planets before Nominated, and likewiſe of the Colour of <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> for <hi>Mars</hi> claims the Redneſs of its Tail, and <hi>Mercury</hi> will put in for a ſhare, by reaſon of its various Colours; therefore we may expect, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the nature of thoſe four Planets, will the effects of this new Star be: which is as followeth.</p>
               <p>A Comet of the nature of <hi>Saturn,</hi> ſignifies many Frights and Fears among people, Trouble, Vexation, Murmuring, and Repining; Exile or Baniſhment to many: ſcarcity of Food, Penury, grievous Sickneſſes, Plague, Conſumptions, Agues, and other Lingring Diſtempers: Tempeſtuous Winds, Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracks, Inundations, great Froſts and Snows; a deſtruction of Fruits by Worms or Catterpillars.</p>
               <p>A Comet of the Nature of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> as this was at its firſt appearance, denotes much ſtrugling among Men for matters of Religion, Laws and Priviledges, ſtrivings, Wraſtling and encountering each other: it ſignifies a plentiful and Fertile time, pleaſant Salubrious Air, Seaſonable Winds and Showers; and truly it is well we have ſome Significations of good, to buoy us up under the many miſchiefs portended.</p>
               <p>Now its Tail being ſometimes Red, <hi>viz.</hi> of the Nature of <hi>Mars,</hi> ſignifies Wars, Quarrels, Sea-Fights, Slaughters, Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, Tumults, Maſſacres, in ſome places change of Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Governments; peſtiferous Winds, terrible Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Lightnings; Tempeſts, Shipwacks, Thieves and Robbers will abound on the Land, and Pyrates at Sea; exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Hot Weather at ſometimes, drying up Rivers and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains: ſcarcity of the Fruits of the Earth, Firing or Burning of Houſes, and violent Feavers among Men.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:94465:17"/>
It being of Various Colours for ſometime, as I told you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Mercury</hi> will have a ſhare in its Effects, and then it denotes much Wit and Policy among Men, and as much buſineſs to imploy it about: <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> ſay, that it ſignifies the Death of Great Men, Wars, Sickneſſes and ſcarcity of Food: many men will imploy their Wits about Vild and Treacherous things, and when they have done, if queſtioned for the ſame, pretend to be as Innocent as Lambs; and truly ſo they may, as <hi>Romiſh</hi> Lambs, which are always of a more Infernal quality, than <hi>Heretick-Lyons,</hi> as they call them.</p>
               <p>In the next place I ſhall give you the ſignification of this Star, in relation to the Signs of Heaven it has already paſt through, which is, <hi>Scorpio, Sagitarius, Capricorn, Aquarius, Piſces,</hi> and is now in <hi>Aries;</hi> but how much farther it will go, time muſt be the Informer.</p>
               <p>A Comet or <hi>Blazing-Star</hi> in <hi>Scorpio,</hi> ſignifies Wars, Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Controverſies, alterations and Changes in the world, and chiefly among men of Martial Diſcipline; Trouble and Animoſities among Princes; a ſcarcity of Waters, and fruits of the Earth, Damage to Merchants by pyrates, and much grief to Teeming Women.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Sagitary,</hi> it denotes Evil to Great Men, Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies about Religion and Laws, Feavers and other dangerous Infirmities.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Capricorn,</hi> a Comet doth ſignifie many Wicked Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons among Men, Murders, Thefts, Robberies, Wars, Plague and Famine in many places; Troubles and Calamities to moſt ſort of People; the Death of Great men by Poyſon, or other violent means: Perſecution of many for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and Contempt of Religion it ſelf; great Froſts, Snows, Hails, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Aquary,</hi> it denotes long laſting Wars, terrible ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, many kinds of Croſſes and Cruelties; and in ſome places a ſweeping Plague or Peſtilence; dark obſcure Air, great Winds, Thunder and Lightnings.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:94465:18"/>
When a Comet appears in <hi>Piſces,</hi> it ſignifies Eminent ſtrife and Contentions about Religion, Deviſions, Seperations, and Alienations of Relations, and former Friends: Strange and Prodigious Apparitions in the Air; ſcarcity of Fiſh, loſſes and croſſes in Sea-Voyages, much troubles amongſt great and Potent Perſons.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, This Comet being in <hi>Aries,</hi> is the fore-runner of much miſchief, troubles, War-like preparations; the Death of ſome Eminent Perſon, which will cauſe or occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion great Conſternation in the Country where it ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen: ſharp Diſeaſes in the Head and Eyes of people, and a Rot or Murrain among ſmall Cattel.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stella Barbata,</hi> or <hi>Caudata;</hi> A Star with a Beard, or long Tayl, as this Comet hath, denotes the Death of Great and Noble Men, and Wars in thoſe Countries unto which it points its Tayl: and we may conclude, that in regard from its firſt appearance, it took its progreſs towards the Sun, its Effects will be manifeſted in a great meaſure on Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent perſons, and Ineminent Actions; and I need not go about to tell where, or in what Countries the ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this Star will appear; but in ſhort acquaint you, That it hath already taken up a large part of <hi>Europe,</hi> ſo well as other parts, for its <hi>Theatre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus far have I adventured to ſpeak of this</hi> Blazing-Star <hi>unto the World, and in ſo doing I well hope I have Offended none that I ought not to have Offended. I would have none to be conſtartned or affrightned at thoſe Preſages, though they be according to the true and experienced Rules of Art; but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Prudent and Wiſe ſaying of</hi> Charles <hi>the Great, when he was beholding the New Star that preſaged and preceeded his Death, he was very Inquiſitous and deſirous to know what it ſignified; One who ſtood by anſwers him in the Words of the Prophet</hi> Jeremiah, <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. Fear not the Signs
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94465:18"/>
of Heaven, though the Heathen be afraid of them; <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which the Emperour replyed,</hi> That he did not indeed fear any Signs of that Nature, but the Maker or cauſe of thoſe Signs. <hi>A Wiſe Saying, and deſerves to be Written in Letters of Gold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know ſome Critical Perſons will be ready to ſay, that I have given no <hi>Mathematical,</hi> or <hi>Aſtronomical</hi> accout of this Star; to which I anſwer, neither can it reaſonably be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected that I ſhould, any more than I have, conſidering the ſtreightneſs of my Limits: I leave that therefore to thoſe that ſhall Write a more Large Diſcourſe hereof, to certisfie the Learned.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To conclude this Diſcourſe, my Prayer ſhall be,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That</hi> Venus <hi>and</hi> Jupiter <hi>i'th Heavens may agree.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
