<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A philosophical essay of musick directed to a friend.</title>
            <author>Guilford, Francis North, Baron, 1637-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-03">2005-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42318</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G2216</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38780</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18112159</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18112159</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106827</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A42318)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106827)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1124:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A philosophical essay of musick directed to a friend.</title>
                  <author>Guilford, Francis North, Baron, 1637-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>25 [i.e. 35] p., [1] folded leaf of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Martyn ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Guilford by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>"Feb. 3d 1676/7. Imprimatur, Guil. Sill."</note>
                  <note>Folded plate not photographed.</note>
                  <note>Page 35 numbered 25.</note>
                  <note>Errata: inserted at end.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Music --  Acoustics and physics.</term>
               <term>Music theory --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11</date>
            <label>Andrew Kuster</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11</date>
            <label>Andrew Kuster</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-01</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106827:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106827:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A
Philosophical
ESSAY
OF
MUSICK
Directed to a
FRIEND.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>Imprimatur,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Feb. 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 1676/7</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>Guil. Sill.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed for <hi>John Martyn,</hi> Printer to the Royal
Society; at the <hi>Bell</hi> in Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s
Church-Yard, 1677.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:106827:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106827:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving often tyred you with Discourses of
several Parts of <hi>Musick,</hi> wherein you desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
to receive satisfaction, without obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the Effect I proposed to my self; I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected
upon the saying, That no man understands that
which he cannot so express as to make another under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand
it, and doubted whether the Hypothesis I enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
were not founded upon Errours, which I had
swallowed without any due examination. I resolved
for tryal of it, to trace my Notions as near their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples
as I could, and set them down in method, that I
might discover whether they were well deduced from one
another, and from such Experiments as I had in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.
Having done this I send them to you, as the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verest
judge I know: It has not been your custome to
flatter me, and now I desire your censure, if I may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose
it upon you to give it in writing, wherein you will
be obliged to quote what I say truly, before you object to
it, and to stand to those Allegations and Inferences you
will set down for your own, in both which respects I
had great disadvantage in Discourse. I shall prevent
you in condemning the stile, for being too contracted and
obscure; and you must take the fault to your self when
you know it does not proceed from the aversion I have
to Philologie, but that I thought it would be labour lost
to enlarge, when writing to so great a Philosopher and
Musician as you are, I cannot fail of being understood.
<pb facs="tcp:106827:3"/>
In other things I expose it to you; and if I shall receive
plain Confutations, it will not much disappoint or mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie
me: for I have hardly in my whole Life made one
set experiment upon this Subject, nor know many of
the Instruments I have spoken of: But what I heard
from others, or occasionally observed, I laid up in mind,
and established this Systeme, which I shall be glad to
lose, if I may improve my Knowledge by your Disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries.
This may seem strange to you, considering how
fond men are of their own Inventions: At the worst, I
hope for this fruit of my pains, that you will make such
Experiments as your Curiosity will suggest whilst you
read this, and let me know the success of them; though
I may thereby be driven out of his Hypothesis, perhaps
I shall receive light towards another, which you may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
I shall take as much pleasure in making, as you,
or any body else can to destroy.</p>
            <closer>I am, <salute>SIR,</salute>
Your most Faithfull Friend
and Servant.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="section">
            <pb facs="tcp:106827:3"/>
            <head>Of SOUND.</head>
            <p>MY design being to explain the nature of <hi>Musick</hi> it
will not be improper to enquire first, concerning
the cause of Sound; and here though I cannot
hope to give full satisfaction, because our Senses
want subtilty to discover the motions of the minute parts
of the Air whereupon it depends, yet perhaps I may assign a
possible cause for the producing of Sound, the knowledge
whereof will give some ease to the wondring Philosopher;
and if I have the good fortune to shew a probable cause,
the Curious will acquiesce from any farther enquiry, which
is all the benefit they can have by speculations of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Phaenomena</hi> of <hi>Sound</hi> which I think considerable
are these, 1. It may be produced in the Torricellian va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuity.
2. It causes motion in solid bodies. 3. It is diminish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
by interposition of solid bodies, and 4. If the bodies in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terposed
are very thick, its passage is wholly obstructed.
5. It seems to come to the Ear in strait lines when the object
is so scituated that it cannot come in a straight line to the
Ear. 6. When the air is not in motion its extent is <hi>sphaerical.</hi>
7. When there is a wind, the <hi>sphaere</hi> is enlarged on that part
to which the wind blows, and diminished on the contrary
part. 8. That it arrives not to the Ear in an instant but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderably
slower than sight. 9. That it comes as quick against
the wind as with it, though not so loud nor so far.</p>
            <p>There are many other observable Appearances, and
more will daily occurre to the Curious upon Experiments,
but the consideration of these qualities of <hi>Sound</hi> and the
visible actions that produce it, hath made me entertain the
following Hypothesis.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:106827:4"/>
I suppose the air we breath in to be a mixture of divers
minute bodies which are of different sorts and sizes, though
all of them are so small as to escape our senses: the grosser of
them are elastical, and are resisted by solid bodies, which
are in no sort pervious to them; the smaller parts pass through
solid bodies, but not with that ease but that upon a sudden
and violent start of them, they shock the parts of solid
bodies that stand in their way, and also the grosser parts
of the air; and there may be another degree of most subtil
Ethereal parts with which the interstices of these and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
bodies are repleat, which find freer passage every where,
and are capable of no compression, and consequently be
the medium and cause of the immediate communication of
sight. The middle sort of these I esteem the medium and
cause of <hi>Sound,</hi> and that at any time when the grosser air
is driven off any space and leaves it to be possest by these
and other more subtil bodies, and returns by its elastici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
to its former place, then are these parts extruded with
violence as from the center of that space, and communicate
their motion as far as the sound is heard.</p>
            <p>Or when any solid body is moved with a sudden and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent
motion, these parts must be affected thereby: for as
these parts are so much resisted by solid bodies as to shock
them, so on the contrary they must needs be moved by the
sudden starting of solid bodies.</p>
            <p>So that sound may be caused by the tremble of solid bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
without the presence of gross Air, and also by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution
of gross Air when it has been divided with any
violence.</p>
            <p>We see a Bell will sound in the Torricellian space: and
when the Air is divided with any sudden force, as by the
end of a Whip having all the motion of the Whip contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in it, and by a sudden turn throwing off the Air; by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cension,
as in Thunder and Guns; or by any impression of
force carrying it where other Air cannot so forcibly follow,
as upon compressing of Air in a bladder till it breaks, or in
a Potgun, a sudden crack will be caused.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:106827:4"/>
I shall leave others to apply this Hypothesis to the afore
mentioned <hi>Phaenomena</hi> (which they may easily do) and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
to the discourse of <hi>Musick,</hi> where I am in its due place
to shew how this action that causes sound is performed by
the several instruments of <hi>Musick.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <head>Of a TONE.</head>
            <p>A Tone is the repetition of Cracks or Pulses in equal
spaces of time so quick that the interstices or intervals
are not perceptible to sense.</p>
            <p>The more quick the Pulses are, the more acute the <hi>Tone</hi>
is. Where the intervals are not equal, nor in musical pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion,
the sound is not in <hi>tone</hi> but an irregular noise.</p>
            <p>The compass of <hi>Musick</hi> extends from such <hi>tones</hi> whose in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervals
are so great that the several Pulses are distinguish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
by sense, to those whose interstices are so very small
that they are not commensurate with any other.</p>
            <p>In which compass the several <hi>tones</hi> are infinite in number
as all space may be divided in <hi>infinitum.</hi> But the <hi>tones</hi> use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
in <hi>Musick</hi> are those within the scale, which are not very
many, and they are placed in the scale as they have relation
to one another.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <head>Of the Relation of TONES and the Vnion
of mixt SOUNDS.</head>
            <p>WHen the Pulses of <hi>tones</hi> are coincident one with the
other, there is an Union of the <hi>sounds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For when any <hi>Sound</hi> is made, solid bodies within the
<hi>sphaere</hi> of it are moved, and if the body moved stands upon
a spring (as all instruments producing <hi>tones</hi> do) it will vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate
by intervals according to the measure of the spring
until the force be spent.</p>
            <p>Now if the moving force be repeated, as it must be where
<pb facs="tcp:106827:5"/>
it proceeds from a <hi>tone,</hi> and the terms of the force are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual
to the terms of vibration, every new stroke strengthens
the former impression, and after some continuance the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration
of a Body affected by <hi>Sound,</hi> may become so great
as to be sensible to the Eye and Ear.</p>
            <p>But where the terms of Vibration are not commensurate
with the terms of concussion, the following pulses destroy
the motion begun by the former, and the Vibration will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
augment beyond what it was upon the first impression.</p>
            <p>Upon this Reason a string tuned in unison to another
will manifestly shake when its fellow sounds, and another
string that has a discording <hi>Tone,</hi> though of the same big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
will not appear to be moved.</p>
            <p>And for this Reason, wheresoever the vibrations of two
sounding strings are equal, the pulses will be coincident: for
although one should set out after the other, yet by this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
they would by the second or third pulse become co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incident.</p>
            <p>Where the terms are equal, and the coincidence is at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
pulse, it may be said the same <hi>Sound</hi> though proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
from several Instruments: for the mixed <hi>Sound</hi> has no
alteration, but by being more loud and full by the addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Where the Termes are 2 to 1, or 4 to 1, or 8 to 1, or 16
to 1, there will be coincidence to every pulse of the Base, and
between those termes the treble is heard alone without any
mixture: so that the <hi>Sound</hi> is not changed but augmented
by the addition of stronger pulses at proportionable inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valls,
which makes the pulses superinduced appear of the
same nature, though more grave or acute; this is the case
of <hi>Octaves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where the Termes are as 2 to 3, every third pulse of the
Treble, and every other pulse of the Base are coincident,
but the intermediate pulses, <hi>sc.</hi> 2 of the Treble, and 1 of
the Base are not so, but keep certain distances, which makes
the mixture produce an alteration: but the coincidences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106827:5"/>
so frequent, and the distances of the intermediate pulses
proportionable, the mixture is very pleasing, and is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal
Chord called the fifth.</p>
            <p>Where the Termes of coincidence are further off, as when
they are but the fourth, fifth or sixth pulses of the Treble
that are coincident with the third, fourth and fifth pulses of
the Base, yet the mixture is pleasing, and produces Chords:
which Chords are more or less perfect, according as they are
more or less coincident.</p>
            <p>Coincidence upon every fourth pulse of the Treble is the
fourth.</p>
            <p>Every fifth pulse is the third sharp.</p>
            <p>Every sixth pulse is the third flat.</p>
            <p>When the fifth pulse of the Treble goes with the third of
the Base, it is a sixth sharp: the eighth pulse of the Treble
going with the fifth of the Base makes a sixth flat.</p>
            <p>That these Chords have their pulses in such proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
line is demonstrable by the division of the Monochord,
which being stopt in ½ gives an Octave, in ⅓ gives a fifth, in
¼ gives a fourth, in ⅕ gives a third Sharp, in ⅙ gives a third
Flat, ⅕ gives a sixth Sharp, ⅜ gives a sixth Flat: This is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed
by all that ever treated of <hi>Musick,</hi> therefore I shall
speak no more of it.</p>
            <p>It may seem strange that a Coincidence in this manner
should unite <hi>Sounds,</hi> and that the fifth and fourth pulses
that are disagreeing should not hinder more, than the sixth
coincident pulse could reconcile: and that a coincidence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
the eighth pulse of the Treble with the fifth of the
Base should make the <hi>Sounds</hi> agreeable, notwithstanding
the variance of those which are intermediate.</p>
            <p>But this will be very clear, when it is observed that the
intermediate pulses do not at all hinder, for they are all
placed in such manner, in relation to one another, that where
any of them distract the pulses of the concording string on
the one hand, there are others that by being just as much
on the other hand, set them right again: they are in balance
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106827:6"/>
one against another, so that it is as if there were no interme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate
pulse at all, as to any effect of hindring the Coincidence.</p>
            <p>And the intermediate pulses being at such symmetrical
distances a new proportion arises from the mixture of them,
which makes the joined <hi>Sounds</hi> pleasing to the sense.</p>
            <p>Where the coincidences are more remote, and all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termediate
pulses disagreeing, as 7 to 6, 8 to 7, 9 to 8,
10 to 9, the by pulses are too many to be kept steddy, and
the pulses on one hand prevail too far before those on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
hand come to set them right, so that the <hi>Sounds</hi> will not
maintain their coincidences, but produce jarring and discord.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Sounds</hi> are in discord, the concussions caused by
them are in opposition one to another; and the Organ of
Sense cannot be affected by both together, but they will
appear ragged and jarring, and extream noisome. Nay some
<hi>sounds</hi> will be so contrary to one another, &amp; so hard a match,
that they cannot sound both together, but each hindering
the other will take turnes. Thus do they imitate the Drum
in an Organ, by joyning two deep discording Notes, that
rumble in that manner sounding by turns. And in tuning Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan-pipes
it may be observed, that the <hi>Sounds</hi> of two Pipes
whilst in discord will flutter, but when the discording Pipe
is brought to the others <hi>Tone,</hi> the <hi>Sounds</hi> will as it were
jump into Tune, as if they had attracted one another, and
afterwards one clear and entire <hi>Sound</hi> will be produced.</p>
            <p>Upon this Relation of <hi>Tones</hi> depends the Scale of <hi>Musick,</hi>
of which I shall shew the Degrees, and the reason why they
are so placed, when I come to speak of <hi>Schismes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I leave this Head I must observe, that Octaves not
altering the manner of <hi>Sound,</hi> but giving a fulness in duple
proportions, which are comprehended in the same time, it
follows, that all Octaves are easily brought in mind, and are
as it were included in any <hi>Tone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This being considered, it will appear, that there can be
no other variety of coincidence within the compass of se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
pulses that is not allowed in <hi>Musick,</hi> and produces some
<hi>Chord:</hi> For,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:106827:6"/>
⅓ is as ⅔ 2 being the Octave to 1.</item>
                  <item>⅕ is as ⅘ 4 being in Octave to 1.</item>
                  <item>⅖ as ⅘, 2/6 as ⅔, ⅙ as 4/6, as ⅔.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And the eighth coincident pulse in a sixth flat, comes in
upon this contemplation, but as the reverse of a third sharp,
⅝ being the reverse of 5/4, and the other sixth ⅗ is the reverse
of 6/5. So that there can be no other coincidences under the
distance of the seventh pulse, but what have the names of
Chords, or the Octaves; and we are not to wonder why
there are no more concording Notes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <head>How TONES are produced, and of assistances
to the SOUND by Instruments.</head>
            <p>WHerever a Body stands upon a Spring that vibrates
in equal Termes, such a Body put into motion will
produce a <hi>Tone,</hi> which will be more grave or acute, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to the velocity of the returns.</p>
            <p>Therefore strings vibrating have a <hi>Tone</hi> according to the
bigness or tension of them; and Bells that vibrate by cross
ovals, produce Notes according to the bigness of them, or
the thickness of their sides: and so do all other bodies whose
superficies being displaced by force, results by a spring which
carries it beyond its first station.</p>
            <p>It is easie to comprehend how every pulse upon such vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brations
causes <hi>Sound,</hi> for the gross Air is thrown off by the
violence of the motion, which continues some moment of
time after the return of the vibrating Body, whereupon some
space must be left to that subtil matter, which upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult
of the Air starts as from a Centre; which action being
the same I supposed to be the cause of <hi>Sound,</hi> is repeated
upon every vibration.</p>
            <p>It is more difficult to shew how <hi>Tones</hi> are made by a Pipe,
where there are no visible vibrations. I will consider the
frame of a Pipe, and the motion of the Air in it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106827:7"/>
attempt to find the cause of the <hi>Tone</hi> of a Pipe, and the
pulse that gives the <hi>Sound.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is in any Pipe a Cavity of a certain gage or big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
which is exposed to the outward Air, but in some parts
of it, and according to that Cavity is the <hi>Tone</hi> of the Pipe.</p>
            <p>The Air in any Cavity being capable of being compressed
by outward force, if the Cavity be large, easily yields to a
compression; but if it be small, is more hardly compressed.
When the compressing force ceases, the Body that was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed
with difficulty flies out with sudden violence; that
which is more easily compressed restores it self not so soon:
whereby it happens, that every Cavity has a certain <hi>Tone</hi>
according to the measure of the vibrations of the Air in it,
which it will keep what way soever the force comes to it:
As the water in a Shallow or Greek moved by the large
waves of the Sea, retains not a motion in such huge waves,
but in waves proportionable to its own bigness and depth.</p>
            <p>Hereupon I conclude, That any Pipe, whether made of
Wood, Stone, Glass or Metal, has a certain and determinate
<hi>Tone,</hi> according to its Gage and Cavity, which is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
<hi>Tone</hi> which will be produced by blowing it. If the
Cavity be small, the <hi>Sound</hi> will be acute, and may be made
more acute by apertures, whereby the Cavity is diminished,
and the inclosed Air exposed to the outward Air in greater
measure.</p>
            <p>When I say, the <hi>Tone</hi> is according to the proportion of
the Cavity, let the Pipe be made of what it well; I do not
deny but that if the materials of the Pipe be soft and yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
it may give some small alteration to the <hi>Tone</hi> from what
it would be if they were of a substance hard and firm, where
the impelling Air would find a more brisk resistance: but
the difference is inconsiderable, and the spring of the Air
depending mainly upon the greatness of the Cavity, I take
no notice of it.</p>
            <p>To shew how the pulses are caused, whereby the included
Air is put into this motion, it is necessary to observe the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106827:7"/>
frame of a Pipe, which chiefly consists in having a long slit
through which the Air is blown in a thin film against or very
near a solid edge that is at some distance opposite to it, in
such manner that the intermediate space is covered by the
stream of Air. This film of Air on the one side is exposed to
the outward Air, and on the inside is defended from it by
the sides of the Pipe, within which the Air inclosed in the
Pipe stagnates, whilst the outward Air is by the blast put
into a vortical motion.</p>
            <p>The vortical motion or Eddy on the outside is so strong,
that there not being a balance to that force on the inside,
the film of Air gives way, and the Eddy bears into the Pipe,
but is immediately overcome by the blast, which prevails un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
the Eddy overcomes it again; and so there is a crossing
of streams by turns and pulses, which causes the voice of
the Pipe, the gross Air of one stream being thrown off by
the interposition of the other.</p>
            <p>These vicissitudes or termes will answer the <hi>Tone</hi> of the
Pipe according to the gage of its cavity: for the spring of
the included Air helps toward the restitution of the blast
and eddy in their turns, which causes those turns to comply
with the <hi>Tone</hi> of the Pipe; and therefore the same blast will
cause several <hi>Tones,</hi> if the gage or measure of the included
Air be changed by apertures in the side of the Pipe.</p>
            <p>But there must be some proportion between the mouth,
(so I call that part of the Pipe where the voice is) and the
gage of the Pipe: for though the pulses will be brought to
comply with the <hi>Tone</hi> of the Pipe in any reasonable degree,
yet when there is great disparity it will not do so; as if the
Pipe be too long for the proportion of the diameter, the
pulses at the mouth cannot be brought to so slow termes as
to answer the vibrations of the included Air, therefore the
Pipe will not speak unless it can break into some higher
Note. If the filmy stream of Air be too thick, the Pipe will
not speak, because the eddy cannot break through; if the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posite
edge be too remote, the stream cannot entirely cover
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106827:8"/>
the aperture, for it mixes with the outward Air, and is more
confused the farther it is from the vent or passage, whereby
some outward Air may have communication to make an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posite
eddy on the inside of the stream. For the same reason,
if there be the least aperture in the region of the mouth of
the Pipe, it will not speak at all.</p>
            <p>Hence is it, that the voice of Organ Pipes is so tender and
nice: but shrill whistles depend not upon this ground; for
they are made in any small cavity where the blast is so ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed,
that the erumpent Air must cross it, whether the
stream be thick or thin. Therefore the bore of a Key, a
piece of nutshell, or any other cavity will make a whistle,
whose <hi>Tone</hi> will be according to the quantity of the inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
Air, for the less that is, the harder it is to be compres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,
and the quicker and stronger it must break forth.</p>
            <p>Another kind of Whistle is, when a hollow body with a
small cavity is perforated by opposite holes, a blast either
way will cause a <hi>Tone,</hi> which seems to be made in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>The Air that is violently drawn or thrust through these
holes is straitned at the passage by the swiftness of the
motion, and within the cavity is somewhat enlarged, and
consequently its force is directed, and it presses beyond the
compass of the opposite aperture, whereupon it bears of all
sides into the cavity; hereby the Air within the cavity is
compressed untill it breaks forth by crossing the stream,
which being done by vicissitudes causes a <hi>Tone:</hi> this kind
of action, as I imagine, is performed when men whistle with
their lips.</p>
            <p>In some Pipes the pulses are caused by springs, as the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goll
stop of an Organ, which is commonly tuned by short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
the spring whereby it becomes stronger, but the Note
will be changed by the alteration of the cavity; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
to make them steddy, some that stand upon very weak
springs have Pavelions set to them.</p>
            <p>A rustick instance may be given of the compliance of a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106827:8"/>
Spring, in taking such vibrations as are proportionable to
the Cavity; It is a <hi>Jews-harp,</hi> or <hi>Jews-trump,</hi> the tongue
whereof has natural vibrations according to strength and
length of the Spring, and so is fitted to one particular <hi>Tone:</hi>
But Countrey-men framing their breath and their mouth to
several Notes make a shift to express a Tune by it.</p>
            <p>In a <hi>Shawm</hi> or <hi>Hautboys</hi> the Quill at the mouth is a kind
of Spring, but so weak and indifferent that it complies with
any measure, and therefore the <hi>Tone</hi> will be according to the
apertures of the Pipe.</p>
            <p>The fluttering and jarring of discording <hi>Sounds,</hi> which I
before did observe, is so regular, and the <hi>Sounds</hi> take their
turns with equal interstices, which makes the joyning of
them produce a harsher <hi>Sound</hi> than either had before: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<hi>Organ-makers</hi> imitate the <hi>Hautboys</hi> or <hi>Trumpet,</hi> without
any Spring or Quill, by joyning discording Pipes.</p>
            <p>In a <hi>Sackbut</hi> the Lips of a Man do the same office as a Quill
does in a <hi>Shaume</hi> or <hi>Hautboys;</hi> when the included Air is
lengthned, the <hi>Tone</hi> varies: nevertheless they can produce
several Notes that are in Chord to the <hi>Tone</hi> of the Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
by strengthning the blast without lengthning the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity:
And in a <hi>Trumpet,</hi> which is the same kind of Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
(only not capable of being lengthned) they can sound
a whole Tune, which is by the artificial ordering the blast at
the mouth, whereby the <hi>Sound</hi> breaks into such Notes as
are to be used.</p>
            <p>This depends upon the consideration of the varying and
breaking of <hi>Tones</hi> into other Notes, whereof I am to speak
particularly in my next Chapter, to which I hasten.</p>
            <p>Having shewed how <hi>Tones</hi> are produced by Instruments
of <hi>Musick,</hi> I must take notice of other assistances Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
give to the <hi>Sound.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>Violins</hi> and <hi>Harpsechords</hi> the <hi>Tones</hi> are made wholly
by the vibrating strings, but the frame of the Instrument adds
much to the <hi>Sound:</hi> for such strings vibrating upon a flat
rough board would yield but a faint and pitifull <hi>Sound.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:106827:9"/>
The help that Instruments give to the <hi>Sound,</hi> is by reason
that their sides tremble and comply with any <hi>Sound,</hi> and
strike the Air in the same measure that the vibrations of the
<hi>Musick</hi> are, and so considerably increase the <hi>Sound.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This trembling is chiefly occasioned by the continuity of
the sides of the Instrument with the vibrating string: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
if the bridge of a <hi>Violin</hi> be loaded with lead, the <hi>Sound</hi>
will be damp; and if there be not a stick called the <hi>Sound-post</hi>
to promote the continuity between the back and belly
of the Instrument, the <hi>Sound</hi> will not be brisk and spright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p>Such a continuity to the nerve of hearing will cause a
sense of <hi>Sound</hi> to a man that hath stopped his ears, if he
will hold a stick that touches the sounding Instrument be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
his teeth.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sound</hi> of it self without such continuity would oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion
some trembling, as may be seen by the moving the
<hi>Vnison</hi> strings in the Instance before given; but this is not
considerable in respect of the other, though it be all the as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance
that the structure of a Chamber can give to <hi>Musick,</hi>
except what is by way of Eccho.</p>
            <p>This tremble of the Instrument changes with every new
<hi>Sound;</hi> the spring of the sides of the Instrument standing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different
to take any measure, receives a new impression:
but a vibrating string can take no measure but according to
its tension.</p>
            <p>Therefore Instruments that have nothing to stop the
<hi>sounding</hi> strings make an intolerable jangle to one that stands
near, as Bells to one that is in the Steeple, and hears the
continuing <hi>Sound</hi> of dissonant <hi>Tones;</hi> such is the <hi>Dulci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer:</hi>
but the <hi>Harpsechord</hi> that hath raggs upon the <hi>jacks</hi> by
which the vibration of the string is staid, gives no distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance
by the sonorousness of the Instrument, for that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues
not the <hi>Sound</hi> after the vibrations determined, and
another <hi>Tone</hi> struck, but changes and complies with the
new <hi>Sound.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:106827:9"/>
            <head>Of the varying and breaking of TONES.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>TOnes</hi> will by accident vary and break into other <hi>Tones,</hi>
which are Chords to the natural <hi>Tone</hi> of the Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
which in Pipes is so regular, that the compass of the
<hi>Musick</hi> depends upon it; upon Strings it will happen, but
not so gratefull to the ear, nor much in use. I will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
to explain how it is caused in Strings, and speak of
Pipes afterwards.</p>
            <p>A perfect string produces a clear <hi>Sound</hi> by entire and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall
vibrations, there being no inequality to hinder the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
from being uniform from one end to the other, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to the Laws of a <hi>Pendulum:</hi> but if the string hath any
inequality towards one end, it will yield a jarring and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracted
<hi>Sound;</hi> for the resistances are not only at the ends
of the string, but there are cross <hi>tugges</hi> that alter the course
of the vibrations; which is evident in the manner where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<hi>Musicians</hi> try if their strings be true: for if the string
be true the vibrations will appear as a clear filme; but they
will appear with cross threads if the string be false.</p>
            <p>If there be a long string <hi>Pendulum,</hi> the motion will be
uniform and synchronous from the bottom to the top: but
if there be a weight fastned to the string towards the top,
it will hinder the regularity of the motion; for the upper
weight will be put into motion, and will have vibrations
of its own, which will be mixed and confounded with the
vibrations of the lower weight. In the same manner in a
false string two or more sorts of vibrations are blended,
which are not in proportion, but casual and discording,
and therefore instead of a <hi>Tone</hi> produce an horrible
jarr.</p>
            <p>Now as a string by such small accidents is brought to
vibrations of several parts of the string that hold no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion
one to another, much more easily may it be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined
to have vibrations of uniform parts, that shall be syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chronous,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106827:10"/>
and produce one single <hi>Sound,</hi> as if the parts that
vibrate severally are half parts, seconds or thirds of the
string: and how this may be caused, I will enquire.</p>
            <p>If a string <hi>Pendulum</hi> be very long, and the weight at
bottom be not sufficient to cause the whole string to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide
the Air; at first the <hi>Pendulum</hi> will be sustained by the
resistance of the Air, and afterwards it will put the whole
string into motion: but not that of a streight line, for the
<hi>Pendulum</hi> will return before the direct motion performed
at the top.</p>
            <p>This will occasion thwarting of motions, which being
balanced between the force at the bottom and the check
at the top, the crossing point will settle in such a division
of the string, that they will continue uniform till the force
be spent.</p>
            <p>I imagine, that if a musical string be so struck, that the
whole string is not removed out of its place to cause the
greatest vibration in the middle, there must be a crossing
of vibrations: for before the motion communicated to the
farther end, the part of the string that was struck may have
restored it self to its first place. This crossing of vibrations,
if the string be true, will be upon equall parts, and produce
an Octave fifth, or some other Chord.</p>
            <p>It is common experience, that a great string struck near
the Bridge with a Bow where the Rosin takes but small
hold, will whistle and break into chords above; which if it
were struck by the thumb that removes it out of its place,
would give the true <hi>Tone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Trumpet marine</hi> that sounds wholly upon such breaks,
is a large and long monochord play'd on by a Bow near the
end, which causes the string to break into shrill Notes. The
removing the thumb that stops upon the string gives mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
to these breaks, and consequently directs the <hi>Tone</hi> to
be produced. The jarr at the Bridge takes the same measure
and makes the <hi>Sound</hi> loud, in imitation of a <hi>Trumpet,</hi> which
otherwise would be like a <hi>Whistle</hi> or <hi>Pipe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:106827:10"/>
The touch of the Thumb less hinders the <hi>Sound</hi> of the
string when it is upon the point where the vibrations cross,
than when it is in any other part: for we see when any great
string has an entire vibration, such a touch would imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately
extinguish the <hi>Sound.</hi> This makes the <hi>Trumpet Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine,</hi>
with the Thumb placed upon it, take to such a Note,
as that the division of vibrations shall lye just under the
Thumb.</p>
            <p>Speaking of the counterfeit <hi>Trumpet,</hi> I must observe that
the true one seems to give all its Notes by way of breaking,
which causing the metal to jarr gives so loud a sound. I
fancy the true gage of the Air included in a <hi>Trumpet,</hi> in
comparison of its bore would fit an eight below the Note
they call the Note of the <hi>Trumpet,</hi> because a fourth below
it is so easily sounded, which is a fifth to the true <hi>Tone,</hi> in
case it be placed eight Notes lower: As it easily divides in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
three to give a fifth, so it may well treble that division,
and give a second to the <hi>Trumpet</hi> Note. And for the rest of
the Notes which a <hi>Trumpet</hi> will easily produce, they are the
third <g ref="char:sharp2">♯</g>, fourth, fifth and sixth sharp, which arise upon the
most easie divisions of the monochord, and therefore most
readily produced by breaking, when the strength of the
blast and the action of the lips direct it. The <hi>Trumpet</hi> not
being able to answer a flat Key, the <hi>Sackbut</hi> as I observed
before is made in such manner that it may be lengthned to
supply this defect, whereby it will give any Note at the
pleasure of him that plays: but when he is to <hi>Sound</hi> an eighth
or fifth above, he never lengthens the Instrument, for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
any remove of his hand, the Note easily breaks into
those higher Chords.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Trumpet</hi> is of the nature of <hi>Pipes,</hi> and therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly
leads me to speak of the varying Notes upon <hi>Pipes,</hi>
which is so regular, and so much in use, that the compass of
the <hi>Musick</hi> depends upon it.</p>
            <p>I have shewed that <hi>Sound</hi> does cause a motion not only
of solid bodies, but of the grosser parts of Air within the
sphere of it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:106827:11"/>
Now if the Air that is moved by being inclosed stands
upon such a degree of resistance to compression, that it has
a spring vibrating in the same measure with the sound that
puts it into motion, there will be the same effect as when two
strings are tuned in unison, that is, the motion will be so
augmented by succeeding regular pulses, that the enclosed
Air may be brought to ring and produce a <hi>Tone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vitruvius</hi> in his <hi>Architecture</hi> advises, that in making a
<hi>Theatre</hi> there should be vases or hollow pots of several sizes
to answer all the Notes of <hi>Musick</hi> placed upon the Stage in
such manner, that the Voice of them which sang upon the
Stage might be augmented by the ringing of them: And
he mentions divers ancient <hi>Theatres</hi> where such were, in
some of <hi>Brass,</hi> in some of <hi>Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An <hi>Organ-pipe</hi> of a very deep <hi>Base</hi> will not speak sudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
when it is alone; but if an <hi>Octave</hi> be in play at the same
time, it will answer the quickest touch: because the <hi>Tone</hi> of
the lesser Pipe being in chord causes a motion of the Air in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded
in the greater Pipe, and the vibrations of the inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
Air being coincident with those of the <hi>Tone</hi> of the Pipe,
promote its speaking by putting the pulses at the mouth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
a regular motion, or at lest assisting thereto.</p>
            <p>These instances shew the manifest effects of <hi>Sound:</hi> and
certainly <hi>Sounds</hi> in discord are in contrariety, and offer
violence one to another; but <hi>Sounds</hi> in <hi>Musical Chords</hi> are
consistent, and united together, and promote each other, as
I have before shewn in what I said concerning the Relation
of <hi>Tones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The synchronous motion of the pulses at the mouth of the
Pipe with the vibrations of the included Air promote the
<hi>Sound</hi> of the Pipe, and it is hard for a Pipe to speak where
those motions are in opposition: but if by strengthning the
blast the pulses at the mouth are so quickned that they bear
a <hi>Musical</hi> proportion to the vibration of the Air enclosed,
as 2 to 1, 3 to 2, 4 to 3, 5 to 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> there will be no hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance
but some advantage; so that it may be easily imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106827:11"/>
that the pulses at the mouth in such case will receive no
interruption by the included Air, but may maintain their
stations, and produce a <hi>Tone</hi> varying in the same proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
from the <hi>Tone</hi> of the Pipe.</p>
            <p>It may be objected, that if it were so, there would be a
mixture of <hi>Sounds;</hi> and not only the <hi>Tone</hi> that is in chord to
the <hi>Tone</hi> of the Pipe would be heard, but also the <hi>Tone</hi> of
the Pipe with it.</p>
            <p>To which it may be answered, that the vibration of the
included Air is not so considerable as to be heard distinctly,
though it may give alteration to a <hi>Sound;</hi> as we see, that
when a Pipe gives the true <hi>Tone,</hi> it speaks more in the belly
than when it breaks into an Octave. But to wave that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer,
perhaps when the Note breaks, the column of inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
Air divides into proportionable parts, by reason that
the vibrating force at the mouth, and the resistance at the
aperture meet one another in the middle, or upon other
divisions, which will make the vibrations of the included
Air coincident with every pulse at the mouth of the Pipe:
which is the more probable, because a very small aperture
in the middle of a Pipe will make it break into an eighth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove,
which seems not to happen by any diminution of
the included Air, but interrupting the intireness of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumn.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <head>Of the nature of Keys in MUSICK, and
of a single TUNE.</head>
            <p>BEfore any Note struck the Ear is indifferent to all <hi>sounds,</hi>
but when any <hi>Tone</hi> is heard, that indifferency is deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined,
and the mind taken up with the present <hi>sound.</hi> If
the second Note be not of relation to the first, the impers<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
made by the first will be wholly obliterated and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten,
the <hi>sounds</hi> will be disjoynted and incoherent: But
if the second Note be of relation to the first, it is confistent
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106827:12"/>
with the memory of the first: if the third Note be more in
chord to the first, then is that remembrance continued and
strengthned: if succeeding Notes are in discord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or of less
relation to the Key Note, the mind and fancy is drawn from
the Key Note by the present <hi>Sound;</hi> but by repeating the
Key Note and its relatives with loudness and emphasis, the
memory of the Key Note may be restored again.</p>
            <p>Thus in passing to and from the Key, by Notes that have
relation to the preceding Notes may a Tune proceed to any
length, and amuse the hearer: but when the fifth, which is
the principal chord to the Key, and most strengthens the
memory of it, comes in play, nothing can be more perfect and
satisfie expectation but the Key Note it self, which gives a
perfect acquiescence to the hearer, and a conclusion to the
Tune.</p>
            <p>For this reason all Tunes end in the Key Note, and the
next preceding Note is the fifth above.</p>
            <p>In the progress of a long Tune other Notes may gain so
great impression in the mind by dwelling upon the relatives
to them, that the first Key may be forgotten, and the same
way new Notes may gain possession, so that the Key may
change many times. Thus it is in long Fancies and Preludes,
and it is no matter in such case what Key the Tune con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes
in: but in short Airy Tunes there are but small di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressions,
leaning to the fifth or third, or other relative
Notes, and sometimes suddenly closing upon them, which
does not destroy the memory of the first Key Note, and
therefore the Ear is not satisfied with such close, but expects
another strain, which ending in the Key Note concludes the
Song.</p>
            <p>Generally speaking, a Tune must begin and conclude in
the Key Note, because that Note takes possession of the
Ear; but this is not such a Rule but that sometimes a Tune
begins or ends upon Notes relative to the Key; and the Key
is shown by them, though it be not struck: as in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress
of a Tune the Key is to be traced by the relatives to it,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106827:12"/>
as well as by the Note it self: Hereby it appears that any
Note may be the Key Note, as to the pitch: As to the species
or sorts of Keys they are two, <hi>viz.</hi> Flat and Sharp.</p>
            <p>When a Tune begins with a Flat third it must continue
so; for the third being a relative to the Key Note, is joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
with the memory of it, and become as it were part of it,
and a third Sharp being discord to it would disjoynt the
Tune, though it be a better chord to the Key Note; it
being necessary that the Tune should proceed with regard
to the preceding Notes: for the same reason a third Sharp
when once taken into play must be continued.</p>
            <p>When the third is Flat or Sharp the sixth must be so like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise,
else the third to the Key which is of principal regard
and relation to the Key, and sometimes hath closes upon it,
will have neither a fourth above, nor a fifth below in the
Scale, but a false fifth, which could not set it off in that lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stre
it ought to have.</p>
            <p>There is no natural difference betwixt the Musick in one
Key Note or another; accidental differences there are: for
in some Keys the emphatical Notes lying high are more
sprightly than in others. Upon some Instruments, by reason
of holdings, or open strings the emphatical Notes are of a
mellow and durable <hi>Sound,</hi> which gives advantage to the
Key. Upon most Instruments the emphatical Notes are not
in Tune, by reason of the Schismes of <hi>Musick,</hi> (whereof I
am presently to speak) therefore such Keys are not in use,
and when play'd upon yield but a harsh Tune. But these
differences are but accidental, and relating to the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages
or imperfections of Instruments.</p>
            <p>I shall collect from what hath been said, That the <hi>Musick</hi>
of a single Tune consists in the succeeding Notes having a
due relation to the preceding, and carrying their proper em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phasis
by length, loudness and repetition, with variety that
may be agreeable to the hearer. This is called the forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
of a single part, wherein <hi>Musick</hi> is so copious, that it
has afforded to every Age and Nation a several fashion,
and to every <hi>Musician</hi> a particular stile.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:106827:13"/>
Graces in <hi>Musick</hi> depend upon the same reason with the
formality of a single Tune, and skilfully applyed do much
advance it, by strengthning the memory of preceding, and
the expectation of succeeding Notes, the doing whereof is
left to every Player.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <head>Of SCHISMES, and the Scale
of MUSICK.</head>
            <p>THere are <hi>Schismes</hi> in <hi>Musick,</hi> because the Scale is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally
fitted to one Key; and though it will indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently
serve to some others, yet it will not to all.</p>
            <p>The Scale of <hi>Musick</hi> is not set out by any determinate
quantities of whole Notes or half Notes, though the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees
are commonly so called; but the degrees in the Scale
of <hi>Musick</hi> are fixed by the Ear in those places, where the
pulses of the <hi>Tones</hi> are coincident, without any regard to the
quantity. I shall endeavour to show how all the Notes
come into the Scale by their relation and dignities; and then
it will be obvious why for easiness of instruction and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience
the Scale of degrees of <hi>Musick</hi> is made as the <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicians</hi>
now exhibit it.</p>
            <p>The Key Note being given, the first Note in dignity is
the fifth above, which must have its true place; for whilst
the Tune is in the Key, it has the greatest emphasis; and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
any digression from the Key, this Note is nearest to usurp
it: and therefore when the Chords to the Key Note are
placed, the Chords to this Note are to begarded, for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
them there cannot be any variety, this being the first
step from the Key.</p>
            <p>The other Chords to the Key are the third ♭ and <g ref="char:sharp2">♯</g>, the
fourth and the sixth ♭ and <g ref="char:sharp2">♯</g>.</p>
            <p>The Chords to the fifth above the Key are the 5/2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>, and 3/7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ♭
and <g ref="char:sharp2">♯</g>, which are the fifth and third ♭ and <g ref="char:sharp2">♯</g> to that Note.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:106827:13"/>
When the fifth has usurped the Key, the fifth above that
must have the same emphasis, and will bring in the sharp
fourth, or false fifth, which is its third sharp.</p>
            <p>The half Note above the Key is farthest from the Keys
relatives, and therefore the <hi>Sound</hi> of it removes the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
of the Key Note farther off than any other; the near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est
way of bringing it in request is when the fifth below has
usurped the Key, to which it is a sixth flat: The fifth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
taking the Key makes an ingratefull remove, for it is
not a Chord comprehended in the Key Note, but the Key
Note is comprehended in that, and so it diminishes the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
to the Key Note more than any other, making the
transition to the Key Note, not as a restitution, but as a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression
to a secondary Key, which should not continue.</p>
            <p>These are all the Notes of the Scale within the compass
of an Octave, and by this method should they be Tuned,
<hi>viz.</hi> Third ♭ and third <g ref="char:sharp2">♯</g>, fourth, fifth, sixth ♭, and sixth <g ref="char:sharp2">♯</g>,
by the Key Note, second and seventh ♭, and seventh <g ref="char:sharp2">♯</g> by
the fifth above the Key or its Octave; false fifth or fourth
<g ref="char:sharp2">♯</g> must be third <g ref="char:sharp2">♯</g> to the second, and the ½ Note above
the Key must be a sixth ♭ to the fifth below the Key.</p>
            <p>An Instrument thus tuned will be exact to that one Key,
and serve to play Tunes in that Key; but when the <hi>Musick</hi>
turns to other Keys that are not relative to it, the divisions
and degrees that fitted the first Key will not sute with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
but must be removed, and thereby the <hi>Schismes</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear,
without which the Notes which ought to be princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal
and most perfect Chords to the new Key, will be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festly
out of Tune.</p>
            <p>This will best appear upon view of the division of the
Monochord, which I have set down in the plainest manner
I could frame.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:106827:14"/>
               <table>
                  <head>A Monochord.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>540</cell>
                     <cell>fourth below</cell>
                     <cell>360</cell>
                     <cell>second</cell>
                     <cell>270</cell>
                     <cell>180</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>fifth below</cell>
                     <cell>480</cell>
                     <cell>Key</cell>
                     <cell>320</cell>
                     <cell>fourth</cell>
                     <cell>Octave.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>The Key Note is 360, whose division gives all the Chords.</p>
            <p>The fourth below is 480, whose division gives the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and second.</p>
            <p>The 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> below is 540, whose flat 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> is the half Note above the Key.</p>
            <p>The second is 320, whose third sharp is the false fifth.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>The Divisions appear thus:</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3/8 of 540 = 202 ½ half note above the Key</cell>
                     <cell cols="2">Semitone is 22 1/<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>sc.</hi> 360/16th part of the string.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>480/3 = 160 the second above the Key</cell>
                     <cell>Semitone is 17 ½ <hi>sc.</hi> 3371/1922/7</cell>
                     <cell>tone is 40 <hi>sc.</hi> 360/9th p<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, of the string.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>360/6 = 60 the third flat</cell>
                     <cell>Semitone 20 <hi>sc.</hi> 320/16th part of the string</cell>
                     <cell rows="2">tone is 32 <hi>sc.</hi> 320/10th p<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>360/5 = 72 the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> sharp</cell>
                     <cell>Semitone 12 <hi>sc.</hi> 360/25th part of the string</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>360/4 = 90 the fourth</cell>
                     <cell>Semitone is 18 <hi>sc.</hi> 288/16th part of the string</cell>
                     <cell>tone is 30 <hi>sc.</hi> 300/10th p<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>404 320/5 = 104 the false fifth</cell>
                     <cell>Semitone is 14 <hi>sc.</hi> 2707/192ths of the string</cell>
                     <cell>tone is 32 <hi>sc.</hi> 288/9th p<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>360/3 = 120 the fifth</cell>
                     <cell>Semitone is 16 <hi>sc.</hi> 256/16th part of the string</cell>
                     <cell>tone is 30 <hi>sc.</hi> 270/9th p<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3/8 of 360 = 135 the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> flat</cell>
                     <cell>Semitone is 15 <hi>sc.</hi> 240/16th p<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of the string</cell>
                     <cell rows="2">tone is 24 <hi>sc.</hi> 240/10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2/5 of 360=144 the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> sharp</cell>
                     <cell>Semitone is 9 <hi>sc.</hi> 225/25th p<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of the string</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>480/5 = 96 seventh sharp below</cell>
                     <cell>semitone below the Key is 24 sc. 384/16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> part of the string</cell>
                     <cell>tone is 40 sc. 400/10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>480/6 = 80 seventh flat below</cell>
                     <cell>Semitone is 16 <hi>sc.</hi> 400/25th part of the string</cell>
                     <cell rows="2">tone is 24 216/9th</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Semitone betwixt sixth sharp above seventh flat is</cell>
                     <cell>16 <hi>sc.</hi> 216/13 ½ p<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of the string</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>Which is better represented to the view by the following Scheme, being an Octave
divided into Semitones, the whole string being 360.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>places of the Semitones</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>22 1/2</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>60</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>72</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>90</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>104</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>120</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>135</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>144</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>160</cell>
                     <cell>168</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>180</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>quantity of the several semitones</cell>
                     <cell>22 1/2</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>17 1/2</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>what proportionable part of the string each semitone takes up</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>19 2/7</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>19 2/7</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>13 1/2</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>what part of the string each tone takes up</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>flat Key</cell>
                     <cell>A la mi re</cell>
                     <cell>B fa b mi</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>C sol fa ut</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Da la sol</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>E la mi</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>F fa ut</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>G sol re ut</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>A la mi re</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The degrees of an Octave in a flat Key.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>sharp Key</cell>
                     <cell>C fa ut</cell>
                     <cell>D sol re</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>E la mi</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>F fa ut</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>G sol re ut</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>A la mi re</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>B fa b mi</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>C sol fa ut</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>1<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>1<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>1<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:106827:14"/>
By these divisions it appears, that the Tone above the
Key, and that between the fourth and fifth, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
the sixth and seventh, whether flat or sharp, are ninths
of the string, which is called the <hi>Tone Major;</hi> the other
<hi>Tones</hi> are tenths of the String, and the natural <hi>Semitones</hi> are
sixteenths.</p>
            <p>Other <hi>Semitones</hi> which are placed in the Scale, by the
Rules before mentioned have other porportions, because
neither <hi>Tone Major</hi> nor <hi>Tone Minor</hi> can he divided into
sixteenths: therefore if one <hi>Semitone</hi> be a sixteenth in a
<hi>Tone Major,</hi> the other will be 19 2/7, and if one <hi>Semitone</hi> be
a sixteenth in a <hi>Tone Minor,</hi> the other will be a 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, which
is the <hi>Somitone</hi> that naturally lies between a third ♭, and a
third <g ref="char:sharp2">♯</g>. If a <hi>Tone Minor</hi> be so divided, that one <hi>Semitone</hi>
is 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of the string, the other will be 13 1/2.</p>
            <p>These unequall <hi>Tones</hi> and <hi>Semitones</hi> having their proper
places in relation to the Key Note must needs produce
Schismes upon displacing the Key Note. I shall give one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance:
Suppose the Key Note a <hi>Tone</hi> lower, which is at 400
upon the Monochord in the first Scheme, then by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
Scale the fifth should fall upon the fourth to the former
Key, which is 270, but by the division of the Monochord
400/3 produces 133 ⅓, whose complement is 266 ⅔, so that the
Schisme there is three and ⅓, which makes a vast difference,
and is occasioned, because, whereas there should be two
<hi>Tones Major,</hi> one <hi>Tone Minor,</hi> and a <hi>Semitone</hi> to make a
perfect fifth; this consists of two <hi>Tones Minor,</hi> one <hi>Tone
Major,</hi> and a <hi>Semitone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It will be easie, by turning the <hi>Octave Line</hi> divided into
<hi>Semitones</hi> into a <hi>Circle,</hi> and supposing the Key Note upon
other <hi>Semitones,</hi> to find the differences of the <hi>Tones</hi> and <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitones,</hi>
that lye in order above it, from what they are in
relation to the true Key Note, which will show more gross
Disproportions or Schismes.</p>
            <p>Quarter Notes have been invented, which placed in those
parts where these Schismes are the greatest, make the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument
<pb facs="tcp:106827:15"/>
serve those Keys to which otherwise it would not
be in tune. <hi>Organs</hi> and <hi>Harpsechords</hi> that have no quarter
Notes are tuned with allowances, so that there is but one
perfect fifth in the compass of an Octave, the rest bear on
the one hand or the other, and so are indifferently well in
tune to all Keys, but exactly in tune to none.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Harpes, Lutes,</hi> and <hi>Lyra Viols,</hi> that are tuned to a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
Key, will be well in tune without any regard to
this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pipes</hi> may be helped by the strength of the blast, and fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
Instruments by a favourable stopping.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Violin</hi> has a great advantage by not being confined
to frets: but above all, the Voice is most excellent, because
it is not any way confined, but carried by the ear to those
degrees which make exact Harmony.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <head>Of MUSICK consisting of several
Parts in Consort.</head>
            <p>MVsick <hi>in Consort consists of</hi> Harmony, Formality <hi>and</hi>
Conformity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Harmony</hi> is the gratefull sound produced by the joyning
of several <hi>Tones</hi> in Chord one to another.</p>
            <p>I shewed before, that <hi>Tones</hi> in Chord one to another will
joyn and give one entire sound, whereas discording <hi>Tones</hi>
will jar; and also that some Chords were more perfect than
other, according as the coincidence of their pulses was more
frequent: It will be proper here to say something concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the several natures of the Chords in conjunction, and
the qualities of conjunct sounds.</p>
            <p>In all conjunct sounds the Base is according to its name
the foundation, and all the upper Chords are gratefull as
they have relation to that, because it comprehends all the
rest, and its pulses are according to Nature bigger and
<pb facs="tcp:106827:15"/>
stronger than those of the other parts, and so of more effect
to maintain the coincidence; and for this reason, where a
Tune begins with conjunct sounds, the Base is always the
Key Note.</p>
            <p>Octaves as I have shewed before do not at all alter the
sound, but only swell and fill it: for the sound has its qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
from the terms of the interstices between the pulses;
which if they are larger makes the sound more grave, if
they be less, the sound is more acute: Now as in Division,
the mode of the time is never alter'd by doubling the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
of Notes in the same space of time, but the mind or
memory couples them and comprehends them in the same
space as if they were whole Notes; so is it by Octaves, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
they increase by duplication of the pulses, in the same
space of time it produces no alteration of the sound: And
though there be Octaves above which are more acute, and
Octaves below which are more grave, so that they differ
from unisons; yet as to appearance they are the same, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect
of such difference as there is between other sounds; as
if a man looks upon a Dye with the naked eye, and after
should look upon it with a magnifying glass, though it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears
bigger, yet by the figure and scituation he judges it
the same.</p>
            <p>Therefore the <hi>Musick</hi> is not changed but filled by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
Octaves above the upper parts: but Octaves below the
upper parts that should come below the Base, would change
the <hi>Musick,</hi> by changing the foundation and basis of it, to
which all the Chords would have other relations than they
had to the former.</p>
            <p>A fifth is the principal Chord (for the Octave cannot
properly be called a Chord) in which there is an acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>escence;
there being no other sound to which it can change
to a more grateful one, and therefore is allowed in the close
to fill the sound.</p>
            <p>A fourth by its coincidence of pulses should stand in the
second place, but it is not allowed in <hi>Musick,</hi> according
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106827:16"/>
to the sweetness of its sound, because its Octave below the
Base mends the Harmony so much, that it cannot be kept
out of mind, but will be desired and expected: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
a fourth is a binding Note that strongly induces a close
in the fifth below. So that a fourth is not for its sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
allowed to be a Chord by most <hi>Musicians,</hi> because it
is not stable but subservient to a change, which change is
more induced, because only a sixth can be joyned with it,
which will be a third to the fifth below, and so increases the
expectation of a change.</p>
            <p>A third sharp is a Chord so gratefull that it is allowed
in the close to fill the sound; it being in Chord to the fifth
bears it company, and its Octave to reverse would change
the <hi>Musick</hi> into a sixth flat, which is the least pleasing of all
Chords, and therefore is not at all regarded; but the mind
acquiesces in the third sharp.</p>
            <p>A third flat, nor the sixth flat nor sharp, claim not any
place in the close, because they are in discord to the third
sharp and fifth, so that both cannot be allowed, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
are preferred: but they are in the body of a Tune
very gratefull Chords that never offend the ear, nor do they
invite any change by their Octaves below the Base, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford
a stable and pleasant Harmony.</p>
            <p>I shall not speak of discording <hi>Tones</hi> which are often
conjoyned in <hi>Musick,</hi> because they are not allowed for
their own sake, but for reasons which will appear in what
I have further to say concerning Consort.</p>
            <p>Wherein the second requisite is <hi>Formality,</hi> which every
part ought to have, though not to that degree of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>santness
that is expected from a single Tune, yet in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable
degree.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:106827:16"/>
The formality of a single Tune must be exact, because the
Composer is not confined, but may follow his fancy; but in
Consort the Composer must consider the harmony of the
Parts conjunct, and therefore is not at liberty.</p>
            <p>And there are allowances which the nature of the Parts
require; the formality of the Treble must be airy and
brisk, that of the Base slow and robust, the inner parts are
generally employed to fill the <hi>Musick</hi> with Chords, and have
little curiosity of formality, except upon following a point:
but these allowances considered, an expert <hi>Musician</hi> will
give a competent share of formality and sweetness to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
part, making the Treble move in a grave pace, and the
Base rest, that the beauty of the inner parts may be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned.</p>
            <p>The third requisite of <hi>Musick</hi> in Consort is <hi>Conformity</hi>
of all the parts: as the Formality of a single part requires,
that the succeeding Notes should be agreeable to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer;
so Conformity requires that each part should have the
like tendency to the succeeding Notes.</p>
            <p>Which tendency is many times so regarded, that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
Harmony must yield to it: for if the succeeding Notes
are of great relation to the Key, and the formal way to
them in the several Parts is by discording Notes; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless
that way which gives so good expectation must not
be balked, but rather the discords will be allowed, whose
harshness is taken off by the expectation of the succeeding
Chords, and the Harmony of the following Notes is the
more welcome for the badness of the passage.</p>
            <p>Discords are allowed in <hi>Musick</hi> upon this score, and they
are also in other respects of excellent use; as when the
mind is to be carried from any particular Note, it may be
affronted by a discord; or if a Note in small esteem be to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106827:17"/>
be favoured, some other Note may come in that agrees with
that, and is discord to the rest, and so may draw the mind
to the regard of that Note which it strengthens and sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports.
Infinite other instances may be made, but my busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
being only to illustrate the Reasons I go upon, and not
to teach Rules, these shall suffice.</p>
            <p>From what I have said, it appears, that when each part
has its kind and proportion of formality, and the parts are
in Chord to the Base, and not in discord to one another,
but carry all the Chords to fill the Harmony, when they
have a like tendency to their respective succeeding Notes,
when they imitate one anothers measure; then is the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sort
compleat: for the ear is pleased with the Harmony,
and the mind is amused and entertained to observe the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
Parts how they dance to and from the Key, and
from one Key to another, how they hunt one another, and
in a manner imitate humane passions.</p>
            <p>To the end the hearer may the more indifferently ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve
the contexture of the Parts, it is necessary that they
be fairly interwoven, one Part must not cling to another,
by moving together in eighths or fifths which would draw
the attention too much: for the same reason they may not
jump into eighths, which I have heard called, hitting an
eighth in the face; but an equall hand should be held over
all the Parts, and the sweetness distributed amongst them.</p>
            <p>I will not go about to describe Excellent <hi>Musick,</hi> which
would require a <hi>Poet</hi> as well as a <hi>Musician;</hi> I am only in
the part of a <hi>Philosopher,</hi> to show what is allowable <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick,</hi>
in order to make the Reasons upon which their Rules
are founded understood.</p>
            <p>And that I have done, as it were by a glimpse, knowing
the difficulty of being exact upon such a Subject; He that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106827:17"/>
desires to be more fully informed concerning it, may have
recourse to other large Treatises that have been writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
of <hi>Musick</hi> by Authors of our own, as well as other
Nations.</p>
            <p>There are tricks in <hi>Musick,</hi> as <hi>Fugues, Points, Descant
upon plainsong Cannons,</hi> &amp;c. the former, <hi>scil. Fugues</hi>
and <hi>Points</hi> are extream delightfull, and embellish the
<hi>Musick,</hi> carrying the attendance of the mind from one
part to another, and restrain not the fancy of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poser,
but advance it.</p>
            <p>The other tricks that are more elaborate, are to teach
or shew mastery in Composing, rather than to please; for
such fetter'd <hi>Musick</hi> is alwayes worse, and the hearer
shall not observe the Art till he be told of it: it is like
Acrostick Verse, or rhithm in Plays, which shew skill
or labour, but serve not those ends for which the pieces
were designed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <head>Of TIME, or the measures of
MUSICK.</head>
            <p>AS the <hi>Musick</hi> and <hi>Harmony</hi> of <hi>Tones</hi> depends upon
the regular distance of the pulses, though the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terstices
are not perceived, nor can be measured by us:
So when the interstices are so large that they can be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured
by our sense, the observance of a regular propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of <hi>Time</hi> affords great pleasure; as in the beating
a <hi>Drum,</hi> or striking a pair of <hi>Castanets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The due observance of time is gratefull for the same
reason that I gave for the formality of a single <hi>Tune,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
the subsequent strokes are measured by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106827:18"/>
of the former, and if they do comprehend them,
or are comprehended by them, it is alike pleasant, the
mind cannot chuse but compare one with the other, and
observe when the strokes are coincident with the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory
of the former.</p>
            <p>Therefore the less the intervals are, the more grateful
is the measure, because it is easily and exactly represent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
by the memory, whereas a long space of time that
cannot be comprehended in one thought, is not retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in the memory in its exact measure, nor can abide the
comparison, the time past being alwayes shortned by so
much as it is removed from the time present.</p>
            <p>The modes of <hi>Time</hi> are very few, being only in duple
or triple proportion, and the diminishing is alwayes in
Geometrical proportion, as two, four, eight, sixteen; that
it might serve not only to the Basis of the <hi>Time,</hi> but also
to the other intermediate degrees of diminution, which
are in memory, if not in play.</p>
            <p>The triple can give two spaces to one, the duple can
give three spaces to one, and although the duple or plain
<hi>Time</hi> seems to have spaces of even length, yet there is
loudness and briskness given to every other pulse, which
makes it eminent, and alwayes happens upon coincident
strokes: this difference is between the fore-stroke and
back-stroke in <hi>Musick,</hi> where the Notes are marked to
be of an even length.</p>
            <p>These disparities of even and odd, and of two to one,
and three to one are necessary, not only where <hi>Time</hi> alone
is regarded, as in a <hi>Drum,</hi> or upon a <hi>Horn,</hi> to show the
coincident strokes; but in respect of <hi>Musick,</hi> for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
length and loudness is given to the Key Notes, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106827:18"/>
such other Notes as should bear an emphasis: and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Notes that have the short or odd foot, seem but steps
and passages to them, and indeed are so little regarded,
that whether Chord or Discord they must be taken if
they lye in the way. In the same manner, in all shaking
graces the hovering is unequal betwixt two Notes, the
advantage is given to the true Note, and the other has
but faint touches, to make preparation for that which is
to succeed.</p>
            <p>It is now time to put bounds to this Discourse, which
by reason of the Method I engaged my self in, is become
much longer than I intended; I will only add these Two
Observations:</p>
            <p>1. It appears plainly how <hi>Musick</hi> comes to be so copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous:
for considering the species of Keys, the number of
them, the variety of Chords, the allowable mixing of
Discords, the diversity of measure, it is not to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
at, that it should like Language afford to every Age,
every Nation, nay, every<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Person, particular stiles and
modes.</p>
            <p>2. It appears that <hi>Tones</hi> or <hi>Modes</hi> of <hi>Musick</hi> in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient
time could not be of other kinds than are now; for
there can be no other in Nature: therefore the great ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects
it then had, if truly related, must be imputed to the
rarity of it, and the barbarity of the People, who are not
transported with any thing after it becomes common to
them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:106827:19"/>
            <head>MISTAKES.</head>
            <p>PAge 9. l. 18. for <hi>line</hi> read <hi>time:</hi> l. 25. for <hi>fifth and fourth</hi> read
<hi>five and four.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 24. l. <hi>penult.</hi> for 5/2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>and</hi> 3/7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ♭ read 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>and</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ♭</p>
            <p>Pag. 30. l. 13. for <hi>Octave to reverse</hi> read <hi>Octave or reverse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 15. l. 12. <hi>so regular</hi> dele <hi>so.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 26. It must be observed that the <hi>Monochords</hi> are not divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
as they ought to be; the <hi>Reader</hi> therefore is to regard on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
the Figures, and not the length of the Lines.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106827:19"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
