<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Remarks on remarks, or, The Rector of Bury's sermon vindicated his charge exhibited against the dissenters for endeavouring to corrupt the word of God justified and farther confirmed : also the absurdities and notorious falsities of Mr. Owen and other pretended ministers of the Gospel are detected and expos'd / by Thomas Gipps, Rector of Bury.</title>
            <author>Gipps, Thomas, d. 1709.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 185 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-03">2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42786</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G780</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34916</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14908276</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14908276</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102854</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A42786)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102854)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1571:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Remarks on remarks, or, The Rector of Bury's sermon vindicated his charge exhibited against the dissenters for endeavouring to corrupt the word of God justified and farther confirmed : also the absurdities and notorious falsities of Mr. Owen and other pretended ministers of the Gospel are detected and expos'd / by Thomas Gipps, Rector of Bury.</title>
                  <author>Gipps, Thomas, d. 1709.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ephraim Johnston ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCVIII [1698]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [3]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Owen, James, 1654-1706. --  Remarks on a sermon, about corrupting the Word of God.</term>
               <term>Bible --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102854:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Remarks on Remarks:</hi>
OR, THE
RECTOR of <hi>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RY</hi>'s
SERMON
VINDICATED:
His CHARGE Exhibited againſt the <hi>Diſſenters</hi>
for Endeavouring to Corrupt the <hi>Word of GOD,</hi> Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
and farther Confirm'd.</p>
            <p>ALSO
The Abſurdities and Notorious Falſities of Mr. <hi>Owen,</hi> and
other pretended Miniſters of the Goſpel are detected and
expos'd.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS GIPPS,</hi> Rector of <hi>BURY.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Siquis eſt, qui dictum in ſe in clementiùs exiſtimet eſſe, ſic
existimet; ſciat Reſponſum non dictum eſſe, quia laeſit prius.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Terent. Eunuch. Prol.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed for <hi>Ephraim Johnſton,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi>
MDCXCVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:102854:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102854:2"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 1. Lin. ult. r. <hi>attack,</hi> p. 4. l. 9. for <hi>Acts</hi> read <hi>Accounts,</hi> p.
5. l. 22. r. <hi>Remarker,</hi> l. 37. r. <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> p. 8. l. 5. r. <hi>Remarker's,</hi>
l. 14. r. <hi>intolerable,</hi> p. 14. l. 32. for <hi>the</hi> r. <hi>that,</hi> p. 15. l. 13. <hi>dele?</hi> p.
21. l. 7. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, l. 23. after <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> add <hi>by,</hi> p. 27. l. 8. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
p. 30. l. 28. r. <hi>Diviſions,</hi> p. 40. l. 32. r. <hi>ſubprior,</hi> p. 41. l. 36. for
<hi>noiſing</hi> r. <hi>noſing,</hi> p. 46. l. 31. r. <hi>convivae,</hi> p. 52. l. ult. r. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oaligon.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:102854:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102854:3"/>
            <head>CHAP. I.</head>
            <p>IN theſe Parts of the Nation, for any thing I ever heard or
knew, there had been for ſome Years a perfect Peace, at
leaſt a Ceſſation of Arms between the Church of <hi>England</hi> and
the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> there was no Writing, no Publiſhing Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives,
no raiſing of the old Diſputes, nor ſo much as Preaching
againſt one another, at leaſt not in any foul and exaſperating Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner:
Our common Danger (I verily thought) and our common In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt,
like a Charm, had laid the Devil of Contention, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd
him to his own Place, never to enter in among us any more,
till Peace, Plenty and Security from Foraign Enemies ſhould (as 'tis
too apt) conjure him up again, and embroil us with new Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.
But contrary to all expectation, even when our public Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs
were at a low ebb, and whilſt we were ſtrugling with greater
Difficulties, then we could hope of a ſuddain to ſurmount, the
<hi>Peaceable Men</hi> (as they affect to be call'd) blew the Trumpet, and
when we dream'd of no ſuch Thing, aſſaulted us in our very
Camp.</p>
            <p>In the Year 1695. appear'd at <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> an Author of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious
Confidence, who, without any juſt Provocation, caus'd to
be Printed his Scurrilous Libel entituled—<hi>Notes upon the Lord Biſhop
of</hi> Salisbury's <hi>four laſt Diſcourſes,</hi> &amp;c. It is incredible how the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters</hi>
hugg'd and commended it as one of the ſweeteſt Morſels
they had ever taſted. And tho' it's ingredients were moſtly Gall
and Wormwood,<note place="margin">Ezek. 3. 3.</note> Impudence and Slander, yet <hi>was it in their Mouths
as Honey for ſweetneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By it's Title one would imagin it calculated for the <hi>Meridian</hi> of
<hi>Salisbury</hi> Dioceſs: But 'twas compos'd at <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> there beſt known,
and deſign'd to expoſe the Members of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in
thoſe Quarters. We lay at that time (as I hinted before) in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found
Peace, and had given no Occaſion for ſuch a ſudden and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing
Attach. The <hi>Notes</hi> pretend indeed to be an Anſwer to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102854:4"/>
the Biſhop's <hi>four Diſcourſes,</hi> and the Libeller plainly tells the World,
that he was induc'd to write as he did, becauſe my Lord of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisbury</hi>
had (as he ſpeaks) <hi>reflected upon the Diſſenters as Separatiſts;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Notes p. 1.</note> but
this will not (I preſume) excuſe the Authors Rudeneſs, and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies,
which he fill'd that Pamphlet with. It muſt be confeſt,
that excellent Prelate in one of his <hi>four Diſcourſes</hi> directed his Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy,
how to demean 'emſelves towards Separatiſts (meaning the
<hi>Diſſenters:)</hi> But at the ſame time he us'd 'em with all the Meekneſs
and Charity, that is due unto thoſe, who differ from us. He gives
'em no hard Words, neither purſu'd 'em with any offenſive Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage:
His buſineſs there was not to prove the Charge of Schiſm
upon them (that was taken for granted between him and his Clergy,)
but to ſhew how they were to be brought back into the Fold, and
into Unity with the Church: To which purpoſe <q>He diſtinguiſh'd
between thoſe, who ſeparated thro' Ignorance or Prepoſſeſſion,
and others whom worldly Intereſt, ungovournable Paſſions, or
ſome Evil Affections had prevail'd with to depart from our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.
The former <hi>(he ſaid)</hi> are to be dealt with, with a
great deal of Tenderneſs and Candour, are to be pitied rather
then inſulted over, they are not the Schiſmatics which St. <hi>Paul</hi>
calls <hi>Carnal:</hi> Their Ignorance will happily find the ſame Mercy
at the hand of God, as we hope our own will in other Caſes.
But the latter the Carnal Schiſmatics, being ſuch, as are gone
out from us, not upon any true Principle of Conſcience, but on
ſome carnal worldly Deſign, were to be handled more roundly,
and their Wounds lay'd open with more ſharpneſs and ſeverity.</q>
After this manner the good Biſhop wrote unto his Clergy, nor can
I recollect any thing ſaid by him, that could Exaſperate any ſober
and conſcientious <hi>Diſſenter:</hi> I am ſure the Note-maker pretended
nothing elſe, but the ſuppoſing them Separatiſts.</p>
            <p>Now by Carnal Schiſmatics, are (I reckon) to be underſtood all
tho<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, who upon any worldly Account whatever, deſert the Churches,
and joyn themſelves to the Separate Aſſemblies <hi>ex. gr.</hi> a Perſon
leaves the Parochial Communion, and runs to the Barns, induc'd
thereto thro' the reſtleſs importunity of his Wiſe an Heireſs, to
ſecure unto himſelf and Family her Eſtate, and to keep Peace at
home. This Man is the Carnal Separatiſt, St. <hi>Paul</hi> and the Biſhop
ſpeak of. His Religion is vain, it hangs on his Wife's Apron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrings
not on his own Conſcience; he abandons the Authority,
which God has given him over his Wife, and truckles to hear as
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102854:4"/>
               <hi>Adam</hi> did unto <hi>Eve.</hi> In a word, he ſuffers his Wife to uſurp
the Dominion to command him, whom ſhe ought to obey, and
to preſcribe Rules to him,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 35.</note> of whom ſhe ought to learn, and to
be inſtructed. Upon the ſame Principle ſuch a Man would turn
<hi>Mahometan,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> did Idolater. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11. 3. But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn
to the Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> and the Notes.</p>
            <p>I cannot ſee that the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> had juſt Cauſe from any thing
ſpoken in that Diſcourſe, to treat his Lordſhip and the whole Body
of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in ſo unmannerly and contemptuous a
Manner, as the Note-maker has taken the liberty to do. It had
been proper enough for any one of 'em to have endeavour'd to ſhake
off the Imputation of Schiſm, and to have faſten'd it upon us, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
he had us'd the ſame Temper of Meekneſs and Candor as my
Lord of <hi>Salisbury</hi> has done: No body then would have blam'd him.
But a Man muſt be excus'd, if, when he wants Arguments to make
good his Point, he laſhes out into down-right Railing and Billingſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate.
For the famous Note-maker has loaded us with all the
ſpightful Reflections and malitious Imputations and artful Declama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
which ill Nature, want of good Breeding, or a corrupt
Phancy could furniſh a profeſs'd <hi>Buffoon</hi> with. It is not my Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
to confirm this in Particulars, and to that end to purſue this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beller
thro' every Paragraph or Page. It ſhall ſuffice to obſerve
that he has impeach'd us expreſly as the Perſons, who have been
the Cauſe of that Deluge of <hi>Atheiſm, Socinianiſm, Popery,</hi> Lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
of <hi>Manners,</hi> ay and of the <hi>Schiſms</hi> too, which have crept in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the Church and Kingdom;<note place="margin">Notes P. 4, 8, 9.</note> and this he has done without any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Occaſion or Provocation pretended, than the Biſhop of <hi>Salis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi>'s
ſuppoſing the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> Separatiſts in his Letter to his own
Clergy; or (I may rather ſay) than the too gentle Expreſſions,
which he in vain beſtow'd upon theſe <hi>Schiſmatics,</hi> the Foxes and the
Firebrands of this Poor <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Nation,</hi> as he might more truly
have ſtyl'd 'em.</p>
            <p>A little after the 'foreſaid <hi>Libel</hi> was come to my Hand, I was
preſented with another call'd <hi>a Sermon preach'd at the Opening of a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate
Chappel by Mr.</hi> Baldwin. This Gentleman being greatly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
(I was told as much by one that heard him ſay it) with the
<hi>Note-makers</hi> admirable Performance, and declaring, that there were
a great many <hi>biting Truths</hi> in it (that is, that we of the Church of
<hi>England</hi> are all of us Promoters of <hi>Atheiſm, Socinianiſm, Popery,
Schiſm</hi> and decay of <hi>Morals</hi> in this Nation) ſuffer'd his ſaid Sermon
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102854:5"/>
to peep abroad, thinking doubtleſs with himſelf to reap ſome of
the Honour due to that mighty Undertaking of trampling underfoot
the eſtabliſh'd Church of <hi>Engl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd.</hi> I have already in another way
delivered my Mind of this Sermon of Mr. <hi>Baldwins,</hi> and perhaps
ſhall hereafter let the World ſee how weak and abſurd it was.
Here only let it be obſerv'd, that he took upon him to revile the
Church of <hi>England</hi> with <hi>Arminianiſm,</hi> and with <hi>Popery,</hi> and now
and then according to his weak Power (for he had a willing Mind)
to give us an impertinent Wipe on ſome other Acts: How juſtly
it makes no matter with ſuch Men; it ſufficeth them that they
have ſome pretence to reproach us, and Confidence enough to load
us with Calumnies.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Semper ego Auditor tantum? Nunquamne reponam,</l>
               <l>Vexatus toties Rauoi Theſeide Cod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i?</l>
            </q>
            <p>Do theſe Men in good earneſt think, after they have firſt brav'd us
and openly provok'd us with Lies and Slanders, to caſt us into a
ſleep with a doſe of <hi>Opium,</hi> to ſtop our Mouths with Maxims,
which they are not at all careful themſelves to obſerve? I mean
thoſe of having <hi>ſincere Affection to the Truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Remarks Epiſt. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic.</note> 
               <hi>Deference towards Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours,
and Charity towards Neighbours, eſpecially in a Conjuncture, whenour
Civil as well our Religious Intereſts do ſo loudly call for the Exerciſs of 'em?</hi>
To ſay nothing here of the Want of Charity, of Truth and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity
in thoſe Notes, has the Author paid due <hi>Deference</hi> to his
Superiours? If he has, why did he not own his <hi>Libel</hi> by affixing his
Name to it? At leaſt, why not the Name of the <hi>Printer?</hi> That we
might have gratify'd our Curioſity with the knowledg of ſo celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
a Writer. The matter is Plain: The Note-maker has paid ſuch
<hi>Deference</hi> to his <hi>Superiour</hi> my Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> as happily
would have coſt him dear, if he had not been <hi>Incognito.</hi> But this
is not the firſt time, that <hi>the Rulers of the People have been evil ſpoken
of</hi> by Authors, who walk the Streets in Maſquerade, and wound
their Honour behind the back.</p>
            <p>It will perhaps be ask'd, what's this to the Miniſter at <hi>Oſweſtry?</hi>
If an unknown Perſon at <hi>Mancheſter</hi> has writ a tart Book againſt
the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Party?</p>
            <p>And I alſo ask what was it to the Miniſter at <hi>Oſweſtry,</hi> if the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor
of <hi>Bury</hi> preach'd a Sermon in Vindication of the Church of
<hi>England</hi> againſt the <hi>Lancaſhire Diſſenters?</hi> But there is no great
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102854:5"/>
Myſtery in this: The Rector had in another Treatiſe diſcover'd
the Miniſters deſign'd Corruption of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> a piece of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Fraud, which ought never to be forgotten, and therefore the
Miniſter with the help of his Friends at <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> was to give
his Adverſary a Diverſion on ſome other Subject, and to patch up
his broken Credit with <hi>Remarks on the Rectors Sermon.</hi> I ſaid, <hi>with
the help of his Friends at</hi> Mancheſter, but I rather believe the <hi>Note-maker</hi>
was Principal in the <hi>Remarks.</hi> Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> is the pretended
Author of 'em, and as I ſuppoſe ſign'd 'em: Yet any one, who
reads the Miniſter at <hi>Oſwestry</hi> his other Writings, may eaſily diſcern
ſuch a different Air in the <hi>Remarks</hi> from his other undoubted Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances,
as will force him to conclude, that Mr. <hi>Omen</hi> is but the
reputed Father of this ſpurious Off-ſpring.</p>
            <p>Or what, if one ſhould gueſs the <hi>Remarks</hi> to be the Work of a
Club of Miniſters, of which he at <hi>Mancheſter</hi> was Preſident <hi>pro
tempore?</hi> This is certain that the <hi>Remarks</hi> in their way to <hi>London</hi> took
a Tour to <hi>Mancheſter;</hi> there we heard of 'em long before their
Publication, and had ſome Account of 'em alſo. There they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd
their laſt finiſhing Strokes ('tis thought) and there they were
dreſt up with all the gaudy Feathers and Embelliſhments, which
the Wit of the Party could furniſh them with. So that if one ask'd
the <hi>Remarker</hi> his Name, and he would pleaſe to return a fair An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,
he muſt ſay, <hi>my Name is</hi> Logion, <hi>for me are many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the great Queſtion is, who is this <hi>Note-maker,</hi> who from
behind the Curtain like the <hi>Heathen</hi> Prieſts delivers his <hi>Oracles?</hi>
What is <hi>his</hi> Name? Unto whom does he belong?</p>
            <p>'Tis no difficult Matter to reſolve this Knot: That he is a <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter,</hi>
no one can doubt, that he is one of that Party in <hi>Mancheſter</hi>
was once fairly acknowledg'd unto me by another, who is in their
Intereſt, and of no ſmall Reputation among them, who alſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<hi>that the Notes were but a Preface to another Work which the Author
intended to ſet forth,</hi> I ſuppoſe to the <hi>Remarks.</hi> So then this <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon's</hi>
Porch is as big as his Temple, his Preface as large as his Book,
and the mighty Work we were put in hopes of, is dwindled into a
few ſorry <hi>Remarks</hi> upon the Rectors Sermon. But we may make
yet a clearer Diſcovery of the <hi>Note-maker,</hi> if we will but conſider
that a <hi>Diſſenter</hi> within the Pariſh of <hi>Macheſter</hi> frankly own'd, that
a certain Miniſter of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> at <hi>Manchester</hi> wrote thoſe <hi>Notes.</hi>
We need no more Evidence. Only it deſerves to be obſerv'd that
the <hi>Defence of,</hi> &amp;c. (a Book ſince Publiſh'd by the Miniſter at <hi>Oſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry)</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:102854:6"/>
was ſent down not to the Author at <hi>Oſwestry,</hi> but to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
at <hi>Mancheſter</hi> to be Revis'd and Corrected, as if Mr. <hi>Owen</hi>
were not able to rectify the Miſtakes committed in the <hi>Printing</hi> his
own Book. This manifeſts a Confederacy and Correſpondence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
'em, and from hence it may be fairly gather'd, that <hi>the
Notes</hi> and <hi>the Remarks</hi> have been done in a great Meaſure by the
ſame Hand at <hi>Mancheſter.</hi> But eſpecially, when we ſee 'em ſo like
one another both in their Features and their Drapery, we cannot
ſuffer our ſelves any longer to doubt, but the <hi>Remarks</hi> were ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer'd
out at the ſame Forge, or at leaſt poliſh'd by the ſame skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
Hand, as were the <hi>Notes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But be theſe Things as they will, I thought it not improper to
give the foreſaid brief Account of the <hi>Notes on the Biſhop of</hi> S. <hi>four
Diſconrſes,</hi> if it were only to vindicate my ſelf from the common
Aſperſion, as if I were the Occaſion of the Diſturbances that are
now among us, whereas I profeſs and I hope it is already prov'd, that
the <hi>Note-maker</hi> has been the Troubler of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> 'Tis He who firſt
blew up the Coals of Diſſention, which before lay as it were Dead
in the Aſhes. Do the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> think that our Hands and our
Tongues muſt be tied, whilſt theirs are at liberty and let looſe to
purſue us in the moſt Contemptuous Manner, with all the Bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
that Malice and Rage can inſpire 'em with? Or can they hope
to lull us aſleep into Patience and <hi>Stoical Apathy,</hi> that they may
with the greater eaſe and ſecurity torment and oppreſs us? Shall
they preſcribe unto us <hi>Charity</hi> towards them, whilſt they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifully
teaſing and expoſing us? What a Maſter-piece of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious
Hypocriſy is this to ſtile themſelves <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel</hi> (of
Peace they wiſely leave out) and chalk out the way wherein we
are to walk, but in the mean time tranſgreſs it themſelves: To
bind heavy Burthens and lay them on our Shoulders and not move
'em with one of their own Fingers? In ſhort there is no colour for
their Complaints, that we write and preach Controverſies, that we
tax our Adverſaries with their Faults, that we ſet 'em forth with
ſome Zeal and Warmth: 'Tis themſelves which compel us, tho'
<hi>non vident id manticae quod à tergo eſt,</hi> they caſt their own Sins behind
their Backs. They have hitherto at moſt been paid, but in their
own Coin, and receiv'd the common Meaſure of Juſtice <hi>quid pro
quo,</hi> with this difference and advantage on our ſide, they were
the Aggreſſors, and Nature it ſelf teaches us to ſtand on our Guard,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102854:6"/>
and to protect our ſelves, whether it be by offenſive or defenſive
Weapons.</p>
            <p>It muſt then be confeſt, that the two firſt mention'd Writings,
<hi>the Notes on my Lord Biſhop of</hi> S. <hi>four Diſcourſes, and Mr.</hi> Baldwin's
<hi>Sermon at the opening of a new erected Meeting-houſe</hi> drew the Rector
into the preſent Skirmiſh, which he was unwilling to decline, leaſt
our Cauſe ſhould ſuffer by ſilence, and the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> vainly ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
they had got any Advantage of us. That Saying of the Wiſe
Man came into my thoughts—<hi>Anſwer a Fool according to his own Folly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 26. 5.</note>
               <hi>leaſt he be Wiſe in his own Conceit.</hi> I ſee no reaſon then but a Man
may be angry, and reſcent the Injuries of an Adverſary with ſome
Indignation, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> permits it, <hi>Eph. 4. 26.</hi> And <hi>Solomon</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
that—<hi>To every thing there is a Seaſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 3. 1, 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>and a time to every Purpoſe
under the Heaven,</hi> among the reſt, that there is <hi>a time to Speak, and a
time of War.</hi> And was it not high time to Speak, when we were
by the <hi>Note-maker</hi> treated with Scorn and Inſolence, and ſuch things
were laid to our Charge, which, if true, would juſtly render us o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious
to God and Man? And unworthy the Protection of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.
I thought fit therefore to make uſe of the Policy of
<hi>Scipio Africanus,</hi> to carry the War into the Enemies own Country,
and to lay unto the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> Charge a Crime, which I believe was
prov'd upon them better than <hi>Atheiſm</hi> or <hi>Socinianiſm</hi> was or can be
upon us.</p>
            <p>Hereat the two Miniſters at <hi>Oſwestry</hi> and <hi>Mancheſter</hi> grew angry,
and have made <hi>Remarks</hi> upon my <hi>Sermon:</hi> 'Tis what I look'd for,
and deſign'd, to the end the World may ſee, that theſe Sober and
Charitable Men can be intemperately Angry, when they appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend
themſelves touch'd to the quick, and therefore ought to give
others leave to be ſenſible of the Injuries firſt done 'em without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Provocation. Briefly, I am not ſurpriz'd at the <hi>Remarks,</hi> which
are fraught with ſo much Venom and Rancour. I never expected
Mercy at <hi>their</hi> Hands, who have no Mercy, no not in the Times
of Peace, and when no Occaſion is given 'em to break out into
Paſſion, who in their calmeſt Mood, when Meekneſs and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
ſeems to ſit on their Brow, and when the whole Face is in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearence
o're-ſpread with univerſal Sweetneſs and Smiles, are even
then, as I have learn'd by Experience, deſigning Miſchief in their
Hearts againſt their Neighbours, and ſecretly undermining 'em.
Upon the whole Matter, then the declamatory and popular Inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations
of the <hi>Remarks</hi> in his <hi>Ep. Dedic of want of ſincere Affection to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102854:7"/>
the Truth, of Deference to Superiours, and of Charity to Neighbours</hi> and
other like Strains againſt falſe and malicious Accuſing our Brethren,
with all the dirty ſtuff wherewith this fierce Champion of the good
old Cauſe has beſpatter'd the Rector, recoil into the <hi>Note-maker</hi> and
the <hi>Remarker</hi> own Faces, and lie heavy upon the whole Body of the
<hi>Diſſenters</hi> and ſome of the Politic and intreaguing Trimmers in and
about <hi>Mancheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in the Reply, I give unto the <hi>Remarker</hi> I will not make it
my profeſt Buſineſs like a Merry Andrew to mind little elſe than
the making Sport with my Adverſary, as he has done with me,
that's the leaſt in my thoughts: I will take care chiefly to attend
unto the Argument it ſelf, and ſee that firmly eſtabliſh'd, not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
much what becomes of the drolling and the ſcoffing Part.
Altho', if now and then, when his intollerable Abſurdities and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties
require it, I take the freedom to ſhew him his own Face in
his own Glaſs, 'tis hop'd I may merit Pardon of the Candid Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. II.</head>
            <head type="sub">Being a Reply to that Part of the Remarks which Mr.
Owen calls the Preface.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Remarker</hi> here in the Enterance, promiſes his Reader
an Idea of the Rector's Sermon, but is not as good as his word.
He has preſented us with whatever he believ'd would bear a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute,
and which he had the leaſt Colour to make a Flouriſh with
among the common People, but he has overlook'd, and neglected
the moſt conſiderable things advanc'd againſt the Exceptions of Mr.
<hi>de Laune,</hi> which he ought not to have paſt over, ſince he underſtood
that Gentleman's Defence. Inſtead then of an Idea of the Rector's
Sermon, he has preſented the Reader with a Specimen of his own
cavilling Humour. This is an hopeful beginning, when he who
is pretending to vindicate others from the Charge of diminiſhing
from the <hi>Word of God,</hi> ſtumbles at the very Threſhold, and makes
no difficulty to diminiſh from the <hi>Words</hi> of his <hi>Neighbours.</hi> If Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge
or Robbing of God be a Crime, I am ſure Burglary or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102854:7"/>
Stealing from one's Brother is no Virtue: And if the former is by
Law puniſhable without Benefit of Clergy, ſo is the latter alſo.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>de Laune</hi> (as I mention'd in my Sermon) had alledg'd againſt
our eſtabliſh'd Worſhip,<note place="margin">Serm. p. 3.</note> 
               <q>That in the <hi>Pſalms</hi> uſed in the <hi>Liturgy</hi>
are left out the Ancient <hi>Hebrew</hi> Titles, which are (ſays he) <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal</hi>
and <hi>Parts</hi> of the holy Scripture, having a Tendency towards
the unfolding the Miſterys therein contain'd. <hi>Hereunto I reply'd,</hi>
That it were well, if the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> would firſt prove, that thoſe
<hi>Hebrew</hi> Titles are <hi>Original</hi> and eſſential <hi>Parts</hi> of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</q>
This Mr. <hi>de Laune</hi> ought to have done before he ſo round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
and peremptorily challeng'd us with corrupting the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God:</hi>
But he did not ſo much as attempt it.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> has now endeavour'd to ſupply that defect, tho' at
the ſame time he profeſſes <hi>he will not enter into this Controverſy:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pref. of Remarks p. 1.</note> But
whether he will or no he's got into it before he's aware, and argues
that, <q>The Titles are as Ancient as the <hi>Pſalms</hi> themſelves for ought
appears to the contrary, they being in all the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi>
Copies, that over I have ſeen: That the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church receiv'd
'em as Parts of Scripture, and they are moſt of 'em tranſlated
by the <hi>LXX</hi> and by <hi>Theodotion Symmachus</hi> and <hi>Aquila,</hi> as alſo by
the <hi>Targumiſt:</hi> That they are received in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church as
Canonical Scripture; <hi>Jerom</hi> tranſlates them in his Verſion, and
they are in the modern Verſions: That ſome of 'em are undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably
Canonical, as that of the 18th <hi>Pſalm</hi> mention'd 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.
Others of them muſt be prefix'd by the Pen-man, or by a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
divinely inſpir'd: For they refer to paſſages of Hiſtory not
mention'd in the body of the <hi>Pſalm,</hi> &amp;c..</q> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto all which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the Subſcriptions of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> are to be found in
all the <hi>Greek</hi> Copies I have ſeen or heard of, ſave that of <hi>Claromont,</hi>
are always tranſlated and taken into our modern Verſions, and
yet the <hi>Remarker</hi> will not own them for Canonical Scripture. It does
not then hence follow, that the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Titles are eſſential Parts of
the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> no more than that the Subſcriptions are Canonical.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church receiv'd the Titles and annext them to
the <hi>Pſalms</hi> I will not diſpute: But that they receiv'd them as <hi>eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
Parts</hi> of the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> is the Queſtion, we receive the <hi>Poſtſcripts</hi> of
St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> and the very <hi>Engliſh</hi> Contents of the Chapters
of the <hi>Bibles,</hi> but we eſteem neither Canonical.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:102854:8"/>
The Subſcriptions of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Epiſtles</hi> are tranſlated into all or
moſt Languages, the <hi>Italian, Spaniſh, French,</hi> high <hi>Dutch,</hi> low
<hi>Dutch, Engliſh</hi> (and <hi>Scotch</hi> I imagin) all <hi>Christian</hi> Churches re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
'em, yet not as Canonical Scripture, but Ancient <hi>Records</hi>
affixt unto the <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> when and by whom is not known. The
like may with Reaſon be ſaid of the Titles. It muſt be confeſt,
that the Subſcriptions of the <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> are not the ſame in all the
ancient M. SS. nor in the <hi>Syriack</hi> and <hi>Arabick</hi> Verſions, from whence it
is rightly concluded; that they were not annext thereunto by any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired
Perſon: And for the very ſame reaſon I argue, that the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles
of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> are not Canonical Scripture, there being great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety
to be obſerv'd in them: If we compare the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> the <hi>Greek</hi>
and the <hi>Oriental</hi> Verſions, not two of 'em agreeing one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
in their Titles.</p>
            <p>That the Title of the 18th <hi>Pſalm</hi> is to be found 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22. is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
true: But it does not follow, that an inſpir'd Perſon affix'd it
unto the 18th <hi>Pſalm,</hi> as it now lies in the Collection of <hi>Pſalms</hi>
commonly call'd the <hi>Pſalter</hi> of <hi>David.</hi> So that thoſe words, as plac'd
before the 18. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> may in ſtrictneſs be ſaid not be to Canonical
there, tho' they be Canonical, 2 <hi>Sam. 22. Ex. gr.</hi> Mr. <hi>Delaune</hi>
has accus'd us for foiſting 3 Verſes into the <hi>14th. Pſalm,</hi> and does
therefore certainly imply, that they are not eſſential parts of that
Pſalm, tho' no body will deny 'em to be Canonical Scripture in
other Places. The like may with as good Reaſon be ſaid of the
Title of the <hi>18th. Pſalm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the other Titles were prefixed by the Pen-men, or by
ſome other Divinely inſpired Perſon (which is the Queſtion in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie)
is not prov'd from that Reaſon, <hi>ſc.</hi> becauſe <hi>the Titles refer
to Paſſages of Hiſtory not mentioned in the Body of the Pſalms.</hi> 'Tis
a great miſtake to affirm, that the Titles refer to Paſſages in Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory
not mention'd in the Body of the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> as I could eaſily
ſhew, if it were worth the while. True, there are no particular and
very obvious Expreſſions in many <hi>Pſalms,</hi> relating to the Hiſtorical
Paſſages to which the Titles refer; but there are general ones,
which gave the Collectors of the Book of <hi>Pſalms</hi> an occaſion of
affixing thoſe Titles to the <hi>Pſalms. Ex. gr.</hi> in the <hi>90th. Pſalm,</hi> tho'
<hi>Moſes and the Iſraelites are not mention'd in it,</hi> yet many Verſes of
that <hi>Pſalm,</hi> and particularly the <hi>9th.</hi> and the <hi>10th.</hi> Verſe, were
thought to allude unto the Condition of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs,
whoſe ſtubbornneſs God puniſh'd by cutting their Live<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:102854:8"/>
ſhort of what in the Courſe of Nature in thoſe days is ſuppoſed to
have been the ordinary length of Mans life. By ſuch general and
obſcurer Paſſages in the Body of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> (I do imagin) obſerving
Men were induc'd to prefix the Titles. Thus Biſhop <hi>Pearſon</hi> after
the ſame manner has with great Judgment and Curioſity fixt the
Time and the Occaſion of all the Treatiſes and Epiſtles of St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi>
grounding himſelf upon ſundry Paſſages,<note place="margin">Annals Cyprian.</note> which he obſerv'd
in them, and accordingly the time and occaſion is affixt unto the
beginning of every Epiſtle and Treatiſe in the <hi>Oxford</hi> Edition.</p>
            <p>But to return to Mr. <hi>Owen's</hi> Reaſon. <hi>The Titles</hi> (ſays he) <hi>refer to
Paſſages of Hiſtory not mention'd in the Body of the Pſalm.</hi> This is a
good Argument, (if it were true) that the Titles were not added
by the Pen-men themſelves, nor by any Divinely inſpired Perſon;
and that they are not Canonical, but the Conjectures of meer Men,
which is the Reaſon alſo (I ſuppoſe) why many <hi>Pſalms</hi> have no
Titles at all, and many none to any purpoſe at all, ſome, whoſe
Titles are grounded on very dark and doubtful Expreſſions in the
Body of the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> and ſome in the 70. have Titles, which the
<hi>Hebrew</hi> Text has not. All which variety ariſes from the ignorance,
or inobſervance of thoſe who prefixt the Titles, which would not
have happen'd, if the Titles had been added by ſome inſpir'd Perſon.</p>
            <p>Having refeli'd the Remarkers Arguments brought to prove the
Titles to be eſſential Parts of the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> I will try what may be
ſaid in proof, that they are not, at leaſt, not of a certainty, eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial
Parts of the <hi>Pſalms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt Place, then I argue, that if ſome, or if any one Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
may juſtly be queſtion'd, then this renders all the reſt ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.
That of the <hi>90th.</hi> Pſalm, <hi>A Prayer of Moſes the man of God,</hi>
ſeems not to have been added by any Divinely inſpir'd Perſon.
There are plauſible Reaſons to be given, why <hi>Moſes</hi> did not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
it. For thus the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks, <hi>ver. 10. The days of our years
are threeſcore years and ten, and if by reaſon of ſtrength, they
be fourſcore, yet is their ſtrength labour and ſorrow; for
it is ſoon cut off, and we fly away.</hi> Now the Life of Man
in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s time was much longer than ſeventy or eighty years.
<hi>Job,</hi> who was ('tis thought) contemporary with <hi>Moſes,</hi> liv'd 140
years, even after his Afflictions, and at length <hi>died being old and
full of days, (Chap. 42. 16, 17.) Levi </hi> liv'd 137 years, <hi>(Exod. 6. 16.)
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>th</hi> lived 133 years, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 18.) <hi>Amram 137. (ver. 20.) Aaron</hi>
was 123 years old when he dy'd, <hi>(Numb. 33. 39.) Joſhua</hi> dy'd
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102854:9"/>
being 110 years old <hi>(Chap. 24. 29.) Miriam</hi> according to <hi>Iſaaeſon,</hi>
(ſee <hi>Numb. 20. 1.)</hi> was 129 years old. <hi>Caleb 85. (Joſh. 147. 10.)</hi>
and was alive, <hi>(Judg. 1. 15.)</hi> And <hi>Jethro, (Heb 11. 24 Exod. 2.
11,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Act. 7. 23. Exod. 7. 7. Chap. 18.)</hi> muſt needs have been
an 100 years old and upwards. Yea, <hi>Ehud</hi> the Judge an Age or
more after <hi>Joſhua</hi> lived to be above 100 years old, having go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd
the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> eighty years, <hi>(Judg. 3. 39.)</hi> But above all, this
<hi>Moſes,</hi> the <hi>Man of God,</hi> the ſuppos'd Pen-man of this <hi>Pſalm,</hi> was
eighty years old when he was ſent unto <hi>Pharaoh (Act. 7. 23, 30.)</hi>
This muſt be before he could Pen the <hi>Pſalm:</hi> He afterwards at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd
unto the <hi>120th.</hi> year, and then dy'd: <hi>His Eyes were not dim,
nor his natural force abated,</hi> Deut. 34. 7. It is not then likely that
<hi>Moſes</hi> was the Author of this <hi>Pſalm,</hi> becauſe the Body of the <hi>Pſalm</hi>
does not at all agree with the times, wherein that Man of God
flouriſh'd, and himſelf had no occaſion of complaining of the
ſhortneſs and labour, and ſorrow of <hi>our</hi> days, including himſelf.
It muſt be confeſt, that this point is bandy'd by Learned Men, and
ſundry Anſwers are offer'd to the Arguments produc'd, which I
will not trouble the Reader with, only let it be conſider'd, that
ſeveral Authors in Mr. <hi>Pool</hi>'s <hi>Synopſis</hi> deliver their Opinion very
cautiouſly,<note place="margin">Argum. ad Pſal. 90.</note> 
               <hi>Veri ſimile eſt Moſem hunc Pſalmum compoſuiſſe,</hi> ſay they.
'Tis but likely then at moſt. I add, <hi>Greg. Nyſſen</hi> reckons this
<hi>Pſalm</hi> among thoſe which had no Title according to the <hi>Jews.</hi> And
<hi>Baſil</hi> ſays, <hi>David</hi> wrote it, and adds, that it wants an Inſcription,
tho' he himſelf gives it one. Of the 91. <hi>Pſalm</hi> likewiſe he notes
that it had obtain'd a <hi>right Inſcription,</hi> implying that Inſcriptions
were Human Additions.</p>
            <p>I'll produce one other Inſtance. 'Tis the Title of the 34. <hi>Pſal.
A Pſalm of David, when he changed his behaviour before Abimelech, who
drove him away and he departed.</hi> The King of <hi>Gath</hi> here meant is
call'd <hi>Achiſh, 1 Sam. 21. 10.</hi> and not <hi>Abimelech,</hi> from whence the
Truth of this Title may be doubted. We are told indeed that <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech</hi>
was a common Name of the Kings of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> as <hi>Caeſar</hi>
and <hi>Auguſtus</hi> were of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors. But I am not ſatisfy'd
with this. For I read but of one, at moſt two Succeſſive <hi>Philiſtine</hi>
Kings of that name, <hi>Gen. 20. 2. Chap. 26. 8.</hi> Kings of <hi>Gerar.</hi> This
was in <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s days. But to fancy that the name of <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech</hi>
was continu'd among the <hi>Philiſtine</hi> Kings unto) the days of
<hi>David</hi> about 800 years is not very likely, we meeting not with
any one King ſo call'd in all that interval of time, ſave one of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102854:9"/>
Kings of <hi>Iſrael, Judg. 9. 6.</hi> who had no other name beſides. Nor
is the <hi>Achiſh</hi> King of <hi>Gath</hi> any where call'd <hi>Abimelech,</hi> except in
this Title. Now that which might give occaſion unto this miſtake
in the Title of his Pſalm was, that in the ſaid firſt of <hi>Sam. 21.</hi>
there it mentior made of <hi>Ahimelech</hi> the High Prieſt of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi>
whoſe Congreſs with <hi>David</hi> takes up the nine firſt Verſes of that
Chapter, and may with ſome appearance of Reaſon therefore be
ſaid to have occaſioned that Error in the Title of putting <hi>Ahime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech</hi>
for <hi>Achiſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the Book of Pſalms has receiv'd ſome humane Additions
may be argu'd from thoſe words rack'd to the 72. Pſalm, at the
end, <hi>The Prayers of David the Son of Jeſs are ended,</hi> which is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly
falſe, if the Titles of the Pſalms are true, there being very
many Prayers of <hi>David,</hi> which follow in this Book of Pſalms.</p>
            <p>If any ſtreſs ſhould be laid upon the Diſtinction between Prayers
and Pſalms, I reply that the 142. Pſalm is call'd <hi>a Prayer of David;</hi>
and the Original word is the ſame in both, <hi>ſc.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
differing only in number. Beſides the Pſalms that follow the 72
are as truly Prayers as they which go before it. Some body then
not inſpir'd has either tranſpos'd the Pſalms, or elſe added to them
the foreſaid Concluſion of the 72. Pſalm, being either miſplac'd,
or thruſt into the Text. It is not then impoſſible, but the like may
have been done at the beginning of the Pſalms by prefixing Titles
unto them.</p>
            <p>There are Titles added to very many Pſalms in the 70 Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
which are not to be met with in the <hi>Hebrew.</hi> For Example,
<hi>Pſal. 137.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Jeremy</hi> compos'd this mournful Song in the
name of the Captives at <hi>Babylon,</hi> as any one will grant, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders
the Subject matter of the Pſalm, and compares it with the
ſtate of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in <hi>Jeremiah</hi>'s time. I ask then, is this Title
Divinely inſpir'd? And yet <hi>Jerome</hi> tranſlates it, and comments
upon it, as he does upon other of the Seventy Titles.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the Oriental Verſions the <hi>Syriack</hi> and the <hi>Arabick</hi> and the
<hi>Chalde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Paraphraſe oft-times want Titles, frequently change 'em,
and ſometimes add Titles, when neither the <hi>Hebrew</hi> nor the <hi>Greek</hi>
lay claim to any at all, which could never have happen'd, if they
had been Canonical Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theodoret</hi> ſeems to believe the Inſcriptions Canonical, as being
found (ſo he ſays) in the Pſalms, when the Seventy Tranſlated 'em
into <hi>Greek.</hi> But <hi>Gregory Nyſſen</hi> who flouriſh'd half a Century be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102854:10"/>
him, obſerves, That among the Chriſtians (who uſed the
Seventy Tranſlation) ſome Pſalms have the Inſcription of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,
but not among the <hi>Hebrews;</hi> that ſometimes the firſt Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
of the Pſalm, (ſo I underſtand him) is put into the Place of
the Title both with the Chriſtians and the <hi>Jews</hi> after the manner
of our Liturgy Tranſlation; that the <hi>Jews</hi> rejected the Titles of
ſome Pſalms, which the Chriſtians receiv'd. He reckons 12 of this
kind, <hi>viz. 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 32, 42, 70, 73, 90,</hi> &amp; 103 Pſalms.
None of which (it ſhould ſeem) had at that time among the <hi>Jews</hi>
any Inſcription, tho' at this day all but the Second have. He no
where pleads for the Divine Authority of the Titles. How could
he, when there was ſuch a diſagreement between the <hi>Jews</hi> and
Chriſtians about 'em? He alſo ſpeaks, as if ſome Titles were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd
by Eccleſiaſtical Cuſtom: but 'tis hard to determine at this
time of day, which are by Divine Inſpiration, and which by
Cuſtom.</p>
            <p>From the whole ſome will be apt to conclude, that the <hi>Hebrew</hi>
Titles are not eſſential Parts of the Pſalms, but the Conjectures and
Additions of uninſpired Perſons. I for my ſhare am of that Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.
All muſt confeſs that they are not Canonical Scripture <hi>of a
certainty,</hi> which was all I inſiſted on in the Sermon; and therefore
that Mr. <hi>Delaune</hi> did unworthily, when he poſitively objected to
the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that ſhe <hi>had left out of the Pſalms ſome Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal
Parts,</hi> meaning the Titles, when 'tis <hi>not certain,</hi> that they are
Original.</p>
            <p>The Miniſter at <hi>Oſweſtry</hi> here takes fair leave of his Client, and
bids him ſhift for himſelf as well as he can, having no more to ſay
in behalf of Mr. <hi>Delaune.</hi> Only, whereas I put the queſtion, why
the Titles were not all tranſlated into plain <hi>Engliſh,</hi> if they were ſo
ſerviceable to the unfolding the Myſteries contain'd in the Pſalms,
he ſurlily tells me <hi>the Biſhops</hi> (they being the Tranſlators of the
Bible into <hi>Engliſh) could beſt reſolve the Queſtion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pref. p. 2.</note> I thank him hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
for this, and deſire the good People among the Diſſenters, to
think of it. Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> has herein done my Lords the Biſhops ſome
Juſtice before he was aware in acknowledging, that the Scriptures
being in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue is owing to their Labours, Learning
and Piety. But 'twill be objected, that they have not Tranſlated
all the Titles. True: Neither have the Diſſenters, tho' they had
power and opportunity in the Reign of the Long Parliament and
<hi>Oliver;</hi> and had more lately Liberty to do it, if twere worth the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102854:10"/>
while, and a matter of ſo great moment, as Mr. <hi>de Laune</hi> has
made the World to believe.</p>
            <p>If it might not be thought a digreſſion from my preſent purpoſe,
I would obſerve, that the Myſteries in the Pſalms (as far as I am able
to judge) are thoſe, which relate unto Jeſus Chriſt, or thoſe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally;
but there is not one Title in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> which is at all uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
to the unfolding any of theſe Myſteries. For I do profeſs that
after I am told it is <hi>a Pſalm, a Song, a Song or Pſalm, a Pſalm of
David, a Prayer of Moſes, a Pſalm at the Dedication of Davids Houſe,
a Pſalm for the Sabbath, ſent to ſuch or ſuch a chief Muſician, on what
Instrument it was to be ſung, a Golden Pſalm, a Pſalm of Inſtruction, of
Degrees,</hi> &amp;c. I am juſt as wiſe as I was before, as to the Myſteries
contain'd in ſuch Pſalms. The like I affirm of the reſt of the Titles?
'Twas therefore unfair in Mr. <hi>de Laune</hi> to bear his ignorant and
unobſerving Readers in hand, as if the Titles unfolded the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
of the Pſalms.</p>
            <p>To the other Queſtions I there put, the Miniſter returns but a
very ſorry and evaſive Anſwer, thus, <hi>They are not worth—An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However, he might methinks have diverted his Friends in and
about <hi>Mancheſter</hi> with a Jeſt or two. They would have taken it for
a ſolid Anſwer, and cry'd him up as the <hi>Jews</hi> did <hi>Herod, Act. 12.
22.</hi> But to the end the impartial Reader may ſee, that at leaſt
ſome of my Queſtions were to the purpoſe, and ought to have
been reply'd to, or elſe Mr. <hi>Delaune</hi> left in the lurch undefended,
and convict of dealing very diſhoneſtly with us, I will draw one or
two of thoſe Queſtions into the form of an Argument, and then
it will be ſeen, whether they are worth Anſwering, or whether
Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> were able to anſwer 'em, ſo as to vindicate Mr. <hi>Delaune,</hi>
or get any advantage of the Rector.</p>
            <p>Setting aſide then the Controverſie about the Titles (which I
will now ſuppoſe are Cononical Scripture of a certainty) yet Mr.
<hi>Delaune</hi> had no Reaſon to accuſe us of leaving them out of our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy
Tranſlation, which we ſing or ſay; becauſe the Diſſenters
themſelves leave 'em out of their Pſalms in Meter, nor do they
ſing 'em at their Divine Worſhip. Mr. <hi>Delaune</hi> therefore had no
room to complain of us, when the Diſſenters were guilty in the
ſame kind. It will be time enough to quarrel with us, after they
ſhall have amended their own fault. In the mean while they are ſo
much the more inexcuſable, that they have not to this day reform'd,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102854:11"/>
what they ſeem to be perſwaded is amiſs. But the Truth is, were
it never ſo manifeſt and certain, that the Titles are eſſential Parts
of the Pſalms, yet I believe neither the Church of <hi>England,</hi> nor
Mr. <hi>Delaune,</hi> nor his Vindicator, nor any wiſe Diſſenter would
think fit to adviſe the Singing them, or putting them into Meter
at the head of the Singing Pſalms. Mr. <hi>Delaune</hi>'s Exception there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
was nothing but noiſe and cavil, and impertinence, which
was the thing I deſign'd, and did effectually demonſtrate in my
Sermon. Inſtead then of ſaying my Queſtions, <hi>Are not worth An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering,</hi>
the Remarker ſhould have done me right, and his Client
no Injuſtice by confeſſing fairly, that Mr. <hi>Delaune</hi> impeach'd the
Church of <hi>England</hi> without cauſe, and that himſelf was not able to
juſtifie him. But he muſt be excus'd. His buſineſs and his
head lies another way, <hi>viz.</hi> abuſing the Rector and Bantering
the ignorant and innocent People of his own Party. He has been
ſo far from <hi>Exerciſing Charity to his Neighbours,</hi> that he has not
been juſt to any ſide, no not to himſelf. In plain terms he has be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly'd
himſelf, and pretended the contrary to what he could not but
know, <hi>ſc.</hi> that thoſe Queſtions merited an Anſwer in the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie
between Mr. <hi>Delaune</hi> and me.</p>
            <p>2. In the next place Mr. <hi>Delaune</hi> excepted againſt the Eſtabliſh'd
Church, <q>That we read ſome ſelect Portions of Scripture, commonly
call'd <hi>Epiſtles</hi> and <hi>Goſpels,</hi> and not the intire Chapters, which <hi>(ſays he)</hi>
is a curtalling and mangling the Scriptures, which thereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
quite another thing,<note place="margin">Serm. p. 5. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> than the Evangeliſts intended in the
Goſpels, or the Apoſtles in the Epiſtles, altogether ruining the
Scope and Connexion in divers Places.</q> To this I reply'd,</p>
            <p>
               <q>That the Diſſenters ſing ſome ſmall Portions of Pſalms, which
with them is not curtailing or mangling the Pſalms: That they
read ſingle Chapters, into which the inſpir'd Pen-men did not
divide their Writings, as well as not into thoſe ſhorter Sections
call'd Epiſtles and Goſpels; that 'tis as lawful (and perhaps as
edifying) to read theſe, as whole Chapters, that there is often a
Connexion between Chapter and Chapter, which binders not the
Diſſenters reading them ſeverally; that this is every whit as much
diſturbing the Scope of thoſe Places, as our reading the Epiſtles
and Goſpels is: that thoſe Paragraphs of Scripture have two
ſenſes, a Relative, and an Independent ſenſe: that tho' the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative
ſenſe cannot be underſtood without its neighbouring Parts,
yet it is not ruin'd thereby; to omit for a time is not ruining
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102854:11"/>
the Scope; nor doing it the leaſt Injury. That the independent
Senſe however is ſtill ſafe; that by the Rule imply'd in this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection,
the Diſſenters (who are not very fond of reading any
at all) will be oblig'd to read many Chapters together, happily
whole Books, and to ſing the 119. <hi>Pſal.</hi> at once.</q> And what
ſays the Remarker to all this?</p>
            <p>He ſuggeſts that we <hi>omit</hi> reading ſome Scriptures (even <hi>whole
Chapters and Books</hi> as he gathers from our Kalender) which <hi>ſeems to
be a diminiſhing from the Word of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pref. p. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This is nothing to the Defence of Mr. <hi>Delaune,</hi> but a Digreſſion
from the Argument in hand, which is call'd <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
and is meer cavil and ſhuffling. It betrays the weakneſs
of Mr. <hi>Owen</hi>'s Defence of Mr. <hi>Delaune.</hi> Our omitting Chapters
and Books will not vindicate Mr. <hi>Delaune</hi>'s unjuſt Accuſation of us
about reading the Epiſtles and Goſpels. As for the reſt of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
to Mr. <hi>Delaune,</hi> the Remarker puts me off with this ſlight An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,
<hi>I leave him and Mr. Delaune to argue,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Delaune</hi> is long ſince dead; where and when we ſhall
meet, God only knows: I am pretty ſure not in this World. Mr.
<hi>Owen</hi> perhaps with the help of our <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> Exorciſts will under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take
to bring Mr. <hi>Delaune</hi> back again. Why not? They who can
caſt out Devils, 'tis probable can raiſe the Dead. One Miracle is
as eaſily wrought as another; yet ſtill the miſchief is, tho' theſe
Wonder-workers ſhould conjure him up again, as the Woman of
<hi>Endor</hi> did <hi>Samuel,</hi> I am not ſure the Rector would have the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
to meet him. In plain terms Mr. <hi>O.</hi> has declin'd the Cauſe,
being as little able to make good the Objection laid againſt us, as
the Accuſer himſelf was.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Mr.</hi> Delaune <hi>tax'd the eſtabliſh'd Church,</hi> That in the Liturgy.
Tranſlation of the Pſalms three whole Verſes are foiſted into the 14th.
Pſalm, immediately after the third Verſe.</p>
            <p>Hereunto I return'd, <q>That the inſpir'd Pen-men of the New
Teſtament had done the ſame,<note place="margin">Serm. p. 7.</note> 1 <hi>Cor. 15. 54, 55, v.</hi> that is,
had put diſtant Paſſages of Scripture together,<note place="margin">See 2 Cor. 6. 16, 17, 18. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with Iſa. 52. 11. Jer. 31. 1, 9.</note> and cited 'em as
one ſingle and intire Teſtimony, That St. <hi>Paul</hi> had borrowed
theſe very three objected Verſes at leaſt from other Pſalms and
Books of the Old Teſtament, and inſerted them with the other
Parts of the Pſalm into <hi>Rom. 3. 10. v.</hi> &amp;c. The which I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
is ſufficient to juſtifie us.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:102854:12"/>
And what has the Miniſter reply'd unto all this? Why juſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
at all: He has not ſo much as taken the leaſt notice of it,
ſo as to vindicate Mr. <hi>Delaune</hi>'s groundleſs clamour againſt us,
that's out of doors. Ne'rtheleſs ſomething he has to ſay againſt
the Rector,<note place="margin">Pref. Rem. p. 2.</note> which whether it be to the purpoſe is no matter;
'twill make a noiſe among his Party, and that's all. He acquaints
us then from <hi>Jerome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pref. ad lib. 16. in Iſ. Tom. 2. 395.</note> 
               <hi>That the ſaid three Verſes were tranſcrib'd out of</hi>
Romans <hi>into</hi> Pſal. 14. <hi>that they are not in the</hi> LXX. <hi>and that none of
the</hi> Greek <hi>Interpreters have commented upon them.</hi> My Anſwer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto
is:</p>
            <p>1. That this is nothing to the Argument before us. It acquits
us from the charge of Mr. <hi>Delaune.</hi> It was not the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
then which foiſted thoſe three Verſes into <hi>Pſal. 14.</hi> Beſides
we have the Authority of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and of the Primitive Church to
warrant our continuing them in <hi>Pſal. 14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. As for <hi>Jerome</hi> I do here proteſt againſt him, as unfit to be a
Witneſs in this Caſe. He too warmly eſpous'd the Defence of
the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Text againſt the LXX, and manifeſtly betray'd his
Partiality. He car'd not what in his heat he ſaid or wrote for the
ſupport of his own opinion.<note place="margin">Tom. 1. pa. 1343. Par, Edit.</note> Let any one conſult his <hi>Hebrew Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
and Traditions on Geneſis,</hi> and it may be he'l be of my mind. Here
arguing for the <hi>Hebrew</hi> againſt the LXX, becauſe forſooth St. <hi>Luke
(Act. 7. 14.)</hi> agreed not with the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Text, but with the <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuagint,</hi>
he gives that holy Evangeliſt this ſcurvy Character, <hi>Lucae
qui ignotus &amp; vilis &amp; non magnae fidei in nationibus ducebatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I'll not <hi>Engliſh</hi> the words, becauſe I will pay ſome <hi>deference</hi> to
the <hi>Presbyterian Father.</hi> This only I ſay, He who ſticks not to
revile the inſpir'd Evangeliſt after this manner, is unworthy to be
believ'd in any thing he affirms upon this Point in Controverſie, or
indeed in any elſe.</p>
            <p>3. I would deſire to know when, and by whom, thoſe three
Verſes were tranſcrib'd out of St. <hi>Paul</hi> into the <hi>14th.</hi> Pſalm. 'Twas
done before St. <hi>Paul</hi> was born for any thing I know.</p>
            <p>4. Whereas <hi>Jerome</hi> affirms (as Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> tells me) that theſe
Verſes are not in the LXX. Tranſlation, I ask, where then did
<hi>Jerome</hi> find 'em, and how came he to enter into the Diſpute about
'em? Looking into the Place, <hi>Jerome</hi> (I find) confeſſes the Verſes
are in <hi>vulgatâ Editione quae Graece <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> dicitur &amp; in toto orbe diverſa
eſt.</hi> I do not well underſtand him, but it ſeems the Copies of the
Scripture then in ordinary uſe, whence <hi>Euſtochium</hi> argu'd, had theſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102854:12"/>
Verſes, and <hi>Jerome</hi> acknowledges, there was a <hi>Greek</hi> Edition call'd
the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or vulgar, which had the ſaid Verſes in it, tho' <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi>'s
had 'em not, if he is to be credited. But by whom and
when theſe Verſes were put into this vulgar Edition of the <hi>Seventy,
Jerome</hi> ſays not.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Vatican</hi> Copy Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> confeſſes to be <hi>one of the beſt,</hi> that
has theſe three Verſes: I dare not then believe that the <hi>Seventy</hi>
Tranſlation in <hi>Jerom</hi>'s days was without 'em. Be this as it will, 'tis
manifeſt that the Church of <hi>England</hi> added 'em not to <hi>Pſal. 14.</hi>
that St. <hi>Paul</hi> made no ſcruple to join diſtant Places of Scripture to
one another; and how this ſhould become ſo heinous a Crime in
us to follow thoſe Examples, Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> is yet in arrear to account
for in behalf of Mr. <hi>Delaune.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Delaune</hi> moreover aſſerted,<note place="margin">Serm. p. 8.</note> 
               <hi>That the three Verſes are not in
any of the Original Copies,</hi> whereas if there be many, as is imply'd
in thoſe words, the <hi>Greek</hi> muſt be one, as I noted, and there they
are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And I further acquaint the Remarker, that they are in the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick</hi>
and <hi>Aethiopick</hi> Verſions alſo. Of this the Miniſter has <hi>ne</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>quidem,</hi> not one Syllable. Only becauſe I took occaſion hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
to offer unto conſideration, whether the <hi>Greek</hi> Copy be not <hi>as
good as the</hi> Hebrew <hi>at this day is,</hi> and grounded my ſelf upon the
Judgment of the Learned <hi>Iſaac Voſſius,</hi> he endeavours to make his
Party believe I deſign'd to <hi>Depreſs the Authority of the</hi> Hebrew <hi>Copies.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pref. p. 2.</note>
Surely this Miniſter never conſiders what he writes.</p>
            <p>If I had affirm'd roundly (which I did not) that the <hi>Seventy</hi>'s
Verſion is as good as the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> this would not have been any
diſparagement unto the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> tho' it would be an advancement
to the <hi>Seventy:</hi> Except Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> thinks that the Commendation of
one Man is the reproach of another. I don't think it any diſpraiſe
unto St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> if in anſwer to <hi>Jerom</hi>'s foremention'd diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of St. <hi>Luke</hi> one ſhould affirm that St. <hi>Luke</hi>'s Writings are of
as good Credit as St. <hi>Matthew</hi>'s. In ſhort, tho' I am inclin'd to
believe the <hi>Seventy</hi> to be of Divine Authority, 'twas never in my
thoughts to depreſs the <hi>Hebrew.</hi> So that it were ſufficient for me to
juſtifie the choice of my Text, tho' it were to be found in the
<hi>Hebrew</hi> only.</p>
            <p>It has (I do believe among them who are as ignorant as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf)
paſt for a current Piece of Wit, when he thus ſpeaks: If the
<hi>Seventy be of at good Authority as the preſent</hi> Hebrew,<note place="margin">Pref. p. 2.</note> 
               <hi>it is very uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
what becomes of the Rector's Text: Thus the Rector by maintaining
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102854:13"/>
one abſurdity runs himſelf into more, and by advancing the Seventy has loſt
his Text.</hi> But how does this follow? when at the ſame time the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi>
is allow'd to be <hi>as good as the Seventy.</hi> The Rector then had his
Liberty to chuſe his Text out of which Copy himſelf pleas'd. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
it falls out ſcurvily to the ſhame and confuſion of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marker,
of Mr. <hi>Tallents</hi> his ſupraviſor, of all his Fellow-helpers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<hi>Oſweſtry</hi> and <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> that the Rectors Text is in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty,
yea in the Vatican Exemplar, yea in that very Edition,
whereof Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> makes mention, and which he has by him. Tell
it not at <hi>Oſweſtry,</hi> publiſh it not at <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> that ſo many <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian</hi>
Miniſters, even when they are labouring to vindicate 'em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
from the Charge of corrupting the Word of God, are at
the ſame time Robbing and Diminiſhing from it. In two words, the
Rector has found his Text, but the Miniſters have loſt their jeſt
and their honeſty too.</p>
            <p>The Rector's Text is not indeed plac'd in the ſame order in
the Vatican <hi>Seventy,</hi> as in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> and our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Verſions.
But one would have thought the Gentleman at <hi>Manchester,</hi> who has
the liberty of a good Library there, muſt have found the Rector's
Text rightly plac'd both in the <hi>Frankford</hi> Edition of the <hi>Seventy,</hi>
and in the <hi>Complutenſian</hi> Bible alſo. But they were ſo fond of a Jeſt
that rather than loſe it, they would forfeit their Sincerity. I would
now inform 'em, where they may meet with the Rector's Text in
the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> according to the Vatican Copy it ſelf, but that I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
they knew it well enough themſelves. Inſtead hereof I deſire
'em to read a little forward to the <hi>8th. ver</hi> after the Rector's Text,
where <hi>Agur</hi> makes this Prayer, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<hi>Remove far from me vanity and lies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It cannot be deny'd, the <hi>Seventy</hi> has been corrupted, and by
conſequence muſt not be allow'd as good as the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Copy, if
the <hi>Hebrew</hi> be perfect and intire as it came out of the hands of the
Pen-men, or of ſome inſpir'd Collector of the Books and Volumes
therein contain'd. But <hi>Iſaac Voſſius</hi> has abundantly prov'd the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi>
Copy corrupted, and I do not care to repeat what another has
with ſo much Learning and Judgment ſaid before me.</p>
            <p>One of Mr. <hi>Owen</hi>'s Reaſons againſt any early Corruption of the
<hi>Hebrew</hi> is drawn from the Teſtimony of <hi>Philo</hi> the <hi>Jew</hi> mention'd
by <hi>Euſeb. prepar. Evang. 8. 2.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pref. p. 2.</note> that paſſage of <hi>Philo</hi> is in <hi>Euſeb. prep.
Evang.</hi> L. 8. C. 6. Pag. 1628. Here <hi>Philo</hi> ſpeaking of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi>
Obedience to the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> acquaints us, <q>The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verenc'd
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102854:13"/>
that Man <hi>(Moſes)</hi> ſo much, that whatſoever ſeem'd good
unto him they all approv'd of it. So that whether he devis'd this
Form of Government of his own head, or whether he receiv'd
it from, Heaven, they accepted it as no other than from God;
and for the ſpace of ſo many years (I cannot determine how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
but above two thouſand) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, alter'd no
one <hi>word</hi> of what he <hi>(Moſes)</hi> wrote, but ſuffer'd tho' it were a
thouſand Deaths rather than be perſwaded unto any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
to his Laws and Cuſtoms.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It is not to be doubted but the Religious <hi>Jews</hi> were always very
careful to preſerve <hi>Moſes</hi> intire and free from all manner of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,
even in the leaſt Tittle, as the Chriſtians have been to
their power in preſerving the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Philo</hi> aims not in this place to aſſert any ſuch thing of the
<hi>Jews</hi> (tho' Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> ſeems to underſtand him thus, and for what
reaſon any one may gueſs, renders the Paſſage, <hi>Than ſuffer the Law
to be changed in any one Point:)</hi> That which <hi>Philo</hi> affirms is, that
the <hi>Jews</hi> alter'd none of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Laws. This will appear by exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
the ſignification of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, tranſlated <hi>Word</hi> by Mr. <hi>Owen.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
is indeed often render'd <hi>Verbum &amp; Vocabulum,</hi> but as often <hi>Dictum
&amp; Sententia,</hi> or an intire Propoſition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Heſychius</hi> expreſſes its Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugate
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Law or Ordinance; and ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
&amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, are in the New Teſtament us'd for ſome complex
Sentence or Propoſition, and are Synonymous with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.
Thus the Ten Commandments are call'd the Ten Words, <hi>Exod.
34 24.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
the Decalogue, the Ten Commandments, or the
Ten Words. So then <hi>Philo</hi>'s <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, imports that the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
<hi>Jews</hi> alter'd not one ſingle Commandment of <hi>Moſes.</hi> But it
follows not hence that there was no alteration not in any Word or
Point. This might happen (tho' the <hi>Jews</hi> did it not wilfully) for
any thing <hi>Philo</hi> offers to the contrary. It is yet more manifeſt from
the Authors precedent Diſcourſe, where he ſpeaks of the Laws and
Statutes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and from what follows in this very Period, where
he explains himſelf thus, <hi>Rather than be perſwaded unto any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
to his Laws and the Cuſtoms.</hi> 'Twas the Laws of <hi>Moſes</hi> then
they were careful of, and not the Words, Syllables or Letters, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to <hi>Philo</hi> in this place.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:102854:14"/>
Tho' the <hi>Jews</hi> were careful to preſerve the Scripture from Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption;
yet <hi>Theodoret</hi> grants that before <hi>Eſdras</hi> corrected it, it had
been depraved partly through the negligence of the <hi>Jews,</hi> partly
by the Impiety of the <hi>Babylonians</hi> (he means in the Seventy years
of the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Captivity.) It may with much more reaſon be
thought, that the Scripture was corrupted again (by the ſame
means) after the Prophets were ceaſed from among the <hi>Jews,</hi> and
they had been harraſſed by the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> for ſome hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds
of years.</p>
            <p>
               <q>The Invention of the <hi>Maſora (as he goes on)</hi> has been an effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual
means to preſerve the Purity of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Copies,<note place="margin">Pref. p. 3.</note> and
renders it impoſſible, that any Corruption ſhould have crept in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
them,</q> ſays <hi>Buxtorf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doubtleſs, before Chriſt's Birth the honeſt <hi>Jews</hi> us'd all their
Endeavours to preſerve the Scripture uncorrupt, and yet who
ſees not that there might notwithſtanding many Corruptions ſteal
into the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Text, and deſignedly be thruſt into it? 'Twas no
hard matter for cunning <hi>Rabbies</hi> to alter Words and Letters, and
ſtill to keep the juſt number of 'em. When <hi>We</hi> is alter'd into <hi>Ye</hi>
there ſtill remains the ſame number of Words and Letters in that
<hi>6. Act. 3. v.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do not affirm, that the <hi>Hebrew</hi> was corrupted in any material
thing till after the Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Nevertheleſs it might
have been corrupted before the Fifth Century, when the <hi>Maſora</hi>
is ſaid to be invented. Yea, 'tis matter of Fact, that the <hi>Jews</hi>
had corrupted the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Bible long before that time, if Mr. <hi>Owen</hi>
will pleaſe to give any Credit to St. <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> who flouriſh'd
above 250 years before <hi>Jerome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall have occaſion in another Place to prove this by ſome Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies
drawn out of <hi>Juſtin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, 'tis but lately ſince the Chriſtians receiv'd the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi>
Bible from the Modern <hi>Jews,</hi> who may very well be ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to have made bold with it in prejudice to the Chriſtian Religion.
And whether it be fit we ſhould build upon the bare Teſtimony of
the <hi>Jews</hi> only, deſerves ſome conſideration. For therefore it was,
that in my Sermon I ſpoke not of the ancient <hi>Hebrew</hi> Copies, but
of that which we have <hi>at this day</hi> from the later <hi>Jews.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Serm. p. 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort,<note place="margin">Pref. p. 2.</note> 
               <hi>I</hi> (ſays he) <hi>will not diſpute at this time the Authority of the
Septuagint:</hi> Nor will the Rector call into queſtion the Purity of the
<hi>Hebrew,</hi> 'tis not neceſſary to decide the Controverſie between Mr.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102854:14"/>
               <hi>Delaune</hi> and me. Whatever becomes of the <hi>Seventy,</hi> or the <hi>Hebrew,</hi>
'tis falſe what he put upon us. The Church of <hi>England</hi> foiſted not
thoſe three Verſes into <hi>Pſal. 14.</hi> But if we had firſt done it, we are
excuſable, the Pſalm being thus put together by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Mr. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laune</hi>
then ought not to have vilify'd us for <hi>foiſting</hi> them into that
Pſalm. Men who will take the liberty of miſrepreſenting others in
ſuch naſty Expreſſions deſerve to be told of their own Faults in
more cleanly Language.</p>
            <p>4. The Rector obſerv'd from <hi>Rev. 22. 18, 19.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pref. p. 3. Serm. pag.</note> 
               <hi>That the Canon of
Scripture is there (for ought we yet know) ſhut<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> up.</hi> I expreſt my ſelf
thus cautiouſly <hi>(for ought we yet know)</hi> becauſe the Paſſage alledg'd
properly refers unto the Book of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> tho' the Learned
ſometimes accommodate it unto the whole Scripture. But the Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick
at <hi>Oſweſtry</hi> would inſinuate, as if the Rector expected more
Revelations ſtill, and an <hi>enlargement</hi> of the Canon.</p>
            <p>And is Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> certain we ſhall not have more Divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations
before the end of the World?<note place="margin">12, 13.</note> I expect 'em as little as
he: but 'tis one thing to ſuppoſe it poſſible, and another to look
for it as probable or promis'd. God has indeed ty'd our hands,
<hi>Thou ſhalt not add,</hi> but he has not ty'd his own, whatever this <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>
of our Age deems to the contrary. God we know add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to his own Word even after <hi>Agur</hi> had warn'd us, <hi>not to add
thereunto;</hi> and he may (if he pleaſe) once more add unto it, after
'tis forbidden unto us in St. <hi>John;</hi> what he will do, is another
Queſtion. <hi>I</hi> am as well content with what we have already, as the
Miniſter can be. But as <hi>Agur</hi> doubtleſs thought it poſſible God
might add unto his own Word (as he did afterwards) ſo 'tis not
impoſſible, but he may yet add thereunto, <hi>for ought I know,</hi> or the
Remarker himſelf dares affirm. If he or his Reviſor at <hi>Mancheſter</hi>
know, that God will ſend us no more Revelations, than what we
have already receiv'd, they might do well to aſſure the World of
it by the Spirit of Propheſie, and ſo contradict 'emſelves in the
ſame breath.</p>
            <p>If any Sort of Men ſhould preſume to add unto the Canon of
Scripture, I know none more likely than thoſe, who make ſuch
mighty boaſts of the Spirit of God. They have made one pretty
good ſtep towards it already. They who diſpoſſeſs Daemoniacks,
will in good time heal all manner of bodily Diſeaſes, remove
Mountains alſo, and throw 'em into the Sea. Who then ſhall
make any difficulty of entertaining their Doctrines, as the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles
of God?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:102854:15"/>
               <hi>The Rector laid down this other Rule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Serm. p. 13</note> Then we diminiſh from the
Word when we cast away never ſo little of it.<note place="margin">Pref. p. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Upon which Words the
Miniſter has the following Remark,</hi> I leave it to conſideration, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
the Titles be not a little part of the Word of God, and own'd for ſuch in
our Authoriz'd Bibles.</p>
            <p>That has been conſider'd already; but if they are own'd for
Parts of the Word of God in our Authoriz'd Bibles, then we of
the Church of <hi>England</hi> do more eſpecially own 'em; we cannot
then be accuſed of caſting them away. But if to leave 'em out of
the Liturgy Tranſlation be a caſting 'em away, then the leaving
'em out of the Singing Pſalms is the ſame.</p>
            <p>Theſe tender-hooft-Creatures, who are convinc'd that the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles
are part of the Pſalms, and ought to be inſerted into every
Tranſlation, yet againſt the Dictates of their own Conſcience pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fix
'em not, neither demand 'em to be prefix'd unto the Singing
Pſalms. Who ever hereafter can believe, that they have any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
at all? Or rather is it not to be ſuſpected, that they have
two Conſciences? with the one accuſing us, and with the other
excuſing themſelves for the ſame thing.</p>
            <p>On this head I inſtanc'd in the <hi>Jews,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Serm. pag. 13, 14.</note> whom <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
with <hi>Trypho</hi> charg'd with corrupting and expunging out of the
Scripture ſeveral Places, which pointed at the Meſſias.</p>
            <p>Ay,<note place="margin">Rem. p. 3.</note> ſays the Miniſter, <hi>with corrupting the Seventy, but not the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal
Hebrew,</hi> which he ought to have taken notice of.</p>
            <p>And why ſo, ſweet Sir? I demand your Reaſon. Is it becauſe
'tis no Fault to corrupt the <hi>Seventy?</hi> Or becauſe the Places were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire
in the Original <hi>Hebrew</hi> Text? This latter cannot be a Reaſon,
becauſe it is not true, that the Places objected by <hi>Juſtin</hi> againſt the
<hi>Jews</hi> were then intire in the Original <hi>Hebrew.</hi> For the <hi>Jews</hi> doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
would have vindicated themſelves, and not have ſuffer'd that
Scandal to paſs ſo ſmoothly and unanſwer'd. They would have let
<hi>Juſtin</hi> know, that their <hi>Hebrew</hi> Bibles were intire in all the Places
by him alledg'd, or elſe that they never belong'd unto the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</p>
            <p>It muſt be confeſt then the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Copy was corrupted in St.
<hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi>'s days, the ſeveral Paſſages by him mention'd to be
thruſt out of Scripture, being then (and ſtill are) wanting in the
<hi>Hebrew</hi> Text as well as in the <hi>Seventy.</hi> For inſtance, that Father
produces <hi>Pſal. 96. 10.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<hi>Say among the Heathen the Lord hath reigned.</hi> But <hi>Juſtin</hi> tells <hi>Trypho,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:102854:15"/>
that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> had been ſtruck out by the <hi>Jews,</hi> and that the
place originally ran thus, <hi>The Lord hath reigned from the Wood,</hi> or
Croſs. But if they had been in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> can any one think
<hi>Trypho</hi> ſo dull as not to have told <hi>Juſtin</hi> as much? Nor are theſe
words <hi>from the Croſs</hi> found in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> or <hi>Seventy</hi> at this day.
The reaſon of the <hi>Jews</hi> Knavery herein is obvious, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe
thoſe words <hi>from the Wood</hi> were an illuſtrious Prediction of the
manner of Chriſt's Death, and by conſequence a plain Teſtimony
of his being the Meſſiah, the brightneſs of which Evidence they
were not able to behold<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and therefore raz'd out the words. In
ſhort, the Croſs of Chriſt was to them <hi>a ſtumbling block</hi> in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie
as well as in the accompliſhment.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Copy in <hi>Jerom</hi>'s days wanted the ſame
words, <hi>From the Wood</hi> He took no notice at all of 'em either in his
Verſion, or in his Commentaries.</p>
            <p>In Mr. <hi>Pool</hi>'s <hi>Synopſis</hi> I find many Arguments againſt <hi>Juſtin,</hi>
charging the foreſaid Corruption upon the <hi>Jews;</hi> but they are
of no weight, if it be conſidered, that <hi>Faminius Nobilius</hi> in his
<hi>Scholia</hi> on this Place writes thus, <hi>Apud Sanctum Auguſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; in Pſalte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio
veteri &amp; Romano ſequitur</hi> à ligno; <hi>eoquo modo affertur à Sancto
Cyprian. Juſt. Mart. Tertulliano, Sancto Leone Papa &amp; in hymno Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtico,</hi>
Regnavit à ligno Deus. Beſides this moſt ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
and Martyr, and the moſt Learned too of all others in and
before his time has produced a great many Examples of the like
kind,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Juſt. pag. 297, 298, 332, 348. &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libi Edit. Pariſ.</note> and not a few whole Periods or ſmaller Sections intirely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pung'd,
which the <hi>Jews</hi> then living and diſputing with him were
not able to deny, or any ways palliate. So that all the pretended
Care of the <hi>Jews</hi> notwithſtanding, the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Copy had been cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted
early in the Second Century, and according to <hi>Voſſius</hi> ſoon
after the Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> and remains ſo unto
this preſent time.</p>
            <p>I muſt not paſs over <hi>Voſſius</hi>'s main Argument, but will repreſent
it in very few words.</p>
            <p>He ſhews, that the Ancient <hi>Jews</hi> believed their Meſſiah would
come about the 6000 Year from the Creation; and that they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected
him about the time when <hi>Jeſus</hi> was born, thoſe two Periods
being coincident. It follows hence,</p>
            <p>1. That they believ'd the World 6000 years old at the Birth
of Jeſus.</p>
            <p>2. That the Ancient <hi>Hebrew</hi> Copies reckon'd 6000 years from
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102854:16"/>
               <hi>Adam</hi> to Jeſus; elſe the <hi>Jews</hi> could not have been in expectation of
the Meſſiah when Jeſus was born, if their Chronology had then
been the ſame as it is this day.</p>
            <p>3. From the whole it muſt be confeſt, that the Modern <hi>Hebrew</hi>
Copies are corrupted, the World according to them, being at
the Birth of Jeſus but about 4000 years old. The 2000 years
wanting in the preſent <hi>Hebrew</hi> are ſupply'd in a great meaſure by
the <hi>Seventy</hi>'s Copy in the Chronology of the Patriarchs, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder
are made good out of the Intervals of the Judges of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
and the Reigns of the <hi>Perſian</hi> Kings, which the <hi>Jews</hi> have ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten'd,
and drawn the Chriſtians into their Error.</p>
            <p>Hereunto may be added another Obſervation near of kind unto
the former. St. <hi>Luke,</hi> Chap. 4. 35, 36, <hi>v.</hi> affirms, <hi>Sala was the
Son of Cainan, Cainan the Son of Arpbaxad.</hi> But <hi>Gen. 11. 12, v. Sala</hi>
is reckon'd the immediate Son of <hi>Arphaxad,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 10. 24.</note> and <hi>Cainan</hi> quite left
out in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Copy, whereas the <hi>Vatican Seventy</hi> agrees with St.
<hi>Luke;</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Alex.</hi> Copy.</note> which is a Demonſtration, that the <hi>Jews</hi> have corrupted
the <hi>Hebrew.</hi> By this one Artifice of theirs are loſt 130 years.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> expect here the Remarker,<note place="margin">1 Chron. 1. c.</note> or the Note-maker will for the
ſake of the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> give the Holy Evangeliſt ſuch another Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter,
as upon the like occaſion their Friend <hi>Jerom</hi> did.</p>
            <p>That Corruption of <hi>Pſal. 22. 16. v.</hi> is known and acknowledg'd
by all. The <hi>Jews</hi> read it thus, <hi>As a Lion</hi> inſtead of, <hi>They pierced my
hands and my feet.</hi> So the Evangeliſt <hi>Mark 15. 24.</hi> and the <hi>Seventy</hi>
more truly have it; the difference is but the half of a very ſmall
Letter, <hi>ſc.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (which is leſs than that between Y and W) and
the <hi>Epentheſis</hi> of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is common among 'em in other Caſes.</p>
            <p>But after all this it was nothing to me or to my Argument in
the Sermon, whether the <hi>Jews</hi> corrupted the <hi>Seventy</hi> only, or the
<hi>Hebrew</hi> alſo, or both. I'll ſuppoſe it was the <hi>Seventy</hi> only, which is
all Mr. <hi>O.</hi> contends for; yet ſtill my Bill of Indictment laid againſt
the <hi>Jews</hi> muſt be found. For the Scripture is the Word of God,
in whatever Language 'tis written. They who would excuſe the
<hi>Jews</hi> for Corrupting the <hi>Seventy</hi> only, and not the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> in good
time will defend the Corrupting the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Verſion only, and not
the Original <hi>Greek.</hi> But if the latter Defence will not bring off the
falſe <hi>Cameronian,</hi> neither will the former juſtifie the faithleſs <hi>Jews.
I</hi> wiſh then the <hi>Jews,</hi> the <hi>Scotch Presbyterians,</hi> and Mr. <hi>O.</hi> in the
name of his Brethren in <hi>England</hi> to concert theſe Matters among
'emſelves for the Good of <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:102854:16"/>
The Rector briefly noted that the <hi>Samaritans</hi> and <hi>Sadducees</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected
all but the Five Books of <hi>Moſes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Serm. p. 14.</note> and the Miniſter calls this
a <hi>Vulgar Error;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pref. p. 4.</note> let us ſee on what Grounds.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> pleads,<note place="margin">Antiq. l. 18 c. 2.</note> that whereas <hi>Joſephus</hi> affirms, <hi>The Sadducees to
have receiv'd the Law only<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Hiſtorian in another place explains him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
as if he meant, The written Law in Oppoſition to the Oral. In</hi> proof
whereof he ſends me back unto the <hi>13th. b.</hi> and 18 <hi>Chap. I</hi> am
there and read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>But now I will ſhew that the
Phariſees having receiv'd from the Fathers many things as legal, which
were not written in the Law of</hi> Moſes, <hi>deliver'd them unto the People.
And for this cauſe the</hi> Sadducees <hi>rejected them alledging, that thoſe things
only were to be accounted Legal which were written (ſc.</hi> in the Laws of
<hi>Moſes) but that they ought not to obſerve the Traditions of the Fathers. I</hi>
will not inſiſt upon this that ſome Learned Men have thought the
Prophetical Books of Scripture were by the <hi>Sadducees</hi> reckon'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
the Oral Traditions of the Fathers; nor will <hi>I</hi> deny, (tho'
there be reaſon to doubt) that <hi>Joſephus</hi>'s Paſſage in his Eighteenth
Book is to be underſtood in the ſame Senſe as that in the Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth
Book, and that they explain one another. However this
be, he ſpeaks only of the Traditions added unto the Laws of
<hi>Moſes,</hi> which the <hi>Sadducees</hi> rejected; but not a Syllable concerning
the Prophetical Writings, which whether the <hi>Sadducees</hi> rejected, or
not, remains ſtill to be examin'd.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>O.</hi> aſſures us 'tis a <hi>Vulgar Error.</hi> But Mr. <hi>Pool</hi> in his <hi>Synopſis,</hi>
informs me,<note place="margin">Iſidor. L. 8. Ch. 4.</note> 'twas the conſtant Opinion of the Fathers, and never
contradicted, til <hi>Scaliger</hi> and <hi>Druſius</hi> of late advanc'd the contrary
Opinion. <hi>I</hi> hope the Miniſter will not thruſt down the Fathers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the <hi>Vulgar</hi> Forme.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sadducees</hi> in all Probability would never have deny'd the
Reſurrection, if they had entertain'd a juſt eſteem of the Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
Books: Hence, our Lord, overlooking all the other more plain
and convincing Teſtimonies in the Prophetical Writings, ſingl'd
out that of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 22. 32.</note> Exod. 3. 6. <hi>I am the God of thy Father, the God
of Abraham,</hi> &amp;c. as the moſt proper and effectual Argument, <hi>ad
Hominem,</hi> in proof of the Reſurrection, which the <hi>Sadducees</hi> on
their own Principles cou'd not deny, tho' they might have avoided
the other.</p>
            <p>But the Remarker ſends me to the Learn'd Dr. <hi>Lightfoot</hi> for fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
ſatisfaction herein, <hi>Vol. 2. pag. 541, 542. I</hi> am content to ſtand
to this Gentleman's Judgment. Dr. <hi>Lightfoot</hi> then <hi>pag. 541.</hi> grants
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102854:17"/>
that <hi>the Samaritans might ſo reject all the Books of the Old Teſtament,</hi>
(except the <hi>Pentateuch) as to forbid their being read in the Synagogues.</hi>
Even this Conceſſion alone were <hi>(I</hi> ſhould think) ſufficient to my
purpoſe. The <hi>Sadducees</hi> and <hi>Samaritans</hi> forbad the reſt of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
to be read in the Publick Congregations. If the <hi>Hagiographa,</hi>
and Prophets were now by a Poſitive Order forbid to be read in
our Churches, we ſhould have Mr. <hi>O (I</hi> queſtion not) ſoon about
our Ears as Men, that put a Slur upon the Word of God, and
queſtion'd its Divine Authority.</p>
            <p>But Dr. <hi>L.</hi> further adds, <hi>pag. 542. That it was one Fundamental of
the Sadducees Faith, That no Article in Religion ought to be admitted,
which cannot be made out plainly from the Five Books of Moſes.</hi> From
hence it appears that they did not believe the other Books of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
to be of equal Authority with the <hi>Pentateuch,</hi> nor ſufficient of
themſelves to eſtabliſh any Doctrine of Faith. Now whereas the
Doctor argues and proves out of his <hi>Rabbins,</hi> that the Sadducees
and Samaritans <hi>us'd and read, and believ'd</hi> all the other Books, as
well as the <hi>Pentateuch,</hi> and that <hi>they were not ignorant of 'em, nor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted
'em Tales and of no value;</hi> and again, that thoſe Books <hi>were
known to 'em, and of Authority among 'em.</hi> All this <hi>I</hi> readily grant,
for they doubtleſs highly eſteem'd the reſt of the Scripture, and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d it in confirmation of any Doctrine reveal'd by <hi>Moſes,</hi> as we
Chriſtians do the Primitive Fathers, tho' uninſpir'd. <hi>I</hi> have been
longer on this trivial Subject, than <hi>I</hi> intended. Only let the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
mark how the two Miniſters are here Advocating for the <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans</hi>
and <hi>Sadducees,</hi> as they before undertook the Protection of the
other <hi>Jews.</hi> In good time the Diſſenters will comprehend theſe alſo.
Some of the <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> the Modern <hi>Sadducees</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometans
I</hi> mean the <hi>Socinians)</hi> and almoſt all the Nation of Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks
and Hereticks are in their Intereſts already: The <hi>Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi>
and <hi>Jews</hi> are happily coming into the Confederacy.</p>
            <p>7. <hi>The Rector laid down this Obſervation alſo:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Serm. p. 14.</note> We diminiſh
from the Word, when we lay it aſide as not neceſſary, or not the Supreme
Rule of Faith.<note place="margin">Pref. p. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Hereunto Mr.</hi> O. <hi>anſwers,</hi> This implys, as if there
were ſome other at leaſt ſubordinate Rules of Faith. We know no other
Rule of Divine Faith, but the Holy Scripture.</p>
            <p>The Man thinks verily he has caught me now. But I am not
afraid to ſay there are many ſubordinate Rules of Faith, and do
pretend here to teach him them, becauſe he ſeems to be ignorant
of them. I reckon then that whatſoever confirms or illuſtrates any
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:102854:17"/>
Doctrine is a Subordinate Rule of Faith, <hi>for whatſoever doth make
manifeſt is Light,</hi> Eph. 5. 13. Such are the ancient Creeds, Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſms,
Decrees of Councils, Teſtimony of Fathers, Conſent of
Adverſaries, the Inſtructions of Parents, the Dictates of Wiſe and
Good Men, the Voice of Conſcience, the Light of Natural Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
the Preaching of the Word, the Intimations of Providence,
and laſtly Univerſal Tradition; every one of which when it ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſters
Light to the Divine Truths contain'd in the Word of
God, are Subordinate Rules of Faith. But of all theſe Univerſal
Tradition may on very good Grounds be accounted a Rule. For
I ask Mr. <hi>Owen,</hi> why he believes the Scripture to be Divinely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpir'd,
but becauſe 'tis tranſmitted unto us as ſuch by Univerſal
Tradition? The Excellency of its Moral Precepts, the high Strains
and noble Flights of Piety, which we meet with there renders it
worthy every good Man's Acceptation; true! but they prove not
that 'twas written by Inſpiration. For then <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Seneca,</hi> St.
<hi>Ignatius</hi> and St. <hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi> the Seven Wiſe Men of <hi>Greece,</hi>
(and Mr. <hi>O.</hi> may reckon himſelf the eighth, if he pleaſe) and a
thouſand other celebrated Authors might lay claim to Inſpiration.
The Miracles reported in Scripture to have been wrought by the
Authors or Divine Writers of the Books do not evince 'em to have
been written by Inſpiration, until it be firſt made out that thoſe
Writers did work thoſe Miracles: and this cannot be proved at
this time of day, but by Tradition. So then it is the Univerſal Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony
of the Church in conjunction with that vein of intrinſick
Goodneſs and Piety running through all the Holy Scriptures, which
convinces us, that they were deliver'd by Perſons inſpir'd and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriz'd
thereto by God. Tradition therefore is at leaſt a Subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
Rule of Faith, and confirms the Divine Authority of the
Books of Scripture. Another perhaps would affirm it the firſt and
leading Rule. But I give Mr. <hi>O.</hi> liberty to aſſign it which place
he pleaſes. Only I ask, whether this Miniſter of the Goſpel, who
pretends to be a Teacher of others, and a Guide of the Blind, was
ever yet able to give a ſolid Reaſon of his own Faith, and of the
Hope that is in him. He can never do it without the help of
Tradition.</p>
            <p>The Rector added under this Head ſome things concerning the
Sufficiency, Perſpicuity and Supreme Authority of the Scripture,
which this Critick (being it ſeems in a better humour than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily
that Generation of Men are) is pleas'd out of his great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion
to declare, <hi>Are well Aſſerted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:102854:18"/>
But I muſt confeſs I like not the Rector one jot the better for
this Commendation, and yet wiſh I could in any meaſure return
his Complement, and let him know, that he has ſaid any one thing
well and wiſely in his Remarks</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maſter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 22. 16.</note> (ſaid thoſe vile and Hypocritical Phariſees and Herodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans)
<hi>we know that thou art true, and teacheſt the way of God in Truth,
&amp;c.</hi> when at the ſame time they had a deſign upon Jeſus Chriſt
to puzzle and inſnare him with a cramp Queſtion. So my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary
here notwithſtanding his Commendations has ſomething a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the Rector. Some Men can never be pleas'd, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marker
is one of that number I perceive.</p>
            <p>Tell me (ſays he) is it lawful to Impoſe indifferent things? His
words are,<note place="margin">Pref. p. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Were this Principle practically acknowledg'd it would ſoon
heal our breaches, &amp;c.</hi> As who ſhould ſay, did we once lay aſide
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſcriptural Terms</hi> of Communion, and thereby <hi>Practically</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg
the Sufficiency, Perſpicuity and Supreme Authority of the
Scriptures, all would be well in a trice, an end then would be
put to our Diviſions.</p>
            <p>Verily if this would do the feat, I would embrace it with
both arms: I'd do any thing for the purchaſe of ſo valuable a
Bleſſing.</p>
            <p>But how comes this wiſe Seer to look ſo far before him, as to
aſſure us of this good iſſue? the experiment has been once made
already but without ſucceſs. Time was when Epiſcopacy was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploded,
and the Unſcriptural Terms of Communion here com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd
of laid aſide; but were our breaches <hi>ſoon</hi> healed? It was ſo
far from that, that they were not healed at all, nor ever will be
upon the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>Congregational</hi> Principles. Our Diviſion
were increas'd and multiply'd, Schiſms and Hereſies grew to be as
numerous as the Heads of <hi>Hydra.</hi> In ſhort, I know no way of
healing our Breaches but that every Man ſhould <hi>obey them that have
the Rule over 'em</hi> in all lawful things, <hi>q.d.</hi> which are not forbidden
by God. For why ſhould any one preſume to ſcruple or call that
unclean, which the Lord has not made ſo? They are much more
ſuperſtitious who abhor a Surplice, than they who wear it.</p>
            <p>I laſtly obſerv'd,<note place="margin">Serm. p. 20.</note> that <hi>We diminiſh from the Word when we add any
thing to it.</hi> I mention'd the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> which the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> inſert in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the Canon of Scripture;<note place="margin">Pref. p. 4.</note> and the Miniſter cavils here at our
reading the <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> and omitting ſome confeſſed parts of Holy
Scripture. I might with as good Reaſon ask him, why do the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:102854:18"/>
Diſſenters neglect the Reading of the Word of God to make
way for their own Sermons and Expoſitions? But this were to
be like Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> to cover one ſuppos'd Fault with another. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
then,</p>
            <p>That this Exception is nothing to my Argument; that it is not
a juſt Vindication of the Papiſts; that to read the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> is not
to Canonize it; to omit reading ſome parts of Scripture is not to
caſt 'em out of the Canon; that in all our publick Offices and
Aſſemblies we read ſomething of Holy Scripture; that the Word
of God has not preſcrib'd any certain and conſtant quantity to be
read; that we read perhaps more Scripture in one Month, than
the Diſſenters do in three. That the Story of <hi>Bell</hi> and the <hi>Dragon</hi>
(wherewith the Diſſenters uſually make moſt ſport, and which Mr.
<hi>O.</hi> ſtiles fabulous) is by many Wiſe Men believ'd true. But grant
it to be a Fiction or Fable, or in more civil and modeſt Terms a
Parable, 'tis however a wiſe and grave one, able to inſtruct and
beget in us a ſenſe of God's Providence and Protection of Holy
Men Zeal for his Glory and Hatred of Idolatry. Many think the
Book of <hi>Job</hi> of this kind a Parable. Our Lord himſelf ſpake many
great Truths, and wrapped them up in Parables or feigned Stories,
and thereby made and left ſtronger Impreſſions upon the hearts of
his Followers. The Diſſenters oft-times in their Sermons make
uſe of Profane Stories, whoſe Truth is not ſupported by Divine
Authority. As for our leaving out ſome few Books or Chapters, or
never reading them in our Publick Congregations, there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
good Reaſons for it; particularly for our omitting the greateſt
part of <hi>Leviticus,</hi> and all <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Song. They have been inſiſted
on too often to be here needleſly repeated.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:102854:19"/>
            <head>CHAP. III.</head>
            <head type="sub">Being an Anſwer to Mr. Owen's firſt Chapter.</head>
            <p>IN the Sermon againſt corrupting the Word of God, I took
particular Notice of <hi>Acts</hi> the <hi>6th. v. 3.</hi> where, as 'tis found in
ſeveral Impreſſions of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bibles, <hi>We</hi> is changed into <hi>Ye,</hi> that
is, the Apoſtles are turn'd out of doors, and the People put into
Poſſeſſion of a Power, to which they can lay no Claim, I obſerv'd
that hence a Queſtion might be ſtarted, <hi>Whether the People or the
Apoſtles did appoint the Seven unto their Office, and by conſequence whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
the People or the Biſhops have Authority to appoint Parochial Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</hi>
But having ſet aſide this Enquiry, I betook my ſelf unto the
Examination of this various Lection. I firſt vindicated the Place,
and reſtor'd it to its right Reading; then I proceeded to ſearch
when the Corruption firſt ſtole into the Text and found it to have
happen'd 1638. This done I made Hue and Cry after the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors
of it. In the purſuit I laid hold on the Diſſenters, as Perſons
juſtly to be ſuſpected, 1. Becauſe when this Alteration firſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd
Presbytery was in the Aſcendant. 2. The Corruption fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
the Diſſenters. 3. Is a Diſadvantage to Epiſcopacy then.
4. I took a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> in the manner, ſupporting the Popular
Government upon the Credit of this falſe Reading, and thence
concluded that Party guilty at leaſt of abetting and countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
the Corruption. This Method I think was clear and eaſie,
tho' Mr. <hi>O.</hi> has endeavoured with much Artifice to perplex it. I
will not concern my ſelf any farther to juſtifie my way of hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
the Argument, the Buſineſs now before me is to conſider,
how he would extricate his Friends. He begins in this Chapter,
and all that he here offers in Vindication of the Diſſenters is, <hi>That
ſeveral Editions of the Bible abound with ſuch Errors as are deſtructive of
the Senſe.</hi> To evince which he has produc'd a Catalogue of above
twenty <hi>Errata's</hi> in his own Bible, <hi>(ſeveral of 'em as bad as that in the
Acts,</hi> as he ſays) which it would be unreaſonable to impute unto
the Diſſenters. Whereunto I reply,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:102854:19"/>
1. That he is ſo unfortunate, as whilſt he is ſtopping one,
and that the firſt hole like a Bungler he makes two. Mr. <hi>O.</hi> thus
repreſents his Amendment of <hi>Eph. 1. 4. According as he hath choſen
us—that ſhe ſhould be holy: It ſhould be that we ſhould be holy</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.
<hi>She</hi> (ſays he in this firſt inſtance) ſhould be <hi>we;</hi> and
(ſays the Rector) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhould be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhould be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>I am apt to ſuſpect Mr. <hi>O.</hi> is defective ſomewhere, elſe ſurely
he would not have overlook'd theſe <hi>Errata's</hi> in that Book of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks,
which he favour'd me with, and corrected with his own
Pen. But becauſe at the ſame time he deſir'd me to take no advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
of Miſtakes in Printing, I'll ſay no more. Altho' if he thought
it reaſonable on my part, he ſhould have been ſo fair as to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred
the Golden Rule, <hi>Quod tibi non vis, &amp;c.</hi> But his buſineſs
is to give Laws to others, not to obſerve 'em himſelf.</p>
            <p>2. Tho' he might juſtly be ſuſpected in the Account given of
theſe <hi>Errata's;</hi> (for he who will make bold with his own LXX,
will not be very Scrupulous to miſrepreſent his own <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bible)
yet I will admit his Obſervations as to the Number to be true
Nevertheleſs,</p>
            <p>3. Tho' ſuch Errors reckon'd up by Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> are <hi>deſtructive of
the Senſe;</hi> yet they do not eſtabliſh any untruth, nor favour any ſide
in the Controverſies now on foot among us, neither laſtly, has the
diligent Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> given us one Example of the ſame Error repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
in ſeveral Editions. There can then no doubt be made, but
theſe were accidental and unwilling ſlips, and the Remarkers Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations
will do him no Service. That <hi>Erratum</hi> in the <hi>6th.</hi> Act
has, as he aſſures us, been continued in (at feweſt) 38 Editions;
it eſtabliſhes a Senſe contrary to the Meaning of the Holy Ghoſt
there, and favours a ſide in the Controverſie between the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
and us. It is then altogether improbable (I think) that this <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum</hi>
ſhould be thus multiplied by chance only.</p>
            <p>4. An Error of the Preſs deſerves not to be taken to task, when
no ill uſe is made of it; but when 'tis improv'd to the advantage
of a Cauſe, and to the prejudice of the Truth, it is both juſt and
neceſſary to take notice of it and to expoſe them, who make it their
own, and a wilful Error too, citing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in ſupport of their own Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
or Practice.</p>
            <p>It may not be improper here to ſpeak of the Places of Scripture,<note place="margin">Rem. ch. 4 pag. 20.</note>
which the Remarker has challeng'd me with, as having quoted
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:102854:20"/>
'em wrong, and not kept my ſelf preciſely to the very Word, and
to their Order in the Texts.</p>
            <p>1. I have not altered the Senſe, neither pretended to promote
any private Opinion or deſign thereby.</p>
            <p>2. This liberty is and ever has been taken by all, who alledge
the Holy Scripture in their Writings and Diſcourſes, not ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly
tying themſelves up unto the very Words. St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf
in that 3. <hi>Rom. 13, &amp;c.</hi> is guilty of all thoſe minute and trifling
Exceptions which the Remarker has laid againſt me, as may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
be ſeen by comparing him with the Places from whence 'tis
thought by my Adverſaries the Apoſtle took his Teſtimony.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Owen Ex. gr.</hi> taxes me for putting the Singular inſtead of
the Plural. St. <hi>Paul</hi> does ſo, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>whoſe mouth</hi> (Plural) but
in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> 'tis <hi>his mouth,</hi> Pſal. 10. 7. and in the <hi>Seventy,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<hi>whoſe mouth,</hi> (Sing.)</p>
            <p>I uſe different words, and of ſomewhat different ſignifications<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
So does St. <hi>Paul, Deſtruction and Miſery,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ver. 16.</hi> In the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew,
<hi>Waſting and Deſtruction,</hi> or breaking, <hi>Iſa. 59. 7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I obſerve not the Scripture-order of Words; nor is St. <hi>Paul</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act
in this, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: In the <hi>Seventy,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>I leave out whole Words: the ſame is true of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:
<hi>Their feet are ſwift to ſhed blood,</hi> v. 15. In
<hi>Iſa. 59. 7.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<hi>Their feet run to evil being ready to ſhed</hi> (innocent) <hi>blood,</hi> almoſt the
ſame in the <hi>Hebrew.</hi> Here alſo St. <hi>Paul</hi> has wholly omitted what is
in the Hebrew, <hi>Their thoughts are thoughts of iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I change Words, even ſo St. <hi>Paul</hi> writes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>v. 17.</hi> for
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Iſa. 59. 8. They have not known,</hi> inſtead of, <hi>They know not,</hi>
in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> the Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er for the Preſent time.</p>
            <p>I further note, our Lord himſelf (or the Evangeliſts) and the
Pen-men of the New Teſtament have left out Words in their Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.
<note place="margin">The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick, <hi>p. 68.</hi>
               </note> Therefore my Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cork</hi> and <hi>Roſs</hi> confeſſes, <hi>The
Sacred Pen-men of the New Teſtament content themſelves with the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
ſenſe of the Text not following that,</hi> (the Seventy) <hi>or any other Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi>
(not the Hebrew) <hi>that we know of.</hi> And again, <hi>They uſed a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty,
—Not following ever the expreſſions of any other known Tranſlation,
or indeed of the Original it ſelf, the</hi> Hebrew, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 71. For this he
cites <hi>Jerom</hi> alſo. For inſtance, I read <hi>Exod. 3. 6. I am the God of thy
Father, the God of Abraham,</hi> &amp;c. But, <hi>the God of thy Father</hi> is left out,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:102854:20"/>
               <hi>Mat. 22. 32. Mark 12. 26. Luk. 20. 37.</hi> And 'tis <hi>Fathers</hi> in the
Plural, <hi>Act. 7. 32.</hi> One might produce infinite Examples of this
kind. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> alſo muſt come in for his ſhare, as will afterward
appear. So putid and ridiculous a Remark is that of the Author,
p. 20. <hi>Allow Men</hi> (ſays he) <hi>a liberty of a literal variation from the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
of the Holy Ghoſt, the ſenſe and meaning cannot be long ſecur'd. I</hi>
may well be content to be corrected by Mr. <hi>Owen,</hi> who takes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
him to reprove Jeſus Chriſt, St. <hi>Paul</hi> and the three Evangeliſts;
yea, and the <hi>great</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> alſo.</p>
            <p>Having thus fully anſwer'd his Argument in this and the fourth
Chapter, I muſt conſider one or two Ref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ections he has here caſt
upon us. He mentions, <hi>the ſhameful ſcandals of ſome of our Clergy too
notorious,</hi> &amp;c. If it were fit to play ſuch a prize, I durſt undertake
to point out as many <hi>Scandalous diſſenting Miniſters</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi>
as he can Clergy-men.</p>
            <p>He twits me here alſo (and oft in the Remarks he makes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
ſport) with what I ſaid of my ſelf,<note place="margin">Rem. ch. 1. p. 1.</note> 
               <hi>ſc. That my diligence and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation
had not been a little in ſearching the ſeveral Editions of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi>
&amp;c. Now what I propos'd to my ſelf was not to ſearch after
all the Corruptions of this kind in the Bible, nor all the Impreſſions,
wherein this was to be found, much leſs after all the other leſs ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial
and accidental Errors of the Preſs. I employ'd my ſelf on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to diſcover the firſt faulty Impreſſion, whereinto this Corruption
had ſtollen, and the Remarker, with all his curioſity and exactneſs,
has not been able to out-do me. For any thing he knows, I have
hit upon the right year, <hi>viz. 38.</hi> I have no reaſon to be aſham'd
yet of my <hi>diligence and obſervation,</hi> tho' Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> may be of his
miſrepreſenting me ſo often on this ſcore.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> here denies the Diſſenters to have been concern'd in
this Corruption, and is very angry at the ſuſpicion caſt upon 'em
for their countenancing or promoting it. My Anſwer here is only
this, <hi>Fecit quiſquam quantum voluit.</hi> They who take the Advantage
and are willing the Corruption ſhould paſs for good among their
Diſciples, and (which is the Caſe of the <hi>Cameronian)</hi> give it enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment
are juſtly taxt with the miſchief done, the Receiver be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
always as bad as the Thief.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:102854:21"/>
            <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
            <head type="sub">In which a Reply is made to Mr. Owen's Second
Chapter.</head>
            <p>MY firſt Argument (which was to bring the Diſſenters un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<hi>a ſuſpition of contributing to this Corruption,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Serm. p. 23.</note> theſe are my
words, tho' Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> would have his Reader believe I now poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively
charge 'em with it) my firſt Argument (I ſay) is taken from
the Circumſtance of time. <hi>The alteration of the Text into</hi> ye <hi>happen'd
in the year 1638, Presbytery being then in the Aſcendant, and all things
in preparation and tending toward the Subverſion of Epiſcopacy,</hi> &amp;c. Mr.
<hi>Owen</hi> Anſwers,</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Two Events may happen at the ſame time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. p. 7.</note> 
               <hi>which have no relation
to one another.</hi> Right, when there is nothing elſe to be alledg'd for
confirming the ſuſpicion grounded on the Circumſtance of time,
they may then have no relation to one another. But I ever thought
this a good preſumptive Argument in conjunction with others,
which is the caſe before us, the turbulency of the times, the ſway
of the Populace, and the Corruption of this Place all looking the
ſame way, <hi>viz.</hi> the extirpation and overthrow of Epiſcopacy.</p>
            <p>2. He aſſerts that I my ſelf <hi>acknowledge the firſt Error was an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing
one,</hi>
               <note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. p. 7.</note> and cites my Epiſtle <hi>Dedicatory</hi> for this. Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> cannot
ſpeak Truth for his heart. The Remarks are all of a Thread, Lyes
and Stories, which we ſhall ſee he purſues unto the end. The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor's
words in the Epiſtle are, <hi>When an Error, which one would have
hop'd was an unwilling one, is ſupported with another, which muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
and believ'd a wilful one, that is, when the Presbyterian Government,
is publickly maintain'd by a Text of Scripture manifeſtly corrupted,</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>The unwilling Error</hi> here ſpoken of is the <hi>Presbyterian Government;</hi>
but 'tis the Error in the Text, which is call'd <hi>a wilful one,</hi> as any
Man will at firſt ſight diſcern, but one, whoſe buſineſs it is not
only to juſtifie others in corrupting the Scripture, but who himſelf
perverts his Adverſaries Words. This is his <hi>ſincere affection to the
Truth, and Charity to his Neighbour.</hi> Yea, Mr. <hi>O.</hi> himſelf juſt before
<hi>(pag. 6.)</hi> had acknowledg'd that I call'd it a <hi>wilful Error</hi> in my
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:102854:21"/>
               <hi>Epiſtle Dedicatory,</hi> behold here what an ingenuous and ſincere Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary
the Rector has to do with. Ay, but <hi>p. 27, &amp; 28.</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor
calls it <hi>an unfortunate overſight, a meer Error of the Preſs, an acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental
ſlip, an unhappy miſtake.</hi> True: yet unto the two firſt I have
added,<note place="margin">Serm. p. 27.</note> 
               <hi>I am willing to believe, and as we will ſuppoſe it was at firſt,</hi>
which it was not neceſſary to repeat any more. Theſe words then
ſhew that having taken a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in the very fact,</hi>
and endeavouring to eſtabliſh his own Perſwaſion by this falſe read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of the Place, I would not any longer inſiſt on the former cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantial
Proofs of the firſt corruption, I needed 'em not: The
matter was plain and could not be deny'd, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<hi>at leaſt have contributed to the Increaſe and Continuance of this Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Serm. p. 23.</note> (p. 23.) <hi>and ſetting it up for Authentick,</hi> p. 28. Hereby we
ſee this Remarker deals with the Sermon, as Mr. <hi>O.</hi> knows who
did with the Holy Scripture, <hi>Mat. 4 6.</hi> telling our Saviour, <hi>He</hi>
(God) <hi>ſhall give his Angels charge concerning thee,</hi> but leaving out a
main part of the Text, <hi>To keep thee in all thy ways.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. <hi>The Miniſter objects againſt the Rector,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rem. p. 7.</note> 
               <hi>that</hi> He is grievouſly
out in his Chronological Hiſtory, <hi>for Presbytery</hi> was not in the Aſcendant
in England Anno 1638, as he ſuggeſts.</p>
            <p>I would not for any thing be found tripping in this part of my
Argument, eſpecially after I have been taught this grave and edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying
Leſſon,<note place="margin">O. H<hi>'s Family-Altar.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>God is the Author of all Topography and Geography, as
well as Genealogy and Chronology.</hi> I will then try whether the Rector
can be vindicated, and that in a very few words too.</p>
            <p>The foundation of Mr. <hi>Owen</hi>'s Miſtake is the Blunder he has
made about the Signification of theſe words, <hi>Being in the Aſcendant,</hi>
which he underſtands of being in full Power and Authority, as if it
were the ſame with <hi>having the Aſcendant,</hi> as the Phraſe is ſometimes
uſed now a days.</p>
            <p>But the Aſtronomers<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Mr. Leyb. Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Math. p. 286.</note> will inform him, that the Eaſtern Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant
of the Heavens is call'd the Aſcendant; and a Star is ſaid
to be <hi>in the Aſcendant,</hi> when having paſt the <hi>Imum Coeli,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
got into the Aſcendant it bends its courſe up towards the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium
Coeli,</hi> and the Meridian, that's to ſay, is aſcending. Allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
hereunto I affirm'd, that in the Year 1638, <hi>Presbytery</hi> was
<hi>in the Aſcendant,</hi> that is, was riſing, and ſo it was; that <hi>Prodigious
and terrible Blazing Star the Covenant,</hi> that very Year began to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
in the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Hemiſphere in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſoon drew the Eyes
(I wiſh I could not ſay the Inclinations) of a great Part of <hi>England</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:102854:22"/>
upon it. I will not abuſe my Reader with an elaborate and tedious
Proof of this. 'Tis notorions, that <hi>Presbytery</hi> had then its foot in the
Stirrup, tho' it had not yet got into the Saddle, that is, was <hi>in
the Aſcendant</hi> (or mounting) tho' it had not yet attain'd unto the
Zenith or Vertical Point. And that this was my meaning appears
from the following words, <hi>When all things were in a preparation and
tended to the Subverſion of Epiſcopacy,</hi> p. 23.</p>
            <p>For I very well knew, and I believe ſcarce any Body is ignorant,
that the Head of the Noble Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> was not yet lopt off by
an unpreſidented Fiction in Law call'd <hi>Accumulative Treaſon,</hi> and
which was not to be drawn into Example for the future; that the
Innocent A. B. <hi>Laud</hi> was not yet murther'd, no tolerable Evidence
being produc'd againſt him; that the Univerſity of <hi>Cambridge</hi> was
not yet purg'd of the Epiſcopal Party, nor the Heads of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges
turn'd out of their Free-holds, impriſon'd, and laſtly clapt
under Deck with deſign either to be expos'd in ſome foreign Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
or perhaps to be ſunk into the bottom of the Sea, where they
could tell no tales, as the <hi>Arrians</hi> ſerv'd ſome of the <hi>Trinitarians;</hi>
that the Sacred Blood of the Royal Martyr was not yet ſpilt by an
Extraordinary Commiſſion and Authority aſſum'd at the inſtance of
the Rabble and the Red-coats. Theſe among many others were
the Pillars and Supports of the Church; and ſo long as they flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh'd,
and in ſome meaſure kept up their Heads from ſinking into
<hi>the Deſcendant,</hi> the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> (it's true) could not be ſaid to have
been <hi>in the Aſcendant,</hi> as the Miniſter ignorantly underſtands that
Phraſe.</p>
            <p>I have repeated theſe old Stories to ſhew, that it is not probable
I could imagine that Presbytery was ſo early, that is in 1638, ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated
or ſet up on the Pinacle of the Temple, as alſo to cure ſome
Men (if it may be) of that ſcurvy Diſeaſe of rubbing on old Sores.
They may ſee we want not Materials to ſet them forth, and are
able to lay unto their charge far more miſchievous and exorbitant
Actions, than they to ours. Whatever A. B. <hi>Laud</hi> did it was in the
courſe of Law; but the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> Proceedings were Arbitrary,
Tyrannical, violent and illegal. Laſtly, hereby the younger ſort
will learn what <hi>deference the Presbyterians have heretofore paid to their
Superiors, and what Charity they had towards their Neighbours,</hi> more
than other folks, and what all Ranks and Orders of Men in this
Kingdom muſt expect of 'em hereafter, if they once more <hi>have the
Aſcendant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:102854:22"/>
All the Queſtion that remains is, whether Presbytery was that
year <hi>in the Aſcendant,</hi> as theſe words truly ſignifie, that was on the
riſing hand in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This cannot be doubted of, nor will be deny'd by Men of Senſe,
who know any thing of the Riſe of the Civil War. I will not
therefore ſpend my time, nor weary the Reader's Patience with
the proof of it.<note place="margin">Rem. p. 10.</note> Only I crave leave to conſider the view of the ſtate
of <hi>Cambridge, Which</hi> (ſays he) <hi>was not Presbyterian or Puritan in 1638,
when and where the Corruption is ſuppos'd to have firſt happen'd.</hi> The
Sum of the Account which he receiv'd from Mr. <hi>Fra. Tallents</hi> is,
that all the Heads of the Colledges, that is Sixteen Perſons, were
for the Church. I'll ſuppoſe this; yet it follows not, but that the
Univerſity (a great part of it) was then inclining to <hi>Presbytery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> here talks like one, who knows not <hi>Cambridge,</hi> nor
had diligence enough to inform himſelf, and the Old Gentleman
Mr. <hi>Tallents</hi> is (I am afraid) paſt his Memory and Judgment, I will
not ſay his integrity: I am ſure he has not given a true and exact
Information of the Univerſity. For beſides theſe Sixteen Heads of
Colledges, there are the Fellows of the ſeveral Colledges, the
Scholars of the Houſes, Noblemen, Fellow-Commoners, Penſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners,
and Siſars or Servitors,<note place="margin">In the laſt Printed Tables they amounted to 2500, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the Colledge-Officers and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</note> which in all make up the number
of 2000 in ordinary <hi>(I</hi> believe) beſides the ſaid Heads of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges.
So that my Gentleman has reckon'd without his Hoſt, and
<hi>I</hi> am oblig'd to bring him to another Account.</p>
            <p>Among theſe 2000 there might be, and <hi>I</hi> am ſure there was a
great number which favour'd <hi>Presbytery,</hi> as will appear from the
Colledge of <hi>Emanuel.</hi> Six Colledges were not long after furniſh'd
with Heads out of <hi>Emanual,</hi> which got the nick-name about this
time of <hi>Pure-Emanuel,</hi> from the abundance of <hi>Puritans</hi> in it. <hi>I</hi> my
ſelf knew very well the 'foreſaid Six Heads by Face. They were
Maſters of <hi>King's, Trinity, St. John's, Jeſus, Clare-Hall,</hi> and <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel</hi>
it ſelf. <hi>I</hi> think <hi>I</hi> may add another of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Colledge. <hi>I</hi>
ſpare their Names. Moreover, in <hi>Trinity</hi> Colledge <hi>Oxford,</hi> there are
but Twelve Fellows, Ten of which were turn'd out at the Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
and their Places all ſupply'd by a like number from <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
'Tis manifeſt then that a great Part of the Univerſity was not well
affected to Epiſcopacy. Mr. <hi>O.</hi> might do well to ask Mr. <hi>Tallents,</hi>
whether he was well affected to Epiſcopacy in 38 or 40. <hi>I</hi> might
add that the King's and Parliament's Armies were no ſooner in the
Field, but the Scholars were up in the Univerſity, and fighting, ſome
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:102854:23"/>
for the King, and ſome for the Parliament, and that with various
Succeſs too.</p>
            <p>From the whole then it may be gather'd, that it was not impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible,
but that the Corruption of the <hi>6th.</hi> of <hi>Acts</hi> might have been
firſt contriv'd at <hi>Cambridge</hi> in the Year 1638. The Ferments
which the whole Nation and the Univerſity it ſelf were then in
might give a favourable opportunity and encouragement to the
attempt; It being too frequent, and as it were natural unto moſt
Men to adore the Riſing Sun.</p>
            <p>The Miniſter has labour'd to prove,<note place="margin">Rem. p. 9.</note> that the Reformation in
<hi>Scotland</hi> was firſt caſt into the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Plat-form. The contrary
hereunto is fully prov'd in that learned Treatiſe, Entituled, <hi>The Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental
Charter of Presbytery examin'd and diſprov'd, &amp;c.</hi> He means
the Article in the <hi>Claim of Right, (Apr. 11. 1689.)</hi> wherein Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy
is aſſerted to <hi>be and to have been a great and inſupportable grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance
and trouble unto the</hi> (Scotch) <hi>Nation, and contrary to the Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the generality of the People ever ſince the Reformation (they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
reformed from Popery by Presbyters) &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Author of the foreſaid Treatiſe has at large, and (if the
Records to which he appeals be true, as I think no doubt can be
made of 'em) by undeniable evidence overthrown all thoſe Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
for <hi>Presbytery</hi> mention'd in that Article. I will offer here a little
out of that Book unto the Reader for a taſte, remitting him to the
Treatiſe it ſelf, which (if I am not miſtaken) is worth any Man's
peruſing: I am ſure it gave me infinite Satisfaction. He tells us
then,</p>
            <p>
               <q>That there were many Prelates, who concur'd in that Work,
<hi>(ſc.</hi> the Reformation from Propery) as the Biſhop of <hi>Galloway,</hi>
and of <hi>Argyle,</hi> the Abbots of <hi>Lundoris,</hi> of <hi>Culroſs,</hi> of <hi>St. Colmes-Inih,</hi>
of <hi>Coldingham,</hi> of <hi>St. Mary Iſle,</hi> of <hi>Aberbrothoick,</hi> of <hi>Kilwin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi>
and of <hi>Newbottle;</hi> the Prior of <hi>St. Andrews,</hi> and the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior.
<hi>Fundament. Chart.</hi> p. 4. <hi>He further ſhews,</hi> that not one
Martyr, Confeſſor, or any that had an hand in the Reformation
in the Year 1560, declar'd for Presbytery or againſt Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
<hi>pag. 20.</hi> not <hi>John Knox</hi> himſelf, <hi>pag. 21.</hi> but that Superin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendency
was erected by <hi>Knox,</hi> p. 35. that <hi>Knox</hi> compil'd the
firſt Book of Diſcipline, <hi>Anno 1560. pag. 36.</hi> that in the Year
1559. the <hi>Scots</hi> being delivered from the <hi>French</hi> Slavery by the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Aſſiſtance, ſubſcrib'd to the Religious Worſhip and Rites
of the Church of <hi>England. [This is taken out of</hi> Buchanan, <hi>p. 714]
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:102854:23"/>
p. 87, 88, 93.</hi> that the <hi>Scotch</hi> Proteſtants uſed the Liturgy of the
Church of <hi>England</hi> in their Publick Devotions, <hi>Anno 1557. p. 95,
96, 101.</hi> that in the fifth Head of the firſt Book of Diſcipline
eſtabliſht at <hi>Perth, Anno 1560,</hi> it was appointed that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil
ſhould nominate Superintendents, <hi>p. 113, 114.</hi> that the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendents
had Diſtricts and Dioceſſes under them; that there
were but ten or twelve deſign'd, for the whole Kingdom; that
they collated or inſtituted Pariſh-Miniſters, <hi>p. 121.</hi> that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd
Pariſh Miniſters, if occaſion requir'd; that the Superin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendents
were to be admitted, (that is Ordain'd) not by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-Miniſters,
but the Neighbouring Superintendents, <hi>p. 122.</hi>
that their Income was five times as much as that of Pariſh Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,
<hi>p. 123.</hi> that they were conſtant Members of General Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies;
that all inferiour Miniſters were bound to pay them Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical
Obedience, <hi>p. 125, 126.</hi> that they appointed Dioceſan
Synods and Faſts, <hi>p. 131.</hi> that Appeals were made to them
from Pariſh Judicatures, <hi>p 132.</hi> that in the ſecond Model at
<hi>Leith, Jan. 12. 1571-72,</hi> it was agreed the old Politie ſhould revive,
<hi>p. 185.</hi> the old Names and Titles of Archbiſhops and Biſhops re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd,
and the old Diviſion of Dioceſſes take place, <hi>p. 186.</hi> that
the Reformation continu'd upon this bottom till 1576, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence,
that Prelacy was the Government of the <hi>Scotch</hi> Church
from the beginning of the Reformation for fifteen years, and not
alter'd then but with much difficulty and ſtruglings, <hi>as it fellows
in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Author.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But let it be ſuppos'd, That the Reformation of <hi>Scotland</hi> was firſt
caſt into the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Platform, it proves not that <hi>Presbytery</hi> was the
firſt and moſt ancient Government of the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> but only
that at the time of Reformation it was agreeable to the <hi>Scots</hi> Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.
For I ſhall in another Paper hereafter to be publiſh'd prove,
that the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> was govern'd by Biſhops of old time.
And therefore I am ſtill of the Opinion, that the <hi>Scotch</hi> Kirk put
away the Wife of its Youth, I mean Epiſcopacy, when it reform'd
from Popery, and join'd it ſelf unto an Harlot (I mean Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery.)
'Tis an odd way for an Husband to reform his Wife by ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perinducing
and noiſing her with a ſtrange Woman.</p>
            <p>Ay,<note place="margin">Rem. ibid.</note> but the Rector reflects upon the King, ſays the Remarker.
This is the firſt time I ever heard of a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> having any
due regard unto a King's Honour, and perhaps it will be the laſt,
if the Commonwealth Principle gets a little more footing amongſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:102854:24"/>
us. But let us examin what Truth is in the Accuſation. When the
<hi>Scotch</hi> Parliament had intimated unto the King their Inclination
unto <hi>Presbytery,</hi> the King tells his Commiſſioner, that he believes it
is ſo, and therefore is willing to condeſcend unto their Petition;
'tis no Reflection on the King (I hope) to deride the <hi>Scots</hi> Reaſon.
The Rector himſelf verily believes, that <hi>Presbytery</hi> is agreeable to
the <hi>Scotch</hi> Parliament's Inclination, but intends not thereby to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect
on himſelf. In ſhort, the <hi>Scotch</hi> Parliaments Reaſon for the
Act, was their Inclination, but the King's was to pleaſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
with them. He has been more kind unto them (I am afraid)
than they mannerly and thankful unto him.</p>
            <p>Now whereas the Act affirms alſo, that the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
is <hi>agreeable unto the Word of God,</hi> as well as <hi>to their Inclination;</hi>
it was in my Opinion very ſawcily done of 'em. Had it not been
ſufficient to acquaint the King, that <hi>Presbytery is agreeble to the Word
of God,</hi> but they muſt needs farther tell his Majeſty, 'tis agreeable
<hi>to their Inclination,</hi> as if they had ſaid, <hi>Sir, 'tis our mind it ſhould be
ſo, we muſt have this Point granted us, or elſe, &amp;c.</hi> Finally this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion,
<hi>Agreeable to the Word of God,</hi> is of doubtful conſtruction.
It may imply, that in their Judgment no kind of Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
being in Scripture expreſly eſtabliſht, <hi>Presbytery</hi> as well as any
other ſort <hi>is agreeable,</hi> that is not contrary <hi>to the Word of God.</hi> Their
Inclination then determin'd their Choice, and was made the Reaſon
of it.</p>
            <p>Before I diſmiſs the Vindication of my firſt Argument, I muſt
look back to an obſervation of the Author's, a very wiſe one I will
aſſure you before hand, and muſt not be forgot. You'l find it <hi>p. 6.</hi>
where (I having call'd the <hi>Cameronians</hi> by the name of <hi>Circumcelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Serm. p. 27.</note> and very rightly too (as were eaſie to make out) he notes that
the Rector <hi>overlooks a little Rule of Grammar in rendring</hi> Circumcelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones,
<hi>Circumcellians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> is juſt as good a Grammarian, as he is an Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.
I know no Rule of Grammar that I have tranſgreſt. The
Pedant would (I imagine) have it render'd <hi>Circumcellions;</hi> for ſo
we <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> are call'd <hi>Saxons,</hi> not <hi>Saxans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But my Rule in rendring <hi>Latin</hi> words into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> is to follow
the Cuſtom of my Country, and thoſe who have gone before me
as to words; and 'twas <hi>Horace</hi>'s long ſince, who was a better Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marian
than Mr. <hi>Owen,</hi> or his Reviſer at <hi>Mancheſter.</hi> He teaches
me to conform my ſelf to the uſual way of ſpeaking:
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:102854:24"/>
               <q>
                  <l>—Si volet uſus,<note place="margin">De Arte Poeticâ.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Quem penes Arbitrium eſt &amp; jus &amp; norma loquendi.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I have heard frequently the <hi>Circumcelliones</hi> call'd <hi>Circumcellians</hi> in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh.</hi>
I read 'em ſo render'd by Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> in his firſt <hi>Propoſ.</hi> on the
<hi>12th. Article.</hi> I find the ſame in <hi>Cole</hi>'s <hi>Engliſh</hi> Dictionary in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
He was a profeſt Maſter of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue. But perhaps Mr.
<hi>Owen</hi> may find 'em rendred <hi>Circumcellions</hi> alſo. Be it ſo. 'Tis then
indifferent which way we write 'em, and I hope Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
me my liberty in an <hi>indifferent thing.</hi> Laſtly, the Remarker
might have attributed this little miſtake to the Tranſcriber or Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
if he had ſo pleas'd. I am willing to deal ſo with him, when I
read <hi>Cacilius</hi> inſtead of <hi>Caecilius.</hi> p. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My ſecond Argument was,</hi> That the Corruption in appearance fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
the Diſſenters,<note place="margin">Ser. p. 24.</note> and their deſign againſt Epiſcopacy, that (if any)
they may be ſuſpected as willing to have it at leaſt continued and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated.</p>
            <p>The Queſtion then here between Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> and me is, whether
the Corruption favours the Diſſenters, and their Deſign againſt
Epiſcopacy. I determine it in the Affirmative, and prove it by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
an Account of the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s and the Diſſenters
Judgment and Practice.</p>
            <p>Of the firſt. After a Perſon is nominated, choſen or preſented
unto a Church or Congregation, the Biſhop firſt ordains him (if
he was not in Orders before; if he was) then the Biſhop inſtitutes
and appoints him by an Act altogether diſtinct from his Ordination,
as we believe was the caſe of the Deacons. But tho' the Elders or
Paſtors among the Diſſenters (who anſwer to our Biſhops) Ordain
Perſons unto the Miniſtry, yet the People or Congregation both
chuſe and appoint 'em, as they pleaſe and can beſt agree among
themſelves. Does not then reading the place, <hi>ye may appoint,</hi> favour
the Peoples power of heaping to themſelves their own Teachers.</p>
            <p>The Heads of Agreement give me no Satisfaction in this Point.
They lay down this Rule: <hi>'Tis ordinarily requiſite, that every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
Church in the Choice of its Miniſter conſult the Paſtors of Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring
Congregations.</hi> But what if the Paſtors of Neighb'ring Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations
differ in Judgment from the People of that particular
Church? Why this is an extraordinary caſe, and then it muſt go
on the People's ſide, for ſo 'tis imply'd in that Head. To ſpeak
freely theſe Heads are meer ſhams to make the World believe
that the united Brethren were come to ſome Agreement and Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:102854:25"/>
among themſelves. But thoſe looſe words <hi>Ordinarily requiſite,</hi>
ſpoil all, and leave the People ſtill to do what ſeems good in their
own Eyes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> They may, if they pleaſe, ask the Approbation of the
Neighbour Paſtors; and if they obtain it, well and good; but
and if they think <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, they may let it alone, or conclude contrary
to their Advice, when they believe it an extraordinary Caſe. And
who muſt be Judge of this but the People? In fine, our National,
Provincial and Claſſical <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Government, is fairly given
up, and dwindled into <hi>Independency,</hi> where the People domineer
over their Paſtor, and over one another alſo.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> argues, that the Diſſenters had no neceſſity to corrupt
this Place, the People's Power being juſt before abundantly aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
in thoſe words,<note place="margin">Rem. p. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Look ye out among you. Here</hi> (he ſays) <hi>the People
chuſe the Deacons.</hi> I anſwer they choſe not the ſeven Perſons imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately
into the Office deſign'd 'em, but only nominate, preſent,
and commend 'em to be approv'd and appointed thereunto by the
Apoſtles. For if the People's looking out and preſenting the Seven
unto the Apoſtles, was an effectual appointing them over the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs,
why is it afterwards added, <hi>Whom we</hi> (the Apoſtles) <hi>may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point
over this Buſineſs,</hi> or as the various Reading has it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<hi>Whom we will appoint over this Buſineſs.</hi> Did the Apoſtles appoint, after
the People had before appointed 'em unto that Buſineſs?</p>
            <p>The Remarker would obviate this by another Device, <hi>The People</hi>
(ſays he) <hi>choſe the Deacons, the Apoſtles ordain'd or appointed 'em ſo choſen,</hi>
plainly intimating the Ordaining and Appointing is the ſame thing.</p>
            <p>Here is not the place to diſpute this matter, thorowly: Suppoſe
Ordaining and Appointing the ſame thing, then the People's look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
out and preſenting the Seven unto the Apoſtles was not the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing
or eſtabliſhing them in their Office. Becauſe the Apoſtles
appointed them afterwards. Nor were the Apoſtles oblig'd to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
the People's choice and preſentation, for then it had been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent
to add, <hi>Whom we may</hi> (or will) <hi>appoint.</hi> The Alteration
then of the Text into <hi>Ye</hi> mightily favours the Power of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
appointing their own Miniſters.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> further objects that I have elſewhere granted, <hi>That
the choice of the Perſons to be preſented unto the Apoſtles was made by the
People. Tentam. nov.</hi> True. And I am of the ſame Opinion ſtill, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
under no neceſſity to alter it, that I am ſenſible of. The Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude
ſought out the Seven to be preſented unto the Apoſtles, and
gave this Teſtimonial of them, as muſt be ſuppos'd, that they
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:102854:25"/>
were Men of <hi>honeſt Report, full of the Holy Ghoſt and of Wiſdom.</hi> But
ſtill the Apoſtles appointed them over the Buſineſs, and not the
People. Whereas if you read <hi>Ye</hi> then the People muſt be confeſt
to have appointed the Deacons, and according to Mr. <hi>Owen,</hi> belike
Ordain'd 'em too.</p>
            <p>I might add (what would have been a ſufficient Anſwer unto Mr.
<hi>Owen</hi>'s Cavil) that the <hi>Cameronian</hi> at leaſt thought the alteration
gave ſome countenance to the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> elſe why did he alledg it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the Miniſter acquaints me,</hi> That the Seven Deacons were no
Miniſters of the Word and Sacrament in the Judgment of the Diſſenters,
and the <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Aſſembly, only Miniſters of Tables, <hi>in other
words, Overſeers of the Poor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot help theſe Men's Judgments, if they do not or will not
ſee it, 'tis becauſe there is no Light in them. I appeal to the Law and
to the Teſtimony of the Scripture in this and the eighth Chapters.
I will not repeat the Evidence. I only ask why do they not Ordain
their Overſeers of the Poor as the Apoſtles did by their own confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion?
I can imagine no other reaſon, but becauſe it is againſt their
inclinations, and looks like a Ceremony.</p>
            <p>To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conclude this Argument: The Remarker ſuggeſts, as if I
were not (according to my own Principle that is of the People's
chuſing their own Miniſters) rightly inveſted with the Rectory of
<hi>Bury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have already accounted for this in the <hi>Pref.</hi> to <hi>Tent. nov.</hi> The
Remarkers Buſineſs is not to argue ſoberly, but to cavil. I adviſe
him in the mean time to examin his own breaſt, whether he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd
his former Poſt at <hi>Wrexham</hi> by fair honeſt means: to ask
himſelf the Queſtion, Whether he did not betray and by a paultry
trick ſupplant Mr. <hi>Barnet</hi> his Predeceſſor and ſtep into his Place;
whether he did not diſcover the Secrets of his inward Friend and
Confident, who diſclos'd his heart to him, as to a Confeſſor. I
might moreover tell Mr. <hi>Owen,</hi> that time was when the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi>
decreed it <hi>Lawful for a Miniſter to take a Preſentation from a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron.</hi>
This Concluſion was made in the Provincial Meeting at
<hi>Preſton, July 6. 1647.</hi> as I find it Regiſtred in the fifth Meeting
of the ſecond Claſſis at <hi>Bury, July 22.</hi> of the ſame Year.</p>
            <p>But the Caſe it ſeems is alter'd; they have now quitted this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple
(I imagin) unto the <hi>Independents,</hi> who have requited them
with ſubmitting <hi>(in ordinary)</hi> unto the laying on of the hands of
the <hi>Presbytery.</hi> A Man cannot tell where to find theſe People.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:102854:26"/>
               <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> are at length Friends; how long 'twill
continue, time muſt ſhew. <hi>I</hi> am told there are ſome Diſſenters, or
Nonconformiſts among 'em already.</p>
            <p>My third Argument was to this purpoſe,<note place="margin">Ser. p. 14.</note> that the Epiſcopal
Party can not be imagin'd to have deſignedly corrupted this Place,
nor to have conniv'd at it ſince; for that would be to deſtroy,
what their Church Government <hi>ſeems</hi> to be built on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hereunto the Miniſter replies,</hi> That this proves nothing againſt the
Diſſenters, who do not charge the Epiſcopal Party with it. <hi>But I return,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it were deſignedly done,<note place="margin">Rem. p. 11.</note> or at leaſt, if it were afterwards
countenanced and propagated with deſign, as I ſhall once more
prove by and by, then becauſe Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> has acquitted us, the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters
muſt confeſs Guilty. And if Biſhops are (as we contend)
properly the Apoſtles Succeſſors, if the Deacons (as has been ſaid)
were Miniſters of the Word and Sacrament, then I am not abſurd
nor ſingular in hinting at an Argument for Epiſcopacy from this
Text, as others before me have done.</p>
            <p>But becauſe this Man of Grammar once more gives us a Caſt
of his Office, and quarrels at the word <hi>Seems,</hi> which (ſays he) is
as much as if I had contradicted my ſelf, and by ſaying <hi>Seems to
be built, had confest, it was not really built upon it.</hi> I muſt again ſhew
what an unhappy Critick and Puny Grammaticaſter he is. Let him
then turn to <hi>Act. 15. 28.</hi> There he'l read, <hi>It ſeemed good to the
Holy Ghoſt, and unto us;</hi> and <hi>Chap. 25. 27. It ſeemeth unreaſonable,
&amp;c.</hi> Was this as good as to ſay, <hi>It was not good to the Holy Ghoſt, &amp;c.</hi>
or <hi>it was not unreaſonable to ſend a Priſoner to</hi> Rome <hi>and not ſignifie the
Crimes laid to his Charge?</hi> Several other Examples of this kind I
could produce out of Scripture, and human Authors were it worth
the while. I only note that <hi>Tully</hi> in an hundred places uſes <hi>videtur,</hi>
when he intends to affirm. Thus <hi>Horace,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Tres mihi conviva propè diſſentire videntur</l>
                  <l>Poſcentes vario multum diverſa palato.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diſſentire videntur pro diſſentiunt,</hi> as the following words evince.
Laſtly, there is not a more common way of diſputing than the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponents
uſhering in their Arguments thus, <hi>Videtur quod ſic.</hi> They
do not thereby mean to intimate, that what they are about to
prove true is falſe. The Remarker then and his Aſſiſtants have
made a fearful ſtumble here and run their—heads againſt the
Authority of Scripture and all good Authors. Nay I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute
them out of Mr. <hi>Owen</hi>'s own mouth, <hi>Pref. pag. 2. Which</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:102854:26"/>
(ſays he, meaning our omitting to read ſome Books of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture)
<hi>ſeems to be a Diminiſhing from the Word of God,</hi> i e. According
to Mr. <hi>Owen</hi>'s Criticiſm, <hi>is not diminiſhing from it;</hi> why then does
he retort it upon us as if it were?</p>
            <p>My fourth and laſt Argument was deduc'd from the <hi>Cameroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>
citing this corrupt Place in favour of the People's Power of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing
over themſelves their own Teachers and Miniſters.</p>
            <p>The Miniſter objects, <q>That the Story concerns not the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
Presbyterians,</hi> that he expected I would have inſtanc'd in ſome
<hi>Engliſh Presbyterians;</hi> who have made uſe of this falſe Reading,
that the <hi>Scotch</hi> Evidence, is but hear-ſay, that 'tis ſcarce credible
a <hi>Cameronian</hi> ſhould aſſert a Doctrine directly contrary to the
<hi>Presbyterian</hi> Principles, that the Error of one Man ought not to
be charged upon all.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer to all this, <hi>I</hi> ſay,</p>
            <p>1. That for the matter of Fact <hi>I</hi> think it unqueſtionable. 'Tis
thus:</p>
            <p>The Honourable Colonel <hi>Fairfax</hi> reported this Fact unto the
Reverend Mr. <hi>Piggot</hi> Vicar of <hi>Rochdale</hi> in the hearing of ſeveral
Perſons then preſent, in particular of Mr. <hi>Rob. Mills</hi> a Shop-keeper
in <hi>Rochdale,</hi> and a known Diſſenter. After Mr. <hi>P.</hi> had ſatisfy'd 'em
about the true Reading of the place in the Original.</p>
            <p>The Company then at <hi>Rochdale</hi> 
               <q>conſulted ſeveral <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,
which they ſent for from private Houſes, and found them
corrupted in like manner; whereupon Col. <hi>Fairfax</hi> declar'd,
that he thought the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> had ſome Knaviſh Deſign. A
<hi>German</hi> Gentleman then in the Company with them pull'd a
<hi>Dutch</hi> Teſtament of <hi>Luther</hi>'s Tranſlation out of his Pocket,
wherein he read <hi>We,</hi> and then added, he was certain the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi>
in <hi>Germany</hi> and in <hi>Scotland</hi> (where he had lately been)
were Knaves, and it was well if they were better in <hi>England.</hi>
               </q> Mr.
<hi>Owen</hi> demanded a particular Account of this Fact; and <hi>I</hi> have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
it him. Theſe latter Circumſtance <hi>I</hi> would have bury'd in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion,
had not my adverſaries importunity forc'd me to make 'em
thus publick. 'Tis Mr. <hi>O.</hi> they are beholden to for it.</p>
            <p>2. The <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians</hi> are like to bear the Burden of their
Brethren in <hi>Scotland.</hi> As they deal with us, they ſhould be content
to be dealt with themſelves. They have no colour of Complaint,
when they duly conſider what they have done unto us.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>I</hi> promiſe him preſently an Example of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Diſſenter,
who has made uſe of this falſe Reading.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:102854:27"/>
4. <hi>I</hi> am apt to believe almoſt any thing even Contradictions of
a <hi>Cameronian.</hi> But the Comfort is, this is not one. The <hi>Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronian</hi>
pleaded not againſt Ordination by the hands of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
(as Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> like a Sophiſter repreſents the Caſe); but for the
Peoples appointing their own Miniſters of Tables. Therefore he
read the Place <hi>Ye</hi> the People.</p>
            <p>5. That 'tis no unuſual thing for the Error of one Man (or a
few) to be imputed to the reſt of that Party. Thus (to make uſe
of his own inſtance) <hi>Haman</hi>'s Offence was reveng'd upon many
Thouſands of the <hi>Perſons,</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi>'s upon Seven of his Children.
And thus the Note-maker fell foul upon the whole Body of the
Epiſcopal Church for a ſuppoſed fault of my L. Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ay,<note place="margin">Rem. p. 13.</note> but the <hi>Cameronian</hi> was an <hi>Ignorant</hi> Man happily.</p>
            <p>I had thought there were no <hi>Ignoramus</hi>'s among the <hi>Presbyterians.</hi>
If a Man will believe 'em hereabouts, all their Geeſe are Swans.
Every little Muſhroom, as ſoon as he firſt prickt up his Ears in
the Pulpit, is immediately cry'd up as an Angel ſent from Heaven,
tho' he ſprung out of the Earth as it were, but a few days before.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. V.</head>
            <head type="sub">Being a Reply to Mr. Owen's Third Chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Miniſter goes on and objects,</hi> That no Proteſtant Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters
have ever urg'd the corrupt Reading in favour of a Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
Government of the Church in their Writings.<note place="margin">Rem. p. 14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis a bold Touch this, to be ſo poſitive in a Negative. Has he
read all their Writings? I'll give him an Example of one, who
tho' he urg'd it not in Writing or in Print, yet alledg'd it in a
Diſputation. One Mr. <hi>Jolly</hi> ſome while ago (ſince dead) at <hi>Ducken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feild
Hall</hi> produc'd that Text in the <hi>6th.</hi> Act as alter'd into <hi>Ye</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the Reverend Mr. <hi>Elliſon</hi> Rector of <hi>Aſhton-under line;</hi> I have
Permiſſion from the ſaid Mr. <hi>Elliſon</hi> to aſſure the World of this
under his Name and Teſtimony, and which he will be ready to
verifie any other way, that ſhall be reaſonably requir'd of him.</p>
            <p>Take another of the like kind: There is a Gentleman now li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
at <hi>Bolton</hi> (ready upon demand to atteſt the Truth of what I
here relate) who heard ſome Diſſenters in a Diſpute about Religion
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:102854:27"/>
cite <hi>Acts 6.</hi> as the <hi>Cameronian</hi> did. But being told 'twas falſe
Printed, they reply'd that they Reading it ſo in ſeveral, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
the <hi>Scotch</hi> Bibles, knew not but it was as true as the other. Theſe
Diſſenters were not ('tis confeſt) Miniſters, but doubtleſs had been
furniſh'd with this Argument grounded on this falſe Reading by
ſome of their Leaders, who ought to have dealt with 'em more ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely.
'Tis remarkable here how they more eſpecially appeal'd to
the <hi>Scotch</hi> Bibles. I believe Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> will be wiſer, than to give
us another Catalogue of the corrupted Editions in <hi>Scotland,</hi> tho' he
has in part promis'd it. I ſhall be beholden to him, if he'l be pleas'd
to anſwer my Expectation herein, ſince I have not my ſelf intereſt
enough among 'em to procure an Accompt. I hope by this time Mr.
<hi>O.</hi> is in ſome reaſonable Meaſure ſatisfy'd.</p>
            <p>The Remarker further argues,<note place="margin">Rem. p 14.</note> that <hi>Had the Corruption been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd
in favour of the Diſſenters, it would have been promoted, when
they were uppermoſt.</hi> To fortifie this Objection, he has taken pains
to examin the Editions of moſt years from 1640 to 1696, and
obſerves, <q>that moſt of the faulty Editions happen'd in the Reign
of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, when the Biſhops had the Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of the Preſs, that the faulty Editions amount to Thirty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eight
according to his Collection, almoſt equal in number to the
other, which were not corrupted.</q> Let us now ſee what is to be
ſaid unto all this.</p>
            <p>1. I cannot tell, whether the Diſſenters would have promoted
the Corruption when they were uppermoſt. I am ſure there was
no need of doing it after they had gain'd their Point by another
Method, that of the Sword.</p>
            <p>By the way we never heard of altering Religion in <hi>England</hi> by
Dragoons, till the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> firſt oblig'd this Kingdom with that
new Invention in the late Civil War.</p>
            <p>2. Tho' far the greater number of faulty Editions were ſet forth
in King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's days, when the Diſſenters were under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt,
yet they may be ſuppos'd to have promoted the Corruption
even then. I never yet could learn, but they found Means at all
times to influence the Preſs in ſpight of Authority.</p>
            <p>3. The Biſhops had not in King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's Reign the
Management of the Preſs. That had been a long while in the
hands of Men having receiv'd it by Patent to them and to their
Aſſigns, who claim it as their Freehold and Inheritance; nor can
they eaſily be controul'd in their Buſineſs. The Lawyers in <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:102854:28"/>
Hall</hi> will tell you as much. The Biſhops have nothing to
do (no Authority) to Print, Licenſe, Order, Over-look, or to
Correct the Impreſſions of the Bible; but the King's Printers have
the ſole Power lodg'd in them; and for the Errors committed in
Printing are anſwerable to the King, or to the Law only. 'Twas
needful to ſet the ordinary Reader ſtreight in this matter, becauſe
the Remarker has ſo often harpt upon it, and entertain'd us with a
great deal of ſtuff, which having no Foundation of Truth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trays
his Ignorance or Malice againſt his Superiors, unto whom
he owes more <hi>Deference.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. 'Tis acknowledg'd by Mr. <hi>Owen,</hi> that there have been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>8.
Editions faulty in this Place, beſides thoſe in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi>
of late; and beſides Mr. <hi>Clark</hi>'s and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s falſe Prints,
and the ſame repeated in their Form of <hi>Church Government.</hi> Who
can believe an <hi>Erratum</hi> to have been thus often repeated by Chance?
Let the Miniſter give us an inſtance of any other miſtake in Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
whereupon depends any Controverſie in Religion, ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
committed in different Volumes, in ſo many Preſſes, by
ſo many Printers, and in ſo many diſtant Places, at <hi>Cambridge, Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,
London</hi> and <hi>Edinburgh;</hi> and it ſhall ſuffice: Till then I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
to be excus'd, if I continue to believe and aſſert the Text to
have ſuffer'd by deſign.</p>
            <p>Here I muſt acknowledge my ſelf beholden to the Remarker,
who by the great Pains he has taken in hunting after the corrupted
Editions has ſtrengthen'd my Argument, and left no Place for his
defence of the Diſſenters.</p>
            <p>To juſtifie my ſelf yet further againſt the Cenſures of ſome Men,
who have believ'd that the Charge, which I exhibited againſt the
Diſſenters in my Sermon, was not ſufficiently made out by ſuch
Proof or Circumſtances, as might have been expected in a thing of
this nature, I ſhall here preſent the Reader with a Parallel Caſe,
which I find in A B. <hi>Laud</hi>'s Speech in the <hi>Star Chamber.</hi> It begins
<hi>p. 64.</hi> The <hi>Puritans</hi> had in a Label accus'd the Prelates, <q>That
to juſtifie their Proceedings they <hi>(the Biſhops)</hi> had forg'd a new
Article of Religion brought from <hi>Rome</hi> giving them full Power
to alter the Doctrine and Diſcipline of our Church at a Blow, and
had foiſted it into the Beginning of the <hi>20th.</hi> Article, <hi>Anno 1628.</hi>
The Clauſe complain'd of is, The Church <hi>(the Libeller expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
it the Biſhops)</hi> has Power to decree Rites and Ceremonies,
and Authority in Controverſies, <hi>(the Libeller ſaid in Matters)</hi> of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:102854:28"/>
Faith. <hi>This Clauſe is a Forgery</hi> (ſaid the Libeller) <hi>not to be ſound in
the Engliſh or Latin Articles of Edward the Sixth, or Q. Elizabeth,</hi>
Ratify'd by Parliament.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Archbiſhops Anſwer unto this heavy Charge is, <q>That the
aforeſaid Clauſe was by theſe Men,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>A. B.</hi> L's Sp. p. 67.</note> or at leaſt by ſome of their
Faction razed out of the Article to weaken the juſt Power of the
Church to ſerve their Turns; that the ſaid Clauſe was in the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi>
Articles Printed 1612, 1605, 1593,<note place="margin">Pag. 68.</note> and in the <hi>Latin
1563,</hi> which was the firſt or one of the firſt Copies Printed but
ſome few Months after the Articles were agreed on. The A. B.
further confirm'd this from the Publick Records in his own Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
under the Hand of a Publick Notary,<note place="margin">Pag. 69.</note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> that the ſaid
Clauſe was in the <hi>20th.</hi> Article. What then, and where lies
the Myſtery of Iniquity? why he tells us that in the year 1571,<note place="margin">Pag. 70.</note>
there were ſome, who refus'd to ſubſcribe; that in the ſame
Year 1571 the Articles were Printed both in <hi>Latin</hi> and in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 71.</note> and that this Clauſe was left out of both; and that this could
not be done, but by the malicious Cunning of that oppoſite Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;
and <hi>(for ſome reaſons there given)</hi> it was no hard Matter to
have the Articles Printed, and this Clauſe left out. The Archbiſhop
adds out of the Records,<note place="margin">Pag. 72.</note> that all the lower Houſe of Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
ſubſcrib'd the Articles that very Year 1571, with the ſaid
Clauſe in them; and then concludes, <hi>I do here openly charge upon
that pure Sect this foul Corruption of falſifying the Articles of the Church
of England.</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>Let them take it off, as they can.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let then the Ingenuous Reader determin, whether I had not as
good, yea the ſame Reaſons to impeach the Diſſenters for this Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption
of <hi>Acts 6.</hi> at leaſt for propagating it; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
the Archbiſhop's Charge laid againſt the <hi>Puritans</hi> is not lyable
to the ſame or greater Objections than mine againſt the Diſſenters.
But that's admitted as Reaſon in one Man's Mouth, which will
not paſs from anothers.</p>
            <p>But to come nearer to my preſent Argument. Beſides the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture
of Col. <hi>F.</hi> and the Suſpicion of the <hi>German</hi> Gent. before ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
of, which 'tis natural for any Man in ſuch Caſes to diſcover, I
further add, the Right Reverend <hi>Edward</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cork</hi> and
<hi>Roſs</hi> in his Treatiſe Entitul'd, <hi>Scripture Authentick, and Faith certain,
p. 18.</hi> took Notice of this Corruption of Act 6. 3. and further
ſays, <hi>p. 19 'Tis not improbable it might be done at firſt with deſign,
and particularly of thoſe who would eſtabliſh the Peoples Power not only in
Electing, but even in Ordaining their own Miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:102854:29"/>
I muſt now take notice of ſome things, wherewith the Remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker
has imbelliſh'd this Chapter of his to give it a more agreeable
Reliſh unto the Reader's Palate.</p>
            <p>No Diſſenters <hi>(ſays he)</hi> have ever urg'd this corrupt Reading againſt
the Biſhops and Ceremonies.<note place="margin">Rem. p. 14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>How came Ceremonies here to be brought in by the head and
ſhoulders, and who ever thought that <hi>Ye</hi> had any thing to do with
the Ceremonies tho' we have? Theſe Mens Brains are ſo full of
Ceremonies, that they fancy they ſee 'em in every Book, and in
every Controverſie. So the Knight imagin'd he ſaw a Giant, and
prepar'd himſelf for the Combate; but it prov'd a Wind-mill;
ſo fearful and ſuperſtitious Men ſee Spirits or Hobgoblins, where
ever they go.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Owen <hi>informs his Readers (the greateſt part of whom will
doubtleſs take it for Truth)</hi> that I confidently affirm without the leaſt
proof that the Scotch Bibles are generally faulty in this Paſſage,<note place="margin">Rem. p. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Ser. p. 28.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Words there are, <hi>Having now juſt Reaſon to ſuſpect the Scotch
Bibles generally faulty in this Paſſage.</hi> Mr. <hi>O.</hi> changes 'em into, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently
affirms without proof.</hi> Whether I have juſt reaſon or not to
ſuſpect it, is ſubmitted to the Judgment of the Impartial Reader;
why elſe did the <hi>Cameronian</hi> ſend a great Congregation to their
Bibles, where they might find it ſo? but for Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> to make
the World believe, that <hi>I confidently affirm'd it without proof,</hi> is an
impudent Slander not to be parallel'd (I think) except in <hi>the Plea
for Scripture Ordination,</hi> and the <hi>five Diſputations of Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
and Worſhip,</hi> of both which more anon.</p>
            <p>That Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> a Miniſter of the Goſpel (as himſelf ſays) mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
Mr. <hi>Owen,</hi> who has <hi>an Affection for Truth and Charity for his
Neighbours,</hi> ſhould in the face of the World ſcandalize his Brother,
and not bluſh nor repent of it, nor in a private way recal and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
it (he knows my Meaning) is extraordinary. <hi>Tell it not in Gath
publiſh it not in Aſhkelon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I beg pardon for gathering a Flower in the Miniſters Garden. I
am not wont to make ſo bold with him. But 'tis a choice one I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,
I found it in his Plea <hi>(p. 71.)</hi> in his Defence, <hi>(p. 72.)</hi> and we
ſhall preſently meet with it again in theſe Remarks, <hi>(p. 18.)</hi> I was
therefore ambitious to have it for once in my Poſie.</p>
            <p>'Tis no wonder to me that the Miniſter is ſo terribly frighted
at the motion of a fire, eſpecially at his own door.</p>
            <q>—Tua Res agitur, Paries cum proximus ardet, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>caligon.</q>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:102854:29"/>
            <p>I can't blame him then for being concern'd. If Forgeries once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
to be ſacrificed unto the Flames, the <hi>Plea</hi> may happily take
fire, and receive its juſt Reward. But it may be 'tis the Light of
the Fire which offends him more than the heat. 'Tis natural for
ſuch as the Miniſter, whoſe Talent it is to corrupt Authors, <hi>to
love darkneſs rather than light. Every one that doth evil hateth the light,
neither cometh to the light, leaſt his deeds ſhould be diſcovered,</hi> Joh, 3. 19, 20.</p>
            <p>But why ſhould the Note maker be ſo ſtartled at my Propoſal?
Time was when he had not ſuch an averſion unto the burning of
Books.<note place="margin">Notes on Biſhop <hi>S. 4.</hi> Diſc. p. 2.</note> This calls to my mind how <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>14th.</hi> after he had
burnt many Goodly Cities, with his Bombs, and forc'd the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates
unto the ſame method of annoying their Enemies, made
hideous complaints of that Barbarous way of fighting, which he
would never be ſenſible of, till it came to his own turn.</p>
            <p>Well! but why burn the Holy Bible for one ſingle Corruption?
Why? becauſe an Error which appears in Maſquerade, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the diſguiſe of Scripture being diſcovered deſerves no pity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of ſo much the more dangerous Conſequence. A Spy, when he
is taken, is always put to death, but an open Enemy is only made a
Priſoner of War.</p>
            <p>The Concern which my Adverſaries here ſhew, leaſt this Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption
ſhould be publickly executed, and their willingneſs to have
it live ſtill under the Protection of the Holy Bible render it impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
for 'em to diſſemble its Parentage any longer. If we will be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd
by the Judgment of <hi>Solomon,</hi> the Bantling muſt belong un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
them, at whoſe doors it has been laid. Whoſe elſe ſhould it be?
but theirs, who palpably diſcover an Affection and Tenderneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
it, and burn their own fingers rather than the Impoſtor
ſhould be flung into the Fire.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
            <head type="sub">An Anſwer to Mr. Owen's Fourth Chapter.</head>
            <p>THE Miniſter has undertaken here a Defence of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi>
whom the Rector charg'd with abuſing the Scripture and
leaving out the word <hi>theſe,</hi> Act. 15. 28. and being accus'd of this
long ſince by Dr. <hi>Hook,</hi> never attempted a Reply or Vindication of
himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:102854:30"/>
If Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> was capable of being excus'd in this Matter, yet
of all Men living Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> ought not at this time o'th' day to have
taken upon him that Province. He has now himſelf ſtood twelve
Months and upward publickly indicted for a like Forgery, and has
not yet been able to aſſoil and clear himſelf. It ſeems unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
that one Criminal ſhould plead the Cauſe of another. Mr. <hi>B.</hi> is
not likely to be brought off by the Miniſter; who cannot, or has
not as yet,<note place="margin">Luc. Epig. 1.</note> made any tolerable Defence of himſelf.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
            <p>'Tis impoſſible that a Man, who manages his own Affairs ill,
ſhould do his Neighbours wiſely.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Miniſter pleads in behalf of Mr.</hi> Baxter,<note place="margin">Rem p. 18.</note> 
               <hi>that</hi> He was not at
leiſure nor diſpos'd to take notice of every trifling Accuſer.</p>
            <p>And yet the Rector had prevented this Excuſe by ſhewing,<note place="margin">Serm. Ep. Ded.</note> that
Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> had ſpare time enough <hi>to acquaint the World with the
moſt trivial and ridiculous paſſages of his own Life.</hi> Cunning Men are
never diſpos'd to anſwer, when they ſee it impoſſible; tho' there
be a ſort of Men who <hi>will always be medling.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rem. p. 19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Miniſter excuſes Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> from our Lord's ſilence towards
his Accuſers at the time of his Condemnation, <hi>Mat. 26. 63.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> had not in the whole courſe of his Life been conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually
engag'd in Controverſies, and then at his death had not left
us an Account of his Performances in the Hiſtory of himſelf, which
is a perpetual Monument of his Pride, and intemperate Heat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
his Betters and Superiors; but had been content at laſt to
have died with the meekneſs of a Lamb (as our Lord did) not
opening his mouth, there had been ſome colour for this compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.
But becauſe he left behind him his own Life wrote by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
in ſo haughty and contemptuous a manner towards his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries,
which one may call his dying words, and deſign'd it for the
Preſs, he cannot, with any Reaſon, nor in any Meaſure be excus'd
from the Silence of Jeſus Chriſt, but will paſs henceforth for an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregious
Example of ſelf-ſufficiency and a reſtleſs Diſpoſition. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
dead he yet ſpeaks, and even in the Grave is carrying on the
Squabbles and Controverſies, which he made a duſt with, when alive.</p>
            <p>I will not deny, but Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> after the Text alledg'd has (at
leaſt in my own Opinion) explain'd well enough what neceſſary
things are there meant, and how they became neceſſary. And I
do allow that no indifferent things ought to be impos'd except
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:102854:30"/>
when they are caſually become in ſome ſort neceſſary. But that,
which I contend for is, that our Ceremonies and our indifferent
things (at leaſt in our own Judgments) are at this day neceſſary in
the ſame ſenſe as ſome of thoſe are, which the Apoſtles injoyn'd,
<hi>Act. 15.</hi> But it is not a proper place to diſpute this Point here.
Only Mr. <hi>B.</hi>'s craft deſerves to be obſerv'd. He by omitting the
word <hi>theſe</hi> leaves an Impreſſion upon the mind of his Readers, that
no indifferent things at all ought to be impos'd on any account.
Many were unable, and others take no notice of his Explication
following.</p>
            <p>The Point which Mr. <hi>B.</hi> was arguing in the <hi>Petition for Peace,</hi>
was that no indifferent things might in any wiſe be impos'd upon
ſcrupulous Conſciences, which is manifeſtly and in the moſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
and unlimited Senſe, the Propoſition is capable of, aſſerted in
that Text, if you leave out the word <hi>theſe,</hi> that is, the two or
three things there mention'd.</p>
            <p>Mr. B. <hi>(ſays Mr.</hi> Owen) when he cites the words of Scripture does it in
a different Character in Italick Letters as in that very Page, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.
19. but <hi>Act. 15. 28.</hi> is cited in this Authors own Roman Character;
<hi>and therefore he intended not to tranſcribe the very Words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, tho' there is no great matter in this, yet I have look'd
into the Page, and find it quite otherwiſe. A Man muſt not truſt
Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> further than he ſees him. He'l be ſure to deceive you if
you do. He is not content to belye his Adverſary only, but he'l
venture hard in the defence of his Friend alſo. The Words of
that Text, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 19. are cited by Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> not in diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<hi>Italick,</hi> but in his own <hi>Roman</hi> Letters, and go before the Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.
'Tis the following paſſage of Scripture, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 2, 3.
which is put into <hi>Italick</hi> Letters, I might laſtly ſhew what Liberty
Mr. <hi>B.</hi> takes ſeven times in this very place, and ſome few that
follow, in citing Scripture not <hi>verbatim,</hi> but with ſome Variation,
which is the heinous Crime laid to my Charge, and ſo dangerous to
the <hi>ſecurity of the ſenſe and meaning</hi> of the Scripture. But 'tis hoped I
have ſufficiently vindicated my ſelf on that account already, and
have got Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> now on my ſide againſt the Miniſters at <hi>Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtry</hi>
and <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> if <hi>his</hi> Aſſiſtance were good for any thing.</p>
            <p>I am further inform'd, that <hi>Had Mr. B. cited the very words of the
Text he would have rendred them in the ſecond Perſon thus: It ſeemed
good unto the Holy Ghoſt, and to us,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>O te Bollane cerebri foelicem!</hi>
What a goodly Remarker's this! To <hi>us</hi> in the ſecond Perſon? Here
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:102854:31"/>
Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> has given us another inſtance of his mighty skill in Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar.
I ever thought the Pronoun <hi>us</hi> was of the firſt Perſon. But
to make ſure I took the Opinion of a little Boy of ſeven years
old; who confirm'd me in it. Theſe People the Remarker and
the Note-maker, tho' they pretend ſo much <hi>Deference to Superiors,</hi>
yet (I perceive) have <hi>no reſpect unto Perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is pleaſant to conſider how theſe Men, who pretend to be
skill'd in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Grammar and Rabbinical Criticiſms, who talk
at ſo confident a Rate of the <hi>Maſora,</hi> and of the <hi>Keri's</hi> and <hi>Cethib's,</hi>
are yet to learn the firſt Rudiments of all Languages, and know
not the very <hi>Engliſh</hi> Accidence. Were not the Lads too big, l'd
adviſe 'em to go to School again, and learn it a little better. And
yet for all this there's a Myſtery in the Miſtake. Their Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
are ſtill towards the <hi>ſecond Perſon,</hi> as ſome Bodys elſe was in
citing <hi>Act. 6. 3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor ſhall Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> eſcape ſo. For, as 'tis no ſmall Impiety to
miſquote the Scripture, ſo 'tis ſome Iniquity to corrupt good Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors.
I am perſwaded he, who makes no Conſcience of doing the
latter, will make no great Scruple of the former. Now Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>
cites and renders that Paſſage in <hi>Jerom</hi>'s Celebrated Epiſtle to <hi>Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grius
(Potentia Divitiarum &amp; Paupertatis Humilitis vel ſublimiorem vel
inferiorem Epiſcopum non facit)</hi> in the Affirmative;<note place="margin">Five Diſp. p. 218.</note> whereas in all
the Editions I have ſeen or can hear of, 'tis in the Negative <hi>non fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit,</hi>
and <hi>Jerom</hi>'s Argument requires it ſhould be ſo. Nor could it be
the ſlip of Mr. <hi>B.</hi>'s <hi>Amanuenſis</hi> or Printer, as any one may know,
who will look into the Deſign of the Author in that Place.</p>
            <p>And now my hand's in, it may not be improper here to take
the Remarker once more to Task by demanding a Reaſonable Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count,
why he, having in his <hi>Plea</hi> corrupted St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> has not
yet ſatisfied the World in that particular. He has indeed endeavour'd
it in the <hi>Defence of, &amp;c.</hi> p. 147. but very poorly, as I will now make
to appear.</p>
            <p>His firſt Excuſe is, that 'tis but a Syllabical Miſtake. And he
ſays true, 'tis no more; yet 'tis of ſuch a Nature, that it quite over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throws
the ſenſe and opinion of the Fathers, changing it from a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative
to an Affirmative Propoſition. He might every whit as well
have altered that Text, wherewith he adorns the Title-page of his
Remarks, and turn'd the Negative Precept into a Poſitive one, thus,
<hi>Thou ſhalt bear falſe witneſs againſt thy Neighbour,</hi> and then have ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gu'd
'tis but a Syllabical Miſtake. I am apt to think the latter Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labical
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:102854:31"/>
miſtake of the Commandment would have ſuited the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks
much better, than the true Reading, I having demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
that he has more than once born falſe witneſs againſt the Rector.</p>
            <p>2. He imputes the Error unto the Tranſcriber, and neglect of
correcting it in the <hi>Errata's</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This will not paſs muſter, good Mr. <hi>Owen.</hi> The matter you
were proving will not bear it, as I told you long ſince, and you
could not gain ſay it. For tho' your Memory be never ſo good,
and mine ſo bad, yet as you have reliev'd mine, I'll rub up yours.
You had affirm'd in your <hi>Plea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 19.</note> (as I obſerved to you formerly)
that Evangeliſts were extraordinary Church Officers, ſuch as were
not Reſident and fixt in one place, but paſt from one City or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince
to another. You endeavour'd to make out this firſt from <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius,</hi>
who writes, that the Evangeliſts <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
then you add, <hi>with whom agrees Chryſoſtome,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
&amp;c. In <hi>Engliſh</hi> thus (according to <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius),
Did paſs over into other Countries and Nations:</hi> And according
to <hi>Chryſoſtome, They did—go up and down every where.</hi> Now St.
<hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſays, <hi>They did</hi> not <hi>go up and down every where.</hi> If then you
had cited <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in the Negative (as you ought) he would not
have agreed with <hi>Euſebius;</hi> and ſo inſtead of confirming your
Point by this Father's Teſtimony, you would have confuted it.
Your Deſign therefore neceſſitated you to corrupt that Place in St.
<hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> that you might confirm your Point by a ſecond Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.
In a word by diſcharging your own fault upon the <hi>Amanu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſis</hi>
(or Printer) you have cover'd one piece of foul play with another.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Mr.</hi> Owen <hi>would vindicate his Innocence by alledging,</hi> That
he lay under no Temptation <hi>of altering</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> into <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>becauſe</hi> He needed nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Euſebius nor Chryſoſtom's Testimony to confirm his Opinion. For the
Acts and Epiſtles of Paul make it evident.</p>
            <p>That's to ſay Mr. <hi>O.</hi> wrote a <hi>Plea for Scripture Ordination,</hi> and in
this part of his Argument, and in this Place produc'd not a Word
of Scripture, but only two Authorities out of the Fathers, which
yet he now pretends he had no need of; that is, he had no need
of the only proofs he produc'd. For tho' now in his <hi>Defence</hi> he tells
us, that it is evinc'd from Scripture, yet in his <hi>Plea</hi> he not ſo much
as intimated any ſuch thing.<note place="margin">Def. p. 147</note> He boaſts of his many <hi>Hundred Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations:</hi>
And had he no need, or did he intend to make no uſe of
them to what purpoſe then did he cite 'em? Indeed, indeed, Friend,
this is a very idle and Boyiſh excuſe, and deſerves a Rod rather
than a Confutation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:102854:32"/>
4. I will confeſs he has in part accounted for his leaving <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
out of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> having at length ſound one <hi>Edition</hi> without it,
tho' 'tis one of the worſt, and does him as much harm as good, for
in aggravates his altering <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> into <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> That very Edition of <hi>Donat
Veron.</hi> whence he tranſcrib'd his Teſtimony having this Paſſage of
<hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in the Negative.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,<note place="margin">Def. p. 148</note> he contends he <hi>has Chryſoſtome on his ſide without that alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi>
This I ſhall hereafter examin, at preſent I ſubmit it to the
Judgment of the Learned, whether this is ſufficient to juſtifie him.
We ſometimes pardon thoſe that ſteal for neceſſity, but certainly
puniſh wanton Offenders.</p>
            <p>It being now manifeſt, that Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> muſt have purpoſely cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted
St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> and that he has not been able in any tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
manner to clear himſelf from this Charge, I crave leave of the
Reader to let him know, what ſome Diſſenters have frankly own'd,
which is to the purpoſe following, <q>That if Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> is indeed
guilty of the Crime laid againſt him, <hi>He is a Great</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">As for this broad Expreſſion, 'tis none of mine, I declare it.</note> 
                  <hi>Rogve,</hi> they
ſuppoſing (I believe) at the ſame time that he would certainly
aequit himſelf.</q> If he has acquitted himſelf I am content to bear the
reproach; if not let his Peers ſee to it, whether they have pronounc'd
a juſt Sentence upon him, and will give him his due Title of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
for the future.</p>
            <p>He has no ſhift, that I can imagin, but fairly to plead Ignorance,
and that he knew not the difference between <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. But the
miſchief is, as he cannot truly (I believe) ſo neither would he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
plead Ignorance in ſo ſmall a piece of knowledge. He had
much rather (I am perſwaded) his Honeſty ſhould be call'd into
queſtion, than his Abilities; and would chuſe to paſs for a Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
R—rather, than an innocent <hi>Ignoramus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort, I would adviſe him to be ſincere for once, to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
what he cannot deny nor palliare, <hi>viz.</hi> that he was <hi>under a
Temptation</hi> to corrupt St. <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi> Let not the Old <hi>Diverb</hi> affright
him; I promiſe to abſolve him, provided he will do ſo no more,
which is a Penance I fear he'l never be prevail'd with to ſubmit unto.</p>
            <p>For, as I was th' other day dipping in the Remarker's <hi>Tutamen
Evang.</hi> or <hi>Defence of Scripture Ordination,</hi> I chopt upon <hi>Pag. 124,
125.</hi> and found him thus arguing, <hi>Where doth Luke mention Paul's
Preaching the Goſpel</hi> in <hi>Illyricum, which we are ſure he did before his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment
at Rome,</hi> Rom. 15. 19. Here is a groſs and deſign'd
corruption of Scripture to ſerve a Cauſe. 'Tis in the Original, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:102854:32"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and in Engliſh, <hi>Round about unto Illyricum,</hi> as
if he had ſaid as far as <hi>Illyricum;</hi> but not <hi>in Illyricum,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Owen</hi>
aim'd to prove. I expect no other defence for this his ſhameleſs fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſifying
the Holy Scripture, but that 'tis a <hi>Syllabical miſtake,</hi> that
<hi>'twas</hi> the <hi>Tranſcriber's Error,</hi> that he was <hi>under no Temptation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>There are two things more which I muſt not paſs over with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
ſome Reflections on them before I conclude.</p>
            <p>The firſt is the mighty Character the Miniſter has beſtow'd
upon Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi> The ſecond is his reproaching me for my natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
or Providential misfortunes.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt, I obſerve he calls Mr. <hi>Baxter, That Great Man,
p. 18.</hi> 'Tis a great Scandal to Religion in my Opinion, when Men
keep themſelves within no compaſs in the commendation
of thoſe of their own Party, repreſenting them as Stars of the firſt
Magnitude in the Firmament of the Church, whereas hundreds
of 'em put together would make but a dim light like that of the
Milky-way, or of an empty Cloud; but much more, when they
ſtretch their Praiſes beyond all the Boundaries of Truth and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty.
I meet with ſeveral inſtances of this kind in the Life of Mr.
<hi>N. H.</hi> One is that the ſaid <hi>N. H.</hi> was wonderfully ſupported and
bleſſed by God, to ſuch a degree as that he lived creditably and
provided well for his Family under very narrow circumſtances;
whilſt his Adverſary Mr. <hi>St.</hi> having no charge but great Incomes,
was ſcarce able to ſuſtain himſelf, and at length died in debt.</p>
            <p>There needs nothing more to diſcover the malice of this Story
than in a few words to let the world know, that the Widow of the
ſaid Mr. <hi>St.</hi> is in very good Condition to this day. I wiſh Mr. <hi>N. H.</hi>'s
Poſterity were ſo. This is all I think fit to ſay at preſent on this
occaſion, unleſs I ſhould be bold to exhort Mr. <hi>O. H.</hi> to be a little
more charitablee to his neareſt Relations, who are not in ſo proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous
condition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Note-maker (as I gueſs) or who ever he be that ſet forth
the Life of Mr.</hi> P. <hi>acquaints the World that</hi> They who were preſent,
obſerv'd him make his Ordination Vows and Promiſes with great Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
of Spirit. <hi>And again,</hi> After he had taken his Degrees at Cambridge.</p>
            <p>By theſe laſt words a Man would imagin that Mr. P. had at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd
unto the Degree of Maſter at leaſt; but I have heard it oft
affirm'd hereabout, that he never took any Degree at all. Mr. <hi>P.</hi>
indeed before his Ordination produc'd a Certificate of his taking
the degree of Batchellor in Arts (as the Claſs-Regiſter informs
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:102854:33"/>
me) and was wont always to affirm it upon occaſion. But this does
not convince me, and forces me to call his Truth into queſtion. For
I am morally certain that he never took any Degree, if the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
Regiſter of the Univerſity may be truſted. But what will not
ſome Men if it may any ways contribute to the credit of the Cauſe,
and buoy up the reputation of the Heads of the Party?</p>
            <p>As for his making his <hi>Ordination-Vows and Promiſes with great Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility
of Spirit,</hi> I have this to ſay, that 'tis ſpoken at Random, yea
and againſt pretty good Evidence to the contrary. Is this conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent
with the Forgery of the foremention'd Certificate? Beſides,
how can any one know another Man's Humility of Spirit? <hi>What
Man knoweth the things of a Man, ſave the Spirit of Man, which is in
him? 1 Cor. 2. 11.</hi> And altho' we may make charitable Conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures
of Men's inward Diſpoſitions from their outward Deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
yet in the caſe of Mr. <hi>P.</hi> there was leſs ground for this, he
being naturally and at all times and in all his Actions of a very
ſtaid, grave and demure Behaviour. But that which I inſiſt on is,
that Mr. <hi>P.</hi> juſt between his Ordination and Examination when the
Claſſis inquir'd into <hi>his gracious Qualifications,</hi> in which ('tis ſaid)
he gave good ſatisfaction, had marry'd a young Woman without
her Parents conſent, yea againſt their declar'd mind. Himſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
at that time ſtood guilty of the breach of the Eighth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment.
He had entic'd the Woman unto the breach of the
Fifth, and engag'd a young Man by Marrying them to be a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker
in both. It can hardly enter into me, that Mr. <hi>P.</hi> was ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable
at that time for Humility of Spirit. I intend not hereby
to leſſen Mr. <hi>P.</hi> in any thing, wherein he was juſtly commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.
I very well know he was afterwards and in the main a good
Man, excepting always his being engag'd in the Schiſm. For this
I praiſe him not, and eſpecially becauſe tho' the Writer of his Life
aſſures us he declar'd upon his Death-bed, that he repented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
not at all of his Nonconformity (that may be true); yet I
have oft heard it from very good hands, that in the year 1662,
he would have conform'd, had not the <hi>Gray Mare</hi> been the better
Horſe.</p>
            <p>The ſum is, our Nonconformiſts commend one another at ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture,
without Reaſon, above meaſure, and beyond Truth, which
I cannot allow of. Thus the Remarker ſtiles Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> Great;
but, if Truth may be ſpoken, tho' he made himſelf great and
buſie, yet he was but a very little Man; however far from truly
deſerving that Character.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:102854:33"/>
If to value and commend a Man's ſelf to write the Minutes of
his own Life, to aggrandize his own Name and Performances,
publiſhing in a vain glorious manner, what pains he had taken,
what Difficulties he had ſtrugled with and ſurmounted, and yet at
the ſame time to inſiſt on the moſt trifling and dirty parts of his
Actions, even how well his Phyſick wrought (therefore I ſaid the
Minutes of his own Life), if ſuch a Man can merit the Title of
<hi>Great</hi> then is it juſtly given to Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If to raiſe one's own Reputation upon the Ruin of other Men's,
to trample upon their good Name, to expoſe their Infirmities, and
tranſmit 'em to Poſterity, to ſpare neither great nor ſmall, neither
Friend nor Foe, neither Stranger nor Neighbour, no not Father
nor Grandfather, ſo it may contribute ſomething to his own glory,
if ſuch a Man deſerves the Title of <hi>Great,</hi> then is it well beſtow'd
on Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If to ſpeak evil of the Rulers of the People, to be continually
declaiming againſt Superiours, undermining and overturning Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments,
ſpeaking evil of Dignities, ſnarling at their Laws,
ſpurning againſt their Commands, deriding their Conduct, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing
over their Misfortunes, and being never at eaſe, but
when he was embroiling the peace of the Nation; if ſuch a Man
may be ſtil'd <hi>Great,</hi> let Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> have the Honour.</p>
            <p>If to follow the Camp, and like ravenous Birds hover about
Armies, attending the Events of Battel, and waiting for the Prey:
If to have <hi>been in the heat of a Man's Zeal forward to change,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Letter to Dr. <hi>Hill,</hi> in <hi>Hyp. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nvail'd, p. 11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and
ways of Blood,</hi> and for that Reaſon <hi>fearful God would not let him have
an hand in the peaceable building of his Church, nor to ſee it;</hi> and yet
ſtill againſt the admonitions and checks of his own guilty Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
to be always buſie in projecting it, making a perpetual noiſe
and eternal wrangling about Church-Government to no purpoſe.
But, I ſay, if to be forward to promote War and Bloodſhed en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titles
a Man to be called <hi>Great,</hi> then may it be allow'd Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi>
as well as <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey,</hi> as <hi>Solyman</hi> and <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV.</p>
            <p>Some doubtleſs will look upon this as hard meaſure and ſevere,
eſpecially when the <hi>Great</hi> Man ſpoken of is gone to his Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Reſt. And I readily grant it is ſevere enough. But why then
did Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> take the liberty to rip up the Faults of the Ancient
Fathers,<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt Hiſtory.</note> to fling all the dirt on them, which Malice and Rage,
and intemperate Zeal, and a curious but ill-natur'd ſearch into their
failings and miſcarriages could furniſh him with? In ſhort my
Apology for this is,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:102854:34"/>
               <q>
                  <l>Dehinc ut quieſcant porro mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o; deſinan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Maledicere, malefacta ne noſcant ſua.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>2. Whereas the Remarker and his Reviſer,<note place="margin">Rem. p. 21.</note> take the liberty to
reflect upon me about my uſe of Spectacles, I am not aſham'd to
own that Age and Diſtempers have at length driven me unto this
very ordinary ſhift. I believe they themſelves have a tenderneſs for
Life, and would be glad to number the days of their Pilgrimage
as far as I have, and be content at laſt to betake 'emſelves to their
Spectacles. But there is no diſcretion, much leſs Humanity, leaſt
of all Piety to reproach any Man for his Natural Infirmities, how
bold ſoever they make with his Morals. They might have remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred
the Story of the Prophet <hi>Eliſha, 2 King. 2. 23.</hi> And tho' there
is no great fear of Bears tearing theſe Scoffers at Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
yet God has other Means in his Power to chaſtiſe this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent
way of Remarking upon his juſt and wiſe Adminiſtrations.</p>
            <p>But of all Men living the Reviſer at <hi>Mancheſter</hi> ought to have
expung'd this Witticiſm. God has not been ſo liberal to him in
the Perfection of theſe parts, but the Rector is ſtill able to vye
with him, and can perhaps ſee as far into a Mill-ſtone as he can.
In retort then, I'le only preſent him with a Paſſage out of <hi>Horace:</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Heus tu?<note place="margin">Horat. l. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 3.</note> Janoras re?</l>
                  <l>Cùm tua pervide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> oculis mala lippus inunctis,</l>
                  <l>Cur in amicorum vitiis tam cernis acutum?</l>
                  <l>—at tibi contra</l>
                  <l>Evenit, inquirant vitia ut tua rurſus &amp; illi.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>If it be reply'd they mean't not to meddle with my Natural Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities,
but glanc'd only at my reading my Sermons: Be it ſo:
Even this is to deſpiſe me for my weakneſſes. What if I have not a
good Memory, or not a voluble Tongue, or not a ſudden Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
ſuch as may enable me to diſcharge the Office of Preaching
off hand in ſo agreeable a manner, as ſome few can? and as, if at
all, it ought to be done? Or what if all this be an effect of the
want of Self-ſufficiency and too great diſtruſt of my ſelf? I had
rather be thought deficient in ſome of theſe Qualities, than be
admired for thoſe Boon-graces of Confidence and Impudence. I
chuſe rather by the help of my Eyes with the advantage of my
Spectacles to deliver my Sermons in a ſet form of words readily and
roundly pronounc'd (as I wiſh more would do) than utter <hi>Ex
tempore</hi> a great deal of rambling incoherent ſtuff with hums and
ha's, and vain repetitions, which tho' they are pretended for the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:102854:34"/>
benefit of the Audience, yet are indeed deſign'd for the Preachers
own eaſe, and to get time to pump for ſome new matter, and
what to ſay next. In ſhort, I rather beſtow my pains in compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
my own Sermons, as well as I can, that they may ſmell of
the Oyl and of the Lamp according to the poor ability, which God
has given me, than ſerve God and my Congregation with that
which coſt me nought, that's to ſay, than Preach other Men's
Works by heart, as Mr. <hi>O.</hi> knows who did.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <head>The CLOSE.</head>
            <p>IT was once in my thoughts to have ſum'd up the whole, that
has been ſaid, and to ſet it in a plain and ſhorter view before
the Reader; but there is no room left for ſuch a repetition. I on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
deſire it may be remembred that Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> and his Brethren ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
undertaken the Defence of the Diſſenters charged with coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing
and propagating the Corruption of the Word of God,
have at the ſame time, as far as in them lay, corrupted it. They
have endeavour'd to caſt out of the <hi>Greek</hi> Bible a conſiderable Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
together, with the Rector's Text, and thrown it over-board.
Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> has falſified <hi>Rom. 15. 19.</hi> meerly to ſerve a turn. They
have unfairly miſrepreſented the Rector every where; but they
have openly with a bare-fac'd and unparallel'd confidence down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right
bely'd him in that Paſſage of the <hi>Epiſtle Dedic.</hi> and that other
of the <hi>Serm. pag. 28.</hi> Whether theſe Men ought to be believ'd in
any thing they ſay or write, is left to the Judgment of the Candid
and Impartial Reader, what is to be thought of the Party, when
the Advocates themſelves are thus plainly detected in ſo many For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geries,
is not hard to determine, whether my Adverſaries will have
the Grace to ask God, the Church, and the Rector pardon for
theſe Scandals, is to be queſtion'd. They are too far gone and
hardned in their Impiety, I am afraid. Being plung'd over head
and ears in Debt they'l deſpair of making any ſatisfaction. Their
Predeceſſors (as in the Caſe of the Articles of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
before ſpoken of in Archbiſhops <hi>Laud</hi>'s Speech) began this
Trade long ago, and it has been their continual practice ever
ſince, as we ſee at this day.</p>
            <p>How many ſlanderous Reports of the Rector have within a few
Months been rais'd by that Party, is well known, and more ſtill
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:102854:35"/>
('tis to be ſuppos'd) are upon the Anvil. The Sin ſeems like <hi>Gehazis</hi>
Leproſy hereditary, and threatens to cleave to them and to their
Seed after 'em for ever. But the comfort is, that as Hypocriſie ſo
Lying when diſcovered tends to the Authors greater ſhame and
diſadvantage.</p>
            <p>As for the Principal Matters debated in theſe Papers, <hi>viz.</hi> the
Corruption of <hi>Act. 6.</hi> 'tis refer'd to the Judicious Reader whether I
had not Reaſon on my ſide, when I tax'd the Diſſenter with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign,
at leaſt of continuing it. It favour'd the Schiſm, which was then
hatching, and it began in a Juncture, when all hands were at work,
and no ſtone was left unturn'd to overthrow the pureſt and moſt flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing
Church in the World: It has increaſed and multipli'd ſince in
ſo many Impreſſions of the Bible, that 'twere ſenſleſs to believe it a
caſual Error: It has been publickly cited in the Pulpit for Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick
and in private Diſputes urg'd and deſended as the true Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
What would any Man have more to make good the Charge
laid againſt them, and what better Evidence can be given? except
one had been ſometime engag'd in their Intereſts and in their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels,
which I thank God I never was, and by his Grace never will be.</p>
            <p>I have not made it my buſineſs to provoke my Adverſaries with
all the keen and tart Reflections, which offer'd themſelves Many, and
eſpecially ſuch as ſeem'd moſt exaſperating I rejected upon ſecond
Thoughts, tho' his paultry Treatment of me deſerv'd it not at my
hands. But I remembred that other ſaying of the Wiſeman, <hi>Prov. 26.
4.</hi> my Purpoſe then hereafter is intirely to lay aſide this way of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverting,
and to leave Mr. <hi>O.</hi> Scolding by himſelf. For I perceive
by that little I have read of his <hi>Tutamen Evang.</hi> or <hi>Defence, &amp;c.</hi> (which
I intend in due time to reply unto and to the Remainder of his <hi>Plea,
&amp;c.)</hi> that he has there likewiſe purſu'd me, as far as his Malice and
Rancor (for which I never gave Occaſion) enabled him, tho' very ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily
Godwo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and very flatly in Compariſon with the Remarks, the
Reaſon whereof I have hinted before. Let him then go on and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per:
I'll give him no further diverſion or trouble of this kind. When
the raging fit is over, and Mr. <hi>O.</hi> is come to himſelf, he will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
ſee that his <hi>Tutamen</hi> is but like a Taylor's Bill, that after his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent
Excurſions, his froward Reflections on the perſon of his
Adverſary, the fulſom Commendations of himſelf, and the nauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Repetition of the ſame things over and over again are ſtruck
off; there will little remain, but what may be without the Expence
of much Labour eaſily anſwer'd.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
