<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>CXI propositions concerning the ministerie and government of the Church</title>
            <author>Gillespie, George, 1613-1648.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-10">2005-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42763</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G752</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21587</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12180378</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12180378</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55624</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A42763)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55624)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 762:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>CXI propositions concerning the ministerie and government of the Church</title>
                  <author>Gillespie, George, 1613-1648.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 31 [i.e. 45] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Evan Tyler ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government.</term>
               <term>Church polity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-05</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55624:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55624:1"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> PROPOSITIONS
Concerning
THE MINISTERIE
AND
GOVERNMENT
OF THE
CHURCH.</p>
            <p>EDINBURGH:
Printed by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to the
Kings most Excellent Majesty.
1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:55624:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55624:2"/>
            <head>Act approving VIII generall Heads of
Doctrine against the Tenents of Era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianisme,
Independencie, and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of Conscience, asserted in the CXI
Propositions, which are to be examined
against the next Assembly.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing tender of so great an ingagement
by Solemn Covenant, sincerely, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,
and constantly to endeavour in
our Places and Callings, the preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
of the Reformed Religion in
this Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in Doctrine,
Worship, Discipline, and Government, the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
of Religion in the Kingdomes of <hi>England,</hi> and
<hi>Ireland,</hi> in Doctrine, Worship, Discipline, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
according to the Word of God, and the
example of the best Reformed Kirks, and to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
the nearest Conjunction and Uniformity in all
these, together with the extirpation of Heresie,
Schisme, and whatsoever shall bee found contrary to
sound Doctrine: And considering withall that one of
the speciall meanes which it becometh us in our Places
and Callings to use in pursuance of these ends, is
<pb facs="tcp:55624:3"/>
in zeal for the true Reformed Religion, to give our
publike testimony against the dangerous Tenents of
<hi>Erastianisme, Independencie,</hi> and which is falsely called
<hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> which are not only contrary to
sound Doctrine, but more speciall lets and hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances
as well to the preservation of our own received
Doctrine, Worship, Discipline, and Government,
as to the Work of Reformation and Uniformity in
<hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> The Generall Assembly upon
these considerations, having heard publikely read
the CXI following Propositions exhibited and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
by some Brethren, who were appointed to
prepare Articles or Propositions for the vindication
of the Trueth in these particulars, Doth unanimously
approve and agree unto these eight generall Heads of
Doctrine therein contained and asserted, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. That
the Ministery of the Word and the Administration of
the Sacraments of the New Testament, Baptisme and
the Lords Supper, are standing Ordinances instituted
by God himself, to continue in the Church to the
end of the World. 2. That such as Administer the
Word and Sacraments, ought to be duely called and
ordained thereunto. 3. That some Ecclesiasticall
censures are proper and peculiar to be inflicted onely
upon such as bear Office in the Kirk; Other censures
are common and may bee inflicted both on Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters
and other Members of the Kirk. 4. That
the censure of suspension from the Sacrament of the
Lords Supper, inflicted because of grosse ignorance,
or because of a scandalous life and conversation; As
likewise, the censure of Excommunication or casting
out of the Kirk flagitious or contumacious offenders,
<pb facs="tcp:55624:3"/>
both the one censure and the other is warrantable by
and grounded upon the Word of God, and is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary
(in respect of divine institution) to be in the
Kirk. 5. That as the Rights, Power, and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of the Civill Magistrate are to bee maintained ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the Word of God, and the Confessions
of the Faith of the Reformed Kirks; So it is no lesse
true and cert<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine, that Jesus Christ, the onely Head
and onely King of the Kirk, hath instituted and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
a Kirk Government distinct from the Civill
Government or Magistracie. 6. That the Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
Government is committed and instrusted by Christ
to the Assemblies of the Kirk, made up of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters
of the Word and Ruling Elders. 7. That the
lesser and inferiour Ecclesiasticall Assemblies, ought
to bee subordinate and subject unto the greater and su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour
Assemblies. 8. That notwithstanding here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
the Civill Magistrate may and ought to suppresse
by corporall or Civill punishments, such as by sprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
Errour or Heresie, or by fomenting Schisme,
greatly dishonour God, dangerously hurt Religion and
disturbe the Peace of the Kirk. Which Heads of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
(howsoever opposed by the authors and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menters
of the foresaid errours respectively) the
Generall Assembly doth firmely beleeve, own, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,
and commend unto others, as Solide, True,
Orthodoxe, grounded upon the Word of God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonant
to the judgement both of the ancient and the
best Reformed Kirks. And because this Assembly
(through the multitude of other necessary and pressing
bussinesse) cannot now have so much leisure, as to
examine and consider particularly the foresaid CXI
<pb facs="tcp:55624:4"/>
Propositions; Therefore, a more particular exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
thereof is committed and referred to the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall
faculties in the four Universities of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
and the judgement of each of these faculties
concerning the same, is appointed to bee reported to
the next Generall Assembly. In the meane while,
these Propositions shall bee Printed, both that Copies
thereof may bee sent to Presbyteries, and that it
may be free for any that pleaseth to peruse them, and
to make known or send their judgement concerning
the same to the said next Assembly.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Ker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="tcp:55624:4"/>CXI
PROPOSITIONS
Concerning
THE MINISTERIE
AND
GOVERNMENT
OF THE
CHURCH.</head>
         <div n="1" type="proposition">
            <head>1.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S our Lord Jesus Christ doth invisibly teach
and governe his Church by the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:
So in gathering, preserving, instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting,
building and saving thereof, he useth
Ministers as his instruments, and hath
appointed an order of some to Teach, and
others to Learne in the Church, and that
some should be the Flock, and others the Pastours.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="proposition">
            <head>2.</head>
            <p>For beside these first founders of the Church of Christ
extraordinarily sent, and furnished with the gift of Miracles,
whereby they might confirme the Doctrine of the Gospel, he
appointed also ordinary Pastors and Teachers, for the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
of the Ministery, even untill his coming againe unto
Judgement, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 11, 12, 13. Wherefore, also as many as
are of the number of Gods People, or will bee accounted
Christians, ought to receive and obey the ordinary Ministers
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:55624:5"/>
of Gods Word and Sacraments, (lawfully though medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately
called) as the Stewards and Ambassadours of Christ
himself.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="proposition">
            <head>3.</head>
            <p>It is not lawfull for any man how fit soever and how
much soever inriched or beautified with excellent gifts, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake
the Administration either of the Word or Sacraments
by the will of private persons, or others who have not power
and right to Call<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> much lesse is it lawfull by their owne judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
or arbitr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment, to assume and arrogate the same to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves:
But before it bee lawfull to undergoe that Sacred Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery
in Churches constituted, a speciall Calling, yea beside,
a lawfull Election (which alone is not sufficient) a mission,
or sending, or (as commonly it is tearmed) Ordination, is
necessarily required, and that both for the avoiding of confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,
and to bar out or shut the door (so far as in us lieth)
upon impostors; as also by reason of divine institution delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
to us in the Holy Scripture, <hi>Rom. 10. 15. Heb. 5. 4. Tit.</hi>
1. 5. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 14.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="proposition">
            <head>4.</head>
            <p>The Church ought to bee governed by no other persons
then Ministers and Stewards preferred and placed by Christ,
and after no other manner then according to the Laws made
by him; and therefore, there is no power on earth which
may chalenge to it self Authority or Dominion over the
Church: But whosoever they are that would have the things
of Christ to bee administred not according to the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
and will of Christ revealed in his Word, but as it liketh
them, and according to their own will and prescript, what
other thing goe they about to doe then by horrible sacriledge
to throw down Christ from his own Throne.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="proposition">
            <head>5.</head>
            <p>For our onely Law-giver and Interpreter of his Fathers
will, Jesus Christ, hath prescribed and foreappointed the rule
according to which hee would have his Worship and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
of his owne House to bee ordered. To wrest this
rule of Christ laid open in his holy Word, to the Counsells,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55624:5"/>
Wills, Manners, Devices <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of Men, is most high im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety; But contrarily, the Law of Faith commandeth the
counsell and purposes of men to bee framed and conformed
to this rule, and overtuneth all the reasonings of worldly
wisdome, and bringeth into captivity the thoughts of the
proud swelling minde to the obedience of Christ. Neither
ought the voice of any to take place or bee rested upon in the
Church, but the voice of Christ alone.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="proposition">
            <head>6.</head>
            <p>The same Lord and our Saviour Jesus Christ, the only Head
of the Church hath ordained in the New Testament, not only
the Preaching of the Word and Administration of Baptisme
and the Lords Supper, but also Ecclesiasticall Government,
distinct and differing from the Civill Government, and it is
his will that there bee such a Government distinct from the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill
in all his Churches every where, as well those which live
under Christian, as those under infidell Magistrates, even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
the end of the World. <hi>Heb. 13. 7, 17. 1 Tim.</hi> 5. 17, 19.
<hi>Rom. 12. 8. 1 Cor. 12. 28. 1 Thes. 5. 12. Acts 1. 20, 28. Luke</hi>
12. 42. 1 <hi>Tim. 6. 14. Apoc.</hi> 2. 25.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="proposition">
            <head>7.</head>
            <p>This Ecclesiasticall Government distinct from the Civill,
is from God committed, not to the whole body of the Church
or Congregation of the faithfull, or to bee Exercised both by
Officers and People, but to the Ministers of Gods Word, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
with the Elders which are joyned with them for the
care and Government of the Church, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 17. To these
therefore who are over the Church in the Lord, belongeth
the Authority and Power, and it lyeth upon them by their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,
according to the rule of Gods Word to discerne and
judge betwixt the Holy and Prophane, to give diligence for
amendment of Delinquents, and to purge the Church (as
much as is in them) from scandalls, and that not only by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring,
inspection, warning, reproving, and more sharply
expostulating, but also by acting in the further and more
severe parts of Ecclesiasticall Discipline, or exercising,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55624:6"/>
Ecclesiastick jurisdiction; <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the greatest and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiest
censures, where need is.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="proposition">
            <head>8.</head>
            <p>None that is within the Church ought to bee without the
reach of Church-law, and exempt from Ecclesiastick
Censures; but Discipline is to be exercised on all the Members
of the Church, without respect or consideration of those ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering
qualities, which use to commend a man to other men,
Such, as Power, Nobility, illustrious Descent, and the like:
for the judgement cannot bee right, where men are led and
moved with these considerations. Wherefore, let respect of
Persons be farre from all Judges, chiefly the Ecclesiasticall:
And if any in the Church doe so swell in pride, that he refuse
to be under this Discipline, and would have himself to be free
and exempt from all tryall and Ecclesiastick judgement, this
mans disposition is more like the haughtinesse of the Romane
Pope, then the meeknesse and submissivenesse of Christs
Sheep.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="proposition">
            <head>9.</head>
            <p>Ecclesiasticall censure moreover, is either proper to bee
inflicted upon the Ministers and Office-bearers onely, or with
them common to other Members of the Church; The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
consisteth in suspension or deposition of Ministers from
their Office (which in the ancient Canons is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>)
The latter consisteth in the greater and lesser Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
(as they speak.) Whatsoever in another Brother de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serveth
Excommunication, The same much more in a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister
deserveth Excommunication: But justly sometimes a
Minister is to bee put from his Office, and deprived of that
Power which by Ordination was given him, against whom
neverthelesse to draw the sword of Excommunication, no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
doth compell.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="proposition">
            <head>10.</head>
            <p>Sometime also it happeneth that a Minister having fallen
into Heresie or Apostasie, or other grievous crimes, if hee
shew tokens of true repentance, may bee justly received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the communion of the Church; Whom notwithstanding,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55624:6"/>
it is no way expedient to restore into his former place or
charge; yea, perhaps it will not bee found fit to restore such a
one to the Ministery in another Congregation, as soone as hee
is received into the bosome of the Church; Which surely is
most agreeable as well as to the Word of God, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 23. 9.
<hi>Ezech.</hi> 44. 10, 11, 12, 13, 14. as to that Ecclesiasticall Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,
which in some ages after the times of the Apostles was
in use.</p>
            <p>So true is it that the Ministers of the Church are lyable as
well to peculiar as to common censures; Or that a Minister of
the Church is censured one way, and one of the people ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
way.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="proposition">
            <head>11.</head>
            <p>Ecclesiasticall censure, which is not proper to Ministers,
but common to them with other Members of the Church, is
either suspension from the Lords Supper, (which by others is
called the Publicanes Excommunication,) or the cutting off
of a Member, which is commonly called Excommunication.
The distinction of this twofold censure (commonly, though
not so properly passing under the name of the lesser and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
Excommunication) is not onely much approved by the
Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the Synode now assembled at <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster,</hi>
but also by the Reformed Churches of <hi>France,</hi> the
Low-countreys, and of <hi>Pole-land,</hi> as is to be seen in the <hi>book
of the Ecclesiastick Discipline of the Reformed Churches in
France. Chap. 5. Art. 9. In the harmonie of the Belgicks
Synodes. Chap. 14. Art.</hi> 8. 9. In the Canons of the generall
Synode of <hi>Torne,</hi> held in the yeare 1597.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="proposition">
            <head>12.</head>
            <p>That the distinction of that twofold Church censure was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
also by antiquity, it may be sufficiently clear to him who
will consult the sixtie one Canon of the sixth generall Synode,
with the Annotations of <hi>Zonaras</hi> and <hi>Balsamon;</hi> Also the
thirteenth Canon of the eighth Synode (which is termed the
first and second) with the Notes of <hi>Zonaras;</hi> Yea besides,
even the penitennts also themselves of the fourth degree, or
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, which were in the <hi>consistency,</hi> were
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55624:7"/>
suspended from the Lords Supper, though as to other things
of the same condition with the faithfull; For, to the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
also of Prayers, and so to all priviledges of Ecclesiasticall
society, the Eucharist alone excepted, they were thought to
have right: So sacred a thing was the Eucharist esteemed. See
also beside others, <hi>Cyprian 1. Book. Epist.</hi> 11. That <hi>Dyanisius</hi>
the Author of <hi>the Ecclesiastick Hierarchie. Chap. 3. Part.</hi> 3.
<hi>Basil. Epist.</hi> to <hi>Amphilochius. Can. 4 Ambros. lib. 2. De offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciis,
Chap. 27. Augustine in</hi> his <hi>book against the Donatists, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
the conference, Cap. 4. Chrysostom Homil. 83. in Matth.
Gregor. the great Epist, lib. 2. Chap. 65. and 66. Walafri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus
Strabo of Ecclesiasticall matters. Chap.</hi> 17.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="proposition">
            <head>13.</head>
            <p>That first and lesser censure by Christs ordinance, is to be
inflicted on such as have received Baptisme, and pretend to be
true Members of the Church, yet are found unfit and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
to Communicate in the signes of the grace of Christ with
the Church, whether for their grosse ignorance of divine
things, the Law namely and Gospel, or by reason of scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall
either of false Doctrine or wicked life. For these causes
therefore, or for some one of them, they are to be kept back
from the Sacrament of the Lords Supper (a lawfull judiciall
tryall going before) according to the interdiction of Christ,
forbidding that that which is Holy be given to dogs, or Pearles
bee cast before swine, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 6. and this censure of su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spension
is to continue, till the offenders bring forth fruits
worthy of repentance.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="proposition">
            <head>14.</head>
            <p>For the asserting and defending of this suspension, there
is no small accession of strength from the nature of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
it self, and the institution and end thereof. The Word
of God indeed is to bee Preached, as well to the ungodly and
impenitent that they may bee convened, as to the Godly and
repenting, that they may be confirmed: But the Sacrament
of the Lords Supper is by God instituted, not for beginning
the Work of Grace, but for nourishing and increasing Grace,
and therefore none is to be admitted to the Lords Supper, who
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55624:7"/>
by his life testifieth that hee is impenitent and not as yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="proposition">
            <head>15.</head>
            <p>Indeed if the Lord had instituted this Sacrament, that
not onely it should nourish and cherish faith, and seal the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises
of the Gospel, but also should begin the work of Grace
in sinners, and give regeneration it self, as the instrumentall
cause thereof, verily even the most wicked, most uncleane
and most unworthy were to be admitted. But the Reformed
Churches do otherwise judge of the nature of this Sacrament,
which shall be abundantly manifest by the gleaning of these
following Testimonies.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="proposition">
            <head>16.</head>
            <p>The <hi>Scottish</hi> Confession, <hi>Art. 23. But we confesse that the
Lords Supper belongs onely to those of the houshold of faith,
who can try and examine themselves, as well in faith, as in the
duties of faith towards their neigbours. Whoso abide without
faith, and in variance with their brethren, doe at that holy
Table eat and drink unworthily. Hence it is that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors
in our Church doe enter on a publike and particular exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,
both of the knowledge, conversation and life of those
who are to be admitted to the Lords Table. The Belgick </hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession.
<hi>Art. 35. Wee beleeve also and confesse that our Lord
Jesus Christ hath ordained the holy Sacrament of his Supper,
that in it he may nourish and uphold them whom hee hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
regenerated.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="proposition">
            <head>17.</head>
            <p>The <hi>Saxon</hi> Confession. <hi>Art.</hi> 15. of the Lords Supper. <hi>The
Lord willeth that every receiver bee particularly confirmed by
this testimony, so that hee may bee certified that the benefits of
the Gospel doe appertaine to himself, seeing the Preaching is
common, and by this testimony<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by this receiving, he sheweth
that thou art one of his members, and washed with his blood. </hi>And
by and by. <hi>Thus therefore we instruct the Church, that at be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooveth
them that come to the Supper, to bring with them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance
or conversion, and (faith being now kindled in the
mediation of the death and resurrection, and the benefits of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55624:8"/>
Son of God) to seek here the confirmation of this faith.</hi> The
very same things are set downe, and that in the very same
words in the consent of the Churches of <hi>Pole-land</hi> in the <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ian</hi>
Synode, <hi>Anno 1570. Art. of the Lords Supper.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="proposition">
            <head>18.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> Bohemian <hi>Confession.</hi> Art. 11. Next our Divines
teach that the Sacraments of themselves, or as some say, <hi>ex
opere operato,</hi> doe not confer Grace to those, who are not first
endued with good motions and inwasdly quickened by the Holy
Spirit, neither doe they bestow justifying faith, which maketh
the soul of man in all things obsequious, trusting and obedient
to God; for faith must goe before (wee speake of them of
ripe yeares) which quickeneth a man by the work of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Spirit, and putteth good motions into the heart. <hi>And after:</hi>
But if any come unworthily to the Sacraments, hee is not made
by them worthy or cleane, but doth only bring greater sinne and
damnation on himself.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="proposition">
            <head>19.</head>
            <p>Seeing then in the holy Supper, that is in the receiving the
Sacramentall Elements (which is here distinguished from
the Prayers and Exhortations accompanying that action) the
benefits of the Gospel are not first received, but for them being
received are thanks given; neither by partaking thereof doth
God bestow the very spirituall life, but doth preserve, cherish
and perfect that life; and seeing the Word of God is accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
in the manner of letters patents, but Sacraments like seals,
(as rightly the <hi>Helvetian</hi> Confession saith, Chap. 19.) it
plainly followeth that those are to be kept back from the Lords
Supper, which by their fruits and manners doe prove them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
to be ungodly or impenitent, and strangers or alients from
all communion with Christ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Nor are the promises of Grace
sealed to any other then to those to whom these promises doe
belong, for otherwise the seal annexed should contradict and
gainsay the letters patents; and by the visible Word those
should bee loosed and remitted, which by the audible Word
are bound and condemned: But this is such an absurdity, as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55624:8"/>
that if any would, yet hee cannot smooth or heal it with
any plaister.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="proposition">
            <head>20.</head>
            <p>But as known, impious, and unregenerate persons,
have no right to the holy Table: So also ungodly persons by
reason of a grievous scandall are justly for a time deprived of
it; for it is not lawfull or allowable that the comforts and
promises which belong onely to such as beleeve and repent,
should be sealed unto known unclean persons, and those who
walk inordinatly, whether such as are not yet regenerate, or
such as are regenerate, but fallen and not yet restored or risen
from their fall. The same Discipline plainly was shaddowed
forth under the Old Testament, for none of Gods People
during their legall pollution, was permitted to enter into
the Tabernacle, or to have accesse to the solemne Sacrifices
and society of the Church: And much more were wicked
and notorious offenders debarred from the Temple ever untill
by an offering for sinne, together with a solemne confession
thereof, being cleansed, they were reconciled unto God.
<hi>Num. 5. 6, 7, 8. Lev.</hi> 5. to the 7. <hi>vers. Lev.</hi> 6. to <hi>vers.</hi> 8.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="proposition">
            <head>21.</head>
            <p>Yea that those who were polluted with sins and crimes
were reckoned among the unclean in the Law, <hi>Maimonides
in more Nevochim, Part. 3. Chap.</hi> 47. proveth out of <hi>Lev.</hi>
20. 3. <hi>Lev. 18. 24. Num.</hi> 35. 33, 34. Therefore seeing the
shedding of mans blood was rightly esteemed the greatest pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution
of all; Hence it was, that as the society of the leprous
was shunned by the cleane, so the company of murtherers
by good men was most religiously avoided, <hi>Lament.</hi> 4. 13, 14,
15. The same thing is witnessed by <hi>Ananias</hi> the high Priest, in
<hi>Josephus of the Jewish Warre. 4. Book, Chap.</hi> 5. where hee
saith that those false Zelots of that time, bloody men, ought
to have been restrained from accesse to the Temple, by reason
of the pollution of murther; Yea as <hi>Philo</hi> the Jew witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth
in his book <hi>of the Offerers of Sacrifices;</hi> Whosoever
were found unworthy and wicked, were by edict forbidden to
approach the holy thresholds.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="22" type="proposition">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:55624:9"/>
            <head>22.</head>
            <p>Neither must that be part by which was noted by <hi>Zonaras,</hi>
Book 4. of his Annals, (whereof see also <hi>Scaliger</hi> agreeing
with him, in <hi>Elench. Triheres. Nicserrar. Cap.</hi> 28) namely
that the Essenes were forbidden the holy Place as being hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous
and p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acular transgressers, and such as held other opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
and did otherwise teach concerning Sacrifices then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the Law, and observed not the ordinances of <hi>Moses,</hi>
whence it proceeded that they Sacrificed privately; Yea and
also the <hi>Essenes</hi> themselves did thrust away from their Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations
those that were wicked. Whereof see <hi>Drusius of
the three sects of Jews, Lib. 4. cap.</hi> 22.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="23" type="proposition">
            <head>23.</head>
            <p>God verily would not have his Temple to bee made open
to unworthy and uncleane worshippers, nor was it free for
such men to enter into the Temple. See <hi>Nazianzen, Orat.</hi>
21. The same thing is witnessed and declared by divers late
writers, such as have beene and are more acquainted with the
Jewish antiquities. Consult the Annotations of <hi>Vetablus</hi>
and of <hi>Ainsworth</hi> an English writer upon <hi>Psal.</hi> 118. 19, 20.
also <hi>Constantius L'empereur Annotat, in Cod. Middoth, Cap.</hi>
2. <hi>Pag. 44, 45. Cornelius Bertramus, of the common-wealth of
the Hebrews. Cap. 7. Henrie Vorstius, Animadvers. in Pi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k.
Rab. Eliezer. Pag.</hi> 169. The same may bee proved out of
<hi>Ezech. 23. 38, 39. Jer.</hi> 7. 9, 10, 11, 12. whence also it was
that the solemne and publike Society in the Temple, had the
name of the Assembly of the Righteous, and Congregation
of Saints. <hi>Psal. 89. 5, 7. Psal. 111. 1. Psal.</hi> 147. 1. Hence
also is that, <hi>Psal.</hi> 118. 19, 20. of the gates of righteousnesse
by which the righteous enter.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="24" type="proposition">
            <head>24.</head>
            <p>That which is now driven at, is not that all wicked and
unclean persons should be utterly excluded from our Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall
Societies, and so from all hearing of Gods Word; Yea
there is nothing lesse intended: For the Word of God is the
instrument as well of conversion as of confirmation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
is to bee Preached as well to the not converted as to the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55624:9"/>
converted, as well to the repenting as the unrepenting: The
Temple indeed of <hi>Jerusalem</hi> had speciall promises, as it were
pointing out with the finger a Communion with God through
Christ, 1 <hi>King. 8. 30, 48. Dan. 6. 10. 2 Chron.</hi> 6. 16. and
7. 15, 16. But tis far otherwise with our Temples, or places
of Church Assemblies, <hi>because our Temples containe nothing
Sacramentall in them, such as the Tabernacle and Temple con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained;</hi>
as the most learned Professors of <hi>Leyden</hi> said rightly,
in <hi>Synops. Pur. Thelogie Disput. 48. Thes.</hi> 47.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="25" type="proposition">
            <head>25.</head>
            <p>Wherefore the point to be here considered as that which
is now aimed at, is this, that howsoever even under the New
Testament, the uncleannesse of those to whom the Word of
God is Preached bee tolerated; yet all such, of what estate or
condition soever in the Church, as are defiled with manifest
and grievous scandals, and doe thereby witnesse themselves to
be without the inward and spirituall Communion with Christ
and the faithfull, may and are to bee altogether discharged
from the Communion of the Lords Supper, untill they repent
and change their manners.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="26" type="proposition">
            <head>26.</head>
            <p>Besides, even those to whom it was not permitted to go
into the holy Courts of Israel, and to ingyre themselves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
Ecclesiasticall Communion, and who did stand betweene
the court of Israel and the utter wall, were not therefore to
be kept back from hearing the Word; for in Solomons Porch,
and so in the <hi>intermurale</hi> or court of the Gentiles, the Gospel
was Preached, both by Christ, <hi>John</hi> 10 23. and also by the
Apostles, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 11. and 5. 12. and that of purpose, because
of the reason brought by <hi>Pineda, of the things of Salomon,
book 5. Chap.</hi> 19. because a more frequent multitude was there,
and somewhat larger opportunity of sowing the Gospel:
Wherefore to any whomsoever, even heathen people meeting
there, the Lord would have the Word to be Preached, who
notwithstanding, purging the Temple, did not onely over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw
the tables of Money changers, and chaires of those that
sold Doves, but also, cast forth the buyers and sellers
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55624:10"/>
them<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elves, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21. 12. for hee could not endure either
such things, or such persons in the Temple.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="27" type="proposition">
            <head>27.</head>
            <p>Although then the Gospel is to be Preached to every creature,
the Lord in expresse words commanding the same, <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.
15. yet not to every one is set open an accesse to the holy Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.
Tis granted that Hypocrites do lurk in the Church, who
hardly can be convicted and discovered, much lesse repelled
from the Lord Supper. Such therefore are to be suffered, till
by the fanne of judgement the graine bee separate from the
chaffe; But those whose wicked deeds or words are knowne
and made manifest, are altogether to bee debarred from parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
those symboles of the Covenant of the Gospel, lest that
the Name of God bee greatly disgraced, whilest sins are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
to spread abroad in the Church unpunished; or lest the
Stewards of Christ by imparting the signes of the Grace of
God, to such as are continuing in the state of impurity and
scandall, bee partakers of their sinnes. Hitherto of su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spension.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="28" type="proposition">
            <head>28.</head>
            <p>Excommunication ought not to be proceeded unto, except
when extreme necessity constraineth: But whensoever the
soul of the sinner cannot otherwise bee healed, and that the
safety of the Church requireth the cutting off of this or that
Member, it behoveth to use this last remedy. In the Church
of <hi>Rome</hi> indeed Excommunication hath beene turned into
greatest injustice and tyrannie (as the Pharisees abused the
casting out of the Synagogues, which was their Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation)
to the fulfilling of the lust of their own mindes; Yet the
ordinance of Christ is not therefore by any of the Reformed
Religion to be utterly thrust away and wholly rejected. What
Protestant knows not that the vassals of Antichrist have drawn
the Lords Supper into the worst and most pernicious abuses, as
also the Ordination of Ministers and other ordinances of the
Gospel? Yet who will say that things necessary, (whether
the necessity be that of command, or that of the means or end)
are to be taken away because of the abuse?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="29" type="proposition">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:55624:10"/>
            <head>29.</head>
            <p>They therefore who with an high hand do persevere in their
wickednesse, after foregoing admonitions stubbornly despised
or carelessely neglected, are justly by Excommunication in the
Name of the Lord Jesus Christ cut off and cast out from the so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety
of the faithfull, and are pronounced to bee cast out from
the Church, untill beeing filled with shame and cast downe,
they shall returne againe to a more sound minde, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession
of their sinne and amendment of their lives, they shall
shew tokens of repentance, <hi>Matth. 18. 16, 17, 18. 1 Cor.</hi> 5.
13. Which places are also alleadged in the Confession of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,
Art.</hi> 8. to prove that the Excommunication of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent
and stubborne, whose wickednesse is known, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
of the Lord: But if stubborne Heretickes or unclean
Persons be not removed or east out from the Church, therein
doe the Governours of the Church sinne, and are found guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 14, 20.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="30" type="proposition">
            <head>30.</head>
            <p>But that all abuse and corruption in Ecclesiasticall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
may be either prevented and avoided or taken away, or
lest the power of the Church either by the ignorance or unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse
of some Ministers here and there, or also by too much
heat and fervour of minde, should run out beyond measure or
bounds, or contrariwise beeing shut up within straiter limits
then is fitting, should be made unprofitable, feeble, or of none
effect: Christ the most wise Law-giver of his Church hath
foreseen and made provision to prevent all such evills which
he did foresee were to arise, and hath prepared and prescribed
for them intrinsecall and Ecclesiasticall remedies, and those
also in their kinde (if lawfully and rightly applyed) both
sufficient and effectuall: Some whereof he hath most expresly
propounded in his Word, and some he hath left to bee drawne
from thence by necessary consequence.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="31" type="proposition">
            <head>31.</head>
            <p>Therefore by reason of the danger of that which is called
<hi>calvis errans,</hi> or a wrong key; and that it may not bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
to particular Churches to erre or sin licentiously, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55624:11"/>
lest any mans cause be overthrown and perish, who in a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
Church had perhaps the same men both his adversaries
and his judges; Also that common businesses which doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long
to many Churches, together with the more weighty and
difficult controversies, (the deciding whereof in the consisto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
of particular Churches is not safe to bee adventured upon)
may bee handled and determined by a common counsell of
Presbyteries. Finally that the Governours of particular
Churches, may impart help mutually one to another against
the cunning and subtill enemies of the truth, and may joyne
their strength together (such as it is) by an holy combinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
and that the Church may bee as a camp of an Army well
ordered; lest while every one striveth singly, all of them bee
subdued and overcome; or lest by reason of the scarcity of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
and Godly Counsellers (in the multitude of whom is
safety) the Affaires of the Church be undone: For all those
considerations particular Churches must bee subordinate to
Classicall Presbyteries and Synodes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="32" type="proposition">
            <head>32.</head>
            <p>Wherefore tis not lawfull to particular Churches or (as
commonly they are called) Parochiall, either to decline the
authority of Classes or Synodes, where they are lawfully set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
or may be had (much lesse to withdraw themselves from
that authority, if they have once acknowledged it) or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse
such lawfull Ordinances or Decrees of the Classes or Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodes,
as being agreeable to the Word of God are with au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
imposed upon them. <hi>acts</hi> 15. 2, 6, 22, 23, 24, 28, 29.
<hi>Acts</hi> 16. 4.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="33" type="proposition">
            <head>33.</head>
            <p>Although Synodes assemble more seldome, Classes and
consistories of particular Churches more frequently; Yet that
Synodes both Provinciall and Nationall assemble at set and
ordinary times as well as Classes and Parochiall consistories is
very expedient, and for the due preservation of Church po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie
and Discipline, necessary. Sometime indeed it is expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
they bee assembled occasionally, that the urgent necessity
of the Church may be the more speedily provided for, namely
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55624:11"/>
when such a businesse happeneth, which without great
danger cannot bee put off till the appointed time of the
Synode.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="34" type="proposition">
            <head>34.</head>
            <p>But that besides occasionall Synodes, ordinary Synodes be
kept at set times, is most profitable, not onely that they may
discusse and determine the more difficult Ecclesiasticall causes
coming before them, whether by the appeal of some person
agrieved, or by the hesitation or doubting of inferiour Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies
(for such businesses very often fall out;) but also that
the state of the Churches whereof they have the care, beeing
more certainly and frequently searched and knowne, if there
be any thing wanting or amisse in their Doctrine, Discipline or
Manners, or any thing worthy of punishment, the slothfull
labourers in the Vineyard of the Lord may bee made to shake
off the spirit of slumber and slothfulnesse, and be stirred up to
the attending and fulfilling more diligently their calling, and
not suffered any longer to sleep and snort in their office; the
straglers and wanderers may bee reduced to the way; the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toward
and stiffe-necked, which scarce or very hardly suffer
the yoke of Discipline, as also unquiet persons which devise
new and hurtfull things, may bee reduced to order. Finally,
whatsoever doth hinder the more quick and efficacious course
of the Gospel, may be discovered and removed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="35" type="proposition">
            <head>35.</head>
            <p>It is too too manifest (alas for it) that there are, which with
unwearyed diligence do most carefully labour, that they may
oppresse the liberties and rights of Synodes, and may take
away from them all libertie of consulting of things and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
Ecclesiasticall, at least of determining thereof, (for they
well know how much the union and harmonie of Churches
may make against their designes.) But so much the more it
concerneth the orthodox Churches, to know, defend and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve
this excellent liberty granted to them by divine right,
and so to use it, that imminent dangers, approaching evils,
urging grievances, scandalls growing up, schismes rising, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resies
creeping in, errours spreading, and strifes waxing hote,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:55624:12"/>
may be corrected and taken away, to the glory of God, the
edification and peace of the Church.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="36" type="proposition">
            <head>36.</head>
            <p>Beside Provinciall and National Synodes, an Oecumenicall
(so called from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is from the habitable World)
or more truely a Generall, or if you will, an Universall Synode,
if so be it be free and rightly constituted, and no other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners
but orthodox Churches bee admitted (for what
communion is there of light with darknesse, of righteousnesse
with unrighteousnesse, or of the Temple of God with idols)
Such a Synode is of speciall utility, peradventure also such a
Synode is to be hoped for, surely tis to be wished, that for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending
the orthodox Faith, both against Popery and other He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resies,
as also for propagating it to those who are without,
especially the Jews, a more strait and more firme consocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
may bee entered into. For the unanimity of all the
Churches as in evill tis of all things most hurtfull, so on the
contrary side, in good it is most pleasant, most profitable and
most effectuall.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="37" type="proposition">
            <head>37.</head>
            <p>Unto the Universall Synode also (when it may bee had)
is to bee referred the judgement of controversies, not of all,
but of those which are <hi>controversiae juris,</hi> controversies of
right, neither yet of all those, but of the chief and most weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
controversies of the orthodox faith, or of the most hard and
unusuall cases of Conscience. Of the controversies of fact
there is another and different consideration to be had; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides
that it would be a great inconvenience that plaintifes, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
accused, and witnesses bee drawne from the most remote
Churches, to the generall or universall Councell; the visible
communion it self of all the Churches (on which the universal
Counsel is built, and whereupon as on a foundation it leaneth)
is not so much of company, fellowship, or conversation, as of
Religion and Doctrine. All true Churches of the World doe
indeed professe the same true Religion and faith; but there is
beside this a certaine commixture and conjunction of the
Churches of the same Nation, as to a more near fellowship,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55624:12"/>
and some acquaintance, conversing and companying together,
which cannot be said of all the Churches thoughout the habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
World.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="38" type="proposition">
            <head>38.</head>
            <p>And for this cause, as in doctrinall controversies which
are handled by Theologues and Casuists, and in those which
belong to the common State of the orthodoxe Churches, the
Nationall Synode is subo dinate and subjected to the universall
lawfully constituted Synode, and from the Nationall to the
Oecumenicall Synode (when there is a just and weighty
cause) an appeal is open: So there is no need that the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals
of them who complaine of injurie done to them through
the exercise of Discipline in this or that Church, should goe
beyond the bounds of the Nationall Synode; But tis most a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable
to reason that they should rest and acquiesce within
those bounds and borders: And that the ultimate judgement of
such matters bee in the Nationall Synode, unlesse the thing it
selfe be so hard and of so great moment, that the knot be just<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
thought worthy of a greater decider: In which case the
controversie which is carried to the universall Synode, is rather
of an abstract generall Theologicall proposition, then of the
particular or individuall case.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="39" type="proposition">
            <head>39.</head>
            <p>Furthermore the Administration of the Ecclesiastick power
in Consistories, Classes and Synodes, doth not at all tend to
weaken in any wise, hurt or minish the authority of the civil
Magistrate, much lesse to take it away or destroy it, yea ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
by it a most profitable help cometh to the Magistrate, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmuch
as by the bond of Religion, mens consciences are more
straitly tyed unto him. There hath been indeed phantasticall
men who under pretence and cloak of Christian liberty, would
abolish and cast out Lawes and Judgements, Orders also, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees
and Honours out of the commonwealth, and have been
bold to reckon the function of the Magistrate armed with the
sword, among evill things and unlawfull: But the Reformed
Churches doe renounce and detest those dreames, and do most
harmoniously and most-willingly confesse and acknowledge
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55624:13"/>
it to be Gods will that the World bee governed by Lawes and
Policy, and that hee himself hath appointed the civill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate,
and hath delivered to him the sword to the protection
and praise of good men, but for punishment and revenge on
the evill, that by this bridle, mens vices and faults may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained,
whether committed against the first or against the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
Table.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="40" type="proposition">
            <head>40.</head>
            <p>The Reformed Churches beleeve also and openly confesse the
power and authority of Emperours over their Empires, of
Kings over their Kingdomes, of Princes and Dukes over their
Dominions, and of other Magistrates or States over their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths
and Cities, to be the Ordinances of God himself,
appointed as well to the manifestation of his owne glory, as
to the singular profit of mankinde: And withall, that by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
of the will of God himself revealed in his Word, wee
must not onely suffer and be content that those doe rule which
are set over their own territories, whether by hereditary or by
elective right, but also to love them, fear them, and with all
reverenee and honour imbrace them as the Ambassadours and
Ministers of the most high and good God, being in his stead,
and preferred for the good of their Subjects; to powre out
Prayers for them, to pay tributes to them, and in all businesse
of the Commonwealth which are not against the Word of
God, to obey their lawes and edicts.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="41" type="proposition">
            <head>41.</head>
            <p>The orthodoxe Churches beleeve also, and doe willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
acknowledge, that every lawfull Magistrate, being by God
himself constituted the keeper and defender of both Tables of
the Law, may and ought first and chiefly to take care of Gods
glory, and (according to his place, or in his manner and
way) to preserve Religion when pure, and to restore it when
decayed and corrupted; And also to provide a learned and
Godly Ministery, Schools also and Synodes, as likewise to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straine
and punish as well Atheists, Blasphemers, Hereticks
and Schismaticks, as the violaters of Justice and Civill Peace.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="42" type="proposition">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:55624:13"/>
            <head>42.</head>
            <p>Wherefore the opinion of those Sectaries of this age is
altogether to be disallowed, who, though otherwise insinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating
themselves craftily into the Magistrates favour, doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
unto him the authority and right of restraining Hereticks
and Schismaticks, and do hold and maintaine that such persons
how much soever hurtfull and pernicious enemies to true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
and to the Church, yet are to bee tolerated by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate,
if so bee he conceive them to bee such as no way vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late
the Laws of the Commonwealth, and in no wise disturbe
the civill Peace.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="43" type="proposition">
            <head>43.</head>
            <p>Yet the civill Power and the Ecclesiasticall ought not by
any meanes to be confounded or mixed together: Both pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
are indeed from God and ordained for his Glory, and both
to be guided by his Word, and both are comprehended under
that precept, <hi>Honour thy father and thy mother:</hi> So that men
ought to obey both civill Magistrates and Ecclesiasticall gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours
in the Lord; To both powers their proper dignity and
authority is to be maintained and preserved in force: To both
also is some way entrusted the keeping of both Tables of the
Law, also both the one and the other doth exercise some ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction,
and giveth sentence of judgement in an externall
court or judicatory: But these, and other things of like sort, in
which they agree notwithstanding, yet by marvellous vaste
differences are they distinguished the one from the other, and
the rights of both remaine distinct, and that eight manner of
wayes, which it shall not bee amisse here to adde, that unto
each of these Administrations, its own set bounds may bee the
better maintained.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="44" type="proposition">
            <head>44.</head>
            <p>First of all therefore they are differenced the one from
the other, in respect of the very foundation and the instituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
For the politicall or civill power is grounded upon the
Law of nature it selfe, and for that cause it is common to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels
with Christians: The power Ecclesiasticall dependeth
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55624:14"/>
immediatly upon the positive Law of Christ alone, that beer
longeth to the Universall Dominion of God the Creator ove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
Nations; but this unto the speciall and Oeconomicall King
dome of Christ the Mediator, which hee exerciseth in the
Church alone, and which is not of this World.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="45" type="proposition">
            <head>45.</head>
            <p>The second differences in the object, or matter about
which: The power politick or civill is occupied about the
outward man, and civill or earthly things, about Warre,
Peace, conservation of Justice, and good order in the
Commonwealth; also about the outward businesse or exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
things of the Church, which are indeed necessary to the
Church, or profitable, as touching the outward man, yet not
properly and purely spirituall, for they doe not reach unto the
soul, but only to the externall state and condition of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters
and Members of the Church.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="46" type="proposition">
            <head>46.</head>
            <p>For the better understanding whereof, tis to bee observed
that so farre as the Ministers and Members of the Church are
Citizens, Subjects, or Members of the Commonwealth, it is
in the power of the Magistrate, to judge, determine and give
sentence concerning the disposing of their bodies or goods; As
also concerning the maintenance of the poor, sick, the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished,
and of others in the Church which are afflicted; To
regulate (so farre as concerneth the civill order) Marriages,
Burials, and other circumstances which are common both to
holy, and also to honest civill societies; to affoord places fit
for holy Assemblies and other externall helps by which the
sacred matters of the Lord may be more safely, commodious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
and more easily in the Church performed: To remove the
externall impediments of divine Worship or of Ecclesiasticall
Peace, and to represse those which exalt themselves against
the true Church and her Ministers, and doe raise up trouble
against them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="47" type="proposition">
            <head>47.</head>
            <p>The matter may further bee thus illustrated: There is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most
the like respect and consideration of the Magistrate as he
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55624:14"/>
is occupied about the outward things of the Church, and of
the Ecclesiastick Ministery as it is occupied about the inward
or spirituall part of civill Government, that is, about those
things which in the Government of the Commonwealth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long
to the conscience. It is one thing to governe the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,
and to make politicall and civill Lawes; ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
thing to interpret the Word of God, and out of it to
shew to the Magistrate his duty, to wit, how he ought to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne
the Commonwealth, and in what manner he ought to
use the sword. The former is proper and peculiar to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate
(neither doth the Ministery intermeddle or intangle it
self into such businesses,) but the latter is contained within the
office of the Ministers.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="48" type="proposition">
            <head>48.</head>
            <p>For to that end also is the holy Scripture profitable, to shew
which is the best manner of governing a Commonwealth, and
that the Magistrate as being Gods Minister may by this guiding
Starre bee so directed, as that he may execute the parts of
his office, according to the will of God, and may perfectly
be instructed to every good work; yet the Minister is not said
properly to treat of civill businesses, but of the scandalls
which arise about them, or of the cases of conscience which
occurre in the Administration of the Commonwealth: So al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
the Magistrate is not properly said to be exercised about the
spiritual things of the Church, but rather about those exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
things which adhere unto and accompany the spirituall
things.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="49" type="proposition">
            <head>49.</head>
            <p>And in such externall matters of the Church, although
all Magistrates will not, yet all, yea even heathen Magistrates
may and ought to aide and help the Church; Whence it is
that by the command of God, Prayers are to be made also for
an heathen Magistrate, that the faithfull under them may live
a quiet life with all godlinesse and honesty. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 1, 2.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="50" type="proposition">
            <head>50.</head>
            <p>Unto the externall things of the Church belongeth, not
onely the correction of Hereticks and other troublers of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55624:15"/>
Church, but also that civill order and way of convocating
and calling together Synodes which is proper to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate;
for the Magistrate ought by his authority and power
both to establish the Rights and Liberties of Synodes assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling
together, at times appointed by the knowne and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
Law, and to indict and gather together Synodes occasio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally,
as often as the necessity of the Church shall require
the same; Not that all or any power to consult or determine
of Ecclesiastick or Spirituall matters doth flow or spring from
the Magistrate as Head of the Church under Christ; but bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
in those things pertaining to the outward man, the
Church needeth the Magistrates aid and support.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="51" type="proposition">
            <head>51.</head>
            <p>So that the Magistrate calleth together Synodes, not as
touching those things which are proper to Synodes; but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect
of the things which are common to Synodes with other
meetings and civill publike Assemblies, that is, not as they
are Assemblies in the name of Christ, to treat of matters spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall,
but as they are publike Assemblies within his territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries;
for to the end that publike conventions may bee kept in
any territorie, the licence of the Lord of that place ought to
be desired. In Synodes therefore a respect of order, as well
Civill as Ecclesiasticall is to bee had; And because of this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill
order, outward defence, better accommodation, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
with safe accesse and recesse, the consent and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of him who is appointed to take care of, and defend hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
order, doth interveene.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="52" type="proposition">
            <head>52.</head>
            <p>Moreover when the Church is rent asunder by unhappy
and lamentable schismes, while they who have raised the
troubles, and have given cause of solemne gathering a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node
(whether by their Heresie or Schisme or Tyranny,
or any other fault of others) use to place the great strength
and safeguard of their cause in declining and fleeing the triall
and sentence of a free Synode, as being formidable to them;
Who seeth not that they cannot be drawn to a publike and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall
tryall, nor other disobedient persons be compelled to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55624:15"/>
obedience without the Magistrate publike mandate and
helpe?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="53" type="proposition">
            <head>53.</head>
            <p>The object of Ecclesiasticall power is not the same
with the object of the Civill power, but much differing from
it; for the Ecclesiasticall power doth determine and appoint
nothing concerning mens bodies, goods, dignities, civill rights,
but is imployed only about the inward man, or the soul; not
that it can search the hearts, or judge of the secrets of the
conscience, which is in the Power of God alone: Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding
it hath for its proper object those externalls
which are purely spirituall, and do belong properly and most
nearly to the spirituall good of the soul; Which also are tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the inward things of the
Church.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="54" type="proposition">
            <head>54.</head>
            <p>Those things then wherein the Ecclesiasticall power is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercised,
are the Preaching of the Word, the Administration
of Sacraments, publike Prayer and Thanksgiving, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techising
and instructing of children and ignorant persons, the
examination of those who are to come to the holy Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
the Ecclesiasticall Discipline, the Ordination of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters,
and the abdication, deposing, and degrading of them
(if they become like unsavory salt) the deciding and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining
of controversies of Faith and cases of Conscience,
Canonicall constitutions concerning the treasury of the
Church and collections of the Faithfull, as also concerning
Ecclesiasticall rites, or indifferent things, which pertaine to
the keeping of decency and order in the Church, according to
the generall rules of Christian love and prudence contained
in the Word of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="55" type="proposition">
            <head>55.</head>
            <p>Tis true that about the same things, the Civill power is oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupyed,
as touching the outward man, or the outward dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing
of divine things in this or that Dominion, as was said;
not as they are Spirituall and Evangelicall Ordinances piercing
into the conscience it self<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But the object of the power Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55624:16"/>
is a thing meerly and purely spirituall; and in so
far as it is spirituall) for even that jurisdiction Ecclesiasticall
which is exercised in an outward court or judicatory, and
which inflicteth publike censures, forbiddeth from the use of
the holy Supper, and excludeth from the society of the
Church) doth properly concerne the inward man, or the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance
and salvation of the soul.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="56" type="proposition">
            <head>56.</head>
            <p>Surely the Faithfull and Godly Ministers, although they
could doe it unchallenged and uncontrolled, and were therein
allowed by the Magistrate (as in the Prelaticall times it was)
yet would not usurpe the power of life and death, or judge
and determine concerning mens honours, goods, inheritance,
division of Families, or other civill businesses; seeing they
well know these things to bee heterogeneous to their office:
But as they ought not to entangle themselves with the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of civill causes, so if they should bee negligent and
slothfull in their owne office, they shall in that bee no lesse
culpable.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="57" type="proposition">
            <head>57.</head>
            <p>To the object also of Ecclesiasticall power belongeth the
assembling of Synodes, so far as they are spirituall Assemblies
proper to the Church, and assembled in the holy Ghost; for
being so considered, the governours of Churches after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
of the Apostles and Presbyters, <hi>Acts</hi> 1 5. in a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest
danger of the Church, ought to use their owne right of
meeting together and conveening, that the Churches endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered
may be relieved and supported.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="58" type="proposition">
            <head>58.</head>
            <p>Thirdly, Those powers are differenced in respect of their
formes, and that three wayes: For first the Civill power, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
in respect of God it bee Ministeriall, yet in respect of
the Subjects it is Lordly and Magisteriall. Ecclesiasticall
power is indeed furnished with authority, yet that authority
is liker the Fatherly then the Kingly authority; Yea also tis
purely Ministeriall, much lesse can it bee lawfull to Ministers
of the Church to bear dominion over the flock.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="59" type="proposition">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:55624:16"/>
            <head>59.</head>
            <p>Emperours, Kings, and other Magistrates are indeed appointed
fathers of the Countrey, but they are withall Lords of their
People and Subjects; Not as if it were permitted to them to
bear rule and command at their own will and as they list (for
they are the Ministers of God for the good and profit of the
Subjects) yet it belongs to their power truely and properly to
exercise dominion, to hold principality, to proceed imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously.
It is indeed the duety of Ministers and Rulers of the
Church to oversee, to feed as shepherds, to correct and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie,
to bear the keyes, to bee Stewards in the house of
Christ, but in no wise to bee Lords over the house, or to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne
as Lords, or Lordlike to rule; yea in brief, this is the
difference between the civill Magistrate and the Ecclesiasticall
Ministery, in respect of those which are committed to their trust,
that the lot of the former is to bee served or ministred unto,
the lot of the latter to minister or serve.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="60" type="proposition">
            <head>60.</head>
            <p>Now we have one onely Lord which governes our souls,
neither is it competent to man, but to God alone to have pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
and authori<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y over consciences. But the Lord hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
his owne Stewards over his own Family, that according
to his commandment they may give to every one their allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
or portion, and to dispense his mysteries faithfully; and
to them hee hath delivered the keyes, or power of letting in
into his house, or excluding out of his house those whom hee
himself will have let in or shut out. <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. 19. and 18.
18. <hi>Luk. 12. 42. 1 Cor. 4. 1. Tit.</hi> 1. 7.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="61" type="proposition">
            <head>61.</head>
            <p>Next, the civill power is indued with authority of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling,
But it belongs not to the Ministery to compell the
disobedient; If any compulsion bee in or about Ecclesiasticall
matters, tis adventitious from without, to wit, from the
help and assistance of the Magistrate, not from the nature of
Ecclesiasticall power, from which it is very heterogeneous;
and therefore if any Suspended or Excommunicate person
should be found who shall be so stiffe-necked, and so impudent,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55624:17"/>
that at once he cast off all shame, and make no account at all
of those censures, but scorne and contemne the same, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure
shall insolently or proudly engyre and obtrude him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
upon the Sacrament, or being also filled with devillish
malice do more and more contradict and blaspheme; the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall
Ministery in such cases hath nothing more to do by
way of jurisdiction: But the Magistrate hath in readinesse a
compelling jurisdiction and externall force, whereby such
stubborne rebellious and undaunted pride may bee externally
repressed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="62" type="proposition">
            <head>62.</head>
            <p>Last of all, the power of the Magistrate worketh onely
politically or civilly, according to the nature of the Scepter
or Sword, maketh and guardeth civill Lawes, which some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
also he changeth or repealeth, and other things of that
kinde hee effecteth with a secular power: But the Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
power dealeth spiritually, and onely in the Name of our
Lord Jesus Christ, and by authority entrusted or received from
him alone: neither is it exercised without Prayer or calling on
the Name of God; nor lastly doth it use any other then spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
weapons.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="63" type="proposition">
            <head>63.</head>
            <p>The same sinne therefore in the same man may be punished
one way by the civill, another way by the Ecclesiasticall
power; by the civill power under the formality of a crime,
with corporall or pecuniary punishment; By the Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
power, under the notion and nature of scandall, with a
spirituall censure, even as also the same civill question is one
way deliberate upon and handled by the Magistrate in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
or place of Judgement; another way by the Minister of
the Church, in the Presbytery or Synode; by the Magistrate
so farre as it pertaineth to the Government of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,
by the Minister, so far as it respects the conscience;
for the Ecclesiasticall Ministery also is exercised about civill
things spiritually, in so far as it teacheth and admonisheth the
Magistrate out of the Word of God what is best and most ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable
unto Gods or as it reproveth freely unjust judgements,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55624:17"/>
unjust warres, and the like, and out of the Scripture threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
the wrath of God to be revealed against all unrighteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
of men; So also is the Magistrate said to bee occupied
civilly about spirituall things.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="64" type="proposition">
            <head>64.</head>
            <p>Therefore all the actions of the civill Magistrate, even
when hee is imployed about Ecclesiasticall matters, are of
their own nature and essentially civill: he punisheth external<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Idolaters, Blasphemers, Sacrilegious persons, Hereticks,
Prophaners of holy things, and according to the nature and
measure of the sinne hee condemneth to death or banishment,
forfeiture of goods, or imprisonment; he guardeth and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derproppeth
Ecclesiasticall Cannons with civill authority,
giveth a place of habitation to the Church in his territorie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straineth
or expelleth the insolent and untamed disturbers
of the Church.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="65" type="proposition">
            <head>65.</head>
            <p>Hee taketh care also for maintaining the Ministers and
Schools, and supplieth the temporall necessities of Gods Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,
by his command assembleth Synodes, when there is
need of them; and summoneth, calleth out, and drawes to
triall the unwilling, which without the Magistrates strength
and authority cannot be done, as hath been alreadie said; he
maketh Synodes also safe and secure, and in a civill way pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideth
or moderateth in them (if it so seem good to him) either
by himself or by a substitute Commissioner. In all which
the power of the Magistrate though occupied about spirituall
things, is not for all that spirituall but civill.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="66" type="proposition">
            <head>66.</head>
            <p>Fourthly, they differ in the end: The immediate nearest
end of civill power is, that the good of the Commonwealth
may bee provided for and procured, whether it be in time of
Peace, according to the rules of Law and counsell of Judges;
or in time of Warre according to the rules of Militarie pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence;
and so the temporall safety of the Subjects may bee
procured, and that externall Peace and civill Liberty may bee
preserved, and being lost may be againe restored.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="67" type="proposition">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:55624:18"/>
            <head>67.</head>
            <p>But the chiefest and last end of civill Government is, the
glory of God the Creator, namely, that those which do evil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
by a superiour Power restrained or punished, &amp; those which
doe good getting praise of the same, the Subjects so much the
more may shun impiety and injustice, and that Vertue, Justice
and the Morall Law of God (as touching those eternall due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
of both Tables, unto which all the posterity of Adam
are oblieged) may remain in strength and flourish.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="68" type="proposition">
            <head>68.</head>
            <p>But whereas the Christian Magistrate doth wholly devote
himself to the promoting of the Gospel and Kingdom of Christ,
and doth direct and bend all the might and strength of his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
to that end: This proceedeth not from the nature of
his office or function, which is common to him with an Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell
Magistrate; but from the influence of his common Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
calling into his particular vocation.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="69" type="proposition">
            <head>69.</head>
            <p>For every member of the Church (and so also the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
and godly Magistrate) ought to referre and order his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
vocation, faculty, ability, power and honour to this end,
that the Kingdome of Christ may bee propagated and promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
and the true Religion bee cherished and defended: So
that the advancement of the Gospel and of all the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
of the Gospel, is indeed the end of the Godly Magistrate,
not of a Magistrate simply; or (if yee will rather) tis not
the end of the office it self, but of him who doth execute the
same piously.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="70" type="proposition">
            <head>70.</head>
            <p>But the end of Ecclesiasticall power, yea the end as well
of the Ministery it self, as of the Godly Minister, is, that the
Kingdome of Christ may bee set forward, that the pathes of
the Lord bee made straight, that his holy mysteries may bee
kept pure, that stumbling-blocks may bee removed out of the
Church, lest a little leaven, leaven the whole lump; or
lest one sick or scabbed sheep infect the whole flock; that the
faithfull may so walk as it becometh the Gospel of Christ,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55624:18"/>
and that the wandering sheep of Christ may be converted and
brought back to the sheepfold.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="71" type="proposition">
            <head>71.</head>
            <p>And seeing this power is given of the Lord, not to destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
but to edification; Therefore this same scope is propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
in Excommunication, (which is the greatest and last of
Ecclesiasticall censures) namely, that the soul of an offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
brother may be gained to Christ, and that being stricken
with fear, and the stubborne sinner filled with shame, may
by the grace of God be humbled, and may (as a brand pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
out of the fire) bee snatched out of the snare of the devill,
and may repent unto salvation; at least the rest may turne
away from those which are branded with such a censure, lest
the soul infection do creep and spread further.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="72" type="proposition">
            <head>72.</head>
            <p>Fifthly, they are distinguished by the effect. The effect
of civill power is either proper or by way of redundance;
The proper effect is the safety temporall of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,
externall tranquillity, the fruition of civill Liberty,
and of all things which are necessary to the civill Society of
men: The effect by way of redundance is the good of the
Church, to wit, in so far as by execution of Justice and good
Lawes, some impediments that usually hinder and disturbe the
course of the Gospel, are avoided or taken away.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="73" type="proposition">
            <head>73.</head>
            <p>For by how much the more faithfully the Magistrate exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuteth
his office in punishing the wicked, and cherishing and
encouraging good men, taking away those things which
withstand the Gospel, and punishing or driving away the
troublers and subverters of the Church; so much the more the
orthodox Faith and Godlinesse are reverenced and had in esti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,
sinnes are hated and feared: Finally, all the subjects
contained (as much as concerneth the outward man) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
the lists of Gods Law; whence also by consequence it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth
by Gods blessing, that the Church is defiled with
fewer scandals, and doth obtaine the more freedome and
Peace.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="74" type="proposition">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:55624:19"/>
            <head>74.</head>
            <p>But the proper effect of the Ecclesiasticall power, or
keyes of the Kingdome of heaven is wholly spirituall; for
the act of binding and loosing, of retaining and remitting sins,
doth reach to the soul and conscience it self (which cannot
be said of the act of the civill power:) And as unjust Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication
is void, So Ecclesiasticall censure being inflicted
by the Ministers of Christ and his Stewards according to his
will, is ratified in heaven, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. 18. and therefore
ought to be esteemed and acknowledged in like manner as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted
by Christ himself.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="75" type="proposition">
            <head>75.</head>
            <p>Sixthly, they are also differenced in respect of the subject:
The politick power is committed sometimes to one, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
to more, sometime by right of election, sometime by
right of succession: But the Ecclesiasticall power is compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
to none under the New Testament by the right of succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,
but he who hath it must be called by God and the Church
to it; neither was it given by Christ to one either Pastor or
Elder, much lesse to a Prelate, but <hi>to the Church,</hi> that is to
the consistory of Presbyters: Tis confessed indeed, and who
can bee ignorant of it, that the power (as they call it) of
<hi>order</hi> doth belong to particular Ministers, and is by each
of them apart lawfully exercised? But that power which is
commonly called of jurisdiction is committed not to one, but
to the unity, that is to a consistory; therefore Ecclesiasticall
censure ought not to be inflicted but <hi>by many. 2 Cor.</hi> 2. 6.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="76" type="proposition">
            <head>76.</head>
            <p>Seventhly, they differ as touching the correlative.
God hath commanded that unto the civill power, every soul,
or all Members of the Commonwealth, of what condition
and estate soever be subject; for what have wee to doe with
the Papists, who will have them whom they call the Clergy
or Ecclesiasticall persons, to bee free from the yoke of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill
Magistrate? The Ecclesiasticall power extends it self to
none other subjects then unto those which are called Brethren,
or Members of the Church.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="77" type="proposition">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:55624:19"/>
            <head>77.</head>
            <p>Eighthly, there remaineth another difference in respect of
the distinct and divided exercise of authority. For either
power ceasing from its duty, or remitting punishment, that
doth not (surely it ought not) prejudice the exercise of the
other power; namely if the Magistrate cease to do his duty, or
do neglect to punish with secular punishment those malefactors
which by profession are Church Members: Neverthelesse, it
is in the power of the Governours of the Church, by the
bridle of Ecclesiasticall Discipline to curb such men; yea also
by vertue of their office they are bound to doe it; and on the
other part, the Magistrate may and ought to punish in life and
limme, honours or goods, notwithstanding of the offenders
repentance or reconciliation with the Church.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="78" type="proposition">
            <head>78.</head>
            <p>Therefore the one sword being put up in the scabbard, it
is free and often necessary to draw the other. Neither power
is bound to cast out or receive him whom the other doth cast
forth or receive: The reason whereof is, because the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall
Ministery doth chiefly respect the repentance to salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
and gaining of the sinners soul; wherefore it also im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braceth
all kindes of wicked men repenting, and receiveth
them into the bosome of the Church: The Magistrate pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poseth
to himself another and much differing scope; for even
repenting offenders are by him punished, both that Justice and
the Lawes may be satisfied, as also to terrifie others; hence
it is that absolution from Ecclesiastick censure freeth not at all
the Delinquent from civill judgement and the externall
sword.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="79" type="proposition">
            <head>79.</head>
            <p>Seeing then there are so many and so great differences of both
Offices, and seeing also that the function of Ministers and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
of the Church is not at all contained in the office of the
Magistrate; neither on the other part, this is comprehended
within that; Magistrates shall no lesse sin in usurping Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall
power, ministring holy things, ordaining Ministers,
or exercising Discipline Ecclesiasticall, then Ministers should
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:55624:20"/>
sin in rushing into the borders of the Magistrate, and in
thrusting themselves into his calling.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="80" type="proposition">
            <head>80.</head>
            <p>Neither are those powers more mingled one with other, or
lesse distinguished, where the Magistrate is a Christian, then
where he is an Infidell; For as in a beleeving Father and in an
Infidell Father, the rights of a Father are the same, so in a
Christian Magistrate, and in an Infidell Magistrate, the rights
of Magistrates are the same; So that to the Magistrate conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
to the Christian Faith, there is no accession of new right,
or increase of civill power, although being indued with true
Faith and Piety, he is made more fit and willing to the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going
of his office and the doing of his duety.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="81" type="proposition">
            <head>81.</head>
            <p>So then the Word of God and the Law of Christ which
by so evident difference separateth and distinguisheth Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticall
Government from the Civill, forbiddeth the Christian
Magistrate to enter upon or usurpe the Ministery of the Word
and Sacraments,, or the juridicall dispensing of the keyes of
the Kingdome of Heaven, to invade the Church-Government,
or to chalenge to himself the right of both swords, spirituall
and corporall; But if any Magistrate (which God forbid)
should dare to arrogate to himself so much, and to enlarge his
skirts so far, the Church shall then straightway be constrained
to complaine justly, and cry out, that though the Pope is
changed, yet Popedome remaineth still.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="82" type="proposition">
            <head>82.</head>
            <p>It is unlawfull moreover to a Christian Magistrate to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand
the practise and execution of Ecclesiasticall Discipline,
(whether it be that which belongs to a particular Church, or
the matter be carried to a Classe or Synode) Now the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate
withstandeth the Ecclesiastick Discipline, either by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitions
and unjust Lawes, or by his evill example stirring up
and inciting others to the contempt thereof, or to the tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling
it under foot.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="83" type="proposition">
            <head>83.</head>
            <p>Surely the Christian Magistrate (if at any time hee give
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:55624:20"/>
any grievous scandall to the Church,) seeing he also is a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
of the Church, ought no wayes disdaine to submit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
to the power of the keyes; Neither is this to be marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
at, for even as the office of the Minister of the Church is
no wayes subordinate and subjected to the civill power, but
the person of the Minister, as he is a member of the Common
wealth is subject thereto: So the civill power it self, or the
Magistrate, as a Magistrate, is not subjected to Ecclesiastick
power; yet that man who is a Magistrate ought (as hee is a
member of the Church) to be under the Churches censure of
his manners, after the example of the Emperour <hi>Theodosius,</hi>
unlesse he will despise and set at nought Ecclesiastick Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,
and indulge the swelling pride of the flesh.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="84" type="proposition">
            <head>84.</head>
            <p>If any man should again object that the Magistrate is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
to resist Ecclesiasticall Government, yet that the abuses
thereof are to be corrected and taken away by him: The an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer
is ready, in the worst and troublesome times, or in the
decayed and troubled estate of things, when the ordinance of
God in the Church is violently turned into tyranny, to the
treading down of true Religion, and to the oppressing of the
Professors thereof, and when nothing almost is found or
whole, divers things are yeelded to be lawfull to godly Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates,
which are not ordinarily lawfull for them, that so to
extraordinary diseases extraordinary remedies may be applyed.
So also the Magistrate abusing his power unto tyranny, and
making havock of all, tis lawfull to resist him by some extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary
wayes and meanes, which are not ordinarily to
bee allowed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="85" type="proposition">
            <head>85.</head>
            <p>Yet ordinarily and by common or known Law and right in
settled Churches, if any man have recourse to the Magistrate
to complain, that through abuse of Ecclesiastick Discipline,
injury is done to him, or if any sentence of the Pastors and
Elders of the Church, whether concerning Faith or Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,
do displease or seem unjust unto the Magistrate himself;
it is not for that cause lawfull to draw those Ecclesiasticall
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:55624:21"/>
causes to a civill tribunall, or to bring in a kinde of politicall
or civill Popedome.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="86" type="proposition">
            <head>86.</head>
            <p>What then? Shall it be lawfull ordinarily for Ministers
and Elders to do what they list, or shall the Governours in the
Churches, glorying in the Law, by their transgression disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
God: God forbid. For first, if they shall trespasse in
any thing against the Magistrate or municipall Lawes, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
by intermedling in judging of civill causes, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
disturbing the peace and order of the Common-wealth,
they are lyable to civill tryall and judgements, and it is in the
power of the Magistrate to restrain and punish them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="87" type="proposition">
            <head>87.</head>
            <p>Again it hath been before shewed, that to Ecclesiasticall
evils Ecclesiasticall remedies are appointed and sitted, for the
Church is no lesse then the Common-wealth, through the
grace of God, sufficient to it self in reference unto her own
end: and as in the Common-wealth, so in the Church, the
errour of inferior judgements and Assemblies, or their evil
Government, is to bee corrected by superior Judgements and
Assemblies, and so still by them of the same order, lest one
order be confounded with another, or one Government bee
intermingled with another Government. What shall now
the adversaries of Ecclesiasticall power object here, which
those who admit not the yoke of the Magistrate may not bee
ready in like manner to transferre against the civill Judicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
and Government of the Common-wealth? Seeing it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth
sometimes that the Common-wealth is no lesse ill Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned
then the Church.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="88" type="proposition">
            <head>88.</head>
            <p>If any man shall prosecute the argument, and say that yet
no remedy is here shewed, which may bee applyed to the
injustice or errour of a Nationall Synode: surely he stumbleth
against the same stone, seeing he weigheth not the matter with
an equall balance; for the same may in like sort fall back
and be cast upon Parliaments, or any supreme Senate of a
Common-wealth: for who seeth not the judgement of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:55624:21"/>
supreme civill Senate to be nothing more infallible, yea also
in matters of Faith and Ecclesiasticall Discipline, more apt
and prone to errour (as being lesse accustomed to sacred Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies)
then the judgement of the Nationall Synode? What
medicines then, or what soveraigne plaisters shall be had which
may be fit for the curing and healing of the errors and misca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages
of the supreme Magistrates and Senate? The very like,
and beside all this, other and more effectuall medicines by
which the errors of Nationall Synods may bee healed, are
possible to be had.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="89" type="proposition">
            <head>89.</head>
            <p>There wanteth not a Divine Medicine and soveraigne
Balme in Gilead; for although the Popish opinion of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility
of Counsels, be worthily rejected and exploded;
yet tis not in vaine that Christ hath promised, he shall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
with an Assembly, which indeed and in truth meeteth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
in his Name; with such an Assembly verily he useth to
be present by a spirituall aide and assistance of his own Spirit,
to uphold the falling, or to raise up the fallen. Whence it is
that divers times the errors of former Synods are discovered
and amended by the latter: sometimes also the second, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
thoughts of one and the same Synode are the wiser and
the better.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="90" type="proposition">
            <head>90.</head>
            <p>Furthermore, the line of Ecclesiasticall subordination is
longer and further stretched then the line of civill subordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
for a Nationall Synode must be subordinate and subject
to an universall Synode, in the manner aforesaid, whereas yet
there is no Oecumenicall Parliament or generall civill Court
acknowledged, unto which the supreme civill Senate in this
or that Nation should bee subject. Finally, neither is the
Church altogether destitute of nearer remedies, whether an
universall counsell may be had or not.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="91" type="proposition">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:55624:22"/>
            <head>91.</head>
            <p>For the Nationall Synode ought to declare, and that with
greatest reverence, to the Magistrate, the grounds of their sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence,
and the reasons of their proceedings, when hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth
or enquireth into the same, and desireth to bee satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied:
but if the Magistrate neverthelesse do dissent, or cannot
by contrary reasons (which may be brought, if hee please)
move the Synode to alter their judgement, yet may he require
and procure that the matter be again debated and canvassed in
another Nationall Synode; and so the reasons of both sides be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
throughly weighed, may be lawfully determined in an
Ecclesiasticall way.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="92" type="proposition">
            <head>92.</head>
            <p>But as there is much indeed to be given to the demand of the
Magistrate; so is there here a two-fold caution to be used: for
first, notwithstanding of a future revision, it is necessary that
the former sentence of the Synode, whether concerning the
administration of Ecclesiastick Discipline, or against any
heresie, be forthwith put in execution; lest by lingering and
making of delayes, the evil of the Church take deeper root,
and the gangrene spread and creep further: and lest violence
be done to the consciences of Ministers, if they be constrained
to impart the signes and seales of the Covenant of Grace to
dogs and swine, that is, to unclean persons, wallowing in the
mire of ungodlinesse; and lest subtile men abuse such interims
or intervals, so as that Ecclesiasticall Discipline altogether
decay, and the very decrees of Synods be accounted as cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>webs,
which none feareth to break down.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="93" type="proposition">
            <head>93.</head>
            <p>Next it may be granted that the matter may be put under
a further examination, yet upon condition, that when it is
come to the revision of the former sentence, regard may be
had of the weaker which are found willing to bee taught,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:55624:22"/>
though they doubt, but that unto the wicked and contentious
tempters, which do mainly strive to oppresse our liberty which
we have in Christ, and to bring us into bondage, we do not
for a moment give place by subjecting our selves; for what
else seek they or wait for, then that under the pretence of a
revising and of new debate, they cast in lets and impediments
ever and anone, and that by cunning lyings in wait they may
betray the liberty of the Church, and in processe of time may
by open violence more forceably breake in upon it, or at
least constrain the Ministers of the Church to weave <hi>Penelope's</hi>
web, which they can never bring to an end.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="94" type="proposition">
            <head>94.</head>
            <p>Moreover, the Christian Magistrate hath then only dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged
his office in reference to Ecclesiasticall Discipline,
when not onely he withdraweth nothing from it, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
no impedient to it, but also affordeth speciall furtherance
and help to it, according to the Prophecie, <hi>Isa. 49. 23. And
Kings shall be thy nursing fathers, and Queens thy nursing
mothers.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="95" type="proposition">
            <head>95.</head>
            <p>For Christian Magistrates and Princes embracing Christ
and sincerely giving their names to him, doe not only serve
him as men, but also use their office to his glory, and the good
of the Church; they defend, stand for, and take care to propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate
the true Faith and Godlinesse, they afford places of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation
to the Church, and furnish necessary helps and sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports,
turne away injuries done to it, restraine false Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
and cherish, underprop, and defend the Rights and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties
of the Church; so farre they are from diminishing,
changing or restraining those Rights, for so the condition of
the Church were in that respect worse, and the Liberty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
more cut short, under the Christian Magistrate, then under
the infidell or heathen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="96" type="proposition">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:55624:23"/>
            <head>96.</head>
            <p>Wherefore seeing these nursing fathers, favourers, and
defenders, can doe nothing against the Trueth, but for the
Trueth, nor have any right against the Gospel, but for the
Gospel; and their power in respect of the Church whereof
they bear the care, being not <hi>privative</hi> or <hi>destructive,</hi> but
<hi>cumulative</hi> and <hi>auxiliary,</hi> thereby it is sufficiently cleare,
that they ought to cherish, and by their authority ought to
establish the Ecclesiasticall Discipline; but yet not with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite
faith, or blinde obedience: For the Reformed
Churches doe not deny to any of the faithfull, much lesse to
the Magistrate, the judgement of Christian prudence and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion
concerning those things which are decreed or deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined
by the Church.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="97" type="proposition">
            <head>97.</head>
            <p>Therefore, as to each Member of the Church respective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
so unto the Magistrate belongeth the judgement of such
things, both to apprehend and to judge of them; for although
the Magistrate is not ordained and preferred of God, that
he should be a judge of matters and causes spirituall, of which
there is controversie in the Church: Yet is hee questionlesse
judge of his own civill act, about spirituall things; namely
of defending them in his own Dominions, and of approving
or tolerating the same; and if in this businesse hee judge and
determine according to the wisdome of the flesh, and not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the wisedome which is from above, he is to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
an account thereof before the supream Tribunall.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="98" type="proposition">
            <head>98.</head>
            <p>However the Ecclesiasticall Discipline, according as it
is ordained by Christ, whether it bee established and ratified
by civill authority, or not, ought to be retained and exercised
in the Society of the faithfull (as long as it is free and safe for
them to come together in holy Assemblies) for the want of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:55624:23"/>
civill authority is unto the Church like a <hi>ceasing gaine,</hi> but
not like <hi>damage</hi> or <hi>losse ensuing;</hi> as it superaddeth nothing
more, so it takes nothing away.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="99" type="proposition">
            <head>99.</head>
            <p>If it further happen (which God forbid) that the Magistrate
do so farre abuse his authority, that hee doth straitly forbid
what Christ hath ordained; yet the constant and faithfull ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants
of Christ, will resolve and determine with themselves,
that any extremities are rather to be undergone, then that they
should obey such things, and that wee ought to obey God ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
then men; yea they will not leave off to performe all the
parts of their office, being ready in the mean time to render a
reason of their practise to every one that demandeth it, but
specially unto the Magistrate, (as was said before.)</p>
         </div>
         <div n="100" type="proposition">
            <head>100.</head>
            <p>These things are not to that end and purpose proposed,
that these functions should be opposed one against another, in
a hostile posture, or in termes of enmity, then which nothing
is more hurtfull to the Church and Commonwealth, nothing
more execrable to them who are truely and sincerely zealous
for the house of God (for they have not so learned Christ:)
but the aime is, First and above all, that unto the King of Kings
and Lord of Lords Jesus Christ the onely Monarch of the
Church, his own prerogative Royall (of which also him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
in the World was accused, and for his witnessing a good
confession thereof before <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> was unjustly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
to death) may be fully maintained and defended.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="101" type="proposition">
            <head>101.</head>
            <p>Next, this debate tendeth also to this end, that the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
as well of Ecclesiasticall censu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e as of the civill sword be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
in force, the licentiousnesse of carnall men, which desire
that there be too slack Ecclesiasticall Discipline or none at all,
may be bridled, and so men may sin lesse, and may live more
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:55624:24"/>
agreeably to the Gospel. Another thing here intended is, that
errours on both sides being overthrowen, (as well the errour
of those who under a fair pretence of maintaining and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
the rights of Magistracie, do leave to the Church either no
power, or that which is too weak; as the errour of others,
who under the vaile of a certaine suppositious and imaginary
Christian liberty, do turne off the yoke of the Magistrate)
both powers may enjoy their owne Priviledges; adde hereto
that both powers being circumscribed with their distinct bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
and bounds, and also the one underpropped and strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
by the help of the other, a holy concord betweene them
may be nourished, and they may mutually and friendly imbrace
one another.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="102" type="proposition">
            <head>102.</head>
            <p>Last of all, seeing there are not wanting some unhappy
men, who cease not to pervert the right wayes of the Lord,
and with all diligence goe about to shake off the yoke of the
Ecclesiasticall Discipline, where now tis about to bee intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced,
yea also where it hath been long agoe established, and
as yet happily remaineth in force, it was necessary to obviate
their most wicked purposes; Which things being so, let all
which hath been said, passe with the good leave and liking of
those orthodoxe Churches in which the Discipline of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication
is not as yet in use: neither can any offence easily
arise to them from hence; yea (if the best conjecture doe not
deceive) they cannot but rejoyce and congratulate at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
and vindication of this Discipline.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="103" type="proposition">
            <head>103.</head>
            <p>For those Churches doe not deny but acknowledge and
teach, that the Discipline of Excommunication is most agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
to the Word of God, as also that it ought to bee restored
and exercised; Which also heretofore the most learned <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary
Vrsine</hi> in the declaration of his judgement concerning
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:55624:24"/>
Excommunication, exhibited to Prince <hi>Frederick</hi> the third
Count Elector <hi>Palatine,</hi> the title whereof is, <hi>Judicium de
Disciplina Ecclesiastica &amp;c. Excommunicatione,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="104" type="proposition">
            <head>104.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>For thus he,</hi> In other Churches where either no Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication
is in use, or tis not lawfully administred,
and neverthelesse without all controversie, it is confessed
and openly taught, that it ought justly to bee received and
bee of force in the Church: <hi>and a little after,</hi> Lest also
your Highnesse by this new opinion doe sever your self and
your Churches from all other Churches, as well those which
have not Excommunication, as those which have it; For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmuch
as all of them doe unanimously confesse, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
confessed that there is reason why it ought to bee
in use.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="105" type="proposition">
            <head>105.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>To the same purpose it tendeth which the highly
esteemed</hi> Philip Melancthon <hi>in his Common places, chap.
of civill Magistrates doth affirme:</hi> Before (<hi>sayeth he</hi>)
I warned that civill Places and Powers are to bee distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished
from the adhering confusions which arise from other
causes, partly from the malice of the devill, partly from
the malice of men, partly from the common infirmity of
men, as it cometh to passe in other kindes of life and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
ordained of God. No man doubteth, that Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall
Government is ordained of God, and yet how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
and great disorders grow in it from other causes. <hi>Where
he mentioneth a Church Government distinct from the civill,
and that</hi> jure divino, <hi>as a thing uncontroverted.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="106" type="proposition">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:55624:25"/>
            <head>106.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Neither were the wishes of the chief Divines of</hi> Zu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick
<hi>and</hi> Berne <hi>wanting, for the recalling and restoring
of the discipline of Excommunication. So</hi> Bullinger
<hi>upon</hi> 1 Cor. 5. And hitherto <hi>(faith he)</hi> of the of the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall
chastising of wickednesse, but here I would have
the brethren diligently warned, that they watch, and with
all diligence take care that this wholesome medicine thrown
out of the true Church, by occasion of the Popes avarice,
may be reduced, that is, that scandalous sins bee punished,
for this is the very end of Excommunication, that mens
manners may be well ordered, and the Saints flourish, the
prophane being restrained, lest wicked men by their impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie
and impiety increase and undoe all. It is our part
ô brethren with greatest diligence to take care of these things;
for we see that Paul in this place doth stirre up those that were
negligent in this businesse.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="107" type="proposition">
            <head>107.</head>
            <p>Aretius <hi>agreeth hereunto.</hi> Problem. Theolog. loc.
33. Magistrates doe not admit the yoke, they are afraid
for their honours, they love licentiousnesse, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
people is too dissolute, the greatest part is most corrupt,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the mean while I willingly confesse, that wee are
not to despaire, but the age following will peradventure
yeeld more tractable spirits, more milde hearts then our
times have. <hi>See also</hi> Lavater <hi>agreeing in this, Homil.</hi> 52.
<hi>on Nehem.</hi> Because the Popes of Rome have abused Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication
for the establishing of their owne tyrannie,
it cometh to passe, that almost no just Discipline can be any
more settled in the Church, but unlesse the wicked bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained,
all things must of necessitie runne into the worst
condition. <hi>See besides, the opinion of</hi> Fabritius <hi>upon</hi>
Psal. 149, 6, 7, 8, 9. <hi>of spirituall corrections, which hee
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:55624:25"/>
groundeth upon that Text compared with</hi> Matthew 16.
19. <hi>and</hi> 18. 18. John 20. 23.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="108" type="proposition">
            <head>108.</head>
            <p>It can hardly bee doubted or called in question, but
besides these, other learned and Godly Divines of those
Churches were and are of the same minde herein, with
those now cited; and indeed the very Confession of Faith
of the Churches of <hi>Helvetia, Chap.</hi> 18. may bee an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
hereof. <hi>But there ought to bee in the mean time
a just Discipline amongst Ministers, for the doctrine and
life of Ministers is diligently to be enquired of in Synodes:
Those that sinne are to be rebuked of the Elders, and to
be brought againe into the way, if they bee curable; or to
be deposed, and like wolves driven away from the flock of
the Lord, if they bee incurable.</hi> That this manner of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodicall
censure, namely of deposing Ministers from their
office for some great scandall, is used in the republike of
<hi>Zurick, Lavater</hi> is witnesse, in his book of the Rites and
Ordinances of the Church of <hi>Zurick,</hi> Chap. 23. Surely
they could not be of that minde, that Ecclesiasticall Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline
ought to bee exercised upon Delinquent Ministers
onely, and not also upon other rotten Members of the
Church.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="109" type="proposition">
            <head>109.</head>
            <p>Yea the <hi>Helvetian</hi> Confession in the place now cited,
doth so taxe the inordinate zeal of the Donatists and Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists
(which are so bent upon the rooting out of the
tares out of the Lords field, that they take not heed of
the danger of plucking up the wheat) that withall it
doth not obscurely commend the Ecclesiasticall forensicall
Discipline, as distinct from the civill Power, <hi>and seeing</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:55624:26"/>
(say they)<hi> tis altogether necessary that there bee in the
Church a Discipline; and among the Ancients in times
past Excommunication hath been usuall, and Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
courts have been among the People of God, among
whom this Discipline was exercised by prudent and Godly
men: It belongeth also to Ministers according to the case
of the times, the publike estate and necessitie, to moderate
this Discipline; Where this rule is ever to be held, that all
ought to be done to edification, decently, honestly, without
tyrannie and sedition; The Apostle also witnesseth, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi>
13. that to himself, was given of God a Power unto edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,
and not unto destruction.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="110" type="proposition">
            <head>110.</head>
            <p>And now what resteth but that God bee intreated
with continuall and ardent Prayers, both that hee would
put into the hearts of all Magistrates zeal and care to che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish,
defend, and guard the Ecclesiastick Discipline, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
with the rest of Christs Ordinances, and to stop
their eares against the importunate suites of whatsoever
claw-backs which would stirre them up against the Church;
and that also all Governours and Rulers of Churches, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
every where furnished and helped with the strength
of the holy Spirit, may diligently and faithfully execute
this part also of their function, as it becometh the trustie
servants of Christ, which study to please their owne Lord
and Master, more then men.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="111" type="proposition">
            <head>111.</head>
            <p>Finally, all those who are more averse from Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siastick
Discipline, or ill affected against it, are to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monished
and intreated through our Lord Jesus Christ, that
they bee no longer entangled and enveagled with carnall
prejudice, to give place in this thing to humane affections,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55624:26"/>
and to measure by their owne corrupt reason spirituall Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline,
but that they doe seriously think with themselves
and consider in their mindes, how much better it were,
that the lusts of the flesh were as with a bridle tamed,
and that the repentance, amendment, and gaining of vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
men unto salvation may be sought, then that sinners
bee left to their own disposition, and bee permitted to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
their owne lusts without controllment, and by their
evill example to draw others headlong into ruine with
themselves; and seeing either the keyes of Discipline must
take no ruste, or the manners of Christians will certainly
contract much ruste; what is here to be chosen, and what
is to bee shunned, let the Wise and Godly, who alone
take to heart the safety of the Church, judge.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
