<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The glory of the west, or, The virgins of Taunton-Dean Who ript open their silk-petticoats, to make colours for the late D. of M's army, when he came before the town, a song. To the tune of the Winchester-wedding. This may be printed, July, 31. 1685. R.L.S.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2006-06">2006-06 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42863</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G882</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216250</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827990</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827990</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32416</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A42863)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32416)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1925:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The glory of the west, or, The virgins of Taunton-Dean Who ript open their silk-petticoats, to make colours for the late D. of M's army, when he came before the town, a song. To the tune of the Winchester-wedding. This may be printed, July, 31. 1685. R.L.S.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for James Dean, book-seller at the Queens Head, between the Royal-Grove and Helmets in Drury-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse - "In Lime began a rebellion,".</note>
                  <note>The "late D. of M" refers to the Duke of Monmouth, Charles II's illegitimate son, who led a rebellion to seize the crown in 1685.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Monmouth's Rebellion, 1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ballads, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="song">
            <pb facs="tcp:32416:1"/>
            <head>
               <pb facs="tcp:32416:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
The Glory of the WEST, Or, The Virgins of <hi>Taunton-Dean.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Who ript open their Silk-Petticoats, to make Colours for the late D. of M's Army, when he came before the Town, A SONG.</head>
            <opener>To the Tune of the <hi>Wincheſter-Wedding.</hi>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="unk">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>This may be Printed,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>
                                 <hi>July, 31. 1685.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline> 
                           <signed>R. L. S.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>IN <hi>Lime</hi> began a Rebellion,</l>
               <l>for there the Rebells came in,</l>
               <l>Rebells almoſt a Million,</l>
               <l>Came there to Proclaim M. King</l>
               <l>The News being uſher'd about,</l>
               <l>The Virgins of <hi>Taunton-Dean,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVith joyful ſurprizing a croud,</l>
               <l>They ſummon'd up all their men,</l>
               <l>And ſent them to meet his Grace,</l>
               <l>Their Proteſtant Prince of the <hi>Weſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>While the Girls from each corner did trace,</l>
               <l>with Ornaments fit for their Gueſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>Round the <hi>Market-Croſs</hi> in the Town,</l>
               <l>Their petticoats down did fall,</l>
               <l>Without either Bluſh or frown,</l>
               <l>They had like to pull'd up all;</l>
               <l>Their petticoats they rip'd open,</l>
               <l>ſome Yellow, ſome Red, ſome green,</l>
               <l>Tho' ne're a Commandment broken,</l>
               <l>Yet all things were there to be ſeen:</l>
               <l>Of theſe they made Enſigns of war,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> the like never bore,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Motto</hi> Embroidered with Hair,</l>
               <l>Such Colours was never before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>Then Notice was given the Army</l>
               <l>Was within a Mile of the Gate,</l>
               <l>The Maids then came to a parly,</l>
               <l>Which ſhould be the Captain in State;</l>
               <l>They twenty Seven in Number,</l>
               <l>That all in white did appear,</l>
               <l>The Collonels Daughter tho' younger</l>
               <l>Made Captain, and Colours did bear;</l>
               <l>All cover'd in <hi>Cambrick</hi> and <hi>Lawn,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With garlands march'd out of the Town,</l>
               <l>Their Skins through their Veils were ſhown</l>
               <l>ſome tawn<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, ſome white and ſome brown.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But when they appear'd on the <hi>Downs,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Proud <hi>Perkin</hi> they did ſurprize,</l>
               <l>And all his Country Clowns,</l>
               <l>Draw'd Luſture from their bright Eyes,</l>
               <l>Then at his moſt gracious Feet,</l>
               <l>they threw down their garlands and Crown</l>
               <l>With Colours fit for Field or fleet;</l>
               <l>Or School-boys about the Town;</l>
               <l>They being upon their knees,</l>
               <l>He kindly ſaluted them round,</l>
               <l>With Congies, and touches and ſqueze,</l>
               <l>He took them up from the ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>Three Vollies of Shot were given,</l>
               <l>To wellcome the Maids in the <hi>Weſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As if they had dropt from Heaven,</l>
               <l>And by whom the Army was bleſt:</l>
               <l>Their Captain was firſt ſaluted,</l>
               <l>By their mighty Monarch o`th`croud,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Katy</hi> did not diſpute it,</l>
               <l>But Crouched and turned about<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>He Carreſs`d them every one,</l>
               <l>As they were drawn up a part,</l>
               <l>Both <hi>Betty,</hi> and <hi>Molly,</hi> and <hi>Jone,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Kate</hi> was the Laſs had his heart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <l>Each Officer took his place,</l>
               <l>His choice he kindly drew forth,</l>
               <l>They all were as free to embrace,</l>
               <l>As Maids of meaner worth:</l>
               <l>Each couple into their <hi>Tent,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>They merrily did retire:</l>
               <l>Where all the ſweet night was ſpent,</l>
               <l>The Virgins had their deſire;</l>
               <l>They learn`d the Diſcipline of War,</l>
               <l>To exerciſe Muſquet or Pike,</l>
               <l>Next morning did freely declare,</l>
               <l>They ne`re had ſo pleaſant a night.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>James Dean,</hi> Book-ſeller at the <hi>Queens Head,</hi> between the <hi>Royal-Grove</hi> and <hi>Helmes</hi> in <hi>Drury-Lane,</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
