<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in the parish church of St. Giles in the Fields at the funeral of Bernard Connor, M.D., who departed this life, Oct. 30, 1698 : with a short account of his life and death / by William Hayley ...</title>
            <author>Hayley, William, 1657-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-07">2003-07 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43127</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1214</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R412</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12012515</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12012515</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52450</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A43127)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52450)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 565:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in the parish church of St. Giles in the Fields at the funeral of Bernard Connor, M.D., who departed this life, Oct. 30, 1698 : with a short account of his life and death / by William Hayley ...</title>
                  <author>Hayley, William, 1657-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jacob Tonson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Connor, Bernard, 1666?-1698.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XC, 10 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52450:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached in the Parish Church of St. <hi>Giles</hi> in the Fields.</p>
            <p>At the FUNERAL of Bernard Connor, <hi>M. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who departed this Life, <hi>Oct.</hi> 30. 1698.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With a Short Account of his Life and Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>William Hayley,</hi> D. D. Rector of the said Church, and Chaplain in Ordinary to His Majesty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Iacob Tonson,</hi> at the <hi>Iudges-Head,</hi> near the <hi>Inner-Temple Gate</hi> in <hi>Fleetstreet;</hi> and at <hi>Grays-Inn Gate</hi> in <hi>Grays-Inn Lane,</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:52450:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:52450:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached at the Funeral of Doctor Connor.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSALM XC. 12.</bibl>
               <q>So teach us to number our days that we may apply our hearts unto wisdom.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THere is nothing more apparent to the capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all men than the <hi>uncertainty</hi> of <hi>life,</hi> and nothing of which mankind is more universally perswaded than the <hi>necessity</hi> of <hi>Death;</hi> these are truths so self-evident, that there needs no labour to demonstrate them, the fate of past Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations has given us palpable arguments to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print them upon our minds, and the <hi>present,</hi> and every such <hi>like</hi> occasion of meeting, are so many
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52450:3"/>
fresh renewals of the impression; so that as to the <hi>Doctrinal</hi> part all men seem to be <gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wise, and the most ignorant does not want an instructor to tell him that he must Die, and that every day of his Life brings him one Step nearer to the Grave.</p>
            <p>And yet though men are thus universally wise in the <hi>Theory,</hi> we find them almost as universally unwise in the more necessary point, that of <hi>practice.</hi> Men <hi>know</hi> they must Die, they daily <hi>discourse</hi> and <hi>complain</hi> of it, nay in their <hi>temporal</hi> concerns their covenants, projects and securities, they consider and <hi>provide</hi> for it, and yet they are so blind that they seldom apply it to their <hi>great,</hi> their <hi>eternal</hi> concerns, or draw from it those plain and easy conclusions, which it naturally furnishes to perswade to a <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumspect</hi> and <hi>religious</hi> manner of living.</p>
            <p>Some look upon it as a great <hi>truth</hi> indeed, but so <hi>plain</hi> as not to need the being reflected on, and therefore neglect it as hardly worth their notice, or at least think the consideration of it may be as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed at their leisure. Some again know it is <hi>too true,</hi> and they are <hi>afraid</hi> of it; they see 'tis <hi>pointed</hi> and must prick their consciences, if they suffer themselves to dwell upon it, and therefore put away the evil day far from them, remove the <hi>thought</hi> of it from their minds, as they wish they could do
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52450:3"/>
the <hi>thing</hi> from their persons, and say in their hearts to such suggestions, as the Demoniacks did to our Saviour, <hi>that they should not come to torment them before the time.</hi> And others use the important truth yet worse if possible, and endeavour to <hi>distort</hi> it to patronize <hi>folly</hi> and <hi>levity;</hi> they conclude since life is short 'tis best enjoy its delights as fast as they can, and live <hi>apace</hi> because they must shortly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part; and so advance for their common Motto, <hi>Let us eat and drink for to morrow we die.</hi> Thus the great and useful lesson of the brevity of life, which <hi>Nature</hi> teaches, and the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>God</hi> incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates, misses of its true end, which is the <hi>reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our manners;</hi> is overlook'd by the negligent, <hi>dreaded</hi> by the voluptuous, and <hi>perverted</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bused by the daring and prophane.</p>
            <p>The Sacred <hi>Author</hi> therefore of this <hi>Psalm,</hi> who is supposed to have been <hi>Moses</hi> the favorite of God, makes it his petition, that he might be directed by the aid of Heaven in the application of this piece of knowledge; and since the world was generally so unfortunate, as not to make a due use of it, that God would graciously please to teach him and his people the way to profit by it. He knew ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well that our days pass on insensibly, and that <hi>we bring our years to an end as it were a tale that is</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:52450:4"/>
               <hi>told; that the days of our years are threescore years and ten,</hi> that if they exceed, 'tis but to bring an accession of <hi>labour</hi> and <hi>sorrow;</hi> and that their date is made much shorter by our own <hi>ill conduct,</hi> and the just <hi>punishment</hi> that it deserves; that the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>anger</hi> frequently cuts the thread of a dissolute life, and the divine <hi>providence</hi> sometimes straitens the bounds of a pious one, and therefore that <hi>all are</hi> concerned to reflect seriously on their frail and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain state, and to make that consideration a motive to a <hi>wise</hi> and a <hi>watchful</hi> conduct; and since all <hi>wisdom</hi> comes from above, and 'tis God himself that must <hi>direct our goings in his paths,</hi> or else <hi>our foot-steps will slip,</hi> he makes this his <hi>supplication,</hi> and thereby directs us to do the same, that <hi>God</hi> the Author of all that is good in us, or useful for us, would <hi>so teach us to number our days, that we may apply our hearts unto wisdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wisdom</hi> is in the sense of my text, the prudent administration of our life, the disposal of our ways agreeably to <hi>reason</hi> and <hi>religion,</hi> the careful preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of our <hi>innocence</hi> in this world, and the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing our <hi>happiness</hi> in a future one; these being the great <hi>ends</hi> of Man, and consequently the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of them being the main of our <hi>hopes,</hi> and the due prosecution of them the most exalted <hi>wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:52450:4"/>
And the <hi>applying our hearts</hi> to this wisdom, is the making it the <hi>ultimate design</hi> of all our thoughts and actions, the fixing our minds upon it, the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining it with such serious meditation as the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the subject requires, the keeping it still in our view, and not letting it either escape by <hi>inad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertency,</hi> or grow remiss by its becoming <hi>familiar,</hi> but the persisting in a constant, uniform contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance and endeavour, to order the little time we have so wisely, as to secure our <hi>eternity</hi> by it, and <hi>so work out our own salvation with fear and trembling.</hi> This is to be the great important result of the <hi>num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring our days,</hi> or the reflecting seriously on the <hi>short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> and <hi>uncertainty</hi> of human life; this is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent lesson that we are to learn by the present, and by all other like occasions of assembling, which were piously designed, not for vain useless <hi>osten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> but for our real <hi>instruction</hi> and <hi>improvement;</hi> and were not so much intended for ceremony to the <hi>dead,</hi> as for advantage to the <hi>living;</hi> this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an opportunity when our hearts are supposed to be more <hi>mollified,</hi> and more capable of serious impressions, when our tears should soften and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the soyl for the reception of God's word, and further its fruitfulness; when our senses being fill'd with the demonstration of the vanity of this world, we should sensibly rellish the joys of another. And
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52450:5"/>
O! that it would please God so to bless what I am now about to deliver, that it might effectually engage us all, not to a <hi>faint</hi> reflection on morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, which passes away with the pomp of the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, but to such an <hi>habitual</hi> remembrance of it, as might work its natural effect, the <hi>applying of our hearts to true wisdom;</hi> to unfeigned holiness and the fear of God. This would be an effect truly answering the charity of our deceased Brother, who being now (as we hope in God) united to the society of the Saints in glory, would with them more rejoyce at the <hi>conversion</hi> of a sinner, than at <hi>panegyricks</hi> on himself; and be more pleased at the improvement of <hi>others</hi> vertues, than at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cital of his <hi>own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in order to this end, I shall in my discourse upon these words observe this following method.</p>
            <p n="1">I. I shall shew that the numbring our days fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishes us with excellent motives to a pious and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly life.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That the applying of them to this end is the highest piece of wisdom.</p>
            <p n="3">III. I shall enquire how it comes to pass that they have generally so little influence on the minds of men, as not to engage them seriously to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant and habitual piety.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:52450:5"/>
IV. I shall conclude with an earnest exhortation, to make that due application of our hearts to wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom which the text directs us to pray for, and the present occasion does so movingly recommend to us.</p>
            <p n="1">I. That the numbring our days furnishes us with excellent motives to a pious and holy life. The <hi>numbring our days</hi> is the serious consideration of the <hi>brevity</hi> and <hi>uncertainty</hi> of life, and the fatal <hi>necessity</hi> of a dissolution; that we must die, that it will not be long before we do, that the time is not at our own <hi>disposal,</hi> no not in our <hi>knowledge,</hi> that the method of our ending our days is as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain as the time, but that whenever or however it happens, it opens a passage into an eternity of <hi>joy</hi> or <hi>misery.</hi> Such reflections as these make up the work of numbring our days, and at first ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension they must strike the mind with attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and concern; but they are too many to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered all together, and too fruitful of arguments to have them all at one glance deduced and attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to. I shall therefore distinctly treat of some at least of the <hi>principal</hi> of them, and shew the motives they afford to piety and a holy life.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The numbring our days implies that we must <hi>die,</hi> and that a <hi>period</hi> must be put to them; whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver can be numbered must end, 'tis only <hi>infinity</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:52450:6"/>
that is always durable. The life of man is indeed properly <hi>eternal,</hi> and his mortal life is but the <hi>prologue</hi> of it, we were made principally for another world, and this present one is but the journey that leads to it. Let it be therefore never so durable we must at last come to our <hi>long home,</hi> and its length will then be nothing, when eternity is put in the balance with it, how pleasant soever the objects of our senses may be, however our affections may doat upon them, and make us say within our selves, as <hi>Peter</hi> did to our Saviour on the mount, <hi>It is good for us to be here.</hi> Yet the eternal Laws of mortality oppose their bent, and cry aloud to us that <hi>we have here no abiding city.</hi> Our bodies are tabernacles that cannot last long, and nature it self by degrees moulders these our houses of clay, to make way for <hi>death,</hi> and that lands us upon <hi>immortality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The consideration of this is sufficient to teach us that the business of <hi>this world</hi> is not to be our great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est care; that what is needful for our temporary support is not of so great importance, as what makes a provision for an <hi>endless life;</hi> what if every thing here does not fall according to our wishes? or what if it does? what if the world frown upon us, and we meet with <hi>disappointments</hi> in our designs, <hi>necessity</hi> in our fortune and pains and <hi>diseases</hi> in our bodies?
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52450:6"/>
what if all these join together to make our journey uneasy? if we are sure in the end to find a lasting comfort, to have all our tears wiped off, and an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance given us into the <hi>joy of our Lord?</hi> and what if Fortune smile upon us here for a moment? what if we are feared or envy'd, caressed or loved by those about us? what if we have health of body, plentiful estates and fair reputations? if in the mean time our hopes reach no farther, and death is to put an end both to our <hi>grandeur</hi> and our <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation?</hi> would not any man that reflects seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously on this be apt to say to himself, shall I spend my thoughts or contrivance for that which profiteth nothing? or for so short a time? shall I loose my <hi>rest</hi> and my <hi>peace,</hi> to be rich or great in the sight of my <hi>neighbours,</hi> when I am poor and miserable in the sight of my <hi>God,</hi> destitute of the riches of his grace, and the Spiritual treasure of good works? shall I gratify my own follies and vices, and in the hurry of them fancy I live for a moment, and so be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away blindly into everlasting Death? O <hi>stupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity</hi> and <hi>madness!</hi> that can please it self with the gaie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a mortal state, and in the mean time not make provision for immortality! 'tis enough that this world passeth away, to make us not value it; and that our home is in another, to perswade us to think of, and provide for it.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:52450:7"/>
2. Another reflexion that the numbring of our days will afford us, is, that life is at best but <hi>short,</hi> and of no considerable duration; if we reckon it from our birth to the period of a good old age, 'tis no vast cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit; when <hi>Iacob</hi> had lived near twice the common age of man, and the days of his pilgrimage were 130 years, he told <hi>Pharaoh</hi> that <hi>the days of the years of his life were</hi> but <hi>few</hi> as well as <hi>evil.</hi> 'Tis the usual com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of those that spend their time in enquiries af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Sciences, in the search of Nature, or the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Arts, that <hi>knowledge</hi> is of a vast extent, and <hi>life</hi> is but short to work it out; but if we measure the greatness of the work that most concerns us, the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing our corruptions, the improving our graces, and the study and practice of our Duty, this short time will appear yet more inconsiderable, the <hi>days</hi> fly swiftly, and the <hi>night</hi> hastily approaches <hi>wherein no man can work.</hi> I do not now mention, that a great part of this life is spent before we come to any maturity of thought, that another great portion is given to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary <hi>employments</hi> and <hi>diversions,</hi> and a third glides away insensibly in the silence of thoughtless Sleep; for the present let us suppose that all of it were in our hands to husband and employ to our spiritual advantage, and that we were sure it should not be suddenly snatcht from us, yet alas! it is easily mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52450:7"/>
we see how short it seems to ourselves, when we look back upon what is past of it, and if we do but compare it with <hi>eternity,</hi> it quite disappears and vanishes into <hi>nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us see then what use <hi>wisdom</hi> would make of such a <hi>consideration</hi> as this; would it pass this little time it has given it to <hi>no</hi> purpose? or to <hi>wicked</hi> ones? would it study methods and contrivances to <hi>waste</hi> and <hi>mispend</hi> it? would it <hi>neglect</hi> its work or <hi>add</hi> to it? would it carelessly let slip the opportunities of repentance and amendment, or render them yet more difficult by affected and habitual impieties? these methods are directly opposite to a perswasion of the brevity of life; such a thought would be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductive of <hi>diligence</hi> and <hi>watchfulness,</hi> and would make us vigilant in catching at and improving eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry opportunity that Providence is pleased to afford us of <hi>making our calling and election sure;</hi> we should account it unexcusable folly to waste our pretious time in the serving of our <hi>lusts,</hi> in the jollities of <hi>extravagance,</hi> or the Supinity of <hi>sloth</hi> and <hi>idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness;</hi> we should then conclude that we ought at least to <hi>employ</hi> our time well, if we could not <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long</hi> it, that we should make some progress in our spiritual race, press on daily nearer and nearer to perfection, and be therefore more active, because we find we have not long to run; but above all we
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52450:8"/>
should dread the going <hi>backward</hi> in our course by vice and licentiousness, and the <hi>fettering</hi> our selves in the sinful pleasures of the world, and <hi>loading</hi> our minds with the clogs of wicked affections and vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous desires. Whoever is truly sensible that his hours are <hi>few,</hi> will not dare to be <hi>prodigal</hi> of them, and he that wisely considers that his work is great, and that it must be done, will tremble at the thoughts of idly neglecting it, remissly engaging in it, or foolishly swelling its bulk or obstructing its progress.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The numbring our days will convince us, that this short life is yet shorter to us; that its pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod is <hi>uncertain</hi> and <hi>unknown;</hi> and what must ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily end quickly by the common laws of nature, is frequently by our own follies, by chance and accident, and by an over-ruling providence suddenly broke off and concluded, or which is equal to us, render'd useless to our <hi>main</hi> design, the preparing for <hi>another life.</hi> We may perhaps arrive to the age of man which the Psalmist assigns, that of three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>score years and ten; we may possibly, by a <hi>gentle</hi> hand of God be called from the hurry of business, the vanities of the world, and the temptations of pleasures, and have <hi>leisure,</hi> upon a bed of retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without acute or discomposing sickness, to think and prepare for <hi>Heaven,</hi> and make our peace
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52450:8"/>
with God; these advantages 'tis possible the divine clemency may afford <hi>some</hi> of us; but we are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect that these are <hi>extraordinary</hi> advantages, that God does not generally vouchsafe to men, but is pleased to indulge only to some few as particular expressions of his Paternal love. The <hi>present</hi> occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of our meeting must divert us from such expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations, and if we turn our thoughts upon the <hi>usual</hi> methods of mens departure, we see that the most are taken off, when they least think of it; some <hi>suddainly</hi> without time to reflect, some by <hi>acute</hi> diseases that <hi>disturb</hi> the mind, and take away ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther its <hi>sense,</hi> or the <hi>calm</hi> which is necessary for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine thoughts; and in some the vigor of the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing wears away with the strength of the body, and <hi>dotage</hi> takes up that time which they had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin'd for the work of their Conversion; thus we see we are not rationally to expect that our years should grow to their <hi>possible</hi> extent, or that they should be <hi>useful</hi> to us if they did; and therefore we should constantly be apprehensive of what may always happen, and be still prepared for what may every day arrive.</p>
            <p>This reflection then must necessarily awaken us from the lethargy of <hi>security;</hi> and shew us the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal imprudence of putting the evil day <hi>far from us.</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:52450:9"/>
Have I not begun my preparation for death till this day, and yet for ought I know this may be the very last day of my life? I may perhaps <hi>this hour</hi> be called to give up my accompts, and wretched man than I am! I have scarce yet had it in my thoughts, that I have an accompt to make! must not such a consideration as this <hi>terrify</hi> the sinner, discover the egregious folly of a <hi>wicked</hi> life, the necessity of <hi>repentance,</hi> and that a <hi>speedy</hi> one? is it possible that a man could take any pleasure in the most de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful of all his sensual enjoyments, if he refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted that in that very moment he were to expect death as the reward of it? this he knows he <hi>deserves,</hi> and he does not know but he may <hi>feel;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he can never be easy or satisfied, while he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members it, till he has made his peace with that God, in whose hands are his life and death. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing sure can be a more rational inducement to draw off our dependance on the world, than to think we do not know how soon we may quit it, nor is there a more natural consequence of the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty</hi> of death, than the absolute necessity of a <hi>present</hi> and certain preparation.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The last suggestion I shall offer from the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring our days, which carries with it one of the strongest motives to a <hi>true use</hi> of life; is, that the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52450:9"/>
same moment that terminates our days, puts an end likewise to all opportunities of <hi>conversion</hi> or <hi>recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation</hi> to God. <hi>As the tree falls so it lies,</hi> and as the <hi>grave</hi> receives us, so will it deliver us to <hi>judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Behold now is the accepted time, behold now is the day of salvation,</hi> but <hi>in death no man can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member God</hi> or make his peace with him in the pit. Were there a <hi>middle</hi> state, where we might have a double prospect, <hi>backward</hi> on the vanities and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of the world, and <hi>forward</hi> on the two portions of endless <hi>bliss</hi> or <hi>torment,</hi> and might we be there admitted to sue out our pardon, and to make at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement for the errors of our life, it would pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly not be reckon'd folly, to defer our preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for another world, till we had done with this; but <hi>Sacred writ</hi> assures us, that there is no such mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle state or opportunity of reconcilement, but that as certainly as 'tis <hi>appointed for all men once to die,</hi> so certainly <hi>after death</hi> succeedeth <hi>the judgment:</hi> and we shall not be judged according to any <hi>future</hi> thoughts we may have hereafter, but <hi>every man shall receive according to what he has done in the flesh whether it be good or evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is there then no thought, or labour <hi>in,</hi> or <hi>beyond</hi> the grave? is there nothing that can avail us to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>joy</hi> in the world to come, but our passing of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52450:10"/>
our days on earth in a conscientious discharge of our duty? and can we live here, as if we had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do, or nothing but what we might defer till a future state? is this life our only stage of <hi>probation</hi> and <hi>tryal,</hi> and must the other receive us as we are qualified when we go out of it; and can we think we are not concerned how we behave our selves <hi>here,</hi> or deliver our selves up to our <hi>Iudge?</hi> if when we depart hence spotted and polluted with unrepented sins, there is no <hi>fountain</hi> left to purge our pollutions, but a devouring <hi>fire</hi> only to punish them, sure we cannot be so stupid as not to wash away speedily our habitual vices, in repentant tears and a bitter humiliation, and labour mightily <hi>in this our day, for the things that belong to our peace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are hid from our eyes.</hi> And if those only are addmitted into the company of the <hi>lamb,</hi> who are sanctified by his <hi>blood,</hi> and cloathed with <hi>innocence,</hi> will not common sense tell us, that we ought to lay hold on the <hi>merits</hi> of his blood and passion, by a zealous performance of the duties of that <hi>covenant</hi> which was sealed by it, and by a careful preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of our integrity, and an affectionate doing of his Will while we are in the flesh, make our selves meet to be received into his glory, <hi>cleanse our selves from all filthiness both of flesh and Spirit, and perfect</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:52450:10"/>
               <hi>holiness in the fear of God?</hi> that when we come to die, we may do it with <hi>joy,</hi> and embrace our dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution, as that which will crown the <hi>pious</hi> life on earth, with an <hi>immortal</hi> one in Heaven.</p>
            <p>These are the genuine <hi>applications</hi> of some of the most considerable <hi>reflections,</hi> that arise from the <hi>numbring our days,</hi> whereby it appears, that this lesson furnishes us with excellent motives to a holy life, I come now to shew</p>
            <p n="2">II. That the applying of them to this end is the highest piece of <hi>wisdom.</hi> And that, whether wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom be taken for <hi>judging</hi> aright, or for the doing what is most for our <hi>interest</hi> and <hi>advantage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. If wisdom be taken for <hi>judging aright,</hi> or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing just consequences from evident truths, what can be more evident than the wisdom of these con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusions? if we must <hi>quit</hi> this world, and then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon an <hi>eternity</hi> of joy or misery, is it not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional to take care how we <hi>steer</hi> our present course, that we do not make a fatal mistake at last? if the time we have to stay be but <hi>short,</hi> is it not just and fit that we be cautious of <hi>loosing</hi> and misapplying it? if its duration be <hi>uncertain,</hi> and futurity be out of our knowledge, does it not highly become an understanding creature, to be <hi>prepared</hi> for what may happen? and if this opportunity being once
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52450:11"/>
lost, there be <hi>no other</hi> to retrieve our hopes, does not common reason urge us <hi>immediately</hi> to embrace and employ it? and do we not all act thus in those affairs that relate to our <hi>temporal</hi> concerns? and how then should it not be <hi>prudence</hi> to judge alike with reference to our <hi>eternal</hi> ones? the contrary judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which <hi>Libertinism</hi> raises, how unconclusive and absurd are they! life must <hi>end,</hi> therefore 'tis no matter how we <hi>spend</hi> it; 'tis <hi>short,</hi> therefore 'tis not worth our <hi>improving;</hi> 'tis <hi>uncertain,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis in vain to <hi>design</hi> any thing in it; and 'tis our <hi>only</hi> opportunity, and therefore—what? that we must <hi>neglect, pervert</hi> and <hi>abuse</hi> it! O senseless folly, and unmanly stupidity! we pretend in vain to reason, if we can judge no better; we have no pretence to <hi>understanding,</hi> no not so much as to that of the <hi>beasts that perish.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. But then if we take <hi>wisdom</hi> for the doing of that which is most for our <hi>interest</hi> and <hi>advantage,</hi> one should think there were no need of proof to evince, that to spend our life in goodness and piety, is the most <hi>useful</hi> deduction we can make from the vanity and brevity of it; for what do we <hi>loose</hi> by it? or what do we <hi>gain</hi> by the contrary? if there be <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly</hi> a future judgment, an eternity of bliss, and a lake of everlasting fire, we are then sure nothing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52450:11"/>
but <hi>piety</hi> can bear the <hi>one,</hi> can be admitted into the <hi>other,</hi> or delivered from the <hi>last.</hi> And I would ask a <hi>prophane</hi> and impenitent person, how he thinks he can bear the pomp of the last <hi>tribunal?</hi> what thoughts would be raised in him from the sight of a <hi>distant Heaven,</hi> and what sense he would have of the torments of a <hi>present Hell?</hi> if these things must be, sure <hi>reason</hi> as well as <hi>religion</hi> must make the Apostles reflection, <hi>what manner of persons ought we to be in all holy conversation and godliness?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what if these things were only <hi>probabilities</hi> and <hi>conjectures?</hi> what if we were not fully assured that there were to be a future state, but only <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended</hi> and <hi>dreaded</hi> it? a pious life would still be the most <hi>advantageous</hi> conclusion we could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce from this; for what do we <hi>loose</hi> by it? nothing but some of the deceitful <hi>pleasures</hi> of <hi>sense,</hi> which alwasy fall short of our hopes, end in <hi>dissatisfaction,</hi> and never fully <hi>gratify:</hi> and yet we gain in exchange the delights of vertue, which are <hi>deep, real</hi> and <hi>lasting.</hi> And what great pleasure is it that we have from vice? is it enough to make amends for the fears and dread we have, least the checks of our <hi>conscience,</hi> and the voice of <hi>reason</hi> and <hi>religion</hi> should prove <hi>true</hi> at last? does it ballance the dismal apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions we have upon a <hi>sickbed,</hi> or upon approaching <hi>death?</hi> No, I am fully perswaded, that as there is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52450:12"/>
no one so wicked but he would <hi>die the death of the righteous,</hi> and wishes it whilst he lives; so there is not any so profligate, but when he <hi>sees</hi> his <hi>last</hi> hour is coming, he would most willingly choose to have had all his years confin'd to a bed of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and debar'd all the sensual delights of the world, so that he might <hi>die</hi> like the <hi>good man,</hi> and have that peace of conscience, and comfortable as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance of happiness, which the <hi>pious Christian</hi> has when he departs this life.</p>
            <p>I shall therefore make no question but that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that hears me is fully convinced, of the wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of applying the thoughts of <hi>death</hi> to the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> of <hi>life;</hi> and so may be all mankind are, when they do but <hi>reflect;</hi> and yet we see these reflections are like man himself, <hi>short-lived, uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> and too often <hi>fruitless;</hi> and therefore that they may not be so with us, let us if we can, find out the <hi>causes</hi> of this unhappiness in order to avoid them, and this I am to endeavour in my <hi>third Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. Where I am to enquire, how it comes to pass that these things have generally so little influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence on the minds of men, as not to engage them seriously to constant and habitual <hi>piety.</hi> Now to omit <hi>others,</hi> I conceive it generally owing to one of these <hi>two reasons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:52450:12"/>
1. Men do not generally <hi>consider</hi> seriously, or <hi>reflect</hi> on these truths, with that attention and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation as is proper for a matter of so great <hi>impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance;</hi> the world is most commonly taken up with <hi>interest</hi> and <hi>pleasure,</hi> and mens thoughts are habitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally possest with contrivances of another nature; and when a person is so overbusy in raising his <hi>fortune,</hi> gratifying his <hi>appetite,</hi> or combating with <hi>necessity,</hi> matters of <hi>religion,</hi> and particularly preparation for <hi>death,</hi> may wait long before they are admitted; and when they are, they have but a short hearing, and are presently dismist with a <hi>be gone for this time and when I have a convenient opportunity I will resume ye.</hi> Now <hi>inconsideration</hi> is a certain obstruction to the most excellent rules or motives that can be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a man; the Doctrine I now press is a <hi>soveraign medicine</hi> indeed, but it must be <hi>applied</hi> and <hi>digested;</hi> if the patient will not <hi>receive</hi> and <hi>keep</hi> it, 'tis in vain to expect any <hi>benefit</hi> from it. 'Tis as plain an argument as sense and reason can invent against the worship of an <hi>image,</hi> that it is a thing <hi>insensible</hi> and <hi>uncapable</hi> of adoration; and yet not only the <hi>Gentile</hi> world, but the <hi>Israelites</hi> themselves; and, I wish I could not add, some <hi>Christians,</hi> have been drawn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the folly, and the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> in his 44. <hi>Ch.</hi> and 19. <hi>Verse</hi> gives the reason for it. And that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52450:13"/>
is, that <hi>none considereth in his heart, I have burnt part of it in the fire, and shall I make the residue of it an abomination? shall I fall down to the stock of a tree?</hi> And thus the certainty of <hi>death,</hi> and the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity and vanity of <hi>life,</hi> are as <hi>strong motives</hi> to vertue and piety, as can possibly be given to men, but yet they can never have a due effect, if <hi>Israel will not know,</hi> if the <hi>people will not consider.</hi> And therefore it is that the mercy of God breaks out into that pathetical wish in the 32. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. <hi>O that they were wise that they understood this that they would consider their latter end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. If there are many that will not consider at all, there are many likewise that <hi>baffle</hi> their consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, with the <hi>hopes</hi> of such advantages as <hi>pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly</hi> may happen. They <hi>know</hi> and <hi>consider</hi> too that they <hi>must die,</hi> and that their life is short and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, and they are not ignorant that they must make their peace with God before they depart this life, or <hi>perish</hi> everlastingly; but yet 'tis <hi>possible</hi> they may live to a good old age, and wear out by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees; may have leisure to <hi>think,</hi> and be <hi>good</hi> when they are no longer able to enjoy the pleasures of life, and <hi>then</hi> they resolve to lay aside all <hi>other</hi> bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness, and think of <hi>eternity.</hi> They see there are some that God blesses with a gradual and a sensible
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52450:13"/>
departure, and therefore they hope for the same mercy which God vouchsafes to these <hi>some,</hi> and do therefore <hi>abuse</hi> his patience and long sufferance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they <hi>hope</hi> for it. I do not now urge the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonableness</hi> and <hi>ingratitude</hi> of such a carriage, nor contend that the goodness of God should rather lead us to a speedy reformation; I am only now noting that how unreasonable soever it be, yet still this is a great cause of the <hi>backwardness</hi> and <hi>roerastination</hi> of repentance: <hi>Hope</hi> is a flattering passion, it will represent what is <hi>possible</hi> as if it were <hi>certain,</hi> and what is <hi>sometimes</hi> given, as if it might be <hi>always</hi> expected; and so by pursuing these <hi>vain</hi> hopes men loose their <hi>real</hi> ones, and are overtaken by evil when they promised themselves <hi>peace.</hi> They hope death will not come quickly, and so squan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der away life, and by expecting a longer durati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their being in this world, are not hasty in laying the well grounded expectation of bliss in a future one.</p>
            <p>Now if there be any here present who have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto <hi>deferr'd</hi> their preparation for another world, who are in the strength of their youth, and resolve still to <hi>put</hi> off this work 'till old age, I need not send them <hi>far</hi> for arguments to convince them of their folly. Our <hi>deceased Brother</hi> God has called away
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52450:14"/>
in the vigor of his <hi>youth,</hi> about the <hi>thirty third</hi> year of his age, when the world was in <hi>expectation</hi> of great things from him, and when possibly improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>natural knowledge,</hi> reputation in his <hi>professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and advancement in his <hi>fortune</hi> filled and employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his thoughts. He had liv'd a <hi>vertuous</hi> and a <hi>sober</hi> life, free from those extravagancies which men in the luxuriant bloom of <hi>youth</hi> and <hi>wit</hi> are too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten carried into, and by which they run into a <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty</hi> decay; and yet God has been pleased to call him away in the <hi>midst</hi> of his course, and to make him our <hi>warning</hi> of the uncertainty of life.</p>
            <p>Thus his <hi>fate</hi> is one argument for us, and if we regard his <hi>judgment</hi> in this matter, that will be ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for though he had been free from the <hi>debauches</hi> of the age, yet what he seem'd most to lament at his death was that he had not been better <hi>prepared</hi> for it, and that he had not employ'd more of that time which he spent in the search of <hi>nature</hi> and the entertainment of <hi>Philosophy,</hi> in the more <hi>useful</hi> search into the state of his <hi>Soul</hi> and the concerns of a <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture life;</hi> so that both the <hi>persuasion</hi> of his mind and his <hi>early departure</hi> strike in with my main design, to press men to apply their hearts betimes to this piece of true <hi>wisdom,</hi> the <hi>early preparing for eternity.</hi> But before I come to the close <hi>application</hi> of this, it will
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52450:14"/>
perhaps not be unacceptable to you to have some short account of <hi>his</hi> life and death who gives the occasion of this present Admonition.</p>
            <p>He was born in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and educated in the Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and remained in his own Country, as I am informed by his Friends, till about the <hi>twentieth</hi> year of his age; when in order to cultivate his <hi>Studies,</hi> and to apply his mind to <hi>Physick,</hi> and work out his <hi>fortune,</hi> he betook himself to <hi>travel.</hi> His parts and conduct were soon taken notice of in the Court of <hi>France,</hi> where the Care and Government of the Sons of the high <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor</hi> of <hi>Poland</hi> who were then in that Kingdom, was committed to him, and he attended them in their travels into <hi>Italy, Sicily, Germany,</hi> &amp;c. which gave him opportunity of making many considerable <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servations</hi> in those Countries. At his arrival in <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> whither he accompanied these Gentlemen in their <hi>return.,</hi> he was made <hi>Physitian</hi> to the late <hi>King,</hi> and by him recommended to his Daughter the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectoress</hi> of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> to have the care of her health. After some stay at the <hi>Elector's</hi> Court, he departed thence with several marks of <hi>esteem</hi> and <hi>favour,</hi> as he had before done from the Court of <hi>Poland,</hi> and he came through <hi>Holland</hi> into this <hi>City,</hi> where he was admitted into the <hi>Royal Society</hi> and the <hi>Colledge of Physicians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:52450:15"/>
Whether it were only to perfect himself in <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick</hi> that he came into <hi>England,</hi> where our <hi>Professors</hi> have deservedly the reputation of excelling those of our neighbouring Nations, or whether his riper years gave him other <hi>Opinions</hi> in matters of <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> than would have been tolerated in the Courts whence he came, I had not opportunity of infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming my self. In fact, he had not been long in <hi>England</hi> but he became so far <hi>acquainted</hi> with our Doctrine and Discipline, and <hi>approved</hi> of both so well, that he professed himself a Member of <hi>our Church,</hi> what were the main arguments and induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to his <hi>conversion,</hi> though I could wish they were publick, I could not particularly examine; for I knew not of his sickness till <hi>two</hi> days before his death, when he was very weak; and I was then ignorant of his having been bred up in the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, and had I known it, I should still have thought it more necessary to employ that little time his <hi>weakness</hi> would enable him to hold a discourse, in examining his present <hi>sincerity,</hi> and directing him in his <hi>last work,</hi> thn in enquiring into the <hi>occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> and <hi>reasons</hi> that brought him to a change of his <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He had in his sickness, before his distemper ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived to a great heighth, and while he was in his <hi>perfect senses,</hi> made his <hi>Will,</hi> in which he left five
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52450:15"/>
pounds to the poor of this Parish where he now li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and desired that if it should please God to take him out of this world, I might preach him a <hi>Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Sermon,</hi> and that it might be made <hi>publick;</hi> his friends let me know this, and at <hi>his</hi> and <hi>their</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest I visited him; I found him very much decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his strength, but perfectly sensible, as he had still been, in the <hi>intervals</hi> of his fits, though the <hi>heighth</hi> of his Feaver put him into <hi>ravings.</hi> As soon as I saw him he requested of me what his friends had told me beforehand, and I presumed his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign in it was that he might be vindicated from the suspicion of some <hi>Heterodox opinions</hi> which his <hi>cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surers</hi> imputed to him, as well as that his <hi>death</hi> might be the occasion of an useful discourse to the <hi>living.</hi> I therefore told him that in case I complyed with his desire, I thought it would be expected I should say something of a <hi>person</hi> whose <hi>writings</hi> and <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter</hi> had rendered him so much known to the world, and had given occasion to some people to speak <hi>doubtfully</hi> of his <hi>principles</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> and that for this reason, among others, it would be very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for me to have some <hi>satisfaction</hi> from him, as to his <hi>Faith;</hi> upon which I put several questions to him, as <hi>whether he believed the Gospel? whether he gave credit to the</hi> Miracles <hi>that are there record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and lookt upon them as</hi> attestations <hi>of the truth</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:52450:16"/>
               <hi>of the Christian Religion? whether he believed that</hi> Jesus Christ <hi>was the</hi> Saviour <hi>of the world, and that he came to be our</hi> Propitiation, <hi>and to</hi> satisfy <hi>divine justice for the sins of mankind?</hi> to which, and such<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like questions he answer'd <hi>affirmatively</hi> with great <hi>earnestness;</hi> and when I discoursed him on the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of that <hi>Book</hi> of his, which occasion'd suspicion of his Principles, he declared that he had no inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to prejudice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Religion</hi> thereby, and remitted me to his <hi>Grace</hi> the <hi>Archbishop</hi> of <hi>Canterbury</hi> for farther satisfaction, to whom he said he had <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd</hi> himself in this matter, and as an attestation of his <hi>sincerity</hi> had received the <hi>Sacrament</hi> upon it, at the Parish Church of <hi>St. Martin's in the Fields,</hi> which I have since found to be <hi>true.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I then began to examine him as to the <hi>state</hi> of his <hi>Soul,</hi> what <hi>sense</hi> he had of his sins? and what <hi>remorse</hi> for having at any time offended God? and whether he were perswaded of the necessity of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance</hi> and <hi>amendment</hi> of life in order to gain the Salvation purchased by <hi>Iesus Christ?</hi> to all which he gave me very <hi>satisfactory</hi> answers, and expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed great sorrow for the <hi>sins</hi> and <hi>errors</hi> of his life past, and then join'd with us very <hi>devouty</hi> in the Prayers of the Church, in the Office for the Visita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sick.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>afternoon</hi> of the same day I went with a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52450:16"/>
desire to have had some farther discourse with him, but the violence of his fit being upon him, he was not in a condition to be spoken with.</p>
            <p>The next morning I visited him again, and found him in one of his <hi>intervals,</hi> still <hi>sensible</hi> but very much <hi>weakned.</hi> I took this occasion to talk with him more particularly concerning his principles, and upon mentioning the <hi>merits</hi> of our Saviour, askt him whether he depended entirely on the <hi>merits</hi> of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, and his <hi>intercession</hi> for pardon of his sins and reconcilement to God? and he made answer that he <hi>relied only on the merits of his Saviour.</hi> He was then put in mind of receiving the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> and he said he desir'd it <hi>with all his Soul,</hi> I asked him whether in receiving the Sacrament he had in his view the professing himself a disciple of <hi>Christ</hi> and a Member of <hi>his Body</hi> the <hi>Church?</hi> and if in receiving it from <hi>my hands</hi> he desired to profess him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self a Member of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> which que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion being a <hi>second</hi> time distinctly put to him by a friend of his then present, he answered with very great <hi>seriousness</hi> that he did; then I put him in mind of his <hi>neglect</hi> of receiving the Sacrament, which he had not done since about <hi>two years</hi> ago when he communicated at St. <hi>Martins,</hi> and he express'd a <hi>sorrow</hi> for it; by all this I thought he sufficiently purged himself from the imputation of <hi>Deism, Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianism</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:52450:17"/>
or <hi>Popery,</hi> I lookt on him as a <hi>true penitent</hi> Member of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and I gave him the Sacrament. He received it with signs of very great <hi>devotion,</hi> with expressions of hearty <hi>repentance</hi> for all the sins and follies of his life, and earnest <hi>petitions</hi> for pardon, and so I left him, as far as we could judge, in a <hi>Christian</hi> disposition for death, which I look'd upon as very <hi>near.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These are things which I think my self <hi>obliged</hi> to give a <hi>particular</hi> account of, partly to answer what I conceive was the <hi>design</hi> of the deceased, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon occasion of an <hi>accident</hi> that happen'd some hours after I left him; which perhaps it will be thought not <hi>fair</hi> to conceal; A certain person, who it seems was a <hi>Romish Priest,</hi> came to the <hi>Doctor's</hi> Lodgings, and desired very earnestly to see him, declaring that he was his <hi>Country-man,</hi> his <hi>Friend</hi> and his <hi>Relation,</hi> those about him, looking upon him as very near his departure, were unwilling he should be disturbed; but upon great <hi>importunity</hi> did at last grant the <hi>stranger</hi> admittance, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Bed side, call'd the Doctor by his name and saluted him in his <hi>native</hi> Language <hi>three</hi> times before he regarded; but at the third time he cry'd out <hi>for God's sake assist me.</hi> Upon which the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany was prevailed with to leave the Room, but the Doctor's most intimate <hi>friend</hi> returned to the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52450:17"/>
door and heard the Doctor repeating over his <hi>Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teor</hi> in <hi>Latin,</hi> in a very <hi>huddled</hi> manner; upon which the <hi>Priest</hi> gave him <hi>Absolution,</hi> and then asked him whether he would have <hi>extream Unction,</hi> and the Doctor said <hi>yes,</hi> after which it is suspected it was given him.</p>
            <p>Now here could I imagine the Doctor was in his <hi>senses,</hi> and that he was really in his heart of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, while he only <hi>acted</hi> this part in the <hi>last scene</hi> of his life, I should look upon it as a very great <hi>stain</hi> on his memory; and I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded it would give everybody a <hi>shocking</hi> Idea of that <hi>Religion</hi> which would allow a person so to <hi>prevaricate</hi> both with God and Man.</p>
            <p>But I confess I believe his <hi>judgment</hi> was now quite <hi>decayed,</hi> and that he did not know what he did; for he was thought dying by those about him, though he recover'd out of that <hi>Agony</hi> and liv'd till next day. His <hi>friend</hi> assures me that in his sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness he turned away another <hi>Romish</hi> Priest, who would have seen him, that the Doctor <hi>thanked</hi> him for it, and desir'd that none of those persons (ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a <hi>reproachful</hi> word which I do not think de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent to publish) should be admitted to him, and that it was the <hi>Doctor's own desire</hi> that I should at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend him in his sickness; and I cannot see what <hi>oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion</hi> there should be for such a piece of <hi>dissimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:52450:18"/>
if he had been of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion. Now if the case were <hi>thus,</hi> that he was really past his senses, it cannot but give us some <hi>resentment</hi> of the <hi>confidence</hi> of persons, who will take such <hi>liberties</hi> in our Land as to obtrude themselves upon the dying Members of <hi>our Church,</hi> when they know what se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verities any <hi>Protestant</hi> must expect, who should dare to do any thing like it in a <hi>Popish Country.</hi> And it must give us some <hi>indignation</hi> against the <hi>vanity</hi> of that <hi>Church,</hi> which hopes to save a man by <hi>words</hi> said over him in which he bears no part; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>prophaneness</hi> of those <hi>Priests</hi> who prostitute the most Sacred parts of their <hi>Religion,</hi> to those who have no <hi>faith</hi> in them or <hi>regard</hi> for them. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be, I thought it a sincere part to lay the thing open as it happen'd, that it might not be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended that any thing was concealed which should argue him of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, or that <hi>we</hi> do, what we justly reproach our <hi>adversaries</hi> for, endeavour to gain credit to our Church by <hi>feigned</hi> and <hi>pretended</hi> conversions.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. It is time now to hasten to the <hi>last</hi> thing I proposed, to conclude with an earnest <hi>exhortation</hi> to all that hear me, to make that due application of their hearts to wisdom which the <hi>Text</hi> directs us to pray for, and the <hi>present occasion</hi> does so movingly recommend to us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:52450:18"/>
Does the <hi>numbring of our days</hi> then afford us the most moving and prevalent arguments to a <hi>pious</hi> course of living, and does the shortness and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of life and other reflections drawn from it, naturally excite us to <hi>caution</hi> and <hi>vigilance;</hi> let us then for our own <hi>interest,</hi> and for the <hi>glory</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> be perswaded to <hi>fix</hi> it in our minds, and <hi>meditate</hi> upon it. <hi>Nature</hi> has written it in legible characters, and <hi>providence</hi> gives us frequent demonstrations of it, in the <hi>Funerals</hi> of our friends and acquaintance; and this day affords us a <hi>fresh</hi> instance to awaken our memories. Let not <hi>this occasion</hi> then be unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and vain, let it not add to our condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by proving a new slighted <hi>call</hi> to conversion; but let the natural death of our <hi>Brother</hi> be the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencement of our spiritual life; and if we have not yet considered of our great <hi>change,</hi> let us <hi>now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin;</hi> and let not business, pleasure or time <hi>obliterate</hi> the thought, or <hi>stop</hi> its growth; but let us constant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recall it upon all occasions, in <hi>temptation</hi> it will help us to <hi>fly</hi> and <hi>resist,</hi> in <hi>business</hi> it will prevent immoderate <hi>care</hi> and <hi>anxiety,</hi> and in <hi>pleasures</hi> it will make us cautious to guide them by <hi>innocence,</hi> and confine them with <hi>moderation.</hi> Thus will it be of use in all the scenes of our life, and keep the <hi>judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> steady, and the <hi>passions</hi> in sobriety.</p>
            <p>But above all, let us take care that our medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52450:19"/>
on this subject be not <hi>bare</hi> thought and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suasion, but that they have their due energy upon our <hi>manners;</hi> let not <hi>actual amendment</hi> of our lives be put off till another day, nor Iet vain hopes of <hi>future</hi> opportunities, which may be will never come, make us loose the <hi>present</hi> which God has put into our hands. If we <hi>know</hi> we must die, let us live as men that <hi>expect</hi> it, if our time at best cannot be very long, let us not give <hi>idleness</hi> or <hi>sin</hi> any share in it, and if our end, for ought we know, may be now at hand, and no one can tell, but his turn may be the next, let us endeavour to leave behind us a pattern for <hi>imitation</hi> and <hi>love,</hi> and not for <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror</hi> and <hi>abhorrence.</hi> And in the last place, since we have no other time allotted us but this mortal life, to provide for eternity, and to secure our happiness; let all our actions speak that we <hi>think</hi> of it, and are <hi>preparing</hi> for it. So shall our life here be a <hi>blessing</hi> to our selves, a <hi>joy</hi> to our friends and a <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit</hi> to the publick, and our death when ever it comes, shall be <hi>acceptable</hi> and <hi>welcome,</hi> not attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with anxious distrust, and doubtful expectations, but <hi>chearful</hi> and <hi>resigned,</hi> and such as gives a bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed presage of a happy immortality.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which God of his mercy in his due time grant unto us all,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:52450:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
