<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>On the most triumphant ceremony of His Most Sacred Maiesties coronation, Charles II</title>
            <author>Henshaw, Thomas, 1618-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43355</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1482A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40969</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19539433</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19539433</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109079</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A43355)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109079)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1689:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>On the most triumphant ceremony of His Most Sacred Maiesties coronation, Charles II</title>
                  <author>Henshaw, Thomas, 1618-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Tho. Henshaw.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Coronation --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109079:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 32 -->
            <head>On the moſt <hi>TRIUMPHANT CEREMONY</hi> Of his Moſt <hi>Sacred Maieſties Coronation, CHARLES II.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S once, in fair Minerva's ſheild,, the name</l>
               <l>Inſerted, kept, looſn'd, diſſolv'd the Frame.</l>
               <l>So under yours (Dread Sir) I ſtand, or fall,</l>
               <l>Courting your favour, or my Funerall:</l>
               <l>Crept near your Crown, t'avoide the Readers curſe,</l>
               <l>Like beggers change, wrapt in a golden purſe:</l>
               <l>And this I dar'd; ſince he who deepeſt dives,</l>
               <l>May curſe his Grammer, for ſuperlatives:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Great as our ſouls, not as your merits were,</l>
               <l>Were our firſt joyes, when firſt you did appear;</l>
               <l>And like the firſt dayes Sun, began your courſe</l>
               <l>With a bright World, and <hi>Chaos's</hi> divorce.</l>
               <l>Each then wiſht quils from <hi>Noahs</hi> dove to ſhew</l>
               <l>Our blood-dround World, her Olive branch a new:</l>
               <l>(For Harvey's circulation had been true,</l>
               <l>And men had Iſlands been, and flouted too;)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:109079:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 33 -->
               <l>Each wiſht his Muſe, like Joves great ſacred brain,</l>
               <l>Teeming <hi>Minerva's,</hi> then in every vein.</l>
               <l>The ſtate (new Chriſt'ned Kingdome, when your oars</l>
               <l>Landed you,) counted Indies on her ſhoars:</l>
               <l>Or elſe (for t'was ſo chang'd) could it have ſwom,</l>
               <l>Sure the Land travell'd, and you ſtaid at home.</l>
               <l>Juſtly nick nam'd by all, a Popiſh age,</l>
               <l>That ſent our Kings themſelves in Pilgrimage.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And if that Infant Mirth, whoſe crutch and chair</l>
               <l>Scarce ſtood a high-lone, between hope and fear</l>
               <l>Ventur'd ſo far, that ſcarcely wak't, they run,</l>
               <l>And Perſians like ador'd their riſing Sun;</l>
               <l>Where ſhall our ſouls find vent? or where ſhall wee</l>
               <l>Be <hi>Metamorphos'd</hi> to an extaſie?</l>
               <l>Whoſe hanging ſleeves of Mirth, are lately growne</l>
               <l>Such robes, wee ſcarce believe, they are our owne.</l>
               <l>Were but the great Aegyptian Queen alive</l>
               <l>Who vow'd (that ſhould the Emperour ſurvive)</l>
               <l>A rigid rape upon her tender heir,</l>
               <l>To ſolemnize her Love, as conquerour</l>
               <l>Her paſſions here, ſurely would not demurre,</l>
               <l>But very joy, would turn her murderer.</l>
               <l>Hoop, hoop the Kingdome, or I fear t'will burſt:</l>
               <l>All Worlds ſtrein court'ſie, which ſhall ſee him firſt.</l>
               <l>The hungry Cities maw, (whoſe throat is ramm'd</l>
               <l>As <hi>Craſſus</hi>'s with gold,) now ſo well cramm'd,</l>
               <l>Surely will fatten, and may learn from hence</l>
               <l>Among their pounds, to pay their <hi>Caeſar's</hi> pence.</l>
               <l>I wonder not, in ſtead of painted glaſſe,</l>
               <l>Each window now preſents a painted face.</l>
               <l>For ſuch the glory was, nature ſent all</l>
               <l>To make this City, ſeem but one Guilt-Hall:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:109079:2"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 33 -->Or elſe (there were ſo many) wee might think,</l>
               <l>'Twas <hi>Noahs</hi> Ark, and all the World were in<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>The ſtreets were pav'd with fire, when MONCK came in,</l>
               <l>But when you're Crown'd, (Dread Sir) with armed men.</l>
               <l>Your Subjects were a worthy ſight, but you</l>
               <l>As to be ſeen, were to be rev'renc'd too:</l>
               <l>And one might learn, by ev'ry weeping ſtone</l>
               <l>(As <hi>Hercules</hi> by 's Pillers:) you were gone.</l>
               <l>Here jealous <hi>Iuno</hi> might have kept her cowe,</l>
               <l>Had ſhee had half thoſe eyes that wait on you:</l>
               <l>Or ſhould your grace demande our ſight as ſpies,</l>
               <l>Inſtead of Ermine you might wear our eyes:</l>
               <l>Each ſtreet ſo fill'd, that like the Trojan Horſe,</l>
               <l>It ſwallow'd men, but yet without a curſe.</l>
               <l>The embroid'red gentry, well preſent the ſhow,</l>
               <l>At each ones back, of Pater-noſter-rowe.</l>
               <l>(Nay I may well allowe that for theire back,</l>
               <l>For each ſteeds tail outvyes a pedlers pack.</l>
               <l>About their hats, the pratling wind preſumes</l>
               <l>To act a part, and whiſtles in their plumes:</l>
               <l>Their Horſes (natures pride,) ſo ſtately grown,</l>
               <l>They walk, yet ſcorne the ground, they walk upon:</l>
               <l>Prance at the ſwitches Muſick, and can ſhow</l>
               <l>Men may ſit ſtill, and yet be dancing too:</l>
               <l>On either ſide, the ſtreets were ſo well lin'd,</l>
               <l>With valiant foot, that ſure the World combin'd</l>
               <l>To ſave you harmleſſe, and had ſet them there,</l>
               <l>In your defence, full of Religious fear.</l>
               <l>Some valiant that they 'de change, had all their breaths</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hippolitus</hi> his lifes, for <hi>Martyres</hi> deaths:</l>
               <l>Some young ſprung warriours, yet ſtrut up, and down,</l>
               <l>Like new ſhell'd lapwings with a feather'd Crown.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:109079:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 34 -->All ſerve, as their conditions owe, to honour you,</l>
               <l>Paying (great Sir) your homage, not your due.</l>
               <l>A Princes Crown ſits Regent over wit,</l>
               <l>Nor Lines, nor Language can Decipher it.</l>
               <l>But this is ſuch a Text, it ſeems to dround,</l>
               <l>Like the <hi>Samaritan</hi> in Oyl, that wound</l>
               <l>That plung'd in blood, and makes us reenjoy</l>
               <l>A ſtately Rome, from ruinated Troy:</l>
               <l>Here's <hi>Hercules,</hi> and <hi>Hydra,</hi> t'other neck,</l>
               <l>Did treaſon dare, once more to blaze in Smeck.</l>
               <l>Which providence prevent, but if my bounds</l>
               <l>Be to pledge deſtinyes in blood, and wounds,</l>
               <l>Might I but dare to kiſſe my Sov'raignes cup,</l>
               <l>Should death fill brimmers, I would drink 'um up.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>THO. HENSHAW. Fellow of A. S. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
