<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from a Jesuite, or, The mysterie of equivocation being the copy of a letter of recommendation, seeming much in favour of the bearer, but by different reading rendred of quite contrary signification : lately discovered by the person who was thereby abused, and now made publick for general satisfaction.</title>
            <author>Hess, Johannes Armondus de.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43465</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1624</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12026</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13016539</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13016539</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96542</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A43465)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96542)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 741:37)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from a Jesuite, or, The mysterie of equivocation being the copy of a letter of recommendation, seeming much in favour of the bearer, but by different reading rendred of quite contrary signification : lately discovered by the person who was thereby abused, and now made publick for general satisfaction.</title>
                  <author>Hess, Johannes Armondus de.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W.W.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96542:1"/>
            <p>A LETTER FROM A JESUITE: OR, THE Myſterie of Equivocation.</p>
            <p>BEING The Copy of a Letter of Recommendation, ſeeming much in favour of the Bearer, but by diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Reading, rendred of quite contrary ſignification.</p>
            <p>Lately diſcovered by the Perſon who was thereby abuſed, and now made Publick for General Satisfaction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With Allowance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>W. W.</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:96542:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96542:2"/>
            <head>A LETTER From a JESUITE: Or, the MYSTERIE of EQUIVOCATION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE word of <hi>Truth</hi> aſſures us, That the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil was a Liar from the beginning;</hi> For early he began that Trade, deluding our firſt Parents with pretenſions of increaſing their <hi>knowledge,</hi> when his deſign was to rob them both of <hi>knowledge and happineſs,</hi> overwhelm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the faculties of their ſouls with diſmal clouds of <hi>Ignorance,</hi> which to this day ſadly <hi>obſcure</hi> the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuals of their unhappy off-ſpring. Nor was his Oracle, infamouſly famous at <hi>Delphos,</hi> wanting to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue the ſame method, only ſomewhat refined with ſemblances of verity, and from thence, 'tis like, the firſt practice of Equivocation came into the world, To keep up the Reputation of his Prieſts and continue the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96542:3"/>
Idolatry of his Votaries, returning anſwers couch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſuch ambiguous expreſſions that whatever hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd he might ſeem to be in the Right; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times giving forth his fallacies in Writing either un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, or dubiouſly diſpoſed, where the unwary Reader was trapann'd to deſtruction by treacherous hopes. Thus one of his Agents a Magician once anſwer'd <hi>Albertus Scotus</hi> Earl of <hi>Placentia,</hi> enquiring of his ſucceſs againſt an approaching Foe ready to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade his Territories— <hi>Domine stes ſecurus inimici tui ſuaviter intrabunt terram &amp; ſubjicientur Domni tuae.</hi> Which <hi>Albert,</hi> flattered by his own wiſhes, interpreted as the words ſeem'd to import thus: <hi>Sir, Reſt your ſelf ſecure, your Enemies ſhall ſweetly</hi> (peaceably or fairly) <hi>enter your Land, and ſhall be made ſubjects to your Family;</hi> But being vanquiſhed and ſubdued, the crafty South ſayer thus read and Interpreted his words, <hi>Domi ne ſtes ſecurus,</hi> do not reſt at <hi>home</hi> ſecure; <hi>ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mici tui,</hi> thy enemies, <hi>ſua viter intrabunt,</hi> by their force ſhall thrice enter thy Land, <hi>&amp; ſubjicient,</hi> and ſhall caſt, <hi>ur,</hi> a Chaldee word for <hi>Fire, Domui tuae,</hi> on they Palace.</p>
            <p>But among all the Scholars to this arch crafts maſter of falſhood, there are none that have more unhappily improved the Myſtery of deceit in this kind, than the Jeſuites and Romiſh Seminaries, their very <hi>looks and garbs</hi> as well as their words are <hi>Equivocations,</hi> Wolves in <hi>ſheeps</hi> clothing, and <hi>Ghoſtly fathers</hi> that have by vows abandon'd the world, ruffling in Courts, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changes, every where, in huffing habits of <hi>Hectoring Gallants.</hi> Their diſcourſes capable of as many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions as an Almanack makers prognoſtications,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96542:3"/>
nor are their writings leſs full of craſty obſcurity and <hi>hidden</hi> meanings. Of this ſort we have here a pretty inſtance, which without doubt was hammer'd in that Forge. A poor Fryar who it ſeems was not very fit for their turn, being ſent from an eminent man of that Fraternity on ſome ſleeveleſs errand, has a Letter of Recommendation given him to carry by his Superiour; and being firſt read to him, finding the Contents ſo much (as he underſtood them) in his favour, did no doubt, return his Ghoſtly Patron abundance of thanks for ſo ſignal a kindneſs, promiſing himſelf what extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary welcome the ſame would procure him with the perſon to whom it was directed, and indeed who could ſuſpect a Snake in ſuch verdant Graſs? or a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous meaning in words that appeared ſo plain and hearty? being as follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:96542:4"/>
                  <head>The Letter.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>MR. <hi>G.</hi> an Iriſh. Fryar of the order of Saint <hi>Benedict</hi> is the bringer unto you of news from me by means of this letter, he is one of the moſt Diſcreet, Wiſe, and leaſt Vitious perſons that I ever yet (amongſt all I have converſt with) knew, and hath earneſtly deſired me to write to you in his favour, and to give him a Letter for you of Credence on his behalf, and my Recommendation, which I have granted to his Merit (I aſſure you) rather than to his Importunity, for believe me, Sir, he is one that deſerves your eſteem, and I am ſorry you ſhould be wanting in the leaſt to oblige him by being miſtaken in not knowing him: I ſhould be exceeding ſed if you were ſo as many others have been, upon that account, who now eſteem him, and are of my beſt friends. Hence Sir, and from no other motive is it that I deſire to advertiſe you That you are obliged more than any to take ſpecial notice of him, to afford him all imaginable reſpect, and to ſay nothing in his preſence that may offend or diſpleaſe him in any ſort; For I may truly ſay, I love him as I do my ſelf and aſſure you there cannot be a more convincing argument of an unworthy perſon in the world, than any way to injure him. I know that your ſelf as ſoon as you ceaſe to be a ſtranger to his vertue, and have occaſion to be acquainted with him, will love him as well as I, and will thank me for this advice. The aſſurance I have of your Civility hindreth me for to write further of him to you, or to ſay more upon this ſubject.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your affectionate Friend,</hi> Johannes Armondus de Heſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Paris, <date>Nov. 21. 1678.</date>
                        </hi>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96542:4"/>Now I dare lay a wager the honeſt Reader ſees no more harm in all this than the ſilly Fryar did that carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it; but if you pleaſe to turn down juſt a quarter of the leaf on the outſide ſo as to cover half the Letter and then read what remains open, you will find it ſtill coherent ſenſe but to a quite contrary import from that which before it carried. For thus it runs: <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Sir,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> G. <hi>An Iriſh Fryar is the bringer to you of this Letter, he is one of the moſt vitious perſons that I ever yet knew,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>But alas! deceiving a poor Fryar with ſuch a neat piece of Gullery is nothing to the practices of the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Politicians of the right Roman breed; their principles delivered by approved Caſuiſts extend to &amp; allow more groſs exploits. Take an inſtance of it in commerce, <hi>To uſe Lies</hi> (ſays <hi>de Graffijs</hi> l. 2. ca. 118.) <hi>in bargain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to get a good price, is but a venial fault, though made a daily practice.</hi> What think you of forſwearing ones ſelf a little? Hear what their great Doctor <hi>Soto</hi> in his book <hi>de Juſt. &amp; Jure</hi> l. 5. q. 7. ſaith, <hi>Teſtimonium falſum in favorem proximi, non eſt mortale.</hi> A falſe Teſtimony in favour of my neighbour is no mortal ſin. And he gives you (though himſelf a Dominican) this true-blew Jeſuitical Reaſon for it; <hi>Becauſe,</hi> ſays he, <hi>the Command is, Thou ſhalt not bear falſe witneſs</hi> againſt <hi>thy neighbour, but forbids not thy doing it</hi> for <hi>him.</hi> Their <hi>Navarr</hi> delivers it for orthodox Popiſh Divinity, That any perſon being <hi>Interrogated unduely,</hi> that is, by any that he thinks not competent Judges in that Caſe, concerning any thing which if confeſſed might <hi>endanger</hi> him, may anſwer with a <hi>mental reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:96542:5"/>
denying that to be done which <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in was done, ſecretly meaning <hi>in ſuch a mo<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> or <hi>was not done with an intent to diſcover it to you,</hi> or the like. Their <hi>Sylveſter,</hi> in his Summs in the wor<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Accuſation;</hi> ſpeaks freely, that the <hi>Accuſed</hi> (in the laſt caſe <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned) <hi>may tell a Lie, which is not any mortal <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>nor ſo much as venial, if anſwering cautiouſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> they ſay <hi>ſophiſtically, he ſpeak that which is falſe in the Judges ſenſe and true in his own; Since not being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly under his Jurisdiction, he is not bound to ſpeak Truth in his ſenſe.</hi> Nor is Truth more ſecure amongſt them in the Pulpit than at the Bar; A Preacher may there <hi>Lie,</hi> by <hi>Gajetans</hi> good leave [<hi>Summ. V. Menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum</hi> p. 437.] if he does it not as a Preacher, and his Lies be not ſcandalous ſo the ſaid <hi>Sylveſter</hi> (on the ſame word <hi>num.</hi> 4.) thus reſolves the point, <hi>Queritur utrum ſit peccitum mortale praedicatori mentiri in Ambono<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> If any enquire whether it be a mortal ſin for a Preacher to tell Lies in the pulpit, <hi>Dico quod non,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I ſay</hi> no, <hi>If he can do it wittily, he may intermix his Sermons with falſe Stories provided they be but jocoſe, for if they only make his hearers innocently merry, 'tis ſcarce ſo much as a venial.</hi> In a word, Since by their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines they may without danger be falſe ſo their <hi>friends</hi> and dependants, to private perſons, to Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, to their Prieſts, to their God, where ought they to have Credit? Since they may practiſe <hi>Lying and deceit</hi> in common Converſation, in Commerce; in Doctrine, in Courts of Juſtice; and even in Gods Worſhip; where may they be truſted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
