<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The test or tryal of the goodness &amp; value of spiritual-courts in two queries: I. Whether the statute of I Edw. 6.2. be in force (against them) at this day, obliging them to summon and cite the Kings subjects (not in their own names and styles, as now they do, but) in the name and stile of the Kings Majesty (as in the Kings Courts Temporal) and under the seal of the Kings arms? II. Whether any of the cannon-law, or how much of the cannon-law is (at this day) the law of England, in Courts Christian? Highly necessary to be perused by all those that have been, or may be cited to appear at Doctors Commons. By Edm. Hickeringill.</title>
            <author>Hickeringill, Edmund, 1631-1708.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 205 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43638</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1829</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216804</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828522</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828522</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32950</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A43638)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32950)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1867:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The test or tryal of the goodness &amp; value of spiritual-courts in two queries: I. Whether the statute of I Edw. 6.2. be in force (against them) at this day, obliging them to summon and cite the Kings subjects (not in their own names and styles, as now they do, but) in the name and stile of the Kings Majesty (as in the Kings Courts Temporal) and under the seal of the Kings arms? II. Whether any of the cannon-law, or how much of the cannon-law is (at this day) the law of England, in Courts Christian? Highly necessary to be perused by all those that have been, or may be cited to appear at Doctors Commons. By Edm. Hickeringill.</title>
                  <author>Hickeringill, Edmund, 1631-1708.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition, corrected.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[4], 22, 18, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by George Larkin, for the assigns of the author, and are to be sold by most booksellers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Part 2 begins new pagination on 2A1.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ecclesiastical courts --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32950:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TEST OR TRYAL OF THE Goodneſs &amp; VALUE OF Spiritual-Courts, IN TWO QUERIES: I. Whether the Statute of 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. be in Force (againſt them) <hi>at this day,</hi> Obliging them to <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> and cite the Kings Subjects (<hi>not in their own Names and Styles,</hi> as now they do, but) in <hi>the Name</hi> and Stile of <hi>the Kings Majeſty</hi> (as in the Kings Courts Temporal) and <hi>under the Seal of</hi> the Kings Arms? II. Whether <hi>any</hi> of the Cannon-Law, or <hi>how much</hi> of the <hi>Cannon-Law</hi> is (at <hi>this day</hi>) the Law of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in <hi>Courts Chriſtian?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Highly neceſſary to be Peruſed by all Thoſe that have been, or may be Cited to Appear at <hi>Doctors Commons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>EDM. HICKERINGILL.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Second Edition, Corrected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>George Larkin,</hi> for the Aſſigns of the Author, and are to be Sold by moſt Bookſellers. 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:32950:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32950:2"/>
            <head>Suavi Devinctiſſimo Sodalitate Amico meo, <hi>A. B.</hi> Utriuſque Juris Profeſſori.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>EGre jam Quaeſtionum iſtarum, quas flocci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis meae Diſquiſitioni (Deſiderii tui in me non acuminis Indicium) tanta volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate ſubjici geſtiviſti Jugiter, Tandem, non ſine Ingratae Invidiae Subſequentis Intuitu, Luce (ut omnium Provocet) examen gaudet Impetratum.</p>
            <p>Quod cum Eccleſiae pace Profertur noſtrae Indigenae, bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumque Auſpiciis, Bono Publico Paciſque Communi conſulere, Dominationi ſaltem veſtrae (ne dicam) omnibus (quorum non ſunt aures veritati clauſae) Conamen nullus dubito pergratum.</p>
            <p>Palamque in otio meo &amp; ſollicitudine (quam non languere patior) omnium Intuli oculis, ne verſutior &amp; callidior &amp; hoc tanto<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Inviſior &amp; ſuſpectior (nec interea temporis mihi, <hi>Patriae,</hi> aut <hi>Eccleſiae</hi> defuiſſe) videar.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Praeſagienti</hi> verum animo, non ſum neſcius quam diverſa ſunt hominum ſtudia, meque in tempore non magis opportuno quam difficili haec diſſerere (Haud enim is ſum qui definiam) Impedito quidem (quid mirum?) ſcribendi ſtylo non tam prae literarum impotentiam ſolummodo, quam prae gliſſentem <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Invidiam</hi> &amp; laſcivientem in hominem, umbra &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſu abditum &amp; <hi>Turbarum Contumeliarum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> nupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum non <hi>Inſolentem;</hi> ſed an majori <hi>Juſtitia</hi> an <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacitate</hi> apud <hi>Poſteros Judicium</hi> eſto.</p>
            <p>Obganniant interea loci &amp; pro conſuetudine detrectent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frictae frontis rabulae: Tales etenim, ut malitia convitiisque. coram vel clanculum deſiſtant, ambire vanum habeo.</p>
            <p>Nec tot adverſis Impar gravate proceſſus eorum <hi>Renuo;</hi> nec hanc <hi>Perperam,</hi> ſed <hi>Fide</hi> (uti <hi>Spero</hi>) ſpectata Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſſui <hi>Provinciam</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:32950:3"/>Hic tamen ſeqvor Eminus (nec inhoneſta cautela) <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem,</hi> in <hi>Tramite</hi> verum (uti par eſt) licet non ad Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem (quod aiunt) <hi>Temeratam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hic namque <hi>Veritas</hi> non tum limatur quam ad guſtum Communem accommodatur <hi>Oratio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ideoque Diſputator non tam Subtilis quam pro re Nata dulcis parumque Vehemens (quanti quanti ſit <hi>Veritas</hi> ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicanda) <hi>Pacis Colendae</hi> cauſa haberi videar uteunque.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Londini</hi> Tertio Iduum Januarii Anno Salutis. 1682/3.</dateline>
               <salute>Reverentiae Veſtrae Addictiſſimus,</salute>
               <signed>EDM. HICKERINGILL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32950:3"/>
            <head>The TEST: OR, TRYAL of the VALUE and GOODNESS OF SPIRITUAL COURTS Querying I. <hi>Whether the Statute Anno</hi> I Edw. 6. 2. <hi>be in</hi> Force, <hi>againſt their Eccleſiaſtical Proceedings</hi> at this day.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His hath been an <hi>old</hi> Queſtion (and never, as yet, Judicially determin'd) and therefore cannot be accounted a <hi>bold</hi> Queſtion: much leſs is it mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved unſeaſonably.</p>
               <p>Men that paſs <hi>quietly</hi> by, making no noiſe, but, <hi>cover'd with</hi> darkneſs and <hi>the Night,</hi> and creep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on their way, <hi>as it were by ſtealth,</hi> may poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly <hi>paſs the Guards,</hi> without the trouble of being <hi>challeng'd</hi> by the watchfull <hi>Centinels,</hi> or of being <hi>forc't to stand</hi> and tell <hi>who they are,</hi> whence <hi>they came,</hi> or <hi>whither away;</hi> But if they <hi>make a bustle,</hi> and a diſturbance, It <hi>Alarm's Examination</hi> to pry into their ways, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire <hi>whether they have a Lawfull Paſsport</hi> from God, and the King, or from <hi>one of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Time was, when <hi>Eccleſiaſtical men did their buſineſs,</hi> and carryed on <hi>the Money Buſineſs</hi> (not very unſucceſsfully) but <hi>without noiſe,</hi> hanging down their heads when the Regiſter went to Church accompanyed only with (his two drudges) <hi>The Surrogate</hi> and the <hi>Summer;</hi> then calling <hi>a Court</hi> in haſte, and with a greater haſte adjourn'd, before the naughty boys and rabble had notice, or could rouſe themſelves to Hiſſe at them, getting as <hi>ſafely</hi> as <hi>ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> to their Lodgings, where <hi>picking up</hi> a few groats amongſt eaſy Church-Wardens, nibling it Procuration money, and Viſitation money amongſt the Parſons, (that for fear of a worſe turn, deliver'd their purſe) which with ſome <hi>Driblets</hi> for Licences of Matrimony, and Adminiſtration-Money, paid <hi>Riding Charges</hi> and the Reckoning <hi>well enough,</hi> and ſomewhat to ſpare, the Regiſter (departing <hi>well lin'd in Body and Pocket</hi>) march't away <hi>as chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully</hi> as <hi>ſecretly,</hi> making <hi>as tittle noiſe</hi> as poſſibly he could.</p>
               <p>But when the <hi>Pastoral ſtaff</hi> began to play <hi>at quarter staff,</hi> driving <hi>whole Flocks</hi> before it (by flocks) to <hi>Pound,</hi> and ſeeming to <hi>make a blow at the ſpirit</hi> and Soul (which no <hi>mortal</hi> blow can <hi>hit,</hi> being ſcituated too high and out of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:32950:4"/>
reach). The ſmart was felt <hi>upon the Fleſh,</hi> and the ſtrokes <hi>ſell heavy upon the outward man, depriving men of</hi> Priviledges and <hi>Temporal</hi> Liberties, Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rights, and Franchyſes <hi>as Engliſhmen;</hi> of Votes, Elections, and Benefits, as <hi>Citizens, Free-Demzons, and Free-holders;</hi> of their debts, and all benefit of the Law, as <hi>Creditors, Witneſſes</hi> and <hi>Jury-men;</hi> and of diſpoſing of their <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates,</hi> by Will and Teſtament, <hi>as Teſtetors;</hi> no wonder if it rowzed Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, to enquire whether the <hi>Lightning</hi> be compos'd of <hi>culinary fire</hi> and Kitchen-ſtuff, rather then of Heavenly Rayes; becauſe <hi>Celeſtial Lightning</hi> melts <hi>the Sword</hi> without ſinging the <hi>Scabbard,</hi> and ſtrikes at the <hi>Life and Soul,</hi> mortifying it, without leaving any <hi>Impreſſion upon the Body</hi> and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man.</p>
               <p>Nay further, when the <hi>Cry,</hi> becauſe of Eccleſiaſtical Oppreſſions and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortions (in illegal Fees for Probate of <hi>Will's,</hi> Adminiſtrations, <hi>&amp;c. contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to</hi> and in <hi>Defyance</hi> of the Statutes of this Realm) <hi>grew ſo loud,</hi> and <hi>notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> that it <hi>ſounded and rung all</hi> the Kingdom <hi>over,</hi> moſt men were <hi>the more willing</hi> to pry into their <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> and examine their <hi>Groundſell,</hi> whether all be <hi>ſound and right at the bottom,</hi> when ſuch Ruines and Dilapidations ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear <hi>above ground,</hi> Ay, and to bring <hi>Indictments</hi> againſt many of them, which <hi>undid ſeveral of them,</hi> for their Extortions; and <hi>moſt justly</hi> did they ſuffer, and <hi>none to pitty them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For men <hi>give Law</hi> to Hares and Deer, but they catch the <hi>Ravenous</hi> and <hi>Rapacious</hi> (the <hi>Poll-Cat,</hi> that ſucks the Eggs and ſpoils <hi>the young Brood;</hi> The <hi>Badger</hi> (too) that worrys the poor Lambs) <hi>when</hi> they can, <hi>How</hi> they can, and <hi>As ſoon</hi> as they can; And who <hi>ſo poor</hi> as not to contribute his penny, or <hi>ſo ungrateful,</hi> as not to be Civil, (at leaſt) and a <hi>Well-wiſher to the Fox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catcher,</hi> and that he may proſper, <hi>praying for his good ſucceſs</hi> in hunting down the noxious Game, <hi>an Employment,</hi> not <hi>more pleaſant and Gentile,</hi> then uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and <hi>ſerviceable to the Commonwealth</hi> and publick good:</p>
               <p>Even ſo, The wiſe States-men have made ſuch excellent Laws againſt <hi>Oppreſſors,</hi> Extortioners, <hi>Promoters,</hi> Suborners, <hi>Common Informers,</hi> and the like Animals (that <hi>rend and tear</hi> the Kings poor Subjects and Lambs) that En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement is given by the ſame Laws to every right <hi>Engliſhman</hi> and <hi>true Proteſtant</hi> (that will put the ſame in Execution againſt them) he ſhall <hi>not only</hi> benefit the publick but <hi>himſelf alſo;</hi> and <hi>deſerve well</hi> of his King and Countrey.</p>
               <p>For who can, <hi>without great Regret</hi> and check of Conſcience, <hi>connive</hi> at, much leſs <hi>Countenance</hi> ſuch publick Scandals, <hi>Oppreſſions,</hi> Grievances, <hi>Offences</hi> and Delinquency's?</p>
               <p>Did our bleſſed Saviour or his holy Apoſtles <hi>curſe</hi> them that <hi>refus'd to pray</hi> with them, or refus'd to <hi>hear them</hi> preach? and yet they were infallibly in the right.</p>
               <p>Some of the <hi>more furious</hi> Zealots amongſt his Diſciples (<hi>once, and but once</hi>) call'd for fire from heaven to <hi>conſume</hi> thoſe that rejected them, (as <hi>Elias</hi> did:) but our Redeemer preſently <hi>Rebuk't the evil Spirit,</hi> and caſt it out of them, ſaying, <hi>ſee know not what manner of Spirit ye are of</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Did the Apoſtles <hi>drive men</hi> to Pound, or the <hi>Jayl,</hi> with <hi>any or all</hi> their Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical rods, and then <hi>replevy</hi> them, and <hi>redeem them,</hi> but never with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Money</hi> in the caſe?</p>
               <p>Did Chriſt or his Apoſtles (whoſe <hi>Poverty and Self-denyal,</hi> (taking up the <hi>Croſs</hi>) was a <hi>qualification</hi> as abſolutely <hi>neceſſary</hi> for a Follower of Chriſt and <hi>Succeſſor of the Apostles,</hi> as was <hi>Faith, Hope and Charity</hi>) did they by any <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Engine</hi> feel their Pockets, get dominion, <hi>or wreak their malice</hi> and revenge, <hi>or truckle to Polititians</hi> to make their Spiritual Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons <hi>Tools of State,</hi> wherewith to do a <hi>State Jobb?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:32950:4"/>Did they either make <hi>money of Souls</hi> or of Sins? Did they call to the <hi>Jaylors,</hi> Hang-men or <hi>Bumbaylies</hi> to come and help them; and <hi>lend them à hand</hi> to carry on the Goſpel? Did they either <hi>force or fright</hi> men to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? or <hi>ſcare them out of their Wits,</hi> or out of their <hi>Conſciences,</hi> or out of their <hi>Purſes,</hi> or out of their <hi>Freedoms,</hi> Liberties, Eſtates, <hi>Birthrights or</hi> Temporal Inheritances? <hi>which,</hi> (he confeſt himſelf) were exempt from his Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, not hooking it in, as the Pope and others, do, with the old Popiſh Cheat—<hi>in ordine Spiritualia:</hi> taking away their <hi>Temporalities</hi> in order to their <hi>Souls</hi> health: Our Bleſſed Saviour taught us <hi>not this cunning;</hi> nor theſe <hi>medendi methodos,</hi> new ways of Cure; and Arts Empyrical.</p>
               <p>Men <hi>never ſooner cry out</hi> then when pincht of their Liberties, or <hi>pincht by the Pocket,</hi> eſpecially if <hi>Spiritual-men</hi> be active in it, they are apt to cry—<hi>By what Authority do you theſe things, and who gave you this Authority?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>old Prelates</hi> (in King <hi>James</hi> his Reign) calling themſelves <hi>the Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> in their <hi>Articuli Cleri</hi> preſented to the King and Councel (againſt <hi>all the Judges</hi>) confeſt judiciouſly, where their great (<hi>Sampſons</hi>) ſtrength lyes as to their <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Juriſdiction, <hi>not in the least</hi> mentioning <hi>God,</hi> nor <hi>Chriſt</hi> therein, neither the <hi>Prophets, Apoſtles,</hi> nor the <hi>Goſpel</hi> for it (their modeſty is Comm endable, becauſe <hi>no ſuch Eccleſiastical Juriſdiction,</hi> Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual nor Temporal, is found in the Holy Bible.)</p>
               <p>But, very plainly and open heartedly they avow, <hi>without diſſembling</hi> the matter <hi>in the least,</hi> That the chiefeſt Temporal <hi>Strength of their Eccleſiasti-Juriſdiction,</hi> is Impriſonment upon the <hi>Writ de Excommunicato Capiendo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Implying that, if their <hi>Sampſon's-Locks were cut,</hi> they would become <hi>weak as other men;</hi> And if this Royal Statute I <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. be in force, <hi>all their Proceſſes Eccleſiastical,</hi> Significavits, <hi>Certificavits, in their own name</hi> and not in the Kings name, muſt all be <hi>illegal,</hi> and conſequently <hi>all Capieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and Impriſonments thereupon, <hi>Illegal,</hi> and ill grounded; Therefore no wonder if men concern'd do <hi>ſtand up ſtoutly to keep</hi> this Law <hi>down,</hi> (For if it <hi>riſe up in Judgment</hi> againſt us, what will become of us) or if all <hi>the ſtanding in the world cannot bind it down:</hi> (For the Law at long run is too hard for any man alive) I profeſs, <hi>The old Prelates knew how it concern'd them</hi> to huſh it down, when it ſeem'd to <hi>riſe up to fright them</hi> by being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looſned <hi>primo Jacobi,</hi> having long been fetter'd and bound down <hi>primo Mariae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And it was honeſtly done of them to confeſs that <hi>their ſtrength did lie</hi> in the Writ De <hi>Excommunicato Capiendo;</hi> why ſhould men ly for the matter? eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in a caſe ſo plain and palpable? <hi>We are all agreed</hi> that Commiſſaries, <hi>Officials, Proctors, Regiſters,</hi> Sumners, and all that drive that Sell-Soul Trade, are not found in Gods Word.</p>
               <p>If therefore it ſhall appear (before we have done) that they are <hi>not of the King neither,</hi> prethee tell me, (if thou canſt) who they <hi>are of?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This Province</hi> (I know) would be beſt managed by a <hi>Lawyer;</hi> yet it is <hi>not his Peculiar,</hi> nor <hi>Exempt</hi> from the proper Cognizance of a <hi>Divine,</hi> eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in Reference to ſuch Statutes, (as this of 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.2.) which relates <hi>only to Divines</hi> and their Surrogates; (eſpecially to ſuch Divines as I am, (to wit) a <hi>Bencher,</hi> and <hi>Judge</hi> Eccleſraſtical.)</p>
               <p>'Tis true, <hi>I only ſtate the Caſe;</hi> for it is the Kings Judges that <hi>(onely) ought to determine its</hi> Validity; And well are they called in Law his <hi>Locum Tenen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> becauſe by <hi>Partiality,</hi> Timidity, <hi>Corruption,</hi> or <hi>Injuſtice,</hi> they have not only been <hi>charg'd</hi> with breaking <hi>the King's Oath,</hi> (thereby) <hi>as well as their own;</hi> put have had <hi>their Necks broke</hi> at the Gallowes, for their p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Nor ſince this queſtion was firſt ſtarted, 4 <hi>Jacobi,</hi> did any of them (<hi>I will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:32950:5"/>
                  <hi>ſay they durſt not</hi>) decide this <hi>Quere</hi> Judicially: For the Judges may declare the Law, but never a man in <hi>England</hi> can either <hi>make</hi> or <hi>Repeal</hi> a Statute, (out of Parliament) 'tis <hi>Fatal</hi> to him, if he attempt it.</p>
               <p>And, I'le <hi>ſpeak a bold word,</hi> I believe the Ingenious Reader will conclude (before I have done,) that all the th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n in <hi>England</hi> are <hi>not able to ſpeak one reaſonable word</hi> againſt the Validity of this <hi>Royal Statute,</hi> thought ſo <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary</hi> for the Preſervation of the King's Supremacy and <hi>Royal Prerogative,</hi> (after the <hi>Popes-head</hi> was <hi>decollated</hi>) that it was the <hi>first Statute</hi> that ever was made (except that concerning the bleſſed <hi>Sacrament</hi> to be taken in <hi>both kinds</hi>) after the Reformation, In the Reign of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. For his Father <hi>Reform'd indeed</hi> the <hi>Monaſteries into his Pocket,</hi> but liv'd and dy'd a <hi>Zealous Papiſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>ANd if in handling this <hi>Serious and Solid</hi> Argument, The Reader happen to meet with an <hi>Angery</hi> expreſſion ſometimes, which he deems <hi>too light, for the Gravity</hi> of the matter in hand, let him know there is not a word here writ, <hi>till well ponder'd, and of Set-purpoſe</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For which mixtures, I have the <hi>Oracle of the Law,</hi> the moſt incomparable (<hi>Cook</hi>) for my <hi>Warrant</hi> as well as <hi>Copy</hi> and Preſident; recommending the <hi>plain down Right</hi> Arguments of Law (<hi>in his Inſtitutes</hi>) by <hi>Interlacing</hi> them with Poetry and vivid Humanity, therefore rendring them <hi>more Am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le</hi> and acceptable,</p>
               <p>Or, (if you pleaſe) He <hi>Damask</hi>'s and <hi>Waters his</hi> beſt and ſtrongeſt <hi>Stuff;</hi> And I (to ſpeak <hi>in his</hi> own <hi>Phraſe,</hi> I mean, the <hi>Cooks Phraſe</hi>) will <hi>Lard</hi> my diſcourſe, where I liſt. And though I have not the skill to do it <hi>Cook-like,</hi> I hope, <hi>not S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ovenly, Though</hi> 'tis but to <hi>make it go</hi> the more <hi>merrily down.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not that I take either Care, or <hi>beſtow any pains</hi> upon <hi>Emblemiſhments</hi> to pleaſe any mans <hi>Guſto,</hi> but, if they readyly and naturally come to hand, and but <hi>pleàſe my own Pallate;</hi> be they <hi>ſalt,</hi> bitter, or <hi>Tart;</hi> no matter, though they diſreliſh a <hi>dull</hi> Phlegmatick or <hi>Inſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>id Taste;</hi> I have <hi>no ware to ſell,</hi> nor other deſign, <hi>In this Treat,</hi> but the diſcovery of Truth and Law; And what's that to any man how I <hi>Cook my own Dyet?</hi> wherefore I will <hi>State the Caſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Impartially, <hi>not omitting any thing</hi> that the Lord <hi>Cook</hi> ſays <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Validity</hi> of this Statute, but will <hi>Improve all</hi> he ſays, to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt; If I do not, ſet any man make <hi>more of them;</hi> when I have done.</p>
               <p>Some <hi>honeſt Lawyer</hi> might have been ſo good as to do this <hi>ungratefull Work</hi> to my hand (but the <hi>Drug</hi> and <hi>ſloweſt Sailer</hi> of the whole Fleet uſually <hi>carrys the Light) most of the Learnedeſt</hi> of them declare (<hi>boldly</hi>) in their <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> for the <hi>Validity</hi> of that famous Statute. 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. as well as for the <hi>Reaſonableneſs of ſuch a Law;</hi> for if the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Courts</hi> be the <hi>Kings Courts,</hi> as well as are the <hi>Temporal,</hi> why ſhould not the Original or Judicial <hi>Writs</hi> and <hi>Proceſſes</hi> run in <hi>his name,</hi> in the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Courts, as well as in the <hi>Temporal?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, though this (and a great deal more to this effect) <hi>be true,</hi> yet men are ſo <hi>Timerous</hi> and wary, that though they thereby get onely <hi>Polephemus his Mercy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> to be one of the <hi>last that ſhall ſuffer,</hi> ſtaying onely to ſee their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes executed, yet they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth to come into the Liſts to try the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries ſtrength, wanting that which is one of the four Cardinal Vertues, <hi>For<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> without which no man can be a good Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>A Coward may be a <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſtick,</hi> or <hi>Summer Christian,</hi> namely a Profeſſor of Truth <hi>Till the Storm of Perſecation come,</hi> but <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> the Fox keeps in his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32950:5"/>
                  <hi>hole,</hi> reſolved, as long as he can, to <hi>ſleep in a whole Skin.</hi> Faint hearts! they are <hi>Well-Willers</hi> to the Mathematicks, they can look <hi>on,</hi> (as they paſs by,) and <hi>ſee the Cudgel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and <hi>with Favour,</hi> to that ſide <hi>they like,</hi> can applaud and cry—<hi>Euge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> well ſtruck! In troth <hi>That was a home-thruſt;</hi> That was <hi>well-followed;</hi> That was a <hi>Down-blow,</hi> at them again! <hi>my Heart!</hi> But, they dare as <hi>we eat their Ears</hi> as come into <hi>Ring</hi> and take up the <hi>Cudgels;</hi> though <hi>the Lub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ers</hi> have more <hi>Strength</hi> then they that <hi>play the prize,</hi> only they <hi>want a go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Sixt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 4. was firſt a Gray-Fryar of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> And from the <hi>Cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> mounte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into the <hi>Holy-Chair;</hi> To whom, <hi>amongst others, came to viſit him an old C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rade</hi> of his, a <hi>Franciſcan</hi> Fryar of the <hi>ſame houſe,</hi> in his <hi>old Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delier</hi>'s<note place="margin">Treaſure of times.</note> 
                  <hi>habit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> which the Pope liad <hi>newly</hi> thrown off.</p>
               <p>Glad was the Pope to ſee <hi>his old Comrog—not</hi> ſo much for <hi>the Fryars ſake</hi> as his own; That his <hi>Quondam Brother</hi> might <hi>behold his Glory,</hi> and the Splendor of his Equipage in all <hi>his Pontiſicalibus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which purpoſe, the Pope <hi>conceal'd nothing</hi> of his ſtately Pride and Pomp, but ſhew'd the poor Fryar <hi>all his Precious ſtones,</hi> Chambers of State, Thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes, Miters, Jewels, and Robes, <hi>not omitting the Golden Slippers</hi> that En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d his ſweaty Toes and Cornes; <hi>at last,</hi> ſhew'd him <hi>his vaſt Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,</hi> a vaſt <hi>Maſſe of Gold</hi> and Silver heaped up together: (as who ſhould ſay) <hi>Brother that was! The Game is alter'd ſince I wore</hi> a Circingle with you <hi>in the Fryary;</hi> for (quoth the Pope) I <hi>cannot now ſay</hi> (as <hi>Peter</hi> did) <hi>Silver and Gold I have none.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>No,</hi> (Replyed the Fryar) <hi>Nor can you ſay</hi> (as he did) <hi>to the ſick of the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey,</hi> (Lame and Impotent People) <hi>Ariſe and Walk.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This bold Anſwer</hi> loſt the poor Fryar a <hi>Cardinals Cap,</hi> and a pair of <hi>Lawn Sleeves,</hi> which the Pope <hi>had laid out</hi> and deſign'd for <hi>his old acquaintance,</hi> in remembrance of many a Waggiſh-<hi>prank they had plaid</hi> together in the Monaſtery; but this <hi>Plain Truth</hi> ſpoil'd all, and the Fryar ſent home, as poor as he came, and as a <hi>fellow not fit for his</hi> purpoſe, not having the wit (or Gift) <hi>of cogging,</hi> lying, flattering and diſſembling, <hi>nor meet for a Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier:</hi> And <hi>as glad was the Fryar</hi> that his Holineſs did not <hi>jayl him, for ſo much Honesty</hi> and naked Truth.</p>
               <p>Though <hi>the Wiſe and Wary<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> The <hi>Time-ſerving Tantivees and the Timerous;</hi> will joyn together to <hi>condemn the poor Fryar</hi> for a <hi>fool,</hi> that had ſo <hi>little wit</hi> as to looſe his Preferment for the ſake of a little <hi>Truth and Goſpel,</hi> and telling his <hi>Popeſhip</hi> his own.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juſt ſuch another Fool</hi> am I, <hi>in their opinion</hi> that know nothing but <hi>World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Wiſdom,</hi> which <hi>is enmity with God;</hi> why? <hi>Do you think I did not fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee all this</hi> Storm that has <hi>toſt</hi> me, (<hi>not wrackt me</hi>) long <hi>before it came;</hi> And let it <hi>bluster,</hi> Gods Will be done, <hi>I thank God for this Grace,</hi> The Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical-men <hi>cannot plague me</hi> with ſo much <hi>courage</hi> and <hi>comfort</hi> for expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their oppreſſions, <hi>extortions,</hi> and vexations of the Kings Subjects, in defyance of the Laws, as I can chearfully and <hi>patiently ſuffer,</hi> for the ſake of <hi>Truth</hi> and the <hi>Laws.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet, will I not <hi>break one</hi> Law, whilſt I <hi>vindicate another;</hi> nor did I ever write <hi>any thing</hi> which is not juſtifyable by Law.</p>
               <p>For <hi>I could find in my heart</hi> to deliver my ſelf <hi>into their hands,</hi> if it be but for an <hi>experiment</hi> to try <hi>how much</hi> Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Clemency is improv'd in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity and Humanity</hi> ſince the bleſſed days of <hi>their Predeceſſor</hi> Biſhop <hi>Bonn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not but that <hi>I am well and warm,</hi> which I ſpeak <hi>not in vapour,</hi> (far be the <hi>Imputation of ſuch vanity from me</hi>) but to the praiſe of <hi>Almighty God's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection,</hi> which I know he will <hi>continue,</hi> and I ſhall <hi>certainly overlive their rage</hi> except God ſee it <hi>more for his, Glory,</hi> and for the <hi>Promulgation of Truth,</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:32950:6"/>
that I ſhould <hi>ſeal it,</hi> with <hi>ſuffering for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of which I am ſo <hi>Indifferent,</hi> that I know not <hi>which is best,</hi> nor would I be <hi>mine own Carver,</hi> Gods Will be done: they alwayes <hi>hitherto have</hi> (and alwayes will) hurt themſelves more <hi>than me,</hi> let then be as <hi>cunning</hi> and <hi>cruel</hi> as beſt like, or as God will permit.</p>
               <p>And this I ſay (the rather) for the <hi>encouragement</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that ſuffer for <hi>Truth and a good Conſcience,</hi> (whatever other <hi>Stratagems</hi> they have <hi>for the pretence of their rage</hi>) let no mans heart therefore fail <hi>becauſe of me;</hi> for I was never better in my life.</p>
               <p>And indeed, if this Statute of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. be in force, <hi>no name is bad enough for Eccleſiasticals,</hi> but we ſeem the moſt <hi>Impudent Conventicle</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Inſolent men that ever did bid defyance to the Law, or <hi>vext the Kings Sub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>s in our own names by vexations, Citations</hi> and oppreſſions, Excommunication<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and <hi>Impriſonments;</hi> for which no <hi>Puniſhment</hi> ſeems ſatisfactory in <hi>this World,</hi> ſo it do but ſpare our Lives; we are in <hi>miſericordia Regis,</hi> and have forfeited all but <hi>our Lives,</hi> if that Branch of that Statute be in force. In the <hi>Interim,</hi> God keep me out of the enemies clutches though, For I think, I know ſufficiently what Eccleſiaſtical Clemency is, if they get a man at <hi>their mercy;</hi> women and timerous men are ſaid to be moſt cruel, <hi>when they get a man down,</hi> they never think themſelves ſafe, till he be made ſure for ever riſing up again; but, if they had not run to <hi>Weſtminster-Hall, cry'd out</hi> there for help, againſt me, I could have dealt well enough with them <hi>till they had been Tyred,</hi> nay, They knew it as well. But <hi>no more of that</hi> at preſent, <hi>for their buſineſs was never ſo fully</hi> and compleatly done as <hi>now.</hi> Take my word for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>THe Branch of the ſaid Statute, 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. now to be conſidered, is this, <hi>verbatim.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BE it therefore further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That all Summons and Citations, or other Proceſs Eccleſiaſtical, in all Suits and Cauſes of Inſtance, vetwixt Party and Party, and all Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Correction, and all Cauſes of Baſtardy or Bigamy or Inquiry</hi> de Jure Patronatus, <hi>Probates of Teſtaments, and Commiſſions of Adminiſtrations of Perſons deceaſed, and all Acquitcances of and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, accounts made by the Erecutors Adminiſtrators, or Collectors of Goods of any dead perſon, be from the firſt day of</hi> July <hi>next following, made in the name and with the ſtyle of the King, as it is in Writs Original or Iudicial, at the Common-Law; And that the</hi> Teſte <hi>thereof be in the name of the Arch-biſhop or Biſhop, or other having Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Iuriſdiction, who hath the commiſſion and grant of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority Eccleſiaſtical immediately from the Kings Highneſs; And that his Commiſſary, Official, or Subſtitute exerciſing Iuriſdiction under him, ſhall put his name in the Citation or Proceſs after the</hi> Teſte.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Furthermore, be it Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that all manner of Perſon or Perſons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who have the exerciſe of the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Iuriſdiction, ſhall have from the firſt day of</hi> July <hi>before expreſſed, in the Seals of Office, The Kings Highneſs Arms decently ſet, with certain characters under the Arms for the knowedge of the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, and ſhall uſe no other Seal of Iuriſdiction, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> wherein his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſties</hi>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:32950:6"/>
                     <hi>Arms be ing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>en, upon pain that if any perſon ſhall uſe Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Iuriſdiction (after the day before expreſſed) in this Realm of</hi> England, Wales, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> other his Dominions or Territories, And not ſend or make out the citation or proceſs in the Kings name, or uſe any Seal of Iuriſdiction, other than before Limited<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That every ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender ſhall in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap> and run in the Kings Majeſties Diſpleaſure and Indignation and ſuffer Impriſonment at his Highneſſes will and pleaſure.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>Now, <hi>what is there in all this</hi> that ſhould make a man loth to act in the <hi>Name and Style</hi> and <hi>Seal</hi> of the Kings Majeſty? (and not in the <hi>old me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod,</hi> when a Prieſt was the head of the Church) if there were not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in <hi>the hollow</hi> of his Heart?</p>
               <p>They <hi>do not pretend</hi> (as aforeſaid) that their <hi>Spiritual-Courts</hi> are nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>God's Word,</hi> if therefore they be the Kings-Courts, what, <hi>in the name of goodneſs,</hi> makes them unwilling that their Proceſſes, Citations, and Summons Eccleſiaſtical ſhould not (as <hi>other Writs Original</hi> or Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, in the <hi>Kings</hi> Common-Law Courts) run in the Name and Style and Arms of the Kings Majeſty?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Edward</hi> 6. was the firſt <hi>Proteſtant-King</hi> ſince the Reformation; For though King <hi>Henry</hi> 8 (as I ſaid) <hi>Reform'd</hi> the luſtful Monaſteries, yet he neither <hi>reform'd his own</hi> life thereby, nor his Popiſh opinions. But his Son was likely to be a happy Inſtrument of good to this Nation; Whatever Doctor <hi>Heylin</hi> (the darling Advocate of ſome Biſhops) have had the Confidence to Print to the contrary, who in the Epiſtle before his (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended) <hi>History of the Reformation,</hi> expreſly affirms—That he <hi>cannot reckon the death, of King</hi> Edward the <hi>Sixth, for an Infelicity to the Church of</hi> England; How Sir! was it not an Infelicity to the Church to loſe ſuch a King? To have the hopes of a glorious <hi>Reformation</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>pt in the very Bud? To have a fearful deluge of <hi>Blood and Idolatry</hi> ruſh in upon us by a <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor?</hi> But what will not the <hi>Craftſmen</hi> of <hi>Epheſus ſay,</hi> when they fancy their <hi>Shrines</hi> in hazzard? And how ready, alas! are ſuch as think Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and vaſt Revenues, and dominering power the Churches, <hi>only Felicit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi>) to Reproach and Scandalize (even in Sacred Princes) the cleareſt <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence,</hi> and the moſt ſolid <hi>Piety,</hi> and the brighteſt <hi>Zeal?</hi> But God he thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this Cenſure of Noble King <hi>Edward of</hi> Bleſſed Memory, is but one <hi>Doctor</hi>'s <hi>opinion,</hi> and I know not an other <hi>honest Protestant</hi> at home or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad that will ſubſcribe to it.</p>
               <p>The very firſt Statute that the Parliament made (as I ſaid before) in this good Kings Reign, was this that we are now conſidering, (except <hi>one onely</hi> concerning the Bleſſed Sacrament, and receiving it in both kindes, <hi>with which</hi> they as <hi>piouſly</hi> begun, and their next work was this Regulation of <hi>Spiritual-Courts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>)</p>
               <p>For it <hi>ſeems very abſurd</hi> that if the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical-Courts</hi> be the <hi>Kings-Courts</hi> and not the <hi>Prelates-Courts</hi> (which they <hi>dare not in</hi> plain words deny) That the <hi>Writs</hi> thence <hi>Iſſuing</hi> ſhould not be in the name and ſtyle of the King, the <hi>Eccleſiastical-head</hi> as well as the <hi>Temporal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, never ſince <hi>King Edwards Reign,</hi> could the Prelates be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to act in the Kings-Name, but in their own:</p>
               <p>Every thing would gladly be Independent, and Noun Subſtantives, And, like reeling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>unkards, ſcorn to be held up<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though they cannot ſtand by themſelves<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>And though <hi>this Statute was Rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>d</hi> in the next Reign by a Popiſh Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, yet King <hi>James</hi> in his firſt Parliament (In the firſt year of his Reign)<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:32950:7"/>
                  <hi>reviv'd this Statute,</hi> by <hi>making void the Force</hi> of that Statute, 1 <hi>Mar.</hi> 2. whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> had long held it under <hi>Reſtraint</hi> and made it <hi>Motion-leſs.</hi> But thoſe <hi>band<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> being Looſned</hi> (by Repeal of 1 <hi>Mary</hi> 2. in and by vertue of the Statute <hi>prim Jacobi cap.</hi> 25.) It was thought to be <hi>reviv'd by the two Lord Chief Juſtices;</hi> at the firſt; in the fourth year of King <hi>James.</hi> But, when the Lord <hi>Chief Baron</hi> and other <hi>Judges</hi> had conſider'd the <hi>Prejudice</hi> that might redound to the Kings Subjects if ſome Dioceſſes had no Lawful Biſhop<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all the Prieſts ordained by ſuch Biſhops (at leaſt) as were made <hi>ſince the first of the King,</hi> namely, the three laſt years, muſt be <hi>Illegal Prieſts,</hi> and Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal Biſhops.</p>
               <p>And many other Inconveniences muſt enſue, if the 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. ſhould be deemed to be <hi>in force,</hi> to <hi>the great Scandal</hi> and Impeachment of <hi>his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Juſtice,</hi> which, <hi>together with the great Influence</hi> the Biſhops had <hi>at Court</hi> (In the three laſt reigns,) together with the <hi>Terror of the High Commiſſion Court,</hi> The buſineſs was <hi>Huſh't up,</hi> pretending that it was repealed and <hi>bound down</hi> with a three fold Cord, (as <hi>Coke</hi> is pleaſed to phraſe it, 2 <hi>Instit. fol.</hi> 685.) or three after Statutes, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. firſt, by 1 <hi>Mar.</hi> 2. Secondly, by 1 and 2 <hi>Phil.</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> 8. Thirdly, By 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>And if <hi>any one of theſe</hi> do but hold, the Statute of 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. muſt ſtand Repealed; But as <hi>drowning men lay hold</hi> of any Root, or knubs (though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der water, and does but <hi>help to drown'd them</hi>) ſo men that are plung'd into a <hi>Neceſſity to hold the Concluſion,</hi> they are very willing to gain it, <hi>upon any Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes,</hi> how ſophiſtical ſoever.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nalſon</hi> in his late <hi>Collection of affairs of State<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. 763. undertakes torecite this Conſult of the Judges. 4 <hi>Jacobi,</hi> as (he ſays) he finds it in the <hi>Paper Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> and tells us, That the being of this <hi>Stat.</hi> 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. in force was <hi>Long</hi> ſtuck upon, but AT LAST an Anſwer was <hi>found</hi>—So that it ſeems there was much longing and abundance of ſeeking for an Anſwer, that is to ſay, for any plauſible pretence to avoid this Statute, and at laſt and with much ado, ſomething (as good as nothing) was found; for he furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es us but with two of the very ſame too weak Cords which <hi>Coke</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>For ſome thought they were <hi>hard put to it</hi> for Arguments againſt the force of that <hi>famous Statute,</hi> when they fly for help to the <hi>two last Cords</hi> or Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaments to bind down that Statute, which they <hi>Trembled to think</hi> might be of terrible Conſequence, (if it happen to be in force) notwithſtanding the Strength of the ſaid Cords and Ligaments, none <hi>of which</hi> ſeemed to have any the <hi>leaſt Power</hi> Imaginable to do the feat, if men were not very willing to believe it, <hi>except the first Cord,</hi> namely 1 <hi>Mar.</hi> 2. for that does expreſly and by name repeal 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2.</p>
               <p>And indeed if it had not <hi>expreſly and by Name</hi> repealed it, It could never have been repealed, if, (what Lawyers ſay) be true; That <hi>no Statute can be Repeal'd</hi> but by another Statute, and that <hi>expreſly and by Name;</hi> or be contrary to the former Statute.</p>
               <p>For if <hi>Wyre-drawn Conſequences and Inferences</hi> might Repeal a Statute, the Subjects would never know when a Statute is in <hi>Force.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For let but a crafty Lawyer with an oyly glib tongue uſe his skill, and he may with <hi>Strains of wit,</hi> and ſtretches and Inferences and <hi>far-fetcht Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences</hi> and oblique Reflections, make <hi>ſuch a Claſh</hi> among the Statutes one againſt another, that none ſhould ſeem of force, that a cunning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Conſequence, driver</hi> had any picque againſt.</p>
               <p>But, our Kings and Parliaments have always been more tender of the Validity of their Laws, then to leave them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tering</hi> thus at the me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> of every <hi>Inference-maker,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:32950:7"/>Eſpecially, when they draw <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Inferences and Conſequences as <hi>could not poſſibly enter ſo much as into the minds</hi> and Cogitations of the Law-makers, when they enacted and made a Statute.</p>
               <p>And this is ſo clear a Truth, and evident to every man that has but <hi>common ſence,</hi> that more needs not be ſaid to it.</p>
               <p>For it would be of <hi>moſt dreadful Conſequence</hi> that the Statutes ſhould be <hi>ſo flexible</hi> as to be made <hi>a Noſe of Wax</hi> of, to ſtand <hi>this way one day,</hi> and <hi>that way</hi> another, juſt as <hi>Mr. Conſequence-maker</hi> is feed to <hi>ſet</hi> them.</p>
               <p>The Diſſenters (for their money) might find cunning Lawyers <hi>enough</hi> (perhaps) to defeat the Act of Uniformity, and Repeal it, if <hi>Far-fetcht Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences</hi> and Conſequences would do the feat.</p>
               <p>But, God forbid, that the Laws of <hi>England</hi> ſhould have nothing to <hi>stand firm</hi> upon, but <hi>ſuch ſlippery</hi> ground, made ſuch by an <hi>oyly Mouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If we cannot find 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. repeal'd but by Conſequences and Oblique Inferences, we ſhall make <hi>baſe Tinkerly work on't,</hi> and to patch up <hi>one hole</hi> of evil Conſequences, <hi>make two</hi> of Conſequence twenty times more dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and pernicious.</p>
               <p>Therefore the <hi>beſt Cord,</hi> and that which ſeems <hi>moſt ſtrongly</hi> to make void and of none effect the ſaid Statute of 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. is <hi>indeed that</hi> which can never be deny'd, namely, that the ſame is <hi>expreſly</hi> and by <hi>name</hi> repealed by 1 <hi>Mary</hi> 2. There let it <hi>ſtand or lie bound</hi> for ever, except we can find its Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Shackles <hi>taken off,</hi> and <hi>again</hi> ſet in its priſtine Liberty, Vigor, and Splendor.</p>
               <p>But, as to thoſe <hi>two latter Cords</hi> that they pretend bind it down for ever by Repealing it, they are thought (by wiſe men) ſo <hi>trivial,</hi> that they are not worthy any conſidera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> and that they were ſurely <hi>ſore put to't</hi> for <hi>ſhifts,</hi> that made them of ſuch <hi>over-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>FOr how <hi>(in the name of Prudence)</hi> could it enter into the thoughts of <hi>wiſe</hi> Legiſlators, <hi>to kill a dead Horſe?</hi> Could the Parliament intend by the 1 and 2 <hi>Phil.</hi> &amp; <hi>Mar.</hi> 8. to repeal 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. which was repealed <hi>already,</hi> and made void but the <hi>very year before,</hi> namely, by 1 <hi>Mar.</hi> 2. They could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get it, it was ſo lately done; nor can they be accounted ſo ſilly as <hi>Actum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere,</hi> and make Laws againſt <hi>Non Entityes.</hi> The Learned Judge <hi>Hobert</hi> uſes<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hobart</hi> in Caſe Shef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field verſ. Ratcliff.</note> a <hi>like Argument</hi> to prove that the King ſhall have (not only the Eſtates (<hi>In Fee</hi>) of Traytors, (Eſtates <hi>in Tail</hi> being not by the Statutes (31 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. &amp; 33 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.) by name given to the King, yet) <hi>alſo Eſtates in Tayl</hi> why? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there being but <hi>two ſorts</hi> of Eſtates of Inheritance (namely <hi>in Fee,</hi> and in <hi>Tayl</hi>) and the Eſtates in <hi>Fee of Traytors</hi> being forfeit and <hi>given</hi> to the King <hi>by the Common-Law,</hi> Thoſe Statutes ſhall not be preſum'd <hi>Actum agere,</hi> but ſhall reach, the other Eſtates <hi>in Tail,</hi> which the Common-Law did <hi>not reach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And by like reaſon, ſince 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. is not ſo much as mentioned or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in 1 &amp; 2 <hi>Phil.</hi> &amp; <hi>Mar.</hi> 8. except by <hi>Inferences and Fetches,</hi> deduced from the Stile and Latitude of thoſe words.—<hi>All Statutes made against the See of Rome Repealed;</hi> There is Life in a Musſle. For the ſaid Statute did not think ſufficient for their Repeal by <hi>General Words,</hi> but do therefore name <hi>particularly and Expreſly</hi> what Statutes they mean to Repeal namely, 25 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. 9. &amp; 24 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8 12. with almoſt a ſcore more, (amongſt which, my dear
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32950:8"/>
Statute of 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6 2 is <hi>not Named</hi>) a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>fore can never be repealed thereby, nor could be intended to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thereby.</p>
               <p>But, ſome have ſaid, that there are (in 1 &amp; 2 <hi>Phil.</hi> &amp; <hi>Mar.</hi> 8. <hi>expreſs words</hi> that do Repeal by <hi>Conſequence</hi> the Statute of 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. namely theſe words,</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>ANd the Eccleſiaſtical Iuriſdiction of the Arch biſhops, Biſhops and Ordinarye to be in the ſame ſtate for proceſs of Sutes, puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Crimes, and Execution of Cenſures of the Church, with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of cauſes belonging to the ſame, and as large in thoſe points as the ſaid Iurisdiction was in</hi> Anno 20 Hen. 8.</q>
               <p>To which it is readily anſwered, That the Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction was thereby made <hi>Valid and Powerful</hi> as it was in Condition and State, as to Proceſs of Sutes, Cenſures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the 20 of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. And yet the manner of their Proceſſes as to the Name and Stile might well enough differ.</p>
               <p>For no man can <hi>rationally</hi> ſay that the Proceſs of Suits, puniſhment of Crimes, and execution of Cenſures of the Church are not in the <hi>ſame State</hi> all over <hi>London;</hi> yet the Proceſſes of Suits run not in the ſame name and Style, but ſometimes in the name of the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> ſometimes in the name of his <hi>Arch-Deacon,</hi> ſometimes in the name of the <hi>Vicar-General,</hi> ſometimes in the name of the <hi>Official, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore this <hi>far fech't Inference</hi> (ſtrained and ſtretcht) is too <hi>ſhort</hi> to reach a Blow, or ſo much as to <hi>touch</hi> that part of the Statute of 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. concerning the uſe of the name, ſtyle, and Arms, in the Citations and Proceſſes Eccleſiaſtical.</p>
               <p>Nay more, It is evident (alſo) that the Popes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Supremacy, and re-eſtabliſhment might well enough <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ith the uſe of the King's Name and Style, in Proceſſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as well as with <hi>Exton's name,</hi> or <hi>Pinfold's</hi> name; or any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ay-Commiſſary's name in the Time of Popery.</p>
               <p>If you ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ut the name of the King's Majeſty in a Writ or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>an <hi>Avow</hi> or <hi>Tacite Recognition</hi> that the Courts-Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>King's-Courts;</hi> I readily grant it, and therefore, it argues the <hi>more ſtrongly</hi> for the reaſonableneſs and great Expediency of that Statute, that well enjoyns His Majeſties Name, Style and Arms in Courts Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical, <hi>If they be the Kings-Courts Eccleſiaſtical, and His Majesty Head of the Church,</hi> as he is of the State.</p>
               <p>This Statute then of 1 and 2 <hi>Phil.</hi> and <hi>Mar.</hi> 8. does not ſo much as by <hi>Conſequence</hi> repeal 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. Yet I well know what my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> ſays to it, and do better know that he <hi>durſt ſay no other then</hi> he did, ſo terrible then were the Prelates, <hi>looking bigg and formidable</hi> in their <hi>High-Commiſſion-Court and Starr-Chamber.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Otherwiſe, a man <hi>of his ſence and acute reaſon</hi> could not have talkt (as<note place="margin">Coke Mag. Chart. p. 68<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> he does) of the dreadful <hi>Conſequences;</hi> if that <hi>Statute of</hi> 1 Edw. 6. 2. <hi>be in force, to the</hi> Infinite Prejudice <hi>of His Majesties Subjects in caſes of great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, and to the Scandal and Impeachment of His Majestics Juſtice,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le <hi>ſecure the Scandal</hi> and all the dreadful Conſequences, before the Reader has turn'd over many more Leaves of this little Tract; if the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the Law, the Learned <hi>Coke</hi> be not miſtaken. And if the Biſhops (in 4 <hi>Jacobi</hi>) had not had ſomewhat elſe at <hi>the bottome</hi> (which I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are not to name) we ſhould have had and ſtill have as good Biſhops and Prieſts as ever we had, if that be all the Objection, that the Statute of 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2 (as to the uſe of the name and ſtyle of the King in Proceſſes Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal) will make us looſe <hi>our Prieſts and Biſhops</hi> (God bleſs us, we are not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32950:8"/>
ſo <hi>loſt and undone</hi> as yet; if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Coke</hi> be not out of his Law; in <hi>this particular;</hi> the <hi>Learned</hi> are affi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> warps.</p>
               <p>But a Statute may by expreſs words, in after-Statutes, be repealed in part and in a Branch, and not alwayes in the <hi>whole;</hi> as is eaſy to inſtance in many <hi>Crowding Preſidents.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And, <hi>Coke</hi> ſays, the Arch-biſhops and Biſhops would <hi>all be illegal</hi> if they were made <hi>according</hi> to our Celebrated Act of 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. Becauſe<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> p. 686.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thought it be not repealed, yet the 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. reviving the Act of 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. 20. is thought to vacate ſo much of it as concerns the making and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting Biſhops.</p>
               <p>And therefore King <hi>James his Biſhops</hi> ſhould not have needed to have been ſo ſcared and affrighted (as if the Sky had fallen) when the 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. was reviv'd by King <hi>James</hi> his repealing 1 <hi>Ma.</hi> 2. if the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> ſay true.</p>
               <p>For Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> had ſecur'd his and her Biſhops by reviving her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Act concerning <hi>Biſhop-making,</hi> in theſe words;</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>And at every Avoydance of any Arch-biſhoprick, Biſhoprick, The King His Heirs and Sncceſſors may grant to the Prior and Covent</hi> (we have got none now) <hi>or to the Dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and a Chapter a Licence under the great Seal,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>containing the Name of the perſon which they ſhall E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and chooſe,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
               <p>
                  <hi>A pretty kind of Election!</hi> for they ſhall <hi>neither will, nor chuſe, nor dare to refuſe</hi> him that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is nominated in the Letters miſſive; yet it is called an <hi>Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on though,</hi> although it be whether they will or no.</p>
               <p>Biſhops then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> need (if <hi>Coke</hi> be not miſtaken) to fear, but they are well enough made, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> I wiſh (with all my heart) that ſome of them were <hi>made better,</hi> for their ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and for my own ſake There's no harm nor ſcandal in this Prayer, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>But ſtill, what's all this to the contempt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ute of 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2 as to the uſe of the name, ſtyle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the King in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>mmons Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical, if that Clauſe (in 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. be unrepealed?</p>
               <p>Why? it is repealed in effect (ſays the Lord <hi>Coke</hi>) by this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that Statute of 25. <hi>Hen</hi> 8. 20. as aforeſaid, by 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. reviv'd, namely, in<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Chart.</hi> p, 686.</note> theſe words.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>And further it is Enacted, that every perſon choſen, Elected. Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted and conſecrated Arch-biſhop, or Biſhop, according to the Form and Effect of this Act</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall do and execute iu every thing and things touching the ſame, as any Arch-biſhop or Biſhop of this Realm,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>might at any time heretofore do.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Thus the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> recites that Branch of the Statute, with greater prevarication then became a man of his <hi>Ingenuity,</hi> which herein far ſurpaſt his <hi>Integrity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Truth is, a <hi>great Lawyer,</hi> (and the higher he is <hi>ſtaged</hi>) had need to be, of all others, a <hi>good man,</hi> like <hi>Roſcius,</hi> of whom <hi>Cicero</hi> gives this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Orat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> pro R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rente augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteno, de conſenſu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>vaugle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cap.</hi> 23. <hi>T.</hi> 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note>—<hi>Roſcium it a peritum dixit ut ſolus eſſet dignus qui in Scenam deberet intrare, ita virum bonum ut ſolus eſſet dignus, qui eo non debeat accedere: Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcius</hi> was ſuch a skilful <hi>Actor,</hi> that he (of all others) did beſt <hi>become</hi> the <hi>stage;</hi> but ſo <hi>good a man</hi> withall, that it <hi>was a Pity</hi> he ſhould ever have come <hi>there.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As the Learned <hi>Coke</hi> does quote the Statute, Arch-biſhops and Biſhops may, nay, they ought to ſay Maſs, baptiſe our Bells, ſpit in our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens mouths when they baptiſe them, and a thouſand idle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>opperies more
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:32950:9"/>
they ought to do, if they ought to do in every thing, as any Popiſh Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop or Biſhop might at any time heretofore do.</p>
               <p>To the great Diſhonour and <hi>Diſparagement</hi> of the <hi>Prudence</hi> and Wiſdom of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and her firſt Parliament, nay, and of all Parliaments ſince that time.</p>
               <p>By <hi>Cooks</hi> Citation of the Statute to ſerve his purpoſe againſt the ſaid clauſe of the Statute of 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. he opens a gap to <hi>let in Popery,</hi> or to <hi>let out the Biſhops thither,</hi> if they pleaſe; if they muſt do and execute in <hi>every thing and things,</hi> as any Arch-biſhop or Biſhop of this Realm might at any time do, before the time of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>Story ſays that <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> was ſtruck by a <hi>Thunderbolt</hi> for taking Immoderate Fees for a Cure: and ſome men think, that it was either <hi>Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of a great Huge banking Fee, or <hi>Fear</hi> of looſing ſome Place or Office by diſpleaſing the Biſhops, that <hi>Cook</hi> did not fully and honeſtly recite the ſaid Statute; For the true words are,</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>As any Arch-biſhop or Biſhop of this Realm,</hi> without offending the Prerogative Royal of the Crown and the Laws and Cuſtomes of this, Realm, <hi>might at any time heretofore do.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Which clauſe (by <hi>Cook</hi>) wilfully or weakly omitted and left out, <hi>quite alters the Caſe,</hi> and gives the Arch-Biſhops and Biſhops no power to act, do, execute, or Iſſue out any Proceſſes Eccleſiaſtical, (<hi>as Popiſh Biſhops uſed to do</hi>) in their own Names and Styles, ſealed with their own Arms, and not the Kings Armes, becauſe it is contrary to the Law and Statute of 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2 And thoſe Armes are uſually <hi>Papa in Cathedra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of my <hi>Court</hi> in the <hi>Soken</hi> of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is the <hi>Mitred Pope ſitting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Chair;</hi> ſo that (ſtill I ſay) The Kings Armes engraven in <hi>all Cour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> would be a good <hi>Recognition</hi> that all the Eccleſiaſtical Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>His;</hi> and He <hi>Head of the Church;</hi> as the Popes <hi>Picture</hi> (of old)<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Court-Seales, (with the two Croſs-keys in his hand,) did <hi>ſeem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Popes Supremacy</hi> and Authority as chief head <hi>of their old <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Eccleſiastical Courts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſecond and third <hi>Ligaments,</hi> or Cords ſaid to <hi>bind</hi> the force of this Act, (namely 1 &amp; 2 <hi>Phil.</hi> &amp; <hi>Mar.</hi> 8. &amp; 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1.) does <hi>not</hi> ſo much as <hi>touch</hi> upon 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. no not obliquely, <hi>much leſs</hi> do they repeal it <hi>expreſly</hi> and by name; and <hi>least of all</hi> could it be any ways poſſible that the Legiſlators had the leaſt thoughts to ſtrike it dead by 1 &amp; 2 <hi>Phil.</hi> &amp; <hi>Mar.</hi> 8. or 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. when they knew it was dead and buryed before by 1 <hi>Mar.</hi> 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>THis <hi>Beloved Statute</hi> then is got looſe from the pretended ſhackles that <hi>Phillip and Mary or Queen Elizabeth,</hi> are ſaid to deſign againſt it; alas they could not poſſibly be ſo weak as to plant their <hi>Artillery</hi> againſt a thing that the Queen had ſtruck <hi>dead whilſt ſhe was a maid,</hi> a year before; they had not the leaſt thought of it, I dare ſay for them.</p>
               <p>Much leſs had Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the leaſt thoughts of deſtroying this Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute by any thing in 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. when they very well knew that it was dead or repealed by 1 <hi>Mar.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>And though 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1, does obliquely glance at it, by making the <hi>old faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of making Biſhops</hi> Legal, in a Proteſtant Church; yet ſhe does not em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32950:9"/>
(by a revival of 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. 20.) any Arch-biſhop or Biſhop to <hi>trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs</hi> any Statute <hi>allready in force,</hi> much leſs any Statute that <hi>ſhould come to be in force after</hi> Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was dead and buryed.</p>
               <p>Which is the very caſe here; For had <hi>Queen Elizabeth,</hi> as Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> (or any other King or Queen) <hi>by name</hi> (expreſly.) <hi>Repealed</hi> this Statute; (with which Cords Learned <hi>Coke</hi> makes <hi>ſuch a Pother</hi> to no purpoſe) yet, by his <hi>own Arguments</hi> all his <hi>Pother is an idle Pother,</hi> and nothing that King <hi>Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> nor Queen <hi>Mary</hi> alone, nor Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> alone, nor all of them <hi>united,</hi> can do, is able to repeal 1. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. for ever.</p>
               <p>For if an after-King and Parliament do but repeal their Repeal, the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Repealed gets <hi>New Life,</hi> and is born again; as <hi>Coke</hi> infallibly proves and affirms, in his diſcourſe upon the Revival of this <hi>very Statute:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke <hi>2d.</hi> Inſtit. p. 685, 686.</note>
               </p>
               <p>For he ſays that by the <hi>Repealing of a Repeal, the firſt Act is Reviv'd;</hi> which is moſt true, for <hi>remoto Impedimento reviviſcit Statutum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore the <hi>Force of this Statute,</hi> about which <hi>Coke</hi> does ſo puzzle himſelf with this Three-fold Cord, eaſily appears and Breaks looſe; from any Tye that 1 <hi>Mar.</hi> or 1 &amp; 2 <hi>Phil.</hi> &amp; <hi>Mar.</hi> or Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> could poſſibly <hi>ſhackle it</hi> and fetter it <hi>with;</hi> which <hi>Shackles</hi> ſhall bind no longer <hi>then till</hi> they or ſome of the ſucceeding Kings and Parliament <hi>do unbind</hi> and take them off.</p>
               <p>All which was ſoon done in the <hi>firſt</hi> of King <hi>James,</hi> in his firſt Parliament, Repealing by Name 1 <hi>Mar.</hi> 2. that by Name had Repealed this Royal Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute (ſo advantagious to the Kings Supremacy and Prerogative Royal) and alſo thereby (<hi>through its Revival</hi>) Virtually <hi>Repealing all Precedent Statutes,</hi> whether of <hi>Phil.</hi> &amp; <hi>Mar.</hi> or <hi>Mary,</hi> or Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> that went before it, if contrary to it; or in <hi>tanto.</hi> For in Statute Law (contrary to the Laws of <hi>Heraldry</hi>) The <hi>Junior always takes place</hi> of the <hi>Senior.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Arch-biſhops or Biſhops ought to have uſed their own names, Styles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in their Proceſſes, whilſt 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. ſtood repealed, during the Reigns of the two Siſters, <hi>Mary</hi> &amp; <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and no longer (it ſeems) then till <hi>Primo Jacobi</hi> It was revived.</p>
               <p>The <hi>only difficulty</hi> that ever I could find that ſeem'd to queſtion the force of this Statute of 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. Is its Repeal by 1 <hi>Mar.</hi> 2. which though its ſelf be Repealed by 1 <hi>Jacobi,</hi> yet the 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2 being not revived <hi>by Name,</hi> therefore <hi>ſome doubt</hi> its vigour, though the <hi>Force it lay under,</hi> be quite <hi>taken away.</hi> Becauſe (ſay they) It is not reviv'd in expreſs words by 1 <hi>Jacobi.</hi> But the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> makes <hi>no difficulty at all</hi> of that, for he has theſe Words on this very occaſion, namely,—</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It was ſtrongly urged and enforced,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that all their</hi> (the Biſhops) <hi>Proceſs and Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings being in their own Names, Stiles, and Seals, (where by the ſaid Act they ought to have been in the Kings Name) and under the Kings Seale were all unlawful and voyd.</hi> (Ay!)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And to prove that the ſaid Act of Anno</hi> 1 Edw<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6. <hi>was n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w in force, They alleadged that this Act of</hi> 1 Edw. 6. <hi>was Repealed by the ſaid Act of</hi> 1 Mar. <hi>above mentioned, which Act of Repeal being Repealed by the ſaid branch of</hi> Primo Regis Jacobi, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nſequently the ſaid Act of</hi> 1 Edw. 6. <hi>was thereby revived.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For when an Act of Repeal is Repealed, The firſt Act that was Repealed is Revived</hi>—A plain Caſe) Remo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Impedimento Reviviſcit Statutum, <hi>And herewith agreeth the</hi> Book-<hi>Caſe in</hi> 15 Edw. 3. Tit. Petition Placit 2. <hi>And this is true, and cannot be denyed. Thus far</hi> Coke.</p>
               <p>Why is it ſo? Then truly I think 'tis no great ſin to be of my Lord Chief Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice <hi>Pembertons</hi> Opinion, (I mean) whilſt he was at the <hi>Bar,</hi> urging the force &amp; Validity of this Statute, in Mr. <hi>Wealds Caſe of Much-Waltham in Eſſex,</hi> moving with Mr. <hi>Rotheram</hi> for a Prohibition againſt the proceedings of the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical mens Proceſs againſt Mr. <hi>Wealds,</hi> becauſe their Proceſs <hi>against him</hi> run in their own Names, &amp; ſealed with their own Seales, and not the Kings-Arms. But, becauſe Sir <hi>William Scrogs</hi> neſtled, and neſtled, and <hi>Scracht his Head,</hi> Sir <hi>Francis Pemberton</hi> (it ſeems) eaſily perceived his <hi>Diſeaſe,</hi> and therefore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32950:10"/>
to Compaſſionate the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Scrogs,</hi> by ſaying, My Lord, I <hi>have urged the Statute</hi> of 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. but I will <hi>not be warm upon it,</hi> becauſe I perceive your <hi>Lordſhip is not prepar'd at this time</hi> to give it an Anſwer; or, he uſed words to the like effect, in Preſence of <hi>above an hundred Witneſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Truth is, the time Sir <hi>Francis Pemberton</hi> urg'd this Statute, was <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament-time;</hi> no very ſeaſonable time for a Judge to declare a Statute to be null and void, that never <hi>any Judge</hi> as yet did upon the Bench <hi>take upon him to do;</hi> ſince 1 <hi>Jacobi</hi> reviv'd it, by Repealing its Repealer 1 <hi>Mar.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>And truly whilſt Eccleſiaſtical-Courts did little elſe but prove Wills, and now and then get a <hi>few crack't Groats</hi> from a poor fearful Church-War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, (rather than contend with them) and ſome ſuch little buſineſs, moſt men <hi>paſt them by</hi> through contempt: As not daigning to trouble themſelves with medling with them; though <hi>in that little</hi> they did, <hi>They opprest</hi> (and ſtill do oppreſs) His Majeſties Subjects moſt <hi>impudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> by extorting <hi>exceſſive Fees,</hi> in deſpight and defyance of the Statutes to the cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y; <hi>Impudent Registers!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But there is this to be ſaid for them, by way of Apology, That when they give ſome hundreds of Pounds for the Sell-Souls-place, they muſt make their money of <hi>Sins and Souls;</hi> which yet is contrary to their own Canons.</p>
               <p>I profeſs, I have many times <hi>long together</hi> been puzling my ſelf by ſtudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ood L. v. Tit. 2. cap. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terea.</note> what thoſe Eccleſiaſtical-Fellows in <hi>their</hi> Eccleſiaſtical-Courts <hi>are good for,</hi> or <hi>what one good thing</hi> they do; every Creature of God is good for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; but, now I think on't, they do not pretend to be purely of <hi>Gods making,</hi> (there's nothing in <hi>holy</hi> Scripture that is alike to their Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;) nor (by what has been here ſaid) will any man that I know venture to ſay they are purely of <hi>the King's making</hi> Legally, if they live in defyance of the Kings Laws, and refuſe to uſe the <hi>Kings Name, Style, and Seal,</hi> in their Proceſſes Eccleſiaſtical, enjoyned by the Statute: I have been in <hi>Popiſh Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, and there</hi> I have ſeen a Crew in many things like them.</p>
               <p>But, (<hi>God knows</hi>) we Proteſtants <hi>do unanimouſly</hi> declare againſt <hi>Implicite Faith,</hi> and yet, the Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, <hi>from the firſt</hi> Citation to <hi>the end,</hi> namely to <hi>Excommunication and the Jayl,</hi> is much carryed <hi>on by Implicite Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the <hi>Judges</hi> believe the <hi>Biſhops Significavit,</hi> and Arch-biſhops <hi>Signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieavits,</hi> whilſt they, (<hi>good men</hi>) ſignify a man Excommunicated, and yet never <hi>heard one word</hi> of the merit of the cauſe; but the Judges believes the Biſhops <hi>Significavit,</hi> and the Biſhop believes the Regiſters <hi>Certificavit;</hi> which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable comes, if you do not ſtop the Regiſters hand with money, to his content: <hi>Oh ſad eſtate of Christianity!</hi> Chriſtianity?</p>
               <p>God bleſs the King, and Parliament (when it ſits, I mean) and by <hi>all Tokens</hi> it is probable, that they'l ſoon reſolve theſe Riddles; and (alſo) not admit palpable Symony and Hypocriſy, to Provoke Gods Wrath and Judgments upon the Nation, by making holy Ordinances and Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vendible, and Goſpel-Keys (<hi>of binding and looſing</hi>) (once another <hi>Gift of God</hi>) a money-buſineſs, or <hi>Political Engine,</hi> to take away men's <hi>Franchiſes</hi> and <hi>Votes,</hi> when there is no other way to deprive them thereof.</p>
               <p>I cannot think that Chriſt entruſted <hi>Anathemas</hi> to his Diſciples to play them <hi>ſo frankly</hi> at a bold Rate <hi>faſt &amp; looſe;</hi> He that eats &amp; drinks unworthily, that is (to a Politick, <hi>Carnal End</hi>) eats and drinks his own Damnation; and he that <hi>opens and ſhuts</hi> Heaven and Hell-Gates, binding and looſing, uſing the Holy-Keys <hi>unworthily</hi> (that is) for <hi>low,</hi> politick, <hi>Carnal</hi>-Ends) uſes them to his <hi>own Damnation;</hi> God <hi>will not be mocked.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:32950:10"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>I Doubt not but all that Read this, muſt ſay, that in this Tract I <hi>have done their buſineſs</hi> already, to all intents and purpoſes.</p>
               <p>A Law <hi>may ſleep,</hi> a Statute may lie <hi>Dormant,</hi> as did the Act <hi>of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> whilſt the King's <hi>Act of Indulgence</hi> (according to his Royal Word, and Promiſe from <hi>Breda,</hi> facilitating his Return) <hi>did laſt;</hi> but though, Laws may be <hi>huſht</hi> and <hi>lull'd aſleep,</hi> awhile, nay, a long time, yet, (if they be not <hi>quite dead</hi>) woe be to him that tramples on them; for the Laws of <hi>England</hi> are ſo <hi>ſacred</hi> that (it has been obſerv'd) they have been <hi>too hard for any man,</hi> at long run, that durſt <hi>oppoſe them,</hi> withſtand them, or <hi>ſtand in their way,</hi> the Laws are (called) the Subjects beſt Inheritance.</p>
               <p>I remember part of Sir <hi>Harbottle Grimſton's</hi> ſpeech (in Parliament <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1640. concerning <hi>Spiritual-Courts</hi>) was to take notice of an Inſolence<note place="margin">Coke 2d. Inſtit. <hi>p63.</hi>
                  </note> of theirs much alike to what has been heard of in other caſes; namely, under <hi>a Religious Pretext</hi> to meddle with mens <hi>Franchyſes,</hi> Charters, and Priviledges, as <hi>Engliſh-men;</hi> for, ſays that <hi>Loyal Gentleman and true Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> ſpeaking of the <hi>Lambeth Canons</hi> of 40. <hi>and the Synod then there</hi>—</p>
               <p>`That the <hi>Synod</hi> called together upon pretence of Religion, <hi>took upon them `the boldneſs out of Parliament to grant Subſidies and meddle with men's Free Holds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh! How diſhonourable is it to any Religion to palliate ſo much venome as <hi>under a notion of a Goſpel Ordinance</hi> of Excommunication or the like, to deſign to make men uncapable of <hi>a Vote,</hi> or Freedoms, Franchiſes, and Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,<note place="margin">Mr Grim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtonsſpeach in Parlia<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> eſpecially if they ſeem to be affraid of nothing ſo much as that ſome ſhould conform, and conſequently be capable of as many <hi>Priviledges</hi> as the Debauchee, or prophane Libertine.</p>
               <p>Chriſtianity do you call it? more like <hi>Ely</hi>'s Sons, or <hi>Simon-Magus,</hi> Oh God! may not ſuch well dread thy Vengeance? Chriſtianity do you call it?</p>
               <p>The wiſeſt of <hi>all the ten</hi> Perſecuting Emperours was <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> whoſe Conſcience ſo tormented his Breaſt, for <hi>Perſecuting the Chriſtians,</hi> that he threw the Diadem from his <hi>hated head,</hi> and hid it in a Garden, in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcureſt <hi>Py-corner</hi> of the World.</p>
               <p>But, the Horrour of <hi>Nero's Viſage</hi> is by <hi>Suetonius</hi> rendred ſo <hi>tremendous</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Suet. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro.</note> to behold (after he vented his <hi>Cruelty</hi> upon the <hi>Chriſtians</hi>) that it would make a mans <hi>Hair stand on end,</hi> to view him, <hi>extantibus vigentibuſque ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad horrorem viſentium,</hi> with ghaſtly Looks and frightful Eyes ſtrike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Horrour in all that ſaw him; ſuch was the Fate of this <hi>Perſecuting A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt, Religionem uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> qua<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Aſpernator,</hi> as <hi>Suetonius</hi> calls him; a Contemner of every <hi>thing that lookt like</hi> Religion.</p>
               <p>And ſuch are the brood of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> that make uſe of Religion (which is intended for the Salvation of mens Souls) only to the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their <hi>Bodies,</hi> and <hi>Eſtates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Simon?</hi> (quoth he) no <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was not thus Impudent, <hi>he did his buſineſs</hi> (indeed) namely, <hi>the money buſineſs,</hi> and to be ador'd and Reverenc't (forſooth) But, he did it, by <hi>juggle</hi> and ſleight of hand; but, the Son's of <hi>Eli</hi> and <hi>Symonists,</hi> (like Ghoſts long enur'd to walk) appeared at <hi>Noon-day</hi> did take <hi>purſes before mens faces,</hi> Swagger, Curſe, Anathematize, Damn, &amp; blu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; In good time they were charm'd down? <hi>In Nomine Domini?</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>If ever you were in <hi>Spain</hi> or <hi>Portugal,</hi> (as I have been) tell me what <hi>Monkey or Baboon</hi> is more contemtible, than a <hi>ſneaking,</hi> perjur'd, <hi>Hypocritical,</hi> Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Property of State.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What more <hi>Ridicule,</hi> then a fawning Spiritual Sycophant in <hi>Antick-Dreſs,</hi> cringing with his <hi>Pin-Buttocks</hi> and <hi>hallow-ſmiles,</hi> upon a Whore
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:32950:11"/>
                  <hi>Atheist</hi> or <hi>Renegade,</hi> that do but ſcoff at his ghaſtly Habilements of <hi>uncouth Guize</hi> and Shape, <hi>Portentous</hi> and Prodigious? <hi>Riſum teneat is Amic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>?</hi> could ye have held from Laughing at the <hi>Holy Mymick.</hi> Or could <hi>ye forbear ſmiling</hi> to ſee a bigotted Fop (<hi>old or young</hi>) throng and <hi>crowd</hi> to kneel for the benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of an <hi>empty Palm,</hi> or Lecherous and <hi>Simoniacal Clutches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whilſt the <hi>gawdy Hypocrite</hi> ſmiles in his <hi>Py-bald Sleeves</hi> (The Trophies (poſſibly) of <hi>Smock-Simony,</hi> Pandariſme, <hi>Flattery,</hi> or Bribery.)</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>OH! what a frightful, <hi>Heatheniſh,</hi> (nay more,) <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Barbarous</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cambdens Eliz. lib. 4 Anno 1602 45. Eliz.</note> 
                  <hi>ſight it is</hi> to ſee a <hi>Biſhop</hi> lye like <hi>Eugenius O-Hegan,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Roſſe,</hi> who (ſiding with the Tories) was ſlain by Captain <hi>Taffe,</hi> and in a moſt <hi>Ghaſtly</hi> and <hi>un-Biſhop-like</hi> Poſture found <hi>Dead</hi> with a <hi>Breviary</hi> (his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-prayer-Book) in <hi>one hand</hi> and a <hi>Sword in the other!</hi> like to the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> that <note n="*" place="margin">Fox. Acts and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> Lecherous <hi>Bonner,</hi> who was a <hi>fool to boot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For, if he <hi>had had any Brains in his Skull,</hi> conſidering (more eſpecially) the <hi>crazy foundation</hi> he ſtood upon, and the <hi>ſlippery Hold,</hi> that hung <hi>onely on the ſlender Thread</hi> of the Quens life, he would not have diſobliged the <hi>generality of Mankind</hi> by the cruel methods of himſelf, <hi>and his Imps,</hi> delivering men <hi>to the Devil,</hi> Jayl, and <hi>Torments,</hi> by <hi>Shoals,</hi> and in groſs, and releaſing them as faſt <hi>for money.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>Pluto</hi> loves Riches, yet he <hi>never</hi> teaches his Servants any <hi>Wit,</hi> but only <hi>ſo much as he teaches Witches;</hi> juſt enough <hi>to do miſchief</hi> when God permits them <hi>the power a while</hi> in their hands, that the <hi>malice</hi> (which lies in their Deviliſh hearts) may be the better <hi>known,</hi> and ſo bring them <hi>the ſooner to their End.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>Witches and Perſecutors</hi> never had <hi>Wit enough</hi> (ſince the World was) <hi>to be wiſe for themſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For if <hi>Bonner</hi> had not been a fool, he would never have been the Devils <hi>Prime-Tool,</hi> and the <hi>Jaylors best Friend,</hi> and <hi>thereby</hi> (alſo) the <hi>Queens great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Enemy,</hi> and the beſt Friend that her <hi>Proteſtant Succeſſor found.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For there was never a poor Soul that <hi>Bonner</hi> deliver'd to the Devil and the Jail, but loſt the Queen a <hi>Thouſand hearts; all which</hi> her Proteſtant Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor <hi>found ready Preſt</hi> for her Service.</p>
               <p>For a Prince that, by ungrateful methods, has loſt the hearts of <hi>the Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of his ſubjects, has loſt <hi>his best</hi> Life-guard and <hi>strongeſt Fort.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So much the <hi>greater</hi> loſs, becauſe <hi>Irrecoverable:</hi> for Oppreſſors, and Faith-breakers, and Promiſe-breakers, can play no <hi>after-games;</hi> becauſe (like broken Merchants) their credit once crack't, no body will truſt them.</p>
               <p>This was too evident to Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> who contrary to her own natural Tenderneſs, was puſh't on to <hi>harſh</hi> &amp; ungrateful Methods by the Inſtigation of the <hi>furious Prieſts,</hi> who ſeldom prove fortunate Counſellors to a Prince.</p>
               <p>For, thus, by their <hi>Tantivec-leaſings,</hi> (onely to uphold their <hi>Spiritual-Tyranny,</hi> Pride and Pomp) ſhe, by looſing <hi>her Peoples</hi> hearts, <hi>broke her own,</hi> more than did the loſs of <hi>Calice,</hi> or the coldneſs of King <hi>Philips</hi> affection towards her.</p>
               <p>All this <hi>wrought well for her</hi> Proteſtant <hi>Succeſſor,</hi> whom the <hi>major part lov'd and long'd for,</hi> wiſhing onely for <hi>an occaſion</hi> to ſhow their devotion.</p>
               <p>Nor does the All-ſeeing Providence <hi>long adjourn</hi> ſuch occaſions, as here fell out, by the Queens ſudden and unexpected death; Oh Monſtrous! To ſee how <hi>Bonner</hi> look't then, and all the little gang of <hi>Polititians!</hi> The Queen's death <hi>breaking the heart of</hi> Cardinal <hi>Pool,</hi> who dyed three hours after he heard the news; though ſome think that <hi>ſorrow alone,</hi> (without ſome other drug) <hi>could not</hi> have diſpatcht him <hi>ſo ſuddenly;</hi> Thus the <hi>poor Levitt</hi> (Aſpiring <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>olſey</hi>) alſo is ſaid to haſten his own death by a <hi>Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs-Purge,</hi> when his <hi>Tottering-ſtate</hi> (which is nothing but <hi>viciſſio</hi>) turned.</p>
               <p>But, to return to my other <hi>Eccleſiaſtical-man Bonner,</hi> who had never a Friend in <hi>Heaven</hi> nor on <hi>Earth:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:32950:11"/>Such a thrifty True is Perſecution of men's Conſciences, whereof God <hi>alone</hi> (as King <hi>Charles the ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſayes) <hi>is the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor will ari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>nan be of the <hi>Perſecuting Trade,</hi> but he that is <hi>more fool</hi> than Knave; for, as it br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>the Spanyard</hi> by <hi>looſing him</hi> the Low-Countreys, ſo <hi>it breaks every man</hi> that (as yet) ever <hi>followed the Trade;</hi> whatſoever <hi>Politick-Roger</hi> does <hi>obſerve</hi> to the contrary.</p>
               <p>Beſides, it is a Trade as uneaſy as accurſed, for it is hard kicking againſt the Pricks, or <hi>fighting againſt the King</hi> of Conſciences: <hi>Let Atheiſt go on,</hi> as <hi>Bonner</hi> did; there was no perſwading him to the contrary: he would go on; <hi>What ſhould a Body talk?</hi> Go, <hi>Bray a Fool in a Mortar,</hi> yet will not his Folly depart from him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That very Fool was,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Loudon,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Bonner,</hi> for, <hi>if he would have hang'd himſelf,</hi> he could not have done the Martyrs <hi>more good,</hi> than by his Helliſh Methods, ſending them <hi>the ſooner</hi> to Heaven, and himſelf (without Repentance) <hi>the ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> to the Devil, by his Curſed Work of <hi>Excommunicating, Jayling, and Halling men to</hi> Torment, ſometimes of one kind, ſometimes another; nay, the unclean Wretclt took pleaſure in whipping <hi>Pretty Boys Buttocks, fumbling at them</hi> with his Epiſcopal <hi>Palms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis true, Queen <hi>Mary</hi> could not have got (ſeek <hi>England</hi> through) a <hi>Metter Engine</hi> for Perſecution; for he was ſo much a Fool that he had <hi>only Wit enough to be A curſed,</hi> Cruel, <hi>implacable Knave,</hi> and the <hi>State's-Fool.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For which employment he was <hi>the fitter,</hi> becauſe he had <hi>been at Rome,</hi> (perhaps for the <hi>very nonce</hi>) to be the more <hi>accompliſht Perſecutor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He being not onely the <hi>Queens Puppet,</hi> but the <hi>Queens</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Aprodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius Canon ſo called.</note> 
                  <hi>Pocket-Piſtol;</hi> for he was the <hi>Roaring-Megg</hi> of miſchief, thundring out his <hi>Anathema's and Excommunications, Damm'em he cry'd,</hi> or elſe, <hi>take them Devil!</hi> If they were <hi>Diſſenters</hi> from Popiſh Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions and happened to <hi>be cited to his Spiritual-Courts,</hi> and yet he lookt <hi>as demure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> as <hi>ſillily</hi> (for I have his Picture) and he looks ſo <hi>like an Innocent,</hi> and yet like a <hi>Holy-cheat,</hi> or <hi>Religious Ape,</hi> being indeed the <hi>Pia-fraus of malice</hi> and wickedneſs.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, if I knew where <hi>this quondam Biſhop of London's Tomb</hi> is, I would draw his <hi>Picture</hi> upon his <hi>Sepulcher,</hi> and expoſe his <hi>Loathſome Features</hi> to Poſterity, by writing <hi>his Epitaph</hi> upon his Grave: (<hi>I have it ready.</hi>)</p>
               <p>For he was the very <hi>Picture of ill-luck,</hi> as ever had the hap to be <hi>London's Biſhop;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>States great Puppet,</hi> a <hi>Tool</hi> that Knaves do work with, call'd a <hi>Fool;</hi> being a meer <hi>property of State;</hi> and the very Compound of Malice and Non-ſence, <hi>ana.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>LEt no <hi>Ingenuous</hi> Reader <hi>blame my ſtile,</hi> as if it were too ſharp and <hi>pungent</hi> on this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion; He that conſiders the Vexations, Torments and Crueltics inflicted by that Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> will not wonder if they <hi>whet my Pen</hi> even to <hi>Exaſperatien;</hi> when I drew <hi>Bonners</hi> Picture in the foregoing Chapter.</p>
               <p>You may ſee the <hi>Biſhops Picture,</hi> in <hi>Fox</hi> his Book of <hi>Martyrs</hi> (if you think <hi>it reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles him ſo well as this</hi> that I have (as aforeſaid) drawn for him.)</p>
               <p>Did you ever ſee any Body like him?</p>
               <p>For <hi>Bonner</hi> was <hi>more Brute than man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet more may be ſaid in Excuſe for <hi>Bonner,</hi> then for ſome others, that ſhall follow his Traáe; (to wit) that <hi>Bonner</hi> had the <hi>Letter of the Law</hi> to juſtify his Perſecution; and yet that <hi>Letter of the Law</hi> could not <hi>juſtify</hi> him, nor keep the Wretch from being <hi>undone</hi> ſoon after; For Cruelty and Perſecution are all <hi>ſhort liv'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But, I am ſure, ſome</hi> Eccleſiaſtical-men <hi>have not ſo much as the</hi> Letter of the Law to juſtify their Sell-Soul-Trade, <hi>Oppreſſions, Illegal Fees, Vexations, Symony, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortions; wherein they are</hi> far leſs juſtifyable <hi>than vile</hi> Bonner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oh! Does our</hi> Bibles teach <hi>us</hi> Symony, <hi>or to take</hi> money for the Gifts <hi>of God that are</hi> not to be ſold nor purchaſed with money?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Does Chriſt or his Apoſtles teach us to</hi> exerciſe Dominion (like the Princes of the Gentiles) <hi>and to</hi> Lord it <hi>over Gods Heritage?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Simon Magus</hi> attempted it, but to cheapen and ask the Price <hi>of the Gift of God, but did not</hi> actually ſell it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>However we do not read that he intended to be twice paid: But it is contrary to our</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical-Oath <hi>and your own Canons, to take or give</hi> money for Letters of Orders, <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> Inſtitutions, <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ptings, Marriages,</hi> Burials, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and contrary to our Oath
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:32950:12"/>
againſt Symony? <hi>or ſelling or purchating Gods Gifts! How are we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>?</hi> What Oath have we ſworn to keep?</p>
               <p>There is yet one, (even moſt <hi>thumping) Objection behind</hi> and unanſwered, which the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> ſeems to lay the <hi>greateſt Streſs upon,</hi> and did <hi>moſt prevail</hi> with the Lord <hi>chief-Baron</hi> and others to get it <hi>huſh't down and laid, after</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wo Lord Chief-Juſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>could not deny but it begun to be reviv'd and walk again,</hi> ſince 1 <hi>Jacobi,</hi> To the great T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rour of the ruling Prieſts, <hi>Commiſſaries,</hi> Officials, <hi>Jaylors,</hi> Regiſters and <hi>Summers;</hi> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Trade ſeem'd to begin to fail, but <hi>for one main Argument,</hi> or Cord that ſeem'd to bind it <hi>down again, viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> It would be great Scandal to the Kings Juſtice (<hi>yea verily</hi>) if there had been no Legal Prieſts and Biſhops made for three long years together, <hi>with other Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences</hi> (to boot) <hi>if the Statute of</hi> 1 Edw. 6. 2. ſhould be in force, <hi>and therefore it</hi> muſt not, <hi>it</hi> ſhall not, <hi>it</hi> cannot <hi>be in force.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Objection is like the <hi>Rancounter of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ayl,</hi> there is no ward (they think) <hi>no fence againſt it;</hi> and <hi>it is</hi> really ſo, if the <hi>Law of England</hi> be <hi>Club-Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Object. <hi>Was it a</hi> Scandal <hi>to have no Legal Biſhops nor Legal Prieſts conſtituted for three long years, how great then would the Scandal be for 70 long years? ſay they.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But, (My friends!) a <hi>Conſumption</hi> or <hi>Gangrene</hi> is never <hi>the better</hi> but the worſe, more <hi>Inveterate,</hi> more noyſome, <hi>more Dangerous,</hi> and more difficulty cured, by <hi>Continuance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Did ever any man plead for the Expediency of an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcer</hi> becauſe it was <hi>an old ſore?</hi> Is not the <hi>Continuance thereof</hi> the ready way to bring it to a <hi>Gangrene?</hi> to the hazard of <hi>mortifying the part,</hi> and <hi>threatning</hi> (moſt formidably) the <hi>Hazard of the Vitals,</hi> and noble parts? Never did Illegality or a Diſeaſe <hi>plead Seniority</hi> rationally for its Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Is it a Scandal, and attended with great Inconveniencies? 'Tis granted, and it is too true: What then? <hi>What is to be done with it?</hi> that is the <hi>next</hi> queſtion, and moſt neceſſary to be decided: Is it a <hi>Scandal?</hi> the more need there is of a ſpeedy Removal of the Scandal, ſuch <hi>an old Scandal:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (or <hi>Scandalum,</hi>) is a Greek <hi>word,</hi> and it properly ſignifies a <hi>Threſhold</hi> or ſtumbling block, and (Metaphorically) <hi>all things that offend</hi> (or lye <hi>in our way</hi>) are called <hi>Scandals?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now what ſhall we do <hi>with his</hi> block or <hi>Threſhold,</hi> or <hi>Scandal?</hi> The Anſwer is <hi>moſt Eaſy; Lay</hi> the block or the <hi>Threſhold at the right Door</hi> whereto it belongs and appertains.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p>DOes the Revival of this Statute put us again into the true Proteſtant dreſs? does it take away the <hi>Conge Deſlires,</hi> and Elections thereupon, which 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. ſays, <hi>are in very deed</hi> no Elections, <hi>but</hi> (meer) <hi>Colours,</hi> Shadows, <hi>and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of Elections, ſerving nevertheleſs</hi> to no Purpoſe, <hi>and ſeeming alſo</hi> Derogatory <hi>and Prejudicial to the</hi> Kings Prerogative <hi>Royal,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Is the Kings Supremacy and Authority Eccleſiaſtical beſt <hi>aſſerted and avowed by his Name, Stile, and Armes, in all Writs, Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal or Judicial, in Eccleſiaſtical-Courts, as well as they are in Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral-Courts?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then why ſhould not Prelats and their Eccleſiaſtical Courts, <hi>conform</hi> themſelves, and be as tender of the Kings Prerogative, <hi>Supremacy</hi> and Authority in <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> as well as <hi>Temporal Cauſes</hi> and Courts, if they have not ſome <hi>Secret Reſerve</hi> in the hollow of their Breaſts? why ſhould they not be <hi>for the King</hi> as well <hi>in things that thwart</hi> as well as in <hi>things that make</hi> for their Intereſt, if they be <hi>ſo Loyal</hi> in things that <hi>ſerve their own turnes,</hi> Intereſt, Power, <hi>Grandeur</hi> and <hi>Dominion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is it a Scandal?</hi> Remove it, lay it at the doors it properly belongs unto.</p>
               <p>If they be <hi>not Legally Conſtituted,</hi> what <hi>then?</hi> why, <hi>then let them be Legally Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted;</hi> and if there be the <hi>more Vacancyes,</hi> there will be the <hi>more firſt-fruits</hi> and <hi>Fees for Letters Patents;</hi> They <hi>may</hi> the better <hi>afford it,</hi> if they have had ſuch ſtately Revenues (<hi>ſo long</hi>) illegally; And what harm of all this?</p>
               <p>Oh! (ſay ſome) A <hi>very great harm,</hi> this would be a <hi>Confeſſion of Guilt,</hi> and a Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Sin,</hi> and errour; <hi>an old Sin,</hi> an old Errour:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What then?</hi> This is the <hi>first time that ever I heard</hi> that <hi>Confeſſion of Sin was a Crime;</hi> Oh, but it argues ſuch an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſsal Error?</hi> why, <hi>whoever ſaid the Prelats are inſallible</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:32950:12"/>
in Spirituals, much <hi>leſs Temporals?</hi> we read of <hi>great Miſchieſs</hi> that have enſhed by <hi>their buzzing at C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ong agoe, and <hi>buſying themſelves</hi> with Politicks, It had been much better <hi>for them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> for Princes too,</hi> that Biſhops had kept themſelves to their <hi>Bibles;</hi> And neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>World</hi> would have been ſo plagu'd with their <hi>Heats,</hi> which (like fire out of the Hearth,) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> has ſometimes <hi>Conſumed</hi> then <hi>Warmed;</hi> having done Miſchief unſpeakable, but what good? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> this (only) my own Obſervation, I learnt it from no worſe man than a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> nay an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I mean <hi>Matt. Parker</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> (in good Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> days,) who in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Intitled <hi>Autiquitates Britannicae,</hi> (ſpeaking of the times of K. R. 1 and the Pranks of <hi>Hubere</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi>) has theſe words—Neque enim ſi verum Judicarc Volumus, in Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica Chriſtiana quicquam ſani, atque Integri Saculum illud tulit. Fictaque et Adusnbrata Religionis ſpecie Propoſita, totus Clerus in Sceleribus Muneribus, honoribus et Rapinis, Neglecto penitus Verbo, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pune Volutabat, Hujus mali Origo ab hoc Proſluxit, quod contra Orthodoxorum Patrum Decreta, Clerus Nimium Mundanis ſe Negotiis Immiſcuit. Nor was there, if we will Judge aright, in that Age anything left ſound, or as it ought to be, in the Chriſtian Common-wealth, for the whole Clergy under a feigned and outſide form of Religion, did with Impunity Wallow (like Swine) in Wickedneſs, Briberies, Honours and R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pines, altogether neglecting the Word of God. The Original of all which Miſchiefs was this, becauſs the Clergy, contrary to the Decrees of the Orthodox Fathers, would needs be thruſting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into, and intermedling with Worldly Affairs;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then he goes on to ſhew a fearful Example of Gods Vengeance upon one of them who had Clam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bered up to a very high Office in the State, and cloſeth that Relation thus—<hi>Cujus Generis Exempla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>id circo proferenda ſunt ut deterreatur a Vectigalibus Regiis, et Civilibus, publiciſque Occupationibus Clerus, et Evangelio Propagando precipue ſtudent a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Incumbat. Examples of this kind ought to be Recorded that the Clergy may be deterred from hankering after</hi> Court-Preſerments, <hi>and buſling in Civil and publick Offices, and mainly Study and devote themſelves intirely to the Propagation of the</hi> Goſpel.</p>
               <p>You are in the Right, Reverend! much in the Right—</p>
               <p>They <hi>are Spiritual men, or ſhould be;</hi> they are <hi>Divines,</hi> or <hi>ſhould be; they are</hi> (like a Fiſh out of the Water) <hi>out of their Element</hi> when they meddle with <hi>Politicks,</hi> out of their Sphere, <hi>Inconſiſtent with their Office,</hi> and perhaps their <hi>Education, nor has God bleſt them</hi> in ſuch Undertakings; <hi>Away with them to their Bibles,</hi> and Common-Prayer-Book, <hi>Thoſe are ſitter and more becoming</hi> Tools, then <hi>Writs,</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piaſſes, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ibels,</hi> Declarations, <hi>Informations,</hi> Citations, <hi>Vexations,</hi> and <hi>Promotions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was <hi>Auguſtine</hi> the Monk (that <hi>first</hi> and <hi>worſt</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi>) that <hi>first brought the Plague into England from Rome;</hi> The Plague-Eccleſiaſtical of <hi>Avarice,:</hi> Pride, <hi>Dominion,</hi> pomp and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Prelacy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If ever <hi>Anti-Chriſt</hi> appear'd in a <hi>Single Perſon,</hi> none could ever <hi>ſhow a better Title</hi> to him then this <hi>proud</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Parker</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> 
                     <hi>Britan</hi> p. 47.</note> 
                  <hi>Monk,</hi> Nor that ever did <hi>defile</hi> the Church of <hi>England</hi> with more <hi>Romiſh Filth</hi> and Rubbiſh, then he; <hi>would it were clean ſwept,</hi> if any Noyſome Corruptions which he brought over with him be not taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; and how <hi>beautifully</hi> it looks then? But the <hi>great Infection of his Plagues had not ſpread,</hi> but that he had ſuch <hi>an Influence</hi> upon King <hi>Eichelbert</hi> and his <hi>Parliament. Anno</hi> 601.<note place="margin">13. <hi>E.</hi> 1. 1. 18 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>He <hi>firſt</hi> got the Conuſans of <hi>Tythes</hi> into his <hi>Eccleſiaſtical-Courts,</hi> as appears by the Statutes 13. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. 1. &amp; 18. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. 7. <hi>at the Requeſt of the Prelats</hi> (ſays the Statute) And that <hi>it uſe to be otherwiſe</hi> before, <hi>as the firſt words of the ſaid Statute</hi> ſpecifyes; and <hi>Inter leges Edw. Regis</hi> cap. 8. fol. 128. which ſpeaks of Tythes, It is ſaid <hi>Hec Predicavit Auguſtinus et Conceſſa ſunt Rege, Baronibus et Popule,</hi> &amp;c. The King, Lords and Commons gave the Eccleſiaſtical men the <hi>Conuſans of Tythes</hi> upon <hi>Auguſtin's preacb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bract. lib. 5. fol. 401.</note> 
                  <hi>to</hi> them to that Purpoſe. For till the Statute of <hi>Circumſpecte agatis,</hi> no Perſon could demand Tythes in Court Chriſtian. <hi>Decimae ſunt Spiritualitats Annexa,</hi> ſays <hi>Braction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They got the <hi>probate of Wills,</hi> and the granting Commiſſions of <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> by Statute, nay, they<note place="margin">Linwood <hi>Tit. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuet.</hi> verb. nullus. Lin. de fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet. lib. 7.</note> could <hi>not make a Will</hi> (by the Common Law) of their own Goods and Chattels, <hi>much leſs could they diſpoſe of other mens Goods;</hi> ſo <hi>Linwood</hi> confeſſes too (who wrote in the Raign of H. 6. <hi>Beneficia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Teſtari de Communi Jure</hi> (ſed de Conſuctudine) <hi>in Anglia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Linwood</hi> Confeſſes the ſame concerning <hi>probates of Wills,</hi> they got them granted to them.</p>
               <p>I name theſe things <hi>before I come</hi> for ever to overthrow this <hi>Laſt Thumping Objection,</hi> to let the Reader know that if it were not for <hi>probate of Wills, Tythes,</hi> and <hi>Adminiſtrations,</hi> (which by their horrible Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions and Extortions they have moſt <hi>Injuriouſly Adminiſtred,</hi> if not <hi>forfeited</hi>) there needs not any Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, no not <hi>this 1 Edw. 6. 2. to correct the Eccleſtaſtical Courts; and Eccleſiaſtical Fellows,</hi> for (ſome think) they muſt (then) either <hi>ſtarve,</hi> or <hi>begg,</hi> or take a <hi>better Trade.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore though the Statute of 1 <hi>Edw. 6. 2. ſhould prove to be in force, what then?</hi> Why <hi>then they would keep no Courts at all,</hi> rather then keep them in the <hi>Kings Name,</hi> and not their own?</p>
               <p>And what then? <hi>where's the Inconvenience,</hi> if the Kings Temporal-Courts again get the <hi>Conuſans</hi> of <hi>Tythes,</hi> Probate of <hi>Wills, Adminiſtrations,</hi> &amp;c. (the great <hi>Buſineſs</hi> (beſides vexing Souls and <hi>Church-War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens,</hi> and poor <hi>Parſons,</hi> and <hi>the Money Buſineſs</hi>) all which Vexations may well be ſpared) And then the <hi>Saddle will</hi> but be <hi>ſet</hi> again upon <hi>the right Horſe,</hi> where it was <hi>handſomely ſet,</hi> Till the <hi>Government</hi> was <hi>Prieſt-ridden by Auguſtine</hi> that Covetous <hi>Supercilious</hi> and <hi>inſolent Monk.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Object. <hi>Ay, but will ſome ſay, Cognizance of Tyths, Fornication, Adultery, Defamation.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>are pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spiritual things, and more concern the Soul.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hobarts</hi> Caſes. Next to <hi>Swan</hi> and <hi>Hollams</hi> Caſe.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But I ſay it is falſe; Tythes, Fornication, Defamation, do <hi>no more</hi> concern the Soul, then do other Injuries, and Sins, Murder, Felony, or Treaſon; no, <hi>nor ſo much.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay, Even as to Baſtardy, in an action upon the Caſe, for calling one Baſtard, if the Deſendant Juſtify, It ſhall be tryed <hi>per Pais,</hi> and not by the Certificate of the Ordinary.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:32950:13"/>
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <p>WEll (<hi>but will ſome ſay</hi>) you promiſt, in <hi>this Treatiſe</hi> before, that the firſt Branch of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of 1. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. concerning the <hi>Biſhop-making,</hi> might be ſav'd by 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. reviving the 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. 20.</p>
               <p>And then if we can <hi>but keep our Biſhops,</hi> and prove them to be <hi>Legal,</hi> they'l diſpence (no doubt) at length with the <hi>old Romiſh way of Summons in their own name</hi> (as did the Biſhops in the Reign of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. for moſt of them were <hi>Popiſh Biſhops</hi> in <hi>Hen.</hi> 8 Reign: <hi>Proteſtant Biſhops</hi> in <hi>Edw. 6. Reign;</hi> And again <hi>Popiſh-Biſhops</hi> in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days; And if they conform ſo far to the Statute of 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. as to <hi>vouchſafe to uſe the Kings Name,</hi> Stile and Seals in their Eccleſiaſtical-Courts, <hi>you promis'd</hi> that the <hi>Firſt Branch</hi> of 1 <hi>Edw. 6. 2. was vacated by</hi> 1. Eliz. 1. <hi>And they (conſequently) Legal Biſhops.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, that I <hi>never promiſt</hi> any ſuch thing in my life, though <hi>the eſteem</hi> I have for Prelates, <hi>together with</hi> my natural <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ropenſity to Lordlineſs,</hi> Ay, and my own <hi>Intereſt too,</hi> (being a Judge of an Eccleſiaſtical-Court, and ſending Proceſſes Eccleſiaſtical (all) in <hi>my own name</hi> hitherto (though if God and the King do but forgive my Sins paſt, herein, I will never do ſo any more; <hi>It is Impriſonmen tdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> the Kings Pleaſure, I confeſs, and to be <hi>in miſerecordia Regis</hi> for what all of us have done) <hi>might be perſwaſive motives</hi> thereunto.</p>
               <p>But, alas! <hi>I can do no more (than I can)</hi> for our Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, <hi>I muſt not dare</hi> (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever others do) to <hi>Impeach the validity of a Statute,</hi> ſeeming ſo long injur'd and looking ſo evidently in force, for fear of <hi>After-Claps.</hi> I ſaid, <hi>indeed,</hi> that if <hi>Oracle Coke</hi> did not miſtake <hi>himſelf and the Law,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke in S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at. 32. H. 8. cap. 38. <hi>p. 686,</hi> 2 d. Inst it.</note> The Biſhops and Arch-biſhops were <hi>Legally made</hi> after the old Faſhion of <hi>Conge Deſlire</hi> and <hi>Elections,</hi> (as in 25. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 20. Revived by 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1.)</p>
               <p>And <hi>he</hi> (alſo) ſays that if they were made according to the Act of 1. <hi>Edw. 6. they were unlawful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, <hi>I never ſaid any ſuch thing,</hi> whatever I might wiſh or think: But <hi>Quere,</hi> whether the 8. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. does not do us a Courteſy <hi>iſ the King pleaſe;</hi> yet the 1 <hi>Edw. 6. revived after 8. Eliz. 1. Quere,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it do not vacate it, as to Elections, or wherein it is contrary to it? Alſo 14. <hi>Car.</hi> 2. 14, conſcrate us.</p>
               <p>Nay, The Learned <hi>Coke</hi> ſeems to give an <hi>impregnable reaſon</hi> for that opinion of his; namely that <hi>all after and ſubſequent Statutes</hi> do vacate and <hi>make null</hi> and void <hi>all precedent Statutes</hi> that are <hi>contrary to them.</hi> And though the 25. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 20. be a <hi>precedent Statute to 1 Edw.</hi> 6. 2, and conſequently was by the ſame defeat ed yet 1. <hi>M <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 2. Repealing the 1. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. and 1, <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. reviving 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8, 20. The Life of 25. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 20. Shall bear date <hi>onely from the Date of its Reviver, (1 Eliz.</hi> 1.) which gave <hi>it its</hi> life and vigour, <hi>onely by that Second Birth:</hi> and conſequently is a Junior Statute, and takes place, of 1. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. otherwiſe the <hi>effect</hi> would <hi>be ſenior to its cauſe,</hi> but <hi>cauſe eſt prior cauſato;</hi> the Son can no more poſſibly be Elder than the Father, then 25. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 2. can be Elder than 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. which <hi>alone, gives it life,</hi> and is the <hi>cauſe of its being aad motion:</hi> Therefore 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. reviving 25. <hi>H,</hi> 8. makes 25. <hi>H. 8. 20. an After-Act to 1, Edw.</hi> 6. 2. And <hi>nulls</hi> it ſo far as it is <hi>contrary</hi> to it; This is the Learned <hi>Coke</hi>'s reaſoning; aud it is pretty well.</p>
               <p>But if the <hi>Oracle had not warpt</hi> ſometimes (as that at <hi>Delos by Demoſtehenes</hi> is ſaid to <hi>Phillipi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> through the underhand-dealing with the Prieſts) ſo wiſe a man could <hi>not ſo Inconſiderately</hi> have over-ſhot himſelf.</p>
               <p>For he needs <hi>no other</hi> Argument than <hi>his own</hi> to confound his ſaid opinion; he <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abs himſelf with his own Keen Weapon;</hi> which otherwiſe is <hi>irreſiſtable;</hi> through raſhneſs, <hi>Precipitancy,</hi> haſte <hi>prejudice,</hi> or I <hi>know what.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For it is <hi>irreſiſtably true,</hi> that 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. reviving 25. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 20. makes it a <hi>Junior-Act,</hi> and conſequently <hi>to take place</hi> (contrary to the Laws as aforeſaid of Heraldry) <hi>of its ſenior, 1 Edw.</hi> 6. 2.</p>
               <p>Even as, in a <hi>Feoffment</hi> made of Land holden in chief <hi>to the uſe of</hi> ſuch Perſon or Eſtate as the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hobart's <hi>Caſes</hi> Shef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field <hi>verſ,</hi> Ratcliff.</note> ſhall give or diſpoſe <hi>in his Will.</hi> Here the uſes ſhall not <hi>opperate by way of Feoffment,</hi> but onely as a <hi>Teſtamentary Device;</hi> which cannot <hi>bear Date nor Life from the Feoffment,</hi> but from <hi>the Will (poſt obi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Teſtatoris, nam viventis non eſt Teſtamentum</hi>) And yet the <hi>Feoffmene is good</hi> (but onely in <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brio,</hi> and without Life or motion) <hi>till the Will operate and give it life</hi>) And therefore in conſtruction of Law (notwithſtanding the <hi>Feoffment,</hi> which the <hi>Donor made in his life time, yet</hi>) he ſhall <hi>dye ſeized,</hi> and his Wife ſhall have <hi>Dower;</hi> becauſe the <hi>Feoffment</hi> (notwithſtanding <hi>its Date and delivery in the life</hi> of the Donor, ſhall be motion-leſs and <hi>life-leſs,</hi> till <hi>The Will</hi> gives it life and <hi>vigour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So alſo, though it be ſaid and <hi>truly too</hi>) That the <hi>Firſt-Feoffment</hi> in Law defeats the <hi>ſecond,</hi> and all <hi>After Feoffments;</hi> yet, if a man (ſeized in demeſue as of Fee) make Feoffment, as aforeſaid, to ſuch Perſon and Eſtate as ſhall be given and declared <hi>in his laſt Will</hi> and Teſtament and then afterwards make a <hi>Second Feoffment</hi> to <hi>A. B.</hi> and his Heirs; and then make his Will and dye, giving the ſame to <hi>C. D.</hi> Here <hi>C. D.</hi> that had the <hi>Second Feoffment</hi> ſhall have the Land; Becauſe, in Intendment of Law, The <hi>Second</hi> Feoffment is the <hi>First Feoffment</hi> that has life and motion, whatever be the Date thereof. But (my Maſters) <hi>Coke</hi> alſo ſays in the ſame Page, (<hi>and ſays true</hi>) that by <hi>Repealing a Repeal, the firſt Act is revived;</hi> The Truth whereof he undoabtedly confirms <hi>in the next foregoing Page</hi> p. 687. And this Stabbs and confounds his own opinion:</p>
               <p>For 1. <hi>Jacobi</hi> reviving 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. the life and date of 1. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. ſhall be accounted <hi>onely from the Date of 1. Jacobi</hi> the author of <hi>its Being, and the Father that gave it life and motion,</hi> knocking the <hi>Shackles off,</hi> wherewith Queen <hi>Mary had bound it</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and conſequently 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. being as young, freſh and youthful as <hi>Primo Jacobi,</hi> It ſhall vacate 1. <hi>Eliz. 1. 1. Mar.</hi> 1. and 2. <hi>Phil. Mar. 8. 25. H.</hi> 8. 20. And
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:32950:13"/>
all other Statutes <hi>made before I Jacobi, if they be contrary to it</hi> I wonder what all my <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>retl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Prelate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in <hi>England</hi> can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry in anſwer to this: For the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Jacobi</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uſt <hi>be repealed</hi> before the 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. (which <hi>take its life</hi> and <hi>vigour</hi> from <hi>Primo Jacobi</hi>) can be vacated.</p>
               <p>And if the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> had ſuffered himſelf to <hi>weigh</hi> this Argument <hi>by bit own Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ales,</hi> he would not have buſyed himſelf with the three fold Cord, (he talkes of) which is ſo <hi>eaſily broken,</hi> by the ſtrength of his own. Max<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes of Law; <hi>Sie ſum Facili rumpitnr triple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Faſciculus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For 25. <hi>H. 8. 20. is yet in force,</hi> but that the 1 <hi>Edw. 6. 2. made it null and void</hi> by eſtabliſhing <hi>a Junior and Freſher Conſtitution</hi> in the Room of <hi>that old Frame</hi> by <hi>Conge D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſlie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and Elections thereon, which 1 <hi>Edw. 6. 2. calls, Pretences,</hi> Colours and <hi>Shadows onely;</hi> and derogatory and <hi>Prejudicial to the Kings</hi> Prerogative-Royal.</p>
               <p>Which <hi>Prerogative-Royal</hi> (by clearing up the the vigour of this Statute that has long <hi>lain clouded and obſcured by ſtrange Arts</hi>) If I have <hi>ſurely vindicated,</hi> I hope no man will deny but I have <hi>deſerved well of my King and Countrey.</hi> And upon the whole, <hi>if Curſt Cows happen tohave ſhort Horns, what Harm? Where's the Scandal?</hi> or Inconvenience.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <p>Obj. <hi>OH! But ſtill (ſay ſome) It muſt not be admitted that the</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Edw. 6. 2. <hi>be in fore: Why? Becauſe the Judges have been of</hi> another opinion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, it does nor appear that ever they <hi>judicially declared themſelves</hi> to be of another opinion; ſome Judges have given their opinion, againſt it, extrajudicially; and ſo alſo ſome Judges (ten of the twelve) gave their opinions for the <hi>Legallity of Ship-money</hi> to King <hi>Charles</hi> 1. And the <hi>ſame King in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> condemned the <hi>ſaid opinion by Statute,</hi> as contrary <hi>to Magna C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arta,</hi> The Petition of Right, and many other good Laws; Judges <hi>have been frail</hi> to their Ruine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If Judges</hi> therefore will <hi>warp</hi> and give opinions againſt <hi>known Statutes,</hi> againſt their Oaths, <hi>their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, thereby breaking their own</hi> (as they have been ſaid to break) <hi>the Kings Oath.</hi> They are the <hi>vileſt of men,</hi> and do merit the worſt of Puniſhments.</p>
               <p>But, <hi>on the contrary,</hi> This is no, novel opinion; The choice Lawyers of this Land have <hi>declared them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> that this <hi>Royal Statute is in force,</hi> and not onely ſo, but that there <hi>is all the reaſon in the World that it ſhould be in force,</hi> and that in <hi>acknowledgment of the Kings Supremacy</hi> in all cauſes and over all <hi>Perſons, as well Eccleſiaſtical as Civil;</hi> There is all the reaſon in the World that <hi>Writs</hi> and <hi>Proceſſes</hi> ſhould run in the <hi>Kings Name</hi> in <hi>Eccleſiaſtical-Courts, if they be (indeed) his Courts,</hi> as are the <hi>Temporal-Courts,</hi> and kept in <hi>his name;</hi> and not in the name of a Commiſſary, Official, or I know not who; If (I ſay) they be the Kings-Courts, and he the Supream Head Eccleſiaſtical, however the Pope has formerly uſurp't.</p>
               <p>What a <hi>fine thing it is</hi> to have the Kings Subjects <hi>run and ride</hi> forty or fifty miles from their <hi>Houſes,</hi> their <hi>Trades</hi> and their <hi>Families,</hi> upon the Summons of a <hi>Commiſſary,</hi> in <hi>his own name,</hi> which is none of the beſt names neither, (ſometimes) however ſome names (abſtracted from the quality of ſome that may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to wear them) may by accident become Scandalous and <hi>Odious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ravilliack</hi> Murther'd His Majeſties great Grandfather <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. the <hi>French</hi>-King, And in <hi>deteſtation</hi> or that <hi>villanous,</hi> treacherous, <hi>King-killing Fact,</hi> the <hi>Loyalty,</hi> Wiſdom, <hi>Justice and Piety of France,</hi> enacted that <hi>the Houſe</hi> wherein the Villian <hi>was born</hi> ſhould be made a <hi>Dunghil,</hi> never to be rebuilt, but (as <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ocurſed ground) layd waſte;</hi> his Father and Mother for ever baniſht, <hi>and all of the name of Ravilliack</hi> to change that <hi>King-killing</hi> name for ſome other, and a better: <hi>So ſacred</hi> are the <hi>perſons of Kings,</hi> that they are not to be <hi>toucht in bloody earneſt, without an eternal ſtigmatize and brand</hi> ſet upon the Prophane A tempt to all <hi>Poſterity;</hi> Nay, <hi>Jolm Scotus loſt himſelf</hi> becauſe <hi>he would not looſe his Jest,</hi> when <hi>the French King</hi> ſitting on the <hi>one ſide of the Table;</hi> and <hi>Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Scotus on the other</hi>) the King askt him merrily what was the difference <hi>between a Scot and a So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>? Scotus bluntly anſwered,</hi> The Table. If it be dangerous <hi>to play at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>yles</hi> with Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, 'tis eternally mortal to play at Sharp's. And therefore I wiſh with all my heart too, that His Majeſties Royal Anceſtor the ſtout King <hi>Richard the ſecond,</hi> had not been <hi>baſely,</hi> cowardly, <hi>and treacherouſly Murther'd with a</hi> Back-ſtroke <hi>by an Exton;</hi> And if it had been in <hi>France,</hi> I doubt not but the <hi>Loyalty, Piety and Prudence</hi> of the <hi>French-men</hi> would have <hi>exterminated</hi> (not all the men that were called <hi>Exton</hi>) But in horrour and <hi>detestation of King-killing</hi> namely they would have ſo <hi>abbominated</hi> that <hi>King-killing name</hi> (as they did <hi>Rabilliacks</hi>) that they would have <hi>oblitterated</hi> it to all <hi>Poſterity,</hi> and have made all the <hi>Exton<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in the Kingdom. change that <hi>King-killing Name</hi> for a better; that the <hi>loathed-name</hi> might (like a hateful S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uff) be put out and extinct to all Poſterity:</p>
               <p>But, if in contempt <hi>of that Royal Statute,</hi> of 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. and in defyance <hi>of the reaſon of that Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute,</hi> The Kings Subjects ſhould happen to be cited in any ſuch untoward <hi>King-killing name,</hi> and then be proſecuted, till they have <hi>ſatisfied and paid,</hi> the onſequence cannot but be the more <hi>ungrateful,</hi> for that (<hi>once deſervedly odious</hi>) name, eſpecially ſince the 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2 commands all <hi>Proceſſes Eccleſiaſtical</hi> to be (all the reaſon in the World) <hi>in the Kinge name, the Eccleſiaſtical-Head</hi> as well as the <hi>Temporal-Head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if the Prelates, and Eccleſiaſtical-men ſhould not <hi>as induſtriouſly endeavour all manner of Legal wayes to</hi> advance and <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>w the Kings Prerogative Royal as</hi> much as Lay-men, then they are very ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and <hi>ill deſerve the Bounty</hi> ſo Gracious a King has confer'd ſo liberally <hi>upon them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If this Statute has been long (I know not <hi>by what Arts,</hi> and yet <hi>I do tooknow in part why it has be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n huſht aſleep,</hi> and <hi>Scandal</hi> and Inconveniences may <hi>enſue,</hi> by its <hi>awakened vertue</hi> and force; the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re ſhame for them that have been the <hi>true cauſes and Authors of ſo grand a Scandal</hi> and Inconveniences: lay the Scandal at the right door; Scandals <hi>and Offences will co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> (ſays our Saviour) <hi>but wo be to them by whom they come.</hi> Now is there any Scandal or <hi>Inconveniences ſo great</hi> but the King and Parliament <hi>can readily avoid them, or compound them; and remedy them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <p>YEt can I not deny but that all Parliaments (ſince the Reformation) have been ſo <hi>Jealous of the Exor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itant Power</hi> of Church-men (finding by woful Experience in the late High-Commiſſion-Court granted by 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. what <hi>Ruefull Work was made</hi>) that they fetcht it down (with as much Celerity as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:32950:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
they could) and by the ſame Statute (that repealed it) have <hi>branded</hi> it to Poſterity; ſaving 17 <hi>Car. 1. 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ded to the great wrong</hi> (mark that) and <hi>Oppreſſion of the Kings Subjects</hi> &amp;c. And though ſome men never had greater Hopes of Regaining that unhappy Power or <hi>ſome-what alike it,</hi> then <hi>by the long Parliament</hi> (faiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> called) <hi>The Pentioner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Parliament</hi> (for though there might be <hi>Judaſſes</hi> amongſt them, yet as to the Major part of them never were there <hi>Wiſer nor Truer</hi> Engliſh-men) All that they could gain (by 13 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. 12.) was onely to place their Eccleſiaſtical Courts in <hi>Statu quo,</hi> juſt as they were <hi>in</hi> 1639. without the Addition of any <hi>new power</hi> or any <hi>new Confirmation</hi> of them, but left their founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>as Tottering as they found it,</hi> before the troubles commen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'t.</p>
               <p>And truly they were, (with the fruſtration) ſo dejected, that <hi>no People</hi> were <hi>more ſcorned</hi> and neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and Indicted for their <hi>Extortions</hi> and Oppreſſions; And yet, for many years, the Regiſters <hi>with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Cypher at his Elbow or over his head</hi> called <hi>a Surrogate,</hi> ſcrap't up a <hi>poor</hi> untoward <hi>living</hi> ſometimes, catching <hi>what they could,</hi> with as <hi>Little Noiſe</hi> as they could:</p>
               <p>But, now, with <hi>Contrary Politicks</hi> (how wiſely? let them look to it) they <hi>have grown ſo</hi> buſy with the <hi>Kings Subjects, torturing their Souls,</hi> Purſes, Liberties, and Eſtates, by their Citations in their <hi>own names,</hi> Certificavits, and <hi>Significavits,</hi> in their own Names, which ought (by the 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2.) to have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>the Seal and in the Name of the Kings-Majeſty,</hi> and then <hi>upon ſuch Significavits</hi> (not ſealed with the Kings Seal) have got the Writ <hi>de Excommunicato Capiendo,</hi> and then what <hi>Gratefull Works</hi> they made for the <hi>Jaylors,</hi> and Bum-bayliffes, is ſo <hi>notorious,</hi> that no man can wonder that men are deſervedly <hi>row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed to Examine</hi> their Frame and <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> and pry whether <hi>all be right within,</hi> when ſuch ghaſtly ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines appear <hi>abroad,</hi> that who can Imagine that the good God ever gave them Commiſſion to make havock of mens Souls, Liberties, and Eſtates; <hi>The Keys</hi> of Excommunication ſeldom opening <hi>any thing ſo ſoon</hi> as a <hi>Jayl-Door, whence</hi> by the other <hi>Croſs-Key</hi> of Abſolution they were never delivered, without <hi>Money,</hi> money.</p>
               <p>Nor is it for Church-men to Vapour long with <hi>Goſpel-Ordinances,</hi> when inſtead of uſing them for <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual-ends,</hi> they abuſe them to <hi>vile,</hi> baſe, and <hi>Sordid Deſigns,</hi> to fill their Pockets, and wreak their <hi>Malice.</hi> This Rapine in the Sons of <hi>Eli</hi> prov'd the <hi>Ruine of his houſe,</hi> for thoſe alone that Honour God <hi>he will Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, but thoſe that deſpiſe, him ſhall be lightly eſteemed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And how truly this threathing has been <hi>verifyed upon the Eccleſiaſticals,</hi> let any man ſpeak his Conſcience, &amp; ſay, <hi>whether any ſort of People</hi> in the Kingdom have been ſo contemned and <hi>lightly eſteemed as they.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not, but that, <hi>Contempt may happen to good men,</hi> and the Scorner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be in the fault; but when the <hi>light Eſteem</hi> is grounded upon the <hi>Avarice, Pride, Idleneſs, Extortion, Malice, and Oppreſſion</hi> of Church-men, it looks certainly like <hi>Digi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us Dei,</hi> the juſt Judgment of Almighty God.</p>
               <p>But if both King and ſome Houſes of Parliament (once) did not like the Act for Uniformity, what <hi>Wiſdom</hi> is it for men to be <hi>ſo fierce for the Letter</hi> of the Law? which yet I wiſh all men did obey, (as well as my ſelf) <hi>whilſt it is a Law;</hi> yet is it pleaſing either to God or man, to <hi>knock mens brains out</hi> becauſe they are blind or <hi>pur-blind,</hi> and will <hi>not go to Heaven</hi> along with us in <hi>our way?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>thouſand wayes</hi> there are to Church and to <hi>Heaven,</hi> as there are a Thouſand lines from the <hi>Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> to the <hi>Centre;</hi> and a thouſand wayes to <hi>London:</hi> I wiſh all men went <hi>my way,</hi> becauſe it is the <hi>neareſt Way I know,</hi> but if they will not, let them go <hi>their own,</hi> in Gods Name, way ſhould we quarrel about the matter? If God and Nature would have had us <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niform,</hi> We had all been <hi>made alike,</hi> of one Stature, Size, and Complexion; but God and Nature <hi>ſeems ſo to delight in Variety,</hi> that there are ſcarcely any two things in the World Uniform: Nay, we Prelats our ſelves are <hi>neither <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niform amongſt our ſelves, nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form according to the Act,</hi> as I have ſufficiently prov'd in—<hi>The Black Non-con-formſts;</hi> ſetting up and Obſerving Ceremonies that <hi>God never made,</hi> nor (yet) our ſo <hi>Celebrated Act for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity:</hi> where's the Juſtice and Honeſty to <hi>puniſh one Non-Con-Formiſt,</hi> and let another <hi>Eſcape Scot-free?</hi> One Prelate ſets Candles upon the Altar, another ſets none; one Prelate <hi>bowes</hi> to the very ground <hi>where</hi> and <hi>when</hi> another, <hi>ſtands</hi> up, <hi>as right as a dart;</hi> one Church Celebrates with all ſorts of Muſick, another with none at all. One Church <hi>Sings their Prayers,</hi> another <hi>reads them;</hi> one reads <hi>the Communion</hi> Service in the <hi>Desk,</hi> another at <hi>the Altar;</hi> one Prays <hi>before Sermon,</hi> another only <hi>bids men pray;</hi> one <hi>Reads his own Notes,</hi> another reads <hi>a Homely,</hi> another has it <hi>Memorit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r;</hi> one wears <hi>a Surplice</hi> only, another a <hi>Surplice and Hood,</hi> another <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of them; and 40 more ſuch Inſtances. Now when <hi>theſe men diſſent ſo from the Act of</hi> Uniformity, and are <hi>Diſſenters alſo one from another,</hi> Are ye not Partial in your ſelves to <hi>prefer one Diſſenter,</hi> and <hi>Jayl the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi> Wo be to them that keep <hi>falſe Meaſures and Scales,</hi> and Ballancies of <hi>deceitful weight,</hi> one to <hi>buy by,</hi> and another to <hi>ſell by.</hi> The Prelates indeed have <hi>gained the Aſcendant</hi> upon the Affections of the three <hi>laſt Kings</hi> (which no man envyes, if they make good uſe of it, and Legal uſe) Their Influence too has not <hi>boen confined to White-Hall,</hi> but has <hi>reach't Weſtminſter-Hall</hi> (I know it, <hi>God knows</hi>) but yet, their Influence ſeldom reach <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o effectually (<hi>Further Weſt</hi>) in the two Houſes, as to gain <hi>over much</hi> of them there, in my Remembrance, or if they did, <hi>Chronicles are ſilent therein.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How therefore they now (of late) or why <hi>In Nomine Domini,</hi> or with what Policy they grow ſo violent, I cannot <hi>Imagine;</hi> for if the 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. be in Force (of which to me there <hi>ſeems not the leaſt doubt</hi>) I think we are <hi>in a fine Pickle,</hi> lyable to every <hi>mans Action</hi> whom we have <hi>Illegally vext,</hi> and damnified, and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned,</hi> through our <hi>Significavits</hi> in our own Nemes; nay, indeed, as I ſaid, what <hi>Puniſhment can equal the Merit</hi> of ſuch <hi>Miſchiefs?</hi> ſuch Epidemical and <hi>national Mischiefs?</hi> Though I doubt not but this little react will ſo <hi>clip our nails,</hi> that we ſhall <hi>ſcarce venture</hi> to <hi>ſcratch terribly</hi> hereafter.</p>
               <p>And truly I think, and I <hi>would ſay it too</hi> (but that it is Immodeſty to <hi>commend my own Modeſty</hi>) that I have handled them <hi>here as Tenderly and Gingerly</hi> as if I had gone about <hi>to draw</hi> the great <hi>aking Tooth</hi> of the Nation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="errata">
               <head>ERRATA.</head>
               <p>PAge 1. line 27. for Summer Read Sumner. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. 8. for Spiritualia. R. ad Spiritualia. p. 3 L. 17. for judiciouſly R. ingenuouſly—p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. l. 51. for-By Partially, Timidity, R. They declare the Kings-Laws; by p. 4. L. 14. for Angeryr. R. Ayery. p. 4. l. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. for Emblemiſhments. R. Embelliſhment. With many other.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32950:14"/>
            <head>PART II. Query 21. <hi>Whether</hi> any of the Canon-Law <hi>or</hi> How much <hi>of the Canon-Law is</hi> in force <hi>at</hi> this <hi>day?</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>To which I anſwer <hi>briefly</hi> that it is undenyably true;</p>
               </argument>
               <p>1. THat <hi>All Laws of England</hi> muſt either be <hi>made</hi> or <hi>Confirmed</hi> by the <hi>Legiſlative-power; and if they be not ſo made</hi> (as are the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes) <hi>or Confirmed</hi> (as is <hi>part</hi> (and <hi>but part</hi>) of the <hi>Common-law</hi> and <hi>Canon-law</hi>) by Statutes <hi>made by the Legiſlative-power, they</hi> are <hi>not Laws of</hi> England, and then <hi>cannot</hi> oblige the Subjects to Obedience.</p>
               <p>For our King is our <hi>Liege</hi> (or <hi>Legal) Lord,</hi> and we are his <hi>liege</hi> (or <hi>Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> (that is) legal <hi>Subjects</hi>) becauſe the Laws <hi>direct his Precepts,</hi> and our <hi>Obedience</hi> and Duty.</p>
               <p>2. All the <hi>Canon-laws</hi> and Conſtitutions, whether Synodical or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial <hi>are now Statute-law</hi> (by 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. 19.) ſo that they <hi>be not contrary</hi> to the Laws of the Land.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hence it follows,</hi> that all <hi>Canons</hi> made ſince 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. 19. and <hi>not made nor Confirmed by Parliament</hi> are not by this rule <hi>the Laws</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently <hi>require not our Obedience</hi> thereunto for that reaſon, whatever other reaſon there may be.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Executive-power</hi> of the Laws is in the <hi>King alone,</hi> but it has been accounted <hi>Treaſon againſt the fundamental Laws of our Kingdom</hi> and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, to aſſert that the <hi>Legiſlative-power is in the King alone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it were, he <hi>needs no Parliaments</hi> when he has a mind to any Money, nor <hi>needs a Parliament to repeal a Statute,</hi> if he could do it <hi>without them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>his Will,</hi> Goodneſs, <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and Oath, and <hi>Declarations</hi> do promiſe us the <hi>continuance of his</hi> Rule and <hi>Reign according to Law:</hi> And when by the King's <hi>Declaration of Indulgence</hi> he <hi>ſuſpended the Statute,</hi> we were in a <hi>moſt</hi> uncertain <hi>Condition,</hi> not knowing <hi>what to truſt to,</hi> having (according to his Royal word from <hi>Breda) liberty of Conſcience</hi> (and by the Indulgence) one day, and <hi>loſt the next;</hi> when the Act took place again, I ſay again; Then,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In nomine Domini then,</hi> how come we <hi>Eccleſiaſticals</hi> to Command and exact of our Inferiours <hi>Canonical Obedience to Canons neither made nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed</hi> by the Legiſlative-power? <hi>but none were</hi> (ſince 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8.) ſo made nor confirmed. By what Law can we exact of the Clergy, then, an <hi>Oath of Canonical Obedience</hi> to thoſe Canons that are not <hi>Leges Angliae,</hi> the Laws of the Land? and command likewiſe and admoniſh the Layety to <hi>Subſcribe the three Canons</hi> (that vouches their Hierarchy and Dominion by Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, Deans, Arch-deacons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) to be <hi>conſonant to the Word of God,</hi> when the Word of God <hi>has not ſuch a Word in it,</hi> (as Archbiſhops, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons, Commiſſaries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) not a word on't; and this under pain of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:32950:15"/>
and <hi>a worſe turn</hi> (as ſome think) the Gaol; theſe are <hi>brave doings the while.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When poor Clergy-men muſt <hi>Swear Canonical Obedience,</hi> elſe we will not Inſtitute them to a Living, and then they muſt <hi>Starve and Dye;</hi> for <hi>Thraſh</hi> they may <hi>not, Farm</hi> and <hi>Trade</hi> they may <hi>not,</hi> being <hi>Spiritual-perſons,</hi> if they <hi>Begg</hi> they'l be <hi>Whipt,</hi> if they <hi>Steal</hi> they'l be <hi>Hang'd,</hi> (for all the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of their Clergy,) and if they take a <hi>blind Oath</hi> of Canonical Obedience, and yet do <hi>not know what is Canonical Obedience,</hi> they muſt be <hi>Forſworn;</hi> as much as when they Swear the <hi>Oath againſt Symony,</hi> and Obedience to the Canons in force, and yet exact Money for <hi>Baptizings,</hi> Burials, <hi>Marriages,</hi> &amp;c. all which are contrary to the Canons whereunto they Swear Obedience, (<hi>Poor-hearts!</hi>) but few of them <hi>(ſurely) know thoſe Canons,</hi> or <hi>know what they Swear to,</hi> for if they did, they <hi>durſt not (ſurely) break their Oaths every day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Canonica Obedientia</hi> (ſayes <hi>Linwood) eſt Obedientia ſecundum exigentiam Canonum;</hi> Canonical Obedience is Obedience according to the Canons, (meaning) the <hi>Canons in force.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe that are <hi>not made nor confirm'd by</hi> Act of Parliament are <hi>not Laws,</hi> nor <hi>are we Sworn to Obedience to them;</hi> but thoſe made before 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>we muſt obey,</hi> (if they be not contrary to the Laws of the Land,) or <hi>be For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſworn,</hi> let me tell you, (<hi>friends mine!</hi>)</p>
               <p>Now, it is not contrary to the Laws of the Land, though a Biſhop <hi>take no Money</hi> for Letters of Orders, Inſtitutions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or if <hi>Miniſters Marry,</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, or Bury People <hi>without exacting Money,</hi> but on the contrary <hi>very pleaſing to the Law,</hi> which has provided <hi>Glebes,</hi> Tythes and <hi>Offerings</hi> for the nonce to pay us <hi>once for all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh! <hi>What a Cage of unclean Birds are we,</hi> from top to bottom? <hi>unclean,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lindwood. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc. <hi>l. 5. Tit. 2.</hi> de Simonia.</note> 
                  <hi>unclean! Firmiter Inhibemus, ne cuiquam pro aliquâ pecuniâ denegetur, Sepultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, vel Baptiſmus, vel aliquod Sacramentum Eccleſiaſticum, vel etiam Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monium contrahendum Impediatur;</hi> we firmly enjoin, that neither Burial, Baptiſm, Matrimony, nor any Eccleſiaſtical holy Duty, or Sacrament, be denyed to any man, though he will not give a farthing for them.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Lyndwood</hi> ſayes, upon the Text and Gloſs, nothing ought to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded<note place="margin">Lynd. <hi>ibid.</hi> verb. ſepultura.</note> or required for Burial in holy ground, whether in the Church or Church-yard, neither for the Ground, nor for reading the Office of Buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, the Benefice being enjoyed therefore by the Incumbent; for the Tythe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleece is given to the Shepherd for his hire, in full. And, if the Prieſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to Baptize any Infant, or one of Age, except he give Money, the Sin be upon him, but the Party deſiring it, though he dye Unbaptized, ſhall<note place="margin">Lynd. <hi>ibid.</hi> verb. Baptiſmus.</note> have the benefit of the Baptiſm of the Spirit, though he want Water-bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm; <hi>Nullo modo deberet pro Baptiſmo pretium dare, ſed potius abſque Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Fluminis decedere; ſuppleretur enim ei ex Baptſmo Flaminis quod ex Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramento</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Concil. Pau. Anglicum, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no 1236. Tit. 4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>deeſſet;</hi> men ought rather to want Water-baptiſme than give ſo much as a penny for it, becauſe it is Symony (ſayes <hi>Lyndwood</hi>) both in the Buyer and in the Seller; how <hi>thriving a Trade</hi> does this Law ſpoyl? except men <hi>will perſiſt in Perjury,</hi> breaking their Oath of Canonical Obedience, in exacting Money for <hi>Baptſm, Burials,</hi> or <hi>Marriages,</hi> of which laſt, (Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony)<note place="margin">Lyndw. <hi>ibid.</hi> verb. impedia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical fellows drive a very ſubtle Trade; Oaths</hi> are <hi>but Oaths</hi> they think ſurely.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dare vel recipere aliquod temporale pro ſpirituali Symoniacum eſt; ſive detur pro Sacramento, ſive pro Officio, ſive pro Oratione, ſecundum quod ly pro notat Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precationem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lyndwood. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc. <hi>l. 5. Tit. 2. cap.</hi> Praeterea vena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatem. Verb. Triennalibus.</note>
               </p>
               <p>It is Symony either to give or receive any temporal Commodity for a ſpiritual commodity; whether for the Sacrament, or for the Office, or for the Prayers, by way of contract, bargain and ſale.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:32950:15"/>It is Symony to exact Money for Sins; <hi>nam Deus Omnipotens, cujus om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia ſunt, pretium quodlibet pro delicto non accipit;</hi> for Almighty God takes not any Money for Pardon of Sins; <hi>nec pecunia recipiatur a ſubditis pro Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine vel delicto notorio;</hi> let no man dare to receive Money of their Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours for Crimes or Offences, be they never ſo notorious.</p>
               <p>It is Symony for a Biſhop to take above Six pence for Ordination, (which<note place="margin">Conſtitut. extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va. Londini. Oct. <hi>10. Anno Dom. 1342.</hi> Joh. Stratford. Archi. Cant.</note> Six pence goes to the Secretary or Regiſter for Wax, Parchment,) or to take above Twelve pence for Inſtitution, Induction, Certificates and all; and againſt the Oath of Canonical Obedience; <hi>Lord forgive us,</hi> what will become of us?</p>
               <p>For, <hi>ſicut non decet Epiſcopum manûs Impoſitionem vendere, ita nec notari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, nec ministrum eorundem, nec calamum, nec ministrium venundare;</hi> ſayes the Canon, as a Biſhop ſhould not ſell Letters of Orders, ſo neither ſhould his Secretary, Regiſters, or Servants <hi>ſell Quills,</hi> or Parchments, <hi>Pens, Inke</hi> or Wax.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nam ordinarii ſuis tenentur miniſtris ſtipendia conſtituere, quibus debent me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rito contentari; pro ſigillatione literarum, aut mareſchallis pro Introitu, ſeu Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitoribus, Hoſtiariis, vel barbito uſeribus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>For the Ordinaries ought to pay their Servants their Wages to their content, and not make poor Prieſts (when they come to their Biſhop for Ordination, or to other Prelates, like my ſelf for Inſtitution, Collation, Induction,) <hi>pay the Porter</hi> to let them in, and <hi>pay the Porter</hi> before they get out; neither (alſo) to pay the Biſhops <hi>Grooms, Butlers, Barbers,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>It is againſt the Oath of Canonical Obedience to remove from a poor<note place="margin">Can. Concil. Nicen. general.</note> Vicaridge to a rich Rectory, or a poor Biſhoprick to a bigger and better, (that is) a richer. (God forgive us!)</p>
               <p>It is againſt the Canons in force, if Biſhops and Prieſts have not <hi>Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Crowns,</hi> as the Popiſh Biſhops and Prieſts have; for the Canons that enjoyn it are in <hi>force,</hi> becauſe <hi>not contrary to the Laws of the Land,</hi> though a Biſhop or Prieſt be ſhaved as bald as the back of my hand; nay, it is ſuſpenſion <hi>ab Officio</hi> for ſix Months to wear long Hair, or a long Beard, or<note place="margin">Concil. Londini in Eccleſ. Sanct. Pauli. <hi>Anno 1342.</hi> Conſtitut. Concil. Londin. pau-Anglicum. <hi>Ann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 1236. Titui. 13. &amp;</hi>
                  </note> Pendules at the Ears, or not having a Shaven crown, or Rings on their Fingers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and if they perſiſt in ſuch uncanonical Deportment, they ought to loſe their Benefices 'till they repent, and then not to be abſolv'd 'till they have given the <hi>ſixth part of the Profits</hi> of them to the Poor.</p>
               <p>It is againſt the Canons for a Prieſt to marry a Widdow, or being a Widdower to marry a ſecond Wife, and againſt the Law of God too, if <hi>bigamus</hi> ſound as much as the Husband of more than one Wife; and alſo the Wife of more than one Husband: And ſuch ought to be degraded and deprived by the Canon Law that have Married a Widdow, there are<note place="margin">Concil. Anglic. Lond. 52. Hen. 3. <hi>Anno 1268. Tit. 5.</hi> Conc. Pau. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glic. 1236 <hi>Tit.</hi> Coke in Articul. Cler. cap. 9.</note> Maids enow, what need have Prieſts to be <hi>bigamus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is againſt the Canons for <hi>one Prieſt</hi> to take <hi>another Prieſts Goods</hi> or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney from him, of which even our <hi>Statute-law</hi> is ſo tender, that it is <hi>not lawful for a Sheriff or Bayliff</hi> to take or <hi>Diſtrain a Clergy-man's Goods out</hi> of his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage-houſe for Debt, in <hi>other places</hi> he may, but not in the ancient Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Indowments.</p>
               <p>Thus careful has the Laws been, that <hi>Clergy-men ſhould not</hi> be (like <hi>Pikes</hi> and <hi>Sharkes</hi>) the <hi>greater ſwallowing up the leſſer Fry;</hi> little things would live, though they be not great, nor <hi>fat,</hi> nor overgrown, and as careful alſo to keep the Layity from their Covetous gripes, in not being forc't to <hi>pay twice,</hi> and beſides Tithes, to pay <hi>alſo for Marriages,</hi> Baptizings, Lectures, Buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, (<hi>a very ſubtle Trade</hi>) no more I hope (though) to be followed for the Oaths ſake, the Oaths againſt Symony, and the Oaths of Canonical Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; and I hope all Biſhops alſo will take warning and look after their Potters, Barbers, Secretaries, and <hi>Gehazies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:32950:16"/>If they do not, they ſhall hear further from me, <hi>I'le promiſe them;</hi> are not Laws and Oaths ſomething? Ha! <hi>let me hear no more on't,</hi> no, not at a Viſitation, I would wiſh them for their <hi>own ſakes,</hi> and for <hi>Conſcience-ſake,</hi> and for the <hi>ſake of the Oaths</hi> of Canonical Obedience, and <hi>that ſmall Oath</hi> againſt Symony, and alſo if they pleaſe (I'le adde) for <hi>their own Souls</hi> ſake, and for the <hi>Shame of the World</hi> and Speech of <hi>People; that are apt</hi> enough to make or find holes in a <hi>Canonical Coat;</hi> they ſhall not need to <hi>make any,</hi> I have ſhewn enow in all Conſcience; and the Miſchief is, <hi>'tis true too,</hi> no body can deny it; bleſſed be God that his Mercy is infinite, or elſe what <hi>would become of us Clergy-men</hi> above all others? whether poor Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy or rich Clergy; whether thoſe that are <hi>lyable</hi> to a Gaol, or thoſe that are above a Gaol, lyable to an Excommunication, or <hi>amici curiae,</hi> and <hi>above it;</hi> whether ſuch as may be <hi>Anathematiz'd,</hi> Gaol'd and Curſt; or ſuch as do Anathematize others; all of us have need to begg abſolution <hi>of God and the People,</hi> ſo much offended and abus'd by us, <hi>contrary to our Oaths,</hi> our Conſciences, and our <hi>own dear Canon-laws,</hi> with which <hi>we Benchers</hi> do ſo thunder upon the Laity, and the ſmall, poor, pitiful and <hi>inferiour Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy-men,</hi> Vicars, Curates, <hi>Journey-men,</hi> and <hi>Day-labourers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the World be ſuffer'd to go on <hi>at this rate,</hi> they'l not know how to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh and <hi>know the difference,</hi> betwixt a <hi>rich</hi> Prelate, and a <hi>Small-day-la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Journey-man;</hi> is it not a general <hi>Scandal. Magnat</hi>—? a very great Scandal certainly.—I wiſh with all my heart <hi>the Poll</hi> had gone on, (which the Biſhops ſet a foot—) that every Clergy-man ſhould certifie the <hi>Cons</hi> and the <hi>Non-cons</hi> in every Pariſh: The Non-cons are <hi>Shrubs</hi> and pitiful fellows, and <hi>but few</hi> to us; we think beſides, the Prelates ſay that they have the <hi>Gift of God by laying on of hands to Ordain,</hi> Inſtitute, <hi>&amp;c. be it ſo.</hi> And Miniſters pretend, that they (by <hi>Ordination</hi>) have got <hi>the Gift of God,</hi> the Gift of <hi>Praying,</hi> Preaching, <hi>Baptizing,</hi> and <hi>administring the other Sacrament,</hi> &amp;c. Be it ſo too.</p>
               <p>And both Prelates and Miniſters we <hi>(all) Swear</hi> and take the <hi>Oath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Symony,</hi> and Oath of Canonical Obedience.</p>
               <p>The merciful God forgive us all? what will become of us <hi>that ſhould be Guides?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis <hi>Symony</hi> to give Money for a Living; 'tis <hi>Smock-ſymony to truckle</hi> to a known Whore, <hi>pimping for her favour,</hi> to give a man a lift into the—I charge no man with theſe kinds of <hi>Symony.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the ſin of <hi>Simon Magus</hi> is to make a <hi>Money-buſineſs of the Gifts of God,</hi> in Letters <hi>of Orders, Inſtitutions, Prayers,</hi> Reading, <hi>Lecturing,</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Baptize my Child; <hi>quantum mihi dabitis?</hi> ſaith <hi>Judas,</hi> then what will you give me, ſayes <hi>the Symoniſt?</hi> Ordain me; <hi>yea,</hi> but pay my <hi>Secretary,</hi> my Regiſter, my <hi>Porter,</hi> and the <hi>Groom of my Chamber;</hi> give me my <hi>Letters of Orders again at a Viſitation,</hi> I have paid for them once, Mr. <hi>Simon, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum dabitis?</hi> pay the <hi>Secretary</hi> and take them.</p>
               <p>Give us a Sermon, <hi>Parſon; quantum dabitis?</hi> ſayes <hi>Simon,</hi> what will you give me and I'le be your <hi>Lecturer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Read Prayers for me, <hi>little Curate;</hi> (ſayes the <hi>Scarlet Doctor,) quantum dabis?</hi> ſayes <hi>Simon,</hi> what will you give me to do <hi>your Drudgery?</hi> come <hi>Doctor,</hi> you may <hi>afford it;</hi> for you are <hi>better paid for ſleeping than I for Praying,</hi> and would you have a man <hi>Pray for nothing,</hi> whilſt you get <hi>ſo much, for Praying but little or not at all! quantum dabis?</hi> ſhall I work and Pray by <hi>the day,</hi> by the week, or <hi>by the Year?</hi> yet we all Swear the Oath againſt <hi>Symony,</hi> God forgive us, <hi>What will become of us?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Church of <hi>England</hi> do <hi>we call our ſelves?</hi> if we that call our ſelves Church,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32950:16"/>
and yet <hi>Crack Oaths like Nuts,</hi> and are <hi>ſo wicked,</hi> ſurely then the <hi>Layity</hi> are <hi>ſad Souls.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIV.</head>
               <p>AND yet <hi>as wretched as we are,</hi> and at <hi>what looſe lock ſoever</hi> we Lye or Swear, <hi>hand over head,</hi> no Parliament (ſince 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8.) ever heeded <hi>our Canons</hi> ſo much as to <hi>reform them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. 19. ſeems to be deſign'd for a <hi>temporary Act</hi> only and a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bationer,</hi> to laſt <hi>only till 32 perſons</hi> had ſelected the choice Canons out of the great heap of <hi>Rubbiſh;</hi> but in ſuch a confuſed, <hi>fusty,</hi> frivolous and <hi>ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding Lump,</hi> the Commiſſioners were <hi>at a loſs</hi> where to make their choice, or elſe thought <hi>none of them worth chuſing,</hi> and ſo <hi>threw all aſide.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor has any <hi>Engliſh Parliament regarded our looſe condition,</hi> ſo much as to take the Canons into conſideration, containing <hi>ſuch a Gallowmawfrey.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet, <hi>we muſt Swear, and Swear Canonical Obedience,</hi> and never a man in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (ſcarcely <hi>can or dares</hi> affirm <hi>what Canons we Swear Obedience to;</hi> or <hi>which</hi> (alone) <hi>are in force:</hi> Oh feeble and <hi>frail condition of Church-men!</hi> the poor Church-men! <hi>for the rich there's no Praying for them,</hi> I mean, No <hi>need of Praying for them but by the Common-prayer-book;</hi> you may truſt them, <hi>they'l ſhift well enough</hi> in this World, I'le warrant you, <hi>let them alone to ſecure</hi> themſelves, and <hi>enrich themſelves too;</hi> yet I cannot deny but <hi>Poverty</hi> and <hi>Self-denyal,</hi> Humility and <hi>taking up the Croſs,</hi> was as <hi>neceſſary an accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and qualification of a Diſciple of Chriſt, and <hi>Succeſſor of the Apoſtles;</hi> as was any other Grace; and if it be (as indeed it is) a qualification, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body takes as ready a courſe as can be to qualifie me.</p>
               <p>But what do you tell us of <hi>Poverty?</hi> 'tis as diſpleaſing <hi>to</hi> us, as is the Statute of 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2.</p>
               <p>Nor, do not you tell us of <hi>Symony neither,</hi> nor of taking <hi>Money for Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> Inſtitutions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of which the <hi>Price is riſen</hi> in <hi>ſome Dioceſſes,</hi> ſince I was Inſtituted almoſt <hi>half in half,</hi> it coſt me not above eight or <hi>ten pounds</hi> to be Inſtituted, <hi>Induct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> and <hi>Ordain'd into the bargain;</hi> but now the <hi>Price they ſay is almoſt doubled,</hi> the Gift of God gives twice as much, not <hi>to the Biſhop himſelf,</hi> no, for his Servants, <hi>Secretary,</hi> Groom, <hi>Varlet de Chambre,</hi> Regiſter, <hi>Porter,</hi> &amp;c. takes the Money.</p>
               <p>The Lord keeper <hi>Bacon</hi> was Condemn'd for Bribery, and <hi>moſt justly was turn'd out</hi> of his place, and the <hi>Broad Seal taken from him,</hi> yet the <hi>neither lov'd Money,</hi> (no, he <hi>lov'd it not ſo much as he ought,</hi> his great Soul was ſo <hi>far above it,</hi> that he took no care for <hi>neceſſary Proviſion,</hi> dying in a Garret, chiefly <hi>for want</hi>) nor did he ever <hi>take a Bribe in his life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But his Servants did, and he conniv'd;</hi> even ſo, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Away with it, <hi>for ſhame!</hi> thy Money <hi>periſh with thee,</hi> (ſaid <hi>Simon Peter</hi> to <hi>Simon Magus</hi>) for <hi>thou art in the gall of Bitterneſs and bond of Iniquity, and haſt neither part nor lot in this matter, for thine heart is not right in the ſight of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, <hi>beſides the Symony,</hi> what can be ſaid to the <hi>frequent breach of the Oath of Canonical Obedience,</hi> which alſo is <hi>daily broke by extorting Money,</hi> and ſell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Prayers,</hi> Ordinations, <hi>Institutions, Lectures,</hi> Sermons, Baptizings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here's <hi>rottenneſs all over.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides alſo many <hi>Inhumanities,</hi> Vexations, Extortions, <hi>Impriſonments, Griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances</hi> and Oppreſſions that have (within theſe thouſand years) been uſed in Spiritual Courts, are againſt the Law of <hi>Nature,</hi> and not the leaſt colour of them in the <hi>Law of God,</hi> and ſome point <hi>blanck againſt</hi> the <hi>law of the Land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:32950:17"/>Was there ever the like <hi>known, that men ſhould not fear</hi> to <hi>trample the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Laws</hi> under their foot, if they make <hi>against them,</hi> and at the <hi>ſame time hale in each Tittle of the letter of the Law againſt Diſſenters,</hi> when there is ſo much Diſſention amongſt themſelves, ſo <hi>little Congruity or conformity either</hi> to <hi>one another,</hi> or to the <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the ſin is greater when Holy Ordinances and <hi>Holy Keyes become Snares</hi> to catch away mens Liberties <hi>in civil matters,</hi> and will be an <hi>addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion heaped up and running over,</hi> that a man would wonder how it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for ſo <hi>much rottenneſs</hi> and corruption (<hi>when it happens</hi>) ſhould <hi>ſubſiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Bulwark against Popery</hi> ſome men talk of; go make a <hi>Bulwark of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but rottenneſs,</hi> and tell me <hi>what it is good for,</hi> eſpecially if the <hi>rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſs</hi> and corruption is of the ſame <hi>nature with that Popiſh filth</hi> that was brought from <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>Augustine,</hi> that vileſt of <hi>Monks,</hi> as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
               <p>A <hi>Bulwark</hi> (quoth he) and <hi>Court-christian.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke in cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſp. agatis Inſt. <hi>l. 2. p. 488.</hi>
                  </note> Court-chriſtian was ſo called (ſayes <hi>Coke</hi>) becauſe <q>That as in the <hi>ſecular Courts</hi> the Kings Laws do ſway and decide Cauſes, ſo in <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Courts</hi> the Laws of <hi>Chriſt ſhould</hi> (ſhould, <hi>that was well put in</hi>) rule and direct; for which cauſe the Judges in thoſe Courts are <hi>Divines, (Ay,</hi> we are <hi>fine Divines,</hi>) as Archbiſhops, Commiſſaries, Deans, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> (<hi>A very ſpecial Christian Regiment,</hi> of which not one ſuch name is found in the holy Muſter-roll of Scripture) <hi>Linwood</hi> ſayes, <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria chriſtianitis in quâ ſervantur Leges Chriſti;</hi> Court-chriſtian <hi>ſo called,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in it is obſerv'd the <hi>Laws of Christ,</hi> whereas in the <hi>Kings Courts</hi> are obſerved the <hi>Laws of the World: (Optime opponis Domine!</hi>) the Kings Laws, the <hi>Kings Courts ſet in diſtinction,</hi> and diametrically oppoſite to the <hi>Laws of Christ, and Court-christian;</hi> I profeſs the King and his Courts are ſtrangely beholden to us: <hi>Laws of the World,</hi> (quoth he) yea, but Laws Eccleſiaſtical they <hi>call the Laws of Christ,</hi> our Courts-<hi>Christian, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth!</hi>) in diſtinction <hi>from the Kings Courts;</hi> our ſelves <hi>Divines, in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction</hi> from earthly <hi>Lay-men that mind</hi> the World and <hi>worldly things;</hi> our ſelves <hi>Spiritual</hi> perſons in diſtinction <hi>from the carnal Layety;</hi> and our Courts <hi>Spiritual Courts in diſtinction</hi> from the <hi>worldly Kings Courts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well, I commend them for <hi>giving themſelves and us a good name,</hi> and a good word, <hi>becoming our own Trumpets</hi> to commend our ſelves; for <hi>if we did not,</hi> who ſtrives to do it? the Papiſts (indeed) were <hi>barbarouſly Inhumane Soul-ſellers,</hi> Cruel, <hi>Revengeful,</hi> Miſchievous, <hi>conſtant Friends to the Devil</hi> and the Gaol, but had the <hi>Law of the Land on their ſide</hi> for their black deeds: But ſome <hi>men Oppreſs,</hi> Extort Money for <hi>Gods Gifts,</hi> Illegal Fees, in high and open Contempt of the <hi>known Laws of the Land,</hi> and in defiance <hi>of their own Oaths againſt Symony,</hi> and <hi>their Oaths of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical Obedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And moreover, if the 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. (being the laſt Statute that ever was revived concerning <hi>Biſhop-making and</hi> Eccleſiaſtical-<hi>Court-keeping</hi>) be in force, (as I doubt <hi>not in the leaſt</hi> that any body will deny) then to all wickedneſs is <hi>added</hi> the greateſt Inſolence, Scandal, and daring <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over the Laws,</hi> that ever any Chronicle <hi>does</hi> mention or <hi>record.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:32950:17"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVI.</head>
               <p>AND Bleſſed be God that has in his Providence <hi>ſo order'd it,</hi> that <hi>out of the Eater is come forth Meat,</hi> and <hi>out of the Strong ſweetneſs to me,</hi> through the Strength, Intereſt, Malice and Power of my Adverſary.</p>
               <p>A Power, that by <hi>bereaving me of my capacity</hi> of being a States mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, or <hi>receiving the States pay,</hi> has <hi>thereby</hi> not only given me leiſure and occaſion, (<hi>Oh deep Polititians!</hi>) not only to pry into their Conſtitution, and obſerve their Motions, but alſo has thereby <hi>emancipated my Judgment,</hi> and <hi>knockt off</hi> thoſe <hi>Shackles</hi> wherewith it might happen to <hi>be feterr'd,</hi> byas't, warpt or <hi>bended the wrong way,</hi> through Self-ends or <hi>private Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects; Intereſt too frequently Bribing,</hi> and conſequently <hi>Blindfolding</hi> the Judgment, that it cannot <hi>diſcern</hi> light from <hi>darkneſs;</hi> nor can I deny but that in compoſing this little Treatiſe, I have had more than ordinary help and <hi>aſſiſtance Divine,</hi> to diſcern further (and yet undeniably true) into the <hi>Validity and force</hi> of this ſo <hi>needful Statute,</hi> (ſo long <hi>deſpiſed) by men</hi> that talk much of the Kings Prerogative, <hi>when it ſerves their own ends.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To which</hi> alſo (I cannot ſay but) they might the <hi>rather</hi> be inclin'd by the Lord <hi>Coke;</hi> but whether they wrought <hi>him to it,</hi> or he <hi>them,</hi> 'tis not a pin matter: <hi>Ignorantia craſſa non excuſat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For, As it is moſt certain, that an <hi>after-Statute vacates</hi> and makes voyd all <hi>precedent Statutes</hi> that are <hi>contrary</hi> thereunto:</p>
               <p>And as it is alſo as certain as that every <hi>child is younger than its father</hi> the author of its life, and every <hi>effect junior to its cauſe,</hi> ſo (alſo) <hi>certain it is</hi> that this <hi>Revived Statute</hi> muſt <hi>date its life</hi> and force from 1 <hi>Jacob.</hi> and therefore vacates 1 <hi>Eliz. 1. 25 H. 8. 20. 1 Mar.</hi> 2. &amp; 1 &amp; 2 <hi>Phil. Mar.</hi> 8. and <hi>all other Statutes</hi> that make Biſhops of <hi>any other faſhion,</hi> or ſend Writs and Proceſſes in <hi>any other name,</hi> than that Statute does direct and enjoyn.</p>
               <p>And though this Argument alone unfetters it from <hi>Coke</hi>'s threefold Cord wherewith he endeavours to bind it down; yet 'tis <hi>ex abundanti;</hi> and more than needs.</p>
               <p>For his <hi>ſecond Cord</hi> is untyed and looſed by ſaying (<hi>as aforeſaid</hi>) that It is <hi>Impoſſible</hi> any Law ſhould aim at the <hi>doing any thing</hi> which is Impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be the aim and <hi>mind of the Legiſlators:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it is Impoſſible that the repeal of 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. could be the <hi>mind</hi> of the Legiſlators; becauſe there was <hi>no ſuch Statute in being,</hi> to offend them, or to <hi>need their repeal.</hi> And beſides the 1 &amp; 2 <hi>Phil.</hi> &amp; <hi>Mar.</hi> 2. is <hi>not contrary</hi> to 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2.</p>
               <p>For though they may be <hi>diverſe,</hi> they are not <hi>contrary,</hi> but may very well <hi>ſubſiſt together;</hi> For the <hi>Pope</hi> may keep his <hi>Supremacy</hi> though Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes Eccleſiaſtical did run in the <hi>Kings Name;</hi> As well as <hi>the King</hi> may keep his <hi>Supremacy</hi> though Proceſſes Eccleſiaſtical run in <hi>Doctor Exton</hi>'s name, or <hi>Pinfolds</hi> name.</p>
               <p>Therefore it was below the Ingenuity of the learned <hi>Coke</hi> to mention ſuch a <hi>frivolous Cord</hi> that is ſo <hi>eaſily broken.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>third Cord ſeems the ſtrongeſt</hi> as to the repeal of the firſt branch of 1. <hi>Edw. 6. 2. though it is very idle</hi> and inſignificant as to the other branch of the Statute, concerning keeping Eccleſiaſtical Courts in the Kings name:</p>
               <p>For 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. 20 only allows Proceſſes Eccleſiaſtical as heretofore uſed.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32950:18"/>
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo that they be <hi>not contrary</hi> to the Laws of the Land: Wherefore here is apparently <hi>Petitio principii,</hi> and the Learned <hi>Coke</hi> firſt prevaricates in reciting the Statute, and yet <hi>leaves out the material words</hi> that limit it; well knowing that otherwiſe this fallacy would be diſcern'd in <hi>begging the Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For he would prove <hi>Proceſſes Eccleſiaſtical</hi> (uſed as in Popiſh times) to be legal by 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. 20. ſo that ſuch Proceſſes be not contrary to the Law of the Land: <hi>Taking it for granted</hi> that 1 <hi>Edw. c.</hi> 2. is not the Law of the Land; <hi>quod reſtat probandum:</hi> He clearly <hi>begs the Queſtion,</hi> taking that for <hi>granted,</hi> which is the <hi>point in controverſie,</hi> and which he <hi>ought to prove</hi> by other <hi>mediums</hi> than what is in 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. 20. becauſe that Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute authorizes no Proceſſes but what are <hi>according to Law,</hi> and therefore <hi>much leſs</hi> can it <hi>make any Law voyd,</hi> or be <hi>a cord to bind</hi> that wherewith its ſelf <hi>is limited, bound</hi> and confined.</p>
               <p>I know he ſets up the 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. (like a <hi>Shrove-tide Top</hi>) only that he may <hi>play at it</hi> and throw it down; but we need not fly to 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. there's no occaſion for its repeal of 1 &amp; 2 <hi>Phil.</hi> &amp; <hi>Marry</hi> 8. (as to this particular) yet it does repeal it.</p>
               <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> and ſtrongeſt and <hi>onely Cord</hi> that he confeſſes did bind it, was but, only <hi>temporary,</hi> during its <hi>own force,</hi> and <hi>whileſt it had ſtrength;</hi> for how could it bind any thing (any) <hi>longer than its own power and vigour laſted?</hi> But 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. reviving as he confeſſes by 1 <hi>Jacob.</hi> (except it have been repealed ſince <hi>primo Jacobi,</hi>) It ſeems without further queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or controverſie to be <hi>in force.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>above all,</hi> (which accurate Lord <hi>Coke</hi> never mentions, and <hi>would</hi> not (<hi>at leaſt did not</hi>) think of) he needs <hi>no other</hi> arguments to defeat his own three cords, <hi>but his own</hi> arguments onely <hi>turning the poynts</hi> of them <hi>againſt himſelf:</hi> For if an <hi>after-Act</hi> ſhall <hi>vacate all former Acts</hi> that are <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi> to it; and if the Life of 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. 20. ſhall be accounted an <hi>after-Act to</hi> 1 Edw. 6. 2. (though its <hi>first</hi> life was <hi>before</hi> it) bearing date <hi>only from</hi> 1 Eliz. 1. the author and cauſe of its <hi>preſent</hi> life and <hi>motion,</hi> which is (alſo) as true as that <hi>cauſa est prior effectu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So alſo, by <hi>the ſame reaſon</hi> muſt 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. be <hi>an after-Act to</hi> 1 Eliz. 1. 1 &amp; 2 <hi>Phil.</hi> &amp; <hi>Mar. 8. 1 Mar.</hi> 2. &amp; 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. 20. bearing date <hi>primo Jacobi,</hi> the <hi>Author</hi> and <hi>cauſe of its preſent life</hi> and motion; and therefore muſt make them null and void in every thing that is contrary to 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2. revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved 1 <hi>Jacob.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if this can be anſwered by <hi>all the men in</hi> England, I will for ever hereafter throw <hi>away my Pen,</hi> and forfeit my Reaſon to the <hi>Maſter</hi> of <hi>New Bethlehem:</hi> And (indeed) <hi>that is the fitteſt place</hi> for me, if the force of this (ſo long-abuſed) <hi>Statute be not</hi> here <hi>made evident</hi> to all rational men.</p>
               <p>But on the contrary, <hi>Bedlam is the fitteſt place for them that have inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently</hi> contemn'd and <hi>trampled on this Royal Statute,</hi> and thereby brought ſuch a horrible <hi>Scandal and Inconvenience,</hi> if it be in force.</p>
               <p>For <hi>if that Statute be in force,</hi> how many <hi>lawful Biſhops,</hi> lawful Prieſts, or <hi>lawful Eccleſiaſtical Courts</hi> have we in <hi>England?</hi> But let the great <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal lye at the right door</hi> whereto it belongs, and let them that have been <hi>guilty of the ſin,</hi> bear alſo the <hi>Shame</hi> and the <hi>blame,</hi> and be <hi>accountable for ſo great a Scandal,</hi> and puniſht accordingly; <hi>look to it,</hi> the Laws are <hi>too hard for all Opponents,</hi> whoever they be in concluſion, and at the upſhot; therefore it <hi>concerns</hi> ſome people to <hi>fence</hi> with all their force and <hi>might,</hi> and all to <hi>no purpoſe,</hi> but <hi>their own Confuſion; How can a corrupt Tree bring forth good fruit?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:32950:18"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVII.</head>
               <p>AND <hi>now I have done my buſineſs,</hi> and alſo I have <hi>done the buſineſs of ſome Eccleſiaſtical</hi> men to all intents and purpoſes, ſome will ſay, and have ſhown what <hi>ſad fellows they are,</hi> though I confeſs ſome of them are <hi>my fellows,</hi> yet I <hi>bluſh for them,</hi> and ſhould <hi>bluſh more</hi> to be ſeen in ſome of their Companies, yet I <hi>care not how ſoon</hi> (now) I come into <hi>their clutches,</hi> if <hi>their Nails</hi> were pair'd ſo ſhort, <hi>ſo ſhort.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He that values any <hi>thing more than Christ</hi> (Chriſt ſayes) <hi>is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of him,</hi> much more unworthy of him are <hi>thoſe</hi> that <hi>value their Malice and Revenge</hi> more than the <hi>Propagation of the Goſpel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis well <hi>that God is</hi> (and muſt) be <hi>just,</hi> and therefore there muſt be <hi>another day of Reckoning</hi> in another World, where <hi>Truth</hi> ſhall <hi>not stand at the Barr</hi> and be Arraign'd, whilſt <hi>Hipocriſie,</hi> Symony, <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> Debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>Cruelty</hi> and Diſſimulation <hi>ſits on the Bench.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Gods Will be done, on Earth as it is in Heaven;</hi> he beſt knows <hi>what is best for us</hi> in this Life; nor would I eat of <hi>ſome mens dainties to</hi> have their <hi>Boſoms,</hi> Cares, Terrours and <hi>Distractions</hi> here, though I might be <hi>excus'd from paying their Reckoning</hi> in another Life.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, <hi>God hates Hipocriſie,</hi> and it will never do a man <hi>good in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Life;</hi> But in <hi>this Life,</hi> It is as <hi>good as true Religion to ſuch kind of States-men</hi> and Machiavilians as make no <hi>other uſe of Religion,</hi> but in <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy,</hi> and to amuze the <hi>vulgar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Horſe <hi>painted in cloath</hi> (which is not <hi>perſpicuous</hi>) is as <hi>good as a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving-stalking-horſe,</hi> to catch <hi>Woodcocks that cannot ſee thorow it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hypocriſie (then) is <hi>good for ſomething,</hi> it will ſerve to catch Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocks in a State, if it be ſo <hi>Substantial</hi> that the <hi>Woodcocks do not ſee tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row it,</hi> but if it be apparently and viſibly <hi>Tranſparent,</hi> it is <hi>uſeleſs</hi> and <hi>good for nothing</hi> in the World, it will not ſerve ſo <hi>much as to cheat with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,</hi> no more than <hi>falſe dice,</hi> after <hi>they are diſcovered</hi> apparently, <hi>where</hi> and how; <hi>even ſo,</hi> any Church (though it be not true,) yet <hi>if it retain but the face</hi> of Religion, and look like <hi>Piety to ſee to,</hi> it will ſerve well <hi>enough in States-policy, where they are indifferent and careleſs for</hi> any <hi>more</hi> than to <hi>ſet a good face</hi> upon the matter, as at <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that Church that <hi>retains not ſo much as the face of Piety,</hi> but that <hi>it is a step to Preferment but to pretend to Piety,</hi> or look ſoberly and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murely, when the very <hi>outſide Hypocritical-mask</hi> and Vizard of Religion is quite <hi>thrown off</hi> and caſt aſide, through palpable and <hi>apparent Symony,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torting Money for <hi>Gods Gifts,</hi> for Ordinations, and for <hi>all Goſpel Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> to the daily and conſtant and <hi>apparent breach of their Oaths against Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and their Oaths of Canonical Obedience,</hi> and alſo through their <hi>Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice,</hi> Malice and <hi>Worldly-mindedneſs,</hi> above all other People; <hi>Pride,</hi> Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and <hi>Cruelty</hi> above all other People; <hi>Formality,</hi> Dulneſs and <hi>coldneſs</hi> in Devotions <hi>above all other People;</hi> Looſneſs of Converſation, <hi>Oppreſſions</hi> and Extortions <hi>above all other People;</hi> fighting againſt their Adverſaries to <hi>wreak their Malice,</hi> ſerve a turn or <hi>State-job,</hi> and miſchief <hi>mens earthly Liberties with the Keyes</hi> of the Church <hi>thrown at them,</hi> my Friends, in ſuch
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32950:19"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:32950:19"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:32950:20"/>
a Caſe, the <hi>very face of Religion</hi> and <hi>Vizard-mask of Religion</hi> is thereby <hi>thrown off,</hi> ſo that it is neither <hi>uſeful for Heaven</hi> nor <hi>Earth,</hi> neither for <hi>God</hi> nor the <hi>State;</hi> it will not ſerve <hi>ſo much</hi> as to catch Woodcocks.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hard is their hap</hi> that are <hi>forc't</hi> to follow <hi>erroneous Guides</hi> and illegal wayes, or upon <hi>refuſal</hi> to be <hi>Anathematiz'd, Gaobd,</hi> and then their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Franchiſes and <hi>Purſes</hi> taken from them, and without, or againſt Law <hi>too.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay and <hi>worſe,</hi> namely, be <hi>Anathematiz</hi>'d and <hi>Curſt by them</hi> that have no more Law, no <hi>more Commiſſion,</hi> no more Power or Authority, neither from <hi>God nor man, to Curſe,</hi> than had (the falſe Prophet) wicked <hi>Balaam</hi> to Curſe the People of God.</p>
               <p>Sad choyce, to be forc't to loſe <hi>Heaven,</hi> or elſe <hi>Earth,</hi> or elſe <hi>both.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Good God! that ever <hi>men (whoſe Anceſtors</hi> baffled the whole Power of <hi>France, Scotland, and the Pope</hi> united, bringing the French King, and the Scotch King and the Pope <hi>captive</hi> and Priſoners at the ſame time) ſhould be ſuch a <hi>degenerate Brood</hi> as to be frighted out of <hi>their Wits</hi> with Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and out of their <hi>Rights,</hi> and out of their <hi>Conſciences</hi> and their <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties</hi> with Illegal Curſes.</p>
               <p>Oh! unhappy (<hi>of all other</hi>) is their <hi>fate,</hi> that are <hi>overwhelm'd</hi> with <hi>filth,</hi> over <hi>run</hi> with <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> and <hi>old</hi> ſpreading <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers</hi> that grow <hi>worſe and worſe,</hi> and run down <hi>with Rottenneſs,</hi> and Pierc't, <hi>Hackled,</hi> Tortur'd and <hi>Mangled with dull Tools</hi> that are ruſty and corrupted <hi>all over.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let no <hi>Catchpole</hi> (here) lye at <hi>lurch,</hi> (for I ſhall have abundance of Readers that deſerve <hi>that Name</hi>) ſetting themſelves to read this <hi>little Book,</hi> with no <hi>other deſign but</hi> (only) to <hi>find ſomewhat therein which they can</hi> ſo far <hi>ſtretch with their Scurvy-teeth</hi> as to <hi>wire-draw it ſo,</hi> as to ſerve their turn to <hi>make a Snare of</hi> to catch me or my Bookſeller, (ſuch Ingenious Reception do <hi>all Attempts towards Truth</hi> receive amongſt <hi>baſe minds</hi>) hoping to beat mine <hi>own Weapons</hi> about mine <hi>own Ears.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But let them <hi>let fall</hi> their edgleſs Swords, <hi>deſpair and dye,</hi> though I doubt not but they will lye <hi>at catch,</hi> and perhaps apply my Metaphors <hi>to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> (as the Phariſees did thoſe of our bleſſed Saviour) when <hi>cut to the Heart</hi> with his keen Parables, they <hi>perceived he ſpoke the Parable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them,</hi> but knew not how to help themſelves: But I, (in all this Metaphorical-diſcourſe) mean <hi>not any Religion in particular,</hi> nor any <hi>Church</hi> (by name) <hi>whatſoever, except that thin</hi> Religion and that <hi>ruiuous</hi> Church that was <hi>huddled up in haſt</hi> and built <hi>upon Crutches,</hi> and the fooliſh Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants had rather it ſhould <hi>fall upon their Heads</hi> than they will confeſs <hi>themſelves Weak-builders,</hi> (ſuch is that <hi>Pride</hi> and pretence to <hi>Divinity,</hi> that (<hi>Lucifer-like</hi>) would gladly attempt to be <hi>like God, Infallible,</hi> as if it were already) <hi>diveſted of Humanity, and not ſubject to Errours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet, (I ſay) I mean no Religion, no Church (hereby) but that <hi>thred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bare</hi> (overworn) <hi>Religion,</hi> and that <hi>ghaſtly Church</hi> (whereſoever it ſtands in the wide World) <hi>whoſe rotten groundſels,</hi> crazy Foundation, <hi>apparent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapidations,</hi> and tranſparent <hi>guilt Accuſes</hi> and Condemns its ſelf, and is <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to every Paſſenger</hi> that does but <hi>view it, and caſt his eyes</hi> (or a ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous look) <hi>upon it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>my Pen (how</hi> keen and <hi>ſharp ſoever</hi> ſome buſie Cenſurers have <hi>judg'd it to be</hi>) ſhall never <hi>cut mine own throat,</hi> in hopes to <hi>ſcratch an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my;</hi> though (I confeſs) a dull <hi>blunt Pen</hi> is uſeleſs, and good for nothing, becauſe <hi>unfit to write with,</hi> ſerving only to <hi>blur paper,</hi> as good do nothing; yet the <hi>acuter any Pen is,</hi> the greater dexterity is required <hi>in the</hi> manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and <hi>guidance thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is with Pens,</hi> as with other weapons; And <hi>Pen-men</hi> like <hi>Sword-men,</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:32950:20"/>
they are <hi>beſt</hi> that give the <hi>moſt woundly-ſmart blowes,</hi> and thruſt it <hi>home</hi> upon the adverſe Party, and make their <hi>Hearts ake again,</hi> ſo they do it cleaverly, <hi>fairly, and upon</hi> the Square.</p>
               <p>The <hi>onely</hi> skill lies in <hi>breaking the Adverſaries head</hi> ſo finely and neatly that <hi>at the ſame time</hi> the nimble Fencer (alſo) <hi>guards his own;</hi> otherwiſe he loſes the <hi>reward</hi> as well as the <hi>Honour</hi> of the Prize he playes: (<hi>Miles Chriſti ſecurus interimit, ſecurior interit,</hi> ſayes <hi>Bernard.</hi>)</p>
               <p>Yet I know alſo, That there is <hi>no fence againſt a flail;</hi> and that the <hi>greateſt skill (more is the pity)</hi> may be <hi>over-powred with a dull ſtrong fool,</hi> by meer force, <hi>power</hi> and <hi>main ſtrength.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that is <hi>no Diſparagement to Art,</hi> nor to the <hi>Gentle-craft of fencing,</hi> which uſually <hi>ſends</hi> the ſtrong Clowns <hi>away</hi> with <hi>ſhame and loſs;</hi> And, for all their great ſtrength <hi>marches the Great Blockheads off</hi> with a broken Pate; <hi>ſending them home</hi> (at length) <hi>by weeping-croſs. Great</hi> things are done many times by <hi>ſmall</hi> means, if we conſider that ſingle <hi>Shammah</hi> (one of <hi>Davids</hi> Worthyes) withſtood the <hi>whole Body</hi> of the <hi>Philiſtines. Truth and the Lawes</hi> may be <hi>oppreſt</hi> and <hi>ſuppreſt</hi> a while, but never <hi>quite ſubdued;</hi> for at length they will be <hi>ſtrongeſt,</hi> and too hard for <hi>any man alive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>face of things do alter,</hi> and do become of another Complexion at <hi>low-water-mark,</hi> when the dry Land appears, <hi>in compariſon of what they ſeem'd</hi> when the Tyde <hi>run ſtrongly and high;</hi> when the <hi>flood</hi> comes roll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and <hi>Tumbling</hi> in; the comfort is, it is ſubject <hi>to viciſſitude</hi> and change, and to ebbe as well as flowe.</p>
               <p>For there are three things—namely, The <hi>Sun,</hi> The <hi>Truth,</hi> and the <hi>Lawes,</hi> (all of them of <hi>ſo heavenly</hi> a nature) that they <hi>alwayes ſhine bright</hi> in their <hi>own Firmament, even when</hi> they are <hi>moſt beclouded</hi> (as ſometimes they are) and <hi>Eclyps'd from mortal view:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But (<hi>the Beſt on't is</hi>) They are alwayes <hi>in motion</hi> towards their <hi>former brightneſs,</hi> (as <hi>alſo</hi> are <hi>the</hi> Interpoſing <hi>clouds,</hi> they are <hi>fugitive</hi> (too) and <hi>upon the goe.</hi>) So that though for a time they may <hi>ſeem dimme</hi> and <hi>obſcur'd</hi> to earthly (and <hi>only to earthly</hi>) and ſublunary <hi>Eyes,</hi> yet when <hi>the miſts va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh,</hi> they regain and <hi>reſume their wonted ſplendour,</hi> nay, look <hi>more</hi> lovely and <hi>beautifull</hi> after they have been <hi>maskt with a cloud.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Profeſſion</hi> of a Clergy-man is the <hi>beſt</hi> Profeſſion; the <hi>Calling</hi> moſt <hi>Honourable,</hi> the <hi>Reward greateſt;</hi> But a <hi>corrupt</hi> or evil <hi>Clergy man</hi> is the <hi>vileſt of Mankind;</hi> Corruption of the beſt is worſt of all: For as <hi>no man</hi> is <hi>more</hi> honour'd, <hi>reverenc'd,</hi> or belov'd, than a humble, <hi>painfull Miniſter</hi> of Chriſt, that ſeeks not his own advancement, but the <hi>propagation of Truth, and univerſal good to Mankind;</hi> ſo, what Creature more odious than a Clergy-man <hi>corrupted with Pride,</hi> miſchief, cruelty, <hi>malice,</hi> revenge, <hi>ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice,</hi> yea, an inſatiable greedineſs <hi>after the world,</hi> worldly Honours, <hi>world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Pleaſures,</hi> worldly <hi>Employments</hi> and <hi>gain not</hi> to be <hi>reſtrain'd by the fear</hi> of daily Perjury; or taking <hi>Gods Name in vain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As they do,</hi> that do not only live in perpetual Perjury <hi>againſt their Oaths,</hi> but alſo in Perpetual <hi>contradiction to their calling,</hi> their Profeſſion, their Preaching, and the Name of God or Religion. Thou that <hi>Preacheſt againſt pride, avarice, perjury; worldly-mindedneſs,</hi> Cruelty, <hi>Malice</hi> and Revenge, (<hi>hold up thy hand!</hi>) Art thou <hi>Guilty?</hi> Well! God <hi>ſend thee good deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance;</hi> for thou art in <hi>evil handling,</hi> and the Devil has got a <hi>strong hold of thee;</hi> therefore <hi>beware</hi> all ye that are Miniſters of Chriſt: <hi>beware</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates! Note (by the way) that by <hi>Prelates,</hi> I mean (what our Canon-Laws mean generally by Prelates; namely) <hi>all Clergy-men that have cure of Souls:</hi> For which cauſe I have here ſometimes put my ſelf <hi>into the number,</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:32950:21"/>
calling my ſelf—(<hi>we Prelates</hi>) in good time, as if I was <hi>proud of the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi>—to be <hi>Cock of three;</hi> (for <hi>not more than three</hi> Pariſhes (if <hi>I would be miſchievous</hi>) are under my Juriſdiction Eccleſiaſtical) and therefore no man <hi>in his Wits</hi> can think that I have <hi>ſo little Wit</hi> as to be proud of that I have <hi>all along expos'd,</hi> and care not one farthing for; <hi>much leſs</hi> do I call my ſelf <hi>Prelate,</hi> in hopes to <hi>beggar any man</hi> that may hap to <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize</hi> my <hi>Hogen-mogen-Eccleſiaſticalſhip;</hi> but I call my ſelf <hi>Prelate,</hi> (as the <hi>Canon-law calls</hi> me,) namely, <hi>Benefic't-Clergyman,</hi> for <hi>all ſuch</hi> are <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates by Law;</hi> not for Prelating (or being preferr'd) <hi>one above another,</hi> (ſo much <hi>condemn'd and ſorbid</hi> by our bleſſed Saviour to all his Diſciples) but becauſe they are <hi>Preferr'd over the Flock, in the Care, Cure and Charge</hi> thereof; and is a name of Burden more than Pride.</p>
               <p>So the Canon <hi>de Sacramentis Iterandis, vel non—Sacramenta, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lyndwood. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc. <hi>l. 1. Tit. 7. cap.</hi> ignorantia Sacerdotum. ver. Praelati Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae.</note> 
                  <hi>Diſpenſatores ſunt Prelati Eccleſiae:</hi> Sacraments, the Diſpenſers or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrators whereof are the <hi>Prelates</hi> of the Church: (that is) <hi>all Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with cure:</hi> ſo ſayes the Gloſſe—<hi>Praelati Eccleſiae. Hic vocantur Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lati nedum ſuperiores ut Epiſcopi, ſed etiam inferiores, ut Archidiaconi, Presoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri Plebani &amp; Rectores Eccleſiarum; (&amp; poſtea) quilibet qui praeeſt curae ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum dicitur eſſe Praelatus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prelates,</hi> (here called) are <hi>not only the high flown,</hi> as Biſhops, but the <hi>Inferiour</hi>-Clergy, as Archdeacons, Countrey-prieſts and Rectors of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and indeed all that have cure of Souls.</p>
               <p>And, <hi>if theſe lights be darkneſs, how great is that darkneſs?</hi> if theſe be <hi>corrupt,</hi> what a <hi>naſty lump</hi> it is? how Nauſeous? <hi>how Peſtiferous?</hi> how Infectious? <hi>how Miſchievous?</hi> how <hi>contrary to the very letter</hi> and <hi>deſign</hi> of the <hi>third</hi> Commandment, if the <hi>Name of God</hi> in their Profeſſion, <hi>Cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> Preaching and Prayers, is <hi>Blaſphemed by them,</hi> daily, by <hi>taking it in Vain,</hi> through <hi>palpable Symony,</hi> Perjury, <hi>Pride,</hi> Avarice, <hi>Cruelty,</hi> Malice and <hi>Revenge?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore the Gloſſe upon the Canon-law, <hi>de Officio Archipresbyteri,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning<note place="margin">Lyndwood. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc. <hi>l. 1. Tit. 11. cap.</hi> Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terorum ver. ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes menti.</note> the duty of an Arch-prieſt, does not only call wicked Prelates, <hi>greedy Dogs that can never have enough,</hi> but ravening Wolves, <hi>malus Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latus aliquando dicitur Lupus rapiens Praedam.</hi> (83 <hi>di. nihil.</hi>) An evil Prelate is ſometimes called a Wolf, ſnatching and devouring his Prey; <hi>Quando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Canis Impudicus;</hi> (2 q. 7. <hi>qui nec.</hi>) ſometimes a naſty Cur, or unclean Dog; <hi>Item Corvus;</hi> (2 q. 7. <hi>non omnis</hi>) a meer Rook; <hi>Item ſal infatuatum ad nihilem proficiens,</hi> (2 q. 7. <hi>non omnis</hi>) alſo Salt that has loſt its ſavour, and good for nothing in the World but the Dung-hill; meaning per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps that as in their Lives they ſeem only to be born (<hi>fruges conſumere na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti</hi>) to make Victuals dear, (by eating them up) ſo they are uſeful for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <hi>but to make muck of,</hi> to manure the Land with <hi>ſuch filth,</hi> and ſo (like Hoggs) they'l be <hi>good for ſomething when dead,</hi> though good for nothing (but to eat, devour and do <hi>Miſchief) whilſt they live;</hi> therefore an evil Prelate is call'd a Hog, <hi>Porcus,</hi> (43 <hi>di. in mandat.</hi>) Nay, (35 <hi>di. Eccleſiae Principes.</hi>) an evil Prelate is called a Capon, <hi>Capo, quia ſicut capo non can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat, ſic nec malus Praelatus; item non generat nec pugnat pro ſubditis, item ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut Capo non vocat Gallinas, ſic malus Praelatus non vocat pauperes; item, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut Capo ſe impinguat, ſic malus Praelatus, &amp; ideo cùm quaerat epulis &amp; deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciis abundare, ejicietur in ignem inferni:</hi> (that is) As a Capon <hi>crows not,</hi> ſo neither does an evil Prelate <hi>lift up his Voice</hi> like a Trumpet; neither does he <hi>encreaſe and multiply</hi> the Brood, nor yet <hi>fight for them,</hi> but (<hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven-like</hi>) poſſibly <hi>fight with thoſe that are under his charge;</hi> alſo as a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon calls not the Hens about him (<hi>chocking them</hi>) to feed, ſo neither does
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32950:21"/>
an evil Prelate <hi>call the Poor.</hi> Alſo as a Capon <hi>ſats himſelf,</hi> ſo does an evil Prelate; and therefore when he thinks of nothing but <hi>cramming himſelf</hi> with his dainty Morſels, he ſhall be thrown into <hi>Hell Fire;</hi> and then (for all his <hi>Flutter</hi>) he makes but a ſad and miſerable <hi>Exit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>all Miſchief (like</hi> Cruelty and <hi>Perſecution</hi>) makes a <hi>Rod for its own back,</hi> and becomes its own Executioner, as well as <hi>its own Scourge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Had not <hi>hard-hearted Pharaoh</hi> (think you) been a <hi>wiſer man,</hi> as well as a <hi>better man,</hi> if he had been <hi>leſs miſchievous?</hi> for <hi>by loſing the Bowels</hi> of humane Compaſſion, <hi>he loſt himſelf,</hi> and his Party; all that <hi>ſided with him,</hi> were not only partakers of his <hi>Sins,</hi> but of his <hi>Plagues</hi> alſo; periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the <hi>ſame woful end,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If I can do my <hi>Brethren</hi> a Courteſie, you <hi>may be ſure</hi> I will; What? <hi>not a Legal Biſhop,</hi> nor <hi>Legal Prieſt</hi> in <hi>England! God forbid;</hi> that <hi>muſt never</hi> be admitted; and therefore, though the Lord <hi>Coke</hi>'s reaſon for 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. 20. ſeems of <hi>no force</hi> at all, yet 8 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. ſeems to cure us all, if his Majeſty pleaſe? I hope we are all ſafe ſtill; the Judges only ought to determine it. But what's all this to juſtifie the <hi>Contempt of that Branch</hi> of the Statute (1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2.) that enjoyns the uſe of the Kings <hi>Name, Style, and Seal,</hi> in all our Proceſſes Eccleſiaſtical, <hi>Certificavit's</hi> and <hi>Significavit's</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſor neither 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> nor 8 <hi>Eliz.</hi> touches that; or if it did, (as it does not) <hi>Quere,</hi> Whether the Revival of 1 <hi>Edv.</hi> 6. 2. by 1 <hi>Jacob.</hi> ſhall not obviate it? But <hi>to admit the other Branch</hi> of the Statute to be <hi>in force,</hi> would be a <hi>horrible</hi> wide <hi>Scandal;</hi> yet <hi>not ſo great a</hi> Scandal, but many greater have been let into the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> when the <hi>Heads happened to be</hi> (like the wooden Heads in a Carvers Shop) <hi>Brainleſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons, are lawfully Conſecrated by 8 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. at leaſt by 14 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. 14. but whether they be legally elected to this or that Cure, or Title, is a Point of which I will not give any Opinion, nor meddle with it: one ſaid well, they are <hi>Legales ad Officium, quales quales ſint ad Titulum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Was not the holy Chair <hi>well lin'd againſt Errour,</hi> when that <hi>Monſter</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Baron. Annal. <hi>Ann. 1033.</hi>
                  </note> of men, and <hi>Opprobry</hi> of the Church, (as Cardinal <hi>Baronius</hi> calls <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict.</hi> 9.) was made Pope <hi>at twelve years of Age,</hi> by means of his Fathers Intereſt and Subtilty, the <hi>Marqueſs of Tuſcia?</hi> That Pope being skill'd in<note place="margin">Faſcicul. ad <hi>Ann. 1033.</hi>
                  </note> nothing but the <hi>Black-art,</hi> being found dead and <hi>ſtrangled</hi> in the Woods by <hi>Devils,</hi> as Cardinal <hi>Benno</hi> affirms: <hi>Platina</hi> calls him the wickedeſt and moſt miſchievous of all the Popes, but he that reads the ſad Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter he gives of other Popes, as dull <hi>Sabinianus, Boniface</hi> 3. that red Dragon, (as Cardinal <hi>Baronius</hi> calls him) Prophane <hi>Formoſus, Ann.</hi> 891. wretched Pope <hi>Stephen</hi> 7. <hi>Ann.</hi> 895. (of whom <hi>Baronius</hi> ſayes) He en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred<note place="margin">Platina de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. pontiſ.</note> like a <hi>Wolf,</hi> and died in a Halter <hi>like a Dog.</hi> Debaucht <hi>Romanus, Ann.</hi> 897. Seditious <hi>Theodore</hi> 2. <hi>Ann.</hi> 897. and next to him Vile <hi>Jo.</hi> 10. <hi>Ann.</hi> 897. (<hi>three Popes in one year</hi>) one after another) or theſe three next ſucceeding Popes, <hi>Benedict.</hi> 4 <hi>Leo.</hi> 5. (<hi>Terrae Filii,</hi> as <hi>Platina</hi> calls them;) and this latter <hi>Ann.</hi> 903. after one months Poſſeſſion of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chair, ejected by <hi>Chriſtophorus,</hi> ſo obſcure a fellow, that no man could find out his Countrey, or Sir-name; only that the name he <hi>was known by</hi> before he was Pope, was <hi>Christopher.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And theſe few (<hi>amongſt many more</hi>) I recite, that men need <hi>not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> if great Scandals come in a Church, if the Heads (at <hi>Rome</hi>) hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be like the <hi>Wooden Heads</hi> aforeſaid, (namely) <hi>brainleſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Like Pope <hi>John</hi> 12. that <hi>Spit-fire,</hi> full of his Anathema's, excommunicating the whole Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> for Articling againſt him to the Emperor <hi>Otho</hi> the Great, for drinking a <hi>Health to the Devil;</hi> for ordaining <hi>Boyes</hi>
                  <note place="margin">L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itprand. <hi>l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. c. 7.</hi>
                  </note> Biſhops at ten <hi>years old,</hi> and Deacons in a <hi>Stable;</hi> for invocating the Devil
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32950:22"/>
to help him (at <hi>Dice</hi>) to a lucky Caſt; for lying with <hi>Stephana</hi> his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Concubine; And for turning his Holyneſſes <hi>Palace</hi> to a common Stews or <hi>Brothel houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in his Anſwer to his Charge, he <hi>curſes them all to the Devil</hi> of Hell by Excommunication; and they in Requital, toſs back his <hi>Bruta Fulmina</hi> and Anathema's, by excommunicating the Pope, ſaying,—<hi>You write by the Suggeſtion of as ſilly</hi> Councellors as your ſelf, <hi>Childiſh Threats;</hi> but we <hi>deſpiſe your Excommunication,</hi> and throw it back upon you: <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> the Traytor <hi>bound nothing</hi> with his Halter but his <hi>own wretched Neck.</hi> So <hi>ridiculous</hi> did they make <hi>that Eccleſiaſtical Tool,</hi> or Sword of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, <hi>growing dull</hi> by uſing it ſo often on <hi>every whiſſling</hi> occaſion, to Curſe whom they hated in meer revenge, 'till no wiſe man heeded them: therefore at laſt they <hi>wheedled in</hi> the Magiſtrate to grant them the Writ <hi>de Excommunicato capiendo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bleſſed be God that there is <hi>a day of Judgment hereafter,</hi> and of all <hi>Miracles,</hi> I moſt wonder that <hi>any man</hi> (in his wits) can <hi>be an Atheist,</hi> to doubt it; for it is <hi>impoſſible</hi> but that the <hi>Sun,</hi> Moon, <hi>Stars, Earth,</hi> (and all we ſee) <hi>had a first Cauſe,</hi> that made and preſerves them; and it is impoſſible but that that <hi>first Cauſe</hi> muſt be infinitely good and <hi>just;</hi> and <hi>conſequently</hi> impoſſible but that there muſt be a <hi>day of</hi> Judgment and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice in another</hi> World.</p>
               <p>For <hi>in this</hi> World, the race is <hi>not to the ſwift, nor the battle to the ſtrong,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>nor Favour men of Skill, nor Bread to the Wiſe, nor yet Riches to men of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding;</hi> but Honeſty and Truth <hi>stands at the Bar</hi> (ſometimes) when Hypocriſie, Cruelty, Atheiſm, and Apoſtaſie <hi>ſits on the Bench;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is impoſſible but that there ſhould be <hi>another day</hi> of Judgment; <hi>when</hi> it ſhall be <hi>well with them that fear God,</hi> which fear before him; but it <hi>ſhall not be well with the Wicked, neither ſhall he prolong his dayes,</hi> which<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8. 12, 13.</note> are as a ſhadow, becauſe <hi>he feareth not before God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if Biſhops (<hi>angry Biſhops</hi> or <hi>angred</hi> Biſhops) would be content to <hi>Scold it out,</hi> as St. <hi>Hierom</hi> at St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> calling him <hi>Corvus &amp; Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicula,</hi> Rook and Raven; and his Commentaries on St. <hi>Luke—Nugas</hi>—(<hi>Trifles</hi>) (though I <hi>like not the ſport,</hi> yet I confeſs (of <hi>the two</hi>) ſuch Duels are moſt proper for Women, or men <hi>of the Gown</hi>) but I hate <hi>playing at Sharps,</hi> eſpecially with men that will not <hi>play upon the ſquare,</hi> and <hi>fairly</hi> with Equal Weapons and <hi>Equal Seconds,</hi> but <hi>to fly to the Magiſtrates long Sword</hi> (upon every Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Skirmiſh of Pen</hi>) I will not, <hi>I dare not ſay</hi> that <hi>it is foul Play;</hi> but I'le ſay, 'tis <hi>not an even Match.</hi> The Learned Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury, Doctor Laud,</hi> (when <hi>Fiſher</hi> publiſhed his Book of <hi>Popery</hi>) did not run to the <hi>King and Council,</hi> crying out—<hi>Help O King;</hi> nor did the <hi>Council trouble themſelves</hi> with ſuch Velitations, or <hi>Pen-pickeer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> but <hi>Laud</hi> anſwered a Scholar like a <hi>Scholar,</hi> with his learned <hi>Pen</hi> to his laſting <hi>Honour,</hi> not borrowing the Magiſtrates <hi>Pike</hi> to his <hi>Diſhonour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No man does well approve of the <hi>Baſtinado,</hi> though given him by <hi>never ſo ſmooth</hi> a Cudgel, but the <hi>Cudgells</hi> do ſo <hi>ill become</hi> the hands that <hi>ſhould bleſs us,</hi> that any man would take the <hi>Lamb-basting</hi> from a Hangman, with much more <hi>Patience</hi> and Alacrity than from a Prelate; it being ſo <hi>incongruous to his holy Office</hi> to turn <hi>Executioner</hi> (ſo much as) <hi>by Proxie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor do I know in all theſe Conteſts, how it is poſſible to follow better advice than that happy and <hi>great States-man</hi> gave Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> in reference to the <hi>Papist</hi> and the <hi>Puritan, (neither of them did he</hi> well like;) yet leſt the <hi>Queen</hi> ſhould take him for a Puritan (a ſort of People to whom ſhe never gave much Countenance, <hi>nor much Diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance</hi>)
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32950:22"/>
much leſs <hi>cut them down with Sham-laves made against Papists,</hi> ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>on purpoſe</hi> becauſe of the late <hi>Spaniſh Invaſion,</hi> the danger whereof was no ſooner quite over; but if ſhe did not quite <hi>ſheath</hi> that two edged Sword, yet <hi>ſhe never drew it againſt Papiſts,</hi> no nor againſt <hi>Popiſh Prieſts,</hi> (except <hi>Treaſon againſt the State aggravated</hi> the virulency of that corrupt Religion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>)<note place="margin">Lord Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer <hi>Burleigh</hi>'s Letter to Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> in <hi>Bacon</hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elicity of Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi>
                  </note> the Stateſman I mean, was the Lord Treaſurer <hi>Burleigh,</hi> who in a Letter to that Queen,</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Proteſting firſt that he was not given over, no, nor ſo much as addicted to the (<hi>Puritan</hi>) Preciſeneſs; thus adviſes her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty Queen <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> 'Till I think that you think otherwiſe, I am bold to think that the Biſhops in theſe dangerous times, take a very ill and unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed courſe (<hi>ſo pious Biſhops were in thoſe dayes</hi>) in driving them from their Cures, and this I think for two Cauſes.</p>
                  <p>1. Becauſe it doth diſcredit the reputation and eſtimation of your pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, when the Princes ſhall perceive and know, that <hi>even in your Proteſtant</hi> Subjects (in whom conſiſteth <hi>(mark that) all</hi> your Force, <hi>Strength and Power</hi>) there is ſo great and <hi>heart-burning a Diviſion;</hi> and how much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation ſwayeth in theſe and all other worldly Actions, there is none ſo ſimple as to be ignorant; and the Papiſts themſelves (though there be moſt manifeſt and <hi>apparent diſcord between the</hi> Franciſcans <hi>and</hi> Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans, the Jeſuites and other <hi>Orders</hi> or Religious Perſons, eſpecially the <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictines,</hi>) yet <hi>will they ſhake off none of them, (mark that, but ſome are wiſe and ſome are otherwiſe</hi>) becauſe in the main point of Popery (<hi>and Proteſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme</hi>) they all agree and hold together, and ſo far (<hi>and ſo may all Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants alſo</hi>) freely bragg and vaunt of their Unity.</p>
                  <p>The other reaſon is, becauſe in truth, (in their Opinions) though they are over-ſqueamiſh and <hi>nice,</hi> and more ſcrupulous than they need, yet with their careful Catechizing and <hi>diligent Preaching,</hi> they <hi>bring forth</hi> that <hi>fruit</hi> which your moſt Excellent Majeſty is (<hi>mark that</hi>) to deſire and <hi>wiſh,</hi> namely, the leſſening and <hi>diminiſhing the Papiſtical Numbers;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this time your Majeſty hath <hi>eſpecial Cauſe to employ them,</hi> if it were but as the <hi>Emperour Frederick the Second</hi> employed the <hi>Saracens</hi> againſt the <hi>Pope,</hi> becauſe he was well aſſured that <hi>they (only)</hi> would not ſpare his Sanctity.</p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The CONCL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SION.</head>
               <p>THerefore (certainly) <hi>Solomon</hi> knew <hi>what he ſaid,</hi> when he ſaid, That <hi>the Throne is eſtabliſht by Righteouſneſs</hi> and Juſtice.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Juſtice,</hi> or (which is all one) <hi>the Law</hi> is the (only) <hi>ſure foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> of the <hi>Throne;</hi> which <hi>William</hi> (Sirnamed) the <hi>Conquerour</hi> ſo well underſtood, that he <hi>poſt-pon'd</hi> or wav'd <hi>his Title</hi> to <hi>England, as Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,</hi> (and a long Sword) <hi>deriving it</hi> (againſt Earl <hi>Harold</hi> that Uſurpt his Crown,) from King <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor, (his immediate Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor) as his <hi>next Heir by nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis true, <hi>Coke</hi> calls him <hi>William Baſtardus,</hi> and the Common-law ſayes<note place="margin">Coke in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em. <hi>2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>.</hi> Inſtitut.</note> (at leaſt) <hi>to all Subjects, Baſtardus non haereditabit,</hi> a Baſtard ſhall not In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit; but whether King <hi>William</hi> had any reaſon, or rather was miſtaken to think it too low to reach the Laws of the Crown; though afterwards Illegitimacy upon another ſcore (ſo declared by Acts of Parliament) proved not a ſufficient Barr to ſeclude either Queen <hi>Mary</hi> or Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> from the Imperial Crown of this Realm) or whether it was but King <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:32950:23"/>
meer fancy, or that he had ſome other Title <hi>by the Will</hi> of King <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> concerns not us at this diſtance, ſo much as to enquire, further than to ſay, (what all Hiſtory agrees in) <hi>negatively,</hi> he did <hi>not claim his Right</hi> to the Crown by <hi>his Sword,</hi> or by laying his <hi>Hand upon his Hilt;</hi> but <hi>gently,</hi> like other <hi>Succeſſive Kings of</hi> England; took the <hi>Coronation Oath,</hi> and <hi>vowed</hi> obſervance of and <hi>Obedience</hi> to the Laws.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Throne of England</hi> is <hi>more ſtately,</hi> magnificent, and <hi>well-ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> than to <hi>ſtand upon ſo Tickliſh a point</hi> as the <hi>Point of a Sword,</hi> be it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo long a Sword; much leſs ſhould it ſtand upon ſo tottering a <hi>Lot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery,</hi> as to come to <hi>meaſuring of Swords,</hi> or the long <hi>Cut carry it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Eſpecially, ſince the Law of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> teaches the vanquiſhed to <hi>put by</hi> the longeſt Sword (as far as they can) from their <hi>Breaſts</hi> and <hi>Throats,</hi> except the <hi>Sword be</hi> Commiſſionated and <hi>Legitimated</hi> from the <hi>Law of the Land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſince the <hi>Law of the Land</hi> is the only, <hi>ſure,</hi> true, <hi>infallible</hi> and impartial <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mpire</hi> in all <hi>Cauſes,</hi> and over all <hi>Perſons</hi> as well <hi>Eccleſtaſtical</hi> as <hi>Temporal</hi> to decide all <hi>differences</hi> and conteſts that <hi>may or can</hi> poſſibly ariſe betwixt <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Luſt, <hi>Rage,</hi> Will and <hi>force</hi> (on the one hand) and <hi>Diſobedience and Rebellion,</hi> (on the other hand) and ſince it has prov'd <hi>ſo fatal</hi> (hitherto) to any man that <hi>has dared to</hi> refuſe to <hi>ſtand to the</hi> Umpirage and <hi>Award</hi> of the <hi>Law;</hi> then (<hi>tell me</hi>) who <hi>will,</hi> nay Indeed, who <hi>may</hi> or <hi>can</hi> withſtand or <hi>gainſay the Law</hi> that is <hi>irreſiſtable?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if, (by the Premiſes) it be <hi>undeniably true,</hi> that—by <hi>the repeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>.</hi> Inſtit. 688.</note> 
                  <hi>of a Repeal, the firſt Act is revived;</hi> and (alſo) that an <hi>after-Statute makes void all its Predeceſſours</hi> that are contrary to it; and (alſo) if the <hi>effect</hi> muſt be <hi>after</hi> its <hi>Cauſe,</hi> then <hi>ſo certain it is,</hi> that this <hi>Royal Statute</hi> (1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 2.) bearing <hi>date of its Life</hi> from its <hi>Cauſe (prim. Jacob.)</hi> that <hi>reviv'd</hi> it, muſt <hi>undoubtedly take place of</hi> (1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. 1 &amp; 2 <hi>Phil.</hi> &amp; <hi>Mar.</hi> &amp; 1 <hi>Mar.</hi> and) <hi>all</hi> (other) <hi>Statutes</hi> that are its <hi>Seniors</hi> in <hi>every thing</hi> where they <hi>thwart</hi> it.</p>
               <p>But, (alas) 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. &amp; 1 <hi>Phil.</hi> &amp; <hi>Mar.</hi> 8. were <hi>not contrary to it,</hi> much leſs could it come into <hi>the hearts and minds</hi> of thoſe Legiſlators to repeal it, more than to <hi>offer to kill a dead Horſe;</hi> for it was (as <hi>dead</hi>) (by 1 <hi>Mar.</hi> 2.) 'till King <hi>James Reviv'd</hi> it, ſince which time <hi>who can deny</hi> but it has had <hi>Life,</hi> by what <hi>Arts</hi> ſoever, or for what <hi>hidden Cauſe</hi> ſoever, or by <hi>whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever</hi> it has <hi>ſeem'd to be ſmothered;</hi> though ſo advantageous and <hi>ſuitable to the Kings Prerogative Royal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alſo,</hi> if all the <hi>Canon-law</hi> made before 25 <hi>H</hi> 8. (and <hi>no other</hi>) be in <hi>force, (in Tanto)</hi> for ſo <hi>much of them as are not contrary</hi> to the Laws of the Realm, nor to the Kings Prerogative Royal; (which the Law (alſo) <hi>does in every thing ſupport,</hi> direct, declare and advance,) and if <hi>Symony</hi> in contracting or purchaſing, ſelling, buying or bargaining for Divine Gifts, Functions and Offices, be odious to God and man, and to the Laws <hi>both of God and man;</hi> then (tell me) who <hi>will</hi> or <hi>dare,</hi> nay, indeed who <hi>may</hi> or <hi>can, give</hi> or <hi>take, require</hi> or <hi>exact</hi> Money for <hi>Baptizings,</hi> Buryals and <hi>Marria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges;</hi> for <hi>Sins, Sacraments</hi> and <hi>Lectures;</hi> for Letters of Orders, <hi>Inſtitutions,</hi> Inductions, <hi>Collations</hi> or the like? much leſs <hi>chop</hi> and <hi>change</hi> Biſhopricks or Benefices for <hi>lucre,</hi> (filthy Lucre) in <hi>defiance of the Oaths</hi> againſt <hi>Symony,</hi> in defiance of the <hi>Oaths of Canonical Obedience,</hi> taken and ſworn (God forgive us!) by <hi>every Benefic't</hi> Prieſt and <hi>Biſhop,</hi> in defiance of the <hi>Law of God and man,</hi> and (<hi>which is worſt of all</hi>) to the apparent hazard of our <hi>Immortal Souls,</hi> and <hi>all this</hi> for a little <hi>ungodly gain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Who will believe <hi>us</hi> or our <hi>Preaching?</hi> or can any <hi>Imagine</hi> that we <hi>believe what we Preach,</hi> whilſt <hi>without repentance we live</hi> in ſuch <hi>Symonical Crimes,</hi> to the <hi>univerſal</hi> ſcandal and <hi>contempt of the Clergy?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:32950:23"/>
                  <hi>Which ſeems not more</hi> Catholick and <hi>general</hi> than <hi>Juſt,</hi> if by our <hi>known Symony</hi> and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varice, <hi>Pride</hi> and Cruelty, <hi>Perſecuting-ſpirit</hi> and <hi>Woldly-mindedneſs</hi> (above all others) we <hi>taint</hi> our <hi>Holy Functions,</hi> and be ſpot and <hi>ſtain our Surplices</hi> with ſo much <hi>filth,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king our ſelves (thereby) the <hi>common Scandal,</hi> as well as <hi>common Odium:</hi> what need have <hi>we</hi> (above all others) <hi>to ask forgiveneſs</hi> both of God and man?</p>
               <p>And ſuch may as lawfully be reſiſted, as an honeſt Woman <hi>may reſiſe</hi> a Goat or a <hi>Raviſher.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Howbeit, It is <hi>ſo far from Purgation,</hi> that it <hi>aggravates</hi> any Villains Crimes, when he thinks <hi>to expiate</hi> his Abominations (as <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> did) by <hi>Humane Victimes,</hi> ſacrificing <hi>Men</hi> to his Wrath, by encouraging inhumane Cruelties and Vexations againſt ſuch who happen to have <hi>ſtraiter Conſciences,</hi> and <hi>not ſo wide</hi> a ſwallow as himſelf.</p>
               <p>How many Hearts were <hi>ever won by vexing</hi> them? or, how can men (in <hi>Juſtice</hi> or <hi>Law</hi>) be <hi>compelled to that Church</hi> (by the Act of Uniformity) which is <hi>not conformable</hi> to the Act, but <hi>coyns or keep up new Ceremonies,</hi> in unlighted Candles on the Altars, cringing and bowing to them, Organs and Muſick, with many ſuch Innovations puniſhable by the Act of Uniformity.</p>
               <p>If men <hi>muſt obey the eſtabliſhed</hi> Religion, let us have <hi>no other but what is eſtabliſhed;</hi> and if Diſſenters <hi>muſt be puniſht, let all</hi> Diſſenters <hi>be puniſht,</hi> and not make <hi>fiſh of one and fleſh of another;</hi> ſince Diſſenters have this <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerable excuſe for not coming to Church,</hi> and to the eſtabliſhed Religion, if there be <hi>another or more</hi> Religion, (or rather) <hi>Superſtition there,</hi> than what is <hi>eſtabliſhed by the Act for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For I (<hi>and all good Subjects</hi>) ought <hi>equally to abhor</hi> all Faction; and all <hi>Innovation,</hi> all <hi>new Religions,</hi> or <hi>new Superſtitions and Ceremonies</hi> to Periwig the <hi>old.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Both</hi> of them <hi>are Diſſenters,</hi> and if any be <hi>Fin'd</hi> and Puniſht<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Fine them and Puniſh <hi>them both alike;</hi> but firſt Fine <hi>thoſe Diſſenters that make Diſſenters</hi> by new Ceremonies contrary to the Act.</p>
               <p>Though (<hi>I confeſs</hi>) I am <hi>not for knocking men down and taking their Purſes, becauſe their eyes are not ſo good as mine,</hi> for fear that the next man I meet (who may happen to <hi>out-ſee me</hi> as well as <hi>oyt-ſtare me</hi>) ſhould (<hi>by mine own</hi> rule and <hi>law</hi>) ſerve me with the ſame ſawce; and (<hi>more eſpecially</hi>) becauſe Almighty God (the only King of Conſciences, has alwayes <hi>Plagued Perſecutors of mens Conſciences,</hi> (although) erroneous Conſciences) <hi>in all Ages;</hi> and <hi>I am apt to think</hi> that the <hi>Merit of Informers</hi> will ſcarcely perſwade Almighty God to <hi>abate his</hi> uſual <hi>Indignation</hi> againſt all manner of Perſecution and Cruelty: How much foever the <hi>Perſecuting ſtrain be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded</hi> and admired by <hi>ſubtle Roger,</hi> and ſuch needy Varlets that are <hi>greedy to ſwallow any bait,</hi> (they are ſo hungry) <hi>though it</hi> will certainly <hi>choak them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His <hi>Gracious Majeſty</hi> (whom God long Preſerve) having ſo <hi>often declared</hi> (as alſo his Parliaments) againſt the <hi>ſeverity-part</hi> of the <hi>Act,</hi> and ſo alſo King <hi>Charles</hi> 1. that tells his Son how dangerous it is to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurp the Juriſdiction of the King</hi> of Conſciences, or to kick againſt the pricks: And I have heard that (therefore) he would never Pardon a Murtherer, ſaying, <hi>Who am I?</hi> to contradict God that ſayes,—<hi>He that ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iddeth mans Blood, by man ſhall his Blood be ſhed?</hi> and ſhall I ſay No, it <hi>ſhall not</hi> be ſhed?</p>
               <p>But, if in this, or in any other word or clauſe in this diſcourſe, any thing have eſcap't my Pen, through Precipitancy or want of Skill, (for who (except the Pope) is Inſallible) or derogatory to the Holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, Faith or good Manners, I wiſh it were <hi>obliterated,</hi> with all my heart.</p>
               <p>For <hi>nothing do I covet</hi> in this World <hi>ſo much</hi> as the <hi>Propagation</hi> of the true <hi>eſtabliſhed Religion,</hi> Peace, Mercy and Goodneſs to humane Nature and all Mankind; <hi>againſt any of which</hi> if I have <hi>in the leaſt</hi> tranſgreſt herein, I hope the <hi>Ingenuous Readers</hi> will the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther candidly <hi>Pardon me,</hi> in <hi>Complacence</hi> to the <hi>Honeſty of this my Attempt,</hi> which may <hi>(at leaſt) Atone</hi> for my Errors and <hi>humane frailties</hi> which are many, <hi>very many; againſt which</hi> (though) <hi>none</hi> can poſſibly be <hi>more enraged than I am,</hi> when they are <hi>diſcover'd to me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, why ſhould men be in love with their <hi>Sins</hi> or their <hi>Sores?</hi> if they were <hi>my Sores,</hi> I would <hi>not kick a Dog that</hi> Ofter'd to <hi>lick them whole.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And was not <hi>apparent Symony,</hi> Avarice, <hi>Spiritual Dominion,</hi> and Encroachment <hi>upon Temporal-Courts</hi> and intruſion into <hi>temporal Employments,</hi> together with <hi>Perſecution,</hi> Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, <hi>Spitting-fire,</hi> Curſes and <hi>Anathema's,</hi> Extortions, Gaoles and <hi>Fines,</hi> new Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and <hi>Superſtitions,</hi> Antick Dreſſes and Antick <hi>Cringes,</hi> &amp;c. (<hi>all which</hi> are ſome mens <hi>darling ſins,</hi>) but were they not <hi>at firſt</hi> brought over from <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> (as aforeſaid) <hi>that ſame</hi> wretched Monk?</p>
               <p>I know not <hi>what</hi> ſuch Romiſh Dreggs are <hi>good for, except</hi> (as the Dreſt Cowcumbers I once <hi>Cookt) for the Dunghill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or, how in the name of goodneſs can any man <hi>abett them,</hi> or ſo far <hi>Countenance them, as to Diſcountenance me</hi> (as hitherto) for Impeaching them?</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, if any bodies Palate be ſo <hi>out of taſt,</hi> as to <hi>love and long for</hi> ſuch Romiſh Dreggs, let them <hi>ſend for the old,</hi> tainted and fuſty <hi>Bottles again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>nothing elſe</hi> is fit to <hi>hold them,</hi> nor <hi>can retain them</hi> long; for the Goſpel is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red<note place="margin">Mark 2. 20.</note> to <hi>new Wine, which no man</hi> (that is, no wiſe man) <hi>puts into old Bottles, elſe the new Wine doth burst the bottles, and the wine is ſpilled and the bottles will be marred, but</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 9. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>new wine muſt be put into new bottles, and both are preſerved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not, but that <hi>I have been</hi> as filly a <hi>Zealot</hi> for Perſecution, as <hi>zealous Roger</hi> himſelf; 'till by ſearching, I could <hi>find no preſident</hi> for it in the <hi>Bible,</hi> nor any <hi>good luck that attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any</hi> that Perſecuted men for Conſcience-fake, though an <hi>erroneous</hi> Conſcience; and eſpecially <hi>in our Soyl, where</hi> that weed <hi>never</hi> thriv'd long; witneſs Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the <hi>German Emperor</hi> to the <hi>Proteſtant Hungarians,</hi> 'till for <hi>ſhelter</hi> they fled to the <hi>(more merciful) Turk,</hi> a Piece of Jeſuitiſme as <hi>unpolitick</hi> as <hi>Impious,</hi> whoever lives to ſee the upſhot.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:32950:24"/>I confeſs, in the Old Teſtament <hi>Joſhua</hi> had ſuch a <hi>Commiſſion to</hi> kill, ſlay and <hi>plunder all Diſſenters,</hi> ſo that it (<hi>poſſibly</hi>) might be true, what <hi>Procopius</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>ſaw,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven on a <hi>Pillar</hi> near <hi>Tangis,</hi> (now called <hi>Tangier,</hi> our Garriſon in <hi>Aſrick</hi>) erected by the <hi>Phoenicians</hi> or <hi>Philiſtines</hi> that fled (ſo far) from the Valour of the Lords Captain, <hi>Joſhua,</hi> to eternize their flight, (and except they had fled into the Sea, they could not well have fled further,) in theſe words—<hi>Nesfugimus à facie Joſhua, Praedonis filii Nave;</hi> We fly from the face of that great Thief, <hi>Joſhua</hi> the Son of <hi>Nun.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, he had <hi>no Commiſſion to plunder his fellow Jews; what feat</hi> was a Province <hi>peculiar to the wicked,</hi> and miſchievous <hi>Priests,</hi> (only) thoſe ravenous Sons of <hi>Eli.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whoſe Symonical Rapine</hi> dragg'd from me theſe <hi>heavy</hi> Verſes.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Prieſts of <hi>Bel</hi> were glad <hi>to Frogg</hi> for meat,</l>
                  <l>Feeding their Wives and Brats <hi>by holy Cheat;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But (High-Prieſt) <hi>Eli's Sons,</hi> without remorſe,</l>
                  <l>Cry—Give, (<hi>ye Slaves!</hi>) or elſe <hi>we'ls tak't by force.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ay</hi>—Theſe were rampant, Hector, rend and tear,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>will be twice paid,</hi> Curſe, Arreſt, and <hi>Swear;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Their frothy</hi> ware <hi>the Layety muſt</hi> buy it,</l>
                  <l>(Juſt as they ſet the Price) <hi>who dare deny it?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Come to the Temple—<hi>Simon</hi>—buy <hi>Gods Word;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If not, then <hi>take him Gaoler,</hi> Ax or Sword.</l>
                  <l>Religion <hi>dreſt in Buffe?</hi> with Gun, <hi>Sword,</hi> Pike?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Religion ſayſt?</hi> the D—it is <hi>more like.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Religion is an <hi>Earthly Paradiſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(<hi>Not an Artillery-Garden</hi>) to the wiſe:</l>
                  <l>Religion's goodneſs and its <hi>Truth (alone)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>An Infinite of Souls to Heaven has <hi>won<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But can we give our God greater <hi>Diſhonour,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Than think—He needs the <hi>Black-Art</hi> of old <hi>Bonner?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Paſtoral-ſtaff</hi> brought home Chriſts Sheep to Folds;</l>
                  <l>Ne're call'd (for Help) to <hi>Qnarter-ſtaff,</hi> of old;</l>
                  <l>If Heaven <hi>allure</hi> not, no, nor Gold to boot,</l>
                  <l>Not all <hi>Earths Magazines nor Hells</hi> can do't.</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Souls</hi> may <hi>well</hi> to God be <hi>drawn,</hi> not <hi>driven;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Did ever Gunpowder <hi>blow</hi> Souls <hi>to Heaven?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Laſtly, <hi>over and above</hi> all this the 15 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. 11. does inflict the penalty of a <hi>hundred pounds</hi> on all Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical-Couriers that take upon them to <hi>inflict,</hi> award or <hi>inflict,</hi> award or <hi>impoſt</hi> any <hi>Pays, Penalty,</hi> &amp;c. upon any the Kings Subjects, <hi>&amp;c,</hi>—Add I do not remember that they did Act till by 13 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. 12. <hi>ſome deemed</hi> a branch thereof to be repealed by 13 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. 12.</p>
               <p>But that 13 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. 12. repealing <hi>only</hi> a branch of a Stature made in 17 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rz</hi> whether that can repeal 16 <hi>Car,</hi> 1. Poſſibly it might be a <hi>miſtake,</hi> but <hi>Quarz,</hi> Whether any but a Parliament can regulate or amend that miſtake?</p>
               <p>For, It is moſt certain, that all Acts of Parliament ſhall bear date <hi>from the Beginning</hi> of every Parliament or from the <hi>beginning of the ſeveral Seſſion</hi> of Parliament, as it is reſolved 3 <hi>H.</hi> 8. B. Parliament 86. in <hi>Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hobart <hi>in the Caſe of</hi> Anne Wheeler, verſus <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Wincheſter.</note> and <hi>Croker</hi>'s Caſe, <hi>Plowd.</hi> 79. And never did any Parliament or Seſſion of Parliament begin in 17 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. and therefore the 13 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. 12 ſeems to affect the 16 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. no more than the 26 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. or any other Statute.</p>
               <p>Does <hi>ſome ill fate</hi> attend our <hi>Eccleſiaſtical-Genius</hi> of Spiritual Courts, that even the Statutes made in our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, prove unſucceſsful? <hi>What's worſe</hi> than ill Luck?</p>
               <p>I profeſs, I <hi>cannot but apprehend the juſt Judgment</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> of God upon <hi>me,</hi> (whatever <hi>evil Inſtruments</hi> he made his <hi>Red of</hi>) for my <hi>apparent Symony</hi> in giving forty Shillings to be <hi>made a Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>eight pounds for Inſtitution</hi> to the <hi>Work,</hi> and then 20 <hi>s.</hi> for Induction; and then 30<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhillings to have <hi>Licenſes to uſe the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Office</hi> of preaching, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but they <hi>would not do it cheaper,</hi> to the apparent breach of our Canonical-Oaths, and Oaths againſt-Simony; And yet I paid all (only) as forc't Fees.</p>
               <p>And is it not alſo <hi>juſt with God</hi> to make us <hi>claſh, and break</hi> us on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon mother, and one by, with (and againſt) another, for ſuch abominable <hi>breach of Oaths,</hi> Extortions and Symonical oppreſſions in exacting money for Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryals, Marriages, Lectures, Baptizings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What? <hi>Sell</hi> holy Sacraments and <hi>holy Offices!</hi> Fy for ſhame!</p>
               <p>But, I repent, <hi>heartily,</hi> heartily, and thus <hi>publickly take ſhanie</hi> to my Self, <hi>ſtanding</hi> (thus) in <hi>a white-ſheet</hi> for it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And if ever I do ſo any more, then, <hi>let my</hi> Heavenly <hi>Father whip me</hi> again with the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d of the Wicked</hi> to my dying day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But <hi>bleſſed be his Name,</hi> that <hi>letting me hereby ſee my Sin,</hi> I may probably <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Inſtrumental to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See Arch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>Parker, de An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiq. Eccleſ. Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan.</hi> p. 47. How. <hi>Auſtin.</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited King <hi>Ethelbers</hi> to kill the Monks of <hi>Bangor,</hi> that were not Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts to his Romiſh Drivel and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies! bloody Monk! <hi>Anno</hi> 60<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>my Brethren</hi> from ſuch horrid <hi>Symony, Avarice</hi> and <hi>dangerous Oaths,</hi> that ſo God may <hi>avert his Judgements,</hi> and the Univerſal <hi>contempt of the Clergy,</hi> under which we <hi>gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an unpitied.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, <hi>no work</hi> (at preſent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) however of <hi>theſe matters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whatſoever is not founded,</hi> neither upon <hi>Gods</hi> Law, nor the <hi>Law of England,</hi> cannot long ſubſiſt, with <hi>what</hi> frail <hi>props ſoever vain</hi> man endeavours to <hi>Shoar it up:</hi>—Stand <hi>clear there</hi>—I'de wiſh you; <hi>As you love</hi> your ſelves, <hi>your Families</hi> and Poſterities, come <hi>not too near</hi> ſuch a c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> frame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſtand where it will.</p>
               <p>For, what <hi>cannot ſtand</hi> muſt fall, <hi>That's all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> are all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and would it not be a kind of Miracle, <hi>to ſee</hi> over the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>s of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> (now ſo pleniſh't <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>—) many Ages hence (I mean) <hi>a Paper</hi> (Paſted over the Gates thereof) <hi>Importing—This Houſe is to be Let?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is <hi>it not juſt,</hi> that they ſhould for ever b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Neck and H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ter'd to <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Poſterity,</hi> that to the <hi>loſs of</hi> their <hi>Honour</hi> as well as Honeſty and Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> do muſt <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>ſhly</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>rle, and moſt <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſhly</hi> ſnap at thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>ble</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ngers that would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Cords?</p>
               <p>Then, <hi>there let them lye,</hi> with their Poſterities, bound down and <hi>crippl'd</hi> with thoſe <hi>bands,</hi> where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>poor Bigots</hi> firſt were <hi>Prieſt-rid</hi> by <hi>Auſtin</hi> the Monk<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:32950:24"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
