<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The aphorismes of Hippocrates, prince of physitians with a short comment on them taken out of those larger notes of Galen, Heurnius, Fuchsius, &amp;c. : with an exact table shewing the substance of every aphorisme.</title>
            <title>Aphorisms. English</title>
            <author>Hippocrates.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 165 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 202 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43859</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2071</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13229</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12278387</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12278387</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58567</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A43859)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58567)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 187:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The aphorismes of Hippocrates, prince of physitians with a short comment on them taken out of those larger notes of Galen, Heurnius, Fuchsius, &amp;c. : with an exact table shewing the substance of every aphorisme.</title>
                  <title>Aphorisms. English</title>
                  <author>Hippocrates.</author>
                  <author>Galen.</author>
                  <author>Heurne, Johan van, 1543-1601.</author>
                  <author>Fuchs, Leonhart, 1501-1566.</author>
                  <author>Soranus, of Ephesus.</author>
                  <author>S. H.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 179 p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Humphrey Moseley ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Aphorismi.</note>
                  <note>The translation is similar to the 1610 London ed., translated by S.H.</note>
                  <note>Interleaved.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
                  <note>"Hippocrates his life out of Soranus": p. [3-10]; "Hippocrates his oath": p. [11-13]</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: portrait lacking on film.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hippocrates.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Aphorisms.</term>
               <term>Medicine, Greek and Roman.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Robyn Anspach</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Robyn Anspach</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58567:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58567:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58567:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58567:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58567:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58567:3"/>
            <p>THE APHORISMES OF <hi>HIPPOCRATES</hi> PRINCE OF PHYSITIANS.</p>
            <p>WITH A ſhort <hi>COMMENT</hi> on Them, taken out of thoſe larger Notes Of <list>
                  <item>GALEN.</item>
                  <item>HEURNIUS</item>
                  <item>FUCHSIUS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>With an exact Table ſhewing the ſubſtance of every <hi>APHORISME.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Humphrey Moſeley,</hi> at the Princes Arms in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church yard. 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb facs="tcp:58567:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58567:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Hippocrates</hi> his life out of <hi>Soranus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ippocrates</hi> was born in an Iſland in the Aegean ſea, called <hi>Cos</hi> or <hi>Ccos.</hi> and was the ſon of <hi>Heraclides,</hi> and <hi>Praxithea</hi> the daughter of <hi>Phenaretes.</hi> He rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned his Pedigree from <hi>Hercules</hi> and <hi>Eſculapius,</hi> and counted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf nineteen generations or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcents from the one, and twenty from the other. Of his Genealo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy <hi>Erat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſthenes</hi> makes mention. and <hi>Pherecides</hi> and <hi>Apollod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rus</hi> and <hi>Arius Tarſenſis.</hi> He was his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Heraclides</hi> diſciple, then to one <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dicus,</hi> and as ſome relate, he heard <hi>Leontinus</hi> the Rhetori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:5"/>

               <pb facs="tcp:58567:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>

               <pb facs="tcp:58567:6"/>
and <hi>Democritus</hi> the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher of <hi>Abdera.</hi> He flouriſhed in <hi>Pelops</hi> his time: and was born (as <hi>Iſthomachus</hi> relates in his firſt book of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> Sect.) in the firſt yeer of the eightieth Olimpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad. But <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ranus</hi> a <hi>Coan,</hi> having ſearched the Library of <hi>Cos,</hi> goes further<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſaith he was born du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Abriada</hi> his Monarchy the ſeven and twentieth day of the month <hi>Agrian,</hi> at which time the <hi>Coans</hi> do to this day offer Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices to <hi>Hippocrates.</hi> Another Author ſaith he lived in the times of <hi>Eliachim, Malachi, Pereno,</hi> and <hi>Socrates.</hi> He being exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing skilful in Phyſick, and the whole courſe of learning, after his parents died forſook his native Country (as one <hi>Andreas</hi> falſly imputes to him in a book which he hath written of the Origine of Phyſick) for having fired the <hi>Cui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:58567:6"/>

               <pb facs="tcp:58567:7"/>

               <pb facs="tcp:58567:7"/>
Library. Others ſay he left his Country through a deſire he had to ſee the effects and ſucceſs of Phyſick in ſeveral effects, Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates, and places. But <hi>Soranus</hi> ſaith the Lord appeared to him in a dream, and wiſhed him go to live in <hi>Theſſalia</hi> Howſoever he was famous all <hi>Greece</hi> over, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired for his skill in Phyſick ſo far that he was by Ambaſſadours ſent for to <hi>Perdi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cas</hi> King of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonia</hi> when he was thought to lye ſick of a Conſumption, and came to him, together with one <hi>Euryphon,</hi> who was elder then he; and by ſome ſignes and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, found that the Kings diſeaſe was a trouble of the mind, for after the death of his Father <hi>Alexander,</hi> he fell in love with one of his Concubines called <hi>Phila:</hi> Which <hi>Hippocrates</hi> diſcovered by his pulſe, in which he felt an alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:8"/>
at her coming into the room, and acquainting <hi>Phila</hi> therewith, cured the King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He was alſo called to <hi>Abdera</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover <hi>Democritus</hi> from his mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and expel the Plague out of the whole City. And the Plague being at a time gotten in amongſt the Pahnonians and Illyrians, they ſent Ambaſſadors for him, who having enquired of them what winds ordinarily blew there ſent them away unſatisfied: and when by prudent Arguments he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw the Plague would prevail up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Atticans dominions, he foretold it, and took great care both of thoſe Cities and of his Diſciples. And he ſo truely lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>Greece,</hi> that the renown of his learning ſpreading it ſelf as far as <hi>Perſia,</hi> and <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> ſending for him by means of <hi>Hyſtanides</hi> Governor of <hi>Helleſpont,</hi> upon 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:8"/>

               <pb facs="tcp:58567:9"/>

               <pb facs="tcp:58567:9"/>
proffer of exceeding great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, preferring honeſty, before lucre of mony, he abſolutely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed him; as by his letter writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to him it plainly appears. He freed his own Country, when the <hi>Athenians</hi> intended to war againſt it, and had called the <hi>Theſſalians</hi> to aid them, whereupon he had great honors decreed him by the Coans. Yea and by the Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians, Argives, and Athenians, who entered him into the Eleuſinian Sacrifices or myſteries, next to <hi>Hercules,</hi> and admitted him into their franchize, and allowed both him and all his poſterity mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Corn out of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Granaries. He taught all as were ſtudious of this Art, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and without envy.</p>
            <p>He died amongſt the Lariſſeans about that time as <hi>Democritus</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo died, ſome ſay at ninety, ſome 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:10"/>
at eighty five, ſome at one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and four, ſome at a hundred and nine yeers of age. And was buried between <hi>Gyrtone</hi> and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſſa,</hi> where his Monument is to this day to be ſeen, in which for a long time there was a ſwarm of Bees, with whoſe hony the nurſes coming to the Monument, would anoint the Ulcers of infants mouths, and cure them. In many of his pictures and Images he is painted with his head covered (ſome ſay) with a hat, it being a ſign of Nobility (for ſo was <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes</hi> painted) Some ſay his head was covered with his Cloak, which ſome affirm was for comelineſs becauſe he was bald, and ſome by reaſon of the weakneſs of his head. But ſome will have it done ſo by him ſignificatively to ſhew that it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fitting to have the chief <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eat of the ſoul well guarded and 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:10"/>

               <pb facs="tcp:58567:11"/>

               <pb facs="tcp:58567:11"/>
covered. Others ſay it is the dreſs of one who loves travel: ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain ſay it was to demonſtrate the obſcurity of his writings. And finally ſome that it was to teſtifie, that we ought in our health time beware of ſuch things as may be hurtful to us. Though ſome affirm it was becauſe his cloak ſhould not hinder him, hanging about his hands when he was about to give Phyſick, and that therefore he wrapped it up and caſt it behind his head.</p>
            <p>There is great controverſie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his writings, ſo that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e being ſeveral opinions, it is not eaſie to aſſert any thing certainly concerning them, for many cauſes which may obcure a mans judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. As firſt his ſirname Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly becauſe it is not poſſible to obſerve his phraſe: Thirdly, becauſe that according to his age 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:12"/>
he alters it, beſides many other reaſons; I could (if I pleaſed) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge. He always contemned mony, was pious, and a lover of the Greeks. Wonderful well-affected to his own Countrymen, ſo that he freed them all from the Peſtilence, as I ſaid before, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he was much honored both by them and the Argives and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians. He left two ſons after his deceaſe, <hi>Theſſalus</hi> and <hi>Draca,</hi> and a great number of Diſciples; but his ſons were the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="oath">
            <pb facs="tcp:58567:12"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58567:13"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58567:13"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Hippocrates</hi> his Oath.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Swear by <hi>Apollo</hi> the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, <hi>Aeſculapius, Hygiea, Panacea,</hi> and call all the Gods and Goddeſſes to witneſs, that I will obſerve and keep this under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written oath to the uttermoſt of my power &amp; judgement. I wil reverence my Maſter who taught me this Art, equally with my Parents, will allow him things neceſſary for his life, and will eſteem his children as brothers, and (do they deſire it)
will teach them this my Art with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſalary or Covenant. I will participate all my inſtructions, and Lectures and whatſoever I know elſe, to all mine own and my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:14"/>
children, yea and to all my ſchollers, who ſhall in writing be bound to me, and tyed by a Phyſical oath, and to none elſe.</p>
            <p>And as what concerns curing of the ſick, I will to the uttermoſt of my power and judgement preſcribe them their diet, and will ſecure them from all detriment and inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. I will not by any mans intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties be moved to miniſter poyſon to any man, nor give any advice to do it. Neither will I give a woman any Phyſick to make her miſcarry of her birth: but will uſe mine Art and lead my life piouſly and chaſtly. I will cut none for the ſtone, but leave that to skilful Chyrurgions. In what houſe ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I come, it ſhall be for the good of the ſick, and will abſtain from offering any voluntary injury, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in any Veneral way to any ſuch as I ſhall have to cure, men or women, bond or free</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:58567:14"/>

               <pb facs="tcp:58567:15"/>

               <pb facs="tcp:58567:15"/>
Whatſoever I ſhall ſee or hear during my cure, yea though I were not called to give phyſick, but as it were being in a common conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of life, if they be not things fitting to be revealed, I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal and keep them ſecret to my ſelf. If I obſerve this oath faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, may I thrive and proſper in mine Art and Living, and grow famous to poſterity. Or may the contrary happen to me upon breach of it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table">
            <pb facs="tcp:58567:16"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58567:16"/>
            <head>An exact Table ſhewing every Aphoriſm pertaining to every diſeaſe.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Note the firſt number ſtands for Aphoriſm, the ſecond for Section.</p>
            </argument>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>Of ſickneſs of the head.</label>
REad Aph. 71. Sect. 4. 64. 5. 67. 5. 40. 2. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 10. 6. 22. 6. 51. 6. Lethargie, read <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. 7. dead-ſleep 1. 2. Overmuch waking 3. 2. Apoplexie 57. 6. 42. 2. 43. 2 Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly 24. 6. 56. 6. 11. 6. 9. 4. Madneſs 22. 6. 5. 7. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ating 53. 6. Sleep 2. 2. Falling-ſickneſs 46 2. 8. 5.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:17"/>
                  <label>Of the diſpoſitions of the Sinews.</label>
Palſie 18. 5. Cramp 57. 4. 66. 4. 67. 4. 79. 4. 1. 5. 2. 5. 3: 5. 4. 5. 6. 5. 7. 5. 18. 5. 17. 5. 23. 5. 39. 6. 9. 7. 10. 7. 13. 7. 18. 7. 26. 7. Aſtoniſhment. 14. 7. Of the wry mouth, noſe, or lips, 49. 4.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of the diſpoſitions if the Eys.</label>
12. 3. 13. 3. 14: 3: 18. 3: 17. 3. 22. 3, 49. 4. 52. 4. 17. 6. 31. 6. 52. 6. 47. 7.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of the diſpoſitions of the Ears.</label>
49; 4.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of the diſpoſitions of the Noſe.</label>
2. 6. 40. 2. 23. 3: 14. 3, 15. 3:
32, 3. 36. 7. 25. 5. Flux of blood 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:17"/>

                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:18"/>

                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:18"/>
at the Noſe. 37. 3. 27. 4. 60: 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 75. 4. 32. 5, 10. 6. 9. 7; Neeſing 34. 5. 12. 6. 52. 7.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of the divers diſpoſitions of the Mouth and Tongue.</label>
25. 3. 32. 6. Diſpoſitions of the Teeth. 26. 3. 53. 4. 26. 3. Of the effects of the Throat, 23: 3. 34. 4. 37. 4. 11. 5. 37. 6. 60. 7.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Affects of the Breaſt and Lungs.</label>
68. 4. Aſthma 46. 6. the voice, 6. 5. 51. 5. 47. 7. ſpitting of blood, 30. 3 67. 4. 47. 4. 14. 5. 10. 6: 15. 7. 37. 8. Pluriſie 12. 1. 6. 3. 24. 3. 9. 5. 16. 5: 16. 6. 33. 6 Peripneumo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia 34. 6. 12. 7. Enpiema or ſpitting of matter 27. 6. Pthiſick 11. 3. 14
3. 23. 3, 30. 3. 8. 4. 10. 5. 15, 5. 13. 5. 16. 5, 64. 5. 16. 7.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:58567:19"/>
               <item>
                  <label>Affects of the Heart.</label>
66. 4. Affects of the paps, 36. 5. 27. 5. 38. 5 39. 5 50. 5 52 5, 54 5</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Affects of the Stomack.</label>
15. 1. 18. 1. 33. 2. Difficulty of ſwallowing, 35. 4. Pain of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, 66. 4. 21. 2. Of thirſt 27. 5
Vomiting, 2. 1. 7. 4. 22. 4. 10. 7. Of the Hicket 45. 13. 6. 15 6. 17. 7.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Affects of the Liver.</label>
Pain of the Liver, 53 7. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſthumes of the Liver, 60, 5. 18. 6. 46. 7. Dropſie 23. 3. 86. 22. 6. 11 4. 35 6. 43 6. 5. 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 48. 7. 46. 7. Of the hypocondres 64. 4. 74. 4. 64. 5. 40. 6.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:19"/>

                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:20"/>

                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:20"/>
                  <label>Affects of the Gall and Spleen.</label>
Jaundies, 64. 4. 63. 4. 71. 5. 42
6. Of the Spleen 23. 3. 43. 6. 48. 6</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Fluxes of all kinds.</label>
14. 2. 21. 4: 22. 4: 23. 4. 24. 4. 26. 4. 28. 4 49. 5. 1. 6. 3. 6. 32. 6
43. 6. 48. 6. 5. 7: 24. 7. 30. 7. 31. 7
Pains of the inteſtines, 11. 4. 49. 4
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 6. 7. 6. Iliac paſſion 44. 6. 10. 7</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Affects of the Fundament.</label>
11: 6. 12. 6. Affects of the reins 6. 4. 80. 4. 7. 6 35. 7. 36. 7. 37. 7. 55. 7</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Affects of the Bladder.</label>
17. 3. 23. 3. 27. 3. 32. 3. 70. 4. 71. 4 73. 4. 72. 4. 74. 4. 75. 4 70
4. 76. 4. 77. 4. 75. 4: 80. 4. 82. 4. 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:21"/>
83.2. 84.4 58.5 19.6. 44.4. 32. 7. 34.7. 35.7. 39.7. 40.7. 49<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>7.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Affects of the members of Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in men.</label>
63. 5. 19. 6.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of the affects of the members of Generation in women.</label>
13.3. 1.4. 28.5. 29 5. 5 30. 5.31. 5
32.5. 33.5. 34 5. 35.5. 36.5: 37
5. 38.5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.6. 40.5. 41.5. 42.5. 43 5. 44.5. 45.5. 46.5. 47.5. 48.5 49.5. 50.5. 51.5 52.5. 53
5. 54.5. 55.5. 56.5. 57.5. 59.5. 60.5. 61.5. 62.5. 28.7.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of the Affects that do appear in the Exteame parts.</label>
46.2. 20.4. 31.4. 33.4. 44.4. 25.5. 21.6. 22.6, 28.6. 29.6. 30

<pb facs="tcp:58567:21"/>

                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:22"/>

                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:22"/>
6. 34.6. 49.7. 49.6. 55 6. 59 6. 60.5.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Aphoriſms touching Feavers.</label>
12.1. 14.1. 23.2. 25.2. 26.2:
28.2. 30.2. 34.2. 7.3. 8.3. 10.3. 12.3. 22.3. 29.4. 31.4. 44.4. 43. 4. 46.4. 48.4. 45.4. 49.4. 50.4. 51.4 52.4. 53.4. 55.4. 56.4. 67. 4. 50.4. 60.4. 62.4. 63.4. 94.4. 66.4. 67.4 68.4. 69.4. 26.6. 54
6. 71.4.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of Diet to be obſerved in Feavers.</label>
4.1. 5.1. 6.1. 7.1. 8.1. 9.1. 10
1. 11.1. 13.1. 14.1. 15.1. 16.1. 17.1. 18.1. 19.1.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:58567:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58567:23"/>
            <head>The <hi>Aphoriſms</hi> of <hi>Hippocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> Prince of Phyſicians.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>This firſt Section doth for the moſt part handle the Dietary part of Phyſicck, preſcribing not onely the meaſure and obſervation in meats and drinks for ſound bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, but alſo for thoſe that are ſick and diſeaſed, with a modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Labour and Exerciſe.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APHORISM. 1.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ife <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is ſhort, the art is long, occaſion ſuddain, experince dangerous, judgement difficult. Neither is it ſuffent that the Phyſician doe his office, unleſs the Patient, and thoſe which are attendants about him do their duty, and that outward 
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58567:24"/>
things be as well ordered, as thoſe that are given inwardly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm is as it were an Introduction or Proeme to the whole Work.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 2.</head>
                  <p>In diſtemperatures, looſneſſes, Fluxes of the belly, and Vomitings which do com of their own accord if ſuch things be purged as ought to be purged, they are eaſily endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and are profitable, otherwiſe it falleth out contrary. In like ſort if an emptying of veſſels be done as it ſhould be, it doth good as is eaſily ſuffered, otherwiſe it doth work contrary effects. Wherefore conſideration is to be had both of the region and the time, and alſo of the age and the quality of the diſeaſe for which ſuch things ought to be evacuated, or elſe not.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the Phyſician ought in all 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb facs="tcp:58567:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb n="3" facs="tcp:58567:25"/>
things to imitate and aſſiſt Nature.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 3.</head>
                  <p>The full habit and ſtate of the bodies of wreſtlers, if it comes to the higheſt degree of fulneſs is dangerous; for it cannot conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue and remain in the ſame ſtate, and when it cannot ſo remain nor grow into a better habit, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, that it muſt needs decline into a worſe. Wherefore that over full plight of body muſt ſpeedily be diſſolved, to the end it may take a beginning of new nouriſhment: Neither muſt we proceed ſo far that the veſſels be quite empty, and void (for that is dangerous) but we muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed ſo far as Nature will bear and tolerate. So extreme evacuations are perilous, and extreme repleti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are likewiſe dangerous.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The former Aphoriſm was of the quality of humors to be evacuated 
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58567:26"/>
now this and thoſe which follow, treat of the quantity.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 4.</head>
                  <p>A ſmall and ſlender diet in long and lingering diſeaſes is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways dangerous, and in ſharp diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes likewiſe, when it is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, and again diet reduced to extreme ſlenderneſs, is as full of peril, as extreme repletion, and fulneſs in laborious and painful.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In this Aphoriſm Hippocrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
ſpeaks, of the diet which fick men ought to uſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 5.</head>
                  <p>The ſick may offend in a ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der diet, for thereby it happeneth that they grow worſe, for every error in this caſe is more danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, then in a ſomwhat fuller diet. For the ſame cauſe, a very ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and too preciſe a diet, is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what dangerous to ſound and healthful bodies, becauſe they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:58567:27"/>
the errors thereof with more difficulty. Wherefore a thin and exact manner of diet, for the moſt part is more dangerous, then that which is a little more full and plentiful then ſhould be.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith for the moſt part; for Hippocrates meaning is not that a ſlender diet is abſolutely hurtful.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 6.</head>
                  <p>To extreme diſeaſes, extreme and exquiſite remedies are beſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Extreme diſeaſes are call'd thoſe which are moſt ſharp and acute.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 7.</head>
                  <p>When therefore the diſeaſe is very ſharp and hath preſently moſt extreme paſſions and pains, we muſt uſe a moſt exceeding ſlender diet when it is ſo. But when it is not ſo, we may uſe a fuller diet, and as the diſeaſe declineth, we may by little increaſe the diet.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By paſſions and pains he means 
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58567:28"/>
ſymptomes, which in theſe very ſharp diſeaſes are ſeldom but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ompanied with hot Feavers.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 8.</head>
                  <p>When the force of the diſeaſe is greateſt, then a moſt ſparing diet is to be obſerved.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm enjoyns that in general which the former doth give order to be done in ſome particular diſeaſes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 9.</head>
                  <p>But we muſt conſider and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture by the ſick man, whether he be able to hold out, and perſiſt with the preſcribed diet, even to the ſtate and uttermoſt extremity of the diſeaſe, or may faint or fail and being too weak with ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, may yield the victory to the diſeaſe, before it retire, and be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For if the patient were able to indure without food, till the extre-<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                           <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 
                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:58567:29"/>
or courſe: in the recourſe of thoſe fits, we muſt uſe abſtinence.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm ſpeaks of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting diſeaſes, which leave men for a ſeaſon, and then return again.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 12.</head>
                  <p>The fits and kinds of the diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the ſeaſons of the year, and the obſervation of the alteration of the times of the fits return, if they come again every other day, or after a longer interval of time, will ſhew the ſharp invaſions or extremities of the diſeaſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſigns and tokens are taken from thoſe things which appear afterwards, as for example in a Pluriſie, if the corrupt matter, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided by ſpitting, appear preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the beginning, it declares the diſeaſe will be but ſhort; but if it be longer before it do appear, it declareth a longer continuance of it. Moreover Urines, excrements 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:58567:30"/>
of the belly, and ſwets declare whither the diſeaſes will prove ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, or difficult, ſhort or long.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For if diſeaſes come in ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, they will for the moſt part proceed from choller, and the fits come every third day, and laſt a ſhort time, if in wiuter they will proceed chiefly from Phlegm, the fits come every day and laſt lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 13.</head>
                  <p>Old men eaſily endure faſting, thoſe who are in their declining age not ſo well, young men worſe, and children worſt of all, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thoſe who are of a more live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Old when they are above 50 un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til 70, for thoſe who are decrepit ought to feed often, but a little at a time.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 14.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe bodies that grow, have 
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58567:31"/>
much natural heat, therefore they require great ſtore of food, or elſe the body conſumeth. But old men have little heat in them, therefore they require but a little food: for much nouriſhment extinguiſheth that heat. And this is the reaſon that old men have not very acute Feavers, becauſe their bodies are not ſo hot.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm ſhews the reaſons of the precedent, namely why old men can endure faſting better then young men and children.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH, 15.</head>
                  <p>The venters by nature are moſt hot in winter, and in the Spring, and ſleep moſt long. Wherefore in thoſe ſeaſons more abundant food ought to be allowed, becauſe they have moſt natural heat; whereby it cometh to paſs, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
they need more abundant food. Of which thing the differences of 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:58567:32"/>
ages, and wreſtlers bodies, are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient proofs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Venters are the ſtomach and bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. And ſleep increaſeth the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral heat.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 16.</head>
                  <p>Moiſt diet is good for all that are troubled with Agues, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for children and others who are accuſtomed to ſuch diet.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe Agues are dry, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe cuſtom is a kind of an acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red nature.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 17.</head>
                  <p>We muſt alſo conſider whom it may be convenient to feed once or twice a day, more or leſs, and by little and little: we muſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute ſomething alſo to cuſtom, age, ſeaſon, and region.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Having before ſpoken of the quantity and quality of food which may be given, he now ſpeaks how it ought to be given, wherein he ſaith 
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58567:33"/>
cuſtom, time, country, and age ought to be conſidered.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 18.</head>
                  <p>Sick folk do moſt hardly brook ſtore of meat in Summer, in Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter moſt eaſily, in the Spring time in a meaner manner.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Here he expounds more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly what he ſpoke generally in the former Aphoriſm, and ſaith that in Summer they brook no ſtore of food, the reaſon is becauſe then the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive heat is weak and languiſheth, and in Autumn the bodies are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, but in Winter, the Venters (namely the ſtomach and thoſe parts) are very hot, and their ſleep is long, and in the Spring the natural heat evaporates more then in Wiuter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 19.</head>
                  <p>Nothing muſt be given to them neither muſt they be conſtrained to take meat, which have fits re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:58567:34"/>
at certain determined courſes: but we ought to dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh food, before manifeſt tokens appeare to judge of the diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To the end that Nature may not be called away from its concoction and digeſtion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 20.</head>
                  <p>We ought not to move, alter, or change thoſe things which are or juſtly have been juſtly determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Nature, either with medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines or other procurements, but to let them alone.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe Nature by her determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation having ſhewn ſhe is of herſelf ſtrong enough, needs no help of art.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 21</head>
                  <p>Carry thoſe things which are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o be drawn out thither whether they ſhall ſeem to encline and bend, by ſuch ways and places as are fitteſt for conveyance and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:58567:35"/>
                     <hi>If Nature be not able of her ſelf (as in the former Aphoriſm) to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel the cauſe of the diſeaſe, then let Art help, to do it that way as Nature enclines.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 22.</head>
                  <p>We muſt move with Medicine thoſe things which are concocted and digeſted, and not thoſe which are raw and undigeſted. Neither in the beginning of diſeaſes, unleſs they be provoked by their own force and violence, which very ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom cometh to paſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nature after concoction doth ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregate and expel humors; which if ſhe be too languid to do, then it is good to help it with medicines.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 23.</head>
                  <p>Things evacuated and purged
are not to be eſtimated by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
multitude, but adviſedly to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered if thoſe things be avoided and ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>forth, which ſhould and <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                        <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:58567:36"/>
purged, which ſhould be, it doth good, and the ſick may eaſily ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it, but if the contrary be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacuated, they do painfully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Having in this latter part of this Section ſpoken of purges given by Phyſicians. He ſets down this to put us again in mind of thoſe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations which come voluntarily from Nature. Having ſaid the ſame thing of them in the ſecond Aphoriſm.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:58567:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:58567:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:58567:37"/>
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>This ſecond Section, of which the univerſal and plenary intention cannot well be aſſigned and ſet down, hath many things apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to the Doctrine of Ages, Signes, Nature, and Purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 1.</head>
                  <p>IF ſleep bring labour and pain in the diſeaſe, it is a mortal ſign: but if it bring eaſe and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigation of pain, the ſign is not deadly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sleep may hurt in two kindes:
the one is common, when ſick men ſleep in the beginning of their fits. The other is proper when they ſlelp 
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58567:38"/>
at any other times. Here we muſt conceive he ſpeaks of the laſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 2.</head>
                  <p>When a Delirium or raving is appeaſed by ſleep, it is a good ſigne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This is an example of the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal aſſertion in the preceding A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoriſm, now the reaſon of it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe nothing cauſeth and nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth raving more then want of ſleep; therefore if that cauſe it to ceaſe, it is a ſigne death is approaching.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 3</head>
                  <p>Sleep and watching, if they be immoderate, and ſhall exceed a mean, are evil.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For all immoderate things are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies and adverſe to Nature, and too much ſleep is a ſign that the brain is too cool and moiſt, and too little argues that it is too dry.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 4.</head>
                  <p>Neither ſatiety nor hunger, 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:58567:39"/>
neither any other thing which ſhall exceed the meaſure of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, can be good or healthful.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For health is defined to be a ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry and juſt proportion, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides too much faſting fils the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricle with evil humors.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 5.</head>
                  <p>Wearineſs and dulneſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of their own accord, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie diſeaſes to come.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Namely ſuch a wearineſs as comes, without any immoderate ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of the body.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 6.</head>
                  <p>They which ſuffer pain of any part of the body, and do not in a manner feel it, have their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding diſtempered and diſeaſed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That is to ſay, have any diſeaſe or ſore which cauſeth pain, and they feel it not.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 7.</head>
                  <p>Bodies extenuated and waſted 
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58567:40"/>
with long ſickneſs, are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored and refreſhed by little and little, but thoſe which have been brought low quickly and in ſhort time, are ſooner to be reſtored.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For in thoſe who are waſted with long ſickneſs, the fleſh is waſted; in thoſe who are quickly brought low, the ſpirits onely, which may ſooner be reſtored then the fleſh.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 8.</head>
                  <p>If any man eating meat after ſickneſs, doth not recover ſtrength it argues his body is burthened and oppreſſed with too much ſtore of food. But if the ſame happen to one feeding meanly, we muſt underſtand that he hath need of evacuation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe the body being oppreſſed with noxious humors, they hinder concoction, wherefore the ſaid hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors muſt firſt be evacuated.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="aphorism">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:58567:41"/>
                  <head>APH. 9.</head>
                  <p>How much the more thou ſhalt nouriſh and cheriſh impure bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, by ſo much the more thou ſhalt harm and hurt them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This gives a reaſon of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Aphoriſm. Namely, becauſe the aliment which you give to ſuch bodies increaſes the quantity of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious humors.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 10.</head>
                  <p>He who will purge bodies, muſt firſt make them fluxible.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Which may be done two ways, either by opening the paſſages, or by cutting off and extennating the thick humors.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 11.</head>
                  <p>It is more eaſie to be reſtored with drink then with meat.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That is to ſay with a liquid ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for that is ſooner altered and diſtributed then a ſolid, and if yet greater ſpeed be required, they may be recreated with odours.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:58567:42"/>
                  <head>APH. 12.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe things which are left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind after the Cryſis, are wont to bring forth relapſes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Left becauſe the matter was not fit to be expeld, or Nature was ſo weakened by ſickneſs, that it was not able to expel all the noxious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 13.</head>
                  <p>The night which goeth before the fit or invaſion is tedious, but the night following is commonly more eaſie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We feel the pains of diſeaſes more by night, then by day, becauſe in the day time, all the ſenſes being awaked are imployed about ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 14.</head>
                  <p>The alteration of the excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, not made to the worſe part in fluxes of the belly is good.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe it is a ſign that thoſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xious 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb facs="tcp:58567:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:58567:43"/>
humors which by the excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments appeared to be in the body, are voided and gone.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 15.</head>
                  <p>When the upper parts of the throat or gullet are ſore or a breaking out of wheals doth ariſe in the body, it behoveth us to look upon the excrements, for if they be cholerick, the body is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſick, but if they be like the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements of ſound perſons, the body may be cheriſhed without danger.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For if the excrements make no ſhow of any further inward diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes thoſe wheals ſignifie that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath been ſtrong enough of her ſelf to drive out the evil humors into thoſe external parts of the body.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 16.</head>
                  <p>When hunger beareth ſway, we muſt reſt from much ſtirring or labour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:58567:44"/>
                     <hi>For hunger and exerciſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, would caſt down ſtrength, and dry up the bodie too much.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 17.</head>
                  <p>When over much meat is recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved againſt Nature, it cauſeth ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as the manner of curing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes proceeding from repletion doth declare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe it oppreſſes Nature now thoſe diſeaſes are cured by evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which ſhews they were cauſed by repletion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 18.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe thlngs which nouriſh ſpeedily and plentifully, are quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excreted and voided.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For being ſpeedily concocted and digeſted the excrements muſt alſo of neceſſity have a ſpeedy paſſage.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 19.</head>
                  <p>Praedictions of death or health in ſharp diſeaſes are not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther certain.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:58567:45"/>
                     <hi>By reaſon of the ſuddain chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which happen in them, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Nature of the humors; which cauſe thoſe ſharp diſeaſes:
and becauſe the moleſtant humor runs out of one part into another.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 20.</head>
                  <p>They which in young age have a moiſt and looſe belly, in old age have it dry. But thoſe who have it dry in their young age, have it moiſt when they are old.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of thoſe who continue in the ſame diet when they are old, which they uſed in their younger years, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it would not be any way remarkable.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 21.</head>
                  <p>Drinking of ſtrong wine, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth away hunger.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By hunger here is meant a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe which is called Appetitus Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninus, or Appetentia Canina, and 
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58567:46"/>
thoſe who are diſeaſed therewith can never be ſatisfyed, though they eat never ſo much.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 22.</head>
                  <p>Diſeaſes which are bred of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiety and ſurfeting are cured by evacuation and thoſe which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from emptineſs are cured by fulneſs, and ſo in the reſt, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are the remedies of contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Neither muſt theſe contraries be uſed in an extreme degree, for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too much repletion nor too much evacuation can conveniently be endured.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 23.</head>
                  <p>Acute and ſharp diſeaſes are judged within fourteen days.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Though ſome may be judged be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, yet fourteen days is the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt day that can be expected for the judgement or Cryſis of ſuch diſeaſes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="aphorism">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:58567:47"/>
                  <head>APH. 24</head>
                  <p>The fourth day is the Index of the ſeventh, the eighth the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the week following. Alſo the eleventh day is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, for that is the fourth day of the ſecond week And again the ſeventeenth day is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, being the fourth from the fourteenth, and the ſeventh from the eleventh.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He hath taught us that acute diſeaſes run out to a Cryſis within fourteen days, which he here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains, and ſhews which are the Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical days for three weeks together.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 25.</head>
                  <p>Summer Quartan Feavers are for the moſt part ſhort: but the Autumnal long, eſpecially thoſe which remain till Winter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe in Summer the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous humors being driven into the outward parts of the body, are 
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58567:48"/>
quickly expelled through the pores, but they laſt longer in Autumn, for they are ſome way peculiar to that ſeaſon, becauſe by the forerunning Summer the faculties of the body are weakened, and in Winter by reaſon that then the humors are thickened, and the pores ſhut up by the ambient cold. And this is but for the moſt part, for ſometimes it may prove otherways.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 26.</head>
                  <p>It is better that a Feaver ſhould ſucceed a Convulſion, then Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſion a Feaver.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For if a Convulſion precede a Feaver, it proceeds from fulneſs, which is eaſily cured by evacuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but if it ſucceeds it proceeds from emptineſs, and is very danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for the Patient.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 27.</head>
                  <p>We ought not to be too confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent if a ſharp diſeaſe ſlacken 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:58567:49"/>
without any reaſon. Neither much fear thoſe diſeaſes which happen without any reaſon. For moſt of them are uncertain, and do not uſually laſt long.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For if it ſlacken without reaſon, it threatens a relapſe, and if it come without reaſon, it is not much to be feared, for it will fall having no good foundation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 28.</head>
                  <p>If the body of thoſe which have a ſharp Feaver abide all at one ſtay, and is nothing abated, or elſe is melted and waſted away beyond reaſon, it is a very evil ſigne, for the firſt doth ſignifie a continuance of the diſeaſe, and the latter a great imbecility of Nature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the firſt is cauſed by a den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity or thickneſs of the skin, and thickneſs and gluttinouſneſs of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, and the latter by a thinneſs 
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58567:50"/>
or tenuity of the skin, and extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of humors which commonly is followed by imbecility of Nature.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 29.</head>
                  <p>In the beginning of diſeaſes if there appears cauſe for moving of any thing; move it. But when they are in their ſtate it is far better to let it alone.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The reaſon of this Aphoriſm is laid down in the next.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 30.</head>
                  <p>Abo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the beginnings and ends of diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> all things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
calm and remiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>d
ſtate more vehement.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm is but the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the precedent, and explains the formers and its own meaning.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 31.</head>
                  <p>If the body thrive not with him who after a diſeaſe feedeth well it is an evil ſign.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For it ſignifies one of theſe two 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb facs="tcp:58567:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb n="31" facs="tcp:58567:51"/>
things, namely that he takes more food, then Nature (yet weakened by ſickneſs) can digeſt. Or that there is yet ſuch abundance of evil humors left in the ventricle and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of the body, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is put into it preſently cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts with them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 32.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which in the beginning of ſickneſs feed much, and do not thrive therewith, for the moſt part do at laſt fall into a loathing of meat. On the contrary, thoſe who in the beginning do vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently abhor food, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards deſire much meat, are more eaſily freed from their ſickneſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe feeding hard whilſt there be yet reliques of evil humors re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in the body, increaſes the quantity of thoſe evil humors, and ſo hinders their convaleſcencie. Whereas thoſe who feed ſparingly in 
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58567:52"/>
the beginning oppreſs not the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Nature, which increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing do at laſt expel thoſe remain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders of evil humors.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 33.</head>
                  <p>In any diſeaſe, if reaſon be not weakened nor hurt, but that it is willing to embrace ſuch meats as are proffered it, it is good, but if it be otherwiſe it is evil.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe to have ones good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding ſound, ſignifies that the brain and all the nervous parts, with the Liver, Heart, and Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricles are alſo well affected, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as if the Reaſon be hurt, it ſignifies that both the Brain and Ventricle are out of frame.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 34.</head>
                  <p>They are not ſo dangerouſly ſick, to whoſe nature, age, habit, or ſeaſon, the diſeaſe is familiar and agreeable; as they to whom the diſeaſe is not agreeable to any of thoſe things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:58567:53"/>
                     <hi>By Nature here is meant the temperament of the body, by habit:
whether a body be compoſed of a ſoft and tender fleſh, or of a thick and ſolid. Age, and ſeaſon are eaſie to be known what they mean, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver for examples ſake, acute Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers are not common to old age, the body being then cold, and likely are deadly in old men. And what diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes have moſt affinity with each ſeaſon of the year, is ſhewn in the third Section, the Aphoriſms 20, 21, 22, 23.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 35.</head>
                  <p>It is better in any diſeaſe that the parts adjoyning to the Navel and nethermoſt belly be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what thick and groſs: for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuation and conſumption of them is evil, and then it is not ſafe to miniſter purgations working downward.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe the thickneſs and groſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs 
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58567:54"/>
of thoſe parts ſignifie that the native heat is more valid, and the concoction better.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 36.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which are endued with health of body, do quickly faint drinking a purging potion: and ſo do thoſe which uſe bad and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nouriſhment.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For in healthful men, the purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing potion finding no vicious nor redundant humor to draw out and evacuate, doth firſt diſſipate the ſpirits, then diſſolves thoſe parts which are humid and moiſt, and finally corrupts thoſe which are ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid. And thoſe which uſe bad food have ſharp and biting humors, which being by the medicament dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven through the ſenſible parts of the body do cauſe fainting:</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="37" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 37.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which are of ſound and perfect health of body, do pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:58567:55"/>
and grievouſly endure purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing medicines.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm is more general then the former, which expreſſed but one ſymptome which befals ſound men when they are purged. But this includes all the reſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="38" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 38.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe meats and drinks which are worſe, yet pleaſant, are to be preferred before thoſe which are better, but yet unpleaſant and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſting.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe they pleaſe the Patient beſt, and becauſe the Ventricle doth more greedily embrace, and ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier concoct thoſe meats and drinks which are pleaſant.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="39" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 39.</head>
                  <p>For the moſt part old men are not ſo often ſick as young are: But being once taken with long diſeaſes they commonly dye.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Old men are preſumed to be more 
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58567:56"/>
diſcreet and temperate in their feeding which is the cauſe of this aſſertion for thoſe which are not ſo, are more ſubject to ſickneſs then young men, being weaker then they.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="40" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 40.</head>
                  <p>Rheums deſcending down to the mouth, and falling down to the throat do not come to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction in thoſe which are very old.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This is as it were an example of the latter aſſertion of the precedent Aphoriſm, namely that old men once taken with long diſeaſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly dye.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="41" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 41.</head>
                  <p>They dye ſuddenly which do often, and vehemently ſwoun and faint without any manifeſt cauſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe it argueth an imbecili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the vital faculty.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="42" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 42.</head>
                  <p>It is impoſſible to cure a vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:58567:57"/>
Apoplexie and very hard to cure a weak one.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For all Apoplexies are cauſed by a ſtopping of the animal Faculties from deſcending any lower into the body then the head.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="43" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 43.</head>
                  <p>Strangled &amp; ſuffocated folk, being not as yet dead, do not return to themſelves, if there appear any foam about their mouth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe it is a ſign that the Lights are violently wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="44" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 44.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which are very groſs by Nature, do enjoy ſhorter life then thoſe which are lean.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe fat mens native heat is weaker then lean mens.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="45" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 45.</head>
                  <p>Change and alteration of place, and diet, and eſpecially of age, free children from the falling evil.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:58567:58"/>
                     <hi>For when they come to their youthful age they are cured by their hot and dry temperament.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="46" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 46.</head>
                  <p>Of two pains at one time, not poſſeſſing the ſelf-ſame place, that which is the moſt vehement, doth dull the pain of the other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It doth neither cure nor expel the other, but onely dull and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="47" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 47.</head>
                  <p>Whiles filthy and corrupt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is digeſting, pains and Agues do rather happen, then when it is come to maturation</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For when it is maturated the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation and burning ceaſeth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="48" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 48.</head>
                  <p>In every exerciſe of the body, when it beginneth to be wearied, reſt doth preſently mitigate the wearineſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For as he ſaid in the two and 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb facs="tcp:58567:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb n="39" facs="tcp:58567:59"/>
twentieth Aphoriſm of this Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, one contrary is the cure of the other.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="49" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 49</head>
                  <p>Thoke who are accuſtomed to daily labours, although they be weak or old men, do more eaſily endure accuſtomed exerciſes, then thoſe who are not accuſtomed to them, although they be ſtrong and young</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe cuſtom is a ſecond nature</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="50" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 50.</head>
                  <p>Things accuſtomed a long time, although they be worſe are wont to be leſs grievous, then thoſe which are unaccuſtomed, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo a change is not to be made to unaccuſtomed things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe the bodies are ſubject to changes, therefore upon ſuch chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges we muſt alſo fall upon ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accuſtomed diet.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="51" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:58567:60"/>
                  <head>APH. 51.</head>
                  <p>It is danderous at one time, much and ſuddainly, either to empty, fill, heat or cool, or by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other means to move or ſtir the body. For any thing paſſing the bonnds of mediocrity is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to Nature, and that is ſafe which is done by little and little, and eſpecially when an alteration and change is to be made from one thing to another.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Namely from accuſtomed to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accuſtomed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="52" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 52.</head>
                  <p>He muſt not paſs forthwith from one medicine to another, when all things fall not out ſo well as they ſhould, to him; who doth proceed by good reaſon; ſo that remain ſtill and continue which ſeemed to him to be ſo from the Beginning.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For it is no point of wiſdom light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb facs="tcp:58567:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb n="41" facs="tcp:58567:61"/>
to recede from that which once you have approved of, though it doth not preſentely work as you would have it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="53" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 53.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which have a moiſt bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, paſs their youthful age more eaſily then thoſe which have the ſame dry: but they paſs their old age more hardly and with more difficulty, for when they wax old, for the moſt part it is dryed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm is of it ſelf plain enough, and compared with the 20
Aphoriſm of this Section, they expound one another.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="54" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 54.</head>
                  <p>Greatneſs and tallneſs of body is comely to the ſtate of young age: but to old age it is improfita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and worſe then a ſhort ſtature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For it burdeneth old men, and makes them go ſtooping and crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:58567:62"/>
               <head>SECT: III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>This third book is almoſt reduced to the diſcourſe of ages or times, expreſſing unto us two common places, that is to ſay the ſtrength and force of ages, and the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of diſeaſes throughout thoſe ages, and times.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APHORISM. 1.</head>
                  <p>ALteration and variableneſs of the ſeaſons, do moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially bring forth diſeaſes, and likewiſe great alterations of cold and heat in thoſe ſeaſons, and of other things anſwering to them in proportion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe they alter the air which we draw in continually with our breaths.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="aphorism">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:58567:63"/>
                  <head>APH. 2.</head>
                  <p>Some natures are well or ill af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in Summer, and ſome in Winter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By natures he means the tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratures:
and of them the cold and moiſt temperatures fare beſt in Summer, and the hot and dry worſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 3.</head>
                  <p>Some diſeaſes are well or ill affected, ſome more to one time, and ſome to another, and ſome ages more to ſome one time, place and kind of dyet then they are to another.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He now affirms that to be true in diſeaſes and ages, which he had in the precedent Aphoriſm aſſerted in temperatures of the body.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 4.</head>
                  <p>Autumnal diſeaſes are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected in thoſe ſeaſons, when on the ſelf-ſame day it is ſometimes hot, and ſometimes cold.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:58567:64"/>
                     <hi>For not the names but the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratures of the ſeaſons, are the cauſes of diſeaſes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 5.</head>
                  <p>The South wind dulleth the hearing, obſcureth and darkneth the ſight, offendeth the head with aches and rheumes, procureth and cauſeth heavineſs and faintneſs in the members. When therefore it is frequent and bloweth often, ſuch things are incident to the weak and ſickly. Contrariwiſe the North wind cauſeth coughs, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperateth and excoriateth the jaws, hardens the belly, ſuppreſſeth U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, ſtirs up cold ſhiverings and ſhakings, ingendereth the pains of the ſides and breaſt. Therefore when this wind bears ſway thoſe that are weak and feeble muſt, look for ſuch accidents.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The South wind by reaſon of its hot and moiſt Nature, and the north 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb facs="tcp:58567:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb n="45" facs="tcp:58567:65"/>
wind becauſe of its cold and dryneſs do work theſe effects in weak bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 6.</head>
                  <p>When the Summer is like the Spring time, we muſt expect much ſweating in Agues.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe by its temperate and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate heat, it draws the humidities of the body to the skin, but cannot diſſolve them into vapors.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 7.</head>
                  <p>Sharp Agues are ingendred by great drought and dryneſs, and if the year prove to be for the moſt part ſuch; as the ſtate of the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, ſuch kinds of diſeaſes for the moſt part muſt be ſo expected.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sharp Agues are thoſe which quickly end, but have heavy and troubleſome ſymptomes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 8.</head>
                  <p>In certain &amp; moderate times, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving their ſeaſonablenes, certain 
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:58567:66"/>
and ſeaſonable diſeaſes having a happy determination are ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. But in uncertain and immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate times, uncertain diſeaſes are ingendred; and evil to be judged.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For diſeaſes follow the nature of the efficient cauſes, and the efficient cauſes are likely ſuch as the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature of the year is.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 9.</head>
                  <p>In Autumn univerſally there are moſt ſharp and deadly diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes:
but the ſpring time is moſt wholeſom, and free from deadly diſeaſes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The reaſons whereof are, firſt by reaſon of its ineqnality, the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and evenings being cold and the midday hot. Secondly, becauſe the preceding Summer hath made the humors aduſt. Thirdly; becauſe the ſaid Summer hath weakened the forces. Fourthly, becauſe the 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb facs="tcp:58567:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:58567:67"/>
morning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and evenings ambient coldneſs drives the vicious humors into the body. And fiftly, becauſe there is abundance of fruits eaten in that ſeaſon, the eating of which breeds ſtore of evil humors.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 10.</head>
                  <p>Autumn is hurtful to ſuch as are in a conſumption.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By reaſon of its dryneſs, coldneſs, and inequality.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 11.</head>
                  <p>Amongſt the parts of the year if the Winter be extraordinary dry, and the Spring very rainy, and ſubject to ſoutherly winds. It muſt of neceſſity fall out that in Summer, ſharp Agues, Rheums in the Eys and Bloody-fluxes do happen, eſpecially to women and men who are of a moiſt nature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By reaſon of the abundance of humors which are ſubject to putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:58567:68"/>
                  <head>APH. 12.</head>
                  <p>Contrarily if Winter be South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ernly, full of rain and warm, and the Spring dry and northernly, women whoſe child-birth and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance happeneth neer the Spring, do upon the leaſt occaſion ſuffer abortment and untimely birth: or if they be delivered at their due time, they bring forth ſuch weak and diſeaſed children, that either they die quickly, or live but weakly and ſickly. To others there happen bloody-fluxes and hot inflammations of the eys, and to old men rheums which ſhortly kill them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſms meaning is plain enough now, the particular cauſes why theſe ſeveral diſeaſes happen are ſet down at large in</hi> Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens<hi>Comments to which we refer the Reader.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="aphorism">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:58567:69"/>
                  <head>APH. 13.</head>
                  <p>Summer being dry and the wind northernly, Autumn full of rain and the wind ſouthernly, vehement pains of the head are to be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the Winter following. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo coughs, hoarſneſſes, &amp; rheums, diſtillings at the noſtrils, and to ſome pining Conſumptions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Having in the preceding Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſms ſpoken of the Winter and Spring, he now ſpeaks of the other two ſeaſons, namely Summer and Autumn.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 14.</head>
                  <p>A northernly and dry Autumn is profitable and good to men which are of a moiſt temperature, and alſo to women, to others it cauſeth hot inflammations in the eys, and Feavers partly ſharp, and partly long, and ſome alſo are troubled with Melancholly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm ought to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the former as part of it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:58567:70"/>
                  <head>APH. 15.</head>
                  <p>Of all the ſeaſons throughout the whole yeer, dryneſs and droughts are more wholſom and leſs dangerous to mans life, then daily ſhowers of rain and moiſture</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm by right ſhould have been placed after the 17th of this Section, and the 17 after the 5, as</hi> Galen <hi>ſhews in his Comment up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this preſent Aphoriſm.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 16.</head>
                  <p>When there is much rain theſe diſeaſes for the moſt part are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred, namely long contlnuing Agues, Fluxes of the belly, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of humors, Falling-ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Apoplexies, Squinancies But when there is much drought there happen Conſumptions, Rheumes in the eys, pains of the joynts, difficulty in making Urine, and paſſions of the inteſtines or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:58567:71"/>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm is as it were an explication of the former, by which ſome ignorant men might infer that in a dry year, there would be no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes at all ingendred.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 17.</head>
                  <p>Daily ſeaſons of weather being northernly do cloſe and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the body and make it nimble, well coloured and quick of hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. They dry and harden the belly, but bite and offend the eys, and if any pain have poſſeſt the breaſt, they make it more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Contrariwiſe ſouthernly ſeaſons looſe and moiſten the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and weakens it, dull the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, cauſe heavineſs, and giddineſs of the head, miſtineſs and dimneſs of the eys, dulneſs and lazineſs of the body, and make the belly looſe and laxative.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the northern wind is cold and dry: and the ſouthern hot and moiſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:58567:72"/>
                  <head>APH. 18.</head>
                  <p>As touching ſeaſons of the year in the Spring and beginning of Summer, children and thoſe which are neereſt to them in age, live in very good health; in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and ſome part of Autumn old men live beſt, but in the reſt of Autumn and Winter they of a middle age.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Summer is good for old men by reaſon of the frigidity of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Winter for men in the ſtrength of their age, becauſe it abates and is contrary to their bilious temper.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 19.</head>
                  <p>Any diſeaſes, are ingendred in any times of the year, yet many are rather cauſed, and ſtirred, in ſome one more then in another.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Intending in the following Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſms to ſet down what diſeaſes are peculiar to ſeveral times of the year he promiſes this as a general one.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="aphorism">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:58567:73"/>
                  <head>APH. 20.</head>
                  <p>In the Spring there happeneth madneſs, melancholly, falling-e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, fluxes of blood, the ſquinancy, rheumes, diſtillations of humors, coughs, leproſies, dry ſcabs, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phues, and many ulcerous wheals, puſhes, and pains of the joynts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Which diſeaſes for the moſt part being not dangerous, but rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to health by driving out no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xious humors out of the inward to the outward parts of the body; this Aphoriſm rather confirms then op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes the latter part of the ninth A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoriſm.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 21</head>
                  <p>In Summer there are ſome of thoſe diſeaſes before ſpoken of; in the Spring alſo continual Feavers and burning Agues, and many Tertians, and Quartans, Vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, Fluxes of the belly, inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of the eys, pains of the 
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:58567:74"/>
ears, ulcerations of the mouth, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefactions of the genitals, and ſweatings,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Namely in the beginning of Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer are incident ſome of thoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes which were alſo towards the latter end of the Spring, for it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame temperature they muſt ingender the ſame diſeaſes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 22.</head>
                  <p>Alſo many Summer diſeaſes are in Autumn, both Quartans and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain wandring Agues, ſwellings of the Spleen, Hydropſie, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions, Strangury Looſeneſs &amp; excoriations of the bowels, aches of hucle-bone, Squinancies, ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of breath, ſtreight preſſings or drawing together of the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els in ſome part of them; the Falling-ſickneſs, madneſs, and melancholly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The beginning of Autumn, and end of Summer have the ſame affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:74" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb facs="tcp:58567:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb n="55" facs="tcp:58567:75"/>
as the beginning of Summer and end of the Spring.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 23.</head>
                  <p>In Winter are ingendred Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies, inflammations of Lungs Lethargie, Rheums in the noſtrils, hoarſneſs, coughs, pains of the breaſts, ſides, and loyns, head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aches, ſwimmings and giddineſſes of the head (cauſing dimneſs to the eys) and Apoplexies.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This and the precedent Aphoriſms concerning ſeaſons, are to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood when ſeaſons do hold their own order and temperature.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 24</head>
                  <p>But as concerning ages, theſe diſeaſes do happen to little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and lately born; Ulcers in the mouth, Vomiting, Coughs, want of ſleep, great fears, inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of the Navil, moiſt run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings at the ears.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Having ſpoken of the ſeaſons of 
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:58567:76"/>
diſeaſes he now ſets down in what ages ſuch and ſuch diſeaſes uſe to happen, beginning with infants newly born.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 25.</head>
                  <p>The time of Teeth-breeding coming, there happen itching of the gums, Feavers, Convulſions, Fluxes of the belly, eſpecially when they bring forth their dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teeth, and eſpecially thoſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren chiefly that are moſt fat, and have their belly bound.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Which time of teeth breeding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins commonly at ſeven moneths of age, and ſometimes at four: the dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teeth at a year or ten moneths.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 26.</head>
                  <p>When children begin to be a little elder, they are ſubject to the inflammations of the Almonds of the mouth, diſlocation of the turning joynts in the nape of the neck inwardly, ſhortneſs of wind, 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:76" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:77" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:58567:77"/>
breeding of the Stone, round-worms, gut-worms, long hanging warts, Satyraſms, Stranguries Scrophules in the neck and other riſings, eſpecially thoſe before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now he ſets down thoſe diſeaſes which children are ſubject to after they are paſt teeth-breeding, to twelve or fourteen years of age.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 27.</head>
                  <p>Moreover to thoſe which are greater and coming to ripe age, there happen many of thoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer diſeaſes, but more long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing Agues, and fluxes of blood at the noſtrils.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm concerns children about twelve, thirteen, or fourteen years of age, and ripeneſs of age comes ſooner or later according to the beat or coldneſs of conſtitutions.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 28.</head>
                  <p>The diſeaſes of children for the 
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:58567:78"/>
moſt part, ſome of them attain to the Cryſis or alteration within 40
days, ſome within ſeven moneths, ſome within ſeven years, others when they come to ripe age. But thoſe which ſhall continue longer, and ſhall neither be diſſolved, in men children when they come to be about fourteen yeers or fifteen or maiden children when their monethly terms do break forth, do uſe to laſt a long time.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Or as</hi> Heurnius <hi>ſaith in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, do laſt as long as they live.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 29.</head>
                  <p>To young men there doth hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſpitting of blood, Conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſharp Feavers, falling-ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and other diſeaſes, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> theſe we have now rehearſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This age according to</hi> Heurnius<hi>is when their voice breaks and they begin to ſpeak big.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                        <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:78" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:58567:79"/>
noſtrils, dimneſs of ſight, Glau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coma, and dullneſs of hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Here by old men he means thoſe who have attained to their laſt age.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:58567:79" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:58567:80" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:58567:80"/>
               <head>SECT. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>This fourth Section is variable, but for the moſt part is reduced to evacuation and prognoſtick ſigns of future events.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APHORISM. 1.</head>
                  <p>THou ſhalt purge child-bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing women if it be needful, at the fourth moneth after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, and ſo unto the ſeventh, but thoſe more ſparingly: but the conception being younger, or elder, thou ſhalt abſtain.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe in thoſe moneths the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaments wherewith the conception is faſtened to the womb, are ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and thickeſt, and not caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e to be 
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:58567:81"/>
broken by the commotions of purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing medicines.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 2.</head>
                  <p>Such things are to be drawn out of the body by the uſe of purging medicines, as they are, which iſſuing out of their own accord would do good to it. But thoſe which iſſue out in a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry manner are to be ſtopped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For it is good in artificial purges to imitate Nature.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 3</head>
                  <p>If ſuch things be purged as ſhould be it is good, and the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent doth eaſily endure it. But if you do otherwiſe, the patient doth indure it painfully.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm being the ſame with the 2 and 25 of the firſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, it needs no further explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſome have in this place left it quite out.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="aphorism">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:81" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:82" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:58567:82"/>
                  <head>APH. 4.</head>
                  <p>In Summer it is more conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to purge the upper Venters, in Winter the inferior by ſtool.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For in Summer choller is the predominant humor, and naturally by reaſon of the ambient heat all things are carried upwards, ſo it is beſt to purge by Vomit.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 5.</head>
                  <p>Under the Canicular or Dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtar, and before it, purgations are painful and difficult.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe the ambient heat ſeeks to draw the humors outwards by ſweat while the purgation forces them out by ſtool.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 6.</head>
                  <p>Lean and ſlender men are eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly provoked to Vomit, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt be purged by vomit, unleſs it be in Winter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For ſlender men are for the moſt part chollerick, which choller if 
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:58567:83"/>
they have a facility in vomiting ſhould be purged upward, unleſs it be in Winter, for then the inferior venters muſt be purged by ſtool.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 7.</head>
                  <p>Purge thoſe which do not vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit eaſily, and are in good plight, downwards by ſtool, ſo it be not Summer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For at any other time of the year you may ſecurely do it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 8.</head>
                  <p>Do not purge them upwar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s
which are ſubject to a Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption or Phtyſick.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For fear of hurting the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental parts of reſpiration which are weak.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 9.</head>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt purge melancholly folk ſtrongly by ſtool, in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner beginning the contrary way of purging.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For light matter bending up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:83" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb facs="tcp:58567:84" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb n="65" facs="tcp:58567:84"/>
muſt be drawn out by the upper parts, but the heavier and groſſer matter by the lower parts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 10.</head>
                  <p>We muſt purge in very ſharp ſickneſſes, if the matter do move to the purging of it; and that the very ſame day wherein the ſickneſs doth begin; for delay in ſuch diſeaſes is very hurtful and dangerous.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Before the ſtrength of body fail, or diminiſh, or the aguiſh heat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, or the humors which wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der up and down the body ſettle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſome principal part.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 11.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which have gripings and wringings in the belly, and horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble pain about the navel and the loyns, and cannot be eaſed and diſſolved by medicine or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, they will fall into a dry Dropſie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:58567:85"/>
                     <hi>Which is called a Timpany.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 12.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe are not to be purged in Winter by vomit, whoſe ſtomack and belly cannot retain meat un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til it be digeſted</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He means ſuch purges as are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and purge the whole body; for in particular purges you may do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. As if we would onely eaſe the ventricle of phlegm, we may do it by vomit in Winter. And by the ſame reaſon, if yellow chol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler be in the inteſtines only, we may in Summer purge it out by ſtool.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 13.</head>
                  <p>Their bodies are to be made moiſt before hand with plenty of food, and with eaſe and reſt; who taking a potion of Hellebor do hardly and painfully vomit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe if the nerves and other dry parts of the body be not moiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Hellebor which is hot and dry 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:85" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb facs="tcp:58567:86" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb n="67" facs="tcp:58567:86"/>
in the third degree, and is very drawing, may cauſe deadly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 14.</head>
                  <p>Hellebor being drunk, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ought rather to be moved, then yielded to ſleep or reſt: For the ſayling in a ſhip doth manifeſt, that our bodies are provoked and ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>irred by motion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And ſeeing that motion of it ſelf provokes the body to vomit, much more will it do it, with the help of a medicine. And reſt keeps the body in the ſame ſtate, motion changes and alters it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 15.</head>
                  <p>If you will have Hellebore to work more forcibly move and ſtir the body, but when you will ſtay it, procure ſleep and do not move.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For ſince motion ſets it more vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olently a working, reſt muſt needs cauſe it to ſtay, ſeeing contrary ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations 
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:58567:87"/>
work contrary effects.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 16.</head>
                  <p>Hellebor is very dangerous to them which have a healthful bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, for it ingendreth Convulſions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For it is one of its chief qualities to cauſe diſtentions, ſo finding no excrements in the body it falls upon the ſolid parts, and eſpecially the nerves.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 17.</head>
                  <p>If he which hath not an Ague doth loath his meat, hath a gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the mouth or the ſtomack, a darkſom giddineſs of the brain, and bitterneſs of the mouth, it ſignifieth that he had need to be purged upwards.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For theſe are three ſymptomes by which the Phyſician may know the Patient hath need of being purged upward.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 18.</head>
                  <p>Whoſoever having need of 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:87" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:88" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:58567:88"/>
hath pains above the Middriff, it is a ſign he muſt be purged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, but the pains which are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame, ſhew a purging downwards to be needful.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For which way the humor natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally deſires to go, that way you muſt by the help of medicines ſend it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 19.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which do not thirſt while they are purged by a medicinal potion, ſhall not leave purging while they do thirſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe the excrements being evacuated, the mouth of the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricle is dryed up which cauſeth thirſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 20.</head>
                  <p>If there be gripings about the Navel without a Feaver, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineſs of the knees, and pain of the loyns, they ſignifie that there is need of purging downward.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe that all theſe ſymptomes 
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:58567:89"/>
ſhew that the noxious humors moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and violence is downward.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 21.</head>
                  <p>Black excrements of the belly like unto black blood, coming forth of their own accord, both with a Feaver, or without, are moſt evil, and by how much the more the evil colours are, ſo much the worſe, the excrements are. But ſuch things to be expelled out by a medicine is far better, and that by how much the more colours there ſhall be.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For if they come out of their own accord it ſhews there are many ill affected humors in the body, which driven out by Phyſick the body re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains ſound.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 22.</head>
                  <p>In the beginning of any diſeaſe if black choller come forth either above or beneath it is deadly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For it ſignifies that nature is ill 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:89" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb facs="tcp:58567:90" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb n="71" facs="tcp:58567:90"/>
affected, which never evacuates ſuperfluous things till they be conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, wherefore if black choller come forth in the beginning of a diſeaſe, it is evacuated by its proper malice and not by the law of Nature.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 23.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which are pined or brought low by ſharp or long diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, or by wounds, or any other means, and do void black choller or as it were black blood, do dye the next day following.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Namely through the imbecility of faculty, and greatneſs of the diſeaſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 24.</head>
                  <p>A Bloody flux if it proceed from black choller is mortal.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe it ulcerates the entrails with an ulcered cancer, which can hardly be cured in the outward parts, to which medi caments may be applyed; therfore much leſs there 
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58567:91"/>
where no ſuch medicaments can be applyed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 25.</head>
                  <p>For blood to be carried upward of what kind ſoever it be, is an evil ſign, but if black blood be avoided downwards it is good.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For if it be carried upwards, it ſhews there is ſome veſſel opened, extended, or broken in the upper parts. And in this place by car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying upward is meant through the mouth, not through the noſtrils, which for the moſt part is good.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 26.</head>
                  <p>If any man being afflicted with a bloody-flux, void as it were little pieces of fleſh, it is a mortal ſign.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For then the exulceration is ſo great that it can no way be healed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 27.</head>
                  <p>To thoſe which have ſtore of blood flowing from what part ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, in Feavers, their bodies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:91" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:92" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:58567:92"/>
come moiſt after they have been refreſhed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe the natural heat is weakened by ſtore of blood flowing, and though here mention be made onely of Feavers, yet it holds in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſeaſes likewiſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 28.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which avoid chollerick excrements downward, if deafneſs come thereupon, they ceaſe from avoiding them. And thoſe which are affected with deafneſs are cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of it by avoiding of chollerick excrements.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He means not a permanent deaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for that is not ſo cured, but of a tranſitory or ſupervening deafneſs cauſed by cholerick humors moleſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the brain, which muſt needs ceaſe when they come down.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 29.</head>
                  <p>If cold ſhakings happen, to them that are ſick of an Ague, 
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:58567:93"/>
the ſixt day they have a difficult Cryſis, and we cannot well judge of the diſeaſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe for the moſt part they preſage either death or return of the diſeaſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 30.</head>
                  <p>In them which are afflicted with fits of Agues, whenſoever the Ague ſhall leave them, if it return the ſame hour the next day it is wont to have a difficult Cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, and determination.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That is to ſay it will not eaſily be diſſolved.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 31.</head>
                  <p>Impoſthumes are cauſed neer the joynts, and eſpecially neer the jaw-bones, or mandibles to them which feel wearineſs or laſſitude in Feavers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe the heat of the Feaver having drawn the humors up into the head, when they fall down again 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:93" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb facs="tcp:58567:94" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb n="75" facs="tcp:58567:94"/>
the jaw-bones being very weak can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expel them to other parts of the body, but there they muſt reſt. And the joynts heated by motion attract the humors of the body.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 32.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which recovering from a diſeaſe have a pain in ſome place ſhal have Impoſthumes or botch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in that place.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſpeaks of ſuch as recover and yet have ſome reliques of feaveriſh matter remaining in their bodies.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 33.</head>
                  <p>If any part be pained before the diſeaſe, there is the ſeat of the diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore if it be a principal part, we muſt indeavor to divert the humors from thence.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 34.</head>
                  <p>If a ſuffocation of the breath do happen upon a ſuddain to one afflicted with a Feaver, no ſwelling 
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:58567:95"/>
appearing in the jaws or gullet, it is deadly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For it is a ſign that Phlegm ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth his breath and reſpiration, without which he cannot live.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 35.</head>
                  <p>If to one afflicted with a Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the neck be ſuddainly turned awry, and he can ſcarce ſwallow, and no ſwelling appear it is deadly</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For it ſhews there is an inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the muſcles lying before the throat, or in the throat it ſelf.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH 36.</head>
                  <p>Sweats are good to thoſe who are ſick of an Ague, if they iſſue forth the third, fifth, ſeventh, ninth eleventh, fourteenth, ſeventeenth, one and twentieth, thirty, and four and thirtieth days, for thoſe ſweats work the diſſolution of the diſeaſe: thoſe which happen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſignifie pain and length of the diſeaſe, or a return of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:95" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:96" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:58567:96"/>
                     <hi>For theſe are the onely days of Critical ſweats, in which we may be judge of the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſolution of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="37" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 37.</head>
                  <p>Cold ſweats with a ſharp Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver betoken death, but with a milde and gentle Ague, length of the diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe it ſhews that the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents body doth ſo much abound in cold humors, that neither the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, nor the ſharp Feavers heat is able to heat them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="38" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 38<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </head>
                  <p>In what part of the body the the ſweat is, there is the diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe in that part, ſtick the redundant and noxious humors.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="39" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 39.</head>
                  <p>And in what part of the body there is heat or cold, there the the diſeaſe is ſetled.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Namely in an exceſſive manner, 
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:58567:97"/>
and not proceeding from any exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal cauſe, for it ſhews a diſtempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature contrary to health.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="40" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 40.</head>
                  <p>And when alterations do hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in the whole body, and it is ſometimes cool, and ſometimes hot, or one colour ariſes after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, it ſignifies continuance of the diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe Nature cannot in a ſhort time concoct and ſubdue ſeveral defects or diſeaſes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="41" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 41.</head>
                  <p>Much ſweating cauſed through ſleep without any manifeſt out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward cauſe, ſignifies that the body is fed with ſtore of food. But if this happen to one that feeds ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly, it ſhews that the body wants evacuation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By reaſon of the evil humors and excrements which are the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of that ſweating.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="42" type="aphorism">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:97" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:98" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:58567:98"/>
                  <head>APH. 42.</head>
                  <p>When there is much ſweat cold or hot always iſſuing forth, the cold ſignifies a longer, the hot a ſhorter diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe it ſhews the matter to be thin, which nature can eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coct and ſhake off.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="43" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 43.</head>
                  <p>Continual Feavers which afflict every third day more vehemently, and do not ceaſe are the more dangerous, but if they ceaſe and pauſe in any manner, they ſignifie that there is no preſent danger.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For it ſheweth the Phlegm doth not trouble any noble part, and that no venemous force hath laid ſiege to any principal part. And natural ſtrength doth recollect it ſelf during the intermiſſion of the Feaver.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="44" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 44.</head>
                  <p>Swellings and pains about the joynts are cauſed to them who 
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:58567:99"/>
are afflicted with long Agues.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By the humors ſet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ng in thoſe places, unleſs they be carried away by a thick white urine making.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="45" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 45.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which have ſwellings and pains of the joynts after long A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, feed over liberally.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the diſeaſe being gone, no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon can be given for this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundancy of humors.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="46" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 46.</head>
                  <p>If a cold ſhivering fit, the Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver being without intermiſſion, do aſſail the ſick man being already weak, it is a deadly ſign.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For it ſhews nature to be ſo far ſpent, that it is able onely to ſtir, but not to thruſt out the excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; or if it doth, the ſick man fainteth therewith.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="47" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 47.</head>
                  <p>Excrements avoided in Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers not intermittent, by vomit, 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:99" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:100" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:58567:100"/>
or ſpitting, if they be of a leaden colour, bloody, ſtinking, or cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerick, they are all evil: but if they come forth conveniently they are good</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Leaden colour becauſe they ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie a mortification of thoſe parts from whence they come; bloody be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſignifie an opening of ſome veſſels. Stinking becauſe they ſignifie putrifaction. Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lerick be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they teſtifie abundance of choller.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="48" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 48.</head>
                  <p>In continual Feavers, if the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terior parts be cold, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward burn, and the Patient be thirſty, it is a deadly ſign.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eat of that inward part draws all the blood to it, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the heart is oppreſſed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="49" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 49</head>
                  <p>In continual Feavers, if the lip, eye, brows, or noſe be turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awry, 
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:58567:101"/>
if the ſick man do not ſee nor hear, which ſoever of theſe ſhall happen, the body being weak, death is neer at hand.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For all theſe are ſigns that the moving animal faculty ſuffereth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="50" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 50.</head>
                  <p>If there happeneth in a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Feaver defficulty and hardniſs of breathing, with delirium and doting, theſe ſigns are deadly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe it ſignifies that both the brain, and the inſtruments of breathing do ſuffer.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="51" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 51.</head>
                  <p>Apoſthumes in Feavers which are not diſſolved in the firſt Cryſis or judgement ſignifie length of the diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe they ſhew that there is a multitude of noxious humors, which nature could not expel at one Cryſis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="52" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 52.</head>
                  <p>It is not abſurd to weep and ſhed 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:101" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:102" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:58567:102"/>
tears in Feavers and other diſeaſes voluntarily, but to weep againſt the will is very abſurd and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe that weeping againſt the will ſhews a weakneſs and imbecili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the retentive faculty.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="53" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 53.</head>
                  <p>They have fierce and vehement Feavers, who have a tough, and clammy moiſture about their teeth in thoſe Feavers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For thoſe clammy moiſtures can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not grow there ſo abundantly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exceſſive heat which dries up the pituitous humor.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="54" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 54.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe who have long laſting dry coughs, in burning Feavers, which do not provoke much, are not wont to be very thirſty.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For by that motion which is made in coughing, there is ſome humidity drawn from thoſe places which are 
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:58567:103"/>
adjoyning to the rough artery.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="55" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 55.</head>
                  <p>All Feavers proceeding from tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors in the groyn, and other ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous parts are evil, except diary Feavers which laſt but one day.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For thoſe Feavers come when thoſe tumors are cauſed by ſome out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thing, as ſome blow or the like, and not by any inward inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="56" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 56.</head>
                  <p>Sweat coming often upon one ſick of an Ague not ceaſing, is evil, for the diſeaſe is prolonged, and it ſignifieth that there is much moiſture.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Which abundance of moiſture asketh nature much time to concoct and diſperſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="57" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 57.</head>
                  <p>If o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e have Convulſions, or Cramps, a Feaver coming diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth them:</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:103" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:104" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:58567:104"/>
                     <hi>Becauſe the Feaver doth heat, extenuate, and ſhake off thoſe cold humors which filled up the nervous parts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="58" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 58.</head>
                  <p>If a cold ſhaking fit doth come upon him which hath a burning Feaver, it diſſolveth it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For a burning Feaver being cauſed by choller putrifying in the veins, and a cold ſhaking, by the cholers being ſwiftly carryed about the ſenſible parts of the body, it ſhews that the choler is come out of the veins, to the skin.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="59" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 59.</head>
                  <p>An exquiſite and perfect Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Feaver cometh to his Cryſis or ſtate, in ſeven circuits or fits, at the utmoſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An exquiſite Tertian is that which is cauſed by yellow choler car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried up and down the ſenſible parts of the body, keeping its nature pure and ſincere.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="60" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:58567:105"/>
                  <head>APH. 60.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe that wax deaf and thick of hearing through Feavers, are delivered from it, by flux of blood at the noſe, or by the belly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is no marvel if diſeaſes ceaſe, when the noxious humors are tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated or carried away.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="61" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 61.</head>
                  <p>Unleſs the Feaver leave the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient in the odd days, it is accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to return again.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If this Aphoriſm ſhould ſpeak of all Feavers it were falſe: if of acute and continual Feavers it is true.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="62" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 62.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which have the yellow Jaundiſe upon Agues before the ſeventh day have an evil ſign.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe the yellow Jaundies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from the inflammation of the Liver.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="63" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 63.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe Feavers which have their 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:105" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:106" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:58567:106"/>
ſhaking fits every day are every day diſſolved.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yet there remains ſome fire wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the paroxiſm is renewed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="64" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 64.</head>
                  <p>It is a good thing for them which have the yellow-Jaundies coming on them in Feavers on the 7 day, ninth, eleventh, or fourteenth, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the right Hypocondrium be hard, for then it is evil.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the Hypocondrium being hard ſignifies there is an inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Liver.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="65" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 65.</head>
                  <p>In Feavers a vehement heat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Stomach, and a gnawing about the heart is bad.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe it ſignifies an ebullition of choler in the tunicles of the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricle or ſtomach.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="66" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 66<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </head>
                  <p>Convulſions and vehement pains about the bowels in ſharp Feavers are evil.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:58567:107"/>
                     <hi>For vehement Feavers dry and ſtretch the nerves like fire, and by the ſame vehemence of heat and drought, the bowels are pained.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="67" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 67.</head>
                  <p>In feavers great fears or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions after ſleep do prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate evil.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For fears ſignifie the repletion of the head with melancholy humors and Convulſions, abundance of phlegmatick humors.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="68" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 68.</head>
                  <p>The breath not keeping its due courſe, is evil: for it doth ſignifie convulſion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cauſed by the over-drying of the muſcles and nerves which move the ſtomack</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="69" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 69.</head>
                  <p>Urines in a Feaver being thick, clotted, and little in quantity, do profit them that make them, if afterwards, thin urine, and much 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:107" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:108" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:58567:108"/>
in quantity be avoided by them. But thoſe urines moſt commonly become ſuch, in which the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſis or ſediment ſhal appear pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after they are made, or not long after.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe the groſs humors cauſing the Feaver are expelled in the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, which makes the urine which comes afterwards to be thin in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of that.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="70" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH 70.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe who have their water troubled or unclean in Agues, ſuch as are the waters of Cattel, have or ſhall have head-aches.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe the windy or flatuous ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is eaſily drawn up into the head together with heat.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="71" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 71.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which ſhall have their Cryſis or alteration of the diſeaſe the ſeventh day, have a little red cloud in the urine the fourth day, 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:109" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:58567:109"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>

                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:58567:110"/>
and other things thereunto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing accordingly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe red clouds are ſeldom ſeen, though the white be frequent, and are both of them ſigns of concoction.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="72" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 72.</head>
                  <p>Urines very cleer and white are bad, eſpecially in thoſe who are afflicted with phrenſies.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe ſuch urines are ſigns of an extreme crudity. And</hi> Galen <hi>ſaith he never knew any one who was afflicted with a phrenſie, and made ſuch water, ſaved.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="73" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 73.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which have an inflation of the Hypoco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dria, and a rum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling pain of the loyns ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, have their bellies moiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; looſened except the wind break forth downwards, or ſtore of urine do iſſue forth. And theſe things happen in Feavers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Namely in eſſential, not ſympto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:110" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb facs="tcp:58567:111" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb n="91" facs="tcp:58567:111"/>
Feavers, and ſuch as are diſeaſes of themſelves.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="74" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 74.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe that have hope of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthumations to come about the joynts, much urine thick and white doth deliver from the Apoſthume, ſuch as is wont to be avoided in painful Feavers the fourth day:
when alſo blood ſhall be voided out of the noſtrils, there ſhall be a diſſolution &amp; deliverance ſpeedily.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For thoſe urines purge out the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors which would cauſe the apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humations, and eſpecially if there be a bleeding at the noſtrils joyned, for then the cauſes iſſue out two ways.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="75" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 75.</head>
                  <p>If any piſs blood or filthy mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it ſignifies an exulceration of the Kidneys or bladder.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That is, if he do it for a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, for otherwiſe it may proceed from ſome other cauſe</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:112" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:58567:112"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
               <div n="76" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:58567:113"/>
                  <head>APH. 76.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which have ſmall pieces of fleſh, or as it were hairs iſſuing forth together with thick urine, do avoid thoſe excrements from the Kidneys.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thoſe ſmall pieces of fleſh are part of the reins or kidneys, and are a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt ſign of their being ulcerated, but the hairs are onely bred there, but are no part of them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="77" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 77.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which avoid thick urine with certain things like bran, have their bladder infected with ſcab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedneſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If the defect be not in the veins for ſuch ſtuff comes ſometime from them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="78" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 78.</head>
                  <p>If any piſs blood on a ſuddain, it is a ſign there is ſome vein of the Kidneys broken.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Namely meer and pure blood, and 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:113" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb facs="tcp:58567:114" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb n="93" facs="tcp:58567:114"/>
without any external cauſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="79" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 79.</head>
                  <p>They in whoſe urine appeareth an hypoſtaſis or ſediment full of ſand, have their bladder troubled with the ſtone.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm is mutilated and defective, for the ſand may come as well from the kidneys as from the bladder.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="80" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 80.</head>
                  <p>If any one piſs blood or clots of blood, and make his water by drops having pain in that part of the belly (which is between the Navel and the ſecret parts) named <hi>hypogaſtrion:</hi> or at the ſeame line of the skin of the Cods, called <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinaeum,</hi> and at the place called <hi>pecten</hi> (where the hair about the privy members groweth) then the places about the bladder are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Namely all the parts belonging 
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:58567:115"/>
to the bladder, and not the bladder onely.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="81" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 81.</head>
                  <p>If any one piſs blood or filthy matter, or little ſcales, and there be alſo a ſtinking or ſtrong ſmell, it betokens an exulceration of the bladder.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The two firſt accidents may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen upon the exulceration of any of the inſtruments ſerving to make water, but the ſcales and ſtink are proper ſigns of the bladder being ill-affected.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="82" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 82.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which have an Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hume bred in the urinary paſſage, are delivered from it, the ſame being brought to ſuppuration and broken.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Which ſuppuration and break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, gives the urine free paſſage.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="83" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 83.</head>
                  <p>Voiding of much urine in the 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:115" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:116" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:58567:116"/>
night doth ſignifie ſmall evacuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of excrements by the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He makes particular mention of the night, becauſe at that time by reaſon of the ſleep Nature is moſt buſie about her concoction and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:58567:117"/>
               <head>SECT: V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>This fift Book or Section is varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet it doth almoſt wholly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of the diſeaſes of women, and of the good and bad diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the womb.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APHORISM. 1.</head>
                  <p>A Convulſion after taking Hellebore is deadly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Namely after white Hellebore, and that for five cauſes. Firſt by reaſon of the agreement which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>etween the nerves and the mouth of the Stomack. Secondly by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the biting humors which it draws to the mouth of the ſtomack. Thirdly by reaſon of the abundant 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:117" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb facs="tcp:58567:118" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb n="97" facs="tcp:58567:118"/>
evacuation the Hellebore cauſeth. Fourthly, by reaſon of the attra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive faculty by which it draws the moiſtneſs from the nerves. And fift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe it vehemently dryes up the ſubſtance of the nerves.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 2.</head>
                  <p>A Convulſion cauſed by a wound is deadly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Not always but for the moſt part.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 3.</head>
                  <p>The Hicket, or a Convulſion af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a copious flux of blood is evil.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe of the great emptineſs cauſed by the copious flux of blood, and becauſe the Hicket is cauſed by a depraved motion of the ventricle.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 4.</head>
                  <p>After an immoderate purgation, a Convulſion or Hicket is evil.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the ſame reaſon that they are evil after taking of Hellebore.</hi> Aph. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:58567:119"/>
                  <head>APH. 5.</head>
                  <p>If one that is drunk ſuddainly fall dumb, he ſhall die with a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſion unleſs he be taken with a Feaver, or preſently recover his ſpeech as ſoon as his ſurfet is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved</p>
                  <p>Obj. <hi>How can wine being hot cauſe a Convulſion which is a cold diſeaſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A. <hi>Wine is hot moderately taken, over abundantly cold as a little oil powred upon a fire will increaſe it, but an over abonnding quantity thrown upon a little will put it out.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 6.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe who are taken with a Cramp or diſtention called Teta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, die within four days, or if they overpaſs them they recover.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe it is a ſign that nature hath overcome the diſeaſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 7.</head>
                  <p>The falling ſickneſs, which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ripeneſs of years may be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red:

<pb facs="tcp:58567:119" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:120" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:58567:120"/>
but that which comes after five and twenty yeers of age for the moſt part accompanies us to death.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By ripeneſs of yeers he means 25
yeers of age, yet they are not all cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable before that age, unleſs they take a care in dieting themſelves.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 8.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which have a pluriſie, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they be purged upwards with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in fourteen days, ſhall have their diſeaſe turned into an impoſthume</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Namely ſpitting and purging ſuch matter upward.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 9.</head>
                  <p>A Conſumption likely happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in that age which is from the 18 to the 35.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Namely that Conſumption which comes by an exulceration of the Lungs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 10.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe who have the evil cauſe of the Squinancy and eſcape it, that 
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:58567:121"/>
evil paſſeth to the Lungs, and they dye within ſeven days, but if they eſcape, the humor impoſthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And if that impoſthumated hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor be not purged out it breeds a Conſumption.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 11.</head>
                  <p>If the ſpittle which they void by coughing that are affected with a Conſumption, do ſtink vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently being caſt upon the coals, and the hairs of the head do fall off, it is a deadly ſign.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the more faculties are weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in ſo much the worſer caſe the Patient is.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 12.</head>
                  <p>If a flux of the belly happen to them, which have their hair falling away by a Conſumption; death is neer at hand.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe it proceeding from weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs alſo, it ſhews a further weaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:121" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb facs="tcp:58567:122" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb n="101" facs="tcp:58567:122"/>
of the natural faculties.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 13.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which cough forth frothy blood, do retch and draw the ſame out of the Lungs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And it is part of the very ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and fleſh of the Lungs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 14.</head>
                  <p>If a flux of the belly happen to him which is in a Conſumption it is deadly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This affirms what was ſaid before Aph. 12 and moreover that a flux of the belly added to a Conſumption, is alone ſufficient to kill without fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling away of the hair.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 15.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which are infected with an impoſthume by a Pluriſie, if they be purged from the corrupt matter within forty days after the breaking of the impoſthume are cured, or otherwiſe they paſs into a Conſumption.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="102" facs="tcp:58567:123"/>
                     <hi>For the matter will otherwiſe be ſo putrified that it will periſh the lungs</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 16.</head>
                  <p>Hot water too often uſed, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth theſe diſcommodities: tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the fleſh, diſtemperature of the ſinews, heavineſs, and ſtupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the mind, fluxes of blood, faintings and ſwounings; and to theſe things ſucceeds death</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hippocrates here wiſheth us to ſhun; the exceſſive uſe of any thing, though never ſo temperate.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 17.</head>
                  <p>The uſe of cold water, bringeth Convulſions, diſtentions or Cramps, blackneſs, and cold Agu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh ſhakings.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This is alſo not of the uſe ſimply but of the immoderate uſe of cold water.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 18.</head>
                  <p>Cold water is hurtful to the bones, teeth, ſinews, brain, and 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:123" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:124" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="103" facs="tcp:58567:124"/>
marrow of the back. But that which is hot is good and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All the parts here rehearſed are by nature the coldeſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 19.</head>
                  <p>We muſt heat thoſe things which are over cold, except thoſe which pour forth or are inclined to pour forth blood abundantly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For when there are more diſeaſes then one coupled together, we muſt make haſt to cure that firſt which is moſt urgent.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 20.</head>
                  <p>Cold water biteth and nippeth Ulcers, hardeneth the skin, hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a ſoreneſs from maturation of the corrupt matter, cauſeth black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, bringeth forth cold ſhivering fits of Agues, Convulſions, and diſtentions of the ſinews.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm relates ſome other hurts which cold water doth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:58567:125"/>
                  <head>APH. 21.</head>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding there is ſome time when in the Cramp without an ulcer in a wel fleſht young man in the midſt of Summer, plentiful pouring out of cold water, doth call back the heat, and ſo the heat diſſolves the Cramp.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This is not done by any vertue of its, but accidentally by drawing the natural heat outward in ſuch well fleſht young men.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 22.</head>
                  <p>Hot water yieldeth unto us a great token of ſecurity and ſafety, when it cauſeth ſuppuration, yet not in all Ulcers. It ſoftneth and mollifieth the skin, and maketh it thin, it doth appeaſe pain, it miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gateth and aſſawageth cold ſhake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Convulſions and diſtentions:
It diſſolveth the heavineſs of the head: It profiteth broken bones very much; eſpecially if they be 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:125" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:126" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:58567:126"/>
bare without fleſh, and principally in the head, if they be ulcerated:
it profiteth thoſe things which are mortified, and ulcerated through cold, eating Ulcers in the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, privy members, womb, and bladder. To all thoſe hot water is a friend, and of good judgement; but cold water is an enemy and deſtroyer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Not in all ulcers, becauſe ſome wil not be brought to ſupuration by heat</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 23.</head>
                  <p>We muſt uſe cold water to thoſe ſores from whence blood doth iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, or is about to iſſue, yet not to the ſame place, but neer to it. And if any inflammation or burning of the parts, do incline to a red and bloody color, with freſh cleer blood, apply cold water to them, but if the inflamations be invete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and old it maketh them black. It helpeth the inflammation called 
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:58567:127"/>
Eryſipelas, if it be not ulcerated, for if it be it hurteth it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now he relates what things cold water is good for.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 24.</head>
                  <p>Cold things, as Snow and Ice are hurtful to the breaſt, they procure coughs, they cauſe ruptures of the veyns, and produce Rheumes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He hath ſpoken of the effects of cold water, now he ſpeaks of the hurt which other cold things do.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 25.</head>
                  <p>Cold water poured out abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, doth eaſe and diminiſh the tumors and pains of the joynts, which are without ulceration. And alſo gouty ſwellings and pains, and Convulſions for the moſt part, and diſſolveth the dolor, and diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it. for a ſmall benumming hath the force of diſſolving and putting away of pan.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The end of this, phoriſm is a reaſon 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:127" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb facs="tcp:58567:128" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb n="107" facs="tcp:58567:128"/>
of the whole Aphoriſms aſſertion. As if he ſhould ſay a little benumming puts away pain; cold water benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, therefore, <hi>&amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 26.</head>
                  <p>Water that is quickly made hot, and quickly cools, is moſt light.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He means not by weight, but he ſpeaks of that water which doth not long burthen the belly, and quickly paſſeth through.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 27</head>
                  <p>It is good for them who deſire to drink in the night, to fall aſleep when they are very thirſty.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe ſleep concocts the food, which being concocted ingenders blood, which nouriſhes and moiſtens the parts of the body.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 28.</head>
                  <p>A Fumigation of odoriferous ſpices brings forth womens terms:
and would be alſo profitable for many other things, if it did not breed heavineſs of the head.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="108" facs="tcp:58567:129"/>
                     <hi>For it doth excite the expulſive faculty of the womb, and open the obſtructions of the veines which touch the womb.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 29.</head>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt pruge a woman with child if neceſſity require, the 4th. month after conception, until the 7th month, though thoſe that come neer the 7th, not ſo much:
but the conception being younger or elder thou ſhalt abſtain.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm is the ſame with the firſt of the fourth Section.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 30.</head>
                  <p>A woman with child, a vein be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing opened aborteth, and ſo much the rather if the conception be of any bigneſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe it taketh away part of its food, namely the conceptions.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 31.</head>
                  <p>It is pernicious and deadly if a woman great with child be taken with any ſharp diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="109" facs="tcp:58567:129"/>
                     <hi>For large feeding will kill the mother by increaſing the diſeaſe, and little ſtore of food will ſtarve the conception.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 32.</head>
                  <p>A woman is cured from vomit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing blood, by her monethly terms iſſuing forth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By the Phyſicians drawing down the blood to the lower parts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 33.</head>
                  <p>A flux of blood at the noſe is good for a woman whoſe month<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly terms do fail contrary to the courſe of nature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For if this happen not contrary to the courſe of nature, ſuch a failing is nothing.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 34.</head>
                  <p>If the belly be very laxative and looſe to a woman with child, there is danger fo abortment.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe the food is not diſtributed to the liver and other parts of the 
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:58567:130"/>
body, ſo that the food is taken away from the conception as when ſhe is let blood.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 35.</head>
                  <p>Sneeſing happening to a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man grieved with ſuffocations of the womb, or that hath a difficult deliverance, is good.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For by a vehement ſhaking of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it excites it, redintegrates the natural heat which was almoſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed, and ſhakes off ſuch noxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous humors as hanged upon ſome part of the body.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 36.</head>
                  <p>The monethly courſes being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coloured, and not coming forth always in the ſame manner and time, declare a purgation to be neceſſary for the woman.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To purge thoſe humors which cauſe the diſcoloration, and the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of time.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="37" type="aphorism">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:130" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:131" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:58567:131"/>
                  <head>APH<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 37.</head>
                  <p>If the paps be ſuddenly extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated and become lank, to a woman with child abortment doth follow</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This alſo happeneth, for want of food for the conceived child.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="38" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 38.</head>
                  <p>If one of the dugs be extenuated and become lank to a woman con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with child with twins, ſhe bringeth forth one of them before the due time; and if the right dug become ſlender, ſhe bringeth forth the male, if the left, the female.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For likewiſe the male conceptions lye on the right ſide, the female on the left: as is ſet down Aph. 48.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="39" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 39.</head>
                  <p>If any woman, neither with child nor having been delivered of child have milk in her breaſts, her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethly courſes have failed her.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The blood which ſhould have turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to monethly terms, turning to milk in the breaſts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="40" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:58567:132"/>
                  <head>APH. 40.</head>
                  <p>Women in whoſe dugs there is blood heaped together, wil be mad</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For that blood is very bilious, which ſtriking up into the head, cauſeth madneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="41" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 41.</head>
                  <p>If you will know whether a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man have conceived or no, give her a potion of hony and water mixed together going to ſleep, and if ſhe feel gripings and wringings of the belly, ſhe hath conceived, if ſhe do not, ſhe hath not conceived</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For ſuch a potion is very windy, and the woman having conceived her womb doth preſs down, and keep together the intrails.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="42" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 42</head>
                  <p>If a woman conceived with child, bear a male ſhe is freſh and well-coloured, if ſhe bare a female ſhe is ill-colored.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm is one of thoſe 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:132" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb facs="tcp:58567:133" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb n="113" facs="tcp:58567:133"/>
which for the moſt part are true, though not always.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="43" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 43.</head>
                  <p>If the inflammation called Ery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipelas be bred in the womb, if the woman be with child, it proves deadly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>One reaſon is becauſe the chief cure for an Eryſipelas is letting of blood and that muſt not be done to a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with child for fear of an abort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> Aph. <hi>30.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="44" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 44.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe women which are very lean contrary to nature, and do bear children, do ſuffer untimely deliverance until they grow fatter</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe that food which ſhould be for the child in the womb, goes to the nouriſhing of the mother.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="45" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 45.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe women which being rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable fat, and make abortion the ſecond or third month without 
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:58567:134"/>
any manifeſt cauſe, have the ends of thoſe veſſels which come to the womb called <hi>acetabula</hi> or <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tylidons</hi> full of a pituitous or phlegmy humor, neither can they contain the conception coming to any weight, but they being broken it falleth down.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wherby ſhe muſt of neceſſity abort</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="46" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 46.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which are fatter then na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture requires and cannot conceive have the orifice of the womb compreſſed and cloſed together by the fat Call of the guts, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not until they grow leaner.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He means the inward orifice of the womb for it hath two.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="47" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 47.</head>
                  <p>If the womb ſhall Apoſthumate in that part where it lieth neer the hip or huckle-bone, it muſt be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with tents dipped in a liquid medicine called in Greek Emmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:134" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:135" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:58567:135"/>
                     <hi>It muſt be thus cured the ſore being firſt broken either by art or nature.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="48" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 48.</head>
                  <p>Men children for the moſt part lye on the right ſide of the womb and females on the left ſide.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This is becauſe the womb is war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer on the right ſide, by reaſon of its vicinity to the Liver.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="49" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 49.</head>
                  <p>A medicine procuring ſneezing put into the noſtrils doth drive and force out the <hi>Secundine,</hi> ſo that you ſtop the noſtrils and mouth, cloſe with the hand.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Which if it remained would pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifie there, and with the ſtench of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the head.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="50" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 50.</head>
                  <p>If a woman will ſtay her courſes apply a very great cupping-glaſs under her breaſts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For there be veins which come up thither from the inferior parts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="51" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:58567:136"/>
                  <head>APH. 51.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe women which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with child, have the orifice of the womb ſhut and cloſed up.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That the air may not get in and corrupt the ſeed, and that the heat of the womb may not get out.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="52" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 52.</head>
                  <p>If milk flow plentifully out of the dugs of a woman bearing a child in her womb it ſignifieth that the child is weak: but if the paps be hard and ſtiff, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare a ſtronger conception.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe it ſhews in the former part that the child is not able to draw it for his own nutriment. But when they are ſolid it ſhews it hath nutriment enough, and that which ſuperabounds goes to the breaſts, and is there turned into milk.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="53" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH 53.</head>
                  <p>The dugs and paps become ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and lank to thoſe women 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:136" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:137" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="117" facs="tcp:58567:137"/>
which ſhall abort: but contrarily if they become hard, pain ſhall moleſt the paps, hips, eys, or knees, but they ſhall not ſuffer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bortment.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe of the ſuperfluous mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which is brought thither from the womb.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="54" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 54.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe women which have the mouth of the womb hard, muſt of neceſſity have it ſhut up.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm had been better placed immmediately after the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoriſm 51.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="55" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 55.</head>
                  <p>Child-bearing women which are taken with Feavers, or are brought to a low ſtate without any manifeſt cauſe, do bring forth their birth painfully, and with danger: or are in danger of life by an untimely deliverance.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="118" facs="tcp:58567:138"/>
                     <hi>Becauſe it ſhews a great weakneſs or imbecility in them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="56" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH 56.</head>
                  <p>If a Convulſion, or ſwouning happen to a woman, in her flux of monethly terms, it is an evil thing</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If they be vehement or laſt long, it may be deadly becauſe the womb is exhauſted and draws all the noble parts into a ſimpathy with it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="57" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 57.</head>
                  <p>Womens terms flowing immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately, diſeaſes are ingendred; and being ſuppreſt or ſtopt, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes happen from the womb.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By their immoderate evacuation, the whole body is cooled, and its forces weakened, if they be ſtopt, in progreſs of time, excremental hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors gather together in the womb.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="58" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 58.</head>
                  <p>The ſtrangurie or dropping out of the urine doth happen by the inflammation of the ſtraight gut, 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:138" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:139" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:58567:139"/>
and likewiſe of the womb, or if the reins be ulcerated. But if the liver be inflamed, the Hicket ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By reaſon of the vicinity of the bladder to the ſtraigbt gut and the womb, and becauſe of the purulent matter of the reins paſſing through the bladder: and the hicket is cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by a high inflammation of the liver becauſe it ſwells the liver, and oppreſſes the ventricle, and the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious humor falling from the liver comes into the ventricle.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="59" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 59.</head>
                  <p>If a woman do not conceive, and thou wouldeſt know if ſhe ſhall conceive at all, let her be wrapped round about with clothes, &amp; make a fume under the lower parts, and if the ſcent be perceived to paſs through her body to her noſtrils, and her mouth, know that ſhe is not barren by any default in her ſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="120" facs="tcp:58567:140"/>
                     <hi>Becauſe then the body is cleer of all vitious humors, and the womb it ſelf is in a good temper.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="60" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 60.</head>
                  <p>If the monethly purgations keep their courſe in a woman that is with child, it is impoſſible that the conception ſhould be well.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe it wants its aliment and food, being fed by that menſtruous blood al the while it is in the womb.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="61" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 61.</head>
                  <p>If a womans monthly courſes ſtop, and ſhe have neither ſhiver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cold nor Ague coming upon her, and ſhe loath her meat, make account that ſhe is conceived.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For at the firſt conceiving of a woman, the child cannot make uſe of thoſe courſes for its food.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="62" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 62.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe women which have their womb cold and dry do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, nor thoſe which have it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:140" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:141" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:58567:141"/>
moiſt, for the ſeed is extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht and periſht in them. Alſo thoſe women cannot conceive which have thoſe places over dry and hot, for the ſeed corrupts for want of nouriſhment. But thoſe women which have obtained a moderate temperature of the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in reſpect of both the oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and contrarieties they are fruitful.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm by right ſhould be placed next to the 59 Aph.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="63" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 63.</head>
                  <p>The ſame conſideration and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is likewiſe to be reſpected in men men, for either through the ſpongy ſubſtance of the body, the ſpirits are diſſipated and ſcattered abroad ſo that the ſeed cannot be caſt forth; or elſe the humor doth not iſſue forth becauſe of its groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or thickneſs; or elſe becauſe of coldneſs it doth not grow hot, 
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:58567:142"/>
to be collected in its proper place<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or by the means of heat, the very ſelf ſame thing may happen.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm is held to be ſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and none of</hi> Hippocrates, <hi>both by</hi> Galen <hi>and others.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="64" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 64.</head>
                  <p>It is not good to give milk to thoſe who are troubled with the head-ach, or with Agues, nor to thoſe who are troubled with <hi>flatus Hypocondriacus,</hi> nor to thoſe who are troubled with thirſt. It is alſo naught for them which avoid cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerick excrements downwards, or to thoſe which have ſharp Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, or have had ſome copious evacuation of blood. But it is good for thoſe which are in a Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, ſo they be not troubled with any vehement Feaver. It is alſo good for long lingering and mild Agues, ſo there be none of the ſore ſpoken of ſignes. And 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:142" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:143" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="123" facs="tcp:58567:143"/>
thoſe who are brought low with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any apperant reaſon or occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The particular reaſons for theſe particular aſſertions may be ſeen at large in</hi> Galen, Fuchſius, <hi>and</hi> Heurnius <hi>Comments, which would be too long to reherſe here.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="65" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 65</head>
                  <p>They are ſeldom troubled with Convulſions or madneſs, which have apparent tumors with their ulcers. But Convulſions and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentions happen to them to whom the tumors ſhall ſuddenly vaniſh away, if they happen on the hinder part of the body. But if they happen on the fore part, there happeneth madneſs, vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment pain of the ſide<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſuppurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or ſpitting of matter, and the bloody-flux.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe the humors reſide there. And if they go away by degrees al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo 
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:58567:144"/>
there is no danger for it ſhews, that the noxious humors are ſhaken off and diſſolved.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="66" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 66.</head>
                  <p>If no tumor nor ſwelling appear in great and bad wounds, it is a great evil</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe it ſignifies a paſſing of the noxious humors to the principal parts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="67" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 67.</head>
                  <p>Soft tumors are good, raw and indigeſted ones evil.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe the firſt ſignifie there is a concoction, and in the ſecond there is none.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="68" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 68.</head>
                  <p>To one who hath a pain in the hinder part of his head, the <hi>vena recta</hi> in the <hi>fore-head</hi> being opened doth good.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The</hi> vena recta <hi>is that which is over againſt that which is oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to that vein which nouriſheth 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:144" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb facs="tcp:58567:145" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb n="125" facs="tcp:58567:145"/>
the part which is evil affected, ſo the opening of it doth both evacuate and divert the noxious humors.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="69" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 69.</head>
                  <p>Cold ſhakings and ſhiverings for the moſt part do begin to wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men from the loyns, and through the back come to the head. But to men they do rather begin in the back part then in the forepart, as from the hinder part of the thighes and from the elbows; the rarity and thinneſs of the skin is a token thereof, which thing, the hair there growing, doth declare and manifeſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the thicker the skin is, the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſs will hair grow upon it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="70" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 70.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which are taken with a Quartan Ague are not at all taken with Convulſions: but if before they have been taken, upon the coming of the quartan, they are delivered.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="126" facs="tcp:58567:146"/>
                     <hi>He means here ſuch Convulſions as come by repletion of the nervous parts, with thin and pituitous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, which by a quartan are both expelled and concocted</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="71" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 71.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe who have their skin acide, and dry, die without ſweating, but thoſe who have a looſe and open skin, end their life with ſweat.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſpeaks here of thoſe who have a Feaver.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="72" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 72.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe that are diſeaſed with the Jaundies are not much moleſted, with windineſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By reaſon of the heat and ſtrength of the parts belonging to the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, which cauſeth them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coct the food fully and perfectly.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:58567:146" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:58567:147" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:58567:147"/>
               <head>SECT. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>This Section doth almoſt altogether concern that part of the Art which foretelleth good and evil things to happen in diſeaſes.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APHORISM. 1.</head>
                  <p>IN a long lubricity and ſlipperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the guts, if a ſoweriſh belching do happen, which was not before, it is a good ſign.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For it ſignifies, that now the food remains a while in the ſtomack, till ſuch time at leaſt as it begins to concoct.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 2.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which have ther noſtrils more moiſt then others by nature, 
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:58567:148"/>
and their ſeed alſo do enjoy their health but badly; but thoſe which have the contrary properties, are more healthful.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By the noſtrils he means the brains which purge that way, and by the humidity of the Seed, the humidity of the whole body, the ſeed coming from the blood.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 3.</head>
                  <p>In long fluxes of the bowels, loathing of meat is evil, and with a Feaver it is worſer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe it ſignifies a mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the nouriſhing faculty.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 4.</head>
                  <p>Ulcers which are every way ſmooth and bald.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe of an evil humor lying in the bottom, which eats up the roots of the hair, as ſalt earth doth the herbs roots which grow on it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 5.</head>
                  <p>In the pains of the ſides, breaſt, 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:148" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:149" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="129" facs="tcp:58567:149"/>
and other parts, we muſt conſider whether they increaſe or differ much, or keep at a ſtay.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whither they differ namely in their kind, or in their vehemency, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be pricking<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſtretching, or provoking.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 6.</head>
                  <p>The diſeaſes and infirmities of the Kidneys and Bladder are of hard and difficult curation in old men.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hich old age begins at fifty years which</hi> Hippocrates <hi>confirms in his ſixt Book Epidemion where he ſaith he never ſaw or knew an ulcer of the reins or bladder cured after fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years of age.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 7.</head>
                  <p>Dolours and pains of the beſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly being aloft and in the upper part are more light &amp; eaſie, thoſe which are not aloft are more ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="130" facs="tcp:58567:150"/>
                     <hi>We muſt underſtand this word aloft not according to the length and height of the body, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to its depth and thickneſs, ſo be thoſe which are not aloft, he means thoſe which are next to the back.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 8.</head>
                  <p>Ulcers or ſores in the body of thoſe which are diſeaſed with the dropſie, are not eaſily cured.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For an ulcer cannot be cured un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til it be exactly dryed, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eaſily be done in thoſe who have the dropſie, by reaſon of their ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abundant humidity.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 9.</head>
                  <p>Broad wheals are not very full of itching.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For they are not bred by ſuch hot humors as thoſe which are narrow and high.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 10.</head>
                  <p>Corrupt matter, water or blood 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:150" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:151" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:58567:151"/>
iſſuing out, by the noſtrils, mouth or ears, diſſolveth and cureth a vehement and grievous head-ach.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If that the pain proceed from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation, or abundance of crude humors gathered in the head, for if it proceed from other cauſes, there muſt be other cures.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </head>
                  <p>The Haemorroides happening to thoſe, which are troubled with melancholly and pain of the Kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys are good.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Both by reaſon of the evacuation, and becauſe they evacuate ſuch hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors as ought to be evacuated.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 12.</head>
                  <p>Unleſs in the cures of Haemor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roides which have long continued there be one vein kept open, it is to be feared that a Dropſie or Convulſion will ſhortly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> follow.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That nature may by that means purge out thoſe evil humors which remain.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="213" facs="tcp:58567:152"/>
                  <head>APH. 13.</head>
                  <p>The Hick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> troubling us is put away by ſneezing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If the ſaid Hicket was cauſed by fulneſs For by ſneezing not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the brain: but the ſtomack alſo, by reaſon of the nerves derived un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, is vehemently ſhaken, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the humors exciting the Hicket are evacuated.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 14.</head>
                  <p>If in him who hath a Dropſie if the water flow from the veins into the belly, the diſeaſe is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If Nature or Phyſick make eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuation of it from thence.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 15.</head>
                  <p>Vomiting coming by the meer benefit of nature diſſolveth and riddeth away a long flux or looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the belly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By reaſon of the retraction and drawing back of the humors which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> downward.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="aphorism">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:152" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:153" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:58567:153"/>
                  <head>APH. 16.</head>
                  <p>A looſeneſs of the belly, to one afflicted with a Pluriſie or inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Lungs is an evil thing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe it ſignifies the liver to be ſo affected, by the conſent of thoſe parts which ſerve for reſpiration, that through weakneſs it is not able to draw the aliment to it ſelf, and convert it into blood.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 17.</head>
                  <p>It is good for him who hath a wateriſh dropping and running of the eys, if he be taken with a flux and looſneſs of the belly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whereby</hi> Hippocrates <hi>ſhews us a convenient way how to cure ſuch eys, namely by drawing the humors which cauſe the diſeaſe downwards</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 18.</head>
                  <p>It is a deadly thing when the bladder is wounded, or the brain, or the heart, the midriff, any ſmall 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:154" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:58567:154"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>

                     <pb n="213" facs="tcp:58567:155"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:155" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:156" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="133" facs="tcp:58567:156"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>

                     <pb n="134" facs="tcp:58567:157"/>
gut, the Stomack or Liver.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Greek word for wounded is here <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> which ſignifies deep wounded; for otherwiſe ſome of thoſe parts have been wounded and cured as</hi> Galen <hi>ſaith.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 19.</head>
                  <p>A bone periſhed or cut off, a cartilage, griſtle, or ſinew, or any little parcel of the eye-lid, or of the foreskin, being diminiſhed, do not grow or joyn together.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yet they may be knit together by ſome other kind of ſubſtance as we ſee in bones.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 20.</head>
                  <p>If blood flow contrary to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture into any concavity it corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and is putrified of neceſſity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That is, into any other concavity beſides the veins and arteries.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 21.</head>
                  <p>If the ſwellings of veins in the legs, called <hi>varices;</hi> or the Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morroides, 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:157" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:158" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="135" facs="tcp:58567:158"/>
ſhall happen to them which are mad, their madneſs is diſſolved.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe nature drives thoſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors which cauſe madneſs into the more ignoble parts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 22.</head>
                  <p>Breaches or fluxes of humors, which deſcend from the back to the elbow, are diſſolved by open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a vein.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By reaſon that thoſe humors are thereby evacuated.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 23.</head>
                  <p>If fear and ſadneſs continue long, it is a ſign of melancholly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Namely without any outward cauſe, for thoſe who are ſad or fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for any outward cauſe, their ſadneſs and fear do not commonly laſt long; but if they do, they will turn to melancholly, if not to mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:58567:159"/>
                  <head>APH. 24<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </head>
                  <p>If any ſmall or ſlender gut be pierced, it doth not grow together again.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This was ſpoken Aphoriſm 18. wherefore</hi> Galen <hi>and</hi> Heurnius <hi>would have it expunged.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 25.</head>
                  <p>If the cholerick tumor Eryſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulas being outward be returned inwards, it is evil; but if being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, it is turned outward, it is a good thing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By this example</hi> Hippocrates <hi>ſhews that it is good to have all ſores and diſeaſes of tbe body to come from the noble and inward parts to the ignoble and outward ones.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 26.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe burning feavers are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved with dotage or raving, in which are trembling ſhakings.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They are indeed diſſolved, but that diſſolution at laſt brings a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:159" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb facs="tcp:58567:160" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                        <pb n="137" facs="tcp:58567:160"/>
diſſolution of the body by death</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 27</head>
                  <p>If the corruption, matter, or water do flow out altogether at once from them which are burnt or cauterized, or cut by the Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion for the cure of the inward apoſthumation between<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the lungs and the breaſt, or of the Dropſie, then the diſeaſed ſhall queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs die<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By theſe examples</hi> Hippocrates <hi>ſhews that all total evacuations made at once, are noxious and dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 28.</head>
                  <p>Eunuchs or gelded men, are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther troubled with the Gout, nor with baldneſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe in Hippocrates time they uſed a very good diet, and lived ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry temperately they were not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with the gout, though now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days they be, and their not being 
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:58567:161"/>
bald comes from their native moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, which makes them have a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thick skin.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 29.</head>
                  <p>A woman is not troubled with the Gout unleſs her monthly terms fail her.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The ſame reaſons may be alleadg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for women as were ſet down in the former, for Eunuchs. But if her terms fail her, then the ſuperfluous humors being driven to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts may cauſe it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 30.</head>
                  <p>A boy is not troubled with the Gout till he hath uſed Venery.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs it come through their ſeed, or if the parents have had the French pox.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 31.</head>
                  <p>Drinking of ſtrong wine, a ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, a fomentation, phlebotomy, or a purgation doth cure the pain of the eyes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:161" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:162" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="139" facs="tcp:58567:162"/>
                     <hi>According as the cauſe of the diſeaſe is, ſo muſt the manner of the taking of it away be various.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 32.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which ſtammer are for the moſt part taken with a long flux of the belly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe ſtammering ſhews an extraordinary humidity of the tongue, whereof the ventricle of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity participates.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 33.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which have ſour belchings are not much ſubject to a Pluriſie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe ſour belching is a ſign of much phlegm, and the Pluriſie for the moſt part invades thoſe who are troubled with much choller.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 34.</head>
                  <p>Great ſwelling veins in the legs called <hi>varices,</hi> are not incident to them who loſe their hair, and if they happen to have <hi>varices</hi> whoſe hair do fall, their hair will grow again.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="140" facs="tcp:58567:163"/>
                     <hi>Becauſe thoſe vicious humors which before corrupted the hair, are now gon down into the legs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 35.</head>
                  <p>If a cough come upon thoſe which are troubled with a Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie it is an evil thing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For it ſignifies the watery humor to be ſo increaſed, that it hath ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon the rough artery, and ſo cauſeth danger of ſuffocation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 36.</head>
                  <p>Phlebotomy cureth the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of making urine, but we muſt open the inward veins.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Namely that difficulty which proceeds from inflamation or fulneſs</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="37" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 37.</head>
                  <p>If a tumor appear in the neck to him that is troubled with a <hi>Squinancy</hi> or <hi>Quinzy,</hi> it is good.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe the humors are come from the inward parts to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="38" type="aphorism">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:163" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:164" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:58567:164"/>
                  <head>APH. 38.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe who have hidden or deep Cancers are not to be cured of them; for they which are healed die ſoon, and thoſe which are not healed, live longer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For fear of provoking or irrita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="39" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 39.</head>
                  <p>A Convulſion is cauſed by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletion or evacuation. So is alſo the Hicket.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Namely when the nerves are fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with ſome thick or clammy hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, or over dryed. And the Hicket is ſaid by</hi> Galen <hi>to be as it were a Convulſion of the ſtomack.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="40" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 40.</head>
                  <p>They who have pain about the the hypocondrium without an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation are cured by a Feaver happening to them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe the humors which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it are diſſolved by the heat of the Feaver.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="41" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:58567:165"/>
                  <head>APH. 41.</head>
                  <p>If a ſuppuration or corrupt matter, hidden in the body doth not ſhew it ſelf, it is by reaſon ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of its own thickneſs, or of that part of the bodies thickneſs where it lies hidden.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yet we may find that there is ſuch corrupt matter hidden by two ſigns namely by the pain, and by a Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver which it cauſeth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="42" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 42.</head>
                  <p>If the Liver wax hard to them which are affected with the yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Jaundies, it is an evil ſign.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For it ſignifies there is either a hard tumor or an inflammation in the Liver</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="43" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 43.</head>
                  <p>The ſplenetick which are taken with a bloody-flux in the bowel, do dye <hi>of the Dropſie,</hi> or a ſlippe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs of the bowels, following a long flux.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:165" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:166" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="143" facs="tcp:58567:166"/>
                     <hi>By ſplenetick he means thoſe who have a tumor in the spleene, bred there, by a melancholly humor.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="44" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 44.</head>
                  <p>They dye within ſeven days, to whom the diſeaſe called Ileos or pain in the ſmall guts ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen after a Strangurie: unleſs a Feaver ſupervening, ſtore of urine iſſue forth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the Fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>er with its heat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocts and ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>ates the thick hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, ſo that they may go out through the paſſage of the urine.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="45" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 45.</head>
                  <p>If ulcers continue a yeer or long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the bone of neceſſity muſt grow foul, and the Cicatrices be hollow.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe the bone being periſhed under, the fleſh cannot grow up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain as was ſaid Aph. 19. of this Section.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="46" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:58567:167"/>
                  <head>APH. 46.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which become Crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backt by ſhortneſs of wind, or a cough before they attain to ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of years, doe die quicklie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe their breſt or bulk doth not increaſe as their lungs and heart doth, they muſt in a ſhort time to ſuffocated.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="47" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 47.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe are to be let blood or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the Spring time, to whom opening of a vein or purging may do good.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the Spring time being tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate is moſt fit for purging or let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing blood.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="48" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 48.</head>
                  <p>The difficulty of the inteſtines &amp; guts, coming upon them which are diſeaſed with the ſpleen is good.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe the thick and melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly humors are thereby eva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as</hi> Aph. <hi>4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="49" type="aphorism">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:167" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:168" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:58567:168"/>
                  <head>APH. 49.</head>
                  <p>Goutie diſeaſes, the inflammation being aſſwaged, within fortie dayes deceaſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the inflammation wil be cured within forty dayes, if the Phyſitian preſcribe right, and the patient be truly obedient.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="50" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 50.</head>
                  <p>It muſt needs be, that a Feaver, and Vomiting of choller muſt come upon them, which have their brain wounded.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Feaver, becauſe any principall members inflammation cauſeth a Feaver, and the vomiting of Choller becauſe of the conſent and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is between the braine and the ſtomack, to which ſome of the great nerves diſcend from the braine.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="51" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 51.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which are in health being ſodainly taken with the head-ache, 
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:58567:169"/>
and preſently become dumb and ſnort, die within ſeven days, unleſs a Feaver come upon them in the mean while.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe the Feaver heats, attenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates and reſolves the windie ſpirit and the pituitous humors which cauſe theſe ſymptomes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="52" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 52.</head>
                  <p>We muſt conſider in their ſleeps if any part of the eyes appear; for if any of the white of them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, the eye lidds not being faſt cloſed, if it doe not happen by a Flux of the bellie, or by the taking of ſome medicinall potion, it is an evil and verie deadly ſigne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If it happen not through ſome externall cauſe, for it ſignifies an imbecillitie of the facultie which moves the eye lids.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="53" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 53.</head>
                  <p>That doting which is done with aughter is not ſo dangerous, as 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:169" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:170" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="147" facs="tcp:58567:170"/>
that which is done with earneſt ſadneſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For it does not proceed from ſo aduſt a Choler, as that which is done with earneſt ſadneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="54" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 54.</head>
                  <p>Painfull breathings in ſharp diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes with a Feaver, as it were of ſuch as ſigh, and mourne, are evill.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For it ſignifies either a hardneſs of the nerves or muſcles, or a weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of naturall ſtrength, or ſome affect that cauſeth paine, or is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſory.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="55" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 55.</head>
                  <p>Paine of the Gout doe moſt commonly afflict, and are provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the Spring and Autumn.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Spring becauſe the humors gathered together in the winter are expelled from the ſtronger parts to the weaker; and in Autumn by reaſon of its inequalitie, and becauſe 
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:58567:171"/>
the evill humors gathered together by eating of fruits in Summer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſettle in thoſe we akeſt parts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="56" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 56.</head>
                  <p>The falling down of humors are verie dangerous in melancholie diſeaſes at thoſe ſeaſons. And de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare an Appoplexie, or a convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or maddneſs or blindneſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If they fall down to the ventricles of the brain, they cauſe an Apoplexie if to the nerves a convulſion, if to the ſubſtance of the braine madneſs, if to the eyes blindneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="57" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH 57,</head>
                  <p>Apoplexies are cauſed moſt eſpeciallie from the fortieth to the ſixtieth year.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He means thoſe Apoplexies which proceed from melancholie, which in thoſe times abound in our bodies.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="58" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 58<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </head>
                  <p>If the Call hang foorth of the bodie, it muſt of neceſſity putrefie.</p>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:171" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:58567:172"/>
               <head>SECT: VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>This ſeaventh Section is altogether prognoſticall and foretelling things to come, and herein he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth of preſages of health and death.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APHORISM. 1.</head>
                  <p>COldneſs of the extreame parts in ſharp diſeaſes is evill.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe is ſhews there is a mightie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nflamation in ſome of the inward parts, which like a cupping glaſſe draws all the blood to it, and ſo leaves the extream parts cold.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="aphorism">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:172" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:173" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:58567:173"/>
                  <head>APH. 2.</head>
                  <p>Fleſh black and blew becauſe of a foule diſeaſed bone, is an evill thing,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For it ſhews there is a great putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the bone, and extinction of the natural heat.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH, 3.</head>
                  <p>The hicket and redneſs of the eyes after vomiting are evill</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For theſe two together ſhew there is a great inflamation, either in the ventricle or the braine.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </head>
                  <p>After ſweate, cold ſhiverings and ſhakings are not good.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For it is a ſigne that nature is weake, and that the ſweat hath not had power to drive out all the noxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous humors.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 5.</head>
                  <p>After madneſs, a bloodie Flux, the dropſie, or an extanſie or trane is good.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="152" facs="tcp:58567:174"/>
                     <hi>For it ſignifieth that the noxious humors are gone from the head to the lower parts</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 6.</head>
                  <p>Abhorring of meat in a long diſeaſe, and the excrements avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down without mixture of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, are evill.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe, it ſhews the inbecilitie of the concocting facultie, and that all natural humidity is dried up by the ſeaveriſh heat.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 7.</head>
                  <p>Cold ſhakings, and fond dotings, after much drinking of wine are evill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The firſt by reaſon, it is a ſigne that the native heat is extinguiſht by the much drinking of wine. And the doting proceeds from the heads being full of fervent blood and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 8.</head>
                  <p>After the breaking of an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſthume 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:174" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:175" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="153" facs="tcp:58567:175"/>
inwardly faintneſſe; vomiting and ſwouning.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſpeakes here of the breaking of impoſthumes which break in the ſtomack, for the ſymptome of vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting followes none elſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 9</head>
                  <p>After a Flux of blood, a <hi>Deliri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> or raveing, or a convulſion are evill.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For it ſhews a great drought of the bodie, and weakneſs of the brains forces.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </head>
                  <p>After the Iliack paſſion, or colick the hicket, raveing, or convulſion are evil.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Which are cauſed by the foulneſs of the ſtomack and conſent which is between the braine and the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 11.</head>
                  <p>After a pleuriſie, an Inflamation of the lungs is evill.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="154" facs="tcp:58567:176"/>
                     <hi>Becauſe it ſignifies that part of the noxious humors is gone from the Ieſs noble part of the ribbs, to the more noble viz. the lungs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 12.</head>
                  <p>A phrenſie after an inflamation of the lungs is evill.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The inflamation of the lungs, ſending up vapours into the head, and they poſſeſſing the braine cauſe a Phrenſie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 13.</head>
                  <p>A Convulſion, or the Cramp, after hot burnings, are evill,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe it ſignifies a great dryneſs of the nerves or ſinewes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 14.</head>
                  <p>Aſtoniſhment and raving through ſome blow of the head is an evill ſigne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe it ſignifies that the wound hath penetrated to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>raine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="aphorism">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:176" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:177" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:58567:177"/>
                  <head>APH. 15.</head>
                  <p>The ſpitting out of corrupt matter, after the ſpitting of blood is evill.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe it ſignifies that the lungs are exulcerated.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 16.</head>
                  <p>A conſumption<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and a Flux of the haire or of the bellie, coming after the ſpitting of corrupt matter are evilſignes, for when the ſpitting is ſtopped, the diſeaſed doe die.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The firſt part of this Aphoriſme is averred, Aphoriſm. 11. and 12. of the 5 Section, to which we referr you. The reaſon of the ſecond part is becauſe if the ſpitting be ſtopped, the lungs are ſo oppreſſed with the abundance of flegme lying on them, that the patient is ſuffocated and ſtrangled, for want of breath.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 17.</head>
                  <p>The hicket comming through an inflamation of the liver is evill.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="156" facs="tcp:58567:178"/>
                     <hi>For it ſhews the greatneſs of the inflamation, of which the ſtomack alſo participates, and being bitten by ſtore of choller ſwiming in it, it cauſes the hicket,</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 18.</head>
                  <p>A convulſion or raving cauſed through watching is an evill thing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For watching doth extreamly evacuate and exiccate the body; which cauſeth both the raving and convulſion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 19.</head>
                  <p>After the laying bare of a bone, the inflamation and hot tumor <hi>Eriſipelas</hi> is evill.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For it ſheweth a confluction thither of hot blood and choler, which corrode, and conſume the ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>jacent fleſh.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 20.</head>
                  <p>Putrefaction or impoſtuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion after, from the inflamation <hi>Eriſipelas</hi> is evill,</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:178" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:179" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="157" facs="tcp:58567:179"/>
                     <hi>For it ſhews the malignitie of the ſaid Eriſipelas, which doth not only exulcerate the upper parts of the bodie, but feeds deeper in, and creeps on to the ſound parts</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 21.</head>
                  <p>A Flux of blood, after a ſtrong pulſe in vlcers is evill.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt becauſe it ſhews an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame inflamation to be joyned to the ulcer; ſecondly becauſe this eruption or Flux cannot be, unleſs the month of the artery be opened:
which is very difficult to be ſtopp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 22.</head>
                  <p>After a long paine of the parts belonging to the bellie, an impoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humation is evill.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Which it muſt needs come to at laſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> unleſs death of the patient pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 23.</head>
                  <p>After avoiding of unmixed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:180" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="157" facs="tcp:58567:180"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>

                     <pb n="158" facs="tcp:58567:181"/>
downwards, a bloodie Flux is evill</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For ſuch humors will erode and periſh ſome parts of the inteſtines.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 24.</head>
                  <p>Raving or <hi>Delirium</hi> enſues af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the wound of a bone, if it pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate into the hollow or void ſpace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſpeaks here of the bones of the head onely, as appears by the 14. Aph.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 25.</head>
                  <p>A convulſion after the taking of a purging potion bringeth death.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe is ſignifies an incurable drought.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 26.</head>
                  <p>A great cold of the uttermoſt parts, through vehement paine of the parts belonging to the bellie is evill.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The reaſon whereof is ſet downe in the comment of the 1. Aphoriſm of this Sect.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="aphorism">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:181" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:182" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="159" facs="tcp:58567:182"/>
                  <head>APH. 27.</head>
                  <p>If the diſeaſe called <hi>Teneſmus</hi> ſhall happen to a woman with child, it is the cauſe of abortment.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Teneſmus is a great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation or deſire to goe to ſtoole, and when they come thither can doe nothing.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 28.</head>
                  <p>If either a bone, cartilage or ſinew, ſhall be cut in the bodie, it doth neither increaſe nor grow together againe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This was ſpoken afore in the 19. Aphoriſm Sect 6.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 29.</head>
                  <p>If a ſtrong Flux of the bellie ſhall come upon him that is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed, with a dropſie called <hi>Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cophlegmatia,</hi> it diſſolveth and cureth the diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe it evacuates the efficient cauſe of the diſeaſe, which is abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of white flegme, from whence alſo comes the diſeaſes name.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:58567:183"/>
                  <head>APH. 30.</head>
                  <p>They have a falling down of flegmatick humors from the head, which doe a vid froathie excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments out of the bellie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For phlegmatick humors being windie, it is no marvell if they be froathie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 31.</head>
                  <p>Sediments in urines, made in the time of agues like unto courſe wheat-meal doe ſignifie that the ſickneſs ſhall continue long.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For it ſhews a kind of groſs thick humor, which cannot be diſolved or voided in a ſhort ſpace.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 32.</head>
                  <p>Cholerick ſediments in urins, which at the firſt were thinn, doe ſignifie a ſharp diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For choller always cauſeth ſharp diſeaſes. And urines are always faithfull meſſengers of the affections of the veines.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="aphorism">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:183" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:184" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:58567:184"/>
                  <head>APH. 33.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which makes diverſe urines, have a vehement diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance in their bodie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For when the urines are ſo, it ſhews a manifoldneſs of humors to be viciouſly diſeaſed</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 34.</head>
                  <p>The urins in which bubbles doe ſwim a loft, ſignifie a diſeaſe of the reins, and that the diſeaſe will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure long.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For thoſe bubbles proceding from humiditie which is extended about by a flatuous ſpirit, doe cauſe a cold diſeaſe which cold diſeaſes are long.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 35.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe to whom a fattneſs ſwims upon their vrine together &amp; on a ſodain, it is a ſigne the diſeaſe is in the reins, and aſharp one too.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For if the diſeaſe were in the whole bodie, it would come forth by little and little, and it is a ſharp 
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:58567:185"/>
one, for the head of it melts the fat of the reins.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 36.</head>
                  <p>If alſo paines be cauſed to thoſe which are diſeaſed with the grief of the kidneys about the muſcles of the back bone, and have the ſignes aboveſaid, if they be felt towards the outward parts, look and expect that the impoſthume ſhall be alſo outwardly. But if the pains bend and decline rather to the inward parts, we muſt then expect the impoſthume will be inwards</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Namely if the paine hath been long and great.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="37" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 37.</head>
                  <p>Vomiting of blood is wholſome to them which doe it without a Feaver: but if it be with a Feaver it is an evill thing, and the cure and remedie of the ſame, is to be performed with things that have a cooling and binding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ualitie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:185" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:186" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="163" facs="tcp:58567:186"/>
                     <hi>All vomits of blood are bad, Sect. 4. Aphoriſme. 25, therefore this muſt be here underſtood com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively, namely that it is more tolerable without, then with a Feaver.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="38" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 38.</head>
                  <p>Diſtillations upon the upper bellie come to ſuppuration and ripeneſs within twenty dayes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By the upper belly, he means the ſtomach, whoſe heat cauſeth the ſuppuration to be made ſo ſoon.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="39" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH 39</head>
                  <p>If any one piſs blood, or clots of blood, and be diſeaſed with the Strangury, the pain falling into the <hi>Perinaeum, Hypogaſtrium,</hi> and <hi>Pectinem,</hi> the places and part about the bladder are diſeaſed.</p>
                  <p>Perinaeum <hi>is the part between the privie Members and the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dament.</hi> Hypogaſtrium <hi>the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the belly: And</hi> Pecten

<pb n="164" facs="tcp:58567:187"/>
                     <hi>that part under the bellie where the haire grows.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="40" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 40</head>
                  <p>If a mans tongue ſodainly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come feeble, or any part of the body benummed without feeling, it is a ſigne of melancholie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For they proceeded from a thick juice which is partly melancholie partlie phlegmatick.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="41" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 41.</head>
                  <p>If the hicket happen to old men, purged above meaſure it is not good.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe ſuch a hicket is bad in all, eſpeciallie in old men, becauſe in them all diſeaſes are greater, and more to he doubted by reaſon of the imbecilitie of that age.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="42" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 42.</head>
                  <p>If the feaver be not cauſed by choller, much warm water poured upon the head doth diſolve it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:187" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:188" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="165" facs="tcp:58567:188"/>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder the name of choler <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e doth here comprehend all other humors, as Phlegme, blood and black choler.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="43" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 43.</head>
                  <p>A woman hath not the uſe of both hands alike,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By reaſon of the imbecilitie of womans nature.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="44" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 44.</head>
                  <p>If a cleare and white matter doe iſſue out from them which are affected with corrupt matter, when they ſuffer cauterizing or inciſion, they doe eſcape: but if bloodie, ſtinking, and filthy matter doe iſſue forth, they die.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By being affected with corrupt matter he means all which have anie corrupt tumor, but eſpecially ſuch as have it gathered between the lungs and the breſt,</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="45" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 45.</head>
                  <p>If clear and white matter doe 
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:58567:189"/>
iſſue from them whoſe liver is corrupted, and is burnt, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover health: for the corrupt matter is contained in the coat, but if that which cometh forth be like the lees of oyle they die.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The reaſon of the Aphoriſm is ſet down in it, when he ſaith, the matter is contained in the coat, for if it pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate into the fleſh or ſubſtance of the liver they dye.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="46" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 46.</head>
                  <p>Cure and heale pains of the eyes, which proceed from drinking of ſtrong wine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and bathing in hot water, by opening of a veyne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſme is by Gallen and Heurnius held to be ſpurious and not worthy of Hypocrates; alludes to the 31. Aphoriſm of the 6
Section, yet it much differs from it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="47" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 47.</head>
                  <p>If a cough come upon one diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed with the dropſie, he is irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverable</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This and the 35 Aphoriſme of the 6 Section are all one.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="48" type="aphorism">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:189" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:190" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:58567:190"/>
                  <head>APH. 48</head>
                  <p>Drinking of neat ſtrong wine, and the opening of a veine diſſolves the <hi>Strangurie</hi> and <hi>Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie,</hi> but the inward veins muſt be opened.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſpeakes not of all Stranguries and Dyſuries, but only of that Strangurie or dropping of urine, which is cauſed by coldneſs, and of that Dyſurie, or the urines painful comming out, which proceeds from a viſcous and flatuous humor.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="49" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 49.</head>
                  <p>A ſwelling and redneſs ariſing on the breſt of him who have a Squiancie is good, for the diſeaſe inclineth outwards.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This differs nothing from the 37
of the ſixt Section, but only in the place of the redneſſes ariſing, ſo that in both, Hippocrates ſcope is to ſhew that in this diſeaſe it is good to have thè humors tend outward.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="50" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="168" facs="tcp:58567:191"/>
                  <head>APH. 50.</head>
                  <p>They die within three dayes, whoſe braine begins to corrupt, but if they overpaſſe them, they ſhall recover their health.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe the brain is a principal and moſt noble part: But if they ſcape three daies it may be hoped, the diſeaſe may remitt and that the naturall forces will ouercome it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="51" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 51.</head>
                  <p>Sneezing is provoked out of the head, the brain being much heated, or the void ſpace of the head being much moiſtned: For the aire incloſed within, doth breake forth; and it makes a noiſe becauſe it paſſeth through a narrow place.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſpeaks in this Aphoriſme only of that ſneezing which is cauſed by the motion if nature deſires to driue out flatuous ſpirit out of the head.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="52" type="aphorism">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:191" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:192" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="169" facs="tcp:58567:192"/>
                  <head>APH. 52.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe who are grieved with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement pain of the Liver, are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from it, if an Ague come upon them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Which vehement pain cometh by windineſs which the feaver diſperſes</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="53" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 53.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which have occaſion to have blood taken from them, muſt be let blood in the Spring.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This is part of the Aph. 47. Sect. 6 look upon that's Comment.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="54" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 54.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which have phlegm in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed between the ventricle and the middriff, which is painful to them, having no paſſage into ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the bellies, are delivered from the diſeaſe, the phlegm be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing turned through the veins into the body.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Matter may come out of the veins into any place of the body, and being 
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:58567:193"/>
extenuated return into them again.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="55" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 55.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe have their belly filled with water and die, whoſe Liver reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht with water, makes an erupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it in the upper part of the belly where the Caul is.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm ſpeaks what is for the moſt part, for by the help of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and medicaments ſuch may be cured.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="56" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 56.</head>
                  <p>Wine being drunk with an equal proportion of water, puts away ſorrow, yawning, and cold ſhaking</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For wine by its moderate heat ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels moſt of thoſe matters which cauſe theſe ſymptomes and temper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the reſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="57" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 57.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which have a little ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the urinary paſſage, they are delivered from it, the ſame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought to ſuppuration and broken.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:193" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:194" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="171" facs="tcp:58567:194"/>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm is the ſame as the 82 of the fourth Secton where it was explained.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="58" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 58.</head>
                  <p>They muſt of neceſſity become dumb preſently, which have their brain vehemently ſhaken &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by ſome outward occaſion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the word dumbneſs he here comprehends all other voluntary motions.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="59" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 59.</head>
                  <p>Hunger and faſting is to be indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by bodies conſiſting of moiſt fleſh. For faſting dryeth the body.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He means ſo much faſting as will ſerve to correct the humidity of the fleſh.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="60" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 60.</head>
                  <p>Where there is alteration in the whole body, and it becometh cold and hot again, or changeth from one colour to another, it ſigniſies length of the diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="172" facs="tcp:58567:195"/>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm is repeated from that which is Sect. 4. Aph. 40.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="61" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 61.</head>
                  <p>Much ſweat hot and dry fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently iſſuing forth, declares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of moiſtneſs, which in a ſtrong body is to be vacuated up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, in a weak one downwards.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm is thought by</hi> Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len <hi>to be ſpurious, and alſo the three following, yet</hi> Heurnius <hi>ſaith no ſuch thing. But ſaith this Aphoriſm means that ſweat which proceeds from ſuperabundance of moiſture, and not from plenty of food.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="62" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 62.</head>
                  <p>If Agues become more fierce and vehement every third day without intermiſſion they are dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous. But in what manner ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they ſhall ceaſe it ſignifieth they are void of danger.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="63" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 63.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which are afflicted with 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:195" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:196" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="173" facs="tcp:58567:196"/>
long Feavers have little ſwellings or aches in the joynts.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="64" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 64.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which have long ſwellings or pains in the joynts after a Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, do uſe too plentiful a diet.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe three laſt Aphoriſms are the ſame with the 43, 44, and 45
of the fourth Section, where they have been already explained.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="65" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 65.</head>
                  <p>If any give the meat to one ſick of a Feaver, which he giveth to a healthful perſon, he ſhall ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the healthful perſon, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the malady of the ſick.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm alſo is falſly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to <hi>Hippocrates.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="66" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 66.</head>
                  <p>We muſt look upon thoſe things which paſs through the bladder, whether they be ſuch as iſſue forth in proſperous health. For thoſe which are unlike them, are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>healthful 
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:58567:197"/>
ſignes, but thoſe which are like them, are healthful ſignes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm ſpeaks that which</hi> Hippocrates <hi>in a manner ſpeaks elſewhere: yet becauſe it hath nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the form nor phraſe of</hi> Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates, Galen <hi>rejects it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="67" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 67.</head>
                  <p>Alſo when the ſediments, if thou ſhalt ſuffer them to reſt, and ſhalt not move them, do ſink down into the bottom like ſhavings of guts or ſuch like matter, if they be few, they ſignifie the diſeaſe is but little; but if they be many, that it is great Then it is neceſſary to evacuate the belly downwards; otherwiſe if thou ſhalt give broth and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhments, without purging the belly, the more thou giveſt, the more thou ſhalt offend.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm</hi> Galen <hi>holds to be foiſted in by ſome ſophiſter and lover of obſcurity and to be none of</hi> Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="68" type="aphorism">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:197" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:198" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="175" facs="tcp:58567:198"/>
                  <head>APH. 68.</head>
                  <p>Crude, raw and undigeſted excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments voided downwards, do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from black choller. If they be many, they proceed from a more copious quantity, if they be few, from a leſſer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm participates of the formers obſcurity, and by ſome is joyned to it and made the latter part of the other.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="69" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 69.</head>
                  <p>Spittings, in Feavers not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting, aſh-coloured bloodyiſh, cholerick, ſtinking, are all evil. But if they come forth conveniently and eaſily they are good, whether they iſſue out by the belly or bladder. And if any thing ſtays unpurged which ſhould have come forth, it is evil.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm is in a manner the ſame with the 47 of the fourth Section</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="70" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="176" facs="tcp:58567:199"/>
                  <head>APH. 70.</head>
                  <p>When any one goeth about to purge unclean bodies, he muſt make them ſoluble and fluxible.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm hath alſo been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained in the tenth Aph. of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Section.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="71" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 71.</head>
                  <p>Sleep and watchfulneſs, if they exceed a meaſure, are a diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This is alſo the ſame Aphoriſm in ſubſtance with the third of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Section,</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="72" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 72.</head>
                  <p>In Feavers not intermitting, if the exterior parts be cold, and the inward burning and the patient have a Feaver.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm was better ſet down Sect. 4. Aph. 48. for why ſhould he add at the end of this, if the patient have a Feaver when he had already ſaid in the beginning, In Feavers not intermitting.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="73" type="aphorism">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:199" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58567:200" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="177" facs="tcp:58567:200"/>
                  <head>APH. 73.</head>
                  <p>In a Feaver not intermitting, if a lip, noſe, eye, or eye-brow be perverted and turned awry, if the ſick man do not ſee nor hear, whatſoever of theſe things ſhall happen to a weak ſick man, death is neer at hand.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm is the ſame with the 49 of Sect. 4.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="74" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 74.</head>
                  <p>After white phlegme comes a Dropſie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Namely when the body and its veſſels, are abundantly filled with it</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="75" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 75.</head>
                  <p>From a looſeneſs of the belly, proceeds a bloody-flux.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Not from all looſneſſes, but onely ſuch as are long laſting, and bilious as Aph 23.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="76" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 76.</head>
                  <p>After a bloody-flux comes a Lienteria.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="178" facs="tcp:58567:201"/>
                     <hi>Which is a flux of undigeſted meat. See Sect. 6. Aph. 43.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="77" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 77.</head>
                  <p>After the corruption of the bone comes the impoſt humation of it called in Greek <hi>Sphaceliſmos.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may be alſo taken for a Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grening of the fleſh about it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="78" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 78.</head>
                  <p>After vomiting of blood, a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, and an evacuation of filthy purulent matter doth enſue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Aphoriſm is ſet down ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ways, but I have followed</hi> Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens <hi>expoſition.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="79" type="aphorism">
                  <head>APH. 79.</head>
                  <p>We ought to behold what things they be which paſs out by urines or by the belly, and what things iſſue out through the fleſh. And we muſt alſo conſider and behold whether the body do decline in any other thing from nature. For if little be a voided the diſeaſe is 
<pb facs="tcp:58567:201" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb facs="tcp:58567:202" rendition="simple:additions"/>

                     <pb n="179" facs="tcp:58567:202"/>
little, if much, the diſeaſe is great, and if very much it is deadly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To the end that the Phyſician may know the diſeaſe, he muſt take ſpecial notice of the excrements, and examine them in ſubſtance, quantity, quality, and the time and manner of getting them out. For the excrements repreſent the Idea of thoſe parts from whence they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
