<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some necessary and important considerations (to be consider'd of by all sorts of people) taken out of (that late worthy and renowned judge) Sir Matthew Hale's writings, and therein his own experience of the inward and invisible guidance of the spirit of God.</title>
            <author>Hale, Matthew, Sir, 1609-1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-03">2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44311</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H261</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17681</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12600025</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12600025</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64156</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A44311)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64156)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 318:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some necessary and important considerations (to be consider'd of by all sorts of people) taken out of (that late worthy and renowned judge) Sir Matthew Hale's writings, and therein his own experience of the inward and invisible guidance of the spirit of God.</title>
                  <author>Hale, Matthew, Sir, 1609-1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The tenth edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are freely given away by me ... John Pennyman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devotional literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64156:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SOME <hi>Neceſſary and Important</hi> CONSIDERATIONS, (TO BE Conſider'd of by all ſorts of People) Taken out of (That late Worthy and Renowned Judge) Sir. <hi>MATTHEW HALE</hi>'s WRITINGS: And therein His own Experience of the Inward, and Inviſible Guidance of the Spirit of GOD.</p>
            <q>The Righteous ſhall be had in Everlaſting Remembrance.
</q>
            <bibl>Pſal. CXII. 6.</bibl>
            <q>Bleſſed are the Dead that Die in the LORD, They Reſt from their Labours; and their Works follow them.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>The Tenth Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed, 1697. And are freely given away by me (who am given up to Spend, and be Spent, for the Everlaſting Well-being of all Mankind) <hi>John Pennyman.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:64156:2"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Character of Judge <hi>Hale.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SIR <hi>Matthew Hale,</hi> That <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwearied Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; That Prudent Man; That Solid Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher; That Famous Lawyer; That <hi>PILLAR</hi> and <hi>BASIS</hi> of <hi>JUSTICE;</hi> (who would not have done an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt Act, if or any Worldly Price, or Motive) That <hi>Godly, Serious, Practical Chriſtian, The Lover of Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and all Good Men.</hi>— That great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temner of the Riches, Pomp, and Vanity of the World; Who, while He fled from the Honour that perſu'd Him, was yet made Lord Chief Juſtice of the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> after His being long Lord Chief Baron of the <hi>Exchequer;</hi> Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Dying—with the moſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Love, and Honour, and Praiſe, that ever did any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subject in this Age, or any that juſt Hiſtory doth acquaint us with, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>JUdge <hi>Hale</hi> was a Perſon well Known, yet Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known; a Publick, yet Hidden Man; which State, was, and is, as yet, known but to few.</p>
            <p>He that Reads this Little Book, in a Serious, and Weighty Mind, may, as in a Glaſs, plainly ſee how it is betwixt GOD and his own Soul.</p>
            <q>What Man is he that Feareth the LORD? Him ſhall HE Teach in the way that HE ſhall chuſe.</q>
            <bibl>Pſal. 25.12.</bibl>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64156:2"/>SOME <hi>Neceſſary and Important</hi> CONSIDERATIONS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
         </head>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The following is taken out of <hi>The Great Audit:</hi> With the Account of <hi>The Good Steward. </hi>
            </head>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>As Touching my Conſcience.</head>
               <p>I Have been very diligent to keep my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence Clean, to Incourage It in the Vicegerency that THOU, [the great <hi>LORD</hi> of the World] haſt given It over my Soul and Actions. I have kept It in the Throne and greateſt Reverence and Authority in my Heart.</p>
               <p>In Actions to be Done or Omitted, I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Adviſed with It, and taken Its Adviſe; I have neither Stifled, nor Forced, nor Bribed It; but gave It a free Liberty to Adviſe and Speak out, and a free Subjection of my Will, Purpoſes, and Actions to It.</p>
               <p>If, through Importunity of Temptations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I have at any time done Amiſs, I have not taken Her up ſhort, or ſtopped Her Mouth, or my own Attention to Her Chiding and Reproof; but I have, with much Submiſſion of Mind, born Her Chaſtiſement, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved it to an Humbling of my ſelf before THEE for my Failings; for I looked upon Her as Acting
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64156:3"/>
by THY Authority, for THY Service, and to THY Glory; and I durſt not Diſcourage, Diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, or Diſobey Her.</p>
               <p>When She was Pleaſed, and gave me Good Words, I was Glad; for I eſteemed Her as a Glaſs that repreſented to my Soul the Favour or Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of GOD Himſelf, and how HE ſtood affected towards me.</p>
               <p>I have more Trembled under the Fear of a Sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or Diſcouraged Conſcience, than under the Fear of a Sharp or Scrupulous Conſcience? becauſe I always accounted the Latter, tho' more Trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, yet more Safe.</p>
               <p>I have been very jealous, either of Wounding,<note n="*" place="margin">A Wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Spirit who can bear?</note> or Grieving, or Diſcouraging, or Deadning my Conſcience. I have therefore choſen rather to forbear that which ſeemed but Indifferent, leſt there ſhould be ſome-what in it that might be Unlawful; and would rather Gratifie my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, with being too Scrupulous, than Diſpleaſe, Diſquiet, or Flat It, by being too Venturous: I have ſtill choſen rather to Forbear what might be Probably Lawful, than to Do that which might be Poſſibly Unlawful; becauſe I could not Err in the Former, I might in the Latter.</p>
               <p>I have been careful to adviſe Impartially with my Conſcience before my Actions; But leſt I had commited any thing Amiſs, either in the Nature or Manner of the Action, I commonly, every Night, brought my Actions of the Day paſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Judicatory of my Conſcience, and left Her to a Free and Impartial Cenſure of them; and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64156:3"/>
what She Sentenced Well Done, I with Humility returned the Praiſe thereof to THY Name; what She Sentenced Done Amiſs, I did humbly ſue unto THEE for Pardon, and for Grace to prevent me from the like Miſcarriages. By this means I kept my Conſcience Active, Renewed, and preſerved my Peace with THEE, and learned Vigilance and Caution for the Time to come.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Touching THY Creatures.</head>
               <p>I have not only looked upon THY Bleſſings and Bounty, in Lending me THY own Creatures for my Uſe; but I have ſought unto THEE for a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon them, in my Uſe of them. I did very well obſerve, That there is by my Sin a Curſe in the very Creatures that I receive, unleſs THY Bleſſing fetch it out; an Emptineſs in them, unleſs THY Goodneſs fill them: Tho' THOU ſhouldeſt give me Quails and Manna from Heaven, yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out THY Bleſſing upon them, they would become Rottenneſs and Putrifaction to me; and therefore I ever begg'd THY Bleſſing upon THY Bleſſings, as well as the Bleſſings themſelves; and attributed the Good I Found, or was to Expect in them, to the Same HAND that Gave them.</p>
               <p>I received and uſed THY Creatures, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to me under a Truſt, and as a Steward and Accomptant for them; and therefore I was always careful to uſe them according to thoſe Limits, and in order for thoſe Ends, for which THOU didſt commit them to me: 1ſt. With Temperance and Moderation; I did not uſe THY Creatures to Luxury and Exceſs, to make Proviſion for my
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64156:4"/>
Luſts, with vain Glory or Oſtentation, but for the convenient Support of the Exigencies of my Nature and Condition; and if at any time THY Goodneſs did indulge me an Uſe of them for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, as well as Neceſſity, I did it but Rarely and Watchfully; I looked not upon the <hi>Wine,</hi> when it gave its colour in the Cup; nor gave my ſelf over either to Exceſs or Curioſity in <hi>Meats</hi> or <hi>Drinks;</hi> I checked my Self therein, as being in THY Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and ſtill remembred I had THY Creatures under an Accompt; and was ever careful to avoid Exceſs or Intemperance, becauſe every Exceſſive Cup and Meal was in danger to leave me ſome-what in <hi>Super,</hi> and Arear to my <hi>LORD.</hi> 2dly. With Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Compaſſion to the Creatures themſelves, which THOU haſt put under my Power and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal. When I conſidered the Admirable Powers of Life and Senſe which I ſaw in the Birds and Beaſts, and that all the Men in the World could not give the like Being to any thing, nor reſtore that Life and Senſe which is once Taken from them; When I conſidered how Innocently and Harmleſly the Fowls, and Fiſh, and Sheep, and Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en take their Food, that THOU, the LORD of All, haſt given them, I have been apt to think that ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly THOU didſt intend a more Innocent kind of Food to Man, than ſuch as muſt be taken with ſuch Detriment to thoſe Living parts of THY Creation; and although THY wonderful Goodneſs hath ſo much Indulged to Man-kind, as to give up the Lives of theſe Creatures for the Food of Man by THY expreſs Commiſſion, yet I ſtill do, and ever did think, that there was a <hi>Juſtice due</hi> from Man,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64156:4"/>
even <hi>to theſe Senſible Creatures,</hi> that he ſhould take them Sparingly, for Neceſſity, and not for Delight; or if for Delight, yet not for Luxury: I have been apt to think, That if there were any more Liberal uſe of Creatures for Delight or Variety, it ſhould be of Fruits, or ſuch other Delicacies as might be had without the loſs of Life; But however it be, this very Conſideration hath made me very Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and Careful, not Vainly, or Superfluouſly, or Unneceſſarily, or Prodigally, to take away the Life of THY Creatures for Feaſting and Exceſs. And the very ſame Conſideration hath always gone a long with me, <hi>in reference to the Labour of</hi> THY <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> I have ever thought that there was a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain degree of Juſtice due from Man to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as from Man to Man; and that an exceſſive, immoderate, unſeaſonable Uſe of the Creatures Labour, is an Injuſtice for which he muſt Accompt.</p>
               <p>To deny Domeſtical Creatures their convenient Food; to exact that Labour from them that they are not able to perform; to uſe Extremity or Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty towards them, is a breach of that Truſt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which the Dominion of the Creatures was committed to us, and a breach of that Juſtice that is due from Men to them; and therefore I have always eſteemed it as part of my Duty, and it hath been always my Practice, to be Merciful to my Beaſts; and upon the ſame Account I have ever eſteemed it a breach of Truſt, and have according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declined any Cruelty to any of THY Creatures; and as much as I might, prevented it in others, as a Tyranny, inconſiſtent with the Truſt and Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardſhip that THOU haſt committed to me. I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64156:5"/>
have abhorred thoſe Sports that conſiſt in the Torturing of the Creatures; and if either Noxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Creatures muſt be Deſtroyed, or Creatures for Food muſt be Taken, it hath been my Practice to do it in that manner, that may be with the leaſt Torture or Cruelty to the Creature; and I have ſtill thought it an Unlawful thing to Deſtroy thoſe Creatures for Recreation-ſake, that either were not Hurtful when they Lived, or are not Profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble when they are Killed; ever remembering that tho THOU haſt given us a Dominion over THY Creatures; yet it is under a Law of Juſtice, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and Moderation; otherwiſe we ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Tyrants, not Lords, over THY Creatures; and therefore thoſe things of this nature, that others have practiſed as Recreations, I have avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as Sins.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Touching my Body.</head>
               <p>My Body, which was given to Serve, and Obey, became the Empreſs, and Commanded, and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted my Soul; Embaſed and Enſlav'd It to Luſt and Diſorder; and my Soul, which was given to Rule, became but the Slave of my Body: I Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd, That if the buſineſs was thus carried, my Happineſs muſt be only in this Life; and that when Death ſeiz'd upon me, I had an <hi>Immortal Soul</hi> that had loſt Her time wholly in this World; and therefore could expect nothing but Vexation and Everlaſting Confuſion to all Eternity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Upon theſe, and the like Conſiderations, I Reſolved, and Practic'd Severity over my Body; and refuſed to Gratify her Intemperate Deſires: Deny'd them, kept them in Awe, and under Diſſipline; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64156:5"/>
I found that my Luſts grew Unruly, by Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety and Curioſſity of <hi>Meats</hi> and <hi>Drinks;</hi> I Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued them by Moderate Dyet, and Temperance.</p>
               <p>My Table was Sparing to my Self, my Cloaths Plain, my Retinue, and Attendance, but Neceſſary: I chaſed away my Luſts, with the Contemplations of the Preſence of GOD, the End of CHRIST's Sufferings, the Certainty, yet Uncertainty of Death, the State after Death; and mingled all my Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Deſires, with theſe ſerious and clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Conſiderations; and I Peremptorily refuſed to gratify the cravings of an Inordinate, Senſual Appetite; and did reſolutely let them know, they ſhould not, might not expect any better dealing from me; and my Practice was accordingly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Concerning my Wealth.</head>
               <p>The more I had, the more was my Care, and the greater the Charge that I had under my Hands, and the more was my Solicitude to be a Faithful Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard of it, to the Honour and Uſe of my MASTER; but my part was the leaſt that was in it: Indeed I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced in this, that my MASTER eſteemed me Faithful, committing the Diſpenſation thereof to my Truſt; but I thought it no more mine, than the Lords Baily, or the Merchants Caſh-keeper, thinks his Maſters Rents or Mony his.</p>
               <p>And therefore thought it would be a breach of my Truſt to Conſume or Embezil that Wealth in Exceſſive Superfluities of <hi>Meat, Drink</hi> or <hi>Apparel,</hi> or in advancing my Self, or my Poſterity, to a maſſy or huge Acqueſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:64156:6"/>
               <head>Touching my Reputation.</head>
               <p>Tho' I have loved my Reputation, and have been vigilant not to loſe or impair it by my own Default, or Neglect, yet, I have looked upon it as a brittle thing, a thing that the Devil aims to hit in a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial manner, a thing that is much in the Power of a Falſe Report, a Miſtake, a Miſ-apprehenſion, to wound and hurt; Notwithſtanding all my Care, I am at the Mercy of Others, without GOD's won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful over-ruling Providence. And as my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation is the eſteem that Others have of me, ſo that Eſteem may be Blemiſhed without my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault. I have therefore always taken this care, not to ſet my Heart upon my Reputation. I will uſe all Fidelity and Honeſty, and take care it ſhall not be loſt by any Default of mine; and if not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this, my Reputation be ſoiled by Evil or Envious Men or Angels, I will patiently bear it, and content my Self with the Serenity of my own Conſcience: <hi>Hic murus ahenius eſto.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The aforeſaid Author in His Book, <hi>Of the Nature of True Religion,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p. 17.</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>TRue Religion Teaches and Tutors the Soul to a high Reverence and Veneration of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty GOD, a Sincere and Upright Walking, as in the Preſence of the Inviſible, All-Seeing GOD: It makes a Man truly to Love, to Honour, to Obey HIM, and therefore careful to know what HIS Will is; It renders the Heart highly Thankful to HIM, both as his Creator, Redeemer, and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64156:6"/>
It makes a Man intirely to depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on HIM, to ſeek to HIM for Guidance, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and Protection; to Submit to HIS Will with all Patience, and Reſignation of Soul: It gives the Law not only to his Words and Actions, but to his very Thoughts and Purpoſes, that he dares not entertain Thoughts unbecoming the Sight and Preſence of that GOD, to Whom all our Thoughts are Legible: It teacheth and bringeth a Man to ſuch a deportment both of External and Internal Sobriety, as may be Decent in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of GOD and all HIS Holy Angels: It cruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and caſts down all Pride and Haughtineſs, both in a Mans Heart and Carriage, and gives him an Humble Frame of Soul, and Life, both in the ſight of GOD and Men: It Regulates and Governs the Paſſions of the Mind, and brings them into due Moderation and Frame: It gives a Man a right eſtimate of this preſent World, and ſets the Heart, and Hopes above it, ſo that he never Loves it more than it deſerves: It makes the Wealth, and the Glory of this World, high Places, and great Preferments, but of a low and little value to Him; ſo that He is neither Covetous, nor Ambitious, nor over Solicitous concerning the Advantages of it: It brings a Man to that Frame, that Righteouſneſs, Juſtice, Honeſty, and Fidelity is, as it were, part of His Nature; He can ſooner Dye, than Commit, or Purpoſe that which is Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, Diſhoneſt, or Unworthy a Good Man. It makes Him value the Love of GOD, and Peace of Conſcience, above all the Wealth, and Honour in the World, and to be very vigilant to keep it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violably:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64156:7"/>
— He performs all his Duties to GOD in Sincerity and Integrity; and whilſt he Lives on Earth, yet his Converſation, his Hopes, his Treaſure, is in Heaven; and he intirely endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to Walk ſutably to ſuch a Hope: This Man hath the Life of Religion in him, and that Life Acts in him, and will conform his Soul to the Image of his SAVIOUR, and to Walk along with HIM to all Eternity.</p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <p>GOD hath given to the Sons of Men,<note place="margin">Knowledge of GOD, <hi>p. 286, 287.</hi>
                  </note> in reſpect of Senſual Things, Objects, not only for Neceſſity, but Delight; But here is their Miſery, as well as their Sin, That they reſt not in what GOD Lawfully allows.— And hence it is, that the GOD of Mercy Curſes, and that moſt Juſtly, HIS own Bleſſings, unto that Man that thus Perverts the Uſe of them. <hi>Wine</hi> Rejoyceth the Heart of Man, as it was given for that end, but when a Man in the Uſe of it looks no higher, but to Satiate himſelf, there is a Sting put into it, and t proves a Serpent. <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.32.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Touching the Conſcience.</head>
               <p>COnſcience is GOD's Vicegerent in Man,<note n="*" place="margin">Knowledge of GOD. p. 269.</note> and when Her LORD is Angry, the Conſcience will Chide: It is a Glaſs, wherein a Man may, by Reflection, ſee the Face of Heaven, and of his own Soul.</p>
               <p>If thy Conſcience blame thee, tho' never ſo little, Diſpiſe It not, nor Neglect this Secret Check,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64156:7"/>
it is a Meſſage from Heaven, that Summons thee to thy Duty. p. 372.</p>
               <p>Certainly the ſenſe of the Love of GOD, is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Not at all, or not Awake, when any Man, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideratly, commits the leaſt Sin againſt his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. p. 297.</p>
               <p>The Direction of Conſcience, when It is well us'd, is ſeldom without the Immediat Direction of the very Spirit of GOD, but if the Guidance of that Spirit be Neglected, it will not Return to thy Aſſiſtance when thou Pleaſeſt. p. 369.</p>
               <p>There is nothing in the World condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth more to the Compoſure and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity of the Mind,<note place="margin">Contemp. p. 373.</note> than the Serenity and Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Conſcience; keep but That Safe and Untainted, the Mind will enjoy a Calm and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity in the midſt of all the Storms of the World. And although the Waves beat, and the Sea works, and the Winds blow; the Mind that hath a Quiet and Clear Conſcience within, will be as Stable and as Safe from Perturbation as a Rock in the midſt of a Tempeſtuous Sea, and will be a <hi>Goſhen</hi> to, and within, it ſelf, when the reſt of the World without, is like an <hi>Aegypt</hi> for Plagues and Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>Whatever thou doſt Hazard, or Loſe, keep the Integrity of thy Conſcience, both before Troubles come, and under them; it is a Jewel will make thee Rich in the midſt of Poverty, a Sun that will give thee Light in the midſt of Darkneſs, a Fortreſs that will keep thee Safe in the greateſt Danger, and that is never to be taken from thee, unleſs thou thy ſelf Betray it, and Deliver it up.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:64156:8"/>
            <head>Judge <hi>Hale</hi>'s Experience of the Inward and Inviſible Guidance of the Spirit of GOD.</head>
            <p>THOSE that truly fear GOD, have a <hi>Secret Guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> from a higher Wiſdom than what is barely Humane; namely, <hi>The Spirit of Truth and Wiſdom,</hi> that doth Really and Truly, but <hi>Secretly,</hi> Prevent and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them. Any Man that Sincerely and Truly Fears Almighty GOD, relies upon HIM, &amp; calls upon HIM for HIS Guidance and Direction, hath it as Really as a <hi>Son</hi> hath the Counſel and Direction of his <hi>Father.</hi> And tho' the Voice be not Audible, nor the Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on always Perceptible, <hi>(or Diſcernable)</hi> to Senſe; yet it is equally as Real as if a Man heard the Voice ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>This is the Way, walk in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this ſecret Direction of Almighty GOD, is Principally ſeen in matters relating to the Good of the Soul; yet it may alſo be found in the Concerns of this Life, which a good Man, that fears GOD, and begs HIS Direction, ſhall very often, if not at all times find. <hi>Contemp. p.</hi> 45.</p>
            <p>I can call my <hi>own Experience</hi> to witneſs, That even in the External Actions of my whole Life, I was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver diſappointed of the beſt Guidance and Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when I have, in Humility and Sincerity, implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Secret Direction, and Guidance, of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Wiſdom. p. 323.</p>
            <p>The Obſervation of the Secret Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition of the Spirit of GOD in the Heart, as It is an Effectual Means,<note place="margin">Knowledge of GOD, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> pag. 331. 378. 391.</note> ſo It is a Calm and Comfortable Means to Cleanſe and Sanctify thy Heart; and the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64156:8"/>
more It is attended unto, the more It will be Converſant with thy Soul, for thy Inſtruction.— In the midſt of thy Difficulties, It will be thy Counſellour: In the midſt of thy Temptations, It will be thy Strength; and a Grace Sufficient for thee: In the midſt of thy Troubles, It will be thy Light, and thy Comforter: Only beware thou neglect not the Voice of This Spirit, it maybe thy Neglect may Quench It, and thou maiſt never hear that Voice more.</p>
            <p>It is impoſſible for thee to Enjoy That which muſt make thee Happy, till thou art deeply ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of thy own Emptineſs, and Nothingneſs; and thy Spirit thereby brought down, and laid in the Duſt.— The Spirit of CHRIST is an Humbling Spirit, the more thou haſt of It, the more It will Humble thee; and it is a Sign, that either thou haſt It not, or that It is yet over-maſter'd by thy Corruptions, if thy Heart be ſtill Haughty.</p>
            <p>Watch, therefore, the Secret Perſwaſions and Diſwaſions of the Spirit of GOD; and beware thou Quench It not, nor Grieve It; be ſure thou Obſerve This Voice.— This Wind that blows where It liſts, if Shut out, Reſiſted, or Grieved, may haply never Breath upon thee again, but leave thee to be Hardned in thy Sins: But if Obſerved, and Obeyed, thou ſhalt be ſure to have It thy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitor, and Director upon all Occaſions. <hi>When thou Goeſt, It will Lead thee, when thou Sleepeſt, It will Keep thee, and when thou Awakeſt, It will Talk with thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <argument>
               <p>[Theſe are Faithful, Weighty, and True Sayings; Happy are thoſe that Witneſs them ſo to be.]</p>
            </argument>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:64156:9"/>
            <p>This Little <hi>Tract,</hi> is a <hi>Treaſure</hi> worth keeping, and to be often Perus'd by People of all Perſwaſions: For We muſt all come to Judgment, To give an Account of our <hi>Talents</hi> and <hi>Stewardſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bleſſed, and Happy, yea, for ever Happy will that Perſon be, unto whom it ſhall be ſaid, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Well done, Good and Faithful Servant, enter Thou into the Joy of thy LORD.</q>
            <bibl>Mat. 25.23.</bibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
