<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A speech, spoken by Mr. Hayles, a student of University-Colledge of Oxford, and son to the Honourable Sir Edward Hayles With His Majesties gracious acceptance.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-12">2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44370</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H266B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216370</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828101</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828101</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32528</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A44370)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32528)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1926:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A speech, spoken by Mr. Hayles, a student of University-Colledge of Oxford, and son to the Honourable Sir Edward Hayles With His Majesties gracious acceptance.</title>
                  <author>Hales, Edward, 1669 or 70-1690.</author>
                  <author>Hales, John, Sir, d. 1744.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet (2 p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for A.M. ,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Edward Hales, eldest son of Sir Edward Hales, who was killed at the Battle of the Boyne. However, as it is unusual for the heir to a title to attend university, it is equally likely that the speech was that of his younger brother John, who became the third Baronet.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:32528:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SPEECH, SPOKEN BY Mr. HAYLES, A STUDENT of <hi>Univerſity-Colledge</hi> of OXFORD, And Son to the Honourable Sir Edward Hayles. With His Majeſties Gracious Acceptance.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Dread Sovereign,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE, Your Majeſties Humbleſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſts of this Houſe, have the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt reaſon to rejoyce in this your Majeſties preſence, in as much as this being the moſt Antient Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and Mother of all the reſt in your Dominions, hath been choſen out to begin the reſtitution of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which was firſt Planted and Watred by ſo many Eminent, Devout and Learned Perſons, of whom Four are accounted Saints in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Kalendar; And we hope that as Providence hath reſerv'd a Reformation to Your Majeſty, after ſo long and Deplorable a Breach; ſo You will be pleas'd to Protect and encourage this tender beginning amongſt Us: For the Winds and the Storms threaten us, yet being founded upon a double Rock, the one of Perpetuity of the Church: The other of your Majeſties Protection, We reſt Fearleſs, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve till it ſhall pleaſe our good Lord to ſettle it in that <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> which we confidently hope for in your Majeſties Life and Government. Next, VVe with the reſt of the Nation, acknowledge your Majeſties great Goodneſs for that abſolute Liberty granted to all your Subjects, reſtraining nothing but what is Eternally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Preſervation of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:32528:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>You have only hindred confeſſed VVickedneſs and Violence to one another, which could not have been committed without the Breach of all Laws, and utter Confuſion.</p>
            <p>And tho' you leave the Duty towards God, to every Conſcience, yet you have hereby taken off the Vizard of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and manifeſted to all the World, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever henceforth takes up Arms againſt your Power, muſt not pretend either <hi>Reformation</hi> or <hi>Religion,</hi> or <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice</hi> of the Government, as an <hi>Indulgence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, wherein your Majeſty and your Co-partners have the leaſt Portion; it is, Great <hi>Prince,</hi> an Exceſſive Kindneſs to your People, that your Self accepts ſparing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what upon others you ſo Bountifully beſtow; as if your Own Intereſt were the leaſt of your Care: And were the Nation United, your Own Self could be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be neglected. It is a long time ſince that the <hi>Wounds</hi> of this Nation have been ſtill wid'ned by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſed Perſons, applying only <hi>Coroſives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your Majeſty hath by powering in <hi>Oyl</hi> and <hi>Balm,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan an <hi>Unction</hi> and <hi>Coalition</hi> of the Parts. An <hi>Union</hi> at leaſt in the concerns of the Nation, tho' not (as we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire) an <hi>Unity</hi> in <hi>Religion.</hi> Yet ſo much of <hi>Religion</hi> too, as to be at Peace with One Another.</p>
            <p>And your Majeſty is now, by your Majeſties giving <hi>Warmth</hi> and <hi>Vigour</hi> to theſe deſires, making the whole Nation Witneſſes of the Sinerity of your Proceedings, as well as that of your Piety, Prudence, and moſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Example, in all Virtue, becoming either a Prince, or even a Private Perſon. VVe hope your Subjects will be made more Cautious, when They ſee ſo much of an Excellent and Divine Spirit, ſeconded with the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> of a <hi>Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor will they pretend <hi>Conſcience</hi> for <hi>Diſobedience,</hi> when they perceive Him, who Demands, to have better <hi>Conſcience</hi> than Themſelves.</p>
            <p>VVhich Speech His Majeſty was Graciouſly pleaſed, kindly to accept, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>A. M.</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
