<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A funeral sermon on the death of that pious gentlewoman Mrs. Judith Hamond Late wife of the Reverend Mr. George Hamond, minister of the Gospel in London. By John Howe, minister of the same Gospel.</title>
            <author>Howe, John, 1630-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-10">2005-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44680</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3029</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215976</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827732</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827732</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32155</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A44680)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32155)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1851:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A funeral sermon on the death of that pious gentlewoman Mrs. Judith Hamond Late wife of the Reverend Mr. George Hamond, minister of the Gospel in London. By John Howe, minister of the same Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Howe, John, 1630-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Parkhurst, at the Bible and Three Crowns at the lower end of Cheapside, near Mercers Chappel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCVI. [1696]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hamond, Judith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32155:1"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:32155:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
A <hi>Funeral Sermon</hi> ON THE DEATH Of that Pious Gentlewoman Mrs. <hi>JUDITH HAMOND.</hi> Late WIFE of the Reverend Mr. <hi>George Hamond,</hi> Minister of the Gospel in <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN HOWE,</hi> Minister of the same Gospel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurst,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> at the Lower End of <hi>Cheapside,</hi> near <hi>Mercers</hi> Chappel, MDCXCVI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:32155:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32155:2"/>
            <head>To the Reverend Mr. <hi>Hammond.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MY offering <hi>this Discourse</hi> to the <hi>Eye of the World</hi> together with <hi>your own,</hi> shews how <hi>great Power</hi> our <hi>Ancient Friendship</hi> hath given you, over me; whereof I have the less unpleasant Sense, believing <hi>you will understand it so;</hi> who, in great part, know how difficult, my circumstances made it, to me, to comply with your desire herein. <hi>Your O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion</hi> of the fitness of publishing so <hi>uncompos'd a thing,</hi> discovers how far <hi>you</hi> were subject <hi>also</hi> to the <hi>same Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer;</hi> whose Judgement I am little apt to distrust, where it meets not with <hi>this byas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It will be a <hi>joy to me,</hi> if it help to mitigate your Sorrow which is, in great part, justify'd, by the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of <hi>your Loss,</hi> in being separated, after so long Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation, from so <hi>Excellent a Consort,</hi> that lived in this World, so much above it.</p>
            <p>I reckon it an evidence of the <hi>real greatness</hi> of her Spirit that She thought <hi>that,</hi> so <hi>little a thing,</hi> wherein others place <hi>Greatness.</hi> And that in almost <hi>Forty Years Acquaintance</hi> with <hi>you both,</hi> I should never hear of her <hi>nearness</hi> to a <hi>Noble Family,</hi> till, occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally, since her Death. It seems <hi>the Blood</hi> that <hi>fill'd her Veins,</hi> did not <hi>swell her Mind.</hi> And her <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Birth</hi> and Relation to the <hi>House</hi> and <hi>Family of God,</hi> made her forget her <hi>Earthly Kindred,</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents House.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:32155:3"/>
SIR,</p>
            <p>Though, <hi>whom God hath joyn'd together, no man might put asunder;</hi> yet when he that made the <hi>Union,</hi> makes the <hi>Separation,</hi> there's no saying to him, <hi>What dost thou?</hi> We must a while, tug with the difficulties of our <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Work.</hi> Wherein <hi>the hope</hi> of helping <hi>Some</hi> (as God shall graciously help us) to gain <hi>this Victory over Death;</hi> and of being, at length, through his Grace, <hi>Victors our selves,</hi> will be a constant Releif and Support to <hi>you,</hi> and</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very respectful Brother and Fellow-Servant in the Labours of the Gospel. John Howe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:32155:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 COR. 15. 54. the latter part.</bibl>
               <q>—Death is swallowed up in Victory.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE <hi>foregoing words</hi> signify <hi>this saying</hi> to have been, before, written elsewhere. <hi>So when this corruptible shall have put on in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruption, and this mortal shall have put on immortality, then shall be brought to pass the saying that is written, Death is swallowed up,</hi> &amp;c. And we find it before-written, <hi>Isa.</hi> 25. 8. in express words; and <hi>Hos.</hi> 13. 14. in such as are equivalent. What their <hi>dependance</hi> or <hi>meaning</hi> is, in either of those places, cannot be discuss't, within our present, narrow, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits. Only it is sufficiently manifest that sundry passages in the <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> are said to be brought to pass, over, and over; once and again; as that of <hi>Rachels weeping for her Children:</hi> and of <hi>Gods bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Son out of Egypt:</hi> with divers others.</p>
            <p>This great <hi>saying</hi> may have had some partial and gradual accomplishment, <hi>within the current of time,</hi> when in reference to a People more specially related to God, and in some more notable delinquency, and defection from him, he may have given a just, but limited, Commission to <hi>Death,</hi> to make great ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage and destructions among them, so that it hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven rode in Triumph, made an huge Carnage, strow'd their Countrey with Carkasses, turn'd their rich Land, more enrich't with humane bloud, into an
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32155:4"/>
Akeldama; and thereupon, but into a place of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulture, and of Graves; And yet, when it hath gone as far as his designed limits, and executed all his pleasure, he may have stopt it in its Career, and said, <hi>hither thou shalt come and no further:</hi> Now, cease, and give over: (as <hi>Hos.</hi> 13. 14.) and so may have <hi>ransom'd</hi> the residue from the <hi>Power of the Grave,</hi> and been the destruction of their Destroyers, Plaguing them who were their plagues. This in the <hi>next intention</hi> hereof may respect the <hi>People of the Jews,</hi> who being returned from their (now foreseen) Captivity, might in the Propheti<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> style, be spoken of as a People risen from the Dead, and newly sprung up out of the Grave; but might have a <hi>further</hi> refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the yet-future state of the <hi>Christian Church,</hi> as <hi>Isa</hi> 25. 6, 7, 8. seems to carry it; when so great a Death as hath long been upon it, as well as the rest of the World, it may be hoped shall be swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd up in a very glorious victory!</p>
            <p>But <hi>this saying</hi> is introduced <hi>here,</hi> as having its fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and ultimate Completion, in conjunction with what is mention'd besides, in this context, <hi>viz.</hi> when <hi>in the close and shutting up of time,</hi> the <hi>Trumpet shall sound,</hi> as we are told elsewhere it shall at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Lord, and the dead (those that dy'd <hi>in him, first)</hi> be raised, the <note place="margin">1 Th. 4. 16.</note> 
               <hi>living changed,</hi> so as to bear <hi>his (the heavenly Adam's) image. When this corruptible shall have put on incorruption, and this mortal, immortality,</hi> then <hi>shall be brought to pass</hi> this saying (whatever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes thereto, <hi>as was written,</hi> there may have been before) <hi>Death is swallowed up in victory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And according to this its fullest sense, is <hi>this saying</hi> to be the subject of our present Consideration. The
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32155:4"/>
               <hi>Expression</hi> is highly <hi>Rhetorical,</hi> but there is a most <hi>rational</hi> solid <hi>sense</hi> intended under it, for which no words can be too big, or of too great a sound.</p>
            <p>Our business must be to <list>
                  <item>Explain, &amp;</item>
                  <item>Apply</item>
               </list>this saying.</p>
            <p>And,</p>
            <p n="1">I. For Explication of its rational Import, we shall shew,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Import.</item>
               <item>2. The Reasonableness of it.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. It imports, in general, Gods determination <hi>to put a perpetual end to death,</hi> to make it cease <hi>in perpetuum,</hi> as a noted <hi>Exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Grot. in loc.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> expresses it, shewing, that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel <hi>Hebrew Phrase</hi> is usually render<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>for ever,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 26. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3. 5. and <hi>in divers other places.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that we may give a more distinct account of its meaning, several things are to be noted;</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>Death,</hi> as it is here spoken of, supposes <hi>a certain, limited Subject.</hi> Its being mention'd in this <hi>Chapter,</hi> and elsewhere, as if it were, itself, a <hi>suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>situm,</hi> and an intelligent, designing One, is an ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant and an usual Figure. The Holy Scriptures, and Common Speech, abound with this sort of <hi>Prosopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poeia,</hi> And it hath its special usefulness, when (as in the present Case) what we are more to remark, and consider with greater intention of Mind, is so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented, <hi>i. e.</hi> when to things of minute, or of no entity, but of great concernment, (such meer priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as <hi>Death</hi> or <hi>Sin)</hi> a sort of Personality is ascri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32155:5"/>
attended with terrible aspects and appearances, it tends more effectually to rouze our minds, and engage our attention, whether we are to consider, and magnify our danger by them, or our deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and to behold them as attempting upon us, or as overcome. But speaking strictly, we must take things as in themselves they are. Death therefore must be considered, in reference to some subject or other. Abstractly considered, 'tis but a notion. As it actually hath taken place, it must be the death of this or that Person. And as it is finally to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and have an end, it must have a limited sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and not be understood of all, absolutely and universally; for then there would be no such thing as <hi>Eternal Death,</hi> which hath no end. And how the subject <hi>here</hi> supposed, is to be limited; the <hi>series</hi> of discourse thorough the <hi>Chapter</hi> shews, they are such <hi>as are Christs, ver.</hi> 23. and to whom <hi>he is</hi> peculiarly <hi>the first fruits, ibid.</hi> Such as shall bear his heavenly Image, <hi>ver.</hi> 49. and, as elsewhere, <hi>whose vile bodies shall be made like his glorious One, Phil.</hi> 3. 21. Such as shall have <hi>spiritual, incorruptible, immortal bodies</hi> like his, and with him <hi>inherit the Kingdom of God,</hi> and <hi>through him obtain this victory,</hi> ver. 50—57.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This limitation of <hi>death to be overcome,</hi> to such a subject only, <hi>connotes the extent of it to the whole of that subject, as that is compos'd</hi> of an <hi>inner and an Outer man,</hi> 2 Cor. 4. 16. It were frigid, and comfortless to suppose, if it were supposeable, that this glorious Conquest of death should extend no further than the giving us a fair specious <hi>outside;</hi> and that our <hi>Mind and Spirit</hi> should not partake, or be nothing the better for it. 'Tis plain the Apostles scope thro' this Chapter is more to assert the future subsistence
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32155:5"/>
of the Soul, than the recomposure of the Body, as his Arguments shew; though what was necessary to be said concerning the future state of <hi>that</hi> also, is not neglected. But what he is now saying in this part of the Chapter concerns not what is common to men, but what is peculiar to Good and Holy Men. And therefore, <hi>as it respects their nobler part,</hi> must intend More than its meer subsistence in another state, which is common to good and bad, and signify the perfection of the <hi>Holy Divine life,</hi> which shall be at last entirely victorious, and Swallow up <hi>Death, in its utmost extent,</hi> and specially as it was opposite to <hi>that life.</hi> Death I mean, <hi>as</hi> it was so heavily incumbent upon the <hi>Minds and Spirits</hi> of Good Men themselves, and was their most intolerable burden; extorting from them such groans as that <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 24. <hi>O wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man that I am who shall deliver me from this body of death.</hi> Nor indeed is this death sensible or grievous, or ever felt, but where the <hi>opposite life</hi> hath some place. Total death knows no grievances, makes no complaints. They that lye buried in the Earth, are in their own Element, where no such thing weighs upon them; a terrene, carnal Mind is no burthen to such Souls, as are quite dead in Trespasses and Sins. I hope I need not tell you that tho' the Souls of men are Universally immortal <hi>in the natural sense,</hi> they are not so <hi>in the moral. Morality</hi> comprehends the means and end, <hi>Vertue</hi> and <hi>Felicity;</hi> or in terms more agreeable to our <hi>Christian Ethicks,</hi> or that are oftener heard by them that live under the Gospel, <hi>Holiness,</hi> and <hi>Blessedness.</hi> These are signify'd by <hi>Spiritual Life,</hi> or <hi>life in the spiritually-moral sense.</hi> And so are <hi>Sin,</hi> and <hi>Misery,</hi> by the <hi>opposite death.</hi> And no man hath reason to think it strange that <hi>Life</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:32155:6"/>
and <hi>Death,</hi> are estimated by such measures; or that a temper of Spirit habitually and fixedly good or evil, should be signify'd by being <hi>alive,</hi> or <hi>dead,</hi> if we consider how perfect an equivalency there is between them <hi>in the moral sense,</hi> and being <hi>naturally</hi> alive or dead. For wherein do we usually state the notion of <hi>Natural Life,</hi> but in a <hi>self-moving power?</hi> Now let any ordinary Understanding be appeal'd to in the Case, and who would not say it were as good, not to be able to move at all, as to move in so perpetual disorder, as never to attain any end, such motion should serve for. The Ends of a reasonable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures motions, must be <hi>duty to its Maker,</hi> and <hi>felicity to it self.</hi> If all its motions be such as import constant hostility towards God, infelicity and torment to it self; this is to be dead not <hi>simply</hi> and <hi>naturally,</hi> 'tis true, but respectively, and not in some by-, and less<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>considerable respect, but in respect of the principal and most important purposes of Life. So that, in full equivalency, such a one is, <hi>as dead,</hi> to all valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able intents and purposes whatsoever. Therefore such are only said to be alive in <hi>a true,</hi> and <hi>the most proper</hi> sense, that are <hi>alive [to God] through Jesus Christ,</hi> Rom. 6. 11. Or that do <hi>yeild themselves [to God] as those that are alive from the dead,</hi> ver. 13. it being the proper business of their life to serve God, and enjoy him. Others that only live in sinful <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, are dead while they live,</hi> 1 Tim. 5. 6. Nor hath such a Notion of <hi>life and death</hi> been altogether strange even <hi>among Heathens,</hi> when we find it said by <hi>One</hi> of no mean note, <hi>That a wicked man is dead, as a soul may be said to die</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>; <hi>and to it 'tis a death, when 'tis (too deeply)</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Plotin. Enn.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>plung'd, immerst into the body so as</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:32155:6"/>
               <hi>to be sunk down into matter, and replete with it.</hi> (Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides much more that might be produc't <hi>from others</hi> of like import) and how agreeable is this passage to that <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 6 <hi>To be carnally minded is death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the whole, I cannot, indeed, conceive, that since <hi>Death</hi> is often taken, and that most reasonably, in so great a latitude, as to admit of comprehending <hi>this sense;</hi> and since, in <hi>these latter verses,</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle is speaking of a final deliverance from it, as the <hi>special priviledge</hi> of such as are <hi>in union with Christ,</hi> not of what is common to all men, but that victory over death <hi>in this respect,</hi> as it imports <hi>aversion from God,</hi> or <hi>indisposition towards him,</hi> must be within his meaning, and that he was far from confining it to <hi>bodily death</hi> only, or from intending, in reference to the <hi>Soul,</hi> the meer <hi>natural immortality</hi> of that alone. But that Death in its utmost latitude was, now, <hi>in reference to this sort of men,</hi> whom his present dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course intends, to be entirely swallow'd up in victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Or in a perfect plenitude of victorious life, as 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 4.</p>
            <p>So much, which was more requisite to be insisted on, being clear, we shall less need to inlarge upon what follows. As, that,</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>This Victory supposes a War.</hi> Or, That <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> were before in a continual struggle. So we find the Case is. Even this Lower World is full of vitality. Yet Death hath spread it self thorough it and cast over it a dark and dismal shadow every where, according as <hi>Sin,</hi> which introduc'd it, is diffus'd and spread. Death is therefore mention'd as an Enemy, <hi>ver.</hi> 26. And so we understand it, <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Death,</hi> as an Enemy to <hi>Nature; Spiritual,</hi> to <hi>Grace. In the Body</hi> numerous maladies, and <hi>round</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:32155:7"/>
               <hi>about it,</hi> multitudes of adverse rancounters, are striv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to infer Death; <hi>In, and about the Mind and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> worse <hi>diseases,</hi> and <hi>Temptations</hi> have the like tendency. Temptations I say, the mention whereof was not to be omitted, as pointing at, the <hi>Tempter,</hi> the <hi>wicked one,</hi> who first brought Sin and Death into this World of ours. And who is (though the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd) the first and most proper seat of the Enmity which gives Death the Denomination of an Enemy; which is so called indefinitely, <hi>The last Enemy;</hi> that we might not understand it to be our Enemy only, but more an Enemy against God than us, from whom the spiteful Apostate aim'd and glory'd to pluck a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and bury in Death and Ruin, the whole Race of humane Creatures. In the mean time <hi>Nature</hi> in all, and <hi>Grace</hi> in the Regenerate are Counter-striv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. In the former the self-preserving Principle is more sensibly vigorous, but less successful; but <hi>they who are born of God,</hi> are better assisted by their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine-keeper, in sub-ordination to whom, they are enabled effectually to <hi>keep themselves, that the wicked one</hi> (mortally) <hi>touches them not,</hi> 1 Joh. 5. 18. but, as must be supposed, not without continual watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and striving, as in War is usual.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Where such a War and striving ends not in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, on</hi> the one side, <hi>they end in victory</hi> on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. This is consequent upon what hath been said of the <hi>limited Subject</hi> here spoken of. Death is not universally overcome; with some it is left to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, therefore, as a Conquerour. We see how it is with the <hi>two Hemispheres</hi> of our <hi>Globe.</hi> When <hi>in the One,</hi> the Light is chasing the Darkness of the foregoing Night, and we behold <hi>the morning</hi> gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>spreading it self upon the mountains,</hi> and <hi>it shines</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:32155:7"/>
               <hi>brighter, and brighter unto perfect day:</hi> So in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a feebler light doth more and more retire and yeild, till at length it be quite swallow'd up in the victorious darkness of a black and horrid midnight. 'Tis much after the same rate <hi>here,</hi> with this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: that vicissitudes, and alternations cease, and whether <hi>darkness and the shadow of death,</hi> or the <hi>light of life,</hi> be finally Victorious, they are so (as hath been said) <hi>for ever. With the One sort,</hi> i. e. <hi>with the righteous,</hi> a vital <hi>light arises in the midst of darkness.</hi> A <hi>Type</hi> of their Spiritual, and a <hi>Prelude</hi> to their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal State. They have a quickening light <hi>within,</hi> under all Clouds of present ignominy, and trouble, and an <hi>Eternal day</hi> awaits them. <hi>Now Death work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in them,</hi> and surrounds them on every side, for a while, and gains a temporary victory, over their <hi>bodily Life;</hi> which while it is doing, and their <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man is perishing, their inward man is renewed day by day.</hi> But at length even that <hi>vanquished life</hi> revives; and that more <hi>noble life</hi> which <hi>is hid with Christ in God,</hi> Col. 3. 3. and of which <hi>he</hi> says, <hi>that whosoever lives and believes in him shall never die,</hi> Joh. 11. 26. becomes perfect, for it is pure Life; as that is said to be pure, which is <hi>plenum sui, &amp; minimum habet alieni; full of it self, without mixture of any thing alien from it;</hi> having quite swallow'd up whatsoever was opposite or disagreeable. So doth Life in the several kinds and degrees of it flourish with them, in a permanent, perpetual, and most consistent State. And, as Regal Power is often founded in just Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest, they do even <hi>reign in life, by Jesus Christ,</hi> Rom. 5. 17—21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But for the other sort,</hi> that sorry, pitiful, dying life they have, wherein they are even <hi>dead while they</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:32155:8"/>
               <hi>live,</hi> will be swallow'd up in a victorious, eternal, Death; in which there remaines to them a perpetual Night, and <hi>the blackness of darkness for ever.</hi> We are next to consider.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Reasonableness of the Divine Determination, which this</hi> saying <hi>imports.</hi> And that is to be collected, by reminding who it is that hath so determined. He that can effect all his determinations, and do all his pleasure. The reason of his intendments, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances, must be fetch't from <hi>himself,</hi> and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of his <hi>own Nature,</hi> unto which nothing can be more agreeable.</p>
            <p>When Death, let in by Sin, hath been <hi>reigning,</hi> doing the part of a King, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 17. over so great a part of Gods Creation, it can be little sutable to him, <hi>who doth all things after the Counsel of his will,</hi> Eph. 1. 11. to let it reign for ever. <hi>Sometime</hi> it must be <hi>swallow'd up in victory.</hi> Otherwise,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>His own Glory would suffer a perpetual Eclipse.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>The Felicity of his Redeemed should never be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Neither of which, as we are taught to apprehend the state of things, can consist with the <hi>absolute per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection</hi> of his <hi>Being.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Can we think it agreeable to him, to suffer such a perpetual soloecisme or incongruity within his Dominion, that when <hi>Death,</hi> by means of a most Criminal Apostasie, had made so great an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rode into the Nobler part of his Creation, <hi>i. e.</hi> had broken in amongst Creatures capable of Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity (who indeed otherwise had not been capable of Sin) and thereby darkened the Glory which shone more brightly in such an Order of Creatures, it
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32155:8"/>
should be so alwayes! <hi>i. e.</hi> that such a sort of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures should be perpetually continued, to be <hi>born,</hi> and <hi>sin,</hi> and <hi>die.</hi> Sometime, we must think, this course of things should have an end, and not by yielding an everlasting conquest to an Enemy. We can well conceive it most worthy of God, when he had made such Creatures, unto whom <hi>liberty</hi> was as agreeable, as <hi>holiness</hi> and <hi>felicity</hi> to leave them to themselves a-while, as Probationers and Candidates for that state of immortal Life, whereof they were not incapable. It well became a self-sufficient <hi>Being,</hi> and an absolute Sovereign, to let them understand <hi>dependance,</hi> and <hi>subjection;</hi> and that <hi>their</hi> state was precarious, not <hi>his.</hi> To let them feel the cost of <hi>ungovernableness,</hi> and <hi>self-will,</hi> and the disagreeable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness thereof to their condition who were not self-sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistent, and <hi>had not their good in their own hands.</hi> If, being put upon this trial, they would transgress, and open a way for Death to come in upon them, the real loss could only be their own, and none of his. He had no reason therefore to prevent it, by so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seasonable an interposition, as should prevent the orderly connection between <hi>duty,</hi> and <hi>felicity; i. e.</hi> the precedency of the former to the other. All this was a most unexceptionable procedure. But then, when being left to themselves, they <hi>as Men,</hi> or as <hi>Adam, had transgrest, Hos.</hi> 6. 7. and done <hi>like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, i. e.</hi> like frail mutable Creatures, in <hi>their lapse into Sin and Death,</hi> How opportune was it for him, now, to do more illustriously <hi>like himself, i. e.</hi> by so surprizing, unthought of, methods as the Gospel reveal, to recover to himself this Glory out of the Cloud, and make it shine more brightly than ever, in this final <hi>Victory</hi> over <hi>Death,</hi> and <hi>him that had the</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:32155:9"/>
               <hi>Power</hi> of it! So that it shall at last retain no Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over any but such as by their own choice, <hi>during a new state of trial,</hi> remain'd in an inviolable union with that Prince of Darkness and Death. How glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious will the Triumphs of this Victory be over the Grand Apostate. And how unsupposeable is it, that he should have occasion left him to glory in an Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Conquest! And</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is not a light thing to him whose nature <hi>is Love, That without this final victory the felicity of the Redeemed should never be fully accomplisht.</hi> Ante-ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently to the Gospel-Revelation, it would seem more agreeable to the Nature of God that some should be rescu'd from the Power of Death, than, that all should lye under it for ever. But we to whom that Revelation is vouchsaf't, cannot now but think it the most unlikely thing in the World that the design of Almighty Love should finally be defeated, and that such as are in Vital Union with the Redeemer, should either be overcome at last by Death, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in an eternal struggle with it. Whence no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be conceived in this case, but that as <hi>to them,</hi> death must be swallowed up in this glorious E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting Victory.</p>
            <p>Whereupon how admirable a display will there herein be of sundry the most known Attributes and Excellencies of the Divine Nature, as his Wisdom, Power, Goodness, Holiness, Justice, and Truth, in the whole Conduct, and in this final issue of things! (as might be distinctly shown of each, if we were not within limits.) He at first dealt with them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry sutably to <hi>their natures,</hi> At length he deals with them according to <hi>his own.</hi> That it may be the Theme of Eternal Contemplation to themselves,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32155:9"/>
and the whole intelligent World. How far <hi>his ways are above their ways, and his thoughts above their thoughts, Isa.</hi> 55. And that as at first he thought it not fit to hinder them from doing as too little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came such Creatures, nothing should at last hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him from doing as became a God.</p>
            <p>But come we now to the Use. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Do we find <hi>this saying</hi> in the Sacred Word of God, that <hi>Death is to be swallow'd up in victory.</hi> Then we are not to doubt, but so it shall be. A plenary assent is to be given to it. But what sort of assent? not that which arises from the sight of our Eye. If <hi>that</hi> were to be our only <hi>Informer,</hi> we see no such thing; but quite the contrary. <hi>That</hi> represents <hi>Death</hi> to us as the only <hi>Conquerour.</hi> It <hi>visibly</hi> swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows up all in Victory, wheresoever it makes a sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zure. Nothing stands before it! We behold it turning every where living Men and Women like our selves into breathless lumps of Earth! It irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistibly introduces <hi>it self,</hi> and Life is fled, and gone! Such as convers't with us, walk't to and fro amongst us, reason'd, discourst with us, manag'd business, pursu'd designs, delighted themselves with us, and gave us delight, become Deaths Captives before our Eyes, are bound in its bands, and we cannot redeem them, nor save our selves. Where then is this swallowing up of Death in Victory? which is it self so constantly Victorious!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Reason</hi> may tell us it shall not be always and universally so, but it flutters, and hallucinates. 'Tis the Divine Word that must at last put the matter out of doubt; and our <hi>Faith</hi> therein, which is the <hi>substance of what we hope for, and the evidence of what</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:32155:10"/>
               <hi>we do not see.</hi> If Faith is to assure our hearts in this matter, it must be as it relies upon his Word who can do this, and hath said he will. If we believe his <hi>Power,</hi> that renders it <hi>possible</hi> to us. If his <hi>Word,</hi> that makes it <hi>certain.</hi> Hath he said it, who then shall gainsay it? 'Tis one of the <hi>true and faithful say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. If this be a <hi>Credible saying,</hi> 'tis certainly a very <hi>comfortable One.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we can but make that first step, and perceive this not to be a hard or incredible saying; it is very obvious to make a second, and acknowledge it to be a very Consolatory saying; and that both in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to,</p>
            <p>The <hi>past Death</hi> of our <hi>Friends and Relatives,</hi> even such as were nearest, and most dear to us.</p>
            <p>And in reference to <hi>our own,</hi> most certainly <hi>future</hi> and <hi>expected Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the one Case, and the other, we are to look upon it as a comfortable saying, That this Mighty raging Enemy shall have all his power lost, and swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up, in so glorious a Victory, one day.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is surely a very comfortable saying in the former of these Cases, the Case of our losing Friends and Relations very dear unto us: And there only needs this to make it most deliciously pleasant, that is, to have a comfortable perswasion concerning such, That they are part of Christs Seed, they are some of them, in reference to whom Christ is, in the most peculiar Sense, the first-fruits, so as that they have a pre-assurance of Victory in his Conquest, and Victory over Death and the Grave. And we have great reason to be so perswaded concerning that Worthy Gentlewoman, whose late Decease is the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:32155:10"/>
               <hi>more special</hi> occasion, of this solemn Assembly at this time. She was one who, (as such as had most op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to observe, and best ability to judge, did reckon) had given abundant evidence of the work of Gods Saving Grace upon her own Spirit, and who thereupon did long walk with God in a very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Course; so indeed, as that tho' her Comforts were observed not to be Rapturous, yet they were steady and even; so as that she was rarely troubled with doubts, to give obstruction or hinderance to her in her Christian Course: If any such doubt did arise, it soon vanished, and she quickly, through the Mercy of God, received Satisfaction, and so went chearfully on in her way.</p>
            <p>She was abundant in reading, especially of the Holy Book, <hi>that</hi> was her business and delight. She very little cared to concern her self in reading Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings that were merely Notional, or Polemical and disputative: But the most practical ones she was most of all taken with, such as treated of the <hi>other state,</hi> and of the <hi>duties</hi> of Christians in the mean time in reference thereto; <hi>future felicity,</hi> and <hi>present spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual-mindedness,</hi> that has so certain connexion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and so direct a tendency thereto, were, with her, the delightful Subjects, which she chose to read of, and meditate upon.</p>
            <p>Her Temper was observed to be even, betwixt a <hi>freeness</hi> and <hi>reservedness.</hi> She was not Melancholy, though much inclined to solitariness, and would fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently lament, that so much of her precious time was past away, either in necessary business, or Civil Conversation, that was not to be avoided.</p>
            <p>It was observed, that her disposition was most
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:32155:11"/>
highly charitable, very apt to give, even to her ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termost, as occasions did occur.</p>
            <p>In reference to her Children her care was most tender. Much of her time was spent in instructing them, while under her Instruction, and within her reach; teaching them their Catechism, with the Proofs at large, and how to apply the Proofs to the Answer, so as to bring them to a distinct understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof. And in this way and course she past through the World.</p>
            <p>Her last Sickness did very little alter the temper of her Spirit, it was calm and sedate all along. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly so much does deserve a remark, That she was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possest with an Apprehension that she should dye sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly; so much of Gods secret he was pleased to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part to her, as he sometimes does to more inward Friends; That discovery he vouchsaf't to her, as to a Favourite, to let her have some kind of pre-signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, that her passage out of this World should be very quick, whensoever it came; and so it was, that sitting in her Chair, amidst familiar Discourse, in a dimidiated Sentence, she made a full stop, and life was ended, before <hi>that</hi> could have an end.</p>
            <p>Now certainly the Decease of such a one ought not to be lamented with that bitter Sorrow, as if there were no such thing as this, that Death were certainly to be swallowed up in Victory, in an intire and compleat Victory, with reference to such a one. It seems indeed in such Cases, as was said to you before, unto the judgment of our sense, that Death only overcomes, we see not beyond that; It turns a living Creature into a dead Clod, and so it is laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong such, it is buried in the Grave, our Sight goes
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:32155:11"/>
no further. But when we are perswaded by the Word of the Lord, that this mortal shall put on im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, and this corruptible incorruption, and death be swallowed up in such a Victory, as you have heard; certainly this takes away the cause of all bitter and reliefless sorrow.</p>
            <p>I am not unapprehensive that Reverend Brother whom this stroke touches more nearly, is much fitter to administer this consolation, than receive it from such a one as I.</p>
            <p>But as we may any of us put in for our share, as our case may require and can admit, in what is so generally spoken with reference to Christians dying in the Lord, and their surviving fellow-Christians, that as yet live in him, 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 4. from <hi>verse</hi> 13 <hi>onward to the end.</hi> So, we are directed to comfort one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther therewith. (Be patient I pray you, while I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to you this Most sutable Portion of Scripture). <hi>I would not have you to be ignorant, Brethren, concerning them which are asleep, that ye sorrow not, even as others which have no hope. For if we believe that Jesus dyed, and rose again, even them also which sleep in Jesus, will God bring with him. For this we say unto you by the word of the Lord, that we which are alive, and remain unto the coming of the Lord, shall not prevent them which are asleep. For the Lord himself shall descend from Heaven with a shout, with the voice of the Arch-Angel, and with the trump of God: and the dead in Christ shall rise first: Then we which are alive and remain, shall be caught up together with them in the clouds to meet the Lord in the air: and so shall we be ever with the Lord. Wherefore, comfort one another with these words.</hi> We shall be in a great promptitude and disposition of Spirit to do so, if these words be lookt upon as <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:32155:12"/>
               <hi>sayings,</hi> as the words of the Living and Immortal God. My Friends, do you not find there is Spirit in these words? Is there not <hi>strong Consolation</hi> in them? How can we but think so, unless our whole Religion be with us but a Fable? This concerns us all upon the common Christian account who are but a residue, a remnant, escaped, and exempted, a-while, from being part of the Spoils and Triumphs of Death; which hath slaughtered, and thrown into the dust, probably a much greater number of our Friends and Relatives, than we our selves do make who are left behind. And 'tis likely we have been most of us divers times Mourners, upon such occasions. <hi>This</hi> shews upon what account, and in what case, we may intermingle very reviving Consolations with our Sorrows, and that we ought freely, as the occasion recurres, to apply it to our selves and one another.</p>
            <p>But I withal think there may be somewhat of <hi>more special import</hi> tending to repress intemperate Sorrow, on such an occasion, in that of <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 24. 16. I think there may be somewhat, I say, collected, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides what was more peculiar, and appropriate by <hi>way of signal</hi> to the Prophet himself, that may reach the last mention'd Case. It was a thing injoined upon him, that <hi>he should not mourn nor weep, nor should his tears run down, when, God should take away from him the desire of his eyes with a stroke.</hi> I reckon that as we have seen Christians should not mourn like other men, so <hi>the Lords Prophets</hi> are not to mourn altogether, <hi>like others of his People,</hi> but somewhat more of restraint they are to put upon themselves, that they may discover an higher excellency, or some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what a greater measure of that <hi>spirit of faith</hi> ruling in them, that gives a great allay to <hi>present things,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:32155:12"/>
whether good or evil, as it begets clearer and more vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid apprehensions of things <hi>yet-future</hi> and out of sight. And that as all believers, should endeavour in things of common concernment to all, to be exemplary to one another and to other men; so they who are so much nearer to God, in Office and Relation should be <hi>examples to Believers</hi> in <hi>Conversation, Spirit, Faith,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 12.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This should be very comfortable too, unto them that are <hi>in union with Christ,</hi> in reference to <hi>their own future death,</hi> which they are continually to <hi>expect. Death</hi> is often saying to us repeatedly, and very sensibly, to our very Bone and our Flesh, You shall be my Prey shortly; at least, sooner or later. It is ready to make its seisure upon us, when, we do not know, but we are sure some time, it will.</p>
            <p>But, my Friends, it does not become Christians, to look upon this <hi>thing called Death,</hi> as so formidable a thing, as it is commonly reckoned; it is ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious to our profession, not to be indured amongst them that have Life and Immortality brought to light, and set in view before their Eyes in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel, such as profess to be united with Christ, who hath <hi>Life in himself,</hi> and imparts it to all that are so united; such a Life, hid with Christ in God; And hope that when he who is their Life shall appear, shall appear with him in Glory. It becomes not such to dye continually, by the fear of dying, or that the very thoughts of Death should be deadly to them.</p>
            <p>This is remote from what was <hi>much observed</hi> to be the Temper and Character of <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Christians.</hi> An <hi>Heathen</hi> Prince, <note place="margin">Marc. Antonin. <hi>de vit. suâ lib.</hi> 11.</note> who throughly understood them not,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:32155:13"/>
Censures them too hardly, as being in the other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream (though he at length became kinder to them) as if they rashly threw themselves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Death. Whereas he says, the Soul <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> should, <hi>rationally,</hi> and <hi>becomingly, be in readiness to be loosed from the body.</hi> But how come we to lose our Character! and our Glory! How de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated a thing is the Christianity of our age! To dye without regret is counted an attainment; it should be with gladness: As <hi>Psal.</hi> 16. 9, 10, 11. and upon the Considerations there mention'd; as being now upon the Confines of that World of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Purity, Bliss, and Joy; and having so great an assurance that the intermediate Death we are to go through, is no sooner suffered, than overcome!</p>
            <p>We should deal closely with our selves in this. Do we think this saying a Fable; or a Trifle? Have these Words no meaning? We should labour to come to a point, and say, If we have no reason to dis-believe them, we will believe them <hi>absolutely;</hi> and live as having gain'd our point, and overcome already, <hi>i. e.</hi> who are as sure of Victory, as of Death. Some overcome by dying, as others are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome by it. There are, who <hi>are not hurt by the second Death.</hi> If Death strike once, it thereby puts it out of its own power ever to strike a second time, or hurt them more. Let us once bring our case to that state as to live in continual defiance of Death, let it strike when it will. Dependance only on the Grace and Spirit of Christ; must give us this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, not an opinion that we are <hi>our selves</hi> strong enough <hi>to act separately,</hi> but that knowing our rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to him, <hi>we are thorough him that loved us, more than Conquerours,</hi> or as that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 27.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:32155:13"/>
may be understood to signifie; We are a glorious Triumphant sort of Conquerours. We not only <hi>Conquer,</hi> but <hi>Triumph</hi> too, <hi>through him that loved us,</hi> being perswaded that neither <hi>Death</hi> nor Life—shall separate us from his Love—. So a <hi>noted Expositor</hi> understands that word, observing how great a delight this Apostle takes, when he would <hi>heighten</hi> a matter, in the use of that particle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>It is elsewhere said, <hi>Colos.</hi> 3. 3. <hi>Ye are dead, but your life,</hi> &amp;c. We <hi>are dead,</hi> i. e. <hi>in our selves,</hi> we are a sort of dead or dying Creatures, Death hath almost got the possession of us already, has partly seised, and partly sentenced us to die, and irreversibly. This the Apostle intimates where he adds, what you have heard, <hi>Ye have a Life bid with Christ in God,</hi> that Life is safe, and out of the reach of Death, no Death can ouch that Life. <hi>They that are born of God,</hi> have in reference to this Life (though <hi>the other</hi> must be given up) a self-preserving principle and power in them; 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 18. <hi>They keep themselves, that the Evil One touches them not;</hi> that is, not <hi>mortally,</hi> or with any <hi>deadly touch.</hi> In having a new, holy, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Life; they have an assuring pledge also of the permanency, perpetuity, and everlastingness of it. If a man have once <hi>drank of that water which Christ gives,</hi> it <hi>shall be in him</hi> a perpetual fountain, <hi>a well of water springing up into everlasting life.</hi> Joh. 4. 14.</p>
            <p>Are we Christians, and with the springings of this life, do we not feel a lively joy springing, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulting in our Hearts! Add <hi>vital Christianity</hi> to the <hi>rational Nature,</hi> and <hi>loathness to dye</hi> is a repugnancy, and a reproach to both. <hi>Christianity</hi> so plainly stat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Case, <hi>Reason</hi> should judge upon it. And sutable affections arise in us thereupon, as they would if our
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:32155:14"/>
               <hi>Christianity</hi> were <hi>vital,</hi> and the product of the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Spirit.</hi> Then, how should we bless God that we are Mortal! and that it is not in the Power of all this World to keep us from dying out of it, when we know in how glorious a Victory, that Death will be swallowed up!</p>
            <p>But it may be said by some, <hi>We should very little fear death, if we did know our interest in Christ, if we were not in great uncertainty, and had not our hearts hanging in doubt within us about this thing.</hi> And therefore,</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. <hi>This saying should be Monitory to us.</hi> (As it is a <hi>Credible,</hi> as it is a <hi>Comfortable,</hi> so it is a <hi>Moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory saying</hi> also). <hi>Death shall be swallowed up in victory.</hi> This said in reference to some, (which cannot be meant as to all), So great a thing, spoken with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>striction, ought to make them of whom it is not meant, look about them! With what solicitude should we concern our selves, to be at a certainty! Am I one of them, in reference to whom Death shall be swallowed up in such a Victory?</p>
            <p>It should awaken us to consider, Have we made our Interest sure in our Lord Jesus Christ, that great <hi>Prince and Lord of Life. He that hath the Son hath life.</hi> 'Tis Eternal Life that is spoken of in that Context, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 11, 12. <hi>This is the record that God hath given us, eternal life; and this life is in his Son;</hi> That is, this Eternal Life. <hi>He that hath the Son,</hi> hath [this] Life, <hi>he that hath not the Son,</hi> hath not [this] <hi>Life.</hi> Spiritual Life, and Eternal Life, are all one, all of a piece; the same in nature and kind. The One will grow up into the other.</p>
            <p>That Life only is here meant, that will be Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life. To the same sense is that, <hi>He that believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:32155:14"/>
               <hi>in me, shall never dye, Joh.</hi> 11. 26. These are plain words. He hath a life in him that is Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, Sacred, and not liable to be touched. It was before said, <hi>They that believe in him, if dead, shall live, ver.</hi> 25<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But not only <hi>that,</hi> but 'tis further ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>they that believe in him shall never dye;</hi> If <hi>dead,</hi> they shall live; If they <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Ham. <hi>in loc.</hi>
               </note> live, they shall <hi>never dye;</hi> What means this? that they have a life, besides <hi>this bodily one;</hi> which is continued thorough Death. Of this line or thred, Death makes no intercision. But we can never justify it to God, or our own understandings, to rest in a dubious uncertainty about a matter of so vast Consequence as this. <hi>Unconcernedness here,</hi> is the most unaccountable thing in the whole World; <hi>i e.</hi> whether we have only <hi>that life</hi> in us which will end in the darkness and rottenness of a Grave, and an horrid Hell; or <hi>that</hi> which runs into <hi>Eternal Life?</hi> Things will come to this issue very shortly with us, that either death must, <hi>as to us,</hi> be <hi>swallowed up in victory,</hi> or we be swallowed up of <hi>victorious death;</hi> Nor have we any ways to ascertain our own state, but (as was said) by uniting with the <hi>Prince of life; i. e.</hi> by <hi>receiving him</hi> in all the Capacities wherein we are to be concern'd with him; and by resigning our selves entirely to him. For if we must <hi>have him,</hi> that we may <hi>have life:</hi> How can we, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, have him but by receiving him. The Gospel, under which we live, can only be a <hi>savour of life</hi> to us, as it disposes us hereunto. Recollect your selves then; How do your <hi>Lords Dayes,</hi> and <hi>other Seasons,</hi> of attending this Gospel, pass over with you? Have you long expected Life, and (which is less likely) do you meet with continual and total disappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:32155:15"/>
And doth it cause with you no qualmish thoughts? But 'tis infinitely a sadder Case if you never feel your selves begin to live, and yet are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver disappointed; because you never attend upon the Gospel-Dispensation with any such design or hope. Is the matter thus, that If you speak the Truth of your Case, you must say, <hi>I have a soul dead to all the Actions, Motions, Sensations, Injoyments, of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Spiritual life.</hi> And shall it be always thus, by our own Consent, with any of us? We have however the rational, intellectual Life, <hi>and can think:</hi> Do we <hi>think</hi> 'tis fit for us to rest satisfy'd, and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, in such a state? What? satisfy'd in the midst of <hi>Death?</hi> such a Death? while we are capable of apprehending at once, the <hi>horror,</hi> the <hi>danger,</hi> and the <hi>remedibleness</hi> of our Case? What will this come to? It can only be <hi>Holy, Divine Life</hi> that must be Victorious over Death, <hi>as the warring, opposite prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple:</hi> If there be nothing to oppose it, <hi>what</hi> shall Conquer? Death is in that Case <hi>Total,</hi> and upon such termes, till Life begin to spring in thy Soul, thou must reckon it likely to be <hi>Eternal.</hi> Yet let none so mistake as to imagine this Life an <hi>Enthusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astical thing,</hi> that must discover it self in rapturous, extatical motions, or <hi>go for nothing.</hi> It perfects our Faculties, therefore destroyes them not. And chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly consists in a rational <hi>Judgment, Choice</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> of what is most worthy of us; what is <hi>fittest to be done by us,</hi> and what is <hi>with fullest satisfaction to be enjoyed;</hi> with a stedfast, most resolved adherence thereunto.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly, <hi>This saying ought to be Instructive to us,</hi> in reference especially to <hi>this one thing,</hi> i. e. <hi>That we abstain from rash Censures of Providence, That God</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:32155:15"/>
               <hi>lets death be regnant in so great a part of his creation, so long a time.</hi> It shall <hi>be swallowed up in victory,</hi> let that solve with us the <hi>Phaenomenon.</hi> It seems in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, an <hi>untoward one;</hi> and might <hi>at first</hi> be an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazing spectacle, <hi>even to the Blessed Angels themselves,</hi> to behold so great a <hi>revolt in Heaven:</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, to take notice of an <hi>intelligent world, of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures beneath them,</hi> successively, <hi>thorough one first, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquent,</hi> drawn in, as Complices, into a like de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; and <hi>Death</hi> hereby spreading its horrid sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and extending its power, over so great and so noble a part of the Universe! Committing such Wasts, making such desolations, from Age to Age, in so great a part of the Creation of God! But there are many alleviating Considerations, that should compose our Spirits to a rational quietude, and be satisfying and pacifying to our minds with reference to this thing. Let me but name some few to you, which I shall leave with you, for this purpose.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Do but consider <hi>how minute a part of the Creation of God, this Globe, this point, this punctilio, rather, of our earth is,</hi> where death has reigned, and so long had place.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Consider <hi>how much of life there is in and about this little World of ours.</hi> When, upon one single Mole-Hill, you see the brisk motions and efforts of so many hundred Lives, you have reason to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend there is a great deal of Vitality about this little spot of Earth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Consider and Collect <hi>how probable it is, that as we go higher and higher, the nobler and finer parts of Gods Creation, must be much more replenished with a nobler and more excellent sort of life.</hi> It is very unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable to think, that this Clod of Earth should be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:32155:16"/>
so full of Life and that in higher and purer Regions, there should not be a richer plenitude of life, or of such Inhabitants as live nobler and more excellent Lives than we And</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>For ought we know, death never reaches higher than this earth of ours, and what is in a nearer vicinity to it;</hi> And that, therefore, there be vast and ample Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, incomparably beyond the range of <hi>our Eye,</hi> or <hi>Thought,</hi> where now, no Death ever comes; after the detrusion of the first revolters, from those bright Regions. When we are told, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 10. our Lord Jesus Christ is <hi>ascended far above all heavens,</hi> as it were a fond attempt to pretend to <hi>count</hi> them so it were rash <hi>Philosophizing,</hi> to go about to <hi>describe</hi> them. But can we suppose them spacious, wild Wasts? Or not suppose them replenished with numberless numbers of excellent Creatures that <hi>in their confirmed state,</hi> fear no Death. And continually pay a willing, joyful Homage to their <hi>Great Preserver.</hi> For <hi>every knee must bow to him, of things in heaven,</hi> Phil. 2. 10. And when we are told, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 20, 21. <hi>God hath set him at his own right hand in the heavenly</hi> places, far <hi>above all Principality, and Power, and Might, and Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and every Name—,</hi> &amp;c. And 1 Pet. 3. 22. <hi>That he is on the Right hand of God. Angels, and Authorities,</hi> and <hi>Powers being made subject to him.</hi> Tho' we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not form <hi>distinct thoughts</hi> what those <hi>Dynastics, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities,</hi> and <hi>Dominions</hi> are, yet we cannot but sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose those unconceivably vast, and ample Regions, fully Peopled, with <hi>immortal Inhabitants,</hi> that <hi>reign in life,</hi> in a more <hi>excellent sense.</hi> For it being said our Lord ascended far above all Heavens, <hi>that he might fill all things,</hi> Eph. 4. 10. This must suppose <hi>sutable Recipients.</hi> And if <hi>his influences</hi> reach down in such
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:32155:16"/>
plenty to our <hi>minute Earth</hi> (as ver. 11, 12, 13.) how copious are they <hi>here!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5thly. Consider, That <hi>here,</hi> where <hi>Death</hi> has made its inrode, tho' the Apostate Spirits surround us, and incompass this Earth of ours, and go to and fro throwing Death among us every where, yet even <hi>here</hi> is a <hi>glorious off-spring</hi> continually arising, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemers Seed in whom a Divine Life is gradually springing up from Age to Age. So that, at length, they make a <hi>great multitude which no man can number standing before the Throne, clothed with white Robes, and</hi> (as Ensigns of Victory) <hi>having palmes in their hands,</hi> Rev. 7. 9. Here is life then disseminated <hi>through all this death</hi> that inwraps our World. Which for ought we know, is the Center of Death; it may be <hi>here,</hi> for ought we can tell, and <hi>no where else;</hi> (here, or hereabouts.) And yet even <hi>here,</hi> an Holy Divine Life is insinuating and spreading it self, even among us, over whom <hi>death has reigned;</hi> and there are great numbers, that having <hi>received abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Grace, and of the gift of righteousness, shall reign in life by one, Jesus Christ,</hi> Rom. 5. 17. Here's supposed a Kingdom, with a Counter-Kingdom, and <hi>one Head</hi> against <hi>another; One,</hi> that brought in <hi>Death and Condemnation</hi> upon the World; but <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> that brings in <hi>righteousness and life.</hi> And that here, even in this lower Region, The Redeemer should have so large a Portion (we know not how large!) This very much narrows the confines of Death. And let it be further considered.</p>
            <p n="6">6thly, That <hi>where Death shall be perpetual, it is there but self-procured. They only</hi> lye under Death, that lov'd it. <hi>All they that hate me love death,</hi> Prov. 8. 36. They inwrap themselves in death, they
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:32155:17"/>
               <hi>make a covenant with it. That Sin,</hi> which <hi>is Death,</hi> which carries Death and Hell in it self, <hi>that</hi> they lov'd; 'Twas so 'tis true, with the rest, that finally perish not; but it was not always so. The Grace of God made a difference, not to be quarrell'd at, when stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with <hi>many,</hi> it is victorious with <hi>some.</hi> But of those with whom it is not so, it must be said, as their final, never-altered sense, even to the last, <hi>They would not be plucked out of the Gulph, that deadly Gulph,</hi> where they therefore lye, as in their most agreeable Element. And let it further be considered.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>That for the death that shall be perpetual, 'tis to be confined,</hi> and go no further. Before it was dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused and continually more and more diffusing it self. But <hi>in the future state of things,</hi> when <hi>time</hi> has run to its period, and the Affairs of it are shut up by the <hi>final Judgment, Death and Hell are now to be cast into the lake of fire and brimstone,</hi> which is the second Death, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. 14. All <hi>death</hi> is now to be gathered <hi>into Death, Hell, into Heil.</hi> It shall be contracted, gathered <hi>into it self.</hi> It's true, it will be therefore <hi>consummate, finished, perfect in its kind,</hi> or full of it self, as that which is without mixture cannot but be, (as was noted before). Here will be pure death, without mixture; and which therefore will have no allay. But then, whereas formerly it ranged to and fro uncontroll'd, now it is confined to its own nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower Circle, and can have no <hi>new subject,</hi> And shall therefore give no further trouble or disturbance, to the rest of Gods Creation. Moreover, Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</p>
            <p>Lastly, <hi>That this victory will not be gradual only, but total and entire.</hi> Every thing of Mortality, that was Hanging about these glorious Victors, shall be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:32155:17"/>
swallowed up in perfect, and in endless Life. Death is unstung first, disarm'd, and then easily overcome. <hi>Its sting</hi> is said to be <hi>Sin,</hi> the deadliest thing in Death. A plain further proof (by the way) the Apostle intended Death also, in the <hi>moral Sense.</hi> And the insulting Enquiry, <hi>Where is it?</hi> implies 'tis not <hi>any where</hi> to be found, and signifies a total abolition of it; and, by consequence, must infer that every thing of Death besides, must (as to them) for ever cease, and be no more. Which also the Phrase of <hi>swallowing up,</hi> doth with great <hi>Emphasis</hi> express. And this compleats the vindication of Providence, <hi>i. e.</hi> in this whole Affair; and not only <hi>vindicates,</hi> but <hi>mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies</hi> the conduct of the <hi>Supreme Disposer</hi> of all things. For by this means, as his <hi>Wisdom, Power</hi> and <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> are most highly illustrated, so the <hi>trial of his Peoples Faith</hi> (the great Instrument of <hi>this</hi> their Victory, as well as of <hi>that over the world,</hi> 1 Joh. 5. 4) <hi>is found unto praise, honour and glory at the appearing of Jesus Christ,</hi> 1 Pet. 4. 7. And <hi>they</hi> find, what, <hi>by patient continuance in well-doing,</hi> they were enjoyn'd <hi>to seek,</hi> (which shews they were not vainly put upon so noble a pursuit) <hi>Honour, Glory, Immortality,</hi> to their actual attainment <hi>of Eternal Life,</hi> Rom. 2. 7.</p>
            <p>Now, therefore shall <hi>this saying</hi> be made good in its fullest sense: And if there shall be such a Victory, so glorious a one won at last; surely we should be tuning our Instruments, and labouring to get our Hearts into a frame to sing the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>triumphant song,</hi> ver. 55, 56. and conclude it, as ver. 57. <hi>Thanks be to God, that giveth us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:32155:18"/>
            <head>
               <hi>These Books Written by the Reverend Mr.</hi> John Howe, <hi>are Sold by</hi> Tho. Parkhurst <hi>at the</hi> Bible <hi>and</hi> Three Crowns, Cheapside.</head>
            <p>OF Thoughtfulness for the Morrow; with an Appendix concerning the immoderate desire of fore-knowing things to come.</p>
            <p>The Redeemers Tears wept over Lost Souls; in a Treatise on <hi>Luke</hi> 19. 41, 42. With an Appendix, wherein somewhat is occasionally discoursed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the sin against the Holy Ghost, and how God is said to will the Salvation of them that Perish.</p>
            <p>Of Charity in reference to other Mens Sins.</p>
            <p>Two Sermons preach'd on these words, <hi>Yeild your selves to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Funeral Sermon for Mrs. <hi>Esther Sampson,</hi> the late Wife of <hi>Henry Sampson,</hi> Dr. of Physick, who died <hi>Nov.</hi> 24. 1689.</p>
            <p>The Carnality of Religious Contention, in Two Sermons Preached at the Merchants Lecture in <hi>Broadstreet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Calm and Sober Enquiry concerning the Possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of a Trinity in the Godhead: In a Letter to a Person of Worth, occasioned by the lately Publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Considerations on the Explications of the Doctrine of the Trinity: By Dr. <hi>Wallis,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> Dr. <hi>S—th,</hi> Dr. <hi>Cudworth,</hi> &amp;c. Together with certain Letters, (hitherto unpublish'd) formerly written to the Reverend Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi> on the same Subject.</p>
            <p>A Letter to a Friend concerning a Postscript to the Defence of Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Notion of the Trinity in Unity, relating to the Calm Enquiry upon the same Subject.</p>
            <p>A View of that part of the late Considerations addrest to <hi>H. H.</hi> about the Trinity, which concerns the Sober Enquiry on that Subject.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32155:18"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
