<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The measvring rod of the Lord stretched forth over all nations and the line of true judgment laid to the rulers thereof wherein all governours and rulers, potentates and powers are measured, and all governments and lawes weighed in the true weight : wherein they all may see how far they are degenerated from the law of righteousness, and the rules of wisdome, which was in the beginning, before tyranny, and persecution, and rebellion had shewed it selfe : also shewing the end that will come upon all those rulers and governments, rulers and lawes that have been made in the apostacy, which is to all overthrown ... : also an advertisement to all the rulers upon the earth ... : published for the information of all the rulers upon earth ... / by one who waits to see the kingdoms of the world to become the kingdomes of the Lord ... Francis Howgil.</title>
            <author>Howgill, Francis, 1618-1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-10">2005-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44798</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3171</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6600</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13506122</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13506122</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99799</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A44798)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99799)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 791:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The measvring rod of the Lord stretched forth over all nations and the line of true judgment laid to the rulers thereof wherein all governours and rulers, potentates and powers are measured, and all governments and lawes weighed in the true weight : wherein they all may see how far they are degenerated from the law of righteousness, and the rules of wisdome, which was in the beginning, before tyranny, and persecution, and rebellion had shewed it selfe : also shewing the end that will come upon all those rulers and governments, rulers and lawes that have been made in the apostacy, which is to all overthrown ... : also an advertisement to all the rulers upon the earth ... : published for the information of all the rulers upon earth ... / by one who waits to see the kingdoms of the world to become the kingdomes of the Lord ... Francis Howgil.</title>
                  <author>Howgill, Francis, 1618-1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Kings and rulers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-12</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-01</date>
            <label>Andrew Kuster</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-01</date>
            <label>Andrew Kuster</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99799:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99799:1"/>
            <p>THE
MEASVRING ROD
OF
THE LORD,
Stretched forth over all Nations, and the
Line of true judgement laid to the Rulers thereof;</p>
            <p>Wherein all Governours and Rulers, Potentates and Powers
are measured; and all Governments and Lawes weighed
in the true weight; wherein they all may see how far they
are degenerated from the Law of Righteousness, and the
Rules of Wisdome, which was in the beginning, before
Tyranny, and Persecution, and Rebellion had shewed
it selfe;</p>
            <p>Also shewing the end that will come upon all those Rulers and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
Rules and Lawes that have been made in the Apostacy, which
is to be all overthrown, and all that which is acted out of Gods power,
to be thrown down by him, unto whom all Power is committed.</p>
            <p>Shewing also that they in whom the power of God is made manifest,
cannot be subject to any Usurper, or to that power which is gone
from the life of God.</p>
            <p>Also an Advertisement to all the Rulers upon the Earth, that they
may wait for the Restorer to be revealed in the Nations, to make up
the Breaches, and to crush that down which hath made the Breach,
that so Righteousness may cover the Earth, and gladness of heart
may possess the People.</p>
            <p>Published for the information of all the Rulers upon Earth:</p>
            <p>By one who waits to see the Kingdoms of the World to become the Kingdomes
of the Lord and his Christ, that he alone may rule for ever and ever,
called <hi>FRANCIS HOWGILL.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London.</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be sold at the Black-spread-Eagle
at the West end of <hi>Pauls</hi> 1658.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="apocalyptic_essay">
            <pb facs="tcp:99799:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99799:2"/>
            <head>The measuring rod of the Lord
streched forth &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Isten oh World, hearken oh Earth,
and all the Inhabitants thereof,
give eare, oh all Nations that are
therein, and all the Isles thereof,
draw near ye Potentates thereof,
ye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Emperours, Kings, Earles,
Dukes, Nobles, Princ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pallities,
and Dominions, my mouth shall
speake the thing that is right, and
my lips shall utter forth understanding, my toungue
shall declare unto you the Counsell of the most high,
and what he is bringing to pass in the latter dayes, he that
is higher than the highest hath said, he that is greater than
the greatest hath spoken, the whole World lies in wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness,
and thick darkness is over the World, his way
is perverted, his Counsell is despised, and all Nations is
out of order, notwithstanding the multitude of their
Counsellers, and notwithstanding all their wisdome, yet
folly is brought forth in the middest of the Nations.</p>
            <p>Because they have asked Counsell and not at the Lord,
and taken advice and not at the holy One, therefore
violence is set up as an Ensign, and wickedness runneth
down as a river, and cruelty and opression as a mighty
stream, the whole Earth is full of folly and madness, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99799:3"/>
all the people thereof are degenerate and grown out of
the Image of God into a monstrous and strange nature,
the prophets are all fooles, the diviners thereof are mad,
and they being degenerate themselves from the life of
God, have not turned the people from their iniquitie, but
hath led them into further blindness, darkness, ignorance,
and deceit, and hath made the Word of truth of none
effect through their traditions, &amp; hath taught for doctrine
the precepts of men, &amp; the traditions of them who are out
of the Faith, and out of the life, and out of the power of
God, and the Counsellors they have established wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
by a law, they themselves being stranged from the
life of God, therefore violence is broken forth into the
earth as a flood, and now all Kings, Rulers, Potentates
of the Earth who have given their power to the Whore,
who sitts upon many waters, and the waters are kindreds,
and tongues, and people, and Nations, yea all Nations
have been drunk with the cup of her Fornication, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
all gone forth from the life, in which the Prophets and
the holy men of God lived in, and were established in; the
Nations are become as waters, reeling to and fro, hither
and thither, unsetled, unstable, there the Whore hath her
seate, and all having drunk of her cup of Iniquity and
Fornication, even of mystery-<hi>Babylons</hi> cup, and are infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
therewith; and so reeles to, and fro, as the waters,
and are as the waves of the Sea unstable, by her who hath
made all Nations drunk, and by them who have been
made drunk with her, even all Nations, kindreds, tongues,
and people, have the Prophets been slain, and the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses
slain, and none to bury them, not in mystery-<hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi>
who is drunk with the blood of the Saints, and they
that have drunk of her cup of Fornication, even all the
Kings, Nobles, Potentates of the earth, they have acted
the like, and have slain the appearance of God, where
ever it hath been brought forth, and the red Dragon hath
stood ready to devour the heir, which is borne of mystery-<hi>Ierusalem</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:99799:3"/>
which is the Mother of all who are borne from
above, who are heires of the promise of Eternall life, and
the powers of the earth hath joyned their power to the
Dragon, who cast out floods of venome after the Child,
which is brought forth by the woman, which is clothed
whith the sun: and now the powers of the earth taketh
part with the Dragon, and their authority and dominion
that they exercise is by his power which arises out of the
bottomless pit; and shall goe into perdition, and he
hath deceived the Nations long, and all hath exercised their
power against him who is the heire of the promise, the
first-born of every Creature, who is higher than the highest,
and greater than the greatest, and have changed his lawes,
and made them void, and hath set up the law of sinne and
death, &amp; hath established unrighteous Lawes by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
of darkness, in which all Nations hath been involved
in, since the Dragon hath power, and whosoever would
not obey those Lawes and customs, and constitutions, the
Dragon hath had power, and all that have joyned to him
for a time, to kill, to imprison, to destroy, and they who
have been exalted have had thought to weary cut the
Saints of the most high, and to root out the memoriall of
the just, that he and all his adherents, might reign for
ever, in the Kingdome of unrighteousness, and in the
dominion of darkness, which is the Devills dwelling place,
and residence for ever, who is at enmity against God, and
the Children of light, which worship God in spirit and
truth, in life and righteousness.</p>
            <p>Now is the time drawing near, and he who is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire
of all Nations appeareth, the ancient of dayes is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
whose throne is established in righteousness for ever,
who will break the head of the Dragon, and will lay hold
upon him, and chaine him up that he deceive the Nations
no more, and all you Emperours, Kings, Dukes, Earles,
Nobles, Lords, and Potentates, who have joyned to him,
your Kingdome shall be rent from you, and your hands
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99799:4"/>
shall grow weake, that you shall not be able to defend your
selves against him who travells in the greatness of his
strength, who is comming up against you, as a Lion greedy
of his prey, and will devoure at once all his enemies, that
thought in their hearts to reign for ever, and to settle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
in iniquity for ever: now the time draws near when
he will put down the authority of the dragon, and of the
beast, and the beast with many heads and hornes, and
their rule shall come to an end, and he will dash you one
againe another as broken pitchers, till you be consumed
and brought to nought, and be worn out as a motheaten
garment, and will overthrow your Lawes and customes,
which is made in the night of ignorance, and blindness,
and will change your customes and the times, and will
reduce the earth again into its first purity, and you that
have ruled, shall serve and be tributary; and as you have
had a time of rejoycing over the wittnesses (who hath
troubled your earthly and devillish peace) and slayn them
as sheep for the slaughter; a time of mourning is comming
upon you, when you shall say alas, alas, for your glory
shall pass away, and your renown shall wither; and for
your dominion which shall grow so weake, tht you shall
not be able to resist him who travells in the greatness of
his strength, and treadeth the winepress of the wrath of
God, who is mighty and strong to judge the Whore, and
all they that have committed fornication with her, and
have drunk of her cup, and are inflamed with Adultery,
and cannot cease from sinne, but burnes in envie against
the appearing of the manchild who is heir of the promise,
yea of life everlasting, born heir to the inheritance which
is incoruptible, unto whom all power belongeth both in
heaven and earth, who will subdue the lower power, and
powers of darkness, and tread them under foot, and all
who act from that power which is below the life, below
the truth, below the light, that power will he (and all
whom he brings out of the grave, and raises above the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99799:4"/>
grave) tread down under foot, which stands but in the
earth wherein dwells unrighteousness.</p>
            <p>Allthough thy teachers and diviners in the oh earth,
who preacheth a divnation of their own brain, &amp; from the
imagination of their own hearts, hath made you beleive,
oh you powers of the earth, who are in the fall, in the
transgression of the life, that you were the higher powers,
every Emperour, King, Duke, Earle, Nobles, Lords, and
that all were to stoop to your wills, how contrary soever
they have been to God, but you and they must know, there
is one higher than the highest, who is King of kings, and
Lord of Lords, who alone will judge the hearts of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
and their consciences, for he will not give his glory
to another, although you have long usurped it, since
the dayes of the Apostacy, and would have had all to bow
to that power which hath transgressed the life, and is gone
from the power of God, oh long hath been the night of
ignorance, and darkness, and great hath been the apostacy
in the earth, since the dayes of the Apostles, and since the
false Christs and false prophets entered into the World,
which Christ said should come, and cry lo here, and there,
and should deceive many, yea all the world wondered after
the beast, and <hi>Iohn,</hi> sa<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it all ly in wickedness, and the
time that Christ prophesied of came to be fullfilled in the
dayes of <hi>Iohn,</hi> and he saw it; <hi>Matt.</hi> 24. 23, 24. that
many false prophets and Antichrists, were gone out
into the World, out from the life, out from the truth, cut
from the light, wherein the Saints had fellowship, who
wrote forth the Scriptures, and he said they were gone into
the World, and he said the whole World lay in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
and so they went from holyness into wickedness, and
from the fathers love into the love of the World, and
<hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Jude,</hi> who lived in the same age, they saw them
that went in the error of <hi>Balaam,</hi> and in the way of
<hi>Cain,</hi> and in gainsaying the Power, being turned from it
like <hi>Corah,</hi> and also their hearts were exercised with cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
practices, <hi>So Iohn saw they were come, 1 John 2. 18,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:99799:5"/>
19, <hi>ver. Little Chilldren it is the last times as you have
heard that Antichrist shall come, even now there are
many Antichrists, whereby we know its the last time,</hi> and
<hi>Peter</hi> saw that false Apostles should come, who should
make merchandise of the people, and prophesied of it, as
you may read 2 <hi>Pet. 2. 2, 3.</hi> and in the 14, 15. verses, you
may know them by their fruits, having eyes full of adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery;
and cannot cease from sinne; beguiling unstable
soules, and hearts they have exercised with covetuous
practices, and they were the cursed children; and these
had forsaken the right way, Christ the way and his
command also: freely ye have received, freely give, and
they laboured to keep the Gospell without charge, who
were true Apostles, but these false prophets, deceitfull
workers, Antichrists and false Apostles, they were gone
in <hi>Balaams</hi> way, after the wayes of unrighteousness in
<hi>Cains</hi> way, in <hi>Coras</hi> way, in Antichrists way, cut of
Christs way, and these false prophets, false Apostles,
<hi>they spoke swelling words of vanitie, and did allure through
the lusts of the flesh,</hi> and they like the rest of the false Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
gone before them, cried peace, and promised peace
unto others, while they run with them into riotous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
and while they put into their mouthes, and these
promised libertie to <hi>themselves and others, while they
themselves were servants of corruption,</hi> and <hi>Jude</hi> bore wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
that they were turned from the Grace of God into
lasciviousnesse, and wantonnesse, even from the grace that
taught them to deny ungodlinesse, and was sufficient
to preserve them from these errours before mentioned, but
they went from it, and from the light and life of men, and
denied him, and owned another, even him who abode not
in the truth (the foundation of God) but went out of the
truth, and so are bottomlesse or without foundation, and
there is the very center, ground and residence of all the
false prophets, Antichrists, deceivers, all comes from or
out of the bottomless pit, and leades to perdition.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:99799:5"/>
And <hi>Paul</hi> if not in that age, yet in the next age after lived,
&amp; he saw the mystery of iniquity already begin to worke,
<hi>2 Thess. 2. 6. and Paul an Apostle of Christ wrote to Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
his Son that the spirit spoke expresly some should
depart from the faith, and they should speake lies in hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crisie
1 Timothy 4. 1, 2. and in the 2 of Tim.</hi> he gave
him notice what fruits they should bring forth, they that
departed from the faith, <hi>Chap. 4. ver. 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</hi> yea
a great Apostacy from the faith there was, while <hi>Paul</hi>
was yet living, for he writes to <hi>Timothy</hi> 2. <hi>Tim Chap. 1.</hi>
this thou knowest, that all they which were in <hi>Asia,</hi> be
turned away from me, and there were a great people in
<hi>Asia,</hi> for great persecution he suffered in <hi>Asia,</hi> and stay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
2 years in <hi>Asia, Acts. 19. ver. 10.</hi> In so much that all
they that dwelt in <hi>Asia</hi> heard the word of the Lord, yea
and divers great men and of the cheife of <hi>Asia</hi> were his
freinds, <hi>Acts 19. ver. 21.</hi> so its manifest there were 2
great people, for <hi>Acts 19. 26</hi> verse, not only at <hi>Ephesus,</hi>
but almost throughout all <hi>Asia</hi> this <hi>Paul</hi> hath perswaded,
and turned away much people, said <hi>Demetrius:</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi>
writing to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> saith <hi>1 Cor, 16. 19.</hi> the
Churches in <hi>Asia</hi> salute you; and <hi>Iohn</hi> writes to seven,
<hi>Rev. 1, 4. Rev. 11.</hi> and as was said before, <hi>all was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted
from the faith, even all they that are in Asia are
turned away from me,</hi> and the Apostle wrote to <hi>Titus;
Titus. 1 ver. 10, 11. that there were many unruly, and
vaine talkers, and deceivers, who subverted whole houses,
teaching the things they ought not, for filthy lucre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Iohn,</hi> who wrote the last in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> he
writes that the whole World wondred after the beast, and
his power was so great, that it was said who is able to
make warre with the beast, &amp; they worshipped the beast,
saying, who is able to make warre with the beast <hi>Rev. 13.
ver. 3, 4.</hi> and the beast that arose out of the Sea, having
seven heads, and ten hornes, and upon his hornes ten
Crownes, and upon his head the name of blasphemy, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99799:6"/>
the Dragon gave him his power, his seat, and great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,
and he opened his mouth in Blasphemy against
God, to blaspheme his Name and his Tabernacle, and
them that dwell in Heaven, and it was given him to make
war with the Saints, <hi>ver. 6. 7,</hi> and to overcome them,
and power was given him over all kindreds, tongues, and
Nations, and all that dwell upon the earth, <hi>ver. 9.</hi> shall
worship him, whose names are not written in the Lamb's
book of life, shin from the foundation of the World,
this Beast receiving his power and authority from the
Dragon hath prevailed; he rose out of the Sea, the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
upon which the whore sits, and the waters are kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds,
tongues and people, and the Beast arose out of the
Sea also, that the whole World wondred after and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped,
and <hi>John</hi> that saw this coming 14 or 15 hundred
years agoe; so that in a few ages after the Apostles all was
worn out, the life lost, the Dragon had power, the Beast
had power, and all wondred after him, and the Whore
had made all Nations drunk with her Fornication; and
then she came to sit upon many Waters, Kindred, Tongues
and People, hears the Waters, hears the Sea out of which
the Beast rose, who received his power from the Dragon,
and this is he who upon his head had the names of Blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy,
and all kindreds, tongues, and Nations whose
names were not written in the Lambs book, they who
honoured the Beast, and worshipped the Beast, and said
who is able to make war with him, admired his power,
and submitted unto him; and he hath had power, and
hath prevailed against the saints, did overcome them, and
the Dragon hath made war with the Seed which keep the
Commandements of God, and the testimony of Iesus, all
this was seen many Ages agoe, and what worke the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon
hath made in the Nations and in the Earth, where he
hath had dominion and prevailed, and what a raging the
roaring Lyon hath kept in the Earth is evident, seeking
to destroy them in whom the seed remained, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99799:6"/>
them in whom the power of God was, or the least
measure, and so the false, Prophets, deceivers, Antichrists,
which wenout then, which the Apostle saw, they cried
up that power which was from the life of God, and hath
cryed it up for the higher power, and said all ought to be
subject to it, and said who is able to make war with the
Beast, for the false Apostles and Deceivers and Antichrists
went from the Grace of God, and from the light, and from
the power of God, into the World and into that Nature,
which all kindreds, and tongues, and people walked in,
and into the power that acts the Children of disobedience,
and joyned with that power upon which the Whore sits:
and they taught Nations and People to admire this
power, and to admire the Beast because of his Heads and
Horns, and Crowns and Names; and hath wrought mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles
before the Beast; and this power which the Beast
had received from the Dragon, this power admires the
false Prophet, and the false Prophet the Beast; so that
none could buy nor sell, nay nor live, but that had his
marke or the number of his name, and so all hath been in
utter darknesse, and the deeds of darknesse hath spread
themselves over the Earth; For the Whore who is adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derated
from God; and the Dragon, and the Beast, and
the false Prophet, all have acted from that power,
which is below the truth, and below the life, which pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
is at enmity against the truth and the life and against
the light; and this power overspread all Nations, and
the Sun being set, the night came over all, and the sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow
of death over all Nations, and a veil and a covering
hath been spread over all: and so out of the midst of
thick darkness all hath acted this long and darke night of
ignorance in the Apostacy, wherein the Dragon hath
had power, and the Beast, and that power hath been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired
and set up, which hath transgressed the life, so that
any who have been zealous for the truth, and have kept
the testimony of Jesus, and the spirit of prophesie; the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99799:7"/>
false prophets in all Nations, who are from the testimony
of Jesus, have called to the Beast to slay and to kill and
to destroy the seed of the woman, which is cloathed with
the Sun, and so the Beast exercising his power which is
from below, have killed and destroyed them who were
subject to the higher power.</p>
            <p>And what torturing and Massacring, and persecution,
what burning and strangling there hath been, what cruell
deaths many have been put to, over all Nations and in
all Nations, where the beast have had power, who makes
warr against the life, so that the streets have run with
blood, and all being gone from the life and power of
God, they set up themselves to be Judges over mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences,
and they who were in the errour, they cryed out
of heresie, and they that are gone from the truth into a
lie, the ground of Blasphemy, they cry out of Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sphemy,
and under the hornes of the beast, and under
the heads, and the Crownes of the beast, what Cannons
constitutions, edicts, and lawes have been in all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
what trapps, ginns, and snares have been laid in every
Nation, yea, every home hath pushed, and every head
hath lifted up it selfe against Christ the head, and every
mortall Crowne hath advanced it selfe against the
Crowne of glory, and against the immortall Crowne, so
that it might be said as <hi>Eliah</hi> said, the altar of the Lord
hath been broken down and his prophets and his wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses
slain, none hath escaped the rage of the Beast.</p>
            <p>Yet there hath been a few who have kept their gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
clean, and were not defiled with women, nor
with the Harlot, those who feared the Lord, and durst
not offend the righteous law of God in their conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
but hath denied whole councells who were erred
from the faith, and all the powers of the earth in which
the beast bore rule, but rather chuse to suffer cruell
deathes, than to let goe the profession and possession of
their faith, whose blood cryes under the Altar, how long
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99799:7"/>
oh Lord, holy, just, and true, will it be ere thou avenge
our blood, which blood and cry is entered into the eares
of the Lord of hosts, who will speedily take vengeance
on the Nations, and dash them one against another, and
will breake down that power which hath slain the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses,
yea, and hath gainsaid the power of God, and
all Nations who are from the life, in which the holy men
of God lived, and in that nature still which persecuted the
life of God wherever it did apear in any measure, yea,
swell'd up and climb'd to the very top of iniquity, which
is Satans Crown and glory, and the preists, and they that
went out from the light into the World, in <hi>Iohns</hi> dayes,
and <hi>Peters</hi> dayes, who then taught for filthy lucre, and
did subvert whole houses from the faith, ever since that
time hath spread themselves over the Nations, and hath
begotten people into a form and into an image, without
the life, and so hath worshipped the beast and his
image.</p>
            <p>And the deceit being entered then, and images then
being set up, one on this wise, another on that, and some
have had an image of many mixtures, such an image as
the preists of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> worship,
and hath got a law to guard it, that whosoever will not
bow to it, the furnace is heat hotter to throw them into
it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> And if any say, why I say so, or how do I make
that appeare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> I answer thus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Cardinalls, Jesuites, and other
Romish Preists had a law made to protect their Idoll, the
Mass, and if any spoke to him that was sacrificing to the
Image, or Idoll, then three months inprisonment, but
now if any declares against the Image, that the Preists of
<hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> have set up, every one is
to pay five pound, or six months imprisonment in a house
of correction, and there be tortured, and whipt, and shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
intreated, nere to the loss of life, nay its now so
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99799:8"/>
much the more hotter now than ever.</p>
            <p>None must come near the house of their Idoll God or
Image, but must be counted a breaker of the peace, nor
speake to a deceiver, and say he is so, nor a hireling and
say he is so, nor to a covetous Preist and say he is so, and
can for proofe bring halfe of his parish to witness the
truth of this, but if he speake the truth never so clear, he
must to prison or pay five pound, or the house of correction,
and there be whipt, and stocked, and fettered, and chayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
and tortured, and so it is manifest that those magistrates,
who had a hand in making of this law have outstript the
magistrates in the time of <hi>Mary,</hi> when the Pope had do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination
in his height in these nations.</p>
            <p>And the Preists <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow, who in these Nations, who have
set up their Image of many mixtures, and one year they
make one, and another year another, and what as that
power likes the best, that is gone out of the life and
power of God, that they present to the authority of the
Nation as an Image of a more comely stature, than the
former, and then authority makes a law to guard it, and
so it may truly be said, as it was said to <hi>Israell,</hi> hath any
other Nation changed their God, but <hi>Israell</hi> had changed
from the living God, to them by nature which are no
Gods, and so hath these Nations gone from God, the
Fountaine of life, and from the power of God, and hath
set up an Image in which is no life instead, nay, they are
not content with their Image, but it growes old, and
then pa<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ches up another of many mixtures, one while
the Masse that was held forth as their publick profession,
and then Prelacy and the book of common Prayer, and
then Presbytery and the Directory mixt and made up:
Ignorance, Blindness and of the fragments of Popery, and
their own invention, and this now is set up for all to
bow to, one while one thing which they call faith, and
another while another, and heaps of confused confessions,
but are all out of the life and from the true Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:99799:8"/>
And now they have manifested themselves to have no
Faith, and to be without faith, and are unagreed upon it,
instance that which is called the humble petition, and
advice presented to O. P. by the late Parliament, that
there may be a publick confession of faith made and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended,
as the publick profession, and also that none
may speak or write against, under a penalty, but this
Image the Lord hath by his immediate hand from Heaven
curst, and confounded them that would have founded it,
before it ever came to be set up, ah silly silly, that ever they
who should profess godliness, should so shame themselves
and all their teachers, for the teachers are not agreed yet
of their faith, so they have either no faith, or else many
forms which is feigned, and in this they are not yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed,
and so being out of the true faith, in which the
Saints had fellowship; in the unity of the faith they are
all in distraction, and confusion, head, and taile, in the jarr,
in the strife about words, and a forme of words, and how
many Confessions and forms and Images is there set forth,
and people still Ignorant of the mystery of faith which is
held in a pure conscience, and wants that which is the
evidence of things not seen, and wants that which should
let people see him who is invisible, and oh how is people
lost in the middest of these fayned, formall, divinations,
and how are the Rulers in most Nations lost in the middest
of their counsells, being gone from that which should be
a terror to evill doers, and should be for the praise of them
that do well.</p>
            <p>And what if all people in all Nations were constrained
under a penalty to hold such a form of words, and to
consent to such a confession, doth this any more but
make hypocrits, when a man is not first perswaded of
those things in his mind by the spirit of truth, is this any
more, but fainedness, how long hath the God of this
World bl<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nded the eyes of people, whole Cities, Townes,
and Countryes, because they have gotten a formall
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99799:9"/>
Confession, made by a Priest, who is out of Christs doctrine,
in the steps of the false Prophets, and in the practice of
the false Apostles, and deceitfull workers, and when
they have made a Confession, or a Catechism, as they call
it, and hath gotten over the words, and can say them
over, now judges they have faith, and are sound Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
when they are Ignorant of the first principle or of
faith towards God, and so are carried on in the mist of
darkness, and ignorance, and knowes not yet repentance
from dead workes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But some of the Rulers, and Potentates of the
earth may say, we have not persecuted them for well doing,
but for heresie, and blasphemy, and sowers of sedition,
and because they have not submitted to obey our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutions
and lawes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> Deceit hath never wanted a cover hitherto, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
hath or can the serpent want subtilty, for its his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
by which he liveth: <hi>Nabucadnezar</hi> made a law, that
whosoever would not obey, should be cast into the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace,
and might not all his magistrates have said to
<hi>Shadrak, Meshach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> that they were not
subject to the Kings decree, and therefore judge they
suffered deservedly, and did not the Jewes who were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumcised
in heart say, when they took up stones to
stone Christ, we stone thee not for thy good work<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, but
thou being a man maketh thy selfe God, and the Jewes
stoned <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Stephen,</hi> and put <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> in
prison, they said they were movers of sedition, and ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders
of Sects, but the cheife Preists and the false pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,
had allwayes their hands, in conspiring against
the life of the just, but persecutors were ever blind, and
yet were so conceited, that they saw, that they said to
Christ are we also blind, but the seed of falshood hath
fitten as Judge long, and hath laid the heritage of God
wast, and hath set it selfe in Gods Temple as the true
heir, and judged the heir not worthy to live, and thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99799:9"/>
of thousands have been put to cruell deaths, and a
numberless number hath suffered since the Apostles
dayes, and since the apostacy came in, yet these which
have done these things would be called Christian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates,
and Ministers of justice, and those teachers who
have called to the rulers to punish such as Hereticks, and
Seducers, they would be counted the ministers of Christ,
and such Nations who are out of the life, they would be
counted holy.</p>
            <p>Oh nay, Christ came not to destroy mens lives, but to
save them, and all you rulers in all Nations, who goes
under the name of Christendom, who are upon the earth,
and all you teachers that are therein, whose actions and
lives, doctrines, and principles, and practices, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
to the life of righteousness, and contrary to the
doctrine of Christ and the practice of the holy men of
God, you are all out of Christs nature, and out of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
nature, in the Dragons natu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and in the corrupt
nature, in the nature in which all the disobedient and
the rebellious are in, who are heires of wrath and eternall
vengeance, therefore repent ye of your iniquity, and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
before the Lord God of heaven and earth, who is
roreing from his dwelling place, and uttering forth his
dreadfull voice, at the sound thereof all Nations shall
fear, and be astonished, and the fenced Cities, in which
you dwell, shall be horribly afraid.</p>
            <p>Behold the time of restoring, is come, and coming,
and the year of Gods controversy with <hi>Sions</hi> enemies is
aproching near you, and he who sits and judges in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness,
hath shewed himselfe, will rule over the
heathen as with a rod of Iron, and will pour forth his
plagues upon all the families of the earth, that calls not
upon his name, but despises it, and tramples upon it, the
earth is filled with violence, cruellty and opression, yea
it is broken forth as a flood, and the Nations is covered
with unrighteousness, as with a garment, the beast hath
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99799:10"/>
exercised his power, and hath overcome and prevailed
long over the heritage of God, and the mountain of the
Lords house is made desolate, all is void and without form,
deceit inthroned, truth trampled upon, Judgement turned
backward, and the devill reignes a King, equity hath
found no place, mercy is shut out of doores, cruelty is
entertained, temperance and moderation hath no resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
lust, uncleanness, excess, riotousness, and
wantoness, is loved as though it were the way to eternall
felicity, pride, hipocrisie, and dissimulation is taken plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
in, sobriety and meekness hath no dwelling place,
but is thrown aside, folly and madness is set up as the
greatest wisdome, and the wisdome which is from above
counted the greatest folly; the fear of the Lord is slighted,
Gods pure law thrown behind their backes, the Nations
and the people therein are compassed about with dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
as a wall, and with ignorance as a curtaine, and with
blindness as with a strong fence, they are situated in the
region of death, and at the side of the pit, and yet saith
no evill shall come near us, nor sorrow touch our taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle,
and is in a dead sleep of security, wrapt up in the
slumber of iniquity, involved in utter darkness, folded up
in the deep pit of ignorance; and desires not the knowledge
of wisdome, neither to walk in her path, but her way is
grievous unto them, <hi>and the eye lid of the morning is unto
them as the shadow of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nevertheless he that weighes all things in an even
ballance, before whom all Nations are but as the drop of
a bucket, he is appearing in his power, and thundring from
his holy place, who will make the Nations shake as an
olive leafe, and the Isles tremble before him, who is ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering
forth his voice as the sound of many waters, which
shall make all the Potentates, and mighty of the earth
bow, the eye-lids of the morning is opened, and the Sun
is rising to his height, and the darke Aire is scattering
by the breath of his mouth, and so all things shall appear
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99799:10"/>
in the earth as they are, and every thing under the face of
the Heaven shall be brought to light, and all the powers
of darkness discovered, and the workes, and workers of
iniquity shall no longer be hid, but shall be discovered by
the light of the sonne of God, and shall be judged and
cendemned by the life of righteousness, and blessed are
they who know a hiding place in him, when his over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing
scourge passeth over the Nations which is already
made ready to execute his judgement upon the heathen
that know him not, oh who may abide his presence, when
he appeares in his power and maj<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sty and glory, all the
ungodly of the earth, sha<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l be as driven stubble before his
bow, and shall fly before him, nevertheless the pursues
shall overtake, and the destroyer shall lay hold upon them,
and all the ungodly shall hear the sentence, go ye cursed
from the presence of the Lord into the pit of everlasting
destruction.</p>
            <p>And when this day comes upon the Nations, all your
prophets, diviners and teachers, who are out of the life of
Christ, who have flattered you and told you, you were
the higher power, and you must sit as judge in the things
of the Father, &amp; Lord it over the consciences of people, and
prescribe the Lord a way, and a limit in your several, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
and dominions, they shall not be able to deliver
themselves neither you, but the helper and the helped
shall both fall together, the strengthener and the strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened
shall grow feeble, &amp; their loines weake, so that they
shall not be able to stand before him who is the higher
power, and the greatest digni<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, who will rule over all
usurpers, and over all the children of pride, the Dragon, the
beast and the false prophet, and teller of lies, shall have
their portion in the lake that burns.</p>
            <p>Then shall the ransomed of the Lord, and the righteous
seed, whom the Nations have slain, and persecuted; the
prophets, and holy men of God, and all that have been
slain for the testimony of <hi>Iesus,</hi> rejoice over the deceit,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99799:11"/>
and it shall be sung in that day, the Lord God omnipotent
reigneth, who will ascend above all principallities and
powers, thrones and dominions, and tread down all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
his feet that the earth may be filled with his glory, and
behold he cometh quickly in a moment, and suddain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction
shall be upon his enemies, and the breath of his
mouth shall make all melt away that hate the Lord, and
their remembrance shall rot for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>Therefore oh all ye powers of the earth, who are the
sons of fallen <hi>Adam,</hi> whose power ariseth out of the
earth, in which the Devill dwells and the serpent fe<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ds,
who bear rule but not by the Lord; who sits as judges in
the earth, and yet your judgment is from the earth, and
from below, know this, you shall all be judged with the
just; and all your unrighteous decrees, lawes constituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
ordinances, and edicts, which is made in the fallen
wisdome, you and they both together will be cast aside as
a thing of nought, and must all be judged with the just,
therefore repent and turn to the Lord of heaven and earth,
that you may know his righteouss judgment set up in your
hearts, and the spirit of in justice and error purged out of
your hearts, or else you judge not for God, for all the lawes,
constitutions, and ordinances, which are made in the fallen
principle, and fallen wisdome, to have all these in the
head or in the memory, so that he may act in a Nation or
Kingdome, according to the letter of a law prescribed in a
Nation; that doth not at all make a man an able mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister
of justice or a magistrate for God for the root being
unholy and corrupt and erronious, from whence those
lawes were given forth, the branches is unholy also, the
ground being corrupt, the tree bad, the fruit is bad also,
and so all nations who are degenerate from the life of God,
their lawes and constitutions doth alwayes imbondage the
regenerate; so the heart being deceitfull and unrighteous,
such lawes proceeds forth which doth oppress the upright
in heart, and all, or most of the lawes in all nations, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99799:11"/>
by tradition from generation to generation, since
the scattering of Israell, who received the law from Gods
own mouth by the hand of <hi>Moses</hi> a Magistrate of the
Lord, and a judge over Israell; and so heapes of decrees,
statutes, and ordinances there is in the nations which
doth not answer that of God in the conscience of every
man, and so that which is pure of God in the conscience of
every one cannot be subject to those lawes and tradi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions,
but rather suffers, as many thousands have done, cruell
deaths, and great oppression all this dark time of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ
reign, and of the beast in all nations since the
apostacy; and death raigning over all the sonnes of the
first <hi>Adam,</hi> in the transgression, death hath breathed forth
it self upon the face of the earth, for sin entering and death
by sinne it rules in the heart, and exerciseth his power
which stands in unrighteousness, and so all mankind in all
their acting, can do nothing for God but against him; and
against his people who are redeemed out of the region of
death, and so all law-givers, and law-makers, and lawes
which stands in the will of man, and in the unrighteous
principle, will the second <hi>Adam,</hi> the Lord from Heaven,
the restorer of mankind utterly overthrow, abolish and
take away their power, for the law-giver shall come out
of <hi>Sion;</hi> who ever in all nations, that ever come to see him
must see him come from thence, whose appearance shall be
as a lamp that burnes, and he shall change the customes
and the times and the lawes, and overthrow all them that
stands in the curse, for he shall lead out of death, and out
of its path; and from under the law of sin and death, that
all that heares him and comes to be subject to his law,
shall deny all those lawes in the very ground, and bear
their testimonie against them, which stands in that nature,
that transgresseth the life, and therefore give ear all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
and all Emperors Kings, Monarkes, Lord, Iudges, and
rulers of the earth, in all nations he is come and coming,
whose right it is to judge the earth in righteousness, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99799:12"/>
the people with equity, even he unto whome all judgment
is committed, and he hath appeared as the sonne of God in
the north region of the world in power and majesty and
great glory, and hath made the mountaines me<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t before
him, and he hath dried up all the springs of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and
hath made the Cedars bow; and made the trees of the
forrest to shake; and the sturdy oakes hath he cut up by the
rootes; and turned a pleasant land into a wilderness, and
hath made the wilderness to blossome, and hath changed
the customes allready, and hath broken deaths covenant,
and hath overthrown the mighty men, yea even the horse
and his rider, and hath taken off their chariot wheeles in
the day of battail, and it hath been a dreadfull day and a
sore slaughter, as in the dayes of <hi>Gibea,</hi> or as in the valley
<hi>Jehos<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phat</hi> and a sorrowfull day hath come, and great
mourning, as <hi>Hadadrimmon</hi> in the valley of <hi>Megiddo,</hi> for
one post hath met another, and the news hath been, <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi>
is taken at both ends, and he hath over-run the
multitude of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and trampled upon them, as the
prancing of horses in battel, so that the mighty are fallen
by him, and the strong hath not been able to help them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
against him who hath come as one that trod the
winepress, and now hath overturned the powers of death,
hell and the grave, and hath broken deathes covenant,
and will put an end to all changeable lawes, and hath
and will establish his law which indures for ever &amp; ever:
and now heare, all that are left unspoyled are angry, and
all that worship the Beast, are left unslain, blasphemes
him and speakes evi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l of his name, and of his wondrous
workes which he hath done in t<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is day, as in the land
of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and in the fields of <hi>ZOAN;</hi> for he hath
turned the waters into blood, and hath cut all the fresh
springs, and hath slain the first-born of <hi>Egypt,</hi> at which
<hi>Pharaoh</hi> and all his wise men, and all the Egyptians are
angry, and still resists the Lord, till they will, with the rest
who have resisted him, be swallowed up of the Deep.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:99799:12"/>
And now oh Nations, who are scituated under the
whole face of the Heaven, he is coming up against you as
a Giant refreshed with wine, and shall run his course, and
none shall be able to stop his way, and shall come as <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi>
after the slaughter of <hi>Edom,</hi> with their Garments
red; and he travails in the greatness of his strength, and
shall make all Nations desolate, who have given their
power to the Beast, and will break their Covenants, and
throw down your traditions which are Heathenish, and he
is bringing a handfull out of the North Country, who
have been eye-witnesses of his power, Majesty, and
Glory, and of his noble Acts, and though but a handfull,
yet they are blessed, and his increase shall be great, for
they shall subdue Nations, and Kings shall be tributary
to them, and they shall be his Witnesses to the ends of the
World, and shall publish his Righteousness from Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
to Generation, &amp; bear their testimony of him, who
lives for ever and ever, who is the Lord of Heaven and
Earth, our Righteousness; who hath broken open the Seals
of the Deep, and hath made the springs of Life to flow
forth as though it issued out of a Wombe; by which his
little ones are refreshed and grow in strength, honour, and
glory to him in the highest, whose judgements are just,
holy, pure and equall for ever and ever:</p>
            <p>Oh who can stand before him, who hath uttered forth
his voice before his Camp, and its very great, devouring
fire is before him, and it is tempestuous round about him,
and his sword devoures much flesh, and all the ungodly
shall be slain, heaps upon heaps, so that there shall be
none left to bury the dead: A glorious high Throne hath
he erected, and he sits thereon, and judges in righteousness,
even he before whose face the Heaven and the Earth shall
fly away, and the Sea be dried up, oh who can dwell with
d<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vouring fire, who can dwell with everlasting burning,
who can stand when he appears, when he draws out his
sword of Justice all Nations shall grow pale, and all the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99799:13"/>
rulers feeble, and the Warriour shall not find his hands in
the day of batta<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l, when they encounter with the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty,
for his sword shall be fatted with slaughter, and
all Nations who resist shall become soked with blood.</p>
            <p>Oh he is dreadfull, who can stand when he appears,
who is a consuming fire, therefore all Rulers in Nations,
and Potentates of the Earth, feare and dread his holy
name, and bow unto his righteous Scepter, least you be
cut off, and perish with the rest of the uncircumcised, who
have resisted him, and go down into the nethermost Hell
for ever; for assuredly the day of your fanning and trying
is near, arme your selves, put on your Armour, see if you
be able to stand in the day of the Lord. Oh, nay you will
all be as dust before the whirl-wind, and shall be scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered
in the fierce anger of the Lord, and all your change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
Laws, Constitutions, Customs, and Traditions, which
is brought forth from the changeable principle, which is
gone out from the life, and all your turning of th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side
down, shall be as the Potters clay, for he unto whom
the eternall being hath committed all Judgement, which
he hath appointed to judge in righteou<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ness is appearing,
and come, and coming, who si<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s as a Refiners fire, and
sits as Judge among the Gods, who will not give his glory
and honour to any other.</p>
            <p>And so all you that b<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are rule and not by him, who is
the true light which in<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ightneth every man that cometh
into the World your p<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wer other is from another, even from
him who is <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> with the light, for by me
saith the L<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rd K<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngs rule, and Princes decree Justice, and
such as were obedient un<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o his righteous Law written in
their hearts; as <hi>David, Solomor, Jehosaphat, Ezekiah,</hi> and
the rest of the holy Kings and Princes, who were guided
by that which was just &amp; unchangeable, they ruled by his
power and decreed Justice, and answered that which was
just in every mans conscience, which is one with that
power in which they ruled, and from whence they acted,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99799:13"/>
and so a terrour they became to none, but evil doers, who were
out of the power, and out of the truth, and in that nature
which stood up against that powers by which the Princes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed
Justice, and so with the power of God, all these Rulers,
and Rules, and Governments, which is not according to the
power of the just God, is to be abolished at the coming of
him, whose day shall come, and in his power and glory he
shall appear, which shall darken and dazell, extirpate, and
utterly destroy all, root and branch together, who is out of
his power and against it, so there shall be a very great over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning,
such as hath not been from the beginning, neither
shall be ever hereafter.</p>
            <p>And then shall the Restorer be seen, who shall restore the
Earth into its first purity, and there shall be Judges as at the
first, and Counsellers as at the beginning; then shall the Earth
injoy her rest, and the Nations their Sabaoth, for the Lord of
glory hath considered it, and he hath listened, and a great
cry is heard out of all Nations, of the poor, and of the opres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,
and of his Creatures which he hath made, how they
have been chopped to pieces, as flesh for the Pot, and ground
to dust as though they had not been Gods workmanship, and
his seed in al<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Nations hath been held in great captivity; whose
sighes, groanes and tears hath pierced through the Clouds,
and is entered to the Throne of God, who is now arising to
plead the cause of the poor and the needy, and now woe to
the World, and to all them that have borne rule, but not by
the Lord.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="exhortation">
            <head>An advertisment to all the rulers
upon earth,</head>
            <p>THere is one onely God, the Creator and the bringer forth
of all things, whose way is equal, and whose Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
are just, whose Law is righteous, whose Statutes are
pure, answering his own pure Witness in every man under
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99799:14"/>
the face of Heaven in all Nations upon the Earth, so as every
man in all Nations upon the Earth comes to own Gods pure
witness in himself, placed by the Lord; he shall be made to
confess unto the righteous acting of those Rulers who rule in
righteousness, by the righteous law of God; but where any
Ruler is not ruled himself, by that which is pure of God which
condemneth self, and self-actings in himself, He bears rule,
but not in Gods Dominion, and so layes yoaks upon a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
Country or People, to make all submit to his will, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees,
and ordinances, and to deny that which is pure of God
in themselves, and then joyns to his deceit, and thus iniquity
gets head, and is set up as a rule, and the law of God, both in
the Ruler, and the ruled, is throwne behind their back, and
so deceit leadeth, and the changeable mind acteth it self out in
every thing that it hath to do withall; and so tyranie and opres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
spreads over a whole Nation, and the just suffers in it.</p>
            <p>And hence it is that there are so many several Laws, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances
and Constitutions, and Traditions, and Customs
among men in many Nations and Countreys, and Regions,
one differing from another, and heaps of confusion, that hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
in any Nations, or few in a Nation knows what is Law,
there is so much variableness, and changeableness amongst
the Lawmakers, one while setting up, another while pulling
down, and as deceit advanceth it self in any particular Ruler,
then there must be a Law made, and a penalty upon the non-performance,
as death, banishment, tortering, whipping,
racking, prisonment, fining, to the utter destruction of many;
and all the ground of this is because the Rulers are gone from
that of God in themselves, and then acts in their own wills,
and by their craft and deceit which stands in the Ground,
which is cursed, and calls this Christian pollicy and wisdom,
and cruelty becomes a Law, and the Devil keeps his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
in the Earth, and deceit gets a Cover and hides it self</p>
            <p>Now it was not so from the beginning; For as God is one,
and his Name one, his Law is one, which is pure and equal,
and unalterable, and indures for ever and ever. Now man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
made in Gods own Image, answered the pure Law of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99799:14"/>
God, and being Gods Image was one with the Law, and the
Law was not against him, but was his life and joy, and he had
power to obey it; for he was of its own nature, for as God is
pure and holy, and the Image which he brought forth man in
was pure and holy, and that which was mans guide and rule
was pure and holy, here was unity and purity, and he that
created, and man that was created was in unity, and then
there was no woe, no condemnation, no sorrow, no death,
no tribulation, nor anguish, nor wrath, revealed against man
who was the Image of God, and he stood in the Dominion
of God, and had dominion over that which was contrary,
here was no tyranie, here was no cruelty, no prisons, no envie,
no persecution, no killing nor destroying, no defrauding, no
jarre, no strife, no devouring, but all Gods creation at unity,
and man at unity with God, being partakers of his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
whereby all the Earth was in order, and in that wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
which changed not, and here man had dominion and
power, and ruled in Gods authority, and was guided by the
higher power, and while he was subject to it, death had no
power over him; now this was before sin entered, and before
death entred, &amp; before enmity had appeared in the Earth, but
now was the Lord King and Law-giver, and Judge, who ruled
in righteousness, and man being subject to him, there was no
Law against him, nor no guilt of any thing, for transgression
was not known in the Earth, and there was no curse, but all
was in unity and peace, no changeableness, but all was in the
covenant, all the workmanship of his hand was united unto
him, and all that he had made was blessed, and all the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
were partakers of his blessedness, and all stood in the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
by which every Creature received power, virtue and
dominion, here was one mind, and here was no double, no
variation, no mutation, nor change, but the dominion of the
everlasting God was felt, which indures for ever and ever,
and any other thing was not seen in the Earth, but man
crowned with honour, dominion and dignity, wherein could
be nothing but rejoycing, and pure peace and joy, now no
evill was known, neither was there any such thing, but good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99799:15"/>
possessed the whole Earth, and righteousness breathed
forth it self in all things in the circumference thereof, and all
the works of his hends pleased him, and man made partakers
of his pleasure, and was accepted, and not rejected, thus in
part I have shewed unto you the state of the Earth, and of
mankind, and the glory of Gods Creation, and the blessed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
thereof, but if I could declare unto the whole World,
from years end, to years end, I should fall short, and words
would be wanting, to express the felicity and happiness in
which man was brought forth in, neither shall any be able
to see into those things, or to declare certainly of those things,
who come not beyond time, to him who is eternal, who
gave them a being.</p>
            <p>But after man had taken of the Tree of Knowledge of
good and evill, and had eate of the fruit thereof; and consen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
to the beguiler, and to the Serpent, sin entered, and death
by sin, man lost his dominion, and became subject to another,
and another had power over him, and now the course of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
was set on the fire of Hell, the curse entered, and man
dead while he lives; and in that day he eate did die, and death
breathed forth it self in the Earth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and <hi>Cain</hi> is brought forth
in his own Image, to wit, in the Image of him who was gone
out of Gods Dominion, and he became a murderer, and slew
him that was accepted of God, and here appeared now the
enmity, and its life was to destroy, and to murder, and to kill
<hi>Abell,</hi> who believed and offered up a sacrifice, and <hi>Cain</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
in the unbelief, and was not accepted, so <hi>Abell</hi> who
was just lived by Faith, but <hi>Cain</hi> who was in the envie and
in the wrath, this life was death to him and to his nature,
and so all who are out of the Faith, are dead while they live.</p>
            <p>Now after the transgression in process of time, when the
seed of fallen <hi>Adam</hi> began to increase in the Earth, being
driven out from the presence of the Lord; they spread over
the whole Earth, and sought many inventions being gone
from that of God in themselves, by which they were united
unto him, having broken his covenant, and joyned in cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
with death, death acts forth it self against the seed, which
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99799:15"/>
is not of its nature, and alwaies sought to imbondage it, and
to kill it as <hi>Cain</hi> did <hi>Abell,</hi> and <hi>Esau, Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Ismael</hi> did
unto <hi>Isaack</hi> and unto his seed.</p>
            <p>Now the seed unto which the promise was received, the
Law from the mouth of the Lord, and they that persecuted
the seed, invented, and made Laws of their own, according to
that nature in which they lived, and so became heathenish in
their Fashions, and Laws, and Customs, and cruelty grew up
as it was nourished, and leavened into its own nature, and
unbelief grew into a mighty stature, and monsters was brought
forth in such a strange shape in every thing, that the enmity
did appear in, as had not been seen in the Earth before, and
and so man being gone astray from the life of righteousness,
every thing is abominable, and of a stranger nature, that he
brings forth: yet take notice of this, that as the seed unto
which the promise was who were in the Faith, and obeyed
through Faith, they had a Law, so they in unbelief had also a
Law, as the seed worshipped the living God, through a lively
and a living Faith, and so sinned not in so doing, the seed of
the serpent imitated a worship, and worshipped in death and
unbelief, and as the Laws of one was equal, such as <hi>David</hi>
and <hi>Solomon,</hi> the other was unequal, such as <hi>Jeroboam</hi> and
<hi>Rehoboam,</hi> and as the one set up equity by a Law, the other
made a Law to set up iniquity.</p>
            <p>And the seed, they sought not their own honour, but the
honour of him who was their reward, but the seed of the evil
doer sought himself and his own honour, and as the spirit of
the Lord breathed forth it self, and spoke the truth in the
power of God, deceit uttered forth lies in hypocrisie, and in
the power of death, and as the upright lived unto God in the
spirit, deceit lived unto the flesh, and unto him who hath the
power of death, which is the Devill, and as they fulfilled the
Law of God, who were led by his holy spirit of God into
all truth, the other followed their own imaginations, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered
the deceit and foolish mind, and they whose under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing
was darkened loved them, and had pleasure in them.</p>
            <p>So it may be truly said, many Nations, Rulers and ruled
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99799:16"/>
sit in the Region of the shaddow of death; and the living God
is forgotten among them, &amp; one against another, they are seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
one anothers ruine, &amp; all in the violence, &amp; in the cruelty.</p>
            <p>Therefore all Rulers and Potentates of the Earth, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates
and Governours under the whole face of Heaven,
hearken unto the words of my mouth, and listen unto under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing,
that you may be partakers of the happiness and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity
which God is shedding abroad, now in the latter dayes,
that so the Restorer you may know in your Regions, and the
deliverer in your Nations, and the maker up of the breach in
your Dominions, that he who is the desire of all Nations may
be revealed among you.</p>
            <p>He which must restore is not born of man, nor cometh not
to a People or a Nation, in the will of man, neither seeks he
himself, but the glory of the Father, who hath sent him to
seek, and to save that which is lost, and to heale the breaches,
and to destroy that which hath made the breach, that so all
Nations who receive him, &amp; believe in him, may be reconcil'd
unto him, and one to another; that the Earth may injoy rest &amp;
the Regions quietness; therefore all be warned not to look
forth in your wils, for there you will not receive him, but slight
him, as many before you have done, and so lie down in sorrow,
and weary your selves in vanity, and lie down in infamy, and
never come to see his dignity.</p>
            <p>Now he, of whom I declare unto you, is the Son of God,
who is the light of the World, and the life of man, and hath
lightened every man that cometh into the World, which light
wherewith all men are inlightned is not contrary to the Law
of God which indures for ever, but one with it, and this will
let you see, violence, treachery, murder, envie, wrath, malicious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
drunkeness, whoredom, lying, cursed speaking, stealing, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauding,
cheating, cosening, rioteousness, pride, arogancy, emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,
contention, strife, hatred, persecution, cruelty, opression, I
say the light which comes from Christ by whom the World
was made, will shew you that all these things is sin and evil
in the sight of God, and also will let you see there is a ground
from whence these, and all other evils proceed, which ground
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99799:16"/>
is in all the Sons of men in the transgression, till it be removed,
and these things before mentioned, be the fruits that grows
from it, and buds forth themselves in all Nations, and in every
man in every Nation, so the Earth is filled with violence, and
the grapes are as <hi>Sodom,</hi> &amp; the fruit as <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> whom God
overthrew, and till these things be done away, and these
fruits wither, and the root from whence they arise be removed
out of every particular man who is a Ruler, he cannot be a
blessing to a Nation, neither rule for God in a Nation, neither
will he or can he be a terrour to all these things before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.</p>
            <p>While he himself is in those, for he cannot destroy his own
life, neither will iniquity set up righteousness, nor the worker
of iniquity advance Christ.</p>
            <p>Therefore listen to the words of my mouth, and despise not
counsell, least you perish among fools, and go down to the
horrible pit, where there is everlasting misery unto all perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity.</p>
            <p>Now God that made both Heaven and Earth, and all things
that therein are; he is light, and with him is no darkness at all,
he never changes his purity; nor alters his righteous decrees,
his eye is pure, and alwaies fixed to behold all the works of the
Sons of men, and he searches the heart of man with his eye,
and pierceth through the secret places, and is near to every
man, although man do not see him, he is invisible, and eternal,
and his Law indures for ever, and the unalterable decree, by
which sin is judged and reproved in the World, and in every
particular man, and every man who hearkens and hears the
words of the pure Law, which judges all sin in man, receiveth
the sentence of death in himself, and is judged by the righteous
words of his mouth, and so sin in the particular comes to be
condemned, and all these changeable things is trodden under
foot, which is acted and brought forth from the changeable
mind of man, and so all Laws, Constitutions and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees,
which is made in the will of man, comes to be thrown
down by his righteous Law which proceeds out of the mouth
of the righteous God, who is light, and so as his unchangeable
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99799:17"/>
and unalterable decree comes to be set up in every particular Ruler, &amp;
Governour, and himself judged with the just, he comes to bear his rule
for the just, and answers that which is just in every man, and no longer
can he act against well doing, but is a leader, and an incourager of it in
all, and is a terrour to the unjust, and so comes to know the dominion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain
which man lost through disobedience and transgression.</p>
            <p>Now all you powers of the Earth, wait that you may come to see that,
&amp; feel it revealed in your selves, to wit the Law of God from the mouth
of God, that so you following it, sin may be judged in your selves, &amp; you
come to know the one Lord the Lawgiver which leads man back out of
sin, &amp; transgression by his Son whom he hath sent into the World, that
all men through him might believe in the Father, &amp; be restored out of
sin &amp; transgression unto life eternal, where death hath no entrance, &amp; so
all who waits upon the light of the Son of God, and is obedient to it,
they come to feel his power and his decree which cannot alter its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty
or verity,, &amp; all who comes to be guided by it, you will come to see
that which unites you unto God, &amp; one Nation to another, in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
of God! Oh that all your eyes were opened, that you might see
that which belongs to your peace &amp; the well being of all Nations, that
so the power of the flock might be refreshed among you, and this I speak
unto you, a change must be witnessed in your selves, before you will cease
acting in the changeable mind, now the time draws near, the Lord will
try you, for the Earth must be left without excuse, and he will have all
warned, for God will no longer be limited, and therefore take heed how
you gainsay any or resist any, vvho may declare unto you the counsell of
God, and cause them not to be persecuted or hurt, but all be calme and
moderate, and learn vvisdom from above, from him vvho hath inlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
you, that you may come to deny your selves, and follovv him vvho
condems all self actings, and self vvill in man, and all Customs, Lavvs,
and Worships, &amp; Traditions, that is made in the vvill of man, that so he
unto vvhom all povver is committed may be feared, and vvorshipped in
spirit, in life, truth and righteousness, that so all sedition, rebellion,
treachery and unrighteousness may be cleansed out of the Earth, and
that all quarrelling, fighting, contention may end; and people come
out of that vvhich the svvord is against, that so the svvords may be beat
into Plovvshares, and the spears into pruning hooks, that so violence
may be done avvay, and cruelty, svvept out of the Nations, that the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion
of God may be set over all, and his truth advanced above all,
that the Kingdoms of the World may become the Lords, &amp; his Christs;
and blessed are they that stoop unto his Scepter, vvho judges the Nations
in righteousness, and the people vvith equity, who is the Salvat<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on of
all his people for evermore, and a hiding place in the day of trouble.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>LONDON, <date>The 20. of the 2. Moneth, 1658.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
