<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of the last words and departure of that antient and honourable woman Loveday Hambly of Trigangeeues, in the parish of Austell in the County of Cornwal. With farther testimonies concerning her life and conversation.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45365</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H472</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216508</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828235</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828235</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32662</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A45365)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32662)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1865:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of the last words and departure of that antient and honourable woman Loveday Hambly of Trigangeeues, in the parish of Austell in the County of Cornwal. With farther testimonies concerning her life and conversation.</title>
                  <author>Hambly, Loveday, 1603 or 4-1682.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by John Gain, living in the Upper Moor-Fields, near the Flying-Horse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.LXXXIII. [1683]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Loveday Hambly. In fact a series of letters written in honor of Loveday Hambly, who died on "the 14th of the 10th month 1682 .." [p. 11] and who "hath, by reason of old age, great weekness and many infirmities kept her bed for the most part this seven weeks, being aged about seventy eight years .." [p. 4].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Friends' House Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hambly, Loveday, 1603 or 4-1682.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  England --  Cornwall --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32662:1"/>
            <p>A RELATION OF THE Laſt WORDS and Departure OF THAT Antient and Honourable <hi>Woman <hi>Loveday Hambly,</hi>
               </hi> OF <hi>Trigangeeues,</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Auſtell</hi> in the County of <hi>Cornwal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With farther Teſtimonies concerning her <hi>LIFE</hi> and <hi>CONVERSATION.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 10.6.</hi>
               </bibl>Bleſſings are upon the Head of the Juſt, but Violence covereth the Mouth of the Wicked.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 31.30, 31.</hi>
               </bibl>A Woman that feareth the Lord ſhall be praiſed: Give her of the Fruit of her Hands and let her own Works praiſe her in the Gates.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Acts 10.4.</hi>
               </bibl>And he ſaid unto him, thy Prayers and thine Alms are come up for a Memorial before God.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Gain,</hi> Living in the Upper <hi>Moor-Fields,</hi> near the <hi>Flying-Horſe,</hi> M.DC.LXXXIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:32662:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:32662:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>DEar Friends unto whoſe hands this may come, this is to ſignifie of the Deceaſe of our dear Friend <hi>Loveday Hambly,</hi> who hath finiſhed her Courſe in this World and is gone to her long home, where the wicked ceaſe from troubling: and if in former time ſuch Women as feared God were eſteemed honourable, and record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Poſterity for their Vertue and good Works, may not this Friend of ours be recorded amongſt the Living at this day whom the Living God raiſed up and made an Inſtrument in his hand to be ſerviceable in doing much good; who was a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of a noble univerſal Spirit, and deſcended of honourable Parentage as amongſt Men: Her fame, no doubt, is already gon far, eſpecially amongſt God's People, though many never knew her, or ſaw her Perſonally, to whom the following Account may be of ſervice, as well as to ſuch as did know her, and be a means to ſtir up the Mind that's Pure in all to admire the Goodneſs of the Lord, &amp; may be encouraged to ſerve and obey him in faithfulneſs in their Day and Time, that they may come to reſt in Gods heavenly Kingdom for evermore, into which this faithful Friend is entred.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not need here much to enlarge concerning this my dear, loving and well beloved Friend, becauſe the Matter is ſo fully and truly Stated in the following Relation and Teſtimonies, to which (much of it) I can truly Subſcribe: for it was my Lot to be a Houſhold Servant to her about two years, to look after her Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and might have been to her dying day for ought I know, if I had not been taken a Priſoner for the Teſtimony of Truth, and kept about eight years in Priſon, at which ſhe was troubled and diſappointed alſo; for ſhe did manifeſt much Love to me; yea, I may ſay, ſhe was more like a Mother to me than a Miſtriſs: I was an Eye-Witneſs to much of her Tryals and Sufferings, in which ſhe was very va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant and chearful: ſhe had a great Family, and God gave her a great Meaſure of Wiſdom to order it: her Tables were largely and plentifully ſpread, which is well known to many, and ſhe took great care that all might have ſufficient, and likewiſe that none of the good Creatures which God had given ſhould be abuſed or waſted upon any account. And how tender was ſhe and pitiful to the meaneſt Servant in her Family, if they were ſick, or wanted her Help and Aſſiſtance, and the Lord wonderfully bleſt her Endeavours; for it may be truly ſaid, ſhe had a true regard unto him, as I have obſerved upon many occaſions, her Heart was often tendered in a ſenſe of the Mercies and Love of God, and this often was her
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32662:3"/>
Expreſſion, <hi>I give God the Glory.</hi> Or, <hi>Bleſſed be the Name of the Lord.</hi> And many times in the day, as ſhe had Opportunity, ſhe betook her ſelf to her Cloſet to be retired, and many times came out amongſt her Family as one whoſe Strength was inwardly renewed, in a cool and tender Frame of Spirit. O what could I ſay of her Sincerity and love to the Lord, his Truth and People! But ſhall ſumme up all in this, That ſhe was a good Woman and very ſerviceable, as many in thoſe parts do right well know. And as it was her earneſt deſire often in my hearing, ſo it is mine, That the Lord who raiſed her up in that Place and County, would be pleaſed to raiſe another in her ſtead and place to do as ſhe hath done, that her Intentions may be fulfilled and anſwered, even the Propagation of the pretious and everlasting Truth, in which I do dearly Salute you all, and am your real Friend,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Reading the</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>20th. of the 1st. Month, 1682/3.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Benjamin Coales.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>A Coyy of a Letter ſent to <hi>M. D.</hi> and Friends at <hi>Plymouth,</hi> the <hi>14th.</hi> day of <hi>10th.</hi> Month, <hi>1682.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Margery Dyer,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>AND the reſt of Friends in <hi>Plymouth,</hi> knowing that you have a deſire to hear how it is with our Friend <hi>Loveday Hambly,</hi> whoſe Fame for <hi>Good Works, Charity</hi> and <hi>Hoſpitality,</hi> is gone forth to the uttermoſt Confines of the Land of our Nativity; and we believe it may be affirmed with confidence, that her Renown is gone forth to the Iſles afar off, as a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon accounted famous among Gods People, for <hi>Sufferings,</hi> and <hi>Zealous of Good Works,</hi> ever ſince the Day that ſhe was turned from <hi>Darkneſs</hi> to <hi>Light,</hi> and from the <hi>Power of Satan</hi> to <hi>God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now Dear Friend, this may certifie thee and Friends there, that our Dear Friend above mentioned <hi>L. H.</hi> hath, by reaſon of <hi>Old Age, great Weekneſs</hi> and <hi>many Infirmities</hi> kept her Bed for the moſt part this Seven Weeks, being aged about ſeventy eight Years; and though we are here as in a Houſe of <hi>Mourning,</hi> under the conſideration of her <hi>Bodily Weakneſs,</hi> and in the ſenſe of the <hi>Departure</hi> of ſuch a Serviceable Friend: yet we are Comforted and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed in that we can give a Living Teſtimony, that ſhe is in a good Frame of Spirit in relation to <hi>Heavenly Things:</hi> for it hath been obſerved of late, that if any Friend or other of her <hi>Relations</hi> have ſpoken to her about any of her <hi>Outward Affairs,</hi> her Memory fail'd her, as to give any direct Anſwer: but when any <hi>Friend</hi> did Read or Pray by her, or ſpeak to her of <hi>Spiritual Matters</hi> ſhe hath been much Revived and full of <hi>good Expreſſions</hi> and <hi>Praiſes</hi> to the Lord for his manifold Mercies towards her; often ſaying, <hi>She deſired nothing but the Kingdom of God:</hi> and in the <hi>Evening</hi> ſeveral <hi>Friends, Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:32662:3"/>
and <hi>Attendants</hi> being about her Bed with a <hi>Candle;</hi> one did deſire to ſee her <hi>Tongue,</hi> ſhe chearfully ſaid, <hi>Take away the Candle, and let me have the Light of the Countenance of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> And dayly and hourly ſhe ceaſed not to ſound forth the Praiſes of the Lord, and her Deſires and Prayers to the Lord were, <hi>to continue his Mercy towards her.</hi> She ſaw her own weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and believed in the Strength of the Lord: and as ſhe drew near her End, ſhe grew into a loving Child-like State and Condition to all that came to ſee her, deſiring earneſtly the Proſperity of Gods Truth; and often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared her Intent in beſtowing her <hi>Outward Eſtate</hi> in the manner as ſhe had done, was, even that the Holy Truth might be propagated, and thoſe that profeſs it might be Supported by her <hi>Free Gift</hi> after her Deceaſe, and that <hi>Friends</hi> who did Travel in the <hi>Truths Service</hi> and were in want, might be ſupplyed by thoſe to whom ſhe left her <hi>Outward Eſtate;</hi> elſe, ſaid ſhe, I ſhould never have left it to him.</p>
                  <p>Here follow ſeveral of her Expreſſions taken by ſuch as were with her the Night before her Departure.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My Heart and Soul is poured forth unto thee, O thou Eternal God, thou art the Comfort and Salvation of Old Age: and the Deſire of my Heart is, that all my Friends may be kept faithful to the Living God: for I declare here in the Preſence of the Lord and before you, that I do love all the Children and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Living God with all my Heart, Soul and Strength. — And I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the God of</hi> Abraham, Iſaac <hi>and</hi> Jacob <hi>with all my Heart and Soul, that I may faithfully fight under his Banner.—</hi> Moreover ſhe ſaid, <hi>The Lord knows my Heart, I never loved the Riches of this World, for what is it worth, it is all Vanity and Vexation of Spirit.—</hi> At another time ſhe ſaid, <hi>I deſire to take up the Shield of Faith and the Helmet of Salvation, and that I may dwell in the Houſe of God.</hi> After ſhe had layn ſtill a pritty while, like one in a ſweet, Sleep, ſhe opened her eyes, and ſeeing ſome of her Friends and Servants about her, ſhe ſmilingly ſaid, <hi>Methinks I have been in a great Warefare, and there was mighty Doings, and O what a Comfort it was to me; we will not fall out about it, for their Kingdom muſt come into my Kingdom.</hi> Again ſhe ſaid, <hi>My God, look over them, keep all thy Handmaids, my God, my God.—</hi> And not long before her Departure, in a good ſence and deep Expreſſion of Soul, ſhe ſaid, <hi>Glory, Glory, Eternal Glory, for thy great Kindneſt and Love to thy Handmaid.</hi> — And many times after ſhe would begin ſome good words, which ſhe was not able to utter forth, but ſome Friends ſtanding by her, would help her therein, and then ſhe would rejoyce that her Mind was uttered by another, and ſo continued quiet as a Lamb for about fourteen hours before her Depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: then deep groans did proceed from her un<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>il the eighth hour in the Morning, on the 14th. day of the 10th Month, 1682, at which time ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted this Life, and ſlept with her Fathers, and as we hope and verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32662:4"/>
is entred into a bleſſed Eternity. And this is written and witneſſed unto by thy Loving <hi>Friends,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Thomas Salthouſe.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Richard Tregenow.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Anne Salthouſe.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Loveday Beachamp.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>With ſeveral Servants and other Attendants.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>A farther Teſtimony concerning Dear <hi>Loveday Hambly,</hi> from <hi>T. S.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SHould I undertake to ſet forth a Declaration of her Vertue in the laſt twenty years of her Life, while I have had acquaintance with her, it would require the Pen of a far readyer Writer, and fill more Paper than is intended at this time, for it is not practicable among us to garniſh the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcres of the <hi>Righteous,</hi> nor is it any way needful to write <hi>Letters of Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation</hi> for the Dead, who are entred into the <hi>Reſt</hi> prepared for Gods Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and in quiet Poſſeſſion of an Inheritance among them that are Sanctifyed by <hi>Faith</hi> in Chriſt Jeſus, for the Spirit ſaith expreſly, <hi>Bleſſed are the Dead that dye in the Lord, for they reſt from their Labour, and their Works follow them.</hi> Our Dear <hi>Friend L. H.</hi> is now gone to her long Home, and we ceaſe to ſorrow for her that is fall'n aſleep, like thoſe that have no hope; for if in this Life only we have hope of Chriſt, we are of all men moſt miſerable, <hi>for many are the Tryals of the Righteous,</hi> &amp;c. And truly the Tribulations, Tryals, and Exerciſes of this good Woman were many in the Days of her Pilgrimage in this preſent World, as may in part appear by the Records of our Friends Sufferings in this County, ſome of which are in Print, and ſome in Manuſcript, beſides Reproaches, Tryals, and cruel Mockings that did attend us while the way was every where ſpoken againſt, in which we walk, and Worſhip the only true God of our Fathers in Spirit and in Truth.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Good Friend</hi> and <hi>Antient Widdow Woman</hi> was ſeveral times caſt into Priſon at <hi>Lanceston</hi> and <hi>Bodmine</hi> for the Poſſeſſion and Practice of her Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and once conſtrained to ride to <hi>London,</hi> which is about 220 Miles from her Houſe, to make appearance there for Non-payment of <hi>Tythes,</hi> &amp;c. and at ſeveral times had her <hi>Goods</hi> taken away in great Quantities, to the value of many hundreds of pounds, ſometimes fourty Head of Cattle at once, for her faithful Teſtimony againſt the <hi>Oppreſſion of Tythes,</hi> and ſhe did always take joyfully the ſpoiling of her <hi>Goods,</hi> with <hi>Bonds</hi> and <hi>Impriſonmen<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> that did often attend her for Matter of Conſcience, for no occaſion could juſtly be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken againſt her, except concerning the <hi>Righteous Law, Way,</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> of the <hi>Living God;</hi> for in other Caſes ſhe was always careful to owe nothing to any Man but Love; greateſt Policy, Prudence and Care was to promote the <hi>Interest</hi> of the pretious Truth, and not only the Form, but the Power of Godlineſs, her Houſe was made a <hi>Houſe of Prayer,</hi> her <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Hand</hi> was
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32662:4"/>
bountiful and open to adminiſter to ſuch as needed <hi>Food</hi> or <hi>Phyſick,</hi> and the Lord was pleaſed to give a great Bleſſing to her Endeavours; many of her Neighbours are witneſſes or it at this day; her <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Hoſpitality</hi> was not confined to her <hi>Relations</hi> and the People of her own <hi>Perſwaſion,</hi> but was extended to <hi>Rich</hi> and <hi>Poor, Strangers</hi> and <hi>Enemies;</hi> yea, ſhe was truly Kind and Charitable in her day to the utmoſt of her Ability, few in this Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did exceed her for <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Good Works<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> ſhe was no <hi>Orator,</hi> as to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs her Mind by Men-pleaſing Excellency of Speech, or inticing fine words that Mens Wiſdom teacheth, but her Love was manifeſted to be real Love, not in words only, but in Deed and in Truth, which gives me this Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to ſay ſhe was a <hi>Diſciple</hi> indeed; and the Lord bleſt her in her Basket and Store, after all her Sufferings for Righteouſneſs ſake, and ſhe never want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Meat, Drink</hi> nor <hi>Cloathing</hi> to accomodate her <hi>Perſecutors</hi> and their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, if they were either in want of <hi>Food</hi> or <hi>Raiment;</hi> neither did ſhe ſay, be warm, and be cloathed and fed by others, but did it dayly and freely, for they were her own words often uttered in my hearing, <hi>What's all the World? I have enough, I will never live miſerable to dye Rich.</hi> And yet ſhe hath left a competent Eſtate to be divided amongſt many of her <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Relations,</hi> and to the <hi>Poor</hi> of the <hi>Neighbouring Pariſhes,</hi> as appears by her laſt <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Testament,</hi> her Command concerning her <hi>Funeral</hi> was carefully obſerved by her <hi>Relations</hi> and <hi>Friends,</hi> and many hundreds of ſober People did accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny her to her <hi>Grave</hi> in a Decent Burying Place, in the <hi>Tenement</hi> of <hi>Trigan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geeves,</hi> where her Dead Body is at reſt, and her Spirit is returned to God that gave it, and to the Spirits of Juſt Men made perfect, and I believe her Name is written in Heaven, and ſhe is entred in the Poſſeſſion of that Peace and Joy in the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> which is the effect of everlaſting Righteouſneſs, and hath a Name and a Place in the <hi>Houſe of the Lord,</hi> and within the <hi>Walls of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> even an everlaſting Name that ſhall never be blotted out nor forgotten.</p>
                  <p>Dear <hi>Friends, Brethren</hi> and <hi>Sisters</hi> who are asking the way to <hi>Zion,</hi> with your Faces thitherward, and who have deſires to have Intelligence of the State of Affairs among Friends in theſe Parts: this gives you advice of the Departure of the above mentioned Mother in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> let it not trouble you, for it is well with her; and this is a living Teſtimony of never dying Love, that's given forth and ſent to you from your <hi>Loving Friend</hi> and <hi>Fellow Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> in the way of Holyneſs,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Auſtell</hi> in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> 
                        <date>the 20th. of the 10th. <hi>Month,</hi> 1682.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Thomas Salthouſe</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>The Testimony of <hi>Thomas Curtis.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AS for <hi>Loveday Hambly</hi> that honourable Woman in the <hi>Flock of God,</hi> I have this Teſtimony to give for her, that her Nam <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> eth, although
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32662:5"/>
ſhe be gone to the Place prepared for all the Living, and her Memorial will abide among many <hi>Brethren,</hi> becauſe of her great Care of the <hi>Truth</hi> amongſt the <hi>Heritage</hi> of the Almighty.</p>
                  <p>Before ſhe was convinced of the Truth, ſhe was a Zealous Profeſſor, a Woman ſeeking after the Living God in the dead Forms of this World, and very diligent to follow after the beſt men then in eſteem amongſt thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, not willing to miſs a <hi>Lecture</hi> or <hi>Sermon</hi> at that ſeaſon, if Sickneſs, or ſome other urgent occaſion drew her not aſide, marvelouſly beloved then by thoſe <hi>Miniſters</hi> that were moſt eminent in that Place and Part of the County, willing to hear them in their Exerciſe, and then greatly to befrind them; and in the beginning or breaking forth of the Truth, when ſome <hi>Friends</hi> rode through the County, and ſounded the <hi>Trumpet</hi> of the Lord (for which they were taken and committed to the Common Goal in that County) a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me upon me to viſit <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Priſoners of the <hi>Great God,</hi> and finding them ſhut up in <hi>Doomſdale,</hi> a Dungeon in the Caſtle in <hi>Lanceſt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n,</hi> I was troubled in my Spirit, and a farther Concern came upon me to go to the <hi>Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> and viſit a Commander whom formerly I was acquainted with, and then in Authority, to ſee if poſſible I might do any Service for the Lord, and aſſiſt my then ſuffering Brethren, which in Gods Strength I did perform, and in my Journying, I was guided to the Houſe of my deceaſed Friend <hi>Loveday Hambly,</hi> where, after ſome diſcourſe with her, ſhe ſeemed to be inclinable to know the Truth, and God gave me a Teſtimony ſuitable to her preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and the Lord opened her Heart as he did the Heart of <hi>Lidia,</hi> and ſhe was melted with the Word of Life, and the Lord ſo wrought upon her, that although I parted with her in a little time, and went forward, as it was with me, to the Place appointed, yet when I returned, her Love was greatly inlarged, and ſhe conſtrained me to ſtay ſome time, and a Door of hope was op<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ned to that Family, and ſeveral of the Neighbourhood, and many were prickt at the heart, and ſeveral good Meetings I had in the Family, and great tenderneſs was amongſt them, &amp; the Fame went forth of her convince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Word of God had a place in their Affections, and many were broken into tears, and this honourable Friend did comfort them, and was a ſtrength to them, and though many ſtood a loof off, and others taunted at them, yet her Affections ſtrongly increaſed towards them, and if any thing did befall them, ſhe made it as her own Concern, for ſhe valued no Delights of this World, but her Delight was in the Lord; ſhe valued not the Glory of great Men, n<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>her did ſhe covet after great Poſſeſſions, but was contented with <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Lot in her <hi>Pilgrimage,</hi> and as one that had found a Spring in a dry Ground, ſo was ſhe in her Meditations; ſo that her Fame went far, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good Inclinations were in Peoples <hi>Minds;</hi> ſo that when I came again, as <hi>Doves</hi> to the <hi>Windows</hi> how did many flock, ſo that it was then very pleaſant to me, &amp; great Deſires after the Lord appeared, &amp; God opened a <hi>Fountain</hi> in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:32662:5"/>
the <hi>Deſert;</hi> but this made the old <hi>Serpent</hi> angry, and ſet his <hi>Miniſters</hi> in a rage, and ſome came to the Houſe like <hi>Champions,</hi> to ſee if they could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover her again, many ſtrong aſſaults were made in that day, but all in vain, ſometimes I was met with by the <hi>Miniſters</hi> on the High Way, ſometimes challenged to come to the <hi>Fair,</hi> ſome private, ſome publick Diſcourſes, but ſtill her Love was fixed to the Lord, ſo that nothing could draw back her Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, becauſe ſhe had in ſome Degree ſeen the Kindneſs of the Lord, the more they ſtrove, the cloſer ſhe ſtuck to the Truth, and the more they preſt on her, the more ſhe ſaw their Weakneſs, and when they perceived that there was no recovery like to be, the Dragon caſt a <hi>Flood</hi> out of his mouth at her, and prepared a Troop to come to her Houſe to lay hold of me, which drew many tears from her eyes, but the Lord was with us, and ſo prevailed with the then Commanders, that the <hi>Lieutenant</hi> and <hi>Coronet</hi> were convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and for ſome time ſtood in their Convincement, and the <hi>Coronet</hi> had a Meeting at his Houſe, and great Peace then was her Portion, and her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light was amongſt the People of the Lord, and which way ſhe might lay out her Endeavours for the Truth: and as Friends came to viſit the Priſoners at <hi>Lanceſton</hi> they came to viſit her, and her heart was open, and her Houſe was free, and <hi>Meetings</hi> began to be ſettled, and as a Nurſing <hi>Mother</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo was ſhe: but when <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> entred her heart, ſo that ſhe could not put into the mouths of the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Impropriators,</hi> they ſoon prepared War againſt her, and a deep Sufferer was ſhe both by <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Impropriator,</hi> and often her <hi>Cows, Horſes, Oxen, Sheep</hi> and <hi>Calves</hi> taken away, as the <hi>Records</hi> of that County can make appear; much ſpoil they made of her Eſtate, ſo that ſometimes her Cattle was ſo clean gone and carryed away by the Spoilers, as if no recovery of a Stock were like to be again, but God was a Portion to her, and whil'ſt that <hi>Propheſie</hi> of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> was fulfilling upon her Adverſaries, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 33.5. <hi>Wo unto thee that ſpoileſt, and thou waſt not ſpoiled.</hi> Her <hi>Cows</hi> did Calve, her <hi>Sheep</hi> did Yean and bring forth, and the <hi>Fleece</hi> did grow again; and Gods Indignation did fall upon the Spoylers, and the Goods did not proſper in their Hands, but a Conſumption came upon it, and it waſted and melted away, doing but little good, and in the End the Lord cut them off from the Earth, and gave them their Portion with the Spoilers: So that Scripture came to be fulfilled, the Righteous ſhall be had in ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Remembrance, but the Name of the Wicked ſhall rot. This did not altogether quiet the Adverſaries, but when they had taken her Goods, they ſought after her Body alſo, which they had at their Pleaſure ready for the Priſon, ſometimes in one Priſon, ſometimes in another, the <hi>Goalers</hi> can give a more full account of her Perſonal Suffering, for having found the <hi>Pearl of great Price,</hi> ſhe was willing to part with all for the Enjoyment of h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t Treaſure, and believing that there was a meaſure of the Sufferings of Chriſt Jeſus behind for her to fill up, ſhe conſulted not with <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> but gave
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32662:6"/>
her Body to the Priſon, and left her Goods to the Spoyler, as believing God was able to multiply her Subſtance; and truly as <hi>Truth</hi> proſpered in her heart, ſo her Subſtance was increaſed, and her Eye was to the Lord that gave it, and Gods Word was her delight, and <hi>Meetings</hi> ſtill increaſed, and her Faithfulneſs was found, and a nurſing Mother was ſhe to the <hi>Feeble</hi> and <hi>Week,</hi> for ſhe was a Woman of great Hoſpitality, and her Love extended to all; the <hi>Rich</hi> knew her heart was free, the <hi>Poor</hi> miſſed not her houſe, the <hi>Stranger</hi> lodged not in the Street, but ſhe opened her Door to the Traveller, and many times relieved ſhe her very Enemies, and to ſay the truth of her, ſhe was very bountiful, and an open handed Woman, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good to all, but more eſpecially to the <hi>Houſhold</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> ſhe was no <hi>Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer</hi> of any Perſon, nor one that would daub with untempered <hi>Mortar,</hi> but as her heart was, ſo was her Language, dealing truly with all without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Perſons, ſhe feared no man, neither could any mans frowns make her ſtart aſide, the Plain-mans Path was her delight, ſhe feared God, and took pleaſure in his People, and it was her <hi>Meat</hi> and <hi>Drink</hi> to do the Will of her Maſter <hi>Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> ſhe loved to hear of the Proſperity of Truth, and of the well-being of Friends, and when ſhe had their Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, then was her heart inlarged to the Lord: after this manner ſhe paſſed over about twenty ſix years of her Sojourning here in this World, and as all our <hi>Fathers</hi> were, ſo was ſhe ſeeking after that Country, and to find out that City whoſe Builder and Maker is the Lord. She conſtantly had <hi>Meetings</hi> at her Houſe once or twice a week, and took great pleaſure therein, and often would have a private time to her ſelf in her Cloſet, to ſpread her condition before the God of <hi>Jacob:</hi> She never turned her back upon the Truth, neither for fear of loſs of Goods, nor did the threatnings of the Priſon daunt her, but according to the meaſure of Grace that ſhe had received, her Bow did abide in its full ſtrength, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>went the ſentence of Many <hi>Fines,</hi> and greatly rejoyced when any were convinced; the Truth was ſo pleaſant to her, that ſhe would ſtill ſend to her Relations to come and hear it, and when ſhe had a Friend that ſhe was well pleaſed with, both <hi>Rich</hi> and <hi>Poor</hi> invited ſhe unto the <hi>Meeting:</hi> but now ſhe is gone from us, and we believe ſhe is taken away from the Evil that is to come, and her <hi>Good Works</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> follow her: yet time will ſpeak of the Integrity of her Heart, and of her great Love to Friends, although ſhe is removed from us; ſhe hath been preſerved af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a wonderful manner in her latter years, and often ſaw it was the Lord that raiſed her up, and would ſay, ſhe believed that the Prayers of Friends did prevail with the Lord, and that her Days were lengthened out that ſhe might be yet more ſerviceable. She lived to a great Age, which but few do come to: <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Age of Man is threeſcore Years and ten.</hi> But this Friend of ours lived fourſcore Years want but two:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32662:6"/>
and if in that day it was counted a wondrous Old Age, what may we now eſteem it? but ſhe hath finiſhed her Courſe amongſt men, and departed out out of this World the 14th. of the 10th. month, 1682. And I doubt not but is aſcended up to God, out of all the Troubles that overtake the Sons of Men.</p>
                  <p>And the Lord Raiſe up many more ſuch Mothers, for the comforting of the Diſtreſſed, ſaith my Soul, who am your Loving Brother and Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Truth of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thomas Curtis.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
