<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Whereas Redmond O Hanlon of Tonderegee, in the county of Armagh, yeoman, Laughlin Mac Redmond O Hanlon of Killeany, yeoman, Daniel Mac Murphy Mac Thorlagh Roe O Murphy of the same, yeoman, Cormuck Raver O Murphy of the same, yeoman, Hugh Turr O Murphy of the same, yeoman [and 22 others] have of late committed several burglaries, robberies, and stealths in the said several counties of Armagh, Kerry, Cork, Limerick, Mayo, Sligoe, and else-where within this kingdom, besides divers other outrages ... by the Lord Lieutenant and Council, Essex.</title>
            <author>Ireland. Lord Lieutenant (1672-1677 : Essex)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-10">2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46161</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I858</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36912</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16151891</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16151891</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104899</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A46161)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104899)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1595:40)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Whereas Redmond O Hanlon of Tonderegee, in the county of Armagh, yeoman, Laughlin Mac Redmond O Hanlon of Killeany, yeoman, Daniel Mac Murphy Mac Thorlagh Roe O Murphy of the same, yeoman, Cormuck Raver O Murphy of the same, yeoman, Hugh Turr O Murphy of the same, yeoman [and 22 others] have of late committed several burglaries, robberies, and stealths in the said several counties of Armagh, Kerry, Cork, Limerick, Mayo, Sligoe, and else-where within this kingdom, besides divers other outrages ... by the Lord Lieutenant and Council, Essex.</title>
                  <author>Ireland. Lord Lieutenant (1672-1677 : Essex)</author>
                  <author>Essex, Arthur Capel, Earl of, 1631-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2] leaves.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Benjamin Tooke ... and are to be sold by Joseph Wilde ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from text.</note>
                  <note>Statement of responsibility transposed from head of title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>"Given at the Council chamber in Dublin the 14th. of December, 1674"--leaf [2]</note>
                  <note>Broadside in [2] leaves.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Society of Antiquaries Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>O'Hanlon, Redmond O'Hanlon, --  Count, d. 1681.</term>
               <term>Brigands and robbers --  Ireland.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1649-1775.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  Politics and government --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:104899:1"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>British royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <p>DIEV ET MON DROIT</p>
               </figure>BY THE Lord Lieutenant AND COUNCIL.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>ESSEX.</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEREAS</hi> Redmond O Hanlon <hi>of</hi> Tonderegee, <hi>in the County of</hi> Armagh, <hi>Yeoman;</hi> Laughlin mac Redmond O Hanlon <hi>of</hi> Killeany, <hi>Yeoman;</hi> Daniel mac Murphy mac Thorlagh Roe O Murphy <hi>of the ſame, Yeoman;</hi> Cormuck Raver O Murphy <hi>of the ſame, Yeoman;</hi> Hugh Turr O Murphy <hi>of the ſame, Yeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> Bryan Moyle O Neale <hi>of the ſame, Yeoman;</hi> James Roe <hi>of</hi> Ballintegart <hi>in the ſaid County, Yeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> Hugh mac Shane <hi>of the ſame, Yeoman;</hi> Peter Pill <hi>of the ſame, Yeoman;</hi> James mac Nicholas O Murphy <hi>of the ſame, Yeoman;</hi> Thomas Willſon <hi>of</hi> Mullaghglaſſe <hi>of the ſaid County, Yeoman; and</hi> Thorlagh mac Patrick Goam O Hanlon <hi>of</hi> Aghynecloghmullen <hi>in the ſaid County, Yeoman; and</hi> Owen oge Carthy <hi>of the County of</hi> Kerry; Cnogher Reardane, <hi>alias</hi> Griagh <hi>of the ſaid County;</hi> John Howrane, <hi>and</hi> Hugh Noonane <hi>of the ſaid County; and</hi> Shane Kittagh O Donnel, <hi>late of</hi> Priſon <hi>in the County of</hi> Mayo, <hi>Yeoman;</hi> James Gallagher mac Edmond Dorragh <hi>late of</hi> Kilmore <hi>in the ſaid County, Yeoman;</hi> Donnogh Boy O Gallagher <hi>late of</hi> Coolkearny <hi>in the ſaid County, Yeoman;</hi> Terlagh mac Kolgeen, <hi>late of the ſame in the ſame County, Yeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> Hugh Bane mac Bre-houne <hi>late of</hi> Carra <hi>in the County of</hi> Sligoe, <hi>Yeo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man;</hi> Donnel oge O Donnel mac Donnel oge, <hi>late of</hi> Sligoe <hi>in the County</hi> of Sligoe <hi>aforeſaid, Yeoman;</hi> William O Keavin <hi>late of</hi> Ballyntrohan <hi>in the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Yeoman;</hi> Bryan mac Donnogh <hi>late of</hi> Coppany <hi>in the ſaid County, Yeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> Donnogh Fitz John O Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t <hi>late of</hi> Knockadooe <hi>in the ſaid County, Yeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> Owen O Doghertie <hi>late of</hi> Coulkearny <hi>in the County of</hi> Mayo, <hi>Yeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> Tirlagh mac Brehoune <hi>late of</hi> Carra <hi>in the County of</hi> Sligoe, <hi>Yeoman; and</hi> William Gallagher <hi>late of</hi> Court <hi>in the ſaid County, Yeoman, have of late committed ſeveral Burglaries, Robberies, and Stealths in the ſaid ſeveral Counties of</hi> Armagh, Kerry, Cork, Limerick, Mayo, Sligoe, <hi>and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where within this Kingdom, beſides divers other Outrages, to the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and annoyance of His Majeſties Loyal and good Subjects, and to the diſturbance of the peace of the Kingdom, upon which miſdemeanors and crimes being purſued by ſome of His Majeſties good Subjects, they the ſaid</hi> Redmond O Hanlon, Laughlin mac Redmond O Hanlan, Daniel mac Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy mac Tirlagh roe O Murphy, Cormuck Raver O Murphy, Hugh Tur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> O Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, Bryan Moyle O Neale, James Roe, Hugh mac Shane, Peter Pill, James mac Nicholas O Murphy, Thomas Willſon, Tirlagh mac Patrick Goam O Hanlan, Owen oge Carthy, Cnogher Reardane, <hi>alias</hi> Griagh, John Howrane, Hugh Noonane, Shane Kittagh O Donnell, James Gallagher mac Edmond Dorrogh, Don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nogh boy O Gallagher, Terlagh mac Kolgeen, Hugh Bane mac Brehoune, Donnell oge O Donnell mac Donnell oge, William O Keavine, Bryan mac Donnogh,
<pb facs="tcp:104899:2"/>
               <hi>Donnogh Fitz John O Hart, Owen O Doghertie, Terlagh mac Brehoune,</hi> and <hi>William Gallagher,</hi> are fled to the Woods and Mountains, where they ſtand upon their keeping, ſo as they are not anſwerable or ameaſnable to Law, but wilfull contemners of the ſame. And foraſmuch as the Actors of theſe diſorders and offences cannot as yet be apprehended, whereby they may be puniſhed by the ordinary courſe of Law, whence We might juſtly be moved, according to the former uſage and cuſtom in this Kingdom in caſes of like nature, to cauſe them to be forthwith proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Rebels and Traytors; yet in mercy to them, We think fit hereby to charge and command them upon their duty and allegiance to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, that they and every of them do before the Firſt day of <hi>February</hi> next, render their perſons to any of His Majeſties Iuſtices of the peace, and ſubmit themſelves to His Majeſties Iuſtice to be tryed for their offences according to the Laws of the Land, wherein if they or any of them doe fail, We do hereby publiſh and declare, that he or they ſo failing, are from and immediately after the ſaid Firſt day of <hi>February</hi> next, to be called, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted and taken for notorious Rebels and Traytors againſt His Majeſty, and accordingly to be proſecuted by all His Majeſties loving and good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in all hoſtile manner. And We declare further, that whatſoever perſon or perſons ſhall comfort, relieve or abet them, or any of them, they are and ſhall be reputed, deemed and adjudged Traytors in like degree with the forenamed Traytors and Rebels themſelves, and to be proceeded againſt according to Law. And We do in His Majeſtis Name ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charge and command all His Majeſties Loyal Subjects, upon their duty of allegiance to His Majeſty, not onely to forbear to receive or relieve the perſons aforeſaid, or any of them, but alſo to make diligent ſearch and enquiry in what place or places the ſaid perſons ſhall from time to time lurk or be relieved, and by all means poſſible to proſecute, apprehend and take the bodies of them, and them to bring or cauſe to be brought under ſafe cuſtody, unto the High Sheriffs of the reſpective Counties where any of them ſhall be apprehended, to be by ſuch Sheriffs kept in ſtrict and ſafe cuſtody, till We upon notice thereof ſhall give further direction concerning them, or reſiſting or refuſing to be taken, to kill them or any of them. And We do hereby declare, that whoſoever ſhall after the ſaid Firſt day of <hi>February</hi> next, bring unto any Sheriff the body of the ſaid <hi>Redmond O Hanlan, Laughlin mac Redmond O Hanlan, Daniel mac Murphy mac Tirlagh roe O Murphy, Cormuck Raver O Murphy, Hugh Turr O Murphy, Bryan Moyle O Neale, James Roe, Hugh mac Shane, Peter Pill, James mac Nicholas O Murphy, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Wilſon, Tirlagh mac Patrick Goam O Hanlan, Owen oge Carthy, Cnogher Rear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dane</hi> alias <hi>Griagh, John Howrane, Hugh Noonane, Shane Kittagh O Donnell, James Gallagher mac Edmond Dorrogh, Donnogh Boy O Gallagher, Tirlagh mac Kolgen, Hugh Bane mac Brehoune, Donnell oge O Donnell mac Donnell oge, William O Keavine, Bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an mac Donnogh, Donnogh Fitz John O Hart, Owen O Doghertie, Tirlagh mac Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houne,</hi> and <hi>William Gallagher,</hi> or any of them alive, or kill any of them, and bring his Head to the Sheriff of the County where he ſhall be killed, to be by ſuch Sheriff ſet up in ſome publick place in that County, ſhall have for his reward for each perſon ſo brought in, or his Head, Ten pounds, for payment whereof We will give warrant as occaſion ſhall require; and whoſoever of the ſaid proclaimed perſons, or any other, ſhall after the ſaid firſt day of <hi>February</hi> next, apprehend &amp; bring unto the High Sheriff of the County where ſuch perſon ſhall be apprehended, or reſiſting, ſhall kill any of the ſaid Rebels and Traytors particularly named as aforeſaid, he ſhall, together with his ſaid reward, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his pardon. And towards the ſpeedy effecting of this Service, all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of Horſe and Foot, and all other His Majeſties Officers and loving Subjects are to be aiding and aſſiſting, as they and every of them will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the contrary at their perils.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at the <hi>Council Chamber</hi> in <hi>Dublin</hi> 
                  <date>the <hi>14th.</hi> of <hi>December,</hi> 1674.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed> 
                  <list>
                     <item>Ja: Armachanus.</item>
                     <item>Mich: Dublin. Canc. Clanbraſill Conway and Kilulta.</item>
                     <item>Maſſereene.</item>
                     <item>Kingſton.</item>
                     <item>Ca: Dillon.</item>
                     <item>J: Povey.</item>
                     <item>Will: Stewart.</item>
                     <item>Theo: Jones.</item>
                     <item>Char: Meredith.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <closer>God ſave the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN,</hi> Printed by <hi>Benjamin Tooke,</hi> Printer to the KING's moſt Excellent Majeſty; and are to be ſold by <hi>Joſeph Wilde,</hi> Book-ſelelr in <hi>Caſtle-ſtreet.</hi> 1674.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
