<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A further discovery of the spirit of falshood &amp; persecution in Sam. Jennings, and his party that joyned with him in Pensilvania, and some abettors that cloak and defend him here in England in answer to his scandalous book, called, The state of the case.</title>
            <author>Keith, George, 1639?-1716.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 188 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-12">2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47147</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K170</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R784</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12305331</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12305331</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59231</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A47147)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59231)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 637:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A further discovery of the spirit of falshood &amp; persecution in Sam. Jennings, and his party that joyned with him in Pensilvania, and some abettors that cloak and defend him here in England in answer to his scandalous book, called, The state of the case.</title>
                  <author>Keith, George, 1639?-1716.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Levis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title; imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signed: George Keith.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jennings, Samuel, d. 1708. --  State of the case.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Pennsylvania.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-06</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:59231:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59231:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A FURTHER
DISCOVERY
Of the SPIRIT of
Falſhood &amp; Perſecution
IN
Sam. Jennings,
And his Party that joyned with him in Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilvania;
and ſome Abettors that cloak and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
him here in England: In Anſwer to his
ſcandalous Book, called, The State of the Caſe.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>IN Order to this further Diſcovery, I think fit to follow this Method;
<hi>Firſt,</hi> to ſet down in order, the groſſeſt Falſhoods and Untruths I find
in his Book; and for which he giveth no other Proof, but his and
their bare Affirmation who are his Confederates, which ought to be
of no Authority, or Credit with them, who know him and them to be our
prejudiced Adverſaries in the Caſe, and whom I can, and doubt not to prove
both him and them guilty of affirming diverſe groſs falſhoods in this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Treatiſe; and for brevity ſake, to give little other Anſwer to many of
the whole Summ, Number, or Tale of them, but this, That they are
groſs downright Falſhoods, Fictions, and Forgeries of his and their devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59231:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
hatch'd and invented by him and them, whereby, as with ſo many
Fig-leaves, to cover his and their Nakedneſs: And, as I go along, to anſwer
particularly, to his ſeeming Reaſons, ſo far as they may ſeem to weak and
unwary Readers, to be ſome ſort of covering to him, and his Party; and
his particular Charges againſt me, ſo far as they ſeem to contain any thing of
Truth in them in matter of Fact, briefly to reply unto.</p>
               <p>For the firſt, ſome of the groſſeſt downright Falſhoods and Untruths,
Fictions and Forgeries aſſerted by him, are theſe in order following.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <p>I. That he ſaith in his Title page, <hi>The ſtate of the Caſe impartially gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi>
&amp;c. [he had ſaid more truly, <hi>The ſtate of the Caſe partially, falſly and
perverſly given,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <p>II. <hi>That ſome few have been ſeduced by me, into a ſeparation,</hi> &amp;c. [but on
the contrary, I have not ſeduced any, but have been made an Inſtrument of
God, (for which I deſire to praiſe him) to preſerve many, and to recover
ſome from being deceived.]</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <p>III. <hi>That we are backsliders, and have reproached, and abuſed him.</hi> [This
is his own Character, and not ours.]</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <p>IV. <hi>That he might have made his Innocency his Sanctuary.</hi> [But inſtead of
that, he maketh Falſhoods and Fictions his Sanctuary.]</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <p>V. That I ſaid to him, <hi>That it was not for any love I had to him, that I had
ſought his Friendſhip,</hi> &amp;c. [This I ſolemnly declare is utterly falſe; and I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge,
I did love him, and ſtill love him, as I ought to love my Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
but the bond of brotherly love he himſelf broke it, and not I.]</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> That I flatter to gain him to my Party. <hi>This is falſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <p>VII. That I conſult the old Proverb, <hi>Throw Dirt enough, and ſome will
ſtick.</hi> [This moſt truly belongs to himſelf.]</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <p>VIII. <hi>That it's matter of Malice, and not Conſcience, that hath occaſioned
me to appear againſt him.</hi> [But my appearing againſt him, was only in my
juſt defence; and what I have ſaid or Printed againſt him, reſpecting ſome
former Paſſages of his Life, before he appeared an unjuſt Adverſary againſt
me, were ſuch as I had not the full knowledge, and certainty of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore;
and beſide, they were of that nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e or quality, that had it not been
for his intolerable Pride, and Arrogancy, as well as Injuſtice, in charging
me, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen Innocent, of what he was moſt guilty himſelf, they might have
been buried, even with them that knew him to be guilty, more than I did;
and it might have been hoped, that he had repented of ſuch things; but he
proceeding to ſhew himſelf worſe then formerly, not amending, but more
degenerating, might give juſt occaſion, in our juſt defence, to let him know
what ſort of Captain theſe twenty ſeven falſe Judges had choſen to follow,
in that unjuſt War they had undertaken. His <hi>Argumentum ad hominem,</hi>
ſheweth him as ignorant in fair Reaſoning, as he knoweth himſelf to be in
the Latin Tongue, which yet he would make ſome ſhew of, as if he skilled
it; for his transferring my Complaint againſt <hi>Arthur Cook,</hi> (citing Reaſons
and Cauſes of the Separation, <hi>page</hi> 18.) to his Complaint againſt me, is not
para<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lel, nor equal. But ſo heedleſs he is, in what he writes, (as in what
he ſaith) that he miſcites the Book; for that Complaint of mine againſt <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59231:2"/>
Cook,</hi> is not in Reaſons and Cauſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but in the Plea of the Innocent,
that was in Anſwer to his, and his Brethrens Paper of falſe Judgment againſt
me; for my Complaint againſt <hi>A. C.</hi> was, <hi>That he tranſgreſt Goſpel Order in
concealing a matter ſo many years, and then bringing it forth againſt me, while
I was in the ſame Profeſſion of Church Memberſhip with them, when he ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed
me; and the matter it ſelf was alſo falſe.</hi> But what I blamed <hi>Sam.
Jennings</hi> for, with reſpect to ſome years paſt, was only in way of my juſt
defence, and was moſt properly, <hi>Argumentum ad hominem,</hi> it being moſt
unreaſonable in him, to require an abſolute Submiſſion from me, in the
greateſt matters of Faith and Conſcience, when he refuſed to ſubmit in ſome
worldly matters; and I made not this Complaint againſt him, in my juſt
defence, until by his, and his Parties falſe Judgment given out againſt me,
<hi>We were no more of one Society;</hi> and it ſtands well conſiſtent with Scripture,
<hi>That if a Man depart from his Righteouſneſs, not only his former Righteouſneſs
is to be forgotten, but his former Vnrighteouſneſs may be juſtly remembred
againſt him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <p>IX. <hi>That the noiſe we make of Perſecution, he doubts not but the Reader will
find, by what follows, is a ſham, and abuſe put upon the World.</hi> [And I refer
it to the Impartial Reader, whether this, his Book, be not a ſham put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the World? and whether, the Sufferings, we did undergo, for matters
purely of Conſcience, were not really Perſecution, as much as what many
Friends have ſuffered here in <hi>England,</hi> in former times. That he ſaith,
<hi>page</hi> 3. of his Preface, <hi>How can any thing deſerve to be called a Suffering or
Perſecution, that is ſo much deſired and ſought for,</hi> ſheweth him extreamly
ignorant, what true Suffering is; and that he is better acquainted with the
Spirit of Perſecution, than with the Spirit of Suffering; and alſo, that he
is little converſant, either in Scripture or Church Hiſtory; for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the
<hi>Prophets, Apoſtles,</hi> and <hi>Martyrs,</hi> not only deſired to ſuffer for <hi>Righteouſneſs
ſake,</hi> (knowing the Bleſſedneſs that belonged to that State) but rejoyced at
their Suffering, not ſimply for the Suffering, but that God might be honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
and the Truth advanced; nor did they deſire Suffering in any evil
will towards Perſecutors, but prayed for them; as ſo I have done, and
have them for my <hi>Example.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <p>X. That my, and our greateſt Suffering from the Government, was, <hi>That
we could not provoke them to do more againſt us.</hi> [This is utterly falſe; we
neither gave them juſt Provocation, nor deſired to provoke them.]</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <p>XI. <hi>That our Crimes were ſo groſs and enormous, as no other Government
would have been guilty of ſuch Impunity,</hi> (I ſuppoſe he means Iniquity)
<hi>to ſuffer to paſs with ſo ſlight a Correction.</hi> [This Aſſertion is ſo extravagant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
falſe, that it may be juſtly queſtioned, whether ever any Government in
the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Dominions, was ſo extreamly ſevere, ridgid, and cruel, to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
Men for aſſerting the ſame Principles, in common profeſſed, both by
the Puniſhers, and puniſhed, as was our Caſe. For it is well known, it is
a profeſt Principle among the People called <hi>Quakers, That it is lawful to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove
Pride, or any other Sin, in a Magiſtrate, as Injuſtice, arbitrary and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful
Proceedings of Magiſtrates;</hi> alſo, it is their known Principle, <hi>neither
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59231:3"/>
to fight, nor to hire Men to fight;</hi> and yet for our practiſing the former, <hi>viz,
Reproving Pride in</hi> Sam. Jennings, and aſſerting the latter, as the <hi>Quakers</hi>
Principle, we were perſecuted by him, and his Party. And I know not, if
many Inſtances or Examples can be found in <hi>England,</hi> or in the Kings Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions
in <hi>America,</hi> that they did puniſh any called a <hi>Quaker,</hi> for his ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
reproving Pride, or other the like Sins in Magiſtrates. But there is not
wanting plenty of Examples out of the Printed Books of the People called
<hi>Quakers,</hi> that they have largely and much more aggravatingly reproved
Pride, Oppreſſion, Injuſtice, and arbitrary Proceedings in Magiſtrates, than
what we have done in <hi>Penſilvania.</hi>] See for proof, <hi>G. F.</hi> his Letter to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
<hi>Savrey,</hi> in his Journal, <hi>page 94. Will. Pen,</hi> and <hi>Will. Meeds</hi> Tryal, and
<hi>G. W.</hi> his Tryal at <hi>Norwich.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <p>XII. <hi>He chargeth it to be Deceit, in the Pen-man of the Book of the Tryal;</hi> to
aſſert it, that <hi>Will. Bradford,</hi> and <hi>John Micomb,</hi> were under any hard uſage,
or cloſe confinement, after they were put in Priſon; and for this he bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
only the Credit of <hi>John White,</hi> then Sheriff and Jailor both, as well as
a prejudiced Adverſary; and who had appeared Attorney againſt us, a Man
of as bad Credit as <hi>Sam. Jennings</hi> himſelf. [But it is well known to many in
<hi>Philadelphia,</hi> who came to ſee them in Priſon, <hi>That they were kept for ſome
time ſo cloſe in Priſon, that by no Entreaty, they could have their Freedom, to
go home to viſit their Families, though</hi> John Micembs <hi>Family greatly needed
him, his Wife being newly brought to Bed, and dangerouſly ill.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <p>XIII. <hi>That</hi> John White <hi>offered them, upon their firſt coming in, if they would
promiſe to come to him, upon notice given them, they might go about their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
till then.</hi> [This is notoriouſly falſe, and is eaſily proved to be ſo by the
expreſs words of the <hi>Mittimus</hi> ſigned by <hi>Sam. Jennings,</hi> and <hi>Robert Ewer,</hi>
both Preachers, that ſaith, the ſaid Perſons being required to give ſecurity
to anſwer it at the next Court, but they refuſing ſo to do, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now can it
be ſuppoſed, that the Juſtices refuſing them liberty to go home without gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
Security, that the Jailor would dare to contradict their ſtrict Order, the
very firſt Night they were committed to Priſon. But that they refuſed to
give Security, by entring into Bonds for their Appearance, is that which
Friends generally have refuſed to do, when they have been committed to
Priſon, both here in <hi>England,</hi> and elſewhere; and as theſe two honeſt Men,
<hi>viz. Will. Bradford,</hi> and <hi>John Micomb,</hi> acted like faithful Friends, in refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
to enter into Bonds, having done nothing worthy of Impriſonment;
So their Perſecutors, whereof <hi>Sam. Jennings</hi> was the chief, acted like the
worſt of our Perſecutors here in <hi>England,</hi> formerly in requiring ſuch Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
of them. But it ſeems after ſome time their proud Hearts fell, and
without requiring any Bonds of them, they had more liberty allowed them
afterwards, more regarding the cry of the generality of the People, both in
Town and Country, againſt ſuch notorious Injuſtice and Oppreſſion, than
any real Mercy and Compaſſion towards the Priſoners they had in Cuſtody.
But what cloak hath he, to cover the other parts of their Cruelty acted on
theſe two honeſt Perſons, having from the one, <hi>viz. John Micomb,</hi> taken
his Licenſe, which he paid dear for, before the time was expired for which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59231:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
he paid; the ſaid Licenſe being to keep an Ordinary, the outward means of
his Livelyhood; and having taken from the other, <hi>viz. Will. Bradford,</hi> ſo
much of his Printing Letter as was in value worth about Ten Pounds, to
his great detriment; and was not reſtored to him, ſo long as theſe unjuſt
and violent Men poſſeſſed the Government. But after they went out, by
Order of the new Governor, his Printing Letter was reſtored to him, to
their great ſhame that had ſo long unjuſtly and cruelly detained it. And
alſo, by another Order of the ſaid New Governor, <hi>Peter Boſſe,</hi> after a
Months unjuſt and undue Impriſonment, upon the change of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
was ſet at Liberty; and divers other abuſes were then rectified. And
what ſaith he to that act of both Injuſtice and Cruelty, that he, <hi>viz. Sam.
Jennings,</hi> and his Party, did take away from <hi>Will. Bradford,</hi> the Printer,
his yearly Salary of Forty Pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> they had bound themſelves
by Indenture to pay him, for ſome years to come, without the leaſt juſt
occaſion given them; or the laſt breach of the Indenture on his part, the
only pretence they made, being his Printing the Sheet, called, <hi>The Chriſtian
Faith of the People of God called in ſcorn, Quakers in</hi> Rhode Iſland, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
which hath been well received by many Friends here in <hi>England,</hi> and
elſewhere: And his Printing it without their Licenſe or Knowledge, they
made ſo highly criminal in him, as to take from him Forty Pounds <hi>per An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi>
for ſome years to come, being ſuch an unparallel'd Inſtance of Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion,
that I think few parts in <hi>Europe,</hi> in a thing of that Nature, can
produce the like, he being left at liberty by the expreſs Terms of the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
Indenture betwixt him and them, to Print what he pleaſed, or might
be for his Profit, that was not againſt the Government, as nothing of this
could, or was pretended to be, (nor indeed was ever any thing that he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards
Printed, in the leaſt againſt it) he never refuſing to print for
them, whatever they required, which none of them can ſay he did; but
ſhewed himſelf always moſt willing to ſerve them, in his Art of Printing.
And it is but Deceit in <hi>Sam. Jennings,</hi> to charge theſe two honeſt Friends
with Deceit, for their Signing a Paper from the Priſon, when they ſigned it
in the Entry, common to the Priſon, and the next Houſe; for the Entry
belonging to the Priſon, it was no Deceit nor Lye, to ſign it from the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
it happening at that time, they had a little Liberty to go home, and
they being Priſoners ſtill by order of the Juſtices, it was moſt proper for
them to ſign their Paper from the Priſon, being, if I well remember, a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
to the Juſtices, requeſting farther Liberty; and the Priſon-houſe Room
hapning to be ſhut at that time, who can blame them with Deceit, for
ſigning it in any place or part belonging to the Priſon, except ſuch as <hi>Sam.
Jennings;</hi> who, to hide his own Deceit, laboureth to repreſent an innocent
Act, as if it were deceit. And ſo much in anſwer to his Falſhoods and Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſentations
contained in his Preface.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <p>XIV. <hi>page</hi> 1. In the beginning of his Book, he telleth a great Falſhood,
<hi>viz. That the publiſhing the Breach made in</hi> Penſilvania, <hi>ſeems deſigned to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie
the Adverſaries of Truth.</hi> [For the deſign of its publiſhing was only
to bear our faithful Teſtimony againſt the vile Anti-chriſtian Errors boldly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59231:4"/>
maintained by ſome there, and cloaked by others; and in Vindication of
our Innocency, which they of the other ſide had laboured to defame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <p>XV. <hi>page</hi> 2. He moſt falſly and injuriouſly chargeth me <hi>with a ſlight of the
Spirits Teachings.</hi> [For I greatly honour and value the <hi>Spirits Teachings;</hi> but
the falſe and vain Pretenſions of ignorant Perſons, to the <hi>Spirits Teachings,</hi>
I diſown and witneſs againſt, as the true Prophets did witneſs againſt the
falſe Pretences of the falſe Prophets, who ſaid, <hi>thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> when the
Lord had not ſpoke unto them.]</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <p>XVI. <hi>page</hi> 2. He falſly chargeth me, <hi>That my charge againſt ſome Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
in</hi> Penſilvania, <hi>is couched in bare generals.</hi> [But in Contradiction to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
within a few Lines, he acknowledgeth the Particulars, wherewith I
did charge them, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>T. Fitſwater</hi> had accuſed me, <hi>For denying the
Sufficiency of the Light,</hi> becauſe I ſaid, as was alledged by the four Eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<hi>That the Light within was not ſufficient without ſomething elſe.</hi> Now if
this be matter of juſt Accuſation againſt me, it muſt to them be a falſe Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion;
and the contradictory Aſſertion muſt be true, <hi>viz. That the Light
within is ſufficient to Salvation, without any thing elſe;</hi> which moſt evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
excludes the Perſon of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> viz. <hi>His Manhood, Death,</hi> and <hi>Sufferings,</hi>
and <hi>ſhedding of his precious Blood,</hi> and <hi>Interceſſion for us in Heaven,</hi> all which
are ſomething elſe than the <hi>Light within.</hi> But whereas he ſaith, may it not
ſeem ſtrange, that I who had been among them Twenty Eight Years, and
moſt of the Time a Preacher, and a Vindicator of them, ſhould not diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
this, (viz. <hi>That ſome among them were guilty of vile Errors.</hi>) But to this
it is eaſily anſwered, I had but a very few Years, or rather Months been
among them in <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> when I had diſcovered ſome among them guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of <hi>vile Errors;</hi> and laboured much among them in love to recover them,
which was not without Succeſs to ſome, though others were hardened.
And for the Time I was among the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> before I came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<hi>America,</hi> moſtly in <hi>Scotland,</hi> my Native Country, and ſometimes in
<hi>England,</hi> and elſewhere, it is well known to ſome now alive in this City,
that many years ago, I had diſcovered ſome here in <hi>England,</hi> guilty of
ſome groſs Errors, ſuch as of late I had diſcovered in <hi>Penſilvania</hi>) and had
alſo complained of them; and diverſe Meetings were had, where my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint
was heard, and theſe Meetings giving due and impartial Judgment in
the Caſe, and ſtanding up for the Truth, and putting to ſilence theſe Men
for that time, this made things quiet, and prevented a breach; and had
theſe to whom I complained in <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> done the like Juſtice there,
they might have prevented the breach that happened, therefore the guilt of
it lyeth at their door; and eſpecially upon <hi>S. J.</hi> who has been a principal
Defender and Upholder of the Perſons guilty of thoſe vile Errors. But what
if I did not diſcover the Error<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that I find too many guilty of now, both in
<hi>America,</hi> and here alſo in <hi>Europe,</hi> not having had the opportunity of inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate
Communication with them, by verbal Conference, perhaps not one
of a hundred; nor having read very many of Friends Books in thoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
days. But ſince our Differences began in <hi>America,</hi> this hath given me
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> occaſion, both of verbal Conference with many, and alſo of more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59231:4"/>
reading in Friends Books than formerly, and upon the whole I can
ſay, I find the whole Doctrine aſſerted by me, in all particulars, well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
out of Friends Books, even in thoſe things, wherein I have been
contradicted by ſome, both in <hi>America,</hi> and here in <hi>England;</hi> and am able
to prove all the parts of Doctrine aſſerted by me, out of the <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi>
and Friends Books; though I muſt needs alſo acknowledge, that by ſome
others it is contradicted in ſome other Books, for which cauſe I did judge,
and I ſtill ſo do, that diverſe Books among us need Correction in diverſe
Places, becauſe they both contradict the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> in ſome Places, and
alſo they contradict the Books and printed Teſtimonies of other Friends; and
theſe palpable Contradictions have done, and will do great hurt, (until cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected)
both to weak Friends, and other friendly People, tending to dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
ſome, and ſtumble others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <p>XVII. <hi>page</hi> 2. His falſe Propheſie or Preſumption concerning me, which
he ſaith, he believes a very little time will try or diſcover; as alſo his falſe
Inſinuation againſt me, <hi>That I am not real in my profeſſing, my being in dear
Vnity with all faithful Friends;</hi> or that any thing of my Deportment hath
diſcovered the contrary. [For I have differed with none here, or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where,
but ſo far as they have differed from Truth; and if I remain in
Unity with the Truth, (as I do, and he, nor any elſe cannot prove the
contrary) I remain in Unity with all the faithful Friends of it. Nor do I
judge that every ſmall difference in Judgment doth break the Unity of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
Friends, when Sincerity, and the Love of the Truth is kept to in the
main.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="part">
               <p>XVIII. <hi>page</hi> 3. His falſely aſſerting the ſufficiency of <hi>W. Stockdales</hi> Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
againſt me, who was notoriouſly known to be a prejudiced Perſon,
by his falſly accuſing me, <hi>Of being guilty of Preaching two Chriſts,</hi> which
<hi>Sam. Jennings</hi> hath been forced to confeſs was proved againſt him, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly
gave at laſt a Judgment againſt him, though it was as an Abortive
out of due Seaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="part">
               <p>XIX. His perverting my words, ſaying, <hi>Divers preſent cleared him,</hi> viz.
<hi>G. K. that they heard him, both then, and at all occaſions that he delivered his
Mind on that Subject, always bear his Teſtimony to the ſufficiency of the Light
to Salvation.</hi> [But this he makes ſo great a difficulty or impoſſibility, <hi>viz.</hi>
to prove a Negative; moſt perverſely arguing, or rather, qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ling, <hi>How
could they hear him at all times, when he delivered his Mind on that Subject.</hi>
[But my words do plainly enough bare this ſenſe, <hi>That they heard me at all
ſuch times, when</hi> W. Stockdale <hi>heard me; to wit, either in publick Meetings,
where ſome of them were always preſent at</hi> Philadelphia; <hi>or at that Meeting
at the Houſe of</hi> S. Carp. <hi>where and when he did falſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly ſo accuſe me.</hi> And
if a Negative Evidence be to <hi>S. J.</hi> ſuch a difficulty or impoſſibility, How
is it, that he is put to bring a negative Evidence to prove he was not drunk
in Eaſt <hi>Jerſey;</hi> See <hi>page</hi> 69. May it not be replyed to him, Was that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
always with him? and had ſuch a perfect knowledge of him, that he
was not drunk, or at leaſt elevated with Drink, ſeeing ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me have aſſerted
that he was; and one, being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uled by Affection, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay judge a Man not to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59231:5"/>
be drunk, when another Man may judge, and perhaps more duely, that he
is. But whether he was, or was not drunk, as I did not accuſe him, ſo it
is not my preſent buſineſs, to prove or diſprove it, only I thought fit to
take notice how partial <hi>S. J.</hi> is, to reject theſe divers Evidences on my ſide,
that proved a Negative, and yet defend himſelf, by one Perſon that proved
a Negative on his ſide.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="part">
               <p>XX. <hi>page.</hi> 3. His Perverſion, and perverſly quibling againſt the Monthly
Meeting that gave Judgment againſt <hi>T. Fiſh;</hi> As, firſt, <hi>That ſome had been
there, that were not in the Profeſſion of Truth,</hi> a thing he ſaith, not uſual in
ſolemn Monthly Meetings. [But this quibble is eaſily anſwered, The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
ſpread abroad concerning our Differences, occaſioned divers to come,
even to other Monthly Meetings as well as that; yea, and to their Yearly
Meeting too, that were not in the Profeſſion of Truth: And it can be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
that ſome have ſigned to ſome falſe Judgments given out againſt me,
that were not in the Profeſſion of Truth. But however <hi>S. J.</hi> doth take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice,
that theſe that were not in the Profeſſion of Truth, were ſaid to have
gone away, before any Judgment was given. Another ſilly quibble of his
is, <hi>That moſt of them that gave that Judgment at the adjourned Monthly Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
were ſuch as afterwards went into the Separation with</hi> G. K. <hi>page</hi> 4. But
here he only begs the queſtion, without all ſhadow of Proof, that they or
I either, went into the Separation; for on the contrary I have ſufficiently
proved it, both in my former Books, and alſo in my laſt Book in Anſwer
to <hi>T. E.</hi> his ſcandalous Defamation, <hi>That they of the other ſide began the Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
and are guilty of continuing it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="part">
               <p>XXI. <hi>page</hi> 4. He moſt palpably perverteth the matter, when he ſaith, <hi>I
make a miſchievous uſe of the Evidence given by them called the four credible
Witneſſes, and ſtrain conſequences from it;</hi> he alledging, <hi>It was not the thing
in queſtion, Whether the Light was ſufficient, without ſomething elſe; but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
G. K. <hi>had ſaid ſo or not, which was proved he had.</hi> [But take notice
Reader, of this Mans groſs Forgery and Prevarication, (enough to diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit
his whole Book, and all his other audacious falſe Affirmations) the thing
in queſtion was, Whether <hi>G. K.</hi> was guilty of denying the <hi>Sufficiency of the
Light within to Salvation, Th. Fiſhwater</hi> having accuſed him, of ſuch a
Crime or Error, as is confeſſed by the Judgment of that Monthly Meeting,
that took the Evidences of that four Perſons (which they took moſt diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly,
<hi>G. K.</hi> being abſent, and having no call nor notice given him to be
preſent;) and to prove his charge againſt <hi>G. K.</hi> he brings four Witneſſes to
prove that they heard me ſay, <hi>The Light was not ſufficient to Salvation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
ſomething elſe;</hi> this the ſaid Meeting takes for a ſufficient Evidence to
clear <hi>T. F.</hi> and therefore without the leaſt ſtrain, according to them, <hi>G. K.</hi>
is guilty of a great Error, for ſaving, <hi>The Light [within] is not ſufficient
to Salvation, without ſomething elſe.</hi> But ſeeing by their Judgment this is
an Error, the contradictory Aſſertion to it muſt need<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be true, <hi>viz. That
the Light within is ſufficient to Salvation, without any thing elſe;</hi> which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes
the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſt, his Death and Sufferings, Blood and Interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
for as in Heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> all which are ſomething elſe than the <hi>Light within,</hi> as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59231:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
all Men of common ſenſe muſt needs confeſs, <hi>That the outward Body or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
of the Man Chriſt, and his Death, Blood, and Interceſſion without us, are
not the Light in us;</hi> and therefore ſomething elſe, though Chriſt is but one,
<hi>both without us and within us,</hi> even as the <hi>Godhead</hi> and <hi>Manhood</hi> of <hi>Chriſt is
but one Chriſt,</hi> and yet his <hi>Manhood</hi> is not his <hi>Godhead,</hi> but ſomething elſe;
for his <hi>Godhead</hi> did not ſuffer Death, but his <hi>Manhood.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="part">
               <p>XXII. <hi>page</hi> 4, 5. His palpable Perverſion, and bewraying his groſs Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance,
or Deceit, in charging me with Inconſiſtency, for ſaying, <hi>The
Light is ſufficient to Salvation,</hi> and yet to affirm it is not ſufficient without
ſomething elſe; as if theſe two Aſſertions were inconſiſtent, or contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.
Whereas the leaſt ordinary Chriſtian, of the ſmalleſt Capacity, cannot
but ſee, both the Conſiſtency and Truth of theſe two ſound Aſſertions, as
much as when I ſay, my Hand is ſufficient to write, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>old a Book, but
not without my Body, which is ſomething elſe; and my Eye is ſufficient
to ſee, but not without my Head; and a thouſand ſuch Examples may be
given. And the Grace of Chriſt is ſufficient to ſave me, but not without
the Man Chriſt; nor is Chriſt ſufficient, without the Father, for he ſaid
himſelf, <hi>I can do nothing of my ſelf;</hi> but together with the Father, he is our
All-ſufficient Saviour. And who will dare to ſay, but the Man <hi>Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
us,</hi> that was born of the Virgin, is ſufficient to ſave us, yet not without
his <hi>inward appearance in our Hearts;</hi> it pitties me to deal with ſuch an ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant
Adverſary. Oh! for ſhame, that ever ſuch an ignorant Perſon ſhould
paſs with any, for a Miniſter of Chriſt, that ſeeth not, or is ſo deceitful,
that he will not acknowledge, that he ſeeth ſuch a thing, as the good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtency
betwixt theſe two Aſſertions aforeſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="part">
               <p>XXIII. His groſs Perverſion, in charging my Words, I ſpoke at the
Yearly Meeting, and which were too mincingly, and unduly repeated in
that Paper, called, <hi>A true Account of the Proceedings of the Yearly Meeting
at</hi> London, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As if they did infer the ſame Conſequence againſt my ſelf,
the ſubſtance of my words being, <hi>viz. That the Light within, being God,
the Word, the Spirit, in every Man, is ſufficient to reveal to every Man, all
that is needful to his</hi> Eternal Salvation. [But let the Reader of the leaſt
true Capacity, judge whether theſe words can admit of any ſuch Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,
<hi>That the Light within us is ſufficient to Salvation without any thing
elſe,</hi> ſeeing as is above ſhewed, theſe two Aſſertions are well conſiſting;
and <hi>Sam. Jennings</hi> knoweth in his Conſcience, that I ſpoke the words more
fully, than he hath related them, <hi>viz.</hi> by adding, yet not excluding the
<hi>Man Chriſt Jeſus, his Death, Sufferings,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and Interceſſion,</hi> &amp;c. from
being joyntly concern'd in our Salvation; as alſo my ſaying, <hi>That the Faith
of Chriſt, as he died for us,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>is neceſſary to our Chriſtianity and Salvation.</hi>
But further, to manifeſt the great Ignorance, or rather Deceit of <hi>S. J.</hi> in
this particular, he intimating it was not the thing in queſtion, <hi>Whether the
Light is not ſufficient to Salvation,</hi> without ſomething elſe; <hi>G. K.</hi> meaning
by that ſomething elſe, <hi>The Manhood of Chriſt, his Death and Sufferings,
and Interceſſion.</hi> He knoweth in his Conſcience, that ſome time after <hi>John
Delawal</hi> accuſed me in a publick Meeting, of being guilty of Hereſie,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59231:6"/>
for ſaying, <hi>The Light within was not ſufficient to Salvation, without ſomething
elſe;</hi> at which time <hi>S. Jennings</hi> moſt ſhamefully, as is known to many, ſet
the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and the <hi>Quaker</hi> at odds in the publick Meeting, ſaying, the
queſtion betwixt us and <hi>G. K.</hi> is not, <hi>Who is the beſt Chriſtian, but who is
the beſt Quaker?</hi> And alſo <hi>S. J.</hi> knoweth in his Conſcience, that I produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
two Manuſcripts of <hi>John Delawal,</hi> that was read in the yearly Meeting
at <hi>London,</hi> wherein he accuſeth me of Hereſie, and of denying the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental
Principle of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> for ſaying, <hi>The Light within is not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
Salvation, without ſomething elſe;</hi> and concerning the Debate betwixt
<hi>John Delawal</hi> and me, upon that head, I refer to the Printed Treatiſe, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<hi>Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Hatred, &amp;c.</hi> the which if any have a mind to ſee, or buy,
let them come to me, and I ſhall acquaint them where they may have
them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="part">
               <p>XXIV. <hi>page</hi> 6. His groſs Perverſion and Inſinuation againſt me, ſaying, <hi>It's
well if he have not ſinned againſt Knowledge in this matter, they of the other
ſide having ſo often and ſolemnly told me, that they did believe all that's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded
is Sacred Writ, concerning our Bleſſed Saviour, &amp;c.</hi> [But how could
I believe them to be ſincere in their Affirmation, any more than I can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
a Papiſt or Mugletonian; who will ſay the ſame in general, <hi>That they
believe all that's Recorded in Sacred Writ concerning our Bleſſed Saviour,</hi> and
yet many of their Doctrines contradict <hi>Sacred Writ.</hi> For to be ſure, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts
<hi>Sacred Writ,</hi> to ſay, it is a fundamental Error and Hereſie, <hi>That the
Light within is not ſufficient to Salvation, without ſomething elſe;</hi> which was
publickly aſſerted by one of their chief Preachers, and Rulers of their ſide,
viz. <hi>ſend Delawall,</hi> and which his Manuſcripts under his own Hand, read
at the yearly Meeting, fully prove; and for which they did never paſs any
due cenſure againſt him, nor againſt <hi>John Humphreys,</hi> for ſaying in his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
read at the yearly Meeting at <hi>London, He was grieved to hear ſome ſay,
they expect to be juſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by that Blood that was ſhed at</hi> Jeruſalem. And though
<hi>Sam. Jenings</hi> mention th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the precious Blood of Chriſt, with which Chriſt
hath purchaſed that Inheritance for us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet he doth not tell what that
Precious Blood is, or what he means by it, ſeeing not only <hi>John Humphrey</hi>
in <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> but ſome here in <hi>England,</hi> by the Blood which with God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piates
for Sin, and cleanſeth from Sin, do not mean the Blood of Chriſt's
Manhood, or Humanity, but the Life, which is the Light, as one <hi>Frances
Ftheridge,</hi> a bold ignorant Soul, lately, in my hearing, and in the hearing
of many, at a publick Meeting, on a <hi>Firſt day,</hi> at <hi>Dev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſhire,</hi> in the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon,
affirmed, <hi>That the Blood</hi> (John 1. 1. 7.) <hi>that cleanſeth from all Sin,
was the Life, and the Life is the Light;</hi> and this perverſe Expoſition goeth
currant among too many here in <hi>England,</hi> as well as in <hi>America.</hi> But in
Oppoſition to his unchriſtian and uncharitable Inſinuation, I ſay, I have
charged them with nothing againſt my Knowledge, but what is moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly
conſiſtent with my Knowledge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="part">
               <p>XXV. <hi>page</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. His groſs Perverſion, in labouring to make void the Credit
of the two Perſons, viz. <hi>W. Bradford,</hi> and <hi>John Macomb,</hi> in giving Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
againſt <hi>W. St.</hi> that he accuſed me of being guilty of <hi>Preaching two
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59231:6"/>
Chriſts,</hi> alledging they were much at my Devotion, and my Creatures, to
uſe them as I pleaſed; which is a falſe and baſe Inſinuation. But if their
Evidence is not to be credited, becauſe they did afterwards joyn with me in
their Chriſtian Teſtimony, to oppoſe the vile Errors held by ſome of their
ſide, by the ſame Reaſon, theſe he calleth the four credible Witneſſes of
their ſide, ought to be rejected; and with as much colour of Reaſon, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
much more, they might be ſaid to be at the Devotion of <hi>Sam. Jennings,</hi>
and <hi>Th. Lloyd,</hi> and uſed by them, as they pleaſed. But the Judgment of
the monthly adjourned Meeting that was given out againſt <hi>Will. Stockdale,</hi>
did not depend upon the bare Credit of theſe two Perſons, though Men ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently
credible. But the Meeting it ſelf, conſiſting of above Sixty Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
declareth, that at that monthly Meeting he did ſay, <hi>That what he had
formerly ſaid in his Charge againſt</hi> G. K. <hi>he did yet ſtand by and juſtifie;</hi> upon
which, that Meeting gave judgment againſt him, <hi>That the ſaid</hi> W. Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale
<hi>ſhould condemn his unrighteous Charge publickly,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="part">
               <p>XXVI. His groſs Perverſion, in labouring to defame theſe two honeſt
Friends, moſt falſly accuſing <hi>W. Bradford with Baſeneſs and Treachery to his
Benefactors in</hi> Penſilvania; who at no inconſiderable Coſt encouraged the
Preſs there, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But let the Impartial Reader judge whether <hi>Sam. Jennings</hi>
doth not baſely accuſe him, for an innocent Act, he not being under the
leaſt tye or limitation, by them he calleth his Benefactors, not to print to
<hi>G. K.</hi> as well as to them, <hi>G. K.</hi> being engaged in the ſame Teſtimony for
<hi>Conſcience-ſake</hi> with him. But <hi>S. Jennings</hi> may be aſhamed, to call them
his Benefactors, who were his Perſecutors and Oppreſſors, and dealt trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſly
with him, by breaking their Indenture with him, and taking away
his Forty Pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> from him, that they had covenanted to give
him, for about ſeven years to come, which he had little above one year paid
him; ſo expoſing his Family to Want and Ruin, had not Providence open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
another way to him. And as is above ſaid, they took his Salary from
him, for printing that ſheet from <hi>Rhode</hi> Iſland, which was before any thing
of our Differences in <hi>Penſilvania</hi> were expoſed in Print; ſo that could it be
ſuppoſed, that his printing the Differences among us in <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
ſome juſt occaſion of Offence to them, (which it did not) yet they ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
away his Salary from him, before that ſuppoſed Offence, was moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt,
ſeeing, according to all Juſtice, the Puniſhment never goeth before the
Offence, but followeth it. His other Story of <hi>John Macomb,</hi> is falſe in d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
things, as his (viz. <hi>J. M.</hi>) being under ſtrong Obligations to <hi>W. S</hi> for
his Care of him, in that time when he wanted it. But I have heard <hi>J. M.</hi>
deny it ſolemnly, that ever he was ſo much obliged to <hi>W. S.</hi> as <hi>W. S.</hi> was
to him: And it's well known, that <hi>W. S.</hi> was not under ſuch Circumſtances,
either in <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> or elſewhere, as very liberally to ſupply the wants of
other, but rather needed, and had ſupply from others; and as for <hi>J. M.</hi> he
was no Servant to <hi>W. S.</hi> but to <hi>R.T.</hi> who is kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n to be both able <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
and ſufficiently enough diſpoſed to do well by his Servants, and to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>p
them to live comfortably, after the time of their Service is expired; ſo that
this Suggeſtion of <hi>John Macombs</hi> want, being ſupplyed by <hi>W. S.</hi> as <hi>S. J.</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:59231:7"/>
would have it believed, is more probable to be a Fiction than any truth, and
we have no other Authority for it, but that <hi>S. J.</hi> or <hi>W. S.</hi> ſaid ſo; and J.M.
his denying it, with the circumſtances related, is ſufficient to counter-bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
But ſuppoſing it to be true, what is alledged of <hi>W. S.</hi> being ſo kind
to J. M. it is falſe, what <hi>S. J.</hi> relates, that J. M. uſed any fly, unmanly, or
ungrateful way, in a Viſit to <hi>W. S.</hi> to pump him by queſtions, concerning
<hi>G. K.</hi> For the ſaid J. M. came to me next morning after the diſcourſe that
paſt betwixt them, and told it to me, no ways, as one that ſought any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
againſt W. S. but ſimply, as one much grieved in Spirit, to find ſo
great a difference in Judgment betwixt W.S. and me, in a thing of ſo great
moment, and he told me alſo, the Viſit and Diſcourſe were both occaſional;
and it came altogether from W.S. of his own accord, without any ſuch thing
as pumping him by queſtions, as S. J. falſly alledgeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="part">
               <p>XXVII. p. 8. He groſly prevaricates, in falſly accuſing me, <hi>That I liberally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow
my</hi> Anathema Maranatha <hi>upon</hi> W.S. <hi>without more a-do, telling him, he was
an ignorant Heathen, not worthy of any place in the Aſſembly of Friends.</hi> [For I
never pronounced an <hi>Anathema</hi> upon W.S. or any other of them, tho ſome of
them have pronounced many woes upon me, in the Hearing of many, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
with <hi>their falſe Prophecies,</hi> which God hath fruſtrated, and (my <hi>faith
is in him</hi>) he will ſtill fruſtrate. But <hi>S. Jennings</hi> is very ignorant, that he
knoweth not an <hi>Anathema Maranatha</hi> is one thing, being a <hi>very ſevere Curſe;</hi>
and to tell a man, <hi>If he believe not in Chriſt without him, as well as in Chriſt
within him,</hi> which were my words to <hi>W. S.</hi> he is but an <hi>ignorant Heathen, and
not worthy of any place among Friends;</hi> which I ſtill affirm to be true, and is
<hi>the true character</hi> of one ſo groſly ignorant.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="part">
               <p>XXVIII. It is a <hi>groſs perverſion,</hi> and <hi>falſe accuſation</hi> in him, to ſay, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
Judgment was not given againſt</hi> W.S. <hi>in my way and time (altho</hi> (as he
falſly alledgeth) <hi>my own turbulency was the great obſtruction) he therefore ſticks
not to unchriſtian many,</hi> &amp;c. [For I have ſufficiently ſhewed in my printed
books, and now lately in my <hi>Anſwer</hi> to T.E. <hi>That they gave no due judgment
or cenſure at all againſt him to this day; and the ſhadow, or bare formality of
judgment the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> publiſhed at laſt againſt him, was like Muſtard after Meat, and
at an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> or one born out of due time, being 9 months after my complaint
made to the Yearly meeting, and about 13 months after my firſt complaint, made
to a meeting of Miniſtring Friends, at the houſe of</hi> Robert Ewer, <hi>and ſeveral
months after the breach began at</hi> Philadelphia. And it is a moſt deceitful Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe,
to ſay, <hi>my own turbulency was the great obſtruction;</hi> which is meerly ſaid,
but not proved, after long and much earneſt Reaſoning and expoſtulating
<hi>the matter with them,</hi> at <hi>the Yearly meeting</hi> at <hi>Philadelphia.</hi> At <hi>their deſire</hi> I
went out of the meeting, that they might agree upon a Judgment <hi>among
themſelves;</hi> (tho <hi>T. E.</hi> groſly <hi>printeth a falſhood,</hi> in the face of the world,
citing my book, <hi>Some Reaſons and Cauſes of the Separation, That I refuſed to
go out;</hi> and my book, p. 18. ſaith expreſly, <hi>I did go out at the meetings deſire</hi>)
and yet they would not ſuffer any Judgment to be intimated to me, neither
at that time, nor for many months thereafter: Yea, the Judgment that was
duly given by the <hi>monthly meeting</hi> adjourned, they denied it to be a due Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59231:7"/>
and <hi>diſowned the meeting that gave it,</hi> as is ſhewed in my former print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
books, and particularly in my late <hi>Anſwer</hi> to <hi>T.E.</hi> However, he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth,
<hi>That judgment was not given againſt</hi> W.S. and giveth the Reaſon, why,
<hi>becauſe they would not give it in my way and time.</hi> But I ſay, <hi>they gave it not in
Truths way and time, but delayed it moſt unreaſonably and unchriſtianly, till the
time was expired; and at laſt what they gave, was but a ſhadow.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="part">
               <p>XXIX. p. 9. He boldly, but moſt falſly chargeth me, <hi>That I have falſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed
the innocent, and that knowingly too, becauſe,</hi> as he alledgeth, <hi>I have heard
very many of them often declare their Faith in the aforeſaid particulars, and what
elſe is neceſſary to be believed and owned by true Chriſtians.</hi> [But I deny, that
ever I heard <hi>any of them give a ſatisfactory account of their Faith in the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
things of Controverſie, but generally from time to time, increaſed our juſt
diſſatisfaction, both by their moſt unchriſtian and unſound expreſſions, and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
and equivocous terms:</hi> Yea, both <hi>I, and many others,</hi> do well remember
that we have heard <hi>Sam. Jennings, himſelf,</hi> declare in a publick meeting at <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladelphia,
That Friends were not gathered by the faith of Chriſt, as he came out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly
to die for us, but by faith in the power of God, inwardly revealed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Thus
ſetting things aſunder that go together: And divers others of them have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared
to the ſame effect; and <hi>John Willford,</hi> to the offence of many, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
in the Hearing of Hundreds, at <hi>Philadelphia, That he had the true faith
of Chriſts Death and Sufferings, before he came among Friends; but it did not
gather him to God, but left him in his ſins.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="part">
               <p>XXX. p. 10. His boldly, and moſt perverſly challenging me, <hi>to name the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
among us, that any orderly complaint hath been made againſt, and the matter
proved, that hath been cloaked; yea, that hath not been teſtified againſt.</hi> [What
greater impudence can be ſuppoſed in a man, than for Him thus to challenge
me, when he not only knows in his conſcience, but doth confeſs in this his
<hi>ſcandalous Pamphlet, the complaints I made againſt both</hi> William Stockdale, <hi>and</hi>
Thomas Fitſwaters, <hi>from meeting to meeting, and yet they never did any thing
effectually to paſs due Judgment againſt them:</hi> And as for <hi>Thomas Fitſwaters,</hi>
their <hi>monthly meeting</hi> at <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> inſtead of paſſing a due Cenſure on him,
for his falſly accuſing me, <hi>That I denied the ſufficiency of the Light to ſalvation,</hi>
did clear him, from the Evidence given by four perſons of their own Party,
that ſaid, <hi>They heard me affirm, the Light was not ſufficient to ſalvation, without
ſomething elſe:</hi> But this was no proof to confirm his accuſation: for the thing
they ſhould have proved againſt me, was, <hi>That I denied the ſufficiency of the
Light to ſalvation:</hi> But inſtead of proving that, they gave Evidence to prove
another thing, quite different; even as far different as to ſay, <hi>Sam. Jennings
is not an honeſt man, without honeſt dealing;</hi> and to ſay ſimply, <hi>he is not an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
man;</hi> For the firſt is certainly true, tho the ſecond were queſtioned. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,
he knoweth in his conſcience, that I complained to <hi>their Quarte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly
meeting,</hi> upon the unſound and vile expreſſions in <hi>John Humphreys</hi> Letters,
(the Original Copy of which was read at the meeting at <hi>London,</hi> laſt 1694.)
and yet I received no Anſwer, but a meer abuſe, <hi>S. Jennings</hi> being preſent,
who told me, <hi>I was none of them; and what had I to do to hinder the Affairs
of the Meeting?</hi> I told them, <hi>if I were</hi> Turk <hi>or</hi> Jew, <hi>they ought to hear my
juſt Complaint againſt one of their Church-Members.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="part">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:59231:8"/>
               <p>XXXI. And he but deceitfully tells, in his <hi>page 10. That at the laſt Yearly
Meeting at</hi> Philadelphia, <hi>a Minute was made, That great care ſhould be taken,
that if any amongſt us had given any juſt cauſe of Offence, they ſhould be orderly
deals withal, that Truth might be cleared, and the Offence removed;</hi> whence he
deceitfully inters, ſaying, <hi>So that I think all his pretences of Friends cloaking,</hi>
&amp;c. <hi>in</hi> America, <hi>are taken away, and will be no more a Cloak for him to cover his
falſe accuſations againſt them.</hi> [But he ſhould have given ſome Example, or
inſtance, when, or where they did execute that Minute, or Order of their Laſt
Yearly meeting, ſo that theſe who had given juſt cauſe of Offence, had been
dealt withal; but nothing of this being produced, nor that can be produced,
ſheweth his and their great deceit, being like to ſome bad Rulers, who make
ſome good Laws, but fail to put them into execution. And ſuppoſe they
made ſuch a Minute at the laſt Yearly meeting at <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> about 18 months
at lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, after the ſeparation and breach was begun, occaſioned by their cloak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
perſons guilty of ſuch vile Errors; this proveth not, <hi>That they were not
guilty of c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oaking thoſe perſons before that time;</hi> but in reality, <hi>they are as guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
ſince as before;</hi> and their making ſuch a Minute, as he alledgeth, if any ſuch
thing was made, is but a meer blind or Cloak, whereby to deceive ſuch ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
ſouls, as are willing to be deceived by them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="part">
               <p>XXXII. p. 11. He falſly accuſeth me, bitterly to envy againſt <hi>Thomas
Lloid,</hi> and <hi>that I abuſe and miſrepreſent him, in charging him, how at the</hi> School-Houſe-Meeting,
<hi>as well as at thoſe other Meetings aforeſaid,</hi> Thomas Lloid <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued,
That Faith in Chriſt without us, as be died for our ſins,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and roſe again,
was not neceſſary to our ſalvation.</hi> He confeſleth, He was not at <hi>the School-houſe
Meeting,</hi> but <hi>at other times, (he ſaith) and once eſpecially, he was preſent at a
diſcourſe relating to that matter; but the Queſtion was not, VVhether Faith in
Chriſt without us, as be died for our ſins, and roſe again, was not neceſſary to our
ſalvation? But, Whether that Faith were indiſpenſibly neceſſary to all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind?
and that none could be ſaved without it, tho they had not the Means, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity
or Capacity to know or receive it, which</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>will include a great
part of Mankind; as namely, all thoſe that have not the uſe of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
nor the advantage of hearing it preached to them, which will affect many
great Nations, as alſo all Infants, deaf and dumb perſons,</hi> &amp;c. [But tho <hi>S. J.</hi> here
takes on him the defence of <hi>Thomas Lloid,</hi> and falſly accuſeth me of <hi>bitterly
e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ying againſt him;</hi> His Vindication of Him in this particular matter, is
utterly deceitful, and grounded on a groſs falſhood; as if <hi>Thomas Lloid</hi> were
not guilty of any ſuch charge as above-related. He confeſſeth, <hi>he was not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
at that School-houſe Meeting; ſo can be no witneſs in the caſe,</hi> if he were ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
to be free of all prejudice and partiality, as he is not.</p>
               <p>But I have many Witneſſes, ſome whereof are here in <hi>England,</hi> and at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi>
that are ready to declare ſolemnly, <hi>They heard him,</hi> viz. Thomas Lloid,
<hi>not only then but at other times, boldly aſſert, That faith in Chriſt without us, as
he d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed for our ſins, and roſe again, was not neceſſary to our ſalvation.</hi> And the
circumſtances, and manner of his arguing, together with the Proofs that he
brought to prove his abſurd aſſertion, are ſo freſh in the minds of many that
heard him, as well as in my mind, that ſufficiently make it evident, that he is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59231:8"/>
guilty of the charge: for he argued, to prove his aſſertion, from two places
of Scripture; <hi>viz. Micah 6. 8. He hath ſhewed thee, O Man! what is good,
and what doth the Lord require of thee, but to do Juſtice, and to love Mercy, and
to walk humbly with thy God:</hi> and <hi>Eccleſ. 12. 13. Fear God and keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments;
for this is the whole duty of man:</hi> on which he thus argued; <hi>That
nothing here is required to believe that Chriſt died for us, and roſe again:</hi> To
which I anſwered; <hi>That tho that faith is not expreſſed in theſe places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
nor in many other, yet it is implied, and implicitly underſtood; for how can
we walk humbly with God, if we be lifted up ſo in pride, as to think that we need
not to have our ſins pardoned for Chriſt's ſake; who died for our ſins, that they might
be forgiven us freely for his ſake through faith in him who died for us:</hi> And at the
very ſame time his Son in Law, <hi>John Delawall,</hi> openly oppoſed him, tho af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards
he joyned with him againſt my Chriſtian Teſtimony; citing for a
Proof againſt <hi>his Antichriſtian aſſertion,</hi> that place of Scripture in <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 9.
(and reading it out of a ſmall Pocket-bible) <hi>If thou ſhalt confeſs with thy mouth
the Lord Jeſus, and ſhalt believe in thine heart that God hath raiſed him from the
dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved.</hi> And it is evident as the Sun at Noon-day, That his
Eſſay to prove his Antichriſtian aſſertion from theſe places of Scripture, makes
it good againſt him, that he did hold, <hi>That faith in Chriſt, as he died for us,
and roſe again, was not neceſſary to our ſalvation;</hi> ſeeing none will ſay, but that
theſe places of Scripture have an univerſal reference to all mankind; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
us as well as theſe not called <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another Proof brought by him at that very time, at <hi>the School-houſe Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
which is yet a further Evidence of my charge, was the late <hi>Act of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament
for Toleration,</hi> made under the preſent Reign; where a ſhort Teſt is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired
of Juſtices of the Peace and others, concerning their faith in God and
in Chriſt, and in the Holy Ghoſt; and becauſe nothing in that ſhort Teſt is
mentioned of faith in Chriſt, as he died for us, therefore <hi>Tho. Lloid</hi> did argue,
<hi>that faith was not neceſſary to our ſalvation.</hi> Now it is to be conſidered, That
this ſhort Teſt is only deſigned, and was only made for ſuch as profeſs Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity;
and not for profeſſed <hi>Heathens;</hi> which makes it ſufficiently evident,
that <hi>Tho. Lloid's</hi> aſſertion, and the matter of diſpute betwixt him and me, was
not concerning <hi>Heathens</hi> at that time, but profeſſed <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> for it cannot
be ſuppoſed that the Parliament's Act did extend to profeſſed <hi>Heathens, Turks</hi>
or <hi>Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</hi> And here I earneſtly i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>treat the Readers to excuſe my expoſing
things ſo particularly, in relation to <hi>Thomas Lloid,</hi> ſeeing I am brought upon
the Neceſſity of doing it, in the juſt defence of my Innocency and Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation,
which this prejudiced Adveſary, <hi>Sam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Jennings,</hi> ſeeks, and moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianly
endeavoureth, by his falſe Accuſations, to take from me. But for
a further proof of <hi>Sam. Jennings</hi> his inſincerity in this particular, he knoweth in
his conſience how <hi>Tho. Lloid</hi> hath defended and juſtified <hi>John Hemphrey</hi> from
time to time, in his <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> aſſertion, <hi>that he was grieved to hear ſome ſay,
they expected to be juſtified by that blood that was ſhed at Jeruſalem;</hi> which moſt
evidently proveth, that neither <hi>J.</hi> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er <hi>Tho. Lloid</hi> did believe it was neceſſary
for them to <hi>have that faith, that we are Juſtified by that blood:</hi> Yea, <hi>S. Jennings</hi>
his charging me with an <hi>inconſistency in my two Aſſertions;</hi> the one being, <hi>that:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59231:9"/>
the light within is ſufficient to ſalvation;</hi> the other being, <hi>that the light within is
not ſufficient to ſalvation without ſomething elſe;</hi> I having always declared, <hi>that
by that ſomething elſe</hi> I mean <hi>the Man Chriſt Jeſus, and his Death and Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
Blood, Reſurrection and Interceſſion,</hi> &amp;c. doth ſufficiently prove him guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<hi>that he doth not believe it neceſſary to his ſalvation that Chriſt died for him;</hi>
for if <hi>the light within</hi> be ſufficient to ſalvation, <hi>without the Death of Chriſt</hi>
(<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich is a part of <hi>that ſomething elſe</hi> underſtood by me) then it is not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
to our ſalvation, to believe <hi>that Christ died for us;</hi> and <hi>the Death of Christ
hath no part or ſhare in our ſalvation,</hi> by this his <hi>Antichristian</hi> aſſertion. But
now in reference to the queſtion, as ſtated by him, he alledging, that I have
affirmed, <hi>that this faith is indiſpenſibly neceſſary to all,</hi> viz. <hi>in order to eternal ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,
to believe in Chriſt, as he died for us, and roſe again.</hi> I freely own it,
<hi>that I have ſo Affirmed, and do ſtill ſo affirm;</hi> but however, that was neither
the only, nor the principal queſtion or matter of Debate betwixt <hi>Th. Lloid</hi>
and me; but a ſecond branch of the queſtion occaſionally happening, that at
ſometimes was alſo diſcourſed betwixt us: But as concerning <hi>the indiſpenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
neceſſity of Faith in Chriſt, as he died for us, and roſe again, as univerſally ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
to ſalvation,</hi> how and in what ſenſe I have affirmed, I have fully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained
in divers of my late printed books relating to our late differences;
where I have diſtinguiſhed betwixt the <hi>expreſs, or explicite knowledg and faith
of Chriſt's Death, in order to eternal ſalvation,</hi> and <hi>the implicite knowledge and
faith of it;</hi> aſſerting this laſt, but not the firſt, as <hi>univerſally and indiſpenſibly
neceſſary:</hi> And in this my <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Teſtimony, as I agree <hi>with the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi>
and all my former books (notwithſtanding of the Inſinuations of ſome
ignorant prejudiced perſons againſt me; ſo with the Printed Books and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies
of divers <hi>friends</hi> of good Repute among the people called <hi>Quakers;</hi>
and with <hi>the General Doctrine</hi> of all moderate <hi>Chriſtian VVriters</hi> throughout
<hi>Christendom:</hi> See my aforeſaid <hi>Explication of my Aſſertion,</hi> particularly in my
Two late Printed Treatiſes; the one called, <hi>Truth and Innocency defended,</hi> from
<hi>page</hi> 10. to <hi>page</hi> 20. where I largely open the ſaid <hi>distinction</hi> of <hi>faith in Christ
explicit and implicit;</hi> and alſo my other, called, <hi>Hereſie and Hatred,</hi> page 13.
As for what he objecteth concerning <hi>the strange Notion</hi> of <hi>the Revolution of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
ſouls,</hi> and <hi>his inſinuation,</hi> of <hi>my countenancing it;</hi> having ſo fully anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to it in the Two aforementioned Treatiſes <hi>in Print,</hi> to which I refer, I need
ſay nothing here, further than to tell him, and alſo to inform the Reader, <hi>that
his thinking, or inſinuation, that my holding the faith of Christ's Death indiſpenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
neceſſary to all that ſhall be ſaved,</hi> doth oblige me to held, <hi>that all to whom
that faith is not outwardly preached, or who have not the outward means, or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
opportunity of receiving it, muſt needs live again, by Revolution, in order to
have it preached unto them, otherwiſe they cannot be ſaved;</hi> doth ſufficiently
prove him extreamly ignorant, and that he hath neither the true faith, nor
a true Notion of the ſufficiency of the Light within. And howbeit he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth,
in his Prejudice and Enmity, to repreſent me, as one undervaluing
the ſufficiency of the Light within, it plainly appeareth, Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the ſufficiency
of the Light within more than he doth, or any of his Party, who thus do
falſly accuſe me; for I ſay, as I have oft formerly ſaid, the Light within (in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59231:9"/>
the higheſt ſenſe) being God and Chriſt, the Eternal Word, and the Spirit in
every man, is ſufficient to reveal and give the Knowledge and Faith of Chriſt
as he died for all men, and roſe again, unto all men, without all outward
means of outward Preaching, or Reading, and conſequently without the
Revolutions of Humane Souls for even. Such who favour the Revolution
of Humane Souls, as a probable <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> do it not upon that ſuppoſition,
as if the Light within were inſufficient to give the Knowledge and Faith of
Chriſt without as well as within; for the ſufficiency of the Light within, hath
not a dependance upon the Revolutions, nor upon any outward means of
Preaching, Hearing or Reading: Inſomuch therefore that <hi>Sam. Jennings</hi> doth
ſuppoſe, <hi>that to affirm the Faith of Chriſt's Death to be indiſpenſibly neceſſary to
ſalvation to all that ſhall be eternally ſaved;</hi> is to infer the neceſſity of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution
of Humane Souls: And alſo that he doth poſitively affirm, <hi>that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
have not the means, opportunity or capacity to know or receive it; which</hi> (he
ſaith) <hi>will include a great part of Mankind.</hi> From this it plainly followeth,
that he thinketh the Light within is not ſufficient or able to reveal or give
that Knowledge or Faith of Chriſt's Death, which I affirm it is, being God,
the Word and the Spirit; and therefore I have a better belief of the ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency
of the Light within than he hath, or his Party that is joyned with him
againſt my Chriſtian Teſtimony; and to ſay, the Light within is not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
as fully <hi>to reveal and give the Knowledge and Faith of Chriſt's Death with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,
as of his Life within,</hi> is a degree of Blaſphemy againſt God, who is that
Light within, and ſoundeth as harſh and offenſive to Chriſtian Ears, as to ſay,
God is not ſufficient to reveal, or give to all men the Knowledge and Faith
of Chriſt's Death, by Internal Revelation, without all outward means of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction;
which yet I think no ſound Chriſtian will dare to affirm. But, as
I have oft ſaid, it is one thing what God, who is Light, and is in all men, is
ſufficient, or able to do, <hi>who is able of ſtones to raiſe up children to Abraham;</hi>
and who can work by his Spirit, when, where, how, and in whom he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth,
even without outward means, whether in Infants, or deaf and dumb
perſons, or in them that never heard the Fame of Chriſt with their outward
Ears: and it is another thing, what he is pleaſed to do in his ordinary way of
working. But it ought well to be conſidered, that our full and perfect ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
depends not wholly upon what God either can, or pleaſeth to reveal in
us; but alſo in great part, upon what the Man Chriſt hath done and ſuffered
for us on Earth, eſpecially in dying, and ſhedding his precions Blood for us,
and his interced on for us now in Heaven; for that is no ſmall part of our
ſalvation, to be ſaved from Wrath, and from the guilt of ſin, and from that
fearful ſentence of <hi>Condemnation,</hi> and <hi>the Curſe of the</hi> Law, due to us for ſin;
and no Internal Revelation can ſave us from that <hi>Curſe, Condemnation and
Wrath;</hi> but it was neceſſary that Chriſt ſhould ſuffer for us in the true Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
of Man, that curſins might be forgiven, and we might be ſaved from
the Wrath of God, and the Curſe and Condemnation of the Law of God,
and Chriſt's ſuffering Death, and ſheading his precious Blood for us, was
not only neceſſary to our Juſtification, but to our Sanctification, becauſe by
his Obedience unto Death, and precious Blood, he hath procured and pur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59231:10"/>
for us that inward principle of God's Grace, whereby we are ſanctified;
and we are ſanctified through a living Faith in Chriſt, as he died for us; and
that Faith is neceſſary to mens Regeneration and Sanctification, as well as to
Remiſſion of ſins; and therefore is neceſſary to all. But that he ſaith, <hi>a great
part of Mankind will be included, who have not had the means, opportunity or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity
to know or receive it;</hi> which carries with it a very harſh and uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Judgment upon all that part of mankind.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But where is then the ſufficiency of the Light he and many others
ſeem ſo warmly to plead for, if it be not ſufficient not only to make them
capable, but alſo to give them the Knowledge of it; <hi>viz. the Death of Chriſt?</hi>
But why ſhould this ſound more harſh and uncharitable, to ſay, a great part
of mankind die as much without the Knowledge of Chriſt within as of Chriſt
without; for as <hi>Chriſt came in the fleſh,</hi> is called a great <hi>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtery</hi> in Scripture,
ſo is <hi>Christ within</hi> alſo called <hi>a great myſtery;</hi> yea, the <hi>myſtery that had been
hid from Ages and Generations:</hi> and he cannot give me an Inſtance of any that
ever knew the myſtery of <hi>Christ within,</hi> but alſo knew in ſome meaſure the
myſtery of <hi>Christ without;</hi> for that which is able to reveal the one, is able
to reveal the other. But that any are ſaved without the knowledge of <hi>Christ
within,</hi> I ſuppoſe he will not ſay, ſeeing the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Know ye not that
Jeſus Christ is in you, unleſs ye be Reprobates?</hi> Or rather, <hi>diſapproved,</hi> or want
a Proof. But the Scripture alſo ſaith, <hi>That it is one God who ſhall justifie the
circumciſion; i.e.</hi> the <hi>Jews, by Faith;</hi> and <hi>the circumciſion; i. e.</hi> the <hi>Gentiles,
through Faith.</hi> And the true Faith is one, whereby both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi>
are juſtified; which is a Faith in Chriſt, as he died for us, as well as that he
doth inwardly enlighten us. But to ſuppoſe a Faith in Chriſt, that doth not
reſpect his outward coming in the Fleſh, and Death and ſufferings, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
and alone that inward common illumination that is in all mankind; is to
ſet up an unſcriptural and Antichriſtian Faith, oppoſite to the true Chriſtian
Faith; which I charge on <hi>Sam. Jennings,</hi> and on all that join with him in
this his abſurd Doctrine, to be a pernicious Error, tending to make v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id the
true Faith of Chriſt, and the Doctrine of the Holy Scriptures, and to teach
men to rely upon their Obedience to the Law, or Light within, for Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
and Life Eternal, without the Faith of Chriſt crucified; that s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain
contrary to the Holy Scripture, that ſaith, <hi>Both</hi> Jews <hi>and</hi> Gentiles <hi>were all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
ſin, and whatſoever the</hi> Law <hi>ſaith; it ſaith to them that are under the</hi> Law,
<hi>that every mouth may be stopped, and the whole world become guilty before God.</hi>
Now this Law that <hi>steppeth every mouth, and maketh the whole world guilty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
God,</hi> is the Law, or Light in theſe <hi>Gentiles</hi> who have not the Scriptures,
or written Law without: and whatever feigned pretence of <hi>Charity S. J.</hi> or
any others that hold this groſs Error, <hi>That men may be eternally ſaved without
all knowledge and faith of Christ crucified;</hi> may have towards that part of
mankind who have not had Chriſt outwardly preached unto them; yet it is
a real undervaluing, and ſeeking to undermine the Chriſtian Diſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſation,
and make it as a mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Indifferent thing;</hi> yea, unprofitable to be under it: for
if men commonly obtain Eternal Life and Salvation, without all knowledge
and faith of Chriſt crucified, and raiſed again; and can be perfectly ſanctified
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59231:10"/>
without it; then there is no need to have that Faith at all: But for ſuch who
ſay, <hi>it is needful, becauſe it is preached;</hi> they uſe a deceitful, but ſilly evaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
for if it's only needful, becauſe it is preached, then the way is not to
preach it, that it may not be needful; and if ſo, why did the Apoſtles, and
many other faithful men preach it, and ſeal to it with their blood? Surely
this is the way to lead people generally both to neglect preaching Chriſt
crucified, and to hear it preached; yea, and if they deſtroy, or bury the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi>
in oblivion, from their poſterity, by this wicked doing they ſhall excuſe
them from being under a Neceſſity to believe the Death of Chriſt in order to
ſalvation. But whereas ſome ſay, it is profitable, tho not abſolutely neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
to ſalvation. to have the Faith of Chriſt's Death; but ſeeing they ſay, men
are commonly ſaved eternally without it, as well as with it; they cannot
ſhew wherein it is profitable, unleſs it be neceſſary: Indeed, they may as well
ſay, with <hi>Pelagians</hi> and <hi>Socinians,</hi> that inward Grace, or the Spirit's inward
operation, is only profitable, but not abſolutely neceſſary to mens ſalvation.
But we find the Terms of ſalvation univerſally without exception, ſet down,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 9, 10. that plainly holds it forth, <hi>that to believe that Christ roſe from
the dead, and that with the heart, as well as to confeſs it with the mouth, is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
to all that ſhall be ſaved:</hi> And tho this Faith is wrought in men in God's
ordinary way, by an outward Miniſtry, yet the Word, or Light within, is
ſuffitient to work it without an outward Miniſtry; and doth ſo work it when
God pleaſeth, as he wrought it in <hi>Abraham, Job,</hi> and many others. But that
<hi>S.J.</hi> ſaith, page 12. he hath heard <hi>T. Lloid</hi> affirm, <hi>he did believe it to be our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
who had the advantage of having the Holy Scriptures, and hearing the Faith
preached, to receive and believe it.</hi> This, I ſuppoſe, is poſſible; but when
was it that he did ſo profeſs to believe? <hi>viz.</hi> after that the Publick Letter
ſigned by <hi>G.W.</hi> and others, from <hi>London,</hi> came to them and us, holding forth
that Faith as neceſſary: but before that Letter came, it is well known to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
as well as to me, that he had oft denied it; but before that the Breach
was made: And ſince it was made, tho we, for our part, uſed great Endeavors
to be reconciled to them in the Truth, yet we could never effect it in Truth's
way.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="part">
               <p>XXXIII. <hi>page<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 3. He proceeds in the next place to ſhew (which moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully
and falſly he ſaith he will do, <hi>candidly, cautiouſly and truly</hi>) the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
cauſe of this unhappy breach and difference: <hi>The General Cauſe</hi> (ſaith
he) <hi>I take to be an unbounded Ambition in G. K.</hi> But he gives no proof of this
<hi>his unchristian and uncharitable aſſertion;</hi> and therefore I return it on him, as
falſe and fictitious.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="part">
               <p>XXXIV. His perverſion, in making it a <hi>Crime</hi> in me, to have ſome Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Controverſie with ſome called <hi>Preachers</hi> in <hi>New England,</hi> and challeng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
ſome of them to diſpute with me; alledging. <hi>that I managed it with
great Heat and Rage, and common Inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lts, when I thought I had advantage, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning
Victory and Vain Glory, rather than Edification.</hi> And of this he brings
no proof, but his bare Authority, he being then in <hi>New England</hi> with me.
But he ſhould have brought either ſome of my Words or Actions to prove
me guilty of his charge; which he not doing, proves him to be evidently
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59231:11"/>
guilty of deep Prejudice, as well as groſs Hypocriſie; for he being with me,
and judging me ſo guilty, as he alledgeth, he was unfaithful, in not admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing
me ſeaſonably; which he cannot juſtly ſay, that he ever did, all that
time we were together; but profeſſed great Unity with me. And for my
book of <hi>Controverſie</hi> againſt ſome Preachers at <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>New England,</hi> called,
<hi>The Presbyterian and Independent Viſible Churches brought to the Teſt,</hi> &amp;c. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
it was printed, the moſt of it, if not all of it, was read in his hearing,
and in nothing diſapproved by him, and was generally approved by all that
heard it read, being an appointed Number of them called <hi>Friends of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry;</hi>
the which book was ſo well accepted by Friends at <hi>London,</hi> and over
<hi>England,</hi> that it being Re-printed at <hi>London,</hi> moſt of them were ſold, and
many Friends bought of them; and tho I have heard divers both in City and
Country ſpeak well of it, I have not heard any ſhew the leaſt diſſatisfaction
againſt it; yea, divers of the profeſſing people in <hi>N. England</hi> ſpake well of it;
and tho I uſed ſome ſharp Words towards ſome Preachers at <hi>Boſton,</hi> who did
too much juſtifie the Perſecution raiſed againſt Friends in <hi>N. E.</hi> yet (as any
that have a ſpiritual ſavour to judg, who read my book, will ſay) I writ with
great moderation, and ſincere expreſſions of Love and charity towards ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
of the people; and I think I can ſay it without Vanity, few have excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
me in moderation, in my way of writing <hi>Controverſie,</hi> among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
called <hi>Quakers.</hi> But if ſeeking to diſpute with perſons of other Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
be an argument of Vain Glory, by the ſame way of Arguing, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
ſome of the beſt Account of the Speakers among the people called <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi>
equally guilty. And that he ſaith, <hi>how little it redounded to Truth's ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage,
he is a witneſs, he being then in</hi> N. E. <hi>with me.</hi> If it be enough to
make a man guilty by the ſingle Evidence of a prejudiced Adverſary, he
hath hit the Mark; but if otherwiſe, he only ſheweth his Enmity and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice.
But that my Labour in <hi>N. E.</hi> was not without ſucceſs, there are at
this day in <hi>N. E.</hi> who will bear witneſs to it, as alſo <hi>the Certificate</hi> I had
from the Meeting in <hi>Rhode Iſland,</hi> declaring <hi>the Vnity they had with me, and
the great benefit they had by my labour of love among them;</hi> which <hi>Certificate</hi> I
can produce; but the witneſs of God in my conſcience hath always been
unto me, and ever ſhall be, more than all witneſs of men, and is a ſufficient
defence unto me <hi>againſt this prejudiced adverſary,</hi> and others of <hi>his Stamp,</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="part">
               <p>XXXV. <hi>page</hi> 13, 14. His falſly accuſing me of a <hi>Spirit of Wrath and Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs,
and hating my Brother,</hi> &amp;c. [But ſharp Words of Reproof againſt
them to whom they duely belong, are no Argument of Hatred, or that I
had not then, or now have not the true Love of God in my Heart: For let
my books in theſe late differences, as well as any others, be compared with
moſt of the Friends books that have writ againſt <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> and it will be
found they have generally exceeded me in ſharp Words; and how far <hi>Sam.
Jennings,</hi> and his Party, have exceeded me in ſharp Words, the printed ſheet,
called, <hi>An Expoſtulation,</hi> &amp;c. doth ſufficiently prove. And tho ſharp words
of Reproof be no infallible Argument of Hatred, or of an <hi>unchriſtian Spirit</hi>
yet to be ſure Perſecution, in <hi>fining or impriſoning men for matters of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi>
is; whereof <hi>S. Jen.</hi> hath ſhewed Himſelf ſufficiently guilty, and who
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59231:11"/>
hath diſcovered Himſelf, <hi>Eſau</hi>-like, not only by <hi>his threatning words,</hi> but by
<hi>his rough hands.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="part">
               <p>XXXIV. His unjuſtly complaining againſt me, for my juſt complaint of
<hi>too great a laxineſs of Church-Diſcipline among them,</hi> and <hi>my preſenting a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
to Miniſtring Friends, in order to have it amended.</hi> [But he mentions no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
wherein that Paper is reprovable; and until He, or ſome for Him, can
ſhew the default of it, his blaming me for it, is but another Inſtance and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence
of <hi>his Prejudice and Enmity againſt me.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="part">
               <p>XXXVII. His unjuſtly accuſing me of <hi>impeaching</hi> (as he terms it) <hi>Friends
Teſtimony, and way of preaching, publickly as well as privately.</hi> [And what
could I do leſs, hearing ſo frequently ſuch falſe Doctrine preached, and the
Scriptures ſo groſly perverted, to the publick Scandal of Strangers, that were
not of our Profeſſion. Nor was I forward to do any ſuch thing, but very
ſparingly and modeſtly did at times correct their falſe Doctrine; and moſt of
the Oppoſition that ever I ſhewed to them in publick, was in defence of the
Truth of the <hi>Chriſtian Doctrine and Teſtimony</hi> I did bear, which they did
boldly contradict; and I dealt orderly with them, by private Admonition,
which they rejected: And when after I made my complaint to them called,
<hi>Friends of the Miniſtry,</hi> they did not regard it, ſo as to paſs any due cenſure
upon the guilty, as is ſufficiently made apparent in my former printed books,
as well as from what is in this before-mentioned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="part">
               <p>XXXVIII. <hi>page</hi> 15. His accuſing me of <hi>tedious, dry and inſipid Diſcourſes
in their Meetings at Philadelphia;</hi> is as falſe as it is improper for him ſo to
accuſe me; for how can it be expected, that ſuch a profeſſed Adverſary, and
open Perſecutor, will ſpeak well of me? But when the <hi>Jews</hi> accuſed our
bleſſed Lord of Blaſphemy, I need not think ſtrange that <hi>Sam. Jennings</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeth
me. But for dry and inſipid diſccurſes, he may take it home to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf;
for very many affirm it to be true of himſelf; and how an open Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor,
that rather glorieth in his Wickedneſs, than repents of it, can have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
other Miniſtry but dry, inſipid, yea and burdening, is eaſie to judge, and
which ſome have judged him for; and ſome that have been too much preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced
againſt me, yet have diſliked <hi>him,</hi> that they have <hi>publickly diſowned his
Prayer.</hi> But however, I may be to him, and ſome like him, a favour of
Death, as the true Miniſters of Chriſt were to ſome formerly; yet to ſuch
as have Salt in themſelves, I have been, and ſtill am, (through God's mercy)
<hi>a ſavour of Life unto Life.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="part">
               <p>XXXIX. His falſly accuſing me, that I ſaid to a meeting of Miniſtring
Friends, <hi>There were more damnable Hereſies, and Doctrines of Devils among the
Quakers, than among any Profeſſion of the Proteſtants, which,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
from my own mouth at that Meeting, and a</hi> Minute <hi>read to me, and not deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
by me; tho ſince</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>I endeavour to evade it.</hi> [But he bringeth no
other Proof for this, but his, and his Parties bare Allegation; which, as I
have formerly denied, ſo I ſtill deny, that ever I charged it indefinitely upon
the <hi>Quakers,</hi> or yet upon that Meeting, <hi>viz.</hi> met at <hi>Burlington,</hi> firſt month,
1691. but only upon a Party in that Meeting, there being in that Meeting
about a 3d part of them, that ſtood with me, and for my Chriſtian Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59231:12"/>
particularly <hi>George Hutcheſon,<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and <hi>Thomas Budd,</hi> who have declared,
that I ſaid not the <hi>Quakers</hi> indefinitely; but them, <hi>viz.</hi> a Faction of that
Meeting, who had ſufficiently ſhewed themſelves guilty of the charge, both
then and formerly. Yea, as I took notice at the Yearly Meeting at <hi>London,</hi>
                  <hi>3d</hi> month laſt, 1694. when that Paper he hath now printed, to his ſhame,
was read in the Yearly Meeting, and a <hi>Copy</hi> of it delivered to me, to anſwer:
In my Anſwer to it, I ſhewed them, how that notwithſtanding <hi>S. J.</hi> had na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
the Name of God, in aſſerting, I had charged the <hi>Quakers;</hi> yet that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
Paper, ſigned by <hi>S. J.</hi> in contradiction both to it ſelf and to him, doth
clear me, that my words were, <hi>That they were met together</hi> (ſee his printed
book, page 18. from line 14. where they ſay, they repeated my words to me,
and I declared the ſame again) <hi>to cloak Hereſies and Deceits; and that there
were more damnable Hereſies, and Doctrines of Devils among them;</hi> (Note, it
is not ſaid, amongſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> but <hi>them</hi>) which word <hi>them,</hi> did only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late
to a Party or Faction of that Meeting, Or, ſuppoſe it did relate to that
whole Meeting (which it did not), yet unleſs they will ſay, that meeting did
repreſent the Body of the people called <hi>Quakers,</hi> (which I judge they will not
ſay) over all parts of the World where they are, it is evident to be a falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation,
to put the word <hi>Quakers</hi> for them, not exceeding in number above
13 perſons; which is as falſe and injurious, as to charge the <hi>Engliſh</hi> with a
thing that only 13, or a few are guilty of. And when I re-minded both <hi>S.J.</hi>
and alſo the Yearly meeting, that he named the Name of God to a Falſhood,
which many preſent did greatly notice, and ſome did charge him with, he
had no other Evaſion, but that by them was meant the <hi>Quakers;</hi> which is as
palpable a perverſion, as to charge the <hi>Engliſh</hi> with a Fault that only 13 per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
are guilty of: And I at the ſame time, with true Reverence, naming
the Name of God, to clear my Innocency, ſaying in the preſence of God, to
the beſt of my remembrance, I ſaid not the <hi>Quakers,</hi> but <hi>them;</hi> ſome of the
Yearly meeting did ſeverely ſpeak to us, one ſaying, we had rent the Name of
God betwixt us; another ſaying, one of us two behoved to be greatly guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<hi>S. J.</hi> having ſaid, in the fear of God, he affirmed that I ſaid the <hi>Quakers.</hi>
And afterwards I produced the Paper of their meeting, ſigned by <hi>S. J.</hi> bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
date the 6th of the 7th month, 1672. wherein they declare, that my
words were as above-mentioned; which, they ſay, the two Friends repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
unto me, Now, Reader, judge what ſmall credit <hi>S. J.</hi> is worthy of, who
by his own declaration, hath printed himſelf guilty of falſly accuſing me, by
perverting my words, putting, moſt fraudulently, <hi>Quakers</hi> for <hi>them;</hi> when
yet in the Paper of that meeting, ſigned by him, he and they declare my
words; were as I have above-mentioned them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="part">
               <p>XL. And as concerning that Paper, called, <hi>The preſent Caſe,</hi> &amp;c. he hath
printed to his own ſhame, in his book with other the like ſhameful Papers,
as ſtanding Monuments of his unchriſtian Proceedings given out by his
Party, 20th of the 4th month, and ſigned by himſelf, it containing palpable
contradiction, and giving the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie to it ſelf, as is above noted. I need not
ſay much to it, but to deny what they falſly charge me with, as that in a
wrathful and better Spirit, I reviled and abuſed the ſaid Meeting, they charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59231:12"/>
me with brittleneſs of diſpoſition; (but my being preſerved by my gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
God, conſtant in my Chriſtian Teſtimony, and Converſation, proveth
them falſe accuſers in this, as in other things; for had I been brittle, their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian
Practices towards me had long a-go broken me; but God has mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully
preſerved me, and to him alone I give the praiſe) charging me with
the breach whereof they, and not I, were guilty; and with calumniating ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
perſons, not giving them Goſpel-Order in any Church-way; all which
are falſe charges. As alſo, that they ſay in their Paper, Notice was given me
of the time to which the Meeting was adjourned, <hi>viz.</hi> to a fortnight longer,
having appointed ſome Friends to viſit me. But in this they uſe great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varication,
hiding their deceit in ambiguous Words. That two came to me
in the Evening of that Meeting, before their fortnight Adjournment, I own
it; but that they told me either the preciſe day, hour or place of their meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
I altogether deny it; or that they did in the leaſt deſire me to come to
it; yea, their Paper ſignifieth no ſuch thing; but only that Notice was given
me of the time; but what particular time or place, they mention not; for
that called a Fortnight, ſometimes includes 14 days, ſometimes 15 or 16:
But what if I had known the preciſe day, hour and place, which I did not,
(for ſometimes they met at one place and ſometimes at another, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time
at one part of the day and ſometime at another) is that enough to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe
their proceeding ſo violently and furiouſly againſt me, without calling
me to hear things charged and proved againſt me? But their Paper doth not
ſo much as alledg, that I had any call to come to their meeting; therefore it
is a plain caſe, they are fallacious, and ſeek to deceive the ſimple with their
fallacious words. And what if they had called me, and I had refuſed to
come, as was not ſo? If they had been endued with the patient and long-ſuffering
Spirit of Chriſt, they would have again and again, at leaſt twice or
thrice, calld me, before they had paſt ſuch a ſevere Judgment againſt me, as
not only to Un-Miniſter and Un-Chriſtian me, but to repreſent me as one of
the worſt of men; was this like the reſtoring me in a ſpirit of meekneſs? Do
not humane Judicatories condemn them in this caſe, who commonly, before
they paſs cenſure, in many caſes, call, or ſummons them twice or thrice, who
are accuſed as guilty perſons; and in caſe of not appearance, on the firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
do not paſs a poſitive ſentence againſt them, till they have another ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
or ſome conſiderable time allowed to make their appearance, in caſe
of abſence, which was my caſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="part">
               <p>XLI. He falſly accuſeth my printed Treatiſe, called, <hi>The Plea of the Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi>
and ſo doth his Party (see his book, <hi>page</hi> 20.) <hi>to be a furious</hi> condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
againſt <hi>them.</hi> [But it was only a Juſt Defence and Vindication of my
Innocency and Chriſtian Teſtimony, and Reputation, which they moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianly
had laboured to deſtroy, with their moſt falſe Accuſations, and bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
Revilings and Invectives. And yet <hi>S.J.</hi> is ſo impudent, as to call th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s
ſcandalous Paper of their meeting aforeſaid, ſigned by himſelf only, <hi>The Act
of ſuch a Meeting as cannot in charity be ſuſpected to be partial or unjuſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</hi>
But it is now new thing to hear Darkneſs called Light, Falſhood Truth,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="part">
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:59231:13"/>
XLII. In their Poſtſcript to their ſaid Paper, there are alſo a great many
Fallacies and Falſhoods, too tedious to enumerate; To give an inſtance in
ſome particulars, 1. That one of my followers (as he ſcornfully calleth him)
read part of our Paper that he calleth <hi>a Challenge,</hi> while <hi>Thomas Jauney</hi> was
at Prayer. Here they uſe a Fallacy; for while that perſon was civilly reading
that Paper, to interrupt his reading, as was uſual to them in other caſes, <hi>T. J.</hi>
kneeled down to prayer; ſo the diſorder was in <hi>T. J.</hi> not in that other perſon:
And his ſtanding up in the Window, was but in order to be heard: And if
he did come in at the Window, being as open as the Door, which I know
not that he did, it is like it was, that the throng of People was ſo great in
the Door, that he could not have acceſs. Are not theſe ſilly and pitiful things
to print, ſo as to make ſuch ſmall innocent circumſtances to be crimes. But
when he wants better ſtuff, he muſt build with ſtraw and ſtubble. 2. They
ſay, They promiſed to give me a ſuitable hearing to my Appeal, provided I
would ſtay till the day appointed for buſineſs. But this was nothing but a
meer evaſion; for they knew in their conſcience, that many Friends, as well
as Friendly People, would be gone home before that time they appointed:
beſides, they had no power to appoint a time to us, and to delay a matter of
ſuch great concern to the laſt day of the meeting, which would have requir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
ſeveral days to have things fairly heard and examined. 3. That we refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
to hear them that were ſent of their ſide, with a Meſſage to us. But their
fallacy is great in this, that they conceal the rude carriage of thoſe they call
Meſſengers, that while one of our Friends was reading a Paper, theſe called
Meſſengers came in a moſt tumultuous manner, and one of them ſtood up
on a bench, and read his Paper, while our Friend was reading; and they that
came in with him, or them, called Meſſengers, raiſed ſuch an hideous Noiſe
with Voice and Feet, that was a great ſhame to hear of; and this was the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
of our removing, not willing to ſtay to ſee ſuch diſorder. 4. Their ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
in their Paper, That we ſet up thoſe who made little or no profeſſion of
Truth, for our Judges; is both a falſhood and a fallacy. It happened that
one perſon ſet his Name to the Paper (unknown to us generally) that was not
under the profeſſion of Truth; but after we knew of it, we razed out his
Name: but I never heard, nor knew of any more, being all, generally, not
only under a profeſſion of the Truth long before the ſeparation, but of Good
Report among Friends. But we can prove, and have proved, that divers of
them that ſigned their ſcandalous Paper of their Yearly meeting againſt us,
were guilty of ſcandalous converſation. 5. That that Paper given out from
our Yearly meeting, was drawn up and compleated according to my directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
This is an abſolute falſhood. 6. As for ſome hard words that I gave
ſome of them, on extraordinary provocation, they have far exceeded me, as
have been ſufficiently proved, calling me not only <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> but <hi>Raunter, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
man,</hi> even when I have been at prayer, in great tenderneſs; and <hi>S. J.</hi> own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,
that he called me <hi>Apoſtate;</hi> and at the ſame time when he profeſſed to
come and viſit me in Love, and deal with me by admonition in a Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,
he called me not only <hi>Apoſtate,</hi> but <hi>worſe than profane.</hi> And is it not
great Hypocriſie in <hi>S. J.</hi> ſo to aggravate ſome hard words of mine, and to paſs
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59231:13"/>
by ſo many, much more hard, as well as more in number of theirs, without
the leaſt noticing. Do a few hard words of mine, prove me a wicked man,
as <hi>S. J.</hi> and his party conclnde, and yet their many more, and more hard
words againſt me, prove them to be Saints? But let the merit of the cauſe
be examined, and a juſt account be caſt up, and I fear not but <hi>S. J.</hi> and his
party, will be found to have far exceeded, in giving hard words. But where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
they labour to repreſent me, as extraordinary paſſionate, and impatient,
they are moſt unfair and partial Judges in the caſe: It is known to many
that well know me, that God hath endued me with a good meaſure of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience;
and what I have born with much patience, is beſt known to God.
As for the Terms, <hi>Blood-thirſty Hounds,</hi> it is well known to many on what occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
I gave it to ſome, that accuſed me in a publick meeting, of a thing moſt
falſly, that had it been believed againſt me, tended to deſtroy my Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
Life; and I might as well call ſuch <hi>Blood-thirſty Hounds,</hi> as <hi>Fox,</hi> in
his <hi>Book of Martyrs,</hi> called ſome Papiſts, <hi>Hell-Hounds,</hi> who ſought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
the Natural Lives of ſome good Chriſtians, in the days of the Martyrs.
The man I called <hi>impudent Raſcal,</hi> I meant it in the Scripture-ſence, to wit,
as being a vile perſon; the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word <hi>Nebal,</hi> tranſlated <hi>vile perſon</hi> in our
<hi>Engliſh Bible,</hi> ſignifying properly <hi>Nebulo</hi> in <hi>Latin,</hi> and that is <hi>Raſcal</hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi>
and this for boldly aſſerting a vile Error, having ſaid before divers Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,
<hi>he did not believe to be ſaved by that which died at</hi> Jeruſalem; and moſt
unchriſtianly falling upon me, in a monthly meeting, ſaying, <hi>Doth the Spirit
ſpeak in Trees?</hi> I Having aſſerted, that God was preſent in all the Creatures,
as Trees, Herbs, Graſs, which ſome of that meeting, even Miniſters, did
diſpute againſt; and the above-mentioned Perſon, with others, urging me
moſt unchriſtianly, to promiſe an abſolute ſubmiſſion to the Judgment of
that meeting; and I not giving, they refuſed to give any Judgment in the
caſe, tho I have appealed to them: And at this Meeting <hi>S.J.</hi> was preſent;
but takes no notice of the Blaſphemy ſome of that Meeting was guilty of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
againſt both God and Chriſt; but only of ſome hard words given to one
or two men; which is a great Argument of his Hypocriſie, and that to him,
Blaſphemy againſt God and Chriſt is a leſſer offence than an hard word a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
man. Beſide, is it not great hypocriſie in <hi>S.J.</hi> to accuſe me for call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
one <hi>Raſcal</hi> who was guilty of vile Blaſphemy, whereas he called an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
Friend, <hi>viz. John Smith,</hi> ſeveral times <hi>Raſcal, Raſcally Fellow,</hi> and <hi>worſe
than an Infidel,</hi> without any Juſt Provocation, as <hi>J.S.</hi> hath declared in print.
See page. 21. of the <hi>Tryal.</hi> As for the words they alledge I ſaid, <hi>Cut me in
Collops, fry me, eat me,</hi> he is moſt unfair and partial, in not telling the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion,
which was their extreme threatning me with their Magiſtratical
Power, and ſaying, <hi>I deſerved to be puniſhed,</hi> thinking to put me in fear;
but I feeling great boldneſs and courage given me, uttered ſome ſuch words,
remembring, yea and mentioning at that very time, the like words of the
Martyr <hi>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rentius,</hi> cited in <hi>Fox</hi>'s Book of Martyrs; and why ſhould this
be ſuppoſed a Crime in me, which was judged a Vertue in him; and <hi>G.F.</hi>
in his Journal, page 86. declareth, That after ſome of the rude multitude
had beat him on his Head, Aims and Shoulders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> stretching out his Arms
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59231:14"/>
among them, he ſaid with a loud Voice, <hi>Strike again, here are my Arms, my
Head and my Cheeks.</hi> But this, according to <hi>S.J.</hi> his way of Reaſoning,
could be no perſecution that <hi>G. F.</hi> ſuffered, becauſe he ſo much deſired it,
as to bid them <hi>ſtrike again.</hi> See page 3. of <hi>S.J.</hi> his book. [<hi>Sam. Jennings</hi> doth
further bewray his great ignorance and perverſeneſs, in making it a Crime in
me, that after I had given ſome of them ſome hard words, which were but
their due, I ſhould ſay, <hi>I was like our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring
my ſelf to a <hi>Dove,</hi> a <hi>Lamb,</hi> while I thus appeared (as he alledgeth,
in a great tranſport of heat and paſſion. For are not all the Followers of the
Lord Jeſus like him, whereof I am one? And he hath not, nor can prove
the contrary, that I am not; and all his Followers are compared in Scripture
to Doves and Lambs, which may well conſiſt with great warmth of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
Zeal againſt vile Errors and wicked Practices, whereof S. J. and his party
were guilty, and of which they have ſhewed no Repentance. But ſuppoſe I
had bewrayed at that time, ſome ſinful paſſion, on great provocation, doth
that prove me, that I did not belong to Chriſt, or had nothing of the true
Nature of a Chriſtian alive in me? Surely if every ſinful paſſion unchriſtian
men, <hi>Sam. Jennings</hi> and his party, have fully unchriſtianed themſelves. But
let the Impartial judge, whether <hi>Sam. Jennings,</hi> or I, be moſt unlike the true
Chriſtian; I, for giving him and his Party only ſome hard words, or he for
not only giving me hard words, but for perſecuting me and others with Fines
and Impriſonments for matters of conſcience? It is a common obſervation,
that Woolves hunt the Sheep, but never that the Sheep hunt the Woolves;
and he that <hi>was born after the fleſh</hi> (as ſaith the Scripture) <hi>did perſecute him
that was born after the ſpirit.</hi> 8. Their reproaching, and falſly accuſing the
ſober and true-hearted Friends of our meeting at <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> which are
known by many, not only to equal, but to exceed moſt of the other ſide,
in Chriſtian Converſation, calling them <hi>Apoſtates.</hi> But that ſome of the
more looſe ſort of other Profeſſions come to our meetings, can be no fault;
for they generally come to all Friends meetings every where; and Friends
neve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> did forbid them, but rather did allow them to come, hoping they
might be benefitted by their coming, as many have been. But their calling
divers ſober and friendly people that came to our meetings, <hi>the Rabble,</hi> is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Chriſt an nor prudent; for it drove them away from their meetings;
thus acting like unskillful I i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hers, that drive away the Fiſh from the Net,
inſtead of gathering them. 9. The Inſtances I gave, mentioned by S. J. pag.
24. of their not having that infallible diſcerning they pretended to, of ones
being guilty of Drunkenneſs, another of Adultery, was in anſwer to their
falſly boaſting of ſuch an high diſcerning that ſome of them at that time
laid claim unto. But that ever I charged the Light within as not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
to give an infallible diſcerning, as is inſinuated, I altogether deny. 10. That
it is alledged by them, I called <hi>Thomas Everdon,</hi> Hypocrite, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and yet the
day before, ſaid, I had good Unity with him: that I called him <hi>hypocrite,</hi> I
own it, and have ſufficiently proved it, in that printed ſheet, called, <hi>Falſe
Judgments reprehended, and a juſt Reproof to</hi> Tho. Everdon. But that the
day before I ſaid, <hi>I had Good Vnity with him,</hi> is falſe; for I remember well,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59231:14"/>
that I ſaid, having heard him declare ſome words in the meeting, that I
owned the words, or matter of his Declaration at that time, to be true, and
had Unity with the ſaid matter; but that I had Unity with his Spirit, or ſo
ſaid, I altogether deny. And I return this, together with many other Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths,
boldly affirmed (but not at all proved) by him and them againſt me.
11. His and their alledging, <hi>that I left the Gallery,</hi> is a groſs fallacy and
perverſion; for they drove me out of it, as many can witneſs; ſo that I had
not room, nor conveniency to ſtand in it, by their preſſing me with the
ſtrength of their bodies, from the place where I ſtood in it, which ſome of
our Friends obſerving, that uſed not to ſit in the Gallery, went once or twice
into the Gallery, to keep them off from ſo preſſing me. 12. Their ſaying, <hi>I
laugh</hi>'d at the pulling down of their Gallery, is another Perverſion and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe:
The caſe was thus; One of their ſide ſaid to me, They were come to
break down my Idol, divers of them having Axes and Saws in their hand,
to break down the New Gallery, which one of them falſly called <hi>my Idol:</hi> I
replied with a ſmiling countenance, it was not my Idol. 13. Their alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
that loſing ground by my extream paſſion and ill conduct in theſe mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings,
I left them, and retired to our ſeparate meeting; which is alſo a groſs
perverſion and miſrepreſentation. [For as they firſt drove me out of the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery,
and otherwiſe groſly abuſed me in it, (many of them ſpeaking to me at
once, by way of interruption, in my peaceable Teſtimony, tho it was not
my way to interrupt them, in their Declaration, as many can witneſs) ſo at
laſt, while I ſtood on the ſtair, on the other ſide of the houſe, one of their
Church-members punched me with his Feet, which I acquainting them with,
gave ſuch diſſatisfaction to ſome ſtrangers preſent, that they were like to have
caſt him down the ſtairs, ſome crying, <hi>throw him down;</hi> ſo for Peace-ſake,
and to prevent theſe diſorders for time to come, we left the Meeting-houſe,
to which we had equal Right with them, that we might enjoy our meetings
peaceably, 14. Their alledging, That a great part of our meeting times
was ſpent in my perſonal Vindication, and in rendring Friends as odious and
contemptible as the Malice and Lies of the worſt of our Adverſaries would
have us to be, is extreamly falſe and abuſive: It was but little I ſaid in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
of my, and our Chriſtian Teſtimony; much of our time was ſpent in
ſilent waiting upon the Lord, a thing little practiſed amongſt them; and
when I, or any other declared, in our meetings, it was generally in a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinal
way, and ſometimes in way of Exhortation, without medling with
perſonal Reflections. 15. Their alledging, that the ſeveral eſtabliſhed mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings
in the 3 Provinces, have diſowned me, is a fallacy and perverſion, like
the former; for only their Faction. in theſe 3 Provinces have ſo done; but
many Friends ſtill own me in all the 3 Provinces, and have their eſtabliſhed
meetings. 16. Their ſaying, I hurried all on a ſtart for <hi>England,</hi> is alſo
falſe; for I had made it known to many long before I went away, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d
it with great deliberation, having intended for <hi>England</hi> before the ſeparation
began. And Laſtly, their charging me with great Apoſtacy, and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
Chriſt in his followers, I reject as falſe, and moſt properly belonging to
them, who have been active, ſome of the chiefeſt of them, and eſpecially
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59231:15"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in perſecuting us both with Tongue and Hands, and the reſt approving
them in ſo doing. And thus I have anſwered to moſt of the things contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in their ſaid Paper and Poſtſcript they call, <hi>The preſent Caſe truly ſtated,</hi>
&amp;c. and which was te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d at the Yearly meeting at <hi>London,</hi> 1694. But it doth
not appear, by that called, <hi>A true account of the Proceedings of the Yearly
Meeting,</hi> that they gave any great credit to it; nor do they paſs any ſuch
ſentence againſt me, as to Judge me Apoſtate, nor confirm the falſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
given cut in <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> and elſewhere, againſt me; but owned me in
Fellowſhip with them; and when I prayed at an appointed meeting, in the
upper Room in <hi>Grace-Church-ſtreet-Meeting-houſe,</hi> when many, or moſt of
the Miniſtring Friends of the Yearly Meeting were preſent, they generally
Joined with me, in being diſcovered when I prayed; which if they had
Judged me to be an Apoſtate, to be ſure they would not have done; and at
the Yearly meeting, many of the Miniſtry declared, they were refreſhed and
comforted in my Teſtimony I did bear among them, and took me kindly
by the hand after meeting; all which ſufficiently prove the Yearly Meeting
did not Judge me worthy of that Character which this ſcurrilous Paper I
have now anſwered, doth ſeem to fix on me. Yea, and after that Friends at
<hi>London</hi> had heard of the ſeparation, in their Letters to us, writing particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly
to <hi>George Hutcheſon</hi> and me, as well as to <hi>Thomas Lloid</hi> and <hi>Sam. Jen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings,</hi>
they call us, <hi>Dear Friends and Brethren,</hi> and declare their diſſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
with our denying one another, as the Letters I have to produce, do ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently
ſhew.</p>
               <p>But that they inſinuate it as a Reaſon of their not Printing againſt me,
<hi>page</hi> 24. about the middle of the page, <hi>hoping</hi> (ſay they) <hi>to have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
thereby kept this unhappy difference from being made more publick by us,
as much as in us lay, and as well aswe could.</hi> [This I proved to be a notorious
Falſhood, at the yearly Meeting, by producing a Letter of <hi>John Delawal,</hi> one
of their chief Perſons that gave out that Paper called, <hi>The preſent Caſe truly
ſtated,</hi> &amp;c. ſigned with his own Hand, which was then read; where he gives
the reaſon of their not printing againſt me, That they had not an imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
Printer, which if they had, they would have printed againſt me. His
words are expreſly theſe. <hi>If there had been an impartial Printer here, thy
ſcurrility and notorious Calumnies againſt us, who never merited it from thee,
would long e're this have been detected;</hi> the date of his Letter is <hi>Philadelphia,</hi>
2d. 11th. Month, 1692. Beſide, it is manifeſt Hypocriſie in them, to ſay,
they hoped to have kept this unhappy difference from being made more
publick by them, as much as in them lay, and as long as they could; when
on the contrary, as much as in them lay, they made it publick all ways
imaginable, (Printing excepted; and that becauſe of their prejudice againſt
the Printer) by cauſing, and in moſt Places forcing this falſe Judgment
of theirs to be read and publiſhed againſt us in all the Meetings of the three
Provinces; and ſending Copies of it far and near, to remote Places, and
over to <hi>England,</hi> which arrived before any of our printed Books; and by
cauſing a Proclamation to be read againſt me at the Market Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce; and
many other malicious and invective Papers and Letters in Manuſcripts they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59231:15"/>
ſent out againſt me to <hi>Berbadoes, Jamaica, Virginia, New England</hi> and <hi>Old
England,</hi> which I never ſaw; and as I oft told them, their manner of fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
againſt me, was like the <hi>Indians,</hi> that skulk behind T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, and ſhoot
at Men in the open Field; for moſt of their work againſt me, was by a
clandeſtine way of back-biting me, and calumniating me by falſe Stories,
Lyes and Forgeries; a moſt ſhameful Libel, and bundle of them being read
againſt me at the yearly Meeting laſt at <hi>London,</hi> without any Name to them,
at which, ſome in the Meeting ſaid, it was a ſhame that ſuch a ſhameleſs Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel
ſhould be read againſt me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="part">
               <p>XLIII. <hi>page</hi> 28. In his following Pages, from 28 to 31, for want of
Matter, he but repeateth the ſame things, formerly mentioned by him for
moſt part, and which I have ſo fully anſwered, I need not ſpend time, nor
Paper, to repeat my Anſwers to them. But that he ſaith, the two Friends
appointed from the Meeting to viſit me, <hi>viz.</hi> himſelf, and <hi>Griffith Owen,
deſired me to be preſent at the next Meeting,</hi> I utterly deny to be true; and
as he hath none to prove it to be true, ſo I have ſome to prove it to be falſe,
who were preſent ſo far as a negative can be proved, there having been three
preſent, who all declared they heard no ſuch thing, one of them being now
in <hi>England,</hi> the other two in <hi>America.</hi> My taking occaſion to be out of
Town, as alledged by him, <hi>to ſlight the Meeting,</hi> is another groſs falſhood;
for I went out of Town upon my neceſſary Occaſion, having no knowledge
either of the particular time, or place of their Meeting. His Complaint
againſt the Judgment concerning <hi>W.S. page</hi> 30. is invalid; for he refuſed
to come, being ſent for, and in Town; and beſide, the Judgment was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
moderate concerning him, they neither denying his Miniſtry, nor Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nity;
but deſiring him to deſiſt from exerciſing his Gift till he did own
his Error, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And his Complaint againſt the judgment of our yearly Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
at <hi>Burlington,</hi> is as invalid, for they had ſufficient notice by our printed
Appeal, and the Meſſengers that we ſent to them, from time to time, which
they rejected. Beſide, that at that time they neither owned our Judicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
nor we theirs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="part">
               <p>XLIV. <hi>page</hi> 30. That he ſaith, the yearly Meeting at <hi>London</hi> hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined
it, <hi>viz. That the Separation lyeth at my door;</hi> his meaning being, that
by their Judgment the only fault of it lyeth at my door, is a Falſhood and
Perverſion; for I have ſhown in my Anſwer to <hi>Tho. Elwood,</hi> that they lay
not the whole blame of it upon me, but in part, if not mainly, upon them;
ſee my Book called, <hi>A ſeaſonable Information,</hi> page 26, And what he calleth
a clear Demonſtration, done by <hi>T. E.</hi> charging me with the blame of the
Separation, I have ſufficiently demonſtrated to be no ſuch thing, but a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration
of his Ignorance, Folly and Perverſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="part">
               <p>XLV. <hi>page</hi> 31. He proceeds in ſome new Charges againſt me, ſome of
which are partly true, and partly falſe; and ſome of them utterly falſe.
1. That I ſaid to <hi>John Wilſford, Friends were not the People, but that there
muſt come another People:</hi> That I ſaid theſe expreſs words I remember not;
but if it be meant, that I did or do expect, that there will be a People rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
up, more pure then that greatly mixed People that are called by the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59231:16"/>
common Name of <hi>Quakers;</hi> and are generally known by the ſingle Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
of Thee and Thou to one Perſon; plain Habit, and other ſmall
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> called by ſome, but moſt improperly, <hi>The form of Truth;</hi> bearing
as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> proportion to the form of Truth, as a piece of the outmoſt skirt of
a Mans Garment doth to the whole Garment. I freely declare, I do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t
that God will raiſe up a purer People, than the generality that go un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
that Name; it being generally owned and lamented by the faithful
among us, that there is a great mixture among us, both of Ignorance and
evil Converſation. But when a greater Reformation cometh, I hope, and
believe that faithful Friends will ſtill belong to that more reformed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined
People, who ſhall then be found alive. 2. That I told <hi>Caleb Puſie</hi>
and others, <hi>That there were not ſix Friends in</hi> America, <hi>nor in</hi> England, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
in the whole World, that preached Chriſt aright.</hi> This I diſown as an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute
Forgery; my words were, <hi>That I knew not ſix in</hi> Penſilvania, <hi>that
preached Chriſt aright at that time;</hi> and no more I did. 3. <hi>That I had that
to preach, that was never yet preached by any</hi> Quaker. But what if I had ſo
ſaid, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> meaning any new fundamental Principle, but ſome further open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of ſome Places of Scripture, not yet underſtood perhaps by any other
among us. If this be a Crime in me, then they muſt needs judge, they
are come to the higheſt degree and top of all divine Knowledge, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
is further to be diſcovered. But who think ſo, I cannot but pitty
their great Ignorance, as well as Arrogancy and Preſumption. 4. <hi>That I
had l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſs now againſt water Baptiſm than formerly;</hi> I do not remember the
words. It is known by my former printed Books, I have been moderate
in my Judgment concerning both water Baptiſm, and the Supper, in the
outward uſe of Bread and Wine, chiefly blaming the great formality in
Mens pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tiſing theſe things, and reſting in the outward Practiſe of them;
but not univerſally judging or concluding, that God neither did, nor would
move any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y his Spirit to practi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e them, ſince the Apoſtles days; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
allowing, it might be poſſible, that ſome were or might be moved;
wherein I have the printed Teſtimonies both of <hi>John Crook,</hi> and <hi>Geo. Biſhop,</hi>
in their Treatiſes concerning Friends Principles; and alſo the Teſtimonies
of other Friends to the ſame effect concurring with me. And if I had ſo
ſaid, as is alledged, what great Offence could it be, conſidering that I did
find too many in theſe <hi>American</hi> parts, that together with rejecting theſe
<hi>Outward ſigns,</hi> have rejected the <hi>things ſignified by them,</hi> viz. <hi>the Body and
Blood of Chriſt,</hi> as being <hi>any Neceſſary matter to be believed</hi> for Juſtification
and Salvation; And I have ſaid, and ſay again, <hi>it is far better to receive both,</hi>
viz. <hi>the ſigns, and things ſignified by them,</hi> than to reject both, as ſome do.
5. That I ſaw now, that <hi>Hicks</hi> and <hi>Faldo</hi> had <hi>more Reaſon to write as they did,
concerning the Quakers; than I then thought they had.</hi> But <hi>this is an abſolute
falſhood,</hi> as laid down. It is like I have ſaid, <hi>If they had but charged only ſome
particulars, called Quakers, ſome of their charges would have proved true;</hi> for
I have found ſome of them true, to my ſad Experience; but I ever blamed
them, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that they charged theſe things <hi>univerſally,</hi> which, I know,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſome of them <hi>falſly charged upon me.</hi> 6. That
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59231:16"/>
if <hi>I ſhould appear in oppoſition to friends, I could do more hurt than all that yet
had appeared againſt them.</hi> It is a falſe and <hi>invidious charge,</hi> which I utterly
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eject and abhor; I hope I ſhall never appear in oppoſition to faithfull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ends,
nor ever was it in my heart to hurt any, nor ever, I hope, ſhall it be. But if
it be any hurt, by word and writ, to teſtifie againſt vile Errors and wicked
Practices, it is only to hurt the Devil's Kingdom. But that he ſaith, <hi>All theſe
things will be proved againſt me, if I deny them, and much more of a like tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy:</hi>
I ask him, Why hath he not now done it? For until he prove them, None
that are impartial, will believe them. Beſide, by whom will be prove them,
ſeeing he hath none but his own Party to give proof in the caſe? which, as
it is no Authentick Proof among men, ſo <hi>eſpecially not in this caſe,</hi> whom I
have ſufficiently proved partial and unfair. For his unchriſtian and unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
inſinuations againſt me, in the latter part of his page 31. grounded upon
<hi>falſhoods and perverſion,</hi> I paſs, as not worth further noticing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="part">
               <p>XLVI: <hi>page</hi> 32. He falſly inſinuates againſt me, not only that I am gone
from Truth, but that I have dealt treacherouſly with the Yearly Meeting, by
appearing in print againſt them, inſtead of ſubmitting to their Adviſe and
Judgment. [But there is nothing appeareth in that called, <hi>The</hi> Judgment <hi>of
the Yearly Meeting,</hi> as if it were their ſenſe that I am gone from Truth. And
it is a moſt falſe ſuggeſtion, that I have dealt treacherouſly with them' for I
took their Advice, in clearing Truth and faithful Friends, by what I printed:
And that I printed any thing againſt the Yearly meeting, I deny; and he
cannot prove it. But if I have printed againſt them, it could not be called
<hi>Treachery,</hi> ſeeing Treachery ſignifieth ſome breach of promiſe, or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand
dealing, none of which I am guilty of; for what I have printed, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared
before them that gave forth that Paper, that I had a mind to do it, for
clearing the Truth and my innocency.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="part">
               <p>XLVII. He groſly perverteth, and abuſeth his Reader, when he accuſeth
me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and them with me at the Yearly Meeting, that we ſhrunk from the charge,
when called upon in the Yearly meeting at <hi>London,</hi> to make it good, none of
us having courage enough to own, or ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd by that (as he calls it) malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
ſcandalous Libel, called, <hi>New England</hi>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s Spirit of Perſecution, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for
I freely declared in that meeting, That I was not the Author of all that
book; but that that part that concerned my own. Trial, was mine. But
that I charged him either with Drunkenn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs, or Riding an Horſe-Race, or
ſome other things ſimply narrated, by way of Relation in that book, as is
common in books called <hi>Tryals,</hi> &amp;c. I deny it; and he cannot prove it;
therefore I did n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſhrink from my charge; nor do I know that any of them
that were ſo concerned with me, did ſo charge him; our charge being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
him, that he had given falſe Judgment againſt us, and was guilty of
Perſecution, and acting unchriſtianly and unjuſtly towards us; which charge
we did not ſhrink from, but ſufficiently proved againſt him; and all his ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Evaſions and Quibbles have not cleared him, nor ever can clear him. Nor
do I find, that the ſaid book of the Trial doth poſitively charge him either
with Drunkenneſs or Horſe-Racing, but ſimply, as to that, narrates the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings
of the Court, how things did paſs there,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="part">
               <p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:59231:17"/>
XLVIII. <hi>p.</hi> 33. He perverſly accuſeth us, as doing neither manly nor ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly,
for not declaring who were the Authors of the reſt of that book,
becauſe ſome of us gave this for our Reaſon of our concealment, That S. J.
might take the advantage of the Law againſt them. And he querieth, <hi>Will
they, to defame a perſon, do that which ſhall ſubject them to the correction of the</hi>
Law, <hi>yet do it clandeſtinely, to avoid the ſtroke of</hi> Juſtice, <hi>and plead conſcience
and Chriſtian conſtraint for it too?</hi> I anſwer to his <hi>Query,</hi> 1. I know nothing
in all that book, that doth defame, or wrong him, if his own Actions had
not defamed him; for books that give an account of mens Trials at Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
and Aſſizes, being commonly ſimple Narratives, cannot be ſaid to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame
the Perſons tried, if they do no other but give a true Relation of things.
2. The concealing the Authors Name, or Names, was not to avoid the ſtroke
of Juſtice, but to avoid any farther occaſion of S. J. his Injuſtice, and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting
them unjuſtly; for I know not that the Authors of that book have
writ any thing in it that can juſtly, in the leaſt, ſubmit them to the correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of the Law. But we know how oft men abuſe the Law, and under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
of Juſtice, act unjuſtly, as S. J. hath manifeſtly done. But if conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
mens Names, leſt Perſecutors be gratified, be ſuch a Crime, by the ſame
Argument S. J. makes many Friends guilty, yea, many Friends of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry,
who have concealed their Names, when asked in a meeting, when
they have been declaring, when the Act of <hi>20l.</hi> for preaching in an unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
Aſſembly (as it was called) was in force: Alſo divers Friends that have
writ books of Trials, and Court-Proceedings, have concealed their Names;
witneſs <hi>W. Pen's</hi> and <hi>W. Mede's</hi> Trial: and by S. J. his falſe Logick, this
was done to <hi>defame perſons,</hi> and a doing of that which did ſubject them to the
correction of the Law, and done <hi>clandeſtinely</hi> to avoid the ſtroke of Juſtice.
But if <hi>his</hi> Logick be bad in the laſt (<hi>as doubtleſs it is</hi>) it is ſo in the firſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="part">
               <p>XLIX. He moſt falſly accuſeth me, That <hi>I knew that divers matters of
charge againſt him therein were falſe:</hi> whereupon he inferreth, <hi>that I have
finned againſt Knowledge, and ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>iouſly and premeditately abuſed him.</hi> But
his Antecedent is falſe (and he brings no ſhadow of Proof for it) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
ſo is his Conſequent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="part">
               <p>L. He moſt uniuſtly blames me, for ſpreading ſome of the ſaid <hi>Books,</hi> call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<hi>The Trial.</hi> But until he prove, that the Authors of that book have any
way wronged him, he is unjuſt in blaming me, for <hi>ſpreading</hi> of them; nor
will the <hi>ſpreading</hi> of them (if I had ſo done) intitle me to own all to be true
that is in every Line of that book; for he is ſo confident, that he hath Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed
the private Letter of <hi>Peter Boſſe,</hi> ſent to him, which was alſo printed
in the book called, <hi>The Tryal;</hi> and yet he will not ſay, that doth intitle
him to own every thing charged on him in that Letter. Therefore his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
as a man, (not to ſay <hi>his true Logick;</hi> for he is innocent of that) in <hi>this,
as in other things,</hi> hath utterly failed him; for <hi>his prejudice blinds him,</hi> and
takes away from him the uſe of <hi>his common Reaſon, as a man,</hi> as any may ſee
that <hi>is not as blind as himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="part">
               <p>LI. <hi>page</hi> 34. That he ſaith, He can prove me guilty of that called a <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar,</hi>
proves himſelf guilty of it, until he bring his proof, which yet he hath
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59231:17"/>
not done; for no man ought to be accuſed of a thing, and for a Gro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
of his Accuſation, ſay, he can prove the thing true for which he is accuſed,
and yet give no proof: for at this rate he may accuſe a man of Felony <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
Murder, and give no other Ground for his Accuſation, but to ſay, he can
prove it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="part">
               <p>LII. <hi>p.</hi> 34. He moſt impudently, and as with a Forehead of Braſs, doth juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
his calling me, <hi>an Apoſtate, and worſe than profane;</hi> all his proof being,
<hi>that it is ſo evident, that to go about to prove it, were a work of Supererrogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
But at this rate, he might have ſpared all his pains, and ſo may every one,
when his proof fails him, ſay, <hi>it is ſo evident, that to prove it, were a work of
Supererrogation.</hi> But this is meerly to trif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le, and more like a man that either
hath not common ſenſe or ſhame. But if the thing be ſo evident, that I am
an <hi>Apoſtate, and worſe than profane,</hi> how is it that the Yearly meeting hath
been ſo far from paſſing any ſuch Judgment on me, that they did not in the
leaſt forbid Friends to receive my Miniſtry, but rather recommended it to
them, to be kind to me; and moſt of the Miniſtring Friends at the Yearly
meeting at <hi>London,</hi> (as above-mentioned) joyned with me in Prayer; and ſo
have City-Friends, at ſome of the publick meetings of Friends in <hi>London.</hi>
Doth he not here grievouſly reflect on them all, as being guilty of joyning
with a man in Prayer, that is <hi>an Apoſtate, and worſe than profane.</hi> But he
hath not ſhewed, nor can he ſhew, wherein my Apoſtacy doth appear, either
in Doctrine or Practice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="part">
               <p>LIII. He is guilty of groſs perverſion, in miſconſtruing my juſt charge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
him, in my calling it <hi>Rank Popery in him and his Faction, to require an
abſolute ſubmiſſion from me, to the Judgment of their Meeting, in a matter of
Faith and Conſcience, as that was:</hi> for that it is Rank Popery, all ſincere Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants
will ſay, to require an abſolute ſubmiſſion to the Judgment of any
man or meeting, in a matter of Faith and Conſcience; for no Profeſſion in
Chriſtendom, that I know, but the Papal Church, requireth abſolute ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
to her Judgment in matters of Faith; for to require it, implies, that
ſuch who require it, think themſelves abſolutely infallible, which is another
branch of Rank Popery. Now his miſconſtruction is this, that my allowing
a conditional ſubmiſſion in the caſe, hath this ſenſe, if the Party, or Parties
like the Judgment, they will yeild to it, but not otherwiſe. But I gave him
no Ground for this groſs perverſion and miſconſtruction of my words; for
perſons may like or diſlike a thing, without any juſt cauſe. The true ſenſe
of a conditional ſubmiſſion in that caſe is, that ſo far as the Judgment of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
meeting, whereof a man is a member, is according to the Judgment of the
Spirit of Truth, (the only ſupreme Judge of matters of Faith) and the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony
of the Holy Scriptures, the greateſt outward Teſt, and Rule of
Tryal; ſo far, and no farther, is he to ſubmit to them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eing no meeting is
abſolutely, and in all caſes and reſpects, infallible, as <hi>Francis Hongel</hi> hath
well aſſerted and proved, in one of his printed Treatiſes, againſt a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
bound up with his other books, in Folio. And ſeeing S. j, hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cted
a conditional ſubmiſſion, as inſufficient, he muſt needs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute
ſubmiſſion of mens Faith and Conſcience, to the meeting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f they
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59231:18"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which, I ſay again, is Rank Popery, and a very great Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
from one of the great fundamental Principles of the People called <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi>
that hold the Light in every man's Conſcience, to be the Supreme Judg
and Rule of Judgment in matters of Religion; for it was an ordinary manner
of ſpeech among the Miniſters among us, To the Light in every Conſcience
I ſpeak; and they did not direct Friends to the Light in others without them;
for that to be ſure derogates from the ſufficiency of the Light in our ſelves, to
tell us, we muſt not believe what the Light in our ſelves convinceth us of, if
it happen to contradict the Judgment of men that call themſelves the
Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="part">
               <p>LIV. He confeſſeth, he ſaid ſomewhat to that effect, as was charged againſt
him by me, viz. <hi>That to do God's buſineſs we needed Gods Wiſdom and Power;
but to do our own buſineſs, as men, we needed it not.</hi> But he alledgeth, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert
his intention therein, wherein he falſly chargeth me; for he maketh me
put this gloſs upon his words, as if he thought we had a ſelf-ſufficiency to do
our own buſineſs, as men; he adds, <hi>I know that all our ſtrength and abilities
are from God.</hi> But as I put no ſuch gloſs on his words, ſo he ſtill equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates,
not defining what he means by Strength and Ability; for if he mean
but Natural Strength and Ability, which is alſo from God, as to <hi>eat, walk.,
&amp;c.</hi> he ſaith no more than any <hi>Pelagian</hi> will ſay. But if he mean a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural
Power and influence of the Spirit of God, to guide us in our common
affairs, he muſt recant and retract his former groſs Error. But he not only
f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lly accuſeth me, but perverteth the ſtate of the Queſtion; which was not
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s he now ſtated it, Whether there be not a greater Neceſſity to wait for it,
<hi>viz.</hi> the Power and Wiſdom of the Word of Life, to manage the outward
part of Church Affairs, than our common Affairs. But I leave it to all ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually
minded, whether even to manage our common Affairs, it be not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
to wait for the Power and Wiſdom of the Word of Life, to guide us, as
much as is po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſible for us, even at all times; and no more to be remiſs in the
one than in the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="part">
               <p>LV. <hi>page<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 36. In his excuſing his not ſubmiting to the Judgment of the
Mens Meeting, in a worldly Matter betwixt <hi>T. Budd</hi> and him, he perverts
the caſe to c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ak his Partiality, by alledging, <hi>Its improper for any Religious
Society to interrupt or alter the Will of the Deceaſed.</hi> But he hath not ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
and I ſuppoſe cannot ſhow, that that Meeting required any ſuch thing
of him; or whether that was it which was to be ſubmitted; the which if
it were, he makes to be a great reflection on the Injuſtice of the Meeting.
But if it be improper for a Meeting to require a Submiſſion, tending to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
the Will of the Deceaſed; How much more improper was it in <hi>S. J.</hi> to
require me to ſubmit my Faith and Conſcience to him, and them of that
Meeting, whereof only Chriſt and God is Lord and Sovereign? And if the
Will of mortal Man iss not to be altered, much leſs the Will and Teſtament
of our bleſſed Lord; a part whereof is to ſtand faſt in the Liberty where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th
Chriſt hath made us free, and not to ſubmit our Faith and Conſcience
to fasllible Men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="part">
               <p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:59231:18"/>
LVI. He perverts the Caſe again, in his Anſwer to that other charge, of
his refuſing to ſubmit to the Judgment of Friends at <hi>London,</hi> in the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
betwixt <hi>Edward Billing</hi> and him. 1. <hi>He ſaith he did ſubmit ſo far as
he had power, elſe, how came a Judgment to be given in the matter; against
which,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>I never heard him open his Mouth?</hi> But theſe are poor Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.
A Judgment might be given, and he not ſubmit to the Equity and
Juſtice of it; yea, he knoweth in his Conſcience, he did not ſubmit to the
Equity of it, but ſtill juſtified his Proceedings, in throwing off the Truſt
committed to him by his Maſter <hi>Edw. Billings;</hi> and that I never heard
him open his Mouth againſt it, is no Argument, he did ſubmit to the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
of it. I did not ſay I heard him open his Mouth againſt it, but others
heard him; and the thing is ſufficiently known, that he hath all along ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified
his throwing off his Truſt committed to him from <hi>Ed. Billing,</hi> and
taking a new Truſt or Commiſſion from the People. 2. That he ſaith,
<hi>the difference lay not betwixt</hi> Edw. Billing <hi>and him, but betwixt</hi> Edw. Billing
<hi>and the Province of</hi> Weſt Jerſey, is notoriouſly falſe; for it lay not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
the Province and <hi>E. B.</hi> but alſo, and that greatly, betwixt E. B.
and him. 3. Whereas he ſaith, <hi>it is falſe, that the Meeting judged him guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of betraying his Truſt to</hi> E. B. It is not enough for him to ſay it is falſe,
but he ſhould prove it to be falſe. 4. Whereas he ſaith, <hi>There is no ſuch
thing in their</hi> Judgment, which he ſaith he hath ſtill by him: Let him pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
a true Copy of that Judgment, and if there be no ſuch thing in it,
either expreſly, or to that effect, then I ſhall acknowledge, I did unadvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly
ſo charge him; but till then he muſt have me excuſed, to remain in
my ſenſe, that I juſtly charged him, having it from ſuch that I have cauſe
better to truſt, then I have to truſt him, whom I have proved guilty of
Prevarication. But ſeeing he confeſſeth a Judgment was given, it cannot
be ſuppoſed it was againſt E. B. for Friends at that time aſſiſted E. B. to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover
the Government, and to appoint a new Deputy, as accordingly he
did, and S. J. was turned out, as the general Obſervation of the Country
was. And if it was not againſt E. B. it was againſt S. J. for if it was
againſt the Province of <hi>West Jerſey,</hi> it was againſt him, ſeeing if the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince
did ill, to make S. J. the Governor, it neceſſarily followeth, he did
ill to accept of it; and he knoweth, that when he did go to purge himſelf
in the yearly Meeting at <hi>London,</hi> in relation to that Judgment, ſome that
knew well enough what that Judgment was, did oppoſe him in that reſpect.
But I did not meddle with the Merit of the Cauſe in my ſo charging him,
whether he did ill in that Affair above mentioned; only I did argue <hi>ad
bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inem,</hi> that ſeeing S. J. did refuſe to ſubmit to the Equity of that Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
in a worldly Matter, it was moſt unreasonable in him to require <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f
me an abſolute Submi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſion, in a Matter that is Spiritual, <hi>viz. Fait<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi>
For his Reflections on my worthy Friend <hi>Geo. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> I pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s
them, as not worth anſwering; for they contain nothing of any real Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
againſt him, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> railing; and I queſtion not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>G. H.</hi> can well
enough anſwer to any thing <hi>S. J.</hi> hath objected againſt him. But that he
ſath it is a notorious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nder, that he went <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:59231:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Diſunity with the moſt faithful Friends; he boldly indeed ſaith it, but
without all proof or probability. For it is much more probable, that it is
true than falſe; for he not owning the Equity of their Judgment, in ſo
far at leaſt he was in Diſunity with them, and it was not about a Trifle,
but a matter of great weight, wherein Sentence or Judgment was given
againſt him. And whereas he ſaith, he knoweth it to be falſe, and there is
not a ſillable to prove it, that the People were generally weary of his too
ſevere Government. I anſwer, it being charged on him, where the Book
was printed, <hi>viz.</hi> in <hi>America,</hi> and where he exerciſed his Government, it is
unreaſonable in him, to demand it to be proved here, as divers other
things of that Nature cannot in reaſon be demanded to be proved here.
But if it were to be proved in <hi>weſt Jerſey</hi> it ſelf, I doubt not, but I ſhould
get ſcores to aſſert it, and prove it alſo, and that ſufficiently. But in part
it can be proved here, for ſome here in <hi>London,</hi> are ready to witneſs, how
moſt unmercifully he cauſed one to whip a Friends Son, for a very ſmall
Treſpaſs; and cauſed a Man to ſell his Horſe to him, after he had ſold
him to another Man.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="part">
               <p>LVII. He groſly perverts the Caſe alſo, in excuſing his ſaying, <hi>That tho'
I denyed their Judgment, yet they would judge me;</hi> ſaying, I could not
trample upon it as falſe, before I knew what it was. For he ſpeaking theſe
words in a menacing inſolent manner, wholly unbecoming a Judge, did
ſufficiently ſhow, they intended a Judgment of Condemnation againſt me,
as the event proved; and I could expect no other from ſuch prejudiced
Perſons; therefore I ſay ſtill, I might well ſay, I did trample upon it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
being falſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="part">
               <p>LVIII. His perverſe way of reaſoning, <hi>That their Judgment of the 28th is
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rue,</hi> firſt from Friends in all Places being ſo unanimous in it. [But this
is palpably falſe, hundreds of faithful Friends in dive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Places have not
owne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it; and I know not that he can ſhew one Meeting of Friends in
all <hi>England,</hi> that doth own it, that is either monthly, quarterly, or yearly
Meeting; for the Paper called, <hi>The Judgment of the yearly Meeting at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi>
doth not own it; however, in ſome things, they blame both ſides;
yet they did not diſown me, or render me gone from truth, as the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of the 28th doth. But his ſecond Argument is as falſe and weak as
the firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> from my and our Meaſures under it. But ought we not to
be uneaſie under your Wickedneſs, and falſe Judgment, ought not the Sins of
others to be a burthen to us? Was not Criſt grieved and burdened with the
Wickedneſs and Enmity of the <hi>Jews</hi> againſt him, and were not the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
and Apoſtles grieved with the wickedneſs and falſe Judgments of falſe
Prophets and Apoſtles? Oh! how carnal and unſenſible ſeems this Man to
be, as if he had never known or felt the burden of other Mens Sins, too
great an Argument, he never duly felt the burden of his own Sins; for,
who feel the one, will, no doubt, feel the other. And how could we but
be grieved and uneaſie to ſee ſo many blinded and deceived by that falſe
Judgment given out againſt us? ſo that our Miniſtry, that formerly was
well received by them, came to be rejected; and they did what they could,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59231:19"/>
by their falſe Judgment, wholly to make void our Work and Service in the
Lords Vineyard? this, and other evil Effects, together with the great
breach it made among all the Meetings in theſe three Provin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s, that were
not broken till then, how could it but grieve and burden <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But
notwithſtanding our Griefs, we can ſay, and I do ſay for my particular,
as my Afflictions and Griefs have been great, becauſe of your fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
and the evil Effects of it, ſo my Comforts have been great, in that
God hath been pleaſed to honour me, to ſuffer ſo much for his Name ſake,
and the Name of his dear Son Chriſt Jeſus; and his bleſſed Spirit in my
Heart has oft made theſe words comfortable to me, <hi>Math. 5. 11. Bleſſed
are ye when Men ſhall revile you, &amp;c.</hi> But laſtly, how inconſiderate is
this Man in his way of arguing againſt us. Hath not he been uneaſie under
what hath been ſaid and printed by us againſt him, his Book beſpeaks it
ſufficiently; and if ſo by his own Argument, all that we have ſaid
or printed againſt him, is a true Judgment. But note Readér, that <hi>S. J.</hi>
(Papiſt like in this, as in other things) brings not his Satisfaction of the
Truth of the Judgment the 28th, gave out againſt us from the Light or
Spirit within, but from Men without; making multitude or plurality the
greateſt mark of Truth, and of the true Church, as the Papiſts do; and
by his Argument, <hi>Paul</hi> was a bad Man, becauſe not only ſome particular
Churches, but all <hi>Aſia</hi> had forſaken him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="part">
               <p>LIX. He is miſerably put to it, by twiſting, and perverting, and feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
great untruths to excuſe their endeavouring to bear us down in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious
Matters, by their Power as Magiſtrates, whereof I give an Inſtance
in Plea, <hi>&amp;c. p.</hi> 16, 17. They impoſing upon the true Liberty and Right
of the Meeting, by encouraging to read it, againſt the Mind of moſt of
the Friends preſent, it being an eſtabliſhed Act of the monthly Meeting,
as well as of divers other monthly Meetings, that nothing ought to be
read in their Meeting, without the general conſent of the Meeting. And
one of them did threaten to bind an honeſt Friend to the Peace, without
the leaſt occaſion given him, <hi>S. J.</hi> calling out for a Conſtable. 1. He
granteth that the ſaid Perſons being Magiſtrates, were at that Meeting,
though none belonged to it, as Members thereof, but <hi>S. R.</hi> 2. He argueth,
why ſhould they be ſaid to countenance the reading of it more than <hi>G. K.</hi>
and thoſe with him to diſcountenance it. I anſwer, let it be granted that
we did diſcountenance it, as much as they countenanced it, but we came
not with Magiſtrates Power, calling for a Conſtable to keep the Peace;
and we had more cauſe to diſcountenance it, than they to countenance it,
becauſe it was not read by the general conſent of the Meeting, as well as
for other Reaſons. 3. He ouerieth, where was the bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e of puting the
Paper into the Hand of <hi>W. P.</hi> he was the Clerk of the Meeting. <hi>Anſw.</hi> The
blame was to put it into his Hand, and biding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> read it without the
general conſent of the Meeting. 4. He ſaith, that the greateſt part or the
Meeting was againſt the reading of it, he cannot believe to be true, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ccord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to his Obſervation. But this doth not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>prove it, for others obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
was as good and better as his, that obſerved many more forbidding it
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59231:20"/>
than deſiring it to be read. But ſuppoſe they were the leſſer part, it is
argument enough that it was an impoſition upon their Liberty and Right,
to read it, againſt their Conſent, as is well known, through all Meetings it
is the order, that what is done be with general Conſent. 5. His reflection
on <hi>Joſeph Fiſher,</hi> charging him with heading a Party, with more Rage,
than true Zeal or Knowledge, ſeeing it is only an abuſive reviling a Man
of known Moderation, and a chief Member of that Meeting, and who kept
Meetings at his Houſe, and Hoſpitably entertained traveling Friends; I
let paſs without thinking it worthy of further noticing. 6. Take notice
Readers, his haughty and ſupercilious manner of reviling me, his words
are. <hi>But met<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inks,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>G. K. ſhould bluſh to ſtile any Man unruly and
d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſorderly, though it were true, ſince its hard to find any thing of Mankind,
(eſpecially pretending to Learning, and a civil Education) that in that reſpect
can equal himſelf.</hi> But I appeal to all impartial Readers, whether <hi>S. J.</hi> hath
not far exceeded me in hard words and Cenſures, which he conſtrueth to
be unruly and diſorderly; beſide his wicked Practiſes of Perſecution, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
And therefore by his Argument, <hi>He is not any thing of Mankind.</hi> But its
well he is not a Juſtice of Peace, or Preſident in any Court here in <hi>England,</hi>
or elſe I might know what I might expect from him, who laboureth to
render me thus invidiouſly. Is this his Chriſtianity or Civility, to make
me worſe than any thing of Mankind, as before he hath juſtified his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion,
in calling me worſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n profane. Can any thing of <hi>Bill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ngs-gate</hi>
Rhetorick exceed this of his? He grants he did enquire, if there were a
Conſtable there. Is not this proof ſufficient, they ſought to bear us down
by their Magiſtratical Power. What inſtance can be given, that ever any
Friend in a monthly Meeting called for a Conſtable? Doth not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the
Crown of Pride, and Antichriſt's Horns of Perſecution, plainly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut
he pretends it was to keep the Peace; for the Woman of the Houſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
him, under much concern, and told him, ſhe feared there would be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. And muſt a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly womans idle imagination be an excuſe to him to
do ſuch an extraordinary thing, as the like, I think, has not been known in a
Friends meeting. 9. He ſaith, <hi>Tho they did not ſtrike, yet in their r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ge, there
were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> catch at the Paper, to have torn it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> had ſo
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that they had no aſſurance, but they could</hi> fight, <hi>as
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> But that any did ſnatch at the Paper in a Rage, is
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> I, can witneſs the contrary; only one or two did civil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> their Hand on the mans Arm, deſiring him not to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> will not men get to juſtifie
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, he ſaith, but they would fight; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
and by the ſame Argument <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Meeting h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>Engl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd,</hi> to keep the Peace when
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Truth: H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w would this
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>? Laſtly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> again and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, I have already anſwered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. But the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Magistrate in that part of the Countrey, more than S. J.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> he was ſuch any where. But what difference is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59231:20"/>
                  <hi>Impudent Raſcal,</hi> (the word <hi>Raſcal</hi> ſignifying no more than what the
<hi>Engliſh Bible</hi> tranſlateth <hi>Vile Perſon</hi>) and the Term he giveth me, viz. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orſe
than profane,</hi> and to which any thing of Mankind is hard to be equall'd, let
the Impartial judge; more eſpecially conſidering I ſo termed him for his
Blaſphemy againſt Chriſt, whereof I have ſufficient Witneſs in that part of
the World: but no ſuch thing can be charged againſt me. For his denying
that he called G. J. <hi>Nonſenſical Puppy,</hi> doth not ſufficiently clear him, ſeeing
it was affirmed by two Witneſſes, both of good Credit, and one of them,
viz. <hi>Tho. Treſſe,</hi> a member of that monthly meeting at that time, and not
then diſowned by them. But his Redection on G. J. (ſaying of him, <hi>what</hi>
G. <hi>is for a Church-Member, he ſuppoſeth is well known here as well as elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where</hi>),
he had better have ſpared, G. J. not being here to anſwer for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.
But if he thought not G. J. qualified to be one of their Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,
he reflects greatly on their meeting, who admitted him to be a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
of it. But G. J. hath as many, or rather more, in that Country, that
will ſpeak well of him, as S. J. hath.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="part">
               <p>LX. His perverſion in excuſing, or clearing himſelf, of charging me, that
<hi>I</hi> ſaid, <hi>there were more damnable hereſies,</hi> &amp;c. among the <hi>Quakers, I</hi> have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently
diſcovered above; ſee <hi>Num.</hi> 39.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="part">
               <p>LXI. <hi>p.</hi> 43. His perverſion in excuſing, or diminiſhing his Fault, in ſaying,
<hi>if he draw forth his hand, he will not pull it in</hi> again, <hi>until he hath quelled us
all,</hi> is eaſily perceived. He confeſſeth, ſomething to this effect he did ſay,
which he acknowledgeth to be unadviſedly ſpoken; but why not proudly
and ambitiouſly, and that in an extraordinary manner, I appeal to all impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial
Readers, and ſenſible men, who can ſavour words, whether they rankly
ſmell not of Height of Pride, and ſavour not of great Preſumption? as if
it were in his power, as he did think, to do ſo much againſt us, in a time to
come, as would quell us all, not beleiving, or not conſidering, that no mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal
man did know what Power he had, in any time to come, and by the
Divine Providence, his Power that he gloried ſo vainly in, was taken from
him not long after. But his meaning he gives his inſolent words, ſtill ſmell
rankly both of Pride and Perſecution, as I appeal to all ſenſible and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial
Readers, if they do not, being this, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> if I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> engage, and make uſe
of the Power I have, in the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion I ſtand, I will not deſiſt, till I have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
you to a better behaviour.</hi> Note, he ſaith, <hi>I will not deſiſt:</hi> but knoweth he
that he will not deſiſt till he has reduced us to that he thinks better behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,
but that he thought his Power was in his own hand? But Soveraign Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence
taught him, he was either a falſe Prophet, or ſpake from a falſe Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;
for he was made to deſiſt from his Violence againſt us, by being turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
out of his ſtation, of Magiſtracy, wherein he gloried. And it is a plain
caſe, he continueth of that perſecuting Spirit, that if any reprove his Pride,
or other his inſolent infirmities, he will puniſh them for their ſo doing, under
the Notion of reviling Magiſtracy, if he happen to be re-inſtalled. But ſuch
as ſhall happen to re-inſtall him, will do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to adviſe him to more mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
or put ſome Curb upon him. But at this rate, many Friends, and
particularly <hi>G. F.</hi> is guilty of reviling Magiſtracy, who more ſharply and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59231:21"/>
reproved Pride and Injuſtice in ſome Juſtices of Peace here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
than ever we did his Pride in <hi>Penſilvania.</hi> And if G, F. had been li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
in the body, and been then in <hi>Penſyvania,</hi> and had but done the like to
S. J. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> muſt have expected he would have uſed him as he had done us, to
reduce him to better behaviour: See G. F. his Letter to Juſtice <hi>Sawrey,</hi> char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
him with Perſecution, Pride, Hypocriſie, p. 94. of his Journal; and his
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Letter to the Magiſtrates of <hi>Derby,</hi> charging them with Oppreſſion,
Injuſtice and Covetouſneſs, p. 51. But that he ſaith, our Friends, <hi>John Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb</hi>
and <hi>Ralph Ward,</hi> did rail and ſnarl intolerably at them, as they were go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Court to Dinner; ſeeing he tells not what that intolerable rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
was, nor gives any proof of it, may be rejected, with many other his
falſhoods, invented by him to cover his evil practices. His inſtance is not
the leaſt ſhadow of proof, that they ſaid, <hi>they thanked God they could not take
their Lives away; but they coveted their Goods.</hi> Have not our Friends here in
<hi>England,</hi> ſaid as much to Juſtices here, who have fined them, and ſtreined
their Goods, as they did to ſome of us in <hi>Penſylvania,</hi> and in particular to
<hi>W. Bradford,</hi> who being fined ſix ſhillings for refuſing to be a Jury-man, it
being a matter of conſcience to him, to promiſe in the Preſence of God, he
judging it of the Nature of an Oath, had Writing-Paper, worth 9 s. taken
from him, which was carried to <hi>Sam. Jennings</hi> his Shop to be ſold, which
<hi>VV. B.</hi> told me. Pray let the Reader judge, if this was not <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> and
<hi>Oppreſſion</hi> both?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="part">
               <p>LXII. p. 45. His perverſion, in uſing that fallacious diſtinction, given by all
Perſecutors, even the worſt ſort, Papiſts as well as others, viz. <hi>That they did
not perſecute us, but proſecuted us by Law, for our abuſes to the Government.</hi>
[His great defence is then, that we have egregiouſly tranſgreſs'd the Law, and
did endeavour to raiſe Sedition, and ſubvert the Government. And for proof
of this, he prints at large that ſcandalous Proclamation given forth by him
and others againſt me (which I have fully anſwered in Print, and ſo need
not anſwer it again here) at <hi>Philadelphia, 25th 6th mo.</hi> 1692. and the Preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of the Grand Jury againſt us. But if to indict and accuſe, be ſufficient
proof, without any other evidence, who but ſhall be guilty, tho the moſt
<hi>innocent?</hi> However, here we have him acknowledging <hi>matter of fact,</hi> which
will be of ſome ſervice to many that would not believe, that ever there was
any ſuch thing done to us in <hi>Penſyvania,</hi> as <hi>fining and impriſonment,</hi> for things
that we have always declared to be to us matters of <hi>conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="part">
               <p>LXIII. But to cloak his Perſecution, he giveth us a wrong Deſcription of
it; and I believe the general<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty of the people called <hi>Quakers,</hi> will ſay ſo:
<hi>Perſecution,</hi> saith he, <hi>is a ſuffering inflicted upon the ſufferers for the diſcharge
of their duty to God.</hi> This, I ſay, according to the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi>
and all others, that are f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r due liberty of <hi>conſcience,</hi> is a wrong deſcription of
<hi>perſecution,</hi> as being far too Narrow, as not including ſuch ſuffering as is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted
upon men, that may be in error, and hold erronious Doctrines and
Principles, it having been all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> our Plea, (witneſs what <hi>VV. Penn,</hi> and
divers ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve printed at great length, concerning the due bounds of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>conſcience,</hi> that ſeeing we live peaceably under the Government,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59231:21"/>
without doing Injury to any Man, we ought not to ſuffer, even though we
be in an Error, whether our Error relate to matters of Faith, or Practiſe.
But according to this Popiſh definition of Perſecution given by <hi>S. J.</hi> Men
ought to ſuffer for their Errors, and be whipt out of them; for to be in
Error, or to practiſe an erronious Worſhip, is no diſcharge of Mens Duty
to God; and therefore if they be puniſhed for their Errors in Principles,
or Practiſes, they are not perſecuted, but proſecuted according to Law.
And by this his Popiſh definition of Perſecution, it will be a great queſtion
with many, whether any Man called a <hi>Quaker,</hi> ever ſuffered any Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
either in old <hi>England</hi> or new, until that be out of queſtion, that the
People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> held no Errors? But according to the true deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of Perſecution, as given by <hi>W. Penn,</hi> and many others, the People
called <hi>Quakers</hi> were perſecuted by Suffering, Fining, and Impriſonment,
for not conforming to the Worſhip eſtabliſhed by Law, ſuppoſing they
were in an Error; for they who are rightly principled againſt Perſecution,
and for due liberty of Conſcience, ſay, Men are not to be whipt out of
their Errors, but perſwaded, and better informed; and if they reject due
Information, they are to be left to God, the only Lord and Sovereign over
Conſcience. The true definition therefore of Perſecution is a ſuffering in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted
upon the Sufferers, not only for the diſcharge of their Duty to God,
but for all that a Man thinks to be his Duty to God. Suppoſe he is in an
Error, if his Error be no Injury to his Neighbor, or a breach of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
called the ſecond Table of the Decalogue. And by this true defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition
of Perſecution, it is out of queſtion, that the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi>
as well as others, of other Nonconformiſts, did ſuffer great Perſecution,
even ſuppoſe they did hold Errors, and ſuffered for them, and acted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
to ſome Laws which are now aboliſhed and repealed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="part">
               <p>LXIV. In his labouring to clear himſelf and his Party of Perſecution,
and to make the World believe it was not Perſecution, but a Proſecution,
in his definition of Proſecution, which he would make applicable to us, he
falſly accuſeth us, but giveth no effectual Proof; Proſecution, ſaith he, is
a juſtice done on Tranſgreſſors of the Law, for their Injuries done to Men,
or their Blaſphemies to God; and then he concludes, that we were proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted
by Law, for our Abuſes to the Government. [But all that, that
ever was duly proved in particular againſt us, was, That <hi>Tho. Budd</hi> and I,
in a printed Paper, in our juſt defence, reprove <hi>Sam. Jennings</hi>'s Pride,
ſaying of him, he was too high and imperious in Friends Meetings, and
worldly Courts, calling him an ignorant, preſumptuous, and inſolent
Man, which laſt words did not relate to his Magiſtracy, as I have former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
declared, but to his religious Profeſſion as a <hi>Quaker.</hi> And that we que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried,
in our printed Appeal, Whether hiring Men to fight, and giving them
a Commiſſion to fight, be not a manifeſt Tranſgreſſion of the <hi>Quakers</hi>
Principle. Now if to reprove Pride, and other Sins, as Injuſtice, Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> in Magiſtrates, be an abuſe done to the Government. and worthy
of Puniſhment, then many Friends of beſt Note among us, are equally
guilty, or rather indeed more guilty, by S. J. his Argument, as G. F. who
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59231:22"/>
hath more ſeverely charged Juſtice <hi>Sawry,</hi> and the Magiſtrates of <hi>Derby,</hi>
with ſuch things, than ever we did any of the Magiſtrates in <hi>Penſilvania.</hi>
See alſo a printed Book called, <hi>The ſecond part of the Peoples ancient and juſt
Liberties,</hi> aſſerted in the Proceedings againſt, and Tryals of <hi>Francis Moor,
Richard M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w, John Boulton, Job Boltoun,</hi> and divers others, at the Seſſions
begun and held at the <hi>Old Bailey</hi> in <hi>Lond,</hi> 6th mo. 1670. where the Publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
of that Book, charge the Magiſtrates more ſeverely, than ever we did,
they ſaying, that in the ſaid Book, their Oppreſſion and Injuſtice are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted,
their Wickedneſs and Corruption detected. See alſo the Tryal of
W. P. and W. M. and the Tryal of G. W. at <hi>Norwich;</hi> and generally it
hath been the way of Friends, in their printed Books of Tryals at Seſſions,
to charge the Juſtices with Injuſtice, and Arbitrary Proceedings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And
ſeeing this was no abuſe to Magiſtracy, but their Chriſtian Complaint, and
bearing witneſs conſcienciouſly againſt Mens Sins, as holy Men of old did,
as is largely recorded in holy Scriptures, no more can it be eſteemed in us,
any abuſe to Government, to have reproved S. J. for his Pride. And as
concerning our querying, or witneſſing againſt ſome called <hi>Quakers</hi> in
<hi>Philadelphia,</hi> in our printed appeal, for hiring Men to fight; this can be no
Sedition, nor having any tendency to Sedition, or to the ſubverſion of the
Government, ſeeing it is well known, for manyyears paſt, that the People
called <hi>Quakers,</hi> have declared it to be their Principle, That it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
for them to fight, and yet the Government hath been ſo tender here in
<hi>England,</hi> that they have not charged them with being guilty of Sedition, or
ſubverſion of the Government, for aſſerting any ſuch Principle; and the
like tenderneſs and moderation have the States of <hi>Holland</hi> ſhewed to the
<hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſte</hi> there, who are a great People, and have publickly aſſerted it to
be their Principle, (as well as the People called <hi>Quakers</hi> here) neither to
fight, nor to ſwear; yea, and learned <hi>Grotius,</hi> who hath writ a learned
Treatiſe, <hi>de jure belli, &amp; pacis,</hi> reckoneth it at leaſt among the Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
Counſels, (which any Man may lawfully obey) not to fight, or make
War. Is it not therefore a very ſtrange thing, that a Juſtice of Peace in
<hi>Penſilvania,</hi> and others of his Party, ſhall make that to be Sedition, or a
ſubverſion of the Government there, <hi>viz,</hi> our publickly aſſerting it to be
our Principle not to fight, and yet the Government here to charge nothing
upon us but to be tendet to us in that reſpect, as well as in other things of
Non-conformity. Doth not this ſhew an extraordinary height of Ambition
in them, as well as degeneration from their former Principle? and will it
not too much confirm the Jealouſie that ſome have had, that if the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
ſhall happen to come into the hands of ſome of that People called
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, they will perſecute others for Conſcience ſake, although they have
cried out againſt their being perſecuted for Conſcience ſake, unleſs ſome
publick Teſtimony be given forth againſt theſe ſevere, and unfair Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
of theſe Men againſt us in <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> and that by ſome ſolemn de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration
in print, given forth in behalf of that People.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="part">
               <p>LXV. His Perve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ion in bringing his and their moſt illegal and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
Proclamation againſt me, which they cauſed to be read at the Market
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59231:22"/>
Place by the common Cryer; and after that, poſted it up both in Town
and Country, as a proof of my being guilty, of endeavouring to raiſe Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,
and to ſubvert the Government. Certainly, if this Man were not
paſt all fear or ſhame, he would not have dared to print ſuch an illegal
and ſcandalous Paper, that makes ſo much againſt him, and expoſe it in
the face of the World, the which I having ſo fully anſwered in Print, to
the ſeveral Falſhoods, Fallacies, and Perverſions in it, I ſhall not now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat;
only I think fit to notice one particular, that doth ſufficiently ſhow
their illegal, unjuſt, and Arbitrary Proceedings, that whereas they ſay, <hi>It
hath been proved before them, that</hi> G. K. <hi>being a Reſident there, did, contrary
to his Duty, publickly revile the ſaid Deputy-Governor.</hi> [Note Reader, they
ſay, <hi>It hath been proved before them, &amp;c.</hi> But they fallacionſly omit to tell,
that I was not called before them, to have that, or any other thing proved
againſt me, but that they did, was altogether in my abſence, in and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
the leaſt Summons, Call, or Citation to come before them, at that
they call their private Seſſions, (which may rather be called a private Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy
to ſubvert Law and Juſtice) though I was known to be at home in
the ſame Town. And whereas they have called two other Juſtices of Peace,
<hi>viz. Lacy Cock,</hi> a Lutheran, and <hi>John Homes,</hi> a Baptiſt, to connive with
them in this work of Darkneſs, <hi>viz.</hi> to proclaim me at the Market Place,
a Perſon ſo highly Criminal, without all Conviction, or calling me before
them, to hear any thing proved againſt me, theſe two Juſtices aforeſaid,
acting like men of Conſcience, as well as Underſtanding what was legal,
refuſed to joyn with them, in ſigning ſuch a Proclamation, becauſe it was
done without any Conviction, or legal procedure. But they deſired I might
be called for, and legally convicted; and if I were found guilty, they
ſhould joyn with them, to puniſh me accordingly. But this not being
granted, without them, they gave forth that ſcandalous Proclamation
againſt me; and I appeal not only to all Perſons called <hi>Quakers,</hi> but to all
others, who may hear or read concerning this Matter, and eſpecially to all,
that are in the leaſt acquainted either with the Engliſh Laws, or with the
Law of Nations, whether their thus proceeding againſt me, be ſo ſevere a
Penalty, as to proclaim me, at the Market Place, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> a Perſon ſo highly
Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, without all Conviction; and whether to take the Evidence of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> againſt me, in my abſence, without any call to be preſent, is not
wholly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and contrary to the fundamental Laws of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="part">
               <p>LXVI. <hi>page</hi> 46. His Perverſion in making the preſentment of the Grand
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> at <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> an Evidence or Proof againſt <hi>Th. Budd,</hi> and me, of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> being guilty of reviling the Magiſtrate, and endeavouring to raiſe Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,
an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſubvert the Government, and to do this to his own ſhame, and
as an inſtance of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, he prints the Preſentments of the ſaid Grand
Jury againſt <hi>T. Budd</hi> and me, and againſt W. <hi>Bradford,</hi> ſee his page 52.
Now let us ſee, how unlike a Magiſtrate, or a man of common Senſe, he
doth argue. The Grand Jury hath preſented us to be guilty of reviling S. J.
being a Magiſtrate, therefore we are guilty. But if this be a true concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
without any further proof, then it follows by the ſame Argument,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59231:23"/>
that what ever any Grand Jury preſents a man to be guilty of, that man is guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of the ſame; and if ſo, there is no room left for any further Tryal of a
Petty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ury; which is another perverſion of the fundamental Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
But why S. J. is wholly ſilent of the Verdict that the Petty Jury gave
in the caſe of <hi>Th. Budd</hi> (I having pleaded in the Court, that I was not preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble,
being my only Plea, the thing being No Nuſance to the County, nor
Offence againſt the Government, they fined me, without any more a-do) is
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>afie to conjecture, their Verdict not being any Verdict againſt <hi>Th. Budd,</hi> in
the Terms or Words of the Preſentment, but a ſpecial Verdict in theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
words, viz. <hi>That</hi> Thomas Budd <hi>was guilty of ſaying</hi> Sam. Jennings
<hi>had behaved himſelf too highly and imperiouſly in worldly Courts.</hi> But this was
no proof that <hi>T. B.</hi> was guilty of reviling Magiſtracy, more than the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
Verdict of the Jury at the <hi>Old Baily,</hi> that <hi>W. P.</hi> was guilty of ſpeaking in
<hi>Grace-Chuack-Street,</hi> was any Verdict againſt him, of being guilty of a Riot,
Rout, or unlawful Aſſembly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="part">
               <p>LXVII. <hi>p.</hi> 54. His perverſion, in blaming me, and ſome others Joyned
with me, in our expoſing their defects (if they were ſo) to the world before
ever we had ſpoken to the Parties thus abuſed by us, as he phraſeth it. But
for anſwer, what he calleth, <hi>our expoſing their defects,</hi> was but in the juſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
of our <hi>Innocency and Chriſtianity,</hi> which he, and 27. unjuſt Judges, had
endeavoured to rob us of, by expoſing to the world, tho not in print, yet pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly
enough otherwiſe) their falſe Judgment againſt us, and cauſing it to
be read in all the Meetings, not only in the Province of <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> but in
the Meetings of the Neighbouring Provinces. And it is falſe, that we had
not ſpoke to them; for we had made our complaint, and ſhown our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like,
at a monthly meeting at <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> where they read their Falſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
againſt us, and at ſeveral other Meetings, before we printed a line a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
them; but received no Redreſs, but abuſive language: And herein
we have done but what many other good and worthy men have done, in the
like caſe, when oppreſſed, and they could have no Remedy, Printing being
the laſt Remedy. And this Remedy hath been uſed by many Friends of
good Account among us, who having been oppreſſed, and unjuſtly dealt with
by Juſtices of Peace, have expoſed their Injuſtice in print to the world, ſome
of their books having this Title, <hi>The Cry of the Oppreſſed.</hi> Nor can this be
called, the expoſing of our brethrens weakneſs; for they had denied us to
be their brethren, before either the book called, <hi>The Plea of the Innocent,</hi> or
the <hi>Appeal,</hi> or the book called, <hi>The Tryal,</hi> was printed; and they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun
the Separation, and refuſed and rejected all Goſpel-Order, before we e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
printed a line againſt them; therefore <hi>Sam. Jennings</hi> his words in p. 54.
I may juſtly retort upon himſelf, which touch not us: What <hi>conſcience</hi> is in
this (for him to fill his book with ſo many falſhoods, forgeries and perverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons)
I leave to any, but a feared conſcience, to determine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="part">
               <p>LXVIII. His perverſion, in taking great pains to prove, that ſome part of
my worhs did reſpect his Magiſtracy; and that therefore <hi>I</hi> am guilty of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling
his Magiſtracy. Now the part of my words which he laboureth to
prove did reſpect his Magiſtracy, was, <hi>That he had behaved himſelf too high and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59231:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
imperious, both in friends Meetings, and worldly Courts.</hi> And will this prove,
that I reviled Magiſtracy, any more than that he who writ <hi>W. Pea's</hi> and <hi>VV.
Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi>'s Tryal, which ſome ſay, was W. P. himſelf, was guilty of reviling
Magiſtracy; or that Friends, who have been oppreſſed and injured by proud
and oppre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſive Magiſtrates, in former times, that have charged them in print
both with Pride and Perſecution? or will it follow, that the true Prophets
were guilty of reviling Magiſtracy, becauſe they did witneſs publickly againſt
Pride and Oppreſſion in Judges and Rulers in former days? Surely theſe
men in <hi>Penſylvania</hi> were come to an extraordinary height of Ambition, to
think, that their place of Magiſtracy had raiſed them up ſo high, as to be above
all Reproof, or witneſſing againſt their Pride, Injuſtice and other ſins, when
many, far greater in Authority here in <hi>England,</hi> have born all that, and much
more than we have ſaid againſt them in <hi>Penſylvania,</hi> without the leaſt noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
it by ſuch ſeverity; a great ſhame to ſuch men, who pretending to be
Teachers of others in the great Chriſtian Duties of Patience and long-ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
ſhould fall ſo ſhort in the practice of it, beneath many who make not
ſo high Profeſſion. And it is but a poor excuſe and evaſion for him, or any
other, that may be ſuppoſed to have aſſiſted him in this Work, to ſay, as he
or they do, p. 45. <hi>In the Infancy of the ſettlement of</hi> Penſilvania, <hi>the</hi> Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors
<hi>ſaw cauſe to make proviſion,</hi> by a Law, <hi>to ſecure the Reputation of the
Magiſtrates from the contempt of others; foreſeeing, no doubt, (and perhaps per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving
ſomething of it then) that people, by reaſon of their equality in other
things, might be under greater tentations, to run into this evil there, than where
the condition of the Magiſtrates had raiſed them above, and ſet them at a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
diſtance from the common people: It was therefore enacted</hi> (ſaith he), <hi>That
whoſoever ſhould ſpeak contemptuouſly, or ſlightingly of a Magiſtrate, ſhould
be puniſhed by a fine, according to the Nature of the Offence.</hi> [But was this
conſideration enough to raiſe the Magiſtrates in <hi>Penſylvania,</hi> ſo far above
their Brethren, who are otherwiſe not only equal to them, but ſome, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps,
far above them, that tho a man do ever ſo conſcientiouſly reprove their
Pride, Injuſtice and Oppreſſion, in caſe ſuch a thing happen, as is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible,
he muſt not do it; otherwiſe he muſt be puniſhed, as a reviler of
Magiſtracy? Were it not much more adviſable, that the Magiſtrates in <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſylvania,</hi>
did labour to excel and exceed all others in that Province, in all
Chriſtian and civil Vertues, who are otherwiſe equal to them, than <hi>Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bna-</hi>
like, to grave them out an habitation, in ſo high a Rock, that <hi>no Man</hi> dare
reprove them, tho ever ſo conſcientiouſly, or having ever ſuch juſt cauſe ſo to
do; ſuch Height was the fore-runner of S. J. and his Brethrens <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lly, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
ſoon after driven out of their ſtation, as God threatned <hi>Shebna, Iſa.</hi> 22.
16, 19. And if they happen to be promoted again, they will do well to
behave themſelves more moderately and Chriſtianly. To revile Magiſtracy,
I acknowledge, is a great ſin, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the reproving of Pride and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice
in a Magiſtrate, when he is not in the publick diſcharge of his Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy,
(as ſitting in the ſeat of Juſtice) eſpecially, is no reviling of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy,
ſo far as I can learn, either out of the Law of God, revealed in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59231:24"/>
or any Laws of <hi>England,</hi> or other Nation, profeſſing Chriſtianity, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</p>
               <p>But why were they ſo partial, and ſhewed ſo great Zeal for their own
Honour, and ſo little for the Honour of God and Chriſt, that they made a
Law to fine a man that ſpake ſlightingly of a Magiſtrate, to any ſum they
pleaſe, provided it b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not leſs than 20 s. (and for our ſuppoſed Offence, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
us each five pounds); but for Bleſphemy againſt God and Chriſt, as
blaſphemous Oaths, and Cur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ings, their Law was not above five ſhillings:
And it is but a poor excuſe for this inequality, given by ſome, that blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
curſing and ſwearing might be ſo common, that had the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w exacted
a great fine for every guilty perſon, they would not have been able to pay it.
But then might not the Legiſlators have made a Law to put them to ſome
corporal puniſhment, or to work in the Houſe of Correction, for ſuch a
time, as their Law is in other caſes? But that <hi>Sam. Jennings</hi> was gui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty of
Pride, and too great height of Spirit, in his Proceedings againſt us, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
called, <hi>An Account of the Proceedings,</hi> &amp;c. is an evidence; therefore to
call him ſo, was no reviling.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="part">
               <p>LXIX. His perverſion, in ſlighting, and ſeeking to make void the Certificate
given me from the Deputy Governour and Council of <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> clearing
me of all theſe charges, amply declaring my <hi>Innocency,</hi> and peacea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour
towards the Government, and them in Authority at that time: <hi>VVho
is it</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that doth not know the propenſity that commonly appears (on any
turn or change) in thoſe that ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ccced in place aud power, to cenſure and exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe
ſuch as were before under the ſame charge,</hi> &amp;c. Hence he concludes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eir
Certificate will not do me <hi>much ſervice, nor weigh much with thinki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g people.</hi>
[Now I appeal to impartial Readers, if this be not a ſpeaking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the
preſent Magiſtrates there, (for which S. J. by his own Argument. ought to be
puniſhed) and poſſibly now in <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> as well as a ſevere Reflection on
them, of their Injuſtice, Partiality, yea and diſloyalty, to give me a Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate,
clearing me of any ſuch Crime laid to my charge, as endeavouring
to raiſe Sedition, aud ſubvert the Government in <hi>Penſilvania;</hi> for what is
this, but to ſay, that the Magiſtrates then in Truſt with the Government,
hath cleared a guilty perſon from an heinous Crime, affecting the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?
for it is an Act of as great Injuſtice, and Male Adminiſtration of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
to acquit and clear the guilty, as to condemn the <hi>innocent.</hi> But
he is fallacious in this alſo, that he inſinuates, <hi>theſe that gave m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate,
aid ſucceed him and his party in the Government;</hi> whereas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me of them,
and particularly <hi>Robert Turner,</hi> who ſigned to my Certificate, was then in
the Government, as well as S. J. and did publickly witneſs againſt their unjuſt
proceedings, as well formerly as ſince.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="part">
               <p>LXX. His pervertion and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llacy, to make void his Crime of perſecution,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>what did he, or</hi> Thomas Budd <hi>ſuffer?
were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> them whipped, or impriſoned? No ſuch matter. They
were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Court; were adjudged guilty, and had
a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> let upon them, which was never levied; for which, if they
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, they onght to acknowledge the clemency of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59231:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and particularly ſuch as might have exacted it.</hi> [But it was a great
ſuffering, thus to expoſe us in the face of the Court, and of both Town and
Countrey, as ſo heinouſly guilty, to defame us, being <hi>innocent perſons;</hi> and
tho we were not impriſoned, yet our Two Friends, viz. <hi>W. Bradford</hi> and <hi>John
Macomb,</hi> were moſt unjuſtly impriſoned, and ſome of W. B. his Utenſils,
detained from him; and W. B. was preſented npon a Statute in <hi>Old Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
That no book ſhall be printed without the Printer's Name to it;</hi> And tho
his Defence was, <hi>That moſt of Friends books were printed without the Printer's
Name to them;</hi> yet their partiality was ſuch, they did not regard it: And
that our fine was not levied, we owe no thanks to them, who paſſed that falſe
Judgment againſt us (<hi>their tender mercies,</hi> as the Scripture ſaith of ſome <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
cruel</hi>), but to <hi>Divine Providence, that reſtrained them for a little ſeaſon;</hi>
and the fear that poſſibly they were under, leſt both the generality of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
of Town and Country ſhould cry out, <hi>ſhame, ſhame upon them,</hi> ſtill more
loudly, who had already concluded them to have dealt unchriſtianly towards
us; and after ſome little ſeaſon, their Power was taken from them. But
their moſt cruel detaining our Friend <hi>Peter Boſſe,</hi> in priſon, for his fine, until
they were put out of their power, doth ſufficiently ſhew it was no <hi>Clemency
in them</hi> to <hi>Th. Budd</hi> and me, that reſtrained them from levying our
fines.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="part">
               <p>LXXI. His Perverſion in telling a Story, <hi>pag.</hi> 35. That ſome in <hi>weſt
Jerſey</hi> heard me ſay, that they ſhould hear, before it was long, that I were
either whipt, or impriſoned, and rather than I would appear a falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,
I did what I could to procure it. [But that I did Propheſie any ſuch
thing, is a groſs Forgery; or that I did in the leaſt do any thing to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
it; but it is probable I might ſay to ſome, by way of probability, they
would hear ere long, I were either whipt or impriſoned; which I ſpoke
not in the leaſt by way of Propheſie, but of ſtrong probability, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the Cruelty that appeared in them, againſt ſome of my Friends, whom
they impriſoned, their Rage being greater againſt me, than them, but Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence
hindred them to execute all that was in their Hearts. And what
leſs could be expected from S. J. who for a ſmall default of a poor Boy
that did throw a little Dirt or Earth at a Conſtable, cauſed him to be whipt
moſt cruelly at <hi>Burlington</hi> in <hi>weſt Jerſey,</hi> with thirty five laſhes on the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
Body, with a Horſe-whip, and cauſed to put the Boys Maſter in the
Stocks, for calling him, the ſaid S. J. <hi>Prick-louſe-Taylor;</hi> this an honeſt
P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſon of good Credit here in Town, who ſaw it, and was one that begged
S. J. to ſhew mercy to the poor Boy, is ready to witneſs, a ſufficient Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
of his too ſevere Government in <hi>weſt Jerſey.</hi> And many having
begged S. J. who was then Governor, for the poor Boy, as well as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gged moſt lamentably for mercy, he being a Friends Son, yet he
would not be entreated. And alſo conſidering the new Preſentments gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
in againſt me, being about ſeven in number, which were read at the
yearly Meeting l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt at <hi>London,</hi> with my Anſwers to them, divers of which
were ſuch, as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> charged in the ſaid Preſentments, had I been
guilty, deſerved not only Impriſonment, but other corporal Puniſhment;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59231:25"/>
and which probably enough might have reached to ſentence of Death
againſt me, had not their moſt cruel Deſigns been diſappointed by the
merciful Divine Providence, conſidering the cruel minds that they gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
had againſt me; and that their Juries, both grand and petty, were
ſuch, as we know to be prejudiced; and many of which had ſigned to
falſe Judgments againſt me, in their Mens Meetings. But whereas he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth,
<hi>p.</hi> 55. That I called <hi>Tho. Lloid</hi> pittiful Governor, I remember no
ſuch thing; and he giving no proof of it, but his bare ſay ſo, the impartial
Reader will not believe it. But that I ſaid, my Back itched for their
Whip, I own I ſaid ſo, in a publick Meeting, on a firſt day, after
they had interrupted me, in my Chriſtian Teſtimony, and did moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily
threaten me, with their magiſtratical Power, I appeal to all
who know, what godly Zeal hath moved men to, whether I might not
ſay theſe words, in a Chriſtian Spirit, implying no more, but a deſire to
ſuffer for Righteouſneſs ſake; to which Chriſt hath pronounced a <hi>bleſſing,</hi>
as well as what <hi>Lawrence</hi> the Martyr ſaid to the Tyrant that perſecuted
him, when he cauſed to roaſt him on a Grid-Iron, for which ſaying he was
greatly commended. He bid him turn up the other ſide, the former being
roaſted enough, to ſee which was the beſt Meat: (Perſecutors in Scripture
being compared to Man-eaters) and what G. F. ſaid, as above noted, to a
man that ſtruck him cruelly, ſtrike again; and what <hi>Edw. Burrough</hi> ſaid
and writ in Lines, to his Perſecutors, <hi>Our backs are ready for your blows;</hi>
and many other ſuch bold Expreſſions that godly Zeal, and holy boldneſs
hath moved many better than I, to give to threatning Perſecutors: Yea,
did not our Savior ſay to <hi>Judas, what thou doſt, do quickly.</hi> But it ſeems
S. J. was never acquainted with any flame of holy Zeal, to ſuffer for Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs
ſake, his Zeal being to perſecute, but not to be perſecuted for
Righteouſneſs ſake. However, I have never juſtified all the words I have
ſaid to there my Adverſaries, but readily have granted, that it's poſſible I
have at times exceeded, on great Provocation. But S. J. and his Parties
Hypocriſie is great, who not only have far exceeded me in hard words,
but made it their work (as is well known) to provoke me exceſſively.
But my gracious God, for which, and for all his many Mercies, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances,
I deſire to praiſe him, hath preſerved me, as to the main; and
my great comfort is, that whatever human weakneſſes have attended me
as to ſome Circumſtances, which have been greater on their part, my cauſe
and ground of de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>te againſt them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in bearing Teſtimony againſt their
vile <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> held by ſome of them, and cloaked by others o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them, and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wicked Pract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſes of Perſecution and Injuſtice) is good, and with a
ſince<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and upright Heart, as to the main, I have managed it, and I have
P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce from my gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cious God in ſo doing, as well as a ſenſe of his pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Mercy wherein I have failed in ſome particular Circumſtances; and this
is more than ever any of my Adverſaries that I know have acknowledged;
who, proud Phariſee like, do juſtifie themſelves, But whereas S. J. hath
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to charge me more than once, with acting againſt my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
I declare ſincerely and ſolemnly, it is a groundleſs Calumnly.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:59231:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
As for his Anſwer to <hi>Peter</hi> B<hi>oſſe</hi> his Letter, I could ſhow ſeveral groſs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varications
in it; but having encreaſed my Anſwer to a far greater bulk al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
than I intended, I think to ſay little at preſent to it, reſerving a more
full Anſwer to another opportunity, if need be, or to <hi>Peter</hi> B<hi>oſſe</hi> himſelf, to
whom it is moſt proper to give the Anſwer; but he being abſent in <hi>America,</hi>
his anſwer at preſent cannot be expected; only I deſire the Reader to
notice theſe following Particulars. 1. <hi>S. J.</hi> takes no other way to clear
himſelf of <hi>P. B.</hi> his charging me with an unſavory Life, (expreſs'd by his
unſavory carriage and words to his Neighbors, equal or ſuperior to himſelf,
at leaſt ſome of them; as when he ſaid to <hi>John S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n,</hi> who had been Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor
of <hi>weſt Jerſey,</hi> and was then in the Magiſtracy, <hi>Thou pittiful whip Jack,
I diſpiſe thee;</hi>) but by charging him in general, without mentioning any
particular matter of Fact. 2. Let it be conſidered; whether it was fair or
orderly in S. J. ſo to purſue P. B. he being a Church Member with him,
and not at that time denyed or diſowned by them, to ſue him in open
Court, for a private Letter ſent to him, to the publick ſcandal of his and
their Profeſſion; and gratifying Adverſaries, who would, and did ſay, <hi>See
how Quakers go to Law with Quakers, contrary to their Profeſſion and Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi>
Nor doth his evaſion excuſe him, that he, <hi>viz.</hi> P. B. was one of my
Party, and denyed together with me. But this is barely alledged, and
not proved; he belonged to <hi>Burlington</hi> Meeting in <hi>weſt Jerſey,</hi> and had not
that I know, been at any of our Meetings falſly called ſeparate Meetings, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
that time, but was generally owned by Friends of that Meeting he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed
to. And his other evaſion is as weak, That the Paper or Letter
came to him open. Doth that prove, that he ſent it open? Or if he had
ſent it unſealed, was that ſuch a Crime, to query into ſuch things as Men
have re-printed of one another, and that in a Neighbourly way. 3. For
his being drunk, and running a Horſe-Race, it was not poſitively charged
on him, but queried; and was, by the manner of Evidences, brought
againſt him by ſome honeſt Perſons, being compared with the negative
Evidence of one ſingle Man, (whom I own to be an honeſt man) I leave it
to be weighed, by the Readers, which has moſt probability. 4. As for his
clearing himſelf of Surveying a Tract of Land, that <hi>John Antrum</hi> had actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
began to do; and of his taking away the Meadow of <hi>Rich. Mathews,</hi>
he but poorly and lamely comes off. Its well known in <hi>weſt Jerſey,</hi> that
<hi>John Antrum</hi> complan'd greatly on S. J. for his ſo doing; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> defence
about <hi>Rich. Mathew</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dow, is more ſophiſtical than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; ſaying, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
it was ſurveyed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>R. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> or it was not; if it were, then he has it.
[But how has he it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> S. J. hath ſold, or may hereafter tell it to
ſome other Perſon? It<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s well known of what ill fame it is, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
great Injuſtice, to ſurvey another Mans Land, and ſo to appropriate it to
him. And for his exception againſt the Record of the Survey by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
it is idle and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>illy. It is ordinary in Surveyes in that Country, where no
ſuch exactneſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> commonly uſed, (as here in <hi>England,</hi>) and when large
allowance is given for barren Land, and high ways, to mention a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all
guſhet of Up-land, or Meadow, without telling the cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e or di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ance, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59231:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
it lyeth adjoyning to a greater Tract, more particularly ſurveyed. And
were all ſuch Surveys made void of ſmall guſhets, and pieces of Meadow,
or Up land that have not the courſe or diſtance particularly mentioned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing
to that part, it would make a great Confuſion in many Surveys in
that Country, and perhaps might give occaſion to have ſome of his Land of
Meadow to be queſtioned. But it's not a new thing for S. J. to pretend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
skilful in what he is groſly ignorant of. 5. For his Abuſes done to <hi>John
Shen,</hi> aud eſpecially his baſe and ſcurrilous reviling him, as above mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
being then a Magiſtrate, is ſo well known, that I think S. J. hath
ſcare the Confidence to deny the unſavory Expreſſion he gave him, and
which was mentioned in the book of the Tryal. 6. For his blaming me,
that I enqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed at <hi>John Shorum,</hi> about S. J. his being drunk, I appeal to
the Readers, what blame could this be in me, ſo to enquire, I having heard
it commonly reported. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> if <hi>John Shorum</hi> denyed it to me, having affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
it to others, it was little to me, whether he did affirm it or not, I made
no matter of it, and ſaw no need to give Evidence in the Caſe, for it
would have ſignified nothing to clear him; and I heeded little what J. S.
ſaid in the Caſe, for what I ſpoke to him, was meerly occaſional, as I
hapned to meet him on the way. 7. What S. J. doth alledge, that <hi>Robert
Cole</hi> told me, he knew no ſuch thing by S. J. as that he was drunk at his
Houſe, and ſpewed in the Bed, I declare is a falſhood; it's true, he ſaid
(<hi>viz. R. Cole</hi>) that he was drunk; but that he ſaid he knew no ſuch thing
by S. J. I remember not in the leaſt; but on the contrary, both I and my
Wife do well remember, that he ſaid, the thing he had ſaid to <hi>Peter Boſſe</hi>
was true, but he blamed his being drunk, that made him ſpeak ſo freely;
(as commonly Men will be more free to reveal a matter when drunk;) but
ſaid <hi>Cole,</hi> I dare not appear a Witneſs againſt S. J. he being a Magiſtrate,
for he will ruine me; and this I ſincerely declare, to the beſt of my Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
and Rememberance. And laſtly, as to his ſevere uſage towards his
Servants, and eſpecially towards his Maid, whom he moſt cruelly whipt
in Bed, with a Horſe-whip, is moſt true, and is ſufficiently proved againſt
him in the Book of the Tryal, as to the firſt part, witneſs the printed Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies
of <hi>John Smith,</hi> and <hi>James Silver</hi> againſt him. And as to that of
his moſt unmerciful, and obſcene way of beating his Maid Servant, an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
Friend here in Town, declareth he had it from the Maids Mother, and
the Maid her ſelf hath declared it to divers.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:59231:26"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>AND thus I have fully anſwered to all that ſeemed any way material in
his Charges in his book againſt me, and my Friends, paſſing by ſeveral
other things not worth noticing, of his falſe charges, and poſſibly ſome may
think I have mentioned too many, and taken too much time and paper to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
them, being in more general and ſubdivided Heads, under the more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
Heads, above an hundred in all; but having thus for once beſtowed ſo
much time, paper, labour and coſt to clear me of theſe falſe charges</hi> T. E. <hi>and</hi>
S. J. <hi>have laboured to beſpatter and defame me with, it is poſſible, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable 
alſo, (tho I come under no tye in the caſe that I may let them Anſwer)
again, and bark on, till they be weary, without much noticing them for time to
come; for indeed any further debate in print touching theſe matters, ſeems to
me, and I judg, will to many, but little profitable to the Readers; The things
for most part charged and recharged, being of words and tranſactions alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to have been ſaid or done in</hi> Penſilvania, <hi>or other parts of</hi> America, 
<hi>and the Evidences on both ſides being confeſſedly Parties, which are no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
witneſſes in theſe things, as I declared at the Yearly Meeting laſt at</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,
<hi>1694. Nor did I any further make uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Evidences of that ſort, but
to make a Ballance againſt the Evidences of their ſide and party, my Eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
being fully as Credible perſons as theirs, yea and more Credible, becauſe I
have diſproved ſome of their Evidences, by their contra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ictions one to another,
and other clear circumſtances! But that which, as to the main, caſts the
ballance, as I declared at the Yearly Meeting laſt at</hi> London, <hi>was the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcripts
of my oppoſite party, under their own hands, which I have to produce
at large, and which, as I ſee great occaſion for may be made publick. But
how little, or indeed, nothing to the purpoſe,</hi> Sam. Jennings <hi>hath waſhed
himſelf clean, of the dirt, not that we have thrown on him, but what he hath
daubed himſelf with, I leave to impartial Readers to Judg, and whether
his Labour to clear himſelf of it, be not with as little ſucceſs, as if an</hi> Ethi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opian
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59231:27"/>
               <hi>would labour to waſh himſelf white. If any place were for my Advice
to him, the best way for him to clear himſelf of theſe things, is to repent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely
of his Falſhood, Hypocriſy, Pride and Spirit of Perſecution, and all other
his great ſins, that are too too manifeſt, however h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeeks to cover them, and
however ſome here in</hi> England <hi>that have eſpouſed his unrighteous cauſe,
ſeek to cloak him. And as for his Certificate which he hath received from
his Party and Aſſociates that are guilty with him in many of the things charged
against him; I judg no impartial Readers will think it of any weight; and
to counterballance it, I could produce a more full and ample Certificate to clear
me, ſigned by thrice as many Hands, and Perſons generally of as good, and
many of better Credit, as any that have ſigned to his. But Certificates from
Parties ſignify little; and when a mans own words and actions cry aloud that
he is guilty, paper Certificates can never have that force to make him innocent.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>George Keith.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Levis,</hi> 1694.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59231:27"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
