<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christian Quaker: or, George Keith's eyes opened Good news from Pensilvania. Containing a testimony against that false and absurd opinion which some hold, viz. that all true believers and saints, immediately after the bodily death attain to all the resurrection they expect, and enter into the fullest enjoyment of happiness. And also, that the wicked, immediately after death, are raised up to receive all the punishment they are to expect. Together with a scriptural account of the resurrection of the dead, day of judgment, and Christ's last coming and appearance without us. Also, where, and what those Heavens are into which the man Christ is gone, and entred into. By George Keith.</title>
            <author>Keith, George, 1639?-1716.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-12">2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47131</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K153</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219221</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830719</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830719</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35173</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A47131)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35173)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2092:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christian Quaker: or, George Keith's eyes opened Good news from Pensilvania. Containing a testimony against that false and absurd opinion which some hold, viz. that all true believers and saints, immediately after the bodily death attain to all the resurrection they expect, and enter into the fullest enjoyment of happiness. And also, that the wicked, immediately after death, are raised up to receive all the punishment they are to expect. Together with a scriptural account of the resurrection of the dead, day of judgment, and Christ's last coming and appearance without us. Also, where, and what those Heavens are into which the man Christ is gone, and entred into. By George Keith.</title>
                  <author>Keith, George, 1639?-1716.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed in Pensilvania, and reprinted in London for Benjamin Keach, and are to be sold by him at his house near Horse-lie-down; and John Harris at the Harrow in the Poultrey,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At foot of title page: price 2d.</note>
                  <note>Copy from the British Library cropped at head with loss of pagination and text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the originals in the Bodleian Library Oxford and the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Quakers --  Pennsylvania --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Death --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-05</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35173:1"/>
            <p>THE
<hi>Chriſtian Quaker:</hi>
OR,
<hi>GEORGE KEITH</hi>'s Eyes opened.
Good News from <hi>Penſilvania.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Containing a Teſtimony againſt that Falſe and Abſurd
Opinion which ſome hold,</hi> viz. That all true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers
and Saints, immediately after the Bodily Death at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
to all the Reſurrection they expect, and enter into the
fulleſt Enjoyment of Happineſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And alſo,</hi> That the Wicked, immediately after Death, are
raiſed up to receive all the Puniſhment they are to expect.</p>
            <p>Together with a Scriptural Account of the Reſurrection of
the Dead, Day of Judgment, and Chriſt's laſt Coming
and Appearance without us.</p>
            <p>Alſo, Where, and What thoſe Heavens are into which the
Man Chriſt is gone, and entred into.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> GEORGE KEITH.</p>
            <p>Printed in <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> and Reprinted in <hi>London</hi> for Benjamin <hi>Keach,</hi>
and are to be ſold by him at his Houſe near <hi>Horſe-lie-down;</hi> and
<hi>John Harris</hi> at the Harrow in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> 1693. Price 2 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:35173:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THIS ſhort Tract thou art here preſented with, was
firſt printed in <hi>Penſilvania, verbatim,</hi> except the
Title; the Publiſher, who lately came from thence, having
one Book of the firſt Impreſſion by him under Mr. <hi>George
Keith</hi>'s own Hand, juſt ſubſcribed as in this ſecond Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
without any Alteration or Addition, which has been care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
examined.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>REader, thou mayſt ſuddenly expect another Book to be
reprinted of <hi>George Keith</hi>'s about Separation, which may
tend farther to open the Eyes of the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi>
and others.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:35173:2"/>
            <head>The Chriſtian Quaker:
OR,
George Keith's Eyes Opened, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>WHereas many hurtful and dangerous Errors have taken place
among too many called <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> which are ſome of the
Tares and evil Seeds that Satan hath ſown while Men have
ſlept in the dark Night of Apoſtacy; and that now ſome do think they
are awakened and come to the Day, and in the Light of God's Day ſee
into the true Chriſtian Doctrine, and pretend to great Openings, and
Diſcoveries, and Revelations; and yet ſome even of ſuch hold ſome
falſe and unchriſtian Opinions; of which there are not a few concerning
the <hi>Reſurrection of the Dead,</hi> altho the Teſtimony of the holy Scriptures
is very full and clear againſt theſe dangerous and hurtful Opinions and
Principles, imbraced by ſome as if they were true Chriſtian Doctrines.
Some alledging, <hi>That there is no Reſurrection of the Body at all;</hi> or, <hi>That
there is nothing of the Body that dieth, that riſeth again.</hi> Others alledging,
<hi>That the Reſurrection is paſt already; and all the Reſurrection they expect, they
have already attained, being</hi> (as they pretend) <hi>riſen with Chriſt in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects.</hi>
Others ſay, <hi>Their vile or low Body is already changed, and made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
to his glorious Body.</hi> Others ſay, <hi>They receive all the Reſurrection they
do expect immediately after Death.</hi> All which are dangerous and unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
Principles, and are directly contrary to the holy Scriptures: for
there were in <hi>Paul</hi>'s time who ſaid, <hi>The Reſurrection was paſt already, and
did overthrow the Faith of ſome, ſuch as</hi> Hymeneus <hi>and</hi> Philetus, <hi>whoſe
Words did eat as a Cankir,</hi> as he declared, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 17, 18. And ſuch
who ſay, <hi>Their vile Body is changed, and made conform to the glorious Body of
Chriſt,</hi> contradict the Scripture, and ſpeak reproachfully, but ignorantly,
againſt the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: for <hi>Paul</hi> uſeth theſe Words by way of
Prophecy, as a thing not then fulfilled, but a thing to be fulfilled at the
Reſurrection of the Dead; <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 21. <hi>Who ſhall change our vile</hi> (or <hi>low</hi>)
<hi>Body, that it may be faſhioned like unto his glorious Body,</hi> &amp;c. He doth not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35173:3"/>
ſay, that the Body was already changed, and made like to the Body of
Chriſt, but by way of Prophecy related it as a thing to come: for the
waſhing and cleanſing of the Body from Sin, is not that Change, but it
is neceſſary to prepare unto it; for even after the Bodies of the Saints
are waſhed and cleanſed from Sin, they remain low, and weak, and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal,
and corruptible, ſubject to Hunger, Cold, Heat, Diſeaſes and Death,
and therefore are not made like to his glorious Body until the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
of the Dead. And ſuch who ſay, <hi>Nothing of the Body that dieth ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
again,</hi> do plainly contradict the Teſtimony of the holy Spirit record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in Scripture, and eſpecially 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 7, 38. for according to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
that the Wiſdom of God giveth of the Grain of Corn, whereby to
open the Myſtery of the Reſurrection, as the true Body of the Seed in the
Grain riſeth; ſo that out of the old Body a new Body doth ariſe, but
the Husk or droſſy Part riſes not; even ſo is the Reſurrection of the Dead:
Therefore the new Reſurrection-Body is raiſed out of the old Body, as
the new Grain of Corn riſes out of the old: but if the Body of the Grain
of Corn did wholly periſh or come to Duſt, nothing could ariſe; which
is a plain Example given us by the Wiſdom of God: and that which ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
is the Mortal that puts on Immortality, and the Corruptible that puts
on Incorruption, and is not raiſed Fleſh and Blood, ſuch as Men now
have, but yet a true Body; for <hi>Fleſh and Blood cannot inherit the Kingdom
of God, neither doth Corruption inherit Incorruption:</hi> but the true Body of
Man and Woman that ſhall ariſe at the Reſurrection of the Dead, lieth
hid within this viſible groſs appearance of Fleſh and Flood, even as the
true Body of the Seed in the Grain of Corn lieth within the Husk, or as
the precious Gold lies within the coarſe Mineral or Mine until the pure
and precious Metal be ſeparated from the Droſs. And becauſe this Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration
is not immediately effected, but requires a Time after Death,
and that even when the Separation is made, the Body remains, and is
lodged by the Divine Providence that gives to every thing its proper
Place, as in a certain inviſible Grave or Sepulchre, that was myſteriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
figured by the Burial-place called <hi>Machpelah,</hi> (that ſignifies a double
or twofold Sepulchre) <hi>Gen.</hi> 23. which <hi>Abraham</hi> purchaſed from <hi>Ephron</hi>
the <hi>Hittite</hi> (which word <hi>Ephron</hi> ſignifies the <hi>Dust-eater</hi>) for four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
pieces of Silver: The which as it is literally true, ſo is an Allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
and points at the Reſurrection of the Body out of the myſtical and
inviſible <hi>Machpelah</hi> or Sepulchre in <hi>Hebron</hi> (which ſignifies bordering) in
the Land of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> figuratively and myſtically underſtood: and by four
hundred pieces of Silver, as by ſo many Vertues ſignified by Silver, this
moſt excellent Burial place is purchaſed from <hi>Ethron:</hi> but he who hath
not theſe Vertues, cannot have the Privilege to be buried in this moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35173:3"/>
Burial-place; and therefore <hi>an untimely Birth is better than he,</hi> as
the holy Scripture declares, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 6. 3. For it is no ſuch Miſery nor
Unhappineſs not to have an outward and viſible Sepulchre, which many
of the dear Children of God have not had; but ſurely they have this
other more excellent Burial in the myſtical <hi>Hebron,</hi> in the myſtical Land
of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> where all the dead Bodies of the Saints ſhall be raiſed up, and
ſtand with the Lamb upon Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> to wit, not the literal <hi>Zion,</hi>
but the myſtical.</p>
            <p>Now that the Bodies of the Saints are not raiſed up immediately af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
Death, or after the Spirit goeth out of the Body, (altho the Souls
and Spirits of the Righteous, and of all the Faithful, both Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
who die in the Faith of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, do immediately go
unto God and Chriſt in Heaven, and enter into a very great and large
Enjoyment of the Heavenly Bleſſedneſs, after the bodily Deceaſe) is clear
from many expreſs Teſtimonies of the holy Scripture. For the decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
Saints, tho their Souls and Spirits are alive with the Lord in Heaven,
and do not ſleep, but are awake, and praiſe God continually; yet they
are ſaid to be aſleep in reſpect of their Bodies, which are rather fallen
aſleep than dead, and are ſaid to ſleep in Chriſt, to wit, under his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
Care and Protection, until he awaken them. For which I ſhall cite
theſe following Scriptures. 1 Kings 2. 10. <hi>So</hi> David <hi>ſlept with his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
and was buried in the City of</hi> David. Deut. 39. 16. <hi>Behold, thou ſhalt
ſleep with thy Fathers, ſaid the Lord unto</hi> Moſes. 1 Cor. 15. 20. <hi>Now is
Chriſt riſen from the dead, and become the firſt Fruits of them that ſleep,</hi> viz.
becauſe he roſe from the dead the third day. 1 Theſſ. 4. 14. <hi>For if we
believe that Jeſus died and roſe again, even ſo them alſo which ſleep in Jeſus,
will God bring with him: for this we ſay unto you by the Word of the Lord, that
we which are alive, and remain unto the Coming of the Lord, ſhall not prevent
them which are aſleep; for the Lord himſelf ſhall deſcend from Heaven with a
Shout, with the Voice of the Arch-Angel, and with the Trump of God; and
the Dead in Chriſt ſhall riſe firſt.</hi> All which Places plainly ſhow, that tho
the Saints, as with reſpect to their Souls, are raiſed up, and aſcended,
and are with God and Chriſt in Heaven, yet as to their Bodies they are
aſleep, and have not attained to the Reſurrection of the Body: for if
they had attained to the bodily Reſurrection, <hi>Paul</hi> would not have writ
of them by way of Prophecy, in the future, or time to come, ſaying, <hi>The
Dead in Chriſt ſhall riſe firſt,</hi> to wit, at the Voice of the Arch-Angel,
and Trump of God. Now what this Trump or Trumpet is, both <hi>Paul</hi>
and <hi>John</hi> declareth, and the Time about which it is to ſound, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.
52. <hi>In a moment, in the twinkling of an Eye, at the laſt Trump; and the
Dead ſhall be raiſed Incorruptible, and we ſhall be changed.</hi> Rev. 11. 15. 18.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35173:4"/>
               <hi>And the ſeventh Angel ſounded,</hi> (which ſeventh is the laſt Trumpet) <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
And <hi>ver.</hi> 18. <hi>Thy Wrath is come, and the time of the Dead, that they ſhould
be judged, and that thou ſhouldſt give reward unto thy Servants the Prophets,
and, thy Saints, and them that fear thy Name, both ſmall and great.</hi> And
becauſe <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. lays down the Reſurrection of Chriſt's Body
from the dead, as the Ground why true Believers, which are his Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,
ſhall attain to the Reſurrection of their Body, it manifeſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears
that they are to attain unto it at the end of the World, or at the
laſt Trumpet, as above mentioned, (yet it may well be allowed, that
ſome did attain to the Reſurrection of the Body immediately after Chriſt's
Reſurrection, according to <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. 52, 53. <hi>And the Graves were opened,
and many Bodies of Saints which ſlept, aroſe, and came out of the Graves after
his Reſurrection, and went into the holy City, and appeared unto many:</hi>) And
therefore the deceaſed Saints have not generally attained the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of the Dead, as touching the Reſurrection of the Body, but do wait
for it until the Sound of the laſt Trumpet. Nor did any of the Saints
attain the Reſurrection of the Body before Chriſt's Body roſe from the
dead, becauſe he is expreſly called, <hi>The firſt-begotten from the Dead,</hi> and
<hi>The firſt Fruits that go before the Harveſt:</hi> And therefore none did attain
the bodily Reſurrection before him, neither <hi>Enoch</hi> nor <hi>Elias;</hi> for though
they were taken up, yet it is not ſaid they had attained the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of the Body, it only implieth ſome particular Privilege, that they
did not taſte of Death as other Men: and the like may be ſaid of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
whoſe Body was more pure and excellent than that of other Men; and
therefore <hi>Michael the Arch-Angel did contend with the Devil about the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
of Moſes,</hi> and would not let him touch it, as being more excellent;
and therefore it is ſaid, <hi>God buried him, and no Man knoweth of his Burial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place
to this day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, it is very plain from Scripture, that the deceaſed Saints,
who lived from the beginning of the World, altho their Souls and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
did aſcend unto God and Chriſt in Heaven, yet waited for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection
of the Body, and that more abundant Glory that ſhould fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
thereupon; for it is ſaid, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 13. <hi>Theſe all died in Faith, not
having received the Promiſes, but having ſeen them afar off, and were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded
of them, and embraced them,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>ver.</hi> 39, 40. <hi>All theſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
obtained a good Report through Faith, received not the Promiſe, God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
provided ſome better things for us, that they without us ſhould not be made
perfect.</hi> Now what this Promiſe is, is clear from <hi>Ver.</hi> 35. <hi>And other:
were tortured, not accepting Deliverance, that they might obtain a better Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection;</hi>
which is the Reſurrection of the Juſt, that is better than the
Reſurrection of the Unjuſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:35173:4"/>
               <hi>Now if ſome ſay,</hi> The Promiſe that they waited for, was Chriſt's Coming
in the Fleſh.</p>
            <p>I anſwer; As it was that in part, ſo it was not only that, but all that
Felicity and Happineſs that ſhould come unto them by the Coming of
Chriſt in the Fleſh, and his Death and Reſurrection, to wit, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
Victory over Death, which is not fully obtained until the Mortal
put on Immortality, and the Corruptible put on Incorruption, as it is
written, <hi>So when this Corruptible ſhall put on Incorruption, and this Mortal
ſhall have put on Immortality, then ſhall be brought to paſs the Saying that is
written, Death is ſwallowed up in Victory: O Death! where is thy Sting?
O Grave! where is thy Victory?</hi> &amp;c. And that very firſt Promiſe that
God gave to Mankind after the Fall, did relate to this Victory over
Death, <hi>That the Seed of the Woman</hi> (which is Chriſt Jeſus) <hi>ſhould bruiſe
the Head of the Serpent:</hi> for tho the Head of the Serpent was inwardly
bruiſed, as in reſpect of the inward Redemption, Salvation and Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
of the Souls of all the Faithful in all Ages of the World, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
and after Chriſt came in the Fleſh; yet until they attain unto the
Reſurrection of the Body, the Head of the Serpent is not in all reſpects
bruiſed, becauſe the laſt Enemy that is to be deſtroyed is Death, who is
not fully deſtroyed until the Bodies of the Saints be raiſed from Death:
for by <hi>Adam's</hi> Fall, Death both of Soul and Body came upon him and his
Poſterity, (<hi>as is at large demonſtrated in another Treatiſe of G. K's</hi>) and by
Chriſt's Death and Reſurrection, to all who ſincerely believe in him and
obey him, that twofold Death is removed, the Death of the Soul, thrô
Faith in him, and that inward quickning, and being raiſed with him,
who is the Reſurrection and the Life, now in the mortal State, but the
Death of the Body at the Reſurrection of the Dead, [ſee this <hi>twofold
Reſurrection,</hi> the one of the Soul, the other of the Body, expreſly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned,
<hi>John</hi> 5. 25, 28.]</p>
            <p>And who ſay, <hi>That the Faithful immediately after Death, receive the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection
of the Body, and all that fulneſs of Glory and Happineſs that they
are to expect for ever:</hi> As it doth tend to overthrow a principal Article
of the Chriſtian Faith, touching the Reſurrection of the Dead, ſo it
tendeth to overthrow that other great and principal Article of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
Faith,</hi> touching the <hi>Great Day of Judgment</hi> that is to be in the End
of the World, called in Scripture, [<hi>The laſt Day</hi>], and [<hi>The great Day</hi>]
and [<hi>That Day</hi>] by way of Diſtinction from other Days, and which is
frequently mentioned in Scripture; for even the fallen Angels have not
as yet received their final Sentence, and full and abſolute Puniſhment, but
are reſerved in <hi>Chains of Darkneſs unto the Judgment of the great Day,
Jude</hi> 6. compared with 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 4. And <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 22. <hi>Many will ſay re me
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35173:5"/>
in That Day, Lord, Lord, have not we propheſied in thy Name?</hi> &amp;c. And
2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1. 7, 8, 9, 10. <hi>When the Lord Jeſus ſhall be revealed from Heaven, with
his mighty Angels, in flaming Fire, taking vengeance on them that know not
God, and obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: who ſhall be puniſhed
with everlaſting Deſtruction from the Preſence of the Lord, and from the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
of his Power: when he ſhall come to be glorified in his Saints, and to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired
in all them that believe (becauſe our Teſtimony among you was believed)
in That Day:</hi> Note well theſe words, [<hi>In That Day</hi>]. Again, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.
31. <hi>Becauſe he hath appointed a Day in the which he will judg the World in
Righteouſneſs by that MAN whom he hath ordained, having offered Faith</hi>
(as the Greek and Margent of the Engliſh Bibles hath it) <hi>unto all Men, in
that he hath raiſed him from the Dead.</hi> And <hi>ver.</hi> 32. <hi>And when they heard
of the Reſurrection of the Dead, ſome mocked, and others ſaid, We will hear
thee again of this Matter.</hi> And theſe were ſome Philoſophers of the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureans</hi>
and the <hi>Stoicks,</hi> to which this Doctrine of the Reſurrection of
the Body ſeemed ſtrange.—And ſo great an Article and Doctrine
of the <hi>Chriſtian Faith</hi> was this of the Reſurrection, that <hi>Paul</hi> calleth it,
<hi>The Hope of the Promiſe made of God unto the Fathers;</hi> as plainly appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,
comparing <hi>Acts</hi> 26. <hi>v.</hi> 6. with <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>Why ſhould it be thought a thing
incredible with you that God ſhould raiſe the Dead?</hi> And <hi>ver.</hi> 22, 23. <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſing
both to ſmall and great, ſaying none other things than thoſe which
the Prophets and</hi> Moſes <hi>did ſay ſhould come, that Chriſt ſhould ſuffer, and
be the firſt that ſhould riſe from the Dead,</hi> &amp;c. Note theſe words, where
it plainly appeareth, That none of the Saints deceaſed before Chriſt's
Reſurrection, were raiſed from the Dead, although their Souls and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
did go unto God. For the Reſurrection of the Dead, as a general
thing, is joined with the great Day of Judgment, <hi>when the Son of MAN
ſhall come in the Glory of his Father, accompanied with his holy Angels, and
ſhall fit upon the Throne of his Glory; and before him ſhall be gathered all
Nations, and he ſhall ſeparate them one from another, as a Shepherd divideth
his Sheep from the Goats; and firſt appointeth the Reward of the Kingdom
(viz.</hi> in the full poſſeſſion of it) <hi>unto the Sheep, which is the firſt Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
and then he paſſeth the Sentence of Condemnation to the everlaſting Fire,</hi>
or Fire of Ages, <hi>unto the Goats on the left hand, that is the Reſurrection of
the Vnjuſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if all Men, both Good and Bad, receive their final Sentence im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately
after Death, there is no occaſion for a Day of Judgment in
the end of the World, for that is prevented by what cometh to paſs
both to Good and Bad immediately after Death, according to this ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd
Opinion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:35173:5"/>
But again, as concerning that <hi>Great Day of Judgment</hi> to come, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
both the Righteous and the Wicked ſhall receive according to the
Works done in the Body, Chriſt doth plainly elſewhere declare, as <hi>Mat.</hi>
24. 36. <hi>But of that Day and Hour knoweth no Man, no not the Angels in
Heaven, but my Father only.</hi> And <hi>Mark</hi> 3. 32. <hi>But of that Day and Hour
knoweth no Man, no not the Angels in Heaven, neither the Son, but the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi>
Which is to be underſtood of Chriſt, the Son, as Man, to whom
then it was not known. The which Day and Hour cannot be the time
immediately after Mens deceaſe; for though after Death there is a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
that followeth every one, according to <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 27. yet that is not
the great and laſt Judgment, nor Univerſal, but Particular. And of this
laſt Day, Chriſt ſaid. <hi>John</hi> 6. 40. <hi>And this is the Will of him that ſent me,
that every one which ſeeth the Son, and believeth on him, may have everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Life; and I will raiſe him up at the laſt Day. Note,</hi> He doth not ſay,
I will raiſe him up in the Body immediately after Death; but in this <hi>laſt
Day,</hi> to wit, <hi>in the End of the World.</hi> And with a reſpect to this <hi>Martha</hi>
made a good Confeſſion of her Faith, touching the Reſurrection of the
Dead, ſaying, <hi>I know that he ſhall riſe again in the Reſurrection at the laſt
Day.</hi> The which Chriſt doth not in the leaſt contradict, but opened a
further Myſtery unto her, to wit, <hi>That he was the Reſurrection and the Life:
he that believeth in me, though he were dead, yet ſhall he live; and whoſoever
liveth and believeth in me, ſhall never die.</hi> And becauſe he was the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,
<hi>viz.</hi> the Author of it, therefore he could and would raiſe <hi>Lazarus</hi>
her Brother from the Dead at that time; which yet was not the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
in the laſt Day, for he was but raiſed at that time a mortal Man,
to die again. And whereas he ſaid, <hi>He who believeth in me ſhall never die,</hi>
containeth a great and moſt comfortable Myſtery, to wit, That neither
the Souls nor the Bodies of true Believers ſtrictly die; their Souls ſleep
not, but are awake; and their Bodies, tho they ſleep, die not; their
ſleep is not the ſleep of Death, ſtrictly taken. And therefore Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
againſt the <hi>Sadduces</hi> the Reſurrection of the Dead, from the Words
of God to <hi>Moſes, I am the God of</hi> Abraham, Iſaac <hi>and</hi> Jacob; <hi>and God is
not the God of the Dead, but the God of the Living;</hi> and therefore nothing
of <hi>Abraham</hi> was ſtrictly dead or periſhed, neither his Soul, nor yet his
true Body; for even his Body did but ſleep, as when the Body of a Man
ſleepeth that is not dead; for the Bodies only of ſuch die, (in the worſt
ſenſe of the word <hi>Death</hi>) who die in final Unbelief and Impenitency;
<hi>on whom Death feeds, and whoſe Iniquities are upon their Bones,</hi> and whoſe
Bodies are called, <hi>the Carkaſſes of them that have tranſgreſſed againſt the
Lord, whoſe Worm dieth not, and their Fire goeth not out,</hi> &amp;c. ſee for this
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 49. 14. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 32. 27, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66. 24. But as concerning the dead Bodies
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35173:6"/>
of the Saints and true Believers in Chriſt Jeſus, it is propheſied. <hi>Thy
Dead, my dead Body ſhall ariſe,</hi> (ſo the <hi>Hebrew</hi> hath it) for the Bodies of
the deceaſed Saints are the Body and Temple of Chriſt, and Members of
him, and therefore cannot periſh: <hi>Awake and ſing, ye that dwell in the
Duſt, for thy Dew is as the Dew of Herbs, and the Earth ſhall caſt out the
Dead,</hi> (to wit, the Earth not vulgarly underſtood, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26. 19.) And
that <hi>Job</hi> had a firm and ſtedfaſt Belief of the Reſurrection of his Body
after Death, is clear from his words, <hi>viz. And though after my Skin,
Worms deſtroy this Body, yet in my Fleſh ſhall I ſee God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Job</hi> 19. 26.
Which is not to be underſtood of the groſs corruptible Body of Fleſh,
but of the Reſurrection Body, that may be called Fleſh in a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
ſenſe than that vulgarly underſtood; as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>All Fleſh is not
the ſame Fleſh.</hi> So the Fleſh that is mortal, groſs and corruptible, is not
that Fleſh that ſhall be raiſed up immortal and incorruptible; for the
word [<hi>Fleſh</hi>] is taken ſometimes in a very high ſenſe, where it is ſaid,
<hi>Vnleſs ye eat my Fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>All Fleſh ſhall ſee the Salvation of God;</hi>
and <hi>I will give them Hearts of Fleſh,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, That there is yet a Reſurrection of the Dead to come, of
all ſuch generally who have died in the Faith, is clear from <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. 4, 5, 6.
<hi>And they lived and reigned with Chriſt a thouſand Years; but the reſt of the
Dead lived not again until the thouſand Years were finiſhed: That is the firſt
Reſurrection. Bleſſed and holy is he that hath part in the firſt Reſurrection.</hi>
Where note well, that the Reſurrection of the Saints in the thouſand
Years, is called <hi>the firſt Reſurrection,</hi> &amp;c. which every true Believer, who
is inwardly riſen with Chriſt, as to his Soul and inward Man, is inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted
in, and hath a right unto, but is not poſſeſſed of until the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
of the Dead: And therefore if any will call the inward riſing
of the Soul from the Death of Sin, the firſt Reſurrection, yet it is not
<hi>That</hi> firſt Reſurrection, mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. 4, 5.</p>
            <p>Moreover, concerning the Nature and Manner of the Reſurrection of
the Bodies of the Saints, how that this Body is not raiſed a mortal cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible
Body of Fleſh and Blood, but immortal and incorruptible. <hi>Paul</hi>
doth plainly declare; and it is altogether ſafe in this and all other Matters
of Faith, to hold to Scripture words, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. from <hi>v.</hi> 44, to 50.</p>
            <p>And here note, 1. That <hi>Paul</hi> doth not call him a Fool that did believe
either the Truth of the Reſurrection of the Body, or the true manner of
it, but called him a Fool, that not believing the Truth of it, nor the true
Manner of it, and by arguing againſt it, did enquire, <hi>How are the Dead
raiſed up?</hi> And for the Inſtruction of this Fool, <hi>Paul</hi> ſendeth him to learn
the manner of it from the ſowing and riſing of the Grain of Corn; and
he reproveth ſuch at <hi>Corinth</hi> ſharply, who did not belive the Reſurrection
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35173:6"/>
of the Body, <hi>as not having the Knowledg of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 34. <hi>Awake,</hi>
ſaid he, <hi>to Righteouſneſs. I ſpeak this to your ſhame.</hi> So that according
to <hi>Paul's</hi> Doctrine, ſuch who have not the true Faith of the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of the Body, greatly fall ſhort of the Knowledg of God.</p>
            <p>Note, 2. That the <hi>Reſurrection of the Dead,</hi> and <hi>Eternal Judgment,</hi>
belonging to the firſt Principles of the <hi>Doctrine of Chriſt,</hi> according to
<hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 1. as well as <hi>Repentance</hi> and <hi>Faith,</hi> are neceſſary to be known and
believed, in order to the perfecting, if not the beginning, the Work of
our Sanctification and Salvation.</p>
            <p>Note, 3. That as the Bodies of the Saints, that ſhall be raiſed up at
the Reſurrection of the Dead, ſhall not be raiſed Mortal and Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
but Immortal and Incorruptible, ſo they ſhall not need any Meats or
Drinks, or other things that this Mortal and Corruptible World doth
afford, nor the Light and Influence of the Sun, Moon and Stars: And
in the Reſurrection, they ſhall neither Marry, nor give in Marriage, but
be as the Angels of God, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. 30. And the Place of their Abode or
Habitation ſhall be that <hi>New Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> mentioned by <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
Chap. 65. 17. and Chap. 66. 22. and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 13. which is not, as ſome
weakly imagine, this viſible Heaven and Earth that waxeth Old, but
thoſe which are far more excellent, and ſhall not wax old, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 1.
But yet it is clear from Scripture, That at the <hi>Coming</hi> and <hi>Appearance of
Chriſt</hi> without us, in his glorified Body, which all good and ſound <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>
joyfully wait for, even that <hi>He ſhall come in the Clouds of Heaven, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied
with his Holy and Glorious Angels,</hi> that all the raiſed Saints ſhall
appear with him in their glorified Bodies, (ſignified by the <hi>coming down
of the New Jeruſalem from Heaven,</hi> Rev. 21. 2, 3.) being made like unto
his Glorious Body, according to <hi>Jude</hi> 14. And <hi>Enoch</hi> alſo, the ſeventh
from <hi>Adam,</hi> propheſied of theſe, ſaying, <hi>Behold, the Lord cometh with ten
thouſand of his Saints, to execute Judgment upon all,</hi> &amp;c. And whereas
ſome ſay, the Greek beareth it <hi>in ten thouſands,</hi> I ſay, he both cometh <hi>In</hi>
them, and alſo <hi>With</hi> them; for the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth frequently ſignify
(in the New Teſtament) <hi>With</hi> or <hi>Among,</hi> as well as <hi>In;</hi> as is clear
from <hi>Matth.</hi> 20. 26. <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 28. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 6. where the
Greek Particle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth <hi>Among,</hi> and cannot be good ſenſe otherwiſe
tranſlated.</p>
            <p>Note, 4. That the Belief of Chriſt's Being in Heaven now in his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified
Nature of Man, both of Soul and Body, hath ſuch a neceſſary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion
with the Belief of his Coming and Appearance without us, to
judg the Quick and the Dead, that theſe two ſtand or fall together; and
every one that believeth the firſt, cannot but believe the latter; for it
were ſtrange to think, that Chriſt hath, and for ever ſhall have the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35173:7"/>
Nature of Man in Heaven, and that the Saints ſhould not ſee him
at the <hi>Day of Judgment.</hi> But as for ſuch as do not believe that Chriſt hath
any Being in the glorified Nature of Man now in Heaven without them,
they cannot believe that ever he will appear unto them, or any other;
and it is nothing but giving way to carnal dark Reaſonings, and Wiſdom
of the Fleſh, called by <hi>Paul, Vain Philoſophy,</hi> and <hi>Worldly Rudiments,</hi> that
hinder Men to believe the Truth ſo plainly declared in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>And, 5. From the like dark Imaginations doth proceed, that they
believe no Heaven nor Hell but within them, while they enquire <hi>Where
is that Heaven into which the Man Chriſt is gone? And hath any of us ſeen
him, or ſpoke with him?</hi> To which I can eaſily Anſwer; That Heaven is
both near to us, and far from us, and is of a far more large Extent than
that it can be contained within us, though we have a Heavenly Seed,
Plant and Birth in us, that is daily nouriſhed with Heavenly Food, and
is watered daily with the Heavenly Dews and Rains; and this Heaven,
tho not viſible to our weak mortal Eyes of Fleſh, yet is viſible to the
Eyes and Sight of our Faith, and is that <hi>New Heaven that never waxeth
Old,</hi> and the <hi>Paradiſe of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 12. 4. compared with <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 7. and
<hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 9, 10. which is the <hi>Throne of God,</hi> and the <hi>Houſe of God,</hi> that hath
many Manſions; concerning which Chriſt ſaid, <hi>John</hi> 14. 2, 3. <hi>In my
Father's Houſe are many Manſions. If it were not ſo, I would have told you;
I go to prepare a Place for you. And if I go and prepare a Place for you,
I will come again, and receive you unto my ſelf, that where I am, there ye may
be alſo.</hi> And tho we have not ſeen the Man Chriſt with our carnal or
bodily Eyes, yet with theſe, concerning whom <hi>Peter</hi> writeth, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 8.
<hi>Whom having not ſeen, ye love; in whom, though now ye ſee him not, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving,
ye rejoice with Joy unſpeakable and full of Glory.</hi> And that the Saints
ſhall ſee the Man Chriſt, and be with him for ever where he is, to behold
his Glory, ſhall be a great part of their eternal Felicity, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. 24. and
becauſe of which they ſhall the more abundantly ſee and enjoy him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly,
and God in him and through him. And Jeſus ſaid unto <hi>Thomas,</hi>
after his Reſurrection, <hi>John</hi> 20. 29. Thomas, <hi>becauſe thou haſt ſeen me,
thou believeſt; bleſſed are they that have not ſeen, and yet have believed.</hi> And
how can all Nations ſtand before the <hi>Son of Man,</hi> Mat. 25. if he ſhall not
appear without us at the Day of Judgment?</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. K.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
