<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of a conference had betwixt G. Keith and T. Upsher, at Colchester the 6th of the fifth month, 1699 the truth of which is attested by three witnesses who took it from their mouths in short-hand and afterwards by joint consent writ it out at length : the question stated at the said conference was whether Thomas Upsher's preaching in the forenoon that faith in Christ, as he was born of the Virgin Mary, and dyed for our sins, &amp;c. was absolutely necessary to salvation, ..., and in the afternoon his preaching that the light within ... is sufficient to salvation is a contradiction : and a brief account of the uncivil and illegal treatment used by some  principal Quakers at Colchester and Bristol toward G Keith ... : and a postscript, containing some notes and observations on the assertions of T. Upsher and his brethren, detecting their self-contradictions : and a certificate from Parson Shelton of Colchester, to the truth of the case in debate ... and to the truth of the conference / by George Keith.</title>
            <author>Keith, George, 1639?-1716.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-12">2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47189</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K222</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14758</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11845648</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11845648</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49836</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A47189)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49836)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 539:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of a conference had betwixt G. Keith and T. Upsher, at Colchester the 6th of the fifth month, 1699 the truth of which is attested by three witnesses who took it from their mouths in short-hand and afterwards by joint consent writ it out at length : the question stated at the said conference was whether Thomas Upsher's preaching in the forenoon that faith in Christ, as he was born of the Virgin Mary, and dyed for our sins, &amp;c. was absolutely necessary to salvation, ..., and in the afternoon his preaching that the light within ... is sufficient to salvation is a contradiction : and a brief account of the uncivil and illegal treatment used by some  principal Quakers at Colchester and Bristol toward G Keith ... : and a postscript, containing some notes and observations on the assertions of T. Upsher and his brethren, detecting their self-contradictions : and a certificate from Parson Shelton of Colchester, to the truth of the case in debate ... and to the truth of the conference / by George Keith.</title>
                  <author>Keith, George, 1639?-1716.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28  p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Brab. Aylmer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Upsher, Thomas, 1672-1704.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  England --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-06</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49836:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49836:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRUE
RELATION
OF A
CONFERENCE
Had Betwixt
<hi>G. Keith</hi> and <hi>T. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pſher,</hi> at <hi>Colcheſter,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>6th</hi> of the Fifth Month, 1699, The truth of which is
atteſted by Three Witneſſes, who took it from their
Mouths in Short-hand, and afterwards by joint conſent
writ it out at length.</p>
            <p>The Queſtion ſtated at the ſaid Conference, was, Whether <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas
<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pſher</hi>'s Preaching in the Forenoon, <hi>That Faith in Chriſt,
as he was born of the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>and dyed for our Sins,</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>was abſolutely neceſſary to Salvation</hi> (as ſome affirmed he ſaid, or
as others affirmed, was neceſſary) and in the Afternoon, his
Preaching, <hi>That the Light within</hi> (univerſally, for which he
quoted many Scriptures) <hi>is ſufficient to Salvation, IS A CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TRADICTION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND A
Brief Account of the uncivil and illegal Treatment uſed by ſome principal
Quakers at <hi>Colcheſter</hi> and <hi>Briſtol</hi> towards <hi>G. Keith;</hi> and ſome other ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial
Paſſages in his Travelling through ſeveral places in the Country,
this and the former Summer. And a POSTSCRIPT, containing
ſome Notes and Obſervations on the Aſſertions of <hi>T. Vpſher</hi> and his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
detecting their Self-contradictions. And a Certificate from Parſon
<hi>Shelton</hi> of <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> to the truth of the Caſe in debate (which is alſo at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted
by Nine other credible Witneſſes) and to the truth of the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
            <p>By <hi>GEORGE KEITH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Brab. Aylmer,</hi> at the <hi>Three Pigeons,</hi> over-againſt the
<hi>Royal-Exchange,</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> MDCXCIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="disputation">
            <pb facs="tcp:49836:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49836:2"/>
            <head>A TRUE
RELATION
OF A
CONFERENCE
BETWIXT
G. Keith and T. Vpſher, at Colcheſter, &amp;c.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>THEY that heard me on the firſt Day, may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,
that I ſaid, That, to the beſt of my
remembrance, <hi>Tho Vpſher</hi> in the Afternoon
contradicted what he declared in the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon;
if it happens to be proved that he did
not, all the damage that will happen to me, is, that I am miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
or I miſunderſtood him.</p>
               <p>Now I offer to prove it, to the beſt of my underſtanding and
remembrance. <hi>Tho.</hi> ſaid in the Forenoon, That Faith in Chriſt,
both as he was born of a Virgin without us, and dyed for our ſins
without us, as his Blood was ſhed without us, and as he aroſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain
without us, and as he aſcended into Heaven without us,
and as he ſits at the right Hand of God, as our Mediator, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
us, and as he will come again and judge us, and as he is ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually
revealed in us, is abſolutely neceſſary to Salvation. To
prove it, <hi>Tho.</hi> brought 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. 7. That we are cleanſed from
Sin by the Blood of Chriſt, even by the ſame Blood that was
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49836:3"/>
ſhed without the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and ſaid, That his Friends
and he differed not in Faith, and that the whole drift of Friends
Teſtimony tended to the ſame Doctrine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Upſher.</speaker>
               <p>It is not worded as I worded it; for I did not ſay abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely
neceſſary to Salvation. And obſerve, Friends, I am not come to
give an account of my Faith, nor to be Chatechiſed by <hi>George Keith;</hi>
but I am come to ſtand on the defenſive part: I ſaid neceſſary.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>Thou ſaidſt abſolutely neceſſary: For this I offer Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rob. Hannay.</speaker>
               <p>Thou ſaidſt <hi>abſolutely neceſſary.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tho. Cook.</speaker>
               <p>To the beſt of my remembrance, he did ſay, <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely
neceſſary.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Figget.</speaker>
               <p>You ſaid, <hi>abſolutely neceſſary.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Geo. Wetherly.</speaker>
               <p>He did ſay, <hi>abſolutely.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faith Till.</speaker>
               <p>He did ſay it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>I ſay, that I am ſure, that I did not ſay abſolutely neceſſary.
I have Witneſs as well as thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>There can be no Witneſs to prove a Negative.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>My Witneſs may be heard as well as thine. Call <hi>Will Drewit.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Will. Drewit.</speaker>
               <p>I do really believe he did not ſay <hi>abſolutely neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tho. Danks.</speaker>
               <p>I don't remember he ſaid <hi>abſolutely neceſſary.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rich. Waller.</speaker>
               <p>I do believe he did not ſay <hi>abſolutely neceſſary.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rob. Hoskins.</speaker>
               <p>I can't tell whether he ſaid it or not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tho. Wier.</speaker>
               <p>I remember nothing of the word <hi>abſolutely.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tho. Kettle.</speaker>
               <p>To the beſt of my Memory, he ſaid, <hi>neceſſary.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Moderator, <hi>Parſon</hi> Shelton.</speaker>
               <p>Well, then you all remember, that he
ſaid <hi>neceſſary;</hi> but you don't remember he ſaid <hi>abſolutely neceſſary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is but a Negative Teſtimony (ſaid Parſon <hi>Shelton</hi>) that
will not hold in Law. They anſwered, The difference was not a
matter in Law. <hi>G. Keith</hi> ſaid, Nor will it hold before any reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
Judicatory; however, <hi>neceſſary</hi> here is equivalent to <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely
neceſſary.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>Now I offer to prove the Contradiction, that is, to the
beſt of my remembrance and underſtanding, he Preach'd in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
ſtrain, and brought ſeveral Scriptures to prove the Light
within ſufficient to Salvation; <hi>John 1. 4, 9. In him was life, and
that life was the light of men. He was the true light, which lighteth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49836:3"/>
every Man that cometh into the World.</hi> John 3. 16. <hi>God ſo loved
the world, that he gave his only begotten Son, a light into the world, that
whoſoever believeth in him ſhould not periſh,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>Thou ſayest wrong; I ſaid not that the Light within is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
for Salvation; I never uſed the Expreſſion in any Meeting in my
Life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>Thou broughteſt Eleven or Twelve Scriptures to prove
it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>Thou art not against my uſing Scriptures.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>No, but againſt a perverſion of the Scripture, and a
miſapplication of them. How didſt thou word that Scripture?
<hi>God ſo loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>I worded it only thus, <hi>That God ſo loved the world, that
he gave his only begotten Son into the world,</hi> that in him they
might have Light.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe Scriptures thou madeſt uſe of, were to prove,
That the Light within was ſufficient to Salvation, <hi>John 3. 16.</hi>And ſome Verſes thou ſpoke to after; <hi>He that doth evil, hateth
the light.</hi> And every one that doth Truth cometh to the Light.<hi>49</hi> Iſa. <hi>6. I will alſo give thee for a light to the Gentiles, that thou
mayeſt be my ſalvation to the ends of the Earth. 27</hi> Pſal. <hi>The Lord
is my light and my ſalvation. 26</hi> Acts <hi>17, 18. Delivering thee from
theſe people, and from the Gentiles, unto whom now I ſend thee, to open
their eyes, to turn them from darkneſs to light, and from the power of
Satan to God, that they may receive forgiveneſs of ſins, and an inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance
among them that are ſanctified. 2</hi> Tit. <hi>21. The grace of God
that bringeth ſalvation, hath appeared to all men.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>I ſpake of them; but thou art gone from the word Light.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>You know it hath been common, what-ever denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
the principle goes under, to ſay the Light, or the principle
of the Spirit of God, or the Grace of God, or the Manifeſtation
of the Spirit; you make them all one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>When I ſay the Grace of God, or Light, or inward Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation
of the Spirit, I mean Chriſt's inward Manifeſtation to the
Soul.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>Thou quoted that Scripture <hi>2 Cor. 4. 6. God, who
commanded light to ſhine out of darkneſs, hath ſhined into our hearts, to
give the light of the knowledge of God in the face of his Son.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:49836:4"/>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>I don't remember that I uſed that Scripture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>There is Witneſs thou didſt uſe it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>John Raller.</speaker>
               <p>I think he did.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rob. Hannay.</speaker>
               <p>He did uſe it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>5 Eph. <hi>13. For all things that are reproved, are made
manifeſt by the light; for whatſoever doth make manifeſt is light.
2</hi> Cor. <hi>12. 9. My grace is ſufficient for thee.</hi> There is the ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency;
and by Grace he means Light. <hi>20 Acts 32. Now brethren,
I commend you to God, and the word of his grace, which is able to build
you up, and to give you an inheritance among them that are ſanctified.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>O! <hi>George,</hi> thou art wrong: I did not make uſe of that
Scripture on the firſt Day; it was on the fourth Day.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>Then thou contradicts thy ſelf two or three Days after;
it's no great difference; but thou didſt uſe it in part on the firſt
Day.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>To the beſt of my remembrance, on the firſt Day I committed
them to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and to the word of his Grace; and ſo
drew towards a Concluſion after that manner.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>Thoſe in the <hi>Revelations</hi> who have waſhed their Robes,
and made them white in the Blood of the Lamb. This Blood, to
the beſt of my underſtanding, he meant to be the Light: I think
he did expound it ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>I did uſe thoſe words; but I deny I meant the Light.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>If I can't prove it, all the damage will be, that I was
miſtaken. In the Afternoon he brings 1 <hi>John 4. 9. In him was
life,</hi> &amp;c. And that Scripture, <hi>My grace is ſufficient for thee.</hi> Theſe
we ſhall go through with: That I ſhall inſiſt on, that <hi>Tho.</hi> brings
theſe Scriptures to prove, that every Man that cometh into the
World is ſo lighted, and ſo taught, that if he obey the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
and diſcoveries of that inward Principle, it is ſufficient for
Salvation, or he ſhall be ſaved. All theſe Scriptures he brought
to prove it, <hi>And I will give thee for a covenant to the people, a light
to lighten the Gentiles, that thou mayeſt be my ſalvation to the ends of the
earth.</hi> Thus he paraphraſed upon them; and, to the beſt of my
underſtanding, ſaid, That whoſoever was obedient to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates
and diſcoveries of this Light, the Grace of God, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
appearance of Light, it ſhall be his Salvation: This he
ſaid in the Afternoon, which contradicts what he ſaid in the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49836:4"/>
Forenoon. Now the Contradiction lies here; whereas <hi>Tho.</hi> in
the Forenoon, ſaid, it was his belief, and the drift and tendency
of all the Friends and their Books and Writings, and that his
Faith and Friends did not differ in this point, That Faith in
Chriſt, as he was born of the Virgin without us, ſuffered without
us, aroſe and aſcended without us, and as he is ſpiritually revealed
in us, is neceſſary for Salvation; I ſay, he ſaid, That he and
his Friends did not differ in this; but that it was the drift of
all their Friends, though they did not expreſs it as he did.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>I did not mention the Faith of the Friends; I did not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
their Books, as I remember; but I ſaid, It was neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
to believe theſe things; and that it was the drift and tendency of
my Teſtimony.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>Call <hi>Rob. Hannay.</hi> Who prov'd he was ſpeaking before
of ſome that falſly charg'd Friends about this doctrine; but, ſays
he, they miſrepreſent us, and falſly accuſe us; it hath been, and
is the drift and tendency of all our Friends, to preach this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.
<hi>Tho. Cook,</hi> I call thee for a Witneſs, Whether <hi>Tho. Vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher</hi>
ſaid ſo or not? He anſwered, Yea. One ask'd <hi>Tho. Cook,</hi>
What <hi>Vpſher</hi> ſaid? He anſwer'd, That <hi>Tho. Vpſher</hi> ſaid, it was
the drift and tendency of our Friends to Preach ſuch Doctrine.
<hi>Tho. Lawrence</hi> offers himſelf a Witneſs; he ſaith, That <hi>Tho. Vpſher</hi>
mentioning ſome oppoſing the Quakers, that charg'd them, that
they not did hold Faith in Chriſt outwardly as neceſſary to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
ſaith he, I do verily believe, and it is my Faith, and I have
Faith in Chriſt Jeſus, as he ſuffered without the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
and it is the drift and tendency of our Declarations which we
Preach to the People.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>I did ſay Friends, but not a word of Books and Writings.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>Now, two ways, I prove, that he contradicts himſelf.
If I prove, that his Faith differs from the Faith of ſome, or moſt
of his Friends, as <hi>Will. Penn, Geo. Whitehead,</hi> and the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent,
is not here a Contradiction to himſelf? Is not their Faith
his Faith?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>George,</hi> this is from the matter; we are not come
here to meddle or diſpute what others hold, but thou art to ſhow, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted
in the Afternoon what I ſaid in the Forenoon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:49836:5"/>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>It is my Senſe, that whereas he ſaid in the Forenoon,
that his and his Friends Faith was one and the ſame, if he dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers
from his Friends, he differs from himſelf; and then, I ſay,
what he ſaid in the Afternoon, contradicts both himſelf and his
Friends.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>I ſaid, it is the drift and tendency of our Friends.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tho. Auger <hi>ſaid,</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>He meant the Friends there preſent; What
have we to do with <hi>W. Penn</hi> and <hi>G. Whitehead,</hi> they are not
here?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>If any ſay, What have we to do with our Friends <hi>W. Penn</hi>
and <hi>G. Whitehead,</hi> that are not here? Then, I ſay, thou ſhouldſt
have been more wary than to have mention'd ſuch a thing in an
Auditory. If I have any underſtanding in what he ſaid, I never
heard a greater Contradiction in my life. The places he brought
eſpecially 49. <hi>Iſa. 6. 2. Titus. 11. 26 Acts</hi> 18. He did not bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
quote theſe places, but paraphraſed on them, and applyed them
to Chriſt's inward appearance; call it what you will, Light or
Grace, as it is in every Man; for he numbers theſe places with
<hi>John</hi> 1. 4, and <hi>9th</hi> Verſes: this is a Contradiction; theſe places
he brings to prove the Light in every Man; 2 <hi>Cor. 12. 9. My
grace is ſufficient for thee.</hi> It hath no reference to that inward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance
or Principle of Chriſt in the Heathens that the Goſpel is
not Preached to. This in <hi>Iſa. I will give thee for a covenant to
the people, for a light to lighten the Gentiles, that thou mayeſt be my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
to the ends of the earth.</hi> This hath no reference to the Light
of the Gentile World, that hath not the Goſpel Preached: I
ſay it is a Prophecy which was not then fulfilled to the Gentile
World, nor is not now fulfill'd to the Heathen Gentiles; but it
is fulfill'd to us Chriſtian Gentils; 2 <hi>Titus 11. The grace of God
that bringeth ſalvation hath appeared to all men; teaching them,</hi> &amp;c. I
ſay, this Text hath no relation to the common diſcovery or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightening
that the Gentile World hath, that never had the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pel
preached.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>This is what I ſpoke in the Afternoon; compare it with what I
ſaid in the Forenoon, and ſhew the Contradiction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>There is no illumination or diſcovery in the Heathen
World, that hath not the Goſpel outwardly preached, that
gives them and teacheth them what to believe concerning Chriſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49836:5"/>
as he was born of a Virgin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſay, what is ordinary and uſual
according to the Methods of divine Providence, I do affirm the
Heathen World hath no Principle in them, that doth teach or
diſcover what they ought to believe concerning Chriſt outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>Where is the Contradiction? I never medled with Gentile or
Heathen; but that which was the tendency of my Teſtimony, was, That
People ſhould take heed to the inward appearance of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt
to their Souls, in order to their Sanctification.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>Thou didſt ſpeak it univerſally; and thou laideſt great
Importance on theſe two Scriptures, <hi>In him was life, and the life
was the LIGHT OF MEN; and the grace of God that bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
ſalvation, hath appeared TO ALL MEN.</hi> Now, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,
thou meant all Men without diſtinction, Chriſtians, Turks,
Jews, or Heathens; all Men. Now if there be no Principle in
the Heathen univerſally (what knowledge the Sybils had concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Chriſt's coming in the Fleſh, was not by that ordinary Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination,
but by ſuch extraordinary Revelation, as the Prophets
among the Jews had) that teacheth them to believe in Chriſt, as
he was born of a Virgin, then he contradicts himſelf, to ſay, that
Faith is neceſſary to Salvation, when there is nothing in thoſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens
to teach them it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>Had I ſaid in the Forenoon, that Faith in Chriſt's outward
appearance was abſolutely neceſſary to Salvation, even to the Gentile
Heathens, that are depriv'd of the hiſtorical Means, and ſaid, in the
Afternoon, that there is a Light within that is able to teach all Men to
Salvation, it had been a Contradiction, if it be proved, that the Light
is inſufficient: But I did not paraphraſe, or treat of the univerſality of
this Light; though I came to the Scripture that ſpoke of the Light, yet I
did not paraphraſe on that which lightened all Men in the World; I
did not ſpeak of the Heathens, my great Work was to ſhew, that thoſe
that were priviledged with the hiſtorical Account of theſe things, have
reaſon to be thankful for it, and their Work is to walk anſwerable to
it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>Obſerve, he grants, that if he had ſaid, that Faith in
Chriſt's outward appearance was abſolutely neceſſary to Salvation
to the Gentile Heathens, he had contradicted himſelf, on this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,
that I will prove, that the Light given to the Heathens is
inſufficient to Salvation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:49836:6"/>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>I ſay, that the Gentiles, that have not the priviledge of the
outward means, by which we come to underſtand and inſtrumentally, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
deprived of this, if they walk anſwerable to thoſe diſcoveries the
Lord hath given them, doubtleſs the Lord will accept of them; and if
they have not this means, doubtleſs, it's probable, the Lord will ſave
them, ſeeing they walk anſwerable to what they know.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tho.</hi> ſays, That if he have affirmed, that Faith in Chriſt's
outward Manifeſtation is abſolutely neceſſary to Salvation of thoſe
Heathens that have not the outward Means, and if he ſaid, that
there was a Light in all Men that was ſufficient, and I prove this
Light is not ſufficient, then it is a Contradiction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>I ſay it is, upon that condition thou proveſt the inſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
of the Light within, and proves the univerſality of that Faith ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
to Salvation, then it is a Contradiction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tho. Vpſher</hi> ſaith, That Faith, in the outward Manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
is abſolutely neceſſary to thoſe that have the outward Means,
and if there be not that Light in them that have not the Hiſtory,
he contradicts himſelf; if he affirmed, that there was a Manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
in all Men that was able to give them that Diſcovery and that
Faith; and that I can prove, that there is no ſuch Manifeſtation,
that was able to give them Salvation, he contradicts himſelf.
But <hi>Tho.</hi> ſaid, That there was a Manifeſtation in Men univerſally,
that was able to give this Diſcovery; he brought places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
to prove it, as the 1 <hi>John 4th</hi> and <hi>9th</hi> Verſes: He argued
for it, that there was that that would give a Diſcovery to all Men
of that that was neceſſary to Salvation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U</speaker>
               <p>I deny it, I did not ſay abſolute.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rich. Waller.</speaker>
               <p>He did not ſay abſolute.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arthur Cotten, William Drewit,</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>He did affirm, That there was that Manifeſtation, or
Light, or inward appearance; he paraphraſed upon thoſe places
of Scripture, <hi>He was the true light, that lighteth every man that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
into the World. I have given him for a covenant to the people, a
light to the Gentiles, and the grace of God hath appeared to all men.</hi>
Now if he did not mean univerſally, let him deny it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>I did mean univerſally then.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:49836:6"/>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>I offer to prove, that there is no Manifeſtation in the
Heathen World, where the Goſpel hath not been Preached, that
gives to that Heathen part of Mankind, or can give that which is
neceſſary to Salvation: Now neceſſary is a Scripture Word, and
if by neceſſary we mean not really neceſſary, we may deny, that
Obedience to the Light within is abſolutely neceſſary. I ſay, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary,
in Scripture Senſe, is abſolutely neceſſary, with reſpect
to Chriſt without as well as Chriſt within; for otherwiſe you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
ſhew a Scripture that will prove, that Obedience to the
Light within is abſolutely neceſſary. I offer to prove, that there
is no Manifeſtation in the Heathen World, that hath not the
Goſpel preached to them in God's ordinary way, that either does,
or can give them to believe all that is neceſſary to Salvation. But
firſt, I diſtinguiſh between Light within, as it ſignifies the great
inlightener, that is God; and the Manifeſtation and Diſcovery
that comes from this great God. I know this great God is in
all Men, he gives ſome Manifeſtation of himſelf in all; but, I ſay,
he gives no Diſcovery or Manifeſtation of himſelf to all Men,
that does or can give that Knowledge or Faith in Chriſt that is
neceſſary to Salvation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>Prove this, that there is no ſuch Manifeſtation in Man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>I ſay, I diſtinguiſh between the Light, as it ſignifies God
the great Illuminator, and the Manifeſtation, or Illumination
that comes from God. When I ſay the Manifeſtation is not
ſufficient, I do not ſay, that God is not ſufficient; but, I ſay,
that there is no Manifeſtation or Diſcovery in the Heathen World,
that God gives them ordinarily, that is ſufficient to Salvation:
This I offer to prove, 10. <hi>Acts 43. To him give all the Prophets
witneſs, that through his name whoſoever believeth in him, ſhall receive
the remiſſion of ſins.</hi> 26. Acts 18. <hi>I ſend thee to the Gentiles, to turn
them from darkneſs to light,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that they may receive forgiveneſs of
ſins, and inheritance among them which are ſanctified through FAITH
THAT IS IN ME.</hi> [This <hi>Me,</hi> is Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> as
without them.] And <hi>Rom. 10. 8, 9. The word is nigh thee, even
in thy mouth, and in thy heart: that is the word of faith which we preach,
That if thou ſhalt confeſs with thy mouth the Lord Jeſus, and believe
in thine heart, that God hath raiſed him from the dead, thou
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49836:7"/>
ſhalt be ſaved.</hi> Now, I ſay, this is the abſolutely neceſſary
terms of Salvation; and if there be no ſuch thing in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
to teach them this, and ſeeing th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re is no ſuch Manifeſtation
in the Gentile Heathen World that diſcovers or teacheth this,
then there is no Manifeſtation in them ſufficient to Salvation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>He hath not proved, that the Manifeſtation of God and
Chriſt, in his Light to all Men, doth not give, nor can give to Man,
that which is neceſſary to Salvation; becauſe he cannot bring one word
of abſolute neceſſity, or that ſaith after this manner, that without this,
and this kind of knowledge they cannot be ſaved.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>The Light within teache them and all Men, even the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,
that I muſt not commit Murther, Adultery, nor be
Drunk, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I find in Scripture as poſitively Faith in Chriſt
without us, required to remiſſion of Sin and eternal Salvation, as
obedience to the Light within us; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 21.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhould be loath to be ſo uncharitable to the poor Heathens,
which live up to their Light, as <hi>G. Keith</hi> is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>I am no more uncharitable to the Heathen, than you or
any Man; I dare not conclude, that any of the Heathens that
live vertuouſly are damned: What is wanting to Heathens in
reſpect to the outward, God may make up to them in an inward ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary
Manifeſtation. What do we know what God may
reveal to them in a dying Hour?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. U.</speaker>
               <p>I never did declare, that the Light within, without the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
Manifeſtation of Chriſt, is ſufficient for Salvation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. K.</speaker>
               <p>Whither <hi>Tho.</hi> did not ſpeak to this purpoſe, That the
Light within, without Faith in Chriſt, is ſufficient for Salvation,
I apprehend I have proved by his Paraphraſes on thoſe Scriptures
that he brought; from thoſe Scriptures, ſay I, <hi>Tho.</hi> did ſay, That
this Light, or this inward Manifeſtation, is enough for the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of Man; then, ſay I, if one thing be enough, there needs
not two: If this be enough, then there is no need of that Faith in
Chriſt that he mention'd in the Morning; which is a Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:49836:7"/>
            <p>In the Concluſion, divers of T. Upſher's Friends gave this Conſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
and ſo did he, viz.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="confession">
                        <p>It is neceſſary to Salvation, to believe in Jeſus Chriſt, that was
born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and was Crucified without the Gates of
<hi>Jeraſalem,</hi> and is aſcended into Heaven, and is there in Glory,
and from thence will come without us at the end of the World;
this we acknowledge to be our abſolute Belief, and that he is our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly
to come in a glorified Body.</p>
                        <p>This they owned as neceſſary to believe, to thoſe that live in
the Chriſtian World.</p>
                        <p>Parſon <hi>Shelton</hi> told them, This plainly did contradict the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
in their Friends Books; however, he was glad of this their
Confeſſion now.</p>
                        <closer>We having carefully compared, and thoroughly examined,
do affirm this to be a true Copy of the Conference
between <hi>G. Keith</hi> and <hi>T. Upſher,</hi> 
                           <date>the 6th of <hi>July,</hi> 1699.</date>
                           <signed>Witneſs our Hands,
Edw. Braſier.
Tho. Streaton.
Arthur Winſley, <hi>Junior.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>This</hi> 6th <hi>of</hi> July <hi>was the</hi> 5th <hi>Day of the Week, next to that</hi>
1ſt <hi>Day wherein</hi> G. Keith <hi>had charged</hi> T. Vpſher <hi>with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:49836:8"/>
            <head>A BRIEF
ACCOUNT
OF THE
Uncivil TREATMENT</head>
            <head type="sub">Vuſed by ſome principal Quakers at Colcheſter and Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtol
towards G. Keith; and ſome other material Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
in his Travelling through ſeveral places in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
this and the former Summer.</head>
            <p>THE occaſion of the above mentioned Conference (the
true Relation whereof is above given) was, That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<hi>G. Keith,</hi> at the publick Meeting-Houſe of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
called Quakers, at <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> the Second of the Firſt Month,
1699, in the Afternoon, had affirmed, That <hi>T. Vpſher</hi> had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted
in the Afternoon what he had Preached in the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon,
the which <hi>T. Vpſher</hi> denied, and put <hi>G. Keith</hi> to prove it;
whereupon it was mutually agreed by them both, to debate it
before Witneſſes on both ſides, on the <hi>6th</hi> of that Inſtant follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
as was accordingly done. The Moderators choſen to regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late
the Debate, were <hi>William Shelton,</hi> a Miniſter of the Church
of <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> and <hi>Samuel Rider,</hi> a Presbyterian there.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49836:8"/>
But it is ſit the Readers ſhould be further informed of ſome other
Particulars relating to the Difference betwixt <hi>T. Vpſher</hi> and his
Friends at <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> and <hi>G. Keith</hi> and ſome of his Friends there;
one of which is, That whereas <hi>T. Vpſher</hi> did offer a Conference
with <hi>G. Keith,</hi> in order to defend his Doctrine from being a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction,
<hi>G. Keith</hi> did readily accept it, on the Condition that
he would agree to debate it with him before Witneſſes, whether
<hi>T. Vpſher</hi> had done juſtly and Chriſtianly at a Meeting in Great
<hi>Staten</hi> in <hi>Huntingtonſhire,</hi> in the Month called <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1698. to
pronounce Woes and Curſes in the Name of the Lord againſt
<hi>G. Keith,</hi> and all that adhered to him, that were there preſent,
and came to hear him (which were many, reckoned in the U<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity
with <hi>T. Vpſher</hi> and his Friends) ſaying, God would confound,
deſtroy, and daſh to pieces both him and them, which, he ſaid,
he was moved by the Lord ſo to affirm (as many are ready to
witneſs if he deny it) but this Condition <hi>T. Vpſher</hi> would by no
means agree unto. Another is, that whereas <hi>G. Keith</hi> had been
accuſed at the ſaid Meeting at Great <hi>Staten</hi> in <hi>Huntingtonſhire,</hi> by
<hi>T. Vpſher,</hi> that he was an Apoſtate, and had wronged and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted
Friends Books in his printed Narratives, and that he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
to prove it againſt him, providing <hi>G. Keith</hi> would begin
to diſpute with him the next day; <hi>G. Keith</hi> replied, He was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
deſirous to hold the Debate with him, but it was well known
to divers there preſent, he could not begin any ſuch Meeting for
Debate next Day, being under an Engagement to be at a Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
at <hi>Bedford</hi> next Firſt Day, which was the Day following;
but he was ready to engage with him the Third Day following,
which <hi>T. Vpſher</hi> by no means would yield unto; alledging for his
Excuſe, the great need he had to be at home; which to many ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared
fallacious, becauſe he had before proffered to hold the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute
with <hi>G. Keith</hi> for two Weeks together, if he would begin
next Day. <hi>R. Bridgeman,</hi> a Friend at <hi>Huntington,</hi> did propoſe to
have the Meeting for the Debate begin next Day, and he would
undertake, in defence of <hi>G. Keith,</hi> that he had not wronged the
Friends Books in his ſaid Narratives, and proffered to hold a
Diſpute with <hi>T. Vpſher</hi> on that account, until <hi>G. Keith</hi> ſhould
have time to return to manage the Diſpute by himſelf; but this
<hi>T. Vpſher</hi> would not agree unto. Some few Days after, in the <hi>6th</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:49836:9"/>
Month called <hi>Auguſt, 1698. G. Keith</hi> came to <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> and in
the publick Meeting of the Friends there, put <hi>T. Vpſher</hi> in
mind of his former promiſe to ingage in Diſpute with <hi>G. Keith,</hi>
in order to prove him an Apoſtate, and a perverter of Friends
Books in his ſaid Narratives, telling him, He hoped he had
time now to do it, being at home; but <hi>T. Vpſher</hi> replied, Since
his former offer was not accepted, he found himſelf clear of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
ſuch Engagement. And now again in the beginning of the
<hi>5th</hi> Month called <hi>July, 1699. T. Vpſher</hi> refuſed to ingage in any
ſuch Debate with <hi>G. Keith,</hi> though earneſtly deſired by him.
And the like proffer he made to the principal Friends, called Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,
at <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> That whereas they had the laſt Summer ſent
out a Paper againſt him, ſigned by many Hands, charging him
to be an Apoſtate, and an Enemy to Truth and Friends, they
would now make that one of the Matters of debate, as well
as this, <hi>viz.</hi> Whether <hi>T. Vpſher</hi> had contradicted himſelf?
But by no means would either he or they aſſent to any ſuch
Debate, ſave only, that it might be debated before ſufficient
Witneſſes, Whether <hi>G. Keith</hi> could prove a Contradiction in
<hi>T. Vpſher</hi>'s Doctrine to himſelf, expecting that they might have
ſome advantage againſt <hi>G. Keith,</hi> if the Subject of the Debate
ſhould be confined to that alone Particular? But why they
were not as willing to debate other Matters with him as well
as that, which yet were of greater moment than that, as whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<hi>T. Vpſher</hi> had contradicted himſelf (it being very common
both to him and his Brethren to Preach Inconſiſtencies and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions
in great plenty) is eaſie to be underſtood, even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
they knew they were never able to prove againſt <hi>G. Keith,</hi>
that he was an Apoſtate, or Enemy to Truth, or guilty of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
of the hard Names they had given him. And therefore the
further to detect them, and to leave them without Excuſe, <hi>G. Keith</hi>
did yield to have a Debate with <hi>T. Vpſher</hi> only upon that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle
Head, <hi>viz.</hi> Whether <hi>T. Vpſher</hi> was guilty of Self-contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction?
The which is now left to the Judgment of the Impartial
Reader, after he has viewed and conſidered the foregoing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents.</p>
            <p>And here let it be noted, that on the ſaid Firſt Day, at <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi>
Meeting, the <hi>2d</hi> of the Fifth Month called <hi>July,</hi> 1699,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49836:9"/>
in the Forenoon, after <hi>G. Keith</hi> had peaceably ſat and heard
<hi>T. Vpſher,</hi> and their other Preachers, and ſtood up to Speak,
he was, moſt uncivilly, and contrary to the Act for Tolleration,
interrupted by many of their principal Men, called Friends,
who cried out againſt him, <hi>Thou Apoſtate, hold thy peace, this
Houſe is ours, thou haſt no right to ſpeak in it without our conſent.
G. Keith</hi> replied, He was no Apoſtate, and if they thought him
to be ſuch, they ought to prove it; and their Proof he deſir'd
to have. They told him, Friends at <hi>London</hi> had judged him
to be ſuch, and they ſtood to their Judgment. <hi>G. Keith</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied,
That was downright Popery, to believe as the Church
believed, by an implicit Faith; and as for their right to the
Houſe, his Right was as good as theirs, until they did prove, that
he had forefeited his Right which he formerly had, all being Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants
in common, and that place being no Man's proper Right,
but free to all travelling Friends of the Miniſtry among that
People, and to him as well as to any of them, until they did
prove, that he was no Friend of Truth; which he believed they
could never do, he retaining all the common Marks of a Friend,
and that he had better Principles than they, that was no bad
ſign of his being a Friend of Truth. But they continuing in
their uncivil and illegal manner of interrupting him, which
many friendly People that were preſent who were deſirous to
hear <hi>G. Keith,</hi> both of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and Diſſenters,
did blame them for, (being illegal as well as uncivil and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian)
ſome Conſtables ſeeing the Peace broke, being called
upon by ſeveral to keep the Peace, took away one, called a Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,
before the Mayor, for his illegal Behaviour, who threaten'd
to bind him over to the Peace, though divers others were as
rude and uncivil as he, eſpecially they of the richer ſort. In
the Afternoon the Mayor ſent ſeveral Conſtables to keep the
Peace, which they broke as much in the Afternoon as in the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon,
crying out at <hi>G. Keith,</hi> while he was ſpeaking, and calling
him Apoſtate, and Enemy of Truth; the which great diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
and interruption the Conſtables, who in the Afternoon were
ſent to keep the Peace, ſoon did quiet, by telling them who made
the greateſt Interruption (who generally were the richeſt Men
among the People called Quakers in that place) that they would
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49836:10"/>
take them away to the Mayor, in order to have them bound
over, if they would not forbear; whereupon, they generally, in
great haſte, went away, and as faſt as they thronged to go out,
as faſt did many more throng to get in, who were not Quakers,
but ſober and friendly People of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and
of the Diſſenters of ſeveral ſorts, who had a deſire to hear
<hi>G. Keith,</hi> and did hear him after the Friends did generally
withdraw, ſome few remaining that were his Friends in that
place, and ſome others that were friendly affected towards him.
On the <hi>4th</hi> Day following, <hi>G. Keith</hi> did again go to their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
Meeting place, which they ſuſpecting that he would do,
and ſpeak again in their Meeting as he did the foregoing
Firſt Day, which gave great content to many, and was a great
trouble to his Adverſaries, to find them ſo expoſed, and their
great and vile Errors ſo detected by <hi>G. Keith,</hi> they ſet Men
at the Door to keep him out; ſo that when he eſſayed to get
in, they hindred him: This gave occaſion to <hi>G. Keith</hi> to go
to the Mayor and complain of their uncivil and illegal treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
who forthwith commanded two Conſtables to go to their
Meeting to make free entrance for him, as accordingly was done,
(whoſe Generoſity, as well as Juſtice in that Affair, is greatly
commendable and worthy of imitation by Perſons of his Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
and Station) but after he came in and waited patiently
till their Miniſters had done, and then ſtood up to ſpeak, they
bid the Friends withdraw, the Meeting, they ſaid, was ended;
and as many of them were going out, and others coming in,
deſirous to hear <hi>G. Keith,</hi> that were not of their Profeſſion,
they ſhut the great Door, bolted and barr'd it, and knocked
in the Barrs, that the People that were got in might not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
them (leaving only a little private Door open, that few
but themſelves knew) and indeed they made ſuch diſorder, and
eſpecially the richer ſort of them, that it was a ſhame to ſee
it, to behold their rude actions, and hear their outcries againſt
<hi>G. Keith,</hi> many crying to him at once, and pulling him by the
Sleeve to be gone, inſomuch that a Friend there preſent, ſaid,
It ſeemed like <hi>Bedlam</hi> let looſe.</p>
            <p>The like Incivility and illegal Proceedings, the People called
Quakers at <hi>Briſtol</hi> uſed againſt <hi>G. Keith,</hi> the <hi>23d</hi> of the Month
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49836:10"/>
called <hi>July,</hi> 1699. who offering peaceably to come into their
Meeting-Houſe, was ſtopt by a great Guard of them they had
ſet at the Door to keep him out by Violence; he did very ſoftly
expostulate with them (and ſo did ſome other of his Friends that
came from <hi>London</hi> to countenance him, and to be Witneſſes
of their treatment towards him) that it was contrary to their
former Profeſſion, to uſe any carnal Reſiſtance; let them not
henceforth ſay, their Weapons are not carnal, for he ſaw no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Weapons they had to fight with him, but their Arms,
Shoulders, and Breaſts, wherewith they oppoſed him as he eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayed
to come in. He alſo and his Friends told them, They
would have formerly re<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>koned it Perſecution, and did ſo, when
some of their Preachers came in to oppoſe the Miniſters, both
of the Church of <hi>England</hi> and Presbyterians, in their publick
Meeting-places, and met with ſome reſiſtance on that account.
But that whi<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the more aggravates the matter againſt them, is,
that <hi>G. Keith</hi> told them that ſtood a Guard to keep him out,
he came <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Intention not to ſpeak at that time in their
Meeting, but only to hear, having a real deſire to hear how
their Miniſters did Preach, he being inform'd, that they did
preach better Doctrine than formerly; ſome of them replied,
Our Miniſters are not chang'd in their Doctrine. <hi>Charles <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ones,</hi>
Father-in law to <hi>Will. Penn</hi> Junior, ſaid concerning <hi>G. Keith,
He is a falſe Fellow, we will not truſt him.</hi> To whom <hi>G. Keith</hi>
modeſtly replied, That is not enough to call me ſo, but he
ought to prove it. I<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I (ſaid <hi>G. Keith</hi>) ſhould call thee Thief
or Adulterer, thou wouldſt p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t me to prove it. Some of them
that were the Guard at the Door asked <hi>G. Keith,</hi> What he
was? he ſaid, <hi>He was a Chriſtian.</hi> They asked again, Was he
a <hi>Quaker?</hi> he replied, He was never proud of the Name <hi>Quaker,</hi>
that Name being given to that People is a Na<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of Reproach,
which now they ſeem to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
and asked them, What <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>of a Friend of
Truth,</hi> which he had <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to his
Queſtion. One <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, who <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by <hi>G. Keith,</hi>
at the Door, If he was <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> which they
took for ſome great <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49836:11"/>
Friend. <hi>G. Keith</hi> bid them ask him, If he did not own himſelf a
Friend of Truth? he ſaid, Yea, he was a Friend of Truth; but
the Name <hi>Quaker</hi> he diſowned, as well as the Errors that were
among them. <hi>G. Keith</hi> did further Expoſtulate with them, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
If the Power of God be among you, as ye ſay it is, what
know ye, if ye let me come in, but that Power may reach me,
and bring me out of what ye call my Apoſtacy, and join me again
to you? Some of them replied, Thou doſt not believe it thy
ſelf. <hi>G. Keith</hi> anſwered, Though I do not believe it, yet that
Power might make me believe it. How many have come into
a Chriſtian Aſſembly Unbelievers, and have gone forth Believers?
am I paſt all poſſibility of Converſion? But as uncivil as the
Quakers, his old Friends, at <hi>Briſtol</hi> were to him, the People called
Baptiſts were as civil; who freely, at his requeſt, granted him
liberty at their publick Meeting-place, near to the Quaker's Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-place
(and about as capacious) to have a Meeting that Day, the
Meeting-place being called, <hi>Andrew Gifford</hi>'s Meeting-place; who
freely conſented, and his Son and Friends alſo, that he ſhould
have the uſe of it. The Meeting began about the <hi>6th</hi> Hour in
the Afternoon, which was very full of People, both of the Church
of <hi>England</hi> and other Diſſenters; who generally ſhewed their
great ſatisfaction with what they heard him ſpeak at the ſaid
Meeting. In the cloſe of the ſaid Meeting, he did intimate to
the People, his purpoſe of having another Meeting the next
Day, to begin at the ſame time, in order to detect the great
and vile Errors of the moſt approved Authors among the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,
particularly of <hi>G. W.</hi> and <hi>W. P.</hi> and in order to the
clearer detecting them, to read large and full Quotations out
of their Books, as accordingly he did; and did intimate his
purpoſe to write to <hi>W. P.</hi> and other noted Miniſters of the
People called Quakers at <hi>Briſtol,</hi> to deſire them to come; and
if they did think they were able to defend their Cauſe, they
ſhould be freely allowed, and have a fair Hearing. The next
Morning, being the <hi>24th</hi> of that Inſtant, he writ to them to
that effect; they ſent no direct Anſwer to him, but writ a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere
Letter to <hi>Andrew Gifford,</hi> and his Son, and another Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt
Teacher, called <hi>Found,</hi> greatly blaming them for letting
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49836:11"/>
him have the uſe of the Houſe, comparing what was to be done
there to a Stage-play, and <hi>G. Keith</hi> to be the Actor: And among
other frivolous and empty Reaſons they give why they will not
meet him, one was, that it was offenſive to Authority; and yet,
in the ſame Letter, they pro<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er to meet with thoſe Baptiſts if
they will Imbark on his Bottom; as if to meet with <hi>G. Keith</hi>
were offenſive to Authority, but to meet with the Baptiſts were
not; whereas neither is offenſive to them if diſcretely managed;
and if any behave themſelves indiſcretely, they are juſtly obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
to Cenſure. At the time appointed, a great Meeting of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
aſſembled (both Towns-people, and others, it being at the
beginning of the Fair time) where he laid open the Errors,
particularly of <hi>G. Whithead, W. Penn,</hi> and <hi>Edw. Burroughs,</hi> in
many Quotations, which he did publickly read out of their
Books, and which another did read the ſecond time, ſtanding
on a Table in the Peoples audience, that the People might be
ſatisfied, that the Quotations were all truly read; the Quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
were the ſame as are noted in a late printed Sheet, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<hi>An Account from Colcheſter, of the Quakers Errors againſt the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
Foundation of the Chriſtian Religion;</hi> Signed by Nine credible Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
of <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> two of which are Miniſters of the Church of
<hi>England,</hi> and two others, Non conformiſt Miniſters; and ſome
other Quotations were read out of their Books, that are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
in <hi>G. Keith</hi> his ſaid Narrative; to which, as to divers
other his Books againſt his Adverſaries, they have made no
Reply, though they moſt falſly alledge, they have replied to
all he hath publiſhed in Print againſt them, whereas there are
at leaſt Six of his late Books in Print, to which they have
made not one Line of Reply; as his <hi>2d</hi> and <hi>3d</hi> Narratives, his
Book anſwering their Arguments againſt Baptiſm and the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
the Deiſm of <hi>W. Penn</hi> and his Brethren, in anſwer to his
Diſcourſe of the general Rule of Faith and Practice; and his
late Book, called, <hi>Some of the many Fallacies of</hi> W. Penn, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
In his Paper called, <hi>Goſpel Truths,</hi> &amp;c. and his larger and ſhorter
Chatechiſms; all which do plainly detect and refute their vile
and groſs Errors and Hereſies, prejudic<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and deſtructive to
Chriſtianity. And here I give the Reader to underſtand, how
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49836:12"/>
as I was civilly treated and reſpected by ſober People, both of
the Church of <hi>England</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, at <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> and at <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtol,</hi>
ſo I found the <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Reſpect generally in all other
places where I travelled, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Summer and this, as at
<hi>Bedford, Huntington <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> bridge,</hi> and divers
other places, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> this preſent Summer,
having travelled through the ſame places again, and had conſid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erable
Meetings at them all, either in Licenſed Houſes, or ſuch,
as by the favour of the Magiſtrates of the place, were allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;
and in divers other places where I had not had Meetings
before, as at <hi>Cogſhel,</hi> in <hi>Eſſex;</hi> at <hi>Chippenham,</hi> in <hi>Wiliſhire;</hi> at
the <hi>Deviſes,</hi> at <hi>Caln,</hi> at <hi>Malebury,</hi> at <hi>Lambourn Woodlands,</hi> at
<hi>Wantage,</hi> at <hi>Oxford,</hi> at <hi>Reading;</hi> in all which places where I
had Meetings, many of which were very conſiderable for num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
of ſober, diſcreet, and well affected People, I met with
great Civility, Kindneſs, and Reſpect, for my Teſtimony to
the great Truths of the Goſpel, and againſt the great and vile
Errors that abound among the People called Quakers, which
their Leaders have drawn them into; though in divers places
above mentioned, few of the People called Quakers came to
hear me; and in ſome of them not one, ſo far as I could hear.
I generally ſent to them, to come and ſhew before the People
what they had againſt me; but they generally fled before me,
and would not ſo much as appear to reaſon the Caſe with
me. One at <hi>Caln,</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> in a great Meeting which was
in a large Barn on a Firſt Day (the laſt of the Month called
<hi>July</hi>) called <hi>John Savage,</hi> a Quaker, while I was ſpeaking, ſaid, I
ſpoke by the Spirit of the Devil; becauſe I was proving, That
the Light that is common to all Mankind, and is in Heathens,
was not the Goſpel that <hi>Paul</hi> preached, but another. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired
him not to interrupt me, but let me alone till I had
done, and then I would anſwer to what he would object;
but he ſaid nothing to me after I had done. At <hi>Huntington</hi> and
<hi>Ives</hi> alſo I met with ſome Interruption, but none of them would
come to any fair Debate with me; ſome of their Miniſtry at
<hi>Ives</hi> calling me <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Demas,</hi> but when I put them to
prove it, and offered to ſhew, that Character did not belong
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49836:12"/>
to me, but to ſome of them, they would not reaſon the caſe
with me. One of the chief Men among the Quakers in that
Town, ſaying, That place was for Preaching, but not for Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute;
and as by his means I had got liberty to ſpeak there (for
which I thanked him) but he would not ſuffer me to diſpute;
I did expoſtulate the caſe with him, Why he would be leſs fair
than the <hi>Jews,</hi> who not only ſuffered <hi>Paul</hi> to Preach, but to
Diſpute in their Synagogues. But the greateſt openn<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
reception, among any of my former Friends called Quakers I
found, was in divers Country places in <hi>Huntingtonſhire,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts;
who met in divers places on purpoſe to hear me, and
appointed ſeveral Meetings for me, at ſeveral places, both this
and the former Summer, whither they came to hear me, and
declared their ſatisfaction with my Teſtimony, and my oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
to the great Errors among the Quakers; and they have
declared, that it is their Senſe, That there is great need of
a Reformation in Doctrine among the ſaid People, and that the
great Errors contained in the Books of their great Authors
ought to be diſowned and retracted, otherwiſe a ſeparation
will neceſſarily follow; whereof <hi>Margaret Everard,</hi> a Speaker
among them, has given a plain and Chriſtian acknowledgment in
her printed Epiſtle to them; and particularly to the Miniſters
among them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:49836:13"/>
            <head>A
POSTSCRIPT
TO THE
Impartial READERS,</head>
            <head type="sub">Containing ſome Notes and Obſervations on the Aſſertions
of T. Upſher and his Brethren, diſcovering their Self-Contradictions.</head>
            <p>THE Impartial Readers are deſired to compare the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
Aſſertions of <hi>T. Vpſher</hi> here, one with another;
and alſo with the many Aſſertions of <hi>G. Whithead,
W. Penn,</hi> and others of the moſt approved Writers among the
People called Quakers, contained in their Books, as moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
quoted in <hi>G. Keith</hi>'s three printed Narratives, and in the
late printed Sheet, called, <hi>Some Account from</hi> Colcheſter <hi>of the
Quakers Errors againſt the very foundation of the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
&amp;c. and I doubt not but it will evidently appear to them,
that <hi>T. Vpſher</hi> hath both foully contradicted himſelf, and alſo
his ſaid Brethren. And eſpecially I deſire the Readers to take
notice of this one Inſtance of <hi>T. V</hi>'s Self-contradiction, in
p. 8. of the printed Copy, <hi>ad finem,</hi> he grants, that there is
univerſally in Men (both Heathens and Chriſtians) ſuch a Grace
or Manifeſtation of Chriſt, as can give them a diſcovery of that
that is neceſſary to Salvation; for which he grants, he quoted
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49836:13"/>
               <hi>Titus 2. 10, 11. Iſa. 49. 6. John</hi> 1. 9. and divers other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;
and this is the known Principle of <hi>G. Whithead, W. Penn,</hi>
and moſt of the greateſt Authors among the Quakers; and yet,
in contradiction both to himſelf and them, he hath told us (ſee
pag. 10. of the printed Relation) he never did declare, <hi>That the
Light within, without the outward Manifeſtation of Chriſt, is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
for Salvation.</hi> And yet (as in the ſame pag. 10.) he did plead,
that Heathens are ſaved (who live up to their Light) and yet
have no K<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owledge or Faith of Chriſt's outward Manifeſtation.
Again, pray let the Reader well conſider this Aſſertion of <hi>T. V.
That he never declared that <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Light within, without the outward
Manifeſtation, was ſufficient to Salvation;</hi> and his and his Brethren
of <hi>Colcheſter</hi> their Aſſertion (as in pag. 11.) that i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute
Belief, <hi>That Faith in Chriſt, as he did outwardly come,</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>and was Crucified, and as he is outwardly to come in a glorified Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi>
is neceſſary to their Salvation, and compare it with <hi>G. Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi>
his Aſſertion, in his late Antidote againſt the Venom of
the Snake, p. 28. where he plainly affirmeth, <hi>That the Quakers
are offended with</hi> G. K. <hi>for undervaluing the Light within, and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
it is not ſufficient to Salvation, or not ſufficient without ſomething
elſe.</hi> That ſomething elſe he confeſſeth, is (according to <hi>G. K.</hi>)
Chriſt's outward Manifeſtation, and coming in the Fleſh, and
the Doctrine and Faith of it, without which, <hi>G. K.</hi> hath affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
the Light within either Heathen or Chriſtian is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
to Salvation; for which Aſſertion of his, not only <hi>G. Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,
W. Penn,</hi> and generally the moſt approved Writers and
Preachers among the Quakers, but alſo <hi>T. Vpſher,</hi> and moſt of
his Brethren at <hi>Colcheſter (John Rallet,</hi> and a few more at <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi>
excepted, who own <hi>G. K</hi>'s Doctrine to be ſound) have
judged him to be an Apoſtate, and do ſtill ſo judge him; this
being the chief Controverſie betwixt them and him, <hi>viz.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
the Light within be ſufficient to Salvation without Chriſt's
outward Manifeſtation and coming in the Fleſh, his Death and
Sufferings, and the Doctrine and Faith of it, which are that
ſomething elſe, without which, no Light in Men is ſufficient
to Salvation? And yet now <hi>T. V.</hi> and theſe his <hi>Colcheſter</hi> Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
by their late ſolemn Confeſſion, have declared themſelves
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49836:14"/>
to be of the ſame Faith in the caſe with <hi>G. K.</hi> ſo that by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable
conſequence, either <hi>G. K.</hi> is no Apoſtate for his ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<hi>The light within is not ſufficient to Salvation without ſomething
elſe,</hi> or if they think he is for his ſo affirming, they are as
great <hi>Apoſtates</hi> as he, and guilty of the ſame <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> with him.
Again, is it not a palpable Contradiction betwixt theſe <hi>Colche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi>
Quakers, who ſay it is their abſolute Belief, That Faith in
Chriſt without them, is neceſſary to their Salvation; and
<hi>G. Whithead,</hi> who hath poſitively and expreſly affirmed, That
it is contrary to Scripture to confide in Chriſt without Men;
and to tell of a Chriſt whoſe perſon is above the Clouds, and of
a Chriſt within, is to make two Chriſts. See his Book, <hi>Truth
defending the Quakers,</hi> p. 65. and p. 23. And in his Book called
<hi>The Light and Life,</hi> p. 61. he ſaith, It is contrary to Scripture
(viz. <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.) for People to ſeek their Saviour
above the Clouds and Firmament, or to look to the Blood that
was ſhed at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for Juſtification. And in p. 56. he ſaith (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding
<hi>Acts</hi> 20. 28.) Now the Blood of God, or that Blood
that relates to God, muſt needs be ſpiritual, he being a Spirit;
and the Covenant of God is inward and ſpiritual, and ſo is
the Blood of it. Here <hi>G. Whithead</hi> perfectly agreeth with
<hi>W. Bailly</hi> in his Notion, That the Blood is the Life, and the
Life is the Light of Men (ſee <hi>W. B</hi>'s Teſtimony of the Light
in him, pag. 23.) This I did take to be alſo <hi>T. V</hi>'s Notion of
the Blood, ſeeing he told us, he differ'd not in his Faith from
other Friends; and yet he will not allow, that by the Blood of
Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7. 14. he meant the Light, ſee <hi>True Relation,</hi> p. 5. This
is another Inſtance of his Contradiction both to himſelf and his
Friends, from whom, he ſaid, he doth not differ. As to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction,
making the Faith in Chriſt, as he outwardly came in
the Fleſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> neceſſary to the Salvation of thoſe that live in the
Chriſtian World, but not to the Heathen Gentiles. I query
firſt, Doth not the Scripture plainly refute that diſtinction, that
holdeth not forth two ways of Juſtification and of eternal Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
one by Faith in Chriſt without Men, another by obedience
to the Light within, without Faith in Chriſt without Men;
which is a plain ſetting up of Salvation by the Covenant of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49836:14"/>
Works; ſee <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 26. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 30. Where Faith in Chriſt
Jeſus, as he outwardly ſuffered, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is declared to be neceſſary,
as well to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> as the <hi>Jews.</hi> 2. If the Light in Heathens
be ſufficient to Salvation, without the Faith of Chriſt's outward
Manifeſtation, is it not as ſufficient in Chriſtians without that
Faith (otherwiſe it is leſs ſufficient in Chriſtians than in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens)
and conſequently that Faith is ſuperfluous, or at leaſt
not more neceſſary in Chriſtians than in Heathens? 3. Why
is that Faith neceſſary to the Chriſtians but not to the Heathen?
If it be ſaid, becauſe that the Doctrine concerning Chriſt, as he
outwardly came and was Crucified, is Preached, or declared to
the Chriſtians (though not to the Heathens) by the Scriptures
and other outward means. But the Queſtion is again, Is that
Faith neceſſary to us, becauſe externally the Doctrine is Preached
or declared to us, then let it not be Preached or declared to them
that are ignorant of it, and they ſhall be ſaved without it; yea,
according to this corrupt Notion, they ſhall be more eaſily ſaved
without it than with it; becauſe the dictates of the Light within,
as common to all Men, are fewer and eaſier to be obeyed, than the
many Commands given by Chriſt in the Writings of the New
Teſtament. Again, if the Doctrine of Chriſt, as outwardly Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the Faith of it be neceſſary to us in <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi>
becauſe Preached or declared to us, what makes the Faith of that
Declaration neceſſary to us? Not <hi>the Scriptures,</hi> ſeeing they are not
with them the Rule of Faith and Practice to Chriſtians; nor the
Light within, becauſe the Light within doth not, without the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal
Doctrine, teach us that Faith; and if the external Doctrine
be neceſſary to have that Faith, it is a plain caſe the Light within
is not ſufficient to us, without the external Doctrine, to beget
that Faith in us, and conſequently is not ſufficient to our Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
without that external Doctrine. That the Scripture is not
to them the Rule of Faith and Practiſe, is expreſly affirmed by
<hi>W. P.</hi> in his Diſcourſe of the General Rule of Faith and Practice,
Reprinted this Year, 1699. To which I have printed an Anſwer,
called, <hi>The Deiſm of</hi> W. Penn <hi>and his Brethren.</hi> If the external
Doctrine be neceſſary to be added to the Light within, in order to
give the Faith of Chriſt's outward Manifeſtation and coming in
the Fleſh, then the Light within is not ſufficient without it, if not
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49836:15"/>
neceſſary; then ſeeing the Light is the ſame in kind and nature (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to theſe my Adverſaries among the Quakers) both in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens
and Chriſtians, the Light in the Heathens doth as much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige
them to have that Faith, as it doth oblige us to have it in
order to Salvation; becauſe, according to this way of arguing, the
Light within doth, without the neceſſity of the Scripture, or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
means, reveal it in Chriſtians, and therefore alſo in the
Heathens; or if it doth not in the Heathens, and yet doth it in
the Chriſtians, then it is of a differing kind, becauſe of a differing
ability, as not performing that in the Heathens which it perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
in the Chriſtians; by all which it doth plainly appear, how
ſelf-contradictory and inconſiſtent theſe <hi>Colcheſter</hi> Quakers are,
both with themſelves, and with their moſt approved Authors and
Brethren at <hi>London,</hi> and elſewhere, and indeed all of them one
with another.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="certificates">
            <div type="statement">
               <head>Here followeth a Certificate of Parſon Shelton to the truth
of the Caſe in debate betwixt G. Keith and T. Upſher,
as the ſaid Parſon Shelton ſum'd it up at the end of the
Conference; atteſted likewiſe by Nine other credible Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes:
And another Certificate of his to the truth of the
Relation of the ſaid Conference that is now printed.</head>
               <p>WHereas I <hi>William Shelton</hi> am informed, that a Quaker
in <hi>Colcheſter</hi> has Written to a Quaker in <hi>London,</hi> that I
ſtood up at a Conference in <hi>Colcheſter</hi> (when <hi>G. Keith</hi>
was to prove, that <hi>T. Vpſher</hi> had contradicted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf)
and did declare openly, that <hi>G. Keith</hi> had wrongfully charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<hi>T. Vpſher</hi> with contradicting himſelf, and that <hi>G. Keith</hi> was,
in my Judgment, quite routed, and worſted in that Diſpute; I
do hereby teſtifie, that it is a very falſe Report, and he that wrote
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49836:15"/>
the Letter has done me great wrong; for I do averr, that (as I
was not, that I remember, deſired to do it, ſo) I did not at all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
my Judgment at that time, whether <hi>G. Keith</hi> had wronged
<hi>T. Vpſher</hi> or no. That which I then ſaid, was a ſumming up the
ſtate of the Caſe in theſe words, or, I am ſure to this Senſe; but
conditionally, <hi>viz.</hi> If <hi>G. Keith</hi> has proved, that <hi>T. Vpſher</hi> in the
Forenoon did affirm, that Faith in Chriſt, as he was born of the
Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and dyed without the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended
into Heaven, and is there in his Glory, and ſhall come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain
at the end of the World, is abſolutely neceſſary (as ſome ſay
he ſaid) or (as others) is neceſſary to Salvation; and if in the
Afternoon he did affirm, that the Light within, or Chriſt within,
or Grace within, (or any other word in uſe with them of the ſame
ſignification) is ſufficient to Salvation, then <hi>G. Keith</hi> has proved
<hi>T. Vpſher</hi> contradicted himſelf. Taking a Pen in my Hand, I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded;
If I ſhould ſay this Pen is neceſſary for me to write with,
and ſhould ſay, I can write without it, I ſhould contradict my
ſelf. To this they generally aſſented, that I had ſtated the Caſe
right and fair; and this if proved was a Contradiction. But
whether <hi>G. Keith</hi> had proved this or no, I did not ſay on either
ſide.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>William Shelton,</signed> 
                  <dateline>
                     <date>July 17. 1699.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="statement">
               <p>That thus <hi>William Shelton</hi> ſummed up the State of the Caſe in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate
betwixt <hi>G. Keith</hi> and <hi>T. Vpſher,</hi> the 6th of <hi>July,</hi> 1699, as
he himſelf has above declared, is further atteſted by <hi>Daniel Gilſon,</hi>
and <hi>John Gledhil,</hi> Non-conformiſt Miniſters, <hi>Samuel Ryder,</hi> the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
choſen by the Quakers for their Moderator, <hi>Edward Braſier</hi> and
<hi>Thomas Streaton,</hi> who were two of them that took the Conference
in Short-hand, <hi>Jacob Johnſon, Peter Covency, Noah Raoiil,</hi> and
<hi>Thomas Cook,</hi> all very credible Perſons (the laſt of which, <hi>viz.
Tho. Cook,</hi> is a noted Quaker, and of good report among the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers
at <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> but that they blame him for being a friend to
<hi>G. Keith,</hi> and for owning his Doctrine) all which above-named
Perſons have ſigned to a Certificate of the truth of <hi>W. Shelton's</hi>
Teſtimony, as above delivered. The ſaid <hi>William Shelton,</hi> at the
end of his ſaid Teſtimony, adds theſe following words. If I
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49836:16"/>
may but know who it is has done me this wrong, I doubt not but
I ſhall prove to his Face, by many credible Witneſſes then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
that he has abuſed me, and conſequently done his Cauſe
wrong, by thinking to ſtrengthen it with ſuch a notorious Lye.
When I have taken a more thorough view of the Narrative of that
Conference, than I have yet time to do, then it may be time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
to ſay how far <hi>G. Keith</hi> has proved what he undertook.
In the mean time, becauſe my words are ſo liable to be miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented,
I only ſay, that I think <hi>G. Keith</hi> has no reaſon to be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
nor <hi>T. Vpſher</hi> and his Friends to boaſt of that days Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Witneſs my Hand, 
<date>this 17th Day of <hi>July,</hi> 1699.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Will. Shelton.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="statement">
               <p>And in another Paper, he gives the following Teſtimony to the
truth of the Relation (that is now in Print) of that Conference.</p>
               <p>Being (at <hi>G. Keith</hi>'s requeſt) preſent at a Conference between
him and <hi>T. Vpſher</hi> in <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> on the 6th Day of this Inſtant <hi>July,</hi>
and having read over the Narrative of the ſaid Conference, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed
by <hi>Edward Braſier, Thomas Streaton,</hi> and <hi>Arthur Winſley</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior,
who took it in Short-hand Writing, I do hereby teſtifie,
That to the beſt of my remembrance (though I do not undertake
for every word) this Narrative ſubſcribed by the forenamed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
is, as to the ſubſtance of it, a juſt and true Account of the ſaid
Conference; and I am not aware of any thing unduly expreſſed to
the advantage or diſadvantage of either ſide.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Witneſs my Hand,
<date>this 14th Day of <hi>July,</hi> 1699.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Will. Shelton.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAGE 10. l. 11. for</hi> them, <hi>r.</hi> me. <hi>p, 12. l. 3. for</hi> unſed, <hi>r.</hi> uſed. <hi>p. 12. l. 12.
for</hi> Firſt, <hi>r.</hi> Fifth.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49836:16"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
