<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Kings Most Excellent Majesty at Oxford by H.K., D.D.</title>
            <author>Killigrew, Henry, 1613-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-03">2005-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47366</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K445</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K503_CANCELLED</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18028</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11865276</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11865276</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50085</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A47366)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50085)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 35:17 or 243:E93, no 13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Kings Most Excellent Majesty at Oxford by H.K., D.D.</title>
                  <author>Killigrew, Henry, 1613-1700.</author>
                  <author>King, Henry, 1592-1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[21] p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Web,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Henry Killigrew by BM and Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.); also attributed to Henry King.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and authorship in some doubt. Cf. Madan.</note>
                  <note>This item identified at reel 35:17 as Wing K503 (number cancelled in Wing CD-ROM, 1996), and at reel 243:E.93, no. 13 as Wing (CD-ROM, 1996) K445.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library and Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:50085:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>CHARLES BY THE GRACE OF GOD King of England, Scotland, France and Ireland, Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of the Faith, &amp;c.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50085:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON <hi>PREACHED</hi> Before the KINGS Most Excellent Majesty at OXFORD,</p>
            <p>By <hi>H. K.</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD, Printed for</hi> W. Web. 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:50085:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50085:2"/>
            <head>To the CHRISTIAN Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or somuch as I was at this Sermon among other au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditours, who judged it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry divine like for the matter and the manner of handling of it, and afterward understood that divers which heard it preached, and more which did onely heare of it by the report of others, were very desirous to have the view either writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,
<pb facs="tcp:50085:3"/>
or rather printed: therefore ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving obtained a copy of it for mine own use, I thought it expedient to commit it to the presse, for the publick good of all such as will vouchsafe to read it with patiencee, and judge, of it by the rule of charity.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:50085:3"/>
            <head>A Sermon preached at Oxford before the Kings Most Excellent Majesty.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Psal. 101. 1.</bibl>
               <q>I will sing mercy and judgement, to thee, O Lord, will I sing.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Psalm the Kingly Prophet <hi>David</hi> declareth, how he will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have himselfe in his Kingdome: first touching his own person: and afterward touching his subjects, both in the Coutrt, and in the Countrey.</p>
            <p>In this first verse of the Psalme, he undertaketh or promiseth to sing; the dittie of the song is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and judgement. The person to whom he sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth is expressed in these words, <hi>to thee, O Lord, will I sing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In that he assumeth to sing the matter which he hath in hand, it implyeth that he will doe it with joy, with a loud voice, and with his full power. <note place="margin">Jam. 5. 13 Psal. 137. 1. 2. 3. 4</note> It argueth joy: <hi>For is any man among you afflicted? let him pray is any merry let him sing:</hi> And how should the children of the Captivity sing one of the longs of <hi>Zion</hi> in a strange land, when they sit mourning and weeping by the Rivers of Babell, where they hung up their harps upon the willows that grow thereby? And as a pleasant song requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a merrie heart so doth it also a stretched out
<pb facs="tcp:50085:4"/>
voice with great strength put thereunto. So then by this example of <hi>David</hi> we are taught in the meditations of our heart, the words of our tongue and the actions of our life, tending to godlinesse &amp; justice, to do all with chearfullnes, fervency, and to the utmost of our power. For example, in the case of our inward affection toward God, our duty is, <hi>To love the Lord our God with all our heart, with all our soule, and with all our strength.</hi> In the <note place="margin">Deut. 6. 5.</note> matter of Gods worship, joyned with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing of his glory, &amp; the furtherance of our sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: behold David <hi>danceth before the Ark with all his might:</hi> Of the Kingdome of Christ it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesied <note place="margin">2. Sam. 6. 14.</note> thus by the Psalmist: <hi>Thy people shall come willingly at the time of assembling, thine army in holy beautie. The zeal of Gods house did eat up the Princely</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Psal. 110. 3. Psal. 69. 9.</note> 
               <hi>prophet.</hi> And from the time of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptist hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, <hi>The Kingdome of heaven suffereth violence, and the violent take it by force. If</hi> Paul <hi>come to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 12. Act. 17. 16. Act. 14. 14</note> 
               <hi>and see the Citie subject to Idolatrie, his spirit will be stirred within him, and if he and</hi> Barnab<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>being as Lystra perceive the people to sacrifice and there by the names of Iupiter <hi>and</hi> Mercurie, then they will <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in signe of d<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>asting <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it. If Moses <hi>when he cometh down from the Mount understand that the people in his absence have <note place="margin">Exod. 32 15. unto the <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1.</note> 
                     <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="4 lines">
                        <desc>〈4 lines〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Calfe he burneth it in the fire, and grindeth it to
<pb facs="tcp:50085:4"/>
powder and streweth it upon the water, and maketh the children of Israel to drink of it, to despite them of their Idolatrie.</hi> If we speake of charitable almes, then by S. <hi>Pauls</hi> rule, <hi>The Lord loveth a chearfull giver.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 9. 7</note> If execution must be done upon the enemies of God and his holy Church, then <hi>Ieremie</hi> pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth him cursed that doth the worke of the Lord neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jer. 48. 1<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> We should by <hi>Pauls</hi> advice to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, <hi>be servent in spirit.</hi> And by this admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 14. Tit. 2. 14.</note> given in the Epistle to <hi>Titus, we ought to be zealous of good works.</hi> And surely, if any doe frame themselves after the pattern of the Laodiceans who were luke warm, neither hot nor cold, it will come to passe that God shall spew them out of <note place="margin">Apoc. 3. 16.</note> his mouth.</p>
            <p>To prevent which inconvenience, <hi>David</hi> here affirmeth that he will sing this heavenly ditie of mercy and judgement: the which words may be construed two wayes, the Analogie of faith pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served. First, in respect of the time past by way of praise for Gods mercy toward himself, and Gods judgements against his enemies. Secondly in regard of the time to come touching the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Kingdom by way of practice of mercy toward the good, and of judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the bad.</p>
            <p>The first interpretation yeeldeth unto us this doctrine in generall, that we should shew our selves thankfull unto almighty God for all his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits bestowed upon us according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God joyned with a comfortable
<pb facs="tcp:50085:5"/>
               <hi>Call upon me in the day of trouble, and so will I deli<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">Psal. 50. 15.</note> 
               <hi>thee, and thou shalt glorifie mee.</hi> And after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Psalmist saying: <hi>Open thou my lips O Lord:</hi> (that is, give me occasion to praise thee <note place="margin">Psal. 51. 15.</note> 
               <hi>and my mouth shall shew forth thy praise.</hi> And if God vouchsafe to deliver <hi>Davids</hi> desolate soule from the sword and the power of the dog, from the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <note place="margin">Psal. 22. 20. 21. 22.</note> mouth, and the hornes of the Unicornes, then will <hi>David</hi> declare his name unto his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and praise him in the midst of the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. But alas if a view be taken of us upon whom the ends of the world be come, it is to be feared that we shall be found no better in this case then they were in the daies of our Saviour Christ, when as <hi>of ten lepers that were cleansed, onely one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to give thanks.</hi> And verily so have worldly <note place="margin">Luk. 17. 15. 16.</note> minded men been usually accustomed to mistake the originall and spring-head of the temporall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits which they receive, that the Nimrods of the earth, which lived in the dayes of <hi>Habbacud</hi> when as they took up all with the angle, and <note place="margin">Hab. 1. 15 16.</note> catched it in their net, land gathered it in this yearn, whereof they rejoyced and were glad, thee they sacrificed to their net, and burnt incense to their yearne, because (in their falso imagination) by them their portion became fat, and their mea<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> plenteous; that is they flattered themselves, and gloried in their own wit, force, and power, as though there by they had gotten all their victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries with increase of wealth and honour, and so robbed God of his glory.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:50085:5"/>
In revenge of such kind of unthankfulnesse, when as superstitious people, in the time of <hi>Hosea,</hi> ascribed <note place="margin">Hos. 2. 5. to the 11.</note> unto their lovers, (that is to their Idols) the gift of their bread and wine, corne and oyle, wooll and flax, silver and Gold, then Almighty God returned in his high displeasure, and took away his corn in the time thereof, and his wine in the season thereof, and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered his wooll and his flax which he had lent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them for a time to cover their shame withall.</p>
            <p>But <hi>David</hi> to avoid the like both sinne and punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment also thereof, protesteth here, <hi>that he will sing the mercie of God.</hi> I say the mercy of God toward him, and not his owne merits. And here upon it was that being hardly beset, and greatly distressed and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed in the daies of <hi>Saul,</hi> while his hope of the Kingdome was suspended, he maketh his prayer in these termes, <hi>Shew thy marvellous mercies thou that art the Saviour of them that trust in thee, from such as resist</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Psal. 17. 7</note> 
               <hi>thy right hand.</hi> And he hopeth one day to come into the house of God, <hi>in the multitude of his mercie,</hi> looke <note place="margin">Psal. 5. 7.</note> back to former ages: and you shall find <hi>Iacob</hi> at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from Mesopotamia, homeward in the way to Canaan being greatly enriched after the service of almost three apprentiships under <hi>Laban,</hi> framing his prayer of thanksgiving in this wise. <hi>O Lord I am not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 32. 10.</note> 
               <hi>worthy of the least of all thy mercies, and all the truth, which thou hast shewed unto thy servant: for with my staffe came I over this Iordan, and now have I gotten two hands.</hi> And I conceive assured hope, that by this example my gracious Soveraigne doth often meditate upon the mercy of God toward himself, in respect of the great increase of temporall blessings which he hath found and felt. And as for us beloved, all of us which
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:50085:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:50085:6"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:50085:7"/>
be ranged in the number of subjects, considering on the one side the manifold and heinous sinnes, which have formerly reigned amongst us, both unpunished and unrepented of: and on the other side the fearfull dangers that we have escaped, I can say nothing, but that which <hi>Ieremie</hi> spake in his lamentations long ago: <hi>It is the mercies of the Lord that we are not consumed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lam. 3. 22</note> 
               <hi>his compassions faile not.</hi> Pray we therefore on the behalfe of our King, that it would please Almighty God to pronounce of him as he spake in elder time, by <hi>Nathan</hi> of <hi>Salomon: I will be his father, and he shall be</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 7. 14. 15.</note> 
               <hi>my son, and if he sin, I will chasten him with the rod of men, and with the plagues of the children of men, but my mercy shall not depart away from him.</hi> Pray we likewise for this Church of England, Scotland, and Ireland, that God would vouchsafe to hallow it with that blessed promise which in <hi>Isay</hi> was uttered over the whole church of Christ militant by the spirit of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesie thus; <hi>The mountaines shall remove, and the hills shall fall downe: but my mercie shall not depart from thee, neither shall the covenant of my peacefull away, saith the Lord, that hath compassion on thee.</hi> This done, then may both King and Subjects, even every of us utter with joyfull chear that which we reade in the Psalm, <hi>I will sing the mercies of the Lord for ever.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Psal. 89. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thus <hi>David</hi> having already sung the mercy of God toward himself, he will sing also the judgement of God toward his enemies. And to begin with his grand and capitall enemie King <hi>Saul:</hi> after that he had been wounded by the archers of the Philistines, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">1. Sam. 31. 3. 4,</note> left the uncircumcised should have come and thrust him thorow, and have mocked him, he took a sword, and fell upon it himself: and so a cruell life
<pb facs="tcp:50085:7"/>
had a desperate end. And as for <hi>Davids</hi> chief enemies in the Court among <hi>Sauls</hi> favourites, namely <hi>Chush</hi> and <hi>Doeg,</hi> we read the ruine of them both. For <hi>Chush</hi> travailed with mischief, and brought forth a lie: he <note place="margin">Psal 7. 1. 15. 16.</note> made a pit and digged it, and fell into it himself, his mischief returned upon his own head, and his cruelty fell upon his own pate. And after that <hi>Doeg</hi> had for a space boasted himself in his wickednesse, that being a <note place="margin">Psal. 52. 15.</note> man of power he could doe mischiefe, at the length God plucked him out of his tabernacle, and rooted him out of the land of the living. Beside these particulars, God gave unto <hi>David,</hi> the necks of <note place="margin">Psal 18. 40. 42.</note> his enemies in generall, and he did beat them as small as the dust before the wind, and he did tread them flat as the clay in the streets. Thus let thine enemies pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish O Lord, and the King enemies likewise, but let <note place="margin">J<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. 5. 31.</note> him be as the Sunne when he riseth in his might.</p>
            <p>Now the good that may enfue by the considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the fall of Gods &amp; the Churches enemies, is of two sorts. First God is thereby magnified, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in the person of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> whom God appointed <note place="margin">Ex. 9 16.</note> for this cause, to shew his power in him, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his name throughout all the world. And in the destruction of the Babilonians, the earth was filled with the knowledge of the glory of the Lord, as the <note place="margin">Hab. 2. 14</note> waters cover the Sea. Secondly, men (if they have grace) may thereby be edified, according to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of the faithfull in <hi>Isai,</hi> saying: <hi>We O Lord have</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Isa. 26. 9.</note> 
               <hi>waited for thee, in the way of thy judgements: for seeing thy judgements are in the earth, the inhabitants of the world shall learn righteousnesse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto <hi>David</hi> hath sung <hi>mercy and judgement,</hi> in respect of the time past by way of praise and thanks-giving.
<pb facs="tcp:50085:8"/>
Now he proceedeth to sing the same song in regard of the time to come touching the administrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Kingdom by way of practice, knowing that <hi>the duty of Princes and publick Magistrates, is, to be the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>Rom. 13. 3.</p>
                  <p>1 Pet. 2. 14</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ministers of God for the wealth of them that do well by the exercise of godlinesse and honesty, and to take vengeance on them that doe evill, committing impiety and iniquity.</hi> And these two <hi>mercy,</hi> and <hi>judgement,</hi> must go hand in hand, being in association combined together lest if they were altogether, and utterly severed, then mercie without judgement might turne into foolish pity, and judgement without any temper of mercie might become extreme cruelty.</p>
            <p>And first to speak of <hi>Mercie,</hi> happy is that Prince who hath the wisedome and the will to be mercifull to whom, and when, and where it is expedient. <hi>For such mercie and truth preserveth the King; and his throne</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>Pro. 20. 28</p>
                  <p>Psal. 85. 10.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>shall be established with mercie,</hi> Moreover happy is that countrey, where mercie and truth meet together, and so righteousnesse and peace kisse one another, and worldly happy are those subjects to whom the prince vouchsafeth to shew mercie and loving kindnesse. <hi>For the Kings wrath is like the roaring of a Lion, and as mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sengers of death: but in the light of his countenance is life,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 16. 14 15 &amp; 19. 12.</note> 
               <hi>and his favour is as a cloud of the latter raine, and like the dew upon the grasse.</hi> And <hi>David</hi> well knowing how laudable and honourable it was to be mercifull with discretion, being established in his Kingdome, he made enquiry if there remained yet alive any of the house of <hi>Saul,</hi> in whom he might shew the mercie of <note place="margin">2 Sam. 9. 1. 3.</note> God (that is, such mercie as is acceptable to God) for his old deare friend <hi>Ionathans</hi> sake. And we find it to be a laudable custome of Princes, that I may speak it
<pb facs="tcp:50085:8"/>
the Scripture phrase in the Psalmes, by hearing the mourning of the prisoners, and delivering the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren <note place="margin">
                  <p>Psal. 102 1.</p>
                  <p>Isa. 58. 7.</p>
               </note> of death. And in <hi>Isay,</hi> by loosing the bands of wickednesse, and by taking off the heavy burdens, by letting the oppressed go free, and by breaking every yoke, former extortions, exactions, and other grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous oppressions: O how faire a thing is this mercie <note place="margin">Eccles. 35. 19.</note> in the time of anguish and trouble? It is like a cloud of raine that cometh in the time of drought. Thus can <hi>David</hi> shew <hi>Mercie,</hi> when he thinketh it meet, and <hi>Iudgement</hi> also when the matter so requireth it. For he <note place="margin">
                  <p>Prov. 16 12.</p>
                  <p>Isa. 32. 17.</p>
               </note> is not ignorant, that <hi>the establishment of the Kings throne is Iustice, and Iudgement: and the seat thereof is peace.</hi> Yea manifold is the good effect which followeth the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting of justice upon malefactours.</p>
            <p>First it is profitable to the offendours themselves, <hi>for affliction giveth understanding. Foolishnesse is bound</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 22. 15.</note> 
               <hi>in the heart of a child: but the rod of correction shall drive it away from him. The rod and correction give wisedome:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 29. 15</note> 
               <hi>the blewnesse of the wound serveth to purge the evill, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20 30</note> 
               <hi>the stripes within the bowells of the bellie:</hi> that is, sharpe punishment which pierceth even the inward parts, is profitable for the wicked to bring them to amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But on the contrarie, <hi>he that spareth the rod</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 13 14</note> 
               <hi>spilleth the child:</hi> witnesse the example of <hi>Hely</hi> towards his sonnes <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phinehas.</hi> And of <hi>David</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <note place="margin">
                  <p>1 Sam. 2. 12. 22. 23. 24.</p>
                  <p>1 Reg. 1. 6</p>
               </note> his son <hi>Adonijah</hi> whom he would not displease from his childhood, to say, <hi>Why hast thou done so?</hi> and so in the end he proved a presumptuous traytor, and rank rebell. Secondly, this exemplarie justice is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious unto others that are by-standers and behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, who may learn to beware by their neighbours harms, <note place="margin">Deut. 13. 11. and 17. 13. and 21. 21.</note> according as <hi>Moses</hi> willeth punishment to bee afflicted upon the transgressours of the law, that Israel may hear and feare.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:50085:9"/>
Whereupon <hi>Salomon</hi> groundeth this exposition of policie, or judicial proceedings: <hi>Smile a scorner and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 10.</note> 
               <hi>the foolish will beware:</hi> that is to say, the simple and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant men learn their duty when they see the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked punished. And for this cause did God by Moses command that the censers of <hi>Korah</hi> and his complice being 250 in number, who had been destroyed and <note place="margin">Numb. 16 37. 38. &amp;c</note> consumed by a fire that came out from the Lord, should be taken and beaten forth into broad plates, for the covering of the Altar, that they might be a signe to the children of Israell of Gods judgements against all mutinous, i<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ditious, and rebellious persons. Whereas on the other side, If the incestuous person at Corinth be not censured by excommunication, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, <hi>a little leaven leaveneth the whole lump.</hi> And by <note place="margin">1. Cor. 5. 6 Eccles. 8. 11.</note> the judgement of the preacher, because sentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst an evill worke is not executed speedily, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the heart of the children of men, is fully set in them to doe evill: that is, by way of abridgement, where Iustice is delayed, there sinne reigneth. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Princely Psalmist promises in the last verse <note place="margin">Psal. 101. 8.</note> of this Psalme, betimes to destroy all the wicked of the land, that he might cut off all the workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity from the citie of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the executing of hainous and notorious offenders withholdeth the wrath of God from the <note place="margin">
                  <p>Deut. 17. 12. &amp;. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2 22.</p>
                  <p>Josh. 7. 1. 5</p>
               </note> publick state of the Realme, by taking evill out of Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell. But the unpunishing of <hi>Achan,</hi> (though his crime was unknown) was so hurtfull to the host of Israell, that the hearts of the people melted away like water. Neither could the great dearth in <hi>Davids</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 21. 1. 6. 14.</note> time be removed, nor God fully pacified for <hi>Sauls</hi> cruelty, long before committed against the Gibeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,
<pb facs="tcp:50085:9"/>
till seven of <hi>Sauls</hi> ofspring were hung up to the Lord in Gibeah of <hi>Saul.</hi> In brief due execution done upon great and grievous malefactors, is a sacifice ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable unto God, and a preservative of the state of the Church and commonwealth. Therefore, <hi>a wise King scattereth the wicked, and causeth the wheel to turne</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 20. 26.</note> 
               <hi>over them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here must be inserted a caveat against all cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in execution of justice. For by the law of <hi>Moses</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in seeking of birds nests, it was not lawfull to take <note place="margin">Deut. 22. 6</note> the damme with the young. Neither might the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the executed malefactour remain all night up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">Deut. 21. 22. 23.</note> the tree. Beside this, God would not turn to them of Damascus, because they had threshed <hi>Gilead</hi> with threshing instruments of iron, neither would he turne to the children of <hi>Ammon,</hi> because they had ript up the women with child of <hi>Gilead</hi> that they might enlarge <note place="margin">Amos 1. 3 13.</note> their own border: there is like to be judgement mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilesse to <hi>Pilate,</hi> who would shew no mercy: but min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled <note place="margin">
                  <p>Jam. 2. 13</p>
                  <p>Luke 13. 1</p>
                  <p>Pro. 12. 10</p>
               </note> the bloud of some that had offended him, with their own sacrifices. Yet no marvell it is that he did so, for though the righteous man regardeth the life of his beast, yet even the mercies of the wicked are cruel.</p>
            <p>Howbeit, though cruelty is alwaies to be abhorred, yet remisnesse in dealing with the adversaries of the <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruth, the practicers and mainteiners of a false wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, is likewise to be excluded, because it is most pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ilous to the church of God, as appeareth by the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story of the Canaanites, who by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nivency of the Israelites being permitted to converse with them, and to live quietly among them, became prickes in their <note place="margin">Numb. 33 55.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies, and thornes in their sides. When <hi>Ioash</hi> the King of Israel came downe to visit <hi>Elisha</hi> lying sick upon
<pb facs="tcp:50085:10"/>
his death bed, he was willed by the Prophet to take into his hand the arrow of the Lords deliverance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Aram,</hi> and to smite the ground: wherupon he smote thrice and ceased: But the man of God was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with him and said, thou shouldest have smitten five or six times, so thou shouldest have smitten <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Reg. 13. 14. to the 20.</note> till thou hadst consumed it, where now thou shalt smite <hi>Aram</hi> but thrice; the meaning is, that <hi>Ioa<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> deserved just reproof, and great blame, because he see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med content to have victorie against the enemies of God, for twice or thrice, and had not a zeal to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them continually, and destroy them utterly. <note place="margin">
                  <p>1: Sam. 15 22. 23.</p>
                  <p>1 Reg 20. 42.</p>
                  <p>2 Chio. 15. 16.</p>
               </note> And surely <hi>Saul</hi> cannot spare <hi>Agag</hi> saving to his own hurt. Neither can <hi>Ahab</hi> have the life of <hi>Ben-hadad,</hi> but with his own losse. Wherefore the King <hi>Asa</hi> did not faile to depose his grandmother <hi>Maachah</hi> from her regency, because she had made an Idoll in a grove, which Idoll he brake down, and stamped it, and burnt it at the brook Kidron.</p>
            <p>Consider here a little with me (beloved) the mishap, (that I say not miserie) of divers Princes (keeping me within the limits or bounds of the holy Scripture) in this case of shewing mercy, &amp; practising of judgement</p>
            <p>For first of all it falleth out not seldome, that those notorious malefactours deserving death, whom Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces do pardon in mercie, (if not upon foolish pitie) doe afterward most unthankfully and treacherously seek to take the Scepter out of the hand, and to pull the Crown from the head, and to withdraw life from the body of their benefactours, who had graciously forgiven them their crimes, and so consequently gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to them their lives, lands, goods, libertie and all. This may be fitly exemplified in <hi>Absalon,</hi> who after
<pb facs="tcp:50085:10"/>
that he was pardoned for the murdering of his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Amnon,</hi> and restored to favour in Court, rose up early, and stood hard by the entring in of the gate, and <note place="margin">2 Sam. 15.</note> reached forth his hand to every suiter of account, and by slander, flattery, and faire promises, he stole away the hearts of the people, and at the length he brast forth into actuall rebellion against his naturall father. <hi>Ioab</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 3 27.</note> likewise when he had escaped without punishment for stabbing of <hi>Abner,</hi> he was thereby emboldned to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed forward to the murdering of <hi>Amasa,</hi> and this <note place="margin">Ibid. 20. 9, 10.</note> done without controlement, he presumed to aid aspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Adonijah</hi> to the prejudice of <hi>Salomon,</hi> who was to <note place="margin">1 Reg 1. 7</note> succeed in the Kingdome by the appointment of his father <hi>David</hi> yet living.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Princes have beene sometimes overaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Peeres of the Realme, or otherwise for fear of the tumult in the State, they durst not either shew kindnesse, and give entertainment to good men whom they loved, or to execute mighty malefactours, as in duty they should have done. Of the first sort we have an example in <hi>Achish</hi> the King of Gath, who confessed that <hi>David</hi> pleased him as an Angel of God, but there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall <note place="margin">1 Sam. 29 6. 9. 10.</note> he told him that he must be packing out of his company, because the Princes of the Philistines did not favour him. Of the second sort we have an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in <hi>David</hi> who though he spake &amp; did much in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation of <hi>Ioabs</hi> murdering of <hi>Abner,</hi> yet he durst not put him to death for it, as it may be collected by these words of his: <hi>I am this day weake and newly anointed King: and these men the sonnes</hi> of Zeruiah <hi>be too hard</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 3. 36.</note> 
               <hi>for me: the Lord reward the doer of evill according to his wickednesse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this falleth out well and rightly, that whom <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:50085:11"/>
spared in policie, those <hi>Saloman</hi> executed in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <note place="margin">1 Reg. 2. 5. 6. 8. 9. 31. 44 45. 46.</note> as railing <hi>Shim<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and bloody <hi>Ioab.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here let me stand a little upon <hi>Davids</hi> promise to sing <hi>mercy and judgement,</hi> and consider whether hee performed the same alwaies or not. I will put the case in the example of lame <hi>Mephibosheth</hi> the sonne of his old and deare friend <hi>Ionathan,</hi> to whom I confesse he <note place="margin">2 Sam. 9. 1. 3. 7.</note> did kindly shew mercy for his fathers sake, by resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring unto him all the fields of his Grandfather <hi>Saul,</hi> and licensing him to eat bread at his owne Table con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually: but when he came to the point of judgement, I finde him defective. For when <hi>David</hi> fled before the face of <hi>Absalon. Ziba</hi> the servant of <hi>Mephibosheth</hi> mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <note place="margin">2 Sam. 16. 1, 2, 3, 4.</note> him with a large present of his Masters goods, and presenting the same unto him, he frameth sycophantly a most false accusation of treason against his Master, as though he had said, this day shall the house of Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el restore me the Kingdome of my father. Whereupon rashly without leaving the one eare for the defendant, he gave sentence, condemning the innocent in favour of the plaintiffe, being a calumniator; saying to <hi>Ziba,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thine are all that pertained unto <hi>Mephibosheth,</hi> and when as <hi>Mephibosheth</hi> afterward met <hi>David</hi> returning after the overthrow of <hi>Absolon,</hi> &amp; fully cleared himself of the haynous crime of treason wherewith he had beene falsely charged, then <hi>David</hi> giveth sentence in <note place="margin">2 Sam 19. 29.</note> this wise, <hi>Thou and</hi> Ziba <hi>divide the lands.</hi> Herein <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> did evill in taking his land from him before hee knew the cause, but much worse that knowing the truth, he did not restore them. And here we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve that in the case of justice our <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is more upright then our <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, our contemplation is sounder then our practice. Or to speake to the capacity of the meanest
<pb facs="tcp:50085:11"/>
hearer, a man may more easily penne the cause of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice in his private study, then rightly practice it in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke upon the Bench. For in solitary meditation a man may without difficulty abandon all rashnesse, and partiall affection, but in judiciall place abroad, respect of persons, and other corruptions doe easily enter into our mindes and hearts, by the Ministery of our eies and ears.</p>
            <p>Now the way to prevent this mischiefe, is to doe that sincerely, which <hi>David</hi> promiseth here to doe; namely, <hi>to sing unto the Lord,</hi> that is to shew <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi> and practise <hi>Iudgement</hi> to the glory of God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto all things ought to be referred, according to Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> direction, <hi>whether ye eat or drinke, or whatsoever</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 31.</note> 
               <hi>ye doe, do all to the glory of God.</hi> Insomuch as almes must be given in charity without the sound of a trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and prayer must bee made of devotion without <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 1. to the 7.</note> publicke ostentation. And to descend from the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall doctrine to the particular instruction which I have in hand, miserable was the case of that wretched Judge who did right to the poore widow, nor for feare of God, or reverence to man; but only to avoid her cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor <note place="margin">Luke. 18. 4. 5.</note> and importunity. And no better was the case of the Philistins in the booke of the Judges, who when as the Timnite gave his daughter being <hi>Sampsons</hi> wife, <note place="margin">Judg. 15. 1 to the 7.</note> to another man, they regarded not to punish this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just and adulterous act: But when as <hi>Sampson</hi> in revenge of this wrong, had with three hundred Foxes turned taile to taile having firebrands fastened thereto, set on fire, and burned up the rickes and the standing corne with the Vineyards and Olives of the Philistins: then they came up in troopes and burnt the Timnite and his daughter with fire. Thus the wicked punish not
<pb facs="tcp:50085:12"/>
vice for love of Justice, but to be revenged in respect of former losse, and for feare of future danger which else might come unto them.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>to thee O Lord will I sing;</hi> that is, howsoever by the chaunting of this ditty of <hi>mercy &amp; judgement,</hi> I shall seem to howle in the eares of the ungodly, yet my song to thee, O Lord, shall be thought very melodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Whereby we are taught this generall doctrine, that in doing of our duty in our severall vocations, this ought to be our comfort, that our words and workes are pleasing unto God, howsoever they be displeasing to the world of wicked men. So though <hi>Noe</hi> was scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the men of his time for preparing the Arke and urging repentance to prevent the perill of the Deluge to come: yet is he by the providence of God <hi>ad per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuam rei memoriam,</hi> Chronicled for a Preacher of righteousnesse. And though <hi>David</hi> for dancing before the Arke, being girded with a linnen Ephod, was by his wife <hi>Michal</hi> despised in her heart, yet was he had is <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 5. 2 Sam. 6. 14. 16. 20. 21. 22.</note> most high reputation by the maids of honour atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding upon <hi>Michal.</hi> Yea <hi>David</hi> will yet bee more vile then thus, and he will be low in his owne sight, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that all shall bee acceptable in heaven, which is here on earth done before the Lord, that is for no worldly affection, but only for the zeale which wee beare to Gods glory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Isai</hi> and the children which God gave unto him, <note place="margin">
                  <p>Isa 8. 18. VV<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s. 5. 15.</p>
                  <p>Mat. 51. 18. 19.</p>
               </note> were as signes and wonders in Israel: yet their reward was with the Lord. If <hi>Iohn</hi> come neither eating nor drinking, they say he hath a divel. And if the Sonne of man come eating and drinking, they say behold a glutton, and a drinker of wine, a friend of publicans <note place="margin">Act. 26. 24. 25.</note> and Sinners: But yet wisdome is justified of her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.
<pb facs="tcp:50085:12"/>
If <hi>Festus</hi> be judge of <hi>Pauls</hi> speeches, then <hi>Paul</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5. 9. 13.</note> is beside himselfe, much learning doth make him mad. Howbeit, <hi>Paul</hi> is not mad, O noble <hi>Festus,</hi> but he spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <note place="margin">Ibid. v. 3.</note> the words of truth and sobernesse. The Apostles were made a gazing-stock unto the world, and to the Angels, and to men, they were counted as the filth of he world, and the off-scowring of all things: howbeit <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey passed very little to bee judged of mans judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 15. 16.</note> knowing that they were unto God the sweet sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Christ in them that are saved, and in them which perish: to the one, the savour of death unto <note place="margin">2 Sam. 23.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eath, and to the other the favour of life unto life.</p>
            <p>Thus the sweet singer of Israel promiseth to sing he divine ditty of <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Iudgement,</hi> to the Lord of Lords, even God the Father, the Son and the Holy Ghost; to whom three Persons, and one everliving God, be all honour and glory both now, and for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
