<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The glory of a true church, and its discipline display'd wherein a true gospel-church is described : together with the power of the keys, and who are to be let in, and who to be shut out / by Benjamin Keach.</title>
            <author>Keach, Benjamin, 1640-1704.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-12">2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47522</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K66</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19810</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12352725</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12352725</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60040</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A47522)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60040)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 213:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The glory of a true church, and its discipline display'd wherein a true gospel-church is described : together with the power of the keys, and who are to be let in, and who to be shut out / by Benjamin Keach.</title>
                  <author>Keach, Benjamin, 1640-1704.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>iv, 5-69 [i.e. 72] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church discipline --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Baptists --  Government.</term>
               <term>Baptists --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60040:1"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:60040:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>THE GLORY OF A TRUE CHURCH, And its Discipline display'd. Wherein a true Gospel-Church is described. Together with the Power of the Keys, and who are to be let in, and who to be shut out.</p>
            <p>By <hi>BENJAMIN KEACH.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 18.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Whatsoever ye shall bind on Earth, shall be bound in Heaven; and whatsoever ye shall loose on Earth, shall be loosed in Heaven.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON; Printed in the Year 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prefatory_letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:60040:2"/>
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:60040:2"/>
            <head>To the Baptized Churches, particularly to that under my Care.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>EVery House or Building con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth both of Matter and Form: And so doth the Church of Christ, or House of the Living God.</p>
            <p>The Matter or Materials with which it is built are <hi>Lively Stones, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. e.</hi> Converted Persons: Also the Matter and Form must be according to the Rule and Pattern shewed in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Mount, I mean Christ's Insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, and the Apostolical Churches Constitution, and not after Mens In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions.</p>
            <p>Now some Men, because the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ical Church of the Jews was Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ional, and took in their Carnal Seed (as such) therefore the same Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er and Form they would have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Gospel.</p>
            <p>But tho a Church be rightly built in both these respects, <hi>i.e.</hi> of fit Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and right Form, yet without a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular and orderly Discipline, it will
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:60040:3"/>
soon lose its Beauty, and be polluted.</p>
            <p>Many <hi>Reverend Divines</hi> of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Congregational way,</hi> have written most excellently (it is true) upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Subject, I mean on Church-Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline; but the Books are so voluminou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that the Poorer Sort can't purchas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them, and many others have not Tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or Learning enough to improve them to their Profit; and our <hi>Brethren</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Baptists</hi> have not written (as I ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gather) on this Subject by it self<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Therefore I have been earnestly desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by our Members, and also by on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of our Pastors, to write a small and plain Tract concerning the Rules <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Discipline of a Gospel-Church that all Men may not only know our Faith, but see our Order in this cas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> also. True, this (tho plain) is bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> short, but may be it may provoke som<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other Person to do it more fully. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, ignorance of the rules of Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline causes no small trouble and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders in our Churches; and if this may be a Prevention, or prove profit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to any, let God have the Glory, and I have my End: Who am, Yours</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Aug. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1697.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Benj. Keach.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:60040:3"/>The Glory of a Gospel-Church, and the true Orderly Discipline thereof explain'd.</head>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Concerning a True and Orderly Gospel-Church.</head>
            <p>BEfore there can be any Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly Discipline among a Christian Assembly, they must be orderly and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly constituted into a Church-state, according to the Institution of Christ in the Gospel.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Church of Christ,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2.41, 42, 43, 44.</note> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Gospel-Institution, is a Congregation of Godly Christians,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 8.14. <hi>Act.</hi> 19.4, 5, 6. <hi>Eph.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1, 2. and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.12, 13, 19.</note> who as a Stated-Assembly (being first baptized upon the Profession of Faith) do by mutual agreement and consent give themselves up to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60040:4"/>
the Lord,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1.2, 4, 12.</note> and one to another, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Will of God;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5.</note> and do ordinarily meet together in one Place,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 5.13, 14.</note> for the Publick Service and Worship of God;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.17.</note> among whom the Word of God and Sacraments are duly administred,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2.</note> according to Christ's Institution.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3, 4, 5.</note>2. The Beauty and Glory of which Congregation doth consist in their being all Converted Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4, 5, 6.</note> or <hi>lively Stones</hi>; being by the Holy Spirit,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.20, 21.</note> united to Jesus Christ the Precious Corner-Stone, and only foundation of every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 2.19.</note> as well as of every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Congregation, and of the whole <hi>Catholick Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That every Person before they are admitted Members, in such a Church so constituted, must de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to the Church (or to such with the Pastor, that they shall appoint) what God hath done for their Souls,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psa.</hi> 66.16. <hi>Act.</hi> 11.4, 5, 6, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 23, 24.</note> or their Experiences of a Saving work of Grace upon their Hearts; and also the Church should enquire after,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15.</note> and take full satisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion concerning their Holy Lives,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5.</note> or Good Conversations.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:60040:4"/>And when admitted Members, before the Church they must so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly enter into a Covenant, to walk in the Fellowship of that particular Congregation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.</note> and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themselves to the Care and Discipline thereof, and to walk faithfully with God in all his Holy Ordinances, and there to be fed and have Communion, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship God there,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1, 2.</note> when the Church meets (if possible) and give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves up to the watch and charge of the Pastor and Ministry there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: the Pastor then also signifying in the name of the Church their acceptance of each Person, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to take the care of them, and to watch over them in the Lord, (the Members being first satisfied to receive them, and to have Communion with them.) And so the Pastor to give them the right Hand of Fellowship of a Church, or <hi>Church Organical.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Of an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganical Church.</hi>
               </note>A Church thus constituted ought forthwith to choose them a Pastor, Elder or Elders, and Deacons, (we reading of no other Officers, or Offices abiding in the Church)
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60040:5"/>
and what kind of Men they ought to be,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.</note> and how qualified, is laid down by <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.</note> and to <hi>Titus.</hi> Moreover, they are to take special care, that both Bishops, Overseers, or Elders, as well as the Deacons, have in some competent manner all those Qualifications; and after in a Day of solemn Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Fasting,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Act.</hi> 6.6.</note> that they have elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22.</note> (whether Pastor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or Deacons) and they accepting the Office, must be ordained with Prayer, and laying on of Hands of the Eldership; being first prov'd, and found meet and fit Persons for so Sacred an Office: Therefore such are very disorderly Churches who have no Pastor or Pastors or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, they acting not according to the Rule of the Gospel, having something wanting.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of the work of a Pastor, Bishop or Overseer.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THe work of a Pastor is to preach the Word of Christ, or to feed the Flock,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16, 17.</note> and to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster all the Ordinances of the Gospel
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60040:5"/>
which belong to his Sacred Office,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 20.31 35.</note> and to be faithful and laborious therein, studying to shew himself approved unto God,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>a Work-man that needeth not be ashamed, rightly dividing the Word of Truth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1, 2.</note> He is <hi>a Steward of the Mysteries of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.</note> therefore ought to be a Man of good Understanding and Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, being sound in the Faith, and one that is acquainted with the Mysteries of the Gospel:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.15.</note> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he is <hi>to feed the People with Knowledg and Vnderstanding.</hi> He must be faithful and skilful to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the Mind of God,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2.</note> and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent therein, also to <hi>preach in sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and out of season</hi>; God having committed unto him the Ministry of Reconciliation,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19</note> a most choice and sacred Trust. What Interest hath God greater in the World which he hath committed unto Men than this? Moreover, he must make known the whole Counsel of God to the People.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 20.20, 27.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A Pastor is to visit his Flock,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 27.23.</note> to know <hi>their state,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Thess.</hi> 5.15.</note> and to <hi>watch over them,</hi> to <hi>support the weak,</hi> and to <hi>strengthen the feeble-minded,</hi> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60040:6"/>
succour the tempted, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them that are unruly.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To pray for them at all times, and with them also when sent for, and desired, and as Opportunity serves; and to sympathize with them in every State and Condition, with all Love and Compassion.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And to shew them in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects, as near as he can,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.12.</note> a good Example <hi>in Conversation, Charity, Faith and Purity</hi>; that his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry may be the more acceptable to all, and the Name of God be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, and Religion delivered from Reproach.</p>
            <p n="5">5. He must see he carries it to all with all Impartiality,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.4.</note> not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring the Rich above the Poor,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.21.</note> nor lord it over.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. and 5.6.</note> God's Heritage, nor assume any greater Power than God hath given him; but to shew a humble and meek Spirit, nay to be <hi>clothed with Humility.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The Office and Work of Deacons.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons Work.</hi>
               </note>THE Work of Deacons is to serve Tables,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 6.1, 2, 3, 5, 7, 8, 9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> to see to provide for the Lord's Table, the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60040:6"/>
Minister's Table,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 5.7, 8, 9, 10.</note> and the Poor's Table (1.) They should provide Bread and Wine for the Lord's Table. (2.) See that every Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber contributes to the Maintenance of the Ministry,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.2.</note> according to their Ability, and their own vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Subscription or Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. (3.) That each Member do give weekly to the Poor, as God has blessed him. (4.) Also visit the Poor, and know their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition as much as in them lies;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 6.1.</note> that none, especially the aged Widows, be neglected.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of the Duty of Church-Members to their Pastor.</head>
            <p>1<hi>st.</hi> 'TIS the Duty of every Member to pray for their Pastor and Teachers. <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Thess.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.25.</note> 
               <hi>pray for us,</hi> that the Word of the Lord may run <hi>and be glorified.</hi> Again, saith <hi>Paul, Praying also for us, that God would open unto us a door of ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.18.</note> 
               <hi>to speak the Mystery of Christ. Prayer was made without ceasing of the Church unto God for him.</hi> They that neglect this Duty
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60040:7"/>
seem not to care either for their Minister, or their own Souls, or whether Sinners be converted, and the Church edified or not. They pray for their daily Bread, and will they not pray to have the Bread of Life plentifully broken to them?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>
               <hi>Motives</hi> to this.</head>
            <p n="1">1. Ministers Work is great: <hi>Who is sufficient for these things?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.9.</note>2. The Opposition is not small which is made against them.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3, 4, 5.</note>3. God's loud Call is (as well as Ministers themselves) for the Saints continual Prayers and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication for them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Their Weakness and Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations are many.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Increase and Edification of the Church depends upon the Success of their Ministry.</p>
            <p n="6">6. If they fall or miscarry, God is greatly dishonoured, and his Ways and People reproached.</p>
            <p>2<hi>dly.</hi> They ought to shew a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verential Estimation of them,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.19, 20.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Christ's Ambassadors, also cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Rulers, Angels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they that honour them, and receive them,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60040:7"/>
honour and receive Jesus Christ.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Thess.</hi> 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>Esteem them very highly in Love for their Work sake.</hi> Again, he saith, <hi>Let the Elders that rule well,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>be accounted worthy of double Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, especially they who labour in Word and Doctrine:</hi> that is, as I conceive, such that are most labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious.</p>
            <p>3<hi>dly.</hi> 'Tis their Duty to submit themselves unto them, that is, in all their Exhortations, good Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels and Reproofs; and when they call to any extraordinary Duty, as Prayer, Fasting, or days of Thanksgiving, if they see no just cause why such days should not be kept, they ought to obey their Pastor or Elder, as in other cases also.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5, 17.</note> 
               <hi>Obey them that have the Rule over you, and submit your selves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4<hi>thly.</hi> It is their Duty to take care to vindicate them from the unjust Charges of evil Men, or Tongue of Infamy,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.10. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 2.8.</note> and not to take up a Reproach against them by report, nor to grieve their Spirits,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.21, 23.</note> or weaken their Hands.</p>
            <p>5<hi>thly.</hi> 'Tis the Duty of Members to go to them when under Trouble or Temptations.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:60040:8"/>6<hi>thly.</hi> It is their Duty to provide a comfortable Maintenance for them and their Families, sutable to their State and Condition. <hi>Let him that is taught in the Word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>communicate to him that teacheth, in all good things. Who goeth a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare at his own Charge?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>who plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a Vineyard, and eateth not of the fruit thereof?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Even so hath the Lord ordained,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>that they that preach the Gospel, should live of the Gospel.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>If we have sown unto you spiritual things, is it a great thing if we shall reap your carnal things?</hi> They should minister to them chearfully with all readiness of Mind.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.9, 10.</note> Ministers are not to ask for their Bread, but to receive it honourably. The Ministers Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, tho it is not by Tythes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as under the Law, yet they have now as just a right to a comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Maintenance as they had then, the equity of the Duty is the same: Our Saviour,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Dr.</hi> Owen'<hi>s E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shod,</hi> p. 21, 22.</note> saith Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> and the Apostles plead it from grounds of Equity and Justice; and all kind of Laws and Rules of Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness among Men of all sorts calls for it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:60040:8"/>7<hi>thly.</hi> It is their Duty to adhere to them, and abide by them in all their Trials and Persecutions for the Word.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16, 17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>Ye were not ashamed of me in my Bonds,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>8<hi>thly.</hi> Dr.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eshod,</hi> pag. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Owen</hi> adds another Duty of the Members to their Pastor, <hi>viz.</hi> to agree to come together upon his Appointment: <hi>When they were come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 14.27.</note> 
               <hi>and had ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered the Church together,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Query, <hi>Are there no ruling El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders besides the Pastor?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> There might be such in the Primitive Apostolical Church, but we see no ground to believe it an abiding Office to continue in the Church, but was only temporary.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Because we have none of the Qualifications of such Elders men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd, or how to be chosen.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Because we read not particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly what their Work and Busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness is, or how distinct from preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Elders; tho we see not but the Church may (if she sees meet) choose some able and discreet Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to be <hi>Helps in Government:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.8.</note> We have the Qualifications of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60040:9"/>
and Deacons directly laid down,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.</note> and how to be chosen, and their Work declared,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5, 6, 7.</note> but of no other Office or Officers in the Church, but these only.</p>
            <p>Quest. <hi>May an Elder of one Church if called, warrantably admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister all Ordinances to another?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 20.17, 27, 28.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> No surely; for we find no warrant for any such Practice, he being only ordained Pastor or El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of that particular Church that chose him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and hath no Right or Authority to administer as an Elder in any other where he is not so much as a Member.</p>
            <p>Quest. <hi>May a Church call out a Teacher that is no ordained Elder to administer all Ordinances to them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> You may as well ask, May a Church act disorderly? Why were Ministers to be ordained, if o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers unordained might warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly do all their Work? if therefore they have no Person fitly qualified for that Office, they must look out from abroad for one that is. Yet (as we say) Necessity has no Law; provided therefore they can't do either, it is better their Teacher
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60040:9"/>
be called to do it, than that the Church should be without their Food, and Church-Ordinances neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected; yet let all Churches take care to organize themselves, and not through Covetousness, or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of Duty, rest incompleat Churches, and so under Sin. <hi>God is the God of Order, and not of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33, 38.</note> 
               <hi>in all the Churches of the Saints.</hi> And how severely did God deal of old with such that meddled with the Priests Work and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, who were not of the Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, nor called by him to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister in holy things!</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of the reception of Members.</head>
            <p>Quest. <hi>WHat is the Order of receiving Members into the Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of Members into the Church.</note> 
               <hi>that were no Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers any where before?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>Answ.</hi> 1. The Person must give an account of his Faith;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 66.16.</note> and of the Work of Grace upon his Soul be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Church;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 9.26, 27.</note> and also a strict Enquiry must be made about his Life and Conversation:<note place="margin">3 <hi>Joh.</hi> 9, 10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17, 19.</note> but if through Bashfulness the Party can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not speak before the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60040:10"/>
1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40.</note> the Elder and two or three more Persons may receive an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his or her Faith, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it to the Church.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.1, 2.</note> But if full Satisfaction by the Testimony of good and credible Persons is not given of the Party's Life and Conversation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 11.2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</note> he must be put by until Satisfaction is obtained in that respect. Moreover, when the Majority are satisfied, and yet one or two Persons are not, the Church and Elder will do well to wait a little time, and endeavour to satisfy such Persons, especially if the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of their dissent seem weighty.</p>
            <p>Quest. <hi>What is to be done when a Person offers himself for Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion from a Church that is corrupt, or erroneous in Principles?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>Answ.</hi> 1. The Church ought to take an account of his Faith in all Fundamental Points, and of the Work of Grace upon his Heart.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And if satisfied, then to send also to that corrupt People, to know whether they have any thing or not against his Life and Conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: If satisfied in both these re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects, the Church may receive him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:60040:10"/>Quest. <hi>To whom is it Members <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oin themselves? is it to the Elder,</hi>
               <note place="margin">To whom Members join them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves.</note> 
               <hi>or to the Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> They are joined to the whole Community of the Church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2.47. &amp; 5.11, 15.</note> being incorporated as Members thereof, and thereto abide, tho the Pastor be removed by Death.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The Power of the Keys, with Church — Discipline, and Members Duties one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>A monthly day to be appointed for Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</hi>
               </note>1. WE judg it necessary that a Day monthly be appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed particularly for Discipline, and not to manage such Affairs on the Lord's-day, which should be spent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the publick Worship of God, of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> different nature: besides, such <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hings may (on the account of Discipline) come before the Church which may not be expedient to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eard on the Lord's-day, lest it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>isturb the Spirits of any Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and hinder their Meditation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the Word which they have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ewly heard: tho in small Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60040:11"/>
perhaps a day in two or three Months may be sufficient.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Power of the Keys committed to the Church.</hi>
               </note>2. The Power of the Keys, or to receive in and shut out of the Congregation, is committed unto the Church: The Political Power of Christ,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 16.5.</note> saith Dr. <hi>Chauncy,</hi> is in the Church,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 1.3, 6.</note> whereby it is exercised in the Name of Christ, having all lawful Rule and Government with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it self, which he thus proves, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p n="1">1. The Church essential is the first Subject of the Keys.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They must of necessity to their Preservation, purge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves from all pernicious Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They have Power to orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize themselves with Officers. Yet I humbly conceive I may add, that the Concurrence of the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery is needful hereunto.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If need be that they call an Officer from without, or one of another Church, they must first admit him a Member, that they may ordain their Officer from among themselves.</p>
               <p n="5">5. They have Power to reject a scandalous Pastor from Office and Membership.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:60040:11"/>'This Power of Christ is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erted as committed to them by the Hands of the Elder appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Christ,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy on the Power of the Keys,</hi> p. 335.</note> the due manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof is in and with the Church to be his Care and Trust, as a Steward, whereof he is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable to Christ and the Church, not lording it over God's Heritage. And that the Power of the Keys is in the Church, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to me from <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. <hi>If he will not hear the Church</hi>; it is not said, if he will not hear the Elder,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4, 5.</note> or Elders. As also that of the Apostle, in directing the Church to cast out the Incestuous Person, he doth not give this Counsel to the Elder or Elders of the Church,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 3.6, 14.</note> but to the Church; so he commands the Church to withdraw from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Brother that walks disorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>Purge out the old Leaven, that you may be a new Lump.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of Church-Censures.</head>
            <p>NOW as to Church-Censures I understand but two besides Suspension,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Of Church-Censures.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> (1.) Withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from a Member that walks
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60040:12"/>
disorderly. (2.) Casting out, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Excommunicating such that are e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther guilty of notorious or scanda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Crimes, of Heresy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of contemning the Authority o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Church.</p>
            <p>Briefly to each of these.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Suspension is to be when'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Member falls under Sin, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Church wants time fully to hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the matter, and so can't withdraw from him, or cast him out.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If any Member walks disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, tho not guilty of gross scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Sins, he or she, as soon as it is taken notice of, ought to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monished, and endeavours to be used to bring him to Repentance:<note place="margin">2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 3.11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>For we hear that there are some which walk disorderly, not working at all, but are busy-bodies.</hi> Such as meddle with Matters that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern them not, it may be (instead of following their Trade and Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness) they go about from one Member's House to another, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or carrying of Tales and Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of this Brother, or of that Brother or Sister, which perhaps may be true, or perhaps false, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60040:12"/>
may be too to the Reproach or Scandal of some Member or Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, which, if so, it is back-biting; and that is so notorious a Crime, that without Repentance they shall not ascend God's holy Hill.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psa.</hi> 15.1, 3.</note> Back-biting is a diminishing our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, or Brother's good Name, either by denying him his due Praise, or by saying any thing to his Charge falsely or irregularly, or without sufficient cause or evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, <hi>Thus our Annotators.</hi> But this of disorderly walking does not amount to such a Crime, but Evils not so notorious;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>Now them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at are such, we command and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort by our Lord Jesus Christ, that with quietness they work, and eat their own Bread.</hi> They must be admonished.</p>
            <p n="1">1. An Admonition is a faithful Endeavour to convict a Person of a Fault, both as to Matter of Fact and Circumstance; and this Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition must be given first, if it be private, by that Brother that knows or has knowledg of the Fault or Evil of the Person offending, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Elder, or Member; for
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60040:13"/>
any private Brother ought to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monish such with all care and faithfulness before he proceeds far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But if it be publick, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Church ought to send for the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, and the Pastor must admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish him before all.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But if after all due Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours used he is not reclaimed, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> continues a disorderly Person, the Church must withdraw from him. <hi>Now we command you Brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 2.6.</note> is <hi>the Name of our Lord Jesus Christ,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Disorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers only to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn from.</note> 
               <hi>that you withdraw from every B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that walketh disorderly, and not after the Traditions he received from us.</hi> This is not a delivering up to Satan, Excommunicating of dismembring the Person; for this sort are still to be owned as Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, tho disorderly ones: the Church must note him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> so as not to have Communion or Company with him in that sense;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 2.14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>yet court him not as an Enemy, but exhort him as a Brother: if any Man o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey not our Word, note that Man.</hi> It appears that such who refuse to adhere to what the Pastor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and exhorts to, in the Name
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60040:13"/>
of Christ, are to be deemed disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly Persons,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.25.</note> as such are who meet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot with the Church when assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled together to worship God, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat neglect private or family Prayer, or neglect their attendance on the Lord's-Supper, or to contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the necessary Charges of the Church, or suffer any Evils un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reproved in their Children; all such may be lookt upon disorderly Walkers, and ought to be proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed against according to this Rule, or divulge the private Resolves of the Church, as well as in many like cases.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of private Offences of one Brother against another.</head>
            <p n="1">1. AS touching private Offences,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Of private Offences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Brother.</hi>
               </note> the Rule <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. is to be observed, only this by the way must be premised, <hi>viz.</hi> if but one Brother or two have the knowledg of some Members Crime, yet if it be publickly known to the World, and the Name of God be reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60040:14"/>
it being an immoral Act, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> private Brother is not to proceed with such an Offender, according to <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. but forthwith to brin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it to the Church, that the public<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Scandal may be taken off.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But if it be a private Offenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or Injury done to a Brother <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Sister in particular, and not bei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> a notorious scandalous Sin, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Brother must not mention it to one Soul, either within, or without the Church, until he hath proceeded according to the Rule.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) He must tell his Brother his Fault.<note place="margin">Mat. 18.15.</note> 
               <hi>Moreover, if thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shall trespass against thee, go and tell him his fault betwixt thee and him alone; if he shall hear thee, thou hast gained thy Brother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou must labour in Love and all Affections to convince him o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Fault; but if he will not hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thee,</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Thou must take one or two more, but be sure see they are dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet Persons, and such that ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> most likely to gain upon him; and they with thee are to labour with all Wisdom to bring him to the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60040:14"/>
sense of his Fault: 'tis not iust to speak to him, as if that were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; no, no, but to take all due Pains, and to strive to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince him, that so the matter may be issued, and the Church not troubled with it:<note place="margin">Mat. 18.16.</note> 
               <hi>But if he will not hear thee, take one or two more, that in the mouth of two or three Witnesses every word may be esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. But if he will not hear them after all due Means and Admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons used, then it must be brought to the Church; and if he will not hear the Church, he must be cast out:<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> p. 345.</note> The Elder is to put the Question, whether the offending Brother be in their Judgments incorrigible, and refuseth to hear the Church; which passing in the Affirmative by the Vote of the Congregation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Sisters are not to vote in the Church.</hi>
               </note> or the Majori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Brethren by the lifting up of their Hands, or by their Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; the Pastor after calling up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God, and opening the nature of the Offence, and the Justness of their Proceedings, in the Name and by the Authority of Christ,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60040:15"/>
pronounces the Sentence of E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> communication to this effect.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Act of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Church-Censure.</note>
               <hi>That</hi> A. B. <hi>being guilty of great Iniquity, and not manifesting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned Repentance, but refusing to hear the Church, I do in the Name, and by the Authority of Christ com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto me as Pastor of this his Church, pronounce and declare that he is to be, and is hereby excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, excluded or cast out of the Congregation, and no longer to be owned a Brother,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.</note> 
               <hi>or a Member of this Church; and this for the destruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Flesh, that his Spirit may be saved in the day of the Lord Jesus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this we believe is the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of that which the Apostle calls a delivering up to Satan, he being cast into the World, which is called the Kingdom of Satan, where he rules and reigns.</p>
            <p>
               <q>The delivery unto Satan (saith Dr. <hi>Chauncy</hi>) signifies only the solemn Exclusion of a Person from the Communion of the Church,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 345.</note> the visible Kingdom of Christ, and disinfranchizing him, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vesting him of all visible Right to Church Privileges, casting
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60040:15"/>
him into the Kingdom of the World, where the Prince of Darkness rules in the Children of disobedience.</q>
And this being done, he is to be esteemed to be no better than an Heathen Man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17.</note> or Publican, or as an evil Person, and not to have so much as intimate ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Communion withal.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of Scandalous Persons guilty of gross Acts of Immorality.</head>
            <p>IF any Member fall into any gross Acts of Sin,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Of Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Crimes or Evils.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Swearing, Lying, Drunkenness, Fornication, Covet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness, Extortion,</hi> or the like, and it is known and publickly spread abroad to the great scandal and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of Religion, and of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Name of God, his Church, and People; the said Offender so charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Church must send one or two Brethren to him to come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Congregation: if he will not come, but doth slight and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn the Authority of the Church, that will bring farther Guilt upon him, for which Offence he incurs
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60040:16"/>
the Censure before - mentioned But if he doth appear, his Charge is to be laid before him, and the Witnesses called; and after he ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> made his Defence, and said all he hath to say, and the Congregation finds him Guilty,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Church Censure on notorious Offenders is the same with that in</hi> Mat. 18.</note> then the same Censure is to pass upon him, to the end he may be brought to unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Repentance, and the Name of God cleared; and some time must be taken to make it appear that he hath true Repentance, by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of his Life and holy walking afterwards, before he be received again, and the Censure of the Church in a solemn manner be taken off.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 343.</note>Dr. <hi>Chauncy</hi> puts this Question,</p>
            <q>
               <p>Quest.
How is a Church to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in case of open and notorious Scandals?</p>
               <p>The <hi>Answer</hi> is, 'the matter of Fact, as such, being beyond all question; the Church is to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed immediately to censure, to vindicate the Honour of Christ and his Church, and to manifest
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60040:16"/>
to the World their just Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion against such Notorious Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.24. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Jud.</hi> 23. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</note> and wait for a well-grounded and tryed Evidence of his true Repentance under that Ordinance of Christ which is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to that end.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11.</note>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Observe,</hi> It is the opinion of the Doctor, that tho the Person be pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, yet because his Sin is open and scandalous, he ought to be cast out to vindicate the Honour of Christ and the Church, as part of his just Punishment (that being one reason of the Ordinance of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication) as well as to bring the Person to thorow Repentance; and we are of his Mind. <hi>Paul</hi> takes no notice in the case of the <hi>Incestuous Person</hi> of his immediate Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; or if he repent not, then, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But says he, <hi>deliver such a one to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> &amp;c. Saith the Lord,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 12.14.</note> 
               <hi>if her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had but spit in her Face, should she not be ashamed seven Days? Let her be shut out from the Camp seven Day:</hi> (speaking of <hi>Miriam</hi>) <hi>and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that let her be received in again.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:60040:17"/>
            <head>Of dealing with Hereticks and Blasphemers.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Of dealing with Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</hi>
               </note>AS touching Hereticks or He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resy, the same Censure, when they are convicted, ought to pass against them; Heresy is commonly restrained to signify any perverse Opinion or Error in a fundamental Point of Religion, as to deny the Being of God, or the Deity of Christ, or his Satisfaction, and Jus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification alone by his Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, or to deny the Resurrection of the Body, or eternal Judgment, or the like.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Pool's <hi>Annot. on</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19.</note> Yet our Annotators say, the Word signifies the same thing with Schism and Divisions; which if so, such that are guilty of Schism or Divisions in the Church, ought to be excommunicated also. <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies</hi> are called <hi>Damnable</hi> by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle <hi>Peter</hi>; without Repentance such cannot be saved,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>as bring in Damnable Heresies, denying the Lord that bought them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two things render a Man an Heretick according to the common
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60040:17"/>
signification of the Word.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Who is an Heretick.</hi>
               </note> 1. An Error in matters of Faith, Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental or Essential to Salvation. 2. Stubbornness and Contumacy in holding and maintaining it. <hi>A Man that is an Heretick,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>after the first and second Admonition reject.</hi> Now that this Rejection is all one with Excommunication, appears by what <hi>Paul</hi> speaks, 1 Tim. 1.20. <hi>Of whom is Hymeneus and Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>whom I have delivered unto Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, that they may learn not to Blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme.</hi> Their Heresy, or Blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy was in saying the Resurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was past.</p>
            <p>Some would have none be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an Heretick but he who is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed and condemned so to be in his own Conscience, mistaking <hi>Paul</hi>'s Words, <hi>Knowing that he that is such, is subverted, being condemned of himself.</hi> He may be condemned of himself, tho not for his <hi>Heresy,</hi> yet for his spending his Time about Questions, and strife of Words, to the disquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Peace of the Church; or tho not condemned of himself directly, yet indirectly; accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60040:18"/>
to the Purport of his own No<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, or what he grants about the Point in Debate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Else the A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>postle refers to some notable and notorious self-condemned Here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tick. It is a great question, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> condemned in their own Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, about that Heresy charged upon them, and yet were deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up to Satan. However the Rule is plain, respecting any that are sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, and resolutely maintain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Heretical Notion, <hi>i. e.</hi> after he hath been twice (or oftner) ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monished, that is, after all due means used, and pains taken with him, to convince him of his abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Error; and yet if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains obstinate, he must <hi>be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up to Satan</hi>; that is, the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous censure of the Church must pass upon him, as in the case of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther notorious Crimes. Heresy is a Work of the Flesh: and hence some conceive such ought to be punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Civil Magistrate.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:60040:18"/>Quest. <hi>What is an Admonition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> It is a faithful endeavour to convict a Person of a Fault both as to matter of Fact,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>What an admonition is.</hi>
               </note> and his Duty thereupon, charging it on his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science in the Name of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus with all Wisdom and Authority.</p>
            <p>Quest. <hi>What is a Church Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> When an offending Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rejecting private Admonition by one, or by two or three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons; the complaint being brought to the Church by the Elder, the offending Member is rebuked and exhorted in the Name of the Lord Jesus to due Repentance; and if convicted, and he repents, the Church forgives him, otherwise casts him out, as I before shewed.</p>
            <p>Quest. <hi>May a Church admit a Member of another Congregation to have Communion with them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an orderly receiving him as a Member?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> If the Person is well known by some of the Church, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60040:19"/>
that he is an orderly Member of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Church of the same Faith, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing occasionally cast among them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they may admit him to transie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Communion for that time; but i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he abides in that Town or City remote to the Church to whom he belongs, he ought to have his regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar dismission, and so be delivered up to the care and watch of the Church where he desires to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate.</p>
            <p>Quest. <hi>If an Excommunicated Person hath obtained of God true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and desires to be restored to the Church, what is the manner of his Reception?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Reception of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate Person.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> Upon his serious, solemn and publick Acknowledgment thereof before the Church, and due Satisfaction according to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of his Offence being given, the Elder solemnly proceeds and declares in the Name of the Lord Jesus,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.18.</note> that the sentence which <hi>A.B.</hi> was laid under (upon his unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Repentance) is taken off,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6, 7.</note> and that he is received again a as Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To the Praise and Glory of God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:60040:19"/>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How ought a <hi>Pastor</hi> to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>lt withal, if he to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Church, or any Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers thereof, walketh disorderly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd unworthily of his Sacred Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ice, and Membership?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Take the Answer of another Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi>'Those Members, to whom this is manifestly known,<note place="margin">How to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed against a Scandalous Pastor.</note> ought to go to him privately, and unknown to any others, (and with the <hi>Spirit of Meekness, in great Humility</hi>) lay his Evil before him, and intreat him as a Father, and not rebuke him as there E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual, much less as their Inferiour; and if they gain upon him, then to receive him into their former Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Esteem, for ever hiding it from all others. But if after all tender intreaties, he prove Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractory and Obstinate, then to bring him before the Church, and there to deal with him; they having Two or Three Witnesses in the face of the Church, to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stify matter of Fact against him to their personal Knowledge.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:60040:20"/>2.
<q>But before he be dealt with they must appoint one from among themselves, qualifyd for the <hi>work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> a Pastor, to execute the Church Censure against him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
Yet n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doubt,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> see not if they have none fitly qualified, but the Church may cast him out,</note> the Church may Suspend him from his Communion, &amp; exercisin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of his Office presently, upon hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> being fully Convicted. But seeing in the multitude of Counsel there i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> safety, sure no Church would so pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed without the advice of the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery,</hi> or of a Sister-<hi>Church</hi> at least.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Suppose a Member should think himself Oppressed by the Church; or should be Unjustly dealt with; either Withdrawn from, or Excommunicated, has he no Relief left him?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> We believe he hath Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief;<note place="margin">Relief for a Member un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justly dealt with.</note> and also, that there is no Church infallible, but may E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in some points of Faith, as wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as in Discipline. And the way proposed, and agreed to, in a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Assembly, held in <hi>London,</hi> 1692. of the <hi>Elders, Ministers,</hi> and <hi>Messengers</hi> of our <hi>Churches,</hi> we approve of, which is this; <hi>viz. The grieved or injured Person may make his Application to a Sister<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:60040:20"/>
Church for Communion; and that Church may send some Brethren in their names, to that Congregation that have dealt with him, and they to see if they can possibly restore him to his place; but if they cannot, then to report the matter charged, with the Proofs, to the Church that sent them: and if that Congregation shall, after a full Information,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>be perswaded the Person was not orderly dealt with, they may receive him into their Communion.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of such that cause Divisions; or Vnduely separate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves from the Church.</head>
            <p>THis I find is generally assert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all Congregational Divines,<note place="margin">The cause of Disorders in the Church.</note> or worthy men, <hi>i. e.</hi> That no person hath power to dismem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber himself: <hi>i. e.</hi> He cannot, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great Sin, translate himself from one Church to another; but ought to have a Dismission from that Church where he is a Member:<note place="margin">Rom, 6, 17. Heb, 6, 2, 3</note> provided that <hi>Church</hi> is orderly constituted, nothing being wanting as to any Essential of Salvation; or of Church-Communion: But if not, yet he ought to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60040:21"/>
to get his orderly Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission.</p>
            <p>Nor is every small Differenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in some points of Religion, (o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Notions of little moment,) an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> grounds for him to desire his Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission.</p>
            <p>That he cannot, nor ought no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to Translate himself, see what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Reverend Writer saith:<note place="margin">Dr. Chauncy pag. 337.</note>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>He cannot, <hi>saith he,</hi> for many Reasons:</p>
               <p n="1">1.
It is not Decent, much le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an Orderly going away; but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unmannerly, and a kind o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> running away.<note place="margin">Phil. 1.27. Tit. 2.10.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2.
Such a Departure is not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of in Families, or Civi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Societies.<note place="margin">The great Danger of making a Rent in a Church.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3.
It destroys the Relation o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pastor and People: For wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may be done by one individua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Person, may be done by all.</p>
               <p n="4">4.
What Liberty in this kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> belongs to the <hi>Sheep,</hi> belongs t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Shepherd</hi>; much more he ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then also leave his <hi>Flock</hi> at h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pleasure, without giving notice o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reason thereof to the Church.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1.31.</note>5. It is breaking <hi>Covenant</hi> wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:60040:21"/>
Christ, and with the <hi>Congregation,</hi> and therefore a great Immorality; he being under Obligation to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide stedfastly with the Church; <hi>i. e.</hi> till the Church judge he hath a lawful <hi>Call</hi> to go to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Congregation.</p>
               <p n="6">6.
It's a <hi>Schism:</hi> For if there be any such thing in the World,<note place="margin">Acts 2.42.</note> it's of particular Societies.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.6, 14.7.5.1.20, 21, 25.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7.
It is a despising the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10.25. Jude, 19.</note>8.
It is a particular Member's assuming to himself the use of the <hi>Keys</hi>; or rather stealing of them.</p>
               <p n="9">9.
There is as much reason Persons should come into a <hi>Church</hi> when they please, without asking Consent, as depart when they please.</p>
               <p n="10">10.
It is very evil and unkind in another <hi>Church,</hi> to receive such an one, as <hi>not doing as they would, or should be dealt with.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. Such Practices can issue in
no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else than the <hi>breach</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion</hi>
                  <note place="margin">☞</note> of all particular <hi>Churches</hi>; and make them like <hi>Parishes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12.
Such Departures cannot be pleaded for in the least, but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:60040:22"/>
the notion of a <hi>Catholick</hi> visible Church, wherein all Members and Officers are run into one <hi>Organized Church,</hi> which will, and must introduce, a Co-ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate (if not a <hi>Subordinate</hi>) Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storal Government, by combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Elders,</hi> over all the Churches; and therefore by <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods</hi> and <hi>Classes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13.
It is like a Leak in a Ship, which, if not speedily stopped, will Sink at last.</p>
               <p n="14">14.
It tends to <hi>Anarchy,</hi> put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting an <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> in ev'ry Member.</p>
               <p n="15">15.
It breaks all Bonds of Love, and raiseth the greatest Animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities between Bretheren and Churches.</p>
               <p n="16">16.
It is a great Argument of some Guilt lying-on the Party.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Thus the Dr.</p>
            <p>Again he saith,</p>
            <q>
               <p>It is no more in the just Power of a particular Member to dissolve his Church-Relation, than in a Man to kill himself: but by his said withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he doth Schismatically rend himself from his Communion, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60040:22"/>
so Separate himself Sinfully. <note n="★" place="margin">Jude 19. 1 Cor. 1.10. &amp; 3.3. &amp; 11.18. Heb. 10.22.23, 25.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Quest.<hi>What is the just Act of the Church, that cloathes this ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular Separation, with the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality as it were of an Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication.</hi>
               </p>



               <p>
                  <hi>He Answers.</hi> (Calling) this a mixt Excommunication <hi>i. e.</hi> Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally proceeding from, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sists in, the act of the Brother himself, and is the Formality of his Offence; upon which proceeds the just and unviolable act of the Church.</p>
               <p>The Judgment of the Church publickly declared by the <hi>Elder</hi> of the Congregation; as the Dr. words it; <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That</hi> A. B. <hi>having so and so irregularly and sinfully withdrawn himself from the Communion of the Congregation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mixt Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication.</note> 
                  <hi>we do now adjudge him a Non-member,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 19.17, 18. 2 Thess. 3.6.14, 15.</note> 
                  <hi>and one that is not to Communicate with the Church, in the special Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Communion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jude 12.</note> 
                  <hi>till due Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction is given by him.</hi>
               </p>


            </q>
            <p>Yet we believe, as the Dr's O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion is, that a Church may, (if they find the Case to be warranted
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60040:23"/>
by the Word of God; or as it may be circumstanced) give a dismis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to a Member, when insisted on, to another regular <hi>Church,</hi> tho not in every case of small Offence, or dissent in some small points of different Notions,<note place="margin">Let none call the Church a Prison, since all do volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with it, and 'tis dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to break Christ's bonds.</note> or from Prejudice; for, that may tend soon to dissolve any <hi>Church:</hi> For what Church is it, where every Member is of one mind in every particular case and thing about Notions of Religion?</p>
            <p>And such that make Divisions, and cause Schisms, or Discord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Brethren,<note place="margin">2 Timo. 2.23.</note> to disturb the Peace of the <hi>Church,</hi> if they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be reclaimed,<note place="margin">2 Thess. 3.14.</note> must be marked, and dealt with as great <hi>Offenders:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 6.16.</note> It being one of those things that God hates, and is an abomination to him.</p>
            <p>Quest. <hi>What is a full and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Dismission of a Member to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church, upon his removing his Habitation, or on other warranted Cases.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> VVe answer a Letter Testimonial,<note place="margin">Of a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion.</note> or Recommendation of the Person; and if he intends to abide there wholly, to give him
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60040:23"/>
up to that <hi>Communion,</hi> and <hi>Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom 16.1.2.</note> to be watched over in the Lord.<note place="margin">Acts 18.27.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of Disorders, or causes of Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, and how to be prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, corrected, and removed.</head>
            <p n="1">I. ONE cause of Discord is, through the Ignorance in some Members of the Rules of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scipline,<note place="margin">Mat. 18.15.</note> and right Government;<note place="margin">Disorders Corrected &amp; Removed.</note> particularly when that Rule in <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. is not followed.</p>
            <p>But one Person <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>kes up an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence against another, and speaks, of it to this or that Person, before he hath, told the Brother offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, of it; which is a paspable Sin, and a direct violation of Christ's holy Precept: and such must, as Offenders themselves, be in a Gospel way dealt with.</p>
            <p>To prevent this, the Discipline, of the Church should be taught; and the Members informed of their Duties.</p>
            <p n="2">II Another thing that causes Trouble and Disorder in a Church,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60040:24"/>
is want of Love, and tender Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to one another; as also not having a full sight and sense of the great evil of breaking <hi>the Bonds of Peace, and Vnity:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 13.12, 17, Eph. 4.3. Heb. 13.1. Eph. 4.31, 32. &amp; cap. 5.2.</note> O that all would lay this abominable <hi>Evil</hi> to Heart, how base a thing it is to break the Peace of a private Family, or Neighbourhood; but much more sinful to disturb the Peace of the Church of the living God, and <hi>break the bonds of the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity thereof. Behold, how good, and how pleasant it is, for Brethren to dwell together in Vnity!</hi> But,<note place="margin">Psal. 132.1.</note> O how ugly and hateful is the contrary!<note place="margin">Jam. 3.16.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. Another disorderly Practice is this, When one Member or another knows of some sinful act, or evils done by one or more Members,<note place="margin">Acts 5.3.8.</note> and they conceal it; or do not act according to the Rule;<note place="margin">Levit. 19.17.</note> pretending they would not be lookt upon as Contentious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons: but hereby they may become guilty of other Mens Sins, and also suffer the Name of God, and the Church, to lye under Reproach, and all thro their neglect. This is a great Iniquity.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:60040:24"/>IV. When an Elder, or Church shall know that some persons are Scandalous in their Lives, or Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical in Judgment, and yet shall bear or connive with them.</p>
            <p n="5">V. When Members take liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to hear at other Places,<note place="margin">Acts, 4.23.</note> when the Church is assembled to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship God: this is nothing less than a breaking their Covenant with the Church, and may soon dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve any Church: For by the same Rule, one may take that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, another; nay, every Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber may. Moreover, it casts a Contempt upon the Ministery of the Church, and tends to cause such who are Hearers to draw off, and to be Disaffected with the Doctrine taught in the Church, (they knowing these Dissenters do belong unto it.) I exhort there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in the Name of Christ, this may be prevented: And any of you that know who they are, that take this Liberty, pray discover them to the Church. We lay no restraint upon our Members from hearing such, who are sound in the Faith at other times.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:60040:25"/>VI. The Liberty that some take to hear Men that are corrupt in their Judgments; and so take in unsound Notions, and also strive to distil them into the Minds of others, as if they were of great Importance. Alas, how many are Corrupted in these days, with <hi>Arminianism, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinianism,</hi> and what not! This cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses great trouble and disorder.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <note place="margin">Pet. 2.2.</note>VII. When one Church shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Member or Members of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Congregation without their Consent or Knowledge: Nay such that are Disorderly and may be loose Livers, or cast out for Immorality; or Persons filled with Prejudice without cause. This is enough to make Men Atheists, or contemn all Church Authority, and Religion: For hath not one regular Church as great Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from Christ as another.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. Another disorder is, when Members are received without the general Consent of the Church;<note place="margin">Acts 9.27.</note> or before good Satisfaction is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of their Godly Lives, and Conversations: Or when a Church is too remiss in the reception of her Members.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:60040:25"/>IX. Another disorder is, when a Church shall receive a charge against a Member, (it being an Offence between Brother and Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) before an orderly proceed has been made by the offended Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.<note place="margin">Mat. 18.15.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="10">X. When Judgment passes with Partiality; some are connived at, out of favour or affection: <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi</hi> was not to know his <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Mother</hi> in Judgment.</p>
            <p n="11">XI.<note place="margin">Psal. 63.1.</note> When Members do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly and early attend our pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Assemblies,<note place="margin">Cant. 7.12.</note> and the worship of God on the Lord's-day espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially,<note place="margin">Mark 16.1.</note> but are remiss in that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: This is a great Evil.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. When part of a Church shall meet together as dissatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to consult Church-matters, without the knowledge or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of the Church, or Pastor:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 25.</note> This is disorderly,<note place="margin">Romans 16.17.</note> and tends to division; and such should be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. Another thing that tends to disquiet the Peace of the Church is, when there are any undue heats of Spirit, or Passion shewed
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60040:26"/>
in the Pastor,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.25.</note> or others, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging the Discipline of the Church. Have we not found by experience the sad effect of this? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore things must be always mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with coolness, and sweetness of Spirit, and moderation; every Brother having liberty to speak his mind, and not to be interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, until he has done; nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove one speak at once.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. When one Brother or more Dissents in the sentiments of their Minds from the Church, in any matters circumstantial; either in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of Faith,<note place="margin">Jude, 19.</note> Practice, or Discipline, and will not submit to the Majori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but raise Feuds;<note place="margin">Jam. 3.14.16.</note> nay, will rend themselves from the Church, rather than consent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I Quaery,</hi> what reason, or ground, hath any Man to refuse Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with a Church that Christ hath not left, but hath Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with?</p>
            <p n="15">XV. When any Member shall divulge, or make known to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, not of the Congregation, nor being concerned in those mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:60040:26"/>
what is done in Church-meetings, the Church in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect (as well as in others) is to be as a <hi>Garden inclosed, a Spring shut up, a Fountain sealed.</hi> This oft times occasions great Grief,<note place="margin">Cant. 4.12.</note> and the disorderly Person should be detected. Is it not a shame to any of a private Family, to divulge the Secrets of the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? But far greater shame do these expose themselves unto.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. Another disorderly Practice is this; <hi>viz.</hi> When a Member shall suggest, and seem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o insinuate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the minds of other Members some evil against their Pastor,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.29.</note> yet will not declare what it is;<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.4.</note> and may only be evil Surmisings,<note place="margin">Zech. 7.10.</note> &amp; out of Prejudice; and yet refuses to acquaint the Pastor with what it is: This is very abominable,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.19</note> and a palpable violation of the Rule of the Gospel, and Duty of Members to their Minister. Such a person ought to be severely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buk'd, and if he confess not his Evils, and manifesteth unfeigned Repentance, to be dealt with far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Moreover, it is a great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:60040:27"/>
in another to hear such base<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Insinuations, and neither rebuke the Accuser, and so discharge his Duty, nor take two or three more to bring the Person to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.<note place="margin">1 Timo. 5.19.</note> If he deal thus by a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Brother, it is a great Evil, but far worse to an <hi>Elder,</hi> whose Name and Honour, ought with all Care and Justice, to be kept up, as being more Sacred.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. Another disorderly Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice is,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 8.14.</note> (which causes much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) When the publick Charges of a Church are not equally born; but some too much burdened, when others do but little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 16.2.</note>And also, when every one does not Contribute to the Poor, as God has blessed them, on every Lord's day, or first day of the Week, as he hath Commanded.</p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. Another disorder is this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> When Members refuse to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with the Church at the Lord's table, because some person, or persons, they think are guilty of Evil,<note place="margin">Math. 18.</note> and yet they have not proceeded with them according to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:60040:27"/>
Rule: These either Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate the Church, or themselves, or those Persons at least, they censure unwarrantably.</p>
            <p>I beseech you for Christ's sake, that this may never be any more among you: You ought not to deal thus with them; or refuse your Communion, (tho faulty) until the Church has dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member'd, or withdrawn from them; or at least Suspended them.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. When one Member, shall believe, or receive a report against another,<note place="margin">Ier. 20.10.</note> before he knows the truth of the matter.</p>
            <p n="20">XX. When an Accusation is brought against an <hi>Elder,</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Rule, which ought not be without two or three Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.19.</note> as to the matter of Fact.</p>
            <p n="21">XXI. When the word of God is not carefully attended upon,<note place="margin">Isa. 55.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> on Week, or Lecture-days,<note place="margin">Acts 2, 1, 2.</note> by the Members generally; tho the said Meeting being appointed by the whole Church.<note place="margin">Acts, 10, 33.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="22">XXII. VVhen Days of Prayer and Fasting,<note place="margin">Ioel 2, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and of publick Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:60040:28"/>
or when days of Disciplining are not generally attended upon.</p>
            <p>Lastly, VVhen Gifted Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren are not duely encouraged: First privately to exercise their Gifts; and being in time appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, called forth to Preach or Exercise in the Church: And when encouragment is not given to bestow Learning also upon them, for their better Accomplishment. What will become of the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in time to come, if this be not prevented with speed?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>What tends to the Glory and Beauty of a true Gospel-Church.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">What tends to the Glory of a Church of Christ.</note>I. THat which Primarily tends to the Glory of a <hi>Church</hi> is the Foundation on which it is Built,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3, 4.</note> which is Jesus Christ. Now this is a blessed and glorious Fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</p>
            <p n="1">I. In respect of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who laid this Foundation in his eternal Purpose, Counsel, and Decree;<note place="margin">Isa. 28.16.</note> 
               <hi>Behold I lay in Sion</hi>; and this is as the result of his
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60040:28"/>
infinite Wisdom, Love, and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to his Elect.</p>
            <p n="2">II. In respect had unto Christ himself, who is this Foundation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He is a Suitable Foundation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In respect to the Glory of God in all his Attributes.</p>
            <p>2ly. In respect to our Good; he answering all our wants, who are united to him, or built upon him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In respect of the preciousness of Christ, as a Foundation; a Stone; a <hi>precious Stone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. In respect to the Durable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of it <hi>i. e. a tryed Stone</hi>;<note place="margin">Isa. 28.16.</note> a sure Foundation.</p>
            <p>Brethren, a Foundation of a House must of necessity be laid; no House can be built without a good Foundation, that will stand firm, and unmovable; it is the strongest part of the Building, and it beareth all the weight of the whole Superstructure: So doth Jesus Christ.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The Beauty and Glory of a true <hi>Church,</hi> consists in the true and regular, or right <hi>Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of it; nothing being want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60040:29"/>
that is Essential to it, upon this account.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. It consisteth in the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, Glory, and Suitableness of the materials 'tis Built with, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering to the Foundation; all <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Stones, lively Stones; all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated Persons.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2, 5, 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="5">V. In that all the Stones be well Hewed and Squared; all made fit for the Building, before laid in. VVere it thus, there would not be so great a Noise of the Hammer and Ax, in Church Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline,<note place="margin">1 Kings 6, 7.</note> as indeed there is. It was not thus in the Type, I mean in <hi>Solomon's</hi> Temple.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. It's Beauty and Glory consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth in that all the <hi>Stones</hi> being not only united by the Spirit, to <hi>Christ the Foundation,</hi> but also to one another in sincere Love and Affection. <hi>In whom all the Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, fitly Framed together, groweth up unto an holy Temple in the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 2.19, 20, 21.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="7">VII. It consisteth in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness and Purity of the Lives and Conversations of all the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: <hi>Be ye Holy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet, 1, 16,</note> 
               <hi>for I am Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:60040:29"/>
Holiness becomes thy House,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psalm 93.5.</note> 
               <hi>O God, for Ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">VIII. It consisteth in that sweet Union and Concord that ought to be in the Church; all like the <hi>Horse: in Pharoah's Chariot,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 1.9. Eph. 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together: Endeavouring to keep the Vnity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace. By this shall all Men know ye are my Disciples, if you Love one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">IX. In their having the divine Presence with them:<note place="margin">Exod. 20.24. Mat, 18, 20,</note> Or when the Glory of God fills his Temple.</p>
            <p n="10">X. In keeping out all unsancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, or unclean Persons, or if they get in, to purge them out by a strict and holy Discipline, or else it will soon loose it's Beauty.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.5, 6.7.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="11">XI. In that Zeal and Equality that should be shewed in all to keep up the Honour, Peace,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.14. Tit. 3.2.</note> and Comfort of the <hi>Church,</hi> and the Ministery thereof.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. In the Administration of right Discipline; to see no neglect nor delaying of Justice, thro carelesness, or Partiality: (1.) No ways partaking of other Mens Sins; which may be done by
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60040:30"/>
Conniving at it; (2.) By Lessen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or Extenuating of it (3.) By Countenancing, or any ways In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging any in Sin. (4.) By not Restoring a Brother, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesses his Sin when overtaken. (5.) Not bringing in a just Charge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst an Offender, nor rebuking him; and yet have Communion with him.</p>
            <p>2ly. Not to wrest Judgment, out of it's true and right Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel: Nor to inflict a greater cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure than the Law of Christ requires on any.</p>
            <p>3ly. Timely to acquit, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge a penitent Person.</p>
            <p>4ly. Not to do any thing on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Prejudice, but in Love, and Bowels, of affection; and to do all in Christ's Name, or by his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. To <hi>Sympathize</hi> with the <hi>Afflicted, Succour</hi> the <hi>Tempted,</hi> and <hi>Relieving</hi> the <hi>Poor</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stressed: Rejoicing</hi> with them that <hi>Rejoice,</hi> and <hi>Mourning</hi> with them that <hi>Mourn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">XIV. <hi>To speak evil of no Man</hi>; not only speaking no evil of their
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60040:30"/>
Brethren, but of no <hi>Man,</hi> to his hurt or injury, detracting from his Worth and Honour: See <hi>Sirach, Whether it be to Friend or Foe, talk not of other Men's Lives; and if thou canst,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 19.8. Apoc.</note> 
               <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Offence, reveal them not.</hi> We must not discourse his Faults, unless in a Gospel-way; and that too, to amend the Person, and not out of Passion, or Prejudice to expose him, but out of Love to his Soul. Yet we may speak of the evils of others, (1.) When called to do it, in a Legal or Gospel-way; and it is a Sin then to conceal his Crime. (2.) Or when it is to prevent another, who is in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be Infected by his <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,</hi> or ill Example. (3.) Or in our own just <hi>Defence</hi> and Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication. Moreover, consider the evil of Reproaching of others.</p>
            <p>First as to the causes why some do it.</p>
            <p n="1">I. One Cause is from want of Love: Nay from Malice; and Hatred.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:60040:31"/>1. From the Baseness, ill Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and Cruelty of the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers <hi>Disposition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis occasioned from that itch, of talking and medling in the <hi>Affairs</hi> of other Men.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Or perhaps to raise their own Esteem and Honour, some <hi>Degrade</hi> their Brother; which is <hi>Abominable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Consider it is <hi>Theft,</hi> or <hi>Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery</hi>; nay, and 'tis worse than to Rob a Man of his Goods, because thou takest away that which perhaps thou canst not restore again.</p>
            <p>Moreover consider, That such who reproach others, lay them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves open thereby to Reproach.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Moreover know, he that Receives, or Hearkens to the Scandal, is as Guilty as the <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuser</hi>; he is like a Person that receives Stolen Goods, and so is as bad as the Thief.</p>
            <p>This being one of the Grand and Notorious Evils of these <hi>Days</hi> I speak the more to it.</p>
            <p>If you abominate this evil, and avoid it, you will shine in <hi>Grace</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:60040:31"/>
and <hi>Vertue</hi> the more clearly.</p>
            <p>Alas, in our days, some that would be thought to be great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessers stick not to vilifie Christ's Ministers, even some of the best of Men; and are so full of Malice, they care not what wrong they do to their Brethren, nor to the truth it self, or interest of God, and so expose themselves to a last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing shame, and their Spirit,<note place="margin">3 Iohn 9.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and Practice, to an abhorrance; they are like cursed <hi>Cham</hi> who dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered his Fathers nakedness;<note place="margin">Gen. 9.22.</note> these persons violate all Laws, both Humane and Divine.</p>
            <p>3ly. When they bear one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Burdens,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.2.</note> 
               <hi>and so fulfil the Law of Christ:</hi> And that you may do this; consider where is that Church in which there are no Burdens to be Born.</p>
            <p>[<hi>Motives thus to do.</hi>]</p>
            <p n="1">1. Consider what a Burden Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ hath born for thee.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What a Burden thou hast to bear of thine own.<note place="margin">2 Gal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:60040:32"/>3. Mayst not thou in some things be a Burden to thy Brethren?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Wouldst thou not have others bear thy Burden.</p>
            <p n="5">5. May not God cause thee to bear a more heavy Burden; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause thou canst not bear thy Brother's?</p>
            <p n="6">
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3.10.</note>6. 'Tis a fulfilling the Law of Love, nay the <hi>Law</hi> of Christ.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. The Glory and Beauty of a Congregation, is the more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest, when the Authority of the Church, and the Dignity of the Pastoral Office is maintained. How great was the <hi>Evil of the gain-saying of Corah?</hi> The Apostles speaks of some that are <hi>Selfwilled, Presumptious,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude, 11. Numb. 22.7, 21.</note> 
               <hi>who are not afraid to speak evil of Dignities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God has put a Glory and high Dignity upon the Church and in it's Authority and Power; <hi>Whom ye bind on Earth shall be bound in Heaven.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.10</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:60040:32"/>Moreover, the Pastoral Office, is an Office of Dignity;<note place="margin">Rev. 2.1.</note> they are called <hi>Rulers, Angels, Fathers:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.5. Act. 23, 5.</note> For any therefore to cast contempt on the Church, or Pastor, is a great evil, and a reproach to Christ, and tends to Disorder and Confusion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lastly,</hi> When Holiness, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness,<note place="margin">Psal. 110.3. 1 Pet. 1.25.</note> Charity, Humility, and all true Piety is prest upon the Consciences of every Member, and appears in the Minister: also that all strive to excell therein, with their uttermost Care and Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The Conclusion.</head>
            <p>KNow my Brethren,<note place="margin">Psal. 87.2.</note> That <hi>God loves the Gates of Sion more than all the dwelling places of Jacob:</hi> Therefore the publick Worship of God ought to be preferred before private.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This supposeth there must be a visible Church.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:60040:33"/>2. And that they frequently meet together to worship God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That they have an orderly Ministery and one ordained <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> at least, to administer all Publick Ordinances.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Moreover, that all Persons have free liberty to assemble with the Church, and to partake of all Ordinances, save those which pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly belong to the Church; as the Lord's Supper,<note place="margin">Neh. 1.2.</note> holy Discipline, and days of Prayer and Fasting. Then the Church of Old sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated themselves from all Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How should Sinners else be Convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Church in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased.</note>Yet others may attend on all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther publick Ordinances with the Church; as publick Prayer, Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Preaching the Word and in Singing <hi>God</hi>'s Praises, as hath formerly been proved. May others my Brethren, join in Prayer with us, and not praise <hi>God</hi> with us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>But, O my Brethren! let me beseech you to shew your high
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:60040:33"/>
Value, and Estimation for the publick Worship of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>[<hi>Motives hereunto.</hi>]</p>
            <p n="1">1. Since <hi>God</hi> prefers it thus: Or has so great Esteem of his publick Worship.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Because he is said to dwell in <hi>Sion; It is his Habitation for ever.</hi> The place,<note place="margin">Psal. 132.13. Psal. 26.8.</note> where his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour dwells.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Here God is most Glorified.</p>
            <p>In his <hi>Temple</hi> every one speaks of his Glory; <hi>My Praise shall be in the great Congregation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 29.9.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Here is most of God's gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious presence (as one observes it.)</p>
            <p n="1">1. His effectual Presence, <hi>in all Places</hi>;<note place="margin">Exod. 20.24.</note> 
               <hi>Where I record my Name, thither will I come; and there will I bless thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Here is More of his intimate presence<hi>: Where two or three are gathered together in my Name,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18.20.</note> 
               <hi>there am I in the midst of them.</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:60040:34"/>
He walks in the midst of the seven <hi>Golden Candlesticks.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 1.13.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Here are the clearest mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festations of God's Beauty, which made holy <hi>David</hi> desire <hi>to dwell there for ever.</hi> See the appearance of Christ to the Churches,<note place="margin">Psal. 27.4.</note> 
               <hi>Rev,</hi> 2. cap. 3.</p>
            <p n="6">6. In that it is said, that those that should be Saved, in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles days, God added unto the Church.<note place="margin">Acts 2.47.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Here is most Spiritual Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to be got: <hi>Here the Dews of Hermon fall, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scend upon the Mountain of Sion. Here God commands the Blessing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 132.3.</note> 
               <hi>even Life for evermore. I will abundantly bless her Provision,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 130.15.</note> 
               <hi>and satisfie her Poor with Bread.</hi> Here <hi>David</hi>'s Doubt was resolved.<note place="margin">Psal. 73.16.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="8">
               <note place="margin">Psal. 87.5.</note>8. Here you received your first spiritual Breath, or Life, many Souls are daily Born to Christ. That good which is most Diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive, is to be Preferred; but that good which most partake of, is most Diffusive; <hi>O magnifie the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60040:34"/>
Lord with me! let us exalt his Name together.</hi> Live Coals se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated,<note place="margin">Psal. 34.3.</note> soon die.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Brethren (as a worthy <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine</hi> observes) the Church in her publick Worship is the nearest Resemblance of Heaven, especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Singing God's Praises. What Esteem also had God's Worthies of old, for God's publick VVor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship? <hi>My Soul longeth, yea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 84.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven fainteth for the Courts of the Lord. How amiable are thy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles, O Lord of Hosts!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. See how the Promises of <hi>God</hi> run to <hi>Sion,</hi> or to his <hi>Church:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isaiah 35.</note> 
               <hi>He will bless thee out of Sion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 128.3.</note> O let nothing discourage you in your waiting at the Posts of Christ's Door:<note place="margin">Isai. 51.3. Prov. 8.34. Psal. 26.14.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> desired <hi>Rather to be a Door-Keeper in the House of God, than to Dwell in the Tents of Wickedness.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 87.4.</note> Yet nevertheless do not neglect, for the Lord's sake, private Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>viz.</hi> Secret, and Family-Prayer: O pray to be fitted for publick Worship!<note place="margin">Mat. 6.6.</note> Come out of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:60040:35"/>
your Closets to the Church?<note place="margin">Jer. 10.25.</note> What signifies all you do in Publick, if you are not such that keep up the Worship of God in your own Families?</p>
            <p>O neglect not Prayer, Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Meditation! And take care also to Educate and Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chise your <hi>Children</hi>; and live as Men and Women <hi>that are dead to this World:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 6.4. Phil. 1.27.</note> and walk for the Lord's sake as becomes the <hi>Gospel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See that <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> go together; a good <hi>Conversation.</hi> and a good <hi>Doctrine</hi> go together These <hi>Two</hi> together, are better than <hi>One.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Brethren, he that makes the VVord of God his Rule, in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever he doth,<note place="margin">Eccl. 4.9.10.11.12.13.</note> and the Glory of God his end in what he doth, shall have the Spirit of God to be his strength. This is like <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi>'s Three-fold Cord; that will be One, or it will be Three; it can't be Two; not can it be broken.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:60040:35"/>
            <head>The Solemn Covenant of the Church of Christ, meeting in <hi>White-street,</hi> at it's Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>June,</hi> 5. 1696.</head>
            <p>WE who desire to walk together in the Fear of the Lord, do, through the Assistance of his Holy Spirit, profess our deep and serious Humiliation for all our Transgressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And we do also solemnly, in the Presence of God, of each other, in the Sense of our own Vnworthiness,<note place="margin">Ezek. 16.6, 8. 2 Cor. 8.5. Hos. 2.23. 2 Cor. 6.16.</note> give up our selves to the Lord, in a Church state according to the Apos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolical Constitution that he may be our God, and we may be his People, through the Everlasting Covenant of his Free grace, in which alone we hope to be accepted by him, through his blessed Son Jesus Christ, whom we take to be our High Priest, to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stify and sanctify us, and our Prophet to teach us; and to subject to him as our Law-giver, and the King of Saints; and to conform to all his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Laws and Ordinances,<note place="margin">Church-Communion proved.</note> for our growth, Establishment, and Consola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; that we may be as a Holy Spouse
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60040:36"/>
unto him, and serve him in our Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and wait for his second Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, as our glorious Bridegroom.</p>
            <p>Being fully satisfied in the way o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Church-Communion,<note place="margin">Exod. 26.3.4, 6. Isa. 62.5. Psal. 122.3. Eph. 2.23. Eph. 4.16. 1 Pet. 2.5.</note> and the Trut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Grace in some good measure upon one anothers Spirits, we do solemnly join our selves together in a Holy V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and Fellowship, humbly submit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Discipline of the Gospel,<note place="margin">Psal. 93.5. Isa. 55.8. Luke 1.74.75.</note> and all Holy Duties required of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> People in such a spiritual Relation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We do promise and ingage to walk in all Holiness,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.1. 1 Tim. 6.11. 2 Pet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.6, 7.</note> Godliness, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and Brotherly Love, as much as in us lieth to render our Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion delightful to God, comfortable to our selves,<note place="margin">Act. 20.19. Phil. 2.3. Ioh, 13, 34, and 15, 12,</note> and lovely to the res<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Lord's People.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We do promise to watch over each others Conversations, and not to suffer Sin upon one another,<note place="margin">1 Pet, 1, 22, Lev. 19, 17, Heb, 10, 24, 25,</note> so far <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God shall discover it to us, or any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> us; and to stir up one another to L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> and good Works;<note place="margin">1 Thess, 5, 14, 15, Rom, 15,</note> to warn, rebuke, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> admonish one another with Meekness according to the Rules left to us of Christ in that Behalf.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">Eph. 6.18. Iam. 5.16.</note>3. We do promise in an especial manner to pray for one another, and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:60040:36"/>
for the Glory and Increase of this Church,<note place="margin">Col, 4, 12.</note> and for the Presence of God in it, and the pouring forth of his Spirit on it, and his Protection over it to his Glory.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We do promise to bear one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Burdens,<note place="margin">Gal, 6, 2, Heb, 12, 12, Heb, 13, 31 Rom, 12, 15 2 Cor, 11, 29,</note> to cleave to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to have a Fellow-feeling with one another, in all Conditions both outward and inward, as God in his Providence shall cast any of us into</p>
            <p n="5">5. We do promise to bear with one anothers Weakeness,<note place="margin">1 Iohn 3.17, 18, Gal 6, 1, 1 Thess, 5, 14, Rom, 15, 12, Eph, 4, 31, 32,</note> Failings, and Infirmities, with much Tenderness, not discovering to any without the Church, nor any within, unless ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Christ's Rule, and the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Gospel provided in that case.</p>
            <p n="6">6. We do promise to strive toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the Truths of the Gospel,<note place="margin">Iude, v, 3, Gal, 5, 1, Tit, 3, 9, 10, 2 Iohn v, 10,</note> and Purity of God's Ways and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, to avoid Causes, and Causers of Division, endeavouring to keep the Vnity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace; <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4 3.</p>
            <p n="7">7 We do promise to meet together on Lord's Days, <note place="margin">Heb 3, 10, and 10, 25, Mal, 3, 16, Rom, 14, 18 and 15, 16,</note> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ther times, as the Lord shall gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to serve and glorify God in the
<pb facs="tcp:60040:37"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Worship,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 26,</note> to edify one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and to contrive the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Church.</p>
            <p n="8">8. We do promise according to our Ability (or as God shall bless us with the good things of this World) to Communicate to our Pastor of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor, 9, 7,</note> God having ordained that they that Preach the Gospel should live of the Gospel.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 9, -12, 13</note> (And now can any thing lay a greater obligation upon the Conscience,<note place="margin">Gal, 6, 6,</note> than this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, what then is the Sin of such who violate it?)</p>
            <p>These and all other Gospel-Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties we humbly submit unto, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing and purposing to perform, not in our own Strength, being consciou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of our own Weakness, but in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Power, and Strength of the Blessed God, whose we are, and whom we desire to serve: To whom be Glory now and for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:60040:37"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
