<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mr. Speakers speech before the King in the Lords House of Parliament July the third 1641 concerning the passing of three bills viz : poll-money, star-chamber and high commission.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-01">2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47693</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1080</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11632</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13013421</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13013421</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96524</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A47693)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96524)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 259:E198, no 29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mr. Speakers speech before the King in the Lords House of Parliament July the third 1641 concerning the passing of three bills viz : poll-money, star-chamber and high commission.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
                  <author>Lenthall, William, 1591-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-05</date>
            <label>TCP Staff (Oxford)</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96524:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. SPEAKERS SPEECH, Before the King, in the Lords House of <hi>Parliament. July</hi> the third, 1641. Concerning the passing of three Bills. Viz. Poll-money. Star-chamber, and High Commission.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:96524:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96524:2"/>
            <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Speaker's <hi>SPEECH.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Government of Common wealth rests in the Rules of order, and hath so much affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and consent with the Rules of Nature, in the government of the World, that the first copie and mutation of the one may seeme to be taken from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall and first modell of the other.</p>
            <p>This contemplation (most excellent and gracious Sovereigne) casts our eyes upon your sacred Majesty, as that Celestial Orbe, which never resting without the office of perpetuall motion, to cherish the lower bodies, not enriching it self with any trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures drawn from below, exhales in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours from the inferiour Elements, what in due season it returns in showres.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:96524:3"/>
The application makes us consider our selves, those subluninary creatures which having their essence and being from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of those beames (as the flowers of the field) open to receive the glory of the Sun.</p>
            <p>In this relation both contribute to the common good, your sacred Majestie as a Nursing Father designed to bestow on your people, the blessing of peace and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and wee as the children of obedience returne our duties and affections in Aids and Tributes. And this compacted in one body by the ligaments of Religion and Laws, hath been the object of admiration to the whole world.</p>
            <p>Amidst the distraction of forreigne Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, wee onely have sate under the sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of our Vines, and dranke the wines of our own Vintage.</p>
            <p>But your crafty adversaries, perceiving that the fervent profession of your own re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and the firme observation of our Laws, have beene the pillars of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperity, By subtile insinuations, pretending
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96524:3"/>
a politike necessity to admit of a moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in our Religion, to comply with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain Princes, and suggesting it a principall in the rule of Soveraignty, to require and take into, aske and have, that it must <hi>postu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lare</hi> by power, not <hi>petere</hi> by Laws, and keepe this misery of war and calamity, between Nation and Nation, and put us in the posture of gaze to the whole world.</p>
            <p>But when wee behold your sacred Majesty discended from the Royall loines of that glorious King, which by his wisdome and policie, first ingrafted the white Rose and the Red, upon the same stock, and sheathed the sword that had pierced the bowels of so much Nobilitie, glutted with the bloud of people, and then laid the first hopes of the happy union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Nations.</p>
            <p>When our thoughts refresh themselves with that happy memory of that religious King your gracious Father, on whose sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Temples both diadems were placed, wrethed about with this motto, <hi>Faciam eos ingentem unam,</hi> we cannot but believe that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96524:4"/>
God and Nature (by a lineall succession from those Fathers of peace) hath ordained you that <hi>lapis Angularis</hi> upon which the whole frame settles, and put into the hands of your sacred Majestie, the possibility and power to firme and stablish this happy u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion between your Kingdomes, and so raise your memory a Statue of glory and wisdome from generation to generation.</p>
            <p>In all this length of time, the assurance of this Vnion and peace hath beene the chief object of our desires, Our Purses have beene as open as our hearts, both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing to this great work manifested by so many Subsidies already presented, suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in our first hopes for the full perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>But finding that faile, have again ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured upon your peoples property, and in an old and absolute way, new burnisht by the hand of instant necessity, expressed to the World the heart of a loyall people, and howsoever guided with a new name of tranquility &amp; peace to your Kingdome, that with more ease the people may dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96524:4"/>
the bitternesse of this Pill, yet still our hearts had the same aime and object.</p>
            <p>A gift sutable to the necessity of such vast extent that time cannot paralell it by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny example.</p>
            <p>And by which, if your sacred Majesty vouchsafe your Royall assent, wee shall not doubt you may soone accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plish those happy effects that may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent your wisdome the object of wonder, and your policy to bee admired amongst the Nations.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
