<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>L'Estrange his appeal humbly submitted to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty and the three estates assembled in Parliament</title>
            <title>Appeal humbly submitted to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty and the three estates assembled in Parliament</title>
            <author>L'Estrange, Roger, Sir, 1616-1704.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-03">2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47806</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1202</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13428</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12936056</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12936056</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95761</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A47806)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95761)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 388:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>L'Estrange his appeal humbly submitted to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty and the three estates assembled in Parliament</title>
                  <title>Appeal humbly submitted to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty and the three estates assembled in Parliament</title>
                  <author>L'Estrange, Roger, Sir, 1616-1704.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 37 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-11</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95761:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95761:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>L'ESTRANGE</hi>
HIS
APPEAL
Humbly Submitted to the
KINGS most Excellent MAJESTY
And the
THREE ESTATES
Assembled in
PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed for <hi>Henry Brome</hi> at the Gun in S. <hi>Pauls</hi>
Church-yard, 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="appeal">
            <pb facs="tcp:95761:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95761:2"/>
            <head>L'Estrange's APPEAL. &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IF the matter here in question had been the single
case of <hi>L'Estrange,</hi> nothing could have been more
<hi>Ridiculous,</hi> then the <hi>Vanity,</hi> and <hi>Ostentation</hi> of this
<hi>Appeal:</hi> But as His Case stands complicate with
Other Circumstances, that import no lesse then the
<hi>Honour,</hi> the <hi>Iustice</hi> and the very <hi>Security</hi> of the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;</hi>
the business of these Papers is no longer a
<hi>private Apology,</hi> but a <hi>publick Duty.</hi> This will be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
understood, upon a clear Distribution of what I
have to say into such and such Heads; and then deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
expounding, and distinguishing (in an Orderly
Method,) upon the several Members of my Discourse.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> First Point <hi>shall be</hi> the <hi>Subject matter</hi> of those
Swarms of Libells that in their Outrageous Course,<note place="margin">The Subject of This Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course.</note> have
taken <hi>Me</hi> in their way toward the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, To <hi>vindicate,</hi> and <hi>discharge</hi> my self from
those <hi>Calumnies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly; To lay open the <hi>Quality</hi> of the <hi>Libellers:</hi>
And the True <hi>Reason</hi> of their Rancour against <hi>me,</hi> in
despite of all <hi>Pretensions</hi> to the <hi>Contrary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly; To set forth their <hi>Designs,</hi> and <hi>Practices</hi>
upon the <hi>Dignity,</hi> and <hi>Safety</hi> of the <hi>Government,</hi> and
upon the <hi>Publick Peace.</hi> And</p>
            <p>Lastly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a Modest Deliberation how far in <hi>Honour, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice</hi>
and <hi>Policy,</hi> it may concern any <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>State</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever
to <hi>Support, Countenance,</hi> and <hi>Protect</hi> the <hi>As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serters</hi>
of their <hi>Laws, Rights</hi> and <hi>Priviledges,</hi> against
the bold, and Seditious attempts of the <hi>Enemies</hi> of the
<hi>Constitution. Of These in Order, and as briefly as
I may.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:95761:3"/>
Touching the <hi>First point:</hi> The Libellers have drawn
the Main of my Charge into these <hi>Six Articles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. That I have turn'd the <hi>Plot</hi> into <hi>Ridicule;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Articles against me.</note> and put
an <hi>Affront</hi> upon <hi>King, Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> in so doing.</p>
            <p>2. That I have Countenanc'd a <hi>Sham-Plot; ;</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd
to turn it upon the <hi>Presbyterians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. That I have made it my businesse to lessen the <hi>Credit</hi>
of the <hi>Kings Witnesses.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. That I have comprehended All the <hi>States, Orders,</hi>
and <hi>Divisions</hi> of men, both <hi>Lords, Citizens,</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi>
of <hi>England,</hi> under the Opprobrious Names of <hi>Citt,</hi>
and <hi>Bumpkin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. That I have Scandalously misrepresented all the <hi>Late
Petitions,</hi> and the <hi>Promoters</hi> of them.</p>
            <p>6. That my Writings create <hi>Misunderstandings,</hi> and
tend to the <hi>Embroyling</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to discharge my self of these odious and mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
Imputations, in course as they lye; I shall speak,
First, to the <hi>Ridiculing</hi> of the <hi>Plot,</hi> in contempt of the
Authority of the Nation; and refer my self to the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denyable
Evidences of my own Papers: beginning
with my Particular Opinion of it, as I have deliver'd
it to the World.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>§. 1. My Opinion of the Quality of the Plot.</head>
               <p>The bringing of this <hi>DEVILISH Plot,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of a DEVILISH Plot.</note> upon the Stage,
has struck all men of <hi>Piety,</hi> and <hi>Loyalty,</hi> and Love to their
<hi>Country,</hi> with <hi>Amazement</hi> and <hi>Horrour.</hi> The <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
of a <hi>Prince;</hi> the <hi>Subversion</hi> of the <hi>Government,</hi>
and <hi>Religion;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Plot ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated.</note> What can be more <hi>Execrable?</hi> The Thought
of so <hi>DIABOLICAL</hi> a Practice has justly transported the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95761:3"/>
People to the highest degree of <hi>Rage</hi> against it imaginable;
and it is a <hi>Meritorious</hi> and a <hi>Laudable zeal</hi> too,<note place="margin">A Legal zeal against it Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended.</note> so long
as it contains it self within the bounds of <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>Duty;</hi>
While the <hi>King,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">With a Defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</note> 
                  <hi>Councell,</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> are in the
mean time <hi>Sifting</hi> and <hi>Examining</hi> the <hi>Design;</hi> and doing
<hi>Justice</hi> upon the <hi>Offenders. Case Put, Pag.</hi> 33.</p>
               <p>After all this care taken to tear up the <hi>ACCURSED
PLOT</hi> by the <hi>Root.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">An accursed Plot.</note> 
                  <hi>Further Discovery Pa.</hi> 23.</p>
               <p>As to the <hi>HELLISH DESIGN</hi> upon the Life of our
Gracious Sovereign,<note place="margin">A Hellish de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign.</note> by Pistol, Sword, or Poysou. <hi>Ibid.
Pag. 25. And again</hi> [This <hi>DETESTABLE PLOT</hi>
now in Agitation] <hi>Hist. of the Plot,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A Derestable Plot.</note> 
                  <hi>Preface.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let This serve as to my Opinion of the <hi>Quality</hi> of the
<hi>Plot.</hi> A word now to the <hi>Believing</hi> of it.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Touching my Belief of it.</head>
                  <p>As to the <hi>Popish Plot,</hi> that is Sworn by the <hi>Kings
Witnesses,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Sworn Plot given for Granted.</note> I lay my Faith at their feet, without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<hi>Enquiry,</hi> or <hi>Dispute. Narrative. Pag.</hi> 20.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Under colour of asserting and making out the Truth of
the Plot,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Plot un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>questionable.</note> (which no sober man doubts of) <hi>&amp;c.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer
to the Appeal. Pag. 33.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All our</hi> Courts <hi>of</hi> Justice,<note place="margin">Proved upon Record.</note> 
                     <hi>and</hi> Journals <hi>of</hi> State <hi>bear</hi>
Witnesse <hi>to it. (The</hi> Popish Plot.) <hi>Narrative,</hi> Pa. 4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whoever carefully</hi> peruses their Writings, <hi>and</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions;
compares <hi>their</hi> Testimonies, (that is, the
Kings Witnesses,) <hi>and yet</hi> doubts <hi>of the</hi> Plot; <hi>is little
better certainly then</hi> Seal'd up under <hi>the Spirit of</hi> Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<hi>and</hi> Delusion.<note place="margin">He's mad that believes it not</note> Ibid. Pag. 3.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Question is not the</hi> CERTAINTY <hi>of</hi> One Plot,<note place="margin">No Question of the Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the Plot.</note>
                     <hi>but the</hi> Superfaetation <hi>of</hi> Another. Ans. to the Appeal.
Pag. 19. And further, <hi>It is no clearing the</hi> Papists <hi>of</hi>
One Plot <hi>upon the Kings Life,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Papists not clear'd by Charging the Presbyterians:</note> 
                     <hi>the Charging of the</hi> Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians
<hi>with</hi> Another. Ibid. Pag. 22.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:95761:4"/>
There are a Sort of men that,<note place="margin">One Plot un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Another.</note> under countenance of <hi>THIS
Plot,</hi> advance <hi>another</hi> of their <hi>Own.</hi> And if a man
<hi>Writes,</hi> or <hi>Speaks,</hi> or <hi>Reasons</hi> against them, he is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently
a <hi>Favourer</hi> of the <hi>Papists,</hi> a <hi>Lessener</hi> of the <hi>Plot,</hi>
and run down with <hi>Nonsense,</hi> and <hi>Clamour. Case
Put. Pag.</hi> 34.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>My turning it into Ridicule.</head>
                  <p>[For my own part I am so far from <hi>Laughing</hi> at it <hi>(the
Plot)</hi> that it wounds my Soul,<note place="margin">The Plot no Laughing matter.</note> the very thought on't.] <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
Catholique, Pa.</hi> 10. 11.</p>
                  <p>Nor have I been lesse Punctual in my acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of the <hi>Iustice</hi> of all <hi>Proceedings</hi> upon't, and in
my <hi>Submissions</hi> to the <hi>Sentences</hi> that have been Pass'd
in the Case.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>All Proceedings upon the Plot, Iustified.</head>
                  <p>After so many <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Jesuits</hi> and other Leading
men of That Party removed by the Stroke of <hi>Publick Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice.</hi>
&amp;c.<note place="margin">Publick Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice.</note> 
                     <hi>Further Discovery. Pag.</hi> 23.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We have had</hi> Legal Tryalls,<note place="margin">Legal Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings.</note> Proofs, Verdicts, Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences,
<hi>and</hi> Legall Executions <hi>in the Case.</hi> Ans. to the
Appeal. Pag. 10.</p>
                  <p>His Majesty hath two main Difficulties to Encounter at
once;<note place="margin">The King un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der two diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties.</note> the <hi>One</hi> to Master the <hi>Plot it self;</hi> the <hi>Other,</hi> to
<hi>Temper</hi> and <hi>Sweeten</hi> the <hi>Passions</hi> of men, <hi>Zealous</hi> in the
<hi>Contrary Extreme;</hi> that no Inconvenience may arise
from Their Misapprehension of things Another way. <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born
Subject. Pag. 27. And again.</hi> [The <hi>Depositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
have been Formally taken before his <hi>Majesty,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces strictly weighed and Examined.</note> and his
<hi>Privy Councell;</hi> and the <hi>Evidences STRICTLY
weigh'd,</hi> and <hi>Examin'd;</hi> and from thence afterwards
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95761:4"/>
heartily <hi>recommended,</hi> and faithfully Transmitted to the
<hi>Two Houses of Parliament. Ibid. Pag. 28.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Be it always understood that where AUTHORITY hath
passed a <hi>Sentence,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Sentence of Authority is Sacred.</note> there is no longer any Place for Hesita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
or Demur. <hi>Further Discovery, Pag.</hi> 3.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§. 2. The Shamming of the Plot.</head>
               <p>Now as to the <hi>Shamming</hi> of the <hi>Plot,</hi> and casting it
upon the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> the learned Authour of the
<hi>Gyants War,</hi> and of several other <hi>Course Complements
upon his Majesty;</hi> (they say he puts in for a <hi>Patrimonial
Right</hi> to a Place upon one of the <hi>City Gates,)</hi> This
Learned Authour (I say) has been pleased to Glosse
upon My Text,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>L'Estranges</hi> charge, as if he made the Plot only a blinde.</note> as if I represented <hi>[The Plot only as a</hi>
Blind <hi>to enrage People; and that there was a reall</hi> Design
<hi>to destroy the</hi> Hierarchy, <hi>and all the Sons of the Church,
by the name of</hi> Papists <hi>in</hi> Masquerade, <hi>and get all the
places of</hi> Profit <hi>to</hi> themselves] Now for my Suggesting
the <hi>Popish Plot</hi> to be only <hi>a Blind to enrage People;</hi> I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy
the world, either to shew that I have <hi>misrecited my
Self</hi> in what I have already deliver'd;<note place="margin">No colour for any such charge.</note> or to produce
any one passage out of all my Writings, that, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
extreme Violence, will in any degree countenance
Such a Construction. But still, as I am Innocent of
rendering <hi>That</hi> to be only a <hi>Blind,</hi> which <hi>King, Lords,</hi>
and <hi>Commons</hi> have pronounced to be <hi>a damnable and
hellish Plot;</hi> So am I thoroughly convinc'd, on the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
hand, that there are <hi>Several Sham-Plots contriv'd,</hi>
and <hi>Started,</hi> where there was no colour or pretense for a
man to Imagine that there was any Plot at all: and that
great use is made of these Inventions, for a <hi>Blind</hi> to the
Advancing of a <hi>Fanatical Design.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Blind lies on the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natical side.</note> And how far That
Project may reasonably tend toward the destruction
of the <hi>Hierachy,</hi> and the <hi>Sons of the Church,</hi> under the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95761:5"/>
notion of <hi>Papists</hi> in <hi>Masquerade;</hi> and the <hi>engrossing of all
Power into their own hands,</hi> shall be set forth in its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
place.</p>
               <p>But how comes <hi>L'Estrange</hi> to be charg'd with turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the <hi>Popish Plot</hi> over to the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Why a sham in 1680. and none in al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>most 20. years before.</note> now in
1680. that has been perpetually ringing the same Peal
in the ears of the Government, ever since 1661. that
he does at <hi>This Instant?</hi> And I do not remember any
<hi>Popish Plot</hi> that was taken notice of in those days.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the</hi> Epistle Dedicatory <hi>of my</hi> Holy Cheat <hi>to</hi> the House
of Commons,<note place="margin">I said the same thing in 1661, and ever since.</note> 1661. <hi>I have these Words (speaking of
the</hi> Presbyterians) [they cast the blood and guilt of the late
War upon his Majesty; make his Adherents Traytors; place
the Supreme Authority in the two Houses; Subject the Law
to an Ordinance; the Government to a Faction; and Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate
the Schismatiques to Serve his Majesty in Being, as
they did his Father. This is the Drift of their Seditious
Libells <hi>&amp;c.] And a little farther, This Citation of</hi>
Douglas's Coronation-Sermon, <hi>Then</hi> newly Reprinted.</p>
               <p>[This may serve to justify the Proceedings of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
against the late King,<note place="margin">Presbyterian Treason in 1660.</note> who in a Hostile way set himself
to overthrow Religion, Parliaments, Laws, and Liberties.
<hi>Pag.</hi> 10.] What could I say lesse to the Insolence of
such Pamphlets; or what is it more that I do <hi>now</hi> upon
this Subject, that what I did <hi>twenty years since?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§. 3. About disparaging the Kings Wittnesses.</head>
               <p>The next Calumny layd to my Charge, is the <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crediting</hi>
of the <hi>Kings Witnesses;</hi> wherein I once again
repayre to my own Papers; which, without a <hi>new
Dictionary,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Black <hi>is</hi> White; <hi>and</hi> White <hi>is</hi> Black.</note> and a <hi>new Grammar,</hi> will abundantly acquit
me. For according to <hi>Common English,</hi> and <hi>Syntaxe,</hi>
I have rather strain'd a point of <hi>Modesty</hi> upon an <hi>Excess</hi>
of <hi>Respect,</hi> then, on the <hi>Other side,</hi> been <hi>wanting</hi> to it.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95761:5"/>
As for Example; in my <hi>Further Discovery,</hi> to <hi>Dr.
Oates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They are <hi>wonderfull things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A Personal Respect to Dr. <hi>Oates.</hi>
                  </note> Dr. which you have done
<hi>already;</hi> and I am Perswaded that you are yet reserved for
<hi>more wonderfull things to come;</hi> which must be the work
of <hi>Time</hi> to disclose; when <hi>Truth</hi> shall deliver her self from
the Rubbish of <hi>Oppression</hi> and <hi>Slander:</hi> and in despite
of <hi>Envy,</hi> and <hi>Imposture,</hi> render your <hi>Name</hi> as famous to
<hi>Posterity,</hi> as your <hi>Virtue</hi> has made it to the <hi>present Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi>
And this I write with little lesse then the <hi>Genius</hi> of
a Prophet. <hi>Pag.</hi> 21.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>These very words</hi> from the Pen of a <hi>Servile Parasite,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>L'Estr</hi>'s Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities are turn'd into Libels.</note> would have pass'd for a <hi>Panegyrick,</hi> which in <hi>L'Estrange</hi>
must be Interpreted for a <hi>Libell:</hi> Nay all the force of
<hi>Argument,</hi> and <hi>Intention</hi> must be destroy'd, and the
very <hi>Standard</hi> of the <hi>English Tongue alter'd,</hi> to do <hi>me
a good Turn.</hi> Every Syllable is put to the <hi>Torture,</hi> to
know what <hi>Moutbs</hi> I made upon the Writing of it:
And if I do but stumble upon a <hi>Figure,</hi> that would be
an <hi>Ornament,</hi> perhaps, upon <hi>another mans Paper,</hi> it is
a <hi>Blot</hi> upon <hi>mine;</hi> and the most <hi>Innocent</hi> of my <hi>Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phors,</hi>
and <hi>Allusions</hi> are melted down into <hi>Articles,</hi> and
<hi>Depositions,</hi> without the Allowance of so much as <hi>one
grain</hi> for <hi>Humane Frailty.</hi> And all this, by the virtue
of a kind of <hi>Inverted Alchymy,</hi> that instead of the more
<hi>Generous Operation</hi> of <hi>exalting Baser mettles</hi> into <hi>Nobler,</hi>
and turning <hi>Copper</hi> into <hi>Gold,</hi> sets up a <hi>New Profession</hi>
of turning <hi>Gold,</hi> into <hi>Dirt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>[Who was it but <hi>You,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The same Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu'd, and the Fact founded upon the Narrative.</note> again; that so effectually layd o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
the <hi>Intrigues</hi> of the <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Jesuits,</hi> with the
<hi>Schismatiques,</hi> in the late <hi>Rebellion?</hi> That shew'd his
Majesty so plainly who they were that <hi>Dethron'd</hi> and <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd</hi>
his <hi>Father:</hi> and painted the whole <hi>Conspiracy</hi> so
to the Life, that a body might <hi>Wink</hi> and see <hi>thorough</hi> it?
Who but <hi>you,</hi> Sir, to trace them down to this very In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95761:6"/>
through all their Disguises and Caballs, Fomenting
a <hi>Rebellion</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi> with the <hi>Presbyterians; Incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diaries</hi>
in <hi>London</hi> with the <hi>Millenaries;</hi> and up and
down Tampering with the whole Crew of of <hi>Sectaries?</hi>
Who was it but <hi>You</hi> that first found out the <hi>Conspiracy</hi> it
self, and then the <hi>Conspirators?</hi> Who but You the Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
Instrument in the opening of the <hi>Combination?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is all this,<note place="margin">All Honour paid to the Doctor.</note> but to <hi>Trace</hi> the <hi>Dr.</hi> in the very
<hi>History</hi> of <hi>himself?</hi> And to say more to his <hi>Honour</hi> then,
perchance, ever any man sayd before me: bating on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
the Person that, First, gave him the Title of THE
SAVIOUR OF THE NATION.</p>
               <p>It cannot be deny'd but that the Kings Witnesses have
ventur'd as far,<note place="margin">The Industry and Hazzard of the Kings Witnesses ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged.</note> and done as much as men could do, under
Their Circumstances, to make out the Truth of a <hi>Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi>
and <hi>Hellish Popish Plot</hi> upon the Life of his Sacred
Majesty, our Religion, and Civill Government, <hi>Ib. pa.</hi> 23.</p>
               <p>It would be endlesse to encounter the Malice of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
Scurrilous Buffoon that neither dares own his
Name to the Government, nor to the Subject of his
Outrage and Venom: But yet in regard that the whole
pack of them fall in with full Cry upon two Passages
in the Second and Third Pages of my <hi>Further Discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi>
I shall bestow a word or two more upon those Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections.
The Words are These.</p>
               <p>I have naturally a Veneration for the <hi>Government,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A mighty Bustle about this passage.</note> and
all that Love it; for the Kings <hi>Loyall Wittnesses;</hi> and the
Preservers of his Sacred Life, in the <hi>First</hi> place: with an
Equall <hi>Horror</hi> and <hi>Detestation</hi> for all his <hi>Enemies,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
what <hi>Mask</hi> or <hi>form</hi> Soever. I <hi>believe</hi> the <hi>Plot;</hi> and
as much as every <hi>good Subject ought</hi> to believe; or as
any man in his <hi>Right Wits can believe:</hi> Nay I do so <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely
believe</hi> it, that in my Conscience <hi>You your Self,</hi>
Doctor, do not <hi>believe more</hi> of it, then <hi>I do.</hi> Pag. 2.</p>
               <p>Now where's the <hi>disparaging</hi> of the <hi>Kings Wittnesses</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:95761:6"/>
in all This?<note place="margin">The foresaid passage justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd.</note> I <hi>believe</hi> the <hi>Plot;</hi> and as <hi>much of it</hi> as an
<hi>honest man ought,</hi> or a <hi>Sober man can</hi> believe; nay as
much of it as the Dr. himself believes: And would
any body have me, now, to believe <hi>more?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the whole World <hi>(Say I)</hi> shall never bring <hi>me</hi> to
<hi>believe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exceptions to another pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage.</note> or to <hi>Say</hi> that I <hi>believe</hi> That which I neither <hi>do,</hi>
nor <hi>can believe;</hi> As the businesse of <hi>Bedingfields</hi> being <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live</hi>
again; or that <hi>I my self</hi> am in the <hi>Conspiracy.</hi> Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose
my Boy should come in, and tell me that it rains <hi>But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd
Turnips,</hi> I should go near to open the Window to see
whether it be so or no, <hi>Pag.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Shall any man call This now, that is with so much
<hi>Caution,</hi> and <hi>Distinction</hi> apply'd to <hi>Cases</hi> that are <hi>mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festly
false</hi> and <hi>groundlesse;</hi> shall any man (I say) call
<hi>This</hi> an <hi>arraigning</hi> of the <hi>Doctors Evidence?</hi> Or rather
how shall any man dare to <hi>apply</hi> these <hi>false</hi> and <hi>ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse
Storys</hi> to the <hi>Doctors Case?</hi> does it follow, because
I do not believe a thing that is <hi>False,</hi> that therefore I
do not believe a thing that is <hi>True?.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>§. 4. For abusing all Sorts of People in my
Citt and Bumpkin.</head>
               <p>The Fourth Article runs for Comprehending all the States,<note place="margin">Complaint against <hi>Citt</hi> and <hi>Bumpkin.</hi>
                  </note>
Orders, and Divisions of men, both Lords, Citizens, and
Commons of <hi>England</hi> under the Opprobrious names of <hi>Citt</hi>
and <hi>Bumpkin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And is not the World much beholden to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour
of this <hi>Discovery,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">My Libellers Libell the Doctor, and the Nation.</note> now, for the <hi>Resemblance</hi> he
finds betwixt the LORDS, CITIZENS, and COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MONS
of <hi>England,</hi> and my CIT, and BUMPKIN?
For it is <hi>he alone,</hi> out of <hi>his own mother Wit,</hi> that has
found it out. And yet he pronounces, in another place,
that I make my <hi>Bumpkin</hi> to represent a <hi>Cunning, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting,
Canting Knave;</hi> which <hi>He,</hi> by <hi>Interpretation</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:95761:7"/>
makes to be a <hi>Common Representative</hi> of the <hi>Nation.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">☞</note> But
so far am I now, from confounding men of Honour
and Integrity with Rascalls; that I have set upon these
Varlets an Expresse mark of <hi>Opposition</hi> to the <hi>Sober</hi> and
<hi>considerable part of the Land;</hi> and I have done This too,
with all the <hi>Clearnesse,</hi> and <hi>Contempt</hi> imaginable.</p>
               <p>And <hi>YOU,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Citt</hi> &amp; <hi>Bump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin</hi> a couple of Rascals.</note> (says <hi>Truman)</hi> are the <hi>Representative,</hi>
forsooth, of the <hi>City;</hi> and <hi>YOU,</hi> of the <hi>Country: Two</hi>
of the <hi>Pillars</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> with a <hi>Horse-Pox</hi> a man
would not let down his Breeches in a House of Office, that had
but <hi>two such Supporters.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Citts</hi> Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter.</note> Do not I know you, Cit, to be
a little <hi>Grub-street-Insect,</hi> that but to'ther day Scribled
handy dandy for some <hi>eighteen pence</hi> a <hi>Jobb pro and
con;</hi> and glad on't too? And now, as it pleases the Stars,
you are advanc'd from the <hi>Obort,</hi> the miscarriage of a <hi>Cause-Splitter,</hi>
to a <hi>drawer up</hi> of <hi>Articles;</hi> and for your Skill in
<hi>Counterfeiting hands,</hi> preferr'd to be a Sollicitor for
Fobb'd Petitions. <hi>You</hi>'l do the <hi>Bishops business,</hi> and
<hi>you</hi>'l do the <hi>Dukes businesse;</hi> and who but <hi>you</hi> to tell
the <hi>King</hi> when he shall make <hi>War</hi> or <hi>Peace;</hi> call <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi>
and <hi>whom</hi> to <hi>Commit,</hi> and <hi>whom</hi> to <hi>let go?</hi>
And then in your Fuddle up comes all; what such a <hi>Lord</hi> told
<hi>you,</hi> and what <hi>you</hi> told <hi>him,</hi> and all this pudder against
your Conscience too, even by your own Confession. Pag. 26.
And then <hi>Truman</hi> again, Pag. 35.</p>
               <p>Who made <hi>You</hi> a Commissioner for the <hi>Town,</hi> or <hi>You</hi>
for the <hi>Country?</hi> But we are like to have a Fine businesse
of it,<note place="margin">The dregs of the people.</note> when the <hi>Dreggs</hi> of the <hi>People</hi> set up for the <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentatives</hi>
of the Nation, to the Dishonour of the most <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable</hi>
and <hi>Sober part</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom.</hi> Pre'thee,
<hi>Bumpkin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bumpkin</hi> an Ignorant saw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy Fellow.</note> with thy <hi>Poles</hi> and <hi>Baltiques,</hi> how shouldest
Thou come to understand the <hi>Ballance</hi> of <hi>Empires;</hi> wbo
are <hi>Delinquents,</hi> and who <hi>not;</hi> the Right of Bishops Votes?
And you (forsooth) are to teach the King when to call a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
and when to let it alone.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:95761:7"/>
Our Libellers should do well now to <hi>name</hi> the <hi>Lords,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">My Adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries proved the Libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers.</note>
                  <hi>Citizens,</hi> and <hi>Commoners,</hi> that sat for their <hi>Pictures</hi> to
the <hi>Designer</hi> of <hi>These two Figures.</hi> But Calumny is
shamelesse; they would never else have bespatter'd me
for an Abuse, wherein I have so many Thousands of
Wittnesses to the Contrary. But no better can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected
from the Scum of the Rabble, whosc Blouds
run as Course as their Manners. And then they hit
me in the Teeth with it, upon all occasions, what
<hi>Rogues</hi> I make of the <hi>Citizens;</hi> and it is not a pin matter
to Them whether a Suggestion be <hi>True,</hi> or <hi>False,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
that the <hi>matter</hi> of it be but <hi>Scandalous,</hi> and the
<hi>Consequence</hi> of it <hi>dangerous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where was This Zeal,<note place="margin">The Appeal a damn'd Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell and no notice taken of it.</note> I wonder, for the Honour
of the Lords, Citizens, and Commons, in the case of
the <hi>Appeal</hi> from the COUNTRY to the CITY; where
they were all of them made <hi>Rascalls indeed,</hi> and under
the very notion too, of the <hi>Representatives</hi> of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
It strikes In with a ONE <hi>and</hi> ALL, at the very
first dash <hi>[Most Brave and noble Citizens—With</hi> you
<hi>we stand, and with</hi> you <hi>we</hi> fall. <hi>Appeal. Pag. 1.]</hi> This
is one of the most virulent Libells against his Majesty,<note place="margin">Full of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal.</note>
in his Person, Authority, and Administration; against
the whole Body of the Clergy, and against all the
Faithfull Friends and Subjects of the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Crown,</hi>
that ever yet was Printed: Nay it proceeds even to the
Tacit Proposal of a <hi>New King.</hi> This was <hi>no bespattering</hi>
(was it?) of the <hi>Nobility, Citizens,</hi> and <hi>Commonalty,</hi>
to represent them all as in so lewd a Conspiracy against
the Establisht Government. But our pretended Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots
and Zealots,<note place="margin">Our Zelots are blinde of a side.</note> are all of them blind on That Side;
and there is not so much as one man of them that has
ever taken any sort of notice of these daring Affronts
upon Authority, unlesse to countenance the Sedition;
But Recrimination is no discharge: wherefore I shall
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95761:8"/>
remit my self, upon the matter of <hi>Respect</hi> to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens
of <hi>London,</hi> to the <hi>Reply</hi> I publisht upon the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
out of That villanous <hi>Libel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a wonderfull thing,<note place="margin">A just Respect to the City of <hi>London.</hi>
                  </note> the Confidence of this audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Pamphlet, in addressing it self to the <hi>City,</hi> after so
Fresh, so Loyal, and so Generous an Instance of their
Scorn, and Detestation of any thing that looks like a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious
Practice. Why should a <hi>Wat Tyler</hi> expect better
Quarter from a <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> under <hi>Charles the Second,</hi>
then he had from a <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> under <hi>Richard the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond?</hi>
Nay, that very Rebellion of <hi>Forty One,</hi> is most
injuriously charg'd upon the <hi>City</hi> of <hi>London;</hi> for <hi>Gour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay,
Ricaut, Garraway,</hi> and the most considerable of the
Citizens, were not only against it in their <hi>Opinions,</hi> but
opposed it to the Utmost with their Estates and Persons.
And That Honourable Saciety has not yet forgotten either
the <hi>Calamities</hi> of the War, or the Methods and <hi>Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi>
which brought so great a Reproach upon the <hi>City.
Answ. to the Appeal, Pag. 2. And again,</hi> [How can
the Appellant imagine that the most eminent <hi>City</hi> of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendom</hi>
for Purity of Religion,<note place="margin">The Glorious City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
                  </note> Loyalty to their Prince,
Power, good Government, Wealth, and Resolution, should
be <hi>cajoll'd</hi> out of all these Blessings and Advantages by the
<hi>Jesuitical Fanaticism</hi> of a <hi>Dark-Lanthorn Pamphlet?
Ibid. Pa. 38.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is a Passage in my <hi>Second Citt</hi> and <hi>Bumpkin,</hi>
Pag. 27. which some of my <hi>Over-Critical</hi> Adversaries
pretend to lay a more then Ordinary stresse upon;
and I shall here submit it to any Impartial Judgment.</p>
               <p>Prethee (says <hi>Bumpkin)</hi> let's leave This Noddy
<hi>(Truman)</hi> a little, and talk of something else. What
dost think was the Reason that Parliaments <hi>have been</hi>
put off so of late?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:95761:8"/>
                  <hi>Citt.</hi> The very Question that I put 'tother day my self;<note place="margin">Matters of State.</note>
and 'twas Answer'd Thus, That the <hi>Nation</hi> could not be
<hi>Happy,</hi> but in the Preservation of the <hi>Government,</hi> as it
is Establisht by <hi>Law;</hi> For the tearing of the <hi>Law</hi> to Pieces
must needs distract the <hi>People,</hi> when they have no Rule to
walk by: That a great many Worthy Persons were disappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
in the <hi>Elections,</hi> by being <hi>Misrepresented</hi> to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:
That by these Practises diverse Persons were obtruded
upon the Nation, of <hi>remarkable Disaffections</hi> both to
<hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State:</hi> And that Therefore (I suppose) they
might be put off, to the end that some <hi>other Distempers</hi>
might be <hi>Compos'd,</hi> before their Meeting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bum.</hi> And what Return didst thou make him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Citt.</hi> I told him he smelt of the <hi>Court;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Old To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pique.</note> and that he
had a <hi>Pope</hi> in's belly; and so I would have no more to do
with him.</p>
               <p>For the better Clearing of this Passage, I shall set
forth, in the First place, the true <hi>Occasion,</hi> and <hi>Intent</hi> of
my <hi>Two Dialogues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon the Reading of a Venemous,<note place="margin">The Occasion and scope of <hi>Citt</hi> &amp; <hi>Bump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin.</hi>
                  </note> if not a Treaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous
Libell, call'd, <hi>An Appeal from the</hi> Countrey <hi>to the</hi>
City; I found it to be a direct Encouragement to a
<hi>Rebellion;</hi> and yet recommended to the World, as the
<hi>Sense</hi> and <hi>Act</hi> of the whole <hi>Nation.</hi> Now to vindicate
the <hi>Sober,</hi> and <hi>Loyall Part,</hi> both of the <hi>Country,</hi> and
<hi>City</hi> from This Audacious Scandal, I thought I could
not do better, then to expose the Conspirators under
the Character of a Couple of <hi>mean, factious, ignorant,</hi>
and <hi>busy Knaves,</hi> and under the Reproachfull names
of <hi>Citt,</hi> and <hi>Bumpkin;</hi> who are here Introduc'd in a
Discourse upon <hi>Matters of State,</hi> and <hi>Ironically</hi> poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
at in the very Margin, for meddling with Affairs
which they did not understand.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:95761:9"/>
Passing from one thing to Another, <hi>What dost think</hi>
(says <hi>Bumpkin) was the Reason,</hi> &amp;c?</p>
               <p>Now This is not a Question put in such a manner,
as either to require,<note place="margin">A Question to the Person, not upon the Fact.</note> or to draw on an <hi>Assertory Resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
upon the true <hi>Reason;</hi> but a <hi>Question</hi> accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
to the <hi>Character</hi> of the <hi>Person</hi> that Asks it: It being
the Constant Practise of those People, upon all <hi>Proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations,</hi>
or <hi>Dissolutions,</hi> to <hi>Write,</hi> and to <hi>Print</hi> their
Thoughts upon the poynt; and effectually to call his
Majesty to an Account upon the whole matter.</p>
               <p>And beside, as it is a Question Congruous to the
Humour of the <hi>Person;</hi> So has it no regard at all to an
<hi>Answer</hi> upon the matter of <hi>Fact.</hi> What dost <hi>Think?</hi>
(says <hi>Bumpkin) was the Reason</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The very Question</hi>
(says <hi>Citt) that I put t'other</hi> day my self. And Then
without delivering his own Thoughts, he tells
what another sayd to Him upon the same Question.
And <hi>Citt</hi> does not lay any stresse upon That Answer
neither; but brings in the <hi>Respondent</hi> speaking only
upon a bare supposal.</p>
               <p>By This,<note place="margin">A Question of Connexion and Transi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> and by what follows, it will plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
that This <hi>Intervening Clause</hi> was only made usc of
for <hi>Connexion-Sake,</hi> and as a Clause of <hi>Transition,</hi> for
the carrying on of the <hi>Character,</hi> out of <hi>One Impertinence</hi>
into <hi>Another.</hi> For without coming to any Conclusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
at all upon the Poynt, <hi>Citt</hi> betakes himself imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately
to the Ordinary Refuge of the Party, of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<hi>two or three Answers</hi> serve to all manner of <hi>purposes,</hi>
and <hi>questions.</hi> I <hi>told him</hi> (says he) <hi>that he smelt of the
Court, and had a Pope in his belly.</hi> I make no doubt but
This Apology will satisfy any man that has not my
<hi>Person</hi> in his <hi>Eye</hi> rather then my <hi>Errors.</hi> I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<hi>Boccalini's Laconique Senate,</hi> that pass'd so grievous
a Sentence upon a <hi>Letterato,</hi> for making use of <hi>Three
Words</hi> when <hi>Two</hi> would have done his businesse<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95761:9"/>
the Question is Here, whether or no I have <hi>Sayd</hi> any
thing that was <hi>Ill meant,</hi> and not whether that which
I <hi>have</hi> Deliver'd might have been <hi>Spoken better.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After This Demonstration of the Innocent Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
and Application of the matter in Exception, it
may seem Superfluous to speak any thing to the Sense
and Wording of it; And yet I must needs say further
that I cannot find any one Syllable in This Passage,
that will so much as bear an Ill Construction, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
forcing it beyond the Measures of Common Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
and Acceptation. For <hi>First,</hi> the <hi>Position</hi> is <hi>True</hi>
that the <hi>Preservation</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> is the <hi>Security,</hi> of the
<hi>Government:</hi> and <hi>Secondly,</hi> the <hi>Fact</hi> is <hi>True;</hi> that <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
Worthy Persons were disappointed in their</hi> Elections
<hi>by being</hi> Misrepresented <hi>to the People.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eminent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons mis-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented.</note> As in the Noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
Instance of <hi>Essex</hi> (and other places) where so
many Eminent Persons as well of the <hi>Layity,</hi> as of the
<hi>Clergy,</hi> were run down by the Multitude; by the
Names of <hi>Courtiers, Pentioners, Papists, Baals-Priests,
Iesuitical Dumb Doggs, the Black Regiment of Hell;</hi> and
the like; to the Scandal of <hi>Christianity</hi> as well as of
<hi>Common Iustice,</hi> and <hi>Good Manners.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now if the Exception be taken to the Expression of
<hi>obtruding</hi> upon the Nation some Persons of <hi>Remarkable
Disaffections</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">What is meant by <hi>Obtruding.</hi>
                  </note> Here is First, no Reflection upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<hi>Particulars;</hi> nor is there any more signifi'd by the
word OBTRUDED, then what we find <hi>verify'd</hi> in
<hi>all Elections;</hi> when upon <hi>Double Returns,</hi> the House of
Commons pronounces the Person <hi>rejected,</hi> to have
been <hi>unduly Chosen,</hi> and, effectually, <hi>obtruded</hi> upon the
Nation.</p>
               <p>It is again, to be consider'd; that the Tenses WAS,
and HAVE BEEN, have a regard to what is <hi>past;</hi>
and that the Word <hi>Parliaments,</hi> (in the <hi>Plural Number,</hi>
cannot be understood of That which is <hi>now</hi> in <hi>Being;</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:95761:10"/>
Which was not neither, at the time when This was
Written, in the Exercise of its Power.</p>
               <p>And moreover,<note place="margin">Disaffections explained.</note> If the stresse be layd upon the Word
DISAFFECTIONS, I do not see, in Propriety of Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,
how That word should arise to a <hi>Scandal;</hi> having
only a respect to a <hi>Diversity</hi> of <hi>Opinion,</hi> without any
Relation at all to an <hi>Evill Practice,</hi> or <hi>Design:</hi> And it
amounts to no more then a <hi>Disinclination;</hi> which Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports
only a <hi>different Liking</hi> of any thing, upon a <hi>diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
Perswasion, of</hi> or <hi>about</hi> it; and I never yet heard it
imputed to any man for a fault, to think otherwise of
any thing then Another man does, or to frame his <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations</hi>
to his <hi>Opinions:</hi> For such a <hi>Dissent,</hi> fairly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted,
is no Other then an <hi>Insuperable Diversity</hi> of
<hi>Iudgment;</hi> which is both <hi>Warrantable,</hi> and <hi>Honest,</hi> so
far as it keeps it self within Compasse, and without
breaking forth into <hi>Contumacy</hi> and <hi>Action:</hi> And there
is not the least Colour given for such a Construction,
in This place. But still, as there neither is nor can be
sayd to be any thing <hi>Unlawfull</hi> in such a <hi>Disagreement,</hi> it
were neverthelesse a thing highly to be wish'd, that
the Several Members of all great Councells might be
previously <hi>Vnited</hi> in the <hi>Fundamentals</hi> of the main Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
of their Debate.</p>
               <p>Upon the Upshot; DISAFFECTED, Sounds no
more in This place then a <hi>Non-Conformist;</hi> and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever
Scruples the <hi>Order</hi> and the <hi>Authority</hi> of <hi>Bishops,</hi>
and doubts of the <hi>Kings Power</hi> in <hi>Ecclesiastical Matters</hi>
and over <hi>Ecclesiastical Persons,</hi> is in such manner <hi>Disaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected</hi>
to the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> as to answer the Lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
meaning of This Clause, and no otherwise. Nor
is any man to blame for being of such or such a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple,
that lyes under the force of an <hi>Invincible Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion,</hi>
and consequently under the <hi>necessity</hi> of a <hi>Suita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Inclination.</hi> So much for This Poynt: The Next is,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:95761:10"/>
               <head>§. 5. My falling foul upon all the Petitioners.</head>
               <p>The <hi>Fifth Exception</hi> is,<note place="margin">Exception up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Petitions.</note> that I have <hi>Scandalously mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>represented
all the Petitioners, and Promoters of the late
Petitions.</hi> How far this Imputation is True or False,
and upon what grounds I support my Opinion; shall
be seen in what follows.</p>
               <p>[But may not <hi>men Petition, you will say,</hi> and <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
for a good thing?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Petitions ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and how far.</note> Yes; if the thing be <hi>Simply Good;</hi>
the <hi>Petitioners</hi> Competent Iudges of it; and every man
keep himself to his own Post, I see no hurt in't: But for
the <hi>Multitude</hi> to interpose in matters of <hi>State,</hi> as in the
<hi>Calling</hi> or <hi>Dissolving</hi> of <hi>Parliaments; Regulation</hi> of
<hi>Church-Government;</hi> or in other like Cases of <hi>Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi>
and <hi>Hazzardous Event,</hi> wherein they have no <hi>Skill</hi>
at all, nor any <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Intermeddling:</hi> Why may not
Twenty Thousand <hi>Plow-jobbers</hi> as well <hi>Subscribe</hi> a Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
to the <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> for the calling of a
<hi>Common Councell?</hi> Or as many Porters and Carr-men
here in <hi>London</hi> put in for the better Government of the
<hi>Herring-Trade</hi> in <hi>Yarmouth?</hi> Seasonable Memorial.
Pag. 21. <hi>And then again,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let the <hi>matter</hi> of the Petition be never so fair;<note place="margin">Not so much the Matter, as the scope of the Petition.</note> if it be
a businesse out of the <hi>Petitioners Sphere,</hi> and <hi>Capacity</hi>
either to <hi>meddle in,</hi> or to <hi>understand;</hi> it is a <hi>Suspitious</hi>
way of Proceeding. Such were the <hi>Confederate Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> for a <hi>Parliament</hi> in 1641.
which were but a <hi>Prologue</hi> to the Opening of the <hi>Subse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent
Confederacy</hi> against the <hi>Government:</hi> when the
Petitions that <hi>follow'd</hi> sufficiently expounded the Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of the <hi>Former.</hi> They Petition'd against <hi>Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
Courts, Ceremonies,</hi> Scandalous <hi>Ministers, Bishops
Votes</hi> in <hi>Parliament,</hi> and <hi>Episcopacy</hi> it self; against
<hi>Evill Councellors, Monopolies,</hi> Corruptions of <hi>State,</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:95761:11"/>
Courts of Oppression, and innumerable Grievances: And
so for the <hi>Militia:</hi> the Kings <hi>Towns,</hi> and <hi>Forts;</hi> till
they brought the King to the Block. Pag. 20. <hi>And after
this manner have they proceeded now again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Petition</hi> was at <hi>first,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The advance of the Petition from one thing to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</note> 
                  <hi>for the Meeting of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament;</hi>
and then they came to twit the King with his
<hi>Coronation-Oath:</hi> and then <hi>Delinquents</hi> must be brought
to <hi>punishment;</hi> and then the <hi>Parliament</hi> was to sit as <hi>long</hi>
as they pleas'd: And at last, every man must be mark'd
for a <hi>Common Enemy,</hi> that would not <hi>Subscribe</hi> to't. So
that <hi>First,</hi> they would have the <hi>Parliament Sit;</hi> and
<hi>Then,</hi> they would cut them out their work; and, in
<hi>Fine,</hi> it was little other then a <hi>Petition</hi> against <hi>those</hi>
that would <hi>not Petition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Late Kings Observations upon the <hi>Growth</hi> of
<hi>Petitions</hi> of this kinde are very Pertinent.<note place="margin">The Late Kings Obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations upon Petitions.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Vpon <hi>[the tumultuous Confluxes</hi> of mean and rude
People, who are taught first to Petition, then to Protect,
then to Dictate; at last, to Command and Over awe the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.
<hi>EIK.BAS.</hi> upon TUMVLTS]<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>And the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices
of these people are excellently well set forth by
his late Majesty also</hi> Ex. Coll. Pag. 536.</p>
               <p>Their Seditious Preachers,<note place="margin">And the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of them.</note> (<hi>says he</hi>) and Agents, are
by them, and their Special and particular directions, sent
into the Several Countys, to infuse Fears and Iealousies into
the minds of our good Subjects, with Petitions ready drawn
by <hi>Them,</hi> for the <hi>People</hi> to <hi>Sign,</hi> which were yet many
times by them changed three or four times before the Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;
upon accidents, or occasions of either or both Houses.
And when many of our poor deceived People of our several
Countyes have come to the City of <hi>London,</hi> with a Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
so <hi>fram'd, alter'd,</hi> and <hi>sign'd,</hi> as aforesaid; That
Petition hath been <hi>Suppress'd,</hi> and a <hi>New one</hi> ready drawn
hath been put into their hands, after their coming to Town,
(inso much as few of the Company have known what they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95761:11"/>
Petition'd for) and hath been by them presented to one or
both our Houses of Parliament; as That of <hi>Bedfordshire,</hi>
and <hi>Buckinghamshire:</hi> witnesse those Petitions, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
the rest That of <hi>Hertfordshire,</hi> which took notice of
matters agreed on, or dissented from, the night before the
Delivery: which was hardly time enough to get so many
thousand hands, and to travel to <hi>London</hi> on that <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>So that I have very good Authority here,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Good Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority for suspecting Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> 
                  <hi>for ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending
the danger of</hi> Popular Petitions; <hi>And to
shew now that I am not at all possess'd against Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
in</hi> Generall, <hi>or against</hi> ALL <hi>the</hi> Petitioners;
Truman <hi>says, that</hi> [to joyn in a <hi>Petition</hi> for the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of a <hi>Parliament,</hi> to bring <hi>Malefactors</hi> to a <hi>Tryall,</hi>
or to <hi>extirpate Popery,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Some Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons both Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable.</note> is, in the appearance of it, not
only <hi>Lawfull,</hi> but <hi>Commendable:</hi> But then it must be
promoted by <hi>Lawfull Means,</hi> and under <hi>Decent Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances.
Citt and Bum. Pag.</hi> 27. [It is a good
thing to execute <hi>Justice,</hi> but yet a <hi>Private man</hi> must
not invade the <hi>Judgment-Seat,</hi> tho' it were to passe even
the most <hi>Righteous Sentence, Ibid. Pa.</hi> 28. And More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over;<note place="margin">Many worthy persons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in the Petitions.</note>
                  <hi>Truman</hi> acknowledges that he finds many <hi>honest</hi>
and <hi>considerable men</hi> concern'd in these <hi>Petitions.] Ibid.</hi>
Which is more Evidence then needed for the purging of my
self from so grosse a Slander. I come now to the Last Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle
of my Charge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>§. 6. My Writings (they say) create Misunderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings,
and tend to the Embroyling of the Kingdome.</head>
               <p>It it be so,<note place="margin">The scope of all my <hi>Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings.</hi>
                  </note> I have been extremely out in my Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures
all this while, to be still <hi>creating</hi> of <hi>Misunderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings</hi>
in the very Act of Endeavouring, either to
<hi>rectify,</hi> or to <hi>prevent</hi> them. And to be <hi>Endangering</hi> the
<hi>Peace</hi> of the Kingdome in the <hi>Design</hi> of <hi>preserving it.</hi> If
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95761:12"/>
to Assert the <hi>Law,</hi> aud the <hi>Government</hi> against all Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posers;
If to lay open the <hi>Malice</hi> and <hi>Calumny</hi> of so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
bold <hi>Libells</hi> against his Majesties <hi>Person, Authority,</hi>
and <hi>Government;</hi> if to maintain the <hi>Apostolical Order,</hi>
and the <hi>Constitutions</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> against <hi>Schism;</hi> and
the <hi>Powers,</hi> and <hi>Priviledges</hi> of the <hi>State</hi> against all
Principles of <hi>Sedition;</hi> If to inculcate <hi>Reverence,</hi> and
<hi>Obedience</hi> toward our <hi>Superiours;</hi> If to recommend the
<hi>Blessings,</hi> and <hi>Duties</hi> of <hi>Vnity,</hi> in a due Submission to
the Provisions that are made for the Upholding of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi>
both in <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>State:</hi> If the bending of all
my thoughts, and Applications to these Ends, be to
create <hi>Misunderstandings,</hi> and breed Ill Blood in the
Hearts of his Majesties Liege People, <hi>Thus</hi> am I guilty
of the matter charged upon me in This Article, and
no <hi>Otherwise.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I shall passe now, in Order, from the <hi>Particulars</hi> of
my <hi>Charge</hi> to the <hi>Quality</hi> of the <hi>Libellers,</hi> and the <hi>true
Reason</hi> of their Rancour against <hi>me,</hi> in despite of all
their <hi>Pretensions</hi> to the <hi>Contrary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the <hi>Quality</hi> of the <hi>Libellers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Quality of the Libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers.</note> a man may judge
of the <hi>Meannesse</hi> of their <hi>Souls</hi> by the <hi>Condition</hi> of the
<hi>Office:</hi> which is the Part of the very <hi>Devill himself;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
only to <hi>Blacken,</hi> and to <hi>Defame.</hi> They have lickt
up the Vomit of the Nation, which they discharge
again in their Writings, <hi>partly</hi> upon my self, and the
<hi>rest</hi> upon the <hi>Government:</hi> for I have still the Honour
to suffer, not only by the same Hand and Fate, with
the King and with the Church, but for their very
sakes too.</p>
               <p>In this Mercenary Crew of Beastly Libellers,<note place="margin">A Hackny Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beller.</note> there's
one little Creature among the rest, that serves as a
Common Instrument to the Faction: And that which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95761:12"/>
They put into his mouth the Fore-part of the week, he
commonly throws Out again upon the Government,
and all that Love it, toward the End on't. There is
not perhaps so Insolent a Libell permitted upon the
face of the Earth, where ever <hi>Christianity,</hi> or <hi>Good
manners</hi> set footing; so <hi>Profane, Scurrilous</hi> and <hi>Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous;</hi>
nor has the pretended Authour of it any other
Protection for his Crimes, then the Obscurity of his
Person; for there is no Touching of him, without
fouling a man's Fingers. And yet to let him see now
that I am not absolutely a stranger to his History. For
several years he never knew what it was to sleep, but
in a Cellar or in a Garret, saving now and then, in
his Beer, upon a Bulk. In the days of his Prosperity
he was receiv'd into the House, of a Boyling Cook,
where he spung'd out a poor Livelyhood upon the
Fragments of a Three penny-Ordinary; but his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation
was yet more Reproachful then his Quality
and Fortune. Whosoever doubts the Truth of This,
needs but go into <hi>Salisbury-Court</hi> to be better enform'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>Is not the World at a fine Passe now, when such<note place="margin">☜</note>
Fellows as This shall come to hold the Ballance of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires?
To trample the Crown and the Miter under
their feet? To Charge his Majesty himself with a
Confederacy for the bringing in of the <hi>French King</hi>
and <hi>Popery;</hi> as I am ready to Prove he has done? To
expose the <hi>Episcopacy,</hi> and the <hi>Papacy</hi> under the same
Notion, promiscuously, to the Hatred and Contempt
of the Common People; To make sport with the very
Badge of our Profession? <hi>(That TOOL the CROSSE,</hi> as
the <hi>Buffoon</hi> calls it) To Canton out the Nobility and
Gentry into what Tribes They please: as Fools and
Knaves; Papists and Traytors; Courtiers and Pensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners?
The <hi>Egyptian Locusts</hi> were nothing to This
Plague of our <hi>English Scarabs,</hi> that <hi>devour,</hi> not only the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95761:13"/>
                  <hi>Fruit,</hi> but the <hi>Honour</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> and render the
<hi>English</hi> Nation as much as in Them Lyes, a Laughing-stock
to all our Neighbours round about us. It is not
that I am angry with <hi>Harry Care</hi> for the delicate <hi>Back-strokes</hi>
he gave me in <hi>Prances last Narrative,</hi> by his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention
for the setting up of a Correspondence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> and <hi>my self;</hi> a Person whose Face I
never saw in my whole Life that I know of, till (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the Couneell) about a week or ten days after the
publishing of That Book: 'Tis true it was as false and
as shamelesse a Contrivance as Possible: But why
should I expect better from him when God Allmighty
has Written the <hi>Signature</hi> of what he is, in the very
Visage of the <hi>Animal?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now as to the <hi>Pretended Reasons</hi> of these Wretches
<hi>Rancor</hi> against <hi>me.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Why this Rancour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst me?</note> First, they say that I <hi>began</hi> with
them. Secondly, that I have been pertetually Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
upon <hi>one and Forty,</hi> and <hi>the Rebellion of One and
Forty;</hi> without any Ground, or Provocation for ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
It must be my part now to shew that I have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
put pen to paper yet, but either in <hi>my own Defence,</hi>
or in the <hi>Vindication</hi> of the <hi>Publique.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The First Reflection I past upon any man,<note place="margin">The Faction began with me.</note> was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<hi>Care,</hi> for Libelling me in the <hi>Epistle Dedicatory</hi> to
his <hi>Histiory of the Damnable Popish Plot.</hi> I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
layd open the Malice, and the Sillynesse of That
Imposture against me, and I have said something like-wise
to the Venom of that pittifull Pamphlet against
the Government: Especially Page 91; where he
borrows no lesse then a whole Page of Libell, against
the King, from a sheet intitled <hi>a Letter to a Friend in
the Country,</hi> which ('tis sayd) was the work of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
hand. From This time forward I was ply'd with
Fresh Calumnyes; which have given me fresh and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95761:13"/>
fresh Occasion still of Writing to clear my self.</p>
               <p>As to the Other point of pressing the business of One
and Forty more than needed, I must Appeal to the
Pieces themselves which I have publisht.</p>
               <p>My <hi>Reformed Catholick</hi> was written with a Design to
Unmask the Fallacy of Imposing upon the People,<note place="margin">My End of Writing.</note> under
the Name of <hi>Dissenting Protestants,</hi> a kind of <hi>Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi>
to the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> which is <hi>by Law Establisht;</hi>
and to Expound the meaning of several <hi>Quaeres</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posals,</hi>
that were Then Printed, to deter People from chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
Men that had either any <hi>Relation</hi> to the <hi>King,</hi> or
<hi>Kindness</hi> for the <hi>Church,</hi> into the <hi>Next Election.</hi> I shall
refer the Reader for further Satisfaction in This Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
to <hi>Page</hi> 9. and so from p. 21. to p. 27; where there are
several Instances of <hi>Libels</hi> Printed at That time, that fell
little short of downright <hi>Treason.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In my <hi>Free-born Subject,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Free born Subject,</note> p. 14. and so forward, there
are several Instances likewise of the same Quality; My
<hi>Answer to the Appeal</hi> was more directly upon the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject;
and after <hi>That,</hi> I wrote <hi>A seasonable Memorial,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly
to lay open the Arts and Methods by which the
Glorious City of <hi>London</hi> was <hi>formerly</hi> betrayed to <hi>slave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi>
and <hi>Faction;</hi> the very same Practices being at <hi>That</hi>
time promoted by some particular Persons, and attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
over again.</p>
               <p>My Two <hi>Dialogues</hi> of <hi>Cit</hi> and <hi>Bumpkin</hi> were (as I have
said already) Composed for the Undeceiving of those
Credulous People,<note place="margin">Citt. <hi>and</hi> Bum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin.</note> that had been Unhappily misled by
the Insinuations of That accursed <hi>Libel,</hi> called <hi>The Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Letter to Mr. <hi>Oate's</hi> was founded upon Mr. <hi>Oates's
Discovery,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">My Letter to Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</note> and only a more vigorous Emprovement of
His <hi>Evidence,</hi> toward the Rooting out of all <hi>Priests</hi> and
<hi>Iesuits</hi> out of the Land; by such ways and means as do
naturally arise from the <hi>Reasons</hi> of his <hi>Depositions.</hi> And
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95761:14"/>
I have done <hi>This</hi> too, with all due Deference and Respect
to the <hi>Kings Witness<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> as well as to the <hi>Plot,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing
Mr. <hi>Oate's</hi> scandalous and undeserved Revilings
of me; which might perhaps have stagger'd some man
less considerate than my self, at least in some part of his
Duty; especially falling so bitterly withal upon the
Memory of a Person for whose Holy Ashes I have so
great a <hi>Veneration,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A Passionate Expression.</note> LAUD (says he) <hi>was a</hi> RASCAL,
<hi>and a</hi> TRAYTOR; and This he said over and over, and
without any manner of Provocation. Without running
into any more Particulars; <hi>This</hi> has been the <hi>Case</hi> of my
Affair from <hi>on</hi> end of it to the <hi>other.</hi> But to come now
from the <hi>pretended Cause</hi> of their <hi>malice</hi> to me, to the
<hi>Cause it self.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have liv'd long enough in the World to understand,
<note place="margin">The Effect of popular Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels.</note> in some measure, both <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Books;</hi> and that <hi>popular
Passions</hi> are mov'd by <hi>popular Discourses,</hi> as the <hi>VVaves</hi>
of the <hi>Sea</hi> are by the <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>VVinds.</hi> It is the
<hi>First</hi> Office of <hi>Political Pamphlets</hi> or <hi>Treatises,</hi> in all Cases
of <hi>Design</hi> upon any Eminent <hi>Alteration</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> to pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sess
the People with <hi>fals Notions</hi> about the <hi>Original,</hi> the
<hi>Nature</hi> and the <hi>Ends</hi> of <hi>Government;</hi> and so to train
them on, from <hi>Perverse Principles,</hi> in the matter of <hi>Rule</hi>
and <hi>Subj<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ction,</hi> to <hi>Evil Thoughts</hi> of their <hi>Superiors</hi> and
<hi>Governors;</hi> and from <hi>Thence,</hi> to transport them into <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutiful</hi>
and <hi>Intemperate Practises</hi> against the <hi>publick Peace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
We have already felt the Effects of This way of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding,
in the most outragious <hi>Rebellion,</hi> in all Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances,
perhaps, that ever was heard of: And the Late
King himself imputed it principally to the Force of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions
Libels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the <hi>same</hi> Methods being set a foot again,<note place="margin">The Reason of my Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</note> and That
Invective Course of <hi>Liberty</hi> against both the <hi>Church</hi> and
the <hi>State,</hi> proceeding without any <hi>Check</hi> or <hi>Controll;</hi>
I thought my self bound in <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Duty,</hi> both as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95761:14"/>
an <hi>English Man,</hi> and as a <hi>Subject,</hi> to use the best means
I could, either to <hi>Stop,</hi> or to <hi>divert</hi> that <hi>Torrent.</hi> Upon
<hi>This</hi> I took upon me, (so much as in Me lay) the <hi>Defence</hi>
of the <hi>Law,</hi> and the <hi>Government</hi> against all those <hi>Errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi>
and <hi>Disloyal Positions,</hi> that were dayly Published,
and imposed upon the <hi>Unskilful</hi> and <hi>Unwary Multitude,</hi>
to the extreme Hazard and Dishonour of the <hi>State.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I brought the <hi>Terms</hi> of <hi>Dominion</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> to the
<hi>Right Standard;</hi> I laid Open and Rectified all their <hi>Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacious
Distinctions,</hi> and the dismal <hi>Consequences</hi> of the
<hi>Peoples</hi> swallowing such <hi>Mistakes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>Cheat</hi> laid open.</note> I took off the <hi>Baits</hi>
of <hi>Religion, Liberty</hi> and <hi>Reformation</hi> in the very sight of
the Common People; and laid open the <hi>Hook</hi> that was
under them: I shewed them that the whole <hi>Pretence</hi>
was no other than a <hi>Counterfeit;</hi> and that there was no
more of <hi>Religion, Liberty</hi> or <hi>Reformation</hi> in the bottom of
it, then of a <hi>Living Fly</hi> in an <hi>Artificial</hi> one; and that
one <hi>Leap</hi> at it was as much as their <hi>Lives, Estates,</hi> and
their <hi>Souls</hi> were worth. I gave the Multitude <hi>Antidotes</hi>
against all their <hi>Pestilent</hi> and <hi>Poysonous Infusions;</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solv'd
all their Riddles, and from their own <hi>Actions,</hi>
and <hi>Acknowledgments</hi> in the <hi>like Cases,</hi> expounded their
<hi>meanings.</hi> In one word, by the blessing of God upon this
Naked and honest Simplicity of Dealing, I have found
<hi>some Well-meaning Dissenters</hi> reclaim'd from their <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors,</hi>
and <hi>Others</hi> that were <hi>wavering</hi> before, Now to be
fully <hi>fatisfyed</hi> and <hi>Confirm'd.</hi> Nor can it well be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise,
in so <hi>Righteous</hi> and <hi>Reasonable</hi> a <hi>Cause;</hi> where the
manifest <hi>Iustice</hi> and <hi>Evidence</hi> of the <hi>matter</hi> would do its
own business, with the help even of a very slender <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate</hi>
to support it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:95761:15"/>
I have spoken enough to the <hi>Circumstances</hi> of my
<hi>Charge;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">My Loyalty is my Crime.</note> but all <hi>That</hi> Story serves only for a <hi>Blind.</hi> And
in truth my <hi>Zeal</hi> for the <hi>Upholding</hi> of the <hi>Government</hi>
is my <hi>Unpardonable Crime;</hi> the <hi>Libellers</hi> would, Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise,
take notice of the <hi>many,</hi> and the <hi>open Scandals,</hi>
that are cast upon the <hi>King,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">No notice ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> and the <hi>Church,</hi> with an
Evident Design to expose <hi>Majesty</hi> and <hi>Episcopacy</hi> to <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred</hi>
and <hi>Scorn;</hi> and shew their <hi>Affections</hi> That way for
the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> of the KING, and for the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant
Religion;</hi> and not stand picking of Holes in the
Coat of a person that has so unquestionably dedicated
all the Faculties of his <hi>Soul, Body, Fortune</hi> and <hi>Interests</hi>
to the Service of his <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Country;</hi> and to set
Spyes upon every Action and Line in his whole Life, to
try if they can find but any one poynt, either in his
<hi>Conversation</hi> or <hi>Writings,</hi> that might bear a <hi>Double mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi>
and, at last, to render that very <hi>Ambiguity</hi> (if it
were possible) no less than <hi>Capital</hi> too. But I thank God
My <hi>Faults</hi> of <hi>That</hi> kind are as hard to be found out, as
my <hi>Accusers Virtues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It goes a great way with many <hi>Moderate Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">I never recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved any <hi>Reply.</hi>
                  </note> and other Reasonable Persons too, that have
not as yet taken any strong Impressions, either on the
one side, or on the other; that notwithstanding all
the rudenesses of <hi>Clamor</hi> and <hi>ill Language</hi> against me,
for the Papers I have Published, I have not as yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
one single Reply to the <hi>Argument</hi> of any thing
that ever I wrote, more than the Opposing of <hi>Revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings</hi>
to my <hi>Reasons:</hi> So that their <hi>Quarrel</hi> to me is
purely for interposing betwixt <hi>Faction</hi> and <hi>Authority.</hi>
It will be said perhaps, that my <hi>Papers</hi> are not worth
the Answering. How comes it then that they think it
worth the while to bestow so much pains upon my
<hi>Person?</hi> nay and to propound and meditate so many
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95761:15"/>
extraordinary Ways of <hi>Animadversion</hi> upon <hi>L'Estrange,</hi>
as if the Foundations of the Government were to be
removed for my sake, and that an <hi>Englishman</hi> were to
be no longer <hi>safe</hi> under the <hi>Protection</hi> of the <hi>Law?</hi>
But these are only <hi>Coffee-House-Imaginations,</hi> and which
I am sure, will never receive any <hi>Countenance</hi> or <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement</hi>
from the <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Wisdom</hi> of a <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But since my Hand is in upon this Subject,<note place="margin">Two points worth the clearing.</note> there
are <hi>Two Points</hi> more worth the Clearing than all the
<hi>rest;</hi> as being of greater Importance toward the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding
of the present Controversie: The One
has a Respect to the more effectual Discovery of <hi>Priests</hi>
and <hi>Iesuits.</hi> The Other, To the <hi>Impartial Stating</hi> and
<hi>Discussing</hi> the Business of <hi>Toleration.</hi> The former of
these I have handled in my <hi>Further Discovery,</hi> Dedicated
to Dr. <hi>Oates,</hi> and Grounded upon the Authority of his
Evidence: The Other I have Treated upon more at
large, in my <hi>Toleration Discussed,</hi> and with a regard
to all the Circumstances that I could fairly bring
within the Compass of the Question. Let the whole
World fairly, and by dint of Reason, overthrow ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
the One or the Other, and I will yield my self to
have been all this while under a great Mistake.</p>
               <p>I know very well that I am Charg'd for writing
<hi>more</hi> than my <hi>Share;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Why I have written so much.</note> when the true Reason of it was,
that others wrote <hi>less:</hi> and in effect, it was more than
one Man's Work to attempt what I have done: But
upon a Sense that the thing was of <hi>absolute Necessity</hi> for
some body to do; and finding other People more <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi>
than I thought was either <hi>Needful</hi> or <hi>Expedient,</hi>
in so Publick a Case, I engag'd my self further than
my Neighbours: and not without the Foresight of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95761:16"/>
these Outrages which I knew I was to draw upon my
self: Neither is this the first time that I have Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<hi>all other Considerations</hi> to my <hi>Duty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some will have it,<note place="margin">No Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the case.</note> that I have been set on by the
<hi>Promises</hi> and <hi>Temptations</hi> of <hi>Advantages</hi> and <hi>Reward;</hi>
which is an <hi>Imagination</hi> so far from the truth of this
Matter, that all things considered (saving my <hi>Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
and <hi>Humble Acknowledgments</hi> to His Majesty, who
hath been very <hi>Gracious</hi> to me) I do positively averr,
that the King has not a Subject in his Three Kingdoms,
that has suffered <hi>harder Measure,</hi> and more contrary
to <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Iustice,</hi> than <hi>I my self</hi> have <hi>done;</hi> and all
this, without the Ballance of any other Recompence
than a <hi>little Court-Holy-Water</hi> and <hi>Fair Words.</hi> Besides
that in the <hi>Worst of Times,</hi> I did the <hi>same thing</hi> through
all <hi>Difficulties</hi> and <hi>Hazards.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having already in general Terms reflected upon
<hi>Scandalous</hi> and <hi>Dangerous Libels,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Designs and Practices up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Peace.</note> as the <hi>Occasion</hi> of my
<hi>Writings;</hi> I shall now take a Taste of the <hi>Condition</hi>
and <hi>Tendency</hi> of those <hi>Libels,</hi> and lay open as briefly
as I can, their <hi>Designs</hi> and <hi>Practices</hi> upon the <hi>Dignity</hi>
and <hi>Safety</hi> of the <hi>Government,</hi> and the <hi>Publick Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There needs no more to the proving of a <hi>Design,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A Lewd Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice implies a Design.</note> than
such an Explication of a Lewd <hi>Practice,</hi> as carries with
it a <hi>Necessary Congruity</hi> and <hi>Tendency</hi> to such or such a
<hi>Determinate</hi> and <hi>Evil End:</hi> And the <hi>publishing</hi> of a
<hi>Treasonous Position</hi> is but so far the putting of a <hi>Disloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
Imagination</hi> into <hi>Act:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reward and Punishmen.</note> As for Instance; The Author
of the <hi>Plea to the Dukes Answers,</hi> does very plainly
conclude the <hi>King</hi> to be <hi>Accountable</hi> to his <hi>People;</hi> and
after that, declares in express Terms, that <hi>God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves
of the Removal of Evil Kings:</hi> And his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95761:16"/>
in the same Sheet, of a <hi>Male-Administration,</hi>
does fairly make known his <hi>Dissatisfaction,</hi> and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
explain his <hi>Intention</hi> in that Point. Where's
my fault now, for Crying out both to <hi>King</hi> and <hi>People,
Have a Care of That Man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Author of another Libel, call'd <hi>The Impartial
Proceedings,</hi> &amp;c. recommends the Case of <hi>Portugal</hi> for
a <hi>Precedent</hi> to <hi>England;</hi> and sets the People at <hi>Liberty,
If they do not like one King, to Chuse another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Writer of the</hi> Appeal <hi>does not only</hi> Intimate
<hi>this;</hi> but <hi>enforces it with an</hi> Encouragement; He
who has the worst Title <hi>(says he)</hi> ever makes the best
King.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Compiler</hi> of the <hi>Political Catechism</hi> places the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereignty</hi>
in the <hi>Two Houses;</hi> and says, that they have
<hi>Legal Power</hi> to <hi>Command</hi> the <hi>People</hi> to <hi>Assist</hi> them,
whensoever they shall <hi>Declare</hi> that there is a <hi>Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
toward a <hi>War:</hi> and in such a Case to <hi>dispose of
the Kings Forts, Ports, Magazines, Ships,</hi> and <hi>Power</hi>
of the <hi>Militia;</hi> and to <hi>Levy</hi> Money, Arms, Horse, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition
<hi>upon</hi> the Subjects, <hi>in such Cases of Danger,
even WITHOUT, or AGAINST the Kings Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Marvel, <hi>in his</hi> Growth of Popery, <hi>justifies</hi> Self-De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<hi>in a</hi> Subject <hi>against his</hi> Prince, when he is run
up to the Wall. <hi>And nothing more ordinary than
Printed Censures of the</hi> King <hi>and his</hi> Ministers; <hi>the</hi>
Branding <hi>of all his</hi> Officers <hi>and</hi> Domestiques <hi>for</hi> Pension<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<hi>and</hi> Papists; <hi>the</hi> Church <hi>it self for</hi> Will-Worship <hi>and</hi>
Superstition; <hi>and the</hi> Hierarchy <hi>for</hi> Antichristian. These
Sons of <hi>Belial (says the Author of</hi> The Free-holders
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95761:17"/>
Choyce) <hi>and then a little below,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Brutal Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilities.</note> I believe <hi>(says he)</hi>
good Father <hi>Jacob</hi> had a Foresight of these Sons of <hi>Levi,</hi>
when in his last Will and Testament he left them a Curse
for a Legacy, instead of a Blessing; and if the whole
World were now to make their Wills, all but Knaves and
Fools would do the like. <hi>And he Treats the</hi> Parliament
defunct <hi>with the same Generous Freedom:</hi> That so we
may fall again <hi>(says he)</hi> into the hands of as <hi>Treacherous</hi>
and <hi>Lewd</hi> a <hi>Parliament</hi> as the wisdom of God, and the <hi>Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi>
of <hi>Man,</hi> has most miraculously freed us from. <hi>Another
falls foul by</hi> Name, <hi>upon a</hi> List <hi>of as many Worthy Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
out of such a number, as ever met perhaps in such
a Body; and three or four of them no less then Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
of his Majesty's</hi> Privy Councel: <hi>And</hi> This Catalogue
<hi>he is pleased to call</hi> the Infernal Regiment of Pensioners.
<hi>To say nothing of those</hi> Scurrilous <hi>and</hi> brutal Affronts
<hi>upon the very</hi> Person <hi>and</hi> Honour <hi>of his</hi> Sacred Majesty,
<hi>that an Honest man cannot so much as</hi> Think <hi>of, much
less</hi> Repeat <hi>without</hi> Horror:</p>
               <p>Here's not One word all This while of the <hi>Contrivers</hi>
and <hi>Advancers</hi> of <hi>These Villanies:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Safer to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Sedition then to Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure it.</note> but it is become more
<hi>Criminal,</hi> in the judgment of our <hi>Pretended Zealots</hi> to
<hi>Censure</hi> these <hi>audacious Extravagances</hi> then to commit
them.</p>
               <p>But now to conclude: How far in <hi>honour, justice,</hi>
and <hi>policy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">How far to encourage Loyalty.</note> it may concern any <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>State whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever</hi>
to <hi>support, countenance,</hi> and <hi>protect</hi> the <hi>Asserters</hi> of
their <hi>Laws, Rights,</hi> and <hi>Priviledges,</hi> against the <hi>bold</hi> and
<hi>seditious Attempts</hi> of the <hi>Enemies</hi> of the <hi>Constitution,</hi>
will be the next Question.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:95761:17"/>
The <hi>Two Main Pillars</hi> of <hi>Government</hi> are <hi>Reward</hi> and
<hi>Punishment.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reward and Punishment.</note> The neglecting of these, is like the
letting of a House fall over a mans Head for want
of <hi>Repair:</hi> But the Magistrate that <hi>inverts</hi> them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and
<hi>Rewards</hi> where he should <hi>Punish,</hi> and <hi>Punishes</hi> where
he should <hi>Reward</hi> (in what Form of Government so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
it be) is like a man that plucks down his own
House with his own Hands; and <hi>nothing can be more</hi>
dangerous, <hi>than to shew an</hi> Honest man <hi>that he has no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi>
to hope for, <hi>or a</hi> Knave, <hi>that he has nothing to fear.</hi>
But this were a <hi>Supposition</hi> against the Impulse of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi>
as well as against the <hi>Rules</hi> of <hi>Politicks;</hi> there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
nothing more <hi>Inglorious,</hi> or more <hi>Perillous,</hi> then
the <hi>Humour</hi> of <hi>Obliging</hi> our <hi>Enemies,</hi> to the <hi>Ruine</hi> of
our <hi>Friends.</hi> This is a Point so <hi>clear</hi> of it <hi>self,</hi> that it
needs no <hi>Illustration;</hi> and so Consonant to the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
of <hi>Right Reason,</hi> (even in the <hi>weakest</hi> of men) that
it does as little need a <hi>Caution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what is it that we call the <hi>supporting</hi> and <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting</hi>
of those that <hi>Assert</hi> the <hi>Government?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">It is Interest of State to protect the Servants of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> This is not
intended as a <hi>Benignity,</hi> or <hi>Respect</hi> toward the <hi>Person</hi>
that does the <hi>Office;</hi> but it is meant of a <hi>Common Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice</hi>
to a <hi>Principle</hi> òf <hi>Government it self;</hi> without which
it is impossible for any Government to be of <hi>Long Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance:</hi>
For all <hi>Publique Services</hi> are <hi>accompany'd</hi> with
<hi>hardship,</hi> and <hi>pain;</hi> as they, are <hi>follow'd</hi> with <hi>Envy,</hi> and
<hi>Detraction.</hi> 'Tis nothing for a man to go <hi>down Hill,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially
when he sees <hi>Profit, Pleasures,</hi> and <hi>Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
at the <hi>Bottom;</hi> and that in such a Course, he does
but follow the <hi>Byass</hi> of his own <hi>Appetites,</hi> and <hi>Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi>
But it is another Case for <hi>Flesh</hi> and <hi>Bloud</hi> to ly
<hi>beating</hi> of it out a <hi>whole Age</hi> against <hi>Wind</hi> and <hi>Tide;</hi> and
when he has <hi>Conquer'd That Difficulty,</hi> to be cast upon
the <hi>Rocks,</hi> and There <hi>abandon'd</hi> at <hi>Last.</hi> Or, to follow
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95761:18"/>
my first <hi>Allegory;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cold Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</note> It is but a cold Comfort for a man
to lie <hi>striving Thirty or Forty Years</hi> to gain the Top of
a <hi>Hill,</hi> only upon a <hi>barren Instinct</hi> of <hi>Honour</hi> or <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue;</hi>
and when he comes <hi>there,</hi> to have only the choyce
either of a <hi>Iayl,</hi> or of a <hi>Gibbet,</hi> for his <hi>last Retreat:</hi>
the Duty of <hi>Persevering</hi> is never the less <hi>binding,</hi> for
the <hi>Difficulty</hi> of the <hi>Attempt;</hi> but yet, according to
the Measures of <hi>Humane Frailty,</hi> the <hi>French King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self</hi>
perhaps, would find it an hard Matter to Levy an
Army of Fifty or Threescore <hi>Thousand Men</hi> (out of
all his Dominions) of <hi>That Complexion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the Cherishing of this sense of <hi>Loyalty,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Loyalty is to be valu'd, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy.</note> is not
only a necessary point of <hi>Prudential Iustice</hi> to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served
in all Regiments whatsoever; but it is likewise
the <hi>Interest,</hi> and the <hi>practice</hi> of all <hi>well-govern'd Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions,</hi>
to pay an <hi>Esteem</hi> to the <hi>Character</hi> of an <hi>Invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late
Integrity,</hi> even in an <hi>Enemy:</hi> For it falls out many
times, that Differences of that sort may come to ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate
in the most Amicable and profitable Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:
Beside that, they are sure of <hi>fair play,</hi> in the
very <hi>heat</hi> of the <hi>Dispute;</hi> whereas what <hi>security</hi> can
any man promise to himself, from a <hi>State-Weather-Cock,</hi>
that still keeps his Eye upon his <hi>Interest,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
any regard to his <hi>Conscience;</hi> and changes his <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion,</hi>
and his <hi>Party,</hi> as often, perhaps, as his
<hi>Shirt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not that I either pretend to pin my self for Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection,
<note place="margin">My Appeal to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable House of Commons.</note> upon the Government, for my own sake; or
that, in Truth, I am Conscious of any thing, to my
self, that requires more than the common benefit of
the Law, to keep me in safety: And I have yet a
greater security than all this; which is, that when
the Honourable House of Commons shall come to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:95761:18"/>
know me better by my <hi>Actions,</hi> and <hi>open dealings</hi> and
<hi>Professions,</hi> than the world does hitherto, by the <hi>Fid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi>
and the <hi>Rascals</hi> that the <hi>Paultry News-mongers</hi> here
of the Town have represented me to be; I make no
doubt, but they will think me worthy of some <hi>Publique
Reparation</hi> from the <hi>Authors</hi> of those <hi>Scandals:</hi> And
that those <hi>worthy Gentlemen,</hi> out of a regard to the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
Bloud</hi> that runs in <hi>their own Veins,</hi> will consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the Case of <hi>another Gentleman,</hi> as their <hi>Own,</hi> and
not suffer Men of <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Family</hi> to be blasted at
this rate, by the Sons <hi>of the People.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of all the <hi>lewd</hi> and <hi>scandalous Calumnies</hi> that have
been advanced against me,<note place="margin">Nothing prov'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst me.</note> there has not been one syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable
prov'd. First, as to my pretended Compliances
with <hi>Oliver:</hi> There are Witnesses enough yet living of
<hi>that Party</hi> that know the <hi>contrary<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and not one man
breathing so much as to <hi>colour</hi> it with any <hi>particular.</hi>
Beside a Cloud of the Kings Friends that can prove my
restless endeavours the other way.</p>
               <p>I have been lately Charg'd for a <hi>Confederacy</hi> with
<hi>Young Tonge;</hi> and in the <hi>Coffee-Houses</hi> and <hi>News
Letters,</hi> for a <hi>Correspondence</hi> with Mrs. <hi>Cellier;</hi> when
yet I made it as clear as the Sun, that I never
saw <hi>Tonge,</hi> but <hi>twice,</hi> in my life; and that till <hi>after</hi> his
<hi>affirming,</hi> and <hi>retracting,</hi> and <hi>renouncing</hi> that <hi>Retracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
(which was the thing that pinn'd the Basket)
and all this upon his <hi>Salvation</hi> too; I never knew so
much as his Person. It appears likewise that I gave
him the <hi>slip,</hi> upon the very time he had appointed to
<hi>visit</hi> me; and that upon his Letter to me <hi>next morning,</hi>
I was so Cautious, that I gave Mr. <hi>Choqueux</hi> warning
of him. When he came to me <hi>that Evening,</hi> with
Company, I told them I would do nothing that lookt
like a <hi>Consultation.</hi> After this, (two Gentlemen that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95761:19"/>
he brought, going away) he would needs have me take
his <hi>Information</hi> as a <hi>Iustice of Peace.</hi> I told him, <hi>I
would receive none, unless under his</hi> own hand, ready
written, <hi>and not to be</hi> alter'd; <hi>and with</hi> a Clause insert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<hi>that it was his</hi> own voluntary act, <hi>without any Induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
to it from me:</hi> And that after all this, <hi>I would
yet consider upon the matter of it, wheth<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r it were fit for
me to meddle with, or no.</hi> Here the business rested; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<hi>Tonge</hi> would be pressing sensless Stories upon me, as
he had at first, till upon shewing my dislike of what
he said, and telling him (as I had done before) that <hi>it
signified nothing,</hi> he gave it off, and went his way. And
I will now <hi>superadd</hi> this <hi>Protestation,</hi> upon the Faith of a
Christian, he said nothing to me that could in any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree
in the world operate upon Mr. <hi>Oats's Testimony:</hi>
And then for Mrs. <hi>Collier,</hi> that was only <hi>Care's Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie,</hi>
(who wrote <hi>Prances Narrative)</hi> and not so much
as mention'd before the King and Councel.</p>
               <p>When I had spoken to the business of <hi>Tonge,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Oates's Charges.</note> Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> let that whole matter fall; and Charg'd
me with a <hi>Misdemeanor,</hi> for insisting upon a <hi>Clause</hi>
for <hi>Clearing of my self</hi> in case of <hi>Tonge's Affidavit;</hi>
but it was lookt upon as a piece of <hi>Necessary Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
and so Mr. <hi>Oates's Iudgment</hi> was <hi>over-rul'd.</hi>
But Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> follow'd <hi>This Charge</hi> with a <hi>sorer one</hi>
upon the Neck on't; which was, for <hi>Concealing</hi> a
<hi>Conspiracy</hi> against the <hi>Kings Witnesses,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">High Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</note> which he
said was <hi>High Treason,</hi> My Answer was to this
Effect,<note place="margin">Nonsense is High Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</note> That <hi>it was a strange Conspiracy, for the whole
Story was Nonsense from one end to t'other·</hi> To which
Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> Reply'd, that <hi>if it be a</hi> Conspiracy, <hi>'tis
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95761:19"/>
no matter whether it be</hi> Sense <hi>or</hi> Nonsense; <hi>for 'tis</hi>
High Treason <hi>however.</hi> But This notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
His Majesty was graciously pleas'd to give
me the Character of an <hi>Honest</hi> and a <hi>Loyal</hi> man;
and so That Arrow fell short too.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> was then pleas'd to beat another
Bush;<note place="margin">Charg'd with being a <hi>Papist.</hi>
                  </note> undertaking to prove me <hi>Popishly-Affected:</hi>
And Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> swore that he had seen me <hi>three or
four times at Mass, at</hi> Somerset-House, <hi>about two
years since; and doing there as other people did; but he
could not say that he saw me</hi> Receive. Whereupon
I did with the most horrid Solemnity of Impreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
Imaginable, declare my self to be of <hi>the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
of the Church of England,</hi> and that I had never
enter'd into any <hi>Popish Chappel,</hi> or been <hi>present</hi> at
any <hi>Mass,</hi> since His <hi>Majesties Return;</hi> which <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation</hi>
I do here again <hi>Resume,</hi> intending by
these words <hi>HIS MAJESTIES RETURN, the
Kings blessed Restauration, in the Year</hi> 1660. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
but note a great <hi>Abatement,</hi> in <hi>Prance's Reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi>
for I am assur'd, that <hi>Prance</hi> swore in the
Company of <hi>Care, Curtis,</hi> and <hi>some other people, that
he had seen me at</hi> Mass, <hi>at least, or about a</hi> hundred
Times.</p>
               <p>Upon the blowing over of This Storm too,<note place="margin">Charg'd with Conveying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way Bulls and Popish Books.</note> I
expected to have had my <hi>Quietus;</hi> but Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:95761:20"/>
reinforc'd himself again, by a <hi>Charge</hi> upon me for
<hi>conveying away certain</hi> Bulls <hi>and</hi> Popish-Books <hi>that
were seiz'd, and lockt up with a Padlock upon the Door;</hi>
but when they came afterward to look for them,
the <hi>Padlock</hi> was taken <hi>off,</hi> and the <hi>Books gone.</hi>
Whereupon the <hi>Messenger</hi> of the <hi>Press</hi> was <hi>sworn,</hi>
and being <hi>examin'd</hi> to the <hi>Points,</hi> he could not say,
either that I took off the <hi>Padlock,</hi> or that I gave
any <hi>Order,</hi> or <hi>Direction</hi> about it; or that I knew
any thing of the <hi>conveying away</hi> of the <hi>Books,</hi> or any
thing <hi>coucerning</hi> the <hi>Books</hi> themselves, one way,
or other.</p>
               <p>This manner of <hi>Prosecution</hi> (methought) was
very <hi>Extraordinary;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Two Charges more yet.</note> considering with what Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence
Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> had call'd me <hi>Rogue,</hi> and <hi>Ras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,
that day Sennet,</hi> before the <hi>Privy Councel.</hi> And
he had not done with me, yet neither; for he
said that <hi>one heard me say at</hi> Wills Coffee-House,
<hi>that there was no Plot:</hi> Which, <hi>by the Oath I have
formerly taken, is false;</hi> for I ever thought there
<hi>was a Plot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One thing I had like to have <hi>forgotten,</hi> Mr.
<hi>Oates</hi> Charg'd me for <hi>Conversing</hi> with one <hi>Grange,</hi>
and <hi>Sing:</hi> The <hi>former</hi> I know nothing of; and
for Mr. <hi>Sing,</hi> I do <hi>Converse</hi> with <hi>him</hi> as I do with a
hundred other people at the <hi>Coffee-House,</hi> and I
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:95761:20"/>
know nothing more of him, then that amounts
to.</p>
               <p>I cannot let pass This Circumstance,<note place="margin">A Violation upon the Rights of Common So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety.</note> without
the Remarque of a strange <hi>Usurpation</hi> upon the
<hi>Common Rights of Humane Society;</hi> if a man must
be Oblig'd, contrary to the Rules of <hi>Humanity,</hi>
and <hi>good Manners,</hi> to <hi>Catechize</hi> every new Face that
he sees, and run, like an <hi>Animal solivagum,</hi> into
<hi>Caves, Forests,</hi> and <hi>Deserts,</hi> for fear of giving any
man the time of the day, till he has taken him to
Task, upon the <hi>Articles of his Faith.</hi> It is not that
I set up for an <hi>Advocate</hi> for the Pleasures of <hi>frequent
Conversations,</hi> and <hi>gaudy entertainments;</hi> but I do
freely confess, that I had rather Associate my self
with <hi>four-footed,</hi> then with <hi>two-footed Beasts,</hi> and
that such an <hi>Imposition,</hi> even from <hi>Authority</hi> it self,
would be <hi>Grievous:</hi> But for a <hi>Private Person</hi> to
assume That <hi>Empire,</hi> is both <hi>Arrogant,</hi> and <hi>Intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for my <hi>Self;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Adieu.</note> This <hi>Disgust</hi> could never have
laid hold of me in a better time; for I am really
as <hi>Sick</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> as <hi>Peevishness</hi> it self can be
of <hi>Me.</hi> And having stood all <hi>Proofs,</hi> both of
my <hi>Fidelity</hi> to my <hi>Master,</hi> and of my <hi>Integrity</hi> in
despight of my <hi>Enemies;</hi> I'le e'ne betake my self
to the <hi>Quietest way</hi> of making my Escape out of
an <hi>Impious,</hi> and <hi>Trepanning</hi> World, into a <hi>better.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
