<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A whipp for the animadverter in return to his second libell. By R. L'S.</title>
            <author>L'Estrange, Roger, Sir, 1616-1704.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-11">2004-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47940</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1325A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217627</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829285</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829285</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33722</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A47940)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33722)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1992:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A whipp for the animadverter in return to his second libell. By R. L'S.</title>
                  <author>L'Estrange, Roger, Sir, 1616-1704.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Henry Brome, at the Gun in Ivy-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>February the 12th. 1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>R. L'S. = Sir Roger L'Estrange.</note>
                  <note>A reply to "A second letter unto a person of honour &amp; quality, containing some farther animadversions upon the Bishop of Worcester's letter" both by Edward Bagshaw.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 3 reads: An ansvver to a libel, &amp;c.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Jesus College Library, Cambridge.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671. --  Second letter unto a person of honour &amp; quality, containing some farther animadversions upon the Bishop of Worcester's letter.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>Melanie Sanders</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>Melanie Sanders</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33722:1"/>
            <p>A WHIPP For the Animadverter In Return to his Second LIBELL.</p>
            <p>By <hi>R. L'S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed for <hi>Henry Brome,</hi> at the <hi>Gun</hi> in <hi>Ivy-lane. February</hi> the 12<hi rend="sup">t</hi>h, 1662.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:33722:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:33722:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An Answer to a Libel, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>I Had no sooner corrected <hi>One</hi> Libell, against the Bishop of <hi>Worcester,</hi> but out bolts <hi>another</hi> against <hi>L'S.,</hi> of the <hi>same Stamp,</hi> and <hi>Force,</hi> and <hi>Calculated</hi> for the <hi>same Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian. What, Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> or <hi>Where</hi> the Authour is, I neither <hi>Care</hi> nor <hi>Enquire</hi>; for meth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nks <hi>Hunting</hi> after <hi>Libellers,</hi> is some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like <hi>Gunning</hi> at <hi>Didappers</hi>; a man's in danger to <hi>Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se</hi> his <hi>Sho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi>; or, if he <hi>Hitts,</hi> 'tis but a <hi>Nasty Quarry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heark ye my Masters of the <hi>Consistory; You</hi> are the Men must do <hi>Mee</hi> Right; <hi>These Fellows</hi> are but <hi>Your Bag-Pipes; You Blow,</hi> and <hi>They Bawl</hi>: But if I turn not up your <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences,</hi> as fair, as ever This <hi>Whipster's Honourable Friend</hi>] did his <hi>Boyes</hi> at <hi>Westminster,</hi> let the world say I have no skill in <hi>untrussing</hi> an <hi>Apostate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In short; the Spirit of <hi>Vntruth</hi> and <hi>Scandal</hi> is sent abroad from among you; and he calls himself <hi>D. E. (the Two first Letters of his Fathers Name, Jeh.</hi> 8. 44.)</p>
            <p>In the <hi>First Page,</hi> the <hi>Phantome</hi> appears in the <hi>Form</hi> of a <hi>Philosopher:</hi> with This <hi>Character</hi> of <hi>L' S. [A Person so lost to all Good Breeding, of so forfeited, so undone a Reputation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n poynt of meer Morality,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> you have been now <hi>Twenty Years</hi> at This sport of <hi>Libelling</hi>: The <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Queen,</hi> the <hi>Royal Family,</hi> the <hi>Bishops</hi>; all that were <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yal,</hi> of the <hi>Nobility, Gentry,</hi> and <hi>Commonalty,</hi> have been <hi>be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>patter'd</hi> by those <hi>Scribblers,</hi> and <hi>Lecturers,</hi> which you h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve kept in <hi>Pens<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pressly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>me them The <hi>Church</hi> the <hi>State</hi>; the <hi>Law,</hi> the <hi>Gospel</hi>; No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing so Sacred as to escape you. (<hi>I speak only to Those that have Revolted f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rce the Pardon.</hi>) Have ye not deliver'd the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33722:3"/>
               <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Devills,</hi> for the <hi>Inspirations</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghost<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Vouching <hi>Texts</hi> for <hi>Perjury,</hi> and <hi>Rapine; Impul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> for <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>; Cutting your <hi>Soveraign</hi> in your <hi>Prayers?</hi> in the same Act; <hi>Seducing</hi> the <hi>People<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ronting</hi> the <hi>King, Dis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> the <hi>Pulpit, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>phaning</hi> the <hi>Or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inance,</hi> and <hi>Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> himself.</p>
            <p>This is not <hi>Passion</hi> Gentlemen, but <hi>Truth</hi> upon <hi>Record</hi>; and <hi>Printed</hi> by <hi>Stati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ners</hi> of your <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Appointment, in Perp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tuam rei Memoriam.</hi> Your <hi>Names</hi> I <hi>spare</hi>; For I wish rather your <hi>Conversion,</hi> then your <hi>Shame:</hi> my D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ift being only to shew that your <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngues</hi> are no <hi>Slander.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next Page, your <hi>Agent</hi> is a little <hi>unsavory,</hi> and I advise the Reader to make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f a <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mander.</hi> He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares <hi>L' S.</hi> to [a <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gg playing up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the Organs.</hi>] I p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay'e, had not this <hi>Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Hand in your <hi>Centuries</hi> of <hi>Scandalous Ministers?</hi> Look a Line further, and <hi>There</hi> you are to Phansy him, [<hi>A Scavenger washing a</hi> Bishops <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice</hi>] How naturally the Sloven goes from the <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gg,</hi> to the <hi>Sir-Reverence</hi>! with Licence, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> what i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a man should now Phansy your <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ubstitute<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to be some <hi>Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m of the Sto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l</hi> to a <hi>Holy Sister</hi>? But soberly, <hi>To cleanse his Mouth would be the fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lest part of a Scavengers Employment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Say now ye <hi>Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thren of the Text:</hi> Have ye a <hi>Scripture-Rule</hi> for <hi>This Language? Wee</hi> must do every thing in <hi>Mode</hi> and <hi>Figure</hi>; according to the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecept. [<hi>Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> every thing be done to Edification</hi>], says the <hi>Apostle; [Bless them that Curse yee</hi>], says our Blessed <hi>Saviour.</hi> Stick to your <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n Rule</hi> then, and <hi>Observe the Precept</hi>; Unles<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e you will deal with the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> as ye have done with the <hi>Law</hi> of the <hi>Land</hi>: Muzzle it with a <hi>Salvo,</hi> and only Practise <hi>Christianity,</hi> so far as it consists with <hi>Presbytery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not to be tedious, what your <hi>Emissary</hi> has <hi>expanded,</hi> take in <hi>Little</hi>; (that is, the <hi>Flowers</hi> of his <hi>Rhetorique.</hi>) [A <hi>Morrice-Dancer,</hi>—A <hi>Fidler</hi>;—A <hi>Common Barreter</hi>; A <hi>Mercenary Songster</hi>;—A <hi>Whiffling Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l'd Adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi>—A <hi>Puny Author,</hi> A <hi>Sack-Drinker</hi>; (beshrew me, I
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33722:3"/>
like the Liquor <hi>but [it goes in, Sack</hi> (he says) <hi>and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s out Water.</hi>] This, he could never have known, without the help of a <hi>Devill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly Gentlemen, (to the point of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sique</hi>) he is a little guilty of some skill in <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g</hi>; and not very <hi>Mercenary</hi> neither, to a <hi>Friend</hi>; hee'll do <hi>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur</hi> Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inesse however, when you please, by the way of a <hi>Madrigall,</hi> and never put ye <hi>to pay th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Fidler.</hi> Try him, and if he does not set ye such a suit of <hi>Hymnes</hi> to your unfumish'd <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>Publique Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,</hi> the very <hi>Ring</hi> of them shall shake the Fundamentals of a <hi>Christ-Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and make the <hi>Brethren</hi> of your <hi>Milk-street Conventicle,</hi> Gape wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and wider, then <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael Angelo's Reprobates,</hi> in his <hi>Day of Judgment,</hi> say I'm no Conjure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. I speak with <hi>Reverence</hi> to the <hi>Good</hi>; and <hi>Charity</hi> to the <hi>Weak</hi>; But to hear <hi>Faction</hi> deliver'd for <hi>Conscience</hi>; to see <hi>People p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yson'd</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>Princes Dethron'd</hi> in the <hi>Pulpit</hi>; Who, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat loves either <hi>God,</hi> his <hi>Prince,</hi> or <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> has not a <hi>Horreur</hi> for it? Further;</p>
            <p>Your Angry mantels the World that <hi>L'S.</hi> is [<hi>One that hath been a Fidler in all Governments, and would have been a Fidler in the worst of them; For which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd</hi> (says he) <hi>Hee knows how may Pittiful Leggs and Faces he made<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to scrape Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the Tyrant Ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er.</hi>]</p>
            <p>In earnest, This Report might do him a great deal of <hi>Hurt,</hi> but that I trust, he has some Friends at Court, will have a C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re that nothing shall do him any <hi>Good.</hi> Pray'e will you speak Gentlemen; <hi>You,</hi> have a great many of you been of <hi>All</hi> sides; did any of you, ever know him of any More then <hi>One?</hi> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. —did <hi>you</hi> ever see him make the <hi>Pittiful Leggs, and Faces,</hi> (he talks of) to that [<hi>Prudent, Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us, and Faithful Governour the Lord Protectour</hi>] Mr. — Don't you Remember that [<hi>the Providences of God did as much appear in the removing of others from, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vesting</hi> their Honours with <hi>the Government of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Nation, as ever they appeared in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>king awa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, or bestowing of any Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in any History of any Age of the World</hi>?] did <hi>You</hi> ever take notice of any such thing? Mr. — <hi>You Inaugu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:33722:4"/>
the <hi>Serene Oliver,</hi> and <hi>Blessed the Scepter in the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nds of his Princely Successour</hi>: What say <hi>You</hi> to the World? Or did Sir <hi>John Presbyter</hi> ever smel out any such matter in the <hi>Protectour's Water? We</hi> could appeal further, but <hi>More</hi> were too <hi>Much,</hi> A <hi>Sober</hi> Line or Two now (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> y L beller apart).</p>
            <p>I know the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Tales are not Believ'd; yet they are <hi>enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd,</hi> in <hi>Whispers,</hi> and <hi>pointed</hi> at, in little <hi>Observations</hi>; and so <hi>One</hi> Scandal is grounded upon <hi>another</hi>: more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the <hi>disadvantage</hi> of my <hi>Fortune,</hi> then the <hi>dis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rder</hi> of my <hi>Thoughts.</hi> If I am <hi>Guilty,</hi> why am I not <hi>Hang'd?</hi> If I am <hi>Innocent,</hi> why am I <hi>Slander'd?</hi> In fine, so innocent I am that I affirm; wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t Person soever, (the <hi>Royal Bloud</hi> excepted) endeavours to possess his Majesty I am other, does in all Likely-hood purpose to Betray him, and his own <hi>Soul</hi> gainsayes his <hi>Tongue.</hi> Enough of This, now to the little Fellow again.</p>
            <p>He saies, [<hi>That many Sober Persons (w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s thought it very fit that the Bishop should be a little humbled) are much satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by it, but the Bishop himself so far concerned, that he hath employed one L' S. to answer it.</hi>]</p>
            <p>A very pretty kind of <hi>Colloquy,</hi> betwixt <hi>D.</hi> and <hi>E.</hi> Both which I dare say, would be extreamly <hi>Satisfy'd,</hi> to see the <hi>Bishop humbled</hi>; yes, <hi>humbled</hi> by the <hi>Head,</hi> as his good Friends humbled the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi>; the Bishop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbury</hi> next; and at last the <hi>King.</hi> And what, <hi>when they had humbled These</hi>; and with These, <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and <hi>Episcopacy,</hi> into a base and inextricable Confusion: what did they <hi>raise,</hi> to fill those <hi>Vacancies,</hi> but <hi>Dunghill Vapours</hi>; that were scarce sooner <hi>up,</hi> then <hi>down</hi> again, in <hi>Plagues,</hi> or <hi>storms</hi> upon the People? I hope any Country-men have not forgot the <hi>Fruits of their last Humbling of the Bishops.</hi> In truth, a Conflict, had the Bishop replyed, might have made him asham'd; but barely to <hi>approve himself; confute a Schismatique,</hi> and <hi>cast out</hi> an <hi>Intruder</hi> from a <hi>Sequestred Living,</hi> was for his <hi>Honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:33722:4"/>Whereas he sayes, <hi>that the Bishop imploy'd one</hi> L'S. <hi>to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer the Animadverter,</hi> That same <hi>L' S.</hi> did, to my Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, declare, upon the first light of the Bishops Letter, that it was below the <hi>Dignity</hi> of a <hi>Pralate</hi> to Cope with a <hi>Libeller,</hi> and that if any man reply'd, hee'd undertake the next.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Innocent,</hi> in the Second Page, Playes with the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops [Dudgeon phrase of <hi>This is the Truth, the whole Truth, and n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thing but the Truth,</hi> &amp;c.] The man is here to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd upon several accompts. First as no Judge of a Good Stile, or el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e he Counterfeits, for <hi>His</hi> Jaggs like a <hi>Saw.</hi> Next; as a Stranger to the <hi>Law,</hi> he would not else have taken the <hi>Common form</hi> of an <hi>Oath</hi> for the <hi>Bishops Phrase.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his fourth Page, he Challenges the <hi>Bishop</hi> and the <hi>world</hi> to make good six <hi>Positions</hi> which he pretends Asserted by the Bishop, and for plain dealing sake, wee'll set them down as the <hi>Animal</hi> delivers them.</p>
            <list>
               <label>Pos. 1.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>That Monarchy cannot consist without Episcopacy.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Pos. 2.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>That the Bishop of</hi> Worcester <hi>is the Sole and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Pastor of all the Congregations in his Diocess.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Pos. 3.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>That it is unlawful for any, though Ordeyned, to preach in the Bishop of</hi> Worcesters <hi>Diocess, without his License.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Pos. 4.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>That it is Lawful in the Worship of God to enjoyn a small thing under a great Penalty.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Pos. 5.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>That the Church hath Power to ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t Confession and Recantation, for these Crimes which the State hath par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Pos. 6.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>That the Presbyterians are</hi> All <hi>Seditious.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The Two first are no more the Bishops Positions, then the Animadverter is his Friend, (<hi>Vide</hi> my Answer to his Animadversions, <hi>Pag.</hi> 5. &amp; 7. &amp; <hi>P.</hi> 13.) the Rest are suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently justified. The Third in <hi>Pag.</hi> 17. The Fourth, <hi>Pag.</hi> 30. The Fifth, <hi>Pag.</hi> 22, 23. The Sixth, <hi>Pag.</hi> 11, 12.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:33722:5"/>You the <hi>Heads</hi> and <hi>Patrons</hi> of the <hi>Revolt,</hi> by what Name or Title soever Dignify'd, or Distinguish'd; take notice that I here dismiss your <hi>small officer:</hi> and now, a Cold, and Serious word Singly, to Your <hi>Selves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly a Stranger to your <hi>Consultations,</hi> and <hi>Cabalts</hi>; from whence I am well Inform'd, that you have been Hammering at an <hi>Answer</hi> to me: but finding that the Cause will hardly beat it, you are a little doubtful whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>That</hi> or a <hi>Libell.</hi> Proceed: and when ye shall have engag'd the <hi>nameless Issue</hi> of some <hi>Carted Strumpet</hi> to <hi>forge</hi> the <hi>Scandal</hi>; Then shall I <hi>Thank</hi> ye, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> for using <hi>me</hi> no worse, then ye have done Your <hi>King,</hi> and all his <hi>friends</hi> before me.</p>
            <p>When <hi>You</hi> have <hi>drawn</hi> your <hi>Goodly Piece,</hi> wee'll try <hi>our</hi> skill in <hi>Printing</hi> too: but I assure ye, <hi>Mine</hi> shall be done from the <hi>Life, Yours</hi> will be but a <hi>Phancy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e est Mendacium, perlucet, s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diligenter inspexeris.</hi> Sen. Ep.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:33722:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
