<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Life of Boetius recommended to the author of the life of Julian</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-01">2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48411</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2024</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20135</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12609239</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12609239</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64306</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A48411)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64306)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 964:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Life of Boetius recommended to the author of the life of Julian</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 101 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by W. Davis ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>An answer to Samuel Johnson's Julian the apostate, in which the Duke of York is portrayed in the character of Julian.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 101.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Johnson, Samuel, 1649-1703. --  Julian the Apostate.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2000-00</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-03</date>
            <label>TCP Staff (Michigan)</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64306:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64306:1"/>
            <p>THE LIFE OF BOETIUS, Recommended to the AUTHOR OF THE Life of Iulian,</p>
            <q>Flebilis heu mestos cogor inire modos.</q>
            <bibl> Boet. Consol. Phil. lib. 1.</bibl>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed, and are to be sold by <hi>W. Davis</hi> in <hi>Amen-Corner</hi> near <hi>Pater Noster-Row,</hi> MDCLXXXIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:64306:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64306:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THo' Loyal <hi>Heraclitus</hi> (who understands <hi>wit</hi> as well as any, and has show'd it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, to the cost of many a Seditious and wretched <hi>Fop</hi>) thought some months ago, with his Friend Mr. <hi>Earnest, that telling of stories is a dull sort of mirth</hi>; Yet I know he cannot but grant, that the alternate way is (to use Mr. <hi>Bays</hi>'s happy expression) <hi>extremely Obliging and Civil</hi>; and Civility, we see, is a <hi>Virtue</hi> has been highly esteem'd, and with the nicest exactness practic'd by the <hi>Pacqueteers, Mercuries,</hi> and rest of the SOBER and Obedient <hi>Authors</hi> of the Times.</p>
            <p>Meeting therefore t'other day with <hi>IVLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AN</hi>'s SQUIRE, who (to honour <hi>Christianity</hi> in general, and to shew also in particular, <hi>His</hi> and his <hi>Parties</hi> Principles of <hi>Obedie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce</hi>) gave me the <hi>Recital</hi> of his <hi>Master</hi>'s LIFE and <hi>Adventures:</hi> I could not (methought) without an unpardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Rudeness and Ingratitude, omit longer the telling of my <hi>Story,</hi> which happened in a Town which this <hi>Godly Prince</hi> once govern'd, and about an Age or two after his <hi>Religious</hi> and <hi>pious</hi> End. The <hi>Squires Account</hi> is, God be thanked, now public enough, and evinces still further the <hi>In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation</hi> and <hi>Folly</hi> of the <hi>Cabal,</hi> even as to the very thing they so earnestly design; for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:64306:3"/>
a particular and Divine <hi>Iudgment,</hi> how can it be conceiv'd, that they who seem'd to idolize <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Bedloe,</hi> as men of <hi>Probity,</hi> and the true <hi>Saviours</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> should still strive, by odious <hi>Reflections,</hi> and their other vain <hi>Insinuations,</hi> to draw His <hi>Royal Highness</hi> within the Verge of the <hi>Plot,</hi> tho' contrary to the <hi>Oaths</hi> even of these two Witnesses? Must not this Procedure therefore bring afresh into mens minds the business of DON JOHN, and PRESTON the <hi>married Priest,</hi> with the other <hi>Contradictions</hi> which are laid to the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s charge by the <note n="*" place="margin">Compend. Staff. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moirs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Papists,</hi> out of every Printed <hi>Tryal?</hi> Will not this too give them a new occasion to tell us, how <hi>Bedloe</hi> swore (at his Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before the <hi>Secretaries of State</hi>) <hi>That he knew nothing of the Plot</hi>; as also, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving matter enough for a <hi>Charge</hi> against <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread</hi> and <hi>Fenwic</hi> in one Tryal, he swears them both Guilty in the next, of the highest <hi>Treasons</hi> imaginable? Nor will these Popish <hi>Whipsters</hi> fail again to rub up our Memory, with the 2000 <hi>l.</hi> offer'd him for his meer help to carry away <note n="*" place="margin">Hill's T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y. <hi>p.</hi> 32.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir <hi>E. Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>frey</hi>'s Body, and then flop us in the mouth with their Remarks, and twit us, that<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his own Testimony, there were (besides <note n="*" place="margin">ib. p. 31.</note>
               <hi>those</hi> who were said to do the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing) as <hi>many ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er persons then in the Room,</hi> when the
<pb facs="tcp:64306:3"/>
               <hi>Iesuits</hi> show'd him the <hi>Corps,</hi> as could have in a night convey'd it, and more <hi>Bodies</hi> than one, to the design'd place or station. Thus do these phrantic <hi>Scriblers</hi> give fresh cause of discourse, and consequently, pull down what they would fain set up; and, in their own terms, <hi>blacken and defame the very Iustice of the Nation.</hi> But what wonder is there of it, when now, by wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful experience, we see, no <hi>Witness, Iury, Court, Iudge, Parliament, Law,</hi> or <hi>Magistrate,</hi> can be so Sacred, that will not be presently blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, if they sute not with their Gust and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour? This is the Treatise, (I mean that of JULIAN) which is so particularly recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us by CARE; a wretch that has not only croak'd, and disgo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d the utmost <note n="*" place="margin">vid. Cou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rant all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven lately Num. 34.</note> 
               <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom</hi> which his feeble and macerated Maw could distill against so many of the best of the <hi>Gentry,</hi> and so many of the greatest of the <hi>Peers,</hi> but against the <hi>present Heir to the Crown,</hi> nay against the v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry <hi>K in ship</hi> it self. This is also the <hi>Book</hi> which CURTIS so often advertizes us of, and <note n="*" place="margin">N. 159.</note> 
               <hi>vindicates</hi> too; a Villain that durst (to the amazement even of the Anarchical &amp; Factious) <hi>bid a</hi> POX <hi>on His</hi> Highness, in his public <note n="*" place="margin">N. 155.</note> 
               <hi>Mercury,</hi> or Intelligence. Since then the <hi>Subversion of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ernment</hi> is evidently meant by their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing to brand, and lay aside this <hi>Illustr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ous
<pb facs="tcp:64306:4"/>
Prince</hi>; for when once <hi>Kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ship</hi> (as has been often <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>appily hinted) becomes <hi>Elective,</hi> why may not the n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xt VOTE, upon any new Freak (besides a long Train of other Mischiefs) be for a <hi>new Line,</hi> or even down-right for a <hi>Democracy</hi> and <hi>Commonwealth?</hi> I say, since this is the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue, and the word <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>antation to bewitch the Inconsiderate. I doubt not but all good men will now look upon this <hi>Morm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> or f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ightful <hi>Represe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tation,</hi> with the same Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt that the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs</hi> of the <hi>Machine</hi> do thems<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> For besides the Laws, which se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Establish<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d <hi>Religion,</hi> there are not, we know, (as appears by the survey made some <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ew years sin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e) <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bove Twenty Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>usand Papists, or thereabo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts, of all Sexes and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>izes in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m</hi>; So that, if those who are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it to fight were even <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ogether, and in <hi>Arms,</hi> Fifteen hundred Disciplin'd <hi>Soldi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs</hi> would cut them all to pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e impudent and Sedious Desig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pretence of <hi>Popery,</hi> brings therefore to the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>embrance of many, the Loyalty of the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Party,</hi> during <hi>This</hi> and the late <hi>King's</hi> Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes; which makes it to be often que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion'd, whether they are generally such <hi>Traytors,</hi> as some would have them thought? nor does it add a little to the doubt, when they find, in the present Pursuit, the <hi>deepest-mouth'd Hounds</hi> to be the <hi>Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and those that (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Pal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ations and Goodmo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rows) <hi>strike at the
<pb facs="tcp:64306:4"/>
Root and Life of the Monarchy.</hi> For my own part, I intend by no means the De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence of the <hi>Popish Religion,</hi> and besee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h God to let the whole Crew see all the <hi>Errours</hi> of it; but if <hi>Retaliation</hi> and <hi>Iustice</hi> to our fore-mention'd <hi>Historiogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher,</hi> prove by chance serviceable to their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Concerns, much good may do them; for no honest man (tho' never so scrupulous, will desist from prosecuting a <hi>Bur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lary,</hi> because the <hi>Iews</hi> or <hi>Pagan</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> who live among us may chance to sleep the quieter and safer for it; And who, but a new-pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ending <hi>Patriot,</hi> will countenance <hi>Ryots,</hi> and the breach of the Peace, that the <hi>Matrons</hi> and <hi>Virgins</hi> of <hi>Whetstones-Park</hi> may be the surer (forsooth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be dis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urb'd in <hi>Easter</hi> and <hi>Whitsun-weeks.</hi> All that I have here further to acquaint the <hi>Reader</hi> with, is, That, had there not been already so many smart and excellent <hi>Reflections</hi> on this <hi>Prostigate</hi> and APO<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>TATE-<hi>Wri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er,</hi> yet I should never have troubled my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lf with any further d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ion of his idle and malicious Lucubrations, than the thus giving h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m <hi>Story</hi> for <hi>Story,</hi> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h a Comment.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="life">
            <pb facs="tcp:64306:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64306:5"/>
            <head>THE LIFE OF Boetius.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Calamities</hi> which <hi>Italy</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series of</hi> Italy.</note> (that Beautiful and Fertil part of the <hi>Vniverse</hi>) Suffer'd in the <hi>Fifth Century</hi> from the <hi>Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> were so great and so many, that the <hi>Antient Histori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> look'd upon them as unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel'd; and certainly they had some Reason to think so, it ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been the <hi>Theatre</hi> on which all (that even their <hi>Poets</hi> could fan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y Dismal by the Ravage and Inhumanity of several <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous People</hi>) was then really
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64306:6"/>
represented. The <hi>Murders</hi> men saw, the <hi>Saies</hi> and <hi>Sequestra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> they felt, and the <hi>Slavery</hi> they were reduc'd to, want still perchance a <hi>Pen,</hi> fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly to express them; for tho they had not <note n="*" place="margin">1. Ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. Cromwel, 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mp.</hi> 3 <hi>Com. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y,</hi> 4. <hi>Long Par.</hi> 5 <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>K.</hi> Ch 2d. <hi>From</hi> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y 59. <hi>to</hi> May 60.</note> 
               <hi>Six new Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ters in one Year,</hi> (as was the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate</hi> of a still <hi>Fortunate</hi> and <hi>Glorious Isle,</hi> if it truly knew its own Happiness) yet they enjoy'd even in their own Memory (as appears by <hi>Prosper Aquita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us, Palmerius,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Chronologists</hi>) the pleasure of as <hi>many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>roads,</hi> each <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour</hi> differing in his Interests, tho never in his Pretences and Fury. <hi>Alaric</hi> and his <hi>Goths; Attila</hi> the <hi>Hun; Genseric</hi> the <hi>Vandal; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igorus,</hi> King of the <hi>Alani</hi>; and <hi>Odoacer</hi> with the <hi>Heruli</hi> (treading as it were upon the heels of each ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er) acted here their <hi>Monstrous</hi> Parts: Nor did some of them fail, (as <note n="*" place="margin">De Reb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <hi>Goth.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandes</hi> well notes) in the midst
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64306:6"/>
of their <hi>Depredations</hi> and <hi>Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> to vaunt, <hi>That Heaven had put them on the Employment</hi>; that is to say, In the phrase of their <hi>younger Brethren; They came to do the Work of the Lord</hi>; and if so, They were, doubtless, very far from the <hi>Curse</hi> of <hi>Performing it negligently.</hi> In fine, <hi>Theodoric</hi> the <hi>Brave</hi> (and thus He is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem'd by <note n="*" place="margin">Chron. &amp; lib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Var.</note> 
               <hi>Cassiodorus,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Vit. Sym.</note> 
               <hi>Enno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius,</hi> and many of the <hi>Writers</hi> of those times) came not only with his <hi>Ostrogoths,</hi> and a drawn Sword to Crop this kind of <hi>Rump</hi> or <hi>Fag End</hi> of these Wild <hi>Peripatetics</hi> and <hi>Wanderers,</hi> but with a <hi>Title</hi> also; for <hi>that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was formally given him,</hi> (as <hi>Paulus Diaconus,</hi> and <note n="*" place="margin">De Occid. Imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rio lib 15.</note> 
               <hi>Sigonius</hi> mention) by <hi>Zeno</hi> the <hi>Eastern Emperour</hi>; who, (being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et a Living Member of that mighty <hi>Eagle,</hi> which once stretcht her Victorious Wings over the best Part of the habitable Earth)
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64306:7"/>
thought He had still, at least, the <hi>Advouzon</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>resentation</hi> to the <hi>West.</hi> The Fortune of this Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ial Man answer'd expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; nor can any body in few Words <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xpress fuller the <hi>Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> of his <hi>Arrival,</hi> than <hi>Heylin</hi> does, when he tells us, <note n="*" place="margin">Geog. Ital lib. 1.</note> 
               <hi>That He reduc'd</hi> Italy <hi>which before was the</hi> Thorough-Fare <hi>of the</hi> Barbarous Nations, <hi>and so</hi> disorder'd <hi>by the frequent</hi> Inundations <hi>of</hi> Lust <hi>and</hi> Rapine,<note place="margin">Theodori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>restores <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ness to</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ly</note> 
               <hi>to su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h a</hi> peaceable and settled Government, that they quite lost the Memory of their former Miseries.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>His glorious Recep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>on, and En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry into</hi> Rome.</note>The <hi>Entry</hi> also of this <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch</hi> into <hi>Rome,</hi> was correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the high Esteem the World had of him; for tho that <hi>City</hi> ever surpast all others in the glorious <hi>Reception</hi> of her great and Famous <hi>Commanders,</hi> ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> now (as the same <hi>Sigonius</hi> words it) <note n="*" place="margin">De Occid. Imp. lib. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Her Citizens did even out-do themselves</hi>; so that in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64306:7"/>
short, He was received with all the <hi>Acclamations and Applause that could possibly be exprest by Art as well as by the Passions of the Inhabitants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, <hi>Theodoric</hi> was a <hi>Goth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theodoric <hi>a Fri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd to all Honest Christians</hi>
               </note> and therefore the <hi>Pope</hi> and He were not of a <hi>Communion</hi>; but happening to be a Generous Prince, and declaring himself a <hi>Friend</hi> and <hi>Patron</hi> to every <hi>Honest Christian,</hi> all Peace and Concord ensued. Nor did his Actions and Words dif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, since in the very choice of his Officers and great <hi>Ministers</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> he considered not <hi>Parties,</hi> but the <hi>Merits</hi> of his Subjects; and so among others, sixt upon <hi>Boetius,</hi> notwithstanding his <hi>Education</hi> and known <hi>Zeal</hi> for the <hi>Roman Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Boetius</hi> was a Man (if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider the <hi>Antiquity of his House</hi>) equal to <hi>Rome</hi> her self,<note place="margin">Boetius's <hi>Quality &amp; Family.</hi>
               </note> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended also from <hi>Ancestors,</hi> not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64306:8"/>
inferior to any of her greatest <hi>Heroe's</hi>; for being a <hi>Manlius,</hi> he was of a prime <hi>Consular Family,</hi> and which is more, <hi>Heir</hi> to the Illustrious <hi>Marcus,</hi> who, by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving the <hi>Capitol, rescu'd</hi> not onl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Standard</hi> or <hi>Imperial <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nsign,</hi>
               <note place="margin">M M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us <hi>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ves the</hi> Standard, <hi>and</hi> Life <hi>of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t.</hi>
               </note> but <hi>sav'd</hi> the very <hi>Life</hi> it self of the <hi>Government.</hi> He had also the same Blood warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Charitable Breast, as ran in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Veins of the Renowned <hi>Torquatus</hi>;<note place="margin">Torquatus <hi>an E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emy to the Peoples Slav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y.</hi>
               </note> who tearing from the neck of his Conquer'd Enemy, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hain,</hi> or Emblem (tho of <hi>Gold</hi>) of the <hi>Servitude</hi> which his <hi>Countrey</hi> might have fallen un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, made himself by that Brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>Author,</hi> as it were, of a <hi>Magna Charta</hi>; shewing also all along the Passion he had for their <hi>Liberties</hi>; for Worthy Men, are ever truly Solicitous of their Fellow Subjects <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and still promoting (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out By-Ends) all their <hi>Iust
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64306:8"/>
Rights</hi> and <hi>Priviledges</hi> Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</p>
            <p>'Twere endless to repeat the <hi>Benef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t,</hi> which the whole <hi>World</hi> (being at last in a manner sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to this Triumphant <hi>City</hi>) must needs receive by the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample</hi> and <hi>Conduct</hi> of this thrice <hi>Noble Clan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Strict Paternal Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice.</hi>
               </note> that did Justice even upon it self, by cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tising a <hi>Child</hi> who preferr'd (as <note n="*" place="margin">Lib. 1. Dec. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Livy</hi> shows) the <hi>Capricios</hi> of his own <hi>Humour</hi> before <hi>Authority.</hi> A <hi>Great</hi> and a <hi>Roman</hi> Action it was; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing our modern <hi>Romanists</hi> (in their <hi>Brags</hi>) pretend to it,<note place="margin">Popish <hi>Brags.</hi>
               </note> as boasting they are all, not only <hi>Obedient</hi> (as far as <hi>God</hi> Commands) to their <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Governours,</hi> but that their said <hi>Governours</hi> are as <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect</hi> and as <hi>Severe</hi> too, against the <hi>Fanatical Illuminati,</hi> or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to <hi>Shams</hi> and <hi>Miracles</hi> among themselves, as against those, they term <hi>Aliens,</hi> and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64306:9"/>
out of the <hi>Houshold</hi> of <hi>Faith.</hi> This <hi>Manlian Impartiality</hi> (which is cry'd up by several <hi>Antient Authors</hi>) pleases <hi>Florus</hi> so well, that he says, <note n="*" place="margin">Flor. lib. 1. cap. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Quis Hostem mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabitur,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Who could wonder, that</hi> Rome's <hi>Enemies should yield, when she had such Generals?</hi> Nay, <hi>Livy</hi> in the 9<hi>th.</hi> of his 1<hi>st. Decad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> represents the said strict <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ther,</hi> as a <hi>Captain, That would have given check to</hi> Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r <hi>himself had his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ourse been</hi> W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>stward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Man able, it seems, to stop that Progress, which <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty</hi> and sudden <hi>Accidents</hi> still bring upon an <hi>amaz'd</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinking</hi> People.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Boetius's <hi>Virtues.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Boetius</hi> being thus supereminent by the <hi>Antiquity, Fortitude,</hi> and <hi>Conduct</hi> of his <hi>Family</hi>; no body can deem it strange, his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonal <hi>Virtues</hi> were transcendent; for he was, as all <hi>Writers</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ess, <hi>Wise</hi> like an Oracle; <hi>Skill'd</hi> (as another <hi>Moses</hi>) in all the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64306:9"/>
               <hi>Learning of the</hi> Egyptians; and of a <hi>Piety</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng a sincere <hi>Professor</hi> of the <hi>Holy Gospel.</hi> His <hi>Rhetoric</hi> was also of a piece, with his other <hi>Sciences,</hi> so that the <hi>Senate</hi> chose him, of all her <hi>Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Members,</hi> to Complement the <hi>King</hi> in a set <hi>Oration</hi> at his <hi>Arrival</hi>; which (tho it be lost) is excellent, we are sure, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his <hi>Composition,</hi> and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially since it brought him into his <hi>Sovereigns</hi> good <hi>Graces,</hi> who soon afterwards found out his many and Matchless <hi>Qualities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theodoric</hi> (as I said) was a <hi>Christian Prince,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ric's <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to the Church.</hi>
               </note> of a <hi>healing Temper</hi>; and knowing besides, that at the <hi>Long Run,</hi> the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> still loses by <hi>Iarrs</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> steer'd on a contrary <hi>Rhumb</hi> to the malicious JU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAN; for instead of <hi>putting Altar against Altar,</hi> (as was the Custom of that <hi>Hater</hi> of the <hi>Christian Name</hi>) <hi>he compos'd
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64306:10"/>
even the</hi> Papal Schism <hi>of</hi> Symma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus <hi>and</hi> Laurentius, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may be seen in <note n="*" place="margin">An. 498. vit. Sym.</note> 
               <hi>Anastasius, Bib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecarius,</hi> and others; which plainly shows, <hi>That a gallant and well meaning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rince, may</hi> (<hi>not only in</hi> Italy, <hi>and</hi> Scotland, <hi>but in</hi> England <hi>also</hi>) <hi>deserve the Thanks of the Reverend Bishops and Clergy for his Patronage, tho he and they should chance to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in some Points of Faith.</hi> Neither did he acquiesce in this one <hi>Act,</hi> but heartily carest all the good <hi>Prelates</hi> who made appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to him: So that <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> Bishop of <hi>Pavia,</hi> and St. <hi>Laurence</hi> of <hi>Milan,</hi> coming as <hi>Intercessors</hi> for some of their <hi>Flock</hi> (who had contrary to the <hi>Edicts,</hi> Shelter'd several of the <hi>Heruli,</hi> or Inveterate <hi>Whigs</hi> of that Age) receiv'd particular <hi>Favour,</hi> and a very gracious <hi>Answer</hi> from him, as <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Baronius</hi> show, at large out of <hi>Ennodius.</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:64306:10"/>
And here we may further add, that he not only made this <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius,</hi> with <hi>Victor</hi> Bishop of <hi>Turin,</hi> his <hi>Embassadors</hi> to the <hi>Burgundian King</hi>; as the said <note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Authors</hi> have it, but constituted (as <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Holy Court, Life of</hi> Boetius, Sect. 4.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ausin</hi> relates) St. <hi>Severin</hi> his <hi>Almoner,</hi> to distribute mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney among the <hi>Poor,</hi> that had much suffered by the Quartering of his Army. Nay <note n="*" place="margin">An. 523. Vir. Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis.</note> 
               <hi>Anastasius</hi> owns him as a <hi>Benefactor and Bestower of rich Gifts on the</hi> Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tican <hi>it self.</hi> Nor was <hi>Theodoric</hi> any <hi>Laodicean</hi> or <hi>Luke-warm Prince,</hi> but on the contrary the great <hi>Defender</hi> of the <hi>Gothic Faith,</hi> as plainly appears by his Eager <hi>Declarations,</hi> as soon as this <hi>Emperour</hi> discountenanc'd that <hi>Religion</hi> in the <hi>East.</hi> Thus then we still see, <hi>That the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences in Worship do not always alienate a Monarchs Heart from his dissenting Ecclesiastics, and consequently, that a Princely and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64306:11"/>
Magnanimous Subject may retain a Tenderness for his Fellows, even when they ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not of his Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Opinion in Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Boetius,</hi> (as I hinted) being now known,<note place="margin">Boetius <hi>much Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd by</hi> Theodoric.</note> was presently high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honour'd, and all the Trust impos'd in Him, that a Knowing <hi>King</hi> usually p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts in a Wise aud Faithful <hi>Minister.</hi> The business of <hi>State</hi> too prospering not a little (as seldom it miscarries in good hands) <hi>Theodoric</hi> increast even his Esteem of him, and therefore gave daily fresh marks of his Royal Munificense and Bounty, as may be amply seen in <note n="*" place="margin">Sect. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Causinus.</hi> But what is du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in this fleeting World, where often <hi>Mistakes,</hi> but oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>Envy</hi> ruins? <hi>Envy</hi> is of the <hi>Bastard</hi> line, <hi>Emulation,</hi> that Spur to <hi>Virtue,</hi> being the <hi>Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate</hi>; nor goes she ever alone, as having <hi>Malice</hi> and <hi>Cruelty</hi> still
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64306:11"/>
about her, for her chief Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and Councellors. These were the Furies that vow'd the imcomparable <hi>Boetius</hi>'s Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw,<note n="*" place="margin">Boetius's <hi>Enemies.</hi>
               </note> and therefore presently distill'd their venom into the susceptible minds of <hi>Triguilla</hi> and <hi>Conigastus,</hi> two Eminent <hi>Goths,</hi> and the first of them in high Favour with the <hi>King</hi>; for he was <hi>Praepositus Regiae Domus,</hi> as the said <note n="*" place="margin">De Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sol. lib. 1. Prosa. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Boetius</hi> himself stiles him, to wit, <hi>Superintendent of his Royal House and Expence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Twas now according to <note n="*" place="margin">Lib. 16. <hi>The Storm begins in the</hi> Thirti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>of the Kings Reign.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sigonius,</hi> the year 525. which <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius</hi> precisely calls the <hi>Thirti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> of <hi>Theodoric's</hi> (yet Quiet and Flourishing) <hi>Reign,</hi> when the black <hi>Cloud</hi> began to gather, and becoming at last a mighty Storm, it brought Ruin along with it, to the <hi>Innocent,</hi> and no little Trouble even to the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:64306:12"/>'Twas in this year also when the <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>Potent Iustin</hi> (and <hi>Princes</hi> of that <hi>Calibre</hi> prove ever by the <hi>Vmbrages</hi> they give, uneasie to their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours) made his <hi>Edicts</hi> (as <note n="*" place="margin">An. 523. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Baronius</hi> writes) against the <hi>Manichaeans, Pagans</hi> and some other <hi>Dissenters</hi> in his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; which doubtless soon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm'd the <hi>Italian Goths</hi>; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ever sollicitous for their <hi>Brethren</hi> there,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Goths <hi>apprehend a Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution in the</hi> East.</note> (as may be seen in <hi>Theodoric</hi>'s <hi>Negotiations</hi> with the <hi>Emperour</hi>) they could not but apprehend, that the Laws would in conclusion reach their said <hi>Brethren</hi>; and so <hi>de facto</hi> it happen'd the very following year.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Boetius <hi>accus'd.</hi>
               </note>These <hi>accidents</hi> prepossessing not a few, and with them <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doric</hi> also, <hi>Triguilla</hi> resolv'd to strike while the Iron was hot; for he was often piqu'd by <hi>Boe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, who severely</hi> (as his own <note n="*" place="margin">Prosa. 4. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:64306:12"/>
show) <hi>reprehended him for several ill practices</hi>; and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, according to <hi>Causinus for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vising the forcing the</hi> Campanians, <hi>in a scarce and wanting year, to sell all their Corn at a low rate, for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Army:</hi> an Oppressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the very <hi>Senate</hi> (that ever wish'd its Disbanding) might perchance resent, and consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly punish to purpose. He went therefore, with <hi>Conigastus,</hi> to the <hi>King,</hi> and after many Preambles (to be sure) of the great <hi>vigilance</hi> and <hi>care</hi> of his <hi>Majesties safety,</hi> they told him of <hi>a mighty</hi> PLOT <hi>against his Sacred Person and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi>; adding, that <note n="*" place="margin">Prosa. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Boetius stifled the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iscovery</hi>; Nay, that he was also in truth, the grand <hi>Projector</hi> and <hi>Architect. Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doric</hi> seem'd greatly surpriz'd at the <hi>Thing,</hi> but much more at the <hi>Author,</hi> who had in so many <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards,</hi> and in so many <hi>Accidents,</hi> still shown the utmost <hi>Loyalty</hi> of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64306:13"/>
a <hi>Subject.</hi> After some pauses, and that he was a little recovered, they assured him there was no room for doubting, since they had no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> only intercepted his <hi>Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Letters,</hi> but that some of his <hi>Partizans</hi> had already discover'd the whole Scheme of the <hi>Design.</hi> Thereupon they acquainted him (as <note n="*" place="margin">Sect. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Causinus mentions</hi>) <hi>that the</hi> Pope <hi>and the</hi> Emperour <hi>were in it also</hi>; and then, producing the forg'd, or <hi>false Letters,</hi> as <note n="*" place="margin">Lib. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Sigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> truly terms them, they call'd in their <hi>Witnesses</hi>; who being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin'd by <hi>Theodoric,</hi> alienated him in the end so far from <hi>Boeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> that, summoning the <hi>Senate,</hi> and acquainting them with the <hi>Plot,</hi> they took forthwith cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of that unexpected and strange Affair.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:64306:13"/>
               <hi>OPilio</hi> and <hi>BAsilius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The names of the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusers.</hi>
               </note> (as <note n="*" place="margin">Prosa. 4. lib. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Boetius</hi> himself records) were the <hi>Names</hi> of the chief Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusers; Names famous among the <hi>Antients,</hi> for their <hi>Testimony</hi> against this Renowned <hi>Person</hi>; and worthy to be considered al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, by those Learned <hi>Caballists</hi> of our Age, who Prying into the <hi>Arcana</hi> of the <hi>Alphabet,</hi> dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover often (Men say) Strange Misteries, even out of the <hi>first Letters</hi> of an <hi>Appellation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This dreadful <hi>News</hi> being once spread about the City,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The King's Evidence<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> carest.</hi>
               </note> who can doubt but <hi>the King's Evidence</hi> were universally applauded and carest, especially the <hi>Accusation</hi> being, as Affairs then stood, like <hi>Manna,</hi> relishing in every Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. For many through their <hi>innate Loyalty,</hi> could not but be exasperated to the utmost, at the meer Relation of <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ric</hi>'s
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64306:14"/>
Danger. Others were sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely concern'd about <hi>Religion,</hi> the late mention'd <hi>Iealousies</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing also not a little to their Distemper. Some again had such Chymerical <hi>Idoeas</hi> of <hi>Forfitures</hi> and <hi>Confiscations</hi> in their Heads, that no body is to wonder if they joyn'd in the <hi>common <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry,</hi> and <hi>Belief</hi>; Interest having often an Influence, we know, upon the best and justest Balance. There were also great <hi>Ministers</hi> of <hi>State</hi> we see, as <hi>Triguilla</hi> and his <hi>As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sociats,</hi> who satisfy'd thus not only their privat <hi>Revenge,</hi> but hop'd to start perchance a <hi>New Hare,</hi> to amuse and divert the <hi>Senate,</hi> from reflecting on their ill <hi>Conduct</hi> and <hi>Managery.</hi> But who can we in all reason imagin so transported at the <hi>King's</hi> fam'd <hi>Escape,</hi> as the <hi>pardon'd</hi> and <hi>late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Indemnifi'd Heruli,</hi> who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sooth in outward Profession, were of the <hi>Gothic Religion,</hi> as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64306:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <note n="*" place="margin">5 Secul. pag. 369.</note> 
               <hi>Gualterus</hi> shows, and being always we may be sure, on the catch (having according to <note n="*" place="margin">An. 494. 32.</note> 
               <hi>Baronius</hi> no small <hi>Party</hi> in the <hi>Kingdom</hi>) could not but <hi>Doate</hi> on his <hi>Royal Person,</hi> with a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>True Protestant</hi> Zeal and Passion.</p>
            <p>This Accident therefore put certainly that <hi>dutiful Party</hi> a-Gog;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Ioy of the</hi> Heruli</note> for what <hi>Prerogative,</hi> what <hi>Heir</hi> or <hi>faithful Subject</hi> to the <hi>Crown,</hi> cou'd now, they thought, stand the shock, when the vey noise of the Danger of <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> was able to ruin and defeat all Opposition. Nay supposing a <hi>Plot,</hi> it would seem (they well knew) an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ice,</hi> not to run down every body of the <hi>Popes Communio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>: So that at length no <hi>Loyal</hi> nor <hi>Envy'd Goths</hi> should escape their hands, since (besides the Power and Effect of down-right Lies) any <hi>ordinary Alliance,</hi> any <hi>casual
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64306:15"/>
Conversation,</hi> or any <hi>Neighbourly courtesie,</hi> done to a <hi>Romanist,</hi> would be ground enough of <hi>Clamour</hi>; a <hi>Monster</hi> not to be resisted, when once the Multitude, are throughly heated and enraged.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us <hi>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the</hi> Senate.</note>Thus then (according to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll-probable Conjecture by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misses) stood the People gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally affected, (every body speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and none hearing) when <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etius</hi>'s Affair was brought into the <hi>Senate</hi>; Nor cou'd <hi>Magic</hi> now, or any unlawful <hi>Science</hi> be needful to find the success of it; for (as <note n="*" place="margin">Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Causinus</hi> to this effect asserts) <hi>Part of the Members of that great Assembly, fearing to be deem'd Accomplices: Others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mortal Enemies to the Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and the Rest following the Violence of the Stream and Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, all of them unanimously</hi> vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him <hi>Guilty,</hi> notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Experience</hi> they had of his unparalled <hi>Integrity,</hi> and the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64306:15"/>
insurmontable <hi>Objections</hi> against the <hi>Witnesses.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For first as to <hi>Opilio</hi> (tho I cannot positively say) that having <hi>Perjuriously</hi> accused others,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>What the Witne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</hi>
               </note> He got out of <hi>Prison,</hi> and so to a foreign <hi>Convent</hi> or <hi>Religious House,</hi> yet <note n="*" place="margin">Prosa. 4. lib. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Boetius</hi> assures us, <hi>That he fled (after many Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeds) to the very Horns of the Altar for</hi> Sanctuary, and <hi>so Stole from</hi> Ravenna <hi>to avoid a Brand or Rogues Mark in his Fore-head, which otherwise he was to undergo.</hi> In the next place as for <hi>Basilius,</hi> the same unquestionable <hi>Author</hi> declares, <note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>That he was hunted for his Villanies from Court, being also over-loaden'd with many Debts.</hi> Nay who can tell (if all Particulars had been examin'd and known) but he might have then been <hi>Starving</hi> in their <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shalsea,</hi> or Common <hi>Prison,</hi> even when the said <hi>Boetius</hi> and his <hi>Party,</hi> were pretended to be most
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64306:16"/>
Buisy, and consequently (besides the <hi>Fear</hi> of him) to have stood in the greatest <hi>need</hi> of his <hi>Help</hi> and <hi>Service.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Boetius <hi>sent to Prison.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Boetius</hi> being (as I mention'd) found <hi>Guilty,</hi> was presently sent to a close Prison at <hi>Pavia,</hi> his Virtuous <hi>Lady</hi> (according to <note n="*" place="margin">Sect. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Causin</hi>) <hi>getting only the Liberty of bidding him Adieu.</hi> But never did he in the whole Course of his Life (after he had once dry'd up the Tears caused by so unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected an Accident;) enjoy himself more than in that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finement; for here he made his near <hi>Approches</hi> to his <hi>Creator</hi>; Here he <hi>Storm'd</hi> Heaven, and <hi>took it by Violence</hi>; and here also, in imitation of <hi>Cicero</hi> (who wrote of the <hi>Immortality of the Soul,</hi> upon the loss of his beloved <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi>) did he compose, as <note n="*" place="margin">Vit. Boet.</note> 
               <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianus</hi> observes in his Life, that famous Treatise, <hi>De Consolatione Philosophiae</hi>; a Book which
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64306:16"/>
shew'd the <hi>Heathen</hi> with what Transcendency and Charms<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality</hi> could appear, when it once had the Advantage of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian</hi> Dress, and which also dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers his own great <hi>Innocence</hi> and Candor; a <hi>grand cause of his Writing it,</hi> as the said <hi>Martianus</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ibid. <hi>His Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints.</hi>
               </note> declare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se</hi> we see was <hi>Hard</hi> from the beginning, to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd; but of all the Particulars none seem'd <hi>harder</hi> to him, than these that follow; for speaking of the <hi>pretended Letters,</hi> and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of the other Accusati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, He uses these Words <note n="*" place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>osa. 4. lib. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Fraus aperta p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tnisset, si nobis ipsorum Confessione. Delatorum (quod in omnibus Negotiis maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas vires habet) uti licuisset.</hi> The meaning of which is; That could he have gotten <hi>Copies</hi> of his <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusers first Narratives, Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Depositions,</hi> and such like <hi>Confessions,</hi> and <hi>Liberty to use
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64306:17"/>
them, he would</hi> (by that mos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Killing</hi> and <hi>convincing</hi> Evidences <hi>have made their Fraud and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury Manifest.</hi> Then in the close of this <hi>Section</hi> or <hi>Paragraph</hi> He cries out. <note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Videre autem videor nefarias Sceleratorum Officinas Gaudio, Laetitia<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fluitantes; Perditissimum quem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> novis De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationum Fraudibus imminentem; jacere Bonos nostri Discriminis terrore prostratos; Flagitiosum quem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad audendum Facinus Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punitate, ad efficiendum vero Praemiis incitari.</hi> That is to say (considering the Premisses) He could as it were <hi>see</hi> from his very Prison (so many hundred of Miles from <hi>Rome</hi>) how the <hi>Nefarious</hi> and <hi>Profligate</hi> Triumpht, how every <hi>Miscreant,</hi> stood racking his Fancy; for some new Project or other to accuse, <hi>i. e.</hi> how to be a <hi>Principle,</hi> or at least some <hi>Collateral</hi> and <hi>By-Witness.</hi> Again, <hi>He saw how Good Men were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64306:17"/>
and dismay'd at the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of his hard chance</hi>; and last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lagitious</hi> were incited by <hi>Impunity</hi> to <hi>dare at Villanies,</hi> and then by <hi>Rewards</hi> to <hi>effect them.</hi> These are some of his <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Enemies having now (as they thought) gain'd the point,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains by the People.</hi>
               </note> glory'd not a little in it; but presently they felt themselves at a stand, and uneasie; for time set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the <hi>passions</hi> of the giddy <hi>Mobile,</hi> the <hi>Artifices</hi> of <hi>Grandees,</hi> with the <hi>quality</hi> and <hi>contradictions</hi> of the <hi>Witnesses,</hi> began to be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally consider'd and talk'd of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cyprianus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyprianus <hi>Forger of the</hi> Interce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note> a Fellow as villanous in his <hi>Pen,</hi> as <hi>Tongue,</hi> (but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Clergy</hi> or <hi>Laity,</hi> Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is silent) was now own'd, as <note n="*" place="margin">Sect. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Causin</hi> says, <hi>to be the Forger of the Letters:</hi> Nor do <hi>Authors</hi> menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n how they came to be interce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted; therefore, in all probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, being directed to <hi>Boetius</hi> by
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64306:18"/>
the <hi>Conspirators,</hi> they privately gave notice that such things were upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d,</hi> and so they were taken by <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thority,</hi> in the hands of the <hi>common Post,</hi> or <hi>Messen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The King m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>v'd to or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der</hi> Boeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us's <hi>Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </note>These <hi>free</hi> and <hi>public discourses</hi> of the people, creating in <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ypria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus</hi> and his <hi>Partizans</hi> much trouble, they by their <hi>Patrons</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taqu'd the <hi>King</hi>; telling him no doubt, That his <hi>Evidence,</hi> or <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses,</hi> must, by this Clemency, be either <hi>vilified</hi> and <hi>disbelieved</hi>; or that he himself would be dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Vnjust,</hi> or, at least, negligent of his own, and his <hi>Subjects</hi> Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; For, if <hi>Boetius</hi> were <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi> why should he be a <hi>Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner?</hi> If <hi>Guilty,</hi> why not <hi>Executed</hi> as a <hi>Traytor?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>His life of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Theodoric</hi> upon this presently dispatch'd an <hi>Officer,</hi> to examine <hi>Boetius</hi> further, and to assure him, (as <note n="*" place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Causin</hi> expresly says) <hi>That he should find favour, would he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64306:18"/>
the particulars of the Fact al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd against him; If not, he was to prepare himself forthwith to die.</hi> But what thing in the world can we conceive able to elevate and transport the over-joy'd <hi>Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> like this <hi>Message!</hi> For no soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was it brought him, but, stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as it were on Tip-toes, and exulting in his unexpected good fortune, he look'd upon himself now in a much happier state, than in his former <hi>Prosperity</hi>; When, <hi>after three</hi> Consulships, <hi>and the sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Tryumph of his two Sons, he was seated between them</hi> (as all Authors have it) <hi>in the open</hi> Theatre, <hi>to receive the applause and salutation of the people.</hi> He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore desired the King's <hi>Officer</hi> to tell his <hi>Majesty, * T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at his</hi> Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <hi>and</hi> Age <hi>were above</hi> Threats <hi>and</hi> Allurements; <hi>That there ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver having been a</hi> Plot, <hi>he could not tell him the</hi> Particulars; <hi>That he did infinitely rejoyce, that they now
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64306:19"/>
began to know his</hi> Accusers <hi>so well, as to need</hi> his Confirmation <hi>of</hi> their Testimony. Then, making a <hi>Recapitulation</hi> of their <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Practices,</hi> he declar'd he was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for <hi>Death,</hi> as having long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected and desir'd that <hi>happy day.</hi> So that, being carried not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the <hi>place</hi> of <hi>Execution,</hi> and behaving himself there with the wonted <hi>Gallantry</hi> of a <hi>Roman,</hi> and the real <hi>Piety</hi> of a <hi>Christian,</hi> he had his <hi>Head sever'd from his shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>He is behea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Thus fell <hi>Boetius,</hi> Glorious in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and Honour'd here on <hi>Earth,</hi> by all that ever read his <hi>story,</hi> as appears by the <hi>Dystic</hi> and <hi>Epigraphie</hi> on his <hi>Tomb,</hi> which <hi>Martianus</hi> has (with other <hi>Verses</hi>) in his praise, recommended to Posterity.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>His Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taph.</hi>
               </note>
               <q>
                  <l>Ecce <hi>Boethus</hi> adest in Caelo mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, &amp; omni</l>
                  <l>Perspectus mundo, mirus haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus homo.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:64306:19"/>Lo! here entomb'd does Great <hi>Boetius</hi> lie;</l>
                  <l>Great, when on Earth; now Greater, in the Sky.</l>
               </q>
Nor did the <hi>Ancients</hi> stile him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise than a <hi>Martyr,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>He is estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, <hi>and why.</hi>
               </note> as being not only put to death <hi>Vnjustly</hi>; that is to say, in the <hi>Scripture</hi> phrase, <hi>Propter Iustitiam,</hi> for <hi>Righteousness-sake</hi>; as also, in <hi>Odium Fidei upon the account of the hatred his Enemies bore to his Religion</hi>; but becau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e he suffer'd (<hi>when they once offer'd him his life</hi>) for that grand <hi>Commandment,</hi>
               <q>Thou shalt not bear False Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness against thy Neeghhour.</q>
Let us then now conclude with the <hi>Wise man</hi>'s saying;<note n="*" place="margin">Eccl. 1. 9</note> 
               <hi>The thing that hath been, is that which shall be; and that which is done, is that which shall be done; and</hi> THERE IS NO NEW THING UNDER THE SUN.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="polemical_treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:64306:20"/>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:64306:20"/>THe story of <hi>Boetius</hi> being ended, we will now consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a little the silly malice of our <hi>Narrative-monger,</hi> or <hi>Dwarf</hi> in wit; <hi>Dwarfs</hi> every body knows are still great <hi>Tale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellers</hi> in the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t Classic and Authentic Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of <hi>Chivalry</hi>; I say, we will a little consider his silly malice, having acted here the part of some <hi>Witnesses</hi> (since the landing of <hi>Brute</hi>) who, to serve (as they thought) a prsent turn, swear not only what clashes and interferes with several branches of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Evidence,</hi> but what plainly ruins their whole project and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign.</p>
            <p>Thus does this happy <hi>Writer</hi> make, by his foolish Illation, a <hi>Rod</hi> for himself and friends; For, were His <hi>R. Highness</hi> a <hi>Papist,</hi> and therefore to be prosecuted for deserting the <hi>Religion</hi> of His <hi>late Ancestors</hi> now established by
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64306:21"/>
Law: How can this same Writer, I say, with his <hi>Apostate</hi> Brethren, avoid ruine and destruction also? unless by the vile and damnable practice they use, even that of the <hi>Simonians, Adamites,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Old</hi> Troublers of <hi>Christian unity,</hi> who in former times <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied,</hi> as the <hi>Spanish</hi> and <hi>Portugal Iews</hi> still do, with all Laws en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenching on their <hi>Advantage,</hi> though never so opposite to their real <hi>Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ession,</hi> and Belief. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, this <hi>Doctri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> highly vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates the <hi>Papists</hi> in the beginning of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> and even the worst of their <hi>Actions</hi> here in <hi>England,</hi> and what continually they are hitten in the teeth with; I mean Qu. <hi>Maries Tragical and Bloudy Scene.</hi> For, if every body that <hi>peacably</hi> and <hi>modestly</hi> differs from the <hi>Religion</hi> of a <hi>Nation</hi> out of <hi>conscience,</hi> must be presently deem'd a <hi>Iulian,</hi> and one that deserves not to breathe: why
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:64306:21"/>
should the <hi>Squire</hi> and his <hi>turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Tribe</hi> blame the proceedure of that unhappy <hi>Princess,</hi> who only according to <hi>Law,</hi> Punish't those that had (in the <hi>Popish</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alect) <hi>Apostatiz'd from the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of their Ancestors</hi>; and from a <hi>Religion</hi> too warranted and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriz'd (as the <hi>Queen</hi> verily thought) even by <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Holy Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But our <hi>Author</hi> is not conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with collaterally <hi>blanching</hi> and <hi>defending</hi> in this manner <hi>Popery</hi>; but quotes even the <hi>Preamble of an Act</hi> then made, which says; <note n="*" place="margin">J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lian's <hi>Life,</hi> p. 96.</note>
               <q>That the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants,</hi> did out of their <hi>Malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Stomacks</hi> Pray against the <hi>Queen's Majesty, That God would turn her Heart from Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry to the true Faith, or shor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten her days, or take her quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of the Way.</hi> A <hi>Prayer</hi> (as the <hi>Act</hi> further urges) ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of, or read to have
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64306:22"/>
been us'd by any <hi>good Christian,</hi> against any <hi>Prince,</hi> tho a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan</hi> or an <hi>Infidel.</hi>
               </q>
Now what can <hi>Papists</hi> say more for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves? Nay, do's not their <note n="*" place="margin">V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,</hi> p. 195</note> 
               <hi>Apologist</hi> urge this very unruly proceedure of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>stants,</hi> as the Cause (among such other pieces of <hi>Zeal</hi>) that made the <hi>Queen</hi> so severe, and consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recal that <hi>Toleration,</hi> which she had <hi>granted</hi> during the two <hi>first years</hi> of her <hi>Reign.</hi> Nor has our <hi>Religious ESQVIRE</hi> any other inference from this <hi>Villai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Citation,</hi> but to tell us to this effect; <note n="*" place="margin">Jul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'s <hi>Life,</hi> p. 98</note> 
               <hi>That the</hi> Popish Parliament <hi>was blinded, and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken; The</hi> Primit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve Christians <hi>not being for</hi> If's <hi>and</hi> Ands, <hi>but for IVLIAN</hi>'s <hi>downright Destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi> So that first here is a <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal</hi> and a <hi>Lie</hi> too cast upon <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity</hi> in general; for no Man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver publickly Pray'd for the <hi>Emperours Death,</hi> but only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:64306:22"/>
               <hi>the Psalms against</hi> Idols <hi>and</hi> Idol-makers, <hi>desiring God to Iudge his own Cause, to remember his Vine, the Wild Boar,</hi> &amp;c. as all sorts of <hi>Iews</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hristians</hi> do, when they suffer <hi>Persecution</hi> and <hi>Trouble.</hi> And secondly, Here is a vindication of <hi>Bonner,</hi> and the <hi>Laws</hi> then in being; <hi>so that he willfully Stab's FOX under the fifth Rib, and with one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uff Blow's up his friend CARE and all his Works</hi>: For whereas a <hi>Papist</hi> (when prest with that <hi>Bloodshed</hi>) used Commonly to say to his Antagonists; <hi>Pray Sirs break not my head with Stories of Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ks and Bulls, I a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>prove not the Transactions you mention, were all true that is Writen</hi>; Now we shall have the very same <hi>Papist</hi> (after reading our wise SQUIR<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) make this pert addi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion, to his former Harangue; <hi>But Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, If you will have me further speak, I refer my self to the Tale-Teller
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:64306:23"/>
and the worst of his Gang, and let them tell you, whither any Magistrate in</hi> England <hi>would spare me, or any good Man pity my Sufferings, Should I Pray to God, To make the King a</hi> Papist, <hi>or else to take him presently out of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the same manner has Old <hi>Hickeringili</hi> (that <hi>Babe of Grace,</hi> that <hi>Neophyte,</hi> or <hi>young Convert</hi>) in the very last Leaf of his <hi>Black Nonconformist</hi> (to have it the more in view and remember'd) belsh't out the ranckestand most dangerous <hi>Notion,</hi> that ever <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery</hi> vented against the <hi>Protestant Religion</hi>; just as if <hi>F. Parsons</hi> or some other <hi>Notable Iesuit</hi> had had the guidance of his very Pen. His words are these:
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Black Non-Conf. Pos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>scrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note>
               <q>Well, this I'll say for the <hi>Pope,</hi> and a fig for him; (for we ought to give the <hi>Devil</hi> his due, much more the <hi>Arch-Bishop of all Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops,</hi> the <hi>Pope.</hi>) I say, give him
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:64306:23"/>
his due, <hi>he builds the fabric of his Ecclesiastical policy rationally,</hi> if the <hi>foundation</hi> were true; But <hi>Protestants</hi> do not, <hi>that confess Themselves and their Churches fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>il,</hi> as does the Church of <hi>England</hi> in her 19<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 
                  <hi>Article.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now, what is the plain <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish</hi> of all this? Is not his inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion first to make all our <hi>Prelates Pen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ioners</hi> to the <hi>Pope,</hi> and <hi>Birds of a feather?</hi> So that, by still ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>Odium,</hi> (and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Procession of the <hi>Bishops</hi> with his <hi>Holyness</hi>'s <hi>Pageant</hi> was design'd for it) he hopes the <hi>True Protestants</hi> will be no longer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with the bare <hi>wounding my Lord of</hi> Chichester's <hi>Coach-hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> (as they have done) but burn the whole <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> when their <hi>Head,</hi> the ARCH-BISHOP of all BISHOPS, as he maliciously stiles him, is next condemn'd to a <hi>Bone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire</hi> at <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> or in <hi>Smith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:64306:24"/>In the next place, how will a <hi>Papist</hi> chuckle and crow at the asse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ion; it being what the <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmines,</hi> the <hi>Baronius's,</hi> the <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natians,</hi> and the rest of their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test <hi>Hect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs</hi> have ever aim'd at. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he one side, the <hi>Church of England</hi> is render'd by him to be a <hi>pitiful, silly thing,</hi> and no more to be heeded or minded, than an old woman's <hi>chat,</hi> or <hi>tattle</hi>; and on the other side, the <hi>Pope,</hi> and his <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reatures,</hi> are applauded as <hi>excellent Architects, rational in their fabric,</hi> and in fine what not? only, out of fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m sake, (for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise he would be hang'd for <hi>a down-right Papist</hi>) he doubts, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sooth, whether the <hi>foundation</hi> be so firm and solid as it should be. So that still (without the trouble of breaking ground, and intrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.) he gives a subtle Priest the <hi>Counterscarp</hi> at a dash; I mean, he puts him (without more ado, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the desirable and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ushious To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pic
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:64306:24"/>
of the CHURCH, a <hi>Notion,</hi> which he continually dreams on, and is no sooner started, but he runs division without end; as the famous <hi>Whitaker</hi> hints to the <hi>Iesuit Campian</hi> in these words: <note n="*" place="margin">Whit. cont. Durae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, p. 246</note> 
               <hi>Catholici vestri turbulentis alia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum disputationum procellis jactati, in isto Ecclesiae Portu libenter ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiescunt.</hi> This is the <hi>Recipe</hi> which every <hi>Papist</hi> makes so many brags of; which he offers to the <hi>Rich,</hi> and to the <hi>Poor</hi>; to the <hi>Scholar,</hi> and to the <hi>Fool.</hi> This is the <hi>Hook</hi> with which he catches your <hi>Bristows,</hi> your <hi>Bellassis,</hi> your <hi>Berkshires,</hi> and the rest of them; and this is the <hi>Bait</hi> which they lay for the great <hi>Dutchess,</hi> as well as for the low and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Chamber-maid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is not then this <hi>Conventicler</hi> (for I'll never own him a <hi>Minister of the Gospel</hi>) a rare Champion of the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> that shoots thus hand over head among them
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:64306:25"/>
he calls <hi>Protestants,</hi> even without any caution, or pre-arming them? But what will not blind malice do? or what will not a <hi>mad-man</hi> ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, who dares not only (as may be seen all along in his <hi>Scandalum magnatum</hi>) equal himself (tho' a mean <hi>Parson</hi>) to a <hi>Bishop of London</hi>; but represents himself so, that any body (that knows nothing but what the Libel says) must take him for a far better man than the <hi>Earl of Northampton</hi>'s <hi>Son</hi>; a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily</hi> not only <hi>Illustrious</hi> for the rank it has in the Catalogue of <hi>Peers,</hi> and of <hi>Note,</hi> as being a <hi>Compton:</hi> but to be honour'd &amp; esteem'd for the signal Loyalty of a <hi>Father,</hi> for those faithful and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent <hi>Sons; &amp; spes crescentis Iuli,</hi> for the hopes of a Grand-son, that may perchance out-vie that Noble and Great Subject, his <hi>Great-grand-father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Enough then of <hi>Hickeringill,</hi> an honest man one may swear
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:64306:25"/>
when, upon a Heady pique, he could presently herd himself with a Race of <hi>Animals,</hi> made <hi>blacker</hi> than <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iends</hi> in his own <note n="*" place="margin">vid. that Sermon.</note> 
               <hi>Curse ye Meroz</hi>; Enough, I say, now of honest <hi>Hick,</hi> who has yet this excuse left for himself and Mr. <hi>Iulian,</hi> that several <hi>True Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants,</hi> long before them, have, in their very <hi>Hue</hi>'s and <hi>Cry</hi>'s against <hi>Popery,</hi> zealously taught their Flock the horridest Tenets which they brand any of the <hi>Red-letter'd Gallants</hi> with; as may be seen at large in the late <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Scotch-Declaration.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">vid. that large folio Declarat</note>
            </p>
            <p>Having therefore done with JULIAN's <hi>Life,</hi> and being come now to the Section of <hi>passive O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience</hi>: how can I with good manners pass by this <hi>Aphorism</hi> of that Primitive <hi>Saint,</hi> the <hi>True Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant</hi> Mr. <hi>Goodman,</hi> in his very <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 52</note> Treatise <hi>Of Obedience</hi>; For there he tells us in express terms, <hi>That altho'</hi> Popes, <hi>for sundry Enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:64306:26"/>
have deposed</hi> Kings <hi>by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul Authority; the reason yet that moved them so to do, was Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest, Iust, and meet to be received and executed by the body of every</hi> Commonwealth Is not this an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent way of <hi>destroying Babylon?</hi> And are not <hi>Papists</hi> like to repent, and be asham'd of the Principles and Actions laid to their charge, if this <hi>Puritan Divinity</hi> be true? But Mr. <hi>Iulian</hi> has out gone all his bold Predecessors many a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long; for he dares not only call St. <hi>Gregory</hi>'s counsel of <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Tears</hi> (in time of Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) <note n="*" place="margin">Julian's l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fe, page 95.</note> 
               <hi>Treason</hi>: but spends se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral pages against this following position; <note n="*" place="margin">ibid. pag 85.</note> 
               <hi>That the Gospel is a suffering Doctrine, and so far from being prejudicial to</hi> Caesar'<hi>s Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that it makes him the</hi> Minister of God; <hi>and commands all its</hi> Professors <hi>to give him, and all that are in Authority under him, their dues; and rather to</hi> die, <hi>than</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:64306:26"/>
               <hi>him by force.</hi> To which he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers, <hi>That, at this rate, under a P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pish Successor, the Lives of all Protestants shall ly at the Mercy of any Iustice of Peace</hi>; And then he runs on in his old gibbe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, to the very end of the Chapter.</p>
            <p>'Tis n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t my intention (as I mentio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed in the beginning) to answer him in all particulars, for that has been amply and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently done already; only now &amp; then I mmst take leave to shew you the <hi>Devil</hi> by his <hi>Claw,</hi> or <hi>clove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> foot,</hi> and consequently to let you see what a TRUE PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TESTANT is; to wit, <hi>One that cares not what he grants or what he deny's, so it conduces (in his poor Iudgment) to his private design; which is the destruction of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy.</hi> This shall make him therefore to paint JULIAN a <hi>Cherubin,</hi> or at least a <hi>Lamb,</hi> or very <hi>moderate Prince</hi>; on the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:64306:27"/>
other side to describe the <hi>Primitive Christians</hi> (especially the most fam'd for <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>) to be a Company or <hi>Legion</hi> of <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bean</hi> Coxcombs, or else more <hi>Factious</hi> and <hi>Rebellious</hi> than the <hi>Fallen Angels</hi>; This shall oblige him also to furnish the <hi>Papists</hi> (as has been shew'd) with <hi>Arms</hi> both <hi>Defencive</hi> and <hi>Offencive</hi>; ane this shall cause him, like a <hi>true Huntsman,</hi> to let the <hi>Hare</hi> (which with great eagerness and Crys he has long persu'd) get home to her <hi>Forme,</hi> that he may have (at a seasonable and Critical time) the advantage of another <hi>chase</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> And truely seeing I am talking of JULIAN, and of a <hi>True Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant,</hi> I must not pass by the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonet</hi> BLONDEL, who (to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute forsooth <hi>Purgatory,</hi> as his Adversary <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Cra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> against</hi> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ondel.</note> 
               <hi>Crasset</hi> shows) decry's the famous and long celebrated <hi>Prophesies</hi> of the SYBYLS as <hi>forged,</hi> making the most <hi>Ancient
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:64306:27"/>
Christians</hi> the <hi>Forgers,</hi> tho JU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAN himself, who sought all manner of means to disparage <hi>Christianity,</hi> never question'd the <hi>Books,</hi> nor taxt its <hi>professors</hi> with any Cheat.</p>
            <p>But now before I end with JULIAN, I must tell my <hi>Reader,</hi> that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Popish Writers</hi> have had the start of this his SQUIRE; for as he draws inferences from his <hi>Master</hi> against them, with by-blows (home to purpose) against the <hi>Church of England</hi>; so they have their <hi>Remarks</hi> too upon this famous Man, not very ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous I'l assure you to <hi>true Protestants.</hi> For whosoever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sults <hi>Gualterus,</hi> a <hi>Iesuit</hi> eminent for <hi>History,</hi> he shall find the four fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, and only <hi>Observations</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that <hi>Apostate</hi>; And by the way I must add this, that his drift all along is to make the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinian Doctrine</hi> to agree <hi>ad amussim,</hi> even to a hair with
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:64306:28"/>
some old condemn'd <hi>Heretic</hi> or <hi>Infidel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His first Note is, That <note n="*" place="margin">Tabula Chron. p. 300.</note> 
               <hi>IVLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AN was a</hi> Monk (for, you must know for his Security, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyd Suspicion he became one) <hi>and presently with his</hi> Coul, <hi>He left Christi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nity also.</hi> so that thus we may see, that SAINTS, who for their <hi>profit,</hi> and to <hi>serve a turn,</hi> can (contrary to their <hi>Iudgement</hi>) exteriourly comply with <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that Religion,</hi> will at the first <hi>advantageous</hi> opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not barely leave their <hi>Coul,</hi> that is to say, their <hi>Profession,</hi> but shake hands as we see (if it be more convenient for them) with <hi>Christianity,</hi> and all <hi>Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> too. His <hi>Second</hi> observa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion is;<note place="margin">2</note> 
               <hi>That as after IVLIAN</hi>'s <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postasie, He made himsely</hi> High Priest; <hi>so our</hi> Henry <hi>the</hi> VIII. <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his abandoning</hi> Popery, <hi>would be deem'd Head of the Church, a power his Successors</hi> (as he tells
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:64306:28"/>
us) <hi>still assume.</hi> Here then we find our <hi>Iesuit</hi> and a true <hi>Protestant</hi> (for all their noise and quarrel) to go hand in hand; the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and other <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries</hi> being as eager forsooth against the <hi>Supremacy</hi> as a <hi>Papist</hi>; Nor has Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> nor Mr. <hi>Luther</hi> been less Satyrical and Touchy in that Point, than the great <hi>Guy of Warwick,</hi> the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Bellarmin</hi> himself.<note place="margin">3 <hi>and</hi> 4.</note> His <hi>third</hi> and <hi>fourth Observations</hi> are, upon JULIAN's <hi>Calvinistical proceedure in pulling down</hi> Crosses, <hi>and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroying our</hi> SAVIOURS's <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffigies, even that miraculous Statue</hi> (<hi>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd by</hi> Eusebius) <hi>which the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that had the Issue of Bloud erected in his memory.</hi> Now how exactly the <hi>English</hi> JULIANS have imitated their <hi>Ancestors</hi> herein; We who have seen the late <hi>War,</hi> and felt the <hi>Plagues</hi> which accompany'd it, can to their eternal Honour abundantly Witness.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:64306:29"/>Nay, neither must, nor can we forget, how godly Sir <hi>W. Waller</hi> (a man <hi>Loyal</hi> in his <hi>Father, Loyal</hi> in <hi>Himself,</hi> and a great <hi>hater of Beads,</hi> (especially those that look like <hi>Pearl</hi>) publicly burnt the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Picture of Christ in the <hi>Palace yard,</hi> to the horrour of all <hi>good Protestants,</hi> the <hi>real,</hi> and not <hi>preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi> Children of the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Nor are we to wonder, that those who approv'd or gave a helping hand to such an action, should afterwards cut and slash His <hi>Royal Highness's Picture,</hi> or make so many desperate offers even at the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rown</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> Himself.</p>
            <p>Having done with this <hi>second Section</hi> (which shows us not only the <hi>Obedient Principles</hi> of Mr. <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> and his <hi>Fellows,</hi> but how still they promote <hi>Popery,</hi> by thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Arguments, Parallels,</hi> and <hi>In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences</hi>) we will now hasten to the <hi>Third</hi> and last, tho' he cannot be
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:64306:29"/>
but Victorious there, especially when I my self must already sing him an <hi>Io Poean.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Argument of the said <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> is, <hi>a Comparison between</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery <hi>and</hi> Paganism; and so let it be; Yet in Justice I must inform my <hi>Reader,</hi> that we are not one whit beholding to the <hi>Pilfering Squire</hi> for the <hi>Simile,</hi> seeing the <hi>Nation</hi> has had it long ago from <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. <hi>His Survey of</hi> Popery.</note> Dr. <hi>Sutcliffe,</hi> and many a <hi>grave Retailer</hi> since. In the next place, had I the faculty of Squabling; for I confess and declare—<hi>Timeo Danaos &amp; dona ferentes</hi>; I fear <hi>light</hi> it self, when 'tis convey'd to me by a <hi>Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> who under the shelter of the deepest <hi>Execrations</hi> and <hi>Oaths,</hi> and by the <hi>Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Stile of</hi> HAILE SOVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAIGN, <hi>Your most Dutiful, your most Obedient, and most Loyal Subjects,</hi> can lay hold on their <hi>Kings Sword</hi> or <hi>Milita,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Seise his <hi>Royal Person,</hi> and lastly
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:64306:30"/>
               <hi>Cut his Throat</hi>; I say had I a Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling faculty (and such <hi>Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banks</hi> afford sufficient matter) my Tongue and Hands are tied, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing still (as I did in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning) <hi>That I heartily pitie all the Errors of the</hi> Papists, <hi>and will never desend them therein</hi>; Tho' for their <hi>Loyalty,</hi> I think them in general very Eminent, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially those <hi>Gallant Men</hi> I knew, during the late <hi>Rebellion.</hi> Let then <hi>Paganism,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Calvino-T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ismus <hi>proves a true</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant <hi>a</hi> Turk.</note> TUR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CISM and all the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alse Doctrines</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> perish together; yet this must not hinder me from telling the SQUIRE to his Face, <hi>That 'tis better be a</hi> Papist <hi>then a</hi> true Protestant, <hi>for several rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, besides the formentioned brand of</hi> Mahometism. Therefore see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many of the <hi>Cabal</hi> have made mighty Complaints, and been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly angry forsooth with the <hi>Church of England</hi> for this Asser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, I think it very fit to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:64306:30"/>
and set down what <hi>She</hi> and <hi>her Loyal Children</hi> mean by it.</p>
            <p>But before I come to particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, I must premise this; That no body (I suppose thinks) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less we take <hi>Sectaries</hi> in a <hi>Lump,</hi> and together, but that the TRUE PROTESTANT, and a GOOD ONE, (I mean a <hi>Reform'd Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senter,</hi> and a <hi>Church of</hi> England <hi>Man</hi>) agree in more points of Faith, or differ openly in fewer, then do a <hi>good Protestant,</hi> and a <hi>Papist</hi>; from whence arises the fallacie and surprise; that seing this is so, How a <hi>good Protestant</hi> can assert a thing which puts him at such a Distance with a <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian, Independent,</hi> and the rest of the <hi>Godly Iuncto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I answer, that <hi>Iudaism</hi> and <hi>Gentilism</hi> differ'd in far more particulars from an <hi>Othodox Christian,</hi> than <hi>He</hi> from any of the first <hi>Hereties</hi>; Yet many of the <hi>Faithful Beleevers</hi> (in those
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:64306:31"/>
times, and why not since) had rather been <hi>Iews</hi> or <hi>Gentils</hi> (<hi>as more excusable at the last day</hi>) than <hi>Ebionits, Cerinthians,</hi> or e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pecially <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> so dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted by God in the <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 2. 15</note> 
               <hi>Apocalips.</hi> And here be pleased to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that a Man has no more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion to <hi>Popery,</hi> by making this <hi>declaration,</hi> than he has to be SHOT, because he had rather <hi>die so,</hi> than be HANG'D. This is the <hi>Scandal</hi> which the <hi>true Saints</hi> asperse a rational <hi>Axiom</hi> with; and I am sure in the late <hi>Rebellion</hi> both <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Independents</hi> did often use it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst each other, whilst they were discovering their mutual <hi>Nakedness</hi> and <hi>Villa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies.</hi> Besides <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ince every <hi>good Protestant,</hi> that stands in their way is <hi>Blackned</hi> by them with the odious name of <hi>Papist</hi>; what can be more pertinently urg'd (after he has given the <hi>Calumniators</hi> the lie by
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:64306:31"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>requenting the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments</hi>) than by thus asserting, <hi>That 'tis yet better be a</hi> Papist, <hi>than a Sectary or true</hi> Protestant (a NICKNAME of their own giving) for these, and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand other <hi>Reasons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. What Man had not rather (of the two) be of a <hi>Religion,</hi> which was once <hi>true</hi> according to the opinion of very good <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants</hi> (which seems to be ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Congratulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>That the</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 1.8.</note> Roman <hi>Faith was spoken of throughout the World</hi>) than of one that has been always <hi>false</hi> and <hi>troublesom.</hi> And if a Man must believe (to Sodder up the breaks and contradictions.) That all our opposit <hi>Sects</hi> (by uniting against the <hi>Government</hi>) have a <hi>saving Faith</hi>; He will I fear at his <hi>Deat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> say, <hi>Sit Anima mea cum Philosophis</hi>; I wish my <hi>Sou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> then, with <hi>Socrates, Plato, S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neca,</hi> and such like <hi>Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:64306:32"/>II. The <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to all <hi>good Protestants</hi> too) is a <hi>true Church,</hi> tho corrupt and diseas'd; for as a <hi>King</hi> remains a true one, notwithstand his ill administration; and a <hi>Man</hi> is still a <hi>Man</hi> tho <hi>Leprous,</hi> so this <hi>Church</hi> (they tell us) falls not by her <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrors</hi> from being a <hi>Church,</hi> or still having <hi>Iurisdiction.</hi> This made <hi>King Iames</hi> to call the <hi>Pope</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. <hi>His work,</hi> pag. 305.</note> 
               <hi>Patriarch of the West</hi>; and this is the reason why the <hi>Priesthood</hi> and <hi>Ordination</hi> of that <hi>See</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains good here; and why the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> draws thence her <hi>Succession</hi> and <hi>Descent</hi>; a thing zealously insisted upon by her learned <hi>Members,</hi> and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly by the smart and inquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Mr. <hi>Mason.</hi> Now the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Assembly</hi> (and much more that of the other <hi>Dissenters</hi>) is no <hi>Church</hi> at all, having no <hi>Bishop,</hi> and therefore no <hi>Ordination</hi> or <hi>Sacraments</hi>: Nay the <hi>Church</hi> of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:64306:32"/>
               <hi>England</hi> in her <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> p. 86.</note> 19th. <hi>Article</hi> defines <hi>the true Church</hi> to be, A <hi>Congregation of Faithful Men that have the Sacraments duly admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistred</hi>; So that the wilful loos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this <hi>Blessing</hi> is a <hi>Curse</hi> of the first Magnitude, depriving them that incurre it, of the very <hi>Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stick,</hi> at least of the inestimable benefit of our <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> which was instituted for our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freshment</hi> and <hi>Strength,</hi> and for the <hi>remembrance of his Passion till he comes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. What <hi>good Protestant</hi> would not sooner be of a <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> which converted us from <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganism,</hi> and left (as <note n="*" place="margin">Brit. p. 163.</note> 
               <hi>Cambden</hi> says) <hi>Many Monuments of Piety and Devotion, to the Honour of God, and the propagation of the Christian Faith</hi>; (And among these may be nam'd <hi>Churches, Bishoprics, Deaneries, Canonries, Colledges,</hi> &amp;c.) I say what <hi>good Protestant</hi> would not prefer such
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:64306:33"/>
a <hi>Religion</hi> to <hi>One</hi> which (instead of advancing the <hi>Christian Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship</hi>) has not only put us in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant <hi>broils,</hi> but profan'd and pull'd down the very <hi>Churches</hi> themselves; and which <hi>de fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to</hi> gobbled up and swallowed (without the least stop or Keck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) <hi>the Lands of the Prelates,</hi> and the other <hi>Ecclesiastical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours</hi>? Nor would the <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versities</hi> have stood two years longer, had not <hi>God</hi> by a Miracle restor'd His <hi>Majesty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV. To come even to <hi>down right</hi> Popery, and their most <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ightful <hi>Opinions</hi>; What <hi>good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>testant</hi> would not rather with a <hi>Lutheran</hi> and a <hi>Papist</hi> believe (if <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Choice</hi> can make a Man believe) <hi>That</hi> Christ <hi>is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally present after Consecration,</hi> than as <hi>Sectaries</hi> do, <hi>That the outward part or sign of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is still meer</hi> Bread <hi>&amp;</hi> Wine; a Tenet wholly opposit to our
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:64306:33"/>
very first <hi>Rudiments</hi> in <hi>Religion</hi>; for the public <hi>Catechism</hi> in the <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> declares and tells us, * <hi>That the Body and Bloud of</hi> Christ <hi>are verily and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed taken and received by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aithful in the Lords Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">V. Who had not rather <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate under one Kind,</hi> than not at all; for several of the <hi>true Protestants</hi> never do: Nay, in their very expressions they call the SACRAMENTS by the name of <hi>Beggerly Elements,</hi> and <hi>Formalities beneath the Sain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and Regenerate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">VI. Who would not rather say AMEN to <hi>Prayers in the China or Coptic Languages,</hi> where he is sure that the <hi>Bishops</hi> and other <hi>pious</hi> and <hi>wise Governours</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> fram'd them, than to the extemporary Vociferati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of every <hi>Enthusiast</hi>; to whom (as long experience has show'd us) <hi>Tautologie</hi> and <hi>Nonsence</hi> are
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:64306:34"/>
Essential; And more especially when <hi>Sedition</hi> (we know) is their Aime, and <hi>Blasphemy</hi> an usual Adjunct.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. Who will not deeme it a less and a more pardonable error, <hi>To desire the Prayers of a good fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Creature, who (as it chances) hears not our Requests; and to wish also a happy Voyage, and the speedy getting home of a friend, who is already (it seems) at his Iourney's End</hi> (for thus in effect lyes the Insignificancy of <hi>Invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Saints,</hi> and of <hi>Suffrages for the Dead</hi>) than in the first place (omi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ting the many horrid <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions</hi> of other <hi>Sects</hi>) to deny with <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ez.</hi> Act. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> BEZA, and his <hi>Desciples</hi> the PRESBYTERIANS, <hi>Christ</hi>'s <hi>descent into Hell,</hi> one of the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant Victories</hi> of his <hi>Death</hi>; And secondly to affirm <hi>His not d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing for all</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Doctrine that (besides the Blackness of it) makes so many of their <hi>Hypocon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driacal
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:64306:34"/>
Followers</hi> (commonly the quietest and best meaning Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Rout) <hi>to Hang them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves,</hi> and so ensure their <hi>Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> out of meer fear of being <hi>Damn'd</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>And here again I must desire my <hi>Reader</hi> to remember what I have now said, dos by no means prove any <hi>Popish</hi> opinion true, but only that the <hi>Phanatical</hi> Doctrine is worse, and certainly what follows will yet more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently make it appear.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. 'Tis better be under the lash of one <hi>spiritual Superiour,</hi> than Ten thousand <hi>Popes; Presbytery</hi> making every pragmatical <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> worse in some respects than a <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> or any of his <hi>angry Successors</hi>; For, as to a private man (unless he be like <hi>Wickliff, Oldcastle,</hi> and the like, very e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent and remarkable) he will hardly or never be taken notice of by the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and its
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:64306:35"/>
great <hi>Officers</hi>; whereas, under <hi>Calvin</hi>'s <hi>Iron Rod,</hi> no <hi>youthful Man</hi> shall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>merry</hi>; no body mus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> so much as <hi>dance</hi>; no <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal</hi> or <hi>Handmaid</hi> shall <hi>cramp Sir Roger</hi> with the Book of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> or play little tricks with his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend <hi>Cloak,</hi> or wilfully fail per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance in <hi>well starching</hi> his <hi>mystical band,</hi> but will be presently sent headlong to the <hi>Devil,</hi> or forc'd to a <hi>Penance</hi> harder (it may be) in their opinion, than going half way to him. Then, for great <hi>Monarchs,</hi> and great <hi>Governours,</hi> let any man judge, whether it be not first more honourable for them to contend with a Foreign <hi>Bishop</hi> and <hi>Prince,</hi> than with an <hi>Assembly</hi> of their meanest Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, both in <hi>Quality</hi> and <hi>Estate.</hi> But in the next place, when we come to consider the <hi>peril</hi> of their <hi>sacred Persons,</hi> there is no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of equality in the matter; for there are even <hi>Laws</hi> in every
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:64306:35"/>
               <hi>Popish Kingdom</hi> against the <hi>Popes Bulls, Sentences,</hi> and the like: and the entrance of his <hi>Legats</hi> and <hi>Envoys</hi> may be legally hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd; Nay, the very <hi>Decrees</hi> of his <hi>Councils</hi> (as we see by those of <hi>Trent</hi>) are receiv'd and unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd as <hi>Princes</hi> order. Besides this, the <hi>stout ones</hi> have <hi>Imprison'd</hi> ruffling <hi>Popes</hi>; as did the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Charles</hi> V. and <hi>Philip the Fair</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> Others have laugh'd at his <hi>Holiness's anger,</hi> and beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en him with his own Weapons; that is to say, have oppos'd him with the <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Clergy.</hi> Thus dealt the <hi>Venetians</hi> with <hi>Paul</hi> V. and thus serv'd this <hi>French King</hi> the late <hi>Alexander</hi> VII. and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, the present <hi>Innocent</hi> XI. whom the <hi>Gallican Church</hi> has so notably baited. Our <hi>Will. Rufus,</hi> our <hi>Henry</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our <hi>Edw.</hi> I. and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other of our <hi>Kings,</hi> (and reckon'd also <hi>good Sons of the Church</hi>) have disputed, and got
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:64306:36"/>
the <hi>point</hi> of the <hi>Pope</hi>; and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever reads the story of <hi>Hen.</hi> II. and King <hi>Iohn,</hi> will find, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat they had done the like, had they not been altogether <hi>inconstan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>irresolute.</hi> Now, under the <hi>Presbyterian Yoak,</hi> what <hi>Prince</hi> ever contended with those <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants,</hi> without the utmost shame and loss; for these <hi>AEgyptian Taskmasters</hi> being at home, and not only knowing their own strength, but (like skilful <hi>Knight <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrants</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>defects</hi> of their Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries <hi>Armour,</hi> they never strike but the <hi>Blow</hi> proves deadly, their greatest <hi>mercy</hi> being to make their <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rince sit publicly in the Stool of Repentance</hi>; nor must their <hi>Synodical Ordinances</hi> be disputed or disobey'd by any <hi>Governour</hi> whatsoever. These and the like vexations made <hi>King Iames</hi> (who understood the <hi>Party</hi> fully) so often to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat that true and witty <hi>Apothegm
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:64306:36"/>
No Bishop no King</hi>; as also be so severe with them in his <hi>Basili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con Doron,</hi> as to incite even his hopeful <hi>Heir,</hi> the great <hi>Prince Henry</hi> against them.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. Let us now come to the <hi>Deposing Doctrine</hi>; and whoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever reads but <hi>Knox, Bucanan, Goodman,</hi> Bishop <hi>Bancro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Positions,</hi> the <hi>Disse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ters sayings</hi> &amp;c. (all writen within the four <hi>Seas</hi>) <hi>Must needs aver and say that no Imp of Hell has ever yet out done them on this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</hi> Then for the <hi>Practice,</hi> DOCTOR HEYLIN's <hi>History of Presbyterians</hi> (without the pains of searching and turning over Volumns) plainly shows, That the proportion between the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> and <hi>Calvinian Heros,</hi> in this dispute (and more especially if we consider the extent of <hi>Iuris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction,</hi> and the <hi>age</hi> of them) is like the <hi>Tyber</hi> to the <hi>Mediterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nean</hi>; nor are the Sain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ever
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:64306:37"/>
contented with the bare depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of a Governour, but like <hi>Turks</hi> persue the whole <hi>Line,</hi> and which is more are never quiet till they have alter'd the very <hi>Government</hi> also. But what can a man think, when we add this aggrevation; that not only <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Papists</hi> have it seems writen several Treatises against the <hi>Power of Deposing Kings,</hi> but even in <hi>Popish Countries,</hi> the <hi>Santarelluses,</hi> the <hi>Marianas,</hi> the <hi>Schopiuses,</hi> the <hi>Bellarmins,</hi> the <hi>Suarezes,</hi> the <hi>Becanuses,</hi> and <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Books haue been publickly Condemn'd or Burnt,</hi> as the <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend.</hi> p 75.</note> 
               <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings</hi> themselves make appear; and which is yet much further, the very <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Supporters</hi> of the <hi>Triple Crown</hi> have this very year in <hi>France</hi> (as our <hi>News Books</hi> publish) damn'd the said <hi>Opinion</hi> to the <hi>pit of Hell</hi>; a thing never yet done by any one <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Author</hi> that I know of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:64306:37"/>
(tho Justi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ied by <hi>Thousands</hi>) and much further from having been openly <hi>censur'd</hi> in any of their <hi>Convocations</hi> or <hi>Assemblies.</hi> Nay our <hi>Goodmanites</hi> and <hi>Cargilites</hi> will bitterly Exclaime at the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> as <hi>Antichristian</hi> in the <hi>Pope,</hi> and yet die with it in their <hi>Mouths,</hi> and own it with their last breath as an <hi>Article of Faith.</hi> Nay how have the <hi>party</hi> even in <hi>London</hi> labour'd and sweated like so many <hi>Cyclopses</hi> in their <hi>Caves</hi> and secret <hi>Dens</hi>; and at last (thinking themselves strong and irresistible) how openly have they declar'd, with the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence of Prostitutes, <hi>For the putting by the Heir of the Crown</hi> (the <hi>Prelude</hi> of degrading our present <hi>Sovereign</hi>) and this not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding his often hazarding his <hi>Royal Person</hi> in defence of his <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Countrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis out of the hatred to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> and not out of the least
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:64306:38"/>
fear or <hi>apprehension</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> that moves them to this fury; for (as most of our notedst <hi>Writers</hi> of the times remark) no <hi>true</hi> or <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Authority</hi> since the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> winkt more at <hi>Papists,</hi> than the loud <hi>Criers</hi> against <hi>Popery,</hi> as soon as they got into the <hi>Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle,</hi> or would have sooner given them <hi>Toleration,</hi> had not the said <hi>Papists</hi> been such known and desperate Enemies to a <hi>Rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But further, What <hi>Man</hi> in <hi>England</hi> of the least understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or Moment, that did not as much know the <hi>Duke</hi>'s Religion since the year 74, as since that of 78. Yet till <hi>Oates</hi>'s <hi>Information or Discovery</hi> (for then the whole gang were <hi>Cock a Hoop</hi>) how did the considerablest of the harmless <hi>Lambs</hi> still run to that compassionat <hi>Prince</hi> for favours? Did not Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> and the chief of their respective <hi>Levites,</hi> and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:64306:38"/>
in fine all the eminent Men (as well <hi>Pastors</hi> as <hi>Sheep</hi>) that found themselves agriev'd, make appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations to him, tho the possibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his Succession (against which none of them exclaim'd, till they could stand on their own Legs) had then the same fatality and inconvenience atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it, as at present. Nay the PLOT should raise in any Man (that do's not effectively deny it) a higher esteem and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this <hi>Great Man</hi> than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; seeing <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Bedlo</hi> have both Sworn, <hi>That the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spirators ever dreaded his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of their Designs</hi>; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing it tended on the one hand to the Establishment of his now suppos'd <hi>Religion,</hi> and on the other, to the exal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing him to the <hi>Crown</hi> it self.</p>
            <p>But the partiality of the <hi>Saints</hi> (when any thing crosses, as they think, their purpose) will not
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:64306:39"/>
only damn BEDLG, but OATES too, and all his <hi>Family</hi> and <hi>Abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi>; for thus they serv'd DUG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DALE, tho' not long before he had been so highly <hi>vouch'd</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Oath</hi> by their <hi>Martyr</hi> COLLEGE of famous memory.</p>
            <p>Thus too TURBER VIL was u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was so serviceable, that he even carried away the <hi>Bell</hi> from his <hi>elder Brethren,</hi> in the <hi>Tryal</hi> of my <hi>L. Stafford.</hi> Thus it has also far'd with SMITH, a Man once honour'd with several <hi>Elogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums</hi>; and among othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, with that of his <hi>great Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rning,</hi> by reason of his <hi>Narrative,</hi> which (like <hi>Affrica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Asi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ticus, &amp;c.</hi>) gave even lustre and distinction to his NAME; but now this very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>piece</hi> (as an addition to his Misfortunes) <hi>is declar'd and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess'd by a True</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. No. Protestant Plo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> st part,</hi> p. 31.</note> 
               <hi>Protestant to be written by a</hi> PHANATIC. But who knows, (to the honour of the <hi>Phanatical Tribe</hi>) but they
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:64306:39"/>
have been the <hi>Writers</hi> and <hi>Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> too of all the NARRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIVES? and certainly, that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid imposition on the People of BEDLO's <hi>Narrative of the Fires,</hi> does abundantly confirm us; CARE being the <hi>Author,</hi> and three or four <hi>Tender-conscienc'd</hi> BOOKSELLERS the <hi>Promoters,</hi> as the <hi>All-discovering</hi> OBSER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VATOR has most fully prov'd.</p>
            <p>But of all the <hi>scrupulous</hi> and <hi>consciencious Witnesses,</hi> I must needs confess none have been so <hi>stigmatiz'd,</hi> and hardly used, as the IRISH; <hi>for the Godly have even made the Testimony of all the Natives of that Kingdom Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbial</hi>; and yet, <hi>Who</hi> but <hi>They</hi> brought these poor <hi>Men</hi> upon the <hi>Stage? Who</hi> but <hi>They</hi> fed them with the <hi>fat things,</hi> and with the very <hi>Grapes of Canaan,</hi> till at last <hi>they put their Teeth on edge?</hi> and <hi>Who</hi> but <hi>They</hi> were the common <hi>Vouchers</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgators</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:64306:40"/>
for their Manners, and the learned <hi>Heralds</hi> and <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaries</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o prove their great <hi>Des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> and <hi>Quality?</hi> Yet now, how many mean <hi>Villains, Scoundrels, Beggers, Papists, Tories, Bog-trot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, not to be credited by any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian,</hi> &amp;c. were they call'd, after they once appear'd against the <hi>Brethren?</hi> Nay, so illuminated were all the <hi>True Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>estants</hi> on a sudden, that, notwithstanding the <hi>Oaths</hi> of seven or eight of these <hi>Teigues,</hi> upon whose <hi>Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> the <hi>Parliament voted an</hi> IRISH PLOT; and, notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding half as many <hi>English</hi>-men, who had (with the general ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plause of the <hi>Saints</hi>) so illus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rated and made evident the <hi>English Plot,</hi> that several were <hi>Hang'd</hi> and <hi>Executed</hi> upon their <hi>Oaths</hi>; and, notwithstanding also a <hi>pretty Paper,</hi> declar'd <hi>Treason</hi> by the four INNS of COURT, and by the <hi>Loyal Addresses</hi> of most of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:64306:40"/>
the NATION: they brought in the <hi>Bill</hi> IGNORAMUS, though some of the <hi>Iury</hi> were of such <hi>tender consciences,</hi> (a thing that cannot be too often remembred, and which our <hi>Chronicles</hi> will never forget) they could <hi>Indict,</hi> (and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Bill</hi> was also <hi>found!</hi>) no meaner a <hi>Person</hi> than the <hi>Earl of Danby,</hi> upon the Account of one <hi>single man</hi>'s <hi>Accusation,</hi> who was then actually at the <hi>Bar</hi> for <hi>Treason,</hi> and whose <hi>Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> plainly tended to his own <hi>security and advantage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But who dares or can censure a <hi>Iury-man</hi>'s <hi>Conscience,</hi> say they, and their <hi>Apologists</hi>? I answer, a MONSTER that has no <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> no <hi>Principle,</hi> but <hi>Will</hi>; that can think any thing a <hi>Sin,</hi> which runs counter to his <hi>Aim</hi>; and yet, to promote it, shall (without <hi>scruple</hi>) do <hi>the same thing,</hi> and a thou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and times <hi>worse.</hi> For were not Sir G. WAKEMAN's <hi>IVRY
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:64306:41"/>
Middlesex</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>Gentlemen, and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants</hi> of <hi>Account</hi> and <hi>Estates?</hi> And was it not proved to them in open Court, <hi>That</hi> CORKER <hi>was never President of the</hi> Benedictins, <hi>contrary to</hi> Oa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es's <hi>positive Oath?</hi> with many o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her by <hi>particulars,</hi> as ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be seen in the printed <note n="*" place="margin">vid. Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'s Tryal. p. 75</note> 
               <hi>Tryal.</hi> But besides this, did not Sir <hi>Philip Lloyd</hi> declare, That the said <hi>Oates,</hi> before the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (when Sir <hi>George</hi> was first ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused by him,) <hi>call'd upon God,</hi> and <hi>with lifted-up hands,</hi> (being prest to a positive Accusation by the <hi>Board</hi>) cry'd,<note n="*" place="margin">ib. p. 55.</note> 
               <hi>That he knevv n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thing m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re against him, than vvhat he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> already accused him of</hi>; which was only about some <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>-says</hi> from the <hi>Iesuits.</hi> Yet, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and Sir <hi>Philip</hi>'s being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n of Quality</hi>; nay, a <hi>Man</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Pap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> rightly urges) <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> not for his head assert th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hing</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> well knowing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouncel,</hi> and my LORD
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:64306:41"/>
SHAFTSB. their then <hi>President,</hi> would not countenance a Lie; I say, notwithstanding all these cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances, that JURY was so <hi>calumniated</hi> by all <hi>True Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants,</hi> that <hi>One</hi> of them (I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member) coming upon the CHANGE next day, <hi>was houted at, and shun'd as if he had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, or the most infamous man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live.</hi> Nor are their <hi>Tongues</hi> and <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> yet quiet in that Affair; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s for Sir <hi>Philip,</hi> they have thirst<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d for his very Bloud ever since.</p>
            <p>But to proceed a little further upon the same Key; what At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts have the <hi>Tender Conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> made upon His <hi>Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi>'s very <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Life!</hi> For <hi>first,</hi> tho' <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Bedlo</hi> (as I said before) freed that excellent <hi>Prince</hi> from any <hi>Conspiracy</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>King</hi> or his <hi>Crown</hi>; yet no sooner did <hi>Dangerfield</hi> appear, with that most impossible <hi>story,</hi> That three of the <hi>Imprison'd
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:64306:42"/>
Lords,</hi> when they had already smarted for their supposed <hi>Credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> when they had several <hi>Popish younger Brothers</hi> at hand, and <hi>Partizans</hi> (to be sure) in any <hi>Plo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of <hi>Theirs</hi>; and when they well saw what <hi>Rewards</hi> and <hi>Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements</hi> all the <hi>Discoverers</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, should yet take a <hi>common Rogue,</hi> a meer <hi>Stranger,</hi> out of <hi>Newgate,</hi> to <hi>Kill the King.</hi> I say, no sooner did this <hi>Fellow</hi> appear with his <hi>impossible story</hi> (and tho' afterwards he was prov'd (in the <hi>Tryal</hi> where he was concerned) the greatest <hi>Recorded Villain</hi> that has been heard of, and false also in the main particulars of his <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verments</hi>; and, which is more, a Forger of an <note n="*" place="margin">prov'd by Justice <hi>Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> in Councel.</note> 
               <hi>Affidavit</hi> even against His <hi>Highness</hi>;) but the whole Party toil'd like <hi>Bulls</hi> to have him received for a good Witness; which would have cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly succeeded, had not the <hi>Peers</hi> utterly rejected it, as abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:64306:42"/>
Nay, to shew further how <hi>tender</hi> a thing a <hi>True Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Conscience</hi> is! they asserted in Print, <note n="*" place="margin">vid. that Pamphlet.</note> 
               <hi>That</hi> Dangerfield'<hi>s Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony</hi> (<hi>tho' he were prov'd</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd) <hi>was te be taken against a</hi> Papist; and all this passion and heat only <hi>to Murther the first</hi> Prince <hi>of the Bloud</hi>; For the <hi>Reader</hi> must know, that <hi>Danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> had formerly been with the <note n="*" place="margin">vid. Dang Narrative</note> 
               <hi>King, Duke, Lord Peterborough</hi> and <hi>Secretary Coventry,</hi> and had thereby sufficient room to expa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate in, as <hi>True Protestants</hi> and the <hi>Spirit</hi> should suggest. Now, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this <hi>hopeful Youth</hi> had been (as I said) with the <hi>King, Duke, &amp;c.</hi> he and his infer, <hi>That his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count must be True forsooth, since it shews</hi> (they say) <hi>he was mightily intrusted with secrets, by his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving access to such</hi> Great Persons; and yet who knows not, but the <hi>common Hang-man,</hi> if he says, <hi>he has a Treason to discover,</hi> (and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:64306:43"/>
               <hi>Dangerfield</hi> pretended to know of a * <hi>Presbyterian-Plot</hi>) shall have admittance to His <hi>Majesty,</hi> and to his <hi>greatest Officers,</hi> at an easie rate.</p>
            <p>In the next place, when this project fail'd, <hi>Fitz-Harys</hi> afforded a new one; for tho' he were sent to <hi>Newgate</hi> by the <hi>King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel,</hi> as being (besides other Crimes and Suspicions) taken with a <hi>Treasonable Libel</hi> in his Pocket, yet durst two or three <hi>City-Officers</hi> go and examine him, tho a <hi>Prisoner of State,</hi> and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by that <hi>Supreme Power</hi>; So that presently after, he that had seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral things to say against the <hi>True Protestants,</hi> (had the <hi>King</hi> or His <hi>Ministers</hi> encourag'd such Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers) <hi>had now God knows what to declare, not only concerning the</hi> Popish Plot, <hi>and many</hi> Great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons <hi>not yet accused, but even against His Royal Highness</hi>; and how <hi>undeniable</hi> and <hi>plain</hi> an <hi>Evidence</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:64306:43"/>
(as the times stood) would this have been, if the <hi>Lords</hi> had receiv'd the <hi>Impeachment,</hi> every body is fully sensible. Nay, the <hi>Peers</hi> were highly exclaim'd at, because they wav'd their own <hi>Iurisdiction,</hi> and left the <hi>Malefactor</hi> to the <hi>Common Law.</hi> Nor did the <hi>men of conscience</hi> fail to threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> if they dar'd to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with him; and all this (we see) to gain a <hi>new Witness,</hi> who, by the help of their <hi>Cries,</hi> and other <hi>Artifices,</hi> would have certainly at last overthrown the very <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi> Yet, after all this huge Clutter and Do, when the poor <hi>Creature</hi> came to the <hi>Gallows,</hi> he sufficiently show'd how he had been tamper'd with, and that he knew nothing of any <hi>Plot,</hi> but what ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the <hi>Eternal Shame,</hi> and not <hi>Rest,</hi> of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>Saints,</hi> as may be seen in Dr. <hi>Hawkins</hi>'s <hi>Narrative</hi> all along.</p>
            <p>Lastly, (for I'l run to no more particulars at present) let any sober <hi>man</hi> consider, what a fearful stir they would have made, and how many fatal disorders and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions must have ensued their improvement
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:64306:44"/>
if Mr. THYN's <hi>Murther</hi> had not been discover'd as it was? The <hi>Horse-men of Israel</hi> (we see) were all booted and spur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and unanimously ready (for the <hi>Quiet</hi> again of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> to throw the Fact on the <hi>Papists,</hi> who now have some rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son (I confess) to boast of <hi>Miracles</hi>; for had not the Assassins been miraculously taken (as it were) in the Act, which even hinder'd them from the impudence of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying it, they would have been so far from being search'd after, that a <hi>man</hi> might have run in danger of the <hi>Pillory,</hi> (especially if some <hi>tender consciences</hi> were of his <hi>Iury</hi>) for offering so much as to suspect them. Things therefore standing thus, how could the <hi>Popish Duke</hi> (as they call him) have escap'd the <hi>new Witnesses</hi> (that were already consulting the <hi>Coffee-houses</hi> for their Lesson) when there was so much malice in the <hi>Party,</hi> and some small pretence for a <hi>Lye?</hi> Nor should any of the obnoxious <hi>Ministers o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> State,</hi> nor any <hi>Courtier</hi> (Mr. <hi>Thyn</hi> being reputed an Enemy to the <hi>Court</hi>) have mist of being hamper'd, no not the King Himself been free from <hi>Calumny</hi>; &amp;
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:64306:44"/>
truly, some have had the impudence al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready to suspect Him of knowing the <hi>whole Plot,</hi> and all its <hi>Appendices,</hi> unless that of <hi>Pickering</hi>'s <hi>Silver Bullets</hi>; for as to Sir <hi>George W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>keman</hi>'s <hi>Pills</hi> and <hi>Design,</hi> Sir <hi>Philip Lloyd</hi>'s being sent to his <hi>Tryal</hi> by the Board, makes it plain, and (as they think) beyond dispute.</p>
            <p>Now, after all these cursed <hi>Defamations</hi> of <hi>His Majesty</hi>; these bloudy <hi>Conspiracies</hi> against His faithful <hi>Brother and Heir</hi>; and the many <hi>Endeavours</hi> against His <hi>best Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Friends and Servants</hi>: I would ask the SQUIRE himself, whether we have not reason to believe infallibly, and hand over head, every PLOT, and every <hi>Story</hi> of their recommendation; and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially since we find they can at pleasure <hi>cry down,</hi> and in effect <hi>perjure</hi> any <hi>Witness</hi>; even those that have assured us, upon their <hi>Words</hi> and <hi>Oaths,</hi> (and what else has yet proved it?) of a <hi>Damnable</hi> and <hi>Hellish</hi> PLOT of the PAPISTS against the KING? But since I am comparing the <hi>Faith, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> and <hi>Actions of the True Protestants and the Papists,</hi> whom the said SQUIRE
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:64306:45"/>
makes <hi>worse than</hi> Pagans: I would fain know of him, whether the <hi>proceedure</hi> of the <hi>Papists,</hi> in the kind we are now speaking of, was not something <hi>fairer,</hi> even in the <hi>Reign</hi> of QUEEN MARY? For in all her Time, tho' she highly <hi>dislik'd</hi> her Sister ELIZABETH's <hi>Religion,</hi> and had also a pique against her <hi>Person,</hi> upon the account of their <hi>Mothers Quarrel</hi>; yet never was there one VOTE of Parliament, and much less a BILL for her EXCLUSION. And, what is yet more, when WYAT was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, who was a <hi>Protestant,</hi> and <hi>General,</hi> or <hi>chief Commander</hi> in his <hi>Insurrection,</hi> He accused the said <hi>Princess</hi> ELIZABETH as a <hi>Complotter</hi>; yet for all that, neither the <hi>Queen</hi> nor the <hi>Councel</hi> would believe him, notwithstanding the probability of the <hi>Accusation</hi>; so that, when he was brought to the place of <hi>Execution,</hi> and finding no <hi>benefit</hi> or <hi>encouragement</hi> by his <hi>Lye,</hi> like a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <hi>Fits-Harys, He ask'd God and his</hi> Prince <hi>forgiveness for that horrid</hi> Crime, <hi>and so dyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:64306:45"/>X. But <hi>Tenthly</hi> (to proceed with the <hi>Parall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l,</hi>) they are the better <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hrictians,</hi> who assist their <hi>Prince</hi> and are <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riends</hi> to his <hi>Friends,</hi> than they, <hi>who still speak ill of Dignities</hi>; who watch for every occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to oppose &amp; <hi>ensl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve</hi> their <hi>Sovereign</hi>; and who think it a sufficient cause to hate any man, and persue him unto <hi>Death,</hi> if he offers to stand for the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Prerogative.</hi> I shall not now speak what the <hi>Papists</hi> did during the late trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of <hi>Charles</hi> I. and II. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morp.</hi> lib. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Vidistis enim sua narret Vlisses,</hi> I mean let <hi>Mr. Iulian</hi> repeat his, and the <hi>True Protestant Loyalty,</hi> for we have been all eye Witnesses of the <hi>Popish</hi> actions. I say I intend not to speak what either <hi>Party</hi> did from 41 to the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Restauration,</hi> but what they have done since. On the one hand then, if any <hi>Royalist</hi> or <hi>Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Subject</hi> stood <hi>Candidate</hi> at an <hi>Election,</hi> he had to be sure the <hi>Voices</hi> of all the <hi>Papists</hi> there. If there happened to be any of your <hi>Strictlands</hi> or your <hi>Swalls</hi> in the <hi>Lower-House</hi>: (to wit, <hi>new Converts</hi> as the busie <hi>Priests</hi> call them) their <hi>Votes</hi> fell ever
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:64306:46"/>
(we see) on the <hi>Crown side.</hi> If again any thing for the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Advantage</hi> and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> came to be proposed to the <hi>Lords,</hi> let it be even the <hi>readmission</hi> of the <hi>Bishops,</hi> the <hi>Catholick Noble-men</hi> fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'d not (with a <hi>Nemine Contradicente</hi>) to be for it. Again if the <hi>King</hi> thinks a <hi>War</hi> for his <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erest</hi> to be best, the <hi>Papists</hi> at <hi>home</hi> will not only approve and abet it, but the <hi>Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>glasses</hi> and the other considerable <hi>Officers abroad</hi> leave (at the first Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd) their respective great <hi>Imployments</hi> and returne. If <hi>Tangier</hi> be in distress, if <hi>Argiers</hi> troublesome, or any other pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>Misfortunes</hi> appear, these <hi>Gentlemen</hi> become all on a sudden chang'd into <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Phanaticks,</hi> that is to say, they se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m Surley, Dogged and wholy ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of humou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; but if any <hi>happy News</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive, whom do we find more <hi>gay</hi> than the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and <hi>wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se Bonefire</hi> makes a greater Flame? Now on the other side (not to speak of <hi>the actual insurrections</hi> of the <hi>True Protestants</hi> since the <hi>King</hi>'s return) what <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lier</hi> or known Servant to the <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> has been designed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or any <hi>Elective
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:64306:46"/>
Office,</hi> but had his whole life ript up, with a thou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and addi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ional l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es and <hi>Nick-names</hi> of <hi>Papist, Pensioner,</hi> &amp;c. on purpose to put him by the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ddle? What Stout <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi> or <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>Honour</hi> crost a Seditious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igue, but was presently pointed at as a <hi>Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ordian,</hi> and as unfit for any <hi>Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st and Imployment?</hi> In our late <hi>War</hi> what Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices have been us'd to put His <hi>Majesty</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on streights; or if that miscarried, how have they rai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'d at the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Councellors</hi> and <hi>Advisers</hi>; so that <hi>Doleman</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the <hi>Cabal</hi> might without censure <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the Enemies Ships</hi> up to <hi>Chatham</hi>; and the <hi>Fitz-Patrics</hi> and the rest Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand <hi>Boilduke</hi> and the <hi>Adjacent Coast,</hi> tho' it were to hinder and oppose our <hi>Landing?</hi> As for <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngier</hi> and <hi>Argiers</hi> the <hi>Mahometans</hi> are not ignorant of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kling</hi> and good wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hes of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir <hi>Brethren</hi> he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e; and that <hi>Coll. Sackvil</hi> and <hi>Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Herbert</hi> have had many a <hi>Prayer</hi> at least many a hearty <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>jaculation</hi> offered up for their Ruine and Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>usion; seeing the <hi>King</hi> by their <hi>Galantry</hi> has fewer Irons in the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e than before. No wonder then
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:64306:47"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey abhor all <hi>publick Ioy,</hi> and that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of contributing to the <hi>Festivity,</hi> they'l put out their very <hi>candles,</hi> and even cover their <hi>Hearths,</hi> as if <hi>William the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror</hi>'s <hi>Coverfeu-Bell</hi> were still Ringing.</p>
            <p>One (<hi>Bonefire</hi> I must needs confess) they now Religiously observe, <hi>viz.</hi> That on the <hi>Anniversary</hi> of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s <hi>Coronation</hi>; tho' they never intended by it to shew any hearty hatred to the <hi>Pope</hi> or any sincere Reverence and affection to the memory of that great <hi>Princess,</hi> but only to vent their inveterate <hi>Malice</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the whole <hi>Line of the</hi> STUARTS, for as the <hi>Old True Protestants</hi> were <hi>goads in the Sides, and prickles in the Eyes of Her Majesty</hi> during her whole <hi>Reign,</hi> so their Faithful and Legitimate <hi>Children</hi> continue the same rancour by railing at, and breaking those <hi>Laws</hi> of Hers, which, preserving the <hi>uniformity</hi> of the <hi>Ppotestant Religion,</hi> are the certain cause of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Quiet.</hi> And if the meer <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracing</hi> of his good <hi>Holiness</hi> were the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Solemnity,</hi> the 5<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>November</hi> would be much the fitter day; she having
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:64306:47"/>
been a <hi>Papist,</hi> and <hi>He</hi> thereupon an open and declar'd <hi>Enemy,</hi> so that every thing he did against Her might in some manner be expected; whereas <hi>King Iames</hi> and <hi>He</hi> were not at any particular odds, which renders every <hi>Plot</hi> of <hi>His</hi> against His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty</hi> more reflecting and odious. But <hi>Saints</hi> care not for congruities, their aim being only to blacken the present <hi>Royal Family,</hi> add by crying up the <hi>Protestant,</hi> the <hi>Protestant Queen,</hi> to insinuate <hi>as if all the</hi> STUARTS <hi>were ever Papists.</hi> But this I must acknowledge is no new thought or invention of the <hi>Gang,</hi> but a small im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of their <hi>Fathers practice</hi> after the <hi>Murder</hi> of <hi>Charles</hi> I. for they then made Her our <hi>last Monarch,</hi> and therefore never (but by accident) destroy'd and pull'd down any <hi>Statue Arms</hi> or <hi>Ensigns of Regality</hi> during our <hi>Bondage</hi> under them, unless those that related to this <hi>Princely</hi> and <hi>Glorious House.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing then by their former and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent <hi>Artifices</hi> the <hi>English World</hi> has un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted assurance of their <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Affection</hi> to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Government</hi>; 'tis no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:64306:48"/>
if they should destroy the very <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>redit</hi> and <hi>belief</hi> of the late PLOT. For who can we upon second thoughts hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ily blame for want o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Faith,</hi> when on the one side the <hi>Infidel</hi> sees not only several <hi>Old Caviliers,</hi> seve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lous <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and several <hi>persons</hi> (whofe whole <hi>Livelihood</hi> depends on the <hi>King</hi>'s well<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are) question not a li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tle (by reason of many strange <hi>stories</hi> in the <hi>Narratives,</hi> &amp; man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> evident <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sproof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> in <hi>Tryals</hi>) whether His <hi>Maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sty</hi> were really <hi>in all this so long talk'd of danger</hi>; and especially when the <hi>Lives, poverty, parts,</hi> and <hi>odd coming in of the Witnesses</hi> happened not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver advan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>agious to their <hi>Testimony</hi>; to w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ich may be also added that all <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Emb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ssadors</hi> and <hi>Ministers</hi> smile at the Noise; nor has any <hi>Reform'd Prince</hi> or <hi>State congratulated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Majesty's escape,</hi> as they and their Predecessors have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways done when any of our <hi>King</hi>'s were in real dan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er. I say who can heartily bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the <hi>Infidel,</hi> when on the one side he sees the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing</hi>'s <hi>known <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riends</hi> to Hesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, and on the other side finds all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:64306:48"/>
               <hi>Iudges</hi> of <hi>Charles</hi> I. all that were at <hi>Retrive</hi> for <hi>Charles</hi> II. after <hi>Worcester Fight</hi>; all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> were in <hi>Garison</hi> in <hi>Haber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dashers</hi> and <hi>Goldsmiths-Hall</hi>; all <hi>Venner</hi>'s <hi>Brigadeers,</hi> and in fine all mankind that are op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nly <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aters</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> wonderfully <hi>Solicitous</hi> for His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty's <hi>Safety, support the Witnesses,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand with zeal <hi>Iustice</hi> on the <hi>Conspirators</hi> and their ABETTERS, and will not only go to <hi>fisty-cuffs</hi> with any man that <hi>doubts,</hi> or <hi>scratches his head</hi> at some <hi>hard particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars,</hi> but <hi>hang</hi> him without mercy, if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he comes under any <hi>Iury</hi> of Theirs.</p>
            <p>Certainly, one may with some reason doubt <hi>Miracles</hi> which <hi>Iews</hi> (and <hi>Iews</hi> that never agreed together before, so much as in the <hi>day of the month</hi>) promote and cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> up; assuring us all the while, <hi>that the defence of Christianity</hi> is their dri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t and aim. Nay, <hi>Iews</hi> too that fly in the faces of these <hi>infallible Witnesses,</hi> and presently make <hi>them</hi> the greatest <hi>Monsters in Nature,</hi> if they chance to accuse a <hi>Brother</hi> of any <hi>Villany,</hi> tho' never so probable or plain.</p>
            <p>To shew yet further the real zeal a <hi>True
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:64306:49"/>
Protestant</hi> bear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to His <hi>Majesty,</hi> what <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate</hi> or <hi>Magistracy</hi> asserts His <hi>Kingly Rights,</hi> whom they have not <hi>vilified</hi> and <hi>Lampoon'd,</hi> at the very time perchance when they are running down <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of His Majesty,</hi> even upon pretence of his defaming the Justice of the Nation? 'Tis lawful in them to rail at a <hi>Surrey Iury,</hi> if they censure Mr. <hi>Pilkington</hi> for discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diting a fellow Citizen. They may (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sooth) without any fault, <hi>libel</hi> some of the eminentest <hi>Gentlemen of Essex,</hi> as <hi>corrupt</hi> and <hi>perjur'd,</hi> if they find <hi>Billingsgate-Hickeringill</hi> to have a <hi>black</hi> and <hi>scandalous m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h</hi> Nor shall the <hi>Oxfordshire Iury</hi>-men want <hi>Iudgments,</hi> if Pamphlets can creat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them, for condemning COLLEDG, a <hi>Traytor</hi> of as rank a smell (in a manner) as the late <hi>Regicides</hi> themselves. For he was publicly <hi>Seditious</hi> in his words, and he himself confess'd, <hi>that he came with Horse and Arms to</hi> Oxford <hi>to guard the</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>against the</hi> Papists; and what that means in the mouth of one that reckon'd the <hi>Bishops Tantivies,</hi> and the rest of the King's <hi>Friends</hi> at least <hi>Popishly inclin'd,</hi>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:64306:49"/>
may be easily imagin'd. 'Twas prov'd also against him, that, in a Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arrel about the <hi>Parliament,</hi> he said, <hi>he had lost bloud in the</hi> Cause, and <hi>that more ere long would be lost.</hi> He said also openly, <hi>He might (for ought he knew) be a</hi> Colonel <hi>shortly.</hi> Again, 'twas proved, that, upon the old sham and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Protestant Religion and Property,</hi> he was a promoter (even by distinctive Ribbons) of <hi>Ligues</hi> and <hi>Parties</hi>; That he was a <hi>disperser</hi> of <hi>Villanous Pictures</hi> and <hi>Ballads,</hi> to the <hi>King's Dishonour</hi>; That the first <hi>Draught</hi> of the Trayterous <hi>Libel</hi> the RARE SHEW was found in his House; That He had given it out to be Printed; and that he justified the horrid <hi>Proceedings</hi> of the <hi>Long Parliament,</hi> even the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Murther,</hi> All which, and more was made out against him, by Witnesses of unspot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Reputation; besides the many positive and <hi>probable Treasons,</hi> sworn by <hi>Dugdale, Smith, Turbervil,</hi> and the rest of his inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate <hi>Companions</hi>; And yet for all this, the <hi>Miscreant</hi> is vindicated by the <hi>Party,</hi> honour'd with a <hi>Picture,</hi> and under i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> that vilifie the <hi>public Iustice</hi> in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est degree.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:64306:50"/>But, if we come to <hi>single Persons,</hi> who has in the Nation been so <hi>harrast,</hi> and <hi>bespatter</hi>'d with so many Calumnies and Lyes, as Mr. L'ESTRANGE? One, if we consider his <hi>Quality,</hi> not only of a <hi>Family</hi> still in being, and Eminent among us, but as ancient as the <hi>Conquest</hi>; and, which is more, so <hi>Noble</hi> and <hi>Great</hi> then, that a <hi>Princely</hi> House (to wit, that of <hi>Darby</hi>) deem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Title</hi> and Honour it receives thence, as the <hi>first <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lower</hi> in its <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ronet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we come to his <hi>Breeding,</hi> He is a Man of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etters,</hi> and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> excellent <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion</hi> too. Nor was there ever a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Master of the <hi>English Tongue,</hi> whether we consider the clearness and <hi>variety</hi> of his Expression, or his stupendious <hi>celerity</hi> in writing.</p>
            <p>Then, for his <hi>Loyalty</hi> (which is his <hi>great fault,</hi> and has contracted him all his <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi>) He sided early with the <hi>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e King</hi>; was in <hi>Newgate</hi> for <hi>Treason</hi> also (as they call'd it) for Him; He was esteem'd, in the worst of Times, by all the <hi>Cavaliers</hi> as one of their <hi>choice Members</hi>; and as soon as the <hi>King</hi> return'd, by defending the <hi>Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch</hi>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:64306:50"/>
He drew all the enrag'd <hi>Hornets</hi> about his Ears; which now shows us further his <hi>Fidelity,</hi> since, upon the discovery of any <hi>Treachery</hi> or <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alshood</hi> in him, they might have <hi>legally</hi> excluded him from all <hi>Pardon</hi> and <hi>Indemnity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lastly, for his <hi>Religion,</hi> and firmness to the <hi>Church of England,</hi> no man from first to last ever gave g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er testimony of it than he; being still in the Cap, still in the Breach, as his disadvantageous Books to <hi>Popery</hi> show, as well as those against the Treachercus and <hi>Apostate Children</hi> of the Church, the most dangerous Enemies by many degrees, as the Affairs of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on have stood these sev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ral years. Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> therefore got as little <hi>Credit</hi> by accusing him for a <hi>Papist,</hi> as he did by his voluntary and open <hi>Confession</hi> to the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Council, That what he said of Sir</hi> E. Godfrey'<hi>s Murther, was false from Top to Bottom.</hi> Nor could he have invented a more <hi>foolish</hi> and <hi>unlikely</hi> place than SO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MER SET-HOUSE, for Mr. <hi>L'Estrange</hi> (as a conceal'd <hi>Papist</hi>) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o frequent; since <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rotestants</hi> of all conditions are daily run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:64306:51"/>
thither (as they do to the <hi>Iews</hi> Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue) to view their Fashions and Ceremonies.</p>
            <p>But what has this <hi>Gentleman</hi> done, to deserve their Barbarous and Republican Usage? Why, because like a faithful <hi>East-Angle,</hi> or <hi>Nor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olk</hi>-man, OBSERVING the <hi>Danish</hi>-Fleet on the Coast, their <hi>Hinguar</hi> and <hi>Hubba</hi> landed, King <hi>Edmond</hi> and his <hi>Family</hi> pursu'd: he fires the <hi>Beacons,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larms his <hi>Fellow-subjects,</hi> and thereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends not only <hi>Christian Religion,</hi> but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents also the spilling of more <hi>Royal Bloud</hi>; and therefore, I dare affirm, if ever any body sav'd a <hi>Kingdom</hi> by a PEN; Mr. <hi>L'Estrange</hi> has really done it.</p>
            <p>Besides, we are not only beholden to Mr. <hi>L'Estrange</hi> and ingenious <hi>Heraclit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> (who follows him close, and with long strides) for discovering the many abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Lyes and Contrivances against <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> but for preventing <hi>Ten thousand</hi> more; for these <hi>Loyal</hi> and <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> men have (after much Fatigue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated Out-cries) taught the <hi>Seditiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Scriblers,</hi> or rather their <hi>Grave Directors,</hi>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:64306:51"/>
a little <hi>Orthography</hi>; that is, to <hi>spell</hi> now and then <hi>true,</hi> a passage not <hi>false</hi> in every word; as also, some little caution in their ill-design'd insinuations and Comments, since they dare not proceed in their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer impudent and prodigious way of <hi>vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating here,</hi> and <hi>defaming there,</hi> which must (had it continu'd) have insensibly inflam'd the whole <hi>Nation</hi>; for they now find by woful experrience, <hi>That</hi> Truth <hi>will out next day; and that all things are at length, nay presently, answer'd to their loss.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I am mentioning these <hi>Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent men,</hi> and how outrageously they have been us'd by the KETTS, or <hi>True Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Mechanics</hi> of the Age, because they zealously stood up (as I said) for <hi>His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty,</hi> and all <hi>His faithful Followers and Servants:</hi> I cannot pass by Mr. DRY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DEN's Case, since it so particularly shows us (according to my Design) the Nature and Folly of the <hi>Herd</hi>; who, to make some little noise, or evasion, will run down their very <hi>darling Arguments,</hi> and <hi>most specious pretences,</hi> without the least care
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:64306:52"/>
or regard; for this <hi>Gentleman</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (looking doubtless upon <hi>Neutrality</hi> or <hi>Idleness</hi> as a piece of <hi>Ingratitude,</hi> as well to that <hi>Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Giver</hi> of the <hi>Talents He enjoys,</hi> as to to the <hi>Great Monarch,</hi> who has still been so Indulgent and Kind) thought fit to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe the <hi>Kingdoms Miseries,</hi> and their <hi>Cause</hi> in <note n="*" place="margin">Absalon &amp; Achitophel, The Medal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>POEMS, that convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the very <hi>Factious</hi> in Their <hi>Iudgment,</hi> and tryumph'd over every f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>culty of theirs, exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that <hi>Diabolical Will,</hi> which (as we see) resists even GOD Himself. No sooner then had he publish'd his <hi>happy Thoughts,</hi> which pleas'd many an <hi>honest man,</hi> but the <hi>Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets</hi> were presently about him too; and, to give him (as they thought) his <hi>mortal wound,</hi> they printed his <hi>Elegy</hi> upon <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel,</hi> with great clamour and joy; But whether they have hurt <hi>Him</hi> or <hi>Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves</hi> most by it, I desire the <hi>Reader</hi> to judge. For how hideously have they bawl'd against every <hi>Royallist</hi> who twit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them (and that with great <hi>Reason</hi> and <hi>Necessity</hi>) with FORTY ONE, the KING's MURTHER, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> because it intrench'd,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:64306:52"/>
forsooth, on the <hi>Act of Indemnity</hi>; when as that <hi>Amnesty</hi> or <hi>Pardon</hi> never intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (<hi>had man the power of knowing Thoughts and future Actions</hi>) the forgiving of any, but those that were sorry for their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Crimes, and consequently resolv'd to be afterwards <hi>True Subjects.</hi> What <hi>impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ools</hi> therefore a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>They,</hi> who throw the said <hi>Elegy</hi> into the <hi>Author</hi>'s Dish, who has not only the genuine and true <hi>Plea</hi> of <hi>Inconsideration</hi> for himself<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (as being, when he wrote it, a <hi>young Graduate,</hi> or <hi>Boy</hi> newly come to Town) but also (which is much more) his <hi>latter apparent Duty to his King, both in Words and Actio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> ought most effectually to vindicate hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, no <hi>Transgressors</hi> are charged with the late <hi>Rebellion,</hi> or any thing belonging to it, but <hi>Those</hi> who manifestly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>un now to <hi>Sanctuary</hi> with <hi>polluted hands,</hi> and with their former blackne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of <hi>Intention.</hi> Nay, if we consider this Accusation as to Mr. <hi>Dryden,</hi> and interpret it <hi>verbatim,</hi> what can it mean but this? <hi>You wrote,</hi> Sir, <hi>once in praise of</hi> Cromwel; <hi>and therefore are a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reat Villain for opposing any body that either
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:64306:53"/>
writes or acts at present against your law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful King and Master</hi>; And truly, thus in effect (that is to say, as to the matter of Fact) stands their Justice to any one, whom they decry and calumniate.</p>
            <p>But to draw to a <hi>conclusion</hi> for the present, (tho' the Subject abounds with such <hi>Supersluit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Matter</hi> as to render the sterilest fancy exuberant) I will, in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the SQUIRE (having already given him <hi>Preface</hi> for <hi>Preface, Story</hi> for <hi>Story,</hi> and <hi>Section</hi> for <hi>Section</hi>) end my <hi>Treatise</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> also, with my <hi>end</hi> of writing it; which is (I must needs say) to remind the <hi>Reader</hi> of our late <hi>Miseries,</hi> and of our <hi>happiness</hi> by the <hi>King</hi>'s Return; To let Him see the <hi>True Protestant</hi> DESIGN, <hi>viz.</hi> That of <hi>Subverting the Gevernment,</hi> and of bringing us again into our former <hi>Bondage</hi> under the threed-bare pretences of the <hi>fear of Popery</hi>; to give Him also a short account of their <hi>Religion</hi> in spec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and practice; and then to shew their <hi>disobedient Principles,</hi> and restless<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, who will have even JULIAN in
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:64306:53"/>
their mouths, when they themselves are the most abandon'd APOSTATES that ever were. And so transcendent and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular are they herein, that notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their publickly owning themselves <hi>Seperatists,</hi> their constantly frequenting <hi>Conventicles,</hi> their openly writing and exclaiming against the <hi>Superstition of the Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> yet for the <hi>Office</hi> of a SHERIFF shall Mr. <hi>Bethel</hi> himself go <hi>to Church, Assist at the Common Prayer,</hi> and then not only <hi>receive the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> at an <hi>Altar</hi> surrounded with <hi>Rails,</hi> and from a <hi>Priest</hi> in his <hi>Surpliss</hi> but with the horrible (as they some<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>imes cry) and unsufferable aggravation of <hi>Kneeling</hi> also, What <hi>Mercy</hi> therefore can the most com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passionating <hi>Government</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hew to such a sort of People? Or what would tender <hi>Origen</hi> (were he alive) think could be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of them at the <hi>Day of Iudgment?</hi> The <hi>Papists</hi> have perchance some thing to Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lifie an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>asie <hi>Magistrate</hi> with, when he really see<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> both <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Small</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, <hi>leave Imployments, suffer Confiscations, endure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mprisonments and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:64306:54"/>
the like, for what what they think and call Conscience.</hi> This also makes several good Men to <hi>commiserate</hi> not a little the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> who believing their way of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship</hi> conformable to <hi>Gods</hi> command, <hi>will bear afflction and loss rather than forego it</hi>; so that 'tis evident no <hi>Dissenters</hi> from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> have any Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence except these two; and therefore none but they (could the <hi>Legislative Power</hi> with prudence <hi>Indulge</hi>) deserve any favour or connivance; all the others meeting meerly out of <hi>Faction</hi> and <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest</hi>; to the great damage of the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These are the Motives (to wit <hi>Interest</hi> and <hi>Faction</hi>) that cause the SQUIRE, (instead of quieting the minds, of his <hi>Party,</hi> and endeavouting to bring them to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir due <hi>Obedience</hi>) to declare against <hi>Gregory</hi>'s <hi>Tears</hi> and <hi>Prayers,</hi> and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>still <hi>Fear</hi> (if posible) into the <hi>Silly,</hi> and furnish at the same time the <hi>harden'd</hi> and <hi>inveterate</hi> with his best <hi>pretences</hi>; these al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so moved him so earnestly to wish, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the unnatural tearing a <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rother</hi> out
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:64306:54"/>
of the <hi>King</hi>'s Arms, who (humanly spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king) is His sole Bulwark and Defence; but to aim (by His <hi>Exclusion from the Crown,</hi>) at the subversion of our most <hi>Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Laws,</hi> which must certainly have created unexpressible Troubles in our Age, and most dismal consequences here after, and lastly, these made him so mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious against a <hi>Prince of Valour</hi>; a <hi>Prince of His word</hi>; and a <hi>Prince of that virtue</hi> and <hi>conduct</hi>; that His <hi>Goodness</hi> has thaw'd the very <hi>Orcades</hi> and <hi>Thule,</hi> and His matchless <hi>Prudence</hi> (in spight of His late mighty disadvantages) rendred <hi>Scotland</hi> even quiet and united, notwithstanding its turbulent temper during the Reigns of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> King <hi>Iames, Charles</hi> I. and <hi>Charles</hi> II. till now. Nay when every thing is fully considered, the <hi>Interest</hi> he has preserv'd in <hi>England,</hi> and the real <hi>Affection</hi> the Persons of <hi>Quality</hi> and <hi>Estate</hi> (both <hi>Noblemen</hi> and <hi>Gentlemen</hi>) bear him is as great a demonstration of his <hi>Wisdom</hi> as can possibly be imagined. Had the said SQUIRE thought of his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession</hi> and follow'd the admirable example
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:64306:55"/>
of the present <hi>Clergy,</hi> he would instead of his villanous JULIAN have spent his time in descanting on the <hi>Accidents</hi> of the late <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and then remember'd the <hi>Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> that the <hi>first promoters</hi> even of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperous <hi>Sedition</hi> are still left in the Lurch, whilst a <hi>new Brood</hi> (perchance 5 or 6 re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves off) are they that get the Prize; <hi>for thus I am sure it happen'd formerly with all the first Sticklers among the Lords, the Commons, the Army, and the City also.</hi> I say had the SQURIE thought of his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession</hi> and perform'd his Duty, he had sav'd his own <hi>Reputation,</hi> and my <hi>trouble</hi>: for being an <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nglish Subject</hi> and having seen with my own eyes the late glorious <hi>King</hi> at the Head of a Loyal, tho unsuccessful <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> and afterwards March before Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, besmeer'd with the gore of His most <hi>faithful Servants,</hi> and conducting Him to the bloudy <hi>Theatre</hi> on which He made Himself <hi>greater</hi> than the <hi>Caesars,</hi> I cannot (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ess) but have often <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad thought<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, especially when I see the same <hi>Methods</hi> and <hi>Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sick</hi> prescrib'd again, and many of the same <hi>Mountebanks,</hi> the present <hi>Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators</hi> and <hi>Dispensers.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="advertisement">
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:64306:55"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>There was intended at the end of this small Treatise <hi>an Account of the Blessings</hi> of a <hi>Commonwealth</hi> which the SQVIRE aims at, with some pretty STORIES rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to that <hi>Pretious</hi> Government, but it being thought at present too long, 'tis defer'd to another time,</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
