<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great and wonderful predictions of that late famous astrologer Mr. Lilly; and Mr. Partridg and Mr. Coley, concerning this present year 1683 To which is added a true and faithful account of the famous prophecies of the three German prophets; predicting and foretelling, some years since, this present invasion of the Turks into the empire of Germany and Hungary, with the events of the same, to the admiration of all that shall hear or read the same. Also their strange and wonderful predictions concerning the Pope, and the King of France: with the total and sudden destruction of the papal power; and the miraculous conversion of the Turks and Jews to the Christian faith. As also presaging the uniting of all religions into one visible church. Which prophecies have been had in esteem by many famous and illustrious persons of these times.</title>
            <author>Lilly, William, 1602-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-08">2004-08 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48501</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2223</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216548</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828275</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828275</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32702</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A48501)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32702)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1927:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great and wonderful predictions of that late famous astrologer Mr. Lilly; and Mr. Partridg and Mr. Coley, concerning this present year 1683 To which is added a true and faithful account of the famous prophecies of the three German prophets; predicting and foretelling, some years since, this present invasion of the Turks into the empire of Germany and Hungary, with the events of the same, to the admiration of all that shall hear or read the same. Also their strange and wonderful predictions concerning the Pope, and the King of France: with the total and sudden destruction of the papal power; and the miraculous conversion of the Turks and Jews to the Christian faith. As also presaging the uniting of all religions into one visible church. Which prophecies have been had in esteem by many famous and illustrious persons of these times.</title>
                  <author>Lilly, William, 1602-1681.</author>
                  <author>Partridge, John, 1644-1715.</author>
                  <author>Coley, Henry, 1633-1695?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Josh. Conyers at the black Raven in Duck-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M DC LXXX III. [1683]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Predictive astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Europe --  History --  1648-1715 --  Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32702:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Great and wonderful PREDICTIONS Of that late Famous Astrologer Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi>; and Mr. <hi>Partridg</hi> and Mr. <hi>Coley,</hi> concerning this present Year 1683. To which is added A true and faithful ACCOUNT OF THE Famous Prophecies of the three <hi>German</hi> Prophets; Predicting and Foretelling, some years since, this present Invasion of the <hi>Turks</hi> into the Empire of <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Hungary,</hi> with the events of the same, to the admiration of all that shall hear or read the same. Also their strange and wonderful Predictions concerning the Pope, and the King of <hi>France</hi>: With the total and sudden destruction of the Papal power; and the miraculous Conversion of the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Iews</hi> to the Christian Faith. As also presaging the uniting of all Religions into one visible Church. Which Prophecies have been had in esteem by many famous and illustrious persons of these times.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Iosh. Conyers</hi> at the <hi>black Raven</hi> in <hi>Duck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane,</hi> M DC LXXX III.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:32702:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Kind Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE here present thee with some remarkable Prophecies of that Ancient and Famous Astrologer, Mr. <hi>William Lilly,</hi> lately deceased; concerning this great year 1683. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted by him many years since, in the year 1655. Saith he,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>In the year eighty three,</l>
               <l>Great Changes there will be</l>
               <l>In <hi>England.</hi> But —</l>
               <l>Long ere that time poor <hi>Merlin</hi> sleeps</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In's Grave secure; sad <hi>England</hi> weeps.</l>
               <l>Left he no Heir unhappy Man,</l>
               <l>That this obscurer Riddle can</l>
               <l>Vnfold? —No.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>In his <hi>Anglicus</hi> for 1677. he hath these words.</p>
            <p>Those pretending to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eligion, or such as are famous for Schisms or Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, or those of different judgment from that Religion Established by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, for some years will grumble and repine for that restriction on their Consciences, (as they will term it) and the nearer to the time of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, the more Confederations they will have, either, near the time of the Conjunction it self, or a little after; we fear great disturbance of those Nations, and the Princes they live under, disquieting their Governors: this for Conscience sake, as they pretend. But in our Nation, (as before was expressed) breach of the people's just priviledges, antient customes, and former injoyed rights will animate the generality to a strong and sturdy Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, and countenance that translation of Monarchy mentioned by <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, saith he, Many believe the last Age of the World is at hand; we verily conjecture, That a troublesome and vexatious time is approaching upon most Nations of <hi>Europe,</hi> wherein those pretending to Religion, whether Papist or Protestant, will shew little mercy or compassion to those persons whose un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>appiness it will be to fall under their subjection. God bless us from such a Reformation that must be advanced in the ruins of a well setled Government.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Partridg</hi> in his Astrological judgment on this year 1683. hath these words; <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Iupiter</hi> in conjunction in <hi>Leo,</hi> are contriving to make themselves secure, and to this end there are many and various endeavours
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:32702:2"/>
used to convene those of the greatest and best policy, to invent and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive some new ways of Trade, commerce, and Government: But methinks <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Iupiter</hi> both peregrine, look rather like Plotters than States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and seem to be such as would rather overthrow a Kingdom, Laws, and Religion, than secure any, unless it be such as serves their own turn: for you know that Highway men in their way are for self-preservation, though the Law be directly against them, and say, they ought to be hanged. Well let them plot on, then they have the worst success that ever men had; for what ever they contrive or consult, it will be known to their enemy, be it never so deep or Clandestine.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The great and wonderful Prophecies of the three <hi>German</hi> Prophets, <hi>Christopher Kotterus, Christiana-Pomatovia,</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Drabicius.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WE present thee, kind Reader, with these remarkable Prophecies of the three <hi>German</hi> Prophets, which have been highly esteemed of by the famous and illustrious persons of these times, which some years since foretold the invasion of the <hi>Turks</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> and the events of the same: Also Predictions concerning the <hi>French</hi> King's Wars, and the destruction of the Papal See of <hi>Rome,</hi> with the conversion of <hi>Iews</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi>; which take as followeth.</p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <p>On the 11<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>Iune</hi> there first of all appeared an Angel in the shape of a Man to <hi>Kotterus,</hi> which spake to him as followeth: That the anger of God was kindled against mankind, and that in fury he hastened to inflict punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on them, except they repent of their Pride and Impurity, and for contempt of God and his Word. After this he vanished.</p>
               <p>The Prophecy concerning <hi>Rome</hi> is, That the Lion of the Tribe of <hi>Iudah</hi> shall rore against the Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> behold she is now falling, but is not yet fallen, but presently shall fall. O thou cold, thirsty and presum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous City! it is not the height nor strength of thy Walls shall defend thee; behold the time is coming that thou shalt totter, and thy horrid lies, and false perverting of the Scriptures with thy spiritual fornications. O you Kings, you Princes, and Potentates, who do flatter her, and drink the Wine of her impurities, and partake of the Cup of her blasphemies. Behold the dry and withered Tree of the East begins to shoot forth her leaves, and her blushing knots; but the trees of the North do stand unmoved.</p>
               <p>Behold the Lion of the North begins to rouse himself, and two other of the same colour do follow him that will pluck up the trees of the South, Root
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32702:3"/>
and Branch. O that thou hadst known the day of thy visitation; but glory be to him that doth Wonders. After a little silence, the Angel said, O <hi>Babylon</hi>! fair but painted, and destitute of true foundation, false in thy Doctrine, false in thy L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fe, evil in thy Works, two and forty Months shall quickly be expired, and the three Days and half a Day shall come to an end: and the spirit of life shall return into those whom thou, O wicked <hi>Babylon,</hi> hast murdered. The five Months of thy Judgments will quickly be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plished, and then the Pope, the Spouse of the Devil shall fall. The Angel further said, That besides the Devil, the great adversary of the Church, there are two others that shall destroy and tread down all things: one of them doth not yet know the true God, of whom he is now ignorant; but shall know him, for the time is at hand that he shall acknowledg the true God, and shall accomplish his dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ees against the great Whore, sitting upon the hills above the Sea, who is another trampler upon, and destroyer of the Church, whose remembrance is come in the sight of God, to give her a cup of the Excandescence of his Anger; he cares not for God, nor doth God care for him, for his time is almost past. Then <hi>Kotterus</hi> demanded of the Angel, Will there be a great effusion of Blood? the Angel answered, Yes: for since <hi>Germany</hi> is so stubborn as not to pray to Almighty God to withdraw his Rod and heavy Hand held over it, but doth more and more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke him, and doth still fill up the measure of her sins, that it runs over with the abundance thereof, therefore there shall be a great battle and overthrow to the Devil and the Dragon, and a great supper shall be prepared for the fowls of the air. Woe unto <hi>Caesar</hi> the King, and Princes, the Counts, and Barons: Woe unto the Countries and Cities of the <hi>German</hi> Empire; all these things shall fall upon you, Famine, Dearth and War, and effusion of Blood; for the condemnation of the great Beast is near and certain. <hi>Kot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terus</hi> interposed again, and said, Shall the faithful be delivered from these great Judgments? the Angel answered, Reioyce O little Flock, thy Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd shall defend thee, you have in the Scriptures infallible promises of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance.</p>
               <p>The Lion of the Tribe of <hi>Iudah</hi> is he who wageth war against <hi>Germany,</hi> and he doth manage it by the Lion of the East, and the Lion of the North, neither doth he want power or means to inflict his punishments for many great Causes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:32702:3"/>
               <head>The Visions, Revelations and Prophecies of <hi>Christiana Pomatovia.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere appeared to me a man armed from Head to Foot, whose Head was as fire, and flame came out from his Mouth; he came forth, and stood by himself, and one of the company brought him a Sword, and did put it into his right hand, saying, This is my strength, and with the right Hand of my strength, and this Sword will I destroy my adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary, behold I am prepared, and will come unexpectedly in a day that the wicked shall not think of me, and will render unto every one according to his deserts, and in my wrath will I grind into powder all Unbelievers. I will now hasten my Judgment, I will perform a wonderful thing, much evil shall come from the North, and from the East, upon all the Inhabitants of the Earth. And immediately were heard these words, <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bylon</hi> is fallen, it is fallen, the great House of <hi>Austria</hi> is fallen, that proud and lofty House is fallen to the ground, neither shall it ever be built up again, and the Pope, and all that devilish Antichristian Synagogue shall suddenly be cast down, and blotted out of memory. By the Lions are the <hi>Hungarian,</hi> the <hi>Turk,</hi> the <hi>Tartar,</hi> the <hi>Sweed,</hi> the <hi>Dane,</hi> the <hi>Hollander,</hi> the <hi>English,</hi> the <hi>French,</hi> the <hi>Switzer</hi> and <hi>Saxon,</hi> by these Antichrist and <hi>Babylon,</hi> and Kingdom of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan shall be utterly overthrown, especially that great house of <hi>Austria,</hi> which they were not able to pluck down without the assistance of the white Lion of the tribe of <hi>Iudah.</hi> And I beheld innumerable troops of Horse, and bands of Footmen of all Nations, drawing themselves into two great bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, marshalled in batallia one over against another: And the Lord said unto me, Observe them now, and immediately I heard Drums beating, and Trumpets sounding, and the Lord said, Let us go up yonder Hill and observe the success of the battle more distinctl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; I heard the sound of the Trumpet, but the battle was fought beneath us on the foot of the Hill. Then he said unto me, This is the Army of the South, the Antichristian Army, the Army of the Whore and the beast, pointing to the Southern Army. And turning himself to the other Army, he said, This is the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of the East and North, of which I have made mention to you. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber these things that I have declared, for all will come to pass according to the Prediction. (By the Eastern Army is always meant the Army of the <hi>Turks.</hi>) And I looked a long time upon them, till I observed few of the Northern Army remained, the sad sight oppressed me with grief, fearing they would be utterly overthrown, but the Antient of times comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32702:4"/>
me, and said, Behold help cometh from <hi>Sion,</hi> the Throne of my Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. And I looked again, and behold a great Army descended from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, which was commanded by a man in a flame, with a great Sword in his hand, uniting himself to the northern Army.</p>
               <p>And I beheld also Clouds of smoak waving down, and falling down on the Southern army; and the fight was renewed, and the Southern army did fall like leaves in Autumn beaten by violent wind, many of the Southern Army after this were slain, and the rest fled, that not one of them remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of them: But the northern Army having gained great spoils, returned with great ioy, and the Army from Heaven ascended from whence it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The Visions and Prophecies of <hi>Nich. Drabicius.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis <hi>Drabicius</hi> was born at <hi>Straswick</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> (his Father was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sul of the said City) he was Minister of Gods Word at <hi>Zeranick,</hi> he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s attractive in his disc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urse, and grave in his conversation, he had a love and zeal to piety: His first vision was in the year 1643. <hi>A</hi> voyce spake unto him, saying, Write that the time is now come, I will revenge the offences given to my holy Name, I will cause the <hi>Turk</hi> to come and to overthrow <hi>Vienna,</hi> as <hi>Ierusalem</hi> was overthrown; and I will bring evil upon the house of <hi>Austria</hi> to cut it off from the earth, for she hath g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ven no ear to the peaceable coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels of the King of <hi>Polonia,</hi> now her destruction approacheth. <hi>Drabicius</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ked, When it would come to pass? it was answered, to day and tomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row will fill up the measure of her iniquities; and I will bring many great and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Nations upon the house of <hi>Austria,</hi> and they shall tread upon <hi>Vienna,</hi> as <hi>Ierusalem</hi> and <hi>Samaria</hi> were trodden upon, to revenge my quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, and to drive away Idolaters, with the false Prophets, and to vindicate the in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uries offered to <hi>Frederick</hi> that was King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and to his proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, with whom you also have been banished. <hi>Drabicius</hi> asked, whether the progeny of the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> be restored to their dignities? it was answered, Wherefore have I afflicted <hi>Germany,</hi> but because they did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake him; woe to the <hi>Bohemians,</hi> wo to the <hi>Silesians,</hi> wo to the <hi>Moravians,</hi> for now is their destruction at hand. The Revelation, (<hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>une</hi> 11.) Hear the voyce, O house of <hi>Austria,</hi> thy roots are in <hi>Hungaria,</hi> which I am now going to pluck up: but thou shalt perish with the Captain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thy Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and thy posterity, thy strong men shall fall. The Revelation of <hi>April</hi> 7. 1646. As I awaked out of sleep, a voice sounded in m Ears: O house of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32702:4"/>
                  <hi>Austria!</hi> O thou house of <hi>Austria,</hi> I have born with thee, I have born; with thee, so many ages, I have advanced thy glory on high in the midst of many Nations, with much patience I expected thy conversion unto me thy Creator; but thy heart is grown fat, and thy eyes are darkened, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thy self, nor thy Captains shall see their lamentable fall and ruine, for the abomination thou hast committed. Who did seduce thee, O house of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stria?</hi> thou hast forsaken me, and thrown my Laws behind thy back, and hast erected Idols of abomination throughout thy Cities and Streets, and in thy Temples and Chancels, thou hast set up Statues and Images, gilded and painted with beautiful colours. Thou with thy Counseller, and Judges, and Princes, hast neglected my word, and hast neglected justice, and righteousness, and mercy; therefore have I brought evil upon thee, and thy house: in vain dost thou lean upon a Reed, which is <hi>Spain</hi>: in vain thou ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectest help from the Pope, <hi>Bavarian</hi> or <hi>Saxon, Mentz</hi> and <hi>Cologn</hi> will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thee, for they have lost their strength with thee; for I have risen up against them, and have delivered their powers into their hands, who do make war against thee, that he may do to thee as to the house of <hi>Ahab,</hi> and to thy Priests, as my Servant <hi>Elias</hi> to the Prophets of <hi>Baal. October</hi> the 10. The word of the Lord came to me again, saying, Although it be not yet come to pass, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h not long since I declared to you, yet undoubtedly it shall take effect: For though he hath gained a peace for a time, he shall gain nothing by the delay of a little time, which nevertheless shall come, and is even at hand, for the destruction of the beast must begin in <hi>Hungaria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And after a long silence, the Lord said to me again, All my words shall be fulfilled, that it may be manifest unto all, That I am he that will confound the counsels of my enemi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, and will remove the half dead person from his Throne, by electing to me that chosen Vessel; the King of <hi>France,</hi> for whom <hi>Germany</hi> shall cry out, <hi>Long live, long live the King of</hi> France; which as soon as it shall be done by my command, who am King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, your liberties shall be restored, O ye worshippers of me.</p>
               <p>And O you Kings, Princes, and commanders of my Army, and you my Ministers of the Gospel, throw in your net into the Sea, to fish for the Jews the remainder of my Vintage, on the right side, and on the left, for the Nations of <hi>Turkey</hi> and <hi>Tartary,</hi> and other places, for I have opened my Prisons, and healed the wounded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that they may be admitted to the Banquet of my House, the Church, and many rooms that are in it, are yet empty for those persons to be brought into it, the <hi>Iews</hi> and the <hi>Turks,</hi> and other peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32702:5"/>
ignorant of the worship of the true God, and the Gospel of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, who are to acknowledg me, and to come into the pales of my beloved Spouse.</p>
               <p>I will have a reformation amongst the Idolatrous Ministers of the Whore, and those that shall be found refractory shall be put to death, for I will not have the least root of Popish Doctrine in any Nation, and I will that there be but one order and government of the Church amongst all Nations.</p>
               <p>The chief scope of all these Prophecies and Revelations, being to invite men to attend the judgments of Almighty God in his punishments of the sin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the world, and to be made worthy of his mercies, which in the last age of the world he will pour forth on all mankind; It well becomes all mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to admonish one another to repentance, and to increase our faith in the promises of God, and to inflame our mutual charity, to pray for one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that we may be made partakers of so unspeakable mercy. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:32702:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
