<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon at the funeral of the Right Honourable the Lady Jane eldest daughter to His Grace, William, Duke of Newcastle, and wife to the Honourable Charles Cheyne, Esq, at Chelsey, Novemb. I, being All-Saints day by Adam Littleton ...</title>
            <author>Littleton, Adam, 1627-1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-08">2004-08 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48732</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2568</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21390</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12406230</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12406230</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61397</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A48732)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61397)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 767:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon at the funeral of the Right Honourable the Lady Jane eldest daughter to His Grace, William, Duke of Newcastle, and wife to the Honourable Charles Cheyne, Esq, at Chelsey, Novemb. I, being All-Saints day by Adam Littleton ...</title>
                  <author>Littleton, Adam, 1627-1694.</author>
                  <author>Person of quality and neighbor in Chelsey.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5-56, [6] p., 2 leaves of plates : ports.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Macock,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Added t.p. on p. [57]: An elegy on the death of ... Lady Jane Cheyne ... / by a person of quality and neighbor in Chelsey.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cheyne, Jane, --  Lady, 1621-1669.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="frontispiece">
                  <pb facs="tcp:61397:1"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>CAVENDISH Duke Of NEWCASTLE.</head>
                        <p>Sherlock sculp.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:61397:2"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:61397:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A
SERMON
AT THE
FUNERAL
OF THE
<hi>RIGHT HONOVRABLE</hi>
THE
Lady JANE Eldest Daughter to his GRACE
WILLIAM, Duke of <hi>NEWCASTLE,</hi>
AND
Wife to the Honourable
<hi>CHARLES CHEYNE,</hi> 
                     <abbr>Esq</abbr>
At <hi>CHELSEY. Novemb.</hi> 1. Being <hi>All-Saints</hi> day. <hi>By</hi> Adam Littleton, <hi>Priest.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed by <hi>Iohn Macock,</hi> MDCLXIX.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:61397:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:61397:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>PROV. XXXI. 30.</bibl>
                     <q>Favour is deceitful, and Beauty is vain: but
a Woman that feareth the Lord, She shall
be Praised.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>WHO King <hi>Lemuel</hi> and his
Mother, mentioned in the
first <hi>Verse</hi> of this <hi>Chapter,</hi>
were, I shall not undertake
to decide; 'Tis agreed on by most Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
that by <hi>Lemuel</hi> is intended <hi>Solomon,</hi>
who, as <hi>Grotius</hi> observes, was <hi>Octanominis,</hi>
had eight several Names given him in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,
and by his Mother consequently is
meant <hi>Bathsheba,</hi> (thought the same <hi>Grotius</hi>
intimate too, it might be <hi>Hezekiah</hi> himself,
who order'd the Collection of these Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61397:4"/>
and his Mother <hi>Abijah</hi> the Daughter
of <hi>Zechariah:</hi>) and that <hi>Lemuel</hi> was <hi>blanda
matris Appellatio,</hi> a made word of Kindness
to sweeten her motherly Instructions.</p>
                  <p>In the <hi>Chapter,</hi> that we may come orderly
to the <hi>Text,</hi> there are two main Parts to be
observed.</p>
                  <p>I. The <hi>Queen Mothers Lesson</hi> to the young
Prince her Son, in the Nine first <hi>Verses.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>II. The <hi>Character of a good Woman,</hi> from
the 10. <hi>verse</hi> to the end. Which if it be
but the continuation of the Mother's Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture,
is then a <hi>Direction</hi> to him how to
chuse a Wife: but if we take it for a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posure
of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s, then 'twill be a dutiful
<hi>Return</hi> of the Son to his Mother's Instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
in a large <hi>Commendation</hi> of her Wisdom
and Care; wherein he sets her forth as the
Pattern of her Sex, and pleats <hi>Laudum Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rollam,</hi>
a Garland and Imperial Wreath of
Praises for his Mother's Royal Head.</p>
                  <p>Be this <hi>Good Woman</hi> then, in the History,
<hi>Bathsheba,</hi> or <hi>Abijah,</hi> or (as the Popish Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positors
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61397:4"/>
turn it) the <hi>Blessed Virgin;</hi> be she,
in the Allegory, the <hi>Church,</hi> or any pious
<hi>Soul:</hi> it cannot be deny'd, but that even <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terally</hi>
it belongs, and may properly be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd
to any Good Vertuous Woman what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever
of the whole Sex; who is here Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended
through all the Letters of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew
Christ-cross-row: This being <hi>Carmen
Alphabeticum in Laudes Bonae Foeminae,</hi> an
Alphabetical Poem in the Praise of a Good
Woman.</p>
                  <p>And though the whole of the Descripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
be <hi>Praise;</hi> yet we may take a distinct
notice of two <hi>Particulars</hi> contained in this
<hi>Poem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I. Her <hi>Properties</hi> or <hi>Vertues,</hi> reckon'd up
all along to the 28. <hi>verse.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>II. Her <hi>Praise</hi> more Emphatically ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prest
in the very Close, the four last <hi>Verses.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Her <hi>Vertues,</hi> to give you a brief <hi>Summa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>
of them, are</p>
                  <p>Her <hi>Conjugal Fidelity;</hi> verse 11.</p>
                  <p>Her <hi>Kindness</hi> and <hi>Constancy of Affection;</hi>
verse 12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:61397:5"/>
Her <hi>Houswifery</hi> and <hi>Diligence;</hi> v. 13. 19.</p>
                  <p>Her <hi>Thrift</hi> and <hi>Menage;</hi> verse 15, 16.</p>
                  <p>Her <hi>Industry</hi> and <hi>Assiduity;</hi> vers. 17, 18.</p>
                  <p>Her <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Liberality to the Poor;</hi>
verse 20.</p>
                  <p>Her <hi>Providence</hi> and <hi>Forecast;</hi> verse 21.</p>
                  <p>Her <hi>Magnificence</hi> in her <hi>Furniture</hi> and
<hi>Apparel;</hi> verse 22.</p>
                  <p>Her <hi>Reputation</hi> in <hi>Publick;</hi> V. 23. 25.</p>
                  <p>Her <hi>Traffick</hi> and <hi>Credit abroad;</hi> in Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
v. 24. in Buying, v. 16. and in
both, v. 14.</p>
                  <p>Her <hi>Discretion</hi> and <hi>Obligingness</hi> in her
<hi>Discourse;</hi> v. 26.</p>
                  <p>Her <hi>Care of Home,</hi> and <hi>good Government
of her Family;</hi> v. 27.</p>
                  <p>Her <hi>Praise</hi> to these many <hi>Vertues</hi> is three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</p>
                  <p>1. <hi>At Home,</hi> by her <hi>Husband</hi> and <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren;</hi>
who do not speak out of Flattery, but
as having been constant Witnesses of her
Vertuous Carriage, <hi>ver.</hi> 28. commending
her in this form of words, <hi>ver.</hi> 29. <hi>Many
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61397:5"/>
Daughters have done Vertuously, but Thou ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellest
them all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2. <hi>Pro Rostris,</hi> solemnly out of the <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit,</hi>
in the words of the <hi>Text:</hi> for so <hi>She shall
be praised,</hi> implies a solemn <hi>Commemoration</hi>
of her <hi>Vertues,</hi> and an Encomiastick <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rangue</hi>
upon her <hi>Person.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>3. For an everlasting <hi>Memorial</hi> of her,
throughout <hi>the whole Country,</hi> where she li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved:
common <hi>Fame</hi> shall do her that right;
in the last Verse, <hi>Her own Works shall praise
her in the Gates:</hi> to wit, <hi>among the Elders of
the Land,</hi> as 'tis <hi>ver.</hi> 23. among the Nobles
and Rulers of the Kingdom; Persons of the
highest Place and greatest Quality.</p>
                  <p>Our present business is that Part of her
<hi>Praise,</hi> which is to be perform'd in this place:
whereto, as I have always accounted it no
mean Advantage of my life to have been
known to a Person of so eminent a Worth
and Goodness; so I find my self somewhat
enabled by that personal Knowledge for a
fair discharge of the Duty of this Hour,
without being much beholden either to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61397:6"/>
publick Report, or private Information:
though the Whole almost, of what I have
to say, will be That too, which All, that
hear me, will readily back with their Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</p>
                  <p>To come to the business then; the <hi>Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Woman's Commendation</hi> here is expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,</p>
                  <p>I. Negatively, or, if you will, Compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively.
<hi>Favour is deceitful, and Beauty is vain.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>II. Positively: <hi>But a Woman that feareth
the Lord, She shall be Praised.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As if he had said, <hi>Favour</hi> and <hi>Beauty</hi> are
Idle, Insignificant, sorry, mean, toyish Things,
that deserve not serious Commendation, at
least are not fit to come in Competition
with Vertue and Discretion and Piety, which
are the truly Laudable Qualities, and make
the only durable lasting Foundation, to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
a Monument of <hi>Praise</hi> upon. 'Tis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
the Humour and Custom of wanton
loose Wits, to Court the Beautiful, to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
the Fair, and the Gay ones in their
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61397:6"/>
Sonnets; and to make <hi>Elogies</hi> upon them,
while they are Living, and <hi>Elegies</hi> when
Dead: but alas! Those are poor Subjects in
comparison of the Good and Vertuous; and
when those Poets Laurels and their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresses
Praises too shall be blasted by <hi>Truth,</hi>
and withered by <hi>Time,</hi> the Woman that <hi>fears
the Lord,</hi> the Pious Lady, the Vertuous Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron
<hi>shall be Praised</hi> on still, and her Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
ever continue fresh and green.</p>
                  <p>We shall, to clear our way for the prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<hi>Vertue</hi> the alone Praise-worthy thing,
shew the <hi>Deceit</hi> &amp; <hi>Vanity</hi> of those other two
Candidates for Praise. <hi>Favour and Beauty.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Favour,</hi> in the Original, <hi>Grace,</hi> that is, the
gracefulness of Habit, Gesture, Gate, Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course,
and the Attractives of a hansom
Carriage, so as to gain Beholders Love;
<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> say the Septuagint, <hi>the Complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sances</hi>
of Conversation, which do readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
procure peoples Favour and good Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.
Ag in, <hi>Beauty</hi> in the Symmetry and
Proportion of Parts, in the Feature and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61397:7"/>
Complexion; That which strikes the Eye
and affects the Heart. And yet both these
<hi>deceitful</hi> and <hi>vain;</hi> for these Reasons.</p>
                  <p>1. <hi>As Frail and Subject to Decay,</hi> whether
in their own <hi>Nature,</hi> (or which is all one as
to the Praise and Esteem of them) in the
<hi>Opinions</hi> of Men. The Fairest Face is as brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,
as the Glass it views it self in, and is at
best thus but a <hi>Miroir</hi> of Beauty, and when
broken with Age or marr'd by Disease, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes
a <hi>Looking-glass</hi> of Mortality. The
distinction betwixt Beauty and Deformity
is quite lost in the Grave, and many times
before they come there. Besides, These are
things, that owe their Estimate to the <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi>
of men, and not to any Intrinsick Value;
which is therefore as mutable and uncertain
as Opinion, which 'tis built upon. And this
crys up one thing to day, another to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.
<hi>Thamar,</hi> after <hi>Amnons</hi> wicked satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction,
was as Unpleasing in his eyes, as she
was Fair before. Nay, the Text says, that
<hi>the Hatred, wherewith he hated her, was great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
than the love, wherewith he had loved her.</hi>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:61397:7"/>
And it appears so by his usage of her; for
a <hi>Friend</hi> was imploy'd to bring her in, but
a <hi>Servant</hi> serv'd to turn her out, and bolt
the door after her.</p>
                  <p>2. <hi>As things that may be Counterfeited
and put on.</hi> These are many times but asci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titious
Ornaments: when <hi>Art</hi> is taught
to supply the defects, and to repair the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cays
of <hi>Nature.</hi> Nor is <hi>Beauty</hi> alone thus
false, when some through a Fantastick
Pride or some worse Distemper, walk as if
they were their own <hi>Sepulcres, Painted;</hi> but
<hi>Favour</hi> or <hi>Grace</hi> it self may be abus'd to
meretricious ends; whilest in a demure
Aspect, and a graceful Behaviour, it may
be difficult to distinguish betwixt a <hi>Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesan,</hi>
and a <hi>Matron,</hi> betwixt the <hi>strange
woman</hi> and the <hi>woman that fears the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>3. <hi>As they prove too frequently Occasions
of Evil, and Incentives to Lust.</hi> This is
indeed <hi>Fallax Gratia, a deceitful Favour,</hi>
which leads into Temptation, and a <hi>vain
Beauty</hi> which insnares and betrays the Soul.
Thus some of the <hi>Fathers</hi> tell us, the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:61397:8"/>
themselves were surpriz'd with the
Beauty of <hi>the daughters of men;</hi> from whom
came the Impious race of <hi>Giants.</hi> Some
Holy persons have upon this consideration
been remarkably Severe to themselves, mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieving
their Bodies to secure their Souls,
and preferring a Voluntary Deformity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
an Involuntary Temptingness. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi>
of <hi>Westminster</hi> tells us, that in the
year of <hi>Christ</hi> 870. when the <hi>Danes</hi> were
got into this Island, <hi>St. Ebbe</hi> with all her
Nuns of <hi>Colingham</hi> did all by one consent
cut off their noses and upper lips, to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage
wicked Attempts, and to preserve
their Chastity: which disappointment so
inrag'd the <hi>Danes,</hi> that, turning their Lust
into Cruelty, they burnt them all alive to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
with their Abbey. And <hi>Vincenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us
Bellovacensis</hi> tells us of another English
Nun, who being for her lovely Eyes covet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
of one of the King <hi>Richards,</hi> and by
him demanded of the <hi>Convent,</hi> got both her
Eyes pluck'd out, and sent them to him,
as a Present, in a Dish; with this Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61397:8"/>
that <hi>her Eyes were at the King's ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,
but her Heart was to be only Christ's.</hi>
This was very close to the Letter; <hi>If thine
Eye offend thee, pull it out.</hi> O dangerous
<hi>Beauty,</hi> which dost so hazard Vertue, when
'tis in thy company! O unfortunate <hi>Vertue,</hi>
that art thus fain to wound and mangle
thy self, that thou may'st be kept Intire!</p>
                  <p>However, notwithstanding this <hi>deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness</hi>
and <hi>vanity,</hi> Those Advantages of
good Carriage and a Courteous Behaviour,
of Beauty, and a graceful Aspect, are not
absolutely to be condemn'd, or to be at
all disparaged by us, where God gives
them; they being Blessings, as they come
from his Hand. And <hi>Vertue</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> it
self doth by this means oftentimes meet
with a fair Respect, and a kindly Welcom
in the World; a good Face and an inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous
Address being a kind of potent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation
even to Strangers, who will
be ready to think the Face a good <hi>Index</hi> of
the Mind; and a fair compos'd Body a suit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61397:9"/>
lodging for a Beauteous Soul. So I
know not how, <hi>Vertue</hi> having <hi>Favour</hi> and
<hi>Beauty</hi> for its Attendants and Maids of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,
appears more Serene, and yet no less
Majestick; and does more plausibly insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate
its Aw and Veneration into peoples
minds.</p>
                  <p>Nor is our <hi>Vertuous Woman</hi> here want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
in these Imbellishments, which may be
requisite either to her Sex or State; but is
like <hi>the Merchants Ships,</hi> to which she is
compar'd in the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                     <hi>ver.</hi> even in this Sense,
that she is not without her Tackle and
Ornaments. We find in the 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                     <hi>ver.</hi> that
<hi>her Cloathing is Silk and Purple:</hi> she goes
in good Habit, in a rich and fashionable
Garb, and <hi>ver.</hi> 26. that <hi>she openeth her
Mouth with Wisdom; and in her Tongue is
the law of Kindness:</hi> she charms all she
Converses with, and wins them with her
Discourse. But then she prizes these <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages</hi>
under these three <hi>Conditions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1. <hi>Not so as ambitiously to seek them, or
fondly to Vaunt them.</hi> She would not bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:61397:9"/>
a Complexion from her Boxes; but,
what S<hi rend="sub">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Nazianzen</hi> says of his Sister <hi>Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonia</hi>
in her <hi>Funeral Oration,</hi> likes that <hi>Red</hi>
best, which she owes to a blushing Modesty,
and that <hi>White</hi> or <hi>Pale,</hi> which comes by a
severe Abstinenee.</p>
                  <p>2. <hi>Not so as to be Proud of them, or to
Rely upon them as solid goods. Beauty</hi> is
a thing but skin-deep, and at best is but a
<hi>Set-off,</hi> no real Substance. <hi>Piety</hi> is her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone
Confidence, and <hi>Vertue</hi> design'd for
the Pillar of her <hi>Praise;</hi> whereon her fair
<hi>Name</hi> shall be ingrav'd in legible Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters
to succeeding Generations.</p>
                  <p>3. <hi>Not so as to Mis-imploy them, but to
Guide them with Vertue and Discretion.</hi> She
likes a Chearful, but would not have it a
tempting Look. She composes her self all
over exactly to Innocence, and then makes
that very Innocence all over Complaisant:
and above all things takes care, that Beauty
may not be her Crime, and that the Fair
<hi>Vessel,</hi> her Soul is Imbarked in, may not want
a good <hi>Pilot,</hi> a Vertuous Mind to Govern it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:61397:10"/>
And this for the <hi>Negative</hi> or <hi>Compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi>
Part, that <hi>Favour</hi> and <hi>Beauty</hi> are not
of themselves Things commendable in
Women, any further then they are accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied
and manag'd by Discretion and
Vertue. We come now to the <hi>Position,</hi>
which is that <hi>a Woman, which feareth the
Lord, she shall be Prais'd.</hi> In which <hi>Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition</hi>
we have,
<list>
                        <item>1. The Subject; <hi>a Woman,</hi> with her
Qualification; <hi>that fears the Lord.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. The Predicate; <hi>She shall be Praised.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>WOMAN, in the primitive design of
Nature, <hi>God's Master-piece,</hi> being the last
work of Creation, and made with a great
deal of Deliberation and Solemnity. For
to look upon her as a Supernumerary
Creature, and one brought into the world
by the <hi>By,</hi> besides the Creator's first Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
upon <hi>second Thoughts</hi> (though Those
too amongst us Men, with whose methods
it pleases God out of condescension to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61397:10"/>
comply, pass for the Wisest) is to lay a
foul Imputation upon <hi>Divine Wisdom,</hi> as
if it had been at a stand, and were to seek.
Wherefore, as we use to argue, that <hi>All
things</hi> were made for the use and service
of Man; because He was made Last of all:
I do not see, if that Argument be good,
why the same <hi>Consequence</hi> should not be of
like force here too, that <hi>Man</hi> himself was
made for the service and affectionate Care
of the <hi>Woman,</hi> who was fram'd not only
<hi>after</hi> him, but <hi>out of</hi> him too, the more to
Ingage his tenderest, and dearest Respects.
Certainly this manner of Production doth
plainly evince the Equality of the <hi>Woman's</hi>
Merits and Rights with <hi>Man;</hi> she being a
noble <hi>Cyon</hi> transplanted from his Stock,
and by the Mystery of Marriage Implanted
into him again, and made One with him.
She is then Equally at least partaker with
him of all the <hi>Advantages,</hi> which apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
to <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> and alike Capable
of those <hi>Improvements,</hi> which by the Efforts
of Reason and the Methods of Education
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61397:11"/>
and the Instincts of the Blessed Spirit are to
be made upon it, and no less fitted in her
natural Ingeny for all kind of <hi>Studies</hi>
and <hi>Imployments:</hi> though Custom, like a
<hi>Salique Law,</hi> hath excluded them from
Publick Offices and Professions; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd
them mostly to the narrow Territories
of <hi>Home.</hi> Our <hi>Vertuous Woman</hi> here, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides
her <hi>Oeconomical</hi> Government (wherein
her Husband's cares are not concern'd)
plays the <hi>Purchaser</hi> and the <hi>Merchant,</hi> ver.
16. and 24. though too, whilst <hi>her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band
is sitting in the gates among the Elders
of the Land,</hi> ver. 23. <hi>her hands are holding
the distaff at</hi> home, <hi>ver.</hi> 19. A Learned
Woman of <hi>Vtrecht,</hi> has in a Printed Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course
fairly in this behalf vindicated the
Reputation of her Sex. Nor are there
wanting Illustrious Examples of <hi>Those,</hi> who
for Atchievments in <hi>Arms</hi> and Attainments
of <hi>Arts</hi> have not come short of the Bravest
Men; and lest behind them signal proofs,
that their <hi>Minerva</hi> can upon occasion, as
well weild the <hi>Sword,</hi> and manage the <hi>Pen,</hi>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:61397:11"/>
as lay her hands to the <hi>Spindle.</hi> One In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance
out of our own History will be suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient;
<hi>Elizabeth</hi> of Happy Memory, who
44 years together sway'd the Scepter of
this Realm, with as much Repute as ever
any of her Predecessors did, and through
all her Reign shew'd at once the Spirit and
Resolution of her <hi>Father,</hi> and the Policy
and Wisdom of her <hi>Grand-father,</hi> without
their Vices.</p>
                  <p>Hence it was, that all <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences,</hi>
all <hi>Vertues</hi> and <hi>Graces,</hi> both <hi>Divine</hi> and
<hi>Moral,</hi> are represented in the shape and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit
of Women. Nor is there any reason for
fancying <hi>Angels</hi> themselves more of Our
Sex then of the Other; since amongst them
there's no such Distinction, but they may
be as well imagin'd <hi>Female,</hi> as Male. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
all, for <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Devotion,</hi> which is
the Top-perfection of our Nature, and
makes it most like <hi>Angelical,</hi> as the Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city
of Women is as large, so their Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations
are generally more vigorous; the
natural Biass and Tendency of their Spirits
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61397:12"/>
lying that way, and their softer Temper
more kindly receiving the supernatural
Impressions of God's Spirit. This is <hi>That,</hi>
if any thing, which gives their Sex the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence
above us Men, and gains them
just advantages of <hi>Praise;</hi> that, whereas
Those, who have only a hansom Shape and
good Features to command them, are A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor'd
and Idoliz'd by persons of slight Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensions
and ungovern'd Passions; <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi>
and <hi>Vertuous Women</hi> command the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration
of the most Judicious, and are
deservedly Admired by Holy Men and
Angels. Hereupon S<hi rend="sub">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Ierom,</hi> though no
Friend to a Married life, yet seem'd to pride
himself in his Acquaintance with <hi>Vertuous
Women,</hi> and made so many Addresses to
<hi>Religious Ladies,</hi> that those very <hi>Epistles</hi>
and <hi>Missives</hi> of His, which wear <hi>Female</hi>
Names, would make a competent Volume
of themselves. And our Blessed <hi>Lord</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
has in his History honour'd <hi>Them</hi> with
a frequent mention, as his ordinary Asso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates
and constant Attendants. Thus
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61397:12"/>
                     <hi>the Woman who feareth the Lord shall be
praised.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That's the Qualification; <hi>She that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
the Lord:</hi> for that is the right <hi>Vertuous
Woman,</hi> in the 10. <hi>ver. whose price is far
above Rubies.</hi> But there we have an <hi>Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi>
which I must first take out of the way:
Where shall we meet with such an One?
<hi>Who can find a Vertuous Woman?</hi> I can
speak it with as much Truth, as I must
speak it with Sorrow, we have lost <hi>One;</hi>
for by all the Description, if there be
such an One to be found, This was <hi>She.</hi>
But this <hi>Question</hi> does not import an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possibility,
but only the Difficulty of find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
her. He had in vain taken all this pains
to describe her so at large, if there be no
such Person to be found. There are sure
such Women; more perhaps then Men,
as Men are now, deserve there should be;
and as they are extraordinary Blessings, so
they that Fear God shall meet with them.
'Tis shrewdly <hi>Observ'd</hi> by one, that the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61397:13"/>
of their Paucity proceeds from us
Men. Men being generally so Evil, as
they are, make Women generally not so
good, as they would be. For at that time
of the World, when Men priz'd <hi>Vertue,</hi> and
made that the Standard of their Affection
and the Sole Object of their Choice; when
Discretion and Goodness were lookt on as
the Taking things, and Piety alone, was
accounted a sufficient Portion; then in that
<hi>Golden Age,</hi> the great Emulation of that
<hi>Sex</hi> was, who should weigh most in real De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serts,
and come best Dowried with those
desirable Qualities, when <hi>Wives</hi> were to be
bid for, and purchased at considerable
Rates. But now since the Scales have been
turn'd, and love has been brought into the
Market, that <hi>Vertue</hi> and good Education
are undervalued, and <hi>Wealth</hi> is become the
Lovely Thing, and all the Shafts of mens
Destres are Tipt with Gold and Silver; or
else by <hi>Some</hi> that lay their Judgments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side,
and let their Fancy choose for them,
<hi>Beauty</hi> is made the Mark, and so there be a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61397:13"/>
fair inviting Outside, no regard had to the
Inward disposition of the Mind; 'twas Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequent
that Women also should grow
more negligent of Vertue, and apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
more particularly to those Things,
for which they were to be priz'd and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem'd
by Men. And yet there are still,
notwithstanding this Degeneracy of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
such Women to be found of the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive</hi>
Stamp; who, though they may, in
common Civility to Vulgar Error, comply
in sinless <hi>Fashions</hi> and <hi>Modes,</hi> and in the
Innocent <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of life (taken up by
Others peradventure, to ill Ends, in these
corrupt Ages) yet do make it their main
Imploy to inrich and beautifie their Minds,
and bestow most of their Time in the Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
and Adornments of their Souls. To
find them out, let us Examine the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter,
by which the Hue and Cry is
made. She, whom we call the <hi>Vertuous
Woman,</hi> goes amongst the Interpreters un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
several names.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>[<hi>Esheth Hhaïl</hi>] say some, a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61397:14"/>
                     <hi>Stout Valiant Woman;</hi> so the French, <hi>une
Vaillante Femme:</hi> a <hi>Virago,</hi> one fit to lead
an Army; so that, as it follows in the next
verse, <hi>her Husband shall have no need of
Spoil.</hi> Fear being so natural to this Sex.
it looks like Miracle to meet with such an
One; and yet we read there have been
whole Nations of Them: Witness the
<hi>Amazonian</hi> Courage, and the valour of the
<hi>Spartan</hi> Ladies.</p>
                  <p>Others, <hi>strenuain &amp; sedulam,</hi> a busie In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrious
Woman, one of a stirring active
Spirit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Woman of Wealth and Riches,</hi> says
<hi>Aben Ezra,</hi> which is not One of a great Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
for Then there was no such Custom;
but one that by Industry and good Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagery
got Wealth: so in the <hi>verse</hi> before
the <hi>Text</hi> she is commended in the <hi>Margin</hi> of
our Bibles, <hi>Many Daughters have gotten
Riches, but Thou surpassest them all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A right good Vertuous Woman,</hi> so the
<hi>Chaldee:</hi> one that in her Carriage and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
shews that she has the Fear of God in
Her.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:61397:14"/>
                     <hi>A Discreet Wise Woman,</hi> say Others; or
as an ancient <hi>Armenian</hi> Copy has it, one <hi>of
a Sound Brain,</hi> and a good Understanding:
and this falls in with <hi>the Fear of God</hi> here,
which, the Wise Son and the Pious Father
both tell us, is <hi>the Beginning,</hi> or, as the
Hebrew word imports, <hi>the Sum Total of
Wisdom. And they have a good Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing
that Do thereafter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This <hi>fear of God</hi> doth not only Contract,
but Dilate the Heart too, laying Restraints
indeed upon the Conscience from Sin, but
withal Inlarging the powers of the Soul to
all kind of Duty: for 'tis an Ingenuous
<hi>Filial Fear,</hi> that has a very quick sense and
tender Apprehension of God's Displeasure,
and makes her wary of offending him,
either in Doing any thing that should not
be done, or Omitting ought that should.
'Tis not a <hi>Fear</hi> then, that ariseth from the
Weakness and Imbecillity of Female Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution,
which renders them more apt to
Devotion; but is very well consistent with
that <hi>Valour</hi> and <hi>Courage,</hi> which the 70, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61397:15"/>
other Interpreters make the great Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
of the Character, Imboldning us and
putting us on to Do or Suffer any thing
for God's sake. And we may consider it
Two Ways. 1. In the <hi>Root</hi> and <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple.</hi>
2. In the <hi>Branches</hi> and <hi>Productions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the <hi>Principle,</hi> 'tis a <hi>Reverential Fear,</hi>
which composes the Inner man to becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Thoughts and awful Apprehensions of
God, and obliges the Heart close to him
with Silken Cords, and binds up all the
Affections, that they may not run loose
after Vanities, but fixes them upon Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly
things, and suits all the <hi>Passions</hi> of
<hi>Humane Nature</hi> in a fit and constant Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spondence
to the <hi>Attributes</hi> of the <hi>Divine;</hi>
so as to <hi>Love</hi> him for his <hi>Goodness, Admire</hi>
him for his <hi>Wisdom, Dread</hi> him in his <hi>Power,</hi>
stand in <hi>Aw</hi> of his <hi>Iustice,</hi> take <hi>Delight</hi> in
the remembrance of his <hi>Mercies,</hi> and at
last to be swallowed up into <hi>Him</hi> in the
Contemplation of his <hi>Infiniteness,</hi> in all
These.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:61397:15"/>
In its <hi>Operations,</hi> that is, in all the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of Life; for, like the <hi>Warp,</hi> it runs
through the whole <hi>Web</hi> of all Her Duties;
it Tutors the Senses, and puts all the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
in Array, and orders the Outward man
into an answerable <hi>Decorum</hi> to the Inward;
that her Looks, her Speech, her very Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture
and Carriage, prove innocent Expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions
of honest Meanings, and a Vertuous
Mind; and all the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
Appearances of Her in her Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation
are but the natural Representments
of her Bright Spotless Ingenuous <hi>Soul,</hi> the
fair Inmate of a rightly Disciplin'd and
well Order'd <hi>Body.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Fear of God</hi> then comprehends in it
all <hi>Religious Worship,</hi> both <hi>Internal</hi> and
<hi>External:</hi> nor doth it consist in an hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical
Demureness, and a distantial Pride,
or supercilious Contempt of others, but in
a sincere <hi>Humility</hi> to God, and <hi>Charity</hi> to
Men; when, which is the Vertuous Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's
Practice, what with <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>set</hi>
on the one side, to which she alway pays
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61397:16"/>
a regular Attendance; and her <hi>Family</hi> on
the other, which she is always, what with
Instruction, what with Example, looking
after, She is continually Imploy'd, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides
her Time betwixt the Offices of a
Chearful <hi>Devotion</hi> and the Duties of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dearing
<hi>Converse.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now certainly if there be such a Reward
as <hi>Praise</hi> appointed for the <hi>Pious,</hi> if <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi>
hath its Temple adjoyn'd to that of
<hi>Vertue;</hi> then this Pious <hi>Vertuous Woman,</hi>
here mention'd, must be reckon'd the truly
<hi>Honourable Woman,</hi> and will deserve to
have her Grave strow'd with Roses and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets,
and her Memory crown'd with Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
Chaplets and Myrtle Wreaths of fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant
and lasting <hi>Praises.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That's the <hi>Next</hi> thing we have to do;
<hi>She shall be Praised.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is a Morose <hi>Humour</hi> in some, even Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters;
that they will not give a due <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation</hi>
to the <hi>Deceased:</hi> whereby they
not only offer a seeming Unkindness to the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61397:16"/>
Dead, but do a real Injury to the Living,
by discouraging Vertue, and depriving us
of the great Instruments of Piety, <hi>good Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples;</hi>
which usually are far more effectual
Methods of Instruction, then any Precepts;
These commonly urging only the Necessity
of those Duties, which the Other shew the
Possibility and Manner of Performing. But
then 'tis a most Unchristian and Uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<hi>Mistake</hi> in those, that think it unlawful
to <hi>Commemorate</hi> the Dead, and to Celebrate
their Memories: whereas there is no one
thing does so much uphold and keep up
the Honour and Interest of Religion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
the Multitude, as the due Obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance
of those <hi>Anniversaries,</hi> which the
Church has, upon this Account, scatter'd
throughout the whole course of the Year,
would do: and indeed to our Neglect of
this in a great Part the present Decay of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
may rationally be Imputed. Thus
in this Age of our's what <hi>Pliny</hi> saith of His,
<hi>Postquàm desiimus facere laudanda, Laudari
quo<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ineptum putamus.</hi> Since People have
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:61397:17"/>
left off doing things that are Praise-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,
they look upon <hi>Praise</hi> it self as a silly
thing. And possibly the Generality of
Hearers themselves are not free from this
Fault; who peradventure may Fancy their
Own Life Upbraided, when they hear A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers
Commended. But that the servants
of God, which depart this life in his <hi>Faith</hi>
and <hi>Fear,</hi> may and must be <hi>Praised,</hi> I
shall endeavour to make good upon these
three <hi>Grounds.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1. <hi>In common Iustice to the Deceas'd
themselves.</hi> Ordinary Civility teaches us to
speak well of the Dead. <hi>Nec quicquam San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctius
habet Reverentia Superstitum, quàm
ut Amissos Venerabiliter Recordetur;</hi> says
<hi>Ausonius,</hi> and makes this the ground of the
<hi>Parentalia,</hi> which had been ever since <hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi>'s
time. <hi>Praise,</hi> however it may become
the Living, is a just Debt to the deserts of
the Dead, who are now got clear out of
the reach of Envy; which, if it have any
thing of the Generous in it, will scorn,
Vultur-like to prey upon Carcass. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:61397:17"/>
Christianity lays a greater Obligation
upon us; The <hi>Communion of Saints</hi> is a <hi>Tenet</hi>
of our Faith. Now as we ought not to <hi>Pray</hi>
To them or For them, so we may and must
<hi>Praise</hi> them. This is the least we can do in
Return for those great Offices they did the
Church <hi>Militant,</hi> while they were with Us,
and now do, they are with God: nor have
we any other probable way of <hi>Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi>
with them. The <hi>Philosopher</hi> in his <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals</hi>
makes it a Question, whether the Dead
are any way Concern'd in what befals Them
or their Posterity after their Decease; and
whether those Honours and Reproaches,
which Survivers cast upon them, reach them
or no? and He concludes it after a long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate
in the <hi>Affirmative:</hi> not so, he says, as
to alter their <hi>State,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute
to it. <hi>Tully,</hi> though not absolutely
perswaded of an Immortal Soul, as speaking
doubtfully and variously of it, yet is constant
to this, that He takes a good Name and a
Reputation, we leave behind us, to be a
kind of <hi>Immortality.</hi> But there is more in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:61397:18"/>
it then so: Our Remembrance of the Saints
may be a Means to Improve their Bliss, and
Heighten their Rewards to all Eternity. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi>
the Father of the Faithful, hath his
Bosom thus daily Inlarg'd for New Comers.
Whether the Heirs of the Kingdom are at
their first Admission Instated into a full Pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session
of all their Glory, and kept to that
Stint; I think may be a Doubt. For if the
<hi>Faculty</hi> be perfected by the <hi>Object,</hi> about
which 'tis Conversant; then the Faculties of
those Blessed Ones being continually Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd
upon an Infinite Object, must needs
be Infinitely Perficible, and Capable still of
being more and more Inlarg'd, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
of receiving still new and further
Additions of Glory. Nor only so (This is
in Heaven:) but even the Influence of that
<hi>Example,</hi> they leave behind them on Earth,
drawing still more and more Souls after
them to God, will also add to those Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements
to the End of the World, and
bring in a Revenue of <hi>Accessory Ioys.</hi> And
would it not be Unjust in us then to deny
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:61397:18"/>
them those Glorious Advantages, which our
<hi>Commemoration</hi> and <hi>Imitation</hi> may and ought
to give them?</p>
                  <p>2. <hi>In a due Acknowledgment of Gods Gifts
and Graces.</hi> The <hi>Praise</hi> of his Servants re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounds
to his <hi>Glory;</hi> as Water rises to the
same height it had in its Well-spring. The
<hi>Father of Lights</hi> gives order, that <hi>Our
Light,</hi> which he communicates to us, <hi>may so
shine, that men may see our good Works and
Glorifie Him:</hi> nor has he only annexed to
our Temporal Services an Eternal weight of
Glory hereafter; but even here in this
World is content we should go Shares with
him, and be made Partakers of that Glory,
we bring into his Infinite Stock. The <hi>Servant</hi>
was justly condemn'd, that put his Master's
<hi>Talent</hi> in a Napkin, and buried it under
ground: nor would our Ingratitude be less
Inexcusable, should we in silence bury those
Gifts he has bestowed upon any his Eminent
Servants, that have by his Grace well Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd
them, and wrap up the Memories of
his Saints in the same Shrowd with their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:61397:19"/>
Lastly, <hi>For the Benefit of the Living;</hi> and
that two Ways: for their <hi>Instruction,</hi>
and for their <hi>Comfort.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the Instruction of all that are to come
After, 'tis fit the lives of those that have gone
Before should be Remembred.</hi> 'Tis not enough
to have a <hi>Map</hi> of the Country we are Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling
to, unless we have experience'd <hi>Guids,</hi>
whose Conduct and Directions we may safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
follow. Our way to Heaven does not
lye so ready and plain, that we cannot Miss
it; and here 'tis dangerous to trust to our
own Judgment, and (which was one kind of
ancient <hi>Superstition</hi>) to resolve our selves as
our <hi>Staff</hi> falls: but our surest Course will
be, to observe the Track of others Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steps,
and walk in their Faith, and go on in
the beaten Road of <hi>Holy Examples,</hi> for fear
of being either led aside into the untrodden
By-paths of <hi>Schism</hi> and <hi>Separation,</hi> or carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
along in the broad High-way of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneness</hi>
with the mistaking Multitude. As
in a Voyage by Sea the skilful <hi>Pilot,</hi> though
he consult his Card, and steer by his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pass,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:61397:19"/>
yet he neglects not the Discoveries, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<hi>Navigators</hi> have made, that have sayl'd
those Seas, and given notice of Rocks and
Shelves, and describ'd the Coastings and
<hi>Rhumbs</hi> of the whole Course. <hi>Example</hi>
gives life to a <hi>Rule,</hi> makes it Intelligible and
Practicable. God's bare Commanding us to
do any thing is a sufficient Obligation to O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience;
but when by Others he shews us
<hi>How</hi> 'tis to be done, this as it renders it
more Easie to Obey, so it puts our Disobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
past all Excuse.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the Comfort of Survivers that stay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind,
the Vertues and Praises of their Deceas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
friends are to be Recounted;</hi> that they may
not Mourn and hang down the Head with
Despondence, as having no <hi>Hope.</hi> It was
the Custom of some <hi>Barbarous Nations</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the very consideration of the Troubles of
this Life, from which Death sets us Free, to
attend their Dead with solemn Shouts and
Expressions of Joy: but <hi>We,</hi> who have bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
Assurances, when any of our Relations
are delivered from the Sins and Miseries of a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:61397:20"/>
Wicked and Wretched World, have much
greater reason to Rejoyce in their behalf, if
by the Testimony of a good Life they have
confirm'd those blessed Expectations, Upon
which the Hinge of all Religion turns. For
in that we Grieve, 'tis for our Own sakes,
not for Theirs. 'Tis Our loss, we Lament.
They are infinitely Advantaged by the
Change. Why then should we repine at their
Advancement, with them back to their Hurt,
and be discontented for the want of their
Company, who, as <hi>St. Paul</hi> says in another
case, <hi>are therefore Departed for a season, that
we may Receive them for ever,</hi> if We by fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
their good Example be found wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
to be Admitted to Them. If it be a
Kindness to Them, that our Hearts are
touch'd with, we should rather, according
to the Apostle's Rule, <hi>Rejoyce with them
that Rejoyce,</hi> and not Weep over them,
since all Tears are now wiped away from
their Eyes. 'Tis usual in great transports
of Joy for Tears to burst out: and such
should be our Tears over Those, that by
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:61397:20"/>
Living well Learnt and Practis'd to <hi>Dye
Well,</hi> to flow from Joy as well as Sorrow;
and our <hi>Ioy</hi> that they are in Heaven should
far exceed the <hi>Grief</hi> we show for their leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Earth. I have read of Parents, that,
when their Sons have return'd Conquerers
from the <hi>Olympick Games,</hi> could not master
their Resentments, but have dyed with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessive
Joy. Now, in a Christian sense, to
have fought a good Fight, and with a Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
Faith to overcome the World, how
much more considerable a Conquest is it,
and how does it deserve our most concern'd
Joys? That in any Friend's case, that Dyes
thus, it would become us to say what S. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi>
did, when word was brought of <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi>
his death, <hi>Come let us go, and Dye with
him.</hi> It was Kindly said, and perhaps not
Fondly neither. For certainly the most
exquisite Felicities of Life are not Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
to the Advantage of a Holy Death.
Let us then upon such Occasions, (as we use,
when any Friend alters his Condition to the
Better, to <hi>Wish</hi> him <hi>Ioy;</hi>) Gratulate those
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61397:21"/>
that Dye thus in the Lord; not consider
what We have Lost, but what they have
Gain'd; and joyn with Them in singing
<hi>Hallelujahs,</hi> Praising them, and Praising God
for them, and Praising God with them.
<hi>Praise</hi> is a Chearful Exercise; wherefore
let me Entreat, that those <hi>Noble Friends</hi>
and <hi>Relations,</hi> who have any Share in this
day's Loss, whilst I practically <hi>Apply</hi> to the
Duty of the Text in Praising this <hi>Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Vertuous Woman</hi> before us, would lay
aside their own Concerns, and be Comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
as they do mean heartily to Joyn with
me in the Acknowledgment of her <hi>Praises.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I would not detain you long, I need not.
All that has been, or may be said of the
<hi>Vertuous Woman,</hi> belongs to Her. To say
all that might be said, would not be the
Business of an Hour, but of Days and
Weeks. The bare Relation of her Life
would make the best <hi>Panegyrick.</hi> I shall
gather it up as close as I can, that it may be
both Brief and Useful: and That according
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:61397:21"/>
to our former Method, where we treated
of the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> which is here given as
Her Character.</p>
                  <p>First as to <hi>Principle;</hi> the Candour of
Her Disposition, the Sweetness of her Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
and the Evenness of her Temper,
whereof throughout her whole Life she
gave Innumerable Demonstrations. And
certainly <hi>Good Nature</hi> (however some Ill-natur'd
People, who would pass for the
most strictly Religious, may declaim against
<hi>It</hi> and all <hi>Morality</hi>) is the best Seed-plot
for Piety and all Vertue to thrive in; the
Kindliest Soil for the Fruits of the Spirit,
<hi>Meekness, Ioy, Patience, Gentleness, Long-suffering,
Loving kindness,</hi> &amp;c. which were
abundantly seen in all the Instances of her
Conversation.</p>
                  <p>Now because much of This may seem to
be Extracted from the Parents, and by Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neal
Descent to be derived from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily;
(For <hi>Fortes creantur Fortibus, &amp; Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni
Bonis.</hi> Vertues and good Qualities
likely run in a Blood) I must so far mention
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:61397:22"/>
Her <hi>Pedigree,</hi> as to give the True Blazonry
of her <hi>Vertues.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>She was <hi>Eldest Daughter</hi> to His <hi>Grace</hi> the
<hi>Duke of Newcastle,</hi> a Person of no less <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence</hi>
in His Merit and in His Nature, then
he is in his Title; One that has been the
most Illustrious Example in all the three
Nations of an Acting and Suffering Loyalty.
To him, besides His other vast Deserts, the
World ow'd this <hi>Excellent Lady;</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
powerfully inclin'd by Instinct and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
and Choice to be like Her Noble Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
did so Naturally Resemble Him, and
so Affectionately Imitate Him, that She re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented
the lively Characters of his Soul
as well as Feature.</p>
                  <p>Nor must I omit her <hi>Pious Mother,</hi> a
Lady of most Exemplary Charities, from
whom She received the first Elements of her
Vertuous Education; and Her Noble
<hi>Grand-Mother,</hi> the Lady <hi>Ogle,</hi> whose Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
she was; who, to this Lady <hi>IANE</hi>
did in her life and at her death give parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
Testimonies of an extraordinary Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:61397:22"/>
which were often gratefully remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred
and repeated by Her.</p>
                  <p>From these Advantages of <hi>Birth,</hi> that
Natural Principle of <hi>Goodness</hi> flow'd, which
being Inlarged by the Moral accessions of
Noble Breeding, and Impregnated with
Holy Exercises, and the Influences of God's
good Spirit, stream'd into all the Faculties
of her Soul; by which she became the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute
Governess of Her own Mind.</p>
                  <p>She had that Command of Her <hi>Passions,</hi>
that it might be questioned, whether she had
Any. <hi>Anger</hi> and She were so utter Strang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
that the very Expressions of Dislike
from Her were Obliging. <hi>Greatness</hi> and
<hi>Goodness</hi> of Mind kept her Soul always in
an equal Poise, so that she could never
fancy an Injury or an Ill meaning from any
one, or be upon any Provocation Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious.
She knew her self so Innocent and
<hi>Good,</hi> that she deserv'd no Ill, and therefore
suspected none; and withal She was of so
Generous and <hi>Great</hi> a Spirit, that unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses,
if intended, could not reach Her. So
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:61397:23"/>
that as on the one hand no body (she <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd</hi>)
would wrong Her, if they could;
so on the other, (she <hi>resolv'd</hi>) they should
not, if they would. Her soft yielding Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance
back'd with Magnanimity was like
polish'd <hi>Marble,</hi> smooth and strong. She was
seated above the clouded <hi>Atmosphere</hi> of
Worldly Joys and Troubles, even while
she was Here; and had wrought Her self to
a perfect <hi>Indifference</hi> and <hi>Vnconcernedness</hi> in
all things, but Her Service of God, and
Kindness to her Friends. She had no Value
for the World, nor Over-value for Her
self, who was one of the Best Parts of it.
For as Her <hi>Worth</hi> had set Her Even with
the Greatest; so Her <hi>Humility</hi> plac'd Her
familiarly with the Meanest: and yet this
attended with so natural a <hi>Becomingness,</hi>
that her very Humility exalted her, and
her Condescensions made her the more Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable
and Highly Esteemed.</p>
                  <p>Where the <hi>Passions</hi> are kept in this Aw
and Order, the <hi>Superiour Faculties,</hi> being
clear and undisturb'd, must needs exercise
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:61397:23"/>
all their <hi>Functions</hi> aright. She took, when
Young, special delight in her <hi>Father's</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
Composures. And she hath left in
Writing a considerable Stock of Excellent
ones of Her own, ever spending the time
that best pleased Her with her <hi>Pen.</hi> Above
all, <hi>Reading</hi> of good Discourses and making
of <hi>Pious Meditations</hi> were Her chief and
daily Imployment: to which and to Her <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions</hi>
she was so Constant, that, as she hath
fill'd some Volumes with the One; so for
the Other, from her Youth to her late
Death-bed she fail'd not of <hi>Prayer</hi> (as I am
Informed) thrice a day; and if Morning or
Noon hapned to be omitted, She would
make amends at Night, and then to be sure
even that Account. Herein lay her solid
Satisfaction, in Conversing thus with God,
that She lookt upon all Occasions, that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted
That, as Impertinent and Unea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie;
and if She had any Quarrel to <hi>this Place,</hi>
'twas this, the Multitude of Formal Visits,
which she could not avoid receiving from
<hi>London</hi> and returning, that took off her time
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:61397:24"/>
from these Spiritual Exercises.</p>
                  <p>This as to her <hi>Principle.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then as to the <hi>Emanations</hi> of It to the
Eye and Observation of the World, for we
have as yet been but in the <hi>Closet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In her <hi>Maiden-state;</hi> Of her Infant-years,
which were spent at <hi>Welbeck,</hi> (a place that
bears the Proportion and Resemblance of a
Court) under the Tuition of her Father and
Mother, we have already spoken. We shall
now treat of her more <hi>Adult Vertues.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What <hi>Courage</hi> and <hi>Loyalty,</hi> as the right
Daughter of a <hi>General,</hi> as the <hi>Valiant Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
here spoken of, did she shew, in keeping
the Garrison'd House of her Father, where
she was left with <hi>One</hi> of her <hi>Noble Sisters,</hi> as
a Sharer, in her Vertues and the Misfortunes
of Ill times (the <hi>Other</hi> being before that
Time Happily bestow'd) amongst the Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid
Circumstances of War, till taken by the
Enemy, and there made their Prisoners?</p>
                  <p>What Gallantry of <hi>Charity</hi> at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking
it by the King's Forces, when She
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:61397:24"/>
became Petitioner to save her <hi>Iaylor's</hi> life,
whose Treatments, though not Barbarous,
yet had been much short of such Civilities,
as to Persons of their Age, Tenderness, and
Quality were due?</p>
                  <p>What <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Magnanimity</hi> in all
the Disasters of Her <hi>Loyal Family;</hi> Her
Mother's Death, the Loss of my <hi>Lord's</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,
his leaving <hi>England,</hi> His and her Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
Banishment after and Proscription,
and the Seizure of all their Fortunes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side
Her own Personal Sufferings and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>settlements?</p>
                  <p>What <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Piety,</hi> when after the
<hi>Fifths</hi> were procur'd, She was inabled to
become Sollicitor for her Father and Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
when Loyalty was so Criminal, that
nothing less would serve then to Except
them from Life: when with all Her early
Diligences, and Attendances, and Petition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
how humbly and closely soever prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted,
She could not prevail for Her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
Her Brothers only with much diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty
had Pardon for Life? And then when
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:61397:25"/>
things were grown to that Extremity, that
All that could be had from an Enemy was
too scant a Support for Her Banisht Father.
(I have it from an Excellent Hand, that
with great Obligingness gives this Account
in Print) She converted Her own <hi>Peculium</hi>
of Jewels and Plate (which her Father and
Grand-Mother had given Her) into Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,
and sent it over a Token of Affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
Duty.</p>
                  <p>Nor stopt Her <hi>Duty</hi> here, but She con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
it together with her <hi>Obedience</hi> to her
<hi>Married state:</hi> having resolv'd without his
Leave and Consent not to change her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition;
nor so neither, without a Liberty
from her Intended Husband, out of that
Fortune, Her Father's Nobleness had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd
Her, to make him a considerable
Present (so I find it <hi>Nobly</hi> Acknowledg'd
by the same Excellent Authoress) of which
<hi>His Grace</hi> (I understand) soon after his
<hi>Restauration</hi> no less obligingly with greatest
Kindness of all generous and indearing Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions
Ordered a liberal Return.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:61397:25"/>
And then with what <hi>Condescending
Prudence</hi> and <hi>Iudicious Moderation</hi> did She
make her Choice, when having through
the Iniquity of the Times observ'd the
Desolation made in the Greatest Families,
and the little Choice then amongst those
Few left of the Higher Nobility, (for She
resolved to match with no Family, which
had ill-treated her King and Father, how
advantageous soever) She suiting her
Judgment to her Inclination accepted a
<hi>Gentleman,</hi> yet One (besides His othet
<hi>Accomplishments,</hi> and the <hi>Merit</hi> of his most
Affectionate <hi>Respects</hi>) of an <hi>Ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily</hi>
and a very <hi>Noble Descent,</hi> with whose
<hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Fortune</hi> She perswaded her
self of <hi>Content.</hi> And she found That per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion
did not deceive Her, having here
in <hi>Chelsey</hi> lived these 14 years and few
Months, as Well to Her own, as to the
great Satisfaction and Joy of every Body
else that knew Her.</p>
                  <p>How willing She ever was to Oblige all
persons; how Ready to all good Offices;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:61397:26"/>
how Meek, and Humble, and Charitable,
and Familiarly Courteous to Neighbours
and all others, let <hi>Fame,</hi> let <hi>Envy</hi> it self
speak.</p>
                  <p>Of her <hi>Charity</hi> to this <hi>Place</hi> I question
not but we shall see in a short Time some
fair Testimonies erected.</p>
                  <p>Her <hi>Devotions</hi> she lov'd particularly to
make out in Observing the <hi>Fasts</hi> of the
Church, as much and as oft, as the tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
of Her Constitution could well permit.</p>
                  <p>Next to <hi>Reading</hi> and <hi>Writing</hi> she de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted
much in her <hi>Needle,</hi> and hath left
great quantities of Work to her Children.</p>
                  <p>This in short the account of her <hi>Life</hi> in
its Healthful time.</p>
                  <p>We come at last to the sad Scene of her
<hi>Sickness</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi> wherein it pleas'd a
good God in some measure to answer her
desires (who had always a tender Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
for <hi>Pain</hi>) that, though the Fits to sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful
By-standers seem'd not to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
Pang and Agony, yet were graciously
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:61397:26"/>
Alleviated to Her by a <hi>Surprize</hi> of her
Senses, for the time, and That so Gentle
too, as never to cause any Disorder or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decency.
Nor after the Fits, at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn
of Spirits, sufficient to give Her li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
of Speech, did She ever (except two
of her four last days) complain of <hi>Pain,</hi>
which was then violent in her Head, but
even then and at all other times of her Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
while She had Speech, She used it
most in <hi>Devotion,</hi> and in many gentle chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
and obliging Expressions to her <hi>Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,
Children, Doctors,</hi> and other her
mournful <hi>Assistants.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Particularly in the Three weeks <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val,</hi>
She had, when there were very good
hopes of her <hi>Recovery,</hi> She used often to
say, <hi>That though she resigned up Her self
wholly to the wise disposal of a good God, yet
She being in expectation of being call'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
in her first Fits, look'd upon her Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
as a gracious kind of Disappointment</hi>
(they were Her own Words) <hi>by God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.
This She did</hi> (She said) <hi>not out
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:61397:27"/>
of Discontent at her Sickness, which she
thankfully acknowledged tolerable Easie, but
(as having conquered this World, and being
now in her Passage to a Better) out of her
intuition of a glorious Crown, that, She
trusted, awaited her in Heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now, now, was the Time, when all the
Powers of Her Soul, all Her Vertues and
Graces were Summon'd together, with uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
force to make up the <hi>Complin</hi> of her
<hi>Devotions;</hi> wherein she Profess'd, to the
Equal Comfort and Grief of Those that
heard Her, her <hi>Confidence</hi> in God, her patient
<hi>Submission</hi> to Him, her Holy <hi>Resignation,</hi>
her <hi>Indifference</hi> to Life, and her <hi>Prepared<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi>
to Dye. Of which, amongst many
others, there were two Remarkable <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances.</hi>
One to a <hi>Reverend Father of our
Church,</hi> whom she told with great Uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernedness,
as he was discoursing piously
to Her, <hi>That she was not afraid to Dye;
not that she had or fear'd any Trouble or
Discontent here, but that she might Injoy the
Blessings of that Better World.</hi> The Other
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:61397:27"/>
to <hi>Her</hi> sad and afflicted <hi>Husband,</hi> whom, as
He was at her Bed-side praying to God, that
he would restore Her again to Health, that
she might Live and Glorifie him, when
those, that went down into the Pit, could
not Praise him; she stopt Him in his <hi>Prayer,</hi>
and with a comfortable Look and strong
Voice (though a great difficulty of Speech
had some time before possest Her) said, <hi>She
would Glorifie God, whether she lived or dyed:</hi>
and then recommended <hi>her Children to His
Care:</hi> Who as He did in all her sickness out
of a strong <hi>Sympathy</hi> of Love, suitable to
His constant Tenderness and Her great Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
entertain all her Ills with quicker and
deeper Resentments (if we may consider
Those as Two, who were so nearly
One) then if they had been His Own;
that those <hi>Epileptick</hi> and <hi>Convulsive</hi> Fits,
which seiz'd Her Brain, did at the same time
seize His Heart: so after Her Dissoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
and the Departure of His Better Soul,
He finds no Reason to live, no Joy in life,
but This, to look after those living Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:61397:28"/>
of his Dear and Pious <hi>Deceased,</hi> and
to be Paying on that Love, which was Due
to Her, in the Indulgent Care of Her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
                  <p>These dear <hi>Children</hi> of Hers, as She had
often in her Health, so she did now more
frequently in her Sickness Instruct, charging
them to apply themselves much to <hi>Reading,</hi>
especially to be diligent in constant <hi>Prayers</hi>
to God, to be Observant to their <hi>Dear Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
and transferring that <hi>Obedience</hi> they
had to Her self upon Him, to pay Him now
a <hi>double Duty,</hi> and to be intirely <hi>Loving</hi> to
One another; Then and not else they might
assure themselves of all good things from
God and their Father. Further injoying
them to be <hi>Respectful</hi> to those that had the
charge of them, and ever to give ear to
their just and vertuous Advices: and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
to decline the Company of vain and
impertinent Persons.</p>
                  <p>As it was Her only Trouble in all her <hi>Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi>
that her Indisposition made Her unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable
of giving that Attendance to the <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:61397:28"/>
of Religion, Praying, Meditating, Reading,</hi>
as she used to do: So in the <hi>Close,</hi> it was the
great Affliction of <hi>All</hi> about Her, and that,
which of any thing She her self shew'd most
Sense of, that her Speech Fail'd her: upon
the Loss of which she had no other means of
Expressing those pious <hi>Ejaculations,</hi> She in
her last Sickness Incessantly poured forth,
but by Sighs, and Eyes and Hands lifted up
to Heaven; whither She is gone <hi>Bless Soul,</hi>
to increase the number of <hi>Saints,</hi> whom the
Church this day Commemorates, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
into the <hi>Ioy</hi> of her Saviour, having left
<hi>Grief</hi> behind Her.</p>
                  <p>Whom in the Whole, as to all <hi>Relations,</hi>
as Her <hi>Noble Father</hi> (in Whose Affections
if Any had a greater share then Other, it was
<hi>She</hi>) in a <hi>Letter</hi> of <hi>His</hi> since her Sickness
Stiles Her <hi>the Best of Daughters;</hi> so Her
<hi>Husband</hi> praises Her for the <hi>Best of Wives;</hi>
Her <hi>Children</hi> rise up and call <hi>the Best of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers;</hi>
Her <hi>Servants</hi> (for whose Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
and Reward she took care to the Last)
own as <hi>the Best of Mistresses;</hi> Her <hi>Allies</hi>
lookt upon as <hi>the Best of Friends;</hi> Those
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:61397:29"/>
that had the Honour to know Her, <hi>the Best
of Acquaintances;</hi> and Those that liv'd near
Her, <hi>the Best of Neighbours.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>May We All, that knew <hi>Her,</hi> keep her
<hi>Vertues</hi> alive in our Memory, and in our
Imitation. May her Worthy and Afflicted
<hi>Husband,</hi> as he does, praise Her, and with
a chearful gratitude mitigate his Sorrow, and
comfort himself with the expectation of a
Happy Meeting, when <hi>Her own Works shall
Praise her in the Gates</hi> of Heaven. May
her <hi>Children,</hi> those Three Noble Plants She
hath left behind Her as the dear Pledges of
her Memory, <hi>rise up</hi> and grow up in her
Example, and <hi>call her Blessed.</hi> And may
the <hi>Echo</hi> of her <hi>Praises</hi> tend to the setting
forth of the <hi>Praise</hi> of God, the <hi>Father</hi> of
<hi>Spirits,</hi> and the <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>Lights,</hi> from
whom cometh every good and perfect Gift.
To whom, the Immortal and Ever-blessed,
<hi>Three Persons</hi> and <hi>One God,</hi> We, together
with the whole Company of <hi>All</hi> his <hi>Saints,</hi>
ascribe, as is most due, all <hi>Honour, Praise</hi>
and <hi>Glory,</hi> Now and for Ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:61397:29"/>
                  <p>AN
ELEGY
ON THE
DEATH of the THRICE NOBLE
And VERTUOUS LADY
THE
Lady <hi>IANE CHEYNE,</hi>
Eldest DAUGHTER to <hi>WILLIAM</hi>
DUKE of <hi>NEWCASTLE,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By a Person of</hi> Quality <hi>and</hi> Neighbour <hi>in</hi> Chelsey.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:61397:30"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:61397:30"/>
                  <head>An Elegy on the Death of the Thrice
Noble and Vertuous Lady
the Lady Jane Cheyne, Eldest Daughter to Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am
Duke of Newcastle.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>DIsmal the darkness, fearful was the <hi>Night,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>All thoughts were banish'd bord'ring on delight;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nature</hi> wore <hi>Blacks,</hi> and the <hi>Worlds</hi> beauteous <hi>Eye</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Fled far from the approaching <hi>Tragedy:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>My doubtful <hi>Muse</hi> lay <hi>trembling,</hi> when the Knell</l>
                     <l>More doleful from the midnight passing Bell,</l>
                     <l>Subtracting hopes addition gave to <hi>Woe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Now ripe in <hi>Numbers,</hi> and in <hi>Tears</hi> to flow.</l>
                     <l>Ye <hi>Chelsey</hi> Fields no more your pleasures boast,</l>
                     <l>Your greatest <hi>Pride,</hi> is with your <hi>Lady,</hi> lost;</l>
                     <l>No more cry up your sweet, and healthy <hi>Air,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Now only fit for such as breath despair;</l>
                     <l>Of your delightful River brag no more,</l>
                     <l>Briny its Waves, and <hi>Fatal</hi> is its Shore;</l>
                     <l>Not all its Sands can count the Tears we spilt,</l>
                     <l>Not all its Stream can wash away this guilt.</l>
                     <l>Farewel (<hi>Dear Lady</hi>) now a blessed <hi>Saint:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Did not <hi>Religion</hi> on us lay restraint,</l>
                     <l>Our <hi>Vows</hi> and <hi>Prayers</hi> soon would turned be</l>
                     <l>From Praying for, to Praying unto <hi>Thee;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But these as fruitless are, as those are vain;</l>
                     <l>Thou feelest none, nor pitiest our pain,</l>
                     <l>Our Eyes will better shew the <hi>Love</hi> we bore,</l>
                     <l>Where to lament's more fit, then to implore;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:61397:31"/>
And sorrow sure our loss will most become,</l>
                     <l>Like <hi>losing Gamesters</hi> when we count the <hi>sum.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Her Noble <hi>Birth</hi> she from <hi>Newcastle</hi> took;</l>
                     <l>High in <hi>Bridgwater,</hi> and in <hi>Bullingbrook:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But she not half so <hi>Great</hi> as she was <hi>Good,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Ow'd her least <hi>Praise</hi> to her <hi>Illustrous blood;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>By her intrinsick <hi>Worth</hi> her <hi>Titles</hi> rise</l>
                     <l>More splendid from her <hi>Vertues,</hi> then <hi>Allies;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And she more <hi>Honour</hi> gave unto their <hi>Fames,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then she derived from their mighty <hi>Names,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet not pufft up with <hi>Honours Timpany,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Like <hi>Stars</hi> she less appear'd for being <hi>High;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And like them too she freely did dispence</l>
                     <l>On all beneath her gentle Influence;</l>
                     <l>So sweetly condescending, as if she</l>
                     <l>Less then our selves had own'd a <hi>Dignity;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Her Goodness did our <hi>Modesty</hi> besiege,</l>
                     <l>She never knew where she did not oblige:</l>
                     <l>Hence at her Ills so common was our grief,</l>
                     <l>Nothing but hers could perfect our relief;</l>
                     <l>Tears drown'd our Joy, Joy did from Tears release,</l>
                     <l>As her Distempers did arise or cease;</l>
                     <l>And at her Death an Universal groan</l>
                     <l>Was heard, as if her Fate had been our own.</l>
                     <l>Since then she's gone, Oh! that I could inherit</l>
                     <l>One portion of her great <hi>Poetick</hi> Spirit,</l>
                     <l>Like him who caught <hi>Elijah</hi>'s Mantle, I</l>
                     <l>Of Her and <hi>Heaven</hi> soon would <hi>Prophecy:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>My <hi>Muse</hi> should learn to bear a noble <hi>Part,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And boundless Grief make regular by <hi>Art:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>An <hi>Art</hi> she knew and practised so well,</l>
                     <l>Her <hi>Modesty</hi> alone could it excell;</l>
                     <l>Which by concealing doubles her Esteem:</l>
                     <l>'Tis hard to understand and not to seem.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:61397:31"/>
Wandring abroad small <hi>Poets</hi> does become,</l>
                     <l>Great <hi>Wits</hi> (like <hi>Princes</hi>) best are seen at home:</l>
                     <l>And yet her Name might <hi>Patronize</hi> a <hi>Muse</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Defying strictest Censure to accuse;</l>
                     <l>For whatsoe'er her <hi>Fancies</hi> stamp did own,</l>
                     <l>Was <hi>Sterling Coin</hi> to be refus'd by none;</l>
                     <l>Without <hi>allay,</hi> and as her self <hi>refin'd</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>High as her <hi>Birth,</hi> yet gentle as her mind;</l>
                     <l>Where <hi>Female</hi> sweetness manly strength did meet,</l>
                     <l>At once (like <hi>Samsons</hi> riddle) <hi>strong</hi> and <hi>sweet,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>If such her <hi>Art,</hi> her <hi>Nature</hi> was the same,</l>
                     <l>As this her <hi>Wit,</hi> so that adorn'd her Frame</l>
                     <l>Mov'd by a <hi>Soul</hi> so Pious, that might be</l>
                     <l>Well term'd a <hi>Beam</hi> of the <hi>Divinity;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which in her Life, and Actions shone so bright</l>
                     <l>That <hi>We</hi> i'ts <hi>Heat</hi> perceiv'd, as well as <hi>Light;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Her thousand <hi>Graces</hi> with a mingled <hi>Ray,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Made her Lifes Path seem one pure milky <hi>Way;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whilst others <hi>Splendors</hi> only shew their <hi>Blots;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>As the <hi>Moons</hi> Light discovers her own <hi>Spots.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Her <hi>Passions</hi> all to <hi>Reason</hi> gave the sway,</l>
                     <l>As she unto her <hi>Husband</hi> did obey;</l>
                     <l>From just <hi>Complyance</hi> neither did desist,</l>
                     <l>'Cause neither were accustom'd to resist;</l>
                     <l>Each kept within it's proper bounds, and range,</l>
                     <l>Serving to <hi>vary</hi> her, but ne're to <hi>change.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Her <hi>Humor</hi> still in Complaisance did 'bide,</l>
                     <l>Ne're ebb'd to Sullenness, nor swell'd to <hi>Pride.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>In her a <hi>Multiply'd Example's</hi> gone;</l>
                     <l>And many Noble <hi>Patterns</hi> lost in <hi>One:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>None more Devout, none was more Chast of Life,</l>
                     <l>None better <hi>Mother,</hi> none more loving <hi>Wife;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Three <hi>Blessings (Copies</hi> of her self) she brought,</l>
                     <l>Yet was her self the greatest <hi>Blessing</hi> thought:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:61397:32"/>
Worthy by none, but him to be possest,</l>
                     <l>Who best deserv'd her, 'cause he lov'd her best;</l>
                     <l>Such his affection as in <hi>Truth</hi> extends</l>
                     <l>Beyond th' Examples of the loving <hi>Friends:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Her griefs he griev'd, and all her <hi>Pains</hi> he felt,</l>
                     <l>As if one <hi>Soul</hi> within two <hi>Bodies</hi> dwelt;</l>
                     <l>And she from that did part (I'm bold to say)</l>
                     <l>With less regret then <hi>He</hi> from her away:</l>
                     <l>With hers He would have given up his <hi>Breath,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And Love preserv'd untoucht by mighty <hi>Death:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But that to dare to suffer life might prove</l>
                     <l>More kindness to the <hi>Pledges</hi> of her Love.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Pardon (<hi>Dear Saint</hi>) my <hi>Muses</hi> wandring fire;</l>
                     <l>Silence is heard, where'ts easie to admire:</l>
                     <l>The praise that him I give (praise justly due)</l>
                     <l>I'm sure you will not think detain'd from you;</l>
                     <l>'Tis equal to rejoyn, whom cruel Fate</l>
                     <l>So hardly did attempt to separate.</l>
                     <l>As you to dye his glory were content,</l>
                     <l>So may he live your noblest <hi>Monument.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
