<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Queen at White-Hall, January the 30th being the day of the martyrdom of King Charles the First by the Bishop of St. Asaph, Lord Almoner to Their Majesties.</title>
            <author>Lloyd, William, 1627-1717.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-08">2004-08 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48854</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2715</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20281</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12402576</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12402576</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61298</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A48854)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61298)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 767:35)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Queen at White-Hall, January the 30th being the day of the martyrdom of King Charles the First by the Bishop of St. Asaph, Lord Almoner to Their Majesties.</title>
                  <author>Lloyd, William, 1627-1717.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Jones ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half title: The Bishop of St. Asaph's sermon preach'd before the Queen at White-Hall.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Chronicles, 2nd, XXXV, 24-25 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61298:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the QUEEN AT WHITE-HALL <hi>Ianuary</hi> the <hi>30th.</hi> Being the day of the Martyrdom of King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the First.</p>
            <p>By the Bishop of St. <hi>Asaph,</hi> Lord Almoner to Their MAJESTIES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Published by Her Majesties Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Iones</hi> at the <hi>White-Horse</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi> MDCXCI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:61298:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61298:2"/>
            <p>The BISHOP of St. <hi>Asaph</hi>'s SERMON Preach'd before the QUEEN AT WHITE-HALL.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:61298:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:61298:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:61298:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61298:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preach'd before the QUEEN AT WHITE-HALL.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2 Chron. xxxv. 24, 25.</bibl>
               <q>And all <hi>Juda</hi> and <hi>Jerusalem</hi> mourned for <hi>Josiah:</hi> And <hi>Jeremiah</hi> lamented for <hi>Josiah;</hi> and all the singing-men and the singing-women spake of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siah</hi> in their lamentations to this day; and they made them an Ordinance in <hi>Israel;</hi> and behold, they are written in the <hi>Lamentations.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WE are here met this day to humble our selves before God, for one of the greatest Sins that ever was committed by any People that profess'd the true Religion; except only the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61298:5"/>
               <hi>Iews</hi> rejecting and crucifying their <hi>Messias;</hi> and to bewail the greatest loss, I think the greatest, that ever befell any Nation, in the death of any one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son; both which Sin and which Calamity toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I would have parallel'd in one Text, but I know not where to find it in Scripture.</p>
            <p>For the Example of our Saviour is too high to be brought into comparison with any other: And to go lower (as it becomes us, when we speak of a mere Man, a Temporal Prince;) for so excellent Goodness in Man, for such a Blessing in a temporal King, to be so wretchedly lost, so wickedly destroyed, by them that were blessed with it; there is no Example of the like to be met with, I say, not only in Scripture, but not in any Story that I know, from the beginning of the World to this day.</p>
            <p>In the Age of Gospel-Story, while <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apostles</hi> were here, there was then no Christian King upon the Earth; and if there had been, we may guess what Affection, what Obedience, what Veneration would have been paid him by them that so abounded in their Precepts of those Duties, to Heathen Princes, to cruel Tyrants, to monsters of Men, such as <hi>Nero,</hi> under whom two <hi>Apostles</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they were to suffer Death, yet commanded <hi>every Soul</hi> to be <hi>subject to the higher Powers,</hi> the People <hi>to submit to them for the Lords sake,</hi> and their Pastors <hi>to put them in mind to obey them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61298:5"/>They which taught thus, (and we are sure they liv'd as they taught,) how glad would they have been to have had those Duties to pay to such a Prince as we have seen, by some great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors of Religion, but quite contrary to their Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns and Rules, most contumeliously treated and abused, most sacrilegiously and barbarously mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd.</p>
            <p>Among the <hi>Iews,</hi> who had many Kings of their own Religion, some approv'd of God, and others tax'd as they justly deserv'd; it is observable that their Carriage towards them all (as well the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil as the good,) was generally such as the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel requires of us <hi>Christians.</hi> If there were amongst them any Murtherers of Kings, the Scripture is care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to let us know what they were, wicked Men, <hi>Sons of Belial;</hi> and it shews us how they sped, they were <hi>put to Death</hi> for it, <hi>according to the Law of</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses; it is most careful to separate them from the Generation of Gods People, to shew their detesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of such Persons and Practices. By what we read, we cannot but judge, they would have tremb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to think of that which they that call'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves Gods People had the impiety to do; they had the prodigious wickedness to do it, and yet they had the face to call themselves Gods People. I am sure 'tis in vain, to look for any thing like this in Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:61298:6"/>But to shew how the <hi>Iews</hi> demean'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves toward their Kings, and first to evil Kings, I ought to take my first measures from their Behaviour towards <hi>Saul;</hi> and especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally from the most memorable instance of <hi>David,</hi> whom God himself having declar'd to be a Man after his own heart, we have the divine Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of what he said and did in this matter.</p>
            <p>But of his excellent behaviour toward <hi>Saul,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides many other remarkable instances, we have one in the Lesson that was read to you this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. There you heard, how when one brought <hi>David</hi> the News of <hi>Sauls</hi> death, by a sure token, that he had kill'd him himself, which one would have thought should have been welcome News to one that could never be safe while <hi>Saul</hi> liv'd, and that now upon his death was sure to be his Successor; for all that, <hi>David</hi> had such a detesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Fact, and of the impudence of him that boasted of it, that first he caus'd him to be put to death; he pronounc'd his Sentence in those memorable words, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> i. 16. <hi>Thy Blood be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy head, for thy mouth hath testifyed against thee, saying, I have slain the Lords Anointed:</hi> And having thus aveng'd his Death, how he mourn'd for it afterwards, we see in his mourning Song that he compos'd, and which was read to you out of the same Chapter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:61298:6"/>But we are novv upon the Death of a good King, and to shew the Peoples sense of this, and their Behaviour upon it, you cannot pitch upon an instance more likely, than at the Death of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siah.</hi> A most remarkable instance in two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> Considering their loss of so excellent a Person.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Secondly,</hi> the many harsh Circumstances of his death.</p>
            <p>For the Person, a holy and good Man, a just and a merciful Prince, such a Prince as came not in many Ages; in many hundreds of years.</p>
            <p>They had three Kings, in whom they gloried<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> xlix. 4.</note> above all other; they were <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> and <hi>Iosias.</hi> And yet <hi>David</hi> had faults, which one would tremble to think of. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> was not free from Faults, as appear'd when God left him, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> xxxii. 31. The least Evil we read of any King in Scripture, is of <hi>Iosiah.</hi> Some Indiscretion it was perhaps in him, to engage in that War against <hi>Pharaoh Necho.</hi> I dare not say it was <hi>sin</hi> in him, for Scripture hath not said it. But if that was not <hi>sin,</hi> I am sure we read of none that he had. And in this respect, we may place him above <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Hezekiah;</hi> so the Scripture does in general Words, saying, that <hi>like him there was<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> xxiii 25.</note>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:61298:7"/>
no King before him, that turned to the Lord with all his heart, and with all his Soul, and with all his Might, according to all the Law of</hi> Moses; <hi>neither after him arose there any like him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was a singular Prince, and had a singular mark of it in that Prophesie, which named him 300 years before he was born: <hi>Behold a Child shall</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Kin.</hi> xiii. 2.</note> 
               <hi>be born to the House of</hi> David, Josiah <hi>by Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No small things you may be sure he was to do, that God thought worth speaking of, and foretelling so many <hi>Ages</hi> before.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Iosias</hi> was born, and came to be King, he did all those things which were foretold of him in that Prophesie. He abolisht that Idolatry and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstition, that had grown up under his loose Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessors. He restor'd and establish'd the true Religion according to the Scriptures: Which Scriptures were lost, (say the <hi>Iews</hi>) through disuse, in the Reign of King <hi>Amon</hi> his Father; and it appears in his Story, how he brought them to light, and restor'd them unto their Authority and Dignity. You read how Zealous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Industriously he provided for the Worship of God: for the place of it, by repairing and beautifying of the Temple; for the Service by fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing it with Vessels and Utensils; for the Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of it, appointing Musick according to the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61298:7"/>
Commandment of <hi>David;</hi> for the Festivals of it, he made all <hi>Israel</hi> and <hi>Iuda</hi> to be present at the Passover; he brought all their Religions into one, he had that Exercis'd in one manner, and in one place; <hi>he made all that were present in Israel to serve the Lord their</hi> God, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> xxxiv. last verse.</p>
            <p>All this the Scripture saith of him, and approves in him; and therefore we are sure he did well in it. And as well one would think he might have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected at Gods hands, especially, if we consider those Scriptures of the Jewish Dispensation; which stirred men up to Obedience, with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise of Temporal Blessings; and deterred them from sin, with the threatning of temporal Punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Among those promised Blessings are Peace and long Life; for which, who, in <hi>Iosias</hi>'s Case, would not have thought he might have taken God's <hi>word?</hi> But with this excellent Prince it seem'd to fall out on the contrary.</p>
            <p>For great and just cause, as I shall shew you, (but it may seem very strange the mean while) when he had done all that in him lay to advance the Kingdom of God; in an hour unlook'd for, his Kingdom was at an end, and his Life with it. Both these were cut off in the <hi>37th.</hi> year of his Age, which is but half the Age of Man, the Noon of it as 'tis term'd in that Prophesie, <hi>Amos</hi> viii. 8, 9, 10.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:61298:8"/>'Tis a remarkable Prophesie, I shall first read you the Words, and then I shall shew you the Accomplishment. The words are, <hi>Shall not the Land</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> viii. 8, 9. 10.</note> 
               <hi>tremble for this, and every one Mourn that dwelleth therein? And it shall rise up wholly as a Flood, and it shall be cast out and drowned as by the Flood of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt. And it shall come to pass in that day, saith the Lord God, that I will cause the Sun to go down at Noon, and I will darken the Earth in the clear Day. And I will turn your Feasts into Mourning, and all your Songs into Lamentations; and I will bring up Sackcloth upon all Loyns, and baldness upon every head: And I will make it as the mourning of an only Son, and the end thereof as a bitter day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this Rabbi <hi>Salomon Iarchi</hi> observes, was fulfil'd upon the death of <hi>Iosiah.</hi> The King of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyt</hi> there specified, <hi>Pharaoh Necho</hi> (or the Lame) Wars with the King of <hi>Babylon;</hi> and <hi>Iosiah</hi>'s Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try lying between them, he marches through it with an Army, without his leave, nay against his Prohibition. Which injurious attempt against his honour and safety, while <hi>Iosiah</hi> endeavoured to oppose, he engag'd himself in a War, which soon after cost him his Life.</p>
            <p>One Arrow puts an end to that Holy Life, that good Reign, that Righteous Government, by which he thought he had secured a lasting peace
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61298:8"/>
to himself and his Kingdom. So good <hi>Iosiah</hi> is gone; and <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Ierusalem</hi> with him. Gone are all those Blessings they enjoy'd, and hoped for, by his means. There was nothing more to be lookt for, but a bitter day, a day of Captivity; <hi>a bitter day</hi> according to <hi>Amos</hi>'s Prophecy; which they knew, and which if you read over again, you cannot wonder at that which follows in my Text; All <hi>Iuda</hi> and <hi>Ierusalem, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the method of my Discourse upon this Text,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> I shall consider what the People of God did in that Age, <hi>upon</hi> the Death of <hi>Iosiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I shall consider the Reasons of their doing it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I shall consider how it is applicable to our Occasion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> What they did, it appears in my Text, they <hi>lamented</hi> him at present, they laid up their <hi>Lamentations</hi> for future times. They had a set Form drawn up for that purpose, and they made a Law that <hi>that</hi> Form should be observed; and so it was <hi>unto this day,</hi> saith the Text, that is for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 100 years; how much longer we know not, but so long we are sure it continued; For it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued from <hi>Iosiah</hi>'s Death, at least till the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Story, and this was written much above a hundred years after <hi>Iosiahs</hi>'s Death.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:61298:9"/>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> For the Reasons of it, which are not in my Text, they are easy to be collected out of this Chapter, compared with other places of Scripture. It appears they had great cause to lament the death of <hi>Iosiah;</hi> and that, not for any loss it was to <hi>him,</hi> but for the great loss to Gods Church and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> And principally for the cause of it, that was for their Sins. And,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> For the punishment of their Sins: they were punish'd at present in the want of his good Example and Government; and for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, great cause they had to fear, it might por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend and bring on the ruine of their Nation.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Third</hi> part of my Discourse (that is,) what we are to do in our Circumstances; it will be very easy to judge, when we have consider'd what they did in theirs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> At present they lamented King <hi>Iosiah's</hi> Death, as being no doubt, a great Calamity to their Church and to their Nation. Saith my Text, <hi>All</hi> Juda <hi>and</hi> Jerusalem <hi>mourned for</hi> Josias; in the <hi>Arab.</hi> Translation, <hi>they were cast down with vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Grief for</hi> Josias; in the <hi>Syriac</hi> Translation, <hi>they laid up mourning and lamentation for</hi> Josiah; it was a great, a publick, a lasting Calamity; it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd a great, a publick, a lasting lamentation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:61298:9"/>Especially my Text saith, <hi>the Prophet</hi> Jeremiah <hi>lamented for</hi> Josiah; the vulgar Translation adds <hi>Ieremia</hi>'s <hi>Maxime, Ieremiah</hi> above all others. No question but as he best knew the worth of <hi>Iosiah,</hi> so he most grieved for the irreparable loss in his Death.</p>
            <p>But was that all? I suppose not; for <hi>Ieremiah</hi> was a Prophet; he foresaw the sad consequence of this loss to his Nation: He felt how it Shook the Foundation of their Happiness: He was concern'd, not only for the present, but for after times; as a wise and good Man, he lamented with them of the present Age; as being also a Prophet, he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented for them of future Ages. And to engage the whole Church to mourn and lament with him, he provided a Form, both for the present and for the future.</p>
            <p>Their publick Forms in the time of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Temple, were no other (that I know) but Hymns suited to their occasions; whether ordinary, on their Sabbaths, and New Moons, and other Festi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals; or extraordinary, on their Fasts, and Days of Thanksgiving.</p>
            <p>For every Fast-day, they had a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or Song of Lamentation. <hi>Iosiah</hi> deserv'd a yearly Fast up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the day of his Death. <hi>Ieremiah</hi> compos'd the Office for it, which was a Song of Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61298:10"/>
               <hi>A Song of Lamentation,</hi> so it is plainly expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press'd in the Original, and it is sufficiently rend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> but imperfectly in our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> Translation. He made on him a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as the <hi>Greeks</hi> call it, he made a mourning Song or Psalm of Lamentation.</p>
            <p>Which Song, being (as I have said) the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Office of the Church for that day; he put it it into their hands, by whom that Service was to be perform'd. Now that was chiefly by <hi>singing Men</hi> and <hi>singing Women:</hi> Yet not so, but that <hi>all the People</hi> join'd with them in singing the Publick Office, or Psalm <hi>in their Lamentations.</hi> They do it still <hi>to this day,</hi> saith the Writer of this Book, who is thought to have been <hi>Ezra</hi> the Scribe: Sure e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, it was one that lived after the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Captivity; for the last Chapter and Verse of this Book, speak of their return from that Captivity, and the same is the first Verse of the first Chapter of <hi>Ezra.</hi> From hence it certainly appears, that till after the Captivity, that is, for 140 years, they still continued their Lamentation, and still us'd this Form of Lamentation for the Death of <hi>Iosiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And they did it not arbitrarily, but by a Lavv vvhich oblig'd them to it. So my Text saith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is, they vvhich then governed made it a Lavv upon <hi>Israel,</hi> that every
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61298:10"/>
year upon the day on vvhich <hi>Iosiah</hi> vvas slain, these Offices should be used for the lamenting of <hi>Iosiah.</hi> Thus <hi>Pagnin</hi> and <hi>Malvenda</hi> interpret my Text.</p>
            <p>And that which follows, <hi>behold they are written in the Lamentations;</hi> they understand, not of those Lamentations in the Bible, but the whole Body of the <hi>Iewish</hi> Lamentations, that were used upon their solemn Fast-days. Those now extant in the Bible, were particularly composed for the <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonian Captivity.</hi> Which Captivity having occasio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned so many Fast-days in the year; one for the besieging of <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> another for the taking of it; another for the destrustion of the <hi>Temple,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the loss of the Remnant with <hi>Gedaliah;</hi> these Lamentations in after-times swallowed up the remembranee of all other Lamentations; and of this for <hi>Iosiah</hi> among the rest.</p>
            <p>They remembred it, (as I have said) until <hi>Ezra</hi>'s time; when tho' perhaps they observed not the day, yet they continued the Office or Form for it.</p>
            <p>But how? They sung not this by it self, but (saith my Text) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> they used this <hi>Among</hi> their other Lamentations. But since his time (as it may seem) for the shortning of the Office, which was long upon those Fast-Days in remembrance of the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61298:11"/>
they left out this particular Office for the loss of <hi>Iosiah;</hi> and so probably by this means we came to lose the words of this Lamentation.</p>
            <p>But these four things I have sufficiently prov'd from my Text:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> That there was a general Mourning for <hi>Josiah</hi> at his death;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> made a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Office for it;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That this Office was used among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers upon the Day of Lamentation;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That this Use was established by a Law upon <hi>Israel;</hi> and that this Law was observed till <hi>Ezra</hi>'s time, that is, for 140 Years, even till the end of the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Captivity.</p>
            <p>Next, I am to proceed to the Reason of this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution.</p>
            <p>The Reason of it was, not for his sake that was taken from them, but for their sakes from whom he was taken.</p>
            <p>As (for him) there was no cause to lament. He died in Peace; or else how could God's Promise to him be fulfilled? 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34. 28. It was said to him from God by <hi>Hulda</hi> the <hi>Prophetess, Behold, I will gather thee to thy Fathers, and thou shalt go to thy Grave in Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet it is plain, that he died in War. What
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61298:11"/>
shall we say to this? He that died in War, did he go to his Grave in Peace?</p>
            <p>Then surely Peace in Gods Language is some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else than in ours.</p>
            <p>It is so, it is Peace with God. Take it so, and there is nothing strange in those Paradoxes of Scripture, that <hi>there is no peace to the wicked,</hi> but <hi>abundance of peace is to the righteous.</hi> These and all the like Sayings are plain, if you understand them aright, of Peace with God.</p>
            <p>It is certainly true, that whether Peace or no Peace, it must be judg'd, by having God to our Friend, or to our Enemy. This is a sure way of judging, as sure as it is that God is true; only the truth of it does not appear in this life, as it will in the future. The Righteous in this life, though he is in Friendship with God, which nothing can break but wilful or habitual Sin; yet his Peace is disturbed often times, even with Sins of Infirmity, 'tis eclipst with troubles in this World, it is cloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with melancholy Doubts, which even good Men are subject to. It is never perfect and clear while we live in Houses of Clay; but when these are dissolv'd, then the Righteous <hi>enters into peace,</hi> that is, into the perfection of it; into that cleer Light, the calm Sun-shine of Gods presence for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more. Now this blessed estate, being that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61298:12"/>
which <hi>Iosiah</hi> gain'd by his Death, according to the promise of God; a blessedness which none can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain but by Death; and which he could not have had so soon by dying otherwise: What reason had they to lament for <hi>Iosiah,</hi> that was such a Gainer by his Death? There was no cause of lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation for him.</p>
            <p>They only had cause to lament for his Death that lost by it: And that did all <hi>Iuda</hi> and <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem.</hi> They lost all they had to trust to, they lost the Lease of their safety and well-being; for they held it only by his Life, the holy and good Life of <hi>Iosiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was decreed against them in the Court of Heaven, after a long Tryal, for their National Sins, that they should be carried away into Captivity. There was no Remedy, for the Lord had sworn it, <hi>Amos</hi> 8. 7. <hi>I will remove</hi> Juda <hi>out of my sight, I</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings xxiii. 27.</note> 
               <hi>will cast off</hi> Jerusalem, <hi>which I have chosen, and the house of which I said my Name shall be there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was thus decreed; but when was it to be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted? Not in good <hi>Iosiah</hi>'s days; for it is against Gods Rule to punish the good Child for the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Father's sake. And besides, God had promis'd him in the fore-mentioned place, that his Eye<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> xxx. 28.</note> should not see all the evil that he would bring up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that place.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:61298:12"/>What then? Should God for <hi>Iosiah</hi>'s sake whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reverse that Judgment which he had sworn to execute upon <hi>Israel?</hi> He could not reverse it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause his Oath was immutable. And yet, for his promise sake, God could not execute it in his days. Tho' in his days the People deserv'd it; for they were then a wicked People, notwithstanding all the good they derived from his Influence; they serv'd God, because <hi>he made them</hi> do it, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34. 33. they <hi>turn'd to God, not with all their heart, but feignedly,</hi> Jer. 3. 10. even in those days, in the days of King <hi>Iosiah,</hi> as you read in the <hi>6th.</hi> Verse of that Chapter: Yet that hypocritical People, was protected by this Religious Prince; God's Judgment could not come at them, till he was taken out of the way.</p>
            <p>But when he was removed, they lay bare to the Vengeance of God. Then he would have a full blow at them, then wrath was to be poured out upon them to the uttermost. Then God's Judgments were to rush in upon them, like the breaking in of the Sea. Then they were to suffer those things, which to hear of, were enough to make ones Ears tingle. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> xxi. 12. <hi>Ier.</hi> xix. 3.</p>
            <p>And if they understood this, as we are certain they might, and <hi>Jeremy</hi> did understand it; we
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61298:13"/>
cannot wonder that all <hi>Juda</hi> and <hi>Jerusalem</hi> mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for <hi>Josiah,</hi> and <hi>Jeremy</hi> especially: Since they saw, and he saw it especially, their Walls and Bulwarks were broken down by that good King <hi>Josia</hi>'s death. They had lost that good Prince of whom they were not worthy, and were now to expect those things of which they were most wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy. They had great cause therefore to lament themselves before God.</p>
            <p>They could not but do it voluntarily, that were sensible of their Condition. And they did well to make a Law for it, to oblige them that were not sensible.</p>
            <p>But beside this Cause, which was peculiar to them; there was another in Common to them and us, and all Nations; that is, considering their own Sin, and God's punishment of it. For the death of a good King is a great publick Calamity. And such Calamities are always for the sins of the People.</p>
            <p>I begin first with the Punishment, for of that we are most apt to be sensible.</p>
            <p>And yet many are not sensible of that; not of a publick punishment, till it comes home to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, till it touches their own Persons and Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies; 'tis pity that such should ever want such pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment;</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:61298:13"/>But for such as have a sense of Publick Affairs, they cannot but be deeply sensible of this; that, the loss of a good King is a great Calamity to a Nation.</p>
            <p>The death of any King is a loss, unless God change him for a better. But he must be extream bad that is not better then none at all. It was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver worse with <hi>Israel</hi> then when there was <hi>no King</hi> amongst them; for then, <hi>every one did what was good in his own Eyes.</hi> In the 4 last Chapters of the Book of <hi>Judges,</hi> God says this four times over, as fit for more than common Observation.</p>
            <p>But specially there is a great loss of a good King, a good Example, a good Governour, one that makes it his business to do all that can be done for the protecting and uniting of his People, for the preserving and advancing of Truth and Peace, of Religion and Righteousness among them. Such a nursing Father to the Church, such a Wise Mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the State, such a Fortress and Bulwark to his Nation, when he is taken away from them; what can they think of it?</p>
            <p>If they are not lost to all Sense, they cannot but be sensible of this. A good King being so great a Blessing to a Nation, vve have cause to impute the loss of him to our Sins. We are taught so in sundry places of Scripture. And therefore vve are
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61298:14"/>
taught to lament for those Sins; both National and Personal; for our ovvn sins and the sins of our Nation.</p>
            <p>For our own sins in the first place. It should be every ones care, when we bewail the Publick Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, to consider, that such are for the sins of the Nation. But the Nation is made up of Indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual Persons; and I am one of those Individuals, therefore I am to search into my own sins, (I speak now as being one that lived and sinned in those times;) to lay my hand upon my breast, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin my own heart, and seriously to consider, how far I contributed to that publick Guilt which brought down this publick Judgment upon us. And as far as I find I contributed to it, to confess and bevvail my ovvn sins before God; to ask par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don; and that I may be capable of it, to mourn deeply and heartily; and to shew the proof of it in my real amendment; that as I have throvvn in my Talent, into the National sin, so I may do my part in promoting the National Reformation.</p>
            <p>If I have no sin of my own to mourn for, (vvhich in strict speaking is impossible,) but if I have no presumptuous and clamorous sin to answer for; or if my sins are of a latter date (which is the case of the greatest part of you that hear me;) yet for such, they are all to consider themselves as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61298:14"/>
Members of this Nation, and mourn for the sins of the Nation; for those Epidemical sins, that brought down such a publick Judgment upon us.</p>
            <p>For so doing, we have the Examples of <hi>Ez.</hi> 9. 3. of <hi>Neh.</hi> 9. 16. of <hi>Daniel</hi> 10. 1. How did those Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Men Mourn, and humble themselves before God for the sins of Ages past, that brought upon them the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Captivity? And yet that Captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty also was past when they poured out their Souls before God, in tears for the sins of their Fathers. How much more have Holy Men lamented for the sins of their own Age? The Prophet <hi>David</hi> on this account poured out <hi>Rivers of Tears, Psal.</hi> 119. 136. The Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> 9. 1. Wish'd that his <hi>head</hi> were <hi>Water,</hi> and his <hi>Eyes</hi> a <hi>Fountain of Tears,</hi> to bewail the sins of his Nation. But especially our blessed Saviour himself, tho' he had no sin, yet he had Tears for them that had, <hi>Luke</hi> 19. 42. He beheld <hi>Ierusalem</hi> and wept over it, saying, <hi>Oh that thou hadst known, even in this thy day, the things that belong to thy peace! but now they are hid from thine Eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tears are of no use, without hearty endeavours, where endeavours may be used, and we have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to hope they may do good. And therefore these also were applied, by those Holy Men whom I have mentioned. And these also are required of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61298:15"/>
us, even our utmost Endeavours, every one within the Sphere of his Calling, to bring o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to a sight and sense of their Sins; and to persuade them to join with us, every one, by his particular, to help on the publick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</p>
            <p>This is the end of all Judgments, which are not to final Destruction, <hi>Isaia</hi> 27. 9. <hi>This is the fruit of them to take away our sin.</hi> And this is the end of our Sorrow, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 10. <hi>Godly Sorrow works Repentance to Salvation, not to be repented of.</hi> And this is the end of our Fast days, as God teaches us: <hi>Ioel</hi> 2. 12. <hi>Turn you to me with all your hearts, with fasting, and with weeping, and with mourning; and rent your hearts, and not your Garments, and turn you to the Lord your God.</hi> So <hi>Hosea</hi> xiv. 1, 2. <hi>O Israel, turn unto the Lord thy God, for thou hast fallen by thy iniquity; take with thee words, and turn to the Lord; say unto him, take away all our Iniquity, and receive us graciously; so will we render thee the Calves of our Lips.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ought to have been the Fruit of their Lamentation for <hi>Iosia;</hi> but for want of this, it did them no good; their Iniquity was their ruine.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:61298:15"/>That ours may not be so to us, God grant we may mend that fault in our Lamentation.</p>
            <p>'Tis our business on this day to lament our <hi>Iosiah,</hi> above 40 years after; as the <hi>Iewish</hi> Church did theirs, 140 years after his Death. I shall first consider the Cause of our Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and then our Duty in consequence of it.</p>
            <p>On both these Heads, I have much more to say then I can bring within my time. But if I do exceed, I hope you will bear with me; for I suppose I hinder nothing but what may well be spared on this day.</p>
            <p>Our business on this day, is to lament for the Death of our <hi>Iosiah;</hi> that most excellent Prince, on whose Name his greatest Adversaries have fastned no more, nor indeed no other blame, then God hath left upon the Memory of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whatsoever good we read of in <hi>Iosiah,</hi> it is known, to all that knew him, to have been eminently in that Prince, whom we lament on this day.</p>
            <p>They were both alike, born and bred up in the true Religion. But herein the advantage was on our <hi>Iosia</hi>'s side, that this was he true <hi>Christian</hi> Religion; which as far excels the <hi>Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:61298:16"/>
as the clear Sun-shine doth the light of a dark misty day. And as we have reason to believe that <hi>Josiah</hi> had studied his Religion, for he as well taught as commanded both his Priests and People their Duties; so had our <hi>Josia.</hi> He understood his Religion throughly. It was his judgment that indear'd it to his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. And with both these together, like a true <hi>Defender of the Faith,</hi> he maintain'd it all ways against all sorts of Adversaries.</p>
            <p>Especially, he was a most zealous observer and assertor of God's Worship, as was <hi>Josia.</hi> He was an heroick Pattern of all Virtues, as was <hi>Josia.</hi> He was like <hi>Iosias</hi> in all the Divine Perfections of his Life; and for our Sins he was too like him in suffering an untimely and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Death.</p>
            <p>So the Parallel runs quite through between the two Persons; and it doth not fall short in any part of that Duty that was paid to their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories. All that my Text saith, was done up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Death of <hi>Iosia,</hi> we have seen, and yet see, the same done to the Memory of our King. All true Servants of God in our Church, do and will for ever bewail and lament for him. We have a Set Form prescrib'd for it, which was read to us upon this day. And it is to be read year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61298:16"/>
upon this day, for (as my Text saith,) it is <hi>made an Ordinance throughout</hi> Israel.</p>
            <p>But in the Lamentation of the <hi>Iews</hi> for <hi>Iosia,</hi> there was, as I have shewn, a just Reflection made, by <hi>Ieremiah</hi> especially, upon those Sins of the Nation, for which God depriv'd them of that Blessing that they enioy'd in such an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Prince. The like was made afterwards by <hi>Daniel,</hi> and by <hi>Ezra,</hi> and by <hi>Nehemia,</hi> upon those Sins of their People in those Times, which provoked God afresh to send down his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon them to their utter destruction.</p>
            <p>This is that we have reason to fear; and their way to prevent it must be ours. Our Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon the Sins of this Nation, as well before the Kings Death, as since, even to this day, in order to our Amendment, these are the most useful and necessary Ingredients of our Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <p>And this will be more requir'd of Us, then it was of the <hi>Iews,</hi> in respect of that much great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Light which God hath given Us. We shall find in our Account, that we are the Disciples of <hi>Christ;</hi> and that in the upper Form of his School, whatsoever we think of it. We have his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in as great perfection, as ever it was in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:61298:17"/>This advantage we have had by our Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation from Popery. Ever since, God hath given us the free use of the Scriptures; and together with it, those helps of Learning that never were before in any Age; which singular Blessings of God, to set forth to you as they deserve, would be the business of a Book, and not of the end of a Sermon.</p>
            <p>Now what returns to God have we made for all this? I must needs say, for an Age after the Reformation of Religion, there seem'd to be a great Reformation of Mens Lives. There was then a zeal for Religion kindled in their hearts, by seeing so many holy Men burn for it in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s days.</p>
            <p>But when that heat was over, (their first love I may call it,) as they cool'd to Religion, so they went off by degrees, from their Primitive Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Holiness. It was but too visible in this blessed Monarch's Reign, that they that had the Conduct then of Religion, had not the same zeal for it that they had, whom God made the Instruments of our Reformation. They were indeed more concern'd than they for external things, but not so much for that which is the Soul and Life of Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:61298:17"/>This gave occasion to others to fly out ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way. They call'd every thing of external Worship, Popery. They were against all Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, even in lawful things. They made such a noise against it, as turn'd Mens heads. They so scar'd them with little things, made great by false Lights, that they run into the greatest Evils to avoid them. Into a War, the worst sort of it, a Civil War; a bloody Rebellion, that drew a long Train of Calamities after it. It came to this at last: We lost the best King that God e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver gave to this Nation. How we lost him, I tremble to say; and yet we all know; it is the saddest part of our Lamentation on this day. It soon appeared what a blow this gave to Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by the general dissolution of Order and of Discipline in the Church. And to the Nation likewise, by the Confusions that followed; which, if they had run a little further, we should soon have ceas'd to be a Nation.</p>
            <p>In this miserable condition, when we lay (as it were) gasping for Life, it pleased God out of the Cloud to look upon us. He gave us, as it were, a New Life, a Resurrection from the dead. He restor'd us, when it was visible that none but he could do it. It was such a mercy to this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61298:18"/>
such a heap of Mercies together, that all Nations stood amaz'd at it.</p>
            <p>We cannot but be astonish'd our selves, if we consider what opportunities<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God put then into their hands. They that were at the Helm, need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but ask and have, whatsoever they thought fit, to settle both Church and State. To have secured Truth, and Peace, and Unity, and Love, and Holiness; in a word, all that pleases God, and all that makes a People happy.</p>
            <p>We have cause for ever to lament the loss of these Opportunities. But how much more the wretched purposes to which they were misap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed? For the gratifying of Mens Lusts, for the wrecking of their Revenge, for the enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of themselves and their Friends.</p>
            <p>For them that had no such designs, they seem'd to live like Men without any. Instead of glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying God, they fell to drinking of Healths. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of being stricter in Religion, they grew looser in their Lives. Instead of frequenting God's Worship, they fill'd the Play-houses, and worse places. Instead of adorning the Gospel, they expos'd it to the scorn of our Adversaries: Instead of composing Differences among our selves, they were rather for widening them.</p>
            <p>This was bad enough otherwise, but much the <hi>worse</hi> through their fault that should have mended
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:61298:18"/>
these things. Instead of Reforming, they us'd ways to debauch us more; and instead of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, they us'd ways to inflame our Divisions.</p>
            <p>It was a Riddle, that any Government should suffer such things; till at last it appear'd, they were not only suffer'd but design'd. The design of it was plainly this, to bring in Popery again. And that had certainly return'd; It had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd over us e're this time; if God had not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully deliver'd us from it.</p>
            <p>It pleas'd God to give us a second Resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, more wonderful then the former. The marks of Gods Hand were so visible in it, at first, and are so daily more and more; that he is blind that doth not see them. There is enough, one would think, to convince even the Atheist to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of a Providence. But whosoever doth believe it, should consider the work of God; and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever considers, cannot but see what it drives at: and he that sees that, how can he but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with his Design? It is plainly the design of God by this turn, to establish the Protestant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in these Kingdoms. And in order to that, to unite us among our selves: all that can unite in Worship, and the rest in their Interests and Affections. And especially, to unite us in that common design, of driving out all immorality and prophaneness out of this Kingdom. It is not
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61298:19"/>
sense, it is a plain contradiction, to call that a Reform'd Religion, which hath not the power of reforming Men's Lives.</p>
            <p>It is the purifying and Reforming of these, that is the chief business of Religion. And this is the chief design of God's Providence, in this Revolution. That this is Gods design, he hath shewn us particularly, by giving us such Princes, as enjoin us nothing but what they are Patterns of themselves. I know not what can be a clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er token of the design of Gods Providence than this.</p>
            <p>But hath this good Providence of God the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect that he designs, and may justly expect at our hands? We are so far from it yet, that it is a shame to say what all Men know. We are now, as to our Morals, perhaps as bad as ever we were. I fear I said too much, in saying perhaps: It is too sure, it is notorious to all the World. There ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was louder Swearing, never more open Drunkeness, never more impudent Adultery, such daily Robbing, and Killing, not only in Houses, but in the open Streets. And if this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiousness should run on, what will it come to in time? <hi>This is a Lamentation, and shall be for a Lamentation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are so far from being fit for those Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and Blessings, which we had otherwise all
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61298:19"/>
the reason in the World to expect and to hope for under their Majesties Government; that now on the contrary, we have reason to fear that God will have mercy on us no more; that having tryed the utmost means to do us good, when those fail, he should give us over as incorrigible.</p>
            <p>My Principal hope is in the Mercies of God. Not his Ordinary Mercies, for we seem to be past them; but I speak it with respect to those abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Promises that he hath given to his Church, to be fulfilled in this Age. God's Promises will be made good to his Church, though we deprive our selves of the benefit of them.</p>
            <p>It was an absolute promise that God made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> that he would bring his Seed out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and that he would seat them in the promis'd Land. And God was as good as his word; though of all them that came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> only two had the full benefit of it; all the rest of them died in the Wilderness. God will fulfill his Promises to them, and only them, that are careful to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Conditions. He preserv'd righteous <hi>Lot</hi> that was <hi>griev'd with the filthy Conversation</hi> of them with whom he liv'd in <hi>Sodom,</hi> when that City was destroyed. And at the destruction of <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> he did set <hi>a mark upon them that mourn'd for the abominations of</hi> Jerusalem. He will do the like for all them that fear his Name; he will preserve
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:61298:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
them from the common destruction. <hi>They sha<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be mine, saith the Lord of Hosts, in the day that <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> make up my Iewels. I will spare them, as a Ma<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> spares his own Son that serves him. Then shall y<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> discern between the righteous and the wicked; betwee<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him that serves God, and him that serves him no<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Mal. iii. two last Verses.</p>
            <p>God grant that this may be the lot of all th<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> hear me this day. God grant this blessing effect<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our Lamentations: that beholding the Judgment of God, considering those that are past, and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing those that are to come; we may fear to <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> against God; we may not only keep our selves unspotted from the World, but do all we can to save others from Sin and Death, <hi>snatching</hi> them (as the Apostle saith,) <hi>like Brands out of the fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At present, it would be a greater thing to stop the growing course of wickedness, then it will be afterwards to restore Religion and Vertue. And re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stor'd, I trust, it will be to a greater lustre then ever, by their Majesties Zeal, and Wisdom, and Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence; which will be wholly applyed to this busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, when God hath well discharg'd them of the other, the great burden of War that is now up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their hands. <hi>God grant a speedy and happy is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue of it, for his Mercies sake, through Iesus Christ our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
