<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon against schisme, or, The seperations of these times preacht in the church of Wattlington in Oxford-shire, with some interruption, September 11, 1652 : at a publick dispute held there between Jasper Mayne, D.D. and one ----- ...</title>
            <author>Mayne, Jasper, 1604-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-07">2003-07 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50415</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1475</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32061</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12308726</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12308726</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59326</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A50415)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59326)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1016:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon against schisme, or, The seperations of these times preacht in the church of Wattlington in Oxford-shire, with some interruption, September 11, 1652 : at a publick dispute held there between Jasper Mayne, D.D. and one ----- ...</title>
                  <author>Mayne, Jasper, 1604-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Royston ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Schism --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59326:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON AGAINST SCHISME: OR, The SEPERATIONS of these TIMES.</p>
            <p>Preacht in the Church of <hi>Wattlington</hi> in <hi>Oxford</hi>-shire, with some Interruption, <hi>September</hi> 11. 1652.</p>
            <p>At a publick dispute held there, Between JASPER MAYNE, D.D. And one—</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>MAT. 13.47.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for R. ROYSTON, at the Angel in Ivie-lane, 1652.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:59326:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59326:2"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F you please to turne to the 19. <hi>Chapter</hi> of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> and to read from the 24. to the 33. <hi>verse</hi> of that <hi>Chapter,</hi> there is there mention made of a great Assembly, and concurse of <hi>people</hi>; Who upon the Instigation of one <hi>Demetrius,</hi> a <hi>Silver-Smith,</hi> were confusedly drawne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether into a <hi>publick Theater.</hi> And when they were met there, the <hi>Confusion</hi> was so great, that the <hi>Theater</hi> for the time, was quite changed into a <hi>Babel</hi>; there was a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Division of <hi>speech,</hi> and <hi>Tongues</hi> among them, scarce any two spoke the same <hi>Language</hi>; For <hi>some cryed out one Thing, and some cryed out Another,</hi> as you may read at the 32. v. of that Chap. Rudenesse, Clamour, Tumult, Noyse, was all that issued from them. Nay 'twas a <hi>Meeting</hi> so confused, so wholly void of Reason, that the greatest part knew not why they were come together, as you may read in the end, and close of that verse. And hence 'tis, that when Saint <hi>Paul</hi> would have ingaged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe among them, and would have preacht to them to <hi>convert</hi> and turne them from their Errour, 'Tis said at the 31. verse of that Chapter, That some of the <hi>chief</hi> of <hi>Asia,</hi> who were his <hi>Friends,</hi> sent to him, and desired him, that he would not adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture himselfe among such a rude, Tempestuous rout of <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now, if you desire to know why I have sayd this to you,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59326:3"/>
'tis to let you see, First, That this hath partly been my case, I have been sent, nay spoken to, by some <hi>persons</hi> of <hi>Quality</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> not to ingage my selfe among such a mixt <hi>Multitude</hi> as this; where my <hi>Affronts</hi> may be great, but my <hi>successe,</hi> and <hi>Harvest</hi> small: And to speak truth to you, if I had been left to the peaceablenesse of my owne quiet Temper, (which never did delight in <hi>stormes,</hi> nor to dispute with <hi>Fire.</hi>) If the fierce, and eager Importunity of <hi>some</hi> who have provokt me, had not drawn me from my <hi>Iudgement,</hi> I should have followed their <hi>Advice,</hi> this <hi>Meeting</hi> had not beene. Nay, I should have lookt upon my <hi>Appearance</hi> here, as a <hi>Distemper,</hi> like to <hi>theirs,</hi> who have provokt and called me hither. For my coole and wiser Thoughts have still suggested to me, that to dispute of <hi>Truth</hi> with those who doe not understand it, is such a piece of <hi>Madnesse,</hi> as if I should dispute of <hi>Colours</hi> with a <hi>Blind man,</hi> of <hi>Musicke</hi> with a <hi>Deafe,</hi> or of the <hi>Sent</hi> of <hi>Flowers</hi> with <hi>One</hi> borne without a <hi>Smell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next, therefore, having so farre departed from my <hi>Reason,</hi> as to submit to a <hi>Dispute</hi> in this great publick <hi>Meeting,</hi> lest it should prove such a <hi>confused Meeting,</hi> as I described to you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; A <hi>Meeting</hi> where my <hi>Logick</hi> must fight <hi>Duels</hi> with Men made of Rudenesse, Tumult, Noyse; Or lest it should prove a <hi>Meeting</hi> where Men who can speak nought but <hi>English,</hi> shall yet speak <hi>divers Tongues</hi>; And where <hi>some shall cry out one Thing, and some shall cry another,</hi> I have made it my humble suit to some <hi>persons</hi> of <hi>Honour</hi> here present, that by their <hi>presence</hi> they will free the place from all such <hi>wild Confusions.</hi> And that, if I must dispute, I may dispute with <hi>civill men,</hi> and not undergoe Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s misfortune, who fought with <hi>Beast's at Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, lest this <hi>Meeting</hi> should prove like the <hi>confused Meeting,</hi> which I mention'd to you before, in one particular more; That is, lest the greatest part of you should not know why you are this day come together. Before I enter upon a full pursuit, or handling of this <hi>Text,</hi> it will be needfull that I tell you the occasion of this <hi>Meeting,</hi> which that I may the better doe, I shall desire you to beleeve, that 'tis not a <hi>Meeting</hi> of my <hi>projection</hi> or <hi>Contrivance.</hi> I appeare not here to raise a <hi>Faction,</hi> or to draw a <hi>party</hi> after me, nor to adde to the <hi>Rents</hi> of the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:59326:3"/>
which are too wide already. Nor am I come hither to revenge my selfe in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> or to speake ill of those who have most lewdly railed at me. Let them wallow themselves, as much as they please, in their owne grosse filth, and mire; let them, if they please,<note place="margin">Jude 13.</note> be those <hi>raging Waves</hi> of the <hi>Sea,</hi> which Saint <hi>Iude</hi> speakes of, which are alwayes <hi>foming out their owne shame,</hi> when they have steept their <hi>Tongues</hi> in <hi>Gall,</hi> and spewd forth all their <hi>Venome,</hi> They shall not make me change my <hi>Opinion</hi>; which is, that to cast <hi>dirt</hi> for <hi>dirt,</hi> or to returne <hi>Ill-Language</hi> for <hi>Ill-Language,</hi> is a cou<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se so unreasonable, as if two Men should fight a <hi>Duell,</hi> and chuse a <hi>Dunghill</hi> for their <hi>weapon.</hi> As therefore, I am not come hither to shew my selfe <hi>Malitious,</hi> so I am not come hither to gaine <hi>Applause,</hi> or <hi>Reputation</hi> by this <hi>Meeting.</hi> No thirst of <hi>Fame,</hi> no affection of <hi>Victorie</hi> hath drawne me from my <hi>Study</hi> to steppe into this <hi>Pulpit.</hi> I understand my owne <hi>Infirmities</hi> too well to be so selfe-conceited. Or if my Abilities were farre greater then they are, yet I have alwayes lookt on <hi>Fame</hi> thus got, to be so slight a Thing, as if a Man should feed on <hi>Ayre,</hi> or make a meale of <hi>shaddows.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not to hold you therefore any longer in suspense, if you, who know it not already, desire to know the true o<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>casion of this <hi>Meeting,</hi> 'tis briefely this; I have for some yeares (even with <hi>Teares</hi> in my eyes) seen one of the saddest curses of the <hi>Scripture</hi> fulfill'd upon this <hi>Nation</hi>: With a <hi>bleeding Heart</hi> I speake it, I have seene, not onely <hi>three Kingdoms,</hi> but our <hi>Cityes, Towns,</hi> and <hi>Villages,</hi> nay even our <hi>private Familyes</hi> divided against them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. I have seene the <hi>Father</hi> differing in opinion from the <hi>Sonne,</hi> and I have seene the <hi>Sonne</hi> differing in opinion from the <hi>Father.</hi> I have seene the <hi>Mother</hi> broken from the <hi>Daughter,</hi> and I have seen the <hi>Daughter</hi> divided from the <hi>Mother.</hi> Nay, our very <hi>Marriage-Beds</hi> have not scapt the curse of <hi>Separation.</hi> Like <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Esau</hi> issuing from the same <hi>wombe,</hi> I have seene <hi>two Twins</hi> of <hi>Separation</hi> rise from between the same <hi>Curtains.</hi> I have seen the <hi>Wedlock knot</hi> quite untyed in <hi>Religion</hi>; I have seene the <hi>Husband</hi> in opposition to the <hi>Wife</hi>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> goe to one, and I have seene the <hi>Wife</hi> in opposition to her <hi>Husband,</hi> for many years together, goe to another <hi>Congregation.</hi> In a Word (my Brethren,) the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> among us, which was once as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59326:4"/>
                  <hi>Seamelesse</hi> as his <hi>Coate,</hi> is now so rent by <hi>Schismes,</hi> so torne by <hi>Separations,</hi> that 'tis become like the <hi>Coate</hi> of <hi>Ioseph</hi> which you reade of in the 37. Chapter of <hi>Genesis,</hi> at the 3. verse, scarce <hi>one piece</hi> is colourd like <hi>another</hi>; And I pray God it prove not like the <hi>Coat</hi> of <hi>Ioseph</hi> in one particular more; I pray God the <hi>Weaker</hi> be not sold by his <hi>Brethren,</hi> and his <hi>Coate</hi> be not once more dyed <hi>red,</hi> once more imbrued in <hi>Bloud.</hi> This, you will say, is very sad, and yet this is not all; That which extremely adde to the Misery of our <hi>Rents,</hi> and <hi>Separations,</hi> is, that the <hi>wisest</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hope they will ere be <hi>peeced,</hi> or reconciled. For the <hi>persons</hi> who thus <hi>Separate,</hi> are so far from beleeving themselves to be in an <hi>Errour,</hi> that they strongly thinke all <hi>Others</hi> erre who <hi>seperate</hi> not too; They thinke <hi>themselves</hi> bound in <hi>Conscience</hi> to doe as they doe. Nay, zealous Arguments are urged, and Texts of <hi>Scripture</hi> quoted, to prove that 'tis a <hi>damning sinne</hi> not to goe on in <hi>Separation.</hi> The <hi>Churches</hi> where their <hi>Neighbours</hi> met ere now contemned, and Scorned: Nay, I have with mine owne Ears heard a <hi>Dining Room,</hi> a <hi>Chamber,</hi> a <hi>Meeting</hi> under <hi>Trees</hi>; Nay, I have heard a <hi>Hog-stye,</hi> a <hi>B<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rne,</hi> called places more sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied then they. In a word, one <hi>of</hi> the great Reasons which they urge, why they thus forsake our <hi>Churches,</hi> and make divided <hi>Congregations,</hi> is, because (They say) the <hi>people</hi> which assemble there are so wicked, so prophane, that they turne <hi>Gods House</hi> of prayer into a <hi>den of Theeves.</hi> To keep this infection from spread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in my <hi>Parish,</hi> and to keepe this piece of <hi>Leaven</hi> from sour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the whole <hi>Lumpe</hi>; And withall to satisfie one, whom I looke upon as a <hi>well-meaning,</hi> though a <hi>seduced,</hi> and <hi>erring per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> who hath ingaged her selfe by promise, that if I can take the <hi>mist</hi> from her <hi>Eyes,</hi> and cleerly let her see her <hi>Errour,</hi> she will returne back to the <hi>Church,</hi> from which she hath for some yeares gone astray; and being invited to doe this in a way of <hi>Christian challenge,</hi> which hath raised a great expectation in the <hi>Countrey,</hi> I have taken up the <hi>Gauntlet,</hi> and here present my selfe before you; and before I enter the <hi>Lists,</hi> to let you all see the Justice of the <hi>Cause</hi> which I here stand to <hi>defend,</hi> I have chosen this <hi>Text</hi> for my <hi>shield</hi>; where <hi>He,</hi> who wrote this <hi>Epistle</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> sayes, <hi>Let us consider one another to provoke one another to love and to Good works, not forsaking the Assembling of our selve<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> together, as the manner of some is.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:59326:4"/>
               <head>The Division.</head>
               <p>IN which <hi>words,</hi> the only <hi>poynt</hi> which I shall insist upon, as the <hi>fittest,</hi> and most <hi>seasonable</hi> to be preacht to this <hi>divided Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,</hi> shall be the <hi>point</hi> of <hi>Schisme</hi>; or, in plaine English, <hi>Separation,</hi> as 'tis exprest to us in these Words, <hi>Let us not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake the Assembling of our selves together, as the manner of some is.</hi> In the pursuit and handling of which words, I will proceed by <unclear>these</unclear> two plaine and easie <hi>steps.</hi> First, I will prove to you, by <hi>Arguments,</hi> which have a <hi>sun-beame</hi> for their <hi>parent,</hi> That the <hi>Rent</hi> or <hi>Separation</hi> which is now made in the <hi>Church,</hi> is a very <hi>grievous sinne</hi>: Indeed, a <hi>sinne</hi> so <hi>grievous,</hi> that I scarce know whether <hi>Christians</hi> can be guilty of a <hi>greater.</hi> Next, I will <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine</hi> and answer their <hi>Arguments,</hi> and <hi>Texts</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi>; who doe perswade <hi>themselves</hi> and <hi>others</hi> that their <hi>separation</hi> is no <hi>sinne</hi>; Nay, that would be a <hi>grievous sinne</hi> not to <hi>separate</hi> as they doe. In the meane time I beseech you to lend me a <hi>quiet</hi> and <hi>favourable</hi> Attention, whilest I <unclear>begin</unclear> with the <hi>first</hi> of th<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se <hi>parts,</hi> and that shall be to prove to you, that the <hi>separations</hi> of our <hi>Times,</hi> are <hi>great</hi> and <hi>grievous sinnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Among the other <hi>Characters</hi> and <hi>Descriptions</hi> which have been made of us <hi>Men,</hi> we have been called, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. That is, a <hi>Creature</hi> borne and made, and created for <hi>Society.</hi> Towards the preservation and maintenance <hi>wherof</hi> God at the <hi>Beginning,</hi> ordered his <hi>Creation</hi> of us so, that whereas other <hi>Creatures</hi> take their <hi>Originall</hi> and <hi>Birth</hi> from a <hi>Diversitie</hi> of <hi>parents.</hi> He made us <hi>Men</hi> to spring from one, undivided, single <hi>
                     <unclear>payre</unclear>.</hi> One <hi>Adam,</hi> and one <hi>Eve</hi> were the two <hi>joyn'd parents</hi> of <hi>Mankinde.</hi> And the Reason of this was, That there might not onely be among us one common <hi>Kinred</hi> and <hi>Alliance,</hi> but that we might hold a firme, and constant <hi>League</hi> and <hi>Friendship</hi> with each other too. And hence 'tis we see, that without any other <hi>Teacher</hi> but their owne <hi>Naturall Instinct,</hi> Men in all Ages have avoided <hi>seperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> by gathering themselves into formed Bodyes of <hi>Cittyes, Towns</hi> and <hi>Commonwealths.</hi> Neighbourhood, Society, mutuall help, and Conversation, being one of the great <hi>Ends</hi> for which God made us <hi>Men.</hi> And upon this <hi>Ground</hi> it hath been disputed,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59326:5"/>
whether a <hi>Hermit,</hi> or <hi>Monastic man,</hi> breake not the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> because he <hi>separates</hi> himselfe from the company of <hi>Men</hi>? And 'tis clearly stated by some great <hi>Casuists,</hi> That if he <hi>seperate</hi> from others for no End but <hi>separation,</hi> if he retire himselfe into a <hi>Cave</hi> or <hi>Wildernesse,</hi> or <hi>Desart,</hi> (as some of the <hi>Ancient Hermits</hi> did) not for <hi>Devotion,</hi> but out of a hatred, or distaste of the rest of <hi>Mankinde</hi>; In that particular he cannot well be called a <hi>Man,</hi> but some <hi>wilder Creature,</hi> made to dwell in <hi>Caves, Desarts, Forrests, Dens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As then, the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> doth require us to preserve <hi>society</hi> and <hi>Friendship,</hi> so the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> hath tyed, and woven this <hi>knot</hi> much faster. We are all of <hi>Kinne</hi> by <hi>Nature,</hi> but we are all <hi>Brethren</hi> as <hi>Christians:</hi> Men allyed to one another by one <hi>common Hope,</hi> one <hi>common Faith,</hi> one <hi>common Saviour,</hi> one <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon God,</hi> and <hi>Lord,</hi> and <hi>Father</hi> of us <hi>all.</hi> And upon this <hi>Ground,</hi> when <hi>one Christian</hi> shall divide or forsake the <hi>society</hi> of <hi>Another,</hi> unlesse it be upon a just <hi>principle</hi> of <hi>Conscience,</hi> and to avoid a <hi>sinne,</hi> the <hi>Scripture</hi> calls it not barely <hi>Separation,</hi> but <hi>Separation</hi> which is <hi>Schisme.</hi> That is, such a <hi>Separation</hi> as is a <hi>Gospel-sinne <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which, that you may the more clearly understand, give me leave to aske you in truth what is <hi>Schisme?</hi> Why the best <hi>Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition</hi> of it that was ever yet given is this, That <hi>Schisme</hi> is nothing else, but a <hi>separation</hi> of <hi>Christians</hi> from that part of the <hi>Visible Church,</hi> of which they were once <hi>Members,</hi> upon meere <hi>fancyed, slight, unnecessary Grounds.</hi> In which <hi>Definition</hi> of <hi>Schisme,</hi> three things doe offer themselves to your serious observation, to make it <hi>formall Schisme,</hi> or a <hi>signe</hi> of <hi>Separation.</hi> First it must be a <hi>separation</hi> of <hi>Christians</hi> from some part of the <hi>Visible Church,</hi> of which they were once <hi>Members</hi>; That is, (according to the <hi>Definition,</hi> a <hi>visible Church</hi> as it concerns this present purpose) it must be a Deniall of <hi>Communion</hi> with that <hi>Congregation</hi> of <hi>Christians,</hi> with whom they were once <hi>united</hi> under a <hi>rightly-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted Pastor.</hi> Next, they who thus <hi>separate,</hi> must betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to some other <hi>Teacher,</hi> whom, in opposition to the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> they chuse to be their <hi>Guide,</hi> and so make themselves his <hi>Followers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, they must erect a <hi>New Assembly,</hi> or place of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,</hi> as a <hi>New Church</hi> distinct from that from which they doe <hi>divide.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:59326:5"/>Lastly, This choyce of a <hi>New Guide,</hi> and <hi>Separation</hi> from the <hi>Old,</hi> this <hi>Erection</hi> of a <hi>New Church,</hi> and <hi>Division</hi> from the <hi>former</hi> must be upon slight unnecessary <hi>Grounds</hi>; For if the <hi>Cause,</hi> or <hi>Ground</hi> of their <hi>Separation</hi> be <hi>needlesse, vaine, unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary,</hi> if it spring more out of <hi>Humour, Pride,</hi> desi<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of <hi>change,</hi> or <hi>Hatred</hi> of their <hi>Brethren,</hi> then out of any <hi>Christian love</hi> to keepe themselves from <hi>sinnes</hi>; 'Tis in the <hi>Scripture</hi>-Language <hi>Schisme,</hi> That is, a <hi>sinne</hi> of <hi>Separation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or if you will heare me expresse my self in the language of a very <hi>learned Man</hi> (who hath contrived a <hi>clue</hi> to lead us through this <hi>Labyrinth</hi>) This breach of <hi>Communion,</hi> This <hi>separation</hi> from a Church <hi>rightly constituted</hi>; This choyce of a <hi>New Guide, New Teacher, New Instructer.</hi> Lastly, This setting up of a <hi>New Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,</hi> or place of <hi>private Meetings,</hi> is the same sinne in <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which <hi>Sedition,</hi> or <hi>Rebellion</hi> is in the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> or <hi>State.</hi> For upon a right examination of the matter 'twill be found, That <hi>Schisme</hi> is a <hi>Religious,</hi> or <hi>Ecclesiasticall Sedition,</hi> as <hi>Sedition</hi> in the <hi>State</hi> is a <hi>civill, Lay-schisme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which two <hi>sinnes,</hi> though they appeare to the World in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse <hi>shapes,</hi> the one with a <hi>Sword,</hi> the other with a <hi>Bible</hi> in his Hand; yet they both agree in this, that they both disturbe the <hi>publick peace.</hi> The one of the <hi>State,</hi> where men are tyed by <hi>Laws</hi> as <hi>Men</hi>; The other of the <hi>Church,</hi> where men should be tyed by <hi>Love</hi> as <hi>Christians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To let you yet farther see, what a <hi>grievous sinne</hi> this sinne of <hi>Schisme</hi> or <hi>Separation</hi> is; If the time would give me leave, I might here rayse the <hi>Schoolemen, Antient Fathers,</hi> and <hi>Generall Councells</hi> from the dead, and make them preach to you from this <hi>Pulpit</hi> against the sinne of <hi>Separation.</hi> I might tell you, that in the purest Times of the <hi>Church,</hi> a <hi>Schismatick,</hi> and <hi>Hereticke</hi> were lookt upon as <hi>Twinnes</hi>; The one as an <hi>Enemy</hi> to the <hi>Faith,</hi> the other to <hi>Communion.</hi> But because in our <hi>darke Times, learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> is so grown out of date, that to quote an <hi>Ancient Father,</hi> is thought a piece of <hi>Superstition</hi>; And to cite a <hi>Generall Councell</hi> is to speake words to our <hi>New Gifted men</hi> unknowne, I will say nothing of this sinne, but what the <hi>Scripture</hi> sayes before me.</p>
               <p>First, then, I shall desire you to heare what S. <hi>Paul</hi> sayes in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59326:6"/>
this <hi>case,</hi> in the last Chapter of his <hi>Epistle</hi> to the <hi>Romans</hi> at the 17. verse. Turne to the place, and marke it well I beseech you. <hi>Now I beseech you, brethren,</hi> sayes he there, <hi>Marke them which cause Divisions, and offences, contrary to the Doctrine which ye have learned, and avoid them:</hi> That is, in other words, <hi>Separate your selves from them.</hi> And then he gives you a <hi>Character,</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription</hi> of those <hi>Separaters</hi> at the 18. verse of that Chapter; And sayes, <hi>For they that are such, serve not our Lord Iesus Christ, but their owne Belly. And by good words and faire speeches deceive the Hearts of the simple.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In which words, <hi>Foure things</hi> are so exactly drawn to life, as makes them a perfect <hi>Prophecye,</hi> or rather <hi>picture</hi> of our <hi>Times</hi>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The first is, that there were some in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> dayes, who caused <hi>Divisions</hi> in the <hi>Church; Men,</hi> who in a way of <hi>Schisme,</hi> and <hi>Separation,</hi> made themselves the <hi>Heads</hi> and <hi>Leaders</hi> of <hi>divided Congregations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next, The <hi>Ground</hi> upon which they built their <hi>Separation</hi>; 'twas not upon any just, true, lawfull, Scripture-<hi>Ground.</hi> For the Text sayes, <hi>'Twas contrary to the Doctrine which the Apostles taught, and preacht.</hi> But the true <hi>cause,</hi> or <hi>Ground,</hi> why they thus caused <hi>Separations,</hi> was meerly <hi>self-Interest</hi>; And that they might <hi>gaine</hi> by their <hi>Divisions.</hi> Nay, 'twas such a poore, base, unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>selfe-Interest,</hi> that 'tis there said, they did it in compliance to their <hi>Belly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third thing which will deserve your <hi>observation,</hi> is, the <hi>cunning Art</hi> they used to draw the <hi>weake</hi> to be their <hi>Followers.</hi> 'Tis there sayd, that by <hi>good Words and faire Speeches, they decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Hearts of the simple,</hi> especially the <hi>simple</hi> of the <hi>weaker sex.</hi> And who these were, S. <hi>Paul,</hi> in other words, but to the same purpose tells you, in the 3. <hi>Chapter</hi> of his second <hi>Epistle</hi> to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> at the 5, 6, 7. <hi>verses</hi> of that <hi>Chapter.</hi> Where speaking of such <hi>Coseners,</hi> he sayes, they had a <hi>Forme of Godlinesse,</hi> an outward seeming <hi>Holynesse</hi> to deceive and cosen by; And that under this <hi>Forme of Godlynesse they crept into Houses,</hi> and there <hi>led Captive silly Women, loaden with sinnes, and drawne away with divers Lusts. Women</hi> so unable to distinguish <hi>Right</hi> from <hi>Wrong,</hi> that they were <hi>alwayes learning, and never able to come to the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:59326:6"/>And certainly, my Brethren, 'tis no new thing under the <hi>sunne,</hi> to see the <hi>weaker sexe</hi> misled by <hi>holy Formes,</hi> and <hi>Shews.</hi> 'Tis no new thing, I say, under the Sunne, for a man that makes <hi>long prayers,</hi> to eat up a <hi>Widdows House</hi>; Or for a <hi>cunning Angler</hi> to catch the <hi>sillyer sort,</hi> with a hooke <hi>bayted</hi> with <hi>Religion.</hi> 'Twas so in our <hi>Saviours</hi> time, and 'twas so in S. <hi>Pauls.</hi> And whether their demure lookes, their precise carriage, their long prayers, their good words and fayre speeches, be not the <hi>Hooke,</hi> and snare, by which <hi>weake people</hi> are caught now; whether the feasting of, their <hi>Bellyes,</hi> or the making <hi>Gayne</hi> of <hi>Godlinesse</hi>; Or whether the <hi>Itch</hi> and <hi>pride</hi> of being the <hi>Leaders</hi> of a <hi>Faction</hi>; Or whether the vaine <hi>Ambition</hi> of being thought more <hi>holy</hi> or more <hi>gifted</hi> than the rest, be not the true end of those, who doe now cause <hi>Separations,</hi> I will not rashly censure, but I have some reason to suspect<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But this is not all.</p>
               <p>The fourth, and last thing, which most deserves your <hi>observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> is, that <hi>Separation</hi> in that place is such a <hi>Scripture-sinne,</hi> that S. <hi>Paul</hi> commands us to <hi>separate</hi> from those, who doe thus cause <hi>Separations.</hi> Heare the place, I pray, once more repeated to you, <hi>I beseech you, Brethren,</hi> sayes he, <hi>Marke them who cause Divisions among you, and avoid them.</hi> That is, as I said be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Separate your selves from them.</hi> If they, who upon no just <hi>cause</hi> doe <hi>Separate,</hi> must be <hi>Separated</hi> from, I hope you'l all confesse that <hi>Separation</hi> is a sinne.</p>
               <p>And what <hi>sinne</hi> thinke you is this sinne of <hi>Separation?</hi> Why, I know some of you will thinke it strange if I should say, 'tis a <hi>sinne</hi> of the <hi>Flesh.</hi> And yet S. <hi>Paul</hi> sayes, that 'tis a <hi>sinne</hi> of the <hi>Flesh,</hi> in the 3. <hi>Chapter</hi> of his first <hi>Epistle</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> Marke I beseech you what he sayes in that place. <hi>Are ye not carnall?</hi> sayes he there. For <hi>whereas there are among you Envyings,</hi> and <hi>Strifes,</hi> and <hi>Divisions; Are ye not carnall, and walke as men?</hi> Sayes He at the 3. verse. Againe, <hi>when one saith, I am Paul; And when another saith, I am of Apollos; Are ye not carnall?</hi> sayes he at the 4. v. of that <hi>Chapter.</hi> If to <hi>divide</hi> and <hi>separate</hi> from the <hi>Followers</hi> of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and to make themselves the <hi>Followers,</hi> and <hi>Disciples</hi> of <hi>Apollos</hi>; or if by way of <hi>Separation</hi> to make themselves the markes of severall <hi>Churches,</hi> to which <hi>Apostles</hi> were the <hi>Guides,</hi> were a sinne of <hi>Carnality</hi>;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59326:7"/>
(as S. <hi>Paul</hi> sayes it was) what shall we say of some people of our <hi>Times?</hi> who instead of severall <hi>Apostles</hi> to divide themselves by, doe chuse to themselves <hi>Guides</hi> so <hi>meane,</hi> so <hi>unlearned,</hi> so lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to <hi>Errour,</hi> that they perfectly make between them the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of <hi>Mistakes</hi>: The <hi>Blinde leading the Blinde,</hi> and both <hi>fallen into a Ditch?</hi> 'Tis not now, as 'twas then. When some said, <hi>we are of Paul,</hi> and when others said, <hi>we are of Cephas,</hi> and when others said, <hi>we are of Apollos</hi>; Others, <hi>we are of Christ.</hi> Though to make the Names of <hi>Christ,</hi> or <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>Cephas,</hi> names of Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, was a sinne. But we are faln on <hi>Times</hi> so made of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration,</hi> that people doe divide themselves by <hi>Teachers,</hi> whose second <hi>Trade</hi> is <hi>Teaching. Teachers</hi> so <hi>obscure,</hi> so bred to <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall Occupations; Teachers</hi> so sprung up from the <hi>basest</hi> of the <hi>people.</hi> Lastly, <hi>Teachers,</hi> so accustomed to the <hi>Trewell, Forge,</hi> and <hi>Anvill,</hi> that I almost blush to name them in the <hi>Pulpit.</hi> 'Tis not now sa<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, <hi>we are of Paul,</hi> And we are of <hi>Apollos</hi>; But we are of <hi>Wat Tyler</hi>; We are of <hi>Iacke Cade</hi>; We are of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the <hi>Coporsmith</hi>; We are of <hi>Tom</hi> the <hi>Mason</hi>; and we are of <hi>Dicke</hi> the <hi>Gelder.</hi> And whether to <hi>Divide</hi> and <hi>Separate</hi> under such vulgar <hi>Names</hi> as <hi>These,</hi> be no a <hi>sinne of the Flesh,</hi> I leave to every one of you, who have read S. <hi>Paul,</hi> to judge.</p>
               <p>And here, now, if <hi>Time</hi> were not a Winged Thing, or if it would but stay my leisure, I might lay before you many other places of the <hi>Scripture,</hi> which clearly doe <hi>demonstrate</hi> that <hi>Separation</hi> is a sinne. For though, like the <hi>Ghost</hi> of <hi>Samuel,</hi> which you read of in the <hi>Scripture,</hi> it usually appeare cloathed in the <hi>Mantle</hi> of a <hi>Prophet,</hi> though it were <hi>Holinesse</hi> in the <hi>Tongue,</hi> And <hi>precisenesse</hi> in the <hi>Face</hi>; yet to let you see what an <hi>Apple</hi> of <hi>Sodome</hi> it is; How it lookes with a <hi>Virgin</hi> check without, and is nought but <hi>Rottennesse</hi> within, I shall once more desire y<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u to heare what S. <hi>Paul</hi> sayes of it, In the 5. Chapter of the <hi>Galatians</hi> at the 19. and 20. verses of that chapter, Where he once more reckons it among the <hi>sinnes</hi> of the <hi>Flesh.</hi> As for Example, The <hi>Works of the Flesh are manifest,</hi> sayes he, <hi>which are these<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Adulterie, Fornication, Vncleannesse, Lasciviousnesse, Idolatrie, Witchcraft, Hatred, Variance, Emulation, Wrath, Strife, Seditions, Haeresies,</hi> sayes our English<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Translation. But the words in the <hi>Originall Greek,</hi> (which are the true <hi>Word</hi> of God) will beare it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59326:7"/>
thus. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, That is, <hi>Divisions, Sects, Envy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Murthers, Drunkennesse, Revellings, and such like. Of the which I tell you before,</hi> sayes he, <hi>As I have told you in Times past, Th<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t They which doe such Things shall not Inherit the Kingdome of God.</hi> Where you see <hi>Seditions, Sects,</hi> and <hi>Schismes,</hi> as well as <hi>Adulterie,</hi> and <hi>Murther,</hi> are there listed by S. <hi>Paul</hi> among those <hi>works of the Flesh,</hi> which doe shut men out of <hi>
                     <unclear>Heaven</unclear>,</hi> and exclude them from <hi>salvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Many such like places of the <hi>Scripture</hi> I might lay before you. But I will content my selfe with one <hi>Argument</hi> more; which shall not onely prove to you, That <hi>Separation</hi> is a <hi>sinne</hi>; But one of the <hi>Greatest sinnes,</hi> of which <hi>Christians</hi> can be guilty.</p>
               <p>To make this cleare to you, and beyond all <hi>Dispute,</hi> or <hi>Questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> That which I will say to you (and mark it well) is this. 'Tis a Rule in <hi>Divinity,</hi> (and tis a <hi>Rule infallible</hi>) That those <hi>sinnes</hi> are the <hi>Greatest,</hi> which are most <hi>contrary,</hi> and doe most <hi>oppose</hi> the <hi>greatest Christian vertues.</hi> Now the Three Great Christian <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues</hi> which doe make and constitute a <hi>Christian,</hi> are set downe by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> in the 13. chapter of his first <hi>Epistle</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> at the last verse, where he sayes, Now abideth <hi>Faith, Hope,</hi> and <hi>Charity; But the Greatest of these is Charity.</hi> Thus, then, stands the case. <hi>Distrust in Gods promises,</hi> or an <hi>unbeliefe</hi> in his <hi>power,</hi> is a very great sinne. For 'tis a sinne which doth <hi>oppose</hi> and quite cut off the wings of <hi>Hope. Haeresie,</hi> or the strife, and obstinate <hi>Defence,</hi> and persisting in a <hi>knowne Errour,</hi> is a farre <hi>greater sinne.</hi> For 'tis a sinne against <hi>Faith,</hi> a sinne which strives to draw a Cloud about the Beames of <hi>Truth.</hi> But if it be true what S. <hi>Paul</hi> sayes, (as most certainly it is) If it be true that <hi>Charity</hi> is <hi>greater</hi> then either <hi>Faith,</hi> or <hi>Hope,</hi> Then 'twill follow by <hi>Good Logick</hi> and all the <hi>Consequence</hi> of <hi>Reason</hi>; That that <hi>sinne</hi> which doth <hi>untie,</hi> and <hi>break</hi> the <hi>Bond</hi> of <hi>peace</hi>; That sinne which destroyes <hi>Christian Friendship,</hi> and <hi>Communion</hi>; Lastly, That sinne which rends, and teares the Cords of <hi>Charity</hi> asunder, is a farre <hi>greater</hi> sinne then <hi>unbeliefe</hi> or <hi>Haeresie.</hi> And the sin which doth all this is the sin of <hi>Separation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>First 'tis a <hi>greater</hi> sinne in it <hi>selfe,</hi> and the very <hi>formality</hi> of the <hi>sinne.</hi> As being the <hi>worst Extreme</hi> to the best, and <hi>greatest vertue,</hi> Namely, The <hi>vertue</hi> of <hi>Love</hi>; By which <hi>Christ</hi> would have his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59326:8"/>
                  <hi>Followers</hi> distinguisht from the rest of <hi>Mankinds.</hi> For <hi>by this shall all men know,</hi> sayes he, <hi>that you are my Disciples,</hi> if yee <hi>love one another.</hi> As you may read in the 13. chapter of <hi>Iohn</hi> at the 35. verse. And agreeable to this is that which is delivered here in this Text, where the <hi>Authour</hi> of this <hi>Epistle</hi> to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> sayes, <hi>Let us consider one another to provoke one another to Love. And not forsake the Assembling of our selves together, as the manner of some is.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as <hi>Schisme,</hi> or <hi>Separation</hi> upon a <hi>slight,</hi> or <hi>needlesse Ground</hi> is in it <hi>selfe</hi> one of the <hi>greatest</hi> sinnes; So tis one of the <hi>greatest</hi> sinnes too, in its <hi>dangerous Effects.</hi> Besides the <hi>Hatred, Envy, Strife,</hi> which it begets among Men of divided <hi>Interests,</hi> and <hi>Mindes,</hi> Tis many times the <hi>Coale</hi> which sets whole <hi>States</hi> and <hi>Common-wealths</hi> on fire. It pretends, indeed, very much to the <hi>Spirit,</hi> And at first cloaths it selfe in the <hi>Dresse</hi> of <hi>Humility</hi> and <hi>Meekn<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sse</hi>; But they who have written the <hi>Chronicles</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> can tell you, That those <hi>pretences</hi> to the <hi>Spirit</hi> have no sooner gathered strength, but they have proceeded to <hi>bloudy Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tells,</hi> and <hi>pitcht fields.</hi> Where the <hi>Meeke</hi> persons have throwne aside their <hi>Bibles</hi>; and have changed the <hi>Sword of the Spirit</hi> into the <hi>Sword of Warre.</hi> The proceedings of the <hi>Donatists</hi> in <hi>Affricke,</hi> and of the <hi>Iohn</hi>-of <hi>Leyden</hi>-Men at <hi>Munster</hi> are two sad <hi>Examples</hi> of the truth of what I say.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Grounds of Separation examined.</head>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <p>BUt here, perhaps, will some of you, who heare me this day, say, What's all this to us? In saying this which you have hitherto said, like those who wrote <hi>Romances,</hi> you have but created an <hi>Adversary</hi> out of your own <hi>fancy,</hi> and then foyl'd him; or like the man in <hi>Aristotle</hi> who drove his <hi>shaddow</hi> before him, you first frame a man of <hi>Ayre,</hi> and then cry he flyes from you. But if this be to conquer, one of our <hi>Gifted Men</hi> who is at all no Scholler, can as well triumph over men of <hi>Ayre,</hi> and <hi>shad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes,</hi> as <hi>your selfe.</hi> To let you see, therefore, that I am one of those, who desire not to fight <hi>Duels</hi> with <hi>naked unarmed Men,</hi> nor to meet any in the <hi>Field,</hi> before we have agreed upon the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59326:8"/>
just length of our <hi>Weapons:</hi> If your <hi>patience</hi> will hold out so long, who come <hi>disinterested</hi> hither, This second part of this <hi>Sermon</hi> shall be spent in the pursuit of that, which Master <hi>Deane</hi> of <hi>Christ-church</hi> just now very <hi>seasonably</hi> noted as a <hi>Defect</hi> in our present way of <hi>Arguing,</hi> and <hi>Dispute,</hi> which was, that the <hi>Grounds</hi> were not examined upon which the <hi>present Separations</hi> of these Times, do build themselves. These <hi>Grounds,</hi> therefore, I shall now in the next place call to some <hi>reckoning</hi> and <hi>Account,</hi> And in the doing of this, I will hang up a payre of <hi>Scales</hi> before you, you shall see their <hi>Arguments</hi> placed in <hi>One Scale,</hi> and my <hi>Answers</hi> in the <hi>Other:</hi> And because no <hi>Moderatour</hi> sits in the <hi>Chayre</hi> to judge (which was a thing foreseen by <hi>me,</hi> but could not well be compast) I shall make <hi>you</hi> the <hi>Iudges</hi> who heare me this day. And because the <hi>Rudenesse,</hi> and <hi>Ill-language</hi> of those who have disturbed me in this <hi>Pulpit,</hi> hath made me stand before you here like a man arraigned for <hi>Errour,</hi> I will freely cast my selfe upon <hi>God,</hi> and you the <hi>Countrey.</hi> Thus, then, I shall proceede.</p>
               <p>Here (as I said before) may some of the <hi>Separating party,</hi> say to me, How doth the former part of your <hi>Sermon</hi> concern us? We <hi>separate,</hi> 'tis true, But not on those <hi>false Grounds</hi> which you have all this while described. We grant, indeed, That if we broke <hi>Communion</hi> with you out of <hi>Faction,</hi> or <hi>Selfe-Interest,</hi> or <hi>Pride,</hi> or desire of <hi>Gaine,</hi> or meere <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>Separation,</hi> you might well call us <hi>Schismaticks</hi>; and we should well deserve that <hi>Name.</hi> But the <hi>Ground</hi> on which we <hi>separate</hi> from you, is, because you are not fit to be <hi>Assembled</hi> with, you are <hi>sinners</hi>; wicked, lewd, profane, notorious <hi>sinners.</hi> The <hi>places</hi> where you meet breathe nothing but <hi>Infection.</hi> Your <hi>Teachers</hi> preach false <hi>Doctrine</hi>; and your people practise <hi>Lyes.</hi> In a word, we cannot with the safety of our Conscience frequent your <hi>Congregations.</hi> Since to appeare there would be an enterprize as dangerous, as if we should make Visits to a <hi>Pest-house</hi>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and there hope to scape the <hi>Plague.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This you will say (good people) is very hard language. And How, thinke you, do they prove it? why, as they thinke by two cleare places of the <hi>Scripture,</hi> which no man can <hi>oppose</hi>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and not make <hi>Warre</hi> with <hi>Heaven.</hi> Two places of <hi>Scripture,</hi> I say, have
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59326:9"/>
beene produced, and quoted to me, like <hi>Sampson</hi> and <hi>Achilles,</hi> with Invincible <hi>Lances</hi> in their Hands. Places which doe not onely <hi>allow,</hi> but <hi>command</hi> a <hi>separation</hi>; Nay, they <hi>command</hi> it so fully, that if they should not <hi>separate,</hi> or forsake our <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations,</hi> they say they should sinne greatly, and disobey the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</hi> And what are these two <hi>places?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>fi<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>st</hi> you shall finde set downe in the 5. last <hi>verses</hi> of the 6. Chapter, of the second Epistle of S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> where the words run thus. <hi>Be ye not unequally yokt together with unbeleevers. For what Fellowship hath Righteousnesse with unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse? And what Communion hath Light with Darknesse?</hi> And <hi>what Concord hath Christ with Belial? Or what part hath he that believeth with an Infidell? And what agreement hath the Temple of God with Idolls? For ye are the Temple of the living God;</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Levit. 26.11.</note> 
                  <hi>As God hath said, I will dwell in them, and walke in them; And I will be their God, and they shall be my people. Wherefore come out from among them, and be ye seperate,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Esay 52.11.</note> 
                  <hi>saith the Lord, and touch not the uncleane thing, and I will receive you.</hi> This is their <hi>first</hi> great <hi>place,</hi> which they urge for <hi>separation.</hi> Will you now heare their <hi>second?</hi> That you shall finde set downe in the 4. first <hi>verses</hi> of the 18. <hi>Chapter</hi> of the <hi>Revelations.</hi> Where the words run thus, <hi>After these things,</hi> sayes S. <hi>Iohn</hi> there, <hi>I saw another Angel come downe from Heaven, having great power; and the Earth was light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with his Glory. And he cryed mightily, with a strong voice, saying, Babylon the Great is fallen, is fallen, and is become the Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Divells, and the hold of every foule Spirit; And the Cage of every unclean, and hatefull Bird. For all Nations have drunke of the wine of the wrath of her Fornications; And the Kings of the Earth have committed Fornication with her. And the Merchants of the Earth are waxed rich, through the Abundance of her Delicacyes. And I heard Another voyce from heaven,</hi> (sayes he) <hi>saying; Come out of her my people, that yee be not partakers of her sinnes, and that yee receive not of her plagues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>These <hi>two places</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> (if you will heare me expresse my selfe in the <hi>thred-bare Language</hi> of the <hi>Times</hi>) They say, doe <hi>hold Forth</hi> themselves soe clearely, that I may sooner quench the <hi>sunne</hi> than finde an <hi>Answer</hi> to them. Nay, to deale freely with you, these <hi>two places,</hi> and <hi>these</hi> only are a piece of the <hi>Challenge</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:59326:9"/>
which hath occasioned this <hi>Dispute.</hi> For I am promised by <hi>Her,</hi> whom I here come to <hi>undeceive,</hi> that if I can answer these <hi>two places,</hi> she wil be my <hi>Convert</hi>; And will <hi>separate</hi> from these who doe now make <hi>separations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I take <hi>her</hi> at her word, and doe thus contrive, and shape my <hi>Answers</hi>; Marke them I beseech you. As for the first place in the 6. <hi>Chapter</hi> of the second <hi>Epistle</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians</hi>; you are to understand, that when S. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote that <hi>Epistle,</hi> The City of <hi>Corinth</hi> was not wholly converted to the <hi>Faith,</hi> but was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in <hi>Religions,</hi> some were yet <hi>Heathens,</hi> and sacrificed to <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>: Others did imbrace the <hi>Gospell,</hi> and gave up their Names to <hi>Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>N<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>verthelesse, th<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y were not so divided in <hi>Religions,</hi> but that dwelling together in the same <hi>City,</hi> certaine Neighbourly <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villities,</hi> and Acts of <hi>kindnesse</hi> past between them. As for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, when a <hi>Heathen</hi> or <hi>Vnbeleever</hi> offerd a <hi>sacrifice</hi> to his <hi>Idol,</hi> 'twas usuall, for old Acquaintance sake, to invite his <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Friends</hi> to be <hi>Guests</hi> to his <hi>sacrifice</hi>; And to eate of his <hi>meate</hi> which was <hi>offered</hi> to his <hi>Idol,</hi> As you may read, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.27, 28. And the <hi>place</hi> where the <hi>sacrifice</hi> was eaten, and where the <hi>Feast</hi> was made, was, for the most part in the <hi>Temple</hi> of the <hi>Idol,</hi> As you may read, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.10. Now, this mingling of <hi>Religions</hi>; This meeting of <hi>Christians</hi> with <hi>Heathens,</hi> at a <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Feast</hi>; Nay, at a <hi>Feast</hi> where the <hi>Meat</hi> was first <hi>offerd</hi> to an <hi>Idol,</hi> Nay in that <hi>Idol</hi> was offered to the <hi>Devils,</hi> as you may reade, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.20. Nay, this meeting of <hi>Christians</hi> with <hi>Heathens</hi> at an <hi>Idol sacrifice,</hi> and their eating with them of that <hi>sacrifice</hi> in the very <hi>Temple</hi> of the <hi>Idol,</hi> was a thing so <hi>dangerous,</hi> so apt to call <hi>weake Christians</hi> back againe to their former <hi>Idolatry,</hi> That Saint <hi>Paul</hi> thought it high time to say, <hi>Be not</hi> thus <hi>unequally <unclear>jokt</unclear> with unbeleevers.</hi> In which expression he doth cast an eye upon that <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which you may read set downe in the 22 <hi>Chapter</hi> of <hi>Deuteronomye,</hi> at the 9, 10, 11. <hi>verses</hi> of that <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> Where <hi>God</hi> sayes, <hi>Thou shalt not sow thy Vineyard with diverse seeds; Nor shalt thou plough thy field with an Oxe, and an Asse yokt together; Nor shalt thou weare a Garment of divers sorts, Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of Linnen, and Woollen woven together in one piece.</hi> To the <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall</hi> meaning of which <hi>Law,</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> here alludes, when he sayes, <hi>Be not unequally yokt with Vnbeleevers.</hi> For a <hi>Christian</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:59326:10"/>
mingling with a <hi>Heathen,</hi> in a <hi>Heathen Congregation:</hi> Nay, a <hi>Christian</hi> mingling with a <hi>Heathen</hi> in the <hi>Temple</hi> of an <hi>Idol,</hi> was a more <hi>disproportion'd</hi> sight, then to see an <hi>Oxe yokt with an Asse</hi> in the same <hi>Plough</hi>; Or th<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n to see <hi>Corn</hi> sown with <hi>Grapes</hi> in the same <hi>Field</hi>; Or then to see <hi>Wool</hi> mixt with <hi>Linnen</hi> in the same <hi>Garment.</hi> In a Word, the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of the <hi>Heathens</hi> was so incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistent with the <hi>Religion</hi> of the <hi>Christians,</hi> that S. <hi>Paul</hi> proceeds, and sayes, that they might as well reconcile <hi>Light</hi> to <hi>Darkn<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sse,</hi> or contrive a League betweene <hi>Christ</hi> and <hi>Belial</hi>; Or tye a Marriage knot between <hi>Righteousnesse</hi> and <hi>sinne,</hi> as make it hold in fitnesse; That <hi>Christians</hi> who are the <hi>Temples</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and of his holy <hi>Spirit,</hi> should meer, and eate, and beare a part in the <hi>Idol Temples</hi> of the <hi>Heathens.</hi> And these <hi>Infidels,</hi> these <hi>Heathens,</hi> who did not believe in <hi>Christ</hi>; These <hi>Corinthians unconverted,</hi> These <hi>Worshippers</hi> of <hi>Idols,</hi> who strived to draw the <hi>Christians</hi> back to their former <hi>Superstitions,</hi> were they from whom S. <hi>Paul</hi> bids his <hi>New Converts</hi> separate themselves. <hi>Come out from among them, and be ye separate,</hi> sayes he, at the 17. <hi>verse</hi> of that <hi>Chapter.</hi> O, (in the Language of the place) <hi>Come out from among them, and be ye separate, saith the Lord, and touch not the uncleane thing, and I will receive you.</hi> Which <hi>words</hi> are but a <hi>string</hi> struck by the Prophet <note n="*" place="margin">Esay 52.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Esay</hi> first, and spoken by him, of the <hi>separation</hi> of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> from the then <hi>Idolatryes</hi> of the <hi>Heathens.</hi> And that this is the true Interpretation of <hi>this place,</hi> will appeare to any who shall compare, what S. <hi>Paul</hi> here sayes, with that which he sayes, in the 10. <hi>Chapter</hi> of his first <hi>Epistle</hi> to the <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inthians,</hi> from the 19. to the 30. <hi>verse</hi> of that <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This then, being so, Let me aske the <hi>zealous persons,</hi> who thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in <hi>Separation,</hi> are <hi>They</hi> from whom they <hi>separate</hi> such <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dells,</hi> such <hi>Heathens,</hi> such <hi>Worshippers</hi> of <hi>Idols,</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth here describe? Doe they see any <hi>Gods</hi> of <hi>Gold,</hi> erected in our <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples?</hi> Or doe they see any <hi>Images</hi> of <hi>Silver</hi> adored, and sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed to by our <hi>Congregations</hi>? Doe any of us make <hi>prayer</hi>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to a <hi>stocke?</hi> Or doe any of us burne <hi>Incense</hi> to a <hi>Stone?</hi> Nay, l<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t them (if they please) examine us by their <hi>private-meeting. Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chisme.</hi> Doe we not confesse <hi>the same God</hi> that they doe? Doe we not beleeve in <hi>the same Iesus Christ?</hi> Do we preach another <hi>Gospel?</hi> Or hope to be <hi>saved</hi> by any other <hi>Name</hi> but His? Are not our <hi>Congregations</hi> built on the <hi>Scripture-Rock</hi>? Is not <hi>Christ</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:59326:10"/>
our <hi>Corner Stone,</hi> and his <hi>Apostles</hi> our <hi>Foundation?</hi> Doe we not <hi>agree</hi> with them in <hi>all</hi> things, but where they <hi>differ</hi> from the <hi>Scripture</hi>? As for Example, we doe maintaine, and say, that <hi>separation</hi> is a <hi>sinne.</hi> They doe maintaine and say, That 'tis a <hi>Christian Duty</hi>; We urge that Text which sayes, <hi>One Lord, One Faith, One Baptisme</hi>; They urge no Text, which sayes, Men must be twice Baptised. We say, that if a <hi>Child</hi> of <hi>God</hi> doe breake Gods <hi>Laws,</hi> a <hi>Child</hi> of <hi>God sinnes.</hi> Some of them say that <hi>God</hi> beholds no sinne in his <hi>Children.</hi> Lastly, we say of the <hi>Scripture,</hi> as <note n="†" place="margin">2 Pet. 3.16,</note> S. <hi>Peter</hi> said of S. <hi>Pauls Epistles; That there be some things in seem, very hard to be understood, which they who are unlearned w<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>st to their owne Destruction.</hi> They say <hi>unlearned Gifted</hi> Me are the best <hi>Expounders</hi> of the <hi>Scripture</hi>; What they meane by <hi>Gifted Men</hi> I will not here examine. But that which I will say is this, because We differ in <hi>Opinions</hi> to <hi>divide</hi> themselves from us; Nay to apply such a <hi>reproachfull</hi> place of <hi>Scripture</hi> to us, as makes us no better then <hi>Infidels,</hi> and <hi>Heathens,</hi> and <hi>Worshippers</hi> of <hi>Idols,</hi> is to <hi>revile</hi> us with the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and to <hi>Libell</hi> us with <hi>Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Would <hi>They</hi> take it well, if we should apply to <hi>Them</hi> that place which sayes; <hi>Woe to you, yee Hypocrites, yee Blind Leaders of the Blind</hi>; you who <hi>strayne at Gnats,</hi> and yet securely <hi>swallow Camels</hi>? Would <hi>They</hi> take it well, if we should quote a place of <hi>Scripture,</hi> and make it call <hi>Them whited Sepulchers</hi>; which showe <hi>fayre</hi> and <hi>beautifull without,</hi> and <hi>hold nought</hi> but <hi>stinke,</hi> and <hi>Rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tennesse</hi> within? Againe, would <hi>They</hi> take it well if we should apply to <hi>them,</hi> that place which speakes of Men, who have a <hi>Forme</hi> of <hi>Godlinesse,</hi> but <hi>deny the power thereof</hi>? Men, who like the old <hi>Pharisees,</hi> with a <hi>long prayer</hi> in their Mouth, <hi>creep into Houses, and there leade Captive silly Women?</hi> Lastly, would <hi>They</hi> take it well if we should apply that place to <hi>Them,</hi> which sayes; <hi>That as Iannes, and Iambres withstood Moses, so doe these men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>si<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t the Truth? Men of corrupt Mindes; Reprobate concerning the Faith?</hi> (as 'tis in the <hi>Greek,</hi> and the <hi>Margin</hi> of your <hi>Bibles</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Men <hi>purblinde, voide</hi> of <hi>Iudgement</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>true</hi> knowledge of the <hi>Faith?</hi> If they would not take it well, why doe they not observe the <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Equity,</hi> and <hi>Iustice,</hi> which is, <hi>To doe to us,</hi> but as They <hi>would have us doe to them</hi>?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:59326:11"/>But here perhaps, will some of you who heare me this day, say; We doe not <hi>separate</hi> from you, because you are out-right <hi>unbeleevers, Pagans, Infidels,</hi> or <hi>Heathens</hi>; But because you weare the Names of <hi>Christians,</hi> and yet live the Lives of <hi>Heathens.</hi> Though you doe not worship <hi>Idols,</hi> yet there is <hi>Covetousnesse</hi> among you, which S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls <note n="†" place="margin">Col. 3.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Idolatry.</hi> And though you d<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>fesse <hi>Christ,</hi> yet you walke <hi>disorderly</hi>; And doe commit <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>sinnes</hi> which they who <hi>denyed Christ</hi> did. Though we see no <hi>Gods</hi> of <hi>Gold</hi> nor <hi>Silver</hi> in your <hi>Temples,</hi> yet if we came there, we might see a <hi>Congregation</hi> of such people as S. <hi>Paul</hi> in other places bids us <hi>Separate</hi> from. As for <hi>Example,</hi> turne to the 3. <hi>Chapter</hi> of his second <hi>Epistle</hi> to the <hi>Thessalonians,</hi> and the 6 verse. Doth he not there command us <hi>In the name of the Lord Iesus to withdraw our selves from every Brother, who walkes dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly, and not according to the Traditions which he taught?</hi> Or if this place be not cleare enough, turne to the 5. <hi>Chapter</hi> of the first <hi>Epistle</hi> of S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and to the 11. verse, Doth he not there say, that if <hi>Any man that is called a Brother, be a Fornicatour, or Covetous, or an Idolater, or a Rayler, or a Drunkard, or an Extortioner,</hi> with such a one we are not to keep Company, <hi>No, not to eat?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I grant, indeed, S. <hi>Paul</hi> sayes so, and doe think it very fit that S. <hi>Paul</hi> should be obeyed. But how doth this prove that they are to <hi>forsake</hi> our <hi>Congregations</hi>? That there are <hi>such men</hi> among us, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth there describe, is a <hi>Truth</hi> too cleare to be denyed. But are our <hi>whole Congregations</hi> composed of such men? Are <hi>all Drunkards</hi>? Are <hi>all Fornicatours?</hi> Are <hi>all Raylers?</hi> Are <hi>all Extortioners</hi>? Are <hi>all,</hi> both <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>People</hi> so like one another, that when they meete they make not a Church. <hi>Assembly,</hi> but a <hi>Congregation</hi> of such <hi>sinners</hi>? Or are they onely <hi>some?</hi> And they, perhaps, the <hi>lesser part</hi> who are guilty of those <hi>sinnes?</hi> Nay suppose they should be farre the <hi>greater part,</hi> who are guilty of these <hi>sinnes</hi>; yet you know out <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Saviour Christ</hi> compares the <hi>Church</hi> to a <hi>Field sowne with good seed</hi>; But then he tells us too. That to the Worlds end, among the <hi>good seed</hi> there shall still grow <hi>Weeds,</hi> and <hi>Tares.</hi> Againe, in the 13. <hi>chapter</hi> of S. <hi>Mathew</hi> at the 47. and 48. <hi>verses</hi> of that <hi>Chapter,</hi> he compares the <hi>Kingdome of God</hi> here in this World, to a <hi>Net cast into the Sea,</hi> which inclosed <hi>Fishes</hi> of all
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59326:11"/>
                  <hi>sorts, Bad</hi> as well as <hi>Good.</hi> And what the meaning of this draught of <hi>mingled Fishes</hi> is, I shall desire you to read at the 49. and 50. <hi>verses</hi> of that chapter, where he sayes; That at the <hi>End of the world,</hi> and not till then, the <hi>Angles shall go forth,</hi> and shall <hi>separate the wicked from among the Iust:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, sayes the Originall <hi>Greek,</hi> They shall <hi>separate</hi> the <hi>wicked</hi> fro the <hi>midst</hi> of the <hi>Iust,</hi> which clearely doth prove to us, That till this fi<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all <hi>Separation,</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>God</hi> here on earth, there will alwayes be a <hi>mixture</hi>: To <hi>divide</hi> or <hi>separate,</hi> therefore, from the <hi>whole Congregation,</hi> because some <hi>wicked men</hi> are in it, is a course so <hi>unreasonable,</hi> as if they should refuse a <hi>Field</hi> of <hi>
                     <unclear>Corne</unclear>
                  </hi> because there grew some <hi>weeds,</hi> or should renounce a <hi>Field</hi> of <hi>Wheat</hi> because it beares some <hi>Tares.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Besides, I would faine know, how farre they will extend the meaning of that <hi>Text,</hi> where S. <hi>Paul</hi> sayes, That they are <hi>not to eat with a Brother,</hi> who is a <hi>Drunkard,</hi> or <hi>Adulterer,</hi> or <hi>Rayler,</hi> or <hi>Extortioner.</hi> Will they extend it to <hi>all sorts</hi> of persons who are such? If they will, Then if a <hi>Woman</hi> have a <hi>Drunkard</hi> to her <hi>Husband,</hi> she must <hi>separate</hi> from him because he is a Drunkard, if she doe not, every time she eats with him, she disobeyes S. <hi>Paul</hi>; and in every <hi>meals</hi> she makes with him she commits a <hi>Scripture sinne.</hi> By the same reason also, If the <hi>Sonne</hi> have a <hi>Drunkard</hi> to his <hi>Father,</hi> he must remove <hi>Tables,</hi> and not dyet with his <hi>Father.</hi> And so there will be one <hi>Division</hi> more then those the <hi>Scripture</hi> speakes of: For that onely tells us that the time shall come when the <hi>Sonne</hi> shall be divided from the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and the <hi>Mother</hi> from the <hi>Daughter.</hi> But if this <hi>Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> be true, the <hi>Wife</hi> must <hi>divide</hi> and <hi>break</hi> her selfe from her <hi>distemper'd Husband</hi> too.</p>
               <p>Nay give me leave to goe one step farther yet. If the sinnes of a <hi>part</hi> be a just sufficient Ground to <hi>separate</hi> from the <hi>whole,</hi> Why doe not <hi>they</hi> who <hi>separate, divide</hi> and fall <hi>assu<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r</hi>? For here let me ask them, and let me ask without offence; Are they <hi>all</hi> so <hi>Innocent,</hi> so <hi>pure,</hi> so <hi>free,</hi> so voyd of <hi>sinne,</hi> that there is not one <hi>disorderly Brother</hi> among them? Is their place of <hi>private Meetings</hi> so much the <hi>New Ierusalem,</hi> That no <hi>Drunkard,</hi> no <hi>Adulterer,</hi> nor <hi>Rayler</hi> enters there? I wish there did not, my Brethren. We <hi>Ministers</hi> should not then so oft be called <hi>Dumb Doggs, Idol shepheards, Limbs of Antichrist, Baals Priests,</hi> by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59326:12"/>
                  <hi>Tongues,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jam. 3.6.</note> wich if S. <hi>Iames</hi> say true, <hi>are set on fire of Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If then, it be not the meaning of S. <hi>Paul</hi> in that place, that we should <hi>separate</hi> from <hi>all</hi> because <hi>some</hi> of those <hi>All</hi> are <hi>wicked,</hi> upon what other <hi>just Ground</hi> doe they break <hi>Communion</hi> with us? Is it because we preach in <hi>Churches</hi>? They are Gods House of <hi>prayer.</hi> Made his by the <hi>Piety,</hi> and <hi>Devotion</hi> of our <hi>Fathers,</hi> who if they lived now would hardly call them <hi>Saints,</hi> who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre a <hi>Barne,</hi> nay a <hi>Hog-stye</hi> before a <hi>consecrated Temple.</hi> Or is it because there is <hi>Haeresie</hi> or <hi>Superstition</hi> mixt with our once <hi>Common Forme of prayer?</hi> If there had been, you see that <hi>scandall</hi> is removed. Or doe we persecute, or force, or drive them from our <hi>Congregations</hi>? We are so farre from that, that you see, they are ready to require that our <hi>publick Congregations,</hi> should <hi>stoope,</hi> and <hi>bow the Knee</hi> to their <hi>private Meetings.</hi> What other <hi>secret</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son tis which thus <hi>divides</hi> them from us, I can by no meanes think, unlesse it be wrapt up in the <hi>Mystery</hi> and <hi>cloud</hi> of the 18. chap. of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> which is their other strong <hi>Herculean</hi> place of <hi>Scripture,</hi> which hath been urged to me to make good their <hi>Separation.</hi> From which dark place of <hi>Scripture</hi> when I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved the <hi>veyle</hi> and <hi>Curtaine,</hi> I will put a period, and conclusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to this Sermon.</p>
               <p>Tis there said, that S. <hi>Iohn</hi> heard an <hi>Angel</hi> proclaime aloud, and say, <hi>Babylon the Great is fallen, is fallen; and is becometh Habitation of Divels, the Hold of every uncleane Spirit, and a Cage of every uncleane, and hatefull Bird</hi>; As you may read at the 2. <hi>verse</hi> of that <hi>chapter.</hi> Tis farther said, That he heard another voice from heaven, saying, <hi>Come out of her my people, that yee be not partakers of her sinnes, and that ye receive not of her plagues.</hi> As you may read at the 4. <hi>verse</hi> of that <hi>chapter,</hi> where by <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon fallen,</hi> they understand the <hi>Church of England fal<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</hi> By the <hi>Habitation of Divels,</hi> the <hi>Hold of foule Spirits,</hi> and <hi>Cage of uncleane Birds.</hi> They understand our <hi>Parish Churches,</hi> and <hi>Congregations</hi> which meet there; which, they say, are so much a <hi>Cage of uncleane Birds,</hi> places so <hi>corrupt,</hi> so full of <hi>wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednesse,</hi> and <hi>sinne,</hi> that <hi>God,</hi> by his <hi>Spirit,</hi> as it were, by a <hi>voice</hi> from the <hi>Clouds,</hi> hath said unto them, <hi>Come out of</hi> them, <hi>my people,</hi> divide your selves from them, <hi>lest ye be partakers of this sinnes,</hi> and go sharers in their <hi>plagues.</hi> This is, or must be that <hi>Interpretation</hi> of that <hi>place</hi>; or else 'twill no way serve to uphold
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59326:12"/>
their <hi>Separation.</hi> If, I say, by the <hi>Habitation of Divells,</hi> and <hi>Cage of uncleane Birds</hi> be not meant our Church <hi>Assemblyes,</hi> from which they doe <hi>divide,</hi> they doe but build a <hi>House of straw,</hi> and choose the <hi>sand</hi> for a <hi>Foundation.</hi> I am sure I have been told that this was the very <hi>Interpretation</hi> which the <hi>Gentleman</hi> gave of <hi>this place</hi>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who just now <hi>disputed</hi> with me, at a <hi>dispute</hi> which not long since he had with Mr. <hi>Gibson</hi> of <hi>Chinner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now will you heare my <hi>censure</hi> of this wilde <hi>Interpretation</hi>? Take it then, thus. Among the severall <hi>Expounders</hi> of the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> I once met with <hi>one,</hi> who when he came to interpret the <hi>Seven Angels,</hi> which blew the <hi>Seven Trumpets.</hi> He said that by one of those <hi>Angels</hi> was meant <hi>Luther,</hi> by another <hi>Queen Elizabeth.</hi> And when he came to give the meaning of the <hi>Locusts</hi> which ascended from the <hi>Bottomelesse pit,</hi> with <hi>Crowns</hi> on their <hi>Heads,</hi> by the <hi>Locusts,</hi> He understood <hi>Schollers</hi> of the <hi>Vniversi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi>; And by the <hi>Crownes</hi> on their <hi>Heads,</hi> He understood <hi>Square Caps.</hi> Methinkes, these <hi>kinde</hi> of <hi>people</hi> deale just so with this place of the <hi>Revelation.</hi> They see <hi>strange visions</hi> in it which S. <hi>Iohn</hi> never saw; Namely, th<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y see <hi>Babylon</hi> in our <hi>Churches,</hi> and <hi>uncleane Birds</hi> in our <hi>Assemblyes.</hi> Nay, though the <hi>Divels</hi> being <hi>Spirits</hi> are too <hi>invisible</hi> to be seen, yet, by the benefit of a <hi>New-light,</hi> they can see <hi>sights</hi> which no other <hi>Eyes</hi> can see without being present in the place to which <hi>soul Spirits</hi> do resort, (as if they had borrowed one of <hi>Galilaeo</hi>'s Glasses) they can see <hi>Divels</hi> take <hi>Notes</hi> at our <hi>Sermons.</hi> But whether in <hi>short-Hand,</hi> or at <hi>length,</hi> S. <hi>Iohn</hi> hath not revealed.</p>
               <p>Pardon me, I beseech <hi>you, you</hi> who are of the more <hi>grave</hi> and <hi>nobler</hi> sort, that I am thus <hi>pleasant</hi> in the pulpit; I am compelled to be so when I meet with <hi>people</hi> who deale with the <hi>Scripture,</hi> as men of <hi>melancholly Fancyes</hi> use to deale with the <hi>Clouds.</hi> For as I have knowne some <hi>Hypocondriack</hi> men, who have faigned to themselves <hi>flying Horses, winged Troops,</hi> and <hi>Ships sayling</hi> in the <hi>Aire</hi>; Nay, as I have knowne some, who, like the <hi>Melancholly man,</hi> who thought himselfe a <hi>urinall,</hi> have thought they have seene two <hi>Armyes</hi> in the <hi>Skie</hi>; and have mistaken <hi>Clouds,</hi> and <hi>Meteors</hi> for <hi>Soldiers, Trumpets, Drums,</hi> and <hi>Cannons</hi>; So I do not wonder that our <hi>Gifted, thinking people</hi> should so mistake the <hi>Revelation</hi> as they doe; or that they should see <hi>Monsters</hi> in the Scripture <hi>Clouds.</hi> Where the <hi>Scripture</hi> is most <hi>cleare,</hi> they hardly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59326:13"/>
understand it; How then should they finde out the <hi>Key</hi> to such <hi>da<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke prophecies</hi> as <hi>this</hi>?</p>
               <p>But here may some man say to me, if they <hi>mistake</hi> this place, whats your <hi>Interpretation of it</hi>? Why, my <hi>Interpretation</hi> is the very same which S. <hi>Iohn</hi> Himselfe delivers, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.8. Where the <hi>Angel</hi> expresseth himself in the very same words. And sayes, <hi>Babylon is fallen, is fallen; That great City which made all Nations drinke of the Wine of the Wrath of her Abominations.</hi> And what was that <hi>Great City?</hi> Why the <hi>City</hi> built on <hi>seven Hills</hi>; As 'tis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed in <hi>another</hi> place of the <hi>Revelation.</hi> That <hi>Great City</hi> which was the <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>Nations</hi>; Namely, the <hi>City</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> when 'twas the <hi>seat</hi> of <hi>Heathen Emperours.</hi> Lastly, that <hi>Great City,</hi> which gave Laws to all the <hi>World,</hi> to <hi>worship</hi> her <hi>False Gods,</hi> and to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of her <hi>Idolatryes.</hi> And this was that <hi>Great City,</hi> which S. <hi>Iohn</hi> calls <hi>Babylon</hi>; either, because speaking of the <hi>Fall</hi> and <hi>Ruine</hi> of it, He thought it not safe to call it <hi>Rome,</hi> or by its right and proper <hi>Name</hi>; Lest, if he had done so, he might draw <hi>persecution</hi> on the <hi>Christians.</hi> Or els, Because as <hi>Babylon</hi> was the <hi>Head City</hi> of the <hi>Persian Monarchy,</hi> so <hi>Rome</hi> was then the <hi>Head City</hi> of the <hi>Roman.</hi> In a word, this is that <hi>Great City,</hi> which was then the great <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Idolatry</hi>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>Superstitions</hi>; And therefore, justly called by the <hi>Angel</hi> which spoke to S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> The <hi>Habitation of Divels,</hi> and <hi>Cage</hi> of <hi>uncleane Birds.</hi> And from this <hi>Babylon,</hi> this <hi>Rome,</hi> the then <hi>City</hi> of <hi>confusion,</hi> the <hi>Angel</hi> of <hi>God</hi> bid the <hi>Christians</hi> of <hi>those Times</hi> to <hi>come forth,</hi> and <hi>separate themselves</hi>; lest they should be <hi>partakers</hi> of her <hi>sins,</hi> and go sharers in her <hi>plagues.</hi> But to say as they do, that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> is that <hi>Babylon the great</hi>; or that our <hi>Parish Congregations</hi> from which they do divide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, are the <hi>Habitation</hi> of <hi>Divels,</hi> the <hi>Hold</hi> of <hi>foule spirits,</hi> and <hi>Cage</hi> of <hi>unclean Birds</hi> here mentioned in this <hi>chap.</hi> is such a piece of <hi>Ignorance,</hi> as well as <hi>zealous slander,</hi> that they will never be able to prove it, till they can make the <hi>Capitol</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> stand in our <hi>London streets,</hi> or till they can make the <hi>River Tiber</hi> run, where now our <hi>Thames</hi> doth; or till they can change the <hi>Countries</hi> in our <hi>Mapps,</hi> and make the <hi>Mid-land Sea</hi> flow on our <hi>English shore.</hi> And farther then this I will not trespasse on your <hi>patience</hi>; or inlarge my selfe to prove to you that <hi>Separation</hi> is a <hi>Sin.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:59326:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
