<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A narrative of the principal actions occurring in the wars betwixt Sueden and Denmark before and after the Roschild Treaty with the counsels and measures by which those actions were directed : together with a view of the Suedish and other affairs, as they stood in Germany in the year 1675, with relation to England : occasionally communicated by the author to the Right Honourable George, late Earl of Bristol, and since his decease found among his papers.</title>
            <author>Meadows, Philip, Sir, 1626-1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 91 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-01">2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50498</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1566</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36497</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15704159</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15704159</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104474</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A50498)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104474)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1152:67)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A narrative of the principal actions occurring in the wars betwixt Sueden and Denmark before and after the Roschild Treaty with the counsels and measures by which those actions were directed : together with a view of the Suedish and other affairs, as they stood in Germany in the year 1675, with relation to England : occasionally communicated by the author to the Right Honourable George, late Earl of Bristol, and since his decease found among his papers.</title>
                  <author>Meadows, Philip, Sir, 1626-1718.</author>
                  <author>Bristol, George Digby, Earl of, 1612-1677.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 176 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. C. for H. Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London,</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.LXXVII [1677]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Philip Meadowe.</note>
                  <note>"A view of the Suedish and other affairs, as they now stand in Germany this present year, 1675. with relation to England" has special t.p.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 176.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with print show-through and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dano-Swedish War, 1643-1645.</term>
               <term>Denmark --  History --  1660-1814.</term>
               <term>Sweden --  History --  Charles X Gustavus, 1654-1660.</term>
               <term>Sweden --  History --  Charles XI, 1660-1697.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Sweden.</term>
               <term>Sweden --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2000-00</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2001-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-07</date>
            <label>Kirk Davis</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-07</date>
            <label>Kirk Davis</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-08</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104474:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104474:1"/>
            <p>A NARRATIVE OF THE PRINCIPAL ACTIONS Occurring in the WARS BETWIXT <hi>Sueden</hi> and <hi>Denmark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before and after the <hi>ROSCHILD</hi> TREATY: WITH The Counsels and Measures by which those Actions were directed: <hi>Together With</hi> A View of the <hi>Suedish</hi> and other Affairs, as they stood in <hi>Germany</hi> in the year 1675. with Relation to <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Occasionally communicated by the Author to the Right Honourable <hi>George</hi> late Earl of <hi>Bristol,</hi> and since his decease found among his Papers.</p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed by <hi>A.C.</hi> for <hi>H. Brome,</hi> at the Gun in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. M. D.C. LXXVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:104474:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104474:2"/>
            <head>FOR The Right Honourable THE EARL of <hi>BRISTOL.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Esteem it as a singular fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and honour that your Lordship thinks me capable of giving you any information concerning the Northern Affairs; the Scene of your Lordships many eminent Employments and Actions having been laid nearer the warm Sun. The Draught I have here sent was made several years since, and only communicated in private with
<pb facs="tcp:104474:3"/>
some friends: In the composing whereof I was not a little advantaged by being a spectator of the Actions, and privy to some of the Counsels of both Kings. But how far I have answered those advantages in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing Narrative I submit to your Lordship's Censure, and remain</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute> 
               <signed>Your LORDSHIP'S Most humble and Obedient Servant, Philip Meadowe.</signed>
               <dateline>Parham in Suff. <date>Sep. 24. 1675.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="unk">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104474:3"/>
                  <head>A NARRATIVE OF THE PRINCIPAL ACTIONS Occurring in the WARS BETWIXT <hi>SUEDEN</hi> and <hi>DENMARK.</hi> Before and after the <hi>ROSCHILD</hi> TREATY. With the Counsels and measures by which those Actions were directed.</head>
                  <p>THE ancient Emulation and jealousies betwixt the two Crowns of <hi>Sueden</hi> and <hi>Denmark,</hi> occasioned by their near Neighbourhood and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Wars, have been still heightned and promoted by the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104474:4"/>
late Conquests the Crown of <hi>Sueden</hi> has made in <hi>Germany.</hi> By which the <hi>Suede</hi> enlarging his Dominion beyond the <hi>Baltic</hi> to those goodly possessions of <hi>Pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren</hi> and <hi>Bremen,</hi> has betwixt his ancient Patrimony on one side, and his new acquisitions on the other, as it were enclosed and beleaguered <hi>Denmark.</hi> The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal effects of a <hi>Suedish</hi> Power established on this side the <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic,</hi> the <hi>Dane</hi> experimented in the year 1643. in the Reign of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiern</hi> the fourth, when upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of some differences arising betwixt the two Crowns in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the commerce and navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of each others subjects, and the new impositions exacted by the <hi>Dane</hi> in the <hi>Sound,</hi> Queen
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104474:4"/>
                     <hi>Christina</hi> without any previous denunciation of War sent secret Orders to General <hi>Torstenson,</hi> who at that time commanded the <hi>Suedish</hi> Army in <hi>Germany,</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade therewith the <hi>Danish</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, which that wise Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral performed with such secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and diligence, that the first in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence of his attempt was brought to <hi>Copenhagen</hi> by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary post, advertising how the <hi>Suede</hi> was entred <hi>Holstein</hi> with an Hostile Army. In that war the <hi>Dane</hi> lost <hi>Halland, Jempterland, Gothland</hi> and the <hi>Oesel.</hi> For though <hi>Halland</hi> by the Treaty at <hi>Brooms<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borow</hi> was not formally aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Crown of <hi>Denmark,</hi> as it was in the succeeding <hi>Ros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child</hi> Treaty, but only mortga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104474:5"/>
or leased to <hi>Sueden</hi> for thirty years; lest the reputation of <hi>Denmark</hi> should seem too much prostituted by the utter abscission and dismembring of so consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable a Province from that Crown; yet was it such a mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage as in truth did amount to an absolute cession or alienati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; For the term of years when expired was made renewable from thirty to thirty, till the <hi>Suede</hi> should receive an equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent for <hi>Halland</hi> to his own liking and satisfaction.</p>
                  <p>A Peace being thus reesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished in the year 1644. by the Treaty made at <hi>Broomsborow</hi> upon the Frontier of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, things continued quiet betwixt the two Crowns for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104474:5"/>
some years, till the late <hi>Charles Gustavus</hi> King of <hi>Sueden</hi> in the year 1655. imbarquing himself in a war against <hi>Poland,</hi> trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported thither the choicest of the <hi>Suedish</hi> souldiery to serve in that expedition; where that martial King carried all before him, but grasped at more than he could well enclose, and conquered more than he could reasonably hope to keep, till at length old <hi>Zarnetsky</hi> makes head against him with a powerful body of horse, and by his example the newly submitted Provinces re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt as quickly from their new Lord, insomuch that the <hi>Suede</hi> was embarass'd on all sides, and his affairs in great decadency.</p>
                  <p>This conjuncture gratified the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104474:6"/>
                     <hi>Dane,</hi> who thought his turn was now come to retaliate upon the <hi>Suede,</hi> and hoped by the favour of this opportunity to regain what he had lost in the former surprises. And to give the better colour of justice to his Arms, lest it should be thought he was rather invited thereto by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the occasion, then constrained by the cause of any new provocations or injuries, open war is solemnly proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed against <hi>Sueden</hi> by the antiqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted formalities of a Herald. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides public letters and manifests are sent abroad to satisfy forein Princes and States, and to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the Right of his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking.</p>
                  <p>The truth is, the Party was not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104474:6"/>
ill concerted, for the <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burger</hi> was already drawn off from the <hi>Suedish</hi> Alliance, and upon good assurance given him from the <hi>Polish</hi> Court, that the Soverainty of the Ducal <hi>Prussia</hi> should be conferred upon him (which he accordingly now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joys) He confederated himself with the <hi>Pole</hi> and <hi>Dane</hi> against <hi>Sueden.</hi> The <hi>Hollander</hi> also was of the party, though as yet but covertly, and great sums of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney were advanced by <hi>Amster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> and the trading Companies (for they would not have it seem the Act of the States but of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate persons) by way of loan to the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> upon secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities of the Customs in the <hi>Sound</hi> and <hi>Norway.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:104474:7"/>
                  <p>The <hi>Dane</hi> raised a considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Army of about fifteen or six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen thousand men well appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, rendesvous'd them in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stein,</hi> from thence passed the <hi>Elb,</hi> besieged and took <hi>Bremerford</hi> a Town belonging to the <hi>Suede</hi> in the Bishoprick of <hi>Bremen.</hi> But here some military men took the freedom to blame the <hi>Danish</hi> Conduct. For had he carried the war on the other side of the <hi>Baltic,</hi> entred <hi>Sueden</hi> it self, at that time disfurnished of her principal Officers and Souldiers, her King being absent in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more Countrey, reported to be dead, the very terrour of an invading Army might have wrought such consternation in the minds of the people, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104474:7"/>
to have given the <hi>Dane</hi> an opportunity of advancing the war as high as <hi>Stockholm.</hi> But he on the contrary attacks the <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dish</hi> Dominions in <hi>Germany,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by alarming friends as well as enemies: For the Princes of the nether <hi>Saxon</hi> Circle entring into a combination declare this inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the Bishoprick to be a breach of the Peace of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and a violation of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strumentum Pacis</hi> concluded at <hi>Munster,</hi> for the observation whereof they stood reciprocally Engaged.</p>
                  <p>Thus, not waging war in good earnest, the <hi>Dane</hi> by middle Counsels lost his opportunity, for whilst his Army stood at a gaze not well knowing which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104474:8"/>
way to take, the King of <hi>Sueden</hi> marches with all imaginable speed from <hi>Poland,</hi> and laying all in ashes behind him to secure his rear from the infal of the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> horse, and leaving strong Garrisons in <hi>Thorren, Marienburg, Elbing</hi> and some other Towns in <hi>Prussia,</hi> passes through <hi>Pomeren</hi> and marches directly for <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stein</hi> and <hi>Jutland.</hi> It was generally conceived that now, if ever, the <hi>Dane</hi> would have fought him harassed and tired as he was with a tedious march. But the new Levies durst not adventure the shock with veteran Troups, used to fight and used to conquer. The <hi>Danish</hi> Army plies and yields ground before the <hi>Suede</hi> without fighting, who pursues
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104474:8"/>
his point and increases in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers as he does in fame, all things favouring the victorious. The <hi>Danes</hi> diminishing as fast gave back till they came to <hi>Fredericsode</hi> in <hi>Jutland,</hi> where they sheltred the remainder of their Infantry, having left Garrisons behind them in <hi>Gluckstad, Cremp</hi> and <hi>Rensburg.</hi> The Horse were transported into <hi>Funen</hi> an Island opposite to <hi>Fredericsode,</hi> so that the <hi>Suede</hi> was left absolute Master of the Campagne, and possessed of the convenient quarters of <hi>Holstein</hi> and <hi>Jutland.</hi> Some of the Inhabitants conveyed the richest part of their goods to <hi>Wensussel</hi> an Island on the North of <hi>Jutland,</hi> and to <hi>Samsoe,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther near adjoyning Isle, both
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104474:9"/>
which became soon after prize to the Victors.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fredericfode</hi> was now besieged by General <hi>Wrangel,</hi> a new Town endowed with a large Charter of Privileges to invite dwellers and Trade, fortified according to the modern way with Bastions, false bray, and ditch, but the. works not fully finished. The Circumvallati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons describe a bow or semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circle, and the little <hi>Belt</hi> running by it, the chord.</p>
                  <p>To the <hi>Belt</hi>-side it was not fortified at all, no more than by the water and channel, only the two bastions upon the two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities of the semicircle were set as far into the bed of the River as conveniently they could
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104474:9"/>
be, and then from the corner of each bastion a strong palisade was run into the River as far as deep water. <hi>Wrangel</hi> so far pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited of the security of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, or the treachery of some correspondents, that he found means in a dark night to cut asunder those Palisades, and making two false attacks in two other places to amuse and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stract them within, and rush<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on at the same time with a prepared body of Horse and Foot up to the saddle-skirts in water, wheel'd about the Bastion and entred the Fort. Had there been but an ordinary work along the bank of the River from one Bastion to another, or a body of men drawn up in Battalia to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104474:10"/>
the Enemy upon the file, he must of necessity have taken the water again; But there was neither of these. The Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour was a Grave Senatour of the Kingdom, but no experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced souldier, only justified his fidelity to the King his Master by dying upon the place, and was accompanied by about four thousand more, who were either slain or taken prisoners. Some time after, a Lieutenant and a Corporal who had served in <hi>Fredricsode,</hi> and were afterwards surprised by the <hi>Dane</hi> in the <hi>Suedish</hi> Quarters, were publickly executed at <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> as those who had traiterously betrayed the place. But whether their Crime was really such, or that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104474:10"/>
they otherwaies criminal were made use of as a sacrifice to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pease the angry Citizens en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged at the loss of <hi>Fredericsode,</hi> is uncertain.</p>
                  <p>Thus we have posted the <hi>Suede</hi> in that important Fortress, which bearing the name of the then King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and thus unhappily taken, might seem as it were to presage by an inauspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious omen the succeeding mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes which involved that King: We will leave him there a while Master of the Continent, and the <hi>Dane</hi> retreated to his Islands: And having thus far drawn down the general scheme of the military affairs, let us step back a little to take a short sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104474:11"/>
of the civil transactions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary with the former.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>England</hi> had too great an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest in the <hi>Baltic,</hi> (the <hi>Mediter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranean</hi> of the North) to sit still without making reflection upon those commotions in the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Kingdoms. For besides the general concerns of a free Trade, which of necessity must have suffered interruption by the continuance of this War, <hi>England</hi> being at that time Engaged in a War with one branch of the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strian</hi> family, <hi>viz.</hi> with <hi>Spain,</hi> would rather the <hi>Suedish</hi> Arms had been at liberty to give check to the other branch in <hi>Germany</hi> as occasion might offer, then to be diverted therefrom by a war with <hi>Denmark.</hi> Two Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104474:11"/>
are sent over to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour a reconciliation betwixt both Kings, Mr. <hi>Meadowe</hi> who was dispatched to the <hi>Danish</hi> Court, arrived there in <hi>September,</hi> 1657. much about the time the <hi>Suede</hi> entred <hi>Jutland.</hi> His busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness was to remonstrate how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome it was to them in <hi>England</hi> to understand of a Rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture betwixt the two Crowns, albeit they esteemed the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication there of by the Letters and Manifest of that King as an expression of friendship. That besides the effusion of Christian bloud betwixt two Nations linked together by the common bonds of Nature and Religion, and both of them leagued in Amity with <hi>England,</hi> the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104474:12"/>
of that War might in so perilous a juncture considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly endanger the whole Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Cause and Interest; and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could have happened more advantagious to <hi>Spain,</hi> with whom <hi>England</hi> was in open Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stility. Besides his Majesty o<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Denmark</hi> could not but be sensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble how much the freedom o<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Navigation and Commerce in the <hi>Baltic</hi> would be impeached thereby, to the prejudice of the Neighbouring Nations, but o<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> none more than <hi>England,</hi> as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually fetching Naval Store from those Countries. He was therefore sent on the part of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to that King to offer the best and most friendly offices for accommoding all differences be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104474:12"/>
twixt the two Crowns, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a stop to so unhappy a War, and to assure him that they would imploy their utmost In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest with the King of <hi>Sueden</hi> to dispose him thereto, and to that purpose had already sent a Gentleman to Him. And that if this their tendred Mediation were accepted, they would in the management thereof deal im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially, and endeavour that the Peace once reestablished might for the future be inviolably observed.</p>
                  <p>To this Proposal the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> returned Answer in writing under his Seal and Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nature, bearing date <hi>September</hi> the twenty fifth, 1657. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring that the care of <hi>England</hi>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:104474:13"/>
for the tranquillity of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, the freedom of public commerce, and quieting all differences, was gratefully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted by him. And that he was ready to enter upon a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a sure and Honourable Peace under the mediation of <hi>England.</hi> And so soon as the King of <hi>Sueden</hi> should testifie a suitable concurrence on his part, he would further declare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self as to time, place and other the Preliminaries to an ensuing Treaty.</p>
                  <p>This Declaration was trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the King of <hi>Sueden</hi> with all possible diligence, and drew from him a Reply dated at <hi>Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar, October</hi> the nineteenth, 1657 In which after many Expostula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104474:13"/>
how injuriously he had been dealt with by the <hi>Dane,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termixed with some language which the <hi>Dane</hi> resented as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachful, he declares likewise his consent to enter upon a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty under the mediation of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England.</hi> And that the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liminaries as to place of Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, number of Commissioners, safe Conducts, &amp;c. should be adjusted according to the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action betwixt the two Crowns in the year 1644. Provided that safe conducts in due form be without delay delivered to the Mediators, and a reasonable time prefixed by the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> for meeting of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners.</p>
                  <p>This Reply of the <hi>Suede</hi> being
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104474:14"/>
communicated to the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> produced from him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Declaration of the third of <hi>November,</hi> 1657. That he also consents to the Transactions in forty four, only as to the place of the future Treaty he conceives <hi>Lubec</hi> or some other Town in that Neighbourhood to be most commodious. That the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty commence under the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>England,</hi> and of the States General of the <hi>United Provinces.</hi> And so soon as <hi>France</hi> should Offer him their mediation, he would accept thereof. And that the designed Peace be not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained to the two Crowns of <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Sueden,</hi> but the King of <hi>Poland</hi> and Elector of <hi>Brandenburg</hi> be comprehended in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:104474:14"/>
the same. These things being first accorded by His Majesty of <hi>Sueden,</hi> that he was ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver his safe conducts into the hands of the Mediators.</p>
                  <p>It was easie to foresee how this comprehension of the <hi>Pole</hi> insisted on by the <hi>Dane</hi> would trouble the whole scene of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, which consideration put the <hi>English</hi> Mediator upon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting against it as a new pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posal forrain to the present questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. How that the mediation of <hi>England</hi> was offered only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the two Crowns, and so accepted by his Majesty of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> without any mention of <hi>Poland.</hi> How that this would render the so much desired Peace tedious and difficult, if not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:104474:15"/>
for that the differences betwixt <hi>Sueden</hi> and <hi>Denmark</hi> were a sudden distemper easily cured if taken in time, but those betwixt <hi>Sueden</hi> and <hi>Poland</hi> were in the nature of an inveterate malady, harder by much to be eradicated. That the Great Seal of <hi>Poland</hi> by which the Ministers of that Crown must be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missionated as Plenipotentiaries for a Treaty, was engraven with the Arms of <hi>Sueden,</hi> which that King would never admit of.</p>
                  <p>However this second Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> of the third of <hi>November</hi> was sent to the King of <hi>Sueden,</hi> and begat another from him of the seventh of <hi>December</hi> dated at <hi>Wismar,</hi> wherein he declares himself not
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104474:15"/>
satisfied with the nomination of <hi>Lubec</hi> for the place of Treaty, as being a recession from the Cust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oms anciently practised betwixt the two Kingdoms, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulation agreed on in the year 1644. that when occasional differences arose betwixt the two Crowns, the Commissioners of both sides should meet upon the Frontiers for adjusting thereof with the more speed. Moreover He takes notice of the conquisite delays and difficulties made by the <hi>Dane</hi> in intermixing other controversies with his own, and which have no reference to the <hi>Danish</hi> War. Yet notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he was willing to grant safe conducts to such Confederates of the <hi>Dane,</hi> as should testifie a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104474:16"/>
desire of being present at a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in any place of the confines. And as for the States General, after their ratification of the Treaty made by their own Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadors at <hi>Elbing,</hi> whereby the friendship betwixt <hi>Sueden</hi> and them is renewed; He would so declare himself on their behalf, in case they offer him their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation for composing this War, as should sufficiently prevent any just occasion of complaint.</p>
                  <p>To this the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> rejoyn'd another Answer of the twenty seventh of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1657. insisting upon the immediate admission of the States General to the mediation, without sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending it upon the previous Act of first ratifying the <hi>Elbing</hi>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:104474:16"/>
Treaty, a point which had been depending twelve months, and was like to be longer. Adheres to the place formerly nominated by him for assembling the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners. And that the <hi>Pole</hi> and <hi>Brandenburger</hi> should not only have a bare license of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing present at the Treaty, but that the respective Treaties to be had with them as Confederates and Principals with the <hi>Dane</hi> in the same War, should proceed by the same gradations and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures as that with <hi>Denmark.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The truth is, in the reasoning and debate concerning the place of meeting there was a secret drift on both sides, unexpressed by either. The <hi>Dane</hi> would have it at <hi>Lubec</hi> or any other neutral
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:104474:17"/>
place in <hi>Germany,</hi> convenient for the <hi>Pole</hi> and <hi>Brandenburger</hi> to be there present as parties with him, whereby to have the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of strengthning each the others hand by a communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Councils, and concert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Affairs to the promoting of a common Interest. On the other hand the <hi>Suede</hi> would have it on the frontiers over the <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic,</hi> whither the <hi>Pole</hi> and <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburger</hi> could not with any reasonable convenience come, designing thereby to disunite the Confederates by the jealousie of a separate Treaty. And perhaps might at the same time have treated openly with the <hi>Dane,</hi> and underhand with the <hi>Pole,</hi> and they two striving to prevent
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:104474:17"/>
each other in the Peace, for fear of being deserted each by other in the War, where he found most advantagious conditions granted him, there conclude Peace and prosecute the War against the other.</p>
                  <p>To prevent this the <hi>English</hi> Mediator endeavoured to draw from the King of <hi>Sueden</hi> a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious intimation on what terms and conditions he would rest satisfied, in case the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> would condescend to a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate Treaty; That so when the Commissioners came to meet they might have nothing more to doe then to digest the several Articles into form to be signed and sealed, and so the business effected before the rumor of a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:104474:18"/>
Treaty divulged; And likewise partly to facilitate the way of an Agreement, and partly to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taste the temper of Affairs, some Conditions were insinuated of the following nature.</p>
                  <p>A general Amnesty of what was past. Restitution of places taken each upon other. A solemn Renewal under good Garranties of the Treaty in <hi>1644.</hi> A redress of Grievances relating to Trade. And a way ascer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained for better prevention of all defraudations in the <hi>Sound,</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended cause of the War on the <hi>Danish</hi> part.</p>
                  <p>And to incline the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> to disjoin his Interests from <hi>Poland,</hi> it was represented by the Mediator, what a broken reed <hi>Poland</hi> had hitherto proved
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:104474:18"/>
to him. Sometimes making proffer to pass their forces over the <hi>Oder,</hi> then presently retreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon pretence of joining the <hi>Austrian</hi> foot, not so much as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring <hi>Pomeren</hi> all this while to give the <hi>Suedish</hi> Army a diversi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who lay securely quartered in <hi>Holstein</hi> and <hi>Jutland.</hi> That the Conditions of the Alliance were mutual and reciprocal, which not being performed on the <hi>Polish</hi> part, His Majesty of <hi>Denmark</hi> was no longer obliged. That Confederacies were for mutual safety, and not intended to oblige Princes to their Ruine, either singly or in company with others. That he had the fresh Example of his Heroic Father of happy memory, who
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:104474:19"/>
though he had entred into an Alliance with the Protestant Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> yet the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of his Affairs to recover what was lost, and secure what was left, constrained him to make a Peace with the Emperor in the year 1629. exclusive of his Allies.</p>
                  <p>But neither did these Reasons prevail with the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> to depart from his Alliance with the <hi>Pole,</hi> till a more cogent necessity extorted afterwards from him a separate Treaty. Nor was the King of <hi>Sueden</hi> willing to anticipate the business of his Commissioners by prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daneous intimations of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. Nor to content him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self as to the terms and conditions
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:104474:19"/>
of the Peace with less then an honourable amends for the wrong done him. But in his jolly way of expression, since the <hi>Dane</hi> had led him so long a dance from <hi>Poland</hi> to <hi>Jutland,</hi> he was resolved, at least to make him pay the fidlers.</p>
                  <p>Thus the War of the Cabinet was managed by missives and memorials, but that of the field was carried on in a smarter man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. The extraordinary violent frost was by this time encreased to such a degree, that the little <hi>Belt</hi> which divides <hi>Jutland</hi> from the Isle of <hi>Funen</hi> was so intensely frozen, as suggested to the <hi>Suedish</hi> King an Enterprize (full of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard but not disagreeable to a fearless mind edg'd with Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion)
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:104474:20"/>
of marching over the ice into <hi>Funen,</hi> with horse, foot and Cannon. Some little skirmish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings there were upon the shoar of the Island, if it may be called a shoar where there was no longer Sea, and the <hi>Dane</hi> had in the most commodious landing places made large cuts in the Ice, which were soon congeled again though with a softer crust. Into one of these a small division of about forty <hi>Suedish</hi> Horse with a Cornet unwarily fell, and were there swallowed up. Major General <hi>Henderson</hi> a <hi>Scotch</hi> man was posted at <hi>Middlefar</hi> with a Body of men, but upon the <hi>Suedes</hi> approach deserted his sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for which he was after in great danger of a Council of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:104474:20"/>
War, had not the <hi>English</hi> Minister seasonably interposed for his rescue. The <hi>Dane</hi> had about three or four thousand foot and two thousand Horse upon the Isle, who were all of them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated and taken: and some of them being <hi>Germans</hi> took party with the <hi>Suede</hi> invited by the hopes of good booty the plunder of a fertil and well peopled Island. The <hi>Suede</hi> marched di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to <hi>Odensea</hi> the capital Town, spacious and well built, which they entred without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance. For as well <hi>Funen</hi> as the other <hi>Danish</hi> Isles are all open and unfortified, and have no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fensible places except <hi>Copenhagen</hi> and <hi>Cronenburg,</hi> both upon the Isle of <hi>Zeland,</hi> having been ever
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:104474:21"/>
esteemed sufficiently fortified by being Islands, and the Kings of <hi>Denmark</hi> having been alwaies Masters of a considerable Naval strength. But now being no longer considered as such, but as contiguous and fastned with the continent, they were exposed an easie prey to an adventurous and forward Enemy.</p>
                  <p>'Tis observable that this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous march over a breadth of the Sea of more than twenty <hi>English</hi> miles, for such is the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance betwixt <hi>Funen</hi> and <hi>Zeland</hi> the way the Army marched, was the resolve of the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self contrary to the sense of <hi>Wrangel</hi> and the principal Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of his Army, and 'tis but just he should have the glory of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:104474:21"/>
the success, who had he mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carried could not have avoided the imputation of temerity.</p>
                  <p>The News of the loss of <hi>Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen</hi> being arrived at <hi>Copenhagen</hi> brought the more terror with it, because besides the loss of so im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant an Isle, it awakened the apprehension that the same Bridge which had let the <hi>Suede</hi> over the little <hi>Belt</hi> into <hi>Funen,</hi> might do the like over the great <hi>Belt</hi> into <hi>Zeland.</hi> Whereupon the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> sends in haste to the <hi>English</hi> mediator, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siring him to renew with all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence the former proposal of a separate Treaty which had been for some time interrupted, and to set it on foot with all possible Expedition. The Mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:104474:22"/>
assured of the reality of the King's Intentions, dispatches forthwith an Express to the King of <hi>Sueden</hi> with a Letter, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents whereof I shall insert, as being that upon which the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing business turned. It ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted him that the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> had already nominated and authorised the Lords <hi>Joachin Gersdorf</hi> Rix Hofmaster, and <hi>Christian Scheel,</hi> both Senatours of the Kingdom, his Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and Plenipotentiaries to meet, treat and conclude with like Commissioners from him at such time and place as he his Majesty of <hi>Sueden</hi> should please to appoint. It requested him on the part and at the Instance of <hi>England,</hi> to depute in like manner
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:104474:22"/>
his Commissioners, to prefix a time and place for meeting, to send safe Conducts for him the Mediator and the <hi>Danish</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners. Adding moreover, that his Majesty of <hi>Sueden</hi> being as it were in possession, or at least in assurance of an Honourable Peace, if he would Please hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward to suspend Hostility, testifying thereby the moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and temper wherewith he Governed his Prosperity and success, he would perform a work worthy the greatness of his Name, gratify the neighbouring Princes and States, and more especially oblige <hi>England</hi> by doing it in favour of a particular request.</p>
                  <p>This Letter bore date from
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:104474:23"/>
                     <hi>Copenhagen February</hi> the third, 1657. To which the King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned Answer by the same mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senger from <hi>Newberg</hi> in <hi>Funen, February</hi> the fifth, so quick was the dispatch at a distance of four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>score miles <hi>English.</hi> The King's Answer was as followeth; To thank him the Mediator for his diligence in promoting the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of a Peace, which the <hi>Dane</hi> had hitherto so obstinately op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed: That he was willing to enter immediately upon a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with <hi>Denmark</hi> under the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spective mediations of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England.</hi> And since it was left to him to appoint the place and time, he gave the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> the choice either of the Isle of <hi>Sproo</hi> or of <hi>Rudkoping</hi> in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:104474:23"/>
                     <hi>Langland</hi> for the Commissioners sufficiently Authorised on both sides to meet at, within eight days after the date of this his Letter. That together with this Letter he had sent safe Conducts in due form for him the said <hi>English</hi> Mediator and for the <hi>Danish</hi> Commissioners, to come stay and return at pleasure. That the business required the greater haste because he could promise himself no security in a suspension of Arms.</p>
                  <p>This Answer was a full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession of the desired Treaty, but the King would not be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plimented out of his advantages into a cessation of Arms, well knowing the powerful effects of panic fears from the suddenness
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:104474:24"/>
of a successful Invasion, and that the only way to profit by them is to give no respit for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collecting. The <hi>Suedish</hi> King contiues his march with all pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible diligence: His nearest way to <hi>Zeland</hi> had been over the great <hi>Belt</hi> from <hi>Neuburg</hi> to <hi>Corsure</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout sixteen miles <hi>English,</hi> but he chuses rather the way of <hi>Lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> so to <hi>Laland</hi> &amp; <hi>Falster,</hi> which though the farther was the safer, because the traject from Island to Island was no where so broad as it was in the Channel of the <hi>Belt</hi> betwixt <hi>Neuburg</hi> and <hi>Corsure.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The forementioned dispatch with the safe Conducts from the <unclear>King</unclear> of <hi>Sueden</hi> being arrived at <hi>
                        <unclear>Copenhagen</unclear>,</hi> the <hi>Danish</hi> Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners accompanied with the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:104474:24"/>
                     <hi>English</hi> Mediator, put themselves without delay upon their jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney towards <hi>Rudcoping</hi> in the Isle of <hi>Langland,</hi> the place appointed for the Treaty. They had tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed little more than sixty miles <hi>English,</hi> when not far from <hi>Wardinburg</hi> the first Town from the Sea upon <hi>Zealand,</hi> they met with the avant-curriers and scouts of the <hi>Suedish</hi> Army, by whom they were advertised the King was newly entred upon <hi>Zeland,</hi> and not far behind. This in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible diligence was an asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing surprise to the <hi>Danish</hi> Commissioners, whom in their journey from <hi>Copenhagen</hi> to <hi>Rud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coping</hi> the King met at half way. Passing by the Scouts unmolested under the security of the safe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:104474:25"/>
they soon after met the King himself riding in a slide (after the manner of the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Countries when the Snows are deep) at the head of about two hundred <hi>Finnish</hi> Horse. All alighting to salute the King, and he the same to resalute them, he willed them to pass on to the neighbouring Town, where he would speedily be with them, for that he was going only to view a ground where conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently he might draw up his Army in Battalia.</p>
                  <p>To <hi>Wardinburg</hi> they went and there made the first entry upon the Treaty, and met there the Chevalier <hi>Terlon</hi> Ambassador of <hi>France,</hi> who came out of <hi>Germany</hi> in Company with the <hi>Suedish</hi>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:104474:25"/>
King. The Commissioners for the Treaty on the part of <hi>Sueden</hi> were Count <hi>Ulefeldt,</hi> who though a <hi>Dane,</hi> yet having received great disobligations from his native Countrey after many services, turned malecontent, and had for some time refug'd himself with the <hi>Suede.</hi> He being a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of Excellent endowments and withal of a haughty and vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicative nature, was made use of as a fit Instrument upon this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion against the <hi>Danish</hi> Court. The <hi>English</hi> Mediator at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of the <hi>Dane</hi> had privately moved the <hi>Suedish</hi> King to change him for some more grateful per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, but it would not be granted. The other Commissioner was the Baron <hi>Steno Bielk</hi> a Senator
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:104474:26"/>
of <hi>Sueden.</hi> But Monsieur <hi>Coyet</hi> and Secretary <hi>Ernstein</hi> though neither of them Commissioners, because not being Senators of the Kingdom, their Character was inferior to that of the <hi>Danes,</hi> yet being persons of mature knowledg in affairs of State were made use of as principal Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the negotiating part.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Suedish</hi> King staid no longer at <hi>Wardinburg</hi> then was necessary for drawing over his Army from the Isle of <hi>Falster,</hi> and then ranging them in Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talia with a large extended front, in view of the <hi>Danish</hi> Commissioners and their retinue, to oftentate their numbers and make them greater in appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance than they were in truth, at
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:104474:26"/>
length filed into a march the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect way to <hi>Copenhagen.</hi> There was little comfort in Treating whilst the King was marching, and the Mediators and <hi>Danish</hi> Commissioners whose persons might in so dangerous a <hi>crisis</hi> be needful nearer their own King, not being satisfied to be left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the Army, adjourned the Treaty and breaking up from <hi>Wardinburg</hi> overtook the <hi>Suedish</hi> King at a Town called <hi>Keug</hi> four leagues from <hi>Copenhagen.</hi> The next morning he drew up in Battalia again, and then fell off as before into an orderly march after a division of <hi>Polish</hi> Horse upon the forlorn. His number about seven or eight thousand men well disciplin'd
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:104474:27"/>
and enured to hardships, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of one half were Horse, and a small train of Artillery of eight or ten field-pieces. Some were left behind to guard the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered places besides the garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of <hi>Fredericsode.</hi> That night he took up his head quarters at a village within a league and half of <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> and within sight of it, of which he would sportingly say she was a fair Lady and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served dancing for. And he had reason to say so, for had he won her as he wood her, she had brought him for her dower all <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Norway,</hi> and then without the tedious enumerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all his particular Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities, he might have short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his Imperial Style and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:104474:27"/>
Title into that of <hi>King of the North.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Mediators and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners went to <hi>Torstrup</hi> a near adjoyning village there to draw up the concept or minutes of a Treaty, which when mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually agreed on, all Hostilities were immediately to cease, though it would require longer time to deduce those minutes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a larger form fit for the rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of both Kings. Let us leave them a while at their work and take a short view of the posture and condition of those in <hi>Copenhagen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Portifications of the City were much decayed, partly through long security not having, seen an Enemy for many Ages,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:104474:28"/>
partly through parsimony, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void an expence supposed need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less. Besides great Trading Towns are not willing to be fettered up with walls and basti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and perhaps in this case the <hi>Danish</hi> Nobility were as little willing as the Citizens, fearing the strength of the Town might make the Burgers heady: The Walls being only of earth and not revested or faced with brick or stone, were much crumbled down with the frost, and easie to be climb'd without the help of scaling ladders; and the earth so petrified that spade or mattock could not be made use of for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent repair. The spring waters began to fail, and some being long frozen were corrupted for
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:104474:28"/>
want of air and motion. There was not one piece of Cannon upon the Walls when the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners parted thence, but by this time good store were hastily drawn from the Arsenal and ships in the Harbour, and moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon ship-carriages. There was no provision of food or fewel for a siege, no garrison more than the Burgers, only upon this Alarm a body of five or six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred horse and some few foot were drawn from <hi>Sconen,</hi> and passed over the <hi>Sound</hi> upon the Ice into the City. But the horse would soon have wanted forrage, and being most of them <hi>Germans,</hi> the least disorder might not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probably have seduced them over to others of their Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:104474:29"/>
in the <hi>Suedish</hi> Army, in hopes to have shared in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised harvest of rich plunder. Besides the <hi>Dane</hi> quitting the field in <hi>Sconen,</hi> the <hi>Suedish</hi> Feld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theer <hi>Steinboch</hi> was ready on that side with five or six thousand men to have passed the Ice and joined his Master in <hi>Zeland.</hi> But nothing so much dismaied the <hi>Dane</hi> as the consideration how none of his Confederates was in possible capacity of relieving him in this utmost extremity. The <hi>Pole</hi> and <hi>Brandenburger</hi> were remote as in another world, and seem'd glad that the storm had passed over their heads and fallen in another quarter. The Ice which was a bridge to the <hi>Suede,</hi> was a bar to the <hi>Hollander.</hi> And
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:104474:29"/>
so wonderful was that year, the Seas were not open for above three months after. On the first of <hi>May</hi> following, a ship at an Anchor in the Road before <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penhagen</hi> had her Cable of sixteen Inches circumference cut by a shoal of Ice. Add to this the temper of the people, some mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring (as is usual in such occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) against the conduct of their Governours, others exclaiming they were betrayed, all affrighted and looking on their condition as desperate. As a Testimony whereof let me add this one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, the <hi>English</hi> Mediator re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning upon some occasions from the Camp into the City, found his house well fraught with rich goods, which the best
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:104474:30"/>
of the Inhabitants had conveyed thither as to a sanctuary against the plundering <hi>Suede.</hi> And yet this testimony is due to the person of the <hi>Danish</hi> King, that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported himself with a magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous constancy and firmness a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midst all these misfortunes.</p>
                  <p>'Tis not irrational to suppose that if the King of <hi>Sueden</hi> had been truly informed of the state of the Town, he would not have slipped the most advantagious opportunity he ever had of taking <hi>Copenhagen.</hi> But though he knew all was not well with the <hi>Dane,</hi> yet he did not know the worst, and being already laden with a heap of prosperities crowded beyond expectation upon him, <unclear>esteemed</unclear> it more prudential to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:104474:30"/>
lay hold on those eminent and securer advantages offered him by Treaty, than to depend upon the issues of War subject to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cissitudes. Yea 'tis not irrational to believe that some of the wiser heads in the <hi>Suedish</hi> Court did not heartily desire to see their King Master of <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> lest the commodiousness of the situ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation preferable to that of <hi>Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holm</hi> should invite either him or his Successor to make that the capital seat of the Monarchy, whereby <hi>Sueden</hi> should in process of time have insensibly degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from a Kingdom to a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince.</p>
                  <p>The minutes of the Treaty were in few days concluded at <hi>Torstrup,</hi> upon which a cessation
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:104474:31"/>
of Arms immediately followed: And from thence the Mediators and Commissioners removed to <hi>Roschild,</hi> to digest more at leisure those summary Articles into the body of a Treaty. Ten days were spent upon that Affair, till the whole was fully perfected and finished. And then the respective Instruments were in solemn form signed and sealed by the Mediators and Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners on both sides, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeably delivered each to other. Which from the place where it was finally concluded, though begun at <hi>Wardinburg,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed at <hi>Torstrup,</hi> yet finished here, was denominated the <hi>Ros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child</hi> Treaty.</p>
                  <p>By this Treaty the King of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:104474:31"/>
                     <hi>Denmark</hi> was a great loser if we consider what he quitted, but it may as well be said he was a great saver if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider what he kept. For he who had lost all in the field could not reasonably expect to regain it in the cabinet; And though some of his principal branches were lopt off, which in time might grow again, yet the root was preserved which else had been lost without resource. So that it was but an expression of tenderness to his King and Countrey what the <hi>Danish</hi> Rix Hofmaster (a right worthy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son) whisperd into the ear of the <hi>English</hi> Mediator, <hi>Utinam nescirem literas.</hi> The lands and Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries which by this Treaty were
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:104474:32"/>
alienated and transferred from <hi>Denmark</hi> to the Crown of <hi>Sueden,</hi> were the Provinces of <hi>Sconen</hi> and <hi>Bleking</hi> (as for <hi>Halland</hi> I reckon the <hi>Suede</hi> had that before) like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise the Isle of <hi>Bornholm</hi> and the two Governments of <hi>Bahuys</hi> and <hi>Drontheim</hi> in <hi>Norway.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>English</hi> Mediator had two parts to act in this Scene; one was to moderate the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands as far as he could in favour of the Sufferer, without disob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging the <hi>Suede</hi> by a too noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious partiality. The other was to watch lest any thing be stipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated betwixt the two Kings prejudicial to the Interests of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</hi> It was moved that the whole Kingdom of <hi>Norway</hi> should be rent off from <hi>Denmark</hi>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:104474:32"/>
and united to <hi>Sueden,</hi> with which it lay contiguous: This in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenched upon <hi>England</hi> as giving the <hi>Suede</hi> the sole and entire pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session of the chief materials, as Masts, Deals, Pitch, Tar, Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Iron, &amp;c. needful for the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel and equipage of our ships, too great a Treasure to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trusted in one hand. The Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator in avoidance of this was the first who insinuated the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posal of rendring <hi>Sconen</hi> and <hi>Ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi> to the <hi>Suede,</hi> which would cut off that unnecessary charge both Crowns sustained in gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risoning a Frontier each against other, by enlarging the <hi>Suedish</hi> Dominions to the bank of the <hi>Sound,</hi> the ancient and natural boundary of <hi>Sueden.</hi> This though
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:104474:33"/>
uneasie to the <hi>Dane</hi> because of the vicinity of those Provinces to <hi>Copenhagen</hi> the Metropolis, yet was safe for <hi>England,</hi> because by this means the <hi>Suede</hi> is become Master of one Bank of the <hi>Sound</hi> as the <hi>Dane</hi> is of the other, though the accustomed Duty of passage, (the best flower in the <hi>Danish</hi> Garland) was by this Treaty reserved wholly to the <hi>Dane.</hi> Thus the Power over that nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row entry into the <hi>Baltic</hi> being balanced betwixt two emulous Crowns, will be an effectual preventive of any new exacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or usurpations in the <hi>Sound,</hi> which occasioned a fierce War betwixt them in the year 1643. In which the States General judged themselves so nearly
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:104474:33"/>
concerned (<hi>England</hi> being at that time most unhappily embroild with Intestine Commotions, and not in condition to look after her concerns abroad) that they sent a considerable Fleet of War to the assistance of the <hi>Suede,</hi> by help whereof the <hi>Dane</hi> was bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and forced to a dishonourable Treaty at <hi>Broomsborow,</hi> as was before mentioned. And the Duties payable in the <hi>Sound</hi> were from that time regulated as they now stand at this day.</p>
                  <p>An Article had been framed obliging both Kings to hinder the passage of any forrain Fleet of War into the <hi>Baltic,</hi> which though directly and immediately levelled against <hi>Holland,</hi> yet obliquely and remotely reflected
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:104474:34"/>
upon <hi>England,</hi> with which the <hi>English</hi> Mediator not being satisfied, caused the word <hi>inimica</hi> to be inserted, and then the sense was this, that both Kings to their power should endeavour to impede the passage of any forrain Fleet of War Enemy of both Crowns. By which the edge of the Article was rebated, and the King of <hi>Sueden</hi> displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed thereat, after acquiesced.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Roschild</hi> Treaty thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded bears date, <hi>February</hi> the twenty sixth, 1658. or as we in <hi>England</hi> write 1657. and was ratified by both Kings under their Royal Seals and signatures, together with the seals and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scriptions of the Senators of both Kingdoms, according to the time
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:104474:34"/>
and manner prescribed by the Articles. The next thing which in order followed, was the solemn interview betwixt the two Kings at <hi>Frederiosburg,</hi> a Palace of the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> about four leagues from <hi>Copen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hagen,</hi> the most magnificent of any in the North. Thither both of them went and which is remarqueable, without any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious stipulations concerning Guards or number of Followers usually practised betwixt doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Friends, but with a frank and Northern simplicity, without any seeming distrust each of other: Yet the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> had at least five hundred horse with him, being those who were formerly drawn out of <hi>Schonen</hi>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:104474:35"/>
besides his ordinary Foot-Guards in Livery, and the several Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Officers of his Court; The King of <hi>Sueden</hi> had not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove four hundred and those not so well mounted or armed as the other.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Danish</hi> King set forwards from his House about two <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish</hi> miles or more to meet the <hi>Suede</hi> upon his way from <hi>Pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child.</hi> Both Kings at a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent distance alighted at the same time out of their Coaches and saluted by joyning their right hands, then both entred the <hi>Danish</hi> Coach, the <hi>Suede</hi> going first, then the <hi>Dane,</hi> accompanied by the <hi>English</hi> Mediator and Duke <hi>Ernest Gunther</hi> of <hi>Holstein Sunderburg.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassador
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:104474:35"/>
was not present at this Entertainment: The same Order was afterwards observ'd, only at the Table, the Queen of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> sat at the end, on the Queens right hand the King of <hi>Sueden,</hi> next below him on the same side the King of <hi>Denmark.</hi> On the Queens left hand the Dutchess of <hi>Holstein</hi> and the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator; at some distance the Senators of both Kingdoms and principal Officers of the Army. Let it suffice to say the Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment was magnificent and such as became so unusual a Solemnity, for two Kings but now in War, to go together from the Field to the Table. The So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity continued from <hi>Thursday</hi> to <hi>Saturday,</hi> both Kings for two
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:104474:36"/>
Nights lodging under the same Roof. At parting they exchang'd Horses and other friendly Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents, and those Officers of the <hi>Danish</hi> Court who were appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to attend the Person of the <hi>Suedish</hi> King were Nobly regaled by him. On <hi>Saturday</hi> he took his leave and went to <hi>Elsinore,</hi> the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> accompanying him part of the way, from thence he crossed the <hi>Sound</hi> to take possession of his new Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests in <hi>Sconen,</hi> the two Castles of <hi>Cronenbnrg</hi> and <hi>Elsenburg</hi> (the latter now his own) thundring out their Salutations during his passage. From thence he went to <hi>Gottenburg</hi> where his Queen met him, the first time she had seen him since his first enterprize
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:104474:36"/>
upon <hi>Poland,</hi> and there an as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly of the States of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was celebrated.</p>
                  <p>The Mediators went to <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penhagen</hi> to meet the Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners newly arrived from the Duke of <hi>Holstein Gottorp,</hi> Father in law to the King of <hi>Sueden,</hi> for adjusting the satisfaction due to that Duke, who had been a great sufferer by the War, in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suance of the twenty second Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the <hi>Roschild</hi> Treaty. The <hi>English</hi> Mediator received seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Letters from the Duke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>questing him to expedite that affair, which by the said Article was to be terminated by the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of <hi>May.</hi> Besides the King of <hi>Sueden</hi> though he had already quitted <hi>Zeland,</hi> yet he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solv'd
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:104474:37"/>
not to dislodge his Troops from the rest of the <hi>Danish</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions till his Father-in-law had received an equitable sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction. This Business met with more difficulties than was expected, and grew so high, that the <hi>Danish</hi> Commissioners entred a solemn Protestation in writing into the hands of the Mediators, protesting that the impediment was not on their part, if all things were not accorded betwixt the Royal and Ducal Houses before the Expiration of the time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed, they having already con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>descended to all equitable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. At last this Affair was ended also by Grant of the Baily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick of <hi>Suabsted</hi> and Release of the Vassallage of the Dutchy of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:104474:37"/>
                     <hi>Slesvic</hi> a sief-of the Crown of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> and the concept of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles was signed and sealed by the Mediators and respective Commissioners, and afterwards ratified by the King and Duke.</p>
                  <p>As to the Dutchy of <hi>Slesvic</hi> 'tis to be noted, that the Dukes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ow Fealty to the Crown of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and consequently are liable to the forfeiture of their Fee in case of disloyalty. But the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> is likewise Duke of <hi>Slesvic</hi> and moreover, Hereditary in <hi>Slesvic</hi> and but Elective in <hi>Denmark,</hi> so that by Release of the Vassallage the Crown of <hi>Denmark</hi> was a loser, the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> a gainer. The Royal House of <hi>Denmark</hi>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:104474:38"/>
and the Ducal House of <hi>Gottorp</hi> are extracted from two brothers, whose descendants are equally and in common sovereign Dukes of <hi>Holstein</hi> and <hi>Slesvic.</hi> All Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributions, Imposts and public Revenues are put into a common Coffer to be equally divided be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt both, and all charges and expences of the Government to be ratably allowed out of the public Stock. And yet they have their Bailywicks, Lands and Possessions apart. But the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, Nobility and Towns of both Dutchies remain undivided and do Fealty to both Princes, who govern alternatively and change turns every year. It had been urged on the part of the Duke that there should be an abolition
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:104474:38"/>
of this alternative communion, whereby the Government and public Justice within both Dutchies is one year in the King and another in the Duke. But the States of <hi>Holstein</hi> would not consent to this, and so 'twas laid aside, because those <hi>Holsteiners</hi> who upon the Division of the Government should have fallen under the repartition and share of the Duke, should have been no longer subjects to the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> to the great hindrance and prejudice of those Noblemen who find better preferments in the Court at <hi>Copenhagen</hi> than can be expected from that at <hi>Gottorp.</hi> Besides having two Masters suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessively, when Justice is delaied them by one, they can have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:104474:39"/>
to the other, as the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment comes to his turn, which they of <hi>Holstein</hi> esteem a privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege.</p>
                  <p>Thus I have continued the Series of the principal affairs Military and Civil down to the Pacification of <hi>Roschild,</hi> and should have ended here, but that the War breaking out again and the new-made Peace soon after violated, oblige me, though unwilling, to proceed.</p>
                  <p>Two Ambassadors were sent from <hi>Sueden</hi> to the <hi>Danish</hi> Court, the Baron <hi>Bielk</hi> and Monsieur <hi>Coyet,</hi> partly to Negotiate such things as appertained to the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the <hi>Roschild</hi> Treaty partly to make the Overture of a strict and intimate Alliance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:104474:39"/>
the two Crowns, by a League mutually Defensive. For it greatly imported the <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dish</hi> King, having many Enemies still before him, to double bolt, and by all possible means secure the back-door of <hi>Denmark.</hi> At leastwise not to leave <hi>Denmark</hi> like a smoaking torch, though the flame of War was extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished, ready to take fire again upon every agitation. But things fell out quite otherwise. The <hi>Dane</hi> was more intent how to free his Country from the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>densome company of the <hi>Suede,</hi> than desirous to entertain with him any stricter alliance of Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And the <hi>Suede</hi> found it true that Treaties extorted by neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity upon unequal and dispropor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionate
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:104474:40"/>
conditions are no longer durable than that force continues which first made them.</p>
                  <p>After the <hi>Suedish</hi> Army had quitted <hi>Zeland</hi> and the relenting Ice was no longer repassable, some in the <hi>Danish</hi> Court whose Zeal and Affection to their King and Countrey was otherwise commendable, were too free and open in Censuring the <hi>Ros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child</hi> Treaty, as if their Affaits had not been reduced to such extremity as to constrain them to so dishonourable conditions. Thus when the danger is passed and the confternation over, all will seek to appear valiant and wise, and he who in a wrack thinks himself happy in a plank to save his life, is no sooner
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:104474:40"/>
ashoar, but grows dissatisfied with himself for not securing his goods. <hi>Van Beuning</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> Ambassador at <hi>Copenhagen</hi> was busie with Intrigues amongst the great persons of the <hi>Danish</hi> Court, and suspected by the jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and watchful <hi>Suede.</hi> A great debate fell out betwixt the <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dish</hi> Ambassadors and <hi>Danish</hi> Commissioners concerning the property of the Isle of <hi>Hueen,</hi> which not being expressly trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to <hi>Sueden</hi> in the <hi>Roschild</hi> Treaty, the <hi>Suede</hi> to salve that omission challenged it as an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix and accessary of <hi>Sconen,</hi> but the <hi>Dane</hi> reclaim'd it as an appurtenance of <hi>Zeland.</hi> The truth is, the Isle of it self without any relative consideration was
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:104474:41"/>
of little or no value, but had it remained in <hi>Danish</hi> hands they might have built a Fort upon it to command the entry of <hi>Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scroon,</hi> by which the onely or most considerable Port which the <hi>Suede</hi> had in <hi>Sconen</hi> would have been rendred useless. And therefore they were resolved at any rate to have it, and if by no other right, at least by that new devised one which we in old <hi>English</hi> have no word for, but the <hi>French</hi> call it <hi>Le Droit de bien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seance.</hi> Other Controversies arose of the like nature, which the <hi>Suede</hi> though seemingly offended at, yet profited upon, making them the pretence for continuing their forces in <hi>Funen, Jutland,</hi> and other the <hi>Danish</hi> Dominions,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:104474:41"/>
which by the sixteenth Article of the Treaty they were to have quitted by the first of <hi>May.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1658. Summer was now approaching and yet the King of <hi>Sueden</hi> was still at <hi>Gottenburg,</hi> ordering the affairs of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, setling himself in his new acquired Estates, and attending the Issue of his Ambassadors Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiation at <hi>Copenhagen.</hi> In <hi>June</hi> he parted thence and arrived at <hi>Fredericsode,</hi> stopped some time at <hi>Flensburg,</hi> and from thence went to his Father-in-law at <hi>Got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torp.</hi> Four Ambassadors met him from the Electoral College, for there was at that time a vacancy in the Empire, and the Electors were assembled at <hi>Francfort</hi> upon choice of a new Emperour. The
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:104474:42"/>
business of the Ambassadors was to proffer all friendly offices for composing the War betwixt him and <hi>Poland,</hi> and accommoding all differences betwixt him and the King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> soon after chosen King of the <hi>Romans</hi> and Emperour. As also to desire and forewarn him to abstain from marching with his Army upon the Territories of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. The Ambassadors had an unwelcome reception, the King reproaching them with their Masters non-performance of the Garrantie of the <hi>Munster</hi> Treaty upon the <hi>Danish</hi> Invasion of the Bishoprick of <hi>Bremen.</hi> Two Ministers came to him in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular from the Elector of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburg,</hi> but were not admitted
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:104474:42"/>
to Audience, the King requiring a previous satisfaction from that Elector for deserting his Alliance and confederating himself with his declared Enemy the <hi>Pole.</hi> The <hi>Brandenburg</hi> Ministers were treated the more roughly, the better to disguise a following de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign, and to induce a general belief that the Dominions of their Master were forthwith to be invaded. The <hi>English</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator had been recalled from the Court of <hi>Denmark</hi> as suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing all quiet there, and placed in that of <hi>Sueden,</hi> and was now in <hi>Germany</hi> setting on foot a new mediation betwixt that King, the <hi>Pole</hi> and <hi>Brandenburger.</hi> The Armies of which two last sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted all this while at the charge
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:104474:43"/>
of their own Countries, but that of <hi>Sueden</hi> made good chear at the cost of <hi>Denmark,</hi> whiles the <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dish</hi> Ambassadors and <hi>Danish</hi> Commissioners were debating at <hi>Copenhagen.</hi> The truth is, the <hi>Suede</hi> was glad of a pretext for continuing in his old quarters contrary to the Treaty, being at at a loss what to do with his Army. To disband was not reasonable, because he had the <hi>Pole</hi> with the <hi>Brandenburger</hi> his new Allie, Enemies before him, and not well assured of the <hi>Dane</hi> behind. To have removed his Quarters into <hi>Pomeren</hi> in the Neighbourhood of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> had been to eat up his own Country, and which was more, would certainly have drawn to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:104474:43"/>
a confederacy in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire against him as a disturber of the Peace thereof.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Suede</hi> thinking it now time to begin his Campagne, which the <hi>Dane</hi> had long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, hoping to be rid of his troublesome Guests, Ordered the Rendesvouz of his Army at <hi>Kiel</hi> a Maritim Town in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stein,</hi> with a Fleet of about sixty sail to be ready in the Harbour, most of them vessels of burden, the rest good men of War. From <hi>Kiel</hi> he marched at the head of some selected Troops to <hi>Wismar,</hi> making semblance as if the gross of his Army should follow. But the Cabinet at <hi>Gottenburg</hi> had otherwise determined it, for there I persuade my self the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:104474:44"/>
was first hatched and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished with all imaginable se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy. It was thought not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visable for the <hi>Suede</hi> to stir in <hi>Germany,</hi> not being assisted by any powerful Allie. <hi>France</hi> at that time faced towards a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage and consequently a Peace with <hi>Spain. England</hi> was a Chaos of confusion and disorder. A War with <hi>Poland</hi> was remote and unprofitable, and had already consumed him to no purpose, one nearer home would be of more safety and advantage. The <hi>Dane</hi> would never want a will so long as he wanted not a power to hurt <hi>Sueden;</hi> It was judged easier to conquer him than re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile him.</p>
                  <p>The King staid but a little
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:104474:44"/>
time at <hi>Wismar</hi> with his Queen, and then privately imbarqued himself upon a <hi>Dutch</hi> Boyer in the River, and arrived at <hi>Kiel.</hi> All hands were now busie in putting the Army, Horse and Foot aboard, which done, the King went also aboard a man of War: The <hi>French</hi> Ambassador went with him, the <hi>English</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister though invited refused to go, not being satisfied whether the design was upon <hi>Prussia</hi> or <hi>Denmark,</hi> however would in neither case put himself as party in Company of an Enemy, whose office had been and was still to be a Mediator. The Fleet set sail with a fair wind and not many hours after arrived at <hi>Corsure</hi> upon the Isle of <hi>Zeland,</hi>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:104474:45"/>
this was in <hi>August,</hi> and the Peace had been concluded but in <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary</hi> before. No longer time was spent at <hi>Corsure</hi> then what was necessary for landing the Army, which consisting of near four thousand Horse, besides se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Regiments of Foot to be transported from <hi>Funen</hi> and joyned with those already brought from <hi>Kiel,</hi> would una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably require some time to disembark, which together with a march of about sixty miles <hi>English</hi> from <hi>Corsure</hi> to <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> was all the warning the <hi>Dauc</hi> had to prepare an Entertainment for their unexpected Guest. The King had prepared no Manifest to declare the grounds and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of this enterprise, because he
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:104474:45"/>
doubted not to carry all before him by the suddenness of the sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, and the success had been the best argument for justifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Arms. The <hi>Danish</hi> King sent to know of him the Reasons of this sudden Invasion after a Peace so lately concluded, and so dearly bought, and by what just ways and means he might allay and pacifie any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived displeasure. But all was now too late, the great <hi>Belt</hi> was behind him and <hi>Copenhagen</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him; he was over <hi>Rubicon</hi> and would to <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The two defensible places upon <hi>Zeland</hi> being <hi>Copenhagen</hi> and <hi>Cronenburg,</hi> the <hi>Suedish</hi> Army divided, part under General <hi>Wrangel</hi> besieged <hi>Cronenburg,</hi>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:104474:46"/>
whilst the King with the greater part invested <hi>Copenhagen.</hi> It would neither be profitable nor delightful minutely to recount the particulars of a long siege, but it was soon made evident that the same prosperous directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which had guided the <hi>Suedish</hi> Arms in the former War did not accompany them in this, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the state of the case was much varied, and the justice of the quarrel more questionable, it being clear that in the first War the <hi>Dane</hi> had been the Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressor. <hi>Cronenburg</hi> made but a faint resistance, and cowardly yielded after about three weeks siege, which supplied the <hi>Suede</hi> with a mighty store of ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all sorts, besides several
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:104474:46"/>
brass Guns of an immense weight purposely cast and planted there to command the passage of the <hi>Sound.</hi> At <hi>Copenhagen</hi> it was quite otherwise, there was a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable Garrison of Soldiers in it with good Officers, besides se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Companies of stour and well resolved Burgers. The <hi>Danish</hi> King considering the Town no longer as seated in the Heart of his Dominions, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Frontier by the loss of <hi>Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen</hi> within view of <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> had employed many hands du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Summer in fortifying and repairing the works, regular enough before, but much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed. The waters being all open, the Marishes, Lakes and false grounds about the Town
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:104474:47"/>
had rendred it in great part in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accessible. These in the former War were all frozen, and as if communicating with the rigour of the Season, the bloud and spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the Inhabitants were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gealed also. But now all flowed again, Anger and Indignation against the Perfidie, as they deem'd it, and insatiate Avarice of the <hi>Suede,</hi> inspired the <hi>Dane</hi> with Courage. But nothing held up their spirits more than the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible assurance Monsieur <hi>Beu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> Ambassador gave them, (who upon the first In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence of the <hi>Suedes</hi> landing posted home to advertise his Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors thereof) that the States General would in few weeks send them Relief, Neither could
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:104474:47"/>
they have weathered out so out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious a storm had the Sheat-Anchor of <hi>Holland</hi> failed them.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Suede</hi> finding the Town in too good a condition to be carried by Assault, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained to a formal siege by way of approach. The Fleet had blocked up the Harbour, as the Army had on <hi>Zeland</hi> side be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>girt the Town, but it was still open to the <hi>Ammak;</hi> which I cannot call an omission, because to have planted a Leaguer on that side would have required another Army. For this little Isle though united to <hi>Copenhagen</hi> by a long bridge, is disjoyned from the rest of <hi>Zeland</hi> by broad flats covered with water and a deep Channel in the midst, so
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:104474:48"/>
that a Leaguer on the <hi>Ammak</hi> could have had no communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with that on <hi>Zeland.</hi> In the Winter ensuing when the waters upon the flats were frozen, the the <hi>Suede</hi> by the benefit of the Ice often visited that Quarter, where a Party of <hi>Danes</hi> being abroad and the Prince of <hi>Homberg</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing with a Squadron of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valry to repel them, but pressing too forward upon the <hi>Danish</hi> Rear had his Leg struck off with a Cannon shot. To be short, the <hi>Danes</hi> defended themselves with great Gallantry and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, their King animating them with his presence, and pitching his Tent upon the Rampart bid his fellow-soldiers <hi>Caesar</hi>-like, not Go but Come. The Cannon, of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:104474:48"/>
which they had some hundreds upon the walls, plaid freely upon the besiegers, not without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable execution. But not content with this, they made several brisk sallies into the <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dish</hi> Trenches with such success, that they began at length to despise that Enemy whom so lately they had feared. The <hi>Suede</hi> lost many good Officers and Soldiers, amongst whom Count <hi>Jacob de la Gardie,</hi> Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant of the Infantry was slain by a Granade.</p>
                  <p>During this time the Elector of <hi>Brandenburg</hi> was entred <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stein</hi> and <hi>Jutland</hi> with a gallant Army, of which the Elector was Generalissimo for the Emperour as King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> but the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:104474:49"/>
Troups were Commanded by <hi>Montecuculi,</hi> and a great Body of <hi>Polish</hi> Horse by old <hi>Zarnetsky.</hi> Prince Palatine <hi>Sultsbach</hi> who Commanded in those parts for the <hi>Suede,</hi> being too weak to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before so potent an Enemy retired first into the fastness of <hi>Ditmarsh,</hi> afterwards into <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dericsode:</hi> Which the <hi>Suede</hi> soon after demolished as requiring greater numbers of men than he could well spare, thence trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting himself into <hi>Funen,</hi> lay intrenched in those Islands whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Confederates for want of shipping could not follow him. The Elector summoned and took the Castle at <hi>Gottorp,</hi> the Mansion and Residence of the Duke of <hi>Holstein,</hi> who though
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:104474:49"/>
he Honoured his. Family by matching his excellent and most deserving Daughter to a great King, yet his active Son in Law involv'd the good old Duke in many troubles unwelcome to his age and humor. He himself was retired to <hi>Tonning</hi> a strong Town of his own, and not long after died.</p>
                  <p>One thing I had almost forgot, the more considerable because both Kings were personally en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in the Action. The <hi>Suede</hi> observing that the <hi>Dane</hi> daily fetched provisions from the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forementioned Isle the <hi>Ammak,</hi> which contained four or five villages, and was about so many <hi>English</hi> miles in length, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solv'd to make a descent in order
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:104474:50"/>
to burn the Villages and destroy whatever might afford sustenance or relief to the besieged. For which purpose he put aboard about twelve hundred foot and four hundred horse, and the King himself would needs be of the party, thinking nothing so well done as where he was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, as well as naturally ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious of sharing personally in the Glory of every brave Action, Coming to the height of the <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> he forced his landing upon the point of the Isle, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain'd them upon the Guard to abandon their Post. He marches up the Isle and destroys all before him, and the <hi>Dane</hi> fearing he came to fortifie some Post on that side, set fire to the Village
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:104474:50"/>
next adjacent to the Town, as the <hi>Suede</hi> had done to the rest. Having done his Work, the <hi>Suede</hi> retreats to his boats too securely, some scattered from the Body, others encombred with plunder; mean while the <hi>Danish</hi> King sallies out in person with three hundred horse and two hundred dragoons, besides some few com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded foot mounted behind, falls in upon the <hi>Suedish</hi> Rear, slew several of them and put the rest in disorder. The <hi>Suedish</hi> King mounted upon an unruly Horse bounding and curvetting with him ran great hazard of falling that day into <hi>Danish</hi> hands. But the <hi>Dane</hi> either not knowing all his advantages, or not willing to be drawn too far from his
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:104474:51"/>
Town by an over-eager pressing upon an Enemy who out num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred him, sounded a seasonable Retreat. The same King not long before narrowly escaped another danger, passing in a small boat a head of a Galliot under sail in a strong Current, the Galliot overset the boat, the Steers-man was drowned, but the King saved upon the Galliot.</p>
                  <p>It was now <hi>October,</hi> 1658, when the much expected <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet began to appear, consisting of thirty eight men of War, six Fire-ships, about three score Fluits, Galliots and other Vessels, with betwixt three and four thousand Auxiliary Foot, and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:104474:51"/>
all sorts of Provisions for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of <hi>Copenhagen.</hi> The Fleet was Commanded by General <hi>Opdam,</hi> who came to an Anchor off the <hi>Lapsand</hi> about half a League below <hi>Cronenburg.</hi> The <hi>Suedish</hi> Fleet was forty two sail; some of them stout Ships, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by General <hi>Wrangel</hi> who was High Admiral of <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> and posted in four Squadrons a little above <hi>Cronenburg,</hi> both Fleets within a League each of other. Some were of Opinion that the <hi>Suedish</hi> Fleet ought to Encounter the other in the <hi>Lap</hi> whiles the Winds were contrary from <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> and so the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet unbefriended of a Port, whereas the <hi>Suede</hi> was Master of both Shoars, and had
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:104474:52"/>
several Ports near at hand. This in some respects was the better, and that King inclinable to it: But he deferring to his Council in so weighty a Concern, most of them opined otherwise. That they had too many Enemies al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready to make themselves Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressors in a new War. That this would heighten and exaspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate things betwixt them and the <hi>Dutch</hi> beyond hopes of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation. That <hi>Holland</hi> in case of any disaster could furnish one Fleet after another, but <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> adventured their All. That it would be more justifiable to Forrain Princes and States in Amity with them, if putting themselves upon the defensive, they did only endeavour to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pede
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:104474:52"/>
the passage of those who would relieve a besieged Enemy. Such considerations prevailed, whiles both Fleets lay for some days at an Anchor.</p>
                  <p>At length the Wind coming fair at <hi>North-west</hi> with a fresh Gale, the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet weighed and set sail for the <hi>Sound.</hi> Both the Castles of <hi>Cronenburg</hi> and <hi>Elsinburg</hi> fired at them as they passed the narrow, some of the Cannon carrying fifty and sixty pound ball, but to no other effect than to shew that those Castles are but bugbears to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright Merchant-men, and that nothing less than a Fleet can command the Passage of the <hi>Sound.</hi> Both Fleets were En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged so close together by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:104474:53"/>
of the Streight, but a League over, that most of the shot took place and made great slaughter on both sides, Vice-Admiral <hi>Wit-Wittensen</hi> had the Van of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who coming up with the <hi>Suedish</hi> Admiral cut off his steer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and made him lie by to mend, but the Vice-Admiral himself was slain by a small shot. He had been brave and bold but ill seconded; his Ship called the <hi>Brederode</hi> (the same that old <hi>Tromp</hi> was slain upon in the <hi>English</hi> Wars) was broken in pieces, and running a ground fell on one side like a wrack. She was mounted with fifty six good brass Cannon, some of which a <hi>Scotchman</hi> afterwards weighed up by the Invention of a Diving-Bell.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:104474:53"/>
                     <hi>Opdam</hi> fought well, though some of his Squadron acted re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misly. <hi>Peter Floriz</hi> the Rear-Admiral was slain. The <hi>Suede</hi> lost four Ships, two whereof were carried to <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> lost two, their Fire-ships spent themselves in vain. The destruction of men was greater then of ships, the fight being smart and close for the time it lasted, which was not long, for the <hi>Dutch</hi> never tacked but onely fought their direct way to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy their supply to <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> and this they effected to the great joy of the City.</p>
                  <p>The fight was no sooner ended, but Orders were islued out to the <hi>Suedish</hi> Fleet to put im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately into the Port of <hi>Land</hi>
                     <pb n="102" facs="tcp:104474:54"/>
                     <hi>scroon;</hi> which was providently done, for the next morning the <hi>Dane</hi> having joyned twelve good ships which lay ready in Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, though detained from the fight by contrary winds, with the ablest ships of the <hi>Dutch</hi> sailed towards the <hi>Sound</hi> to rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage the <hi>Suede.</hi> But he was burrow'd in Port all but one ship, which being disabled in the fight could not make so much hast as the rest, and upon the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the Enemy was fired by her own men. Whereupon the <hi>Dane</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> turn their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign against <hi>Landscroon,</hi> the mouth of whose channel was so narrow, that but one ship could enter at a time, and was guarded by four <hi>Suedish</hi> ships placed at
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:104474:54"/>
convenient distances and by an old Block-house. They durst not adventure up the Channel but sailed in a Line athwart it, and so every ship poured in her Broad-side with huge noise but little or no Execution. Under the Covert of the smoke they sunk old Ships of great Tunnage charged with stones and other materials to choak the mouth of the River, but this was frustrated by the depth of water and strength of the Current. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, this course taking no effect, they made Trial with fire-ships and entred the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel therewith, intending to grapple what they could; or at least to turn their fire-ships a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drift towards the <hi>Suedish</hi> Fleet.
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:104474:55"/>
But the vigilance of the <hi>Suede</hi> prevented this, who mann'd all his boats with Mariners and Soldiers, the King himself as his manner was, putting himself upon a boat to encourage and direct his men. So soon as a fire-ship was coming up the boats rowed down by the sides of the Channel with intention to get beyond her and cut off her Long-boat from her Stern. The fire-ship men apprehending the loss of their boat as their life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the danger of being boar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, set fire to their train and made away. Then the <hi>Suedish</hi> Mariners and Soldiers with Iron Hooks and Chains tow'd the fire-ships till they had turned them a-ground, and there let
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:104474:55"/>
them burn at pleasure. Winter coming on the <hi>Dane</hi> returned also to Port.</p>
                  <p>The State of things being thus altered, the <hi>Suede</hi> changed his measures accordingly. For <hi>Copenhagen</hi> being relieved with a considerable renfort of well com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded men, the Port open, the <hi>Dane</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Masters at Sea, Winter already begun, it was judged most advisable to raise the siege and convert it into a blocade. To this purpose a Camp was fortified upon a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient ground about half a League distance from the Town, which though Numerous enough in Foot to have attacked the Camp it self, yet wanted Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valry
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:104474:56"/>
wherewith the <hi>Suede</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded, and there was a fair level and valley betwixt the Camp and City, so that little of Action passed for a good time. Till at length the <hi>Suede</hi> consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that whatever attempt could be made against <hi>Copenhagen</hi> ought to be done that Winter, because the <hi>Hollander</hi> would certainly be upon him in the Spring of the year with another Fleet; that it was evident no good could be done against the Town by the tedious forms of a siege; that long and lingring services in Camps and Trenches usually consumed more men then brisk and sudden Actions; that the rigour of the Winter when the Earth was co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with snow and the waters
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:104474:56"/>
with Ice had been always most propitious to his greatest under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, and might also favour him in a general and vigorous Assault of <hi>Copenhagen;</hi> that the Enterprise was dangerous and so were all great ones, but if atchieved, would both quit the Cost and reward the Service. It was then resolved to Storm the Town, for which purpose great Recruits of Foot were drawn from <hi>Sueden,</hi> and a better body of Infantry mustered upon this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion, than ever the <hi>Suede</hi> had seen before in <hi>Zeland,</hi> and many hands were busied in making all fitting Instruments such as lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of all sorts, spurs to pass the Ice with, boats covered with Hurdles and Galleries, and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:104474:57"/>
sundry other Engines of War.</p>
                  <p>Three Nights together the <hi>Suede</hi> marched from his Camp towards the Town, partly to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muse the Enemy, but principally to handsel and discipline his men to their several tasks and servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that being practised to the handling and carrying of their Engins they might be the less embarassd thereby when they had occasion to use them in good earnest. The first and second Night nothing was done, but as they marched out of the Camp they returned orderly again, the <hi>Dane</hi> either not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving or making <note place="inline">Febr. <hi>165;</hi>
                     </note> shew not to do so. The third Night the <hi>Suede</hi> drew out as before, but with full reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:104474:57"/>
to make the Attack. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Troops of dismounted Cavalry were intermixed with the Foot, and a good Body of Horse to sustain them, and if need were, secure a Retreat. The King commanded in Person, and put himself under the Covert of an old bank, little more than musket-shot from the Town, ready to give Orders as occasion required. The Cannon of the Town was all pointed low to flank and rake the Ditches and Counterscarps, and the <hi>Dane</hi> never fired till the Enemy was under the Works and ready for their Attack. But then plied them so furiously with great and small shot, Cartridges, Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granades, Bombs from Mortar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieces,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:104474:58"/>
besides others rould down from the Walls, that the <hi>Suede</hi> was repulsed with great slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the rest of his men disordered, the Engins broken, and the whole Enterprise confounded; Which the King perceiving com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded a Retreat, and sent at the same to Sir <hi>William Vavasor</hi> to forbear the Attack on the other side, but the Orders coming too late found him dead upon the place, with many of his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. The <hi>Suede</hi> lost in this Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Erick Steinbock</hi> General of the Artillery, with many brave and old experienced Officers, both <hi>Germans</hi> and <hi>Suedes.</hi> According to the King's List taken from the Muster-Roll, there were slain five hundred thirty four, and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:104474:58"/>
eight hundred ninty five Woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the <hi>Dane</hi> reports them more, perhaps the poor innocent Boors whom the <hi>Suede</hi> too cruelly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to help carry down their Engins and Utensils, might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease the number of the slain.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Suedish</hi> Arms were some time after more prosperous in reducing the Isles of <hi>Langland, Laland, Falster</hi> and <hi>Moenen,</hi> to the great enlargement of their Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and Accommodation of their numerous Horse, who in some places began to be straitned for want of Forrage.</p>
                  <p>In the Spring of the year the <hi>English</hi> Fleet arrived in the <hi>Sound</hi> under Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <note place="inline">1659.</note> 
                     <hi>Mountague,</hi> not with any intention as some vainly
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:104474:59"/>
suggested to assist <hi>Sueden</hi> in the Conquest of <hi>Denmark;</hi> That had been impolitic and irrational, for 'tis evident the conservation of <hi>Denmark</hi> is the common In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest as well of <hi>England</hi> as of <hi>Holland,</hi> neither was there at that time the least fear or danger of any such supposed Conquest. The Elector had an Army in <hi>Jutland</hi> of near thirty thousand men, <hi>Brandenburgers, Poles</hi> and <hi>Austrians,</hi> and could have been as many more if either the Countrey could have supported their numbers, or the service re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired them. <hi>De Ruyter</hi> having joyned <hi>Opdam</hi> with another Fleet of forty sail, the <hi>Dutch</hi> besides the <hi>Dane</hi> were near fourscore men of War in those Seas. <hi>De</hi>
                     <pb n="113" facs="tcp:104474:59"/>
                     <hi>Ruyter</hi> had brought upon his Fleet forty Companies more, besides the thirty eight Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies formerly brought by <hi>Opdam.</hi> Had the War been mannaged in good earnest, and not by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates who have different Aims and Interests, and had the Army in <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> for so I may now call it, joyned with that of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> a thing easie to have been effected by such Fleets, and all this mighty force united under one Head, it had been sufficient not only to have beat the <hi>Suede</hi> out of the <hi>Danish</hi> Isles and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, but out of <hi>Sueden</hi> it self. Besides the <hi>Suede</hi> was at that time involved in a War against the Emperour, <hi>Pole, Brandenburger, Muscovite, Dane</hi> and <hi>Hollander.</hi>
                     <pb n="114" facs="tcp:104474:60"/>
Add to this that the weak side of <hi>Sueden</hi> is towards <hi>Denmark,</hi> and the <hi>Suedish</hi> King has sometimes told-one in private, that were he King of <hi>Denmark</hi> he could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer <hi>Sueden</hi> in two years. Which though it may seem to have something of the Rodomontade in it, may yet to a States-man be of some Instruction.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>England</hi> though sorry for this second repture with <hi>Denmark,</hi> thought it not their Interest to see <hi>Sueden</hi> overset and sinking under the mighty weight of so powerful a Confederacy, but to buoy it up out of those quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands it was fallen into, as being the most proper and necessary counterpoise which <hi>England</hi> had at Sea against the combined Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:104474:60"/>
strength of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark.</hi> Without which Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poise <hi>England</hi> in every War with <hi>Holland</hi> (her emulous and Rival State, and that which stands in the eye and aim of all her Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and Glory in point of Trade and Sea-Dominion) would run a great risque of being excluded from the <hi>Baltic,</hi> and by that means shut out from the Market of all her Naval Stores. The old King of <hi>Denmark, Christiern</hi> the fourth, was too stomachful to truckle under the <hi>Dutch</hi> Lee, he fought them in Person when weakned with old Age, and being wounded by a splin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his Ship to the loss of one of his Eyes, his cloaths be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smeared with blood are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:104474:61"/>
as a Relique to this day. But in the Reign of his Son and Successor the now <hi>Frederic</hi> the third, the <hi>Dane</hi> considering the <hi>Suede,</hi> his ancient and heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Enemy, had by his new Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests in <hi>Pomeren</hi> and <hi>Liefland,</hi> invested himself in so many considerable Ports of the <hi>Baltic,</hi> he twisted his Interest too weak, of it self to hold against the <hi>Suede,</hi> with that of <hi>Holland;</hi> who having a concentric Interest with that of the <hi>Dane</hi> in regard of their <hi>East-land</hi> Trade, both States drawing together by a mutual Cooperation, tied the fast knot of a strict Alliance. And from that time forward the <hi>
                        <unclear>Danish</unclear>
                     </hi> Court, which in the old Kings time was used to lofty <hi>Danish,</hi>
                     <pb n="117" facs="tcp:104474:61"/>
spoke nothing now but Low <hi>Dutch;</hi> Yea so prevalent were the <hi>Dutch</hi> Councils at <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> that 'tis most certain the first War against <hi>Sueden</hi> was declared and denounced by the <hi>Dane</hi> at the instigation of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> to the end that by this revolution they might better open and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure their Trade with <hi>Dantzick</hi> and the <hi>Prussian</hi> Ports, obstructed and endangered by that formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Impression the <hi>Suede</hi> had made upon <hi>Poland.</hi> How well the <hi>Dane</hi> was rewarded for this Service, the sequel of this Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive will declare.</p>
                  <p>The Design of the <hi>English</hi> Fleet was to advance, and if need were to inforce a Peace upon the
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:104474:62"/>
dissenting King, on the terms and conditions of the <hi>Roschild</hi> Treaty, pursuant to what the <hi>English</hi> Mediator (who upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of this second War fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the <hi>Suede</hi> out of <hi>Germany</hi> into <hi>Denmark</hi> again) had by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated instances urged upon both Kings. Which, as things then stood, was conceived the most proper medium for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commoding present differences, and preventing future inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences; the Business requiring the greater <unclear>haft</unclear>, for fear the War continuing and the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates vigorously pursuing their point, the <hi>Suede</hi> should either totally be ruined, or the <hi>Dutch</hi> profiting upon his desperate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, should capitulate from
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:104474:62"/>
him particular advantages to themselves prejudicial to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest of <hi>England.</hi> Therefore in case of an obstinate repugnancy to the Peace on the <hi>Danish</hi> part upon the terms aforesaid, to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist the <hi>Suede</hi> in a defensive way under certain cautions and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strictions. In which case of Assistance, for in War many things may be supposed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided against which never come to pass, the <hi>Suede</hi> was to give real gages and pledges for the Garrantie of his Faith. To which end the <hi>English</hi> Mediator had often and closely remonstrated to him that 'twas not reasonable to put a sword into anothers hand without a previous aslu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of its not being made use of
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:104474:63"/>
against ones self. And used it also as an Argument to dispose the otherwise unwilling <hi>Suede</hi> to a Peace with the <hi>Dane</hi> (for a War with <hi>Denmark</hi> was of all Wars the most commodious for him) because he was not to expect an Assistance from <hi>England</hi> which should cost him nothing. And to foretast the temper of Affairs, proceeded so far as to nominate <hi>Stade</hi> upon the <hi>Elb,</hi> and <hi>Landscroon</hi> in the <hi>Sound,</hi> to be put in case of such assistance into <hi>English</hi> hands; which taking vent afterwards gave occasion to that frivolous report how that <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Sueden</hi> had agreed together to share <hi>Denmark</hi> betwixt them.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>English</hi> Fleet lay all the Summer in the <hi>Sound</hi> and <hi>Bel</hi>
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:104474:63"/>
only as Spectators, to see fair play, and the year declining returned home without doing any thing, contrary to the sense of the <hi>Commissioners,</hi> who some time before, <hi>viz.</hi> in <hi>July,</hi> 1659. arrived from <hi>England,</hi> and would have had the Fleet continued out longer to countenance their new begun Mediation. Which new Mediation upon change of the Government in <hi>England,</hi> was begun and mannaged by new measures taken from <hi>Holland.</hi> For whereas a Treaty had but lately been concluded at the <hi>Hague, viz.</hi> the eleventh of <hi>May,</hi> 1659. betwixt <hi>France, England,</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> for reducing the two Northern Kings to an acquies<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence in the <hi>Roschild</hi> Treaty,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:104474:64"/>
they in <hi>England</hi> upon the change aforesaid, to gratifie the <hi>Dutch</hi> and ingratiate themselves, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude another Treaty with them at the <hi>Hague</hi> of the fourth of <hi>July</hi> following, containing a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession from some material points and Articles in the said <hi>Roschild</hi> Treaty. And moreover oblige themselves to obtain from the <hi>Suede,</hi> and that forcibly if need be, in favour of the <hi>Dutch</hi> the ratification of the Treaty made at <hi>Elbing</hi> betwixt <hi>Sueden</hi> and the <hi>States General,</hi> with the Elucidations thereof made at <hi>Thoren.</hi> The truth is they made no great scruple, at least for that one time, to come under the Stern of their Neighbouring Common-wealth, thereby to
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:104474:64"/>
have better leisure to recollect and refit the scattered planks and pieces of their own broken Republic.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Dane</hi> riding Masters at Sea, the <hi>English</hi> Fleet return'd home, and the <hi>Suede</hi> so disproportionably out-numbred as not to dare to peep out of his Ports, the next Action of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance was the descent which the Confederates made upon the Isle of <hi>Funen.</hi> The strength of the <hi>Suede</hi> had hitherto consisted in being lodged securely within the <hi>Danish</hi> Isles, where the Elector of <hi>Brandenburg</hi> with the Army of the Confederates could not reach him. But what before was his strength becomes now his weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:104474:65"/>
for the <hi>Suedish</hi> Troops lay disjoyn'd upon the several Islands, and the Enemies Fleets intercepted all Communication betwixt them of passing to each others assistance as occasion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. Besides that no Island which has open landing places is defensive but by a Fleet, and such a one as is able to keep the Sea. And lest any should ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, that in this case the <hi>Suede</hi> ought to have drawn together all the divided members of his Army, and to have kept them united in one Body upon the principal Isle, which was <hi>Zeland,</hi> it ought to be considered that the Countrey had been harass'd by a long War, and one Island could not surnish a subsistence to all the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:104474:65"/>
Troops, but the greater part must necessarily have perished for want of Forrage.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Suede</hi> had upon this Isle of <hi>Funen</hi> about fifteen hundred Foot, with some few Companies of Dragoons, and about twenty five hundred of his best Horse. Prince Palatine <hi>Sultsbach</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in Chief, assisted by Field-Marshal <hi>Steinboch.</hi> Part of <hi>De Ruyter's</hi> Pleet transports General <hi>Ebersteyn</hi> with a good Body of Horse and Foot from the Confederate Army in <hi>Jutland,</hi> over the little <hi>Belt</hi> into this Island of <hi>Funen.</hi> Whiles at the same time Field-Marshal <hi>Schack,</hi> by the help of the other part of the Fleet commanded in Person by
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:104474:66"/>
                     <hi>De Ruyter,</hi> lands upon the other side of the Isle by the way of the great <hi>Belt.</hi> Either of these Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies was sufficient to have fought the Prince with his whole uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Force, but divided as he was and his men posted in several the most suspected places to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent landing, he was much too weak. One would think the proper time to have fought the Enemy had been at landing, or if that could not be, because the Cannon favoured his descent, yet at least-wise before both Bodies had joyned, which was not till after a leisurely march of some days. And yet he did nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and which is more, gave afterwards so satisfactory an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt to the King that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr'd
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:104474:66"/>
no displeasure. It seems all he could do was to reunite the scattered parts of his little Army, and posting himself in the most advantagious ground he could make choice of, there attend the Enemy, and fight it out for Safety, if not for Victory. This was done at <hi>Newburg</hi> a small Town upon the extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Funen</hi> opposite to <hi>Corsure</hi> in <hi>Zeland,</hi> in which last the King of <hi>Sueden</hi> was, almost near enough to be the Spectator of the distress and calamity of his Troops, and yet too far to help them; For <hi>De Ruyter</hi> lay with his Fleet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the two Towns. The <hi>Suede</hi> fought it valiantly having also the advantage of the ground, till the small Infantry overlaid
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:104474:67"/>
by numbers was driven from it. For the Confederates had not less than six thousand Foot, the <hi>Suede</hi> not more than sixteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. As for Horse the greatest odds was in Courage and Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, the numbers near equal. I would not upon this occasion conceal the honour of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men, I mean the <hi>English</hi> Regiment commanded by Sir <hi>William Killigrew,</hi> who together with the other Auxiliary Foot brought from <hi>Holland</hi> keeping firm and unshaken, gave oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to the routed Troops to rally behind them, by which good Order and Resolution, they in great measure turned the sometime wavering fortune of the day. The <hi>Suede</hi> at last was
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:104474:67"/>
broken, and lost Horse, Foot, and Cannon, all were slain or priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, none escaping but the Prince and <hi>Steinboch,</hi> who by the favour of the Night and the skill and labour of a few rowers pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet in a Fisher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boat, and landing at <hi>Corsure</hi> brought unwelcome tidings to their Master.</p>
                  <p>This was the greatest foil that King had ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and he did <note place="inline">
                        <hi>Nov.</hi> 1659.</note> not long survive it, and yet 'tis not easie to say what impression it made upon him, more, than that 'twas little or well dissembled. No part of those many dispatches which were sent upon this occasion
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:104474:68"/>
could be read in his Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, having besides his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Courage, the Art of conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all inward emotions and disturbances under a free and masculine appearance, and by seeming to fear nothing deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be feared. Not but that in conversation he would often testifie a tender resentment for the loss of so many brave men, who he thought deserved a better destiny.</p>
                  <p>The Prince was so far from being disgraced, that the King during his absence made him Commander in Chief of all his Forces in <hi>Zeland.</hi> For the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter coming on, and the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet sailing towards <hi>Lubec</hi> to
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:104474:68"/>
Victual, and soon after putting into Port, and the Enemy at Land breaking up their Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagne, gave the King leisure to pass over into <hi>Sconen</hi> and so to <hi>Gottenburg,</hi> where he held a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of the States of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, for the better facilitating of such new Levies of men, and other Contributions which were thought necessary for carrying on his many Wars to some de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirable conclusion. And as his leisure permitted he intended to make an Excursion to <hi>Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holm,</hi> that City much desiring to see their King after four years absence. But his incessant Labours, <note place="inline">
                        <hi>Dec.</hi> 1659.</note> Care and Watchings brought him to a sharp defluxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:104474:69"/>
that, a Feaver; and that, his end.</p>
                  <p>He was cut off in the strength of his days, not forty years of Age, a Prince of undoubted Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and unwearied Industry, low of stature but of aspiring thoughts, of a gross and heavy body, of a quick and active mind. No man of wit or courage could want Employment in his Court, and he had the singular advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of a happy judgment in discerning men, and suiting them to such Affairs to which they were best adapted, either by the secret dispositions of Nature, or by acquired knowledge. His War with <hi>Poland</hi> covered him with Laurels which bore him nothing but gaudy and unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:104474:69"/>
appearances, but the Olive of the <hi>Roschild</hi> Treaty yielded him nourishing and strengthning fruit. His first War with <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> presented him the fair side of Fortunes medal, in the second she turned to him the Reverse. He had early been bred a Soldier under General <hi>Torstenson</hi> in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> whom he usually called his Master, and never named but with great marks of Veneration. He passed through the gradations of the Art Military, from a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of a Troop of Horse to Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain General of as good an Army perhaps as this Age has seen. For at the time of the conclusion of the Peace in <hi>Germany</hi> by the Treaties of <hi>Munster</hi> and <hi>Osnabrug,</hi> he had under his Command of
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:104474:70"/>
everal Nations, fifty three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fand Foot, and twenty four thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fand Horse in Field and Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son; Besides the Confederate Armies of Marshal <hi>Turene</hi> and the Landgrave of <hi>Hess,</hi> who acted by concert with him and were at least thirty thousand more. He kept to his dying day the Muster-Rols of every Regiment with the names of the Officers, some of whom when disbanded upon the Peace, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by Pensions at his own charge, being then but Prince, obliging them thereby to his service, and foreseeing the use he might one day have of them. And has been heard to say, that he thought himself a greater man when Captain General in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi>
                     <pb n="135" facs="tcp:104474:70"/>
than he was now when King of <hi>Sueden.</hi> He would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail the loss of so many good places which <hi>Sueden</hi> demolisht or surrendred, and for doing whereof he as Captain General was also constitued Plenipoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiary at the Treaty at <hi>Osnabrug,</hi> amounting to above two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Towns, Castles and Forts. By which it was easie to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that he sided in opinion with Chancellour <hi>Oxenstiern,</hi> who when the <hi>Spanish</hi> Cabal carried all before them at <hi>Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holm,</hi> having received perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Commands from that Court to conclude the Peace in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> he did it in obedience to the commands of his Superiors, but with such regret that he could
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:104474:71"/>
not forbear to utter those words, <hi>Anima mea non intravit in secretum eorum.</hi> He was the son of the Sister of the great <hi>Gustaphus Adol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> so famous in the <hi>German</hi> Story, and upon the resignation of his Cosin <hi>Christiana,</hi> was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Crown of <hi>Sueden</hi> by the general consent of all the Estates.</p>
                  <p>This King thus removed by the stroke of death, all things resolv'd into a disposition to a general Peace. His Son and Successor was a Minor of five or six years of Age. His Queen was left Regent during the minority of her Son, a mild and gentle Lady, deriving from the bloud of her Ancestors of the House of
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:104474:71"/>
                     <hi>Holstein=Gottorp</hi> and <hi>Saxe,</hi> a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural candor and benignity. She was assisted by the great Officers of the Crown, who were willing with peace and quietness to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy their share in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which the Laws and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutions of <hi>Sueden</hi> allowed them in the minority of their King. The <hi>Suedes</hi> themselves had been harassd and tired out by long Wars, and that Martial Nation almost rode off their metal by a more Martial King. So that all things conspired on that side to Peace and Settlement. On the other side the Queen of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Lady, who had the ascendant in all the affairs of that Kingdom, was wrought over by the means of <hi>France</hi> to a ready
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:104474:72"/>
Concurrence in a Peace with <hi>Sueden.</hi> Besides that the <hi>Pole</hi> was of himself readily disposed thereto, partly in consideration of the many convulsions and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stractions of that Kingdom, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casioned by the contrary moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of disagreeing factions, and partly in regard of the unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableness of a War with <hi>Sueden,</hi> by which much might be lost nothing could be got. A Peace is therefore concluded betwixt both Crowns of <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> under the mediation of <hi>France</hi> at a place called <hi>Oliva,</hi> and the Emperour and <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burger</hi> who were but accessories in the <hi>Polish</hi> War, were easily comprehended in the Peace.</p>
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:104474:72"/>
                  <p>The onely difficulty was for <hi>Denmark;</hi> the late <hi>Suedish</hi> King had made great scruple of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the States General of the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> as Mediators for composing the War betwixt him and the <hi>Dane,</hi> alledging and declaring that they were parties with the <hi>Dane</hi> and Enemies to him, and that they ought to make their own Peace first be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they could be in capacity to interpose for others. But the now <hi>Suedish</hi> Court soon sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts this difficulty, and the four <hi>Dutch</hi> Deputies Extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary who arrived in the summer and went two of them to the <hi>Suede</hi> and two to the <hi>Dane;</hi> atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with a splendid Retinue, I mean with <hi>De Ruyter</hi> and forty
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:104474:73"/>
men of War, were now accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the <hi>Suede,</hi> notwithstanding all former hostilities and provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, as Mediators in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing Treaty. This rub being removed, the next was the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justing the terms and conditions of the Peace. For the <hi>Dane</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected his Confederates should have assisted him to the obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of such a Peace as might in the conditions thereof have born some proportion to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits which they had received by the War, and to the loss and hazard which he had sustained. For this War of <hi>Denmark</hi> had drawn the <hi>Suede</hi> out of the bowels of <hi>Poland,</hi> had delivered the <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburger</hi> from the imminent danger of having his Countrey
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:104474:73"/>
made the seat of a War. It was begun by the Council and insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the States, to secure their <hi>Dantzick</hi> trade, and was continued and prosecuted under the prospect and assurance of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief from them. Many of the <hi>Danish</hi> Court, notwithstanding the calamities they suffered by this second War, were not hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sorry for it, because it gave them an opportunity of bettering by the help of their Allies, those grievous conditions which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity had extorted from them at such a time when no friend could help them.</p>
                  <p>The States General indeed sent them Relief, but such as served their own turn, not that of the <hi>Danes.</hi> The <hi>Dane</hi> expected
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:104474:74"/>
no less than to be reinvested in all those Dominions and Possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which the former War had wrested from him. And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over in compensation and satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for the spoil and ravage of the whole Kingdom of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> by the violation of a Peace so solemnly and lately establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to be reinstated into some or all those Lands and Territories which the <hi>Broomsborow</hi> Treaty had transferred to the <hi>Suede,</hi> as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted in that War by the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> that so both Crowns might return again to their former limits and boundaries. They who cut off the flower of the <hi>Suedish</hi> Cavalry in <hi>Funen,</hi> what hindred but that they might have landed in <hi>Zeland.</hi> Winter
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:104474:74"/>
came not on so fast, but the Fleet might have sailed four Leagues, and it was no more to <hi>Zeland</hi> though more to <hi>Lubec.</hi> If they wanted Foot, <hi>Copenhagen</hi> could have spared them five thousand, and they might have had ten thousand more for fetching from the Confederate Army in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stein</hi> and <hi>Jutland.</hi> But this needed not, the <hi>Suede</hi> had not five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Foot upon <hi>Zeland,</hi> nor so good a Body of Horse as he had left upon <hi>Funen,</hi> besides the Horse of the Confederates was better then before, having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived an encrease of strength from the spoils of their Enemy.</p>
                  <p>But unhappy that Prince who wages a War against a stronger than himself, not by his own
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:104474:75"/>
strength, but by that of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates; and still more unhappy when those Confederates are jealous and distrustful of his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture growth and greatness. The Alliances of States are Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence not Friendship, Interest not Affection, a reason of the head not a passion of the heart. The poor exhausted <hi>Dane,</hi> after all his former and later sufferings, must stoop again under the heavy yoke of the despised <hi>Roschild</hi> Treaty. The dividing of the Banks of the <hi>Sound</hi> betwixt the two Crowns accommodated <hi>Holland</hi> as well as <hi>England.</hi> That ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity which first cast the <hi>Dane</hi> upon the <hi>Dutch</hi> Alliance, if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, might make him recoil from it; to keep him poor was to
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:104474:75"/>
keep him humble and so depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. And yet that the States-<hi>General</hi> might seem to do some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than the bare relief of <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> or which is all one, more then the bare securing of their own Trade in the <hi>Baltic,</hi> They urge and obtain that the Government of <hi>Drontheim</hi> in <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way</hi> be restored again to the <hi>Dane,</hi> to the intent those barren moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains might make some satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and amends for the plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and spoil of a fertil King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, much more exhausted and more cruelly harassd by this se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond War then it had been by the former. And yet 'tis worthy considering whether in this also the <hi>Dutch</hi> did not as well gratifie themselves as the <hi>Dane,</hi> partly
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:104474:76"/>
because <hi>Drontheim</hi> better accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated their <hi>Norway</hi>-Trade whiles in the hand of the <hi>Dane</hi> then when in that of the <hi>Suede,</hi> part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in regard of the Levies of men which the <hi>Dutch</hi> usually make amongst the <hi>Norwegian</hi> Mariners, by the favour of the Court of <hi>Denmark</hi> in times of War, and partly for better recovery of those moneys which some par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Companies of <hi>Amsterdam</hi> had advanced to the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> upon the Gage and Pledge of the dependencies of <hi>Drontheim.</hi> The controverted Isle of <hi>Hueen</hi> is adjudged to the <hi>Suede.</hi> The Isle of <hi>Bornholm</hi> which during this last War had voluntarily returned to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of her former Master,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:104474:76"/>
must be restored again to the <hi>Suede</hi> after the expiration of one year, or else exchanged for an equivalent. In all the other material points, excepting that of <hi>Drontheim,</hi> the <hi>Roschild</hi> Treaty is renewed and reconfirmed, and remains to this day the standard and measure betwixt these two Northern Crowns.</p>
                  <p>There is one thing more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servable with which I shall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude. The onely benefit and advantage which <hi>Denmark</hi> has received by this last War amidst many losses and sufferances was occasional and accidental, and for which the <hi>Dane</hi> has no obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to any of his Confederates, because it sprang meerly from
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:104474:77"/>
the contingencies of the War; It was this. The Crown of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> had been Elective for above two hundred years in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent <hi>Oldenburg</hi> Family. The chief Power of Electing being in the Nobility, gave them the means and opportunity of capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulating advantages to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, as previous conditions to the Election, with every succeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing King, to the despoiling and debilitating of the Crown, and to the prejudice of the other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Kingdom. None but a Nobleman could buy or pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sess in his own right any Seigno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or Mannor. A Citizen or Burgher was not capable of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chasing more than a House, and it may be a Garden and Orchard,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:104474:77"/>
or such like slender curtilage. The Lands and Revenues of the Crown were let to Noblemen it may be not to the third, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times not to the fourth part of what they were really worth, and yet the King must not En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hance the old Rents, though in the mean time the Nobles rackt the poor under-Tenants to the utmost. The Pesants upon the <hi>Danish</hi> Isles were Villains regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant to the Mannors of Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, such as the Civilians call <hi>ascriptitii glebae.</hi> All publick Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and preferments were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to the Nobility, there was no room left for a single and unendowed Desert. Birth had precluded Merit, and the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Bloud had forestall'd
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:104474:78"/>
the rewards of Vertue. By which constitution, <hi>Denmark,</hi> from an anciently glorious and most re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Monarchy, had in a suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession of some Ages dwindled and degenerated to that State and condition which to avoid offence I sorbear to name. But upon occasion of this second War, the better to encourage the Burgers of <hi>Copenhagen</hi> to stand couragiously for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of their King and Country, lest the hope and expectancy of bettering their condition under a new Master should prompt them to desert their old, great privileges were proposed and conferred upon them. Such as these: An equal admission to Offices and Honours, as they and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:104474:78"/>
their Children should render themselves capable and deserv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. A power of purchasing Lands and Lordships with the same rights as Nobles. The City to be one of the Estates of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and to have a suffrage in all publick Councils and Resolves. And the Crown is also delivered out of the Guardianship of the Nobility, being changed from Elective to Hereditary. So that now in <hi>Denmark</hi> there is a more healthful and better proportioned distribution of strength and nourishment to all parts of the Body of that Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whereby the whole is become more vigorous and able to withstand for the future such rude Attacks and Assaults from
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:104474:79"/>
without, as had in the late Wars endangered the Life thereof.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="unk">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:104474:79"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A VIEW</hi> OF THE <hi>SUEDISH</hi> AND Other Affairs, as they now stand IN <hi>GERMANY</hi> This present Year, 1675. WITH Relation to <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Composed in the Year <hi>1675.</hi> when the <hi>Suede</hi> was declared Enemy of the Empire.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>A. C.</hi> for <hi>H. Brome,</hi> at the Gun in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard. M. DC. LXXVII.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:104474:80"/>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:104474:80"/>
                  <head>A <hi>VIEW</hi> OF THE <hi>SUEDISH</hi> AND Other Affairs, as they now stand IN <hi>GERMANY.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>HE who duly reflects upon the State and Condition of <hi>Germany</hi> at the time of the <hi>Munster</hi> and <hi>Osnabrug</hi> Treaties concluded in the year 1648. How the Empire wearied by a tedious War with earnest long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:104474:81"/>
breath'd after a settlement; How the <hi>Suede</hi> at that time pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful in Arms, was courted to a Peace by the proposal of such ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious conditions, as wanted nothing but the name of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest; may justly wonder, that so wise a Council as that of <hi>Sueden,</hi> should submit all their great Acquisitions, of which for many years they have been in the quiet and legal possession, to the uncertain hazard of a new War.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Osnabrug</hi> Treaty is the <hi>Magna Charta</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> and was enacted a perpetual funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Law, and pragmatic Sanction of the Empire. But the <hi>Suede,</hi> upon his late Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:104474:81"/>
of the Marquisate of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburg,</hi> having in full Diet been declared Enemy of the Empire, all the concessions in that Treaty respecting that Crown, are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like the old Charters or Donations of <hi>Charlemagne,</hi> sealed with the Pommel of a Sword to be warranted by the Blade.</p>
                  <p>The Risque the <hi>Suede</hi> now runs is further heightned upon this following consideration. <hi>Sueden</hi> has enlarged her Border upon all the neighbouring Princes. Upon the <hi>Pole</hi> and <hi>Moscovite</hi> by <hi>Liefland, Esthen</hi> and <hi>Ingermanland.</hi> Upon the <hi>German</hi> Empire by the Dukedom of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meren,</hi> Principality of <hi>Rugen,</hi> Bishopricks of <hi>Bremen</hi> and <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi>
                     <pb n="158" facs="tcp:104474:82"/>
Erected upon this occasion into Dutchies, and by the Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of the City and Port of <hi>Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar.</hi> Upon the <hi>Dane</hi> by the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Provinces of <hi>Halland, Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen, Bleking,</hi> &amp;c. Some or all of which Princes do but wait a favourable conjuncture, wherein to attempt the reinstating them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves into those Possessions, which the Accidents of War and other fatalities have extorted from them.</p>
                  <p>It may also be noted upon this occasion, that by vertue of the aforementioned <hi>Osnabrug</hi> Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, some of the then Friends or Allies of the Crown of <hi>Sueden</hi> were devested of part of their Patrimony, the better to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:104474:82"/>
the <hi>Suede</hi> in laying his new acquired Possessions more close and contiguous. Thus the Elector of <hi>Brandenburg</hi> quitted <hi>Stetin</hi> and other Rights which he had in both the <hi>Pomerens.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Mecklenburg</hi> resigned <hi>Wismar.</hi> 'Tis true both these Princes received a compensa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Exchange or Equivalent, such as the necessity of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic Peace constrain'd them to acquiesce in; the first by the Bishoprick of <hi>Halberstad,</hi> the latter by that of <hi>Ratzenburg,</hi> but it must be granted too that the Rents and Revenues of Inland Dominions are not so improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as those arising upon Sea-Ports.</p>
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:104474:83"/>
                  <p>Now if we impartially com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the circumstances of Affairs in this present year 1675. with those in the year 1648. it will be the easier to make an estimate, whether <hi>Sueden</hi> could rationally hope to better the conditions of the <hi>Osnabrug</hi> Treaty, or whether their future expectancies can in any just proportion countervail their present hazard.</p>
                  <p>In the former <hi>German</hi> War, it was no small advantage to <hi>Sueden</hi> to be esteemed the Head of the Protestant Cause and Interest in <hi>Germany;</hi> this brought them many Allies and Adherents; and made their thin and tattered Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments swell into numerous and well appointed Armies. But
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:104474:83"/>
in the present War there is nothing of Religion so much as pretended in the Case. Nay the more immediate quarrel that <hi>Sueden</hi> now has, is with the <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburger,</hi> the <hi>Dane</hi> and <hi>Hollander,</hi> who though of different persua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, are clasp'd together with the <hi>Suede</hi> in the same general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of Religion. Before the <hi>Osnabrug</hi> Treaty, <hi>Germany</hi> was crumbled into many Factions and Interests, both Religious and Civil. Now the whole Body of the Empire is consolidated and united together against strangers, and some in <hi>Germany</hi> esteem the <hi>Suede</hi> no other. In the year 1648. before the Peace, the <hi>Suede</hi> had more than two hundred Garrisons in <hi>Germany,</hi>
                     <pb n="162" facs="tcp:104474:84"/>
and an Army in Field and Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of near fourscore thousand men, the far greater number of them foreiners, but all Vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans exactly disciplin'd, and commanded by a Martial Prince extracted from the Palatine fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of the <hi>Rhine</hi> (the now King of <hi>Sueden's</hi> Father) who upon that accompt was the more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to the <hi>German</hi> Nation. Now their Army is small and consists of new Levies, their Garrisons few, and by occasion of a long Peace neither so well fortified nor otherwise provided. The <hi>Suede</hi> had then many Allies and Confederates within the very bowels of the Empire. The <hi>Landgrave</hi> of <hi>Hess</hi> had a consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Army in the Field, which
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:104474:84"/>
to the very last acted in concert with <hi>Sueden;</hi> besides the Army of <hi>France</hi> under Marshal <hi>Turenne</hi> in <hi>Alsace.</hi> Now the <hi>Suede</hi> has no other visible Confederate but <hi>France,</hi> so remote, that if the <hi>French</hi> Armies should by the Chance of War be put upon the Defensive, the <hi>Suede</hi> may be lost before <hi>France</hi> can help him. The <hi>Dane</hi> who then stood Neutral, has now declared against <hi>Sueden.</hi> The <hi>States General</hi> then in War with <hi>Spain,</hi> now confederated with <hi>Spain</hi> and the Empire against <hi>France,</hi> and consequently against <hi>Sueden.</hi> I need add no more to encrease the wonder I before mentioned, the difficulty would rather be to salve and allay it, were it any thing to my purpose,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:104474:85"/>
who pretend not to have the Key of the Cabinet, or to be able to penetrate the secret of the <hi>Suedish</hi> Councils; only this is obvious, if a lesser Crown con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>descends to become the Pensio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of another more great and opulent than its self, it will be exposed to temptations of being sometimes warped from her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per measures. Besides the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of the Example, for if the Crown receives gifts the Ministers will be less modest in refusing them, when tendred.</p>
                  <p>Add moreover, the inlets into a War are so many and so easie, but the outlets so few and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, that a wise Prince and Council obliged upon remoter
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:104474:85"/>
considerations to a shew and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Arms, may insen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly and unexpectedly be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volv'd in a War, which they never in good earnest intended. And he who proposed to himself to advance his Arms to such a Point and no further, may to his grief find the unruly beast of War so ungovernable, as not to be mannag'd to certain stops and bounds, but to transgress them all, and sometimes throw the Rider.</p>
                  <p>And as a Prince may gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually and insensibly be engaged in a War which at first he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended not, and afterwards be further engaged in it, than he either proposed or desired; So
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:104474:86"/>
'tis ordinary for the consequents and effects of such War to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to the prejudice of other Princes, who had no participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion either in the beginning or the progress thereof. Thus if the <hi>Suede</hi> (for I suppose 'tis no offence to put such a Case, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause what's laid at stake no man can call his own) I say, if the <hi>Suede</hi> should lose all in <hi>Germany,</hi> and be turned back again over the <hi>Baltic;</hi> This would redound greatly to the mischief of <hi>France,</hi> whose Interest it is to maintain the <hi>Suede</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> as a check and counterpoise upon the House of <hi>Austria,</hi> the hereditary Enemy of <hi>France.</hi> But this considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on reaches not <hi>England,</hi> because that House has in this last Age
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:104474:86"/>
been under so sensible a deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, that it gives no longer any just ombrage or jealousie as formerly, of any affectation of an Universal Monarchy.</p>
                  <p>But yet it may greatly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern <hi>England</hi> into what hands the Chance of War may throw those places the <hi>Suede</hi> now possesses. Should the Elector of <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> invest himself in the Ports of <hi>Pomeren,</hi> and by that means erect a third power upon the <hi>Baltic:</hi> Nay should the Duke of <hi>Curland,</hi> whose little Dutchy is a Fief of the Crown of <hi>Poland,</hi> and who of later years has af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to put in for a share in the <hi>Baltic</hi> under the Title of Admiral of that Crown, though his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:104474:87"/>
always suppressed by the early jealousies of those greater Powers of <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Sueden;</hi> should he I say by help of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and consanguinity he has with <hi>Brandenburg</hi> (for that House married a Sister of that Elector) added to the countenance and assistance of <hi>Poland,</hi> establish a fourth Power upon the <hi>Baltic:</hi> All this would not sensibly touch <hi>England,</hi> for a Reason intimated in that Answer, which a Duke of <hi>Burgundy</hi> once made, when it was objected to him how he was no Lover of the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> his Reply was, on the contrary he was so great a Lover of them, that whereas there was one King of <hi>France</hi> he wished there were many.</p>
                  <pb n="169" facs="tcp:104474:87"/>
                  <p>But if the <hi>Dane</hi> should seize the Ports of <hi>Pomeren,</hi> or possess himself of <hi>Stade</hi> and <hi>Boxtehude</hi> in the Dutchy of <hi>Bremen;</hi> or should he so far profit upon the present Conjuncture, as to reinstate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in the opposite Bank of the <hi>Sound,</hi> which was taken from him in the year 1658. every of these will alter the Case in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to <hi>England;</hi> For 'tis evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that the dividing the Banks of the <hi>Sound</hi> betwixt the two emulous Crowns, as it was done by the <hi>Roschild</hi> Treaty, is greatly to the security and benefit of <hi>England.</hi> To our security in time of War, for in case of a War be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> if <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> incline to <hi>Holland</hi> (which is not unreasonable to be suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed)
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:104474:88"/>
                     <hi>England,</hi> in friendship with <hi>Sueden</hi> whilest possessed of one Bank of the <hi>Sound,</hi> will in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spight of the other two Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates maintain the Trade into the <hi>Baltie,</hi> and fetch from thence those materials which are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary for the apparel and equip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page of her Shipping. To our benefit in time of Peace, and that in reference to Trade and Commerce. For 'tis a Gain to the <hi>Dane</hi> to enhance the duties of the <hi>Sound,</hi> but 'tis the Interest, of <hi>Sueden</hi> to oppose it, because <hi>Stockholm</hi> and all the Ports of <hi>Sueden,</hi> except <hi>Gottenburg,</hi> being within the <hi>Baltic,</hi> whatever Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are imposed upon forein Ships in their passage through the <hi>Sound,</hi> are a burden upon
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:104474:88"/>
the Trade of <hi>Sueden.</hi> The same Reason holds for the <hi>Elb,</hi> where the <hi>Dane</hi> has <hi>Gluestad</hi> upon the one Bank, the <hi>Suede Stade</hi> and <hi>Boxtehude</hi> upon the other. If both Banks should come into <hi>Danish</hi> hands, this would more immediately concern <hi>Hamburgh;</hi> and so much the rather because of the old pretensions the Kings of <hi>Denmark</hi> as Dukes of <hi>Holstein</hi> have upon that City. But it will remotely concern <hi>England,</hi> for it will be in the power of the <hi>Dane</hi> to exclude us from the Trade of the <hi>Elb</hi> whenever he pleases. Which perhaps he will not do. But the Assurances of Princes are not to be founded upon the <hi>Will not,</hi> but upon the <hi>Cannot.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="172" facs="tcp:104474:89"/>
                  <p>Add to all this, that as it is the Interest of <hi>France</hi> to maintain <hi>Sueden</hi> as a ballance upon the House of <hi>Austria,</hi> so 'tis the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest of <hi>England</hi> to preserve <hi>Sueden</hi> as her proper counterpoise against the Confederate Naval Strength of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Denmark.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The case thus standing, and <hi>Sueden</hi> having changed the figure it lately made, when the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of that Crown was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed in concert with <hi>England,</hi> by entring into the War and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Party; There is no Prince in <hi>Europe</hi> to whom it can so properly appertain to advance the great work of a Mediation, as to his Majesty of <hi>England.</hi> The Pope not so fit to interpose in these <hi>German</hi> Controversies, as
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:104474:89"/>
upon other considerations, so particularly upon this, because by the <hi>Munster</hi> and <hi>Osnabrug</hi> Treaties, which are the Basis of the Peace of <hi>Germany,</hi> many of the Lands of the Church and other Ecclesiastical Rights, were Alienated and made Secular. Which the Nuncio at that time was so far from consenting to, that he entred a public Protest against it, and <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth declared all the Articles relating to Religion to be nul and void. The <hi>Venetian</hi> State remote, and though admitted Mediator in the <hi>Munster</hi> Treaty betwixt the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire and <hi>France,</hi> yet was not so in the <hi>Osnabrug</hi> Treaty betwixt the Empire and <hi>Sueden.</hi> Besides the Councils of that Republic face
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:104474:90"/>
most to the <hi>Levant,</hi> neither does she intermeddle in the Affairs of the Western Princes so much as in former Ages.</p>
                  <p>Whilest the King of <hi>England</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides his Power, Interest and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, seems to be selected by a coinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of several Providential circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances to undertake this Work, not only Pious, but Safe, Honourable and Profitable. Safe, because all the Interessed Princes court the Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of the Mediator; Honourable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the mediating Prince becomes the <hi>Arbiter</hi> of others Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versies; Profitable because his Ministers being upon the place, and privy to the secrets of the contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Parties, have the opportunity of espying advantages for se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:104474:90"/>
and promoting their Master's Interests.</p>
                  <p>But as in Naturals so in Civils, 'tis Time ripens all things: And 'tis the Wisdome of the Head which directs the diligence of the Hand to gather the fruit in its proper season. The last War of <hi>Germany</hi> was of thirty years con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, and the Peace was se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven years in treating, reckoning from the Preliminaries agreed at <hi>Hamburgh,</hi> to the conclusion of the Peace at <hi>Munster</hi> and <hi>Osna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brug.</hi> This according to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane conjectures seems not of that duration. But mediating Princes are most welcome and successful, when the Parties are wearied with the War, as
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:104474:91"/>
those Physicians are most happy who come in the declension of a Disease.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="errata">
                  <head>Errata.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Page</hi> 117. <hi>for</hi> revolution <hi>read</hi> revulsion. <hi>p.</hi> 124. <hi>for</hi> defensive <hi>read</hi> defensible. <hi>p.</hi> 143. <hi>for</hi> left <hi>read</hi> lost. <hi>p.</hi> 151. <hi>for</hi> Govern <hi>read</hi> Government.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
