<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mercuries message, or, The coppy of a letter sent to William Laud, late Archbishop of Canterbury, now prisoner in the Tower</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-01">2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50633</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1748</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19541</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12351163</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12351163</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60012</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A50633)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60012)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 642:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mercuries message, or, The coppy of a letter sent to William Laud, late Archbishop of Canterbury, now prisoner in the Tower</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Laud, William, 1573-1645 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-03</date>
            <label>TCP Staff (Oxford)</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-03</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60012:1"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:60012:1"/>
               <hi>MERCURIES MESSAGE,</hi> OR THE COPPY OF A LETTER sent to <hi>William Laud</hi> late Archbishop of CANTERBVRY, now priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in the <hi>Tower.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <head>PROV. 11. 10.</head>
               <l>When it fares well with righteous men,</l>
               <l>The City is glad and joyfull then:</l>
               <l>But when with Wicked it fares ill,</l>
               <l>Ther's none of them, take pitty will,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>JOB. 27. 23.</head>
               <l>Clapping of hands with joy there is apace,</l>
               <l>Hissing them out of there great Lordly place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>JOB. 32. 9.</head>
               <l>The great ones are not alwaies wise,</l>
               <l>Who in great pompe and state do rise.</l>
            </lg>
            <figure/>
            <p>Printed in the yeare, of our Prelates feare. 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="identification_of_Antichrist">
            <pb facs="tcp:60012:2"/>
            <lg>
               <head>REVELL. 13. 16.</head>
               <l>The man that understanding hath</l>
               <l>Behold and see, the Scripture saith</l>
               <l>The number of the Beast is numbered</l>
               <l>And comes unto the sum Six hundered</l>
               <l>Sixty and six: the name here writ amounts</l>
               <l>Vnto the same if we doe rightly count.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>The beasts number
<lb/>The mans name
<lb/>is the worlds wonder
<lb/>With beasts the same</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>W</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>L</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>I</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>A</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>L</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                     <cell>V</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>L</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                     <cell>D</cell>
                     <cell>500</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell cols="4">666.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <head>Revelat. 19. 20.</head>
               <l>Into the lake the beast was cast</l>
               <l>Which never dyes: but everlasting lasts</l>
               <l>It burnes with brimstone and with fire,</l>
               <l>According to Gods dreadfull ire.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:60012:2"/>
            <head>TO The late famous, now Infamous Arch-Bishop, <hi>WILLIAM,</hi> a <hi>CANTERBVRY.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <lg>
               <l>I Call you what, not long agoe you were,</l>
               <l>But now those golden dayes are past I feare,</l>
               <l>And so doth all the drooping <hi>Hierachy</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of Lordly Bishops, that er'e while so high,</l>
               <l>Bore up theirs heads to show themselves superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors,</l>
               <l>And proudly trod upon their poore inferiors.</l>
               <l>How did you Domineere in your vaine pride</l>
               <l>Whilst in prosperity you did abide,</l>
               <l>With envious Rage, and foule maliciousnesse,</l>
               <l>Striving to bring Gods people in distresse</l>
               <l>Downe went all painefull and laborious teaching,</l>
               <l>The Service Booke more usefull was, then preaching</l>
               <l>In your account, having an Inclination</l>
               <l>With Popish rites to blind our <hi>Brittish</hi> nation.</l>
               <l>But men of sounder Judgement know full well,</l>
               <l>That Gods pure word mans wisedome doth excell</l>
               <l>And yet for sooth your will being a Law,</l>
               <l>Men better then your selfe, you kept in aw</l>
               <l>Well, next our weekely Lectures lik't you not,</l>
               <l>To put downe them your zeale was wondrous hot.</l>
               <l>It seemes your Lordship had conceivid a thought,</l>
               <l>And feard poore Ignorants would too much be taught,</l>
               <l>And so your Soule deludements learne to see,</l>
               <l>When with <hi>Roomes</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> doth no whit agree;</l>
               <l>Else you might thinke, with plenty being fed,</l>
               <l>They might have loath'd that heavenly bread,</l>
               <l>For men by <hi>Solomons</hi> rule may <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> get</l>
               <l>If finding honey, they too much on't eat.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60012:3"/>
Therefore your Grace tooke a sure course for such,</l>
               <l>Y'ad rather see them starve then have too much</l>
               <l>But now the Sabboth day in your esteeme</l>
               <l>Is kept too strictly, this a fault you deeme,</l>
               <l>For squaring thus our actions by Gods word</l>
               <l>We with the Papists never should accord</l>
               <l>Therefore by smooth, false, base Insinuation</l>
               <l>You did perswade the King by Proclamation</l>
               <l>To give his subjects leave to sport and play</l>
               <l>In spight of all gainsayers on that day:</l>
               <l>This done, one Sermon must content us to</l>
               <l>And that but one houre long, for if men do</l>
               <l>Exceed their time prescrib'd, tho their intention</l>
               <l>Be ne're so good, they may expect suspention:</l>
               <l>In all which did not we Religion fly,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Roome</hi> observe a sweet close simpathy.</l>
               <l>But is this all; no, Altars next you raise,</l>
               <l>And waxen Tapers must upon them blaze;</l>
               <l>Yea in these heapes of Stone such worth is found.</l>
               <l>That passers by must bow to'em downe toth' ground:</l>
               <l>Is Jesus with a large pronunciation</l>
               <l>Vttered by some time serve't being the fashion,</l>
               <l>Legs, Congjes, Bowings, wait upon that name</l>
               <l>In outward Adoration of the same.</l>
               <l>Indeed the Countrey did this trick refuse,</l>
               <l>Because their scraping spoyl'd their Sunday shoo's:</l>
               <l>Besides being full of Nayles and Iron specks,</l>
               <l>They made a Parish charge to buy new bricks.</l>
               <l>To ratifie all this, Cannons are made,</l>
               <l>And yet I thinke the Authors are not paide</l>
               <l>For that good worke of theirs, but let that pas,</l>
               <l>This Parliament then never dreampt of was,</l>
               <l>Or if it were and things had come toth' worst;</l>
               <l>Perhaps you thought to dash it like the first:</l>
               <l>Therefore in uncontrouled pride you raign'd</l>
               <l>Vertue oppos'd, all vices you maintain'd:</l>
               <l>Which made men thinke you had an itching hope</l>
               <l>To be some Cardinall or little Pope.</l>
               <l>Whereby an ancient Proverb's verifide,</l>
               <l>Beggers if set on horse backe, love to ride:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60012:3"/>
Did any Minister detest these things,</l>
               <l>To see you Bishops rule like petty Kings</l>
               <l>Did they out of true zeale and conscience sake,</l>
               <l>A scruple of your Popish orders make:</l>
               <l>Crosse, Surplice, Tippet, would they not allow</l>
               <l>To high Altar, did they scorne to bow:</l>
               <l>Was there no outward signe of Reverence showne</l>
               <l>When Jesus was pronounc'd, and that made knowne</l>
               <l>To your Lordship; straight off went th' offenders eares</l>
               <l>Though nere so old, no pitties tooke of yeares:</l>
               <l>Your worships pillary must their necks adorne</l>
               <l>A triple Tree they say shall serve your turne.</l>
               <l>They peepe through wooden windowes; as for you</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gregory</hi> has a hempen Lattice faire and new.</l>
               <l>Men hope to see you mounted er'e you die,</l>
               <l>I'm sorry for't my Lord, but cannot crie.</l>
               <l>Sure your well wishers hymmes of praise will sing,</l>
               <l>To see you goe to Heaven in a string:</l>
               <l>Or if not so, the common people sweare,</l>
               <l>You'l grace the Block as well as your compere:</l>
               <l>Others suppose that a Clothworkers son,</l>
               <l>Shall never have such honour to him don:</l>
               <l>Thus all men censure, none cares what they say,</l>
               <l>Pusse being cag'd, the Mice may freely play.</l>
               <l>So in a Country pasture have I seene</l>
               <l>The little Lambkins skipping on a greene,</l>
               <l>Whilst the poore wolfe lies tangled in the net</l>
               <l>The carefull Sheapheard for his ruine set:</l>
               <l>This is the talke my Lord that goes about,</l>
               <l>He's nobody now a dayes that cannot flout.</l>
               <l>Imprison'd <hi>Canterbury,</hi> when 'tis cleare</l>
               <l>Your back's to norrow all these quips to beare;</l>
               <l>Oh had your thoughts and stature but agreed</l>
               <l>Together, then all had beene well indeed:</l>
               <l>But when such Pigmy Lords as you will cherish</l>
               <l>Ambitious great desires, both lightly perish.</l>
               <l>How true this happens to your helpelesse wo,</l>
               <l>And sad destruction, sure I am you know;</l>
               <l>For now y're falling 'tis the generall cry</l>
               <l>Downe with him Tyrant fie upon him fie.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60012:4"/>
Blest were the man could light on such good hap,</l>
               <l>To beate our's eyes with's <hi>Babylonian</hi> cap.</l>
               <l>Thus are our wits imploy'd early and late</l>
               <l>With some quient leere to breake your Graces pate,</l>
               <l>We scorne saies one his vices to applaud,</l>
               <l>We know the Divill must have little <hi>Laud:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O saies a second, he's a gallant prize,</l>
               <l>And by his fall, young <hi>Gregory</hi> will rise.</l>
               <l>Who sweares when Surplice &amp; Lawn sleeves h'as got</l>
               <l>Heele send <hi>Romes</hi> Strumpet a veneriall smock.</l>
               <l>As for the Song which goes <hi>Blue cap for mee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hee'l have it chang'd to <hi>Black cap that's his fee.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Lastly, (to passe all others) some suppose</l>
               <l>You have a trick of art to fetch backe those</l>
               <l>Shew'd us their Heeles, where ever they remaine,</l>
               <l>Or else be hang'd when you come backe againe:</l>
               <l>I know you have a great desire to doe it.</l>
               <l>Could you perswade the Parliament unto it;</l>
               <l>But were you sent on such an errand now,</l>
               <l>When should we see ye returne, never we know:</l>
               <l>Oh tis whipping Time my Lord most thinke,</l>
               <l>When such as you, for feare begin to stinke:</l>
               <l>Some run for't their Activity to show,</l>
               <l>Their Heads may thanke their Legs, if they scape so.</l>
               <l>Others that cannot go; Blood sucking Leeches,</l>
               <l>Make Buttons backwards, and defile their breeches:</l>
               <l>So may you see some dogs when death drawes neere,</l>
               <l>Being lifted from the Earth perfume the ayre:</l>
               <l>Me thinks your Honour, yea your Honours head,</l>
               <l>Hangs in the ayre by a small twisted Thread:</l>
               <l>Which to Heav'ns praise, Hells joy, &amp; <hi>Londons</hi> wonder</l>
               <l>The Sword of Justice Arives to cut asunder.</l>
               <l>Alas what Remedy, if downe you must,</l>
               <l>'Tis but a little grace transform'd to Dust;</l>
               <l>Where Dirt and Ashes having stopt your breath,</l>
               <l>You'l find this truth, wages of sinne is death;</l>
               <l>Did you expect my Lord a yeare ago,</l>
               <l>To see your glorious light extinguish'd so;</l>
               <l>Did you once dreame of this disaster sad,</l>
               <l>Sure no, y'ad liv'd much better if you had.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60012:4"/>
So have I seen the treacherous fox or'e shot,</l>
               <l>Persuing his prey with rage and malice hot;</l>
               <l>Till in the height of's pride at unaware</l>
               <l>Thinking to catch the spoyle, he falls i'th snare.</l>
               <l>I know my Lord, you now consume your dayes</l>
               <l>In bitternesse, be't spoken to your praise</l>
               <l>And that's good Reason't should be, so for why?</l>
               <l>Y'ave worne whole yeares away in vanity:</l>
               <l>And yet we doubt y' are onely discontented</l>
               <l>To see your hellish aymes so well prevented.</l>
               <l>But is the head sick, and the members free,</l>
               <l>Do not our other Bishops grieve to see</l>
               <l>Their PROP so sorely shaken; sure they do</l>
               <l>For you once downe they needs must tumble to;</l>
               <l>They know a house that Built upon the Sand,</l>
               <l>In time of windy stormes can never stand.</l>
               <l>Now if great Beelzebub himselfe be scar'd</l>
               <l>Needs must th'inferior Divells be afeard.</l>
               <l>Some other things I meant to write, whic I</l>
               <l>Will now omit t'avoyd Prolixity:</l>
               <l>I feare already I've too tedious been,</l>
               <l>And that you ever judg'd a haynous sin.</l>
               <l>Therefore to close up all, let me I pray,</l>
               <l>Informe you what the bonny <hi>Scotchmen</hi> say:</l>
               <l>They hope in quiet to goe home unbang'd,</l>
               <l>And wish the causer of their coming hang'd:</l>
               <l>And so they vow to see him ere they goe,</l>
               <l>Then farwell <hi>England, Iockey</hi> is no foe.</l>
               <l>Therefore my Lord, take a friends advise,</l>
               <l>And learne to swing adayes if you be wise:</l>
               <l>For I'm perrwaded 'tis your Honours lot,</l>
               <l>To have your old bones stretch't, why should you not?</l>
               <l>Old men must dye you know, and young men may:</l>
               <l>When your turne comes comes, then wee'l make holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day;</l>
               <l>And like old <hi>Israel</hi> skip and sing amaine,</l>
               <l>To see <hi>Goliah</hi> on the Mountaines slaine.</l>
               <l>My Muse growes weary Sir, and now I'le rest</l>
               <l>Mine owne, not yours, I see the Sun's ith west.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Felix quem faciunt aliena pericula Cantem.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But some wil nere learne wit till'its dearly taught them</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:60012:5"/>
            <head>An Accrosticall Caveat to beware of Ambition</head>
            <lg>
               <l>What newes is this I heare</l>
               <l>In all mens mouthes so sweet,</l>
               <l>Laud's taken in the snare</l>
               <l>Laid for anothers feet.</l>
               <l>Indeed I alwaies thought</l>
               <l>Ambitious pride would fall</l>
               <l>Mens waies being lewd and nought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Lead them toth pit of thrall.</l>
               <l>Agreat mans hope is vaine</l>
               <l>Vnlesse his life be just,</l>
               <l>Death ends his dayes in shame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And then wher's human trust</l>
               <l>Riches will not availe</l>
               <l>Cold worlds be then produc'd</l>
               <l>Honnor and wit will faile</l>
               <l>Because th'ave bin abus'd</l>
               <l>In pompe and dignitee</l>
               <l>Sometime tho he remaine</l>
               <l>His greatnes soone will bee</l>
               <l>Obscurd with foule disdaine</l>
               <l>Proud <hi>Nimrod</hi> thus and's troope,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of late have lost their power</l>
               <l>For <hi>Babell</hi> gins to stoope.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Confusion shakes their tower</l>
               <l>Anortherne blast hath blowne</l>
               <l>Nere thirty flat caps downe</l>
               <l>That were so stately growne,</l>
               <l>Each one ore topt the Crowne</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome</hi> wailes their sudden fall,</l>
               <l>But 'tis in vaine to rore</l>
               <l>Vsurping Prelates shall</l>
               <l>Rule us in pride no more:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iure devino</hi> made an Asse you see,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Enland</hi> rejoyce, 'tis happie newes for thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
