<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Michaelmas term the citizens kind welcome to country-men, that from all parts of the land come hither about their needless occasions (needful I mean), with a description of the seasons and manners of the people therein imployed : to the tune of The rambling clerk.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-03">2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50780</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1961B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43453</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">27651718</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 27651718</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110158</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A50780)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110158)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1729:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Michaelmas term the citizens kind welcome to country-men, that from all parts of the land come hither about their needless occasions (needful I mean), with a description of the seasons and manners of the people therein imployed : to the tune of The rambling clerk.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for F. Coles, T. Vere, and J. Wright,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[between 1663 and 1674]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ballads, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  London (England) --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:110158:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
            <head>Michaelmas Term: The Cittizens Kind Welcome to Country-men, that from all parts of the Land come hither about their needleſs occaſions (needful I mean) with a deſcription of the ſeaſons and manners of the people therein imployed. </head>
            <opener>To the tune of, <hi>The Rambling Clerk.</hi>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>COme hither my Muſe if that thou be'ſt cold,</l>
               <l>And warm thy ſelf well with <hi>Promethian</hi> fire,</l>
               <l>VVhich when thou haſt done let me he bold,</l>
               <l>In matter of moment thy aid to require.</l>
               <l>My mind is reſolved to write on a Theam,</l>
               <l>The which my expreſſion I hope ſhall confirm,</l>
               <l>Thoſe men that do come from all parts of the Realm</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I bid them all welcome to Michaelmas Term.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Tradſman of <hi>London</hi> with long Expectation,</l>
               <l>Have lookt for the coming of this happy time,</l>
               <l>They are ſick at the heart of the let tous vexation,</l>
               <l>But now on a ſudden they'l be in their prime.</l>
               <l>They think themſelves happy; eſpecially ſome,</l>
               <l>If <hi>Michaelmas</hi> rent and their dyet they earn,</l>
               <l>But now they are glad for their harveſt is conſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Country brings mony to Michaelmas Term.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Inholders, Vintners, Victualers, and Cooks</l>
               <l>through want of imployment make grievous complaint</l>
               <l>In all this long ſeaſon they were off o'th hooks,</l>
               <l>But now their red Lettiſe they do new paint,</l>
               <l>Some ſet up new ſignes or new floriſh the old,</l>
               <l>And mend their old houſes if they be infirm,</l>
               <l>To venture their many they dare well be he bold,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In hope to regain it in Michaelmas Term.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Lapſters Oſtlers, and Chamberlains all,</l>
               <l>Chiefly about <hi>Holborn, Fleet-ſtreet</hi> and the <hi>Strand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Since <hi>Trinity</hi> Term had takings but ſmall,</l>
               <l>VVhich caus'd many of them to run behind hand.</l>
               <l>But now they are jovial and take heart a grace,</l>
               <l>And both nimble geſtures and ſpéeches they learn,</l>
               <l>Their gains now come tumbling in a great pace,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Long time they have wiſhed for Michaelmas Term.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some Atturnies and ſome that ſolicite Law caſes,</l>
               <l>That all the Vacation in the Country plods,</l>
               <l>They like to king <hi>Janus</hi> can uſe double faces,</l>
               <l>And ſtrive to ſet Neighbour with Neighbour at ods,</l>
               <l>Now hither they come with their bags full of Law,</l>
               <l>But ſee profits they all to themſelves do confirm</l>
               <l>Although it be but for a Truſs of Rye ſtraw,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The caſe muſt be try'dat Michaelmas Term.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The rambling Clerks that for lodging and dyet</l>
               <l>Have run on the Ticket with Vitlers and Cooks,</l>
               <l>Beſides now and then for ſome overplus royot,</l>
               <l>Some of them have pawn'd their gowns &amp; their books</l>
               <l>O now they are froſtick and ſing care alway,</l>
               <l>For Country Clients about them do ſwarm,</l>
               <l>Now all their old ſcores they'l be able to pay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their hands are ſo nimble in Michaelmas Term.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The thire-penny Ordinaries are ſo full throng'd,</l>
               <l>That there you can ſcarce get one bit of meat,</l>
               <l>Your country men proudly do ſcorn to be wrong'd,</l>
               <l>And yet their own beſties they baſly will cheat.</l>
               <l>The Lawyers hands are ſtill itching for fées,</l>
               <l>VVhich makes the plain husbandman let out his farm</l>
               <l>To come up to <hi>London</hi> is eat bread and cheaſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>While Lawyers eat Roſt-meat in Michaelmas Term.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The ſecond Part,</head>
               <opener>To the ſame Tune.</opener>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe dainty fine Girls that keep ſhop in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Change</l>
                  <l>Against this quick ſeaſon have been exerciſ'd,</l>
                  <l>To furniſh their coſters with faſhions all ſtrange,</l>
                  <l>The fineſt and rareſt that can be devis'd,</l>
                  <l>They keep their old Ditty, <hi>Sir what is't you lack,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich Country people are gréedy to learn,</l>
                  <l>The husband muſt carry the wife ſome new knack</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Or elſe he's not welcome from Michaelmas Term.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The javial VVatermen trim up their Botes,</l>
                  <l>And to be more pliant in plying their ſares,</l>
                  <l>VVith ſtrong béer &amp; Ale they do licker their throats</l>
                  <l>For which they will wander to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Alehouſe by pairs</l>
                  <l>And if the froſt do not their labour prevent,</l>
                  <l>Abundance of mony they daily will earn,</l>
                  <l>VVhich in the vacation will freely be ſpent,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And then they will think upon Michaelmas Term.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The feather-héeld wenches that live by their own,</l>
                  <l>VVho long have béen néedy for want of good trading,</l>
                  <l>For when all the gallants are gone out o'th town,</l>
                  <l>Oh then theſe fine Pinaces lack their due lading:</l>
                  <l>Therefore the vocation they rue like the reſt,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe neither dyet nor cloathes they can earne,</l>
                  <l>But now the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'r in hope well to feather their neſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>They looke for good doings in Michaelmas Term.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Pick-pockets &amp; Cheaters with Knights of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Poſt,</l>
                  <l>Doe long for the Term-time like honeſter men,</l>
                  <l>VVhere concourſe of people is, they doe get moſt,</l>
                  <l>VVith rooking exploits which they uſe now &amp; then:</l>
                  <l>And yet if they chance to be got in the nick,</l>
                  <l>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hang-man next ſeſſions will teach them a charm</l>
                  <l>VVill cure their diſeaſe be they never ſo ſick,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh then will they think on Michaelmas Term.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Court and the City, the Country withall</l>
                  <l>If you will behold a part of all three,</l>
                  <l>Then come at this time to <hi>Weſtminſter-hall,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhere people from all parts aſſembled be:</l>
                  <l>And thus Ile conclude as at firſt I begun,</l>
                  <l>Experience all this for truth will confirm,</l>
                  <l>I hope I have given diſtaſte to no man</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For I bid them all welcome to Michaelmas Term.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed for <hi>F. Coles, T. Vere,</hi> and <hi>J. Wright.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
