<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd before the Lord Mayor, and the Court of Aldermen, at Guild-Hall Chappel, on the 28th of May, 1682 by John Moore ...</title>
            <author>Moore, John, 1646-1714.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-01">2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51227</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2552</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20127</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12354054</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12354054</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60078</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A51227)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60078)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 643:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd before the Lord Mayor, and the Court of Aldermen, at Guild-Hall Chappel, on the 28th of May, 1682 by John Moore ...</title>
                  <author>Moore, John, 1646-1714.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Timothy, 1st, VI, 3 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-06</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-06</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:60078:1"/>
            <head>MOORE MAJOR.</head>
            <p>Curia Specialis tent. die Lunae xxix<hi rend="sup">no.</hi> 
               <hi>Maii</hi> 1682. Anno<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Regni Regis <hi>Caroli</hi> Secundi <hi>Angl',</hi> &amp;c. xxxiiii<hi rend="sup">ta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Court doth deſire Dr. <hi>Moore</hi> to Print his Sermon Preached yeſterday at the <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> Chappel before the Lord Mayor and Aldermen of this City.</p>
            <signed>Wagſtaffe.</signed>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60078:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd before the Lord Mayor, AND THE Court of ALDERMEN AT GUILD-HALL <hi>Chappel,</hi> ON The 28th of <hi>May,</hi> 1682.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> JOHN MOORE, <hi>D. D.</hi> Chaplain to the Right Honorable <hi>Heneage</hi> Earl of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> Lord High Chancellor of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kittilby</hi> at the Biſhops Head in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:60078:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60078:2"/>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>To the Right Honorable Sir <hi>John Moore</hi> Lord Mayor, and the Court of Aldermen of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>London.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My LORD,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THE Meekneſs, Peace, and Charity, of which our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our was ſo Zealous a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, and ſo great an Example, ſeem to be in a manner loſt in the beats, bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and noiſe, with which men manage their Diſputes about his holy Religion: as if the Character of a true Chriſtian was to be taken rather from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiouſneſs of his Spirit, and his skill in Controverſy, than the Purity of his Mind and Converſation. When yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can bring a greater diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon Chriſtianity, and prove more fatal to the Profeſſors of it, than to make it the occaſion of thoſe Evils and Miſchiefs among Men, and of that diſturbance in the World, which God purpoſely intended it ſhould allay and extinguiſh.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:60078:3"/>It was my deſign in this Diſcourſe, which in obedience to your Commands, I now make Public, to take men off from their furious debates about <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> often, not material to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> earneſtly to preſs them unto the ex<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of thoſe Primitive Vertues, upon which our Religion has always laid ſo much ſtreſs, and which our Lord hath ſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared to be the indiſpenſable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of our Salvation: by ſhewing that all neceſſary Chriſtian Doctrines have a natural tendency to that Godlineſs, which is now too generally neglected. And I am the more bold to perfix your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips name to it; becauſe you are known to be ſo fair a Pattern of that Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Religion I recommend, both in your private life as a Chriſtian; and in your Public Capacity as a Magiſtrate.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>I am, My Lord, Your Lordſhips moſt humble and obedient Servant <hi>John Moore.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60078:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before the Lord Mayor, &amp;c. <hi>May</hi> 28. 1682.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1 TIM. VI.3.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And to the Doctrine which is according to Godlineſs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WHen we conſider there never was any Religion in the World, which did ſo earneſtly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, and ſo ſtrictly enjoyn Godlineſs, as the Chriſtian Religion has done, and yet that ſo little of it do's appear in the lives of Chriſtians, we muſt conclude, that there are either great defects in the Religion, or faults in the Profeſſors of it: we muſt: either ſay there is not a ſufficiency in the means
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60078:4"/>
Chriſtianity do's preſcribe and afford tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards the attainment of true Piety and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; or elſe that the blame is to be laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, who having undertaken the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Profeſſion, do neglect, or deſpiſe the means and inſtruments provided by their Religion to make them Holy here, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py for ever.</p>
            <p>And it will not be hard to determin on which ſide the fault lies; for God and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion have not been wanting to Men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but Men have been wanting to themſelves. There being nothing required in our Religion as our Duty, and a neceſſary Condition of our Happineſs, which is above our ſtrength aſſiſted with that Grace, which every one may obtaine who ſincerely prays to God for it. <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> S. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> m <hi>Joan.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Therefore <hi>if men will not make uſe of that Grace, which God ſo plentifully poures forth upon all, it is but fit and equal, that they impute their defects to themſelves.</hi> And few have had the boldneſs directly to charge their Vices upon God; as if he had denyed them power and opportunitys to have been better.</p>
            <p>They will lay their faults upon themſelves, but with ſome privat reſerves and Suggeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60078:4"/>
that thoſe faults are very pardonable ones; as being neither much offenſive to God, nor plainly repugnant to the ſtate of good men. So the Common way has been for men to frame ſuch a model of Religion to themſelves, as might ſute with a vitious life, and help to quiet the complaints of an uneaſy conſcience. Thus when Perſons are debauch'd in their morals,<note place="margin">Sed vitam qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem luxurio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam, ſententi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am autem im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piam ad vela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men malitiae ipſorum nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne abutuntur, S. <hi>Iren.</hi> p. <hi>122.</hi> Difficilè haeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum inveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri qui diligie caſtitatem, <hi>Hieron.</hi> in <hi>Oſeae</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> they are apt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to turn Hereticks in their Faith. It having been obſerved, that nothing is more uſual, than for men to ſhelter the Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous impiety of their lives, under ſome or as notoriouſly impious Opinion; and to depart as far in their belief from the true Doctrins of Chriſt; as they had before Stray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their practice from his Holy precepts.</p>
            <p>Thus ſome men have juſtified a wicked life, by denying the differences between Good and Evil; and others have excuſed it, by pretending all their actions are under a fatal decree, and come neceſſarily to paſs. Some again make the performance of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Gods Laws very needleſs, by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owning his providence and care of the World. Others would exempt themſelves from the ties of godlineſs and virtue by fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſying
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60078:5"/>
their Religion to conſiſt only in true believing: and others place it all in outward ſhew and Ceremony. Some again hope they may enjoy both the brutiſh pleaſures of this life and the pure ones of the next, and carry their ſins a long with them to Heaven, by ſo exalting and extending Gods mercy unto obſtinately Impenitent Sinners, as to deny both his Juſtice and Truth: and others cut the ſinews of Religion by calling in queſtion the Reſurrection of the Dead, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of the Life to come.</p>
            <p>So <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> that infamous Magici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and Founder of all the Hereſys which followed him, that he might ſerve his vain Glory and Ambition did covet the gifts of the Holy Ghoſt; and hoped to purchaſe them by Money;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Irenaei</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> he alſo boaſted that he himself was God; and appeared in <hi>Samaria</hi> as the Father, among the Jews as the Son, and to the Gentiles as the holy Spirit: he alſo deny'd that Man had any liberty of will; or that there was any necſſity of good Works,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iren.</hi> l. <hi>1</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> So the <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> for a cover to their abominable Luſts, taught there ought to be Community of Wives, and that to commit Fornication, and to eat meats offer'd
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60078:5"/>
to Idols were things indifferent. Thus <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nander</hi> and <hi>Marcion</hi> diſowned Gods being the maker of the World,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Juſtin Mart. Apol. 2.</hi> p. <hi>70.</hi>
               </note> aſcribing that work of Omnipotency to Angels. Thus al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>Himenaeus</hi> and <hi>Philetus</hi> denied the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
            <p>Some of theſe ungodly Men lived in the days of the Apoſtles, of whom St. <hi>Jude</hi> ſaies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jude</hi> v. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>they turned the grace of God into laſcivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs denying the only Lord God, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Now what in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church was the diſeaſe only of ſome few Men, ſeems in our unhappy age, to have been a plague, which has generally infected, and ſpread its malignity over the Face of the Chriſtian World.</p>
            <p>Great numbers in theſe times, as they have given themſelves up to the filthieſt of the vices among the Ancient Hereticks; ſo have they eſpouſed the worſt of their Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to defend them.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Cerinthus</hi> and <hi>Ebion</hi> of all the Books of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iren.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>26. Epiphan.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ. <hi>8, &amp; 10.</hi>
               </note> would only receive the Goſpel of St. <hi>Mathew</hi>; becauſe it was writ in <hi>Hebrew</hi>:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leviath.</hi> p. <hi>20<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </note> we have them who do affirm that the <hi>whole Bible derives</hi> all its Authority from the Civil Magiſtrate; and that it is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60078:6"/>
the legiſlative power of the Common w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> which giveth it the force of a Law,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Clem. Alex. Strom. 3. Epiphan. Haer. 7.</hi>
               </note>If <hi>Carpocrates</hi> declared that there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſimply and abſolutely good or evil in its ſelf, but only according to the opinion of Men, it is well known who has publiſht the very ſame Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiph. Haer. 24. &amp; 31.</hi>
               </note> If <hi>Baſilides</hi> and <hi>Valentinus</hi> contended for the lawfulneſs of the promiſcuous uſe of Women, and many wives; there is a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender to Reformation among us, who that he may give ſome Reputation to <hi>Baſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Moral Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age,</hi> lib. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>71.</hi>
               </note> and free it from that <hi>Illegitimation,</hi> which conſtantly the Chriſtian Church has fixt upon it, has in Print affirm'd, <hi>that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal knowledg between Perſons not prohibited by the moral Law, tho, without Contract, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, Wittneſſes or Miniſter, is a Marriage Lawful, Holy, and Indiſſoluble according to the Law of God.</hi> To advance which Aſſertion he has arraigned not only the Laws of our own Nation, but of the whole Chriſtian, and I may ſay, Pagan World too. And what well becomes the Publiſhers of falſe and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Opinions, he has managed his bad cauſe with great confidence of the Truth of it, and with as much contempt of all that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60078:6"/>
are of another mind;<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> there being ſcarce a profeſſion of men among us, whom he has not treated with diſreſpect and ill language: nay, he will not allow that the preſent Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel can produce any bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter evidence of their Divine Commiſſion, than thoſe who claim under <hi>Mahomet</hi>;<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>145.</hi>
               </note> and chargeth it as a Wickedneſs upon the <hi>Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators</hi> of the Bible, that in their falſe Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation only, the <hi>ſeventh Comandment</hi> does <hi>forbid Adultry,</hi> and the <hi>tenth</hi> the <hi>Coveting</hi> our <hi>Neighbours Wife.</hi> Now let the People ſee what a kind of Reformation they are to expect in Church and State, if ever the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of it fall into ſuch mens hands, who are daily complaning of the great want of it; and quarreling with every thing in the preſent Eſtabliſhment.</p>
            <p>If ſome hundred years ago there appeared in the World <hi>Evangelium Aeternum</hi> a Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous Book with a ſpecious Title,<note place="margin">Scriptum ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lae Pariſien. Edit <hi>Wolfang. Wiſſenburgh.</hi>
               </note> which pretended to be a far more perfect Goſpel than that of our Saviours; and that in leſs than fifty years it would cauſe it to be laid aſide; we have alſo a Goſpel collected out of the Works of a late Cardinal,<note place="margin">Cardinal <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lavicin.</hi>
               </note> the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trins whereof are as much according to the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60078:7"/>
fleſh and the luſts thereof, as thoſe of our Lords are according to Godlineſs. If there were falſe Apoſtles who would have tied the burden of Jewiſh Ceremonies about the necks of the firſt Chriſtians, are there not alſo at this day a conſiderable party of Men, who by ſuperadding a multitude of poſitive, unuſeful and Arbitrary Conſtitutions to Chriſtianity, have renderd it almoſt inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable. The Humility and the Devotion, the Patience and the Contentment, the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and the Contempt of the World, and the Forgiveneſs of Enemies and Injuries, which made the Primitive Chriſtians ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous among their very Perſecutors, being ſtifled and even buried under ſo much of pompous Dreſs and ſuperfluous Garniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Simon</hi> would have bought the Powers of the Holy Ghoſt, are there not now<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Men who ſell Pardons of Sin? inſomuch that if a Man have mony enough to anſwer for his Sins, and do not tranſgreſs beyond the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of his Eſtate, the preciſe rate is known at which he can certainly redeem his Iniquities.</p>
            <p>Nay, as if theſe times were the ſink in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60078:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
which the very dregs of all Hereſies had ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, it has in our days been Publiſht, (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the colour of Philoſophy) that the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of all things whatſoever is the ſame; in which Aſſertion God and his Creatures are confounded:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Spinoſae</hi> op. p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. p. <hi>398.</hi>
               </note> and that no Subſtance can produce another; the conſequence of which Propoſition is, that every Subſtance in the World is ſelf exiſtent and Independent. Blaſphemies ſurely never before broached among Chriſtians; and which are as falſe and abſurd in all Philoſophy, as they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to true Religion; and as much to be abhor'd for their impiety, as they are eaſy, to be confuted for their inconſiſtency with right reaſon.</p>
            <p>But now ſince there are ſo many Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Rocks upon which the Men of this Age are apt to Split themſelves, the great Queſtion will be by what compaſs we are to ſteer? to which we cannot give a better an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer than by propoſing and recommending to ſerious conſideration, this paſſage of St. <hi>Paul</hi> in our Text, which will prove an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual Rule, whereby to diſcern uſeful Chriſtian Doctrines from falſe and hurtful ones, <hi>viz.</hi> they muſt be <hi>according to Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:60078:8"/>
and that which gave occaſion to St. <hi>Paul</hi> to lay down this Rule, was the ſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Errors contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt, which had ſtolen into the Church in his days: all which he reproveth upon this account, that they were not according to Godlineſs. A liſt of ſome of theſe, we have in this <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle</hi> he giveth a Caution to <hi>Timothy</hi> not to give heed to fables and endleſs Genealogies, which migh miniſter Queſtions for witty Men to diſpute upon: but not edify in the Faith, nor promote Charity, which was the end of the Commandment,<note place="margin">V. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> He reflects upon ſome ſuch Men, as having made a ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rack of the Faith. He aſſureth him, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit had expreſly declared,<note place="margin">C. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that in the latter times ſome ſhould depart from the Faith, giving heed to ſeducing Spirits and Doctrines of Devils</hi> i.e. by the ſeducement of the Devil they would again revive the Pagan Religion of the worſhiping of <hi>Daemons.</hi>
               <note place="margin">C. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Again, St. <hi>Paul</hi> reprehends and confutes another pernicious Doctrine, which had found a welcome entertainment among Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants converted to the Faith, who by the craft of, false Teachers were eaſily led into a perſuaſion, that the Chriſtian Religion had
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60078:8"/>
diſſolved the Bonds they before ſtood in to their Maſters. For if their Maſters were In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels, then Chriſtian liberty was inſiſted upon, Chriſt having made them free from their yoke: but if they were believers, than Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an brotherhood was claimed, for Chriſtians are all brethern in Chriſt; and in Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Spiritual Relation, they preſumed themſelves to be on the ſame level with their Maſters.</p>
            <p>But to the firſt, St. <hi>Paul</hi> replies, that notwithſtanding their Maſters were yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>converted, they were to render them all due honour and ſervice, leaſt either by their haughty carriage, or diſobedience, the Name of God and the Doctrin of Chriſt ſhould be Blaſphemed; and to the others who had believing Maſters, his anſwer was, that they ſhould not deſpiſe them becauſe they are brethern; but rather do them ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; becauſe they are Faithful and beloved partakers of the Benefit: not only becauſe it was one Branch of Chriſtian Duty, for Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to be obedient to their Maſters; but becauſe their Maſters, whoſe tempers were ſoftned by the love which the Religion of Jeſus does inſpire, would treat them ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60078:9"/>
and kindly; and be glad of an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of being beneficial to them, and this is the Doctrine which is according to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">V. <hi>3, 4, 5.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>For if any man Teacheth otherwiſe: and conſent not to wholſom words, even the words of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and to the Doctrine which is according to godlines, he is proud knowing nothing, but doting about queſtions, and ſtrifes of words, whereof cometh envy, ſtrife, railings, evil ſurmiſings, perverſe deſputings of Men of Corrupt minds, deſtitute of the Truth, ſuppoſing that gain is godlineſs, from ſuch withdraw thy ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So dangerous a thing it is for a Chriſtian, more to buſy himſelf about Contentious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes; than the Rules of an holy Life; for a doting upon Queſtions may betray him into that wrath and envy, which ſhuts men out of the Kingdom of Heaven: but it muſt be a continual exerciſe of himſelf according to Godlineſs that will carry him thither. So true alſo is it, that neither the Spiritual re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Brotherhood between Chriſtians has destroy'd the ſeveral Orders, Ranks, and Qualitys of men in civil Societys; nor that Chriſtian liberty has taken away the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60078:9"/>
which is upon Servants to be obedient to their Maſters; and the Duty that is upon the People to be Subject to their Governors; this being part of the Doctrine which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Godlineſs.</p>
            <p>But to come to a further improvement of our Text, there are theſe five Propoſitions which ſeem very proper and natural to be inſiſted on from it, and which accordingly I ſhall make it my buſineſs to treat of in this Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) That Godlineſs is a fixt and certain thing, not variable according to places and times or the humors of men: but the reaſons of it are Eternal and Unchangeable.</p>
            <p n="2">(2) That the Scope and end of the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines of the Goſpel is to advance Godlineſs, and recommend the practice of it to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) That it is an Argument both of the Truth and Excellency of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that all the Doctrines thereof are Conformable to Godlineſs.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) That they who teach or perſwade men they may be ſaved by their true Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or ſound Belief, tho not accompanied with a Godly life, do defeat the very deſign
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60078:10"/>
of the Goſpel, and obſtruct that influence it ſhould have on the minds of men.</p>
            <p n="5">(5.) That whatſoever Doctrins are not according to Godlineſs, are ſo far from being neceſſary, that they cannot be true.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) That Godlineſs is a fixt and certain thing, not variable according to places and times or the humors of men. This is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent both from the Text, and the Reaſon of the thing; firſt of all, the Text plainly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plys it, St. <hi>Paul</hi> requires every man ſhould give conſent to the Doctrine which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Godlineſs. What can we gather from hence, but that according to him God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, muſt be the ſtandard and meaſure, by which men are to Judge of Doctrines? if a Doctrine be according to Godlineſs, he is to aſſent to it, if not according to Godlineſs, he is to diſſent from it.</p>
            <p>All men therefore muſt have one certain unvariable notion of Godlineſs in their minds; or elſe they can never know what Doctrines they are to embrace; and what to reject. But ſecondly, this do's more evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow from the notion of Godlineſs it ſelf: for Godlineſs is nothing elſe but a being like God, it is a Copying out in our minds
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60078:10"/>
and manners, all the perfections of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature, ſo far as we are capable.</p>
            <p>Now if thoſe qualitys and perfections in God be Eternal and unalterable, then cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the notion of Godlineſs in us muſt be ſo alſo. It is true, if we go to the criticiſm of the word, this term of Godlineſs is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times uſed in a ſtricter ſenſe, and imports no more then the worſhip of God properly ſo called; which conſiſts in our having juſt and worthy apprehenſions of God, and in rendring to him that Love, Thanks-giving, Honor and Adoration which is due to the Great Governor of the World, and our beſt Benefactor.</p>
            <p>But in the larger ſenſe of the word, and as it is here taken by the Apoſtle, Godlineſs is a Comprehenſion of all the Moral Virtues; and takes in not only acts of Religion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God; but thoſe of Righteouſneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our Neighbour, and of Sobriety with reſpect to our Selves.</p>
            <p>In a word, It is a walking ſutably to that Nature, and that Reaſon which God has given us, and for Gods ſake. Which notion of Godlineſs being admitted, it cannot poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be thought an Arbitrary thing; but
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60078:11"/>
muſt be eternal and immutable; as the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of mankind is, or rather as God is, who contrived that nature.</p>
            <p>We may talk what we pleaſe of the indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Good and Evil; but the more we think, the more we ſhall be convinced that there is an Eternal goodneſs and evil in things as they fall under a Moral Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Now ſome actions have an agreeableneſs with Gods holy Nature, and ſome an utter incongruity with it: and if his holy Nature is always the ſame eternal and unchangeable, then alſo will thoſe things be eternally good which have an agreement with this bleſſed Nature; and thoſe eternally evil which do vary from it; thus as to love and honour God, are acts moſt agreeable to his perfect Nature; ſo will it be eternally the duty of the Creature to pay them unto him; and it is a repugnancy in terms to ſuppoſe, God can command his Creatures to hate him; or to do the leaſt thing which is contrary to the rectitude of his Nature.</p>
            <p>Beſides there are ſuch eternal reſpects and relations between things, that ſome actions will be ever good and ſome evil. We cannot
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60078:11"/>
ſuppoſe a Benefactor; but we muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg that gratitude and thanks are his due. We cannot allow a perſon to be Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, but we muſt grant too, that no injury or hurt ought to be done unto him.</p>
            <p>How unreaſonable then is that Opinion, which makes the Civil Law of the Magiſtrate the only meaſure of Good and Evil? for ſhould the Magiſtrate forbid me to put up Prayers to God, would therefore the ſervice of God be Evil? or ſhould he Command me to kill my Father, would therefore Parricide be lawful?</p>
            <p>If ſo, then there are actions antecedently good to the Laws of the Magiſtrate, and dutys not alterable by them: in performance of which doth the Godly man exerciſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Day and Night.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They are</hi> (ſaies <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi>) (a) <hi>very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God who do thoſe things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Juſtin. Mart.</hi> dial cum <hi>Tryph. p. 263.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>which are in their own Nature <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally and Eternally good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) The Scope and end of the Doctrines of the Goſpel, is to advance Godlineſs, and to recommend the practice of it to Mankind; it being much truer of Chriſts Doctrines, what was ſaid of the <hi>Lacedaemonian</hi> Laws,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60078:12"/>
               <hi>That it is the property of them all,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nie. Cragins</hi> de Repub. <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedaem. p. 171.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>to inflame mens minds with the love of virtue, and to create a contempt of empty and ſenſual pleaſure.</hi> To this end all the Precepts of our Lord, all his great actions, and grievous ſufferings were directed. But for the further illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and proof of this point, give me leave to offer theſe three things to your Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) That not any of the Diſcourſes, or Sermons of our Saviour, were made upon Subjects purely ſpeculative. The Sermons he Preacht were to teach men to be humble, meek, pure, and peaceable; to bear reviling language patiently, and willingly to ſubmit to Perſecution for Righteouſneſs ſake; to put hypocriſy out of Countenance, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form ſuch notions in Religion as were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments
to real Piety, and upheld men in wicked life. And in this Courſe he was carefully follow'd by his Apoſtles, and thoſe who were joyned with them in planting his Religion.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Original of the Soul, whether it be immediately Created, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, or deriv'd from the Parents, and the manner of its Union with the body; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60078:12"/>
the orders, ranks, and numbers of the Angels, and how they converſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey their thoughts to each other; concerning the bounds, figure, and capacity of Heaven the Scholemen have written great Volums; but the Inſpired Writers have treated very ſparingly; becauſe an accurate skill in theſe nice ſpeculations, and much acquaintance with them, will not make us one jot the better men; ſince we may have our heads ful of theſe curious notions without advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing one ſtep nearer Heaven, and being in the leaſt degree<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> more acceptable to God.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) The revelation God has made of himſelf in Scripture is, ſuch, as moſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth to the promotion of Godlineſs, and of his great deſign of putting us upon the attainment of theſe qualifications which can only fit us for the Kingdom of Heaven, and are the neceſſary terms of our Salvation; for there we conſtantly find God to be ſet forth, as Juſt and Righteous in all his works, as pure and holy in all his ways: and as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warder only of them who love and fear him, and keep his Commandments.</p>
            <p>Nay, God is there pleaſed to aſcribe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60078:13"/>
to himſelf the paſſions of men, love, hatred, anger, revenge, hope, grief and repentance, not that theſe paſſions are properly in God, who is wholy free from the imperfections, which cauſe them in us but meerly in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion to the weakneſs of our Nature, and to help the ſlowneſs of our underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: to the end that what is there declared to be the object of Gods Love and Hatred, his Grief or Anger, might be the object of ours likewiſe; and more ſtrongly affect us. And as an Evidence of this we may Obſerve, that theſe paſſions hardly ever are attributed to God in Scripture, but to encourage Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue or diſcourage Vice. So true is it, that the ſeveral deſcriptions the Bible giveth us of God are accommodated to the Doctrine of Godlineſs, and do tend to the advancement of it.</p>
            <p>Now as this ſeems to be the only Reaſon why God has made ſome diſcovery of the Perfections of his bleſſed Nature unto us, that we ſhould profoundly reverence him and ſincerely love him, and Religiouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form our ſelves unto his Will; ſo if we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect to anſwer the ends of this glorious manifeſtation, God will declare at the day
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60078:13"/>
of Judgment, that he knows us not, as he has already declared we know not him;<note place="margin">St. <hi>John 1.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> v. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>he that ſaith he hath known him and keepeth not his Commandements is a liar, and the truth is not in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this Argument St. <hi>Baſil</hi> ſpeaks ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently, taking his occaſion from thoſe words of our Lord. I know my ſheep and am known of mine.<note place="margin">St. <hi>Baſil.</hi> hom. <hi>25.</hi> p. <hi>599.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>What do you mean by knowing? do you underſtand what Gods Eſſence is? or can you meaſure his greatneſs? no my ſheep know me, that is, they hear my Voice. See then by what means you may Arrive at the knowledg of God; it is by hearing his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and doing them, when you have heard them. The knowledg then of God conſiſts in the obſervation of his Commandments, not in a curious prying into the nature of his Eſſence, and the things above the World: not in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templations of Inviſible Beings; my Sheep know me, and I know Mine. It is enough for you to know you have a good Shepherd, who hath layd down his life for the Sheep. Let this then be the bounds of your knowledg of God. But the queſtions that concern the immenſity of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature are dangerous to him who puts them; and can never be penetrated into, by him
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60078:14"/>
who undertakes to anſwer them; the beſt cure for ſuch is ſilence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that knowledg and practice, how much ſoever they may differ in our notions of them, are in Chriſtian Religion but two terms importing the ſame matter. And as they who keep not the Commandments, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in a Scripture ſenſe, without a lie, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that they know God; ſo neither at the day of Judgment will Chriſt know them, who lived in diſobedience to the great laws of his Religion, and neglected the chief in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of their Duty. Inſomuch that to thoſe who <hi>have eaten and drank in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and heard him Preach in their Streets,</hi> and upon that ſcore only do claime a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of him, and an intereſt in his Death and Sufferings, he will reply, <hi>I tell ye, I know not whence you are, depart from me, all ye Workers of iniquity.</hi> Wherefore that man does but deceive himſelf, and will in the end certainly miſcarry, who diligently Sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches after Knowledg only that he may gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify a vain curioſity, and qualify himſelf to become an able Diſputant in Religion; for all our knowledg will avail us nothing, unleſs it have an influence upon our prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60078:14"/>
and prove ſerviceable to us in the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of our manners.</p>
            <p>In this State then of Imperfection, and tryal of our Obedience, we need to enquire no further after the Eſſence of God, and ſtudy the myſteries of his incomprehenſible Nature, then it may either ſerve to inſtruct us in ſuch Inſtances and Caſes as 'tis our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to imitate him, and be as conformable to him as we can; or furniſh us with Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that will give us courage to break through the difficulties and oppoſition that we may meet with in our Chriſtian Race, and miniſter Patience and Comfort to us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the bittereſt Perſecutions we ſhall ſuffer for the ſake of our Maſter, and becauſe we would not do violence to our Conſciences. Indeed in the life that will follow this, we ſhall ſee God as he is, and all the glories of the Divinity will lie open to our eys.</p>
            <p>Then in the Company of the whole Church Triumphant, of all the Saints and Angels, we ſhall ſtand round about the Throne, and for ever behold, ſearch into, admire, and adore the infinite wiſdom and goodneſs and Power of God; and with the higheſt tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of Love and joy, we ſhall bleſs and praiſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60078:15"/>
and magnify the Lamb, with whoſe blood all our defilements are waſht away, and our Robes made white; and by whoſe all-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful mediation we are admitted into the glorious preſence of God, and ſhall conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to all Eternity, as much as we are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to partake more and more of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perfections.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) There is no fundamental Doctrine of Chriſtianity, but an obligation naturally flows from it to ſome inſtance or other of a good Life.</p>
            <p>If the Doctrine be, that God is the maker of Heaven and Earth, does not an obligation from thence lve upon all his Creatures to Gratitude and Praiſe? if the Doctrine be, that God is the great Soveraign of the World, does not a duty plainly follow, that we his Subjects are to govern our ſelves by his Laws? does not the Doctrine of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Goodneſs make it our duty to love him and imitate him; and that of his irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtible Power to dread the giving him the leaſt offence, and to ſubmit our ſelves to his pleaſure? does not the Doctrine, that Truth is one of his Eſſential Attributes, make it our duty to believe him, and to depend
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60078:15"/>
upon his promiſes? does not the Doctrine of his unſearchable Wiſdome oblige us to give up our wills unto his, and to leave the Events of things to his wiſe Diſpoſal? does not the Doctrine of his Omnipreſence, his all ſeeing Eye engage us to have a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and awful regard of him, and to walk circumſpectly in all our paths?</p>
            <p>The Doctrine of Gods providence being concerned not only in our moſt weighty af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, but alſo extending even to thoſe ſmall things, of which we our ſelves take no thought, what powerful motives does it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford us againſt dejection, penſiveneſs of mind, and immoderate cares? the Doctrine of all things working together for the good of the faithful Servants of God, what a mighty obligation does it lay upon us to be contented and eaſy in our preſent condition, how much ſoever it may be beſet with adverſities and afflictions; and to take no indirect courſe, to uſe no unlawful me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod or meanes to get out of it? the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of Gods only having ſuch a power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our Souls that he can deſtroy them, how plainly does it imply, that we are to dread God more than man, and to diſobey man
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60078:16"/>
rather than God? The Doctrine of the neceſſity of the Sufferings and Paſſion of Chriſt, does it not make it our indiſpenſable duty to mortify the Fleſh and to crucify the Luſts thereof,<note place="margin">Heb. <hi>11.25.</hi>
               </note> and to prepare our ſelves <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſuffer Affliction with the people of God, than to enjoy the pleaſures of Sin for a Seaſon?</hi> and ſhould not the Doctrine of his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and Aſcention, carry our thoughts and great deſigns into the other World, and fix our Hearts and all our Affections upon the Treaſure which is in Heaven? In a word, does not the Doctrine of a day of Judgment, in which ſentence ſhall paſs upon all men for every Thought, Word, and Deed, Oblige us, if we have the leaſt love of our ſelves, and deſsire of our own eternal wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, to put our Accounts in exact Order, and to break off our Sins by a timely and ſincere Repentance?</p>
            <p>And this was the method generally of the Apoſtles; when they have delivered a Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, they preſently draw an Inference from it, which is in the nature of a Precept: and where they do not expreſs the Precept, it is ever imply'd, and eaſy thence to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded. <hi>Seeing all theſe things ſhall be diſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60078:16"/>
what manner of Perſons ought ye to be, in all holy Converſation and Godlineſs?</hi> i. e. if ye believe this Chriſtian Doctrine of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the World, your lives muſt come up to your Principle, and your faith be render'd effectual by the holineſs of your Converſation;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Joh. <hi>3.3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>every man that hath this hope in him, he purifyeth himſelf even as he is pure</hi>; do you hope to ſee God, it unqueſtionably followes, that you are to endeavour to be like him, by imitating his purity?<note place="margin">Col. <hi>3.1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>if ye then be Riſen with Chriſt ſeek thoſe things which are above,</hi> i. e. if ye believe Chriſts Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and as believers of it have been Baptized into a profeſſion of the Chriſtian Faith, then it becomes you to mind thoſe things which will procure your own Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection likewiſe.<note place="margin">C. <hi>2.</hi> v. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>As ye therefore have receiv'd Jeſus Chriſt the Lord, ſo walk ye in him</hi>; if ye have receiv'd the Doctrine of Jeſus Chriſt, let not your behaviour carry any thing in it unſutable to his holy Doctrine, but be ye mindful to Govern your ſelves by the Practical Rules therein contein'd.</p>
            <p>But againſt the point I am now upon, ſome will be apt to object, that one great Doctrine of our Religion, the myſtery of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60078:17"/>
holy <hi>Trinity,</hi> does not ſeem at all to concern a good life; now tho it may ſo ſeem to them who ſlightly examin things, yet thoſe who ſhall be at the pains more exactly to conſider this Doctrine will be otherwiſe perſwaded. For when we conſider God ſo loved the World as to ſend his only begotten ſon, to ſave all them from periſhing who ſhall believe on him, does not this lay the higheſt obligation upon us which is poſſible to make all the returns of praiſe, and love, and grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and obedience?</p>
            <p>When we conſider there was that averſion in the divine nature to ſin, that God would not pardon it before ample ſatisfaction was made at the Coſt of the blood and life of his own Son, can there be any argument in the World more effectual to deter a man from ſin, and if he have any ingenuity, to make him abhor the thoughts of it? when we conſider that this very ſame Son of God, who was the brightneſs of his Fathers glory, and expreſs image of his perſon, is now our high Preiſt, and has entered the holy of holies, and does daily offer up our prayers to God, and conſtantly there intercede with him on our behalf; will not this be apt to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60078:17"/>
create in us a mighty confidence to addreſs our ſelves to the throne of Heaven in all our wants, and ſtrong hopes that God will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver forſake us in diſtreſs?</p>
            <p>When we conſider the holy Spirit has conſecrated our bodies, and made them the Temples wherein he will vouchſafe to dwell, <note n="(a)" place="margin">Vid. Ruper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum de Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatione Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitat Lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> (which is the peculiar privilege and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Goſpel) is there not a deep engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereby laid upon us, to prepare theſe bodies for his reception, by keeping them pure from intemperance and filthy Luſts for fear we greive this holy gueſt, and cauſe him to deſert ſuch unclean habitations, and vex him that he turn to be our enemy?</p>
            <p>And ſo I hope the ſenſe of the 2d. Point is cleared, and the truth of it eſtabliſht, that it is the deſign of the Doctrines of the Goſpel to advance Godlineſs, and that there is an apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and direct tendency in them all to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the practice of it upon Chriſtians, this notion the Ancients had of Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on when they <hi>ſtiled</hi> it <hi>an</hi> 
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>inſtitution accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Godlineſs</hi> 
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Euſeb.</hi> de m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. Evang. <hi>P. 12. &amp; 24.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and an inſtitution that comprehends all virtue</hi>; and accordingly the firſt Chriſtians (as <hi>Minut. Felix</hi> obſerves) <note n="(d)" place="margin">Non tam notaculo Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris guam mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtiae<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentiae. ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no. <hi>Min. Fe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>were diſtinguiſht from other men not by any
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60078:18"/>
thing peculiar in their habit and dreſs; but by their innocence and modeſty.</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Nec aliunde noſcibiles quam de emendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one vitiorum Priſtinorum, <hi>Tertul.</hi> ad <hi>Scapulam</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>There was no other mark of a new convert, but his having forſaken his old vices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">(3.) It is an Argument both of the Truth and excellency of the Chriſtian Religion, that the Doctrines of it are according to Godlineſs. Godlineſs (as we have ſhewn) is the ſum of the duties of natural Religion: and what duty is there in natural Religion, but in the code of the Royal Chriſtian Law it is more clearly propounded, more fully explained, more ſtrongly confirm'd?</p>
            <p>Now what greater Argument is there for the truth of the Doctrines of any Religion, than their agreeableneſs to the common ſentiments of mankind? or what more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt proof of the excellency of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of it, than their harmony with the Laws of Nature? for the moſt material ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections againſt any Inſtituted Religion, are either that its Principles are contradictory to clear Reaſon, or its Duties repugnant to Natural Laws. Since thoſe Principles can not be true which contradict right Reaſon, nor thoſe Precepts good which are repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Laws of Nature.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:60078:18"/>For if we cannot be certain of the truth of thoſe things, for which there is plain and manifeſt Reaſon, we cannot be certain of the truth of any thing; and it muſt be granted, that natural Religion is the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation upon which all revealed Religion does ſtand; becauſe from natural Light is fetcht the proof of the Exiſtence of God, which revealed Religion does always ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>Now there is nothing commanded in our Religion but what becomes the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Divine Nature, and agrees with thoſe Eternal Laws which flow from it: there is nothing required of us but what ſutes with the Native Principles of our own Souls, and our trueſt Intereſt: there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing propounded in our Religion, as a point of Faith, but we have ſufficient Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to believe it; there is nothing exacted as a Duty, but we have exceeding good motives to doe it. We may find the great duties of our Religion all writ upon our own Nature. And it was well ſaid by <hi>Trithemius</hi> in his Anſwer to <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Emperor. <note n="(a)" place="margin">Etſi Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiana Religio inter omnium Mortalium ſectas naturae legibus vicini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, &amp; magis con<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>s ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; prox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ima, &amp;. <hi>Joan. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>ithem.</hi> Praefat. lib. Octo quaeſtion.</note> 
               <hi>That of all the Sects and Religions in the World, none approach'd ſo near to the Laws of Nature,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60078:19"/>
nor were ſo conformable to them as the Chriſtian Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is there any thing that will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute ſo much towards the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our natural capacities, as a life con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the Laws of our Religion; ſince as God deſigned Religion to advance our nature, and make us more nearly reſemble him; ſo prophaneſs and irreligion ſet God and us at the greateſt concievable diſtance, and turn man, upon whom the divine Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age was ſtampt, into the ſhape of the Devil or of the beaſt that Periſh.</p>
            <p>Thus ſhould you ſuppoſe the contray of every Chriſtian Law enacted, that inſted of forgiving Enemys, reconciling our ſelves to our adverſarys, and ſhewing mercy to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed, we ſhould be commanded to revenge every little injury unto Death, to be impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cably malitious where we have had a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, and cruel even to extremity with the poor and unfortunate, would not mankind be chang'd into a race of Wolves and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, ſhall I ſay, or become a new order of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils incarnate?</p>
            <p>And ſuppoſe alſo that we were injoyned to be falſe to our words, unjuſt in our deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60078:19"/>
treacherous to our truſt, would not all civil ſocieties be diſolv'd? all commerce de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd? and the World become a great den of Thievs and Robbers? if it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us to eat always to gluttony and to drink to exceſs, would the effect of our obedience be any other, than the ſpoiling our health, the beſotting our rational facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and the transforming the Children of Men into a Herd of Swine?</p>
            <p>So little reaſon have we to complain of the Commandments of God as either diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, or grievious, when it is evident, that were we to receive laws in the matter and all the circumſtances of them contrary to thoſe with which God now Governs the World, we ſhould cry out of our duty as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable, and ſink under our burdens as not being able to bear them.</p>
            <p>And ſo much cauſe is there to bleſs God for ruling the World by Righteous Laws and having given us a Religion, which our own faculties being judges, and we truſt and rely upon in all other Caſes, is moſt reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and excellent; As being perfective of our nature, and Worthy of the wiſdom of God who contrived it, as being framed with great Condeſcention to the infirmities
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60078:20"/>
of man, and carrying a plaine conformity in it to the attributes of God.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) That they who Teach and Perſwade Men they may be Saved by their true Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or ſound Beleif, tho not Accompanied with a Godly life, do defeat the very deſign of the Goſpel and Obſtruct that Influence it ſhould have on the minds of men.</p>
            <p>Chriſtianity is a Covenant wherein as God has obliged himſelf to beſtow rewards, ſo he has bound man too, to yield Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. How abſurd then is their opinion who think a Covenant does not bind on both ſides, how hurtful is their miſtake who teach Chriſtians, there is no ſervice required on their part in this new Covenant? what ground or colour could there be to think the Religion inſtituted by Jeſus ſhould conſiſt in the beleif only of a ſet of Propoſitions, without intermedling in the affairs of Life, and the Government of our will and affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, when all his Sermons were ſo many Lectures upon virtue, and at the laſt day he will judg us by our Works? when he has Eſtabliſht ſo many rules for the ordering of our thoughts, words, and actions in every Condition; and required a ſincere, though
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60078:20"/>
not a Perfect obſervance of them all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We are Commanded to Watch and Pray, to fight the good ſight of Faith, to ſtrive that we may enter in at the ſtrait Gate, to work out our own Salvation with fear and trembling, to run that we may obtain, and to take the Kingdom of Heaven by Violence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Phraſes contain a Diſcription of the Dutys of a Chriſtian, and the degrees where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are required of him. They ſhew he is to work as well as believe; and that what he does muſt be withal his might, and with as much perfection as he can? his Life muſt be Productive of much, and the beſt fruits; the nature of his Chriſtian Inploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment does make it Neceſſary, that he purſue it with great Intention of Mind and Earneſtneſs of will, and that he put to all his Strength. The Chriſtians duty is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented under the Metaphor of a Race to convince him, that he muſt ſtrip and free himſelf of whatever does Clogg or Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then him, and uſe his utmoſt Speed, and not Slacken his pace till he has obteined, that is, till he comes to the end of the Race and his Life. his Duty alſo is expreſt by a narrow Way, and ſtrait Gate, to ſhew that his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60078:21"/>
is attended with great difficulties, and that they are only to be broke through by Zealous Contention; he that will enter muſt ſtrive. The reward indeed which is propoſed to Chriſtians is very tempting, and of moſt ineſtimable Value; it is a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; but he that ſets himſelf to reſt, and folds his hands ſhall never be the better for it: for that Kingdom ſhall only be taken and poſſeſt by them who violently invade it.</p>
            <p>Nothing can be perform'd without Gods aſſiſtance who works in men to will and to do; but then it is only in thoſe who Concur with him, and do work out their own Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation with Care and Concernment, with fear and trembling. Chriſt has purchaſed for us a liberty, as to Places and Times, as to the choice and difference of meats: but not a liberty to omit our Duty, or do the leaſt ſin, he has freed our ſhoulders from the burden of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law: but not diſcharged our obligation to any one Moral Virtue, or Law of nature. The Faith that will carry a man to Heaven muſt be a Faith that Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by love; and love is the keeping the Commandments.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:60078:21"/>So the holy Scripture declares, ſo the Primitive Fathers taught.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> makes Faith and Love the whole Duty of a Chriſtian; <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Ignat. Ep.</hi> ad <hi>Epheſ.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Faith the beginning, Love the end</hi>; <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Faith the guide, Love the way:</hi> and he hardly ever recommends the one but in the Company of the other. <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Clem, Alex. Strom.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>384.</hi> Credam, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gam Demn <hi>&amp;</hi> proximum, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi caetera non ſunt neceſſaria; <hi>Tertul.</hi> de jejun. c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Faith preceeds, Fear builds, Love makes perfect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">(5) That whatſoever Doctrines are not according to Godlineſs, are ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neceſſary, that they cannot be true. For if it be the Scope and End of the Goſpel to advance Godlineſs; and that it is an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument both of the Credebility and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of it, that it does ſo, as I have before prov'd, then it plainly follows, if we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Doctrine of the Goſpel to be a true Doctrine, that all ſuch Opinions as are either contrary to the Godlineſs, or do diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the intereſts of it, can neither be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Doctrines, nor true ones.</p>
            <p>Seeing then the truth of this Propoſition is evident from the foregoing diſcourſe; I ſhall only now make it my buſineſs briefly to reflect on ſome of the many ill opinions, which tho they have been taught for ſound
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60078:22"/>
and Orthodox; yet, upon examination, will appear not to be according to Godlineſs.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) The firſt I take notice of is that, of Gods being the Author of Sin, <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <p>That God is the Author not of thoſe actions alone, in and with which ſin is, but of the very Pravity, Ataxie, Anomie, Irregularity, and Sinfulneſs it ſelf, which is in them; yea, that God hath more hand in mens ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs than they themſelves. <hi>Archer</hi>'s Comfort for Believers, p. <hi>36, 37. vid.</hi> Dr. <hi>Pierce</hi>'s Preface to his Diſcourſe of the Nature of Sin.</p>
                  <p>Neither do I ſee how Dr. <hi>Twiſs</hi> can be excuſed from this Imputation: his words are theſe. Fatemur Deum non modo ipſius operis <hi>Peccaminoſi;</hi> ſed Intentionis <hi>malae</hi> Authorem eſſe, <hi>&amp;c. Twiſs Vindicat. Gratiae,</hi> p. <hi>36.</hi> Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Deus Praeſcit fore, illa voluit <hi>&amp;</hi> decrevit, at Peccatum Praeſeit ſore, ergo Peccatum voluit <hi>&amp;</hi> decrevit. <hi>Joan. Maccovii</hi> Colleg. de Praedeſim. p. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Et certe hec <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>mmos Tre<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>gos quoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, precipu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Piſcatorem &amp; <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>ſum</hi> cò adduxit, ut Naturam permiſſionis Dei conſiderantes, non ſo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Deum <hi>peccatum veile</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atuerint<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> verum e<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em aliqui eorum <hi>durioribus Phraſibus</hi> quoad Communem Opinionum, <hi>veriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimis</hi> tamen uſi ſint: nimirum Deum <hi>Peccato indigere,</hi> ſive <hi>opus habere</hi> ex hypotheſi decreti illuſtratonis Gloriae <hi>&amp;</hi> Manifeſtationis Miſericordiae <hi>&amp;</hi> juſt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae ſitae, <hi>&amp;c. Joan. Szydlovii</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. queſtion. p. <hi>128.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> which has been expreſly maintained by ſome men. Now it is not poſſible that Opinion ſhould be true, which is incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the Reaſon of mankind, or manifeſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the Attributes of God: for all Controverſies in Religion muſt be decided by Reaſon, either from the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Natural Religion, or Divine Revelation; and from the Principles of Natural Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion it is evident that there can be nothing in a Religion which comes from God, that is repugnant to his Eſſential Attributes, that is, to himſelf.</p>
            <p>Now that God ſhould be the Author of Sin, that is the Author of what does offend and diſhonour him, is very abſurd and unreaſonable, that he ſhould be Author of that which he has ſo often and ſolemnly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60078:22"/>
he does abhor and deteſt thwarts with the attribute of his truth: and that he ſhould be the efficient cauſe of all the wickedneſs, which is done, and he will ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely Puniſh, is a groſs repugnancy not only to his infinite goodneſs, but his juſtice it ſelf, Such Opinions as theſe deprive God of the holineſs eſſential to his Nature; and <note n="(g)" place="margin">In Precati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>embus <hi>DI.</hi> plerum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſancti appella<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>P. Merulae Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> in E<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Fragment. p. <hi>106. Eriſſonii</hi> ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul. lib. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> which even by the Gentiles unaſſiſted with the light of the Goſpel in their <hi>Praiers</hi> and <hi>Devotions</hi> was <hi>conſtantly aſcribed</hi> to <hi>him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) The Doctrine of irreſpective decrees cannot be according to Godlineſs; becauſe it takes away the ground of all the motives to a Godly Life. For if a man be included within the decree of Election, the greateſt ſins will not Damn him; and if he be left out of it, the moſt holy Life cannot put him in a capacity of Salvation.</p>
            <p>Again, if God has decreed to ſave or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate men without regard had to either their good or evil Lives, then they will be ſaved or loſt without any reſpect had of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for what God has decreed, that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly will come to paſs; but to ſay that Men ſhall have ſentence paſs upon them to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60078:23"/>
go either to Heaven or Hell, without any conſideration of their Faith and Obedience on one hand, or their infidelity and impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence on the other, is to make a day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unneceſſary; and repugnant to that juſtice according to which God has declared he will then proceed. <hi>We muſt all appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the judgment of Chriſt, that every one may receive the things done in his Body according to that he hath done, whether it be good or bad.</hi> 2 Cor. 5.10.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) Among theſe ill Opinions we may rank that of the Popiſh Caſuiſts, who teach that the <note n="(a)" place="margin">Et illam ample<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>luntur non ignobiles Magiſtri at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Doctores, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do Deſendunt, Praeceptum Charitatis, per ſe, tantum ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligare in Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo mortis. <hi>Amadaei Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menii Opuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cul.</hi> p. <hi>119.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>precept</hi> of <hi>loving God,</hi> is in it ſelf <hi>only Obligatory</hi> at the very <hi>point of Death,</hi> altho we be always under the protection of Gods unwearied Providence, and do every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that we breath receive good at his hand; tho there is no day of our Lives but we offend, and ſtand in freſh need of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; yet theſe Licentious Caſuiſts, to ſay no worſe of 'em, are of opinion, that it is a <note n="(b)" place="margin">Putat <hi>Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques</hi> ſuſſicere, ſi diligamus <hi>Deum</hi> in ſine vitae. <hi>Eſcobar. Theol. Mo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al.</hi> p. <hi>63.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſufficient</hi> return of Gratitude to God, for the infinite and unſpeakable Acts of his love to us, if in the <hi>end of our Lives</hi> we expreſs one act of <hi>Love</hi> towards him. But there needs no other Confutation in this Auditory of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60078:23"/>
an Opinion ſo impious, and directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the firſt and greateſt Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Evangelical Law, than the bare reherſal of it.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) Another Doctrine to be reflected up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is that, which Teaches and Directs us to the uſe of ſuch Means for the promotion of Chriſtian Religion, as are deſtructive of the ends of it. The end of Chriſtian Religion is to make men ſincere in what they profeſs, true to their word, and upright in their dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings; and therefore they who by lying and perjury, equivocation and reſerves, endeavor to propagate the Religion of our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior, do by the means they uſe, ſubvert the end they pretend to ſerve. The deſign of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion is to teach men Peace and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to all lawful Authority, therefore they who would inſtil Principles of Sedition and Rebellion, in order to the work of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, do defile and corrupt that pure Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which they make ſuch a ſhew of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming.</p>
            <p>The end of Chriſtian Religion is to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der men harmleſs, kind and Charitable one to another, therefore they who Condemn mens bodies to the ſtake and fire, in order
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:60078:24"/>
to refine their Minds? and cut their Throats, to ſave their Souls, inſtead of doing ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to the inſtitution of Chriſt, they bring the utmoſt ſlander and diſgrace upon it, that poſſibly they can. No we muſt not doe evil that good may come of it, we may not make uſe of unlawful means, to bring about an honeſt end. God in no Caſe will allow it; neither can true Religion ever be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſuch extremity, as to ſtand in need of it.</p>
            <p>But the time not allowing, that I ſhould further purſue this point, or take any more of the Doctrines into conſideration, which are not according to Godlineſs: I ſhall beg leave to conclude the whole diſcourſe, with ſome application of it to our ſelves, and the unhappy times, into which we are fallen; times wherein ſo many Errors in Faith; ſo many vices in Practice have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed contrary to the Doctrine of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>And what Guide can we take; what Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod may we uſe, to rectifie our Judgments, and recover our virtue? to remove our preſent evils; and to avert the calamities we all fear? it will be in vain to ſearch for
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60078:24"/>
the cauſes, or the cures of our miſeries in the Politics, or among the Stars: when they are, in great Part, lodged within our own breſts, and there to be found.</p>
            <p>Nations and Kingdoms have their growths and declenſions, their riſe and their periods, as well as particular Perſons: but with this difference, that they never waſte and decline before the temperance, and the modeſty, and the innocence, and the honeſty of their Inhabitants have firſt ſo done.</p>
            <p>When an univerſal corruption has over-ſpread the manners of a Nation, then the diſeaſe will come to a dangerous <hi>Criſis</hi>; its Condition will be deſperate, and ſuch as all wiſe and good men muſt deplore: not only the Reputation, Fame, and Glory thereof will be much obſcur'd; but the very life and being of it will be highly endanger'd.</p>
            <p>When a long Cuſtom of ſinning, has ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from men the very ſenſe of their guilt; and they are ſo deeply enſlaved to their Luſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as to be in love with the fetters that confine them; when the diſtemper has prevailed ſo much upon the vital parts, that no deſire longer remains in the Patient of Recovering,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60078:25"/>
then all hopes will be paſt, unleſs a ſpeedy Remedy can be apply'd.</p>
            <p>And this Remedy every man by the grace of God has in his own power; which is by repentance to turn from the evil of his ways; and without all further delay to make haſt to keep Gods Commandments: this is the only Courſe, whereby he may ſave himſelf; and do as much, as in him lies, to preſerve his Country.</p>
            <p>For it is neither force of Armes, nor a multitude of Laws, that without a thoro re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in the Lives of Men can recover a ſick and languiſhing Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Now if every one would be as Zealouly concern'd, and as really painful and labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to approve himſelf to God by a Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious performance of all the unqueſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Conditions which are required to make a man a true Chriſtian, as he is to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend himſelf to his own party; there would ſoon be leſs faction and turbulency, and more love and Religion among us: and we ſhould not thus be divided and ſubdivided into ſuch a number of little Sects, who ought all to be cloſely united in one body for the defence of our Reform'd Religion againſt the common Enemy.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:60078:25"/>If inſted of being ſo apt to cenſure or miſrepreſent the deſigns and actions of our Governors, which we ſeldom fully know, and often quite miſtake, and by which means their hearts are hardned againſt, and their affections eſtranged from the People; and the juſt Reverence which the People owes them loſt, or abated; and ſo the management of Public affairs render'd in a manner unpracticable; every man would do his part to promote Peace, and Virtue, and the cheriſhing a good underſtanding among us, what a turn would this make in the condition of things? what a viſible ſtop would this put to our growing fears and jealouſies? and our Ears would no more be grated with terrifying ſtories, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, after men were once earneſtly buſy in procuring the Public good and quiet?</p>
            <p>If inſted of inventing names to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, and beſpatter men; and then ſpight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully faſtning them one upon another: if inſtead of narrowly prying into the faults of others; and the ſeeing them all double, or repreſenting them as great again as they are; it being too common to charge the things done ignorantly
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60078:26"/>
upon men as their wilful crimes; to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prit their meer miſtakes for acts of malice; and to add ſomething of our own to every bad report of 'em.</p>
            <p>If inſtead of raking in every kennel to find proper Materials to blacken and vilifie each other, by which means an Infinite Scandal is caſt upon that pure and peaceable Religion we profeſs, and the powerful effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of its Doctrins hindred, not only among our ſelves, but among Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels (as has been <note n="(a)" rend="inter">Verum nihil plane majori eſt impedimento, quam noſtratium Chriſtianorum (quos Ethnicis prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucere ad omnem juſtitiam ac Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitatem oportuerat) tauto Nomini ac Profeſſioni minimè conſentanea quotidianae vitae documenta: ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> enim tantum ſpectata Paucorum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentia <hi>&amp;</hi> virtus adſtruit Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelio fidem; quantum inſignis mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum, <hi>&amp;</hi> notiſſimi ferè cujuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritia <hi>&amp;</hi> improbitas admit. <hi>P. Maf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fei</hi> Hiſt. Indic. lib. <hi>6.</hi> p. <hi>276.</hi>
               </note> often ſadly complained of by thoſe who have endeavoured their Converſion) we would all take a True and Faithful ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vay of our own Condition: and heartily beg the Pardon of God and our Neighbour for all the injuries we ſhall find, we have done to both: and alſo humbly implore Gods Grace, and Joyn to it our earneſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, that in the time to come, our Faith may be ſound, and our manners pure; theſe changes would prove the beſt <hi>Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents,</hi> to recal that Tranquility and Peace, all that love and reſpect, all that good will,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60078:26"/>
mutual truſt and confidence, which at any time heretofore our proſperous Nation has been bleſt withal; and I am ſure <hi>no others without theſe</hi> can.</p>
            <p>How often has God in a Fatherly way admoniſht us, that he might not ſmight us? how often has he given us ſome ſlight wounds, to the end we might avoid the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſtrokes of his juſtice? how often has h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> laid his gentle Chaſtiſements upon us, that we might take care to eſcape being buried under the ruins which his terrible judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are wont to bring upon a Kingdom?</p>
            <p>And ſhall none of the various methods God has uſed work a change, and real a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment in us? ſhall the mighty things he has done for us, and the tender care he has ever had of us be all in vain?</p>
            <p>If neither his clemency will invite us to conſider, nor his ſeverity awaken us out of our ungrounded ſecurity it muſt prove fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to us. May then the threatning dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers affright and perſwade us; may the multitude of the Divine Mercies allure us; may the ſecret motions of the Holy Spirit excite us to ſeek the Lord while he may be found, before the acceptable time paſs away; and his injured and long abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:60078:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
patience change into implacable fury.</p>
            <p>May that Zeal we bear for the beſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and a Church purely Reform'd, and of all others coming neareſt to the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Pattern, which ſo extremly ſuffers by ſo general a decay of Piety, and the increaſe of Schiſms, and Parties, and Factions; may the love we bear to our Country, whoſe overthro is threatned by the wickedneſs of its Inhabitants; may the care of our own Souls, which will everlaſtingly periſh, if we do not every one truly Repent, prevail up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us to return unto God, and our Duty.</p>
            <p>In a word, may all theſe Conſiderations together prevail upon us forthwith to take up firm and ſteddy reſolutions to conform our own wills, in all things, unto the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Will; to govern our thoughts and deeds by the laws and example of our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Savior; to ſubdue every luſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly paſſion, and to make us ſtrictly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe never again, to do any thing to to the diſhonor of the great God that made us, tho in the ſmalleſt inſtance; and where we are ſtrongly tempted to it by the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs either of the profit or danger.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
