<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>More haste than good speed, or, The Devil's got a horse-back being a winding-sheet for weathercocks and the turn-coats of the times : with the tryal of the Lord Kill-devil ... with divers others, and the arraignment and conviction of several malefactors.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2006-06">2006-06 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51341</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2703A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31039</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11766907</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11766907</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48780</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A51341)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48780)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1489:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>More haste than good speed, or, The Devil's got a horse-back being a winding-sheet for weathercocks and the turn-coats of the times : with the tryal of the Lord Kill-devil ... with divers others, and the arraignment and conviction of several malefactors.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for G. Tompson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLIX [1659]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print showthrough with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Anecdotes</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-03</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-03</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48780:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48780:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>More Haſte, than good Speed;</hi> OR, The <hi>Devil's</hi> got a Horſe-back: BEING A Winding-Sheet FOR <hi>Weather-Cocks,</hi> and the <hi>Turn-Coats</hi> of the <hi>Times.</hi> With the <hi>Tryal</hi> of the Lord <hi>Kill-Devil,</hi> the Lord <hi>Never-be-good,</hi> Sir <hi>William Slaſh,</hi> the Lady <hi>Hoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> Mris. <hi>Tittle-Tattle,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Bridget Boldface,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Anne Ever-croſs,</hi> Mirs. <hi>Rachel Rattle-booby,</hi> Deputy <hi>Tell-Money,</hi> and Money-bag the Uſurer. With divers others; And the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignment and Conviction of ſeveral Malefactors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>G. TOMPSON,</hi> MDCLIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:48780:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:48780:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>More Haſte, than Good Speed;</hi> OR, The Devil's got a Horſe-back: BEING A <hi>Winding-Sheet</hi> for <hi>Weather-cocks,</hi> and the <hi>Turn-Coats</hi> of the <hi>Times.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HE that ſayls by the Compaſs of a Conſcience, not toucht by a good Spirit, will undoubtedly erre in ſteering his courſe out of this Tranſitory Orb, and ſplit his Soul on the Rock of aſpiring Honour: Better is it therefore to frame and faſhion his life, according to an exact and perfect <hi>Idea</hi> of Virtue, than (like the Ape) attire himſelf by the fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Glaſſes of others Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, as too many do in theſe Rolling Times; witneſs Madam <hi>Spot,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Paint,</hi> the Lord <hi>Gallant,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Hopabout,</hi> Sir <hi>William Spruce,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Flaſh.</hi> Theſe are them that drink down golden Bolls of Nectar at coſtly Banquets, whileſt many poor Souls lie ſtarving in the ſtreets. Theſe are ſuch who cloath themſelves in ſilk and Sattin, and golden cloth of Tiſſue, and often ride on poor mens backs, as well as in their golden Coaches. Let ſuch know, that when all is done, the Bell muſt toll, and they muſt dance to Death's pipe, who are now ſinging like ſo many Nightingales, their new inchanting Tunes, and Syrian Songs; and with the Rich man deſire to live for ever: Who abounding in wealth every day living in ryot, and following his own delight and pleaſure, that he became ſo careleſs of Religion, Chriſtian piety, and eternal ſalvation, that he did not ſtick to ſay, if he might al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways live ſo here upon Earth, he would never envy God in the fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Heaven. Shortly after (before he was aware) he died. After his death, every day in the Evening ſuch ſtrange Apparitions were ſeen in his ſtately houſes, that every body left them, and no body durſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48780:3"/>
them. This rich Epicure appeared with his gueſts in the Dining Room, which he had divided for his Delicecies and Dainties; that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants ſtood by giving attendance with Light in their hands, ſetting on golden Cups and Veſſels upon the Table, and filling it with moſt gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Diſhes: the Fidlers moreover, and Muſicians were ſtanding by, &amp; no gallantry was wanting, that this rich man uſually enjoyed, when he was alive. By Gods permiſſion and the operation of the Devil, theſe ſpectrals were obvious to the eyes of men, that others might be terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied from that horrid impiety and ungodlineſs of the <hi>Epicureans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider therefore, O ye ſinful fading flowers of <hi>England</hi> That as on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſheet ſhall wind you up at your Death, ſo let this be your Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding-ſheet till you die; That great will be your gain, if you hearken to the ſilver voyce of the Turtle Dove and Goſpel-Harmony in time: for the groans &amp; ſighs of dying Lords and Ladies, as well as Back-ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from the Truth, are many times very ſad and dolorous; but the groans, ſigns and tears of a damned Creature, can never be imagined. The licentious living of many Weathercocks in <hi>England</hi> (for ſo they may be juſtly termed) running out of one Diſpenſation into another, denying the true Church and holding a Deteſtation of the Miniſtry &amp; at laſt falling off from ſomthing are extinguiſh'd into Nothing, which hath cauſed the Divel to take footing, &amp; to walk ſtep by ſtep amongſt them: To demonſtrate which, appears by the Satanical Deluſions of divers Quakers in ſeveral parts; eſpecially in the Weſt of <hi>England,</hi> where many practiſe ſundry abominable Diabolical Sorceries and Witchcrafts: amongſt the reſt, a poor Maid in <hi>Dorſetſhire</hi> being enſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by them, the Devil became prevalent, and made a Contract with her, ſhewing her variety of ſtately Riches and Treaſure, and promiſing her, if ſhe would lye with him, the choice of all, or any thing the world could afford.</p>
            <p>Which ſhe aſſenting to, and afterwards imparting the ſame to a Miniſter, the Devil told her he would torment her, and the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning her skin was full of black and blew pimples, being exceedingly full of anguiſh: inſomuch, that ſome godly Miniſters frequenting her one of them took her by the hand, at which time the Devil held her by the other, as ſhe ſaid; but inviſible to this worthy Divine, although viſible to the poor poſſeſſed Soul; who its hoped, may be brought off, from her deplorable ſtate and condition, all poſſible means being uſed by ſeveral Learned Divines.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:48780:3"/>
To this we ſhall add the Diabolical practiſes of ſome others about <hi>Wrexam</hi> in <hi>Northwales,</hi> who endeavouring to draw off ſome people to their wicked phantaſms, the Devil appeared in the ſhape of a tall black Gentleman, who calling to one <hi>Peter Ramſey</hi> (a conſtant hearer of the Word) ſhewed him through a Criſtal, abundance of Riches &amp; Treaſure, and told him if he would go along with him, he ſhould not want for any thing. <hi>No,</hi> ſaid <hi>Peter, If thou want Company, go to Hell; for I have a better Maſter: the Treaſures of the Word of God, doth far exceed the Riches of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereupon the Devil being mounted a Cock-horſe, ſeem'd to ſet ſpurs to his horſe; but making more haſte, than good ſpeed, down he came, and ſo vaniſhed away in the ſhape of a black D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g, with long Ears hanging almoſt down to the ground.</p>
            <p>Not long after, the Devil again appeared in the ſhape of a young Gentlewoman with two Maids attending her: but <hi>Peter</hi> being well armed againſt the ſnares of the Devil, he ſaid, <hi>Depart, O ye wicked Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifs, you ſhall have nothing to do with me nor mine, we are Baptized and Redeemed by the pretious Blood of Christ, and He will defend us againſt your Diabolical Machinations.</hi> At theſe words, the Devilliſh Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors vaniſhed; leaving behind them, a moſt noiſome ſtink, and the dead bodies of three Apoſtates.</p>
            <p>But in a ſmall Intervall of time, it ſo ſell out, that a certain number of Impoſtors going towards <hi>Ragnal,</hi> they met with two ignorant ſouls, whom they deſired to go to drink, which they did; but no ſooner had one of them quaft down a boll of Ale, (the Devil going down his Throat like a Fly) but immediatly he fell a skreeking, yelling, and roaring, in ſuch a hideous manner, that the Dogs began to bark, &amp; the Cattel to run, to the great aſtoniſhment of all that heard the ſame.</p>
            <p>Many ſuch like Inſtances, we might here inſert; but to amplifie the precedent Lines, be pleaſed to take a Review of the enſuing Examples of Apparitions and Satanical Deluſions, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>White</hi> of <hi>Dorcheſter,</hi> being a Member of the Aſſembly of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, was appointed Miniſter of <hi>Lambeth;</hi> but for the preſent could yet no convenient houſe to live in, but one that was poſſeſſed by the Devil.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:48780:4"/>
This he took, and not long after, his maid ſitting up late, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil appeared to her, whereupon, in a great fright, ſhe ran up to tell her Maſter; He bid her get to bed ſaying, She was well ſerved for ſitting up ſo late: Preſently after, the Devil appeared to Mr. <hi>White</hi> himſelf ſtanding at his beds feet: To whom Mr. <hi>White</hi> ſaid, <hi>If thou haſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elfe to do, thou maiſt stand there ſtill; And I will betake my ſelf to my reſt:</hi> And accordingly compoſing himſelf to ſleep, the Devil vaniſhed.</p>
            <p>Not long ſince at <hi>Stetin,</hi> an Univerſity in <hi>Pomerania,</hi> there was a yovng Student, that upon ſome diſcontent gave himſelf to the Devil, and made a Bond upon the Contract; which, that it might not come to the Knowledge of any, he laid up in one of his Books. But it plaſed God, ſome time after, that another Student wanting that book upon ſome occaſion, knew not where to get it; at laſt he remembred that ſuch an one had it, whereupon he went to him, and borrowed it of him, the young man having forgotten that he had put this Bond into it. The other, when he came home, began to turn over the book, and there met with the Bond, and reading of it, was much affrighted, and not knowing what to do, he went to Dr. <hi>Cramerus,</hi> a Profeſſour of Divinity in that Univerſity, to ask his advice, who wiſhed him to keep the Bond; the other replied that he durſt not: Then ſaid the Dr. bring it to me, and I will keep it. Some few nights after, as the Dr. was in his ſtudy, the Devil came rapping at his ſtudy-door, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Cramer, Cramer, <hi>give me by Bond, for it belongs to me, and thou haſt nothing to do with it.</hi> To whom the Dr. anſwered, Satan, Satan, thou ſhalt not have the Bond, thou haſt nothing to do with it; I have put it where thou canſt not fetch it, for it is in my Bible, at the third Chapter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> where theſe words are, <hi>The Seed of the Woman ſhall break the Serpent's head:</hi> upon this the Devil (taking his Chamber-window with him) went his way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Creſcentius,</hi> the Pope's Legate at the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> as he was upon a time writing Letters, till mid-night, to the Pope; being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to riſe to refreſh himſelf, there came in a great black Dogg, with flaming Eyes, and Ears hanging almoſt to the ground, which came to the Table where he ſate, and then vaniſhed: The Cardinal affrighted called in his Servants, cauſed them to look about the Chamber for the Dog, and when they could not find him he immediately fell ſick, and in his ſickneſſe was alwaies calling upon thoſe about him, to drive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Dog that leapt upon his bed, and ſo continued till he dyed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:48780:4"/>
Thus may you ſee, the product of <hi>Diabolical Deluſions,</hi> and the ſad Contingencies depending upon <hi>Apoſtates;</hi> Let no one therefore backſlide or ſwerve from the ways of Truth; nor with the Lord <hi>Never-be-good</hi> ſay, Methinks I could level a Promontorie into a Province, &amp; tread the Centre through, to read the Deſtinies of <hi>Southern</hi> Stars: O! I could ſigh my body into Air, and weep't into a Lake, that the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Nature hath not gave me a ſubſtance ſuitable, to aſcend the higheſt pinacle of honour: O ſad Deſtiny! what ſhall I do? I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſearch out frozen Climats, and lie whole Nights on hills of Ice, than live to ſleep out the unpleaſant hours, which the Fates have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin'd to me.</p>
            <p>Fond Fool! Do'ſt thou not know, that Honour is like a Bubble, &amp; the greateſt Prince, and Stateſ-man in the word, that hath his Golden Hangings, and gilded Coaches to ſlutter up and down in, will pay dear enough for them one day: for if he apoſtatize from the Truth, &amp; loſe the Jem of Eternity, he will ſurely periſh in his Bed of Dovvn, and the greateſt Doctors with their pearled Cordials cannot ſave him; for he that periſheth for want of Chriſt, periſheth with a Witneſs. Which may allude to a Metaphor, derived from a Tryal, where 12 Apoſtles, 4 Patriarchs, 4 Prophets and Evangeliſts, in all 24 theſe were of the Jury; Mercy and Juſtice ſate that day; and it is well for ſome that Mercy ſits every day, he waits and pleads too for the worſt of ſinners, however take heed of abuſing it: The perſons called to the Barre, were Mr. <hi>Wilful,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Careleſs,</hi> Monſieur <hi>Aulymoade de France,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Kill-Devil;</hi> the Lady <hi>Hoyden,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Tittle-Tattle;</hi> Mr. <hi>New come-cover,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Never-give over;</hi> the Lord <hi>Never-be good,</hi> and the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Chriſtleſs</hi> were in great danger. Money-bag the Uſurer, Alderman Chink, Mr. <hi>Starve-many,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cheat-many,</hi> are to receive a Tryal. Col. <hi>Get-all,</hi> Captain <hi>Fairs-well,</hi> and <hi>Now-we-will-be-quiet,</hi> are to be arraig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. But Mrs. <hi>Never repent,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Silver-ſtuff,</hi> Mris <hi>Rant-about,</hi> Mris. <hi>Butter fly;</hi> the Lord <hi>Lye-a-bed,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Sack-pot,</hi> are convicted: their chief pleaſure was in Tranſitory Delights; but the Lord abhors all ſuch in their preſent courſes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:48780:5"/>
But the Jury being called, and the Malefactors at the Bar, <hi>Solomon</hi> made a great Speech, the ſum and ſubſtance was, <hi>Vanity of Vanties, all is Vanity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider therefore, that a living Chriſt, is precious in a dying hour: for the Devils go a Cat-bating when they get a rich perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n: if a poor man be damned, the Devil is very glad; but if a Dives be, the Devils cry one to another, make haſte, make haſte, great <hi>Orlando</hi> is coming, great <hi>Orlando</hi> is coming: and truly, when your great ungodly Lords and Ladies come near to their Confines, the Devils run and tumble; yea, they ſcramble for a wanton, young and ſilken Fool.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
