<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from a friend in Shropshire to his country-man Mr. Richard Baxter at his meeting-house in London</title>
            <author>J. M.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-12">2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51737</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M38</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5858</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12986810</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12986810</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96217</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A51737)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96217)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 719:41)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from a friend in Shropshire to his country-man Mr. Richard Baxter at his meeting-house in London</title>
                  <author>J. M.</author>
                  <author>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Al. Banks,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Broadside.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed and dated: J.M. Oswalstree in the county of Salop, July 20, 1681.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  London --  17th century</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:96217:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96217:1"/>
            <head>A LETTER From a Friend in <hi>Shropſhire</hi> to his Country-man Mr. Richard Baxter AT HIS MEETING-HOUSE IN LONDON.</head>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <p>BEing well aſſur'd of the reſpect you bear to mankind in general, and particularly thoſe of your Native-Country, I preſume to trouble your Reverence with the peruſing of theſe lines, being moſtly matter of Fact, as it is acted by one Mr. <hi>Hugh P—</hi> and Mr. <hi>Philip ap R—, Preachers</hi> of an <hi>Independent</hi> Congregation at <hi>Swiny</hi> in this Pariſh, at Mrs. <hi>Bakers,</hi> in which you may eaſily obſerve how ſome men corrupt the word, and what kind of gain they make by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Godlineſs</hi> Had I known the particular Reſident at <hi>London</hi> for this part of <hi>England,</hi> I would have forborn this trouble to your ſelf; but preſuming you may have ſome knowledge of him, I deſire, at your firſt conveniency, to communicate this with what you ſhall think fit fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be done in the Affair, as your Reverence's Wiſdom ſhall find moſt expedient. The Caſe is, Mrs. <hi>Baker</hi> before-named was left by her Husband <hi>Baker</hi> (one whom you know to be an honeſt man, and active in the <hi>late Reformation)</hi> in poſſeſſion of an acquir'd Eſtate, to the value of 500 <hi>l. per annum</hi> well ſtock'd, and generally believed to be a money'd man. The ſaid <hi>Preachers,</hi> with one Mr. <hi>M—</hi> of <hi>Shrewſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> a Perſon for his Integrity well known to all the Gentlemen in the County, were deputed Truſtees for the ſecuring of the ſaid Eſtate ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Will of the Donor, his chiefeſt care being to prevent any Claim his Nephew Mr. <hi>John Lloyd</hi> might make to it, for that his ſaid Nephew was a frequenter of the Pariſh-Church all his life-time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and did not partake of the benefits he might have made by Diſſenting in that particular. But ſo it is, the Teſtator has been dead about four years, and our good woman before-nam'd has enjoy'd the Eſtate, and has not in any thing ſlackn'd her hand wherein ſhe might ſerve the <hi>Cauſe;</hi> for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which the more effectually, ſhe converts the Hall of her Manſion-Houſe to a very convenient <hi>Meeting-place,</hi> and furniſh'd it with a <hi>Pulpit,</hi> and all neceſſary Pues and Seats for accommodating of the Auditory,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96217:2"/>
which was very numerous; for the <hi>Word</hi> was preach'd as well in <hi>Welſh</hi> as in <hi>Engliſh;</hi> Mr. <hi>P—</hi> performing the firſt part; and of both Nations there was generally a great appearance.</p>
                  <p>It is to be conſidered in our remote parts, and eſpecially in Villages, there is not Conveniencies for accomodating of People with neceſſary Proviſions, when ſo far from their homes; to ſupply which, the good Woman (out of her own Purſe) relieved all perſons according to their Qualities, which you may reaſonably gueſs coſt Money; and 'tis now more then ſuſpected that ſhe has disburſed above 2000 <hi>l.</hi> beſides the yearly In-come; for that was very inſignificant to the preſſing occaſions of the Congregation; and indeed (to give ſome of 'em their juſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation) they were not wanting at any time to ſupply the good Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman with ſuch ſums of Money as ſhe thought (for the better car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on of the Work) ſhe might ſtand in need of; and for ſecurity, they were ſo much her true Friends, that they never refus'd the meaneſt Servant in the Houſe; by which kindneſs they the more eaſier effected their ends; as you ſhall preſently underſtand.</p>
                  <p>The good Woman being intangled, as you have ſeen, and now hardly is Miſtreſs of any thing ſhe us'd to call her own, ſhe laid it a little too near her heart, and was very much afflicted with melancholly, and by the care of her Truſtees ſhe was convey'd to <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> for the better recovery of her health, and in the mean time the Eſtate is ſeiz'd by the ſaid Preachers for the uſe of the Creditors; which was done ſo effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, that all, or moſt of the poor Servants being engaged with their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, fled, for fear of the ſtorm coming upon themſelves, and left the boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to any that would take it.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>P—</hi> and Mr. <hi>ap R—</hi>having now preach'd themſelves from the Hall to every individual Room in the Houſe, and in full poſſeſſion of the whole, it's obſerv'd that the uſual care that was taken on the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation is ſomewhat abated, and the numbers begin to leſſen, not only in the <hi>Weekly-Meetings,</hi> but in the <hi>Great and Monthly-Meeting,</hi> which was celebrated with <hi>breaking of Bread in the evening, after a good Dinner at noon;</hi> the defect of the latter does ſeem much to impair the uſe of the former; to prevent ſuch an evil, will take up ſome Time and Coſt.</p>
                  <p>And now, my good Country-man, as I have always heard a very good report of your Juſtice and Integrity, and your willingneſs to imploy your ſelf upon all occaſions wherein you might ſerve your Generation in any honourable undertaking, let me deſire you to conſider the ſighs of the poor abus'd Widow, and find ſome expedient that ſhe may be reſtor'd to her Houſe and Eſtate; for in all probability that may be the only effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual way of a certain Cure; for ſo great a burden is too hard for one ſhoulder, (as appears by our Object;) but if laid upon the whole, it will not only cure a Diſtemper in her, but in many hundreds, who (it's fear'd) are infected, more or leſs, with the ſpoils of <hi>a devour'd Widows Houſe;</hi> And if by your <hi>ſpiritual Comforts</hi> to the poor Woman you are ſucceſsful, no doubt but it will be an acceptable piece of Service, and a much greater to God and the whole Kingdom, if your fatherly Admonitions againſt ſuch Practices, there ſhall be no occaſion for the future to make any Complaints of this kind. My ſervice to the Brethren, but more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to your ſelf: I am a hearty well-wiſher, and your Country-man.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Oſwalſtree <hi>in the C<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>un<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y of</hi> Salop,
<date>July 20, 1681.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>J. M.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Al. Banks,</hi> 1681.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:96217:2"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
