<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>London's sins reproved and sorrows lamented, or, A sober check, together with a friendly admonition, to the wilfull, wicked, and wofull city of London under the consideration of her present grievous sins and growing sufferings.</title>
            <author>E. N.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-03">2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52599</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N14A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35059</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14973108</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14973108</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103001</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A52599)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103001)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1575:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>London's sins reproved and sorrows lamented, or, A sober check, together with a friendly admonition, to the wilfull, wicked, and wofull city of London under the consideration of her present grievous sins and growing sufferings.</title>
                  <author>E. N.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 broadside.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: E.N.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: creased and stained, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:103001:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
            <head>LONDON's Sins reproved, and Sorrows lamented: OR, A <hi>Sober Check,</hi> together with a <hi>Friendly Admonition,</hi> to the wilfull, wicked, and wofull City of LONDON, under the conſideration of her preſent <hi>grievous Sins,</hi> and <hi>growing Sufferings.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>ALas, poor <hi>London</hi>! for thy ſake—I am depriv'd of reſt,</l>
               <l>With <hi>grief</hi> my very heart doth ake, -and <hi>pant</hi> within my <hi>breſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To ſee thy <hi>Strength</hi> &amp; <hi>Beauty</hi> fade, —thy <hi>Glory</hi> thus go down,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Famine</hi> too upon thy <hi>Trade,</hi> which did preſerve thy Town.</l>
               <l>For, give me leave to tell thee plain, I have <hi>true love</hi> for thee,</l>
               <l>Although with <hi>hatred</hi> and <hi>diſdain</hi> — thou haſt requited me:</l>
               <l>Therefore in <hi>love</hi> and <hi>tenderneſs</hi>—this word to thee I ſend,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Warning</hi> fair in thy <hi>diſtreſs,</hi>—from one that is thy <hi>Friend.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>AWake, ye <hi>ſleepy,</hi> ſinful ſouls, awake:</l>
               <l>Behold and ſee what God is doing now,</l>
               <l>Whoſe <hi>powerful Hand</hi> doth ev'n the <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſhake,</l>
               <l>And makes the <hi>Strongeſt</hi> ſtoop, ſubmit and bow:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Lofty-minded,</hi> ſmall, and <hi>Great Ones</hi> too,</l>
               <l>Shall now be taught to know what God can do.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Rouſe up each <hi>drowſie</hi> ſoul, 'tis time to riſe,</l>
               <l>For why, the Lord doth <hi>knock</hi> even at thy <hi>door,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And draws his <hi>Angry Sword</hi> before thy eyes,</l>
               <l>Becauſe at <hi>work</hi> thou haſt not been before;</l>
               <l>He takes <hi>Revenge</hi> by day, and eke by night,</l>
               <l>How ſhall they ſcape that <hi>ſtill</hi> in Sin delight?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For if the <hi>Beſt</hi> amongſt the reſt go down,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Judgment</hi> fall upon <hi>the Houſe of God</hi>;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Lord to fear?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Conſider then ye <hi>ſtubborn Ranting Crew,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That <hi>ſtill</hi> in Sin againſt the Lord <hi>rebel,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Will neither <hi>Love</hi> nor <hi>Anger</hi> work with you,</l>
               <l>To ſtop your paſſage in your way to Hell?</l>
               <l>What do you think ſhall be your <hi>portion</hi> when</l>
               <l>God comes to reckon with the <hi>worſt</hi> of men?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O wretched <hi>London,</hi> dar'ſt thou ſtill preſume</l>
               <l>To ride upon the <hi>Chariot-wheels</hi> of Sin,</l>
               <l>When ev'ry day the Lord doth thee <hi>conſume,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And with his <hi>Judgments</hi> makes thee <hi>pale</hi> and <hi>thin</hi>;</l>
               <l>On ev'ry ſide his <hi>Vengeance</hi> doth appear,</l>
               <l>And yet thou wilt not learn the Lord to fear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What art thou ſtill reſolv'd to live and die</l>
               <l>Without Repentance in thy ſinful wayes?</l>
               <l>Shall <hi>Perſecution, Blood,</hi> and <hi>Cruelty</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Be <hi>meat</hi> and <hi>drink</hi> unto thee all thy dayes?</l>
               <l>Beſure God will not <hi>alwayes</hi> take it ſo,</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>wickedneſs</hi> will work thy <hi>overthrow.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Doſt thou not feel the <hi>mighty Hand of God</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Upon thee now, and <hi>many Thouſands</hi> fall?</l>
               <l>Haſt thou not taſted of his <hi>angry Rod</hi>?</l>
               <l>And <hi>yet</hi> for <hi>Grace</hi> doſt thou refuſe to call?</l>
               <l>If ſtill by <hi>Sin</hi> thou doſt the Lord provoke,</l>
               <l>Thou maiſt expect to feel a <hi>greater ſtroke.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But O thy <hi>ſenſleſs</hi> and <hi>obdurate</hi> heart,</l>
               <l>Doth yet appear againſt the Thing that's good;</l>
               <l>Yea, notwithſtanding this thy <hi>preſent ſmart,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou ſtill delightſt in <hi>Cruelty</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi>;</l>
               <l>Thy Sins, thy Sins are aggravated ſo,</l>
               <l>My heart ev'n <hi>bleeds</hi> to think upon thy <hi>Wo.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Why doſt thou now lift up a <hi>cruel</hi> hand</l>
               <l>Againſt the <hi>Sober-minded</hi> in this day?</l>
               <l>Why doſt thou ſtrive to <hi>baniſh</hi> out o'th <hi>Land</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ev'n thoſe which for thy welfare ſtrive and pray?</l>
               <l>Methinks thy heart ſhould more concerned be,</l>
               <l>To think how ſoon the Lord may <hi>baniſh</hi> thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Why art thou ſtill ſo hardned in thy mind,</l>
               <l>To bend thy <hi>force</hi> againſt the <hi>pure in heart</hi>?</l>
               <l>Yea, why art thou ſo wickedly enclin'd,</l>
               <l>To <hi>puniſh</hi> thoſe which do from <hi>Sin depart</hi>?</l>
               <l>Why doſt thou count it ſuch a crime to <hi>pray,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>preach the Word</hi> in ſuch a <hi>gloomy day</hi>?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I tell thee, <hi>London,</hi> theſe provoking Crimes,</l>
               <l>With many more, which ſtill in thee is found,</l>
               <l>Procured hath theſe <hi>ſad and woful Times,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And cauſed <hi>Juſtice</hi> to beſiege thee round;</l>
               <l>And if thy Sins thou wilt not yet forſake,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Righteous God</hi> will <hi>greater Vengeance</hi> take.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊…〉</desc>
                  </gap> plainely doth appea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊◊…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Plague</hi> did firſt begin.</l>
               <l>The Lord hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Vengence <hi>here</hi> and <hi>there.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ev'n by <hi>degrees,</hi> according to thy Sin;</l>
               <l>At firſt he did but <hi>little</hi> break thy Peace,</l>
               <l>But ſince thy Sins have cauſ'd it to <hi>encreaſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now thy poor Inhabitants do <hi>cry,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yea, <hi>grieve</hi> and <hi>mourn,</hi> ev'n with <hi>complaining tears,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And in thy <hi>Streets,</hi> do daily <hi>drop</hi> and <hi>die,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And many thouſands forfeited with fears:</l>
               <l>Nay, more than this, 'tis often truly ſed,</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Living</hi> ſcarce can <hi>bury</hi> all thy <hi>Dead.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now behold, thy <hi>Lovers</hi> all do flee,</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>ſeeming-friends</hi> are now become thy foes;</l>
               <l>In thy <hi>diſtreſs</hi> there's none to <hi>comfort</hi> thee,</l>
               <l>But rather ſtrive thy Comforts to oppoſe:</l>
               <l>If thou amongſt the <hi>Countries</hi> ſeek <hi>Relief,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>They rather ſtrive to aggravate thy <hi>Grief.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The more <hi>Affliction</hi> falls upon thy heart,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Sorrow</hi> doth oppreſs thy <hi>grieved</hi> mind,</l>
               <l>The more from <hi>them</hi> and <hi>theirs</hi> thou muſt depart,</l>
               <l>And in thy <hi>want</hi> thou ſhalt leaſt <hi>comfort</hi> find:</l>
               <l>The more thy fainting ſpirits <hi>gape for breath,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The more they leave thee to the pow'r of <hi>Death.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O then conſider, and in time return,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Break off thy Sins,</hi> amend thy evil wayes;</l>
               <l>If for thy Sins thou wouldſt but <hi>truly mourn,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou mightſt have hopes of ſeeing <hi>better dayes</hi>:</l>
               <l>Then be perſwaded once to be a <hi>Friend</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Unto thy ſelf before thy <hi>Final END.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>E. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>London, <hi>Printed in the Year,</hi> 1665.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
