<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to Dr. Fowler vicar of St. Giles Cripplegate in answer to his late vindicatory preface by William Newbery &amp; William Edmvnds.</title>
            <author>Newbery, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-10">2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53040</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N845</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18268</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13411030</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13411030</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99420</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A53040)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99420)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 468:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to Dr. Fowler vicar of St. Giles Cripplegate in answer to his late vindicatory preface by William Newbery &amp; William Edmvnds.</title>
                  <author>Newbery, William.</author>
                  <author>Edmunds, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fowler, Edward, 1632-1714. --  Great wickedness and mischievous effects of slandering ... in a sermon ... with a preface ... in his own vindication.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Religion --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-11</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-11</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99420:1"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:99420:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
A LETTER TO D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> FOWLER, Vicar of St. GILES CRIPPLEGATE.</p>
            <p>IN ANSWER TO HIS Late Uindicatory Preface.</p>
            <p>By</p>
            <p>WILLIAM NEWBERY, &amp; WILLIAM EDM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDS.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Yspys y dengys y dyn,</l>
               <l>O ba radd y bo ei wreiddyn.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1685.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:99420:2"/>
            <head>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99420:2"/>
A LETTER TO D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Fowler, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Paſtor,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>UPON Peruſal of a Preface to a Sermon upon <hi>Slander,</hi> under your Name, We the Subſcribers of this Paper found you as hard upon us in the <hi>Preſs,</hi> as you uſe to be in the <hi>Pulpit.</hi> And therefore for the Satisfaction of the World, and the Diſcharge of our Selves, we have reſolv'd upon the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of this Addreſs.</p>
            <p>You are pleaſed to mention a Certificate given us, and your Repentance for it. Let it not trouble you, Sir, for the Certificate has done you no harm, and us no good: For a Great Man told us, <hi>That it would ſhake the Credit of our Loyalty;</hi> and ſo we laid it aſide, as a <hi>Thing we were not Proud of.</hi> The Words were, <hi>That we were Peaceable, and Chriſtian like temper'd Men.</hi> And truly, when your Hand was in upon Certifying, we had a mind to Try, If you would do it for Loyal Men, as well as for Others.</p>
            <p>Your Opinion of us, we perceive, is much alter'd ſince you gave us that Character; though the World will witneſs the Juſtice we have to the Title of it, and ſtand in Admiration at us, for Bearing from your Self, and your Aſſiſtant, all the <hi>Satyrs, Invectives,</hi> and <hi>Comminations</hi> againſt us, that have been vented in the Pulpit, without praying the Juſtice of the Law to hold your Hand.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, It hath been your Practice to Diſcourſe of us both, with Great and Small, as <hi>Monſters of Spight and Malice;</hi> which is a Charge, that we ſhall in Charity divide betwixt your Self and your Aſſiſtant.</p>
            <p>And for our own Vindication, We do Appeal to All that know us, and our Conſciences do bear us Witneſs, that we never oppos'd you out of any Ill-Will to your Perſon; but only to put a ſtop to ſome of your <hi>Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinarian</hi> Deſigns and Practices, by a Due Courſe of Law.</p>
            <p>And ſince we are forc'd upon this Way of Clearing our Selves, we muſt Impute the Cauſe now Depending, to your own Irregular and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable Proceedings in your Office, which have Engaged us to Appear, as we do, for the Honour and Defence of our <hi>Mother Church.</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:99420:3"/>
And if this be an Act of <hi>Spight and Malice,</hi> then we are Guilty; and our Crime is, the Service of the Eſtabliſhed Church.</p>
            <p>Your <hi>Preface</hi> goes on in the Praiſe of Mr. <hi>R. W.</hi> and Mr. <hi>S.</hi> The former of theſe you Repreſent for a <hi>Truly Loyal Conforming Man,</hi> and our Proceedings againſt him to be <hi>Spightful</hi> and <hi>Malicious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſhall not Reflect upon his being a Souldier under Colonel <hi>Hacker,</hi> and ſo continuing till near the Kings Reſtauration; A noted <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticler,</hi> and one of <hi>Doelittles Congregation,</hi> till he came to be Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warden of <hi>Cripplegate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſhall not Reflect upon his Rude, Trifling, Antick Geſture, at the Church, in the time of Divine Service, which appeared no other to the Congregation, than a Ridiculing of the very Office, as well as the Performance of that Holy Duty.</p>
            <p>We could tell you, Sir, That ſince his <hi>Certified Conformity,</hi> which we account upon, as the Date of his Converſion, we never heard, that he ever gave the Church Service one good word, or ever Attended to it with that Reverence as he ought to do.</p>
            <p>We preſume you <hi>are no Stranger,</hi> Sir, to a Paſſage of His at a <hi>Ward-Moot Inqueſt.</hi> Where a Motion was made to begin the Work, with Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Morning Prayers. Your truly <hi>Loyal and Conforming</hi> Mr. <hi>W.</hi> op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed it, <hi>Calling it an Innovation. I hope,</hi> Mr. <hi>W.</hi> (ſay's one) <hi>you will not call the Prayers an Innovation, I mean,</hi> ſays Mr. <hi>W. the bringing of them into the Queſt is an Innovation.</hi> To which one Replyed: <hi>That it was generally uſed in all the Queſts in</hi> London, <hi>and had been uſed in</hi> Crip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plegate <hi>too before Mr.</hi> W. <hi>was born.</hi> Whereupon Mr. <hi>W.</hi> flew from the Table, crying, <hi>They that will have a May-pole, ſhall have a May-pole.</hi> And as the reſt were Riſing to go to Church to Prayers, Mr. <hi>W.</hi> got him to the Fire in the Chamber, ſaying; <hi>You that are ſo hot in Zeal, that can be warmed by Prayers, may go into the Church; As for my part, they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver warmed me in all my Life; I'le ſtay and warm my ſelf by the Fire. And if I had thought this, that you would have had Prayers, I would have beſpoke ſome Fidlers this Morning, that I ſaw at</hi> Tom Charnley <hi>'s,</hi> (an Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe-Keeper); <hi>For Prayers without Muſick do's not do well.</hi> And du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the whole Seſſion, he never went with the Queſt to Prayers, though he was a Member of it.</p>
            <p>The Report of this Scandalous Rudeneſs being told in the hearing of Mr. Recorder, he was pleaſed to examine the Matter, and to appoint the Reporters of it to come to the Seſſions at <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> and there to Deliver their Information upon Oath; which accordingly they did. And the Recorder Ordered an Information to be Exhibited againſt Mr. <hi>W.</hi> for Depraving and Ridiculing the <hi>Church Service.</hi> But by great and powerful Sollicitation on his behalf, there was a <hi>Noli Proſequi</hi> granted, before the next Term; not for the Baſeneſs of the Cauſe, as you would have People believe, but for other Reaſons, not ſo proper for this Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>Another Inſtance of Mr. <hi>W</hi>'s Affection to the Church may be this. The Alderman of the Ward Ordered the Preſenting of all Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle Houſes. In purſuance whereof a Motion was made in the very <hi>ſame Queſt.</hi> Upon this up ſtarts Mr. <hi>W.</hi> and called it, <hi>A Spiteful and Malicious Motion: For who could prove the Proprietors of Conventicle Houſes.</hi> To which it was replyed, <hi>That they would be eaſily found out. Why then,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99420:3"/>
aith Mr. <hi>W. make what Preſentments you will, For my part I will never ſet my Hand to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Word more now, with your Favour, to his Loyalty, He was as <hi>Active a Stirrer</hi> in the Tumultuous Elections at <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> as any Man; and Polled al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways on the Factious ſide. He was All in All with his Friend <hi>Bateman</hi> (at preſent Priſoner for the Conſpiracy) to get Hands to a Seditious Petition. And whoever refuſed it, he Branded him for a Papiſt; Particularly Mr. <hi>Newbery,</hi> now Deputy of the Ward. And this muſt be no part of the Quarrel you are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to Mention.</p>
            <p>The Steeple was ſo Crazy it ſeems, that on the 29<hi>th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> Mr. <hi>W.</hi> would not let the <hi>Bells be Rung, for fear it ſhould fall.</hi> And yet upon <hi>Shaftsburie's Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus Jury,</hi> the Steeple was ſtrong enough to bear it. He himſelf, as Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warden, ordered the Bells to be Rung, and made a Bonfire at his Own Door, for Joy, at the Deliverance. Its very true, Sir, that he was <hi>Tallow-Chandler</hi> alſo to your Good Lord and Maſter, and that we hope was the Ground of your Certifying Mr. <hi>W.</hi> to be a truly Loyal Conforming Man.</p>
            <p>As for Mr. <hi>S.</hi> Your Commendations are well beſtowed on him; For he is your Grand Informer, a Talebearer betwixt you and your Pariſhioners, a very Buſy-Body in other Mens Offices and Affairs. And for his Reputation, There is not a Curate in <hi>England,</hi> that either Studies leſs, or Uſurps more upon his Neighbours.</p>
            <p>We do not diſlike him indeed, Sir, for his Sermons upon <hi>Reſtitution,</hi> as you would be thought to Imagine; For they were Preacht before we ever bore Office in the Pariſh. And ſo we could not be Inſtruments of Waſting the <hi>Poors. Stock,</hi> which moſt Untruly, as well as Invidiouſly, you intimate in your <hi>Preface</hi> But if you will allow a Falſhood to bring Truth to light, we ſhall now tell you the Story of thoſe Sermons.</p>
            <p>It was Mr. <hi>S</hi>'s Hap one Day to be chopping of Logick with a <hi>Pawn Broker</hi> in the Pariſh, who Reproving Mr. <hi>S.</hi> for ſome Ill thing he had done, Mr. <hi>S.</hi> was much Offended at him, inſomuch that he fell upon the Mans Calling the next <hi>Sunday</hi> in the Pulpit, with the Doctrine of <hi>Reſtitution;</hi> where he Denounc't <hi>Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> againſt Uſury, Extortion, and Oppreſſion.</p>
            <p>But this Treatment is no News from Mr. <hi>S.</hi> to our Pariſh and Officers, and our Great Slander and Damage. For by theſe Calumnies, He has diverted the Charity of divers of our Good Benefactors, and gotten the Mony into his own Hand, whereof he gives no Account.</p>
            <p>He makes a great Noiſe indeed, how much the Poor are obliged to him, and yet by your Favour and His, the Number is much encreaſed, and the Taxes conſiderably raiſed, ſince he came amongſt us.</p>
            <p>He had once a Project of ſetting up a <hi>Nurſery</hi> in the Pariſh to leſſen the Charge, and bring poor Children up to Learning. To this end he got the Benevolence of ſeveral Good People, and Eighteen pence a Week of the Pariſh for every Child he took, being the very Price they were kept at before. He ſtockt his <hi>Nurſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> with about twenty of theſe Children, who as they went every <hi>Sunday</hi> Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Cornhill</hi> Lecture, gave the Spectators to underſtand, that they were Mr. <hi>S</hi>'s Charity-Children But inſtead of being Taught, theſe Poor Children were let out to <hi>Cooks Shops, Spinning-Wheels,</hi> or the like, at Twelve pence or Eighteen pence a Week, and were ſo ſcantly fed, and naſtily kept, that the Churchwardens or Overſeers, took them away to their old Maintenance, and ſome of them dying, it was not thought convenient to give the Searchers the View of their Bodies.</p>
            <p>This ſhall be made good (whenever Mr <hi>S.</hi> pleaſes) to any Court of Juſtice, without any need of his Prophaning the Pulpit with <hi>Ribaldry,</hi> and <hi>Scandal</hi> againſt his Neighbours.</p>
            <p>And therefore, Sir, as you value your own Credit and Ours, be no longer led by Mr. <hi>S.</hi> into theſe uncharitable Miſtakes; Curates do not behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99420:4"/>
thus in other Pariſhes. And its hard for <hi>Cripplegate,</hi> to be the only Curate-Ridden Pariſh in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many of his Sermons are not only Perſonal Invectives, but ſome of them ſo Broad and Courſe: That the Men he Intends, are Pointed at by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation. But its well<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if he does not play the <hi>Muggleton,</hi> and pronounce them Damn'd.</p>
            <p>We have born theſe Indignities thus long, more out of Reſpect to the Holy Function, than to the Curate; and we do joyntly deſire you would keep him to his <hi>Text,</hi> and adviſe him to Preach <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> as becomes a Miniſter of the Goſpel. But the main Buſineſs is yet to come. The Cauſe depending in <hi>Doctors Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> betwixt your ſelf and One of us.</p>
            <p>The Sum of your <hi>Preface</hi> on that Matter, is partly Accuſation, partly Excuſe. And the Printing of it might have bin ſpar'd, after ſo many Private Diſcourſes and Publick Preachments upon that Subject, wherein you have <hi>made us, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of our Neighbours, a Parcel of Lewd, Vicious, Prophane, Scandalous, Debauch't Fellows.</hi> Wherein the whole Pariſh, and all that know us, and will ſpeak Truth, will appear to our Vindication. Sir, you ſhould do well, to lay your <hi>Certificate</hi> and your <hi>Sermons</hi> together, and Reconcile this Character to the other. In the mean while deal with us as a Gentleman, a Chriſtian and a Miniſter. You are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to Inſinuate, <hi>That we are Netled at your Preaching Impartially againſt certain Vices, which make Loyal Conformiſts a Diſgrace to the King and the Church.</hi> Now the Truth is, Thoſe Vices are rather chargeable upon your ſort of Loyal Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, than upon any of the King's and Churches, that we know of. And the ſcope of your Preſent Deſign is this, There is a Heavy Charge ſworn againſt you at <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors Commons;</hi> And one of us is the Fair and Open Proſecutor of it. So that if you can either Blaſt us in our Credit, or diſable us in our Fortunes, from going thorough with it, you do a great part of your Work. And upon this Conſideration, you have not left a Stone unturned to Defame us with Perſons of Honour, and to Diſparage us in our Dealings with our Cuſtomers and Tradeſmen, to ſay nothing of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon the <hi>Alderman</hi> of the <hi>Ward</hi> for chuſing ſo Vile, Scandalous, and Debauch't a Creature, as you have Repreſented his <hi>Deputy</hi> to be. Who is ſo ſenſible of theſe Indignities, that he is reſolved in the firſt place to acquit himſelf, and afterwards to Reſign on St. <hi>Thoma</hi>'s Day next Enſuing.</p>
            <p>For the beſt Words you can beſtow on him and others are theſe; <hi>Enemies, Mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Enemies, Implacable Spirited Men, Wretched Lyars, Vile-Slanderers, Vicious Debauch't Men, not known whether Papiſts, Contrivers of Miſchief, Deprav'd, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken of Divine Grace,</hi> &amp;c. And whoever compares the Doctrine of your <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> with the Practice of the <hi>Preface</hi> and <hi>Concluſion,</hi> will hardly believe one and the ſame Wiſe Man to have bin the Author of them. Or that the Deſign of Chriſtianity and of your <hi>Preface,</hi> had one and the ſame Father.</p>
            <p>The firſt Viſible Change of your Countenance and Carriage towards us was (as we have Good Cauſe to Remember) juſt upon our Suppreſſing ſix or ſeven <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles</hi> in the Freedom Part of the Pariſh; And after that, upon our Endeavours to Purge the <hi>Veſtry</hi> of ſome very Ill Men, (which by your and Mr. <hi>S</hi>'s Artifice had bin lately Introduc'd) your Countenance ſeem'd to be further altered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us. The one of theſe was an <hi>Anabaptiſt;</hi> Another, an <hi>Anabaptiſt Preacher;</hi> the Third an <hi>Elder of</hi> Griffith<hi>'s Congregation,</hi> and a <hi>Conſpirator;</hi> and the Reſt of the ſame Leaven, and who could never be Admitted by your Predeceſſor the Biſhop of <hi>Glouceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's, Sir, you know, a Populous Pariſh, and we thought it our Duty to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to do what we did. We Petitioned His Majeſty in this Affair, and obtain'd a Gracious Reference to Mr. <hi>Attorney General</hi> and Mr. <hi>Recorder:</hi> And you your ſelf were preſent, with a great many more of the Pariſh, at a full Hearing before Mr. <hi>Recorder</hi> and the <hi>Alderman</hi> of the <hi>Ward;</hi> where you were urged again to clear <hi>the Veſtry of thoſe Men.</hi> Your Reply was, <hi>That they were New Converts, or upon Coming over, and ſober Men; and that you thought in time</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:99420:4"/>
               <hi>hey might prove uſeful Perſons to the Government.</hi> To which the <hi>Alderman</hi> made Anſwer, <hi>Truly Doctor, if they are ſuch, you ſhould have made ſix or ſeven years Tryal of them before you brought them into the Veſtry<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> But at length<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> after much ſtrugling, you deſir'd them to withdraw themſelves from the <hi>Veſtry</hi> in ſuch a manner, that every Body ſaw your Heart went along with them, even when you parted with them.</p>
            <p>You ſpeak of <hi>Articles</hi> Exhibited againſt you, and you ſay, That <hi>the Firſt</hi> (for <hi>Obſtructings Preſentments) had nothing like<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a Proof of it Produc'd in Court;</hi> but in this we Remit our ſelves to the Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You cannot but remember, Sir, how Fierce you were upon the</hi> Deputy <hi>in</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors Commons, <hi>Exclaiming,</hi> What had a Deputy of a Ward to do to meddle with Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments? <hi>and Threatning him,</hi> That if the Churchwardens Preſented thoſe whoſe Names he had given, you would Preſent the Churchwardens for Perjury, and Him for not coming to Church on Holy-days.</p>
            <p>We muſt mind you likewiſe, Sir, of your Suppreſſing the <hi>Order</hi> appointed to be Publiſh'd for the Preſenting of all People that did not come to the <hi>Sacrament;</hi> and of your calling it, <hi>A Device to make the Clergy Odious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You told the Churchwardens (you ſay) <hi>That, they ſhould Preſent Impartially, and not gratifie any Mans particular Pique or Diſguſt.</hi> If your meaning was, They muſt Preſent All, or None, there muſt then be no <hi>Preſentments</hi> at all: For how ſhould they take Cognizance of at leaſt Thirty thouſand Souls in that Pariſh? So that ſince All could not be taken notice of, why might not the ſame Prudent Courſe ſerve in <hi>Cripplegate,</hi> as well as in all other Pariſhes; that is, to Single out the Heads and Ring-Leaders of the Faction, which would probably bring the Inferior Sort of <hi>Diſſenters</hi> into better Order? This Courſe was commended by Dr. <hi>P.</hi> in <hi>Eighty two</hi> and <hi>Eighty three,</hi> and in ſeveral places had good Succeſs.</p>
            <p>We need ſay no more to Prove the Good-will you had to the Obſtructing of <hi>Preſentments:</hi> So that now we ſhall briefly ſet before you the Inconveniences that followed upon your Backwardneſs to Preſent.</p>
            <p>The Warmth which you were pleaſed to expreſs toward the Covering and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting of <hi>Phanaticks,</hi> preſently made <hi>Cripplegate</hi> a Sanctuary for the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> and brought them out of other Pariſhes into Ours, as if they had Fled from Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution into a City of Refuge. They themſelves owning and declaring, <hi>That they ſhould not be Moleſted with us, for any Church Matters or Sacraments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the Second <hi>Article,</hi> concerning your Adminiſtring the Sacrament to <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated Perſons,</hi> there needs no farther Proof, than your own Anſwer to the <hi>Libel</hi> in Court, and your own Confeſſion and Declaration in your <hi>Preface.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's ſomething however, that the <hi>Excommunicates</hi> were Notorious Diſſenters, and choſen (by your Intereſt and Influence) <hi>Churchwardens</hi> in the Lordſhip part of the Pariſh, contrary to the Liking of the Loyal Men in that <hi>Veſtry.</hi> Nay, there are ſome that ſay, <hi>You were reſolv'd they ſhould be Churchwardens, for this very Reaſon, That they would make no Preſentments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this they were Cited to take the <hi>Churchwardens Oath,</hi> which they peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily refuſed to do; and thereupon a Sentence of <hi>Excommunication</hi> was Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd againſt them in the Court, in Form: And an Inſtrument for Publiſhing the ſame in the Church was ſent to you, which for ſome time you laid by, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Good Advice,</hi> (as you ſay) and afterwards <hi>Admitted theſe Perſon's to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament,</hi> being <hi>Actually Excommunicated</hi> and before they were <hi>Abſolv'd;</hi> though after they had Receiv'd, you did your Beſt to have them Abſolved. Let any Man make an Excuſe for this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation,</hi> if he can. <hi>No,</hi> ſay you, <hi>there is no need of it; for I have made a ſufficient Apology for it my ſelf in theſe Words of my Preface.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I had leave to defer the Publiſhing of that Excommunication; and the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was given them before it was Publiſh'd: And I had then great Aſſurance, that <hi>Excommunications</hi> can take no Effect till they are Publiſh'd: And what I did, was done upon the Beſt Advice I was capable of Having; and I rely'd upon the <hi>AU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THORITY OF MORE THAN ONE ECCLESIASTICAL JUDGE.</hi> And
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99420:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the ſame Article had been Exhibited againſt many other Divines beſides my Self, had they been ſo unhappy, as to have had in thoſe Pariſhes any People of ſuch Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Spirits as I am Infeſted with: So that, if this were a Fault, it was a Fault of moſt Excuſable (if I may not ſay) Invincible Ignorance.</p>
            <p>You muſt now give us leave, Sir, to make ſome Remarks upon your Apology. Firſt, We find that <hi>Doctors Commons</hi> and Dr. <hi>Fowler</hi> are divided upon the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion: They are poſitive that it's a Fault, and the <hi>Doctor</hi> is doubtful; for you ſay, <hi>If it be a Fault.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, It ſeems not to ſtand with the Honour of your Dignity in the Church, to pretend <hi>Ignorance</hi> in a Point of the higheſt Nature in our Church Diſcipline.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Your Defence is only <hi>Crimination,</hi> and you ſhould not have brought your <hi>Adviſers</hi> upon the Stage; but rather have kept that Secret behind the Curtain.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, You ſhould have ſpar'd them for the ſake of the <hi>Ten Pounds</hi> Coſt you boaſt of, and ſome other Reaſons: For it's a New thing, for a <hi>Criminal,</hi> who Confeſſes the Fact, to be Clear'd; and the <hi>Accuſer,</hi> or <hi>Proſecutor,</hi> that makes Good his Charge, to be Puniſh'd.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, The Many <hi>Divines</hi> you ſpeak of are Men that we never yet heard of.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, We will leave the World to Judge, whether the Fault lyes in the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous Pariſhioners,</hi> or in the <hi>Peeviſh Miniſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, We take your <hi>Slanders</hi> the leſs ill, becauſe you make no Bolder with us, than with Our Eccleſiaſtical Judges, and many of our Divines, nay, with our Mother Church it ſelf, in giving the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> the Advantage of Throwing a Reproach upon us, which we believe She never had before, ſince the <hi>Bleſſed Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For what will they ſay, to ſee ſuch a Doctrine ſo Authorized, and a Parochial Miniſter in the Church of <hi>England</hi> take more upon him than the Pope of <hi>Rome;</hi> that is to ſay, in Admitting of Excommunicated Perſons to the <hi>Communion</hi> before they are Abſolv'd?</p>
            <p>Sir, As we have done you no Wrong all this while, ſo we will now do you this Right in the Story about the Election of <hi>Common Council</hi> Men, to Declare, That we believe you were no ways concerned in it; but that the Greater part of it belongs properly to Mr. <hi>S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to Conclude, We cannot but Obſerve what an unlucky Hand you have had at Vindications: You wrote one againſt <hi>Bunnion</hi> the Tinker; Another for Breaking the Church-Windows at <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> and making uſe of the <hi>Trinity</hi> in the Seal, that was Idolatry in the Glaſs. This <hi>Preface</hi> of yours is the Third; and we do not know, but that this <hi>Letter</hi> of Ours may Produce a Fourth.</p>
            <p>If all this be for your Health, and by way of Preſcription, as <hi>(a Wag ſaid)</hi> now and then to take a luſty Doſe of Vindication Pills to Purge Choler, <hi>we wiſh you good ſpeed. We would do this in better Terms, but</hi> Letters <hi>and</hi> Vindications <hi>are none of our Talent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You were pleaſed to beſtow a Couple of <hi>Latin</hi> Verſes upon us at the end of your <hi>Preface;</hi> it's poſſible they may be ſomething againſt our Church, but we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them not.</p>
            <p>We preſume however, that they will do as well at the End of a <hi>Letter,</hi> as at the End of a <hi>Preface;</hi> And therefore we ſhall conclude with them, Deſiring, that if your Book comes to a Second Edition you would bleſs the World with your Crippling Verſes in <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Hoc mihi pro certo quod ſi cum Stercore certo,</l>
               <l>Vinco, ſeu Vincor, certe Ego Maculor.</l>
            </q>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute> We ask your Pardon for the Freedom we have taken to Vindicate (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your Certificate,) <salute>Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Peaceable and Chriſtian-like Temper'd Pariſhioners and Servants, <list>
                     <item>WILLIAM NEWBERY, Deputy.</item>
                     <item>WILLIAM EDMUNDS.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:99420:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
