<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The unconquerable, all-conquering, &amp; more-then-conquering souldier, or, The successful warre which a believer wageth with the enemies of his soul as also, the absolute and unparalleld victory that he obtains finally over them through the love of God in Jesus Christ : as it was discussed in a sermon preached at Boston in New-England, on the day  of the artillery-election there, June 3d., 1692 / by Urian Oakes ...</title>
            <author>Oakes, Urian, 1631-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 136 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-03">2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53292</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O24</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC W28467</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13593909</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13593909</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100718</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A53292)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100718)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 797:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The unconquerable, all-conquering, &amp; more-then-conquering souldier, or, The successful warre which a believer wageth with the enemies of his soul as also, the absolute and unparalleld victory that he obtains finally over them through the love of God in Jesus Christ : as it was discussed in a sermon preached at Boston in New-England, on the day  of the artillery-election there, June 3d., 1692 / by Urian Oakes ...</title>
                  <author>Oakes, Urian, 1631-1681.</author>
                  <author>Shepard, Thomas, 1635-1677.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Samuel Green,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: Thomas Shepard.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans VIII, 37 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-12</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100718:1"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:100718:1"/>
THE <hi>UNCONQUERABLE, ALL-CONQUERING, &amp; more-then-CONQUERING</hi> SOULDIER: Or. <hi>The successful WARRE which a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever Wageth with the Enemies of his Soul:</hi> As also the Absolute and Unparalleld VICTORY that he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains finally over them through the love of God in Jesus Christ. As it was Discoursed in a SERMON Preached at <hi>Boston</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> on the Day of the <hi>ARTILLERY-ELECTION there,</hi> June <hi>3d.</hi> 1672.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Urian Oakes</hi> Pastor of the Church of Christ in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Cor. 9. 26.</bibl>
               <p> 
                  <hi>I so run, not as uncertainly: so fight I, not as one that beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Air.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Ephes. 6. 13</bibl>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Take unto you the whole Armour of God, that ye may be able to withstand in the evil day, and having done (or, overcome) all, to stand.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Rev. 13. 7.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>And it was given unto Him to make warre with the Saints, and to overcome them.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Rev. 12. 17.</bibl>
               <p> 
                  <hi>And they overcame Him by the Bloud of the Lamb, and by the word of their Testimony; and they loved not their Lives unto the Death.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Psal. 108. 13.</bibl>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Through God we shall do valiantly: for He it is that shall tread down our Enemies.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>CAMBRIDGE:</hi> Printed by <hi>Samuel Green.</hi> 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:100718:2"/>
            <opener>
               <pb facs="tcp:100718:2"/>
               <salute>Christian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat Title of the Book of the Wars of the Lord,</hi> Numb. 21. 14 <hi>may truly be ascribed to that best of Books, the holy Scripture, wherein accordingly after a short account in the first leaf thereof; of the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing of the Heavens, and the Earth, and all the Host of them, the Lord of Hosts do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>h presently acquaint us with the</hi> enmity put between the seed of the Woman, and the seed of the Serpent, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 3. 15. <hi>whereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is bid, and which Word of the Lord, hath, in a sense, g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ven being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Battels that have been fought in the World, for more then</hi> 5000 <hi>years, even from the beginning thereof unto this day; and whence it is also, that this Earth shall be the continued Field and Stage of War<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ill the last day; witness the close</hi> of this bloody Scene, in the Scriptures last prediction of the great; Pitcht, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal and Final Battel between the same Serpent, the Dragon and his Seed, <hi>in the Book of the</hi> Revelation; <hi>The upshot whereof will be the last and ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing opening, and so the eternal shutting of Heaven and Hell, filled with the Combatants respectively, for the receiving their Arrears therein. The day of Iudgement, doubtless, will be the day of publishing</hi> (and by sound of the left Trumpet) <hi>the compleatest History of the whole fight from first to last; in the interim the</hi> Lord General <hi>hath his many</hi> Heraulds at Arms, <hi>to denounce his Wars, and so proclaim also his Peace to the World, both by Word of Mouth</hi> (as by sound of Trumpet, <hi>Isai.</hi> 58. 1.) <hi>and by Writing also, of some of whom espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially it may be said, as sometime of</hi> Lucan, <hi>viz</hi> ut praelia videatur non canere, sed committere, &amp; tonare Classicum, eodem<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ardore arma scribe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t, quo Caesar tractavit, <hi>they have not shunned to deliver the whole Counsel of God, and that in the demonstration of the Spirit, and with Power; And blessed be the Lord for all the</hi> Alarms, Lectures of War, Instructions and Hortatory Speeches given from the Captain of our Salvation by any of his Commission Officers, for the doubling and fortifying our spiritual Watch. Israel <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law needed the Priests of the Lord (in order to their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to found the silver Trumpets, <hi>Numb.</hi> 10. 2, 9. <hi>that so blowing an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> that H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:100718:3"/>
Camp might be remembred before the Lord their God, and saved from their Enemies: <hi>and the whole life of every Christian, being that of a Man of War, hence what may tend to aceomplish him in his Heavenly Military skill, and encourage him in his spiritual conflict wherein that Cry is still heard</hi> (as Exod. 32. 26.) Who is on the Lords side? <hi>yea, wherein the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>igent is such, that he must either</hi> Fight or Dye, <hi>and that the consequence is for no less then Eternity, must needs be welcome to him, and so, without question, will be this following VVatch-word and Exhortation, delivered to the principal</hi> Artillery Company of this Land, <hi>at whose request it was first published to the Ear and Heart of the Hearer, and is now</hi> (after not a little importunity) <hi>to the Eye also of the Reader, from one of our Leaders</hi> (Heb. 13. 17. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>under the Chief Leader</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Heb. 2. 10.) <hi>Iesus Christ who is given for'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Leader and Commander to the People,</hi> Isai. 55. 4. <hi>this discourse being to ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate each one thereof, as a good Souldier of Iesus Christ to endure hardness; giving us sure intelligence of the happy success of this Divine Militia, the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sedness of every faithful VVarrier,</hi> in being more then a Conquerer: <hi>and though he may seem to be worsted in this or that Battel, yet as to the whole war, that he shall be, yea, in the language of Truth,</hi> that he is an Overcomer, and above an Overcomer. <hi>A Christians victory is indeed like to that of his chief Commander Iesus Christ,</hi> Col. 2. 14, 15. <hi>and through that Blood, and infinite Grace, very strange and mysterious; he is overcoming, when i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance overcome, and triumphing, when to the view of others he is a crucisied Captivs:</hi> as dying and behold we live! 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 9. <hi>A Paradox, and incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible in other Combats; and yet the wonder seems not so great that he should</hi> gain such a Victory over all his Enemies of this World, when we consider him as one that hath (with Reverence be it spoken) conquered the Lord himself, as is said of <hi>Iacob,</hi> whom the Lord Dubbed with the Name of <hi>Israel, Gen.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. 20. because <hi>as a Prince he had power with God, and had prevailed,</hi> whence also that strange word from the Lord himself, <hi>Cant.</hi> 6. 5. <hi>turn away thine eyes from me, for they have overcome me;</hi> thus do they sometimes come forth, <hi>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>arend,</hi> from the dust, <hi>Isai.</hi> 52. 2. and from their wrestling places of Prayer, as <hi>Luther</hi> did with those <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of Faith, <hi>vicimus! vicimus!</hi> and surely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>uch as one may glory in, the Lord, and through him humbly boast even as soon as he hath put on his spiritual Harness, because he is here well assured, by the promise, of the victory, before he sometimes strikes a stroak; and for which cause partly he may be said to be <hi>more then a Conquerer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Every Victory was not celebrated with a Triumph; to be triumphant is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>orc ore then to be victorious. There were, and are the Battels, wherein eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:100718:3"/>
the victor hath no c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>use so much as to rejoyce: of which sort <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> those, of them (who being not only visibly listed under the <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>er</hi> of Jesus Christ, but have Christ in them, the hope of Glory, yet) by whose Divisions and fidings, and warrings one against the other, through the hour and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of darkness, and temptation prevailing, the truth and peace is lost: <hi>these are</hi> Bella nullos habitura triumphos: <hi>and O that a most serious and wise con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration of their common danger from the Gates of Hell, and the necessity of that Brotherly union to which the Lord hath entailed the blessing, by way of command, even life for evermore, might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ause a retreat to it, in all quarters of the spiritual Camp sounded, from those hazardous and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ful pursuits!</hi> shall the Sword devour for ever? will it not be bitterness in the latter end? how will the uncircumeised rejoyce?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The most Warlike Christian Souldier will see, one day, that he had not any Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary skill, strength, courage or weapon to spare, wherewith to sight against Christ, in waging any unbrotherly War against any of the called, thosen and faithful followers of that Lamb. As for those of Christs Enemies, sinful self, the Devil, and this evil World (all</hi> Antichristianism) <hi>fight agains<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> them we should, and not spare them; the severe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> encounters cannot be too sharp; no quarter must either be given or taken here for ever. The Enemy is discovered, and those Stratagems of Faith in the Blood of Christ proposed by the</hi> Reverend Author <hi>of the following</hi> Sermon (whose praise is in the Gates) <hi>as that, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> our right taking the Word, not only victory may be gained, but what is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> transeendent. Thou hast here</hi> (by one of the Lords Auxiliaries, expert in warring the warfare of the service of the Congregation (for such will the service of the Ministry be found, <hi>Numb.</hi> 8. 24, 25.) sent else from asar, upon the relief to us, and in such a day) <hi>graphically represented to thy view the Church even Triumphant here on Earth,</hi> more then conquering <hi>while it is in in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ate Militant. And though their ancient Triumphs were appointed for the General of the Army, not for the common Souldiers, yet in this Spiritu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> War, the meanest of Christs followers shall Triumph with him, and divide the Spoils; an earnest and specimen whereof they that are sincere are not seldome acquainted with in this life; whence there are erected</hi> in heart and life, Trophies of the lesser victories gained, and all to the Glory of him, in whom when they are weak they are strong, through the power of his might, <hi>and may conclude before hand</hi> that they are more then Conquerers, <hi>and shall abide s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> superlatively for ever; roceiving those</hi> dona militaria <hi>which are to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e distribute<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to all such as are faithful unto death:</hi> I <hi>will give thee</hi> (saith the Lord <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>0) <hi>the Crown of life: There is the</hi> corona triumphalis, <hi>not for</hi> Paul <hi>only, a primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilar</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:100718:4"/>
               <hi>Champion, But</hi> 2 Tim. 4. 7, 8. <hi>which shall be given by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Iudge, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them also (even to all them that</hi> fight the good fight, finish their course, and keep the faith: and) <hi>that love his appearing; and that be would so come quickly</hi> (O come quickly) <hi>is the Prayer of</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The least of thy Fellow Souldiers, desirous to serve under the Royal Standard of the Lord Jesus, Thomas Shepard.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100718:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROM.</hi> 8. 37<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</bibl>
               <q>Nay, in all these Things we are more then Conquerers, through him that loved us.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N these Words we have the Apostle <hi>Pauls</hi> not <hi>Ovation, but Triumph,</hi> not <hi>Triumph</hi> only, but <hi>Something<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> I know not how to word it) Exhibited in the Name and on the Behalf of Himself and all true Believers, Indigitating and Importing a more then ordinary Tryumph over all those Enemies that oppose themselves against the Progress and Advance of a Christian in his way to the Fruition of the sweet Fruits of the Everlasting Love of God in Jesus Christ. Having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spicuously, copiously, and demonstratively asserted and vindicated the illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strious Doctrine of Justification in a way of <hi>Free Grace</hi> by Faith in the Lord Jesus Christ, in the beginning of this excellent Epistle, which is ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously stiled by the great <hi>Melancth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>n, the Confession of the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches:</hi> he proceeds in the sixth Chapter to Discourse of the Fruits and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequents thereof, namely, <hi>Sanctification</hi> and <hi>Obedience;</hi> the Mortification of indwelling sin in Believers, and the renovation, or rather infusion of a new Principle of <hi>Spiritual Life</hi> and <hi>Holiness.</hi> Now because this work is but inchoate and imperfect, and in part only transacted in this World; and there are remainders of sin in this life in the best of Saints; and because <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Corruption</hi> are vigorous, active, operative Principles, dwelling so near together, under the same Roof, in the same Soul, yea in the very same Faculties: there must needs arise a sharp and severe War in the Soul be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween these two Neighbouring and Opposite Natures, the particular event<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and successes whereof are various and uncertain; but the Victory is infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly determined in the issue on the side of <hi>Grace. Grace</hi> indeed i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> greatly beset, hardly bestead, much incumbred and almost overthrown at some rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons: but it will certainly <hi>eluctari,</hi> wrestle and recover it self out of all the dangers that threaten it. Now there is a double War which is commenced and waged by Believers in this Life: A War <hi>with the evil of sin,</hi> and a War <hi>with the evil of suffrings</hi> or <hi>afflictions</hi> so far as they would imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e or do op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose them in their March to Heaven. Of the War <hi>with sin, indwelling sin:</hi> (th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> in-bred, home-bred Enemy, that Mother of all the <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ominations</hi> that are brought forth in the lives of Men, that Adversary that is ever molesting the peace, disturbing the quiet, and endangering the condition of the People of God) the Apostle discourseth feelingly and at large in the seventh chapter
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100718:5"/>
of this Epistle: where he finally adjudges the victory to <hi>Grace,</hi> in the last verse of that, and in the beginning of the eight Chapter also. <hi>Of the War with Afflictions, or the evil of sufferings from Satan, or the World, from what hand, of what kind., and howsoever conditioned and circumstanced;</hi> he Discourseth Admirably, at the seventeenth verse of this Chapter and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o forwards, and he comes in the procedure of his Discourse to give unquestionable Assurance to the good Souldiers of Jesus Christ, of the full and final decision of this grand Controversie, and the happy issuing of all these hazardous conflicts, whether with sin or sufferings, in a glorious and absolute victory: Insomuch as having made sure of God on the side of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self and Believers, he doth in his own and their Name make an open Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, and bid defiance to all opposite and adverse powers, <hi>ver.</hi> 31. <hi>If God befor us who then can be against us?</hi> He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ids Sin, Satan, and an evil World do their worst against Believers that are thus entrenched in, and walled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with the Love of God; thus fortified and defended, aided and assisted by the Almighty one, the <hi>Lord of Hosts.</hi> And having laid his foundation in Gods Predestination, and Christs Mediation, he superstructs upon it, and plainly asserts the invincibleness of every sound Believer, notwithstanding the Relicks of sin that incumber him, the Temptations of Satan that molest him, and the afflictions and evils of the World that set themselves in Battel aray against Him. He represents to us the Christian as a person that may be opposed, combated and contended withal: but never routed, run down, totally defeated or overthrown in any Engagement. Now this invincible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the Christian Combatant, the Believing Champion (that in the Name of the Lord defies all the Hosts and Armies of Earth and Hell that come against him) notwithstanding the Remainders of sin, the greatness and unavoidableness of his Afflictions and Sufferings, is expressed,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Negatively, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>er.</hi> 35. <hi>Who shall separate us from the Love of Christ?</hi> The Argument stands thus: if nothing can separate a Christian from the Love of God in Christ, then nothing can conquer him, but he is invincible. But nothing can make that woful destructive separation: which he proves by an enumeration or induction of particulars; <hi>shall tribulation, or distress, or persecution,</hi> &amp;c. therefore he is invincible. This negation is clearly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported in the interrogation. For though it may be a <hi>stale,</hi> yet it is a <hi>true</hi> and <hi>useful</hi> observation, that interrogations affirmatively exprest in Scripture are wont to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>arry in them the force and signification of vehement negations. The meaning of the Apostle in plain terms is, that neither <hi>Tribulation,</hi> nor <hi>Distress,</hi> nor <hi>Persecution,</hi> nor <hi>Famine,</hi> nor <hi>Nakedness,</hi> nor <hi>Peril,</hi> nor <hi>Sword,</hi> nor any thing else of an <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>imical nature</hi> can possibly separate a true Believer from the dear love of Jesus Christ.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Affirmatively, in the Words of the Text; <hi>Nay in all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>se things we</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:100718:5"/>
               <hi>are more then Conquerours through him that loved us.</hi> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> if he should say<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> we are so farre from being worsted and prevailed over by the Enemies of our Salvation that warre against us, from succumbing under the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d they are laying upon us, and losing our Interest in the Fruits of the Everlasting Love of God in Christ, by Reason of the opposition that is made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in our way, that we carry the Day, and are sure of a very glorious victory.</p>
            <p>In this Verse we may remark these two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A singular Priviledge:</hi> And that is <hi>Uictory</hi> &amp; <hi>Conquest,</hi> which is illustrated &amp; amplified, (1.) <hi>From the Extent and Vniversality of it.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in all these things:</hi> such as he had mentioned before, or what else can be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned and imagined by us. (2.) <hi>From the transcendent incomparable Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of it.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>we are more then Conqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rours,</hi> or do more then over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come. It is a <hi>Victory,</hi> with <hi>Surplusage</hi> and <hi>Advantage,</hi> a Victory, and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more then a <hi>Victory: a Superlative and incomparable Conqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>st and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory that is obtained.</hi> (3.) <hi>From the Foundation of this glorious Victory,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the great and only means of acquiring and obtaining it. And that is, Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Lord Jesus Christ. <hi>Through him that loved us,</hi> saith the Apostle: m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ning <hi>Christ,</hi> or <hi>God in Christ Iesus.</hi> (4.) <hi>From the first, grand, impulsive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>use of it,</hi> the <hi>proegumenical</hi> Cause of this glorious Victory which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> infallibly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and that is, the Love of God in Christ. The special love of God in his Son Jesus Christ is the first Cause of these victorious Atchievmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>More then Conquerours through Him that loved us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Persons that are thus Priviledged,</hi> or invested in this great priv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: that have Victory &amp; Triumph ascertained to them. <hi>We are more the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Conquerours.</hi> Not only the great Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> himself, that renowned Warriour, and brave Champion of the Lord Jesus Christ: But all true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers also universally. He ranks Himself with, and discourseth of Believer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> in general, <hi>that walk not after the Flesh, but after the Spirit;</hi> Believing, Justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Sanctified men and women. They are not exempted or Secured from violent Onsets, furious Assaults, hazardous and desperat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Conflict<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> with their mortal Enemies that warre against their Souls: But they have this admirable Advantage above all other men, that they are assured of a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Victory. The Intendment of the Apostle in the words is Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, and may be drawn into this Observation.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>That all true Believers have a transcendent, and incomparably glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Conquest and Victory in all their severe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>agements with the Enemies of their Peace and Happiness, through the Love of God in Christ Iesus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Believing, Justified persons through the Love of God in Christ have the better by many Degrees of the Enemies of their Salvation, and are m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>h too hard for them in all their sharp Disputes and Encounters with them.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100718:6"/>
All the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ve believed through Grace, and are admitted into a st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>te of Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and, Accepration with the Lord <hi>a. c' more then Conquerours,</hi> successful and victorious beyond Expression or Comparison, in their Combates and Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>flicts with their Enemies (those adverse powers that warre against th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>m), through D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>vine Love in Jesus Christ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, This Proposition which we have laid down, as the Subject of our present Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>rcise, and which is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently founded and comprized in the words of the Text, hath a large Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pass and a very great Circumference, as you will readily apprehend. We are now entring into a very large Field, and might traverse a great deal of Ground, if Time and strength would allow us to pace it over. We have many Things before us to be discoursed for the due Explication and Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of this observation. The way of quickest dispatch, and greatest Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition; as well as Clearness, and Demonstration, will be to cast all we have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o say to the Doctrinal part into Six or Seven grand Conclusions.</p>
            <p>Concl. 1. <hi>Eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y true Believer is a Souldier, and engaged in a Warfare.</hi> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ould it were reciprocally true, that every Souldier amongst us is a true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>am suee every Souldier ought to be a Believer: and of all men Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> men, when they are commanded out upon real Service, to look Death and Danger in the Face, and carry their Lives in their Hands, had need of Faith and Grace, and Interest in the Lord Jesus Christ, and thereby the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ition of their Souls well secured for Eternity But it is Infallibly and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ue that every Believer is a Souldier in a spiritual Consideration. The whole Body of Christians that walk by Faith in this lower World, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>lace of Sin, and Sorrow, and Temptation, and Absence from the Lord, is apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>uly called the <hi>Church Militant</hi> in Contra-Distinction from that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hich is, <hi>Triumphant</hi> in the highest Heavens. Those that are arrived at a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>te of Glory have fought their fight, and finished the Course of their Wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>are, and are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> out of pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>h of Pike or Gunshot, farre enough <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>moved out of the Reach of their Adversaries. They are marched out of the Field, and discharged from any further Service, and enjoying their Reward. But the people of God in this world are in a warfaring state and Condition. The first moment that any man is effectually called and converted, and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ingly wrought upon, He is engaged on Christs side against the world, the Flesh, and the Devil, taken into Christs pay, puts on his Armour, and is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Battel. For the Graces of Gods Spirit, which are infused at a Christians Conversion, are a Believers spiritual Armour, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 13, 14, &amp;c. Eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y Chris<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ian when he is new Born is born a Souldier. It is said of <hi>Goliah,</hi> the Philistine Champion, <hi>that he was a Man of warre from his youth,</hi> I Sam. 17 33. But it may be truly said of the Christian Champion, <hi>that He is a Man of warre from his Birth</hi> Neither is He a poor naked Creature, as it is with the Children of the first Birth: but He comes into the new world in his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100718:6"/>
Suit of Armour, armed <hi>Cap apé</hi> with compleat Armour of Proof, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> vested with the Graces of the Spirit of Christ. He hath his excellent and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible <hi>General,</hi> the Lord Jesus Christ; and hath taken his <hi>Sacr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> militare,</hi> his Oath of Fidelity and Obedience to his great <hi>Lord Genera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> He hath also (if there be opportunity, and he walk orderly) his <hi>Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> that he is listed into, the <hi>Church,</hi> I mean, He walks in Fellowship with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> at least He is inrolled among the Members of the <hi>Church-Militant</hi> in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. He hath his <hi>Banner</hi> to fight under: even the love of Christ displayed for a Defence to his Souldiers and Followers, and a Flag of Defiance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o their Adversaries, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3. 4. He hath his <hi>Arms</hi> and <hi>Weapons,</hi> offensive and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fensive to fight withal. He hath his <hi>Souldierly Qualifications,</hi> and milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Accomplishments; Courage, Skill, Patience, Hope of victory, Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to, and Confidence in his General, Orderliness, Disposi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ion to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Hardship, or whatever else may be mentioned. Every wicked<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>dead is a Souldier, but he fights against God, strengthens himself, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ratches out his hand against the Almighty, <hi>and runneth on his Neck; and upon the thick, bosses of his Bucklers,</hi> Job. 15. 25, 26. He fights against hims<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and his own Soul, keeping those Lusts in pay that <hi>warre against the So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> He puts on the whole Armour of the Devil, that He may be able to stand against all the Shocks of Conscience, or encounters of the Word and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, and fight it out to the last with the Infinite Majesty, to the ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> lasting Ruine of his Immortal Soul. But he is neither engaged in, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided and accomplished for the <hi>Holy Warre</hi> we are discoursing of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that is not a Believer is a conquered, disarmed slave, that men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Service of the Enemies of his Soul, and is in no Condition of sight<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> with them. If He begin to bestir himself (through the Convictions, awak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> ings and Alarms of Conscience) and to hold up his Hand, or make any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance, He is knock'd down and overcome presently, and ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> a Captive (as the Believer is said to be <hi>more then a Conquerour)</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> more a Vassal and Drudge to his Lusts, and other Enemies then before. But a Believer is a man of Warre, a Souldier well appointed, in a good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> pacity and Condition to dispute it out with any of his Adversaries.</p>
            <p>Concl. 2. <hi>Every true Believer hath constant fighting work before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> There is no End of his warre in this world, not any time wherein He any give over fighting.
<q>
                  <l>Nunquam Bella piis, nunquam Certamina desunt:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>t quocum certet mens pia semper habet.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>It is not so with other Souldiers. <hi>There is a Time when Kings go <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to Batiel,</hi> 2 Sam. 1. 1. 1. And there is a Time when they disband their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, or draw them into their winter Quarters, or make a Cessation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of Hostility by Leagues or Truces. There is a Time of Warre (saith <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:100718:7"/>
3. 8.) <hi>and a Time of peace.</hi> Other Souldiers are not alwayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: but a Christians Duty and Employment is to fight continually. He cannot assure himself of any Respite or Intermission in the Course of his war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare. This may be convincingly made out in three or four Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Every Believer reacheth after, march<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>th towards the perfect enjoyment of the blessed. Fruits of the everlasting Love of God.</hi> This is the prize He runs for, the Crown he sights for, <hi>the Recompence of re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ard He hath respect</hi> unto, the End and Aim of his Race and wrestling. He is in his Journey or upon his March towards <hi>that City which hath Foundations (Heb.</hi> 11. 10.) that <hi>better Country,</hi> where He may enjoy the glorious Fruits of the peculiar Love of God in perfection. Every Christian is in a wayfaring state, and declares plainly (by the course he shapes and steers) that he is a Stranger <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ere, and <hi>seeking a Country, Heb.</hi> 11. 14. travelling towards the Heavenly <hi>Can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>an,</hi> and the face of his soul is set towards that <hi>Ierusalem whichis above.</hi> He hath Grace and Glory in his Eye, and is engaged in a close and eager pursuit of Happiness. The end of his Faith and Holy Conversation is the Salvation of his Soul, and the perfect and perpetual Fruition of the Love of God in the brightest discoveries and richest effusions of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Every Believer meets with great opposition in his March and way to the God aforesaid from Enemies that make Head against Him, and do what they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>o separate Him from the Love of God in Christ Iesus.</hi> He meets with numerous Adversaries that design and drive at this to hinder Himself and the Rest of Gods people in their Travels to <hi>Canaan,</hi> to divert and turn them out of the Road of Holiness and Obedience, which leads to Happiness, to pluck them (if it were possible) out of Gods Hand, to tear them out of his loving Embraces, to cut them short of the blessed Fruition of the Love of God in Christ. God leads every Believer, as it were, through the <hi>Land of the Philistines</hi> where they must see Warre, and brings Him to the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Canaan</hi> that way. And he meets with this Opposition,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>From Himself, and that sin that dwells in Him.</hi> From his own Heart and Nature, as it is depraved and vitiated: from his natural corruption, or that sin that is inlaid and radicated in his Nature. This is the principal, the Capital, the Grand Enemy, that is bred in his Bowels, raising intestine civil Warrs, without which his forreign Enemies, the Rest of his Adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries could do Him no Hurt, nor make any considerable Head against Him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t was the great Advantage of the <hi>Captain of our Salvation</hi> (as our Saviour is called, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 10.) in all his Engagements with Satan and his Instruments, <hi>that He was Holy, Harmless, undefiled, and separate from Sinners,</hi> Heb. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>6. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hat He know no sin,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 21. that He had no sin in Him. Hence it was that just before his last and greatest Encounter with Satan, He tells his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>isciples, <hi>The Prince of this world cometh and hath nothing in me,</hi> Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>. 14. 30.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100718:7"/>
There was nothing in our Lord Jesus that complied with, or was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>itable to the temptations of the God of this World: nothing to close with his sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestions, or entertain his Terrours: the Enemy without had no correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents within him, Satan could not lay hands, or fasten a Temptation upon him. Christ threw him off with ease in this respect. Hence he was tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted indeed in all points, <hi>like as we are, yet wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hout sin,</hi> Heb. 4. 15. Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Christ was like throwing a But upon a Chrystal Glasse, which will not stick, but glides off. But alas! the sin of our Natures is Satans strength and aduantage. He finds enough in the best of Believers, that found nothng in our Saviour. Satans sparks easily e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>me us, because he finds so much Tinder in us. The Lusts within us are ready to take fire at every injection. There is a Traitour in our own Bowels that is ready to open our Ports, and let in the Adversary. Now of the War which a Christian wages with this home-bred, intestine Enemy, the seventh Chapter of this <hi>Epistle</hi> to the <hi>Romans</hi> gives us a clear account: where the Apostle <hi>raises an Out-cry,</hi> and makes <hi>Doleful Complaints of the remainders of sin, the Law in the Members, the body of Sin and Death,</hi> and Discourseth of the <hi>Nature, Power and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valency of in-dwelling sin, as to some engagements.</hi> The Apostle <hi>Iames</hi> speaks of <hi>the Lusts that War in our Members,</hi> Jam. 4. 1. And <hi>Peter of fleshly Lusts that war against the Soul,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 11. these make up that opposite party within a Christian that would intercept and stop him in his way to Glory: a secret, subtle, treacherous, designing party that creates him a world of trouble and danger in his journey towards Heaven.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>From the World, which is another Enemy that would obviate and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the People of God in their Travels.</hi> Hence the World was a part of Christ his glorious Conquest. <hi>Be of good chear, I have overcome the World,</hi> Joh. 16. 33. And the Believer that is born of God by Faith in the Lord Jesus Christ overcomes it too, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. 4. which plainly implies <hi>that the World is an Enemy.</hi> Considerable are the Expressions of the Apostle to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, <hi>Iam.</hi> 4. 4. <hi>know ye not that the friendship of the World is enm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ty with God? whosoever therefore will be a Friend of the World, is the Enemy of God.</hi> And doth it not follow hence, that he that is a Friend of God is an Enemy to the World, as it lies in opposition to God, and the World (in that respect) an Enemy to him? The World is one of the Associates of that false party within a Christian, and under the conduct of Satan militates against a <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever.</hi> Particularly:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Snares &amp; Allurements of the World, which would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> away and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>stian from following after God.</hi> These make war upon a Child of God; and are dangerous Enemies. As they say, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Fight with Silver or Gold weapons, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100718:8"/>
never doubt of Victory. Some Enemies have bought great Victories, which they could never have won otherwise. All these things wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> give th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e, this profit, pleasure, Honour, (saith the flattering World <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver) if thou wilt fall down, or surrender to me. These ensnaring and allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Objects, which the world presents the Sons of Men with, have such a close and intimate correspondence with the Lusts in their Hearts, and what is carnal in them, that they fight against their Souls with great Advantage and Success. The Apostle having dehorted from the love of the World, and the things that are in the World, sums up all that is in the World in those three particulars, <hi>the Iust of the Flesh, the Iust of the Eyes, and the pride of Life.</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>5, 16. The Apostle speaks as if there were nothing else in the world but <hi>Lusting:</hi> because there is such a curse come upon all Creature-enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with reference to man, that so farre as He is of the world, they are Objects of Lust to Him, exciting, drawing forth, invigorating and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that Lust and Corruption that is in him. By these Lusts the Apostle means the several respective Objects, and puts the Lust which is in us for the things themselves lusted after, <hi>Carnal Pleasures, Profits</hi> and <hi>Preferments.</hi> He saith not sensual Pleasures, Riches, Honour (though he speaks of them) but the <hi>Lusts of the Flesh and Eye, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nd pride of Life;</hi> because our Lusts ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them evil to us (how lawful soever in themselves the Objects are) and make them Objects of Temptation and Seduction from the Lord, putting a painted Whorish Beauty and tempting Lustre upon them, varnishing them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and making false representations of them. Yea, <hi>it is evident</hi> (as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> observes Treatise of Temptat. <hi>pag.</hi> 68. <q>
                  <hi>That all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>se things</hi> (the Lust of the Flesh, &amp;c.) <hi>are principally in the Subject, not in the Object; in the Heart not in the World: But they are said to be in the World, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>cause the World gets into them, mixes it self with them, unites, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporates. As Faith and the promises are said to be mixed,</hi> Heb. 4 2. <hi>So are Lust and Temptation</hi> (from worldly Objects) <hi>mixed; they twine together, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> mutual improvement one from an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ther, grow each of them higher and higher by the mutual strength they administer to one another.</hi>
               </q> From this mixture, Union, and Incorporation of the Objects in the World with the Lusts in the Hearts of Men, and their firm and close combination toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it comes to pass that the enticing, tempting World is a very potent and prevailing Adversary to the Souls of Men: And that Believers themselves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>n whom the Lusts mentioned are but in part mortified and subdued) have hard work sometimes to stand their Ground against the snares and allurements and bewitching insinuations of a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ceitful World. To this Head reduce sinful Examples in the World, Counsels of Carnal Friends, the Friendship of the World, <hi>which is E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>mity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>o God and good men,</hi> Jam 4 4 <hi>False Doctrines</hi> which are spo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> out of the Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ld <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:100718:8"/>
4 5. calculated to the corrupt Humors, Inclinations and Interests of the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of the World, and therefore of a very grateful resentment with them. In a word, <hi>all Worldly Lusts</hi> (as the Apostle calls them, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 12) that are so many baits and snares to entangle and entice the People of God to desert the Holy and good wayes of the Lord: those <hi>Golden <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> that are thrown down before a Christian to invite him to g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ze upon them, and stoop to take them up, that so he may be retarded and stopt in his course, and lose the prize he runs for.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Troubles and Affrightments of the World.</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ightful Afflictions and persecutions that would im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e, or reta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d and hinder the people of God in their Travels towards that H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>enly Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, where the sweet Fruits of Divine Love are to be enjoyed in the greatest maturity and perfection of them. That <hi>Tribulation in the World</hi> against which the Lord Jesus layes in great encouragement from the consideration of his own Corquest of the World, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16. 33. Of this ill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment in the world, the Afflictions that the Children of God must expect to contest withal, the Apostle discourseth here, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 35, 36, 37. <hi>Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Distress, Persecution, Famine, Nakedness, Peril, Sword,</hi> and such like formidable things to Nature, oppose the Faithful in their way, and make warre upon them. A Christian lies open to many sharp and fiery Tryals, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 12. and must look to endure <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a great fight or Concertation of Afflictions, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 32. The World can put on two Faces, and change its Countenance as occasion servs. If feigned flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering smiles will not do, then killing Frowns shall, if it be possible. The World hath Terrours to affright, as well as Allurements to entice Believers out of the way of Happiness. The men of the world are usually pricks in the eyes, and Thorns or Scourges in the sides of Believers. <hi>Briers</hi> and <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>orns</hi> are <hi>with them</hi> in the world (as the Lord tells the Prophet, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 2. 6) that will scratch the Face of their Reputation, wound them in their outward Concernments, and tear th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ir Flesh: yea, they <hi>dwell among Scorpions,</hi> that will put them to great torment, and sting them to Death. <hi>Aelian</hi> reports concerning the <hi>Lybians, ocreatos dormire solere</hi> that they were wont to sleep with their Boots on, lest the Scorpions, their Country was infested with, should sting them. I am sure a Christian had need walk <hi>Booted,</hi> and have <hi>his Feet shod with the preparation of the Gospel of peace,</hi> yea, to be defended and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>med in all respects, or He will be in much danger of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>any scorpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>is way. <hi>vid. Greenhil</hi> on Ezek. 2. 6. As beleivers have bodies of flesh and mortality, that keep open House for sicknesses, pains, Dis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ses, and give Entertainment to them: So they are exposed to the Rage and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>reasonable men. They pass through an Enemie, Country, where
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100718:9"/>
they have many Affronts and Indignities offered them. If lies and Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, Scoffs and Scorns, angry looks and cruel threatnings, opprobrious and injurious dealings, or any kind of Cruelty may be likely to scare a Believer out of his way, or force Him to a dishonourable Retreat, or to run from his <hi>Colours</hi> by quitting his profession; the malignant angry world will be sure (if the Lord permit) to prove Him in that kind. In both the respects mentioned the world is an Enemy, and makes Opposition to Believers in their way to Glory. Furthermore a Believer meets with Opposition,</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>From Satan, the Prince and God of the World,</hi> Eph. 6. 11, 12. If a Christian were to try <hi>Masteries,</hi> and contest only with Flesh and bloud (whether we understand thereby his own Corruptions, or Opposition from men, like Himself) He would have hot and hard service of it. But this is his Case and Lot, to meet with Opposition from <hi>Principalities</hi> and <hi>Powers, the Rulers of the Darkness of this World, and spiritual wickedness in High pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi> He fights at great Disadvantage with Enemies, that have the Hill and upper-Ground. He combates hand to Hand with <hi>the God of the World;</hi> as well as his <hi>Creatures,</hi> the men of the world. Satan is one of the <hi>Allies</hi> of <hi>In-dwelling sin,</hi> and of Conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>deracy with our own Hearts, which are ready every moment, if there be not a strict watch kept upon them, to betray us into his Hands, and deliver us up to Him. A Christian had need look to Himself, considering that <hi>Satan goes about dai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y seeking to devour,</hi> 1 Pet. 5. 8. A Believer will be sure to meet with this <hi>Lion</hi> in his <hi>way.</hi> And our Flesh and Hearts (as was intimated before) are Satans <hi>Correspondents</hi> and <hi>Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates</hi> against the Spiritual Life, and Comfort, and Happiness of our Souls, ready to open to Him, make a Surrender of all, and comport with him in all his dangerous and destructive Applications of Himself unto us. This Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual <hi>Leviathan</hi> is a <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ercing Serpent</hi> and a <hi>crooked Serpent, Isai.</hi> 27. 1. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, he opposes the People of God by Force, and then he is a <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ercing Serpent,</hi> Sometimes he <hi>circumvents</hi> them by craft, and then He is a <hi>crooked Serpent. Vel rectus venit, vel tortuosus.</hi> Satan opposes the people of God in a way of Fraud, (He <hi>playes</hi> the <hi>Dragon</hi> and deceivs them: He is a <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent;</hi> yea, an <hi>old Serpent,</hi> Rev. 12. 9. and hath his Wiles, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 11. and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious Devices, <hi>t Cor.</hi> 2. 11. his methods of Deceit, and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s Depths or deep Contrivances, <hi>Rev</hi> 2. 24.) and in a way of force and violence. He acts the part of a <hi>Lion</hi> and rageth: and he hath his venemous Arrows, his fiery Darts, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 16. and makes many violent On-sets upon the Children or God. The Church of God, or the Body of Saints and Called Ones in the world, have <hi>the Gates of Hell</hi> (Math. 16. 18.) that is (as it is commonly expounded) the Power and Policy of the Devil, and his Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and <hi>Under-Agents,</hi> to oppose them in their way to Heaven, though they sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ll not prevail in that Opposition. Lastly,</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:100718:9"/>
4. <hi>From Death it self, which is the last Enemy.</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 26. When all the rest are beaten cut of the field, and a Christian is marching off and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ready to make his <hi>Triumphant Entrance</hi> into Heaven, <hi>Death</hi> encounte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> him. This comes in by the <hi>Curse:</hi> and the natural or direct tendency of it is to separate a Son of <hi>Adam</hi> from God for ever. It is the great and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Executioner</hi> of the vindictive justice of God. Here men enjoy some Fruits of (at least) the general and common goodness of God: but when Death comes, it pushes them away from God, makes an everlasting separation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, and all the fruits of the goodness of God, turns them into Hell, where they must feed upon the bitter Fruit of their own wayes for ever. When Death hath done its Execut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>on upon the Condemned Sons and Daughters of <hi>Adam,</hi> God will then carry away all his goodness from them, and never afford them so much <hi>as one drop of Water to cool their Tongues to Eternity.</hi> That which makes Death so terrible is, that in the ordinary course of it, it makes a perfect and perpetual separation between the Sons and Daughters of men, and all the Fruits of the <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Goodness,</hi> and <hi>Patience</hi> of the blessed God. <hi>Death passed upon all men, for that all have sinned,</hi> Rom. 5. 12. And where it Reigns and Triumphs, and is Victorious over any man, and fastens its <hi>Sting</hi> in him (as I may allude to 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 55.) it destroyes him utterly by putting him into a condition of everlasting sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from God. Now this is the <hi>last Adversary</hi> that the Believing <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Souldier</hi> contends withal; though upon more advantagious Terms then other men. Thus much for the second Particular under the second Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion. <hi>Every Believer meets with great opposition in his way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>A Believer cannot possibly make his way through all these Enemies, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ar down all this opposition without fighting.</hi> He skirmishes with these E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, yea, fights many a pitch'd Battel against them. <hi>He must put on the whole Armour of God,</hi> Eph. 6. 11. and keep it on, and make use of the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of his <hi>Christian Warfare,</hi> and his Faith and other Graces will be sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put to it. It costs him many a <hi>Bickering.</hi> He runs, and Wrestles, and labeurs, and strives, <hi>and fights the good fight of Faith:</hi> as we might demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate by many Scripture Instances. By <hi>Fighting,</hi> I mean a vigorous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending and conflicting with the Enemies of his Soul, which is exprest vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously by the Holy Ghost in Scripture. He must strive hard that will <hi>enter in at the strait Gate,</hi> Luk. 13. 24. ordinary seeking will not do it. If the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever put off his <hi>Armour,</hi> lay by his <hi>weapons,</hi> suffer the <hi>Sw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> to rust in the <hi>Scabberd,</hi> and draw it not forth as there is occasion; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> He hang down his Hands in Prayer, sink in his Hopes, cool in his Courage, and stand still in a secure careless manner; it will be impossible that he should b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>eak through those <hi>Legions</hi> of Devils, those <hi>Armies</hi> of Temptations, and make his way through those <hi>Adverse Powers,</hi> that oppose themselves in his wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to Happiness</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:100718:10"/>
4. <hi>As the Opposition from, at least, some of his Enemies is perpetual in this life:</hi> So the Believer hath <hi>no rest,</hi> but hath <hi>work enough</hi> every day to contest with them. A Believer hath a <hi>restless E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>my</hi> to contend withal, as <hi>Hamibal</hi> said of <hi>Marcellus</hi> the <hi>Roman Consul</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Plutarch, Marcel.</hi> Let him conquer or be conquered, he would never be quiet nor give over, neither <hi>give</hi> rest to his Enemy, nor <hi>tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> it himself, he would be <hi>at it</hi> still, and never have done. So may we say much more of the <hi>Believers Enemies.</hi> Satan never draws his Forces out of the Field. Corruptions one way or other will be stirring, and the <hi>Christian</hi> shall be exercised <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ill</hi> with some <hi>Thorn in the Flesh,</hi> and <hi>Buf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>etings of Satans Messenger.</hi> The People in <hi>Nehemiab</hi>'s time, when they were Alarmd' and afraid of their <hi>malicious</hi> and <hi>malignant Neighbours, wrought with one hand and held a weapon in the other,</hi> Nehem. 4. 17. But such is the case of a Christian, that he must not only work, with a Weapon in the other hand, but he must actually use his Weapon whilest he is working; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ghting with one hand, and building or labouring with the other. If his Enemies conquer, they will be sure to prosecute their victory to the utmost, and lose no Advantage: if they be worsted and routed in any particular Engagement, they will not fail to rally their Forces, recruit and reinforce themselves presently and fall on again. So that a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian had need eat and drink and sleep in his Arms. He hath no time to <hi>put off his Armour, to lay by his Weapons.</hi> He will be hotly engaged till the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 3. 19. <hi>the times of refreshing and cooling shall come.</hi> He can never be said in this world to be <hi>miles emer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>us,</hi> or <hi>stipendia confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>sse:</hi> which were the <hi>Roman Phras<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> for them that were discharged from the Wars. If a Christian live to <hi>threescore years</hi> of age or more, he is not thereby <hi>superannuated,</hi> nor can he plead <hi>Age</hi> or any thing else to excuse him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self from the duty of a Souldier. Verily there is no discharge in this War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare on this side of the Grave. There is no bringing of these Enemies to a composition, no cessation to be made, no League or Truce to be admitted in this Warfare. A Christian must be constantly fighting and contending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the Enemies of his peace and happiness. Thus much for the second Conclusion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concl.</hi> 3. <hi>A true Believer is never totally and absolutely conquered in any Engagemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> with the Enemies that War against him.</hi> To be Conquered sin the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>se I take it here) is to be separated from the Love of God, and utterly deprived of the special fruits of it. <hi>Who shall separate us</hi> (saith the Apostle <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 35) <hi>from the love of Christ?</hi> that is, <hi>who shall conquer us?</hi> I am perswaded that <hi>neither Death <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>r Life, nor Angel, &amp;c. shall be able to separate us from the love of God, which is in Christ Iesus our Lord,</hi> Rom. 8.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100718:10"/>
38, 39. Importing thus much, that a Christian can never be totally conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, notwithstanding all the opposition that is made against him. Let Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies do what they can against him, yet if he be not separated from the love of God, he is not absolutely Conquered, or defeated of his Happiness. In this respect a Believer <hi>is never Conquered.</hi> For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Nothing befals him in his Warfare, notwithstanding what his Enemies attempt against him, that turns away the Heart of God utterly from him.</hi> Though Sin and Satan may prevail very far in some conflicts, yet never to such a degree as to provoke the Lord to reject him, and cast him out of his favour. God may be provoked by the compliances of a Believer at some turns with Sin and Satan and the World to take away the manifestations of his Love, to deny him some expressions of his Favour, <hi>to visit his transgressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with a Rod, and his iniquity with Stripes;</hi> but <hi>never to take his loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindness utterly from him,</hi> Psal. 89. 30—33. A Believer may be so foiled and worsted by his Enemies, through the neglect of his watch, or otherwise, that God may be displeased with him; that there may be a discontinuance of the sensible expressions of the love of God to him, and an interruption of it as to manifestations: and yet there is no intercision of the love of God to him, as to the being of it. <hi>His love to him is unchangeable and everlasting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Nothing fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s out in his progress or march that absolutely flops him in, or diverts him f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>om his course of proceeding, or moving towards the enjoyment of the sweet fruits of Divine Love.</hi> A Believer may be wounded, Lemed, and retarded; but not totally checked in his way, and turned aside from it. He may receive many a blow that staggers him, that makes him reel and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, that wounds him in his Graces and comforts. <hi>David had his Bones broken,</hi> received <hi>deep and dangerous wounds that were long healing,</hi> that <hi>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ank and were corrupt,</hi> Psal. 38. 5. 7, 8. Because he did not apply a timely Remedy unto them; they were not presently searched and looked after. He was knock'd down and lay in a swoon for a great while, that those about him might be ready to fear he would never come to himself again: but he revived and recovered at last. Satan prevailed with him to commit Folly with <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hsheba,</hi> to murder and imbrue his hands in the Blood of <hi>Vriah,</hi> to vent his pride and vain glorious humor in the numbring of the People, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>re the displeasure of God thereby: but all this did not ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>uss and expel the Love of God out of his heart, or divert him totally from prosecuting the enjoyment of it. Take a Believer in his lowest condition, when he is most worsted and prevailed upon by his Enemies: yet at that time there is the <hi>Seed of God remaining in him</hi> (1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 9.) <hi>that inclines <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> carries him God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ard.</hi> There is a power of Grace, and a work of the Spir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> upon his Heart that gives him an inclination, bent, &amp; tendency Godward cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ually; and though temptations may turn him out of the way for a time, and he may
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100718:11"/>
meet with many <hi>Rubs</hi> and <hi>Impediments</hi> in his <hi>Christian race;</hi> yet there is the strong Byas of <hi>Grace,</hi> the poize and impression of Gods spirit upon his heart that inclines and carries him Godward; so that he will come in again, though he may be turned off for a while. That general Bent &amp; Inclination of his heart towards God, <hi>as his last end &amp; greatest good,</hi> &amp; towards his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as the only best Rules of living and walking, is ever preserved in the Believer by the mighty power of God (according to his Covenant-en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement) even then when his Enemies have gotten him down and laid him at their Feet. So that if the Lord never take away his loving-kindness utterly from the Believer, nor the Believer totally lose his love to God: what follows? but that there can be no separation of a true Believer from the love of God in Christ Jesus, and by consequence that he cannot be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely conquered <hi>in any,</hi> though he may be worsted in <hi>some</hi> Engagements.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concl.</hi> 4. <hi>Every true Believer manageth a successful War, and is sure of Conquest.</hi> My meaning is not that every Christian hath a certainty of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion that he shall prevail, or overcome; for many an one is ready to say sometimes <hi>that he shall one day fall by the hand of this or that Saul:</hi> but there is a certainty of the thing in it self. I speak of the certainty of the object, or the truth of this Proposition [Every Believer shall certainly conquer the Enemies of his Soul] not of the certainty of the Subject, the certioration of the Believer, or his perswasion and assurance that he shall be victorious at last. A Believer shall certainly win the day and conquer all Opposers, whatever his unbelieving heart may at any time suggest to the contrary. Hence <hi>Paul</hi> speaks of it as a thing done: <hi>we do more then overcome.</hi> This may be made out thus:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A Believer in this life gets many signal Victories.</hi> He is not able in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed utterly to drive out the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> they will abide in his Land (Heart, I mean) and be rebelling and vexing him frequently: but the Lord gives him many remarkable victories over them. There are some memorable dayes and happy times wherein the People of God come out of the Field victorious, and triumph over their spiritual Enemies. They <hi>set their feet in the neck of their Lusts, and lay their Corruptions bleeding at their feet,</hi> and do so resist Satan as to <hi>rout him and put him to flight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>If he be for a time overcome, yet he recovers himself at last and gets the Day.</hi> He may be overcome, <hi>and carried Captive</hi> (as the Apostle intimates Rom. 7. 23.) he may be remarkably worsted in some particular conflicts, and taken Prisoner: but he cannot be detained alwayes a Prisoner, all the power and policy of his Adversaries cannot hold him, he will make an escape from them sooner or later, and obtain rescue and deliverance. If he be foiled, and laid on his back for a time; yet it is not long before he reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers himself, and gets up again by godly sorrow, Humiliation and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and renew; the Combat, and is too hard for his Enemies. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> he be routed, he rallies again, and never leaves fighting, till he carries the day, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100718:11"/>
go out of the Field a <hi>Conquerour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>His Enemies lose Ground by all their partial Conquests of Him.</hi> A Child of God gets Good by his Foils and Falls, yea, gets Ground insensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of his Corruptions and other Enemies thereby. His Enemies by win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Day, lose it; and by Conquering, are conquered. Every victory that Sin and Satan obtain, makes a gracious Heart more humble, more sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible of his own weakness, and absolute need of the strength of Christ, more watchful against Sin and Temptation, more Cautious for time to come of admitting Parlyes and Compliances with his Adversares, and so turne (through the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ver-ruling Hand of Grace)</hi> to the <hi>singular Advantage</hi> of a Christian in many respects. Lay these things together, and it will be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest that a Believer manages a very <hi>successful warre,</hi> and is sure at last of an <hi>absolute Conquest.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concl. 5. <hi>A Believers Victory and Conquest is incomparably Glorious. His Conquest is most exceeding Glorious.</hi> Thence <hi>Paul</hi> saith, <hi>we are more then Conquerours.</hi> We do not only <hi>Conquer,</hi> but <hi>triumph;</hi> we have a <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant Victory:</hi> we are much too hard for our Enemies, we do <hi>more then overcome,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>supervineimus,</hi> we <hi>do over-overcome.</hi> It is <hi>Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>tius</hi> his Observation. <hi>Amat Paulus componere verba cum</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> loves th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Composition</hi> of words with the <hi>Preposition</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and He gives many other Instances (besides this in the Text) of such Compositions in <hi>Pauls Epistles.</hi> When He speaks of the <hi>Rich Grace of God,</hi> or of the great and glorious pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of his Children, He thinks He cannot over-speak. They are such things, that, as <hi>Luther</hi> said of God and Heaven, <hi>non patiuntur Hyperbolen,</hi> do not admit, are not capable of an <hi>Hyperbole.</hi> No Expression is so high, or <hi>Superlative,</hi> as to transcend and exceed the measure of the Excellency of such Things. Now the Greatness and <hi>Gloriousness</hi> of a Believers <hi>Uictory</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in many Things, which we shall but glance at, as we pass along. Glorious it is, in that the Believer conquers in Suffering, when He is in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance conquered, overcome and destroyed. <hi>When He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>sslain with the Sword, devoured by Lions, burnt to Ashes a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> a Stake, sawn asunder,</hi> or any way violently put to death; yet <hi>in all these things</hi> he conquers, as the Martyrs have done. They overcome <hi>by the Bloud of the Lamb, the word of their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony, and not loving their lives unto the Death.</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Gualther</hi> takes this to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the sense of the Apostle. <hi>In all these Things we are more then Conquerours.</hi> He doth not say we overcome <hi>all these things,</hi> so as that they shall be no more, or cease to oppose us; But <hi>in all these things we</hi> Conquer. <hi>For afflictions remain, and will remain as long as the World lasts, nor will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ons ever cease, which beget Banishment, Famine, Nakedness an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> the Sword to the Godly: but in these things, and among all these pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ils and evil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> of Suffering, the Faithfull do more then overcome. And this is admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:100718:12"/>
                  <hi>that they over<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>me, when</hi> suecub uisse, &amp; omnino Victi aut Oppressi esse videntur; <hi>when they are slain, or burnt, or destroyed</hi> any other-way.</q> 
               <hi>They are killed all the day long, accounted</hi> (and used) <hi>as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eep for the slaughter;</hi> as in the verse before the Text: And yet <hi>more then Conquerours.</hi> Humane, Carnal Reason cannot comprehend this. It is indeed <hi>Mysterious</hi> and <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious.</hi> Again, Glorious it is, in that he conquers such Enemies as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer all but Himself, and such as He is. The great Conquerours of the World have been slaves to their own <hi>Pride, Ambition, vain-glory, Covetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> and other base Lusts, which a Christian subdues and Conquers. Many of them have been Satans Slaves, when they have been Masters of the world. But the Believer <hi>resists the Devil,</hi> and puts Him to flight. He overcomes Himself (which is a nobler Exploit then to evercome and Conquer Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,) sets his Foot upon Satan, tramples and crushes that Serpent, <hi>(Rom.</hi> 16. 20.) treads the World under his Feet, as the Church of God, the <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 1. is said to have <hi>the Moon</hi> (that is, all these changeable Earthly things) <hi>under her feet.</hi> Nay, he overcomes <hi>Death</hi> it self, which tramples upon and prevailes over other Conquerours. <hi>Death</hi> stings, kills; ruines other men, but cannot <hi>hurt a Christian,</hi> because it cannot separate him from God. <hi>Oh Death! where is thy sting? Oh Grave, where is thy Victory?</hi> 1 Cor. 15 55. Those words which are commonly translated <hi>the Gates of Hell,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 18. and are thought to import the Power and Policy of the Devil, are rendred by Learned <hi>Camero,</hi> the <hi>Gates of the grave, or Death,</hi> alledging that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth never but once in Scripture signifie <hi>Hell,</hi> but either <hi>the Grave,</hi> or the <hi>state</hi> and <hi>condition</hi> of a <hi>deceased person:</hi> And he conceives the mind of our Saviour in that expression to be, that though the Faithfull lye dead for a time as well as other men, <hi>Death exercises a Dominion over them,</hi> the <hi>worm feeds sweetly upon them,</hi> they are imprisoned in the Grave, and lye bound <hi>hand and foot</hi> with the <hi>Cords of death.</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>unes vel acerbissimi Cruciatus Mortis. Psal.</hi> 18. 3.) yet that the Power of Death and the Grave shall not finally prevaile over them. <hi>Si quis</hi> (saith that Learned man) <hi>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>urat a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ac Loeutione significatum velit, perituram omnem Mortis &amp; Sepulchri vim, is demùm profecto a Spiritûs sancti mente mini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> è aberraverit.</hi> The Aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the destructive Dominion of Death is intended by the Lord Jesus, according to this Exposition. <hi>Christiani</hi> (saith Cyprian) <hi>mori possunt, vinci non possunt.</hi> Christians may dye, but cannot be overcome. Death may kill them, but cannot conquer them. The victory of Believers over their Enemies is very glorious in this respect. Glorious also it is in that a Believer conquers his Enemies by cor quering himself, <hi>crucifying himself (the Flesh with the Affections and Lusts,</hi> Gal 5. 24.) <hi>subduing his own Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:100718:12"/>
               <hi>beating down his own Body and bringing it into subjection</hi> (1 Cor. 9. 27.) <hi>plucking out an offending right Eye, cutting off an offending right Hand:</hi> (Mat. 5. 29. 30.) Doing strange Execution upon himself in a way of <hi>Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> which is both a noble and a strange way of Conquering. He overcomes himself and thereby overcomes all his Enemies. Moreover glorious it is in that he is so far from being separated from the love of God by the opposition which his Enemies make against him, that he is thereby greatly furthered in the way to the perfect enjoyment of the Fruits of it. His Enemies, whether they will or no, help him to a most Glorious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest. <hi>For all things</hi> (how adverse and opposite soever) <hi>work for his good, Rom.</hi> 8. 28. that is, <hi>for his most Glorious, Everlasting Triumph in the highest Heavens.</hi> As the Afflictions and Troubles which happened to <hi>Paul</hi> in the course of his <hi>Ministerial Warfare</hi> fell out to the furtherance of the Gospel, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 12. so the Opposition which a Believer meets with from all his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries, falls out to the furtherance of his victorious proceedings in the course of his <hi>Christian Warfare,</hi> and of his <hi>After-Triumph</hi> and <hi>Glory.</hi> Nay this Victory is Glorious, in that he gives his Enemies a total Defeat and Overthrow at last. He hath a perfect and absoute Victory and Conquest over them, so as never to be molested with them more. <hi>He passes to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven through the midst of his Enemies,</hi> and gets out of the reach of their oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, or molestation, and there Triumphs Gloriously to Eternity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concl.</hi> 6. <hi>Every Believer ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ains this Glorious Victory and Conquest through the Lord Iesus Christ. We are more then Conquerours through him that loved us,</hi> that is, through Jesus Christ, or God in Christ which is the same thing. The Apostle having discoursed excellently of this <hi>Spiritual War</hi> with one of the greatest Enemies that a Christian hath to do with, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>In-dwelling sin,</hi> issues all triumphantly in thanks to God through Christ for Deliverance and Victory, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. <hi>ult.</hi> And having spoken of <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ath</hi> &amp; the <hi>Grave,</hi> very formidable Adversaries, &amp; triumphed over them, <hi>Thanks God who gives Victory through Christ,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 55, 56, 57. And there is the like Reason as to all the Enemies of a Christian. A Believer obtains this incomparable Victory and Glorious Conquest over all through Christ. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Lord Iesus Christ hath procured and purchased this Victory and Conquest for Believers.</hi> Therefore he hath <hi>Suffered</hi> and <hi>Dyed, Satisfied</hi> and <hi>Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ted,</hi> that his People might obtain a Glorious Victory over Sin, Satan, World, Death, and all their Enemies. The Foundation of this Victory hath been la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d by an <hi>high hand of Grace</hi> in the <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Medi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of the Lord Jesus. Man having revolted from under the Government and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Gods revealed Will and Law, and thrown off his Obedience, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> made Election of Sin and Satan for his Lords and Sovereigns; The Holy God in Justice and Righteous Severity, delivers him up to the Authority and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100718:13"/>
Soveraignty of Sin and Satan, and his Spiritual Enemies, even Death it self: and they put in their Claim to a <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> yea, and actually exercise a Dominion over Him; So that man in this Condition is a <hi>Captive, Prisoner, Slave,</hi> and cannot get his <hi>Liberty.</hi> If He struggle sometimes, and rise up to warre against them; All his Contendings are vain, He is overcome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently, and held in bondage. The Reason is, because his Enemies are (in a Sense) as strong as the Law and Justice of God. <hi>The strength of Sin</hi> (and by pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ity of Reason, of other Enemies) is the Law, <hi>I Cor.</hi> 15. 56. that is, <hi>the Law broken, and the Iustice of God offended.</hi> But the Lord Jesus having satisfied and merited, when there is an <hi>Application</hi> of that <hi>Redemption</hi> which is in Christ to any man; Now <hi>Sin, Satan, World,</hi> have no <hi>Right</hi> to exercise this <hi>Dominion;</hi> they lose their Claim and Title to such <hi>Dominion,</hi> and this is the <hi>Foundation</hi> of any man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Conquest</hi> of them. Hence though <hi>Sin</hi> may <hi>Tyrannise</hi> sometimes, yet it <hi>shall not reign over them;</hi> not have any of their Enemies any Right to Conquer or prevail, as before. Nay, Christ hath <hi>paid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> great price,</hi> and <hi>bought</hi> the <hi>Victory</hi> for them of Him in whose Hand it is to adjudge it unto them. <hi>They overcome by the Bloud of the Lamb,</hi> Rev. 12. 11.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>He hath actually in his own person conquered their enemies for them, Be of good Comfort</hi> (saith our Saviour) <hi>I have overcome the World,</hi> Joh. 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. That is, <hi>the Lusts of the world, the men of the world, the prince of the world, the shares, temptations, terrours and evils of the World. He hath bru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>sed the Serpents head,</hi> Gen. 3. 15. <hi>destroyed the works of the Devil,</hi> I Joh. 3. 8. <hi>Now</hi> (saith the Lord Jesus with reference to the time of his sufferings) <hi>is the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this World, now shall the Prince of this World be castout,</hi> Joh. 12. 31. The Dethroning of Satan, and destruction of his Dominion by Jesus Christ is that which is intended in that expression. Hence the Apostle saith, that <hi>be spoiled Principalities and Powers,</hi> and <hi>and made a shew of them openly tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing over them in it</hi> (that is, his Cross) <hi>or in himself,</hi> Col. 2. 15. The Lord Jesus took away the <hi>Prey</hi> or <hi>Boo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> of Souls, which Satan had gotten, and led away the Devil and his Angels, as <hi>Prisoners of War:</hi> He divested <hi>Principalities and Powers,</hi> that is, the <hi>Apostate Angels,</hi> of all that Title they had got to the World by the sin of man, yea he triumphed over them as <hi>sawful Captives</hi> to be disposed of at his pleasure. He hath <hi>bound the strong man armed &amp; spoiled his Goods.</hi> Thus Christ is said to <hi>wound the Head</hi> (for so is it in the Original, not <hi>Heads) over many Countries,</hi> Psal. 110, 6. By <hi>the Head <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the large Earth,</hi> Some understand Satan that ruleth as Head o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Children of disobedience every where: though I judge it better to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>pound it to the most comprehensive sense, and then the meaning is, <hi>that Christ breaks in pieces the Head,</hi> that is, the counsel and power of Satan and all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>is Instruments, crushing and conquering all the Enemies of his People.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100718:13"/>
               <hi>He hath conquered Death is self,</hi> and having grapled and fought with that <hi>Serpent,</hi> he hath pulled out the <hi>Sting,</hi> and he hath disarmed <hi>that King of Terrours,</hi> that it may be in no condition to hurt and ruine his People. Death can be no longer a <hi>Curse</hi> to them; but a <hi>Blessing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> An <hi>Out let</hi> as to Misery<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and an <hi>In-let</hi> to all Happiness. He hath <hi>Conquered</hi> and <hi>triumphed</hi> over all the Enemies of Believers, vertually on his <hi>Crosse,</hi> but actually and effectually in his <hi>Exaltation: when he ascended up on high, he led Captivity Captive,</hi> Eph. 4. 8. Psal. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>. 18. And he hath <hi>Conquered</hi> and <hi>Triumphed</hi> over all out <hi>Enemies,</hi> not for himself, but on our behalf, and for our behoof and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. <hi>Victoria Domini est Servorum Triumphus. Hieron.</hi> The Victory of the Lord is the Triumph of the Servants. Well may the Army of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers be assured of Victory and Triumph, when as they fight with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered Enemy, and their General alone in his own person hath routed their Adversaries.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>He puts them into a Conquering-capacity.</hi> He sends his Spirit to make the Application of his Redemption to all his Redeemed ones by working <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>aith in their Hearts,</hi> drawing them to himself, giving them an actual Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest in himself, and his Benefits, and putting them into a State of Justifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is a State of Victory and Triump<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>. A justified person is in a Conquering-capacity and condition. He is under Grace, and not under the Law, therefore <hi>neither Sin, nor any other Enemy shall have dominion over him,</hi> Rom. 6. 14. Take an Elect person, that was given to Christ by the Father from Eternity, and Redeemed by Christ in the fulness of time, yet before his effectual vocation, he is under the feet of his Enemies, in no better condition to fight it out with them then other men; <hi>Sin,</hi> and <hi>Satan,</hi> and <hi>World</hi> are much too hard for him. But when once the Spirit of Christ hath wrought an effectual work of Grace in his Soul, &amp; by uniting him to the Lord Jesus hath brought him into a state of Justification: now he is in a condition to dispute it out to the last with all his Enemies, and to get the day also. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Justified person is invincible, he cannot be Conquered; and he is victorious, none of his Enemies can stand before him. <hi>Victory</hi> &amp; <hi>Triumph</hi> are adjudged by the Lord to a state of Justification, and are infallible consequents thereof. Hence <hi>Paul</hi>'s comfortable perswasion, and Triumphant Expressions, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 38, 39. <hi>Now all the People of God are admitted into this state of Iustification, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ested in the Glorious Priviledges of it, through the Lord Iesus Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>He furnisheth Believers with skill, and Strength, and Courage, and Weapons, and all War-like Furniture, and Military Qualifications, and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishments.</hi> They are in all respects well appointed for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ar: and it is the Lord Jesus that sets them fort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, and furnisheth them with A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s and Weapons for the Battel. The Lord Jesus Christ is the <hi>Christians Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zin.</hi> All those Arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and Weapons which a Believer useth in his spiritual
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100718:14"/>
conflicts (of which you have an enumeration, <hi>Eph. s.</hi> 6. 13, 14, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> are such as come out of Christs Armory. As he puts the Believer into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering state, in his Justification; so he gives him conquering Abilities in his Sanctification. He gives them <hi>Skill</hi> and <hi>Valour,</hi> and <hi>Resolution,</hi> and all other <hi>Qualifications</hi> and <hi>Endowments</hi> that a Militant condition calls for.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>He Administors seasonable supplies and recruits of Grace and Strength unto them.</hi> He sends them <hi>Auxiliary Forces,</hi> and gives them such Assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance as they need for every Conflict. <hi>He giveth Power to them when they are faint, and when they h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ve no might, encreaseth their strength,</hi> Isai. 40. 29. <hi>He gives them a sufficiency of Grace, and his Power rests on them.</hi> Hence <hi>when they are we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>k, yet then they are strong,</hi> 2 Cor. 12. 9, 10. Because habitual inhevent Grace will not carry them through their <hi>difficult Engagements,</hi> therefore he affords actual, and occasional Assistance as their necessities re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. All that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that seasonable help which is Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistred to Believers from the Throne of Grace <hi>(Heb.</hi> 4. 16.) comes from the Lord Jesus Christ. They have the immutable Assistance of the <hi>Spirit of Christ that dwells in them.</hi> They must needs overcome in this respect, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause <hi>greater it be that is in them, then he that is in the World,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Joh. 4. 4. Hence the Apostle, that had low thoughts of himself, and was as much <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> in his own eyes as any man, yet attributes a kind of <hi>Omnipotency</hi> to himself. <hi>I can do all things through Christ which strengtheneth me,</hi> Phil. 4. 13. <hi>He strengtheneth them with all might,</hi> Col. 1. 11.</p>
            <p>Concl. 7. <hi>The Love of God in Christ is the absolute first cause of those <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>torious proceedings, and this infallible conquest of Believers.</hi> For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Everlasting love of God determines, that the Victory shall fall on the side of Believers.</hi> The will of God is that all Believers shall conquer. Hence the Apostle layes the <hi>Foundation</hi> of this <hi>Triumph</hi> in <hi>Divine Predesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> and in <hi>Gods being for us,</hi> Rom. 8. 30, 31. Those that are appointed to obtain Salvation by Jesus Christ (as it may be concluded of all Believers; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ving Faith being a special fruit of Election) may meet with many Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies in their way, but shall infallibly break throughall opposition, &amp; g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t to Heaven at last. The Love of God hath <hi>Decreed</hi> them Victory.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The everlasting Love of God layes in suitable provision of means for an infallible conquest.</hi> Divine Love concluded upon the mission of Christ into the World, to purchase it for his People, and obtain the victory in his own person, as a <hi>common person</hi> representing all Believers. This Love gives them a <hi>Leo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and <hi>General</hi> (the Lord Jesus Christ) that is invincible, <hi>the Captain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the Host of the Lord,</hi> that appeared to <hi>Ioshuae,</hi> Josh. 5. 13, 14. It arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> them with invincible Graces, offensive and defensive; and orders them the insuperable and invincible Assistance of the Spirit of Christ, and the needful supplies and recruits of Assisting Grace. The Love of God in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100718:14"/>
Christ furnisheth the Christian Souldier compleatly every way with all that he needs in order to the Conquest of his Enemies; so that he is better provided for the Combate, and hath more Assistance in the Combate, and more assurance (consequently) of success, then any other Conquerours have. The Christian Souldier is well appointed and set forth for the War, Recruited and Assisted in it at the cost and charges of the Love of God in Jesus Christ.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The Everlasting Love of God adjudges them Triumph at last, and Crowns them with it.</hi> Divine Love sets the Glorious Crown upon the Head of the persevering, victorious, all-conquering Believer. There is a Glorious Day coming, wherein the Believer shall receive the reward of all his Labours and Travels and Combatings with <hi>the Flesh, the World, and the Devil:</hi> And this reward will be adjudged to <hi>him that overcometh,</hi> and actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally conferred upon him by the Grace and Love of God in Jesus Christ. Not his Merit, but Gods Mercy and Love will then Crown him. His present sufferings in the time of his <hi>Warfare</hi> are not worthy to be compared with the <hi>Glory that shall be revealed in him,</hi> Rom. 8. 18. <hi>When Paul had fought his good fight, and finished the cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>se of his warfare,</hi> he expected his <hi>Triumph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Crown from the Lord, the Righteous Iudge,</hi> 2 Tim. 4. 7, 8 A Crown of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Grace it is, and also a Crown of Righteousness: there being a sweet concurrence of the <hi>Remunerative Iustice of God</hi> with his <hi>Infinite Mercy, Grace,</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> in that Glorious work of <hi>Crowning a persevering Christian Souldier with everlasting Triumph and Glory.</hi> Divine Love adjudges and bestows upon Believers at last the Heavenly Prize they run for, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible Crown they fight for in this World. That they Triumph Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally is from the Love of God in Christ. Thus much for the Doctrinal part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Use</hi> 1. We might improve this Observation, <hi>To crush that Errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conceit of the Arminians, concerning the possibility of a Regenerate man's total and final Apostacy.</hi> For to assert this, is to say, that a Believer may be totally defeated and overcome, and Sin, Satan and World may prevaile over him to his utter <hi>Ruine.</hi> The Truth we have discoursed, is ready prest to <hi>militate</hi> against the men of that <hi>Heteredox perswasion:</hi> and is alone (without the Levy of any other force<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>) of strength sufficient to <hi>fight that Enemy and beat him out of the field.</hi> This Text of the Apostle, and the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation we have deduced from it, smites those Adversaries of the Doctrine of Perseverance under the <hi>fifth Rib,</hi> or rather <hi>stabs their fifth Article</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Apostacy of Saints</hi> to the Heart. This one Weap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> if it be well managed and weilded will do real and through Execution. For if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>re may be a total &amp; final defection of Believers, or falling from Grace, &amp; ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of the favour of God, then there is a possibility that a Believer may be totally &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally separated from the love of God: &amp; so totally conquered; which is diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trally
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100718:15"/>
opposite to the Strain and Genius, and Intendment of the Apostles Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course &amp; what we have been regularly superstructing upon it. But let it be enough to have thus <hi>Faced</hi> that Grand Enemy the <hi>Arminian,</hi> without engaging further on this occasion in any pitch'd confutation of him.</p>
            <p>Use 2. <hi>This makes it appear who are the bravest Souldiers, the most Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Warriours, Persons of the greatest Bravery and Gallantry in the World.</hi> They are Believing Men and Women. A Christian Man or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is by many degrees a better Souldier then <hi>Caesar</hi> or <hi>Alexander.</hi> Sincere Believers, of all degrees and conditions, are persons of eminency this way. Among the victorious Worthies, whose Famous Exploits and Atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are Recorded, <hi>Hib.</hi> 11. The Apostle doth not leave Believing Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men out of the <hi>Catalogue.</hi> We read of great Exploits that have been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, even by those of the <hi>weaker Seu,</hi> both in Sacred and Common Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story: but none to be compared with those which Believing Women, through Faith, have enterprized and accomplished. <hi>O Woman, great is thy Faith,</hi> saith our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15 28. Why then it might be said also, <hi>O Woman, great is thy Victory:</hi> For this is the Victory that overcometh the World, <hi>even our Faith,</hi> 1 Joh. 5. 4. True Faith, though it be but <hi>as a Grain of Mustard Seed,</hi> will overcome and bear down all that opposition the World can make against it. As to this Christian Warfare, Victory and Triumph, Believers of all sorts share in it: there is no difference in this matter, but <hi>Iew</hi> and <hi>Greek, Bond</hi> and <hi>Free, Male</hi> and <hi>Female</hi> are all one in this respect through Jesus Christ. The weakest Believer will be too hard for the strongest Adversary. This is a clear Consequence from what we have discoursed, that a Believer is the bravest, and most victorious Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier in the World.</p>
            <p>Use 3. <hi>A word of singular Encouragement and Comfort unto all that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ourn for the sorrowful state and Condition of</hi> Jerusalem. Know it, and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, that the Church of God, <hi>however aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>icted and oppressed in the world,</hi> shall certainly <hi>prevail</hi> and get the <hi>Day</hi> at last. The <hi>Victories</hi> &amp; <hi>Triumphs</hi> that God hath decreed and determined shall certainly be awarded and given to the <hi>conflicting Militant-Church</hi> in the Season thereof. How might we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postulate the Case with the <hi>mightiest</hi> of the <hi>Churches</hi> Adversaries? with the High and Low, Great and Small ones of the Earth in this respect? <hi>why do the Nations rage and People imagine a vain Thing?</hi> vain it is, and will be found so in the Issue, to oppose the Lord Jesus, to fight against his M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>mbers, to plot and pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ct, design and endeavour the Ruine of the <hi>Inter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>st of Christ in the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> For the Lord Jesus, and his called, and Faithful &amp; Chosen, shall certai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> more then overcame</hi> at last. The <hi>Lamb</hi> and his <hi>Followers</hi> shall be <hi>Illust<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ious so quero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s.</hi> The <hi>Beast may arise out of the Bottomless pit,</hi> and raise the <hi>Posse Inferni,</hi> or <hi>Inferorum,</hi> come with <hi>Legions of D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>vile,</hi> and their
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100718:15"/>
Instruments, and set their <hi>Hellish<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Armies</hi> in <hi>Aray,</hi> and <hi>make warre upon the Witnesses and overcome them for a while:</hi> but they shall overcome at last in a <hi>glorious manner.</hi> Verily, <hi>no Weapon that is formed against the Church shall prosper:</hi> Christ laughs at all the Confederacies and Complotments, and mad Rage of the world against <hi>his Interest and Members:</hi> Psal. 2. 4. And his People (that are at present in a sad and sorrowful Condition in the <hi>Heat</hi> of the <hi>Engagement)</hi> shall laugh too, and <hi>Triumph</hi> over all. Excellent were the Expressions of that man of Faith, <hi>Martin Luther</hi> to this purpose. <q>That the <hi>Kings and Princes &amp; People do so rage against the Lord and his Christ,</hi> I account (faith he) an <hi>Happy Omen,</hi> and much better then if they fawned and flattered: For it follows (in the second <hi>Psalm) He that sitteth in the Heavens shall laugh at them.</hi> Hoc autem principe nostro illos ridente, non video cur nobis fle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>dum sit a facie illorum. <hi>As long as our King laughs at them, I see no Reuson why we should cry for them.</hi>
               </q> They that make Christ laugh by their ridiculous Opposition, should not make his People cry. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily every Believer hath that in his Heart (I mean <hi>the Victorious all-conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Grace of Faith)</hi> whose <hi>Prerogative</hi> it is <hi>to laugh to scorn</hi> all the foolish plots, and ill contrived Designs, and feeble Attempts of men against Christ and his Church. For indeed their <hi>wise<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Contrivances</hi> are <hi>Foolishness,</hi> and their strongest Endeavours against the <hi>impregnable and invincible</hi> Interest of Christ and his Church, are <hi>weakness it self,</hi> and will appear so at last. And if Christ <hi>laughs at them,</hi> why should not his Friends and Followers also? <q>For he laughs (as <hi>Luther</hi> goes on) <hi>not for his own, but for our sake, that we also through Faith may laugh at the vain Counsels of Men: S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> much</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>need there is of Faith, that the Cause of Faith may not be managed without Faith,</hi> Ne Causa Fidei sit sine Fide. He that is sure of Victory may well laugh in the Face of his Enemies. Now though wicked men <hi>are plowing and making long Furrows on the Backs of the Righteous,</hi> yet the Lord will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly cut their Traces. The blessed Lord Jesus leads and assists his People, and the <hi>Shout</hi> of a <hi>King</hi> and <hi>General</hi> is among them, <hi>Numb.</hi> 23. 21 And that is assurance enough of Victory. What an <hi>invincible Army</hi> must the <hi>Body of Saints</hi> and <hi>Believers</hi> needs be, whereof not only the <hi>General,</hi> but every private Souldier is <hi>Invincible?</hi> They shall say at last, <hi>Lo this is our God, we have waited for him, And he hath saved us,: this is the Lord, we have waited for him, and n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>w we will be glad and rejoyce in his Salvation,</hi> when all <hi>Moabs shall be trodden down as Straw for the Dunghil,</hi> Is<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>5 9, 10. O Beloved! <hi>Lift up your Heads and Hands</hi> and be encouraged. Though it is <hi>a day of Trouble and perplenity</hi> and <hi>of doub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ful Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ectations</hi> in ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects, yet in the eye of <hi>Faith</hi> it is an <hi>hopeful Time</hi> and a <hi>promising Sease<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> when the world (this blind and mad world) is in a <hi>Tumult</hi> and <hi>Upro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> against the Church of Christ. The great and glorious Things that are to be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100718:16"/>
fulfilled, the <hi>faithful and true sayings</hi> of God cannot be accomplished by the Quietness and sitting still of the <hi>Nations.</hi> When the world <hi>rageth</hi> against the Church, and is up in <hi>Arms</hi> to <hi>make havock</hi> of it; then Christ Jesus, and those <hi>Veteran Legions,</hi> the <hi>glorious Angels;</hi> the <hi>Lord Iesus,</hi> the Man up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Red Horse among the Myrtle Trees,</hi> attended with <hi>Red, speckled and white Horses,</hi> Angels deputed to <hi>several Offices</hi> and <hi>Administrations,</hi> (Zech. 1. 8.) are in a posture of readiness to charge the Enemy, and bring off the people of God with <hi>Safety</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> that are hotly engaged in the Conflict with their Adversaries. <hi>The Witnesses may be overcome and killed, but they shall live again.</hi> They that mourn for <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> shall have a Time to rejoyce for Her, and with Her, <hi>Isai.</hi> 66. 10. men that wage warre against Heaven, and bid open defiance to the great Interest of the Lord Jesus (who is <hi>Faithful and True,</hi> and <hi>in Righteousness doth judge</hi> and make warre; who is <hi>King of Kings, and Lord of Lords,</hi> Rev. 19. 11, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> shall be <hi>confounded;</hi> and <hi>Ierusalem</hi> shall be a <hi>Burdensome Stone and a Cup of trembling to the Adversaries thereof.</hi> Indeed we must wait Christs Time for the exerting of his Power, and the Lighting down of his <hi>Omnipotent Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Day of his power and wrath, when He shall gird his Sword on his Thigh,</hi> and his <hi>Arrows</hi> shall be <hi>sharp</hi> in the <hi>Heart</hi> of his Enemies, and he shall <hi>Smite through the Loines of them that rise up against him, and of them that hate Him, that they rise not again.</hi> There is a Day coming when the Right Hand of Christ shall teach Him <hi>terrible Things,</hi> Psal. 45. 4. In the mean while our work is to <hi>wait and pray,</hi> and exercise <hi>Faith and Patience</hi> (For <hi>here,</hi> or in this matter is the <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Patience</hi> of the Saints proved and exercised) and when the Day comes which God hath determined, your ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>General</hi> alone can win the Field, <hi>and turn the Battel to the Gate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and give you a <hi>signal Victory:</hi> and will do it right-early for his Suffering Servants, that shall need to do nothing then, but <hi>stand still, and see the Salvation of the Lord,</hi> and what Destructions He will make among their Adversaries. If one Saint be thus Victorious (as you have heard) never question but the <hi>whole Body</hi> of them shall (in Gods Time and way) prevail and Conquer in a <hi>glorious</hi> manner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Use</hi> 4. <hi>Of Exhortation, to such as have Believed through Grace;</hi> in several Branches.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Be Encouraged then to fight this good Fight,</hi> where there is so much <hi>Hope,</hi> nay such <hi>Assurance</hi> to Believers of a <hi>Glorious victory.</hi> They must needs <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>quer,</hi> that fight on such <hi>Termes</hi> as we have mentioned, and have such <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rovision</hi> laid in for <hi>Victory and Triumph.</hi> They must needs <hi>Conquer,</hi> whose very <hi>General</hi> alone, is able to <hi>Conquer</hi> all their <hi>Enemies.</hi> Well may the Christian Souldier be <hi>hardy, daring, venturous, couragious, resolute</hi> in his way to see upon his <hi>Enemies,</hi> that hath such <hi>Assurance</hi> of being <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphantly</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:100718:16"/>
               <hi>successfull</hi> in all his Engagements. Here is encouragement enough, one would think, to make any <hi>Coward</hi> valiant in fight. Never despair nor give in then, <hi>but fight this good fight of Faith.</hi> Therefore for Direction;</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Let all Believers know and consider well that they are Souldiers, and have fighting work before them.</hi> That they have many Foes to deal withal, and that they are in the Field deeply eng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ged in a sharp contest about <hi>the things of their Peace:</hi> And that there is no retreating, or drawing off, or looking back without shame and misery. That they are waging a War, that is of greatest importance, of everlasting Consequence, and of infinite concernment to them. Do not rest in slight Apprehensions, transient and overly Thoughts of your State and Condition in this respect; <hi>left you fall into a Laish like frame,</hi> (Judg. 18. 27.) and dwell securely and carelesly in the World, and expose your selves to the inrodes and inculsions of your E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. Know that you do not dwell far from evil Neighbours: you have Mortal Enemies bordering upon you, that will make all Advantage of your Security. You have a Troublesome, Quarrelsome In-mate, one that was bred and born with you, and hath grown up with you, and is a constant Lodger in your House, and Companion at home and abroad. Indwelling sin (I mean) with its Confederates, that hold exact intelligence one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> another, and watch all Advantages against you.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Labour to get accurate Intelligence of the Policies and Designs of your Adversaries.</hi> Acquaint your selves with the deceitfulness of sin, the Frauds and Impostures of the World, the Wiles, Methods, Depths and Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Devil, the desperate wickedness of the Heart, and the <hi>deep wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> of evil Counsel there. Finde out the <hi>Cabinet Counsels</hi> and <hi>Politick de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign of your Enemies against you:</hi> what they design, what <hi>Stratage<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> they use, what advantagious seasons they chuse to fight you in, what false Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours they put out, that they may surprize you in the Disguise of Friends, what politick Retreats they make, what Ambushments they lay, what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves of fresh Forces they have in readiness, what gradual and secret Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches they make, where they plant their <hi>Artillery,</hi> and are designing to make a Breach in your <hi>Graces</hi> or <hi>Comforts,</hi> that they may Storm your Soule, and make themselves Masters of all. Do what you can to inform your selves what it is they drive at, how and where, and which way they are like to Assault you. In waging of War there is (as One speaks) the greatest improvement of <hi>Humane Wisdome</hi> and <hi>Industry.</hi> Discover as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as may be the Subtleties and Policies, and Forces and Advantages of your E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ies, that you may be provided to obviate them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Get Skill and Dexterity in using the Arms and Weapons of your Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Warfare.</hi> How to put on the <hi>Girdle of Truth,</hi> and <hi>Brest-plate of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:100718:17"/>
how to use <hi>the Shield of Faith, and Helmet of Hope,</hi> and to wield <hi>the Sword of the Spirit,</hi> (the Word of God) and to improve all the pieces of your Spiritual <hi>Armour,</hi> and all the <hi>Weapons</hi> that your <hi>General</hi> puts into your <hi>Hands.</hi> A Christian is compleatly armed and appointed, but many times knows not how to use his Weapons. Have your <hi>Arms</hi> in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diness, and learn to make a ready and dexterons use of them. That you should not only have <hi>Grace,</hi> but be well Skilled in the vigorous, lively, sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable Acting and Exereising of all the <hi>Grace</hi> you have, is the meaning of this Direction.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>List your selves into some particular Company that is engaged in the same VVarfare.</hi> It is a great Disadvantage to a Christian to stand and fight <hi>alone,</hi> and not to have a particular and peculiar <hi>Interest</hi> in the Help of other Christians: which is the Case of those that live out of <hi>Church-Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,</hi> and do not put themselves under the <hi>Watch</hi> and <hi>Discipline,</hi> and <hi>Conduct</hi> of <hi>particular Churches. We</hi> (saith <hi>Solomon,</hi> declaring the Inconveniency of Solitariness) to Him that is Alone, <hi>when he falleth, for he hath not another to help Him up:</hi> And if one prevail against him (that hath a Companion and Helper) two shall withstand him, <hi>Eccles.</hi> 4. 10, 12. It is as true in <hi>Spiritual</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s in <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Common Cases.</hi> It is a great Advantage in our Spiritual <hi>Conflicts</hi> to have <hi>good Company,</hi> whose Help and Assistance is engaged to us. It is the <hi>Lords Appointment</hi> that <hi>Mankind</hi> should live together in Socioties, as in <hi>Families, Common-wealths, Churchis,</hi> in order to <hi>common Help-fulness.</hi> It is the singular priviledge of <hi>Church members</hi> to have a peculiar engaged in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest in the Prayers, &amp; Counsels, &amp; Help of their <hi>Fellow-Brethren,</hi> which is a very desireable Thing, and a considerable <hi>Advantage,</hi> 1 Cor. 12. 25, 26. Do not therefore <hi>Combate</hi> alone, but get into some particular <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Saints Militant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Keep Order. Fight every one in your own places where you are set. Be sure you keep Rank and File.</hi> Order is the Beauty of the World, and of an <hi>Army</hi> in Special (In Allusion whereunto the Stars are frequently called <hi>the Host of Heaven,</hi> because of the exactness of their <hi>Order</hi> &amp; <hi>Regularness</hi> of their <hi>Motion)</hi> and of the <hi>Christian Army</hi> (the Church of Christ in its <hi>Militant Condition)</hi> most of all. Of the <hi>Spouse of Christ</hi> it is said, <hi>Thy cheeks are comely with Rows of Ieweh,</hi> Cant. 1. 10. that is, the <hi>outward Face</hi> and <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Church is Comely, Beautiful</hi> and <hi>Glorious</hi> with keeping their right place and order, as well as the manner of Gods own <hi>Ordinances,</hi> as some Expound it. A Church well ordered <hi>is Beautiful as Tirzab, comely as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> and terrible to her Adversaries <hi>as an Army with Banners,</hi> Mars<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>led and Ordered under their <hi>Banners</hi> and <hi>Ensigns</hi> Cant 64. This of Order is one respect wherein Churches are well compared to <hi>Armies</hi> that are well ordered and diseiplined. This is the Glory and strength of such
<pb facs="tcp:100718:17"/>
Christian Societies, and no small Advantage to every Christian. Those are the best Souldiers that are best exercised to keep their own Place and Order. So <hi>Material</hi> a Thing it is, that it is the <hi>Character</hi> and <hi>Description</hi> of good Souldiers, that they were such as could keep Rank, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Chron.</hi> 12. 38, 36, 38. The private Souldier must not straggle, or leave his place, or thrust Himself into the place and Command of the Officer, but every one keep the place assigned Him. A Souldier that is commanded to stand such a Ground, must not sti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> from it, though He is sure to dye upon the place: If He leave it, he dies for it by <hi>Martial Law.</hi> No personal danger will excuse him for such breach of order. There is no dispensing with it. A Christian Souldier must not be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, One that keeps not his place if I may so render it. Nor <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> One that breaks orders, and be haves himself disorderly. Rules of Order must be carefully attended. Many of you see the Beauty, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the benefit of Order in other Societies, and observe it with much exactness at your Trainings and Artillery Exercises, and must do so in real Engagements. And why should not Christians apprehend the like necessity of attending Order <hi>(Christs Order</hi> I mean) in every <hi>Christian Army,</hi> eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Ecclesiastical Society,</hi> and the like inconveniences of the contrary.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Maintain Peace and Union with your Fellow-Souldiers, or with those of the same Company, or Regiment, or Army, as much as in you lies:</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion I <hi>mean with the Members of the Church wherein you stand, and with the rest of the Churches of Christ.</hi> There are some cases wherein peace with men cannot be kept; nay, wherein it is a duty to contend against them ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly <hi>for the Faith, for the Truth, for the Glory of God,</hi> and <hi>for the good of the Publick:</hi> But if it be possible, as much as lieth in you (as for as it is pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, lawful and expedient) <hi>live peaceably with all men,</hi> Rom. 12. 18. espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>k and follow peace with your Fellow Souldiers, your Brethren and Companions <hi>in Tribulation, and in the Kingdome and patience of Iesus Christ.</hi> Peace among, and mutual Communion of Churches and Church-members is as necessary a thing, as peace and union in an Army. I wish with all my Soul that this might be attended in this great Town of <hi>Boston.</hi> That these three Churches might be as a <hi>threefold Cord,</hi> so twisted together, that they might not be easily broken. Mutinies in an Army between one Company, or Regiment, and another, are hazardous to the safety and good of the whole, and therefore severely punished. A wise General will take the <hi>least: him</hi> of any Overture that way, because it is a thing of dangerous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Army. Christ, your <hi>Centeral,</hi> is as apprehensive and jealous of such things among his People. Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ul was the case of <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> when be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieged by the <hi>Romans</hi> on this account of <hi>divided parties</hi> and <hi>Factions Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hin,</hi> which hastened their ruine, and <hi>facilitated the Roman Conquest.</hi> And do
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100718:18"/>
you think that Divisions in and among Churches are not of threatning Consequence to such societies? The Lord be merciful to us in this respect. <hi>Must the Sword devour for ever? Do you not know that it will be bitterness in the latter end?</hi> I hope you do not wage here <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> An irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable War. If the <hi>Sons of men</hi> shou'd be implacable, yet one would think the <hi>Sons of God</hi> should put on (as the Elect of God, Holy and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved) <hi>Bowels of Mercies, Kindness, Humbleness of Mind, Meekness, Long-Suffering, Forbearing one another, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d Forgiving, if any Man have a Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel against any, as they expect Forgiveness from the Lord Iesus, putting on Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which is the Bond of perfectn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ss,</hi> Col. 3. 12. 13, 14. Shall that of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, speaking of the worst of the Heathen, <hi>(Rom.</hi> 1. 31.) be verified in any of the Professor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> among us, that they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Implacable</hi> God forbid. They are your Enemies, yea, common Enemies to the <hi>Interest</hi> of Christ, and his people that will go about to <hi>Foment</hi> these <hi>Divisions,</hi> or advise to the perpetuating of these Differences. If I were not well assured that Christs Name, and Interest, and your own Souls suffer unspeakably hereby, I should not have opened my Mouth in this manner. However I hope none here are so much in love with Contention as to be angry with Counsels of Peace. It is a matter of great Consequence. O les us not <hi>turn our Swords into one anothers Bowels,</hi> as the <hi>Midianites</hi> (Judg. 7. 22.) <hi>Philistines</hi> (1 Sam. 14 15, 20.) <hi>Moab tes, Ammonites</hi> and the Inhabitants of <hi>Mount Seir</hi> (a Chron. 20. 23.) as well as others, have done to their own Destruction. <hi>I</hi> believ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> really that it is with these Churches, or Companies of Christian Souldiers in this place, so far as there is any Contention among them, as it is with Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers now &amp; then in the Heat of Battel. Sometimes through mistake in the Hurry and Consusion of Battel, one <hi>Reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ment</hi> or <hi>Company</hi> chargeth another of the same Army, slaughtering and destroying their own dear Friends, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged on the same side, and for the same cause, instead of their Enemies. This hath occasioned great Mischief. So through Darkness, Confusions, Mis understandings, and Mis-representations of Persons and Actions in an <hi>Hour of Temptation,</hi> it comes to pass that Brethren contend and quarrel, and wound one another with the wound of <hi>an Enemy, and of a cruel One.</hi> Mistakes and Mis-apprehensions are the usual, sad occasions of great Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions. We had need <hi>watch and Pray, that we enter not into Temptation</hi> in this respect, and to exercise <hi>Charity</hi> towards such as differ from us in Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstantia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in matters of Doubtful Disputation only; lest we bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ndly and pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>pitately run over and ruine, hack and hew down ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Brot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> under the notion of <hi>Enemies.</hi> Oh make and Maintain Peace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong your selves, you <hi>Sould<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ers and Military Companies</hi> of J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>sus Christ A Cessation of Arms for the Present is not enough. It is a League of Amity
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100718:18"/>
and Friendship, and Brotherly Communion that I contend for. O that is might be speedily effected! lest a Common Enemy prove the only effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Mediatour between the Brethren at variance, and a pacification be made at last by such Instruments and Means as neither Party will have any joy or pleasure in. And the Blessing of the <hi>Peace-maker</hi> be upon the heads of those persons that shall be graciously instrumental in Gods way to settle a good and lasting Peace and Correspondence among these Churches, or sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely and vigorously endeavour it.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Make it your chief care and business all the time of your Warfare to please your Great General the Lord of Hosts, the Lord Iesus Christ in all things.</hi> That is the property of a good Souldier, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 4. He design<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to please his Commander in chief, by a <hi>ready Obedience.</hi> This was the sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular commendation of the <hi>Centurions Souldiers,</hi> Mat. 8. 9. Luk. 7. 8. No Men are under more absolute Command then Souldiers, that must not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spute, but obey the Orders of their General. In like manner do you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve all the Orders of the Lord Jesus, obey all his Words of Command, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture upon the hottest and hardest pieces of Service, when he requires it; hold no Intelligence, or Treacherous, close Correspondence with his Enemies; In every Motion or Action consider with your selves whether this or that course, and carriage and Posture will please Christ. And in particular please him by a ready and cheerful Obedience to Inferiour, Commissioned Officers for his sake. <hi>Obey them that have the Rule over you,</hi> is one great word of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand which our Lord &amp; Saviour gives, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 7, 17. Though I am as truly &amp; heartily opposite to the <hi>Presbyterian Perswasion</hi> (with due respect to the Piety and Learning, and Orthodexy and Excellent Abilities and Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishments of those our Fellow-Brethren, and Souldiers that march on that side of the way, be it spoken) wherein it lies in direct Opposition to the Substantials of the <hi>Congregational-way,</hi> as any of you: and though I am remote enough from the intention of improving the Text but now menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, to the establishing of such an Absolute and Arbitrary Rule in the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> as is really inconsistent, and incomportable with the due pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge and liberty of the People: yet I am sure that all are not <hi>Guides, Overseers,</hi> and <hi>Rulers,</hi> but that there are <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>Ruled,</hi> the <hi>Governours</hi> and the <hi>Governed</hi> in all particular Churches according the Sovereign Institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Jesus Christ; there are Officers and Private Souldiers according to the appointment of our Lord General: And I must say freely, that that way of Church-Government that allows not the Rule, and Government truely and properly so called, to Church Officers, is not the way of Christs Institution. Obey therefore such as the Lord Jesus hath set over you in the Lord, if you mean to please him. Otherwise you may be sure that your General will severely punish the undue contempt of the meanest Officer in the Christian Army.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:100718:19"/>
8. <hi>Be willing to endure Hardship.</hi> This is another Qualification of a Souldier, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 3. Church-Officers are called to this in a special manner: but it is the duty also, of every Christian Soulders, that must expect to wrestle with many Difficulties. A man must never think to be a Souldier that is nice and delicate, and loves to favour himself and indulgeth to pleasure and ease. <hi>Nimi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> delicatus es Christiano, qui voluptatem hec seculo concupiscis. Tertull.</hi> Every Souldier must resolve upon enduring, Hunger, and Thirst, and Cold, and Wet, and Weariness, and lying upon the Ground, many Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships and Inconveniences in the course of his Militery Imployment. As <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>cas</hi> the <hi>Scythian</hi> said to <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon: You Command Macedoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans that can fight with men;</hi> But I Command <hi>Scythians that are able to fight with Hanger and Thirst.</hi> A Course of Warfare is usually a Course of Hardship, as well as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. Christians must look for many hardships in their way, ill Usage, and course Entertainment, and sore Inconveniencies, and hard Duty in their <hi>Warfare.</hi> It is their great Wisdome and Duty to exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ct them, and learn to comport ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ght with them.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Do not encumber your selves with other Occasions, or with any thing that may take you off, or hinder you in your Warfare.</hi> No man <hi>that Warreth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>angleth himself with the Affairs of this life,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 4 Souldiers are great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken off from other employments; they cannot follow <hi>Merch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ndizing</hi> or <hi>Husbandry,</hi> or this or that <hi>Trade</hi> to any great purpose. They have enough to do to attend their <hi>Watchings</hi> and <hi>Wardings, Marchings</hi> and <hi>Motions,</hi> the Orders and Commands of their Leaders. True it is that a particular Calling is very well consistent with the General Calling of a Christian Souldier, and should be so attended and managed, that it may be a further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and no hindrance thereunto. But may we not fear that there is a fault among Christian Souldiers in this respect? and that they are generally too much engaged in other matters, and entangled with the World and the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs thereof, and thereby rendred less disposed to the service of Christ in their Christian Warfare? Certainly <hi>inordinate Affection to the thing of his VVorld,</hi> and <hi>over eager pursuit of them</hi> doth in no wise become a good Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier of Christ.</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Be content with your VVagc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> That is the good Quality of a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, as <hi>Iohn the Baptist</hi> intimates, <hi>Luk.</hi> 3. 14. A Christian properly hath no wages, because all he enjoyes is of meer Grace and Courtesie. When he hath done all, He is an <hi>unprofitable Servant,</hi> Luk. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>. 10. But my meaning is, be contented with what the Lord Jesus Christ affords you at present for your sustenance and encouragement. Yea, though he keep you at shore Allowance as to comforts and spiritual suavities, and such a sufficiency of Grace to prevail, and conquer, and tread down all your Enemies, as you could desire; yet he quiet and contented with your present portion; do
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100718:19"/>
not Mutiny or Murmure, but be Humbly Thankful for, and well sufficed with such things as you have, <hi>Heb.</hi> 135. And be assured that the Lord Jesus, though he owe you nothing, and keep you short at present, will pay, you well at last. The time is coming, when you shall be drawn out of the Field, and discharged from this Warfare, and then he will pay you all your <hi>Arrears,</hi> over and over, and gratifie you for all your Service (such is his Grace) with that which you may comfortably subsist on to Eternity.</p>
            <p>This is the first Branch of the Exhortation. <hi>Let all true Believers he great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly encouraged to fight against their Spiritual Enemies; &amp; that both in their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and pubilek Capacities.</hi> For every Believer must engage in a Warfare, not only <hi>General</hi> and Common to all Christians, but also proper and peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar to himself in his place and Condition. Therefore I wou'd crave leave to Address my self here with a word or two of <note place="margin">This Sermon was Preached, when the General Court was sitting, and in the Audience of the much Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Members of it.</note> Encouragement to our Pious, Faithful, Honourable Rulers in their <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> not as they are Christians only, but as they are Christian Magistrates also, and the <hi>Nursing Fathers</hi> of our <hi>Common-Wealth</hi> and <hi>Churches.</hi> It would indeed be a most importune and intollerable Thing, <hi>notorious Boldness</hi> and <hi>Rudeness</hi> in me this Day, and on such an Occasion, to stand here and dictate to our <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Patriots</hi> and <hi>Worthies,</hi> or to direct and advise them about the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular management of their Civil Affairs. As every man should be wise<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> in his own Calling and Concerns: So it is the great Happiness of <hi>New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> that we have Persons of <hi>great worth</hi> and <hi>Wisdom, Integrity</hi> and <hi>Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ruling over us,</hi> and guiding us by the <hi>Skilfulness</hi> of their <hi>Hands;</hi> and such as have no need of the <hi>Instructions</hi> of such a piece of weakness and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthiness as stands before you. They know their own Business, and are <hi>taught of God</hi> to manage the great Affairs under their Hands. I remember well, that I am an <hi>unworthy Minister of the G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>spel;</hi> not a <hi>Statesman,</hi> or <hi>projector.</hi> And therefore I am very faire from the Design of obtruding upon you <hi>(much Honoured</hi> my raw and indig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>sted Apprehensions about the Condition of your Affairs, and what m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y seem Counsellable in that respect. But I would with <hi>all id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lity, Respect</hi> and <hi>Affection,</hi> administer to you a word of Encouragement, in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Application of what hath been disco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>sed of the Christians <hi>Warfare</hi> in <hi>Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ral</hi> to your <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rfare</hi> in <hi>Special.</hi> You must Combate with <hi>Prophaneness,</hi> with <hi>turbulent He estes,</hi> with <hi>Blasphe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ies,</hi> with <hi>Injust<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> with <hi>Disorders</hi> of many Kinds: and in so doing will be exposed to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>hard Speeches,</hi> yea, to many <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Discouragements,</hi> And if you should be ready sometimes to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t in this pub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and complain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hat you are not able to bear this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>avy Burthen that is laid upon you: it would be no more then what we read of <hi>Moses, the meekest man,</hi> and one of the best <hi>accomplish<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d Leaders</hi> and <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:100718:20"/>
that ever was upon Earth, <hi>Numb</hi> 11. 11. 12, 14. The Eminoncy of your place and work makes you the more conspicuous, that you will be the fairet Mark for Setan, and his Instruments. <hi>Qui regit Signum est in quod Sat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nas omnia Iacula dirigit.</hi> Satan and his Followers, that fight un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his <hi>Banner,</hi> will be casting all their Derts at you. <q>
                  <hi>Magistratus indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat vir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>m.</hi> Magistrates places are as Furnaces to try them in. Place of Government <hi>trieth the Spirit of a man, whether he be just or corrupt, liberal</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>or covetous, valiant or fearful, for God or for Man;</hi> as Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> observs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Eccles.</hi> 3. 18—22. Every Calling hath its Temptation: and yours (as <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Honourable</hi> as it is) is not priviledged in that respect. You are <hi>Gods</hi> indeed in the <hi>Scripture Dialect</hi> (Psal. 82 1, 6.) but you are <hi>Men</hi> too, <hi>subject to the like passions, perturbations, Conflicts</hi> and <hi>Temptations,</hi> that other men are: nay, more exposed thereunto on some Accounts. Your Places are High, end you dwell in the <hi>upper Region;</hi> but you are wiser then to look for nothing but Stilness and Serenity there, where you are not out of the way &amp; walk of the <hi>Prince of the Power of the Air,</hi> who will be sure (if he can) to raise many a Storm and Tempest upon you. I am not much acquainted with the State of your Affairs: but if I should improve my Observations, and conjecture from what I have noted elsewhere, I might well conclude, that you have Difficulties more then enough before you in your way. You are continually <hi>travelling in Birth</hi> with the publick good; and there may be some that (as it is said of the <hi>Dragon, that he stood before the Woman that was ready to be delivered, to devour her Child as soon as it was born,</hi> Rev. 12. 4. So) will be ready to stifle the Issues of your Counsels in the <hi>Birth,</hi> or to <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay</hi> them, and devout them as soon as they are born. Now the word of the Lord to you is (as sometimes to <hi>Ioshua,</hi> Josh. 1. 9 <hi>Be strong and of a good Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, be not afraid, neither be you dismayed: For the Lord your God is with you.</hi> O take Courage and <hi>acquit your selves</hi> as the good Souldiers of Christ, and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>aliant Worthies</hi> in your <hi>Warfare.</hi> You have <hi>growing Sins</hi> in a <hi>growing Common-wealth</hi> to grapple withal. <hi>O be Couragious,</hi> and fight your Fight against such Enormities. Do not draw your Sword meerly to flourish and beat the Air; but strike home: And if you have not Swords that are sharp enough, or long enough to reach, to do thorough Execution upon the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of our peace, the <hi>God-provoking</hi> &amp; <hi>State disturbing Sins &amp; evils</hi> among us; Be sure you get such as may do it; I mean such Laws as may be keen and comprehensive enough to reach them. And the Lord bless you, (with the <hi>Honoured <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>puties)</hi> at your great <hi>Councii of Warre,</hi> as I would take Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ay, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o stile your <hi>General Assembly,</hi> where you are considering wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to do <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lare,</hi> to conquer and beat down the Sins and Disorders that lift up the Head amongst us, and are the great Enemies of the Prosperity of our <hi>Common-wealth</hi> and Churches. I might also particularly apply this
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100718:20"/>
word of Encouragement to the pious an laborious Servants of the Lord in the work of the Ministry. <hi>O my Brethren and Fathers!</hi> you are the good Souldiers of Jesus Christ in a peculiar manner, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 3. Paul calls <hi>Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phroditus</hi> the Pastor of the Church of the <hi>Philippians,</hi> his <hi>Fellow-Souldier,</hi> Phil. 2. 25. Both <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>raordinary</hi> and <hi>ordinary Church-Officers</hi> are <hi>Souldiers.</hi> Your <hi>Life</hi> is a <hi>Warfare</hi> in a way of <hi>Specialty.</hi> Besides the Enemies you have to Engage with as you are Christians, you have Enemies also to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict with as you are Ministers. I speak not of the persons of men which are to be pitied and tendered: but of their Vices, which must be opposed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated withal You have <hi>Unruliness, Disorderly Behaviour, Prejudices, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, base Nick-names, hard Usage,</hi> and <hi>injurious dealings</hi> among men; the <hi>Pride, Ignorance, Obstinacy, Unfruitfulness,</hi> and <hi>Ingratitude</hi> of some you have to do with, besides your particular Temptations from Satan (who maligns the Ministers of Christ more then other men) to conflict and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate withal. Some of you may be in <hi>Pauls</hi> Case, <hi>Fears within, and Figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings without, and Trouble on ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ry side,</hi> 2 Cor. 7 5. You are Souldiers and must expect Knocks and Blows in your <hi>Warfare:</hi> but you may be assured of a most <hi>Glorious Victory.</hi> We live in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>imes of great Degeneracy, and in special of great Disaffection to the Ministers of Christ: Times wherein Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan industriously <hi>instills</hi> and infuses endless Jealousies and prejudices into the Heads and Hearts of People concerning the Faithful Ministers of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel. As the King of <hi>Syria</hi> said to his Captains, <hi>Fight neither with small nor Great, save only wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>h the King of</hi> Israel, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22. 31. So doth Satan seem to say to his Follower<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> at this Day; Do you fight neither with one or other, so much as with the Ministers of Christ. This is the Ball that Satan hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Foot, the great Game that He is playing, up and down; to asperse, and vilifie, and bring down the price and esteem of Christs Messengers: as well knowing then how to destroy the Souls of Men and Women, <hi>Heaps</hi> upon <hi>Heaps,</hi> as it were. Well, you are Souldiers, and must not be discouraged. You are well appointed; you have Arms to fight withal. Prayers and Tears and <hi>Ministerial Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>horitative</hi> Dispensation of the word and Ordinances of Christ, with Courage And undaunted Resolution, are the <hi>VVeapons</hi> of your <hi>Warfare,</hi> which <hi>are not Carnal, but Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ritual and mighty throug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> God assisting,</hi> 2 Cor. 10 4. And if it would not sound too much like the Word of a <hi>Commander;</hi> if it were not too much Boldness and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogance, I would say to my Reverend Fathers and Brethren, <hi>Fellow Souldiers Stand to your Arms.</hi> The Day is your own, and the Victory will be finally determined on your side. Your <hi>Sighs, and Groans, and Prayers, and Tears, and M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nilleria! Conflict</hi> shall not be in vain; but the Lord will shortly give you the Victory Take heed of Short-spiritedness, of Impatience, of Faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Contest, though it may be sharp and severe for a time. The <hi>Ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:100718:21"/>
               <hi>terarian Spirit</hi> the <hi>Antiministerial</hi> Spirit, the <hi>Heretical</hi> evil Spirit, the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling</hi> and <hi>Disorderly</hi> Spirit, or whatever else it is that you combate withal shall be routed, run down, put to flight; And the solly of such Things and persons will be made manifest to all men. Nothing will abide, but what is <hi>built,</hi> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> on the <hi>variable</hi> and <hi>uncertain Fancies</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi> of men, but on, the <hi>Everlasting Foundations</hi> of Scripture and Reason. Reason and Truth will stand their Ground, and keep the <hi>Field</hi> when all that is opposite thereunto will be put to flight and totally discomfited. I shall say no more to you but in the words of the Lord to the Prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>er.</hi> 1. 18, 19. <hi>The Lord hath made you Defenced Cities, Iron Pillars, and Brazen Walls; and though men fight against you they shall not prevail; For the Lord is with you.</hi> Nay, further, If I could but get into the Hearts of any of the <hi>People of God</hi> in this Assembly, and make discovery of the particular <hi>Corruptions</hi> and <hi>Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> that this or that <hi>Believing Man</hi> or <hi>Woman</hi> is <hi>Conflicting and Combating</hi> with; I would say to them, <hi>Be strong in the Lord, and in the power of his might.</hi> As the <hi>Priesis</hi> were ordered by the Lord to give a Word of Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to the <hi>People of Israel,</hi> when they were approaching to Batrel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganst their Enemies, <hi>Deut.</hi> 20 3, 4. So give me leave at the Head of this <hi>Christian Camp</hi> here Assembled before the Lord, to bespeak the <hi>Israel of God,</hi> and to say, <hi>Let not your Hearts Faint, Fear not, and do not tremble, neither here terrified, because of your Enemies: For the Lord your God (even your great Lord General, the Lord Iesus Christ) is he that goeth with you to sight for you against your Enemies, and to save you.</hi> What should I do but say to them that are of a fearful Heart, <hi>Be strong, fear not: strengthen ye the weak Hands, and confirm the feeble Kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>es,</hi> Isai 35. 3, 4. You are it may be <hi>Buffeted with Satans Messenger, pained with the Thorn in the Flesh, Molested and Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured (as persons held upon the Rack) with Temptations to Atheism, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, with Blasphemons Injections, and Amazing Suggestions, Tormented with the poysonous fiery Dares and Arrows of that evil one, Combated with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>shly, VVorldly Lusts and Corruptions that give you no rest.</hi> Oh Courage, Courage, Dear Hearts, Fight it out to the last. And if you are Foiled, get up again by <hi>Repentance,</hi> and renew the <hi>Combat in the strength of Christ,</hi> and never ask <hi>Quarter,</hi> or make a Surrender of your selves to the Will of your Enemies; for <hi>you shall obtain a Glorious Victory.</hi> Possibly <hi>(O Believer)</hi> thou hast been sleeping in the Lap of some <hi>Daliloh,</hi> and hast lost thy strength, and art <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>en into the Hands of the <hi>Philistine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> that have bound thee with <hi>Pett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and made thee to <hi>Grinde</hi> (which is the sad condition which some <hi>Christian Souldiers</hi> through Security reduce themselves unto) yet let me tell th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> for thy Encouragement, that though thy <hi>Locks</hi> are shaven off, yet (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Grace) the <hi>Locks of thy Strength</hi> will grow again, and thou shalt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of those <hi>Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>stines.</hi> Let all the Followers of Christ be warned
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100718:21"/>
by the Falls and Surprizes of themselves and others to stand upon their Guard, and continue in a vigilant fighting Posture, that they may not give up themselves to the Will of their Adversaries, that ly in Ambush, and watch all Advantages against them. Watch ye, <hi>stana fest in the Faith quit you like men, be strong,</hi> 1 Cor. 16. 13. <hi>Yet a little while, and you shall triumph over all your Enemies.</hi> The Lord will shortly deliver you from Sin and Sorrow, and the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>res of an evil World, <hi>and bruise Satan under your Feet,</hi> Rom. 16. 20. The God of peace shall do it for you, when the time of your <hi>Warfare shall be accom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>shed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much for the first Branch of the Exhortation. The Second is.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Learn and Labour to improve the Lord Iesus Christin all your Spiritual Conflicts and Engagements.</hi> For want of this Holy skill Men do but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Air, and make a vain flourish; and contend to no purpose at all with the Enemies <hi>that War against their-Souls.</hi> Here all the false Religions in the World, and that of the <hi>Papists</hi> in special, fail Exceedingly. They are wholly unacquainted with the <hi>Mystery of the Gospel,</hi> the Efficacy of the Performances of Jesus Christ, the orderly way of improving the Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, Merit and Intercession, or the Humiliation and Exaltation of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour: and what course do they fix upon? Truly they think to <hi>Vanquish their Corruptions in the strength of their Vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and <hi>Fastings</hi> and <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nances,</hi> and <hi>self-devised, self-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>acerating Austerities;</hi> which may possibly kill the <hi>Natural Man,</hi> but will never destroy the <hi>Corrupt Old Man:</hi> and to fright away Satan (the tame and timerous Devil) with their <hi>Crossings</hi> and <hi>Holy-Water,</hi> and such like Fopperic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>. That which lies at the bottome of all their Miscarriages in this business is, that they know not how to improve the Lord Jesus in order to the Defeat and Overthrow of their Spiritual Adve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries: without which Divine skill Men may Scuffle and Skirmish wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> their Foes, raise much Dust, and make a great noise and bustle, as if they would do great Exploits; and yet all end in <hi>Shame</hi> and <hi>Disappointment.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> you see that all the <hi>Victories</hi> and <hi>Conquests</hi> which Believers obtain are <hi>through him that loved them; even the Lord Iesus Christ.</hi> O therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that Spiritual Art of improving the Lord Jesus in all your Combate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> do nothing. Much should have been said here about that sulne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion that is laid up in Jesus Christ for the support, Relief and Assistance of Believers in their Conflicts, and their Enablement to make a Conque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of their Enemies: and about the <hi>Actings of Faith</hi> upon the Lord Jesus, and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>tehing in all suitable and seasonable supplies of Strength and Grace from his store. Time and Strength would fail me, if I should enter upon so large and spacious a Subject; and I had rather say nothing, then speak generally, superficiarily, and slightily to a matter of such importance; therefore I shall thus pass it with a brief mention of it. The thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d Branch is;</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:100718:22"/>
3. <hi>Acknowledge the Love of God in Christ, and bless the God and Father <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> our Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>esus Christ for all your partial and present Victories and Conques<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> any of your Engagements with the Enemies of your Souls.</hi> Doth the Lord help you <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>o asquit your selves like Men</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) or like Christians rather, &amp; the Souldiers of Jesus Christ in any Conflicts with your own Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, or Satans Temptations? Oh remember that it is through the Love of God in Christ that you Prevail and Conquer: And therefore bless God and be thankful to him for all your Victorious Atchievements, and offer him the Sacrifice of Praise and Thank<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>giving. When <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and his People went forth against that great Multitude of <hi>Moabites, Ammonites,</hi> and the Inhabitants of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>unt Seir</hi> with full assurance from the Lord of Victory; Singers to the Lord were appointed, that should praise the <hi>Beauty of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they went out before the Army, and say, <hi>Praise the Lord, for his m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>cy e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>dureth for ever,</hi> 2 Chron. 20 21. They met the Enemy with Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving in their Mouths for promised and assured Victory. And when their Enemies were overthrown in a wonderful manner, they Assembled in the Volley of <hi>Berach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>h,</hi> so called, because they blessed the Lord there: and they returned to <hi>Ierusalem</hi> with <hi>Psalteries,</hi> and <hi>Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ps</hi> and <hi>Trumpets</hi> unto the House of the Lord, <hi>ver.</hi> 26, 28. In like manner Believers have Assurance from the Lord of the utter Defeat and Overthrow, and of the absolute Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest of their Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s through the love of God in Christ; and may well go forth against their Enemies in the strength of the Lord, with the <hi>High praises</hi> of <hi>God in their Mouth, and a two edged Sword in their hand, even the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ord of the Spirit, the Word of God, that is sharper then a two edged Sword,</hi> and will not fall, if it be rightly managed, to do notable Execution. And when they obtained any signal Victory in this or that particular Engagement with their Spiritual Enemies, what should they do but give the name of <hi>Berac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and Places of Retirement, and bless the Lord and his Holy Name (in which they are to <hi>set up their Banners</hi> (Psal. 20 5.) and through which they have done <hi>valiantly, and trodden down all their Enemi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> Psal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>) with their <hi>Souls and all that is within them.</hi> Though you cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Life hope for the total Defeat and overthrow of the Enemies of your Souls! yet be sure to erect a <hi>Trophy,</hi> and rear up a <hi>Monumental Pillar</hi> of thankful Acknowledgement and Remembrance to the Power and Grace and Love of God in Christ, upon every partial and particular Victory you obtai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> in the Field against them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Lastly, <hi>Wait, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d Pray, and Look, and Long for that Glorious Day, when your Warfare shall be ended, and you shall go out of the Field Victorious, and Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>mphant, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, absolute Conquerours.</hi> I perswade not to any Impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience during the neat of your present Engagements. Take heed of tiring and fainting in your Conflicts, and in the laborious course of your Warfare:
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100718:22"/>
Though your <hi>General</hi> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t you upon hard Duty and Service. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eth for Mastery is not Crowned, exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>pt he s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ve lawfully,</hi> 2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>gitime cer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>are</hi> (saith <hi>Iudicious Calvin)</hi> est pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> qui certamen quant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> quoad Lex praescribit: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>quis sibi modum ante tempus definiat. <hi>To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>awfully is to hola on the Contest, or continue and persevere in the Confli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> as <hi>long as the Law prescribes: and no man is to give over before the Time appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> He that is tired with a first or second Conflict, and withdraws himself out of the <hi>Field</hi> before his Time; will lose his Crown. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>erseverance</hi> in a Course of <hi>Running</hi> and <hi>Wrestling,</hi> and <hi>Combating,</hi> with <hi>Patience,</hi> and <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission</hi> to the good will of God, is the Duty of every Christian. But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, it is the Duty, as well as Allowance, of the Followers of Christ, to have respect to the Recompence of Reward, and the joy that is set before the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>: and to wait (with Hope and Desire) <hi>all the Dayes of their Appointed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> or of their <hi>Warfare</hi> (as the Original hath it) <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ir change come,</hi> Job. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. 14. that happy great Change, when their present <hi>Warfare</hi> shall be changed into everlasting peace and rest from trouble, <hi>and their Helmets sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ll be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi> into Cro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ns of everlasting Ioy upon their Heads, and their Swords and Spears (not beaten into Flow-shares and Pruning-hooks, as Isai. 2. 4 but) changed into <hi>Palms</hi> in their hands in token of assured Victory and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph. O therefore let all Christian S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>uldiers love and long for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Appearance of Christ: And when you are beset and encumbred, and engaged in any hot dispute with your Enemies, <hi>Look upwards, and Sigh to Heaven,</hi> as for present Assistance and Enablement, so also for after perfect Deliverance, Victory and Triumph, which shall be brought to you at the Appearing of the Lord Jesus Christ.</p>
            <p>With this word I shou'd have concluded and issued the whole Discou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and put an End to the <hi>present Engagement;</hi> but that I conceive it may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e rationally expected that I should address my self in the close (in a word <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>r two at least) to the <hi>Military men, the worthy and much Honoured Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> that have pressed and called me forth to the Service of this Day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I need not tell you that I am no Souldier. Possibly mine <hi>ine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t Usage</hi> of some <hi>Military</hi> and <hi>Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ial phrases</hi> in the past Discourse may but too plainly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ll you, that I am but little acquainted with the <hi>Military Science or Faculty.</hi> I am no Friend to warre, but an unseigned lover of Peace. I long for an End of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>Bloud-sheds,</hi> the <hi>Destructions</hi> and <hi>Des<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lations</hi> that the poor world <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>lled withal. <hi>O when will th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s Ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>n-Age expire, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nd that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Morn appear, that Lightsome Day dawn, wherein the Nations shall be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t their Swords into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lough-Shears, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eir Spea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s into Pruning-Hooks, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> shall Nation l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ft up Sword against Nation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>or t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s of men learn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> any more?</hi> The <hi>God of Peace</hi> will certainly put an end unto these <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:100718:23"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, In the mean time it is the wisdom and duty of the people of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o improve all Advantages that are providentially put into their Hands, to secure their peace and precious Enjoyments, and to put themselves into a Posture and Condition of disputing it with those that may invade or assault them. <hi>Military Sk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ll</hi> is necessary in <hi>Military</hi> times and <hi>Martial</hi> Dayes; and these <hi>Military</hi> exercises are not only Lawful and Allowable, but Iauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yea, and necessary also: and the persons by whom they are suppor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ed and carried on deserve singular Commendation and Encouragement. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>l</hi> mighty men are <hi>Cataloguised</hi> in holy writ, as men of <hi>Renow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and worthy to be had in <hi>Honourable Remembrance:</hi> And surely the <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> among us that are men of <hi>Skill</hi> and <hi>Conduct,</hi> and expertness in <hi>Military affairs</hi> should not be s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ghted or discouraged. We live in times of great <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions</hi> and <hi>doub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ful E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>pectations.</hi> How long we may <hi>sit under our Vines and Fig-trees and have none to make us afra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d,</hi> The <hi>God of our Pea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e, our great Protector,</hi> only knows. The Day may come upon us, when we may wish there were many more <hi>worthy men</hi> of <hi>Martial Spirits</hi> and <hi>Military Accompleshments,</hi> then yet appear among us. True it is, that <hi>I</hi> have not directed my Discourse to the Souldiers this Day: Considering that I was not (unless I mistook my Summons) to make a <hi>Military Oration</hi> (which is more proper for some <hi>Gentleman</hi> of that Profession) but to preach a Sermon, on a <hi>Military</hi> occasion, that might be of Use (if the Lord please) to the whole <hi>Assembly.</hi> I have weakly, but designedly endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to imitate and tread in the steps of our <hi>Blessed Saviour (the Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ain of our Salvation,</hi> Heb. 2 10. with whom it was usual and Customa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y in the Days of his <hi>Commoration</hi> and <hi>Converse</hi> upon <hi>Ear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>h,</hi> to take the least <hi>Hint</hi> to make a <hi>Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ritual U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> and <hi>Advantage</hi> of <hi>Common Things,</hi> and to improve obvious Occasions and Occurrences in a <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>abelical, Alleg-rical,</hi> and <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual</hi> way. In like manner I have taken Rise and Advantage from the <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary</hi> occasions of this Day to discourse (as the Lord ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>h enabled of the <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>stian Warfare.</hi> Souldiers love to hear of Battels at Land or Sea, of <hi>Victories</hi> and <hi>Triumphs,</hi> and the Cons<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>quents thereof, the <hi>Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ils,</hi> the <hi>Plunder,</hi> the <hi>Booty,</hi> the <hi>Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ds</hi> of <hi>Gallantry</hi> and good <hi>Behaviour</hi> in such <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ngagements: And I have been acquainting you with such Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ngs in a <hi>Sp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual way.</hi> And I hope none of you will judge this wholly impertinent, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less you have so sarre put on the <hi>Artillery man</hi> this morning, that you have also put off the <hi>Christian Souldier.</hi> I shall say further (by way of Defence and Apology) that what I have disc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>sed may be of great Use unto the <hi>Gentl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>men</hi> I am speaking to in their <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>tary Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ity.</hi> That which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ces <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o the making of men <hi>good Cori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ns</hi> hath a <hi>general Influence</hi> into the due department of men in all <hi>Capacit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> That man that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>th Conquered and Subdued Himself will know how to command, how to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100718:23"/>
obey, much better then One that is a sl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ve to Himself, and his own perverse will, and in Bondage to his own Lusts and Corruptions. Such a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>an will give serious and conscionable Attendance to the Improvement of all means affoarded him, that may accomplish Him in a <hi>Military way,</hi> and furnish Him with <hi>Skill</hi> and <hi>De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>terity,</hi> whereby He may be enabled to fight the <hi>Lords <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>attels</hi> against <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>jurious</hi> and <hi>malignant Adversari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s.</hi> He will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on that God that <hi>teacheth his H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s to warre, and his Fingers to sight,</hi> (Psal. 144. 1.) and <hi>umpires</hi> or determines the success<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s and Events of all <hi>Military</hi> Engagements <hi>according to the Counsel of his own will,</hi> sometimes contrary to the Law and <hi>Common Rule</hi> of <hi>second Causes:</hi> So that the Battel is not alwayes to the strong, but <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Chan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> (some <hi>interveni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Occurrences)</hi> happen to this, as well as other Affairs, <hi>Ecc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>es.</hi> 9. 11. He will go forth, when God calls to the <hi>Defence</hi> of <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Religious Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the strength of the Lord,</hi> and not in his own might or Sufficiency, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had such sensible and instructing Experience, that all his <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>er Conquests</hi> are acquired <hi>through him that loved Him.</hi> He will be one of the <hi>Legio Fulmina t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> the thundring Legion, that by their powerful and princely Prayers will obtain <hi>signal Victories</hi> over their Enemies. He will be one of the <hi>Called, and Faithful, and Chosen, that will follow the Lamb whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the soever he leads them.</hi> He that <hi>(through the Grace and st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ength of Christ)</hi> hath conquered <hi>Sin, and Self, and Satan,</hi> and an <hi>evil World,</hi> and is sure to conquer <hi>his last Enemy Death</hi> (which is the happy Condition of a <hi>Christian Souldier)</hi> will not fear the Face of any man in a Righteous Cause, but have the Spirit, and Courage, and <hi>undaunted Resolution</hi> of a <hi>Souldier</hi> indeed. He will say, as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> in his Case, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 6. 11. <hi>Should such a man a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> flee?</hi> well may He be above Fear and Frights, and <hi>Coward se, and acqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>mself</hi> in all respects as a <hi>Magna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>imous Person,</hi> who hath Deliverance from <hi>the fear of Death,</hi> to the Bondage whereof all men are naturally Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>b.</hi> 2. 15. He that expects to gain by dying (as that <hi>Champion Paul</hi> did, <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>l.</hi> 1 21.) and therefore <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi> rather then <hi>Fears</hi> to dy, will not be afraid of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>oint of the Sw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d or mouth of the Canon, or any other Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Death, when God ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>m to adventure Himself. If <hi>Alexande<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, Iulius Caesar,</hi> and others icc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hed such great Things by their natural Courage and Valour; walt wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> not that man do that hath the Spirit and Valour of a <hi>Christian So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ldier?</hi> He will not be act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>pride, and Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and vain glorious Ham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi> or <hi>mercenary Spirit</hi> that other Souldiers are car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ied with, but will bear upon the <hi>Grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ness</hi> of his God, and the <hi>Goodnese</hi> of his <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and so <hi>jeo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ard</hi> Himself in the <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>gh pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi> of the <hi>Field.</hi> These and the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ke Thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> considered, my Discourse may not seem to be <hi>wholly For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> or <hi>unaccommodable</hi> to the affairs of this day. Whether it hath been <hi>perts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>at</hi> and <hi>proper</hi> to the Design and Business of the Day is lest to the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:100718:24"/>
of my <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> But sure I am that I have discoursed of the Best and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Important Warfare,</hi> and the most <hi>desireable</hi> and <hi>glorious Victory</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. And though <hi>I</hi> cannot but approve and commend and wish the prosperous Continuance of your <hi>Trainings</hi> and <hi>Artillery-Exercises:</hi> Yet behold (as <hi>Paul</hi> speaks in another Case, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 31.) I have been <hi>shewing you a more excellent way.</hi> Of all Souldiers, the <hi>Christian Souldier</hi> is the best: No <hi>Warre,</hi> nor <hi>Victory,</hi> nor <hi>Triumph</hi> can be comparable to His. He is <hi>more than a Souldier; more then a Conqueror.</hi> And happy will that man be that at the end of his Race, and when he is marching out of the <hi>Field,</hi> shall be able to say (as that <hi>great Apostle</hi> and <hi>Renowned Souldier</hi> of Jesus Christ, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 7, 8.) <hi>I have fought a good fight, I have finished the Course of my Warfare: and henceforth there is laid up for me a Crown of Righteousness, which the Lord, the Righteous Iudge, shall give me at the Blessed Day of his Glorious Appearing.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:100718:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
