<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The continued cry of the oppressed for justice being a farther account of the late unjust and cruel proceedings of unreasonable men against the persons and estates of many of the people call'd Quakers, only for their peaceable meetings to worship God : presented to the serious consideration of the King and both Houses of Parliament : with a postscript of the nature, difference and limits of civil and ecclesiastical authority, and the inconsistency of such severities with both, recommended and submitted to the perusal of Cæsar's true friends / by the author of England's present interest, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Penn, William, 1644-1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2006-02">2006-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54125</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1270</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18856</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13048399</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13048399</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96947</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A54125)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96947)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 748:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The continued cry of the oppressed for justice being a farther account of the late unjust and cruel proceedings of unreasonable men against the persons and estates of many of the people call'd Quakers, only for their peaceable meetings to worship God : presented to the serious consideration of the King and both Houses of Parliament : with a postscript of the nature, difference and limits of civil and ecclesiastical authority, and the inconsistency of such severities with both, recommended and submitted to the perusal of Cæsar's true friends / by the author of England's present interest, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Penn, William, 1644-1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 34.</note>
                  <note>A second part was published in 1676. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-01</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96947:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96947:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE
Continued Cry
OF THE
OPPRESSED
FOR
JUSTICE,
Being
A farther Account of the late Unjuſt and
Cruel Proceedings of Unreaſonable Men
againſt the Perſons and Eſtates of many of
the People call'd Quakers, only for their peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
Meetings to worſhip God.</p>
            <p>Preſented to the Serious Conſideration of the <hi>KING</hi>
and both Houſes of <hi>PARLIAMENT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a Poſtſcript of the Nature Difference and Limits
of <hi>Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Authority,</hi> and the inconſiſtency of
ſuch <hi>Severities</hi> with both.</p>
            <p>Recommmended and ſubmitted to the <hi>Peruſal</hi> of <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s
True Friends.</p>
            <p>By the Author of <hi>England's Preſent Intereſt, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Seek Judgment, Relieve the Oppreſſed, Judge the Fatherleſs, and
Defend the Widdow,</q>
            <bibl>Iſa. 1. 17.</bibl>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1675.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="to_the_King_and_parliament">
            <pb facs="tcp:96947:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96947:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>FOR THE
KING
AND
Both Houſes
OF
PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>FOraſmuch as the Maintenance of <hi>Juſtice,</hi>
and Preſervation of the <hi>Peace</hi> of <hi>Civil So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties</hi>
have in all Ages been the great End of
Government; and ſince it hath pleaſed Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty
God to caſt our Lot in a Kingdom,
whoſe Conſtitution is more then ordinarily
careſil of the <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property</hi> of its <hi>free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born
Inhabitants:</hi> And becauſe ſeveral Laws
have been made upon Occaſion of <hi>Diſſent</hi> in
Matters of Religion, to preſs an Uniformity
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96947:3"/>
to the Religion now eſtabliſhed, that in the
Execution of them have generally interferred
with thoſe Laws that give and preſerve <hi>Engliſh
Freedoms,</hi> in that Hundreds of us have been
Impriſoned, and our Goods frequently ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
to the utter Ruine of many Families, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
any <hi>Legal Proceſs</hi> or <hi>Tryal by Peers;</hi> and
This not for refuſing Conformity to the <hi>State,</hi>
or denying <hi>Caeſar</hi> his <hi>Due,</hi> or being chargea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
to <hi>Pariſhes,</hi> or uſeleſs to the <hi>Government</hi>
but only becauſe of our conſcientious Diſſent
from the preſent Church: And ſince this
ſeems to be an Alteration in the ancient <hi>Engliſh</hi>
Government, by making an <hi>ECCLESIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STICAL
CONFORMITY</hi> the Grand
and Neceſſary Qualification in <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men
to the Peaceable Enjoyment of their NA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TURAL
and CIVIL INHERITAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CES:
and foraſmuch as this Courſe tends <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o a
manifeſt <hi>Decay</hi> of <hi>Trade</hi> (the Political Life or this
Iſland) <hi>Diſcouragement of Strangers, Depopulation</hi>
of the <hi>Country, Impoveriſhing</hi> of many Thouſand
<hi>Vſeful Inhabitants,</hi> as well as that ſuch Severities
about Matters of Conſcience are Inconſiſtent
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96947:3"/>
with the Doctrine and Example of Chriſt and
his Followers in all <hi>Ages,</hi> and repugnant, not
only to the very VVay of true Conviction,
but the Doctrine of ancient <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> whoſe
Proteſtation at the Diet at <hi>Spira</hi> againſt Coer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
in Matters of Religion, was the Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of their being called <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> And becauſe
many malicious and covetous Perſons (under
Pretence of doing God, the King &amp; Country
Service) have taken advantage by theſe Laws
to vent their Paſſions, act their Revenge, and
purſue their VVorldly Intereſt, beyond all
Law and Humanity, as wofully appears by
the anexed Particulars, ready to be proved.</p>
            <p>VVe therefore intreat; <hi>Firſt,</hi> That it would
pleaſe you to peruſe the anexed Particulars for
your better Information of the Nature of our
Caſe and Allegations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That you would be pleaſed, for
the Removal and Prevention of the like Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs,
to repeal or qualifie thoſe Laws, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
the Perſons and Eſtates of many Thouſands
of the peaceable People of this Kingdom are
hourly expoſed to Ruine in this VVorld, for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96947:4"/>
meer Conſcience, about Things relating to
the next VVorld, that being aſſured, the ſweat
of our Brows, and hard-gotten Bread for our
Families ſhall not be made a <hi>Forfeit</hi> for our
peaceable Conſciences, we may be better en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged,
for the Time to come, to all virtuous
and induſtrious Living under the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
as hath hitherto been, through
God's Grace, our daily Practice.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="accounts_of_persecution">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96947:4"/>
            <head>A few Inſtances out of many which might be given,
of the great OPPRESSIONS and CRV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ELTIES
lately acted upon Innocent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
and Induſtrious Families, chiefly in Perſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
(as is pretended) of the late Act againſt
Conventicles, for their meeting in peaceable Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
to worſhip God: Read, Conſider, and Redreſs.</head>
            <div type="account">
               <head>Leiceſter-Shire.</head>
               <p>FOR a Meeting at <hi>Long Claxton,</hi> or <hi>Clawſon</hi> four perſons
were ſent to Priſon, and ſo much Goods at divers Times ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
from ſome of the ſaid Meeting, that they had not a Cow left
to give their young Children Milk, their very Bed-Clothe,
wearing Clothes and working-Tools eſcaped not the Violence
or Avarice of their Perſecutors; the total Sum amounts to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
Two Hundred thirty ſix Pounds, nor did this ſatisfie our
Perſecutors for they cruelly dragg'd ſome Women in the Streets
by the Necks, till they were neer ſtiffied, tearing the Clothes
off their Heads and Backs. One Woman that gave Suck was
ſo bea<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n and bruiſed on her breaſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that it ſeſtered and broke,
with which ſhe hath end<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red many Weeks Miſery and Torture;
Another Woman of ſeventy five Years of Age was violently
<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rown <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>own <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon the Gro<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by one W<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Conſtable; the
Men w<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> sorely beaten, drawn and dra<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ged out of the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>i<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
ſome by the Heels, ſome by the Hair of the Head, and
<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, so br<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ised, that they were not able to follow their Day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
 others they whip<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on the Face till the Blood ran down;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96947:5"/>
there was one they furiouſly trod upon till Blood guſht out of his
Mouth and Noſe; To compleat the Matter, the Informer
took away from one of the Priſoners his Purſe and Money, as
if he had not been a quiet Neighbour, but a Priſoner of VVar;
Nor was this accidental; but Deſigns no ſhort Fit of Cruelty,
upon an extraordinary Provocation; for at this bitter Rate have
they treated them for ſeveral Moneths.</p>
               <closer>Witneſſes,
<signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>Edward Hallam,</item>
                        <item>William Marryott,</item>
                        <item>John Wilford,</item>
                        <item>William Smith,</item>
                        <item>Richard Parker.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>Nottingham-Shire.</head>
               <p>UNder Pretence of proſecuting the late Act againſt
<hi>Conventicles</hi> One <hi>Peniſton Whaley</hi> a Juſtice, and one
<hi>Colgrave</hi> a Bum-Bayly, and one <hi>Walker,</hi> both Informers
have utterly ruin'd many poor Families in this County in their
Eſtates, having taken or caus'd to be taken from ſeveral Perſons
about Seven Hundred Pounds, the Juſtice bidding the Officers
take three or four Times the Value of the Fines, that they mig<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t
ſell good peny-worths, never returning, as we are informed,
any one Record of Conviction into the Seſſions, except forced
by perſons appealing: <hi>John Godrick</hi> and <hi>William Hudſon</hi> of <hi>Little
G<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly</hi> appealing to the Seſſions, the Seſſions ordered them their
Money again; but the aforeſaid <hi>Peniſton Whaley</hi> ſtill detains
Sixty pounds in his Hands, contrary to the Orders of the
Seſſions, notwithſtanding it ha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> been divers Times demanded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>T. Sampſon</hi> by Warrant from <hi>G. Nevil,</hi> Juſtice, for two Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
had taken from him nineteen Head of Beaſts and Goods to
the Value of ſixty Pounds and upwards, as was vallued by the
Neighbours; ſo that they left him not a Cow to give his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
Milk: That ever theſe Things ſhould be done by ſuch as
count themſelves <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and Followers of Chriſt Jeſus, who
ſuffered, but would have none to ſuffer for his Religion.</p>
               <closer>Witneſſes,
<signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>Abraham Sampſon,</item>
                        <item>Francis Hawkſmore,</item>
                        <item>Robert Porter.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96947:5"/>
               <head>Norfolk.</head>
               <p>FOR ſeveral Meetings in and about <hi>Cockley Clay</hi> ſeveral Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
have had Goods taken from them to the Value of
fifty three Pounds, <hi>William Wat</hi> being Informer. <hi>John
Patterſon</hi> had Two Hundred Sheep taken from him worth
Eighty Pounds. <hi>William Barber</hi> being informed againſt by <hi>John
Gibbs</hi> a Prieſt of <hi>Gliſſing,</hi> for Meeting, had Cows, Carts, a Plough,
Harrows and Hay taken from him to the Value of Fifty Pounds;
the ſaid <hi>William</hi>'s Houſe hath been rifled TEN Times, and he is
now a Priſoner upon a Writ of <hi>Excommunicato capiendo.</hi> At <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenham</hi>
ſeveral Perſons have been fined, <hi>Wat</hi> the Informer, and his
Wife being the only Witneſſes againſt them, &amp; Goods have been
taken to a great Value;<note place="margin">☜</note> they left one <hi>Joſeph Harriſon</hi> not ſo much
as a Bed to lye upon; but he, his Wife and Children were fain
to lye on Straw.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>Cambridge.</head>
               <p>FOR a peaceable Meeting at the Houſe of <hi>William Braſier</hi>
Shoemaker in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> he was fined Twenty Pounds by
<hi>John Hunt</hi> Mayor, and <hi>John Spencer</hi> Vice-Chancellor, upon
the Information of <hi>Stephen Perry</hi> a Tinker: The Officers that
came to diſtrein for this Twenty Pounds ſaid, <hi>They had
Warrants for Fifty Five Pounds more;</hi> They took his Leather,
Laſts, and the Seat he workt on, wearing-Clothes, and Sheets
where he lay, though on Straw, having taken his Bed before,
not leaving him any Thing to cover him withal;<note place="margin">☜</note>; ſo that he was
fain to lodge abroad, till he could get ſome old Things to cover
him at Home.</p>
               <p>And there hath lately been taken from ſeveral Perſons, for
meeting in and about <hi>Cambridge,</hi> Goods and Cattel to the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue
of Sixty Three Pounds and upwards.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Littleport, Ely,</hi> and other Places in the Iſle of <hi>Ely,</hi> ſeveral
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96947:6"/>
Perſons were fin'd, &amp; had their Goods taken for their peaceable
Meetings, <hi>viz. Cloth, Stuff, Houſhold-Goods and Cattel;</hi> from
one Woman the very Bed ſhe lay on;<note place="margin">☞</note> in all, to the Value of
One Hundred Ninety five Pounds and upwards.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Edward Partridge</hi> and his Favorite <hi>Thomas Richman,</hi> the
old Informer, uſed great Violence to ſeveral; <hi>Edw. Partridge</hi>
ſtruck <hi>Samuel Cater</hi> twice, and being at Prayer, pulled him
down by the Noſe, beating Men and Women till he broak his
ſtaff: He alſo ſtruck one Perſon, ſtanding quietly at the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-houſe
Door, and felled him, that the Standers by ſaid, <hi>There
is one knockt on the Head;</hi> yet he revived in a little Time, but
within ſix Moneths after dyed,<note place="margin">☞</note> and to his dying Day complained
of that Blow.</p>
               <p>Note, <hi>William March</hi> Juſtice, fined one Man (no <hi>Quaker)</hi>
Five Pounds, for refuſing to help to carry away the aforeſaid Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers
Goods, which Five Pounds, the poor Man paid; but
wanting but Two Pence thereof, the ſaid Juſtice forced him to
borrow it, to make up the ſum; and ſhortly after the poor Man
dying, on his Death-Bed he much rejoyced, <hi>That he had<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> no Hand</hi>
                  <hi>in taking away his Neighbour</hi> Adams <hi>his Goods.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">☞</note>
               </p>
               <closer>Witneſſes,
<signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>William Braſier,</item>
                        <item>Samuel Cater.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>Oxford-Shire.</head>
               <p>FOR a Meeting at <hi>Alvskoet</hi> near <hi>Burford (Walter Powel</hi>
Prieſt of the Town, being Informer, who before the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
had ſpoak to the Juſtices, at their Peril to be at the Meeting)
ſeveral Perſons, were fined, and had Goods taken away to the
Value of Forty Four Pounds and upwards.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96947:6"/>
               <head>Sommerſet-Shire.</head>
               <p>THirty two Perſons were fined for being at a Burial, for
which they had taken from them in Cows, Corn and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Goods,<note place="margin">☜</note> to the Value of Eighty Two Pounds and upwards,
by Warrant from <hi>Fra. Pawlet</hi> Juſtice, who when none elſe would
buy the diſtreined Cattle, he ſent Men to buy them for himſelf.</p>
               <p>One <hi>Margery Oſmond,</hi> who was not at the Buryal, and yet
was fined by <hi>F. Paulet,</hi> went to him to know the Names of them
that had ſworn againſt her, and deſired Juſtice of him; he ſaid,
<hi>It was a Miſtake;</hi> by which it did afterwards appear, he was
willing to excuſe the Informers; howbeit, he then read in a
Book in the hearing of ſeveral Perſons, in which <hi>Bayner</hi> and
<hi>Withey</hi> were recorded Informers againſt the ſaid Aſſembly at the
Burial, and ſaid withal, <hi>That ſhe ſhould proſecute them for Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury
at the next Seſſions, and that the Record at the Seſſions ſhould
be Evidence againſt them,</hi> or to that Effect; but he was not ſo
good as his Word; for at the Seſſions Witneſſes were preſent to
teſtifie, that ſhe was not at the ſaid Burial; but <hi>Fra. Pawlet</hi>
(in Favour to theſe Informers) left <hi>Withey</hi>'s Name out of the
Record,<note place="margin">☜</note> and put in another's Name, who was not preſent, and
alſo left out her Name; ſo there could be no Proceedings againſt
the Informers for their Perjury, albeit he had iſſued out his War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
to levy the Fine impoſed on her. The ſaid Juſtice <hi>Pawlet</hi>
for the ſame Burial fined ſeveral perſons Twenty Four Pounds
for an unknown Preacher, yet ſent a Certificate to the Mayor of
<hi>Bridgwater,</hi> to diſtrein Twenty Pounds on the Goods of <hi>John
Anderton</hi> for preaching at the Burial that Day; ſo he would
have Forty Four Pounds in all [Note,<note place="margin">☜</note> this is Twenty Four
Pounds more then the Rigour of the Law allows of, admitting it
had been a Conventicle.] for the Preacher known &amp; one unknown
when in Truth there was none ſpoak, but <hi>John Anderton</hi> that
Chriſtianly exhorted the People to conſider their latter End: And
when <hi>Mary Tyler,</hi> the Widdow of the deceaſed (who was fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
Four Pounds for being at her Husband's Burial,<note place="margin">☜</note> and had
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96947:7"/>
Goods taken for it) ſpoke mildly to him, to ſhew him his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice,
he told her, <hi>It did not become Women to go to their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands</hi>
                  <hi>Burials.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">☞</note>
               </p>
               <p>And ſeveral Perſons for being at Meetings at <hi>Glaſtenbury</hi> and
<hi>Gregory Stoake</hi> in this County, have lately had Cattle, Corn
and Goods taken from them, to the Value of One Hundred
Forty Five Pounds and upwards, by Warrant from two Perſons,
called, Juſtice <hi>Waldron</hi> and Juſtice <hi>Croſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At this Day there remain Priſoners in this County for the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony
of Jeſus, Twenty one Perſons.</p>
               <p>And there hath dyed in Priſon,<note place="margin">☞</note> Sufferers for good Conſcience
ſake, in this County, ſince the Year 1660. Eighteen Perſons.</p>
               <closer>Witneſſes,
<signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>John Cuff,</item>
                        <item>Henry Clothie,</item>
                        <item>George Taylor.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>Berk-Shire.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THomas Curtis,</hi> fined Three Pound Fifteen Shillings, had
a Mare taken from him worth about Seven Pounds,
by Warrant from Juſtice <hi>Craven;</hi> and though an <hi>Appeal</hi> was
tendered (according to the <hi>Act)</hi> it was refuſed; and though
the Officers voluntarily offered the Juſtice the Fine, yet he
would not take it;<note place="margin">☞</note> but had the Mare valued at Four Pounds, and
kept her.</p>
               <p>The 7th Day of the 8th Moneth, 1675. <hi>William Armourer</hi>
and <hi>George Goſwel,</hi> Mayor of <hi>Reading,</hi> came to the Meeting,
and becauſe the Women came not forth ſo ſoon as they would
have them, <hi>W. Armourer</hi> pluckt out of his Pocket a ſharp In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument,
and prickt ſeveral of them in a Shameful Manner,<note place="margin">☞</note>
till it fetcht Blood; and afterwards tendered the <hi>Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi>
to ſeven of them, on purpoſe to enſnare them; and becauſe
for Conſcience ſake they could not <hi>ſwear</hi> at all, they were ſent
to Goal, where they now remain.</p>
               <p>And the Mayor Thruſt ſome Women in a very Abuſive
Manner, perticularly an Antient Woman, without regard to Age
or Sex.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:96947:7"/>
Of which Cruelty, and much more, many in <hi>Reading</hi> are
Witneſſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>Cheſhire.</head>
               <p>JUſtice <hi>Daniel</hi> of <hi>Daresbury</hi> hath fined one Meeting near
him ſeveral times over, and hath taken from <hi>T. Briggs</hi>
and other the Value of One Hundred and Sixteen Pounds,
Fifteen Shillings and Ten Pence, in Kine and Horſes (which
the Juſtice keeps to his Own Uſe and Work, as his own) alſo
Corn, Braſs, Pewter, Bedding, and ſuch like Goods.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Hall</hi> of <hi>Congleton, Shoemaker,</hi> was fined Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
Pounds, by <hi>Will. Knight,</hi> Mayor, and two Juſtices, for
having a Meeting at his Houſe; for which his Mare was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained,
when his Wife was riding on her. And ſome time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
they ſeized on his Shoes in his Shop. And another time, in
his Abſence, with Mathooks brake open the Doors of his Dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
Houſe, and took away Two Cart-Loads of Goods, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<hi>William</hi> tendered an <hi>Appeal,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">☜</note> but the ſaid Magiſtrates de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed
it: Sometime after, the Mare, of her own accord, came
Home, in his Abſence, his Wife let her in; now, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
that upon their Crying the Mare, he went with two
of his Neighbours, and acquainted the Chief Magiſtrate, that
he had the Mare, and ſhe was in the Field, without any Lock
to hinder them from her, and if they had more Right to her
then he, they might fetch her; otherwiſe, if they pleaſed, he
would joyn Iſſue with them, to try whoſe the Mare was; which
they refuſed, and committed him to the Goal, and Arraigned
him for his Life,<note place="margin">☜</note> as a Fellon; but was acquitted by the Judge
and Jury.</p>
               <p>Taken from ſeveral in and about <hi>Nantwich,</hi> by Warrant from
Juſtice <hi>Manwaring,</hi> for Eighty Seven Pound in Fines, Goods
to the Value of One Hundred and One Pounds, in Kine, Bacon,
Bedding, Braſs, Pewter, Corn, Cloth, Shoes and Cheeſe: And
from one Man was taken,<note place="margin">☜</note> the very Beds they lay on to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96947:8"/>
the Dunghil, which they alſo carryed away. Some of the Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers
appealing, the Jury acquitted them, but the Juſtices
would not receive their Verdict; but at the next Seſſions the
Juſtices gave Judgment for the Informers; and not contented
with this, they gave them TREBLE Coſt.</p>
               <p>Note the Cheif Informer in theſe Sufferings, was one <hi>John
Widdowbury</hi> of <hi>Hanklow,</hi> called an Eſquire, who did it to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged
on <hi>Thomas Braiſey</hi> (one of the Meeting) for demanding
Forty Pounds of him, which he owed unto <hi>Thomas Braiſey</hi>
upon Bond, which, that he might (as appears) defraud the ſaid
<hi>Thomas Braiſey</hi> of, he hath ſince (by reviving an old Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication)
ſent him to Priſon, and ſwears he will ſend his Wife
after him from her four SMALL Children.</p>
               <closer>Witneſſes,
<signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>Henry Fletcher,</item>
                        <item>Jonathan Fletcher,</item>
                        <item>Samuel Ellis.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>York-Shire.</head>
               <p>HAving in a former Narrative acquainted you, that Goods
to the Value of Two Thouſand Three Hundred Eighty one
Pounds, Ten Shillings, by the late Act againſt Conventicles,
have been taken from us, with ſome other of our heavy Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures
and Sufferings in the County of <hi>York,</hi> for the Exerciſe of
our Conſciences towards God; and having yet obtained no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs,
but rather an Increaſe of our Sufferings, One having ſince
dyed in Priſon at <hi>York,</hi> where Twenty four yet remain Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
and ſome Hundreds of Families like to be ruin'd by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions,
both in Temporal and Eccleſiaſtical Courts, becauſe
for Conſcience ſake we cannot conform to the Religion and
Worſhip impoſed on us, nor deny the Religion and Worſhip
which we have been taught by the Spirit of God, according to
the Holy Scriptures; and our conſtant adhering to the Religion
and Worſhip in Spirit,<note place="margin">☞</note> which we believe God requires of us,
can injure no Man; but the Denyal of it would greatly injure
us, becauſe every Man muſt give an Account to God for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96947:8"/>
Oh why then ſhould we by Law be expoſed to Ruin and
Deſtruction for the Exerciſe of our Conſciences towards God,
ſince by our Ruines none are like to be raiſed, unleſs it be a few
Informers,<note place="margin">☜</note> Paritors and other inferior Officers in the ſaid Courts;
but the Dammage that may come to the King, and the whole
Nation, by Diſcouraging, Perſecuting or Ruining an induſtrious
innocent People, is like to be very great: Therefore we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire,
that you would be pleaſed to put a Stop to the vexatious
Proceedings of the ſaid Informers and Courts, and confirm to
us, your ſelves and Poſterities the Liberty of our Conſciences
towards God, that we all may worſhip and ſerve him, as we
believe he requires us; ſo ſhall we be accepted of him, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
his Bleſſing, and Peace, and Tranquility in the whole
Nation.</p>
               <closer>Witneſſes
<signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>John Whitehead,</item>
                        <item>John Hall.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>In divers other Counties in this Nation, there are many more
Inſtances, both of great Havock and Spoil of Goods, impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing
and ruining many innocent Families in their Trades and
Livelihoods, which for Brevity ſake, is at preſent here omitted.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:96947:9"/>
            <head>A Poſtſcript,
Wherein
The CIVIL and ECCLESIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STICAL
AVTHORITY
is briefly conſidered in their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
Difference and Extents, not
Vnſeaſonably to the preſent Poſture
of Affairs.</head>
            <p>OUR Bleſſed Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt did long
ſince diſtinguiſh the <hi>Things of</hi> Caeſar from <hi>the Things
of God</hi> in his plain and notable Anſwer unto that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnaring
Queſtion of the <hi>Jews, about paying Tribute to</hi> Caeſar;
<hi>Render</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>unto</hi> Caeſar <hi>the Things that are</hi> Caeſar<hi>'s, and
to</hi> God <hi>the Things that are</hi> God's; that is, <hi>Divine Worſhip,</hi> and
all Things relating to it belong unto God, <hi>Civil Obedience</hi> to
<hi>Caeſar:</hi> God can only be the Author of right Acts of Worſhip
in the Mind, this is granted by all; therefore it is not in the
Power of any Man or Men in the World, to ſway or compel
the Mind in Matters of Worſhip to God; where this is attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
God's Prerogative is invaded, and <hi>Caeſar</hi> (by which VVord
I underſtand the <hi>Civil Government)</hi> hath all; for he doth not
only take his own Things, but the Things appertaining to God
alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:96947:9"/>
If any ſhould ask me, <hi>What are the Things properly belonging
to</hi> Caeſar? I anſwer in Scripture-Language, <hi>To love Juſtice, as
Judgment, relieve the Oppreſſed, right the Fatherleſs, be a Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror
unto Evil-doers, and a Praiſe to them that do well;</hi> for this
is the great End of Magiſtracy; but perhaps my Anſwer ſhall
be reckoned too general and ambiguous, and a freſh Queſtion
ſtarted, <hi>Who are the Evil-doers, to whom the Civil Authority
ought to be terrible?</hi> But this ought in my Judgment to be no
Queſtion with Men that underſtand the Nature of Civil Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity;
for thoſe are the Evil-Doers, that violate thoſe Laws
which are neceſſary to the Preſervation of Civil Society, as
<hi>Thieves, Murderers, Adulterers, Traytors, Drunkards, Cheats,
Vagabonds,</hi> and the like miſchievous and diſſolute Perſons, Men
void of Virtue, Truth and Sincerity, the Foundation of all good
Government, and only firm Bond of human Society; whoever
denies me this, muſt at the ſame Time ſay, that Virtue is leſs
neceſſary to Government then Opinion, and that the moſt <hi>Viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated</hi>
Men, profeſſing but <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s <hi>Religion,</hi> are the <hi>beſt</hi> Subjects
to <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s <hi>Authority,</hi> conſequently, that other Men, living ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
ſo honeſtly and induſtriouſly, &amp; having elſe as good a Claim
to Civil Protection and Preferment, ſhall meerly for their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
from that Religion (a Thing they can't help; <hi>for Faith is
the Gift of God)</hi> be reputed the worſt of Evil-doers, which is
followed with expoſing their Names to Obloquie, their Eſtates
to Ruin, and their Perſons to Goals, Exiles, and Abundance
of other Cruelties: What is this, but to confound the <hi>Things
of Caeſar</hi> with the <hi>Things of God;</hi> Divine Worſhip with Civil
Obedience; the Church with the State, and perplex human
Societies with endleſs Debates about Religious Differences?
nay, is not this to erect new Meaſures to try the Members of
Worldly Societies by, and give an Acceſſion to another Power,
then that which is neceſſary to the Conſtitution of Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment?
But that which ought to deter wiſe Rulers from
aſſuming and exerciſing ſuch an Authority, is the Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the pernicious Conſequences of doing ſo.</p>
            <p>For, <hi>Firſt,</hi> It makes PROPERTY, which is the firſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96947:10"/>
and moſt fixt part of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, floating and uncertain;
no Conformity to the Church, no Property in the State; and
doubtleſs, the Inſecurity of <hi>Property</hi> can be no Security to the
Government.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> It makes me owe more to the <hi>Church</hi> then to the <hi>State;</hi>
for in this Caſe, the Anchor I ride by, is not my <hi>Obedience</hi> to
Laws, relating to the Preſervation of <hi>Civil Society,</hi> but
<hi>Conformity</hi> to certain Things belonging to the Doctrine and
Diſcipline of the <hi>Church;</hi> to that though I may be an honeſt,
induſtrious <hi>Engliſh man,</hi> a great Lover of my <hi>Country,</hi> and an
Admirer of the <hi>Government</hi> I live under, yet if I refuſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs
the Religion that either now is, or hereafter may be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed,
I muſt neither enjoy the <hi>Liberty</hi> of my <hi>Perſon,</hi> nor the
<hi>quiet Poſſeſion</hi> of my <hi>Eſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly,</hi> This not only alters the <hi>Government,</hi> by ſacrificing
Mens <hi>Properties</hi> for that which cannot be called a Sin againſt <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty,</hi>
nor an Offence to the Nature of <hi>Civil Government,</hi> if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Tranſgreſſion at all; but it narrows the <hi>Intereſt</hi> and <hi>Power</hi>
of the <hi>Governours;</hi> for proportionably, what Number they
cut off from their Protection, they cut off from themſelves and
the Government, not only rendering a great Body of People
<hi>Vſeleſs,</hi> but provoaking them to be <hi>Dangerous;</hi> to be ſure it
clogs the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate</hi> in his Adminiſtration of Government,
making that neceſſary which is not at all neceſſary to him as <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar;</hi>
It is a Sort of <hi>DVVMVIRATESHIP</hi> in
Power<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by which the <hi>Civil Monarchy</hi> is broken; for as that
was a Plurality of Men, <hi>ſo this is a Plurality of Powers;</hi> and to
ſpeak freely, the <hi>Civil Power</hi> is but <hi>Lackey,</hi> to run of all the
unpleaſant Errands the froward Zeal of the other ſends it upon,
and the beſt Preferment it receives for its Pains, is to be <hi>Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,
Goaler</hi> or <hi>Executioner</hi> to ſome of the beſt Livers, and
therefore the beſt Subjects in the Kingdom: Oh what greater
Injuſtice to <hi>Caeſar!</hi> then to make his Government vary by ſuch
<hi>Modes</hi> of Religion, and him to hold his Obedience from his
People, not by their <hi>Conformity</hi> to <hi>Him,</hi> but the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:96947:10"/>
               <hi>4thly,</hi> This is ſo far from reſembling the Univerſal Goodneſs
of God, who diſpenſes his Light, Air, Showres, and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
Seaſons to all (and whom <hi>Caeſar</hi> ought alwayes to imitate)
and remote from increaſing the <hi>Trade, Populacy</hi> and <hi>Wealth</hi> of
this Kingdom, that it evidently tends to the utter Ruin of
Thouſands of <hi>Traders, Artificers</hi> and <hi>Husband-men</hi> and their
Families, thereby increaſing the Charges, by increaſing the poor
of the Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>5thly,</hi> This muſt needs be a great <hi>Diſcouragement</hi> to Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,
from coming in, and ſetling themſelves amongſt us, when
they have Reaſon to apprehend, that they, and their Children
after them can be no longer ſecured in the Enjoyment of their
<hi>Properties,</hi> then they ſhall be able to prevail with their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,
to believe that the Religion which our Laws do now,
or ſhall at any Time approve and impoſe, is undoubtedly true;
and the Way of worſhipping of God, which ſhall at any Time
be by our Laws enjoyned, is, and ſhall be more agreeable to
the Will of God then any other Way in which God is worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
in the World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>6thly,</hi> The Religion we are commanded Conformity to, doth
not make better Livers (that's a Demonſtrative) nor better
<hi>Artiſts;</hi> for it cannot be thought, that going to <hi>Church,</hi> hear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing
<hi>Common-Prayer</hi> or believing in the preſent <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi>
learns Men to build <hi>Ships</hi> or <hi>Houſes,</hi> to make <hi>Clothes, Shoes, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als</hi>
or <hi>Watches, Buy, Sell, Trade</hi> or <hi>Commerce,</hi> better then any
that are of another Perſwaſion; and ſince theſe Things are
<hi>Vſeful,</hi> if not <hi>Requiſite</hi> in <hi>Civil Society,</hi> is not prohibiting, nay,
ruining ſuch Men, becauſe they will not come to hear <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi>
&amp;c. diſtructive of <hi>Civil Society;</hi> nor more obedient <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</hi>
If any object, <hi>Diſſenters have not alwayes been ſo;</hi> the
Anſwer is ready, do not expoſe them, protect them in their
<hi>Lives, Liberties</hi> and <hi>Eſtates;</hi> for in their preſent Poſture they
think they can call nothing their own, and that all the Comforts
they have in this World are hourly lyable to <hi>Forfeiture,</hi> for their
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96947:11"/>
               <hi>Faith, Nope</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> concerning the other World: Is not
this to deſtroy Nature and Civil Government, when People
are ruined in their Natural and Civil Capacity, not for Things
relating to either, but what are of a Super-natural Import.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>7thly,</hi> This deprives them of Protection that protect the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;
Diſſenters have a great Share in the <hi>Trade,</hi> which
is the Greatneſs of this Kingdom; and they make a large Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion
of the <hi>Taxes</hi> that maintain the Government; and is it
reaſonable, or can it be <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> when they pay <hi>Tribute</hi> to
<hi>Caeſar,</hi> to be preſerved in an <hi>Vndiſturbed Poſſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſion</hi> of the reſt,
and that the reſt ſhould be continually expoſed for the peaceable
Exerciſe of their Conſciences to God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>8thly,</hi> Neither is this a Conformity to True and Solid Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
ſuch as is neceſſary to Eternal Salvation, wherein moſt
Parties verbally agree, but for a Modification of Religion, <hi>ſome
peculiar Way</hi> of Worſhip and Diſcipline: <hi>All confeſs One God,
One Chriſt, One Holy Cheſt, and that it is indiſpenſably requiſite
to live Soberly, Righteouſly and Godlikely in this preſent evil
World;</hi> yet is one proſecuting the other for his Conſcience,
<hi>ſeizing Corn, driving away Cattel, breaking open Doors, taking
away and ſpoiling of Goods;</hi> in ſome Places not leaving a <hi>Cow
to give poor Orphans Milk,</hi> nor a <hi>B<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to lye on;</hi> in other Places
Houſes have been ſwept ſo clean, that a <hi>Stool</hi> hath not been left
to fit on, nor ſo much as working Tools to labour for Bread. To
ſay nothing of the <hi>Opprobrious Speeches, Bloody Blows</hi> and <hi>Tedious
Impriſonments,</hi> even to Death it ſelf, through <hi>Naſtineſs</hi> of <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous,</hi>
that many Innocent People have ſuffered for their peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
Conſcience only.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>9thly,</hi> But this Way of proceeding for Maintenance of the
National Religion, is of an ill Conſequence upon this Account;
Heaven is barr'd from all further <hi>Illuminations,</hi> let God ſend
what Light he pleaſeth, it muſt not be received by <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
without <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Licence; and if it happen that <hi>Caeſar</hi> be
not preſently convinced it is of God, at this Rate I muſt either
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96947:11"/>
renounce my <hi>Conv<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons,</hi> and looſe my <hi>Soul</hi> to pleaſe <hi>Caeſar</hi>
or profeſs and perſevere in my <hi>Perſwaſſion,</hi> and loo<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e my <hi>Life,
Liberty or Eſtate</hi> to pleaſe God; this hath frequently oc<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urr'd,
and may again; therefore I would entreat <hi>Caeſar</hi> to conſider
the ſad Conſeq<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence of Imp<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sition, and remember, both that
God did never ask Man Leave to <hi>Introduce Truth,</hi> or make fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Diſcoveries of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Mind to the World, and that it hath been
a wof<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l Snare to thoſe Governments that have been drawn to
employ their Power againſt his Work and People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>10thly,</hi> This Way of Proceedure endeavours to ſtiffle, or elſe
to puniſh <hi>Sincerity;</hi> for <hi>Fear</hi> or <hi>Hopes, Frowns</hi> or <hi>Favour</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vail
only with baſe Minds, So<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ls degenerated to the third and
fourth Generation; every <hi>Spark of Integrity</hi> muſt be extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht,
where <hi>Conſcience</hi> is ſacrificed to <hi>Worldly Saf<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty</hi> and <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment;</hi>
ſo that t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Net holds no <hi>Temporizers, Honeſt Men</hi>
are all the Fiſh it catches; but one would t<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ink they ſhould
make but an ill Treat to ſuch as reckon themſelves <hi>generous Men,</hi>
and what is more <hi>Chriſtians</hi> too; but that which renders the
Matter more unjuſtifiable, is, the <hi>Temptation</hi> ſuch <hi>Severity</hi> puts
upon Men, not hardy enough to <hi>ſuffer for Conſcience,</hi> yet ſtrongly
perſwaded they have <hi>Truth</hi> on their Side, to deſert their <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,</hi>
and ſmo<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her their <hi>Convictions,</hi> which in plain Terms is
to make of ſincere Men Hypocrites, whereas it is one great End
of Government, by all laudable Means to pre<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erve Sincerity;
for without it there can be no Faith or Truth in <hi>Civ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l Society:</hi>
nor is this all; for it is a <hi>Maxim</hi> worthy of <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Notice,
NEVER TO THINK HIM TRUE TO <hi>CAESAR</hi> THAT
IS FALSE TO HIS OWN CONSCIENCE; beſides, raped
Conſciences treaſure up <hi>Revenge,</hi> and ſuch Perſons are not likely
to be longer Friends to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> then he hath <hi>Preferm<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ts</hi> to a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lure
them, or <hi>Power</hi> to deter them from being his moſt implacable
Enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>11thly,</hi> There is not ſo ready a Way to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>eiſm,</hi> as this of
extinguiſhing the Senſe of Conſcience for Worldly Ends; de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtroy
that Internal Rule of <hi>Faith, Worſhip</hi> and Pract<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> t<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wards
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96947:12"/>
God, and the Reaſon of my Religion will be <hi>Civil Injunctions,</hi>
and not <hi>Divine Convictions;</hi> conſequently, I am to be of as
many Religions as the Civil Authority ſhall impoſe, however
untrue or contradictory; this <hi>Sacred Tye</hi> of Conſcience thus
broken, farewell to all <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eavenly Obligations</hi> in the Soul, <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Authority</hi>
and ancient <hi>Proteſta<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Principles;</hi> Chriſt may at
this Rate become what the <hi>Jews</hi> would have had him, and his
Apoſtles be reputed Turners of the World upſide down, as
their Enemies repreſented them, and the godly Martyrs of all
Ages ſo many Self-Murderers; for they might juſtly be eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
Reſiſters of <hi>Worldly Authority,</hi> ſo far as that Authority
concerns it ſelf with the Impoſition of Religion, becauſe they
refuſed the Conformity commanded, even to Death. And it
may not be unworthy of <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Conſideration, if from theſe
Proceedings People are tempted to infer, there is nothing in
Religion but <hi>Worldly Aims</hi> and <hi>Ends,</hi> becauſe ſo much Power
is abus'd under the Name of <hi>Religion,</hi> to vex and deſtroy Men
for being of another Religion, that he hazards the beſt Hold and
Obligation he hath to Obedience, which is Conſcience; for
where they are taught to obey for <hi>Intereſt, Duty</hi> and <hi>Conviction</hi>
are out of Doors: By all Means let Conſcience be ſacred, and
<hi>Virtue</hi> and <hi>Integrity</hi> (the under diſſenting Principles) cheriſht;
<hi>Charity</hi> is more powerful then <hi>Severity, Perſwaſion</hi> then <hi>Penal
Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> To the Reproach of this Courſe with wiſe Men it hath
never yet obtain'd the End deſired; for inſtead of Compliance,
the Difference is widened, the Sufferers are pitied by Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators
which only helps to increaſe the Number of Diſſenters;
for whoever is in the wrong, few think the Perſecutor in the
Right. This in all Ages having been the Iſſue of ſevere Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution
of Diſſenters for Matters of <hi>Religion;</hi> what a Cruel,
Troubleſom, Thankleſs, Succeſleſs Office is it for <hi>Caeſar</hi> to be
employed in; may he take better Meaſure of his Authority, and
uſe his Power to the Encouragement of all the <hi>Virtuous</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious,</hi>
and Juſt Puniſhment of the <hi>Lazy</hi> and <hi>Vicious</hi> in all
Perſwaſions; ſo ſhall the Kingdom <hi>Floriſh,</hi> and the Government
<hi>Proſper.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:96947:12"/>
               <head>For Eccleſiaſtical Authori<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y or in plainer Engliſh
Church-Power, which makes up the other Pa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t
of this Poſtſcript, it will be requiſite to conſult
Holy Scripture, wh<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re we ſhall be informed of
the Inſtitution and Practice of it among
the Ancient Ch<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſtians; and by that Canon all
People profeſſing Chriſtianity, pretend a Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs
to be concluded.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CHurch-Power</hi> ſuppoſeth a <hi>Church</hi> firſt; It will not be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper
therefore to examine, <hi>firſt,</hi> What a Scripture-New-Teſtament-Church
is; and <hi>next,</hi> what is the Scripture Power
belonging to ſuch a Church: A Scripture-Church is <hi>a Company
or Society of People, believing, profeſſing and practiſing according
to the Doctrine and Example of Chriſt Jeſus and his Apoſtles,</hi> and
not according to the <hi>Scribes</hi> &amp; <hi>Phariſees,</hi> that <hi>taught
for Doctrine the Traditions of Men:</hi> They are ſuch
as are Meek in Heart, Lowly in Spirit,<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 11. 29</note> Chaſt
in Life,<note n="b" place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 2. 2 Cor. 11. 2.</note> Virtuous in all Converſation,<note n="c" place="margin">Phil. 4. 8. 1 Pet. 1. 15.</note> full
of Self-Denyal,<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 16. 24</note> Long-Suffering and Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<note n="e" place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 6.</note> not only for giving,<note n="f" place="margin">Luke 6. 37.</note> but loving
their very Enemies;<note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 5 44.</note> a People ſo effectually
redeemed from the Impieties and Vanities of
the World;<note n="h" place="margin">Rev. 14. 4.</note> he that thought it no Robbery to
be equal with God,<note n="i" place="margin">Phil. 2. 6.</note> thought it no Diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
to be Head to, and account as his own Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy:
<note n="k" place="margin">Eph. 1. 22. Col. 1. 118.</note> It was upon a Society thus qualified, that
the Holy Ghoſt beſtows theſe excellent Names,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96947:13"/>
                  <hi>Diſciples and Friends of Chriſt;</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Job. 19. 14, 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Heirs
and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> with Chriſt</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Rom 8. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt's Brethren
and Ki<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Heb 2. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>A peculiar People</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Tit. 2. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>The
p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> as moſt p<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ci<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us Blood</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Acts 20 28.</note> 
                  <hi>the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed
from <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Earth</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Rev. 14. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>A Royal Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,
<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Nation;</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>The Church of the
Firſt Born;<note n="s" place="margin">Heb. 12, 23.</note> (Christ's Body,</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Col. 1. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>and the Lamb's
Brid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Rev. 21. 9.</note> which anſwers but Chriſt's own Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter
of himſelf, Religion and Kingdom, which
is the moſt apt Diſtinction that ever can be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
of the Nature of his Church and her Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<hi>viz</hi>
                  <note n="w" place="margin">Joh. 18. 36.</note> MY KINGDOM IS NOT OF
THIS WORLD.
which well connects with <hi>Render unto</hi> Caeſar <hi>the
things that are</hi> Caeſar<hi>'s,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 22. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>and unto</hi> God <hi>the things
that are</hi> God<hi>'s,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It was an Anſwer to a very ſuſpitious Queſtion; for it was fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly
bruited,</hi> that he was a King, and came to
poſſ<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs his Kingdom,<note place="margin">Luke 13. 2.</note> and was by ſome called the
King of the Jews.</p>
               <p>The Jews being then ſubjected to the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned
<hi>Pilate, Caeſar</hi>'s <hi>Deputy</hi> to underſtand his pretentions,
which upon better information he found to center in this, <hi>My
Kingdome is not of this World,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 18. 36.</note> 
                  <hi>elſe would my Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
fight for me:</hi> As if he had ſaid, theſe Reports
are a meer perverſion of my Peaceable and Self-denying Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
an Infamy invented by malicious <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi>
that they might the better prevaile with <hi>Caeſar</hi> to ſacrifice me to
their hatred and revenge: I am <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Friend, I ſeek none of
his Kingdom from him, nor will I ſow Sedition, plot or conſpire
his Ruin; no, <hi>let all Men render unto</hi> Caeſar <hi>the Things that are</hi> Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar<hi>'s</hi>
that's my Doctrine; for I am come to erect a Kingdom
of another Nature then that of this World, to wit, a Spiritual
Kingdom to be ſet up in the Heart:<note place="margin">Luke 17. 21.</note> And Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
is my Throne, upon that will I ſit, and
rule the Children of Men in Righteouſneſs;<note place="margin">Tit. 2. 12.</note> and who
ever <hi>lives ſoberly, righteouſly and godlily in this World,</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:96947:13"/>
ſhall be my good and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>s, and they will certainly
make no ill ones for C<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Virtue is the end of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
and renders hi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> S<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> more eaſie &amp; ſafe then before.
Had I any other Des<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>is, would I ſuffer my Self to be
reproached, traduced and per<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecuted by a conquered people?
were it not more my <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to ſuffer then revenge, would not
their many provocation have drawn from me ſome inſtance of
another Nature then the Forbearance and Forgiveneſs I teach?
Certainly were I animated by another principle then the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
of Meekneſs and Divine Sweetneſs, I ſhould not have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biden
<hi>Peter</hi> fighting,<note place="margin">Mat. 26. 52.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>ing, put up thy Sword,</hi>
or endoctrinated my Followers to bear
Wrongs, but revenge all Affronts, and by Plots and other Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems
have attempted Ruin to my Enemies, and the Acqueſt
of worldly Empire; and no doubt but they would have fought
for me: Nay I am not only patiently (and with Pitty to Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies)
ſenſible of their barbarous Carriage towards me for my
Good Will to them (for their Eternal Happineſs I only ſeek)
but I foreſee what they further intend againſt me, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign
to crucifie me, and to do it, will rather free a Murderer
then ſave their Saviour,<note place="margin">Mat. 27. 20.</note> they will perform that
Cruelty with all the Agravation and Contempt
they can,<note place="margin">Ver. 27. &amp;c.</note> deriding me themſelves, and expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
me to the Deriſion of others, for they will
mock my Divine Kingſhip with a Crown of
Thorns,<note place="margin">Ver. 29.</note> and in my Agonies of Soul and Body
for a Cordial,<note place="margin">ver. 48.</note> give me Gall and Vineger to drink; but
notwithſtanding all this, to ſatisfie the World that my
Religion is above Wrath and Revenge,<note place="margin">Luke 23. 34.</note> I can for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give
them;<note place="margin">Mat. 26. 53.</note> and to ſecure <hi>Caeſar</hi> and his People
from all Fears of Impoſition, whatever Authority
I have, and how many Legions of Angels, ſoever, I might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
both to my Deliverance, and the Enforcement of my Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage
up<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Mankind; I reſolve to promote neither with worldly
Power; for it is not of the Nature of my Religion and Kingdom:
and as I neither aſſume nor practiſe any ſuch thing my Self that
am the great Author, Promoter and Example of this Holy Way;
ſo have I not only never taught my Diſciples to live or act other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96947:14"/>
or given them a Power I refuſe to uſe my Self; but expreſly
forbad them, and warn'd them in my Inſtructions of exerciſing
any the leaſt Revenge, Impoſition or Coertion towards any:
This is evident in my Sermon preached upon the Mount, where
I freely, publickly and with much Plainneſs, not only <hi>prohibited
Revenge,</hi> but <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>njoyned Love to Enemies</hi> making it
to be a great Token of true Diſcipleſhip to ſuffer
Wrongs,<note place="margin">Mat. 5. 44. 45, 46, 47.</note> and conquer Cruelty by Patience and
Forgiveneſs, which is certainly a great Way off Impoſition or
Compulſion upon other Men. And when I was ſtrongly bent
for <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and ſent Meſſengers before to prepare ſome En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment
for me and my Company in a Village,
belonging to the <hi>Samaritans,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 9. 53, 54, 55, 56.</note> and it ſeems the
People refuſed, becauſe they apprehended I was
going to <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> this provoakt ſome of my Diſciples, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
<hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> to that Degree, that they asked me,
if I were willing that they ſhould command Fire from Heaven to
deſtroy thoſe <hi>Samaritans,</hi> as <hi>Elias</hi> in another Caſe had done;
I turned about, and rebuked them, ſaying, <hi>Ye know not what
Manner of Spirit ye are of; for I am not come into the World to
deſtroy Mens Lives, but</hi> by my peaceable Doctrine and Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<hi>to ſave them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At another Time one of my Diſciples, relating to me ſome
Paſſages of their Travails, told me of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
Man they ſaw,<note place="margin">Luke 9. 49, 50.</note> that caſt out Devils in my
Name, and becauſe he was not of their Company, nor followed
them, ſaid he, <hi>we forbad him;</hi> as if they had thereby ſerved and
pleaſed me; but I preſently teſtified my Diſlike of the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
and Narrowneſs of their Zeal, and to inform them better
told them, they ſhould not have forbid him; <hi>for he that is not
againſt us is for us;</hi> my Drift is not Opinion, but Piety; they
that caſt out Devils, convert Sinners, and turn Men to Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,
are not againſt me, nor the Nature and Religion of my
Kingdom, and therefore ought to be cheriſht rather then forbid.
That I might ſufficiently declare and inculcate my Mind in this
Matter, I did at an other Time, and upon a different Occaſion,
preach againſt all Coertion and Perſecution for Matters of Faith
and Practice towards God, in my Parable of the Sower, as my
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96947:14"/>
Words manifeſt, which were theſe; <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven
is likened unto a Man which ſowed good Seed in his Field; but while
Men ſlept, his Enemy came, and ſowed Tares among the Wheat,
and went his Way; but when the Blade ſprung up, and brought
forth Fruit, there appeared the Tares alſo; ſo the Serv<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nts of
the Houſe-houlder came and ſaid, didſt thou not ſow good Seed in
thy Field?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30</note> 
                  <hi>from whence then hath it Tares?
he anſwered, an Enemy hath done this; the
Servants ſaid unto him, wilt thou then that we
go and gather them up? but he ſaid NAY, leſt while ye gather
up the Tares, ye root up alſo the Wheat with them, let both grow
together till the Harveſt, and in the Time of Harveſt I will joy to
the Reapers, gather ye together firſt the Tares, and bind them in
Bundles to burn them, but gather the Wheat into my Barn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that I might not leave ſo neceſſary a Truth miſ appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended
of my dear Followers, or liable to any Miſ-conſtructions,
my Diſciples, when together, deſiring an Explanation, I inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted
my Words thus;</p>
               <p>He that ſoweth the good Seed is the Son of Man; the Field is
the World;<note place="margin">Ver. 36, 37, 38, 39.</note> the good Seed are the Children of the
Kingdom; but the Tares are the Children of the
Wicked One; the Enemy that ſowed them is the
Devil; the Harveſt is the End of the World; and the Reapers
are the Angels.</p>
               <p>This Patience, this Long-Suffering and great Forbearance
belong to my Kingdom and the Subjects of it, my Doctrine
ſpeaks it, and my Example confirms it, and this can have no
poſſible Agreement with Impoſition and Perſecution for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience:
And that I might ſufficiently deter my Followers from
any ſuch Thing, as I profeſs my ſelf to be their Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,<note place="margin">Joh. 15. 12.</note>
ſo have I commanded them to love one another
in a more eſpecial Manner; but if inſtead therof
any grow proud, high minded, and beat or abuſe their Fellow
Servants in my religious Family, when I come to take account
of my Houſhold, he ſhall be cut aſunder, and appointed his Po<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
among the Unbelievers; behold the Recompence I appoint
to Impoſing Lordly Perſons, ſuch as count others Infidels, and to
make them ſuch Believers as themſelves, will exerciſe Violence
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96947:15"/>
towards them, and if they prevail not, will call for Fire from
Heaven to devour them, and if Heaven refuſe them, will fall
a beating and killing, and think (it may be they do God good
Service) b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t their Lot ſhall be with Unbelievers forever: Nay,
I have ſo effe<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ua<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y provided againſt all Maſtery, that I expreſly
charged them, <hi>not to be many Maſters; for one was their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter;</hi>
I told them, that <hi>the greateſt amongſt them was to be Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant
to the reſt,</hi> not to impoſe upon the reſt; nay, that to be
great in my Kingdom, they muſt become as gentle and harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
as little Children, and ſuch cannot force and puniſh in Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
of Religion. In fine, I ſtrictly commanded them, to love
one another, as I have loved them, who am ready to lay down
my Life for the Ungodly, inſtead of taking away Godly Mens
Lives for Opinions; and this is the great Maxim of my holy
Religion, <hi>He that would be my Diſciple, muſt</hi> not crucifie other
Men, but <hi>take up his Croſs, and follow me, who am meek and
lowly,</hi> and ſuch ſo enduring ſhall find Eternal Reſt to their Souls,
this is the Power I uſe, and this is the Power I give.</p>
               <p>How much this agrees with the Language, Doctrine and
Example of Jeſus Chriſt, I ſhall leave them to conſider, that
read and believe Scripture; but ſome affected to preſent Church
Power, and deſiring their Ruine that conform not to her
Worſhip and Diſcipline, will object, That Chriſt did give his
Church Power to bind and looſe, and bid any Perſon agrieved
tell the Church.</p>
               <p>I grant it; but what Binding was that? with outward Chains
and Fetters, in naſty Holes and Dungeous? nothing leſs: Or
was it, that his Church had that true Diſcerning in her, and
Power with him, that what ſhe bound, that is condemned, or
looſed, that is remitted, ſhould ſtand ſo in God's Sight and
Chriſt's Account.</p>
               <p>But tell the Church; and what then? obſerve Chriſt's Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
in the Puniſhment of the Offender; <hi>If the Offender will
neither receive private Admonition, nor hear the Church,
then</hi> (ſayes Chriſt) <hi>let him be to thee as an</hi> Heathen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here's
no Fines, Whips, Stocks, Pillories, Goals, and the like In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96947:15"/>
of Cruelty, to puniſh the Heretick; for the Purport
of his Words ſeems to be no more then this; If any Member of
the Church refuſe thy private Exhortation and the Church's
Admonition, look upon ſuch a Perſon to be no more of you;
let him take his Courſe, thou haſt done well, and the Church
is clear of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well, but ſay the</hi> Church-Fighters <hi>of our Age,</hi> Did not <hi>St.
Paul</hi> wiſh them cut off that troubled the Church in his Time?
<hi>Yes: But with what Sword think you? Such as Chriſt bid</hi> Peter
<hi>put up, or the Sword of the Spirit which is the Word of God?
Give him leave to explain his own Words;</hi> For the WE A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PONS
of our Warfare are NOT CARNAL, but
mighty through God, to the pulling down of ſtrong Holds, caſting
down Imaginations, and every high Thing that ex<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lteth it ſelf
againſt the Knowledge of God, and bringing every Thought into
Obedience to Chriſt.</p>
               <p>What think you of this? Here are Warfares, Weapons,
Oppoſitions and Conformity, and not only no external Force
about Matters of Religion us'd or countenanced, but the moſt
expreſs and pathetical Excluſion and Rejection of any ſuch
Thing that could be given.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now obſerve what Sort of Church-Government he recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends
to his beloved</hi> Timothy; Avoid fooliſh Queſtions, and
Genealogies, and Contentions, and ſtriving about the Law, for
they are unprofitable and vain: A Man that is an Heretick,
after the firſt and ſecond Admonition, reject, knowing that he
that is ſuch is ſubverted and ſinneth, being <hi>CONDEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NED
OF HIMSELF,</hi> or ſelf-condemned.</p>
               <p>It's very remarkable; <hi>firſt,</hi> That t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is is great Apoſtle, in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtead
of exhorting <hi>Timothy</hi> to ſtand upon Niceties, and ſacrifice
Mens Natural Comforts and Enjoyments for Opinions of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
injoyns him to ſhun Diſputes about them, leaving Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
to their own Thoughts and Aprehenſions in thoſe Matters,
which excellently well coheres with another Paſſage of his.
<hi>Let us therefore,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>as many as be perfect, be thus
minded, and if in any Thing ye be otherwiſe mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96947:16"/>
God ſhall</hi> REVEAL <hi>even this unto you;</hi> he did not ſay,
you ſhall be FINED, PILLAGED, EXCOMMUNICATED
and FLUNG into Priſon, if ye be not of our Mind.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> That, in the Apoſtles Definition, an Heretick is a ſelf-condemned
Perſon, one conſcious to himſelf of Error, and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy
in it; but that are not conſcientious Diſſenters; for many
Ten Thouſands in this Nation act as they believe, and diſſent from
the National Religion, purely upon a Principle of Conſcience
to Almighty God; and with Men of any Tenderneſs or common
Senſe, their continual great Sufferings in Perſon and Eſtate,
and their Patience under them, are a Demonſtration, or there
can be none in the World: Nor can their Perſecutors diſprove
them, unleſs they could ſearch Hearts, and that is a little too
far for a Fallible Spirit to reach, and an infallible One they
deny: So that the Apoſtle makes not the Heretick to lye upon
the Side of miſbelieving, or not coming up to his Degree of
Faith &amp; Knowledge, but upon the Side of Wilfully, Turbulently,
Obſtinately and Self condemnedly maintaining inconſiſting
Things with the Faith, Peace and, Proſperity of the Church.</p>
               <p>Granting us then not to be obſtinate and ſelf condemned
Diſſenters (and you cannot reaſonably refuſe it us) how do you
prove us Erroneous in the other Part? All Parties plead Scripture,
and that for the moſt oppoſite Principles; <hi>Homouſians</hi> and
<hi>Arrians, Calviniſts</hi> and <hi>Arminians, Papiſts, Janſeniſts</hi> and
<hi>Proteſtants;</hi> The Scripture, you ſee, cannot determine the
Senſe of it ſelf; it muſt have an Interpreter; he muſt either be
Fallible or Infallible; If the firſt, we are worſe then before;
for Men are apt to be more confident, and yet are ſtill upon
as uncertain Grounds; If the laſt, this muſt either be an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal
or an Internal Judge; If an External, you know where
you are without pointing; for there ſtands nothing between
you and Popery in that Principle; If an Internal Judge, either
it is our ſelves, or the Spirit of Chriſt dwelling in us; Not our
ſelves; for then the Rule is the Thing ruled, which cannot be;
and if it be the Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus (and the Apoſtle tells us,
<hi>That unleſs we have the Spirit we are none of Chriſt's)</hi> then is the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96947:16"/>
Neck of Impoſition broken, and what haſt thou to do to judge
me? let me ſtand or fall to my own Maſter; And upon this Foot
went <hi>Luther, Calvin, Melancthon, Beza</hi> abroad; And <hi>Cranmer,
Ridly, Hooper, Jewel, Bradford, Philpot, &amp;c.</hi> at home, and as
good Men, and conſtant Martyrs in Ages before them.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe Conſcientious Diſſenters as ill Men as the
Apoſtle deſcribes an Heretick to be; what is the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>3dly, A Man that is an Heretick, after the firſt and ſecond
Admoniſion reject,</hi> that is, deny his Communion, declare he
is none of you, condemn his Proceedings by a publick Cenſure
among your ſelves; what more can be ſtrain'd by the fierceſt
Proſecutors of Men for Religion out of theſe Words.</p>
               <p>But was this the Evangelical Rule and Practice? Yes, that it
was; Oh then whence comes Impoſition Force Cruelty, Spoil of
Goods, Impriſonments, Knockings, Beatings, Bruiſings, Stockins,
Whippings, and Spilling of Blood for Religion? What Church is
that, whoſe Officers are ſo far from cloathing the naked, as to
ſtrip the clothed, from feeding the hungry, that they take their
Bread from them, and thoſe poor Widdows and helpleſs
Orphans too; and ſo remote from viſiting the ſick and
impriſoned, that they drag away their Bed from under
them, and caſt People into Priſon for Conſcience ſake;
Nay they haled away an Honeſt Man from a Meeting to Goal
at <hi>Reading,</hi> (but the other Day) not permitting him to
TAKE LEAVE of his poor Wife, newly delivered, and
in a DYING Condition, though ſhe alſo deſired it,
and liv'd but juſt by the Meeting-Houſe where they took him.
In fine, what are they that for no other Cauſe paſs ſuch
dreadful Excommunications, as render the Excommunicants
little better then outlawed Perſons, ſubjecting their Civil and
Natural Rights to their Pride, Paſſion, Intereſt or Revenge,
unleſs they will purchaſe their Enjoyment at the dear Rate of
looſing their own Souls? For what elſe can be the Conſeq<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96947:17"/>
of conforming to that I do not believe? Is not this to deſtroy
ſincere Men, and make and ſave Hypocrites.</p>
               <p>Oh, that ſuch as are concern'd would ſoberly conſider, if any
Thing is ſo Scandalous to True Religion as FORCE; who
can think that evidence Good that is extorted? And what
a Church is that, which is made up of ſuch Proſelites, or
that employes ſuch Means to make them? O where is
that <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Meekneſs, Patience and Forbearance? How
many have been ruined, that were never exhorted, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comunicated
before they were once admoniſhed? This is
not to ſerve God, but Worldly Intereſt: its quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
to Chriſt's Counſel and Doctrine: He came to ſave, and
not to deſtroy Nature to magnifie his Grace. You pretend to
hate <hi>J. Calvin</hi>'s unconditional Reprobation, yet practiſe it;
If you ſay no, Conformity is your Condition: I anſwer, that
its as unreaſonable to require an impoſſibillity, as cruel to damn
Men for not doing it; For as you ſay, his Doctrine makes
God to command them to repent, that cannot repent, and
yet damn them if they repent not; So you injoyn Men to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh
their preſent Faith and Worſhip, and conform to
yours, which is not in their Power to do, yet damn them
in a temporal Reſpect if they refuſe it; For you make ſuch
an unavoidable Diſſent, puniſhable with the Deſtruction of
Mens Liberties and Eſtates: You had better leave off va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luing
your ſelves upon the Mercy and Well-Natur'dneſs of
that Tenet of the univerſal Love of God to Mankind, till
you love more then your ſelves, and abominate the Church
of England's being, ſuch an Elect to the Civil Government
as utterly reprobates the reſt, as you pretend to deteſt the like
Injuſtice in <hi>J. Calvin</hi>'s Notion of Election and Reprobation.</p>
               <p>And the Truth of it is, this helps on <hi>Atheiſm</hi> as much
as any Enormity in the Land, when Witty Men, not willing
to take Pains to examine after the Truth and Excellency of
Religion, behold Men that call themſelves Chriſt's Miniſters,
and the Apoſtles Succeſſors and Followers, to affect and ſeek
Government, and yet twice deny it, when they go to receive
it, that ſome others grow Lordly, live Voluptuouſly, and watch
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:96947:17"/>
after the biggeſt Preferments, not being excited by moſt Service
for God, but Earthly Power and Wealth for themſelves, and
at the ſame Time perſecuting Men of more Self-Denyal, for
Matters of Opinion about Faith and Worſhip towards God;
ſo that <hi>No Conformity</hi> to this Church, <hi>No Protection</hi> from
the State. Which among <hi>Proteſtants</hi> is ſo much the more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable,
becauſe they by theſe Courſes implicitely own
and aſſume the higheſt Infallibility and Perfection, and yet
deny any ſuch Thing; for it ſuppoſes that nothing is Truer, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
Perfecter, or elſe they both perſecute Men to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace
a Fallible and Imperfect Religion, and with cruel Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
provide againſt any Thing more True or Infallible; the
greateſt Injury to the World that can be; for it is a plain En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
to fruſtrate all thoſe excellent Propheſies and gracious
Promiſes God has given, and the holy Scriptures declare of the
latter Dayes. To conclude, I ſhall deſire Men of this Unnatural,
Unreaſonable and Unchriſtian Spirit to conſider:</p>
               <p>1. What Church was that which <hi>John</hi> ſaw, riding upon the
Powers of the Earth, employing their Authority to force CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FESSION,
TRIBUTE and SUBJECTION
to her?</p>
               <p>2. What that Church was which dyed her ſelf in the
BLOOD of them that believed not in her, againſt whom the
poor Souls under the Altar (whoſe Bodies had been beheaded
by her) cryed to God?</p>
               <p>3. What Church it was that would ſuffer none to Buy, Sell or
Traffick without having her <hi>Mark</hi> (CONFORMITY to her)
in their Forehead or right Hand, that is, either thoſe that
heartily and openly confeſt her, or thoſe that baſely complyed
for Fear?</p>
               <p>4. What Church is that which Trades in the Souls of Men?
Read <hi>Revelations, Chap. 13. 18. &amp;</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>5. Whether this Church reigns not, wherever Mens.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:96947:18"/>
                  <hi>LIBERTIES</hi> and <hi>PROPERTIES,</hi> with all the
Comforts of this Life are expoſed and ſacrificed for Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
of <hi>FAITH</hi> and <hi>WORSHIP</hi> to Almighty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
God.</p>
               <p>Weigh theſe Things, you great Church-Men of the
Age, in the Fear of that God who made Heaven and Earth,
and think not to make thus cheap of the Lives, Liberties
and Eſtates of <hi>Free-born Engliſh People, and Harmleſs Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians
for their peaceable Conſcience,</hi> without being accounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
to that Great Lord in the <hi>Terrible</hi> Day of his Judgment, that
draws on upon the World: No Plea you have ſhall be able
to juſtifie theſe things, or fence off the heavy Stroak of
that Juſt Judge, unleſs you repent: 'Tis not Succeſſion in
Name, but Nature, that makes the true Chriſtian Miniſter
and Biſhop: And where the Divine Life and Holy Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications
of Chriſt and his Apoſtles are wanting, there can
be no Succeſſion, but what is as proper to the falſe Church
as the true, the Counterfeit as the Chriſtian: <hi>Be not deceived,
God will not be mocked, ſuch as you Sow, ſuch ſhall you Reap.</hi>
Remember Chriſt's Words; <hi>Bleſſed are the Poor in Spirit;
for theirs is the Kingdom of God. Bleſſed are they that mourn, for
they ſhall be comforted. Bleſſed are the Pure in Heart; for
they ſhall ſee God. Bleſſed are the Meek; for they ſhall
inherit the Earth. Bleſſed are the MERCIFVL; for they
ſhall obtain Mercy.</hi> Therefore Reform, and let your Moderation
be known unto all Men, for the Lord is at hand: <hi>Even ſo
come Lord Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA</head>
            <p>Pag. 18. Line 33. for <hi>Injuſtice</hi> read <hi>Injury.</hi> p. 20. l. 11. dele
<hi>and.</hi> p. 20. 31. read <hi>Heaven is hereby barr'd, as much as in Men
lyes, from.</hi> p. 22. l. 22. for <hi>the</hi> read <hi>though.</hi> p. 25. l. 15. read
<hi>revenged.</hi> p. 28. l. 25. read <hi>Chains.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:96947:18"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
