<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Caroli tou makaritou paliggenesia</title>
            <author>Pierce, Thomas, 1622-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-03">2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54827</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2165A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31122</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11780002</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11780002</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49002</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A54827)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49002)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1491:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Caroli tou makaritou paliggenesia</title>
                  <author>Pierce, Thomas, 1622-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verso.</note>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints to Pierce.</note>
                  <note>All but first word of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard Universtiy Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-01</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-01</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49002:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49002:1"/>
            <p>CAROLI Του Μαχαρίτου ΠΑΛΙΓΓΕΝΕΣΊΑ .</p>
            <p>Printed <hi>Ann. Dom.</hi> 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:49002:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49002:2"/>
            <head>CAROLI <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>I <hi>Come,</hi> but come with trembling, lest I prove</l>
               <l>Th' unequall Greece of <hi>Semele</hi> and <hi>Iove.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As <hi>She</hi> was too <hi>obscure,</hi> and <hi>He</hi> too <hi>bright,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My <hi>Theam</hi>'s too <hi>heavy,</hi> and my <hi>Pen</hi> too <hi>light.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And whilst, like <hi>Midas,</hi> I presume to sit</l>
               <l>In wise <hi>Apollo's Chair,</hi> without <hi>HIS</hi> wit,</l>
               <l>Is it not just t'expect, that He, who <hi>dares</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Higher then <hi>Midas,</hi> should wear longer <hi>Eares</hi>?</l>
               <l>May I not fear <hi>Patroclus Fate,</hi> and feel</l>
               <l>The dangerous honour of <hi>Achilles Steel?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Just like that <hi>busie Elf,</hi> whose vent'rous <hi>Pride</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Found none but <hi>Titan Titan</hi>'s Coach could guide?</l>
               <l>Why; <hi>Hee'l</hi> not <hi>stand</hi> in <hi>Verse.</hi> Can I enclose<note n="*" place="bottom">De <hi>Catone</hi> ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us dict<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m, <hi>Ultimus Romanorum, Primus Hominum.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Him,</hi> whom the greatest Libertie of <hi>Prose</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wants room to <hi>hold?</hi> And whose <hi>unweildy Name,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is big enough to <hi>fill</hi> the <hi>Trump of Fame?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>An Individuall species?</hi> like the <hi>Sun,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>At once a <hi>Multitude,</hi> and yet but <hi>One?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>One</hi> of such vast Importance, that He fell</l>
               <l>The <hi>Festivall</hi> of <hi>Heav'n,</hi> and <hi>England's Hell?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>One,</hi> who for Eminence was these two things,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The last of Christians, and the first of Kings?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:49002:3"/>
                  <hi>One</hi> so diffusive, that he liv'd to <hi>all,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>One</hi> that dy'd the whole world's <hi>Funeral?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For <hi>Charles</hi> being thus <hi>dismounted,</hi> and the <hi>Swain</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>High shoo'd Bootes</hi> leapt into the <hi>Wain,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is not old <hi>Beldame Nature</hi> truly said</l>
               <l>T'advance her <hi>Heeles,</hi> and stand upon her <hi>Head?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Does not the <hi>Iudge,</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> too for a need,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Stirrop</hi> hold, whilst <hi>Treason</hi> mounts the <hi>Steed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is not <hi>Gods Word,</hi> and's <hi>Providence</hi> besides</l>
               <l>Us'd as a <hi>Laquy,</hi> whilst th' <hi>white Devil rides</hi>!</l>
               <l>Sure <hi>all things</hi> thus into <hi>Confusion</hi> hurld</l>
               <l>Make, though an <hi>universe,</hi> yet not a <hi>World.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And so our <hi>Soveraign's,</hi> like our <hi>Saviours Passion,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Becomes a kind of <hi>Doomsday</hi> to the <hi>Nation.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If <hi>Deadmen</hi> did not <hi>walk,</hi> 'twould be admir'd</l>
               <l>(The <hi>Breath</hi> of all our <hi>Nostrils</hi> thus <hi>expir'd</hi>)</l>
               <l>What 't is that gives us <hi>motion.</hi> And can I,</l>
               <l>Who want <hi>my self,</hi> write <hi>Him</hi> an Elegie?</l>
               <l>Though <hi>Virgil</hi> turnd <hi>Evangelist,</hi> and wrote,</l>
               <l>Not from his <hi>Tripod,</hi> but <hi>Gods Altar</hi> taught;</l>
               <l>Though all the Poets of the Age should sit</l>
               <l>In <hi>Inquest</hi> of <hi>Invention,</hi> and <hi>club wit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To make <hi>words Epigrams</hi>; should they combine</l>
               <l>To <hi>crowd</hi> whole <hi>stock</hi> of Fancie in <hi>each line</hi>;</l>
               <l>Sell the <hi>Fee-simple</hi> to advance one <hi>summe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(As <hi>Eglis</hi> spake but <hi>once,</hi> and then liv'd <hi>dumb</hi>)</l>
               <l>'I were all as <hi>inarticulate,</hi> and weak,</l>
               <l>As when those men make <hi>signes,</hi> that cannot <hi>speak.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But where the <hi>Theme confounds us,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Longin.</note> 'tis a sort</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49002:3"/>Of glorious <hi>Merit, proudly to fall short.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Despair</hi> sometimes gives <hi>courage; any one</hi>
               </l>
               <l>May <hi>lisp him</hi> out, who can be <hi>spoke</hi> by none;</l>
               <l>None but a <hi>King</hi>; No King, unlesse He be</l>
               <l>As <hi>Wise, as Iust,</hi> as <hi>Good,</hi> as <hi>Great</hi> as <hi>He.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When <hi>Late Posterity</hi> shall run t'advise</l>
               <l>With <hi>Times impartial Register,</hi> how <hi>Wise</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This <hi>Great-one</hi> was, they'l find it there inroll'd</l>
               <l>That He was ne'r in's <hi>Nonage.</hi> but <hi>born old.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>View him whilst <hi>Prince of Wales,</hi> and it appears</l>
               <l>His <hi>wisdome</hi> did so <hi>antedate</hi> his <hi>years,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t He was <hi>Ful</hi> i'th' <hi>Bud,</hi> and's <hi>Soul</hi> divine,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nestor,</hi> might be <hi>Great-Grandfather</hi> to <hi>thine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>View him agen, where he so <hi>ripe</hi> was grown,</l>
               <l>As not to <hi>rise,</hi> but <hi>drop</hi> into a <hi>Throne.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How did those <hi>rayes</hi> of <hi>Majestie,</hi> which were</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Scatter'd</hi> in <hi>other</hi> Kings, <hi>concenter here?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As if h'ad got King <hi>Sapors sphere,</hi> and prov'd</l>
               <l>How each <hi>Intelligence</hi> his <hi>Orbe</hi> had mov'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wise Charles,</hi> like <hi>them,</hi> sate steering at two Helmes,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>King</hi> of <hi>himself,</hi> but <hi>Father</hi> of his <hi>Realms:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And just as if old <hi>Trismegistus Cup</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Had by his thirsty Soul been <hi>all</hi> drunk up,</l>
               <l>His <hi>understanding</hi> did begirt this <hi>All,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As t' were <hi>Ecliptick</hi> or <hi>Meridionall.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uppose a <hi>Dyet</hi> of all Christian <hi>Kings</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Bishops</hi> too, conven'd to weigh the things</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State:</hi> Nay adde <hi>Inferiour</hi> men,</l>
               <l>Those of the <hi>Sword,</hi> the <hi>pensil,</hi> and the <hi>pen.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:49002:4"/>From th' <hi>Scepter</hi> to the <hi>Sheep-hook, Charles</hi> in all</l>
               <l>Must have been <hi>Vmpire Oecumenicall.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He liv'd a <hi>Perpendicular</hi>; The <hi>Thread</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His <hi>Wisdome</hi> was; <hi>Humility</hi> the <hi>Lead,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By which he measur'd <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Things</hi>; took aim</l>
               <l>At actions <hi>crooked,</hi> and at actions <hi>plain.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He and all from him into <hi>Cubes</hi> did fall,</l>
               <l>And yet as perfect as the <hi>Circle, all,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Twas He took <hi>Natures Bredth,</hi> &amp; <hi>Depth,</hi> and <hi>Hight,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Knew the just difference 'twixt <hi>Wrong,</hi> and <hi>Right.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He saw the <hi>points</hi> of things, could justly hit,</l>
               <l>What <hi>must</hi> be done, what <hi>may</hi>; what's <hi>just,</hi> what <hi>sit.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As if, like <hi>Moses</hi> he had had resort</l>
               <l>Unto Gods <hi>Councell,</hi> ere he was of's <hi>Court.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hence his Religion was his <hi>choice,</hi> not <hi>Fate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Rul'd by <hi>Gods Word,</hi> not <hi>Interest</hi> of <hi>State.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Others</hi> may thank their <hi>stars. He</hi> his <hi>inquest,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who, <hi>sounding all</hi> sides, <hi>anchor'd</hi> in the <hi>best.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His <hi>Crown</hi> contain'd a <hi>Miter</hi>; He did twist</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron, King</hi> and <hi>Casuist.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When the <hi>Mahumetan</hi> or <hi>Pope</hi> shall look</l>
               <l>On his Soul's best <hi>Interpreter,</hi> his <hi>Book</hi>;</l>
               <l>His <hi>Book,</hi> his <hi>Life,</hi> his <hi>Death,</hi> will henceforth be</l>
               <l>The <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England's</hi> best <hi>Apologie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Dove</hi> and <hi>Serpent</hi> kiss'd, as if they meant</l>
               <l>To render him as <hi>wise,</hi> so <hi>innocent.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His own <hi>good Genius</hi> knew not, whether were</l>
               <l>His <hi>Heart</hi> more <hi>single,</hi> or his <hi>Head</hi> more <hi>clear.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Virtue</hi> was his <hi>Prerogative</hi>; and thus</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> rul'd the <hi>King,</hi> before the <hi>King</hi> rul'd <hi>Vs.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:49002:4"/>He knew that to <hi>command,</hi> his onely way</l>
               <l>Was first to teach his Passions to <hi>obey.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And his incessant waiting on <hi>God's</hi> Throne</l>
               <l>Gave him such meek <hi>reflections</hi> on his <hi>own,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That, being forc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to <hi>censure,</hi> he exprest</l>
               <l>A <hi>Iudges Office</hi> with a <hi>Mothers breast.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And when some <hi>sturdie</hi> violence began</l>
               <l>T'unsheath his <hi>sword,</hi> unwilling to be drawn</l>
               <l>He but <hi>destroy'd</hi> (and so soft <hi>mercy</hi> can)</l>
               <l>The <hi>malefactor,</hi> to <hi>preserve</hi> the <hi>Man.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Even <hi>Hell's blind Iourney-men,</hi> those <hi>Sons of Night</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who look on <hi>scarlet murder,</hi> and think't <hi>white,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Unwillingly confess'd, The onely thing</l>
               <l>Which made him guiltie was, <hi>That He was King.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He was <hi>Incarnate Iustice,</hi> and 'tis said</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Astraea liv'd</hi> in him, yet <hi>dy'd</hi> a <hi>Maid.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>We want an <hi>Emblem</hi> for him: <hi>Phoebus</hi> must</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Stand still</hi> in <hi>Libra,</hi> to speak <hi>Charles the Iust.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And yet though he were such, that nothing lesse</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Virtue's mean</hi> stretcht to a <hi>just Excesse</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Flew from his Soul; He, like the <hi>Sun,</hi> was known</l>
               <l>To see <hi>all excellence,</hi> except his <hi>own.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His Modesty was <hi>such,</hi> that All which <hi>He</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Ere <hi>spake</hi> or <hi>thought</hi> of's <hi>self,</hi> was <hi>Calumny</hi>;</l>
               <l>But yet so mixt with <hi>state,</hi> that one might see</l>
               <l>It made him not <hi>lesse Kingly,</hi> but <hi>more free.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He was not like <hi>those Princes,</hi> who t'expresse</l>
               <l>A <hi>learned surfeit,</hi> a <hi>sublime excesse,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Send to <hi>dispeople</hi> all the <hi>Sea</hi> of Fish,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Depopulate</hi> the <hi>Aire</hi> to make <hi>one dish,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:49002:5"/>(Such <hi>skilfull luxuries,</hi> as onely serve</l>
               <l>To make their <hi>minds</hi> more <hi>plentifully sterve</hi>)</l>
               <l>Whatever <hi>Dainties</hi> fill'd his <hi>Board</hi> by <hi>chance,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His onely <hi>constant Dish</hi> was <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Evagr. l. 1. c. 21. <hi>de Monachis quisusdam,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Temperance.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His <hi>Virtue</hi> did so <hi>limit</hi> him, his <hi>Court</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Implied his <hi>Cloyster</hi>; and his very <hi>sport</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Was <hi>Self-deniall.</hi> Nay, though he were seen</l>
               <l>So <hi>roab'd</hi> in <hi>purple,</hi> and so matcht t' a <hi>Queen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As made him glitter like a <hi>Noon day Sun,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet still his <hi>Soul</hi> wore <hi>sackcloth,</hi> and liv'd <hi>Nun.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(b)" place="bottom">Evagr. l. 1. c. 13. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Simeon</hi> the <hi>Stylite</hi> in his Pillar pent</l>
               <l>Might live more <hi>strict,</hi> but not more <hi>innocent.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So <hi>wise,</hi> so <hi>just,</hi> so <hi>good,</hi> so <hi>great</hi> and all,</l>
               <l>What is't could set him <hi>higher,</hi> but his <hi>fal?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When he caught up by a <hi>Celestial Train</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Began his <hi>second,</hi> and more <hi>solid Raign.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How to that <hi>Haven</hi> did this <hi>Pilot steer</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Twixt th' <hi>Independent,</hi> and the <hi>Presbyter,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Plac'd in the <hi>confines</hi> of two <hi>shipwracks?</hi> thus</l>
               <l>The <hi>Greeks</hi> are seated 'twixt the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Vs.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whom did <hi>Byzantium</hi> fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Rome</hi> would condemn;</l>
               <l>And freed from <hi>Rome,</hi> they are enslaved by <hi>them.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So plac'd betwixt a <hi>Precipice</hi> and <hi>Wolf,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>There the <hi>Aegaean,</hi> here the <hi>Venice-gulf,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What with the <hi>rising</hi> and the <hi>setting Sun,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By these th'are <hi>hated,</hi> and by those <hi>undon.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:49002:5"/>Thus <hi>virtues</hi> hemm'd with <hi>vices,</hi> and though either</l>
               <l>Solicites her consent, she yields to neither.</l>
               <l>Nay thus our <hi>Saviour,</hi> to enhance his grief,</l>
               <l>Was hung betwixt a <hi>Murderer,</hi> and a <hi>Thief.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now <hi>Charles</hi> as <hi>King,</hi> and as a <hi>good King</hi> too</l>
               <l>Being <hi>Christs adopted self,</hi> was both to <hi>do</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>suffer</hi> like him; both to live and die</l>
               <l>So much more <hi>humble,</hi> as he was more <hi>high</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then his own <hi>Subjects.</hi> He was thus to tread</l>
               <l>In the same footsteps, and submit his Head</l>
               <l>To the same <hi>thorns</hi>: when <hi>spit</hi> upon, and <hi>beat,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To make his <hi>Conscience</hi> serve for his <hi>retreat,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>overcome</hi> by <hi>suffering</hi>: To take up</l>
               <l>His Saviours <hi>Crosse,</hi> and pledge him in his <hi>Cup.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Since then our <hi>Soveraign,</hi> by just account,</l>
               <l>Liv'd o're our <hi>Saviours Sermon</hi> in the Mount,</l>
               <l>And did all Christian Precepts so reduce,</l>
               <l>That's <hi>Life</hi> the <hi>Doctrine</hi> was, his <hi>Death</hi> the <hi>Use</hi>;</l>
               <l>Posterity will say, he should have dy'd</l>
               <l>No other <hi>Death,</hi> then by being <hi>Crucified.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And their renownedst <hi>Epocha</hi> will be</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Great Charles his Death,</hi> next <hi>Christ's Nativity.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Treason's</hi> grown most <hi>Orthodox</hi>; who since</l>
               <l>They said they'd [<hi>make him the most glorious Prince</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In all the Christian World</hi>] 'tis plain, this way</l>
               <l>They onely <hi>promis'd,</hi> what they meant to <hi>pay.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For now (besides that <hi>beatifick Vision</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where all <hi>desire</hi> is <hi>lost</hi> into <hi>fruition</hi>)</l>
               <l>The <hi>stones,</hi> they hurled at him, with intent</l>
               <l>To <hi>crush</hi> his <hi>fame,</hi> have prov'd his <hi>monument.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:49002:6"/>Their <hi>Libels</hi> his best <hi>Obeliske</hi>; To have</l>
               <l>A fit <hi>Mausóle,</hi> were to <hi>want</hi> a <hi>Grave</hi>;</l>
               <l>His <hi>Scaffold,</hi> like <hi>mount Tabor,</hi> will in story</l>
               <l>Become the proudest <hi>Theater of Glory,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Next to the <hi>blessed Crosse</hi>: and thus 'tis sense,</l>
               <l>T'affirm him <hi>murder'd</hi> in his <hi>own Defence.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For though all <hi>Hells Artillery</hi> and <hi>skill</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Combin'd together to <hi>besiege</hi> his <hi>Will</hi>;</l>
               <l>And when their <hi>malice</hi> could not bring't about</l>
               <l>To hurt <hi>God's</hi> Image, they raz'd <hi>Adam's</hi> out,</l>
               <l>(Like men repuls'd, whose <hi>Choler</hi> think's it witty</l>
               <l>To burn the <hi>Suburbs,</hi> when they can't the <hi>City</hi>)</l>
               <l>Howe're they <hi>storm'd</hi> his <hi>walls,</hi> and <hi>draind</hi> his <hi>blood,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which <hi>moted round</hi> his <hi>Soul</hi>; yet still he stood</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Defender of the Faith,</hi> (and that which He</l>
               <l>Found sweeter then revenge) his <hi>Charity.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This then the utmost was their rage could do,</l>
               <l>[<hi>It</hi> shew'd him <hi>King</hi> of his <hi>afflictions</hi> too.]</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vntempted Virtue</hi> is but <hi>coldly good,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(As she's scarce <hi>chaste,</hi> that's so but in <hi>cold blood</hi>)</l>
               <l>To scorn <hi>base Quarter</hi> is the best <hi>escape,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(As <hi>Lucrece</hi> dy'd the <hi>chaster</hi> for her <hi>rape</hi>)</l>
               <l>These <hi>two</hi> did <hi>Charles</hi> his <hi>Virtue</hi> most <hi>befriend,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His <hi>glorious hardships</hi> first, and then his <hi>end.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Death</hi> we forgive thee, and thy <hi>Bourreaux</hi> too,</l>
               <l>Since what did seem <hi>thy rape,</hi> proves but <hi>his due.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For how could he be said to fall <hi>too soon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whose <hi>green</hi> was <hi>mellow,</hi> &amp; whose <hi>dawn</hi> was <hi>noon?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Since <hi>Charles</hi> was onely by thy <hi>curteous knife</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Redeemd</hi> from this great <hi>injury</hi> of <hi>life</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:49002:6"/>To one so lasting, that 'tis truly said</l>
               <l>Not <hi>He,</hi> but his <hi>mortality</hi> is <hi>dead</hi>—</l>
               <l>To weep his Death's the <hi>treason</hi> of our <hi>eyes</hi>;</l>
               <l>Our <hi>Sun</hi> did onely <hi>set,</hi> that he might <hi>rise.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But we do <hi>mock,</hi> not <hi>cheat</hi> our <hi>grief,</hi> and sit</l>
               <l>Onely at best t' <hi>upbraid</hi> our selves in <hi>wit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>want</hi> him <hi>learnedly</hi>: such <hi>colours</hi> doe</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Disguise</hi> disasters, not <hi>delude</hi> them too.</l>
               <l>For though, I must confesse, a Poet can</l>
               <l>Fancy things <hi>better</hi> then another man,</l>
               <l>He can <hi>but</hi> fancy'um; and all his pains</l>
               <l>Is but to fill his <hi>belly</hi> with his <hi>brains.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He may both <hi>Petrify'd</hi> and <hi>famisht</hi> sit,</l>
               <l>That <hi>wears</hi> his <hi>thoughts,</hi> and onely <hi>dine's</hi> on <hi>wit.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Were I a <hi>Polypus,</hi> and could go on</l>
               <l>To <hi>be</hi> those very things I <hi>think</hi> upon,</l>
               <l>I would not then complain: but since I know</l>
               <l>To <hi>call</hi> things <hi>thus,</hi> is not to <hi>make</hi> them so,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Great Charles is slain</hi>: and say we what we will,</l>
               <l>Yet we shall find, <hi>judgements</hi> are <hi>judgements</hi> still.</l>
               <l>For though 'tis true, that his <hi>now-immense</hi> Soul</l>
               <l>Doth hold commensuration with each <hi>Pole</hi>;</l>
               <l>Though he doth shine a <hi>Star</hi> more <hi>fixt</hi> and bright</l>
               <l>Then where the <hi>yeare</hi> makes but <hi>one day and night</hi>;</l>
               <l>And, least he fill the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> doth appear</l>
               <l>Not in the <hi>Eighth,</hi> but <hi>Empyraean</hi> Sphere;</l>
               <l>Yet we his <hi>Rise</hi> may our <hi>Descension</hi> call,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Libra's mounting</hi> is poore <hi>Aries fall.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He was the onely <hi>Moses</hi> that could stand</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:49002:7"/>Betwixt the <hi>sinnes</hi> and <hi>judgements</hi> of the Land.</l>
               <l>And what can we expect, our <hi>Lot</hi> being gon,</l>
               <l>But that a <hi>Hell</hi> from <hi>Heav'n</hi> should tumble down</l>
               <l>On our more sinfull <hi>Sodom?</hi> unlesse we</l>
               <l>Are <hi>damn'd</hi> yet <hi>worse,</hi> to an <hi>impunity.</hi>)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Kings</hi> are <hi>Gods once remov'd.</hi> It hence appears</l>
               <l>No <hi>Court</hi> but <hi>Heav'ns</hi> can trie them by their <hi>Peer.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So that for<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Charles the Good</hi> to have been try'd</l>
               <l>And <hi>cast</hi> by <hi>mortall</hi> Votes, was <hi>Deicide.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No <hi>Sinne,</hi> except the <hi>first,</hi> hath ever past</l>
               <l>So black as this; no <hi>Iudgement,</hi> but the <hi>last.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How does our <hi>Del<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> vvhich so lately stood</l>
               <l>Unmov'd, lie <hi>floating</hi> in her <hi>Pilots blood?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And can vve hope to <hi>Anchor,</hi> vvho discern</l>
               <l>Nought but the <hi>tempest</hi> ruling at the <hi>stern</hi>;</l>
               <l>Whil'st <hi>Pluto's Rival,</hi> vvith his <hi>Saints</hi> by's side,</l>
               <l>Dravvn by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>avarice</hi> and <hi>pride,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Being fairly placed in the <hi>Chair</hi> of <hi>scorn</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sits <hi>brewing Tears</hi> for Infants yet <hi>unborn?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Vast <hi>stocks</hi> of <hi>misery,</hi> vvhich his <hi>Guardian-rage</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Does <hi>husband</hi> for them till they come to <hi>age?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When <hi>future times</hi> shall look vvhat <hi>Plagues</hi> befe</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aegypt</hi> and <hi>Us,</hi> by'vvay of <hi>Parallel,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>They'l find at once presented to their <hi>view</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Frogs</hi> and <hi>Lice,</hi> and <hi>Independents</hi> too.</l>
               <l>Onely this <hi>signal difference</hi> vvill be knovvn</l>
               <l>Tvvixt those <hi>Aegyptian</hi> judgements and our <hi>own,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Those vvere <hi>Gods Armies</hi>; but th' <hi>effect</hi> doth tell</l>
               <l>That these <hi>our Vermin</hi> are the <hi>Host of Hell.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pausanias</hi> and <hi>Herostratus</hi> vvill look</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:49002:7"/>Like <hi>Pygmy-Sinners</hi> vvrit in <hi>Times black-book.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Spanish Fleet,</hi> and <hi>Powder-plot</hi> vvill lack</l>
               <l>Their usuall <hi>mentions</hi> in our <hi>Almanack.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>—Nay, vvhich is more, <note n="(c)" place="bottom">Socrat. l. 7. c. 10. <hi>hoc Alarichiresponsum recitat.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> [<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.]</note> 
                  <hi>Alaricus</hi> his <hi>name</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Will scarce be <hi>legible</hi> i'th' <hi>leaves</hi> of <hi>fame,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When <hi>Cromwel</hi> shall be read. <hi>Nature</hi> vvas ne're</l>
               <l>So blessedly <hi>reform'd,</hi> since <hi>Lucifer.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O for a <hi>Ieremy</hi> to <hi>lamemt</hi> our <hi>woe</hi>!</l>
               <l>From vvhom such <hi>tragick Rhetorick</hi> might flovv,</l>
               <l>As vvould <hi>become</hi> our <hi>misery,</hi> and <hi>dresse</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our <hi>sorrows</hi> vvith a <hi>dreadfull gaudinesse</hi>!</l>
               <l>For next those <hi>hovering judgements,</hi> vvhich the fall</l>
               <l>Of <hi>One</hi> so <hi>great,</hi> so <hi>good,</hi> makes <hi>Verticall.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(And rushing dovvn, may onely be vvithstood</l>
               <l>If <hi>Charles</hi> his <hi>praiers</hi> crie louder than his <hi>blood</hi>)</l>
               <l>I say next that, It is our second Crosse</l>
               <l>We can't grieve <hi>worthy</hi> of so great a Losse.</l>
               <l>To vveep upon this <hi>subject,</hi> and <hi>weep sense,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Requires vve should be born <hi>ten Ages hence.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>greater</hi> are the <hi>hights</hi> an Artist's hand</l>
               <l>Designes to take, the <hi>farther</hi> he must <hi>stand.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And as vvhen <hi>Sol's</hi> in's <hi>Zenith, He</hi> imply's</l>
               <l>His dazling glory <hi>best,</hi> that <hi>shuts</hi> his eyes,</l>
               <l>So, vvhere the <hi>Theme's ineffable,</hi> the vvay</l>
               <l>To <hi>speak</hi> it is, <note n="(d)" place="bottom">Herodot. l. 3. <hi>Psammeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus ad Cambysem, cùm Amicorum vicem lacrymis lugeret, suam verò silentio,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Not to know what to say.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
